<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>品部</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinabe (Technicians in Offices)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinabe (Technicians in Offices)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinabe (Technicians in Offices)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>品部（しなべ/ともべ）とは、「しなしなのとものを」あるいは「とものみやつこ」の和訓を持つ古代日本の人的集団・組織のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinabe (technicians in offices), or &quot;shinashinano tomonowo&quot; or &quot;tomono miyatsuko&quot; in the Japanese way of reading, refers to the human group or organization in ancient Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinabe (technicians in offices), or &quot;shinashinano tomonowo&quot; or &quot;tomono miyatsuko&quot; in the Japanese way of reading, refers to the human group or organization in ancient Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinabe (technicians in offices), or &apos;shinashinano tomonowo&apos; or &apos;tomono miyatsuko&apos; in the Japanese way of reading, refers to the human group or organization in ancient Japan.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot; → &apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>複数の部民制あるいは部全体の総称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">General term for multiple &quot;Be&quot; (groups of people who belonged to the Yamato Dynasty) or whole Be.</e>
<cmt>原文には「部民制」とありますが、リンク先の単語のようです。ウェブで確認すると用語が「部」となっておりましたので、こちらを訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinabe refers to general term for multiple &quot;Be&quot; (groups of people who belonged to the Yamato Dynasty) or whole Be.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくするために、主語を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinabe refers to general term for multiple &quot;Be&quot; (groups of people who belonged to the Yamato Dynasty) or whole Be.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>大化前代においては、朝廷に直属する部民（職業部・名代）のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bemin (members of Be) under the direct control of the Imperial Court (shokugyobe [professional Be], nashiro [bemin privately owned by the Imperial Family]) before the Taika Reforms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the Taika Reforms, Shinabe refers to bemin (members of Be) under the direct control of the Imperial Court (shokugyobe [professional Be], nashiro [bemin privately owned by the Imperial Family])</e>
<cmt>主語がなく、わかりにくかったので、主語を追加しました。また、before the Taika Reforms を文頭に移動させました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the Taika Reforms, Shinabe refers to bemin (members of Be) under the direct control of the Imperial Court (shokugyobe [professional Be], nashiro [bemin privately owned by the Imperial Family])</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="4">
<j>大化以後及び律令制において官司に配属されて宮中で用いる物資の生産・技術伝習にあたった人々。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those who were assigned to government offices to produce and learn techniques to produce goods used in the Imperial Court after the Taika Reforms under the ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinabe were people who were assigned to government offices to produce goods used in the Imperial Court and learn those techniques after the Taika Reforms and under the ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code).</e>
<cmt>主語が省かれていたり、誤訳の部分がありましたので、文全体を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinabe were people who were assigned to government offices to produce goods used in the Imperial Court and learn those techniques after the Taika Reforms and under the ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>大化前代の職業部の後身とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed to be the successor of shokugyobe before the Taika Reforms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinabe is believed to be the successor of shokugyobe before the Taika Reforms.</e>
<cmt>わかりにくいため、It　⇒　Shinabe　に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinabe is believed to be the successor of shokugyobe before the Taika Reforms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="6">
<j>上記のように複数の意味を有する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The word shinabe contains more than one meaning as described above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The word shinabe contains more than one meaning as described above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word shinabe contains more than one meaning as described above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="7">
<j>大化前代においては、伴造などの豪族に率いられて朝廷（ヤマト王権）に様々な物資あるいは労働力の形で奉仕を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the days before the Taika Reforms, shinabe, led by Tomonomiyatsuko and other local ruling families, served the Imperial Court (Yamato sovereignty) by providing various goods or labor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the days before the Taika Reforms, shinabe, led by Tomonomiyatsuko and other local ruling families, served the Imperial Court (Yamato sovereignty) by providing various goods or labor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the days before the Taika Reforms, shinabe, led by Tomonomiyatsuko and other local ruling families, served the Imperial Court (Yamato sovereignty) by providing various goods or labor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、5世紀後半以後に渡来した渡来人の技術者集団の中には品部に属した者が多いとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Is is believed many of the toraijin (people from overseas, especially from China and Korea, who settled in early Japan and introduced Continental culture to the Japanese) technical experts who came to Japan in groups after the late 5th century belonged to shinabe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Is is believed many of the toraijin (people from overseas, especially from China and Korea, who settled in early Japan and introduced Continental culture to the Japanese) technical experts who came to Japan in groups after the late 5th century belonged to shinabe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Is is believed many of the toraijin (people from overseas, especially from China and Korea, who settled in early Japan and introduced Continental culture to the Japanese) technical experts who came to Japan in groups after the late 5th century belonged to shinabe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>大化の改新以後、一部は廃止されるが残りは再編されて官司に付属され、貢納の一環として宮廷で用いる奢侈品や特殊な技術を必要とする工業製品の生産を義務付けられるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some shinabe were dissolved after the Taika Reforms, while the rest were reorganized to be affiliated with government offices where they were obliged to produce luxury goods used in the Imperial Court and industrial products requiring special techniques as part of tribute.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some shinabe were dissolved after the Taika Reforms, while the rest were reorganized to be affiliated with government offices where they were obliged to produce luxury goods used in the Imperial Court and industrial products requiring special techniques as part of tribute.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some shinabe were dissolved after the Taika Reforms, while the rest were reorganized to be affiliated with government offices where they were obliged to produce luxury goods used in the Imperial Court and industrial products requiring special techniques as part of tribute.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>学術的には同様の組織である雑戸と合わせて品部・雑戸制（しなべ・ざっこせい）とよぶ場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinabe and zakko (special technicians) are sometimes lumped together as the shinabe and zakko system, as these two organizations are academically similar.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinabe and zakko (special technicians) are sometimes lumped together as the shinabe and zakko system, as these two organizations are academically similar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinabe and zakko (special technicians) are sometimes lumped together as the shinabe and zakko system, as these two organizations are academically similar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし、軍事関係の技術労働に従事して一般の戸籍とは違う雑戸籍に編入された雑戸とは違って、法的には良民と同じ扱いとされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, unlike zakko who were engaged in military-related technical work and listed in zakkoseki (family register for zakko), shinabe were treated the same as ryomin (one of the two main castes of the ritsuryo system, meaning good citizens) by law.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But, unlike zakko who were engaged in military-related technical work and listed in zakkoseki (family register for zakko) which was different from the general family register, shinabe were treated the same as ryomin (one of the two main castes of the ritsuryo system, meaning good citizens) by law.</e>
<cmt>一般の戸籍とは違う　の文が訳漏れのため、which was different from the general family register,　を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But, unlike zakko who were engaged in military-related technical work and listed in zakkoseki (family register for zakko) which was different from the general family register, shinabe were treated the same as ryomin (one of the two main castes of the ritsuryo system, meaning good citizens) by law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="12">
<j>品戸は畿内及びその周辺諸国に在住し、恒常的な貢納を義務付けられた常品部（つねのしなべ）と臨時の徭役労働に近い形態を有した借品部（かりのしなべ）に分けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinabe were divided into tsuneno shinabe who lived in Kinai region (provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara) and its surrounding provinces and who were obliged to pay tribute on a constant basis, and karino shinaba with a form close to temporary yoeki (corvee under the ritsuryo system) work.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinabe who lived in Kinai region (provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara) and its surrounding provinces were divided into tsuneno shinabe who were obliged to pay tribute on a constant basis and karino shinaba with a form close to temporary yoeki (corvee under the ritsuryo system) work.</e>
<cmt>誤訳のため、文全体を訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinabe who lived in Kinai region (provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara) and its surrounding provinces were divided into tsuneno shinabe who were obliged to pay tribute on a constant basis and karino shinaba with a form close to temporary yoeki (corvee under the ritsuryo system) work.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>狛戸及び染戸の一部は毎年一定量の料物を貢納したが、その他は1戸あたり1名が一定期間の交替制か臨時に官司に上番して労役を行うか一定量の製品を貢納した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some komahe and someko (both are one of the shinabe) offered a certain amount of materials and costs every year, while the others offered either labor in such a way that one member from each shinabe served government offices on a periodic rotating or temporary basis, or a certain amount of products.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some komahe and someko (both are one of the shinabe) offered a certain amount of required materials and costs every year, while the others offered either labor in such a way that one member from each shinabe served government offices on a periodic rotating or temporary basis, or a certain amount of products.</e>
<cmt>料物：共有用語のとおり、required materials and costsに訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some komahe and someko (both are one of the shinabe) offered a certain amount of required materials and costs every year, while the others offered either labor in such a way that one member from each shinabe served government offices on a periodic rotating or temporary basis, or a certain amount of products.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>その代わりとして戸内の課役の一部もしくは全てが免除され、兵役からも除外された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In return, they were exempted from all or part of assignments imposed as well as military service.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In return, they were exempted from all or part of assignments imposed in he as well as military service.</e>
<cmt>[戸内の]訳漏れのため加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In return, they were exempted from all or part of assignments imposed in he as well as military service.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="15">
<j>ところが奈良時代に入ると、養老5年（721年）に主鷹司の品部廃止が行われ、続いて天平宝字3年（759年）に高度な技術を要する「世業相伝者」以外の品戸は原則廃止されて公戸に編入（一般の公民扱い）された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But in the Nara period, shinabe of shuyoshi (department of the ritsuryo bureaucracy responsible for falconry and hunting dogs) were abolished in 721, and then shinabe except the one of &quot;those who assume a hereditary profession&quot; requiring advanced techniques were dismantled in principle to be incorporated into koko (one of the subcastes of ryomin) (regarded as general citizens) in 759.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But in the Nara period, shinabe of shuyoshi (department of the ritsuryo bureaucracy responsible for falconry and hunting dogs) was abolished in 721, and then shinabe except the one of &quot;those who assume a hereditary profession&quot; requiring advanced techniques were dismantled in principle to be incorporated into koko (one of the subcastes of ryomin) (regarded as general citizens) in 759.</e>
<cmt>were　⇒　was　に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But in the Nara period, shinabe of shuyoshi (department of the ritsuryo bureaucracy responsible for falconry and hunting dogs) was abolished in 721, and then shinabe except the one of &apos;those who assume a hereditary profession&apos; requiring advanced techniques were dismantled in principle to be incorporated into koko (one of the subcastes of ryomin) (regarded as general citizens) in 759.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot; → &apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>その後も品戸の廃止が続き、平安時代の『延喜式』には鼓吹司にのみ品部が設置されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinabe continued to be abolished one after another, and &quot;the Engishiki&quot; (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers) published in the Heian period shows shinabe existed only under Kusuishi (Drums and Fifes Office).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinabe continued to be abolished one after another, and &quot;the Engishiki&quot; (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers) published in the Heian period shows shinabe existed only under Kusuishi (Drums and Fifes Office).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinabe continued to be abolished one after another, and &quot;the Engishiki&quot; (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers) published in the Heian period shows shinabe existed only under Kusuishi (Drums and Fifes Office).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これは古い部民制の残滓である品部そのものが律令制と相容れなかったこと、律令制の衰退によって品部の維持が困難になってきたこと、社会経済水準の向上によって民間からの調達・雇役が可能になったこと（この場合の民間には旧品部の商工業者からの調達を含む）が複雑に絡み合っていたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This situation was caused by intricately intertwined reasons, i.e., the fact that shinabe, which was the remnant of the bemin system, itself was incompatible with the ritsuryo system, that it became difficult to preserve shinabe as the ritsuryo system was weakened, and that improved social economy standard enabled procurement from and koeki (forced labor under the ritsuryo system) by ordinary citizens (procurement from ordinary citizens here includes procurement from commercial and industrial men in former shinabe).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This situation was caused by intricately intertwined reasons, i.e., the fact that shinabe, which was the remnant of the bemin system, itself was incompatible with the ritsuryo system, that it became difficult to preserve shinabe as the ritsuryo system was weakened, and that improved social economy standard enabled procurement from and koeki (forced labor under the ritsuryo system) by ordinary citizens (procurement from ordinary citizens here includes procurement from commercial and industrial men in former shinabe).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This situation was caused by intricately intertwined reasons, i.e., the fact that shinabe, which was the remnant of the bemin system, itself was incompatible with the ritsuryo system, that it became difficult to preserve shinabe as the ritsuryo system was weakened, and that improved social economy standard enabled procurement from and koeki (forced labor under the ritsuryo system) by ordinary citizens (procurement from ordinary citizens here includes procurement from commercial and industrial men in former shinabe).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>