<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>神仏習合</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinbutsu-shugo (Syncretization of Shinto with Buddhism)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinbutsu-shugo (Syncretization of Shinto with Buddhism)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinbutsu-shugo</e>
<cmt>以下説明が続くので、英語説明を削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>神仏習合（しんぶつしゅうごう）とは、土着の信仰と仏教信仰を折衷して、一つの信仰体系として再構成（習合）すること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinbutsu-shugo (syncretization of Shinto with Buddhism) refers to blending an indigenous belief and Buddhistic faith to reconfigure one belief system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinbutsu-shugo (syncretization of Shinto with Buddhism) refers to blending of indigenous belief and Buddhistic faith to reconfigure one belief system.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinbutsu-shugo (syncretization of Shinto with Buddhism) refers to blending of indigenous belief and Buddhistic faith to reconfigure one belief system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>一般的に日本で神祇信仰と仏教との間に起こった現象を指すが、広義では、世界各地に仏教が広まった際、土着の信仰との間に起こった現象をも指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it generally refers to the syncretism of Japanese faith in Jingi (gods of heaven and earth) and Buddhism, in a broad sense, it may refers to a syncretism of an indigenous belief and Buddhistic that had happened various parts of the world as Buddhism was spread.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it generally refers to the syncretism of Japanese faith in Jingi (gods of heaven and earth) and Buddhism, in a broad sense, it may refer to a syncretism of an indigenous belief and Buddhistic that had happened in various parts of the world as Buddhism was spread.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it generally refers to the syncretism of Japanese faith in Jingi (gods of heaven and earth) and Buddhism, in a broad sense, it may refer to a syncretism of an indigenous belief and Buddhistic that had happened in various parts of the world as Buddhism was spread.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>以下、日本における神仏習合について述べる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hereafter, the syncretization of Shinto with Buddhism in Japan is described.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hereafter, the syncretization of Shinto with Buddhism in Japan is described.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hereafter, the syncretization of Shinto with Buddhism in Japan is described.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>神仏混淆（しんぶつこんこう）ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also known as &quot;Shinbutsu-konko.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also known as &quot;Shinbutsu-konko.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also known as &quot;Shinbutsu-konko.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>仏教の伝来</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Introduction of Buddhism</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Introduction of Buddhism</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Introduction of Buddhism</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>552年(538年説あり)に仏教公伝した当初には、仏は、蕃神（となりのくにのかみ）として日本の神と同質の存在として認識された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 552 (in 538, according to another theory), when Buddhism was officially introduced in Japan, Buddha was recognized as banshin (deity of neighbor country) and equivalent to Japanese deity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 552 (in 538, according to another theory), when Buddhism was officially introduced into Japan, Buddha was recognized as banshin (a deity of a neighboring country) and equivalent to a Japanese deity.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 552 (in 538, according to another theory), when Buddhism was officially introduced into Japan, Buddha was recognized as banshin (a deity of a neighboring country) and equivalent to a Japanese deity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>日本で最初に出家して仏を祀ったのは尼（善信尼）であるという記録が日本書紀にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), the first Japanese Buddhist priest who deified the Buddha was a nun called Zenshin-ni.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), the first Japanese Buddhist priest who deified the Buddha was a nun called Zenshin-ni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), the first Japanese Buddhist priest who entered into priesthood and deified the Buddha was a nun called Zenshin-ni.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>これは巫女が日本の神祇を祀ってきたというのをそのまま仏にあてはめたものだと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The nun thought to have deified the Buddha in the same manner as a shrine maiden deified Japanese gods of heaven and earth.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The nun thought to have deified the Buddha in the same manner as a shrine maiden deified Japanese gods of heaven and earth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The nun thought to have deified the Buddha in the same manner as a shrine maiden deified Japanese gods of heaven and earth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>寺院の焼亡による仏の祟りという考え方も、仏には祟るという概念が無いため神祇信仰をそのまま仏に当てはめたものと理解できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The view that burning down of a temple may cause curse of the Buddha is thought to come from the belief in Jingi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The view that burning down of a temple may cause a curse of the Buddha is thought to come from the belief in Jingi.</e>
<cmt>grammmar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The view that the burning down of a temple may result in the arsonist being cursed by the Buddha is thought to come from the Japanese belief in Jingi, as Buddhism does not accept the concept of curses.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>神宮寺の建立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Erection of Jingu-ji Temples (temples associated with shrines)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Erection of Jingu-ji Temples (temples associated with shrines)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Erection of Jingu-ji Temples (temples associated with shrines)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>日本人が、仏は日本の神とは違う性質を持つと理解するにつれ、仏のもとに神と人間を同列に位置づけ、日本の神々も人間と同じように苦しみから逃れる事を願い、仏の救済を求め解脱を欲しているという認識がされるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Japanese people realized that the Buddha had the nature different from Japanese deities, they began to regard deities and human being in the same level and think that like human being, Japanese deities also wish deliverance for salvation of the Buddha to end suffering.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Japanese people realized that the Buddha had a nature different from Japanese deities, they began to regard deities and human beings on the same level and thought that like human beings, Japanese deities also wish deliverance for salvation of the Buddha to end suffering.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Japanese people realized that the Buddha had a nature different from Japanese deities, they began to regard deities and human beings on the same level and thought that like human beings, Japanese deities also wish deliverance for salvation of the Buddha to end suffering.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>715年には越前国氣比神宮の託宣により神宮寺が建立されるなど、奈良時代初頭から国家レベルの神社において神宮寺を建立する動きが出始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the beginning of the Nara period, Jingu-ji Temples started to be erected in the national shrines; for example, in 715, a Jingu-ji Temple was erected from an oracle of Kehi-jingu Shrine, Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処http://kehijingu.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the beginning of the Nara period, Jingu-ji Temples started to be erected in the national shrines; for example, in 715, a Jingu-ji Temple was erected from an oracle of Kehi-jingu Shrine, Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the beginning of the Nara period, Jingu-ji Temples started to be erected in the national shrines; for example, in 715, a Jingu-ji Temple was erected from an oracle of Kehi-jingu Shrine, Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また満願 (僧)らによる鹿島神宮、賀茂神社、伊勢神宮などで境内外を問わず神宮寺が併設された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, Jingu-ji Temples were built within or out of precincts of shrines, such as Kashima-jingu Shrine, Kamo-jingu Shrine and Ise-jingu Shrine, by priest Mangan, et al.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, Jingu-ji Temples were built within or out of precincts of shrines, such as Kashima-jingu Shrine, Kamo-jingu Shrine and Ise-jingu Shrine, by priest Mangan, et al.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, Jingu-ji Temples were built within or out of precincts of shrines, such as Kashima-jingu Shrine, Kamo-jingu Shrine and Ise-jingu Shrine, by priest Mangan, et al.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また、宇佐神宮のように神体が菩薩形をとる神（僧形八幡神）も現れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, bodhisattva-like statues were made as shintai (an object of worship housed in a Shinto shrine and believed to contain the spirit of a deity), known as Sogyo Hachimanshin, in Usa-jingu Shrine, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, bodhisattva-like statues were made as shintai (an object of worship housed in a Shinto shrine and believed to contain the spirit of a deity), known as Sogyo Hachimanshin, in Usa-jingu Shrine, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, bodhisattva-like statues were made as shintai (an object of worship housed in a Shinto shrine and believed to contain the spirit of a deity), known as Sogyo Hachimanshin, in Usa-jingu Shrine, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>奈良時代後半になると、伊勢桑名郡にある現地豪族の氏神である多度大神が、神の身を捨てて仏道の修行をしたいと託宣するなど、神宮寺建立の動きは地方の神社にまで広がった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the late Nara period, erections of Jingu-ji Temples were widly seen even at rural shrines; Tado Ogami (great god) who was a guardian deity of a local ruling family in Kuwana County, Ise province, wished to practice of Buddhist teachings, in a oracle, giving up a title of deity.</e>
<cmt>HPの文章に差し替え一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the late Nara period, erections of Jingu-ji Temples were widly seen even at rural shrines; Tado Ogami (great god) who was a guardian deity of a local ruling family in Kuwana County, Ise province, wished to practice of Buddhist teachings, in a oracle, giving up the title of deity.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the late Nara period, erections of Jingu-ji Temples were widely seen even at rural shrines; Tado Ogami (great god) who was a guardian deity of a local ruling family in Kuwana County, Ise Province, wished to practice of Buddhist teachings, in a oracle, giving up the title of deity.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>若狭国若狭彦大神や近江国奥津島大神など、他の諸国の神も8世紀後半から9世紀前半にかけて、仏道に帰依したいとの意思を示すようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the late eighth century to the early ninth century, deities in various provinces, such as Wakasahiko Ogami, Wakasa Province and Okitsushima Ogami, Omi Province, began to show willingness to embrace Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the late eighth century to the early ninth century, deities in various provinces, such as Wakasahiko Ogami, Wakasa Province and Okitsushima Ogami, Omi Province, began to show willingness to embrace Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the late eighth century to the early ninth century, deities in various provinces, such as Wakasahiko Ogami, Wakasa Province and Okitsushima Ogami, Omi Province, began to show willingness to embrace Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>こうして苦悩する神を救済するため、神社の傍らに寺が建てられ神宮寺となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this way, in order to relieve an agonized deity, a temple was built by the side of a shrine, and it was called Jingu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this way, in order to relieve an agonized deity, a temple was built by the side of a shrine, and it was called Jingu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this way, in order to relieve an agonized deity, a temple was built by the side of a shrine, and it was called Jingu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また神前で読経がなされるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, sutra was chanted before Shinto altar.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, sutra was chanted before Shinto altar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, sutra was chanted before Shinto altar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>こうした神々の仏道帰依の託宣は、そのままそれらを祀る有力豪族たちの願望であったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such oracles of deities embracing Buddhism were thought to be a wish of powerful local ruling families who enshrined the shrines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such oracles of deities embracing Buddhism were thought to be a wish of powerful local ruling families who enshrined the shrines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such oracles of deities embracing Buddhism were thought to be a wish of powerful local ruling families who enshrined the shrines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>律令制の導入により社会構造が変化し、豪族らが単なる共同体の首長から私的所有地を持つ領主的な性格を持つようになるに伴い、共同体による祭祀に支えられた従来の神祇信仰は行き詰まりを見せた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the social structure changed by introducing the system of the ritsuryo legal codes, local ruling families, who were simply the head of a community, became like feudal-lords with private property, and the conventional Jingi belief supported to the religious service by a community was in deadlock.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the social structure changed by introducing the system of the ritsuryo legal codes, local ruling families, who were simply the head of a community, became like feudal-lords with private property, and the conventional Jingi belief supported the religious service by a community was in a deadlock.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the social structure changed by introducing the system of the ritsuryo legal codes, local ruling families, who were simply the head of a community, became like feudal-lords with private property, and the conventional Jingi belief supported the religious service by a community was in a deadlock.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>私的所有に伴う罪を自覚するようになった豪族個人の新たな精神的支柱が求められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The local ruling family started to be aware of the guilt owing private property and sought a new personal emotional prop.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The local ruling family started to become aware of the guilt owing private property and sought a new personal emotional prop.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The local ruling family started to become aware of the guilt owing private property and sought a new personal emotional prop.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>大乗仏教は、その構造上利他行を通じて罪の救済を得られる教えとなっており、この点が豪族たちに受け入れられたと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason Mahayana Buddhism became popular among local ruling families might be that it taught that sin was forgiven through Ritako (Altruistic Practice).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason Mahayana Buddhism became popular among local ruling families might be that it taught that sin was forgiven through Ritako (Altruistic Practice).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason Mahayana Buddhism became popular among local ruling families might be that it taught that sin was forgiven through Ritako (Altruistic Practice).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>それに応えるように雑密を身につけた遊行僧が現われ、神宮寺の建立を進めたのだと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yugyo-so (traveling monk) who learned Zo-mitsu (the Mixed Esoteric Buddhism) thought to appear to meet their demands and encourage building Jingu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yugyo-so (traveling monk) who learned Zo-mitsu (the Mixed Esoteric Buddhism) thought to appear to meet their demands and encourage building Jingu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yugyo-so (traveling monk) who learned Zo-mitsu (the Mixed Esoteric Buddhism) thought to appear to meet their demands and encourage building Jingu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>まだ密教は体系化されていなかったが、その呪術的な修行や奇蹟を重視し世俗的な富の蓄積や繁栄を肯定する性格が神祇信仰とも折衷しやすい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although esoteric Buddhism had not been systematized yet, it might be easy to blend with Jingi belief because of its magical practice and teachings, focusing on miracle, and affirming accumulation and prosperity of secular wealth.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although esoteric Buddhism had not been systematized yet, it might be easy to blend with the Jingi belief because of its magical practice and teachings, focusing on miracles, and affirming accumulation and the prosperity of secular wealth.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Esoteric Buddhism had not been systematized yet, it might be easy to blend with the Jingi belief because of its magical practice and teachings, focusing on miracles, and affirming accumulation and the prosperity of secular wealth.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>また豪族の配下の人々に受け入れられ易かったのだろうと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It might be also easy to be accepted by people under the local ruling family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It might be also easy to be accepted by people under the local ruling family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It might be also easy to be accepted by people under the local ruling family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="24">
<j>こうして神社が寺院に接近する一方、寺院も神社側への接近を示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While shrines came close to temples, temples also came close to shrines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While shrines came close to temples, temples also came close to shrines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While shrines came close to temples, temples also came close to shrines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>8世紀後半には、その寺院に関係のある神を寺院の守護神、鎮守とするようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the late eighth century, temples recognized a deity that was related to them as their guardian deity or tutelary shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the late eighth century, temples recognized a deity that was related to them as their guardian deity or tutelary shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the late eighth century, temples recognized a deity that was related to them as their guardian deity or tutelary shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>710年（和銅3年）の興福寺における春日大社は最も早い例である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The relationship between Kofuku-ji Temple and Kasugataisha Shrine in 710 was the oldest example.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The relationship between Kofuku-ji Temple and Kasugataisha Shrine in 710 was the oldest example.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The relationship between Kofuku-ji Temple and Kasugataisha Shrine in 710 was the oldest example.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>また、東大寺は大仏建立に協力した宇佐八幡神を勧請して鎮守とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, Todai-ji Temple made a branch shrine for deity of Usahachiman-shin, which helped the erection of the Great Buddha.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, Todai-ji Temple made a branch shrine for deity of Usahachiman-shin, which helped erecting the Great Buddha.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, Todai-ji Temple made a branch shrine for deity of Usahachiman-shin, which helped erecting the Great Buddha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>これは現在の手向山八幡宮である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shrine is called Tamukeyama Hachimangu Shrine at present.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shrine is called Tamukeyama Hachimangu Shrine at present.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shrine is called Tamukeyama Hachimangu Shrine at present.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>ほかの古代の有力寺院を見ても、延暦寺は日吉大社、金剛峯寺は丹生都比売神社、東寺は伏見稲荷大社などといずれも守護神を持つことになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for other influential temples in the ancient times, Enryaku-ji Temple had Hiyoshi-taisha Shrine, Kongobu-ji Temple had Niutsuhime-jinja Shrine, and To-ji Temple had Fushimi Inari-taisha Shrine, as their guardian shrines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for other influential temples in the ancient times, Enryaku-ji Temple had Hiyoshi-taisha Shrine, Kongobu-ji Temple had Niutsuhime-jinja Shrine, and To-ji Temple had Fushimi Inari-taisha Shrine, as their guardian shrines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for other influential temples in the ancient times, Enryaku-ji Temple had Hiyoshi-taisha Shrine, Kongobu-ji Temple had Niutsuhime-jinja Shrine, and To-ji Temple had Fushimi Inari-taisha Shrine, as their guardian shrines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="30">
<j>この段階では、神と仏は同一の信仰体系の中にはあるが、あくまで別の存在として認識され、同一の存在としてみるまでには及んでいない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this phase, although deities and the Buddha were under the same belief system, they were recognized as different existence; they were not yet considered same existence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this phase, although deities and the Buddha were under the same belief system, they were recognized as a different existence; they were not yet considered same existence.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this phase, although deities and the Buddha were under the same belief system, they were recognized as a different existence; they were not yet considered same existence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>この段階をのちの神仏習合と特に区別して神仏混淆ということもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The phase may be called Shinbutsu-konko to differentiate from later Shinbutsu-shugo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The phase may be called Shinbutsu-konko to differentiate from later Shinbutsu-shugo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The phase may be called Shinbutsu-konko to differentiate from later Shinbutsu-shugo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>数多くの神社に神宮寺が建てられ、寺院の元に神社が建てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jingu-ji Temples were built in many shrines, and shrines were built in temples.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jingu-ji Temples were built in many shrines, and shrines were built in temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jingu-ji Temples were built in many shrines, and shrines were built in temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>それは従来の神祇信仰を圧迫する事なく神祇信仰と仏教信仰とが互いに補い合うかたちとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It compensated Jingi belief and Buddhism each other, without oppressing the conventional Jingi belief.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It compensated Jingi belief and Buddhism, without oppressing the conventional Jingi belief.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It compensated Jingi belief and Buddhism, without oppressing the conventional Jingi belief.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>大乗密教による系列化</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The systematization by Mahayana esoteric Buddhism</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Systematization by Mahayana esoteric Buddhism</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Systematization by Mahayana Esoteric Buddhism</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>これらの神宮寺は雑密系の経典を中心とし、地域の豪族層の支援を受けて確立しようとしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such Jingu-ji Temples were led by the Zo-mitsu Buddhist scripture and tried to settle with the support of the local ruling families.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such Jingu-ji Temples were led by the Zo-mitsu Buddhist scripture and tried to settle with the support of the local ruling families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such Jingu-ji Temples were led by the Zo-mitsu Buddhist scripture and tried to settle with the support of the local ruling families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>一方でこの事態は豪族層の神祇信仰離れを促進しかねなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, this situation might accelerate the separation of Jingi belief from local ruling families.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, this situation might have accelerated the separation of Jingi belief from local ruling families.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, this situation might have accelerated the separation of Jingi belief from local ruling families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>神祇信仰の初穂儀礼に由来すると見られている租庸調の徴収や神祇信仰を通じた国家への求心力の低下が懸念されることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was concerned that it might affect collection of the Soyocho (a tax system, corvee), which was thought be derived from first-crop-offering ritual of Jingi belief, and the centripetal force of the country through Jingi belief.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a concern that it might affect collection of the Soyocho (a tax system, corvee), which was thought be derived from first-crop-offering ritual of Jingi belief, and the centripetal force of the country through Jingi belief.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a concern that it might affect collection of the Soyocho (a tax system, corvee), which was thought be derived from first-crop-offering ritual of Jingi belief, and the centripetal force of the country through Jingi belief.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>一方で律令制の変質に伴い、大寺社が所領拡大を図る動きが始まり、地方の神宮寺も対抗上、大寺院の別院として認められることを望むようになってきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, as the system of the ritsuryo legal codes changed, major temples and shrines had started to aim at territorial expansion while local Jingu-ji Temples had begun to desire to be approved as a branch temple of main temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, as the system of the ritsuryo legal codes changed, major temples and shrines had started to aim at territorial expansion while local Jingu-ji Temples had begun to desire to be approved as a branch temple of main temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, as the system of the ritsuryo legal codes changed, major temples and shrines had started to aim at territorial expansion while local Jingu-ji Temples had begun to desire to be approved as a branch temple of main temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="38">
<j>朝廷側も、国家鎮護の大寺院の系列とすることで諸国の神宮寺に対する求心力を維持できることから、これを推進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial-Court promoted the movement to keep centripetal force of Jingu-ji Temples in various countries by joining Jingu-ji Temples to the main temples that were under national protection.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処”諸国の”は”諸国での（場所）”という意味と仮定しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial-Court promoted the movement to keep centripetal force of Jingu-ji Temples in various countries by joining Jingu-ji Temples to the main temples that were under national protection.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial-Court promoted the movement to keep centripetal force of Jingu-ji Temples in various countries by joining Jingu-ji Temples to the main temples that were under national protection.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>しかし神祇信仰と習合しやすい呪術的要素を持ちながら国家護持や普遍性・抽象性を備えた教説を整えた中央の大寺院として諸国神宮寺の心を捉えたのが空海の伝えた真言宗であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Kuukai&apos;s Shingon sect of Buddhism attracted Jingu-ji Temples of various countries because it had magical essence, which was easy to combine with Jingi belief, as well as preaching story, providing protecting nation, universality and abstractness.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処”国家護持を備えた教説”という意味が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Kuukai&apos;s Shingon sect of Buddhism attracted Jingu-ji Temples of various countries because it had magical essence, which was easy to combine with Jingi belief, as well as preaching a story, providing protection for the nation, universality, and abstractness.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Kukai&apos;s Shingon sect of Buddhism attracted Jingu-ji Temples of various countries as a central large temple because it had magical essence, which was easy to combine with Jingi belief, as well as preaching a story, providing protection for the nation, universality, and abstractness.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>一方でこのような要望を取り入れるべく天台宗においても、円仁や円珍による密教受容が進んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, to meet the demand, esoteric Buddhism was also progressively accepted by Ennin and Enchin in the Tendai-shu sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, to meet the demand, esoteric Buddhism was also progressively accepted by Ennin and Enchin in the Tendai-shu sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, to meet the demand, esoteric Buddhism was also progressively accepted by Ennin and Enchin in the Tendai-shu sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="41">
<j>この一方で、奈良時代から発達してきた修験道も、両宗の密教の影響を強く受け、独自の発達を遂げることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Shugendo (mountain asceticism-shamanism), which had developed from the Nara period, was also strongly influenced by the esoteric Buddhism of both sects and was evolving independently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Shugendo (mountain asceticism-shamanism), which had developed from the Nara period, was also strongly influenced by the esoteric Buddhism of both sects and was evolving independently.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Shugendo (mountain asceticism-shamanism), which had developed from the Nara period, was also strongly influenced by the esoteric Buddhism of both sects and was evolving independently.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>怨霊信仰</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Worship of Vindictive Spirits</e>
<cmt>Belief in Vindictive Spirits</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Worship of Vindictive Spirits</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Worship of vindictive spirits</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="42">
<j>他方で、このような密教の興隆は王権の相対化をもたらした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, prosperity of such esoteric Buddhism brought relativization of sovereignty.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, prosperity of such esoteric Buddhism brought relativization of sovereignty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, prosperity of such esoteric Buddhism brought relativization of sovereignty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>藤原氏の勢力拡大に伴う旧来の名族の没落もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, expansion of the Fujiwara clan&apos;s influence ruined former prestigious families.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, expansion of the Fujiwara clan&apos;s influence ruined former prestigious families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, expansion of the Fujiwara clan&apos;s influence ruined former prestigious families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>こうしたことが相まって、政争敗死者を担ぐことにより王権への不満や反撥を正当化する怨霊信仰が盛んとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under such circumstances, worshiping vindictive spirits became popular to justify the discontent and repulsion to sovereignty by using the name of deceased, who lost in a political strife.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under such circumstances, worshiping vindictive spirits became popular to justify the discontent and repulsion to sovereignty by using the name of deceased, who lost in a political strife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under such circumstances, worshiping vindictive spirits became popular to justify the discontent and repulsion to sovereignty by using the name of deceased, who lost in a political strife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="45">
<j>この動きは9世紀には御霊会の流行を引き起こした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This trend led to the epidemic of the goryoe (ritual ceremony to repose of spirits of a deceased person) in the ninth century.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This trend led to the epidemic of the goryoe (ritual ceremony to repose of spirits of a deceased person) in the ninth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This trend led to the epidemic of the goryoe (ritual ceremony to repose of spirits of a deceased person) in the ninth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>これが神祇信仰に従来からあった怨霊祭り上げの風習に加えて、密教の側からの鎮魂も行われた点に神仏習合の類型を見ることが出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One may see it as an example of shinbutsu-shugo since ritual for repose of souls, based on esoteric Buddhism, was carried out in addition to the custom of vindictive spirit festival based on traditional Jingi belief.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One may see it as an example of shinbutsu-shugo since ritual for repose of souls, based on esoteric Buddhism, was carried out in addition to the custom of vindictive spirit festival based on traditional Jingi belief.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One may see it as an example of shinbutsu-shugo since ritual for repose of souls, based on esoteric Buddhism, was carried out in addition to the custom of vindictive spirit festival based on traditional Jingi belief.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>特に菅原道真の怨霊が天神信仰へと発展するに際し、仏教の論理により天部として位置づけられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially, when vindictive spirit of SUGAWARA no Michizane turned to Tenjin belief, he was regard as Tenbu (deities who reside in a heavenly realm, one of six realms in which the souls of living beings transmigrate from one to another) according to Buddhistic logic.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially, when the vindictive spirit of SUGAWARA no Michizane turned to Tenjin belief, he was regard as Tenbu (deities who reside in a heavenly realm, one of six realms in which the souls of living beings transmigrate from one to another) according to Buddhistic logic.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially, when the vindictive spirit of SUGAWARA no Michizane turned to Tenjin belief, he was regarded as Tenbu (deities who reside in a heavenly realm, one of six realms in which the souls of living beings transmigrate from one to another) according to Buddhistic logic.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>このことは、王権に対する祟りという考え方が密教の影響であることを示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it is shown that esoteric Buddhism influenced the view of curse to sovereignty.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it is shown that esoteric Buddhism influenced the view of curses to sovereignty.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it is shown that esoteric Buddhism influenced the view of curses to sovereignty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="49">
<j>この典型的な例が平将門即位の状況に見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The typical example is seen at TAIRA no Masakado&apos;s accession to the throne.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The typical example is seen at TAIRA no Masakado&apos;s accession to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The typical example is seen at TAIRA no Masakado&apos;s accession to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>将門の新皇即位は、神仏習合の神であり天皇家の祖神でもある八幡神がその位を授け、位記（辞令）を菅原道真が書いたとし、仏教音楽により儀式を行うようにと神祇信仰の巫女が託宣したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the enthronement of new emperor Masakado, it supposed that Hachiman (God of War), deity of shinbutsu-shugo and Imperial Family&apos;s soshin (ancestor honored as god), granted the throne, SUGAWARA no Michizane wrote the Iki (court rank diploma), and a shrine maiden of Jingi belief had an oracle to play Buddhistic music at the ceremony.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the enthronement of new emperor Masakado, it supposed that Hachiman (God of War), deity of shinbutsu-shugo and Imperial Family&apos;s soshin (ancestor honored as god), granted the throne, SUGAWARA no Michizane wrote the Iki (court rank diploma), and a shrine maiden of Jingi belief had an oracle to play Buddhistic music at the ceremony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the enthronement of new emperor Masakado, it supposed that Hachiman (God of War), deity of shinbutsu-shugo and Imperial Family&apos;s soshin (ancestor honored as god), granted the throne, SUGAWARA no Michizane wrote the Iki (court rank diploma), and a shrine maiden of Jingi belief had an oracle to play Buddhistic music at the ceremony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>王権相対化の論理を正当化する手段としての仏教の影響が強く表れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The influence of Buddhism, as a means to justify the logic of sovereignty relativization, is strongly seen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The influence of Buddhism, as a means to justify the logic of sovereignty relativization, is strongly seen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The influence of Buddhism, as a means to justify the logic of sovereignty relativization, is strongly seen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>ケガレ忌避の論理</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Logic of &quot;muck&quot; evasion</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Logic of &quot;muck&quot; evasion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Logic of &quot;muck&quot; evasion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="52">
<j>このように呪術的な信仰を求める大衆に対しての仏教の側からの浸透に対抗し、神祇信仰の側からも理論武装の動きが出てきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, the Jingi belief started to arm with reasoning to confront Buddhism, which spread to the public who demanded magical belief.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, the Jingi belief started to arm with reasoning to confront Buddhism, which spread to the public who demanded magical belief.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, the Jingi belief started to arm with reasoning to confront Buddhism, which spread to the public who demanded magical belief.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="53">
<j>神祇信仰においては従来それほど顕著でなかった二極対立の考え方が発達し、清浄とケガレの二極が強調されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The view of bipolar confrontation between purity and &quot;muck,&quot; which had not been very notable formerly for Jingi belief, developed and was emphasized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The view of bipolar confrontation between purity and &quot;muck,&quot; which had not been very notable formerly for Jingi belief, developed and was emphasized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The view of bipolar confrontation between purity and muck, which had not been very notable formerly for Jingi belief, developed and was emphasized.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>このため9世紀から10世紀にかけて、従来は祓いで済んでいたケガレ除去の方法が、陰陽道の影響もあり物忌み中心に変わってきていることが確認されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, the way of &quot;muck&quot; removal had been changed; it is confirmed that from the ninth century to the tenth century, purificatory asceticism was mainly applied, under the influence of Onmyodo (way of Yin and Yang; occult divination system based on the Taoist theory of the five elements), instead of former purification.</e>
<cmt>物忌み：ここでは、「神事などのため、ある期間、飲食•言行などを慎み、沐浴をするなどして、心身のけがれを除くこと」と判断しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, the way of &quot;muck&quot; removal had been changed; it is confirmed that from the ninth century to the tenth century, purificatory asceticism was mainly applied, under the influence of Onmyodo (way of Yin and Yang; occult divination system based on the Taoist theory of the five elements), instead of former purification.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, the way of muck removal had been changed; it is confirmed that from the ninth century to the tenth century, purificatory asceticism was mainly applied, under the influence of Onmyodo (way of Yin and Yang; occult divination system based on the Taoist theory of the five elements), instead of former purification.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="55">
<j>神祇信仰の論理性の強化は、仏教側からの侵食に対抗し、これと共生することを可能とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of the consolidation of the logicalness, Jingi belief was able to confront the invasion of the Buddhism and symbioses with.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of the consolidation of the logicalness, Jingi belief was able to confront the invasion of Buddhism and symbioses with.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of the consolidation of the logicalness, Jingi belief was able to confront the invasion of Buddhism and symbioses with.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>10世紀末には、浄土教にもケガレ思想の影響が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The influence of &quot;muck&quot; idea was seen in Jodo (Pure Land) sect at the end of the 10th century.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The influence of &quot;muck&quot; idea was seen in Jodo (Pure Land) sect at the end of the tenth century.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The influence of muck idea was seen in Jodo (Pure Land) sect at the end of the tenth century.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>往生要集などには本来の仏教の浄穢思想理解のための手段として神祇信仰のケガレを利用した論理が見受けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, &quot;Ojoyoshu&quot; (The Essentials of Salvation) describes a logic employing &quot;muck&quot; of Jingi belief to explain Buddhism&apos;s own pure and impure thought.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, &quot;Ojoyoshu&quot; (The Essentials of Salvation) describes a logic employing &quot;muck&quot; of Jingi belief to explain Buddhism&apos;s own pure and impure thought.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, &quot;Ojoyoshu&quot; (The Essentials of Salvation) describes a logic employing muck of Jingi belief to explain Buddhism&apos;s own pure and impure thought.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>本地垂迹説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honji-suijaku setsu (theory of original reality and manifested traces)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honji-suijaku setsu (theory of original reality and manifested traces)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honji-suijaku setsu (theory of original reality and manifested traces)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="58">
<j>しかし、浄土思想の普及は、ケガレを忌避する神祇信仰に対し、ケガレから根本的に離脱する方法を提示できる仏教の優位を示すこととなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the spread of Pure Land Buddhism showed the predominance of Buddhism, which could present the way to fundamentally flee from &quot;muck,&quot; while Jingi belief could only evades &quot;muck&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the spread of Pure Land Buddhism showed the predominance of Buddhism, which could present the way to fundamentally flee from &quot;muck,&quot; while Jingi belief could only evade &quot;muck&quot;.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the spread of Pure Land Buddhism showed the predominance of Buddhism, which could present the way to fundamentally flee from muck, while Jingi belief could only evade muck.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>仏や菩薩を本地であると考え、その仏や菩薩が救済する衆生に合わせた形態（垂迹）を取ってこの世に出現してくるというのが本地垂迹説である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Honji-suijaku setsu, Buddha and bodhisattvas are honji (original ground or true nature), and they come to this world, in the shape (suijaku (literally, trace manifestation)) in accordance with the live to be saved.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処文の流れがおかしかったのでHPを確認し、文章を差し替えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Honji-suijaku setsu, Buddha and bodhisattvas are honji (original ground or true nature), and they come to this world, in the shape (suijaku - literally, trace manifestation) in accordance with the life to be saved.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Honji-suijaku setsu, Buddha and bodhisattvas are honji (original ground or true nature), and they come to this world, in the shape (suijaku - literally, trace manifestation) in accordance with the life to be saved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>これは、このような仏教上位の状況下において仏教側から神祇信仰を取り込もうとする動きとも理解できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It may be understood that Buddhism tried to take in Jingi belief while Buddhism was considered superior.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It may be understood that Buddhism tried to take in Jingi belief while Buddhism was considered superior.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It may be understood that Buddhism tried to take in Jingi belief while Buddhism was considered superior.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>絶対的存在としての仏や菩薩と、その化身である神という形を取ることにより、神仏の調和の理論的裏づけとしたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The harmonization of Shintoism and Buddhism might be theoretically supported by assuming that Buddha and bodhisattvas were the absolute beings while deities were their incarnations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The harmonization of Shintoism and Buddhism might be theoretically supported by assuming that Buddha and bodhisattvas were the absolute beings, while deities were their incarnations.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The harmonization of Shintoism and Buddhism might be theoretically supported by assuming that Buddha and bodhisattvas were the absolute beings, while deities were their incarnations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="62">
<j>また、このような仏教優位の考え方は、ケガレと日常的に接する武士の心を捉え、以後の八幡神信仰や天神信仰の興隆にもつながることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, such view of Buddhism predominance touched the hearts of samurai, who were commonly close to &quot;muck,&quot; and led to prosperity of future Hachimanshin belief and Tenjin belief.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, such a view of Buddhism predominance touched the hearts of samurai, who were commonly close to &quot;muck,&quot; and led to prosperity of future Hachimanshin and Tenjin beliefs.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, such a view of Buddhism predominance touched the hearts of samurai, who were commonly close to muck, and led to prosperity of future Hachimanshin and Tenjin beliefs.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="63">
<j>更に鎌倉時代になると本地垂迹説による両部神道や山王神道による大祓詞(おおはらえのことば)の密教的解説や、記紀神話などに登場する神や神社の祭神の密教的説明の試みが活発化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, in the Kamakura period, it became popular to make explanation, according to esoteric Buddhism, of Ryobu Shinto based on Honji-suijaku setsu, Oharae no Kotoba based on Sanno Shinto and the enshrined deities of deities and shrines appeared in Kiki-shinwa (the Kojiki, Nihonshoki and mythology).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, during the Kamakura period, it became popular to make explanations, according to esoteric Buddhism, of Ryobu Shinto based on Honji-suijaku setsu, Oharae no Kotoba based on Sanno Shinto and the enshrined deities of deities and shrines appeared in Kiki-shinwa (the Kojiki, Nihonshoki and mythology).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, during the Kamakura period, it became popular to make explanations, according to esoteric Buddhism, of Ryobu Shinto based on Honji-suijaku setsu, Oharae no Kotoba based on Sanno Shinto and the enshrined deities of deities and shrines appeared in Kiki-shinwa (the Kojiki, Nihonshoki and mythology).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>いわゆる中世日本紀といわれる現象が見られるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The phenomenon is so-called chusei Nihongi (medieval Nihongi).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The phenomenon is so-called chusei Nihongi (medieval Nihongi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The phenomenon is so-called chusei Nihongi (medieval Nihongi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="65">
<j>ただし仏教の天部の神々も元はヒンドゥー教の神であったように、日本だけでなくインドの地域社会や中国においても、それら土着民族の神々を包摂してきた歴史がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Historically, Buddhism had connoted local deities not only in Japan but also in India and China; the gods of the Buddhistic Tenbu were originally the deities of Hinduism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historically, Buddhism had connoted local deities not only in Japan but also in India and China; the gods of the Buddhistic Tenbu were originally the deities of Hinduism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historically, Buddhism had connoted local deities not only in Japan but also in India and China; the gods of the Buddhistic Tenbu were originally the deities of Hinduism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>仏教にはそのような性質がもともと具わっていたことが神仏習合を生んだ大きな要因であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such nature of Buddhism was the key factor of the birth of shinbutsu-shugo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such nature of Buddhism was the key factor of the birth of shinbutsu-shugo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such nature of Buddhism was the key factor of the birth of shinbutsu-shugo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>神本仏迹説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinponbutsujaku setsu</e>
<cmt>神本仏迹説：定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinponbutsujaku setsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinponbutsujaku setsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="67">
<j>鎌倉時代末期から南北朝時代 (日本)になると、僧侶による神道説に対する反動から、逆に、神こそが本地であり仏は仮の姿であるとする神本仏迹説を唱える伊勢神道や吉田神道が現れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the end of the Kamakura period to the Period of the Northern and Southern Courts, Ise Shintoism and Yoshida Shintoism appeared; they advanced the Shinponbutsujaku setsu, insisting that their deity was honji while the Buddha was incarnation, objecting Buddhist priests&apos; Shintoism view.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the end of the Kamakura period to the Period of the Northern and Southern Courts, Ise Shintoism and Yoshida Shintoism appeared; they advanced the Shinponbutsujaku setsu, insisting that their deity was honji while the Buddha was an incarnation, objecting to the Buddhist priests&apos; Shintoism view.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the end of the Kamakura period to the Period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), Ise Shintoism and Yoshida Shintoism appeared; they advanced the Shinponbutsujaku setsu, insisting that their deity was honji while the Buddha was an incarnation, objecting to the Buddhist priests&apos; Shintoism view.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>江戸時代には朱子学の理論により両派を統合した垂加神道が誕生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period, Suika Shinto, which integrated both schools by the theory of the Neo-Confucianism, appeared.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo period, Suika Shinto, which integrated both schools with the theory of Neo-Confucianism, appeared.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period, Suika Shinto, which integrated both schools with the theory of Neo-Confucianism, appeared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>これらは神祇信仰の主流派の教義となっていき、神道としての教義確立に貢献した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They served as doctrine of the mainstream faction of Jingi belief, and contributed to the doctrine establishment of Shintoism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They served as doctrine of the mainstream faction of Jingi belief, and contributed to the doctrine establishment of Shintoism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They served as doctrine of the mainstream faction of Jingi belief, and contributed to the doctrine establishment of Shintoism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="70">
<j>しかし、神仏習合の考え自体は明治時代の神仏分離まで衰えることなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, shinbutsu-shugo thought itself had undiminished until the &quot;separation of Buddhism and Shintoism&quot; in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, shinbutsu-shugo thought itself undiminished until the &quot;separation of Buddhism and Shintoism&quot; during the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, shinbutsu-shugo thought itself undiminished until the &quot;separation of Buddhism and Shintoism&quot; during the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>近現代においても日本人の精神構造に影響を及ぼしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has also influenced mental structures of Japanese in modern times and the present day.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has also influenced the mentality of Japanese in modern times and the present day.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has also influenced the mentality of Japanese in modern times and the present day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tau(id:629), Decchi(id:170970), 浩(id:70121), Deepimpact(id:129352), Tangmo(id:86444), Nnh(id:474), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Stanislaus(id:1806), Law soma(id:45202), Punipico(id:25163), Kahusi(id:1523), Tiyoringo(id:70026), Fenice(id:11886), Aibot(id:104981), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Ons(id:21830), Gombe(id:27), Johncapistrano(id:969), Interregnum(id:25269), らりた(id:1327), Kyube(id:9866), Boca samba(id:137526), Ash(id:15625), Loveless(id:129239), Shimoxx(id:9332), Peccafly(id:54812), 梅の里(id:15035), 巣に帰れ(id:208008), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>