<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>京都電燈</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Dento</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Dento</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Dento</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>京都電燈株式会社（きょうとでんとう）は、1888年（明治21年）に創立された日本の電力会社。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Dento was a Japanese electric power company founded in 1888.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Dento was a Japanese electric power company founded in 1888.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Dento was a Japanese electric power company founded in 1888.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>近畿地方から北陸地方にかけての地域をテリトリーとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The territory of the company was Kinki region and Hokuriku region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The territory of the company were the Kinki and Hokuriku regions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The territory of the company were the Kinki and Hokuriku regions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>戦時統制によって1942年（昭和17年）に解散。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the government control during the World War II, it was dissolved in 1942.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under government control during World War II, it was dissolved in 1942.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under government control during World War II, it was dissolved in 1942.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="4">
<j>日本初の営業用水力発電である琵琶湖疏水の蹴上発電所（発電所は京都市営）から生み出される当時としては大量の電力を背景として、発電コストを低下させ電灯料金も引き下げ、電灯の本格的普及に貢献した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Dento contributed to the widespread installation of electric lamps by lowering the cost of power generation and the price of the electric lamps by drawing on the large amount (for that time) of electricity generated in Keage Power Plant (run by Kyoto City) on Lake Biwa Canal, which was the first commercial hydraulic power generation in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Dento contributed to the widespread installation of electric lamps by lowering the cost of power generation and the price of electric lamps by drawing on the large amount (for that time) of electricity generated at the Keage Power Plant (run by Kyoto City) on Lake Biwa Canal, which was the first commercial hydraulic power generation in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Dento contributed to the widespread installation of electric lamps by lowering the cost of power generation and the price of electric lamps by drawing on the large amount (for that time) of electricity generated at the Keage Power Plant (run by Kyoto City) on Lake Biwa Canal, which was the first commercial hydraulic power generation in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また京都電燈から供給される豊富な電力は、京都市の産業振興に大きく貢献し、日本初の路面電車である京都電気鉄道（後に京都市電へ買収）を1895年（明治28年）に走らせる事にもつながった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The large amount of electricity supplied by Kyoto Dento also greatly contributed to the industrial development of Kyoto City, as it led to the inauguration of Kyoto Electric Railway (later sold to Kyoto City Trams), which was the first Japanese electric tramway, in 1895.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The large amount of electricity supplied by Kyoto Dento also greatly contributed to the industrial development of Kyoto City, as it led to the inauguration of Kyoto Electric Railway (later sold to Kyoto City Trams), which was the first Japanese electric tramway, in 1895.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The large amount of electricity supplied by Kyoto Dento also greatly contributed to the industrial development of Kyoto City, as it led to the inauguration of Kyoto Electric Railway (later sold to Kyoto City Trams), which was the first Japanese electric tramway, in 1895.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>京都電燈は、1888年（明治21年）4月、京都電燈会社として創立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Dento was established as Kyoto Dento Gaisha in April 1888.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Dento was established as Kyoto Dento Gaisha in April 1888.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Dento was established as Kyoto Dento Gaisha in April 1888.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>（1893年（明治26年）2月に京都電燈株式会社に改称。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(it was renamed Kyoto Dento Kabushiki Gaisha in February 1893.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(it was renamed Kyoto Dento Kabushiki Gaisha in February 1893.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(it was renamed Kyoto Dento Kabushiki Gaisha in February 1893.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>翌1889年（明治22年）7月21日に全国で4番目の電燈会社として、高瀬川 (京都府)西岸に社屋を設け営業を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 21 in the following year of 1889, the business started as the forth electric power company in Japan, and a company headquarter was built on the west bank of Takase-gawa River (Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 21 in the following year of 1889, the business started as the forth electric power company in Japan, and the company headquarters were built on the west bank of Takase-gawa River (Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 21 in the following year of 1889, the business started as the forth electric power company in Japan, and the company headquarters were built on the west bank of Takase-gawa River (Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>当初は会社敷地内で石炭による火力発電を行い、直流による近距離低圧配電を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, coal-fired thermal power was generated within the company premises, and the short-distance and low-voltage power distribution, which was operated on direct current, was carried out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, coal-fired thermal power was generated within the company premises, and short-distance, low-voltage power distribution, operated on direct current, was carried out.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, coal-fired thermal power was generated within the company premises, and short-distance, low-voltage power distribution, operated on direct current, was carried out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>琵琶湖疏水の蹴上発電所が市営事業として営業を開始した後、1892年（明治25年）に京都電燈は火力発電を廃止し蹴上発電所からの電力の供給を受けることを願い出、許可を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Keage Power Plant on Lake Biwa Canal started its city-run business, Kyoto Dento applied in 1892 to have its power supply from Keage Power Plant and to stop the thermal power generation, and their application was accepted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Keage Power Plant on Lake Biwa Canal started its city-run business, Kyoto Dento applied in 1892 to have its power supply from Keage Power Plant in order to stop thermal power generation, and their application was accepted.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Keage Power Plant on Lake Biwa Canal started its city-run business, Kyoto Dento applied in 1892 to have its power supply from Keage Power Plant in order to stop thermal power generation, and their application was accepted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>これを契機に低圧直流から高圧交流への転換を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon this occasion, high-voltage direct current was switched to high-voltage alternate current.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this occasion, high-voltage direct current was switched to high-voltage alternating current.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this occasion, high-voltage direct current was switched to high-voltage alternating current.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>石炭火力は1894年（明治27年）にいったん全廃するものの、その後需要の増加に伴い復活し、1900年（明治33年）には新たな火力発電所である東九条発電所を着工することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the coal-fired power generation was stopped in 1894, a new thermal power plant, Higashikujo Power Plant, was started in 1900 in response to the increasing demand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although coal-fired power generation stopped in 1894, the new thermal power plant, Higashikujo Power Plant, was started in 1900 in response to the increasing demand.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although coal-fired power generation stopped in 1894, the new thermal power plant, Higashikujo Power Plant, was started in 1900 in response to the increasing demand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>その後、1914年（大正3年）からは京都府と福井県において鉄道業を行うようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since 1914, Kyoto Dento started railway businesses in Kyoto Prefecture and Fukui Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1914, Kyoto Dento started a railway businesses in Kyoto and Fukui Prefectures.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1914, Kyoto Dento started a railway businesses in Kyoto and Fukui Prefectures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これは安定した電力の供給先を確保するのが目的で、戦前は東京電燈（後の江ノ島電鉄線や東武伊香保軌道線などが該当）など多くの会社で行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was to ensure stable supply destinations of electricity, and it was a common practice for many companies such as Tokyo Dento (which established subsequent Enoshima Electric Railway and Tobu Ikaho Permanent Way) before the World War II.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was to ensure stable supply destinations of electricity, and it was a common practice for many companies such as Tokyo Dento (which established the subsequent Enoshima Electric Railway and Tobu Ikaho Permanent Way) before World War II.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was to ensure stable supply destinations of electricity, and it was a common practice for many companies such as Tokyo Dento (which established the subsequent Enoshima Electric Railway and Tobu Ikaho Permanent Way) before World War II.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>1918年（大正7年）には、京福電気鉄道嵐山本線を合併した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1918, Kyoto Dento merged Arashiyama Main Line of Keifuku Electric Railroad.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1918, Kyoto Dento merged with the Arashiyama Main Line of Keifuku Electric Railroad.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1918, Kyoto Dento merged with the Arashiyama Main Line of Keifuku Electric Railroad.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>1925年（大正14年）9月27日 にはそのノウハウを生かして叡山電鉄叡山本線を開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 27, 1925, the company opened Eizan Main Line, Eizan Electric Railway by utilizing their knowhow in the business.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 27, 1925, the company opened the Eizan Main Line, Eizan Electric Railway by utilizing their knowhow in the business.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 27, 1925, the company opened the Eizan Main Line, Eizan Electric Railway by utilizing their knowhow in the business.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>1927年（昭和2年）には子会社として鞍馬電気鉄道を設立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1927, the subsidiary company, Kurama Electric Railway, was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1927, a subsidiary company, Kurama Electric Railway, was established.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1927, a subsidiary company, Kurama Electric Railway, was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>そして沿線のバス会社と猛烈な乗客争奪合戦を繰り広げた後傘下に収めた（京都バスの前身）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Dento competed fiercely with other bus companies of the area for customers, and eventually succeeded in making them subsidiary companies (former Kyoto Bus).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処をしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Dento competed fiercely with other bus companies of the area for customers, and eventually succeeded in making them subsidiary companies (former Kyoto Bus).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Dento competed fiercely with other bus companies of the area for customers, and eventually succeeded in making them subsidiary companies (former Kyoto Bus).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>事実上、洛北、嵐山方面の交通機関を一手に担うこととなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It virtually controlled all the transportation system in Rakuhoku and Arashiyama areas.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処をしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It virtually controlled all the transportation systems in the Rakuhoku and Arashiyama areas.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It virtually controlled all the transportation systems in the Rakuhoku and Arashiyama areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="20">
<j>戦時統制により、1941年（昭和16年）に発送電部門と配電部門の出資命令が出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the government control during the World War II, the contribution from the electric power generation and transmission department and the electric power distribution department was ordered in 1941.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under government control during World War II, the contribution from the electric power generation and transmission department and the electric power distribution department was ordered in 1941.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under government control during World War II, the contribution from the electric power generation and transmission department and the electric power distribution department was ordered in 1941.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="21">
<j>鉄道業等の陸上輸送事業は、1942年（昭和17年）3月に京福電気鉄道として分離発足した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The land transportation business, such as the railway business, was started separately with the foundation of Keifuku Electric Railroad in March 1942.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The land transportation business, such as the railway business, was started separately with the foundation of Keifuku Electric Railroad in March 1942.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The land transportation business, such as the railway business, was started separately with the foundation of Keifuku Electric Railroad in March 1942.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="22">
<j>同年4月1日に発送電部門を日本発送電、配電部門を関西配電、北陸配電に出資、以降清算に入り、1944年（昭和19年）に、清算を完了した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 1, 1942, the electric power generation and transmission department of Kyoto Dento contributed to Japan Electric Generation and Transmission Company and the electric power distribution department contributed to Kanasai Haiden and Hokuriku Haiden, and at the same time the liquidation of the company started, which was completed in 1944.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 1, 1942, the electric power generation and transmission department of Kyoto Dento contributed to Japan Electric Generation and Transmission Company and the electric power distribution department contributed to Kanasai Haiden and Hokuriku Haiden, and at the same time the liquidation of the company started, which was completed in 1944.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 1, 1942, the electric power generation and transmission department of Kyoto Dento contributed to Japan Electric Generation and Transmission Company and the electric power distribution department contributed to Kanasai Haiden and Hokuriku Haiden, and at the same time the liquidation of the company started, which was completed in 1944.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="23">
<j>その後京福電気鉄道は、京都電燈の鉄道子会社を統合していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keifuku Electric Railroad then merged the subsidiary railway companies of Kyoto Dento.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keifuku Electric Railroad then merged the subsidiary railway companies of Kyoto Dento.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keifuku Electric Railroad then merged the subsidiary railway companies of Kyoto Dento.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>1946年（昭和21年）に京都バスを設立して京都電燈の傘下であった京都地区のバス会社をまとめ、1950年（昭和25年）頃には京都と福井で合わせて120.9kmもの路線網を擁することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1946, Kyoto Bus was founded by merging the subsidiary bus companies of Kyoto Dento in Kyoto area, which came to cover the routes of 120.9km in Kyoto and Fukui by 1950.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処をしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1946, Kyoto Bus was founded by merging the subsidiary bus companies of Kyoto Dento in the Kyoto area, which eventually covered the routes consisting of 120.9km in Kyoto and Fukui by 1950.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1946, Kyoto Bus was founded by merging the subsidiary bus companies of Kyoto Dento in the Kyoto area, which eventually covered the routes consisting of 120.9 km in Kyoto and Fukui by 1950.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>しかし小規模な路線が多く経営的には苦しく、1955年（昭和30年）頃から比叡山方面への進出をもくろむ京阪電気鉄道の傘下となっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as the managing of many small-scale routes led to the financially difficulty for the company, from around 1955, many routes were sold to Keihan Electric Railway, which was planning to extend their business in the Hiei-zan Mountain area.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処をしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, managing many small-scale routes led to the financial difficulties for the company, from around 1955, many routes were sold to Keihan Electric Railway, which was planning to extend their business in the Hiei-zan Mountain area.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, managing many small-scale routes led to the financial difficulties for the company, from around 1955, many routes were sold to Keihan Electric Railway, which was planning to extend their business in the Mt. Hiei area.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>不採算路線の廃止、1986年（昭和61年）に叡山電鉄の分社化、2003年（平成15年）に福井県における鉄道事業の廃止（一部路線はえちぜん鉄道が継承）をおこなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The non-profitable lines were abandoned, Eizan Electric Railway was split-up in 1986, and the railway business in Fukui Prefecture was discontinued in 2003 (except a part of lines which was inherited by Echizen Railway).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処をしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The non-profitable lines were abandoned, Eizan Electric Railway was split-up in 1986, and the railway business in Fukui Prefecture was discontinued in 2003 (except for part of the lines inherited by Echizen Railway).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The non-profitable lines were abandoned, Eizan Electric Railway was split-up in 1986, and the railway business in Fukui Prefecture was discontinued in 2003 (except for part of the lines inherited by Echizen Railway).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>その結果、2009年（平成21年）現在では、鉄道事業としては京福電気鉄道嵐山本線、京福電気鉄道北野線、京福電気鉄道鋼索線（叡山ケーブル）、叡山ロープウェイの4路線12.8kmを残すのみとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today in 2009, four remaining lines, which are Arashiyama Main Line of Keifuku Electric Railroad, Kitano Line of Keifuku Electric Railroad, Kosaku Line of Keifuku Electric Railroad (Eizan Cable), and Eizan Ropeway, covering 12.8km, are still in operation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処をしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today in 2009, four remaining lines, which are Arashiyama Main Line of Keifuku Electric Railroad, Kitano Line of Keifuku Electric Railroad, Kosaku Line of Keifuku Electric Railroad (Eizan Cable), and Eizan Ropeway, covering 12.8km, are still in operation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today in 2009, four remaining lines, which are Arashiyama Main Line of Keifuku Electric Railroad, Kitano Line of Keifuku Electric Railroad, Kosaku Line of Keifuku Electric Railroad (Eizan Cable), and Eizan Ropeway, covering 12.8 km, are still in operation.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>JR京都駅の烏丸口（北口）側にある関西電力京都支店の建物（鉄筋コンクリート造8階建）は、京都の近代建築の一つであるが、もともとは1937年（昭和12年）に、京都電燈の本社として建設されたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 8 storey reinforced concrete building of the Kyoto branch of Kansai Electric Power, which stands in front of the Karasuma Exit (North Exit) of JR Kyoto Station, is one of the modernist buildings in Kyoto and was originally built as the headquarter of Kyoto Dento in 1937.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The eight storey reinforced concrete building of the Kyoto branch of the Kansai Electric Power, which stands in front of the Karasuma Exit (North Exit) of JR Kyoto Station, is one of the most modern buildings in Kyoto and was originally built as the headquarters of Kyoto Dento in 1937.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The eight storey reinforced concrete building of the Kyoto branch of the Kansai Electric Power, which stands in front of the Karasuma Exit (North Exit) of JR Kyoto Station, is one of the most modern buildings in Kyoto and was originally built as the headquarters of Kyoto Dento in 1937.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 七之輔(id:55793), Straysheep(id:42448), Ignis(id:28979), Y3006(id:155535), Unamu(id:14627), 三菱善次郎(id:21924), 210.(id:9838), うら(id:40695), Shinkansen(id:13703), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>