<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>旗本札</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hatamoto-satsu (a local money in the Edo period)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hatamoto-satsu (a local currency during the Edo period)</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hatamoto-satsu (a local currency during the Edo period)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>旗本札（はたもとさつ）は、江戸時代に領地を持つ旗本が自領内において独自に発行した紙幣である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hatamoto-satsu was the paper money that a Hatamoto (a direct retainer of the bakufu) who possessed his own territory in the Edo period issued independently in his own territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hatamoto-satsu was the paper money that a Hatamoto (a direct retainer of the bakufu) who possessed his own territory in the Edo period issued independently in his own territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hatamoto-satsu was the paper money that a hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu [Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun]) who possessed his or her own territory in the Edo period issued independently in his or her own territory.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>旗本札は、その名の通り江戸時代に旗本が知行地において発行した紙幣である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As shown in its name, Hatamoto-satsu was the paper money that a Hatamoto issued in his chigyo-chi (territory) in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As is evident in the name, Hatamoto-satsu was paper money that a Hatamoto issued in his chigyo-chi (territory) during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As is evident in the name, Hatamoto-satsu was paper money that a Hatamoto issued in his chigyo-chi (territory) during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>旗本の知行地は通例として藩とは呼ばれないため、藩札とは区別する用語としてこのように呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because the chigyo-chi of Hatamoto was not called Han (a domain), the paper money was called in the term to differentiate it from Han-satsu (the paper money issued by a domain).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the chigyo-chi of Hatamoto was not called Han (a domain), this paper money was called as such to differentiate it from Han-satsu (the paper money issued by a domain).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the chigyo-chi of Hatamoto was not called Han (a domain) in general, this paper money was called as such to differentiate it from Han-satsu (the paper money issued by a clan).</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>しかし、その発行・運用形態は藩札と非常に類似しているため、広義の藩札として扱われる場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since being issued and operated in quite similar ways as Han-satsu was, Hatamoto-satsu is sometimes dealt with as Han-satsu in a broad sense.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since it was issued and operated in a manner that was quite similar to Han-satsu, Hatamoto-satsu is sometimes treated as Han-satsu in a general sense.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since it was issued and operated in a manner that was quite similar to Han-satsu, Hatamoto-satsu is sometimes treated as Han-satsu in a broad sense.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>旗本の知行地は、江戸がある武蔵国を中心とした関東地方にも広く存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The chigyo-chi of Hatamoto existed widely in the Kanto region centered on Musashi Province where Edo was located.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The chigyo-chi of Hatamoto existed widely in the Kanto region centered on Musashi Province where Edo was located.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The chigyo-chi of Hatamoto existed widely in the Kanto region centered on Musashi Province where Edo was located.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>しかしながら、これらの地域において旗本札が発行されたという記録はなく、信濃国・三河国以西、九州地方まで、特に近畿地方（近江国・大和国・摂津国・丹波国・但馬国・播磨国）及び中国地方の備中国といった地域に発行例が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, while no record that Hatamoto-satsu was issued in this region exists, many records that such money was issued in the following areas exist: the areas from Shinano Province and Mikawa Province to the Kyushu region, in particular, the Kinki region (Omi Province, Yamato Province, Settsu Province, Tanba Province, Tajima Province, and Harima Province) and Bicchu Province in the Chugoku region.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, while no record exists that Hatamoto-satsu was issued in this region, many records exist concerning money being issued in the following areas; areas from Shinano Province and Mikawa Province to the Kyushu region, in particular, the Kinki region (Omi Province, Yamato Province, Settsu Province, Tanba Province, Tajima Province, and Harima Province) and Bicchu Province in the Chugoku region.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, while no record exists that Hatamoto-satsu was issued in this region, many records exist concerning money being issued in the following areas; western areas from Shinano Province and Mikawa Province to the Kyushu region, in particular, the Kinki region (Omi Province, Yamato Province, Settsu Province, Tanba Province, Tajima Province, and Harima Province) and Bitchu Province in the Chugoku region.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>関東地方は幕府のお膝下にあってその統制力は強く、また札遣いは銀遣い経済の地域である西国で盛んであったことなどが原因であろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This situation would have been generated due to the following reasons: The Kanto region, where the base of bakufu was located, was strongly controlled by the bakufu, and as economy was based on silver in Saigoku (the western region of Japan), more paper money was used there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This situation would have been caused by the following reasons: The Kanto region, which was the base of the bakufu, was strongly controlled by the bakufu, and as the economy was based on silver in Saigoku (the western region of Japan), more paper money was used there.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This situation would have been caused by the following reasons: The Kanto region, which was the base of the bakufu, was strongly controlled by the bakufu, and as the economy was based on silver in Saigoku (the western region of Japan), more paper money was used there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>なお、関東諸藩の場合も、西国の飛地領における発行例を除外すれば、明治維新前には藩札を発行していない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The domains in the Kanto region did not issue Han-satsu before Meiji Restoration, except in the territories that they had in Saigoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The domains in the Kanto region did not issue Han-satsu before the Meiji Restoration, except in the Saigoku.territories.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clans in the Kanto region did not issue Han-satsu before the Meiji Restoration, except the issuance in the tobichi (detached land) territory in Saigoku.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>畿内に飛地領を有する藩が関東の所領で藩札の発行を試みたが、領民が札遣いに馴染みがなく中止された例もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some domains in the Kanto region that had their territories in the Kinai region (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto) attempted to issue Han-satsu in their own domains in the Kanto region, but the issuance was forced to be stopped because the peoples in these domains were not familiar with use of paper money.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some domains in the Kanto region that had their territories in the Kinai region (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto) attempted to issue Han-satsu in their own domains in the Kanto region, however the currency had to be halted as people in these domains were not familiar with the use of paper money.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some clans in the Kanto region that had their tobichi territories in the Kinai region (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto) attempted to issue Han-satsu in their own clans in the Kanto region, however the currency had to be halted as people in these clans were not familiar with the use of paper money.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>近畿諸国及び備中国においては、幕府領、諸藩領、他地方の藩の飛地領、御三卿領、旗本領などがモザイク状に入り組んでおり、商品経済の先進地域でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the provinces in the Kinki region and in Bicchu Province, bakufu&apos;s territories, domains&apos; territories, the territories owned by remotely-located domains, the territories of Gosankyo (three privileged branch families of the Tokugawa family), and Hatamoto&apos;s territories existed mixed quite complicatedly, and commodity economy had advanced in these areas.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the provinces in the Kinki region and in Bicchu Province, bakufu&apos;s territories, domains&apos; territories, the territories owned by remotely-located domains, the territories of Gosankyo (three privileged branch families of the Tokugawa family), and Hatamoto&apos;s territories existed mixed quite complicatedly, and commodity economy had advanced in these areas.</e>
<cmt>Translation doesn’t make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The provinces in the Kinki region and in Bitchu Province, where bakufu&apos;s territories, clans&apos; territories, the tobichi territories in other clans, the territories of Gosankyo (three privileged branch families of the Tokugawa family), and Hatamoto&apos;s territories mixed quite complicatedly, were the area of advanced commodity economy as well.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>そのため、他領地との取引が諸領の経済活動に占める割合が非常に大きかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, transactions with other territories occupied large portions of economic activities in these areas.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, transactions with other territories comprised a large portion of economic activities in these areas.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, transactions with other territories comprised a large portion of economic activities in these areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また江戸時代後期以降は幕府の意図的な銀単位通貨流通量抑制政策のために手形や藩札類による取引も盛んであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, in the latter half of the Edo period, the bakufu took the policy of intentionally controlling the amount of the silver-based currencies circulated, and therefore, lots of promissory notes and Han-satsu were used for transactions.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, during the latter half of the Edo period, the bakufu took the policy of intentionally controlling the amount of the silver-based currencies that was being circulated, and therefore, lots of promissory notes and Han-satsu were used for transactions.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, after the late Edo period, the bakufu took the policy of intentionally controlling the amount of the silver-based currencies that was being circulated, and therefore, lots of promissory notes and Han-satsu were used for transactions.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>そのため、旗本領でも領外の藩札などが流入し、自領の経済が悪化するという悪影響が少なからず生じていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently, the economy in Hatamoto&apos;s territories became quite badly affected by inflow of Han-satsu and the like from other territories.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, the economy in Hatamoto&apos;s territories was quite negatively affected by the inflow of Han-satsu and the like from other territories.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, the economy in Hatamoto&apos;s territories was quite negatively affected by the inflow of Han-satsu and the like from other territories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>それを防ぐための自衛策として、小藩や関東諸藩の飛び地領などと同様に独自の紙幣を発行せざるを得ない場合も少なくなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a self defense measure to prevent such a situation from occurring, not a few Hatamoto&apos;s territories were forced to issue their own paper money just as small-sized domains and the territories owned by remote domains in the Kanto region were.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to prevent this situation from occuring, not a few of Hatamoto&apos;s territories were forced to issue their own paper money as small-sized domains and the territories owned by remote domains in the Kanto region were.</e>
<cmt>&quot;territories owned by remote domains in the Kanto region were.&quot; translation doesn’t make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to prevent this situation from occurring, not a few Hatamoto territories were forced to issue their own paper money as small clans and the tobichi territories of the clans in the Kanto region were.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>その一方で、石高が1万石に満たないために旗本とされながら、参勤交代を行い、大名と同様の支配体制を保障された交代寄合は、やや主体性の高い紙幣発行の事情があった可能性も考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, for the Hatamoto with the Kotaiyoriai status, who were Hatamoto because their earnings were a less than 10,00 0 koku of rice crop (approx. 180 liters/koku) but were obliged to keep Sankinkotai (a system under which feudal lords in the Edo period were required to spend every other year in residence in Edo) and were entitled to use of the territory control system similar to those of daimyo, it is also considered that there might have been slightly more independent situations to issue paper money.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, for the Hatamoto with Kotaiyoriai status, who were Hatamoto because their earnings were less than 10,000 koku of rice (approx. 180 liters/koku) but at the same time were obliged to keep Sankinkotai (a system under which feudal lords in the Edo period were required to spend every other year residing in Edo) and were entitled to use of the territory control system similar to those of daimyo, it is also considered that there might have been slightly more independent situations to issue paper money.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, for the kotaiyoriai (alternate yoriai, a family status of samurai warriors in the Edo period), that were Hatamoto but were obliged to keep Sankinkotai (a system under which feudal lords in the Edo period were required to spend every other year residing in Edo) and ensured the control system similar to that of daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) because their earnings were less than 10,000 koku of rice (approximately 180 liters per koku), it is also considered that there might have been slightly more independent situations to issue paper money.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>また、特殊な例として、三河国宝飯郡長澤の旗本松平氏の紙幣がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular, the paper money by the Matsudaira family in Nagasawa, Hoi County, Mikawa Province was exceptional.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, the paper money by the Matsudaira family in Nagasawa, Hoi County, Mikawa Province was exceptional.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, the paper money by the Hatamoto, the Matsudaira family in Nagasawa, Hoi County, Mikawa Province was exceptional case.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>長沢松平家は、徳川将軍家に近い家系のため格式が高く、交代寄合の待遇を受けていたが、200石の知行しか持たなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being provided with a high status due to its close relationship with the Tokugawa shogun family, the Matsudaira family in Nagasawa was treated as Hatamoto with the Kotaiyoriai status, but earned only a 200 koku of rice crop for chigyo (control of a territory).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Being provided a high status due to its close relationship with the Tokugawa shogun family, the Matsudaira family in Nagasawa was treated as Hatamoto with Kotaiyoriai status, but earned only 200 koku of rice for chigyo (control of a territory).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Being provided a high status due to its close relationship with the Tokugawa shogun family, the Matsudaira family in Nagasawa was treated as Hatamoto with the kotaiyoriai status, but earned only 200 koku of rice for chigyo (control of a territory).</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>このため、幕府から紙幣発行権の許可を得て、その権利を各地の町村などに紙幣発行の法的及び信用上の裏付けとして提供することにより収入確保を図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, obtaining the right to issue paper money from the Bakufu, the family provided the right to towns and villages as the legal guarantee of issuing paper money and as the credibility of such money, to secure income.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, after obtaining the right to issue paper money from the Bakufu, the family provided the right to towns and villages as the legal guarantee of issuing paper money and as the credibility of such money, to secure income.</e>
<cmt>&quot;and as the credibility of such money, to secure income.&quot; doesn’t make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, after allowance of the right to issue paper money from the bakufu, the family provided the right to towns and villages as the legal guarantee of issuing paper money and as the credibility of such money, to secure income.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>この形態の長澤松平氏の旗本札は、近江・大和・河内国・和泉国・播磨・備中などの諸国で発行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hatamoto-satsu in this style by the Matsudaira family in Nagasawa was issued in Omi Province, in Yamato Province, in Kawachi Province, in Izumi Province, in Harima Province, and in Bicchu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hatamoto-satsu in the of the Matsudaira family in Nagasawa was issued in Omi Province, in Yamato Province, in Kawachi Province, in Izumi Province, in Harima Province, and in Bicchu Province.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hatamoto-satsu of the Nagasawa-Matsudaira family was issued in several provinces such as Omi, Yamato, Kawachi, Izumi, Harima, and Bitchu.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="20">
<j>明治4年（1871年）に新政府が新通貨制度の構築のために藩札類の発行状況を調べた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1871, the new government checked the Han-satsu and the like that had been issued, to establish a new currency system.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1871, the new government checked the Han-satsu and the like that had been issued, to establish a new currency system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1871, the new government checked the Han-satsu and the like that had been issued, to establish a new currency system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>そこで、全国の藩の約8割に当たる244藩、14の代官所、9の旗本領が紙幣の発行を確認し、これらは全て紙幣ごとに新貨交換比率が設定されて処理された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, confirming that 244 domains, approx. 80% of all domains in the nation, 14 magistrate&apos;s offices, and nine Hatamoto territories had issued paper money, the government specified a rate of exchanging each of these paper money for a new currency, to correct the situation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, after confirming that 244 domains, approx. 80% of all domains in the nation, 14 magistrate&apos;s offices, and nine Hatamoto territories had issued paper money, the government specified a rate of exchange, to be used to exchange each of these paper moneys for a new currency, to correct the situation.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, after confirming that 244 clans, approximately 80 percents of all clans in the nation, 14 magistrate&apos;s offices, and 9 Hatamoto territories had issued paper money, the government specified a rate of exchange, to be used to exchange each of these paper moneys for a new currency, to correct the situation.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>しかしながら、この紙幣を発行した旗本の数は明治初年の段階で新政府がその実態を把握した数に過ぎない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the number of the Hatamoto who issued the paper money was only that of the Hatamoto who were actually checked by the new government in the early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Hatamoto who issued the paper money were only those of the Hatamoto who were actually checked by the new government during the early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Hatamoto who issued the paper money were only those of the Hatamoto who were actually checked by the new government during the early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>現存する古札類の中には、札面に記された文面から明らかに旗本札に分類されるものが散見され、少なくとも数十の旗本が旗本札を発行していたことが判明している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of the existing old paper money and the like, the one that should be classified apparently into Hatamoto-satsu from the sentences written on the surface of the paper money is sometimes found, and it has been revealed that at least several tens of Hatamoto issued Hatamoto-satsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of the existing old paper money and the like, ones that contain the Hatamoto-satsu written on the surface of the paper money are sometimes found, which can be classified as Hatamoto-satsu, it has been revealed that at least several tens of Hatamoto issued Hatamoto-satsu.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of the existing old paper money and the like, ones that contain the Hatamoto-satsu written on the surface of the paper money are sometimes found, which can be classified as Hatamoto-satsu, it has been revealed that at least several tens of Hatamoto issued Hatamoto-satsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>各地の状況</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Situation in local areas</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Situation in local areas</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Situation in local areas</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>中部地方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Chubu region</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Chubu region</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chubu region</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>信濃国（現・長野県）、三河国（現・愛知県東部）、美濃国（現・岐阜県南部）の3国において旗本札の発行が確認されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been confirmed that Hatamoto-satsu was issued in the three provinces of Shinano Province (present Nagano Prefecture), Mikawa Province (the present eastern part of Aichi Prefecture) and Mino Province (the present southern part of Gifu Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been confirmed that Hatamoto-satsu was issued in the three provinces of Shinano Province (present Nagano Prefecture), Mikawa Province (the present eastern part of Aichi Prefecture) and Mino Province (the present southern part of Gifu Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been confirmed that Hatamoto-satsu was issued in the three provinces of Shinano Province (present Nagano Prefecture), Mikawa Province (the present eastern part of Aichi Prefecture) and Mino Province (the present southern part of Gifu Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>この地域の旗本札の発行元旗本は、多くが交代寄合である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of the Hatamoto who issued Hatamoto-satsu in this region were those with the kotaiyoriai status.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of the Hatamoto who issued Hatamoto-satsu in this region were those with the kotaiyoriai status.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of the Hatamoto who issued Hatamoto-satsu in this region were those with the kotaiyoriai status.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>信濃国・三河国・美濃国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Shinano Province, in Mikawa Province, and in Mino Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Shinano Province, in Mikawa Province, and in Mino Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinano, Mikawa, and Mino Provinces</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>信濃国では、小県郡矢沢（現・長野県上田市殿城）の仙石氏が文久２年（1862年）１２月、幕末の混乱による正銭の流通量減少による商取引上の困難を緩和するために十六文及び二十四文という小額面の銭札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Shinano Province, the Sengoku clan in Yazawa, Chiisagata County issued 16-mon paper money and 24-mon paper money (mon: a currency unit at that time) in December of 1862, to mitigate the difficult situation in trade that had been caused by the shortage of government-issued money due to the confusion towards the end of the bakufu system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Shinano Province, the Sengoku clan in Yazawa, Chiisagata County issued 16-mon paper money and 24-mon paper money (mon: a currency unit at that time) in December of 1862, to mitigate the difficult situation in trade that had been caused by the shortage of government-issued money due to the confusion that occured during the end of the bakufu system.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Shinano Province, the Sengoku clan in Yazawa, Chiisagata County (present Tonoshiro, Ueda City, Nagano Prefecture) issued small amount of zeni-satsu (a kind of Han-satsu) such as 16 mon (a unit of currency) paper money and 24 mon paper money in January 1863, to mitigate the difficult situation in trade that had been caused by the shortage of government-issued money due to the confusion that occurred during the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。「現・長野県上田市殿城」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>また、交代寄合衆の伊那衆である伊那郡伊豆木（現・長野県飯田市伊豆木）の小笠原氏は明治初期に紙幣を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ogasawara clan in Izuki, Ina County (present Izuki, Iida City, Nagano prefecture), who was a member of the Ina group of the Hatamoto with the yoriaikotai-shu status, issued paper money in the early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ogasawara clan in Izuki, Ina County (present Izuki, Iida City, Nagano prefecture), who was a member of the Ina group of the Hatamoto with the yoriaikotai-shu status, issued paper money in the early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ogasawara clan in Izuki, Ina County (present Izuki, Iida City, Nagano Prefecture), who was a member of the Ina group of the Hatamoto with the kotaiyoriai-shu status, issued paper money in the early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>伊豆木小笠原氏の紙幣は、発行が明治2年（1869年）であり、同時期に全国的に発行された諸藩札と同様、明治新政府が発行した太政官札にやや似た様式の札面となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Izuki-Ogasawara clan&apos;s paper money was issued in 1869, and was provided with the surface format style slightly resembling the Daijokan (Grand Council of State)-issued paper money, as the paper money issued by domains in the same era was.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Izuki-Ogasawara clan&apos;s paper money was issued in 1869, and was provided with the surface format style slightly resembling the Daijokan (Grand Council of State)-issued paper money, as the paper money issued by domains in the same era was.</e>
<cmt>Translation doesn’t make sense&quot; as the paper money issued by domains in the same era was.&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Izuki-Ogasawara clan&apos;s paper money issued in 1869 has its surface format style slightly resembling the Daijokan-satsu paper money issued by the Meiji new government, as well as the Han-satsu issued by clans in the same period throughout Japan.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>三河国では、交代寄合表御礼衆の設楽郡新城（現・愛知県新城市新城）の菅沼氏及び交代寄合衆の四衆に準ずる家である宝飯郡長澤（現・愛知県豊川市長沢町）の長沢松平家が紙幣を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Mikawa Province, the Suganuma clan in Shinshiro, Shitara County (present Shinshiro, Shinshiro City, Aichi Prefecture), which was provided with the kotaiyoriai-omoteoreishu status, and the Nagasawa-Matsudaira family in Nagasawa, Hoi County (present Nagasawa-cho, Toyokawa City, Aichi Prefecture), which was provided with the status equivalent to the shishu (四衆) of kotaiyoriai-shu, issued paper money.</e>
<cmt>四衆：　読み、意味ともに調べきれませんでしたので、取り合えず”shishu (四衆)”としてあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Mikawa Province, the Suganuma clan in Shinshiro, Shitara County (present Shinshiro, Shinshiro City, Aichi Prefecture), which was provided with kotaiyoriai-omoteoreishu status, and the Nagasawa-Matsudaira family in Nagasawa, Hoi County (present Nagasawa-cho, Toyokawa City, Aichi Prefecture), which was provided with status equivalent to the shishu (四衆) of kotaiyoriai-shu, issued paper money.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Mikawa Province, the Suganuma clan in Shinshiro, Shitara County (present Shinshiro, Shinshiro City, Aichi Prefecture), which was provided with kotaiyoriai-omoteoreishu (a status of the kotaiyoriai similar to daimyo), and the Nagasawa-Matsudaira family in Nagasawa, Hoi County (present Nagasawa-cho, Toyokawa City, Aichi Prefecture), which was provided with status equivalent to the shishu (four major groups of kotaiyoriai) of kotaiyoriai-shu families, issued paper money.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>新城菅沼氏の紙幣は、その発行地が東海道と信濃国を結ぶ信州街道の物流拠点であったこともあり、東海道の宿駅で発行されたいわゆる宿駅札と似た札様式である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinshiro-Suganuma clan&apos;s paper money had a style resembling the Shukueki-satsu issued in Shukueki (relay station towns) along the Tokaido road, because Shinshiro was located at an important distribution spot connecting the Tokaido road to the Shinano province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinshiro-Suganuma clan&apos;s paper money had a style resembling the Shukueki-satsu issued in Shukueki (relay station towns) along the Tokaido road, because Shinshiro was located at an important distribution spot connecting the Tokaido road to the Shinano province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinshiro-Suganuma clan&apos;s paper money had a style resembling the Shukueki-satsu issued in Shukueki (relay station towns) along the Tokaido road, because it was located at an important distribution spot in the Shinshu-kaido road connecting the Tokaido road to the Shinano Province.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。「信州街道」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>長澤松平氏の紙幣は、上述のように諸国で独自に発行されたため、いずれも発行地の札様式の影響を強く受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As described above, Nagasawa-Matsudaira clan&apos;s paper money was issued in various provinces, and was strongly affected by the money-format style in the area where it was issued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As described above, Nagasawa-Matsudaira clan&apos;s paper money was issued in various provinces, and was strongly affected by the money-format style in the area where it was issued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As previously described, the Nagasawa-Matsudaira clan&apos;s paper money was issued in various provinces independently; it was strongly affected by the money-format style in the area where it was issued.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>いずれも札遣いの盛んな土地であり、大和国、河内国、和泉国、備中国の紙幣では地域特性もあって引請人は多種多様である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each piece of the money was issued in the area where paper money was used widely, and in Yamato Province, in Kawachi Province, in Izumi Province, and in tBicchu Province, various types of persons undertook the paper money.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each piece of money was issued in an area where paper money was used widely, and in Yamato Province, in Kawachi Province, in Izumi Province, and in Bicchu Province, various types of persons used this paper currency.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since several versions of the money were issued in each province, the paper currency in Yamato, Kawachi, Izumi, and Bitchu Provinces were undertaken various people because of the characteristics of the provinces.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="33">
<j>美濃国では、交代寄合表御礼衆である不破郡岩手（現・岐阜県不破郡垂井町岩手）の竹中氏及び交代寄合衆の美濃衆である石津郡多良（現・岐阜県大垣市上石津町宮）の高木氏が紙幣を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Mino Province, the Takenaka clan in Iwate, Fuwa County (present Iwate, Tarui Town, Fuwa County, Gifu Prefecture), which was provided with the kotaiyoriai-omoteoreishu status, and the Takagi clan in Tara, Ishizu County (present, Miya, Kamiishizu-cho, Ogaki City, Gifu Prefecture), which was a member of Mino group of the Hatamoto with the yoriaikotai-shu status, issued paper money.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Mino Province, the Takenaka clan in Iwate, Fuwa County (present Iwate, Tarui Town, Fuwa County, Gifu Prefecture), which was provided with kotaiyoriai-omoteoreishu status, and the Takagi clan in Tara, Ishizu County (present, Miya, Kamiishizu-cho, Ogaki City, Gifu Prefecture), which was a member of Mino group of the Hatamoto with the yoriaikotai-shu status, issued paper money.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Mino Province, the Takenaka clan in Iwate, Fuwa County (present Iwate, Tarui Town, Fuwa County, Gifu Prefecture), which was provided with kotaiyoriai-omoteoreishu status, and the Takagi clan in Tara, Ishizu County (present, Miya, Kamiishizu-cho, Ogaki City, Gifu Prefecture), which was a member of Mino group of the Hatamoto with the yoriaikotai-shu status, issued paper money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>西美濃地方の両氏が発行した紙幣はいずれも、生活必需品であった木炭を売買する際に用いることによって流通を図るべく炭会所が発行した炭代札と呼ばれるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Either of the paper money issued by both clans in the western Mino area was so-called Sumidai-satsu (literally, paper money for charcoal price) issued by Sumikaisho (literally, a charcoal association) to make the money circulated by using it in trading charcoal that was a daily necessity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The paper currencies issued by both clans in the western Mino area was so-called Sumidai-satsu (literally, paper money for charcoal price) issued by Sumikaisho (literally, a charcoal association) to make the money circulated by using it in trading charcoal that was a daily necessity.</e>
<cmt>&quot; to make the money circulated by using it in trading charcoal that was a daily necessity.&quot; doesn’t make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The paper currencies issued by both clans in the western Mino area was so-called Sumidai-satsu (literally, paper money for charcoal price) issued by Sumikaisho (literally, a charcoal association) to make the money circulated by using it in trading charcoal that was a daily necessity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>近畿地方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kinki region</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kinki region</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinki region</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="35">
<j>三都のうちの京・大坂が存在した畿内近国では、紀伊国（現・和歌山県及び三重県南部）や淡路国（現・兵庫県の淡路島全域）などを除いて、関東地方と同様に典型的な非領国地域の状態にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kinai-Kingoku area, where, of the three capitals, Kyoto and Osaka were located, was in the state of a typical hi-ryogokuchiiki area (where the area was divided minutely, with each piece of area owned by a different person) as in the Kanto region, except Kii Province (present Wakayama Prefecture and the southern part of the Mie Prefecture) and Awaji Province (present entire area of the Awaji island).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kinai-Kingoku area, where, of the three capitals, Kyoto and Osaka were located, was in the state of a typical hi-ryogokuchiiki area (where the area was divided minutely, with each piece of area owned by a different person) as in the Kanto region, except Kii Province (present Wakayama Prefecture and the southern part of the Mie Prefecture) and Awaji Province (present entire area of the Awaji island).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Provinces close to Kyoto, where, of the three capitals, Kyoto and Osaka were located, were in the state of a typical hi-ryogokuchiiki area (where the area was divided minutely, with each piece of area owned by a different person) as in the Kanto region, except Kii Province (present Wakayama Prefecture and the southern part of the Mie Prefecture) and Awaji Province (present entire area of the Awaji island in Hyogo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。「兵庫県の」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>旗本札の発行が確認される地域としては、近江国（現・滋賀県）、大和国（現・奈良県）、摂津国（現・大阪府北部及び兵庫県南東部）、河内国（現・大阪府南東部）、和泉国（現・大阪府南西部）、丹波国（現・京都府中部及び兵庫県篠山市・丹波市）、但馬国（現・兵庫県北部）、播磨国（現・兵庫県南西部）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The areas in which the issuance of Hatamoto-satsu was confirmed included the following: the Omi province (present Shiga Prefecture), the Yamato province (present Nara Prefecture), the Settsu province (present northern part of Osaka Prefecture and present southeastern part of the Fyogo Prefecture), the Kawachi province (present southeastern part of Osaka Prefecture), the Izumi province (present southwestern part of Osaka Prefecture), the Tanba province (present central part of Kyoto Prefecture, present Sasayama City and present Tanba City, Fyogo Prefecture), the Tajima province (present northern part of Fyogo Prefecture), and the Harima province (present southwestern part of Hyogo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The areas where Hatamoto-satsu was confirmed to have been issued include the following: the Omi province (present Shiga Prefecture), the Yamato province (present Nara Prefecture), the Settsu province (present northern part of Osaka Prefecture and present southeastern part of the Fyogo Prefecture), the Kawachi province (present southeastern part of Osaka Prefecture), the Izumi province (present southwestern part of Osaka Prefecture), the Tanba province (present central part of Kyoto Prefecture, present Sasayama City and present Tanba City, Fyogo Prefecture), the Tajima province (present northern part of Fyogo Prefecture), and the Harima province (present southwestern part of Hyogo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The provinces where Hatamoto-satsu was confirmed to have been issued were the followings: the Omi Province (present Shiga Prefecture), the Yamato Province (present Nara Prefecture), the Settsu Province (present northern part of Osaka Prefecture and present southeastern part of the Hyogo Prefecture), the Kawachi Province (present southeastern part of Osaka Prefecture), the Izumi Province (present southwestern part of Osaka Prefecture), the Tanba Province (present central part of Kyoto Prefecture, and Sasayama City and Tanba City, Hyogo Prefecture), the Tajima Province (present northern part of Hyogo Prefecture), and the Harima Province (present southwestern part of Hyogo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>スペル、表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="37">
<j>近畿地方は札遣いの中心地であり、旗本の知行地も少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kinki region was located at the center of using paper money, and not a few chigyo-chi territories of Hatamoto existed there as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kinki region was located at the center of the location where the paper currency was used, and not a few chigyo-chi territories of Hatamoto existed there as well.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kinki region was at the center of the location where the Satsu-tsukai (Han-satsu) was used, and not a few chigyo-chi territories of Hatamoto existed there as well.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>このため旗本札の発行も多くの旗本によって行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Hatamoto-satsu was issued by many Hatamoto persons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Hatamoto-satsu was issued by many Hatamoto persons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Hatamoto-satsu was issued by many Hatamoto persons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>国ごとに地域特性もあることから、各国における旗本札発行の状況を示す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because situations depended on the province, how Hatamoto-satsu was issued is described below for each province:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the situation was dependent on the province, how Hatamoto-satsu was issued is described below for each province:</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the situation was dependent on the province, how Hatamoto-satsu was issued is described as follows for each province:</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>近江国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Omi province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Omi province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omi Province</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="40">
<j>近江国における旗本札発行旗本の特徴としては、交代寄合または旗本寄合席といった大身旗本が発行元となっている点が挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The issuance of Hatamoto-satsu in the Omi province was provided with the feature that the money was issued by high-class Hatamoto with the kotaiyoriai or hatamoto-yoriaiseki status.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hatamoto-satsu issued in the Omi province was provided with the feature that the money was issued by high-class Hatamoto with kotaiyoriai or hatamoto-yoriaiseki status.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hatamoto-satsu issued in the Omi Province was provided with the feature that the money was issued by high-class Hatamoto with kotaiyoriai or hatamoto yoriaiseki (a family rank of high-ranking hatamoto, direct vassal of the shogun) status.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>高島郡朽木（現・滋賀県高島市朽木野尻）の朽木氏（交代寄合表御礼衆）は福知山藩朽木家の本家筋で、足利将軍家が有事の際にしばしば頼った名家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kuchiki clan in Kuchiki, Takashima County (present Kuchikinojiri, Takashima City, Shiga Prefecture), from where the Kuchiki family in Fukuchiyama branched, was a distinguished family on which Ashikaga shogun often counted in emergencies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kuchiki clan in Kuchiki, Takashima County (present Kuchikinojiri, Takashima City, Shiga Prefecture), from where the Kuchiki family in Fukuchiyama branched, was a distinguished family on which the Ashikaga shogun often counted on in emergencies.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kuchiki clan (kotaiyoriai-omoteoreishu) in Kuchiki, Takashima County (present Kuchikinojiri, Takashima City, Shiga Prefecture), from where the head family linage of the Kuchiki family in Fukuchiyama clan, was a distinguished family on which the Ashikaga shogun family often counted in emergencies.</e>
<cmt>「交代寄合表御礼衆」を補足し、用語、表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>蒲生郡大森（現・東近江市大森町）の最上氏は、出羽国の名族で山形城主であった最上氏が御家騒動により減知のうえ転封となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mogami clan in Omori, Gamo County (present Omori-cho, Omi City, Shiga Prefecture) was originally a distinguished clan in the Dewa province and the lord of the Yamagata castle, but due to a family trouble, the amount of its chigyo-chi territory was reduced and the territoy of the clan was changed to this place.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mogami clan in Omori, Gamo County (present Omori-cho, Omi City, Shiga Prefecture) was originally a distinguished clan in the Dewa province and the lord of the Yamagata castle, but due to family issues, the amount of its chigyo-chi territory was reduced and the territoy of the clan was changed to this location.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mogami clan in Omori, Gamo County (present Omori-cho, Higashiomi City) was originally a distinguished clan in the Dewa Province and the lord of the Yamagata-jo Castle, but due to family issues, the amount of its chigyo-chi territory was reduced and transferred to this location.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>のち更に減知により国主格のままで交代寄合表御礼衆となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, with its territory further reduced, the clan was provided with the kogoyoriai-omoteoreishu status, while retaining the Kokushu (a daimyo owing a territory) status.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, as its territory was further reduced, the clan was provided with kogoyoriai-omoteoreishu status, while retaining Kokushu (a daimyo owing a territory) status.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, as its territory was further reduced, the clan was provided with kotaiyoriai-omoteoreishu status, while retaining Kokushu (a daimyo owing a territory) status.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>神崎郡伊庭（現・東近江市伊庭町）の三枝氏は、甲斐国の名族で武田氏の重臣であった家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Saigusa clan in Iba, Kanzaki County (present Iba-cho, Higashi-Omi City) was a distinguished clan in the Kai province and its members were vassals to the Takeda clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Saigusa clan in Iba, Kanzaki County (present Iba-cho, Higashi-Omi City) was a distinguished clan in the Kai province and its members were vassals to the Takeda clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Saigusa clan (also referred as the Saegusa clan) in Iba, Kanzaki County (present Iba-cho, Higashiomi City) was a distinguished clan in the Kai Province of which members were senior vassals to the Takeda clan.</e>
<cmt>用語、表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>蒲生郡中山（現・蒲生郡日野町 (滋賀県)中山）の関氏は、伊勢国亀山城主や伯耆国黒坂城主を歴任した大名であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Seki clan in Nakayama, Gamo County (present Nakayama, Hino Town, Gamo County, Shiga Prefecture) had been a Daimyo who assumed the lord of the Kameyama castle in the Ise province and the lord of the Kurosaka castle in the Hoki province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Seki clan in Nakayama, Gamo County (present Nakayama, Hino Town, Gamo County, Shiga Prefecture) had been a Daimyo who assumed the lord of the Kameyama castle in the Ise province and the lord of the Kurosaka castle in the Hoki province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Seki clan in Nakayama, Gamo County (present Nakayama, Hino Town, Gamo County, Shiga Prefecture) had been a daimyo who assumed the lord of the Kameyama-jo Castle in the Ise Province and the lord of the Kurosaka-jo Castle in the Hoki Province.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>しかしながら、御家騒動により領地を没収され、養子が改めて旗本として取り立てられて成立した家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, due to a family trouble, the territory was confiscated, and its adopted son, for whom the Hatamoto status was given anew, established the present Seki family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, due to family issues the territory was confiscated, and its adopted son, for whom the Hatamoto status was given anew, established the present Seki family.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, due to family issues the territory was confiscated, and its adopted son, for whom the Hatamoto status was given a new, established the present Seki family.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>蒲生郡老蘇（現・蒲生郡安土町東老蘇）の根来氏は、紀伊国の根来寺に所属して豊臣秀吉の根来寺攻撃に抵抗し、のちに徳川家に属した成真院盛重の後裔である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Negoro clan in Oiso, Gamo County (present Higashioiso, Azuchi Town, Gamo County), was a descendant of Morishige SEISHININ who belonged to Negoro-ji Temple in Kii Province, resisted attacks on Negoro-ji Temple by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and became to belong to the Tokugawa family later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Negoro clan in Oiso, Gamo County (present Higashioiso, Azuchi Town, Gamo County), was a descendant of Morishige SEISHININ who belonged to Negoro-ji Temple in Kii Province, resisted attacks on Negoro-ji Temple by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and came to belong to the Tokugawa family later.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Negoro clan in Oiso, Gamo County (present Higashioiso, Azuchi Town, Gamo County), was a descendant of Morishige SEISHININ of Negoro-ji Temple in Kii Province who resisted attacks on Negoro-ji Temple by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and came to belong to the Tokugawa family later.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>老蘇根来氏は、陣屋を構えていた老蘇のほかに、大和国宇智郡の領地においても札面が類似した様式の旗本札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to Oiso where the clan had jinya (a regional government office), the Oiso-Negoro clan issued Hatamoto-satsu with similar surface format style, in its territory in Uchi County, Yamato Province, as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to Oiso, where the clan had jinya (a regional government office), the Oiso-Negoro clan issued Hatamoto-satsu with a similar surface format style, in its territory in Uchi County, Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to Oiso, where the clan had jinya (a regional government office), the Oiso-Negoro clan issued Hatamoto-satsu with a similar surface format style, in its territory in Uchi County, Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="49">
<j>近江国の旗本札の特徴としては、銀建て、銭建ての札で、紙幣として使用されることが前提のものでありながら、朽木氏の炭切手、伊庭三枝氏の種切手、中山関氏の豆切手、老蘇根来氏の豆手形、大森最上氏の茶切手というように、いずれも商品切手（商品券）の名目をとっている点がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although assumed to be used as gin-date (payment based on silver) or sen-date (payment based on sen (a unit of currency at that time)) paper money, Hatamoto-satsu in Omi Province was provided with the feature that each piece of the paper money was nominally a stamp for goods (or exchange ticket) in the following way: the Hatamoto-satsu by the Kuchiki clan was issued as Sumi-kitte (stamps for charcoal), that of the Iba-Saegusa clan as Tane-kitte (stamps for seeds), that of the Nakayama-Seki clan as Mame-kitte (stamps for beans), that of the Oiso-Negoro clan as Mame-tegata (promissory notes for beans), and that of the Omori-Mogami clan as Cha-kitte (stamps for tea).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although assumed to be used as gin-date (payment based on silver) or sen-date (payment based on sen (a unit of currency at that time)) paper money, Hatamoto-satsu in Omi Province was provided with the feature that each piece of the paper money was nominally a stamp for goods (or exchange ticket) in the following manner: Hatamoto-satsu by the Kuchiki clan was issued as Sumi-kitte (stamps for charcoal), that of the Iba-Saegusa clan as Tane-kitte (stamps for seeds), that of the Nakayama-Seki clan as Mame-kitte (stamps for beans), that of the Oiso-Negoro clan as Mame-tegata (promissory notes for beans), and that of the Omori-Mogami clan as Cha-kitte (stamps for tea).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although assumed to be used as gin-date (payment based on silver) or sen-date (payment based on sen [a unit of currency at that time]) paper money, Hatamoto-satsu in Omi Province was provided with the feature that each piece of the paper money was nominally a stamp for goods (or exchange ticket) such as follows: Sumi-kitte (stamps for charcoal) issued by the Kuchiki clan, Tane-kitte (stamps for seeds) by the Iba-Saigusa clan, Mame-kitte (stamps for beans) by the Nakayama-Seki clan, Mame-tegata (promissory notes for beans) by the Oiso-Negoro clan, and Cha-kitte (stamps for tea) by the Omori-Mogami clan.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>近江国では、彦根藩札、水口藩札、大溝藩札など、江戸期に発行された同国諸藩の藩札も同様の特徴を有している場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Omi Province, many of the Han-satsu issued in its domains in the Edo period, for example, Han-satsu in the Hikone domain, Han-satsu in the Mizuguchi domain, and Han-satsu in the Omizo domain, were provided with the similar features.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Omi Province, many of the Han-satsu issued in its domains in the Edo period, for example, Han-satsu in the Hikone domain, Han-satsu in the Mizuguchi domain, and Han-satsu in the Omizo domain, were provided with similar features.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Omi Province, many of the Han-satsu issued in its clans in the Edo period such as that issued by the Hikone clan, that by the Mizuguchi clan, and that by the Omizo clan, were provided with similar features.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>大和国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Yamato Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Yamato Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamato Province</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="51">
<j>大和国は日本における商品経済の最先進地域の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamato Province was one of the areas most advanced in commodity economy in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamato Province was an area with one of the most advanced commodity economies in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamato Province was an area with one of the most advanced commodity economies in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>札遣いも、藩札、旗本札のほか、日本最古の紙幣として知られる伊勢国の山田端書に類似した発行形態で、吉野郡の自治組織が幕府の許可を得て発行した御免銀札、大寺院や神社が発行した寺社札など、多種多様な紙幣が発行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to Han-satsu and Hatamoto-satsu, various types of paper money were issued here including the following: the Gomengin-satsu that an autonomous body in Yoshino County issued in a style similar to Yamada-hashigaki in Ise Province, known as the oldest paper money in Japan, by getting approval from the bakufu, and the Jisha-satsu issued by big temples or by big shrines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to Han-satsu and Hatamoto-satsu, various types of paper money were issued here including the following: the Gomengin-satsu that an autonomous body in Yoshino County issued in a style similar to Yamada-hashigaki in Ise Province, known as the oldest paper money in Japan, by getting approval from the bakufu, and the Jisha-satsu issued by big temples or by big shrines.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the Gomengin-satsu that an autonomous body in Yoshino County issued in a style similar to Yamada-hashigaki in Ise Province&quot; doesn’t make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to Han-satsu and Hatamoto-satsu, various types of paper money were issued here including the Gomengin-satsu paper money substituted silver coin which an autonomous body in Yoshino County issued under the allowance of the bakufu with the similar style to Yamada-hagaki in Ise Province, known as the oldest paper money in Japan, and the Jisha-satsu issued by big temples or shrines.</e>
<cmt>読みを変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>また、この地域の経済は、肥料（干鰯や油粕など）の購入や商品作物（木綿、菜種、茶など）の売却のために在郷町が発達し、また主な流通経路である河内国や和泉国との経済的なつながりが強かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this area, Zaigomachi (villages with the function of a town) developed to purchase fertilizers (such as dried sardines and oil cake) and to sell commercial crops (such as cotton, rape, and tea), and this area had strong economical connections with the Kawachi province and Izumi province that were located in the route for distributing the goods produced there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this area, Zaigomachi (villages with the function of a town) developed to purchase fertilizers (such as dried sardines and oil cake) and to sell commercial crops (such as cotton, rape, and tea), and this area had strong economical connections with the Kawachi province and Izumi province that were along the route that distributed the goods produced there.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The economy of this area in which Zaigomachi (villages with the function of a town) developed to purchase fertilizers (such as dried sardines and oil cake) and to sell commercial crops (such as cotton, rape, and tea) had strong economical connections with the Kawachi Province and Izumi Province along the popular distribution channels.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>このため、この地域で発行された藩札、旗本札、寺社札などで、発行元によっては、国を超えてきわめて多様な引請人を持つ場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the Han-satsu, Hatamoto-satsu, and Jisha-satsu issued in this area were undertaken by various persons across the boundaries of the province, depending on the source that issued the paper money.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the Han-satsu, Hatamoto-satsu, and Jisha-satsu issued in this area were undertaken by various persons across the boundaries of the province, depending on the source that issued the paper money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the Han-satsu, Hatamoto-satsu, and Jisha-satsu issued in this area were sometimes undertaken by various persons across the boundaries of the province, depending on the source that issued the paper money.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>また、奈良盆地は米どころであり、米手形形式の銀札の発行例が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because lots of rice crop was produced in the Nara basin, the issuance of gin-satsu (paper money equivalent in value to a silver coin) in the Kome-tegata format (promissory notes for rice crop) was dominant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because lots of rice crops were produced in the Nara basin, gin-satsu (paper money equivalent in value to a silver coin) in the Kome-tegata format (promissory notes for rice crop) dominated the format in which paper money was issued.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because lots of rice crops were produced in the Nara basin, many gin-satsu (paper money equivalent in value to a silver coin) in the Kome-tegata format (promissory notes for rice crop) were issued.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="56">
<j>高市郡曾我（現・橿原市曽我町）の多賀氏は、近江国の領主であったが、浅井長政、豊臣秀長などを経て徳川家の旗本となった家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Taga clan in Soga in Takaichi County (present Soga-cho, Kashiwara City) was originally the lord of Omi Province, but later became Hatamoto of the Tokugawa family after serving Nagamasa ASAI and Hidenaga TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Taga clan in Soga in Takaichi County (present Soga-cho, Kashiwara City) was originally the lord of Omi Province, but later became Hatamoto of the Tokugawa family after serving Nagamasa ASAI and Hidenaga TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Taga clan in Soga, Takaichi County (present Soga-cho, Kashihara City) was originally the lord of Omi Province, but later became Hatamoto of the Tokugawa family after serving Nagamasa AZAI and Hidenaga TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>読みを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>十市郡豊田（現・橿原市豊田町）などを領する佐藤氏は、関ヶ原の戦いで手柄を立て、元から領していた美濃国の所領のほかに、大和国・摂津国・近江国で加増された家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sato clan owning Toyota, Toichi County (present Toyota-cho, Kashiwara City) and other territories accomplished a distinguished achievement, and therefore, gained additional territories in Yamato Province, in Settsu Province and in Omi Province in addition to the territory the clan had originally possessed in the Mino province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sato clan that owned Toyota, Toichi County (present Toyota-cho, Kashiwara City) and other territories accomplished a distinguished achievements in battle, and therefore, gained additional territories in Yamato Province, in Settsu Province and in Omi Province in addition to the territory the clan had originally possessed in the Mino province.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sato clan that owned Toyota, Toichi County (present Toyota-cho, Kashihara City) and other territories accomplished distinguished achievements in the Battle of Sekigahara; therefore, gained additional territories in Yamato Province, Settsu Province and Omi Province in addition to the territory the clan had originally possessed in the Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。読みを修正し、「関ヶ原の」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>宇陀郡福地（現・宇陀市榛原区福地）の織田氏は、織田信長の一子織田信雄の裔で、柏原藩織田氏の分家であり、交代寄合のち高家となった家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Oda family in Fukuchi, Uda County (present Fukuchi, Haibara-ku, Uda City) was a descendant of Nobukatsu ODA, a son of Nobunaga ODA, was a family branched from the Oda family in the Kashiwabara domain, and became provided with the kotaiyoriai-omoteoreishu status.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Oda family in Fukuchi, Uda County (present Fukuchi, Haibara-ku, Uda City) was a descendant of Nobukatsu ODA, a son of Nobunaga ODA, and was a branch of the Oda family in the Kashiwabara domain, and was provided with kotaiyoriai-omoteoreishu status.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Oda family in Fukuchi, Uda County (present Fukuchi, Haibara Ward, Uda City) which was a descendant of Nobukatsu ODA, a son of Nobunaga ODA, was a branch of the Oda family in the Kaibara clan, and became the koke (privileged family under Tokugawa Shogunate) after kotaiyoriai-omoteoreishu status.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。読みを修正し、「高家」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>十市郡田原本（現・磯城郡田原本町）の平野氏は、豊臣秀吉騎下の賤ヶ岳七本槍の一人平野長泰の裔で、交代寄合表御礼衆の家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hirano clan in Tawaramoto, Toichi County (present Tawaramoto town, Shiki County) was a descendant of Nagayasu HIRANO, one of the seven spear soldiers at the Shizugatake mountain under Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and became provided with the kotaiyoriai-omoteoreishu status.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hirano clan in Tawaramoto, Toichi County (present Tawaramoto town, Shiki County) was a descendant of Nagayasu HIRANO, one of the seven spear soldiers at the Shizugatake mountain under Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and was provided with kotaiyoriai-omoteoreishu status.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hirano clan in Tawaramoto, Toichi County (present Tawaramoto Town, Shiki County) was a descendant of Nagayasu HIRANO, one of the seven spear soldiers at Mt. Shizugatake under Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and was provided with kotaiyoriai-omoteoreishu status.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>これらの曾我多賀氏、豊田佐藤氏、福地織田氏、田原本平野氏は、それぞれ領外で取引関係にある多様な在郷商人などが引請の銀札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These Soga-Taga clan, Toyota-Sato clan, Fukuchi-Oda clan, and Tawaramoto-Hirano clan issued gin-satsu undertaken by various local merchants who resided outside their respective territories but with whom they had transactions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These Soga-Taga clan, Toyota-Sato clan, Fukuchi-Oda clan, and Tawaramoto-Hirano clan issued gin-satsu, which was undertaken by various local merchants who resided outside their respective territories but with whom they had transactions.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These Soga-Taga clan, Toyota-Sato clan, Fukuchi-Oda clan, and Tawaramoto-Hirano clan issued gin-satsu, which was undertaken by various local merchants who resided outside their respective territories but with whom they had transactions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="61">
<j>戦国期に京で権勢を誇った三好氏のうち、徳川家康に取り立てられた三好可正の系統は大和国の添下郡丹後庄（現・大和郡山市丹後庄町）及び山辺郡守目堂（現・天理市守目堂町）を所領として有した家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of the Miyoshi clan that was dominant in Kyoto in the Sengoku period, a family in the lineage of Kasho MIYOSHI, which had been picked by Ieyasu TOkugawa, owned Tangonosho, Soejimo County, Yamato Province (present Tangonosho-cho, Yamato-Koriyama City) and Motimedo, Yamabe County (present Morimedo-cho, Tenri City) as its territories.</e>
<cmt>三好可正：　正しい読み不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of the Miyoshi clan that was dominant in Kyoto in the Sengoku period, a family in the lineage of Kasho MIYOSHI, which had been picked by Ieyasu TOkugawa, owned the territories of Tangonosho, Soejimo County, Yamato Province (present Tangonosho-cho, Yamato-Koriyama City) and Motimedo, Yamabe County (present Morimedo-cho, Tenri City).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of the Miyoshi clan that was dominant in Kyoto in the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States), a family in the lineage of Kasho MIYOSHI, which had been picked by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, owned the territories of Tango no sho manor, Soejimo County, Yamato Province (present Tangonosho-cho, Yamato-Koriyama City) and Morimedo, Yamabe County (present Morimedo-cho, Tenri City).</e>
<cmt>表記、読みを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>忍海郡西辻の水野氏は、織田信長、北条氏政などに仕え、後に徳川家の旗本となり、武蔵国の他大和国に所領を有して西辻に陣屋を置いていた家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mizuno family in Nishitsuji, Oshime County served Nobunaga Oda and Ujimasa HOJO, became a Hatamoto of the Tokugawa family later, and owning a territory in Yamato Province in addition to in Musashi Province, placed a jinya in Nishitsuji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mizuno family in Nishitsuji, Oshime County which served Nobunaga Oda and Ujimasa HOJO, and became an atamoto of the Tokugawa family later, and owned territory in Yamato Province in addition to territory in Musashi Province, placed a jinya in Nishitsuji.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mizuno clan in Nishitsuji, Oshime County which served including Nobunaga ODA and Ujimasa HOJO, and became a Hatamoto of the Tokugawa family later, owned territory in Yamato Province in addition to territory in Musashi Province and placed a jinya in Nishitsuji.</e>
<cmt>表記、表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>葛下郡松塚（現・大和高田市松塚）の桑山氏は、新庄藩桑山氏の分家であり、本家が改易された後も存続した家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kuwayama family in Matsuzuka, Katsuge County was a branch family of the Kuwayama family in the Shinjo domain, and remained existing even after the main family of the clan was abolished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kuwayama family in Matsuzuka, Katsuge County was a branch family of the Kuwayama family in the Shinjo domain, and remained even after the main family of the clan was abolished.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kuwayama clan in Matsuzuka, Katsuraginoshimo County was a branch family of the Kuwayama clan in the Shinjo clan, and remained even after the main family of the clan was abolished.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>十市郡池尻（現・橿原市東池尻町）の赤井氏は、元は丹波国の土豪であり、後に徳川家に旗本として仕えた家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Akai family in Ikejiri, Tochi County (present Higashi-Ikejiri-cho, Kashihara City) was originally a local clan, and later served the Tokugawa family as its Hatamoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Akai family in Ikejiri, Tochi County (present Higashi-Ikejiri-cho, Kashihara City) was originally a local clan, and later served the Tokugawa family as its Hatamoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Akai clan in Ikejiri, Tochi County (present Higashi-Ikejiri-cho, Kashihara City) was originally a local clan in the Tanba Province, and later served the Tokugawa family as its Hatamoto.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。「丹波国」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>高市郡坊城・曲川（現・橿原市東坊城町、曲川町）の藤堂氏は、津藩藤堂氏の分家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Todo family in Bojo and Magarikawa, Takaichi County, was a branch family of the Todo family in the Tsu domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Todo family in Bojo and Magarikawa, Takaichi County, was a branch family of the Todo family in the Tsu domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Todo clan in Bojo and Magarikawa, Takaichi County (present Higashibojo-cho and Magarikawa-cho, Kashihara City), was a branch family of the Todo clan in the Tsu clan.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。「現・橿原市東坊城町、曲川町」を補足し用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>山辺郡平等坊（現・天理市平等坊町）の山口氏は奏者番、伏見城番などを勤めた山口直友の裔である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yamaguchi family in Byodobo, Yamabe County (present Byodobo-cho, Tenri City) was a descendant of Naotomo YAMAGUCHI who assumed the post of sojaban (an official in charge of the ceremonies) and that of guarding Fushimi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yamaguchi family in Byodobo, Yamabe County (present Byodobo-cho, Tenri City) was a descendant of Naotomo YAMAGUCHI who assumed the post of sojaban (an official in charge of the ceremonies) and guarded Fushimi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yamaguchi clan in Byodobo, Yamabe County (present Byodobo-cho, Tenri City) was a descendant of Naotomo YAMAGUCHI who assumed the post of sojaban (an official in charge of the ceremonies) and guard of Fushimi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>これらの丹後庄守目堂三好氏、西辻水野氏、松塚桑山氏、池尻赤井氏、坊城曲川藤堂氏、平等坊山口氏は、それぞれ米手形形式の銀札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each of these Tangonosho/Morimedo-Miyoshi family, Nishitsuji-Mizuno family, Matsuzuka-Kuwayama family, Ikejiri-Akai family, Bojo/Magarikawa-Todo, and Byodobo-Yamaguchi family issued its gin-satsu in the kome-tegata (promissory notes for rice crop) format.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each of these Tangonosho/Morimedo-Miyoshi family, Nishitsuji-Mizuno family, Matsuzuka-Kuwayama family, Ikejiri-Akai family, Bojo/Magarikawa-Todo, and Byodobo-Yamaguchi family issued its gin-satsu in the kome-tegata (promissory notes for rice crop) format.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each of these Tangonosho Morimedo-Miyoshi clan, Nishitsuji-Mizuno clan, Matsuzuka-Kuwayama clan, Ikejiri-Akai clan, Bojo Magarikawa-Todo clan, and Byodobo-Yamaguchi clan issued its gin-satsu in the Kome-tegata format.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="68">
<j>添下郡高山（現・生駒市高山町）の東半分及び隣村の鹿畑（現・生駒市鹿畑町）を領していた堀田氏は、他に常陸国及び近江国にも所領を有し、近江・大和の所領は近江国甲賀郡上田（甲賀市水口町嶬峨）に置かれた陣屋が統括していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hotta family that owned the eastern half of Takayama, Soejimo County (present Takayama-cho, Ikoma City) and Shikahata (present Shikahata-cho, Ikoma City), a village adjacent to the area, possessed a territory in Hitachi Province and in Omi Province as well, with its territories in Omi and Yamato totally controlled by a jinya (regional government office) placed in Ueda, Kouka County, Omi Province (present Gika, Minakuchi-cho. Kouka City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hotta family that owned the eastern half of Takayama, Soejimo County (present Takayama-cho, Ikoma City) and Shikahata (present Shikahata-cho, Ikoma City), a village adjacent to the area, possessed a territory in Hitachi Province and in Omi Province as well, with its territories in Omi and Yamato totally controlled by a jinya (regional government office) placed in Ueda, Kouka County, Omi Province (present Gika, Minakuchi-cho. Kouka City).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hotta clan which owned the eastern half of Takayama, Soejimo County (present Takayama-cho, Ikoma City) and neighboring Shikahata (present Shikahata-cho, Ikoma City) possessed a territory in Hitachi Province and in Omi Province as well, where the jinya located in Ueda, Koka County, Omi Province (Gika, Minakuchi-cho, Koka City) totally controlled.</e>
<cmt>読み、表現を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>堀田氏は高山において、庄屋の中谷吉兵衛による銀札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Takayama, the Hotta family issued gin-satsu through Kichibei Pakistani, a shoya (village headman).</e>
<cmt>中谷吉兵衛：　正しい読み、不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Takayama, the Hotta family issued gin-satsu through Kichibei Pakistani, a shoya (village headman).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Takayama, the Hotta clan issued gin-satsu through Kichibei NAKATANI (中谷吉兵衛), a shoya (village headman).</e>
<cmt>読み不明の漢字を補足し、読みも修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="70">
<j>添下郡豊浦（現・大和郡山市豊浦町）の片桐氏及び添下郡伊豆七条（現・大和郡山市伊豆七条町）の片桐氏は、いずれも小泉藩片桐氏の分家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Either of the Katagiri family in Toyoura, Soejimo County (present Toyoura-cho, Yamato-Koriyama City) and the Katagiri family in Izushichijo, Soejimo County (present Izushichijo-cho, Yamato-Koriyama City) was a branch family of the Katagiri family in the Oizumi domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both the Katagiri family in Toyoura, Soejimo County (present Toyoura-cho, Yamato-Koriyama City) and the Katagiri family in Izushichijo, Soejimo County (present Izushichijo-cho, Yamato-Koriyama City) were a branch family of the Katagiri family in the Oizumi domain.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both the Katagiri clan in Toyoura, Soejimo County (present Toyoura-cho, Yamato-Koriyama City) and the Katagiri clan in Izushichijo, Soejimo County (present Izushichijo-cho, Yamato-Koriyama City) were branch families of the Katagiri clan in the Koizumi clan.</e>
<cmt>読み、用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>前者は明治元年に銭札を、後者は慶應二年に米会所から庄屋・年寄・百姓の請負による米手形形式の銀札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former Katagiri family issued sen-satsu in 1868, and the latter Katagiri family issued gin-satsu in the Kome-tegata format from the rice association in 1866, entrusted by the shoya, senior persons and farmers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Katagiri family issued sen-satsu in 1868, and the latter Katagiri family issued gin-satsu in the Kome-tegata format from the rice association in 1866, entrusted by the shoya, senior persons and farmers.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former issued zeni-satsu in 1868 and the latter issued gin-satsu in the Kome-tegata format from the rice association in 1866, entrusted by the shoya, Toshiyori (elder chief of a village or town during Edo Period) and farmers.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>摂津国・河内国・和泉国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Settsu Province, in Kawachi Province and in in Izumi Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Settsu Province, Kawachi Province and Izumi Province</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Settsu, Kawachi, and Izumi Provinces</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="72">
<j>摂津・河内・和泉の3国は徳川幕府成立以後も大部分が豊臣家の領地であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The three provinces of Settsu, Kawachi and Izumi were mostly the territories of the Toyotomi family even after the Tokugawa bakufu was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The three provinces of Settsu, Kawachi and Izumi were mostly Toyotomi family territories even after the Tokugawa bakufu was established.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The three provinces of Settsu, Kawachi and Izumi were mostly Toyotomi family&apos;s territories even after the Tokugawa shogunate was established.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>このため、この地域における旗本は、関ヶ原の戦い前後から大坂の陣による豊臣家滅亡前後まで、徳川家が勢力拡大及び地域安定化のために地生えの武家勢力・豪商などを取り立てた例が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, many of the Hatamoto in this area were the samurai or wealthy merchants who were specifically picked by the Tokugawa family, to expand its power and to stabilize the state of the area in the era from around the Battle of Sekigahara to Osaka no Jin (The Siege of Osaka).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, many of the Hatamoto in this area were samurai or wealthy merchants who were specifically picked by the Tokugawa family, to expand its power and to stabilize the state of the area in the era from around the Battle of Sekigahara to Osaka no Jin (The Siege of Osaka).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, many of the Hatamoto in this area were local samurai or wealthy merchants picked by the Tokugawa family to expand its power and to stabilize the state of the area from around the Battle of Sekigahara to around the downfall of the Toyotomi family by The Siege of Osaka.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。「豊臣家滅亡前後まで」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="74">
<j>摂津国能勢郡地黄（現・大阪府能勢郡能勢町地黄）の能勢氏は多田源氏流の名族であるが、豊臣秀吉の能勢郡侵攻によって領地を追われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nose family in Jio, Nose County, Settsu Province (present Jio, Nose-cho, Nose County, Osaka Prefecture) was a distinguished family in the lineage of Tada-Genji, but lost its territory when Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI invaded Nose County.</e>
<cmt>大阪府能勢郡：　”大阪府豊能郡”の誤りではないかとも思いましたが、原文通りに訳してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nose family in Jio, Nose County, Settsu Province (present Jio, Nose-cho, Nose County, Osaka Prefecture) was a distinguished family in the lineage of Tada-Genji, but lost its territory when Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI invaded Nose County.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nose clan in Jio, Nose County, Settsu Province (present Jio, Nose-cho, Nose County, Osaka Prefecture) was a distinguished family in the lineage of Tada-Genji (Minamoto clan), but lost its territory when Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI invaded Nose County.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>流浪を経て五大老筆頭であった徳川家康の庇護を受け、関ヶ原の戦いで戦功を上げて能勢郡の旧領を安堵された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After having wandered about various areas in the nation, the family entered under the protection of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, the head of Gotairo (the council of five elders) at that time, and could regain its former territory through accomplishing prominent achievements in the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After having wandered about various areas in the nation, the family entered under the protection of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, the head of Gotairo (the council of five elders) at that time, and was able to regain its former territory by accomplishing prominent achievements in the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After having wandered about various areas in the nation, the clan accomplished prominent achievements in the Battle of Sekigahara under the protection of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, the head of Gotairo (the council of five elders) at that time, and was given its former territory of Nose County.</e>
<cmt>用語、表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>能勢氏はその後、所領を一族で分割支配した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, the control of the territory was divided among the families of the Nose clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, the control of the territory was divided among the families of the Nose clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, the Nose clan divided and ruled the territory.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>本家の地黄能勢氏は天保年間より旗本札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Jio-Nose family, the head family of the clan, issued Hatamoto-satsu in the Tenpo era (1830 - 1844).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Jio-Nose family, the head family of the clan, issued Hatamoto-satsu in the Tenpo era (1830 - 1844).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Jio-Nose clan, the head family of the clan, issued Hatamoto-satsu since the Tenpo era (1830 to 1843).</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>分家の能勢郡切畑（現・大阪府能勢郡豊能町切畑）の切畑能勢氏は、加増によって与えられた丹波国氷上郡3ヶ村（現・兵庫県丹波市青垣町）で旗本札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The branch Nose family in Kirihata, Nose County (present Kirihata, Toyono Town, Nose County, Osaka Prefecture) issued Hatamoto-satsu in three additionally given villages in Hikami County, Tanba Province (present Aogaki-cho, Tanba City, Hyogo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The branch Nose family in Kirihata, Nose County (present Kirihata, Toyono Town, Nose County, Osaka Prefecture) issued Hatamoto-satsu in three additionally given villages in Hikami County, Tanba Province (present Aogaki-cho, Tanba City, Hyogo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kirihata-Nose clan, the branch family in Kirihata, Nose County (present Kirihata, Toyono Town, Nose County, Osaka Prefecture), issued Hatamoto-satsu in three additionally given villages in Hikami County, Tanba Province (present Aogaki-cho, Tanba City, Hyogo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="79">
<j>摂津国島下郡溝杭（現・大阪府茨木市星見町）の長谷川氏は、江戸時代初期の大名長谷川守知の子孫である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hasegawa family in Mizukui, Shimashimo County, Settsu Province (present Hoshimi-cho, Ibaraki City, Osaka Prefecture) was a descendant of Moritomo HASEGAWA, a daimyo in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hasegawa family in Mizukui, Shimashimo County, Settsu Province (present Hoshimi-cho, Ibaraki City, Osaka Prefecture) was a descendant of Moritomo HASEGAWA, a daimyo in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hasegawa clan in Mizokui, Shimashimo County, Settsu Province (present Hoshimi-cho, Ibaraki City, Osaka Prefecture) was a descendant of Moritomo HASEGAWA, a daimyo in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>守知は関ヶ原の戦いで西軍に属し、石田三成の居城佐和山城の守備を担当していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moritomo belonged to the western group in the Battle of Sekigahara, being in charge of guarding Mitsunari ISHIDA&apos;s Sawayama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moritomo belonged to the western group in the Battle of Sekigahara, being in charge of guarding Mitsunari ISHIDA&apos;s Sawayama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moritomo belonged to the West squad in the Battle of Sekigahara, being in charge of guarding Mitsunari ISHIDA&apos;s Sawayama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>しかしながら、敗戦後に東軍に内応して落城のきっかけを作ったため、徳川家に大名として取り立てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, after the group was defeated, he secretly communicated with the eastern group, causing the collapse of the castle, and for this, he was rewarded with a daimyo post.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after the group was defeated, he secretly communicated with the eastern group, causing the collapse of the castle, and for this, he was rewarded with a daimyo post.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since his secretly communication with the East squad after defeat in the battle triggered the collapse of the castle, he was rewarded with a daimyo post by the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。「徳川家に」を補足し、表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>守知は、寛永年間に没する際、領地を子らに分割して与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When going to die in the Kanei era (1622 - 1644), Moritomo divided his territory and gave each piece of it to one of his children and others.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When going to die in the Kanei era (1622 - 1644), Moritomo divided his territory and gave each piece of it to one of his children and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When going to die in the Kanei era (1624 to 1643), Moritomo divided his territory and gave each to his children and others.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>そのため、いずれも旗本となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, all of them became Hatamoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, all of them became Hatamoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, all of them became Hatamoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>溝杭長谷川氏は、摂津国島下郡のほか数ヶ所に分散して所領を有していたが、摂津国島下郡溝杭及び備中国窪屋郡大内（現・岡山県倉敷市大内）などでそれぞれ旗本札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mizukui-Hasegawa family, owing several territories in addition to the one in Shimashimo County, Settsu Province, issued Hatamoto-satsu in Mizukui, Shimashimo County, Settsu Province, and in Ouchi, Boya County, Bicchu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mizukui-Hasegawa family, owing several territories in addition to the one in Shimashimo County, Settsu Province, issued Hatamoto-satsu in Mizukui, Shimashimo County, Settsu Province, and in Ouchi, Boya County, Bicchu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mizokui-Hasegawa clan, owing several territories in addition to the one in Shimashimo County, Settsu Province, issued Hatamoto-satsu in Mizokui, Shimashimo County, Settsu Province, and in Ouchi, Boya County, Bitchu Province (present Ouchi, Kurashiki City, Okayama Prefecture), and so on.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。「現・岡山県倉敷市大内」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="85">
<j>河内国では、楠木正成の子孫で、烏帽子形城主などをつとめた甲斐庄氏（甲斐庄氏）が、徳川家康に取り立てられて錦部郡5ヶ村（現・大阪府河内長野市）を知行する旗本となり、旗本札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kawachi Province, the Kainosho family, a descendant of Masashige KUSUNOKI and having been the lord of Eboshi-jo Castle, was specifically picked by Ieyasu Tokugawa to become a Hatamoto entitled to control five villages in Nshikibe County (present Kawachi-nagano City), and issued Hatamoto-satsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kawachi Province, the Kainosho family, a descendant of Masashige KUSUNOKI and having been the lord of Eboshi-jo Castle, was specifically picked by Ieyasu Tokugawa to become a Hatamoto entitled to control five villages in Nshikibe County (present Kawachi-nagano City), and issued Hatamoto-satsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kawachi Province, the Kainosho clan, a descendant of Masashige KUSUNOKI and having been the lord of Eboshigata-jo Castle and so on, was specifically picked by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA to become a Hatamoto entitled to control five villages in Nishikibe County (present Kawachi-nagano City, Osaka Prefecture), and issued Hatamoto-satsu.</e>
<cmt>補足し、表記、読み修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="86">
<j>和泉国堺（現・大阪府堺市）では、豪商今井宗久の子今井宗薫が大坂の陣ののちに徳川家に代官として取り立てられることにより旗本となり、堺宿院町に屋敷を構え、旗本札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Sakai, Izumi Province (present Sakai City, Osaka Prefecture), Sokun IMAI, a wealthy merchant, was specifically picked as a local governor by the Tokugawa family after the Osaka no Jin (The Siege of Osaka) to become a Hatamoto, owned a residence in Sakaijuku-inmachi, and issued Hatamoto-satsu.</e>
<cmt>堺宿院町：　正しい読み、不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Sakai, Izumi Province (present Sakai City, Osaka Prefecture), Sokun IMAI, a wealthy merchant, was specifically picked as a local governor by the Tokugawa family after the Osaka no Jin (The Siege of Osaka) to become a Hatamoto, owned a residence in Sakaijuku-inmachi, and issued Hatamoto-satsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Sakai, Izumi Province (present Sakai City, Osaka Prefecture), Sokun IMAI, a son of Sokyu IMAI of a wealthy merchant, was specifically picked as a local governor by the Tokugawa family after The Siege of Osaka to become a Hatamoto, having a residence in Sakai-shukuin-cho, and issued Hatamoto-satsu.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。「今井宗久の子」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>丹波国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Tanba Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Tanba Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tanba Province</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="87">
<j>丹波国は、南部の丹波亀山藩、篠山藩、北部の福知山藩などが比較的まとまった領地を持った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Tanba Province, the Tanba-kameyama domain and Sasayama domain in the southern part, and the Fukuchiyama domain in the northern part owned each a comparatively large-sized territory.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Tanba Province, the Tanba-kameyama domain and Sasayama domain in the southern part, and the Fukuchiyama domain in the northern part each owned a comparatively large-sized territory.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Tanba Province, the Tanba-kameyama clan and Sasayama clan in the southern part, and the Fukuchiyama clan in the northern part each owned a comparatively large-sized territory.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>しかしながら、そのほかは、小藩領、関東や東北の諸藩の飛地領、旗本領、幕府領などが錯綜する非領国地域であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the other area of the province was a hi-ryogokuchiiki area with the territories of small domains, the territories owned by remote domains in Kanto or in Tohoku, Hatamoto territories and territories of the bakufu existing complicatedly mixed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the other area of the province was a hi-ryogokuchiiki area with the territories of small domains, the territories owned by remote domains in Kanto or in Tohoku, Hatamoto territories and territories of the bakufu existing complicatedly mixed.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the bakufu existing complicatedly mixed.&quot; doesn’t make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the other area of the province was a hi-ryogokuchiiki area with the territories of small clans, tobichi territories of Kanto or Tohoku regions, Hatamoto&apos;s territories, bakufu&apos;s territories, and so on existing complicatedly mixed.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>旗本札を発行した旗本の知行地の分布は、江戸期に存在した6郡のうち、桑田郡、何鹿郡、氷上郡に分布している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The chigyochi (control areas) of the Hatamoto who issued Hatamoto-satsu was located in Kuwata County, Ikaruga County and Hikami County of the six counties that existed in the Edo period,.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The chigyochi (control areas) of the Hatamoto who issued Hatamoto-satsu was located in Kuwata County, Ikaruga County and Hikami County of the six counties that existed in the Edo period,.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The chigyo-chi of the Hatamoto who issued Hatamoto-satsu ranged in Kuwata County, Ikaruga County and Hikami County of the six counties that existed in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="90">
<j>京の町にほど近い口丹波地域には、山陰道の押さえとして丹波亀山藩が置かれ、丹波亀山城を居城としていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kuchi Tanba area near to Kyoto, the Tanba-Kameyama domain was in charge of guarding the Sanindo road, and Tanba-Kameyama-jo Castle was used as the residence of the lord.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kuchi Tanba area near Kyoto, the Tanba-Kameyama domain was in charge of guarding the Sanindo road, and Tanba-Kameyama-jo Castle was used as the lord&apos;s residence.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kuchi Tanba area near Kyoto, the Tanba-Kameyama clan was in charge of guarding the Sanindo road, and Tanba-Kameyama-jo Castle was used as the lord&apos;s residence.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>この地域では、桑田郡馬路（現・京都府亀岡市馬路町）の杉浦氏及び桑田郡河原尻（現・京都府亀岡市河原林町河原尻）の武田氏が銀札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this area, the Sugiura family in Umaji, Kuwata County (present Umaji-cho, Kameoka City, Kyoto Prefecture) and the Takeda family in Kawarajiri, Kuwata County (present Kawara jiri, Kawarabayashi-cho, Kameoka City, Kyoto Prefecture) issued gin-satsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sugiura family in Umaji, Kuwata County (present Umaji-cho, Kameoka City, Kyoto Prefecture) and the Takeda family in Kawarajiri, Kuwata County (present Kawara jiri, Kawarabayashi-cho, Kameoka City, Kyoto Prefecture) issued gin-satsu in this area.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sugiura clan in Umaji, Kuwata County (present Umaji-cho, Kameoka City, Kyoto Prefecture) and the Takeda clan in Kawarajiri, Kuwata County (present Kawarajiri, Kawarabayashi-cho, Kameoka City, Kyoto Prefecture) issued gin-satsu in this area.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>杉浦氏は、和田義盛の裔を称し、徳川家の譜代の臣として多くの旗本を輩出した一族である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The head of the Sugiwara clan called himself a descendant of Yoshimori WADA, and the clan, consisting of retainers of the Tokugawa family from before the War of Sekigahara, produced many Hatamoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The head of the Sugiwara clan called himself a descendant of Yoshimori WADA, and the clan, consisting of retainers of the Tokugawa family from before the War of Sekigahara, and produced many Hatamoto.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sugiura clan called itself a descendant of Yoshimori WADA, consisting of fudai (a daimyo in hereditary vassal) to the Tokugawa family to produce many Hatamoto.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>馬路杉浦氏の所領は相模国及び丹波国に分散していたが、桑田郡馬路に陣屋を置き、蔵米などの産物の会計を担当する「掛屋」の銭屋覚兵衛による紙幣を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The territories of Umaji-Sugiuwa family were located in Sagami Province and in Tanba Province separately, but the jinya was placed in Umaji, Kuwata County, and the family issued paper money through Kakubei ZENIYA in the &quot;Kakeya&quot; post that was in charge of the accounts of products, such as kuramai (the rice crop to be sold).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The territories of Umaji-Sugiuwa family were located in Sagami Province and in Tanba Province separately, but the jinya was placed in Umaji, Kuwata County, and the family issued paper money through Kakubei ZENIYA in the &quot;Kakeya&quot; post that was in charge of the accounts of products, such as kuramai (the rice crop to be sold).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the territories of Umaji-Sugiuwa clan were located in Sagami Province and in Tanba Province separately, the clan placed the jinya in Umaji, Kuwata County, to issue paper money through Kakubei ZENIYA of the &apos;Kakeya,&apos; the position who was in charge of the accounts of products, such as kuramai (the rice crop to be sold).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>河原尻武田氏は甲斐国の戦国大名武田氏の一族で、丹波国内に分散して所領を有していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kawajiri-Takeda family, a branch family of the Takeda family, the daimyo of Kai Province in the Sengoku period, owned territories scattered in Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kawajiri-Takeda family, a branch family of the Takeda family, the daimyo of Kai Province in the Sengoku period, owned territories scattered in Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kawarajiri-Takeda clan, a family of the Takeda clan, a Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period) in Kai Province, owned territories scattered in Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt>前出地名に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>桑田郡河原尻には代官所を置き、蔵元の名で銀札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Placing a magistrate&apos;s office in Kawajiri, Kuwata County, the family issued gin-satsu in the name of kuramoto (the merchant who handled the money of the family)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Placing a magistrate&apos;s office in Kawajiri, Kuwata County, the family issued gin-satsu in the name of kuramoto (the merchant who handled the money of the family)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Placing a magistrate&apos;s office in Kawarajiri, Kuwata County, the clan issued gin-satsu in the name of kuramoto (the merchant who handled the money of the family)</e>
<cmt>前出地名に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="96">
<j>丹波国の北寄りの奥丹波地域の何鹿郡は由良川水運が発達した地域であり、綾部藩、山家藩といった藩のほか、旗本領が散在していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The water transportation route using the Yura-gawa River route flourished in Ikaruga County in Oku-Tanba area in the northern part of Tanba Province, and Hatamoto territories in addition to the Ayabe domain and Yamaga domain were located in this province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The water transportation route through the Yura-gawa River flourished in Ikaruga County in Oku-Tanba area in the northern part of Tanba Province, and Hatamoto territories in addition to the Ayabe domain and Yamaga domain were located in this province.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The water transportation route through the Yura-gawa River flourished in Ikaruga County in Oku-Tanba area in the northern part of Tanba Province, where Hatamoto territories in addition to the Ayabe clan and Yamaga clan were located.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>由良川支流の上林川流域の何鹿郡石橋（城下）（現・綾部市八津合町石橋）の城下藤懸氏は豊臣政権下では大名であったが、関ヶ原の戦いで西軍に付いたため減知され、旗本となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shiroshita-Fujikake family in Ishibashi (Shiroshita), Ikaruga County (present Ishibashi, Yatsuai-cho, Ayabe City) around the Kanbayashi-gawa River, a tributary of the Yura-gawa River, was a daimyo under the Toyotomi government, but its territory was reduced because the clan supported the west group in the Battle of Sekigahara, being forced to become a Hatamoto.</e>
<cmt>城下：　正しい読み、不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shiroshita-Fujikake family in Ishibashi (Shiroshita), Ikaruga County (present Ishibashi, Yatsuai-cho, Ayabe City) around the Kanbayashi-gawa River, a tributary of the Yura-gawa River, was a daimyo under the Toyotomi government, but its territory was reduced because the clan supported the west group in the Battle of Sekigahara, and was forced to become Hatamoto.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shiroshita-Fujikake clan in Ishibashi (Shiroshita [城下]), Ikaruga County (present Ishibashi, Yatsuai-cho, Ayabe City) around the Kanbayashi-gawa River, a tributary of the Yura-gawa River, was a daimyo under the Toyotomi government, but its territory was reduced because the clan supported the West squad in the Battle of Sekigahara to be forced to become Hatamoto.</e>
<cmt>半角英字にし、読み不明の漢字を補足、表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>城下藤懸氏は掛屋から銀札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shiroshita-Fujikake issued gin-satsu through his Kakeya. officer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shiroshita-Fujikake issued gin-satsu through his Kakeya. officer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shiroshita-Fujikake clan issued gin-satsu through his Kakeya officer.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>城下から上林川のやや下流に陣屋を置いていた何鹿郡十倉（現・京都府綾部市十倉中町）の十倉谷氏と、十倉から北側の山地を超えた位置にある何鹿郡梅迫（現・京都府綾部市梅迫町）の梅迫谷氏は、山家藩谷氏の分家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tokura-Tani family in Tokura, Ikaruga County (present Tokuranaka-machi, Ayabe City, Kyoto Prefecture), which placed its jinya at a slightly lower reach from Shiroshita of the Kanbayashi-gawa River, and the Umezako-Tani family in Umezako, Ikaruga County (present Umezako-cho, Ayabe City, Kyoto Prefecture) that was located across a mountainous area in the north of Tokura were each a branch family of the Tani family in the Yamaga domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tokura-Tani family in Tokura, Ikaruga County (present Tokuranaka-machi, Ayabe City, Kyoto Prefecture), which placed its jinya at a slightly lower reach from Shiroshita of the Kanbayashi-gawa River, and the Umezako-Tani family in Umezako, Ikaruga County (present Umezako-cho, Ayabe City, Kyoto Prefecture) that was located across a mountainous area in the north of Tokura were each a branch family of the Tani family in the Yamaga domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tokura-Tani clan in Tokura, Ikaruga County (present Tokuranaka-machi, Ayabe City, Kyoto Prefecture), which placed its jinya at a slightly lower reach from Shiroshita of the Kanbayashi-gawa River, and the Umezako-Tani clan in Umezako, Ikaruga County (present Umezako-cho, Ayabe City, Kyoto Prefecture) that was located across a mountainous area in the north of Tokura were each a branch family of the Tani clan in the Yamaga clan.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>十倉谷氏は、掛屋により銀札を、梅迫谷氏は、領内の黒谷が黒谷和紙の生産地であったため、紙会所などから銀札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tokura-Tani family issued gin-satsu through the Kakeya officer, and the Umezako-Tani family issued gin-satsu through at least the paper association, because Kurotani washi (Japanese paper) was produced in the Kurotani area in its territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tokura-Tani family issued gin-satsu through the Kakeya officer, and the Umezako-Tani family issued gin-satsu at least through the paper association, because Kurotani washi (Japanese paper) was produced in the Kurotani area in its territory.</e>
<cmt>&quot; issued gin-satsu at least through the paper association&quot; doesn’t make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tokura-Tani clan issued gin-satsu through the Kakeya officer, and the Umezako-Tani clan issued gin-satsu through the paper association, and others, because Kurotani washi (Japanese paper made in Kurotani) was produced in the Kurotani area in its territory.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="101">
<j>丹波国の西端にあたる氷上郡は、播磨国を経て瀬戸内海の播磨灘にそそぐ加古川（上流部は佐治川とも呼ばれる）の上流域にあたっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hikami County, in the western end of Tanba Province, was located in the upper reaches of the Kako-gawa River (whose upper reach portion was called the Saji-gawa River as well) that flew to the Sea of Harima in Seto Inland Sea through Harima Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hikami County, in the western end of Tanba Province, was located in the upper reaches of the Kako-gawa River (whose upper reach portion was called the Saji-gawa River as well) that flew to the Sea of Harima in Seto Inland Sea through Harima Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hikami County, in the western end of Tanba Province, was located in the upper reaches of the Kako-gawa River (whose upper reach portion was called the Saji-gawa River as well) that flew to the Sea of Harima in Seto Inland Sea through Harima Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>経済の中心地である大坂への物流の利便性の高さから、本郷や佐治など、加古川水運の船着場が発達し、郡の範囲を超える広い範囲の物流を担っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, as the county was placed in a location highly convenient for transporting goods to Osaka, an economic center, river ports for the water transportation using the Kako-gawa River, such as Hongo and Saji, developed there, providing goods transportation functions in a broad area exceeding the range of the county.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, as the county was placed in a location that was extremely convenient for transporting goods to Osaka, an economic center, river ports for the water transportation using the Kako-gawa River, such as Hongo and Saji, developed there, providing goods transportation functions in a broad area exceeding the range of the county.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of convenience of commodity distribution to Osaka, the economic center, river ports for the water transportation of the Kako-gawa River, such as Hongo and Saji, developed there, providing goods transportation functions in a broad area beyond the county.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>氷上郡には、丹波柏原藩織田氏の陣屋が柏原（現・丹波市柏原町柏原）にあったが、小藩の上に藩領は丹波国内に散在していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the jinya of the Oda family in the Tanba-kaibara domain was located in Kaibara of Hikami County (present Kaibara, Kaibara-cho, Tanba City), the domain was small in the size, and the domain territory was located in various areas of Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the jinya of the Oda family in the Tanba-kaibara domain was located in Kaibara of Hikami County (present Kaibara, Kaibara-cho, Tanba City), the domain was small in size, and the domain territory was located in various areas of Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the jinya of the Oda clan in the Tanba-Kaibara clan was located in Kaibara of Hikami County (present Kaibara, Kaibara-cho, Tanba City), the clan was small in size with its territory scattered in various areas of Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>そのうえ、関東、東海及び近畿諸藩の飛地領や大小旗本領などが混在する非領国地域であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the area was a hi-ryogokuchiiki area as well, with the territories of domains in Kanto, Tokai, or Kinki and big or small Hatamoto territories located mixed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the area was a hi-ryogokuchiiki area as well, with the territories of domains in Kanto, Tokai, or Kinki and big or small Hatamoto territories located mixed.</e>
<cmt>Translation doesn’t make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, it was also a hi-ryogokuchiiki area mixing with tobichi territories of clans in Kanto, Tokai, and Kinki regions and big or small Hatamoto territories.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="105">
<j>氷上郡佐治・小倉（現・丹波市青垣町佐治、青垣町小倉）の牧氏は織田信長や滝川一益の家臣などを経て、豊臣秀吉による小田原城攻めの際に徳川家康の旗本となった家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Maki family in Saji and Ogura, Hikami County (present Saji, Aogaki-cho, and Ogura Aogaki-cho, Tanba City) was initially a retainer of Nobunaga Oda and of Kazumasu TAKIGAWA in a different era, but became a Hatamoto of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA when Hideyoshi Tokugawa attacked Odawara-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Maki family in Saji and Ogura, Hikami County (present Saji, Aogaki-cho, and Ogura Aogaki-cho, Tanba City) was initially a retainer of Nobunaga Oda and of Kazumasu TAKIGAWA from a different era, but became a Hatamoto of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA when Hideyoshi Tokugawa attacked Odawara-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Maki clan in Saji and Ogura, Hikami County (present Saji, and Ogura, Aogaki-cho, Tanba City) became a Hatamoto of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA when Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI attacked Odawara-jo Castle after being a retainer of Nobunaga ODA, that of Kazumasu TAKIGAWA, and so on.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>氷上郡新郷（現・丹波市氷上町新郷）の安藤氏は、上野国高崎藩安藤氏の分家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ando family in Shingo, Hikami County, was a branch family of the Ando family in the Takasaki domain of Kozuke Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ando family in Shingo, Hikami County, was a branch family of the Ando family in the Takasaki domain of Kozuke Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ando clan in Shingo, Hikami County (present Shingo, Hikami-cho, Tanba City), was a branch family of the Ando clan in the Takasaki clan of Kozuke Province.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。「現・丹波市氷上町新郷」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>氷上郡本郷（現・丹波市氷上町本郷）の井上氏は、下総国高岡藩井上氏の分家で、遠江国に所領を有していたが、加増により丹波国氷上郡の所領を加えられた家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally owning a territory in Totomi Province, the Inoue family in Hongo, Hikami County (present Hongo, Hikami-cho, Tanabe City), a branch family of the Inoue family in the Takaoka domain of Shimosa Province, was additionally given a territory in Hikami County, Tanba Province, as well, to increase the amount of rice crop earned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally owning a territory in Totomi Province, the Inoue family in Hongo, Hikami County (present Hongo, Hikami-cho, Tanabe City), a branch family of the Inoue family in the Takaoka domain of Shimosa Province, was additionally given territory in Hikami County, Tanba Province, as well, to increase the amount of rice produced.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Inoue clan in Hongo, Hikami County (present Hongo, Hikami-cho, Tanba City), a branch family of the Inoue clan in the Takaoka clan of Shimosa Province and having owning a territory in Totomi Province, was additionally given territory in Hikami County, Tanba Province, as well, to increase the amount of rice produced.</e>
<cmt>読み、表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>氷上郡中山（現・丹波市春日町中山）の川勝氏は、丹波国の国人領主の裔である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kawakatsu family in Nakayama, Hikami County (present Nakayama, Kasuga-cho, Tanba City), was a descendant of a kokujin ryoshu (local samurai lord) of Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kawakatsu family in Nakayama, Hikami County (present Nakayama, Kasuga-cho, Tanba City), was a descendant of a kokujin ryoshu (local samurai lord) of Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kawakatsu clan in Nakayama, Hikami County (present Nakayama, Kasuga-cho, Tanba City), was a descendant of a kokujin ryoshu (local samurai lord) of Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>これら佐治・小倉牧氏、新郷安藤氏、本郷井上氏、中山川勝氏の諸氏は、銀札あるいは米の代価として支払われることが明記された米代預り銀札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These Saji/Ogura-Maki family, Shingo-Ando family, Hongo-Inoue family and Yamanaka-Kawakatsu family issued gin-satsu or the gin-satsu for borrowing price of rice crop, on which the description of &quot;this gin-satsu is paid instead of price of rice crop &quot; was explicitly made.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These Saji/Ogura-Maki family, Shingo-Ando family, Hongo-Inoue family and Yamanaka-Kawakatsu family issued gin-satsu or the gin-satsu for borrowing price of rice crop, on which the description of &quot;this gin-satsu is paid instead of price of rice crop &quot; was explicitly made.</e>
<cmt>&quot; for borrowing price of rice cro&quot; doesn’t make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These Saji and Ogura-Maki clans, Shingo-Ando clan, Hongo-Inoue clan and Yamanaka-Kawakatsu clan issued gin-satsu or the Komedai-azukari gin-satsu, on which the explicit description it was worth of rice price.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="110">
<j>氷上郡多田（現・丹波市柏原町南多田）の本多氏は陸奥国白河藩本多氏の分家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Honda family in Tada, Hikami County (present Minamitada, Kaibara-cho, Tanba City), was a branch family of the Tada family in the Shirakawa domain, Mutsu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Honda family in Tada, Hikami County (present Minamitada, Kaibara-cho, Tanba City), was a branch family of the Tada family in the Shirakawa domain, Mutsu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Honda clan in Tada, Hikami County (present Minamitada, Kaibara-cho, Tanba City), was a branch family of the Honda clan in the Shirakawa clan, Mutsu Province.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>多田本多氏は掛屋による銀札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tada-Honda family issued gin-satsu through its Kakeya officer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tada-Honda family issued gin-satsu through its Kakeya officer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tada-Honda clan issued gin-satsu through its Kakeya officer.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="112">
<j>氷上郡大新屋（現・丹波市柏原町大新屋）の佐野氏は、鎌倉幕府御家人、室町幕府鎌倉公方の家臣、豊臣政権下の大名などを経て江戸幕府の大名となった名家であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sano family in Oniya, Hikami County (present Oniya, Kaibara-cho, Tanba City), was originally a distinguished family that was gokenin (a lower-ranked direct retainer) of the Kamakura bakufu, a retainer of Kamakura kubo (the governor-general of the Kanto region) in the Muromachi bakufu, and a daimyo under the Toyotomi government.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sano family in Oniya, Hikami County (present Oniya, Kaibara-cho, Tanba City), was originally a distinguished family that was gokenin (a lower-ranked direct retainer) of the Kamakura bakufu, a retainer of Kamakura kubo (the governor-general of the Kanto region) in the Muromachi bakufu, and a daimyo under the Toyotomi government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sano clan in Oniya, Hikami County (present Oniya, Kaibara-cho, Tanba City), was originally a distinguished family of a daimyo of the Edo bakufu after being gokenin (a lower-ranked direct retainer) of the Kamakura bakufu, a retainer of Kamakura kubo (the governor-general of the Kanto region) in the Muromachi bakufu, and a daimyo under the Toyotomi government.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。「江戸幕府の大名となった」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>しかしながら、江戸時代初期に改易され、旗本となり存続した家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the family was abolished in the early Edo period, and remained existing as a Hatamoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the family was abolished in the early Edo period, and remained existing as a Hatamoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the clan was abolished in the early Edo period, and remained existing as a Hatamoto.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>大新屋佐野氏は、銭札ながら金兌換を明記した紙幣を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Oniya-Sano family issued a type of sen-satsu paper money on which it was explicitly written that &quot;the money could be changed into an equivalent amount of gold.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Oniya-Sano family issued a type of sen-satsu paper money on which it was explicitly written that &quot;the money could be changed into an equivalent amount of gold.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Oniya-Sano clan issued a type of zeni-satsu paper money on which it was explicitly written to be converted to gold.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>これは、多くの西日本諸藩などと同様に、明治新政府により銀貨幣の通用が停止されたのちに金・銭単位通貨として発行された紙幣と推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">it is also found that the paper money issued by Saji/Ogura-Maki family also include this type of money in addition to the ginsatsu for borrowing price of rice crop described above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also discovered that paper money issued by Saji/Ogura-Maki family also included this type of money in addition to the ginsatsu for borrowing price of rice crop described above.</e>
<cmt>&quot;for borrowing price of rice crop described above.&quot; doesn’t make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was assumed the paper money was issued as currency of gold or sen unit as well as many clans in western Japan did after Meiji new government stopped the circulation of silver currency.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>また、佐治・小倉牧氏発行の紙幣にも、上記の米代預り銀札以外にこの形式のものが認められる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also found that the paper money issued by Saji/Ogura-Maki family also include this type of money in addition to the ginsatsu for borrowing price of rice crop described above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also found that the paper money issued by Saji/Ogura-Maki family also include this type of money in addition to the ginsatsu for borrowing price of rice crop described above.</e>
<cmt>Same as last sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also found that the paper money issued by Saji and Ogura-Maki clans also include this type of money in addition to the previously mentioned Komedai-azukari gin-satsu.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>但馬国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Tajima Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Tajima Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tajima Province</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="117">
<j>但馬国は京都・大坂の両町奉行所の管轄から外れ、上方から遠かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tajima Province was not included in the control coverage of the machi-bugyosho (the office in charged of townspeople&apos;s affairs) of Kyoto and that of Osaka and was located far from kamigata (the Kyoto and Osaka area) as well.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tajima Province was not included in the area controlled by the machi-bugyosho (the office in charged of townspeople&apos;s affairs) of Kyoto and that of Osaka and was located far from kamigata (the Kyoto and Osaka area) as well.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tajima Province, not included in the area controlled by both machi-bugyosho (the office in charge of townspeople&apos;s affairs) in Kyoto and Osaka, was located far from kamigata (the Kyoto and Osaka area).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>そのためか、隣国の丹後国などと同様、大藩はないものの、近畿地方としては比較的明確に、出石藩・豊岡藩領、幕府領などがまとまった形で分かれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Perhaps due to these reasons, contrary to the other provinces in the kinki region, this province, together with Tango Province, was divided, relatively clearly, into the territory of the Izushi domain, that of the Toyooka domain, and that of the bakufu, though no big domain existed there.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Perhaps due to these reasons, contrary to the other provinces in the kinki region, this province, together with Tango Province, was divided, relatively clearly, into the territory of the Izushi domain, that of the Toyooka domain, and that of the bakufu, though no large domain existed there.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This might be caused the province, as well as the neighboring Tango Province, did not have a large clanbut was shapely-divided and organized such as the territories of Izushi clan, Toyooka clan, bakufu, and so on, rather than other provinces did the Kinki region.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>但馬国に所領を有する旗本家は数家あり、旗本札を発行したのは旧守護大名家や大名の一族である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, several Hatamoto families owned their territories in Tajima Province, but the families that issued Hatamoto-satsu were former shugo daimyo (the daimyo who became a daimyo from shugo, which was a Japanese provincial military governor) families or dimyo families.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, several Hatamoto families owned territories in Tajima Province, but the families that issued Hatamoto-satsu were former shugo daimyo (the daimyo who became a daimyo from shugo, which was a Japanese provincial military governor) families or daimyo families.</e>
<cmt>Spelling, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While some Hatamoto families owned territories in Tajima Province, the families that issued Hatamoto-satsu were former shugo daimyo (the daimyo who became a daimyo from shugo, which was a Japanese provincial military governor) families or daimyo families.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="120">
<j>七味郡村岡（現・兵庫県美方郡加美町村岡区村岡）の山名氏は、室町幕府の三管領四職の一家であった有力大名であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yamana family in Muraoka, Shichimi County (present Muraoka, Muraoka-ku, Kami Town, Mikata County, Hyogo Prefecture), was a powerful daimyo, a family of Sankanrei (three families in the post of kanrei, or shogunal deputy) and of having assumed one of the Shishiki posts (four major feudal lords) in the Muromachi bakufu).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処七味郡：　正しい読み、不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yamana family in Muraoka, Shichimi County (present Muraoka, Muraoka-ku, Kami Town, Mikata County, Hyogo Prefecture), was a powerful daimyo, a family of Sankanrei (three families in the post of kanrei, or shogunal deputy) and assumed one of the Shishiki posts (four major feudal lords) in the Muromachi bakufu).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yamana clan in Muraoka, Shichimi County (present Muraoka, Muraoka Ward, Kami Town, Mikata County, Hyogo Prefecture), was a powerful daimyo, one of the families of Sankanrei (three families in the post of kanrei, or shogunal deputy) and Shishiki (four major feudal lords) in the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>しかしながら、因幡国守護であった山名豊国がのちに羽柴秀吉に降り御伽衆となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, later, Toyokuni YAMANA, having been shugo of Inaba Province, surrendered to Hideyoshi HASHIBA and became Otogishu (whose function was to chat with his master).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, later, Toyokuni YAMANA, having been shugo of Inaba Province, surrendered to Hideyoshi HASHIBA and became Otogishu (whose function was to chat with his master).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, later, Toyokuni YAMANA, the military governor of Inaba Province, surrendered to Hideyoshi HASHIBA to become Otogishu (whose function was to chat with his master).</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>関ヶ原の戦いによって徳川家康に取り立てられ、七味郡全域を与えられて交代寄合表御礼衆の旗本となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yamane family was picked by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA through the Battle of Sekigahara, was given the entire area of Shichimi County and became a Hatamoto with the kotaiyoriai-omoteoreishu status.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yamane family was picked by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA through the Battle of Sekigahara, and given the entire area of Shichimi County and became a Hatamoto with kotaiyoriai-omoteoreishu status.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clan was picked by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA through the Battle of Sekigahara, and given the entire area of Shichimi County to become a Hatamoto with kotaiyoriai-omoteoreishu status.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>明治維新の際には高直しにより村岡藩を立藩したが、旗本であった時期に旗本札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Meiji Restoration, the family established the Muraoka domain, due to the review towards increasing the amount of rice crop, but issued Hatamoto-satsu while having been a Hatamoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Meiji Restoration, the family established the Muraoka domain, as a review was carried out for the purpose of increasing the amount of rice produced, but issued Hatamoto-satsu while having been a Hatamoto.</e>
<cmt>&quot;but issued Hatamoto-satsu while having been a Hatamoto.&quot; doesn’t make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Meiji Restoration, the clan which established the Muraoka clan, as a review was carried out for the purpose of increasing the amount of rice produced, issued Hatamoto-satsu while having been a Hatamoto.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>なお立藩後には、札面の様式を改めて藩札を発行している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After having established the domain, the family changed the surface format of the paper money and issued Han-satsu, replacing the Hatamoto-satsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After having established the domain, the family changed the surface format of the paper money and issued Han-satsu, replacing the Hatamoto-satsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After having established the clan, the clan changed the surface format of the paper money and issued Han-satsu.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="125">
<j>養父郡糸井（現・兵庫県朝来市和田山町寺内）の京極氏は豊岡藩京極氏の分家で、山名氏と同様に四職の一家の後裔である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kyogoku family in Itoi, Yabu County (present Terauchi, Wadayama-cho, Asago City, Hyogo Prefecture), was a branch family of the Kyogoku family in the Toyooka domain and was a descendant of a shishoku family as well as the Yamana family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kyogoku family in Itoi, Yabu County (present Terauchi, Wadayama-cho, Asago City, Hyogo Prefecture), was a branch family of the Kyogoku family in the Toyooka domain and was a descendant of a shishoku family as well as the Yamana family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kyogoku clan in Itoi, Yabu County (present Terauchi, Wadayama-cho, Asago City, Hyogo Prefecture), was a branch family of the Kyogoku clan in the Toyooka clan and was a descendant of a Shishoku family as well as the Yamana family.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>糸井京極氏は、糸井引替会所発行の札や、大坂の和泉屋重助などが引請人となった札などを発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Itoi-Kyogoku family issued paper many from Itoi Hikikae-sho (引替会所) (an exchange place) and the paper money undertaken by Shigesuke Izumiya and others in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>引替会所：　一応”Hikikae-sho (exchange place)”と訳してましたが、本当のの意味が不明ですので、漢字表現も残してあります。和泉屋重助：　正しい読み、不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Itoi-Kyogoku family issued paper many from Itoi Hikikae-sho (引替会所) (an exchange place) and the paper money undertaken by Shigesuke Izumiya and others in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Itoi-Kyogoku clan issued paper money issued by Itoi Hikikae-sho (an exchange place in Itoi) and the paper money undertaken by Shigesuke IZUMIYA and others in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>スペル、用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="127">
<j>出石藩主小出氏は、のちに無嗣改易となるまでに、但馬国内に旗本として4家の分家を興した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Koide family, the lord of the Izushi domain, produced four Hatamoto branch families in Tajima Province before the family was abolished with no heir.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Koide family, the lord of the Izushi domain, produced four Hatamoto branch families in Tajima Province before the family was abolished with no heir.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Koide clan, the lord of the Izushi clan, produced four Hatamoto branch families in Tajima Province before the family was abolished with no heir later.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>気多郡気多郡 (兵庫県)水上・山本（現・兵庫県豊岡市日高町 (兵庫県)水上及び日高町山本）の水上・山本小出氏、出石郡倉見（現・兵庫県豊岡市倉見）の倉見小出氏、養父郡大藪（現・兵庫県養父市大藪）の大藪小出氏、養父郡土田（現・兵庫県朝来市和田山町土田）の土田小出氏である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were the Minokami/Yamamoto-Koide family in Minokami and Yamamoto in Keta County (present Minokami, Hidaka-cho and Yamamoto-Hidaka-cho, Toyooka City, Hyogo Prefecture), the Kurami-Koide family in Kurami, Izushi County (present Kurami, Toyooka City, Hyogo prefecture), the Oyabu-Koide family in Oyabu, Yabu County (present, Oyabu, Yabu City, Hyogo prefecture), and the Handa-Koide family in Handa, Yabu County (present Handa, Wadayama-cho, Asago City, Hyogo prefecture.</e>
<cmt>ウエッブ上の用言から、”気多郡気多郡 (兵庫県)”は”気多郡”、　”日高町 (兵庫県)”は”日高町”とした上で訳してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were the Minokami/Yamamoto-Koide family in Minokami and Yamamoto in Keta County (present Minokami, Hidaka-cho and Yamamoto-Hidaka-cho, Toyooka City, Hyogo Prefecture), the Kurami-Koide family in Kurami, Izushi County (present Kurami, Toyooka City, Hyogo prefecture), the Oyabu-Koide family in Oyabu, Yabu County (present, Oyabu, Yabu City, Hyogo prefecture), and the Handa-Koide family in Handa, Yabu County (present Handa, Wadayama-cho, Asago City, Hyogo prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were the Minokami and Yamamoto-Koide clans in Minokami and Yamamoto in Keta County (present Minokami or Yamamoto, Hidaka-cho, Toyooka City, Hyogo Prefecture), the Kurami-Koide clan in Kurami, Izushi County (present Kurami, Toyooka City, Hyogo Prefecture), the Oyabu-Koide clan in Oyabu, Yabu County (present, Oyabu, Yabu City, Hyogo Prefecture), and the Handa-Koide clan in Handa, Yabu County (present Handa, Wadayama-cho, Asago City, Hyogo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>このうち、少なくとも水上・山本小出氏、倉見小出氏、大藪小出氏が旗本札を発行したことが確認されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been confirmed that, of them, at least the three families of the Minokami/Yamamoto-Koide family, the Kurami-Koide family, and the Oyabu-Koide family issued Hatamoto-satsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been confirmed that, of them, at least the three families of the Minokami/Yamamoto-Koide family, the Kurami-Koide family, and the Oyabu-Koide family issued Hatamoto-satsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been confirmed that, of them, at least the Minokami and Yamamoto-Koide clans, the Kurami-Koide clan, and the Oyabu-Koide clan issued Hatamoto-satsu.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>播磨国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Harima Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Harima Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harima Province</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="130">
<j>播磨国では、藩札、旗本札、寺社札、町村札、私人札など、きわめて多様な札の発行が確認されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been confirmed that, in Harima Province, a quite variety of paper money, such as Han-satsu, Hatamoto-satsu, jisha-satsu, Cho-son satsu (paper money issued by a town or a village), and shijin-satsu (paper money issued by a private person), were issued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been confirmed that, in Harima Province, quite a variety of paper money, such as Han-satsu, Hatamoto-satsu, jisha-satsu, Cho-son satsu (paper money issued by a town or a village), and shijin-satsu (paper money issued by a private person), were issued.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been confirmed that, in Harima Province, quite a variety of paper money, such as Han-satsu, Hatamoto-satsu, Jisha-satsu, Choson-satsu (paper money issued by a town or a village), and Shijin-satsu (paper money issued by a private person), were issued.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>播磨国は全国でも有数の穀倉地帯で、畿内諸国と同様に商品作物の栽培が盛んであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harima Province was one of the richest grain-yielding areas in the nation, and, together with other provinces in the Kinai region, flourished in growing commercial farm products.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Harima Province was one of the richest grain-yielding areas in the nation, and, together with other provinces in the Kinai region, flourished in growing commercial farm products.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harima Province was one of the richest grain-yielding areas in the nation, and, together with other provinces in the Kinai region, flourished in growing commercial farm products.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>さらに、人口も多く、姫路藩、明石藩、赤穂藩などがまとまった所領を有するほかは典型的な非領国地域であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, with lots of population, the province was a typical Hi-ryogokuchiiki, except the Himeji domain, Akashi domain and Ako domain, each of which occupied a sizable territory.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, with their substantial population, the province was a typical Hi-ryogokuchiiki, except the Himeji domain, Akashi domain and Ako domain, each of which occupied a sizable territory.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, with their substantial population, the province was a typical Hi-ryogokuchiiki, except the Himeji clan, Akashi clan and Ako clan, each of which occupied a sizable territory.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>播磨国のほぼ中央部に位置する姫路藩は木綿の専売などで周辺経済に大きな影響力を有していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Located almost in the center of Harima Province, the Himeji domain had a big economic power affecting its surrounding areas, for example, through exclusive sales of cotton.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Located almost in the center of Harima Province, the Himeji domain had a sizable economic power that affected its surrounding areas, for example, the exclusive sales of cotton.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Located almost in the center of Harima Province, the Himeji clan had a sizable economic power that affected its surrounding areas, for example, the exclusive sales of cotton.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>しかしながら、周辺地域の経済は、西国街道、美作・因幡街道などの街道や、加古川、市川 (兵庫県)、揖保川などの船運といった物流経路に依存する形でそれぞれ緩やかな小経済地域を形成していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, each of the surrounding areas formed a relatively independent economic area, depending on road transportation along the Saigoku-kaido road or the Mimasaka/Inaba-kaido roads, or on water transportation on the Kako-gawa River, the Ichi-kawa River (in Hyogo Prefecture), or the Ibo-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, each of the surrounding areas formed a relatively independent economic area, depending on road transportation along the Saigoku-kaido road or the Mimasaka/Inaba-kaido roads, or on water transportation on the Kako-gawa River, the Ichi-kawa River (in Hyogo Prefecture), or the Ibo-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, each of the surrounding areas formed a relatively independent economic area, depending on road transportation along the Saigoku-kaido road or the Mimasaka and Inaba-kaido roads, or on water transportation on the Kako-gawa River, the Ichi-kawa River (in Hyogo Prefecture), or the Ibo-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>旗本札も、それぞれの小地域の影響が強い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hatamoto-satsu was strongly affected by the characteristics of each small territory of the Hatamoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hatamoto-satsu was strongly affected by the characteristics of each small territory of the Hatamoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hatamoto-satsu was strongly affected by the characteristics of each small territory of the Hatamoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="136">
<j>播磨国の藩札、旗本札の特徴としては銭匁札が広く発行されている点が挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a feature of the Han-satsu and Hatamoto-satsu in Harima Province that semme-satsu (see below) was issued widely.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a feature of the Han-satsu and Hatamoto-satsu in Harima Province that semme-satsu (see below) was issued widely.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a feature of the Han-satsu and Hatamoto-satsu in Harima Province that senme-satsu (paper money convertible to sen) was issued widely.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>銭匁札とは、額面表記は銀の単位である匁・分・厘であるが、一定の銀-銭相場に従って銭で兌換することが明記されたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Semme-satsu was the paper money with the following features: The face value was written in Monme, Bu, or Rin (each a monetary unit at that time) on it, but it was also written there that the money would be exchanged into zeni (copper or iron coins) based on a certain gin (silver coin)-zeni exchange rate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Semme-satsu was paper money with the following features: The face value was written in Monme, Bu, or Rin (each a monetary unit at that time), but it was also written there that the money would be exchanged into zeni (copper or iron coins) based on a certain gin (silver coin)-zeni exchange rate.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senme-satsu was a paper money with the following features: The face value was written in monme, bu, or rin (each a monetary unit at that time) of the silver unit, but it was also written there that the money would be exchanged into zeni (copper or iron coins) based on a certain gin (silver coin)-zeni exchange rate.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>備中国の永銭勘定や九州北部・四国西部の銭匁札などと並んで、江戸時代の貨幣経済システムを語る場合に興味深い商習慣である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When talking about the money economy system in the Edo period, this is an interesting business custom, together with the Eisen money-counting system in Bicchu Province and semme-satsu in the northern part of Kyushu and in the western part of Sikoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is an interesting business custom when talking about the monetary economy system in the Edo period, together with the Eisen money-counting system in Bicchu Province and semme-satsu in the northern part of Kyushu and in the western part of Sikoku.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is an interesting business custom when talking about the monetary economy system in the Edo period, together with the Eisen-kanjo (a calculational procedure using Eiraku-tsuho [bronze coins struck in the Ming dynasty] as a fictional unit) in Bitchu Province and senme-satsu in the northern part of Kyushu and in the western part of Shikoku.</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースを削除し、スペル修正、用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="139">
<j>揖東郡新宮の池田氏はもと東本願寺の執事であった下間氏であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ikeda family in Shingu, Itto County, was originally the Shimoma family, steward of Higashi-Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ikeda family in Shingu, Itto County, was originally the Shimoma family, steward of Higashi-Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ikeda clan in Shingu, Itto County, was originally the Shimoma clan, a steward of Higashi Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>しかしながら、執事職相続の際の内紛が原因で舅であった姫路藩主池田輝政の家臣となり、更に池田姓を名乗ることを許され、播磨新宮藩を創設した家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the family became a retainer of Terumasa IKEDA, the lord of the Himeji domain, due to an internal trouble in inheriting the steward post, was permitted to use the name of Ikeda, and then established the Harima-shingu domain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the family became a retainer of Terumasa IKEDA, the lord of the Himeji domain, due to internal problems in inheriting the steward post, and was permitted to use the name of Ikeda, and then established the Harima-shingu domain.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the clan became a retainer of his uncle Terumasa IKEDA, the lord of the Himeji clan, due to internal problems in inheriting the steward post, and was permitted to use the surname of Ikeda, and then established the Harima-Shingu clan.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。「舅であった」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>のちに無嗣改易となるところを、本家の岡山藩主・鳥取藩主家の奔走によって、減知の上で旗本としての存続が許された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, the family was going to be abolished due to no heir, but due to earnest efforts of the family of the Okayama domain lord and Tottori domain lord, its main family, was permitted to exist as a Hatamoto, though its territory was reduced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, the family was going to be abolished due to its lack of an heir, but as a result of earnest efforts by the family of the Okayama domain lord and Tottori domain lord, its main family, was permitted to exist as a Hatamoto, though its territory was reduced.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, the family was going to be abolished due to its lack of an heir, but as a result of earnest efforts by the family of the Okayama domain lord and Tottori clan&apos;s lord, its head family, was permitted to exist as a Hatamoto, although its territory was reduced.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更し、統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>陣屋は、新宮藩当時から引き続いて新宮（現・たつの市新宮町新宮）に置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its jinya was also placed in Singu (present Shingu, Shingu-cho, Tatsuno City) as in the era of the Shingu domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its jinya was also placed in Singu (present Shingu, Shingu-cho, Tatsuno City) in the era of the Shingu domain.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its jinya was also placed in Shingu (present Shingu, Shingu-cho, Tatsuno City) since the time of the Shingu clan.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>美作街道は姫路城の城下町のやや西で西国街道（山陽道）から分岐し、北西に伸びて美作国津山城下に達する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mimasaka-kaido road was branched from the Saigoku-kaido road (Sanyo-do road) in the slightly west of the Himeji-jo Castle town towards the northwest direct, reaching the area of Tsuyama-jo Castle in Mimasaka Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mimasaka-kaido road was branched from the Saigoku-kaido road (Sanyo-do road) slightly west of the Himeji-jo Castle town towards the northwest direct, reaching the area of Tsuyama-jo Castle in Mimasaka Province.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mimasaka-kaido road was branched from the Saigoku-kaido road (Sanyo-do road) slightly west of the Himeji-jo Castle town towards the northwest direct, reaching the area of Tsuyama-jo Castle town in Mimasaka Province.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>新宮の町は美作街道と水運が盛んであった揖保川とが接近する位置にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shingu town was located at the spot where the Mimasaka-kaido road came near to the Ibo-gawa River heavily used for water transportation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shingu town was located at the spot where the Mimasaka-kaido road came near to the Ibo-gawa River heavily used for water transportation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The town of Shingu was located at the spot where the Mimasaka-kaido road came near to the Ibo-gawa River heavily used for water transportation.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>新宮池田氏は銀札及び銭匁札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shingu-Ikeda family issued gin-satsu and semme-satsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shingu-Ikeda family issued gin-satsu and semme-satsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shingu-Ikeda clan issued gin-satsu and senme-satsu.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="146">
<j>美作街道を更に下ると、佐用郡佐用（現・佐用郡佐用町佐用）、佐用郡長谷（現・佐用郡佐用町口長谷）、佐用郡平福（現・佐用郡佐用町平福）の松井松平氏3旗本の知行地がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further down the Mimasaka-kaido road, there were the three chigyochi territories, each of three Matsui-Matudaira families, in Sayo, Sayo County (present Sayo, Sayo Town Sayo County), in Nagatani, Sayo County (present Kuchinagatani, Sayo Town, Sayo County), and in Hirafuku, Sayo County (present Hirafuku, Sayo Town Sayo County).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further down the Mimasaka-kaido road, there were the three chigyochi territories, each of three Matsui-Matudaira families, in Sayo, Sayo County (present Sayo, Sayo Town Sayo County), in Nagatani, Sayo County (present Kuchinagatani, Sayo Town, Sayo County), and in Hirafuku, Sayo County (present Hirafuku, Sayo Town Sayo County).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further down the Mimasaka-kaido road, there were the chigyo-chi territories of three Hatamoto of the Matsui-Matsudaira clan such as Sayo, Sayo County (present Sayo, Sayo Town, Sayo County), Nagatani, Sayo County (present Kuchinagatani, Sayo Town, Sayo County), and Hirafuku, Sayo County (present Hirafuku, Sayo Town, Sayo County).</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="147">
<j>これらの家は、いずれも山崎藩主の松井松平氏から、佐用郡内の所領を同時に分知されて旗本家として成立した同族である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With a portion of the territory, in Sayo County, of the Matsui-Matsudaira family, the lord of the Yamazaki domain, given at the same time, each of these families was established as a Hatamoto family, belonging to the same clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With a portion of the territory, in Sayo County, of the Matsui-Matsudaira family, the lord of the Yamazaki domain, given at the same time, each of these families was established as a Hatamoto family, belonging to the same clan.</e>
<cmt>Translation doesn’t make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These were the same clans derived from the Matsui-Matsudaira clan, the lord of Yamazaki clan, and established as Hatamoto families given the divided territories in Sayo County.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>佐用は美作街道の宿駅で、更に佐用からは北に因幡街道が分岐する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sayo was a shuku-eki (a relay station in road transportation) along the Mimasaka-kaido road, and was branched from there to the Inaba-kaido road in the north.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sayo was a shuku-eki (a relay station in road transportation) along the Mimasaka-kaido road, and was branched from there to the Inaba-kaido road in the north.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sayo was a shuku-eki (a relay station in road transportation) along the Mimasaka-kaido road, which was branched from Sayo to the Inaba-kaido road in the north.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>因幡街道の次の宿駅が平福で、長谷は平福のやや南に位置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hirafuku was a next shuku-eki along the Inaba-kaido road, and Nagatani was located slightly in the south of Hirafuku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hirafuku was a next shuku-eki along the Inaba-kaido road, and Nagatani was located slightly in the south of Hirafuku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hirafuku was a next shuku-eki along the Inaba-kaido road, and Nagatani was located slightly in the south of Hirafuku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>また、これらの陣屋の近傍には千種川水系が水運に利用されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, in the vicinity of each of these jinya places, the Chikusa-gawa River water system was used for water transportation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, in the vicinity of each of these jinya places, the Chikusa-gawa River water system was used for water transportation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, in the vicinity of each of these jinya places, the Chikusa-gawa River water system was used for water transportation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="151">
<j>地理的にも近い3家であるが、いずれも独自に紙幣を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the three families lived near to each other, each of them issued its own paper money.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the three families lived near to each other, each of them issued its own paper money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the three families lived near to each other, each of them issued its own paper money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="152">
<j>赤穂郡若狭野（現・相生市若狭野町若狭野）の浅野氏は千種川の下流の近傍に位置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Asano family in Wakasano, Ako County (present Wakasano, Wakasano-cho, Aioi City), was located in the neighborhood of the downstream of the Chikusa -gawa River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Asano family in Wakasano, Ako County (present Wakasano, Wakasano-cho, Aioi City), was located in the neighborhood downstream of the Chikusa -gawa River.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Asano clan in Wakasano, Ako County (present Wakasano, Wakasano-cho, Aioi City), was located in the neighborhood downstream of the Chikusa-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>元禄赤穂事件で著名な赤穂藩浅野家の分家であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This family was a branch of the Asano family in the Ako domain famous for the Ako incident in the Genroku era (1688 - 1704).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This family was a branch of the Asano family in the Ako domain famous for the Ako incident in the Genroku era (1688 - 1704).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This clan was a branch of the Asano family in the Ako clan famous for the Ako Incident in the Genroku era (1688 - 1704).</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="154">
<j>しかしながら、本家が改易となって赤穂藩が永井氏、更に森氏の支配となっても、赤穂藩領が大部分を占める赤穂郡の只中に所領を有した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, although its main family was abolished and the Ako domain became to be controlled by the Nagai family, followed by the Mori family, this family continued owning its territory within Ako County most of which area was occupied by the Ako domain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although its main family was abolished and the Ako domain came to be controlled by the Nagai family, followed by the Mori family, this family continued owning its territory within Ako County most of which was occupied by the Ako domain.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although its main family was abolished and the Ako clan came to be controlled by the Nagai clan, followed by the Mori clan, this clan continued owning its territory within Ako County most of which was occupied by the Ako clan.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>この若狭野浅野氏は大坂の両替商の天王寺屋などが引請人となった銀札、銭匁札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Undertaken by the Tennoji-ya money exchanger, this Wakasano-Asano family issued gin-satsu and semme-satsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Undertaken by the Tennoji-ya money exchanger, this Wakasano-Asano family issued gin-satsu and semme-satsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Undertaken by the Tennoji-ya money exchanger in Osaka, this Wakasano-Asano clan issued gin-satsu and senme-satsu.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。「大坂の」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>若狭野の陣屋跡地には紙幣関係業務を実施した役所の建物が現存している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the former jinya site in Wakasano, the office building where paper money-related jobs were done still exists.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the former jinya site in Wakasano, the office building where paper money-related jobs were done still exists.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the former jinya site in Wakasano, the office building where paper money-related jobs were done still exists.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="157">
<j>播磨国東部の加東郡家原（現・加東市家原）の浅野氏もまた、赤穂藩主家の分家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Asano family in Iehara, Kato County in the eastern part of Harima Province (present Iehara, Kato City), was also a branch of the main family of the Ako domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Asano family in Iehara, Kato County in the eastern part of Harima Province (present Iehara, Kato City), was also a branch of the main family of the Ako domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Asano clan in Iehara, Kato County (present Iehara, Kato City) in the eastern part of Harima Province, was also a branch of the main family of the Ako clan.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>また、赤穂藩浅野氏は居城が存在した赤穂郡の他に、加東郡にも領地を有し、加東郡穂積（現・加東市穂積）に飛地陣屋を置いていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Asano family in the Ako domain owned a territory in Kato County as well, in addition to Ako County where its castle residence was located, and placed a remote jinya in Hozumi, Kato County (present Hozumi, Kato City).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Asano family in the Ako domain owned a territory in Kato County as well, in addition to Ako County where its castle residence was located, and placed a remote jinya in Hozumi, Kato County (present Hozumi, Kato City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Asano clan in the Ako clan owned a territory in Kato County as well, in addition to Ako County where its castle residence was located, and placed a remote jinya in Hozumi, Kato County (present Hozumi, Kato City).</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>しかしながら、元禄赤穂事件に伴う赤穂藩浅野氏の改易後、幕府に公収され、のちに穂積を含む村々が旗本八木氏の知行地となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, after the Asano family in the Ako domain was abolished due to the Ako incident in the Genroku era, the site was confiscated by the bakufu, and villages including Hozumi became the territory of the Yagi family, Hatamoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after the Asano family in the Ako domain was abolished due to the Ako incident in the Genroku era, the site was confiscated by the bakufu, and villages including Hozumi became the territory of the Yagi family, Hatamoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after the Asano clan in the Ako clan was abolished due to the Ako Incident in the Genroku era, the site was officially confiscated by the bakufu, and villages including Hozumi became the territory of the Yagi clan, a Hatamoto.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>八木氏はこの浅野氏の穂積陣屋を采地陣屋とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yagi family used the Hozumi jinya, which had been the Asano family&apos;s, as the Jinya for its own territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yagi family used the Hozumi jinya, which had been the Asano family&apos;s, as the Jinya for its own territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yagi clan used the Hozumi jinya of the Asano clan as the jinya for its own territory.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="161">
<j>なお、八木氏は、のちに戦国大名となった朝倉氏から鎌倉時代に分かれた支族で、織田氏の但馬国侵攻の際には八木城主であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yagi family was in the lineage of the family branched in the Kamakura period from the Asakura family that became a daimyo later in the Sengoku period, and was the lord of Yagi-jo Castle when the Oda clan invaded Tajima Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yagi family a lineage of the family that branched in the Kamakura period from the Asakura family, which later became daimyo later in the Sengoku period, and was the lord of Yagi-jo Castle when the Oda clan invaded Tajima Province.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yagi clan, a lineage of the family that branched in the Kamakura period from the Asakura clan which later became Sengoku daimyo, was the lord of Yagi-jo Castle when the Oda clan invaded Tajima Province.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>しかしながら、織田氏と毛利氏との衝突により采地を失い、のちに関ヶ原の戦いでの戦功によって徳川家の旗本として取り立てられた家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, its territory was lost when the Mori clan fought with the Oda clan, and the family was picked as Hatamoto by the Tokugawa family, due to its distinguished accomplishments in the Battle of Sekigahara later.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, its territory was lost when the Mori clan fought with the Oda clan, and the family was picked as Hatamoto by the Tokugawa family, due to its distinguished accomplishments in the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, its territory was lost when the Mori clan fought with the Oda clan, and the clan was picked as Hatamoto of the Tokugawa family, by its distinguished accomplishments in the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="163">
<j>家原は加古川支流の千鳥川の近傍、穂積は千鳥川と加古川の合流地点付近に位置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iehara was located in the vicinity of the Chidori-gawa River, a tributary of the Kako-gawa River, and Hozumi around the place where the Chidori-gawa River and the Kako-gawa River merged.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iehara was located in the vicinity of the Chidori-gawa River, a tributary of the Kako-gawa River, and Hozumi around the place where the Chidori-gawa River and the Kako-gawa River merged.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iehara was located in the vicinity of the Chidori-gawa River, a tributary of the Kako-gawa River, and Hozumi around the place where the Chidori-gawa River and the Kako-gawa River merged.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="164">
<j>家原浅野氏及び穂積八木氏は、それぞれ銀札及び銭匁札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Either of the Iehara-Asano family and the Hozumi-Yagi family issued its own gin-satsu and semme-satsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both the Iehara-Asano family and the Hozumi-Yagi family issued its own gin-satsu and semme-satsu.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both the Iehara-Asano clan and the Hozumi-Yagi clan issued own gin-satsu and senme-satsu.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="165">
<j>美嚢郡高木（現・三木市別所町高木）の一柳氏は、伊予西条藩主家が改易となり、のち許されて旗本として取り立てられるにあたり、高木を中心とした村々に知行を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having once been the lord family of the Iyo-Saijo domain that was abolished, the Hitotsuyanagi family in Takagi, Mino County (present Takagi, Bessho-cho, Miki City), was given, as its territory, villages centered on Takagi, when the family was pardoned later and was given the status of Hatamoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having once been the lord family of the Iyo-Saijo domain that was abolished, the Hitotsuyanagi family in Takagi, Mino County (present Takagi, Bessho-cho, Miki City), was given, as its territory, villages centered on Takagi, when the family was pardoned later and was given the status of Hatamoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the lord family of the Iyo-Saijo clan was abolished then pardoned later to become a Hatamoto, the Hitotsuyanagi clan in Takagi, Mino County (present Takagi, Bessho-cho, Miki City), was given villages centered on Takagi as its territory.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="166">
<j>高木は別所氏が拠った三木城の城下町で、豊臣秀吉が免税地としたために金物の町として発展した三木町の近隣に位置し、少し北には加古川の支流である美嚢川が西行している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takagi was located near to Miki Town that was the castle town of Bessho family&apos;s Miki-jo Castle and flourished as a hardware town, because Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI gave the town the tax-free privilege, and slightly in the north, the Mino-gawa river, a tributary of the Kako-gawa River, flowed to the west.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takagi was located near Miki Town which was a castle town of the Bessho family&apos;s Miki-jo Castle and flourished as a hardware town, because Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI gave the town a tax-free privilege, and slightly in the north, the Mino-gawa river, a tributary of the Kako-gawa River, flowed to the west.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takagi was the Miki-jo Castle town where the Bessho clan lived, near Miki Town which was flourished as a hardware town by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI giving the town a tax-free privilege, and slightly in the north, the Mino-gawa river, a tributary of the Kako-gawa River, flowed to the west.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>美嚢郡は木綿の生産地であり、高木一柳氏は木綿切手形式の紙幣を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With Mino County producing cotton, the Takagi-Hitotsuyanaga family issued paper money in the form of stamps for cotton.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With Mino County producing cotton, the Takagi-Hitotsuyanaga family issued paper money in the form of stamps for cotton.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With Mino County producing cotton, the Takagi-Hitotsuyanagi clan issued paper money in the form of stamps for cotton.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="168">
<j>神東郡福本（現・神崎郡神河町福本）の池田氏は、鳥取藩の支藩として立藩した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ikeda family in Fukumoto, Jinto County (present Fukumoto, Kamikawa Town, Kanzaki County), was established as a branch domain of the Tottori domain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ikeda family in Fukumoto, Jinto County (present Fukumoto, Kamikawa Town, Kanzaki County), was established as a branch domain of the Tottori domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ikeda clan in Fukumoto, Jinto County (present Fukumoto, Kamikawa Town, Kanzaki County), was established as a branch clan of the Tottori clan.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="169">
<j>しかしながら、のちに分家を創設した際に一万石を割ったために交代寄合表御礼衆の旗本となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, because its earning became less than 10,000 koku after the family generated branch families, it became a Hatamoto with the kogoyoriai-omoteoreishu status.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, because its earning came to less than 10,000 koku after the family generated branch families, it became a Hatamoto with kogoyoriai-omoteoreishu status.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, because its earning came to less than 10,000 koku after generating branch families, it became a Hatamoto with kotaiyoriai-omoteoreishu status.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>福本池田氏及びその分家2家（屋形池田氏・吉冨池田氏）の所領は、市川 (兵庫県)の上流域に当たる神東郡及び神西郡の北部を占め、福本は市川の東岸近傍にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The territories of the Fukumoto-Ikeda family and of its two branch families (the Ogata-Ikeda family and the Yoshitomi-Ikeda family) occupied Jinto County and the northern part of Jinsei County in the upper reaches of the Ichi-kawa River (in Hyogo Prefecture), with Kufumoto located near to the east side of the Ichi-kawa River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The territories of the Fukumoto-Ikeda family and that of its two branch families (the Ogata-Ikeda family and the Yoshitomi-Ikeda family) occupied Jinto County and the northern part of Jinsei County in the upper reaches of the Ichi-kawa River (in Hyogo Prefecture), with Kufumoto located near the east side of the Ichi-kawa River.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The territory of the Fukumoto-Ikeda clan and that of its two branch families (the Ogata-Ikeda clan and the Yoshitomi-Ikeda clan) occupied Jinto County and the northern part of Jinsai County in the upper reaches of the Ichi-kawa River (in Hyogo Prefecture), with Kufumoto located near the east side of the Ichi-kawa River.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="171">
<j>幕末に鳥取藩から蔵米支給を受けて再度立藩したが、福本池田氏は旗本であった文政5年（1822年）及び立藩後の明治初年に銀札及び銭匁札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although established a domain getting kuramai from the Tottori domain, the Fukumoto-Ikeda family issued gin-satsu and semme-satsu in 1822 when the family was a Hatamoto, as well as in 1868 after having established its own domain newly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although they established a domain that recieved kuramai from the Tottori domain, the Fukumoto-Ikeda family issued gin-satsu and semme-satsu in 1822 when the family was a Hatamoto, as well as in 1868 after having newly established its own domain.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although they reestablished a clan by receiving kuramai from the Tottori clan in the end of the Edo period, the Fukumoto-Ikeda clan issued gin-satsu and senme-satsu in 1822 when the clan was a Hatamoto, as well as in 1868 after having newly established its own clan.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。「幕末に」「再度」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>中国・四国地方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Chubu region and in the Shikoku region</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Chubu region and the Shikoku region</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chubu region and Shikoku region</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="172">
<j>中国地方及び四国地方は岡山藩（備前国、現・岡山県南東部）・広島藩（安芸国、現・広島県西部）・長州藩（長門国・周防国、現・山口県のそれぞれ西部・東部）・鳥取藩（因幡国・伯耆国、現・鳥取県のそれぞれ東部及び西部）・松江藩（出雲国、現・島根県東部）、徳島藩（阿波国・淡路国、現・徳島県及び兵庫県淡路島）、高知藩（土佐国、現・高知県）といった国持ち大名が多かった地方であり、非領国地域の支配形態をとり、かつ旗本領が散在するのは備中国（現・岡山県西部）のみである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Chugoku and Shikoku regions, many kunimochi-daimyo (daimyo with a big territory), such as the Okayama domain (in Bizen Province, the present southeastern part of Okayama Prefecture), the Hiroshima domain (in Aki Province, present western part of Hiroshima Prefecture), the Choshu domain (in Nagato Province and Suo Province, the present western and eastern parts of Yamaguchi Prefecture), the Tottori domain (in Inaba Province and Hoki Province, present the western and eastern parts of Tottori Prefecture), the Matsue domain (in Izumo Province, the present eastern part of Shimane Prefecture), the Tokushima domain (in Awa Province and Awaji Province, present Tokushima Prefecture and Awaji-shima Island, Hyogo Prefecture), and the Kochi domain (in Tosa Province, present Kochi Prefecture), existed, and only Bicchu Province was in the hi-ryogokuchiiki state, with small Hatamoto territories located within.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Chugoku and Shikoku regions, many kunimochi-daimyo (daimyo with a big territory), such as the Okayama domain (in Bizen Province, the present southeastern part of Okayama Prefecture), the Hiroshima domain (in Aki Province, present western part of Hiroshima Prefecture), the Choshu domain (in Nagato Province and Suo Province, the present western and eastern parts of Yamaguchi Prefecture), the Tottori domain (in Inaba Province and Hoki Province, present the western and eastern parts of Tottori Prefecture), the Matsue domain (in Izumo Province, the present eastern part of Shimane Prefecture), the Tokushima domain (in Awa Province and Awaji Province, present Tokushima Prefecture and Awaji-shima Island, Hyogo Prefecture), and the Kochi domain (in Tosa Province, present Kochi Prefecture), existed, and only Bicchu Province was in the hi-ryogokuchiiki state, with small Hatamoto territories located within.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many kunimochi-daimyo (daimyo with a big territory) were in the Chugoku and Shikoku regions, such as the Okayama clan (Bizen Province, present southeastern part of Okayama Prefecture), the Hiroshima clan (Aki Province, present western part of Hiroshima Prefecture), the Choshu clan (Nagato and Suo Provinces, present western and eastern parts of Yamaguchi Prefecture), the Tottori clan (Inaba and Hoki Provinces, present the western and eastern parts of Tottori Prefecture), the Matsue clan (Izumo Province, present eastern part of Shimane Prefecture), the Tokushima clan (Awa and Awaji Provinces, present Tokushima Prefecture and Awaji-shima Island, Hyogo Prefecture), and the Kochi clan (Tosa Province, present Kochi Prefecture), and only Bitchu Province (present western part of Okayama Prefecture) was in the hi-ryogokuchiiki state where Hatamoto territories were scattered.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。「現・岡山県西部」を補足し、用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>備中国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Bicchu Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Bicchu Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bitchu Province</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="173">
<j>備中国は5万石の備中松山藩以下、あわせて8の小藩及び10以上の旗本家、幕府領及び御三卿領などで占められていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bicchu Province was occupied by the 50,000-koku Bicchu-Matsuyama domain, by seven small domains, by the territories of more than ten Hatamoto families, by the territory of the bakufu and by those of gosankyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bicchu Province was occupied by the 50,000-koku Bicchu-Matsuyama domain, by seven small domains, by territories of more than ten Hatamoto families, by the territory of the bakufu and those of gosankyo.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bitchu Province was occupied by 8 clans and more than 10 territories of Hatamoto families, the bakufu, and the Gosankyo, and so on including the 50,000-koku Bitchu-Matsuyama clan.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="174">
<j>これらのうち、同国の全ての藩及び自ら陣屋を構えて領地経営を行っていた旗本のほぼ全てが藩札・旗本札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of them, all of the domains in the province and almost all of the Hatamoto who placed their jinya offices in their territories in the province to manage them issued Han-satsu or Hatamoto-satsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of them, all of the domains in the province and almost all of the Hatamoto who placed their jinya offices in their territories in the province to manage them issued Han-satsu or Hatamoto-satsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of them, all of the clans and almost all of the Hatamoto who placed their jinya offices to manage their territories in the province issued Han-satsu or Hatamoto-satsu.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="175">
<j>備中国は町村や豪農・豪商などが発行した私札類の種類が多いことでも知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bicchu Province is also known as the area where a variety of private paper money and the like were issued as well by towns, villages, wealthy farmers or wealthy merchants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bicchu Province is also known as an area where a variety of private paper money and the like were issued as well by towns, villages, wealthy farmers or wealthy merchants.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bitchu Province is also known as an area where a variety of private paper money and the like were issued as well by towns, villages, wealthy farmers or wealthy merchants, and so on.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="176">
<j>備中国の旗本で旗本札を発行した家は、戦国大名の有力家臣の末裔や、徳川幕府での大名が減知されて旗本となった家、あるいは大名家の分家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hatamoto families that issued Hatamoto-satsu in Bicchu Province were descendants of powerful retainers of daimyo in the Sengoku period, the Hatamoto families that had originally been daimyo but became Hatamoto because their territories were reduced, or branch families of daimyo families.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hatamoto families that issued Hatamoto-satsu in Bicchu Province were descendants of powerful retainers of daimyo in the Sengoku period, the Hatamoto families that had originally been daimyo but became Hatamoto because their territories were reduced, or branch families of daimyo families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hatamoto families that issued Hatamoto-satsu in Bitchu Province were descendants of powerful retainers of Sengoku daimyo, the Hatamoto families that had originally been daimyo of the Tokugawa shogunate but became Hatamoto because their territories were reduced, or branch families of daimyo families.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。「徳川幕府での」を補足し、用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="177">
<j>賀陽郡浅尾（現・岡山県総社市門田）の蒔田氏（浅尾藩主、のち知行の一部を分知して旗本、更に幕末に高直しにより再び立藩）と、浅尾蒔田氏から分知を受けて成立した旗本、窪屋郡三須（現・岡山県総社市三須）の三須蒔田氏はそれぞれ独自に旗本札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Maita family in Asao, Kaya County (present Monde, Shoja City, Okayama Prefecture) (that had originally been the lord of the Aso domain, became a Hatamoto because its territory was reduced due to its division, but later established a domain again due to a review towards increasing the amount of rice crop earned), and the Misu-Maita family in Misu, Boya County, which was established getting a portion of the Aso-Maita family&apos;s territory, issued their own Hatamoto-satsu respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Maita family in Asao, Kaya County (present Monde, Shoja City, Okayama Prefecture) (that had originally been the lord of the Aso domain, became a Hatamoto because their territory was reduced after being divided, but later established a domain again due to a review towards increasing the amount of rice produced), and the Misu-Maita family in Misu, Boya County, which was established getting a portion of the Aso-Maita family&apos;s territory, issued their own Hatamoto-satsu respectively.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Maita clan (the lord of the Asao clan, later Hatamoto reduced its territory, then reestablished the clan by a review towards increasing the amount of rice produced in the end of the Edo period) in Asao, Kaya County (present Monde, Soja City, Okayama Prefecture), and the Misu-Maita clan in Misu, Boya County (present Misu, Soja City, Okayama Prefecture), which was a Hatamoto established getting a portion of the Aso-Maita clan&apos;s territory, issued their own Hatamoto-satsu respectively.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。「幕末に」「現・岡山県総社市三須」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="178">
<j>川上郡成羽（現・岡山県高梁市成羽町下原）の山崎氏は肥後国富岡藩や讃岐国丸亀藩などを治めた大名山崎氏の分家で、本家が無嗣改易となったのちも、かつて本家が城主をつとめたことのある成羽城の跡地に陣屋を構えて存続した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yamazaki family in Nariwa, (present Shimohara, Nariwa-cho, Takahashi City, Okayama Prefecture), was a branch family of the Yamazaki family, a daimyo, which governed the Tomioka domain in Higo Province and the Marugame domain in the Sanuki Province, and continued existing with its jinya placed in the former Nariwa-jo Castle site, even after its main family was abolished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yamazaki family in Nariwa, (present Shimohara, Nariwa-cho, Takahashi City, Okayama Prefecture), was a branch family of the Yamazaki family, a daimyo, which governed the Tomioka domain in Higo Province and the Marugame domain in the Sanuki Province, and continued to exist with its jinya placed in the former Nariwa-jo Castle site, even after its main family was abolished.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yamazaki clan in Nariwa, Kawakami County (present Shimohara, Nariwa-cho, Takahashi City, Okayama Prefecture), was a branch family of the Yamazaki clan, a daimyo which governed the Tomioka clan in Higo Province and the Marugame clan in the Sanuki Province, and so on, and continued to exist with its jinya placed in the former Nariwa-jo Castle site of which the main family once served as the keeper, even after its main family was abolished.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。「川上郡」「かつて本家が城主をつとめたことのある」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="179">
<j>交代寄合表御礼衆として遇され、明治維新後に高直しにより立藩した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was treated a Hatamoto with the yoriai-omoteoreisho status, and established its own domain after Meiji Restoration, due to a review towards increasing the amount of rice crop earned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was treated a Hatamoto with the yoriai-omoteoreisho status, and established its own domain after the Meiji Restoration, due to a review towards increasing the amount of rice produced.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was treated as a kotaiyoriai-omoteoreishu status, and established its own clan after the Meiji Restoration by a review towards increasing the amount of rice produced.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="180">
<j>成羽山崎氏も、旗本であった時期に札を発行している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nariwa-Yamazaki family also issued Hatamoto-satsu when having been a Hatamoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nariwa-Yamazaki family also issued Hatamoto-satsu when they were a Hatamoto.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nariwa-Yamazaki clan also issued Hatamoto-satsu when they were a Hatamoto.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="181">
<j>戸川氏は、元は戦国大名宇喜多氏の家臣であったが、宇喜多家の内紛の際に徳川家康の仲介があった縁で、のちに旗本に取り立てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having originally been a retainer of the Ukita family, a daimyo in the Sengoku period, the Togawa family was given the Hatamoto status due to Ieyasu Tokugawa&apos;s acquaintance the family made when Ieyasu mediated an internal trouble in the Ukita family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having originally been a retainer of the Ukita family, a daimyo in the Sengoku period, the Togawa family was given Hatamoto status due to their aquaintenance with Ieyasu Tokugaw that they made when Ieyasu mediated an internal issue that occured in the Ukita family.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having originally been a retainer of the Ukita clan, a Sengoku daimyo, the Togawa clan was given Hatamoto status because of their acquaintance with Ieyasu TOKUGAWA related with his intermediacy on internal issues of the Ukita family.</e>
<cmt>スペル、用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="182">
<j>旗本戸川氏一族は大きく4家に分かれ、都宇郡撫川（現・岡山県岡山市撫川）の撫川戸川氏（庭瀬藩主から減知により交代寄合表御礼衆）、都宇郡妹尾（現・岡山県岡山市妹尾）の妹尾戸川氏、都宇郡早島（現・岡山県都窪郡早島町早島）の早島戸川氏、都宇郡帯江（現・岡山県倉敷市羽島）の帯江戸川氏がそれぞれ独自に旗本札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hatamoto Togawa clan consisted largely of the four families of the Natsukawa-Togawa family in Natsukawa, Tsuu County (present Natsukawa, Okayama City, Okayama Prefecture) (the family had originally been the lord of the Niwase domain but was given the kotai-omoteoreishu status after its territory was reduced), the Senoo-Togawa family in Senoo, Tsuu County (present Senoo, Okayama City, Okayama Prefecture), the Hayashima-Togawa family in Hayashima, Tsuu County (present Hayashima, Hayashima Town, Tukubo County, Okayama Prefecture), and the Obie-Togawa family in Obie, Tsuu County (present Hashima, Kurashiki City, Okayama Prefecture), and each of them issued its won Hatamoto-satsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hatamoto Togawa clan consisted largely of the four families of the Natsukawa-Togawa family in Natsukawa, Tsuu County (present Natsukawa, Okayama City, Okayama Prefecture) (the family had originally been the lord of the Niwase domain but was given the kotai-omoteoreishu status after its territory was reduced), the Senoo-Togawa family in Senoo, Tsuu County (present Senoo, Okayama City, Okayama Prefecture), the Hayashima-Togawa family in Hayashima, Tsuu County (present Hayashima, Hayashima Town, Tukubo County, Okayama Prefecture), and the Obie-Togawa family in Obie, Tsuu County (present Hashima, Kurashiki City, Okayama Prefecture), and each of them issued its won Hatamoto-satsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hatamoto Togawa clan consisted largely of the four families of the Natsukawa-Togawa clan (from the lord of the Niwase clan to be kotaiyoriai-omoteoreishu status by reducing its territory) in Natsukawa, Tsu County (present Natsukawa, Okayama City, Okayama Prefecture), the Seno-Togawa clan in Seno, Tsu County (present Seno, Okayama City, Okayama Prefecture), the Hayashima-Togawa clan in Hayashima, Tsu County (present Hayashima, Hayashima Town, Tsukubo County, Okayama Prefecture), and the Obie-Togawa clan in Obie, Tsu County (present Hashima, Kurashiki City, Okayama Prefecture), and each of them issued its own Hatamoto-satsu.</e>
<cmt>スペル、用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="183">
<j>花房氏もまた宇喜多氏の家臣であったが、宇喜多家の内紛ののち徳川家康の庇護下に入り、関ヶ原の戦いで東軍についた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having been a retainer of the Ukita family as well, the Hanabusa family taken under Ieyasu Tokugawa&apos;s protection after an internal trouble in the Ukita family, and belonged to the east group in the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having been a retainer of the Ukita family as well, the Hanabusa family taken under Ieyasu Tokugawa&apos;s protection after an internal issued occurred within the Ukita family, and belonged to the east group in the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having been a retainer of the Ukita clan as well, the Hanabusa clan was taken under Ieyasu TOKUGAWA&apos;s protection after an internal issued in the Ukita family, and belonged to the East squad in the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="184">
<j>更に戦後処理で備中国の鎮撫に当たった功によって旗本に取り立てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, the family was given the Hatamoto status for the reason that the family contributed to stabilizing the state of Bicchu Province in the post-war operations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the family was given Hatamoto status for the reason that the family contributed to stabilizing the state of Bicchu Province in post-war operations.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the clan was given Hatamoto status for the reason that the clan contributed to stabilize the state of Bitchu Province in post-battle operations.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="185">
<j>豊臣秀吉の水攻め（備中高松城の戦い）で有名な備中高松城の近傍、賀陽郡高松の原古才（現・岡山県岡山市高松原古才）に陣屋を置き、旗本札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Placing its jinya in Harakosai of Takamatsu, Kayo County, a neighborhood of Bicchu-Takamatsu-jo Castle famous for the inundation tactics of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI (the fighting at Bicchu-Takamatsu-jo Castle), the family issued Hatamoto-satsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Placing its jinya in Harakosai of Takamatsu, Kayo County, a neighborhood of Bicchu-Takamatsu-jo Castle famous for the inundation tactics of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI (the fighting at Bicchu-Takamatsu-jo Castle), the family issued Hatamoto-satsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Placing its jinya in Harakosai of Takamatsu, Kayo County (present Takamatsuhara Kosai, Okayama City, Okayama Prefecture), a neighborhood of Bitchu-Takamatsu-jo Castle famous for the inundation tactics of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI (the Battle of Bitchu-Takamatsu-jo Castle), the clan issued Hatamoto-satsu.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。「現・岡山県岡山市高松原古才」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="186">
<j>また、都宇郡津寺（現・岡山県岡山市津寺）の旗本榊原氏は花房氏の出自であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sakakibara family, a Hatamoto in Tsudera, Tsuu County (present Tsudera, Okayama City, Okayama Prefecture), originated in the Hanabusa family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sakakibara family, a Hatamoto in Tsudera, Tsuu County (present Tsudera, Okayama City, Okayama Prefecture), originated in the Hanabusa family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sakakibara clan, a Hatamoto in Tsudera, Tsu County (present Tsudera, Okayama City, Okayama Prefecture), originated in the Hanabusa clan.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="187">
<j>しかしながら、徳川家康に取り立てられる際に仲介の労をとった譜代大名榊原氏の恩に報いるために姓を榊原に改めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when having been picked by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, the family changed its name to Sakakibara to show its gratitude to the efforts of the Sakakibara family that acted as the intermediary.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after being picked by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, the family changed its name to Sakakibara to show its gratitude to the efforts of the Sakakibara family that acted as an intermediary.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, on being picked by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, the clan changed its name to Sakakibara to show its gratitude to the efforts of the Sakakibara clan, a fudai daimyo (a daimyo in hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family) acting as an intermediary.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。「譜代大名」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="188">
<j>津寺榊原氏も旗本札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tsudera-Sakakibara family issued Hatamoto-satsu as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tsudera-Sakakibara family issued Hatamoto-satsu as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tsudera-Sakakibara clan issued Hatamoto-satsu as well.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="189">
<j>水谷氏は、備中松山藩主であったが、本家は無嗣改易となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mizutani family was the lord of Bicchu-Matsuyama domain, but was abolished due to having no heir.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mizutani family was the lord of Bicchu-Matsuyama domain, but was abolished due to having no heir.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mizutani clan was the lord of Bitchu-Matsuyama clan, but was abolished due to having no heir.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="190">
<j>しかし、旗本として阿賀郡小阪部（現・岡山県新見市大佐小阪部）の小阪部水谷氏と、川上郡布賀（現・岡山県高梁市備中町布賀）の布賀黒鳥水谷氏が存続してそれぞれ独自に旗本札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Osakabe-Mizutani in Osakabe, Aga County (present Osaosakabe, Niimi City, Okayama Prefecture), and the Fukakokucho-Mizutani family in Fuka, Kawakami County (present (fuci, Bicchu-cho, Takahashi City, Okayama Prefecture) existed as Hatamoto, and each issued its own Hatamoto-satsu.</e>
<cmt>布賀黒鳥：　正しい読み、不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Osakabe-Mizutani in Osakabe, Aga County (present Osaosakabe, Niimi City, Okayama Prefecture), and the Fukakokucho-Mizutani family in Fuka, Kawakami County (present (fuci, Bicchu-cho, Takahashi City, Okayama Prefecture) existed as Hatamoto, and each issued its own Hatamoto-satsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Osakabe-Mizutani clan in Osakabe, Aga County (present Osaosakabe, Niimi City, Okayama Prefecture), and the Fukakokucho-Mizutani clan in Fuka, Kawakami County (present Fuka, Bitchu-cho, Takahashi City, Okayama Prefecture) existed as Hatamoto, and each issued its own Hatamoto-satsu.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="191">
<j>後月郡井原（現・岡山県井原市井原町）の旗本池田氏は、鳥取藩や岡山藩の池田氏と同族であり、池田輝政の実弟の初代備中松山藩主池田長幸の子孫である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ikeda family, a Hatamoto in Ibara, Itsuki County (present Ibara-cho, Ibara City, Okayama Prefecture), belonged to the same clan as that of the Ikeda family in the Tottori domain and in the Okayama domain, and was a descendant of Nagayoshi IKEDA, who was a younger brother of Terumasa IKEDA and the first lord of the Bicchu-Matsuyama domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ikeda family, a Hatamoto in Ibara, Itsuki County (present Ibara-cho, Ibara City, Okayama Prefecture), belonged to the same clan as that of the Ikeda family in the Tottori domain and in the Okayama domain, and was a descendant of Nagayoshi IKEDA, who was a younger brother of Terumasa IKEDA and the first lord of the Bicchu-Matsuyama domain.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ikeda clan, a Hatamoto in Ibara, Itsuki County (present Ibara-cho, Ibara City, Okayama Prefecture), belonged to the same clan as that of the Ikeda clan in the Tottori clan and in the Okayama clan, and was a descendant of Nagayoshi IKEDA, who was a younger biological brother of Terumasa IKEDA and the first lord of the Bitchu-Matsuyama clan.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="192">
<j>井原池田氏は本家の備中松山藩池田家が無嗣断絶したのちも存続し、旗本札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ibara-Ikeda family continued existing even after its main family, the Ikeda family of the Bicchu-Matsuyama domain, was abolished due to having no heir, and issued Hatamoto-satsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ibara-Ikeda family continued to exist even after its main family, the Ikeda family of the Bicchu-Matsuyama domain, was abolished due to lack of an heir, and was issued Hatamoto-satsu.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ibara-Ikeda clan continued to exist even after its main family, the Ikeda family of the Bitchu-Matsuyama clan, was abolished due to lack of an heir, and was issued Hatamoto-satsu.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="193">
<j>備中国では、藩札及び旗本札の一部に永銭勘定による額面記載がある場合が散見される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A few of the Han-satsu or Hatamoto-satsu in Bicchu Province was found on which the worth of paper money was written using the Eisen money-counting method.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A few of the Han-satsu or Hatamoto-satsu in Bicchu Province was found on which the worth of paper money was written using Eisen money-counting method.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A few of the Han-satsu or Hatamoto-satsu in Bitchu Province was often found written on the face value by Eisen-kanjo procedure.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="194">
<j>永銭とは、室町時代から、江戸幕府による貨幣制度が整う江戸時代初期まで全国的に流通した永楽通寶銭を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eisen indicated the Eiraku-tsuho coins (bronze coins struck in the Ming dynasty) that were used throughout the nation from the Muromachi period to the early Edo period when the currency system by the bakufu was established</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eisen indicated the Eiraku-tsuho coins (bronze coins struck in the Ming dynasty) that were used throughout the nation from the Muromachi period to the early Edo period when the currency system by the bakufu was established</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eisen referred the Eiraku-tsuho coins (bronze coins struck in the Ming dynasty) that were used throughout the nation from the Muromachi period to the early Edo period when the currency system by the Edo bakufu was established.</e>
<cmt>用語を補足、変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="195">
<j>永楽通寶銭自体は幕府により通用を禁止されたが、呼称は江戸期を通じて永銭一貫文（一千文）を金一両とする金の補助単位として使用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Use of the Eiraku-tsuho coins itself was prohibited by the Edo bakufu, but the name itself was used as an auxiliary monetary unit, with 1kamon (1,000 mon) of Eisen set being equivalent to 1 ryo of gold.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Use of the Eiraku-tsuho coins itself was prohibited by the Edo bakufu, but the name itself was used as an auxiliary monetary unit, with 1kamon (1,000 mon) of Eisen set being equivalent to 1 ryo of gold.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Use of the Eiraku-tsuho coins itself was prohibited by the Edo bakufu, but the name itself was used as an auxiliary monetary unit through the Edo period, with 1 kamon (1,000 mon) of Eisen set being equivalent to 1 ryo (a unit of currency) of gold.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。「江戸期を通じて」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="196">
<j>永銭勘定自体は両替商等でも一般に使用されたが、紙幣の額面として用いられている点はこの地域に特有の特徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Eisen-counting method itself was generally used, for example, by money exchangers, but it was a feature specific for this area that this method was used for expressing the monetary worth of paper money.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Eisen-counting method itself was generally used, for example, by money exchangers, but it was a feature specific for this area in that the method was used for expressing the monetary worth of paper money.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Eisen-kanjo procedure itself was generally used, for example, by money exchangers, but it was a feature specific for this area in that the procedure was used for expressing the monetary worth of paper money.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>九州地方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kyushu region</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kyushu region</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyushu region</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="197">
<j>九州地方において旗本札を発行したことが知られているのは豊前国（現・福岡県東部及び大分県北東部）時枝の小笠原氏、豊後国（現・大分県の北東部を除く地域）立石の木下氏、肥後国（現・熊本県及び宮崎県南西の山間部）米良の米良氏である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is known that, in the Kyushu region, the Ogasawara family in Tokieda of Buzen Province (the present eastern part of Fukuoka Prefecture and the present northeastern part of Oita Prefecture), the Kinoshita family in Tateishi of Bungo Province (present Oita Prefecture, excluding its northeastern part), and the Mera family in Mera of Higo Province (present Kumamoto Prefecture and the present Mountainous area in the southwestern part of Miyazaki Prefecture) issued Hatamoto-satsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is known that, in the Kyushu region, the Ogasawara family in Tokieda of Buzen Province (the present eastern part of Fukuoka Prefecture and the present northeastern part of Oita Prefecture), the Kinoshita family in Tateishi of Bungo Province (present Oita Prefecture, excluding its northeastern part), and the Mera family in Mera of Higo Province (present Kumamoto Prefecture and the present Mountainous area in the southwestern part of Miyazaki Prefecture) issued Hatamoto-satsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is known that, in the Kyushu region, the Ogasawara clan in Tokieda of Buzen Province (present eastern part of Fukuoka Prefecture and northeastern part of Oita Prefecture), the Kinoshita clan in Tateishi, Bungo Province (present Oita Prefecture, excluding its northeastern part), and the Mera clan in Mera, Higo Province (present Kumamoto Prefecture and mountainous area in the southwestern part of Miyazaki Prefecture) issued Hatamoto-satsu.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>豊前国・豊後国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Buzen Province and in Bungo Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Buzen Province and in Bungo Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buzen and Bungo Provinces</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="198">
<j>時枝小笠原氏は中津藩藩主家の分家で、豊前国時枝（現・大分県宇佐市下時枝）を中心とした5,000石を領する旗本であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being a branch family of the lord family of the Nakatsu domain, the Tokieda-Ogasawara family was a Hatamoto that had a territory producing a 5,000 koku of rice crop, centered on Tokieda of Buzen Province (present Shimo-Tokieda, Usa City, Oita Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Being a branch family of the lord family of the Nakatsu domain, the Tokieda-Ogasawara family was a Hatamoto that had a territory that produced 5,000 koku of rice crop, centered on Tokieda of Buzen Province (present Shimo-Tokieda, Usa City, Oita Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Being a branch family of the lord family of the Nakatsu clan, the Tokieda-Ogasawara clan was a Hatamoto that had a territory that produced 5,000 koku of rice crop, centered on Tokieda of Buzen Province (present Shimo-Tokieda, Usa City, Oita Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="199">
<j>時枝小笠原氏が発行した旗本札には、文政9年（1826年）に時枝産物会所、安政5年（1858年）に時枝勘定所より発行した銭匁札などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hatamoto-satsu issued by the Tokieda-Ogasawara family included the Semme-satsu issued in 1826 from Tokieda-bussankaisho (the product business promotion body in Tokieda) and the Semme-satsu issued in 1858 from Tokieda-kanjosho (the organization handling financial and public affairs in Tokieda).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hatamoto-satsu issued by the Tokieda-Ogasawara family included the Semme-satsu issued in 1826 from Tokieda-bussankaisho (the product business promotion body in Tokieda) and the Semme-satsu issued in 1858 from Tokieda-kanjosho (the organization handling financial and public affairs in Tokieda).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hatamoto-satsu issued by the Tokieda-Ogasawara clan included the senme-satsu issued in 1826 from Tokieda-sanbutsukaisho (the product business promotion body in Tokieda) and that issued in 1858 from Tokieda-kanjosho (the organization handling financial and public affairs in Tokieda).</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="200">
<j>立石木下氏は日出藩藩主家の分家で、豊後国立石（現・大分県杵築市山香町立石）を中心とした5,000石の交代寄合表御礼衆であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tateishi-Kinoshita family, a branch of the lord family of the Hiji domain, was given the kotaiyoriai-omoteoreishu status, with a 5,000 koku of rice crop centered on Tateishi, Bungo Province (present Tateishi, Yamaga-machi, Kitsuki City, Oita Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tateishi-Kinoshita family, a branch of the lord family of the Hiji domain, was given the kotaiyoriai-omoteoreishu status, with a 5,000 koku of rice crop centered on Tateishi, Bungo Province (present Tateishi, Yamaga-machi, Kitsuki City, Oita Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tateishi-Kinoshita clan, a branch of the lord family of the Hiji clan, was given the kotaiyoriai-omoteoreishu status, with a 5,000 koku of rice crop centered on Tateishi, Bungo Province (present Tateishi, Yamaga-machi, Kitsuki City, Oita Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="201">
<j>立石木下氏が発行した旗本札には、文政7年（1825年）以降、数度に渡って勘定所などから発行された銭匁札などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hatamoto-satsu issued by the Tateishi Kinoshita family included the semme-satsu issued several times by kanjosho or others in 1825 or later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hatamoto-satsu issued by the Tateishi Kinoshita family included the semme-satsu issued several times by kanjosho or others in 1825 or later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hatamoto-satsu issued by the Tateishi Kinoshita clan included the senme-satsu issued several times by kanjosho (the organization handling financial and public affairs) or others in 1825 or later.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="202">
<j>時枝小笠原氏及び立石木下氏が発行した旗本札には、それらの知行地を含む九州北部で発行された藩札・旗本札に共通した特徴として、額面が銭匁表記になっているものが多く含まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hatamoto-satsu issued by the Tokieda-Ogasawara family and by the latish-Kinoshita family included many on which semme was used to express the face value, as typically seen among the Han-satsu and Hatamoto-satsu issued in the northern part of Kyushu, including chigyo-chi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hatamoto-satsu issued by the Tokieda-Ogasawara family and by the latish-Kinoshita family included many on which semme was used to express the face value, as typically seen among the Han-satsu and Hatamoto-satsu issued in the northern part of Kyushu, including chigyo-chi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hatamoto-satsu issued by the Tokieda-Ogasawara clan and by the Tateishi-Kinoshita clan included many on which the face value was expressed with senme value, as typically seen among the Han-satsu and Hatamoto-satsu issued in the northern part of Kyushu, including chigyo-chi.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="203">
<j>銭匁札とは、銀単位（匁・分・厘）の額面の札でありながら、時の銀-銭相場に従って銭で兌換することが明記されている紙幣を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Semme-satsu was the paper money with the following features: The face value was written in Monme, Bu, or Rin (each a monetary unit at that time) on it, but it was also written there that the money would be exchanged into zeni (copper or iron coins) based on a certain gin (silver coin)-zeni exchange rate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Semme-satsu was paper money with the following features: The face value was written in Monme, Bu, or Rin (each a monetary unit at that time) on it, but it was also written there that the money would be exchanged into zeni (copper or iron coins) based on a certain gin (silver coin)-zeni exchange rate.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senme-satsu was paper money with the following features: The face value was written in the unit of silver (monme, bu, or rin; each a monetary unit at that time) on it, but it was also written there that the money would be exchanged into zeni based on a certain gin (silver coin)-zeni exchange rate.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="204">
<j>銭匁札自体は丹後国・播磨国・伊予国などの地域にそれぞれ独自に（少なくとも地理上の連続性がなく）発行されていたことが確認できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be confirmed that semme-satsu itself was issued in Tango Province, in Harima Province and in Iyo Province independently (at least they had no common boundaries geographically).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be confirmed that semme-satsu itself was issued in Tango Province, in Harima Province and in Iyo Province independently (at least they had no common boundaries geographically).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be confirmed that senme-satsu itself was issued in Tango, Harima, and Iyo Provinces independently (at least they had no common boundaries geographically).</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="205">
<j>しかし、九州北部諸藩・旗本発行の札は、予め銀-銭の交換比率を札面に明記している（Ex.七銭拾匁：一匁あたり七十文で引き換えるという意味で、700文に兌換するという表示）という他地域とは異なる際立った特徴を持つものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, some paper money issued by domains or Hatamoto in the northern part of Kyushu had a distinguished feature, not found in other areas, that an exchange rate between gin (silver) coins and zeni coins was explicitly written on the surface (for example: Seven-sen-ten-monme indicated that the coins of 70 mon should be given for 1 monme, and therefore, this paper money could be exchanged to coins of 7000 mon).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, some paper money issued by domains or Hatamoto in the northern part of Kyushu had a distinguishing feature not found in other areas, in which an exchange rate between gin (silver) coins and zeni coins was explicitly written on the surface (for example: Seven-sen-ten-monme indicated that the coins of 70 mon should be given for 1 monme, and therefore, this paper money could be exchanged to coins of 7000 mon).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, some paper money issued by clans or Hatamoto in the northern part of Kyushu had a distinguishing feature not found in other areas, in which an exchange rate between gin (silver) coins and zeni coins was explicitly written on the surface (for example: 7-sen and 10-monme indicated that the coins of 70 mon should be given for 1 monme, and therefore, this paper money could be exchanged to coins of 700 mon).</e>
<cmt>用語を変更し、アラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>肥後国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Higo Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Higo Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Higo Province</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="206">
<j>米良氏は、南北朝時代 (日本)には南朝 (日本)方につき、敗れた後、九州山地の肥後国米良郡米良山中に逃れた名族菊池氏の末裔である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mera family was a descendant of the Kikuchi family, a distinguished clan that supported the Southern Court (in Japan) in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (in Japan) and fled to the Mera mountain area in Mera County, Higo Province, in the mountainous area of Kyushu, after being defeated in the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mera family was a descendant of the Kikuchi family, a distinguished clan that supported the Southern Court (in Japan) in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (in Japan) and fled to the mountainous area of Kyushu, or more specifically, the Mera mountain area in Mera County, Higo Province, after being defeated in the war.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mera clan was a descendant of the Kikuchi clan, a distinguished clan that supported the Southern Court (in Japan) in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (in Japan) and fled to the mountainous area of Kyushu, or more specifically, in Mt. Mera of Mera County, Higo Province, after being defeated in the war.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="207">
<j>徳川家康より米良山が鷹巣山に指定されたことが縁で召し出され、交代寄合衆（四衆に準ずる家）となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mera family gained acquaintance with Ieyasu TOKUGAWA at the opportunity when the Mera mountain was designated as the Takanosu mountain, and was picked by Ieyasu, getting the kotaiyoriai-shu Hatamoto status (becoming a family with the status equivalent to shishu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mera family became aquainted with Ieyasu TOKUGAWA when the Mera mountain was designated as Takanosu mountain, and picked by Ieyasu, after which they recieved kotaiyoriai-shu Hatamoto status (becoming a family with the status equivalent of that of shishu).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clan became acquainted with Ieyasu TOKUGAWA when Mt. Mera was designated as Mt. Takanosu, and picked by Ieyasu, after which they received kotaiyoriai-shu status (a family with the status equivalent of that of the Shishu).</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="208">
<j>肥後国米良の中心地小川（現・宮崎県児湯郡西米良村村所）に館を構えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family built its residence in Ogawa, at the center of Mera of Higo Province (present Murasho, Nishimera Village, Koyu County, Miyazaki Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family built its residence in Ogawa, at the center of Mera of Higo Province (present Murasho, Nishimera Village, Koyu County, Miyazaki Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clan built its residence in Ogawa, at the center of Mera of Higo Province (present Murasho, Nishimera Village, Koyu County, Miyazaki Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="209">
<j>領地が山中のため米は収穫できず、石高は無高であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the territory located in a mountain, no rice could grow, and therefore, its amount of rice crop was zero.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With their territory located in a mountain, no rice could grow, and therefore, their rice crop production amounted to zero.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With their territory located in a mountain, no rice could grow, and therefore, their kokudaka (crop yield) amounted to zero.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="210">
<j>しかしながら、材木、楮、茶、椎茸などを金穀に換えて収入としていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the family earned income by converting lumber, kazoo (the tree from which washy paper was produced), tea and shiitake mushroom into money or rice crop.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the family earned income by converting lumber, kazoo (the tree from which washy paper was produced), tea and shiitake mushroom into money or rice.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the clan earned income by converting lumber, kazoo (the tree from which washy paper was produced), tea, and shiitake mushroom into money or rice.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="211">
<j>米良氏が発行した旗本札には、文久2年（1862年）頃発行と推定される五百文、百文、四十八文の額面の御勝手座発行の銭預札がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hatamoto-satsu issued by the Mera family included 500-mon, 100-mon or 48-mon Zeniazukari-satsu (銭預札) issued by Okatte-za (御勝手座) in around 1862.</e>
<cmt>”御勝手座”、”銭預札”:：　これらの読み、意味内容ともに調べきれませんでした。こう読むのだろうとして訳したあｒます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hatamoto-satsu issued by the Mera family included 500-mon, 100-mon or 48-mon Zeniazukari-satsu (銭預札) issued by Okatte-za (御勝手座) in around 1862.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hatamoto-satsu issued by the Mera clan included 500-mon, 100-mon or 48-mon Zeni-azukari-satsu (銭預札; paper money equivalent to zeni copper coins) issued by Okatte-za (御勝手座; an organization to undertake the paper money) in around 1862.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="212">
<j>米良氏は軍事的・政治的・経済的に肥後国人吉藩、日向国諸藩、薩摩藩など領境を接する諸藩と強いつながりを持っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mera family had strong connections militarily, politically as well as ecumenically with the domains with common boundaries with its territory, such as the Hitoyoshi domain in Higo Province, domains in Hyuga Province, and the Satsuma domain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mera family had strong connections militarily, politically as well as economically, and was adjacent to domains that shared boundaries with its territory, such as the Hitoyoshi domain in Higo Province, domains in Hyuga Province, and the Satsuma domain.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mera clan had strong connections militarily, politically as well as economically, with adjacent clans that shared boundaries with its territory, such as the Hitoyoshi clan in Higo Province, clans in Hyuga Province, and the Satsuma clan.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="213">
<j>しかしながら、これら3地域は、藩札の額面表記（銀建て、銭建てなど）や様式についてそれぞれ異なった特徴を有する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, each of these three areas issued paper money with its own unique feature in the face value description (including gin (silver) coin-based, or zeni (copper or iron) coin-based) and in the design.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, each of these three areas issued paper money with its own unique feature in the face value description (including gin (silver) coin-based, or zeni (copper or iron) coin-based) and design.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, each of these three areas had own unique features in the expression of the face value (including gin [silver] coin-based, or zeni [copper or iron] coin-based) and the design of their Han-satsu.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="214">
<j>米良氏の旗本札は、銭額面表記、札面の様式などから日向国諸藩の藩札の影響が強い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that, from the face value description method and the design, the Hatamoto-satsu issued by the Mera family was deeply affected by the Han-satsu issued by domains in Hyuga Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that, from the face value description method and the design, the Hatamoto-satsu issued by the Mera family was deeply affected by the Han-satsu issued by domains in Hyuga Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that, from the face value describing in zeni base and the design on the face, the Hatamoto-satsu issued by the Mera clan was deeply affected by the Han-satsu issued by clans in Hyuga Province.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ミッキーマウスのぬいぐるみ(id:80103), Im224(id:57113), Ruikon(id:204937), 千早スパイラル(id:180323), Teisen(id:197266), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 松茸(id:27535), 立志堂(id:132177), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>