<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>日本の貿易史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History of Japan&apos;s trade</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History of Japan&apos;s trade</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History of Japan&apos;s trade</e>
<cmt>全角の’を半角にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>日本の貿易史（にほんのぼうえきし）では、日本の対外貿易に関する歴史について説明する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the history of Japan&apos;s trade, we give explanation of foreign trade history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">We will explain the history of Japan&apos;s trade, as it concerns foreign trade.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">We will explain the history of Japan&apos;s trade, as it concerns foreign trade.</e>
<cmt>全角の’を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>北東アジア地域との接触</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Trade contact with northeast Asia</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Trade contact with northeast Asia</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Trade contact with northeast Asia</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>中国の冊封体制</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tributary system of China</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tributary system of China</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tributary system of China</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>日本列島は最終氷期が終わったおよそ1万年前にユーラシア大陸から切り離された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese islands were divided from the Eurasian Continent about 10,000 years ago when the last glacial period finished.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese islands were divided from the Eurasian Continent about 10,000 years ago when the last glacial period ended.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese islands were divided from the Eurasian Continent about 10,000 years ago when the last glacial period ended.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>以降は外の国や地域との交流を行うさいには海を渡る必要があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then it became necessary to cross the sea in order to interchange with foreign countries and areas.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then it became necessary to cross the sea in order to exchange with foreign countries and areas.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then it became necessary to cross the sea in order to exchange with foreign countries and areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>そのため日本は造船・航海技術の発達が見られるまで、文字通り孤島となって近隣地域と隔絶されることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Japan came to be solitary islands literally separated from neighboring areas until it developed the arts of ship-building and navigation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Japan came to be a group of solitary islands literally separated from neighboring areas until it developed the art of ship-building and navigation.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Japan came to be a group of solitary islands literally separated from neighboring areas until it developed the art of ship-building and navigation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>中国では古代において東アジアの中心的な位置を占めており早くに文明が起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In ancient times, China occupied the central position in East Asia.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In ancient times, China occupied the central position in East Asia.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In ancient times, China occupied the central position in East Asia.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>中国は自らが東アジアの中心となり近隣諸国・地域との冊封体制を構築していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In China civilization occurred earlier times and as the center of East Asia, China built the tributary system with neighboring countries and areas</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In China, civilization occurred during earlier times and as the center of East Asia, China built a tributary system with neighboring countries and areas</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In China, civilization occurred during earlier times and as the center of East Asia, China built a tributary system with neighboring countries and areas.</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースを削除しました。ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>中国が日本を冊封した記録は後漢の時代にまで遡る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The records in which China put Japan in its tributary system, went back to the age of the Later Han Dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Records indicate that China put Japan in its tributary system, going back to the age of the Later Han Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Records indicate that China put Japan in its tributary system, going back to the age of the Later Han Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その後中国王朝への朝貢は邪馬台国の台与以降は途絶えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Paying tributes to Chinese dynasty stopped after Toyo of Yamatai-Koku kingdom.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Paying tributes to Chinese dynasty stopped after the emergence of the Toyo of Yamatai-Koku kingdom.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Paying tributes to Chinese dynasty stopped after the emergence of the Toyo of Yamatai-Koku kingdom.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>4世紀後期には倭の五王が南北朝時代 (中国)南朝への朝貢を再開するも、その後日本は長きにわたり大陸との接触を行っていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In late 4th century, the five kings of Wa opened again paying tribute to Southern Court in the period of Northern and Southern Courts in China, but after that Japan did not have contacts with Chinese continent for a long time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the late 4th century, the five kings of Wa opened up again, paying tribute to the Southern Court during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts in China, but after that Japan ceased to have contact with the Chinese continent for a long time.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the late 4th century, the five kings of Wa opened up again, paying tribute to the Southern Dynasty during the period of the Northern and Southern Dynasty in China, but after that Japan ceased to have contact with the Chinese continent for a long time.</e>
<cmt>Dynastyに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>7世紀なって日本は遣隋使を送るようになるが、これは冊封体制のもとではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the 7th century, Japan started to send Japanese envoys to Sui Dynasty China, but this envoy was not under tributary system.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the 7th century, Japan started to send Japanese envoys to Sui Dynasty China, but this envoy was not under tributary system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the 7th century, Japan started to send Japanese envoys to Sui Dynasty China, but this envoy was not under tributary system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>それはあくまでも対等の関係で行おうとしたものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese government intended to send envoy on an equal footing.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese government intended to send envoy on an equal footing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese government intended to send envoy on an equal footing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>617年に李淵が隋を滅ぼし、翌年に唐を建国した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 617, Ri En ruined Sui Dynasty and established Tang Dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 617, Ri En overthrew the Sui Dynasty and established the Tang Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 617, En RI overthrew the Sui Dynasty and established the Tang Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>En RIに訂正しました。不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>これをうけて遣隋使は遣唐使と改称され、9世紀前半まで交流が続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Coping with this, a Japanese envoy to Sui Dynasty China was renamed a Japanese envoy to Tang Dynasty China and the cultural exchanges lasted until the early 9th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So, in order to cope with this, the Japanese envoy to Sui Dynasty China was renamed the Japanese envoy to Tang Dynasty China and the ensuing cultural exchanges lasted until the early 9th century.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So, in order to cope with this, the Kenzui-shi (Japanese envoy to Sui Dynasty, China), was renamed the Kento-sho (Japanese envoy to Tang Dynasty, China), and the ensuing cultural exchanges lasted until the early 9th century.</e>
<cmt>コンマ補足しました読み補足しました。説明訳を（）に入れました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>唐の都の長安は西アジアやインドからの使節や商人が集まる国際都市となり、長安を中心にさまざまな商品や知識が日本を始め東アジア各地に広まっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Choan, the Capital of Tang became an international city with envoys and merchants concentrating from West Asia and India, and various kinds of commodities and knowledge were spread to Japan and East Asia from Choan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Choan, the Capital of Tang became an international city with envoys and merchants from West Asia and India, and various kinds of commodities and knowledge were spread to Japan and East Asia from Choan.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chagan, the capital of Tang became an international city with envoys and merchants from West Asia and India, and various kinds of commodities and knowledge were spread to Japan and East Asia from Chagan.</e>
<cmt>長安→Changanに訂正しました。capital小文字にしました。不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>この間日本は新羅との関係が悪化し、朝鮮半島をめぐる地域情勢が不安定になると日本は渤海 (国)との交流を深めていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During that period, relationship between Japan and Silla, and then Japan deepened the exchanges with Bokkai (kingdom in Manchuria and North Korea).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this period, the relationship between Japan and Silla worsened, causing Japan to deepen their exchanges with Bokkai (kingdom in Manchuria and North Korea).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this period, the relationship between Japan and Silla worsened, causing Japan to deepen their exchanges with Bo Hai (kingdom in Manchuria and North Korea).</e>
<cmt>不要な改行を削除しました。Bo Haiに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>渤海からは薬用人参や毛皮などが、日本からは絹・綿などの貿易が見られるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bokkai exported Yakuyo ninjin and fur products to Japan, and Japan exported silk and cotton products to Bokkai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bokkai exported Yakuyo ninjin and fur products to Japan, and Japan exported silk and cotton products to Bokkai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bo Hai exported Yakuyo ninjin (ginseng) and fur products to Japan, and Japan exported silk and cotton products to Bo Hai.</e>
<cmt>Bo Haiに訂正しました。(ginseng)補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>894年に遣唐使が廃止され907年に唐が完全に滅んだ後も民間レベルでの交易が続くようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the envoy to Tang was abolished in 894 and Tang was ruined in 907, commerce with Chinese ordinary citizens was continued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the envoy to Tang was abolished in 894 and Tang was ruined in 907, commerce with ordinary Chinese citizens continued.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the envoy to Tang was abolished in 894 and Tang was ruined in 907, commerce with ordinary Chinese citizens continued.</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="20">
<j>宋の出現と武家の台頭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Appearance of the Sung Dynasty and emergence of samurai family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Appearance of the Sung Dynasty and emergence of samurai family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Appearance of the Sung Dynasty and emergence of samurai family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="21">
<j>875年に起こった黄巣の乱以降、唐は統一中国を治める能力を失い、各地の地方勢力である藩鎮が自立傾向を示した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Koso War in 875, Tang lost power to control unified China and Hanchin, local forces in various places showed the independent trends.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Koso War in 875, Tang lost power to a unified China and Hanchin, local forces in various places showed the independent trends.</e>
<cmt>&quot; local forces in various places showed the independent trends.&quot; doesn’t make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Koso War in 875, Tang lost power to a unified China and Hanchin, local forces in various places showed the independent trends.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>表向きは唐が滅亡してから70年ほどであった（五代十国時代）が、事実上1世紀以上にわたって中国は分裂状態にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">China was divided for 70 years officially (Godai-Jikkoku period), but in reality for more than 100 years.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">China was officially divided for 70 years (Godai-Jikkoku period), but in reality it lasted for more than 100 years.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">China was officially divided for 70 years (Godai-Jikkoku period), but in reality it lasted for more than 100 years.</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>これを再び統一したのは北宋であったが、宋王朝は遼や金 (王朝)などと対立していたことなどから、中国全土に対して強力な支配を行っていたとは必ずしもいえないが、宋のもとで中国の社会が安定し農業や商業が飛躍的に発展したと考えることはできる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was Northern Sung Dynasty that unified China again, but it can not be said that Sung Dynasty had a strong power over the whole area of China, because Sung was confronted with Ryo and Jin Dynasties, but it can be thought that society got stable, and agriculture and commerce made a remarkable progress in China during this period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the Northern Sung Dynasty that unified China again, but it can not be said that the Sung Dynasty was able to exert a controlling force over the whole area of China, since Sung was confronted with the Ryo and Jin Dynasties, but it can be thought that society a,chieved stability, and agriculture and commerce made remarkable progress in China during this period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was the Northern Sung Dynasty that unified China again, but it can not be said that the Sung Dynasty was able to exert a controlling force over the whole area of China, since Sung was confronted with the Ryo and Jin Dynasties, but it can be thought that society achieved stability, and agriculture and commerce made remarkable progress in China during this period.</e>
<cmt>不要なコンマを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>一方日本では遣唐使の廃止以降、鴻臚館での貿易は続けられていたものの、一般の宋の商人は博多や敦賀に来航し、民間レベルでの貿易を行っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, in Japan, after the abolition of an envoy to Tang Dynasty, they continued the trade in Korokan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, in Japan, after removing their envoy to the Tang Dynasty, they continued trade in Korokan.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, in Japan, after abolishing their envoy to the Tang Dynasty, they continued trade in Korokan and also the commerce with ordinary Chinese merchants continued on the private-sector level at Hakata and Tsuruga.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>日宋貿易に関心を寄せた平忠盛は独自にこれを活発にし、輸入品を朝廷にもたらして権力を持つようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Tadanori who was interested in the trade between Japan and Sung, made the trade prosperous and grasped the authority by bringing imported goods to the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Tadanori who was interested in the trade between Japan and Sung, made the trade prosperous and grasped authority by bringing imported goods to the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Tadamori who was interested in the trade between Japan and Sung, made the trade prosperous and grasped authority by bringing imported goods to the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>Tadamoriに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>その後平清盛は大輪田泊を改修するなど貿易を振興し、そこから得られる利益をもとに平氏政権を磐石なものにしていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, TAIRA no Kiyomori made the trade with Sung prosperous by improving Owada no tomari and built a strong political system on the basis of profits from the trade.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, TAIRA no Kiyomori developed trade with Sung into prosperity by improving Owada no tomari and built a strong political system on the basis of profits from this trade.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, TAIRA no Kiyomori developed trade with Sung into prosperity by improving Owada no tomari and built a strong political system on the basis of profits from this trade.</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>平氏政権の崩壊後も鎌倉幕府は民間貿易を認め、13世紀の南宋が滅亡する直前まで日宋貿易は続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the collapse of Taira clan government, Kamakura Bakufu approved the trade with Sung by ordinary citizens and the trade between Japan and Sung continued just before Southern Sung Dynasty came to the fall in 13th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the collapse of the Taira clan government, the Kamakura Bakufu approved trade with Sung by ordinary citizens and trade between Japan and Sung continued just before the Southern Sung Dynasty was overthrown in the 13th century.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the collapse of the Taira clan government, the Kamakura Bakufu approved trade with Sung by ordinary citizens and trade between Japan and Sung continued just before the Southern Sung Dynasty was overthrown in the 13th century.</e>
<cmt>不要な改行を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>この間日本には絹織物や陶磁器などが輸出され、とくに12世紀中ごろからの宋銭がもたらされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During that period, silk goods and ceramics were exported to Sung, and in the middle of 12th century Sung currency was introduced in Japan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this period, silk goods and ceramics were exported to Sung, and in the middle of the 12th century, Sung currency was introduced in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this period, silk goods and ceramics were exported to Sung, and in the middle of the 12th century, Sung currency was introduced in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>宋銭がもたらされたことは日本の貨幣経済制度を促進された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This promoted Japanese monetary economy.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This promoted the Japanese monetary economy.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sung currency promoted the Japanese monetary economy.</e>
<cmt>Sung currencyに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>日本からは金や硫黄、日本刀などが輸出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Japan gold, sulfur, Japanese swords etc. were exported.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gold, sulfur, Japanese swords etc. were exported from Japan.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gold, sulfur, Japanese swords etc. were exported to Sung from Japan.</e>
<cmt>to Sung補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="31">
<j>モンゴルの興亡と室町幕府</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rise and Fall of Mongolia, and Muromachi Shogunate</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rise and Fall of Mongolia, and Muromachi Shogunate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rise and Fall of Mongolia, and Muromachi Shogunate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="32">
<j>「13世紀はモンゴルの世紀」とも呼ばれ、モンゴルがユーラシア大陸を席巻した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 13th century was called &quot;the century of Mongolia&quot; and Mongolia swept across the Eurasian Continent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 13th century was called &quot;the century of Mongolia&quot; and Mongolia swept across the Eurasian Continent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 13th century was called &apos;the century of Mongolia&apos; and Mongolia swept across the Eurasian Continent.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて”を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>中国においても北部を支配していた女真族王朝の金、金に追われ南部に逃れていた宋を次々と滅ぼし、中国にモンゴル人王朝の元 (王朝) を建てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In China, Mongolia ruined Jin in the Joshin tribe dynasty and Sung which was driven out to southern China by Jin, one after another, and established Yuan Dynasty, Mongolian Dynasty in China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In China, Mongolia ruined Jin in the Joshin tribe dynasty and Sung which was driven out to southern China by Jin, and established the Yuan Dynasty and Mongolian Dynasty in China.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In China, Mongolia ruined Jin in the Joshin tribe dynasty and Sung which was driven out to southern China by Jin, and established the Yuan Dynasty and Mongolian Dynasty in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>元はさらにその支配領域を拡大しようとベトナムや日本にまで手を伸ばす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Mongolia wanted to enlarge its control territory and tried to extend its influence to Japan and Vietnam.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Mongolia wanted to enlarge its control territory and tried to extend its influence to Japan and Vietnam.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Mongolia wanted to enlarge its control territory and tried to extend its influence to Japan and Vietnam.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>近隣諸国との関係が悪化する中でも民間や地方ベースでは交易が続けられており、とくに江南地方は経済拡大が続いていたこともあって、その規模はむしろ発展していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the relationship with neighboring countries was getting worse, trades among ordinary citizens were continued, especially the Japan&apos;s trade with Jiagnan region was getting prosperous with the development of its economics scale.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the relationship with neighboring countries was worsened, trade among ordinary citizens continued, and Japan&apos;s trade with the Jiagnan region was getting especially prosperous with the development of its economy.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the relationship with neighboring countries was worsened, trade among ordinary citizens continued, and Japan&apos;s trade with the Jiagnan region was getting especially prosperous with the development of its economy.</e>
<cmt>全角の’を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>しかし日本では鎌倉幕府が滅び朝廷が分裂する中で治安が悪化、倭寇が出没するようになり貿易船を襲うなど海賊行為が横行し、社会不安や行政機能の停滞などもあって、貿易は円滑なものとはいえなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in Japan Kamakura bakufu was ruined and Imperial Court was divided, and the social security became worse. In the trade with China, piracy by wako (Japanese Pirates) was rampant, the social security got worse and public administration stagnated, therefore trade with China was not proceeding smoothly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in Japan, the Kamakura bakufu was ruined and the Imperial Court was divided, and social security had declined. In trade with China, piracy by wako (Japanese Pirates) was rampant, with social security worsening and public administration stagnating, preventing smooth trade with China.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in Japan, since the social security had declined when the Kamakura bakufu was ruined and the Imperial Court was divided, the piracy by wako (Japanese Pirates) was rampant and the trade with China didn&apos;t carry on smoothly because of the social security worsening and public administration stagnating.</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースを削除しました。since補足しました。一文に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>この間に中国では元に替わって明が中国を統一し、対日政策として倭寇対策や朝貢を室町幕府に求めるなどした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During that period replacing Yuan, Ming Dynasty unified China and sought Japan to take countermeasures against wako and to bring tributes to Ming.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this period the Ming Dynasty replaced the Yuan Dynasty, uniting China and sought Japan to take countermeasures against the wako and to bring tributes to the Ming Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this period the Ming Dynasty replaced the Yuan Dynasty, uniting China and sought Japan to take countermeasures against the wako and to bring tributes to the Ming Dynasty from Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>室町幕府補足しました。(Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>足利義満はこれに応じ日本国王に封じられ勘合符を使用して独占的に貿易を行うようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA responded to this demand, was appointed King of Japan and started to monopolize the trade with Ming using Kangofu (certificate to show that the ship lawfully registered by Ming).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA responded to this demand, was appointed King of Japan and started to monopolize the trade with Ming using Kangofu (certificate to show that a ship was lawfully registered by Ming).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA responded to this demand, was appointed King of Japan and started to monopolize the trade with Ming using Kangofu (certificate to show that a ship was lawfully registered by Ming).</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>応仁の乱後は日明貿易の日本における主導権は大内氏や細川氏、堺や博多の商人に移っていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Onin War, initiative for trade with Ming gradually moved to Ouchi clan, Hosokawa clan and merchants in Sakai or Hakata.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Onin War, the initiative for trade with Ming gradually moved to the Ouchi clan, Hosokawa clan and merchants in Sakai or Hakata.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Onin War, the initiative for trade with Ming gradually moved to the Ouchi clan, Hosokawa clan and merchants in Sakai or Hakata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>寄港地ちなった琉球は明に対して独自に朝貢を行っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryukyu was the port of call en route to Ming, but Ryukyu brought tributes to Ming of itself.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryukyu was the port of call en route to Ming, but Ryukyu brought tributes to Ming of itself.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryukyu was the port of call en route to Ming, but Ryukyu brought tributes to Ming of itself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>しかしやがて明からの輸入品を日本や朝鮮などに転売することで巨額の利益を上げていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But after a while Ryukyu made an enormous profits by reselling imported goods from Ming to Japan and Korea.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But after a while Ryukyu made enormous profits by reselling imported goods from Ming to Japan and Korea.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But after a while Ryukyu made enormous profits by reselling imported goods from Ming to Japan and Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>16世紀中ごろの大内氏の滅亡で日明貿易は終焉を迎え、明も海禁政策をとるようになっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the destruction of Ouchi clan in the middle of 16th century, the trade between Japan and the Ming Dynasty in China finished and Ming also took the policy to prohibit trade.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the destruction of the Ouchi clan in the middle of 16th century, the trade between Japan and the Ming Dynasty in China came to an end and Ming also enacted a policy to prohibit trade.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the destruction of the Ouchi clan in the middle of 16th century, the trade between Japan and the Ming Dynasty in China came to an end and Ming also enacted a policy to prohibit trade.</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>この間明からは永楽通宝や繊維製品が、日本からは銅などの鉱物資源、漆器や屏風などの工芸品が行きかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During that period Eiraku-tsuho (bronze coins struck in the Ming Dynasty) and textile products from Ming and mineral resources such as copper and handicraft such as lacquer wares and folding screens from Japan were traded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this period Eiraku-tsuho (bronze coins struck in the Ming Dynasty) and textile products from Ming and mineral resources such as copper and handicraft such as lacquer wares and folding screens from Japan were traded.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this period Eiraku-tsuho (bronze coins struck in the Ming Dynasty) and textile products from Ming and mineral resources such as copper and handicraft such as lacquer wares and folding screens from Japan were traded.</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>また日本に倭寇対策を求めたのは李氏朝鮮も同様で、これを機に両国間で使節派遣が行われるようになり、貿易も盛んになっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yi Dynasty Korea also demanded Japan to take countermeasures against wako (Japanese pirates) and taking that opportunity exchange of envoy came to be conducted and trade between the two countries became prosperous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yi Dynasty Korea also demanded that Japan take countermeasures against wako (Japanese pirates) and seizing on the opportunity, envoy exchanges came to be conducted and trade between the two countries prospered.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yi Dynasty Korea also demanded that Japan take countermeasures against wako (Japanese pirates) and seizing on the opportunity, envoy exchanges came to be conducted and trade between the two countries prospered.</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>日本からは銅や工芸品が、朝鮮からは木綿や朝鮮人参が送られていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those day, copper products and handicraft from Japan and cotton materials and Asian ginseng from Korea were traded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those days, copper products and handicrafts from Japan and cotton materials and Asian ginseng from Korea were traded.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those days, copper products and handicrafts from Japan and cotton materials and Asian ginseng from Korea were traded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>しかし室町幕府が求心力を失った後、再び倭寇が出没するようになり、また日朝貿易は一時的に中断した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, after Muromachi government lost its centripetal force, wako (Japanese pirates) made frequent appearances and Japan-Korea trade was interrupted for some time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after Muromachi government lost its centripetal force, wako (Japanese pirates) made frequent appearances and Japan-Korea trade was interrupted for some time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after Muromachi bakufu lost its centripetal force, wako (Japanese pirates) made frequent appearances and Japan-Korea trade was interrupted for some time.</e>
<cmt>bakufuに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>15世紀中ごろには再び貿易が再開されるも、これは李氏朝鮮が貿易に統制をかけようとした目的があった。.</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the middle of 15th century, Yi Dynasty Korea opened the trade with Japan again, but Yi Dynasty tried to put regulation on this trade.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the middle of 15th century, Yi Dynasty Korea opened trade with Japan again, but the Yi Dynasty tried to regulate this trade relationship.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the middle of 15th century, Yi Dynasty Korea opened trade with Japan again, but the Yi Dynasty tried to regulate this trade relationship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>16世紀になると日朝関係が悪化し、貿易も衰退の一途を辿った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the middle of 15th century, the relationship between Korea and Japan got worse and the trade of both countries underwent the only way of decline.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the middle of 15th century, the relationship between Korea and Japan worsened and the trade between both countries declined.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the middle of 16th century, the relationship between Korea and Japan worsened and the trade between both countries declined.</e>
<cmt>16に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="49">
<j>ヨーロッパ人との接触</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Contacts with Europeans</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Contacts with Europeans</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Contacts with Europeans</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>ポルトガル人との貿易</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Trade with Portuguese</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Trade with Portuguese</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Trade with Portuguese</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="51">
<j>ルネサンス期の16世紀にヨーロッパ人は日本に到着し、極めて日本を賞賛した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the 16th century, during Renaissance period, Europeans who visited Japan, admired Japan very much.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the 16th century, during the Renaissance period, Europeans who visited Japan admired Japan very much.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the 16th century, during the Renaissance period, Europeans who visited Japan admired Japan very much.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>マルコポーロが金の寺や宮殿の説明をしていたので、日本は黄金の国と考えられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Marco Polo made the explanation of a golden temple and a golden palace about Japan, therefore Japan was considered the country of gold.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Marco Polo described Japan as having a golden temple and palace, therefore Japan was considered to be a country of gold.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Marco POLO described Japan as having a golden temple and palace, therefore Japan was considered to be a country of gold.</e>
<cmt>POLO大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>しかし、火山地形による表層の鉱石の豊かさにより、大規模の鉱石発掘がされる前に工業の時代に突入した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But due to the abundant ores resources in the top layer of soil in volcanic mountain terrain, Japan went into the age of industry before digging out of large scale ores</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But due to the abundant ores resources in the top layer of soil in the volcanic mountain terrain, Japan went into the age of industry before digging out of large scale ores</e>
<cmt>&quot;went into the age of industry before digging out of large scale ores &quot; doesn’t make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But due to the abundant ores resources in the top layer of soil in the volcanic mountain terrain, Japan went into the age of industry before digging out of large scale ores.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>日本はこの時代に銅と銀の主輸出国となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this age, Japan became the main exporting country of copper and silver products.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this age, Japan became the main country exporting copper and silver products.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this age, Japan became the main country exporting copper and silver products.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="55">
<j>日本はこの時代、豊富な前工業時代的技術と高い文化を兼ね備えた洗練された封建社会であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A refined feudal society was established in Japan with rich preindustrial arts and developed culture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A refined feudal society was established in Japan with rich preindustrial arts and a developed culture.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A refined feudal society was established in Japan with rich preindustrial arts and a developed culture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>ヨーロッパ諸国よりも人口は多く都市化されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan had a larger population than European countries and urbanization was developing in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan had a larger population than European countries and was being urbanized.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan had a larger population than European countries and was being urbanized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="57">
<j>初期に到着したヨーロッパ人たちは日本の職人の技能と金属細工に驚かされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Europeans who visited Japan in the first stage of this era were surprised at the art of workmen and metal ware of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Europeans who visited Japan in the first stage of this era were surprised at the art of craftsmen and metal crafts from Japan.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Europeans who visited Japan in the first stage of this era were surprised at the art of craftsmen and metal crafts from Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>それは日本は鉄鉱石に乏しいという事実から来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It stemmed from the situation that Japan was short of iron ore.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This stemmed from the fact that Japan was short of iron ore.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This stemmed from the fact that Japan was short of iron ore.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>それゆえ日本人はその限りある資源を職人の技術で有効利用することで有名となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore Japanese were famous for the art of workman to make effective use of the limited resources.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore the Japanese became well known as craftmen who were able to make effective use of their limited resources.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore the Japanese became well known as craftmen who were able to make effective use of their limited resources.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>銅と鉄の品質は世界最高で、その武器は最も鋭く、紙の技術は並ぶ国がなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Quality of copper and iron were best in the world, the weapons made out of those materials were very sharp and Japan also stood unrivaled in the art of paper products</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The quality of copper and iron were the best in the world, and weapons made out of those materials were very sharp while Japan also stood unrivaled in the art of paper products</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The quality of copper and iron were the best in the world, and weapons made out of those materials were very sharp while Japan also stood unrivaled in the art of paper products.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="61">
<j>ヨーロッパ人は南から来たので、日本人は彼らを「南蛮人」と呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese called Europeans &quot; southern barbarians &quot; because they came from the south.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese called Europeans &quot; southern barbarians &quot; because they came from the south.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese called Europeans &apos;Nanban-jin&apos; (southern barbarians) because they came from the south.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。読みを記載し、説明訳を括弧に入れました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>ポルトガルの船(毎年、通常大体小さなサイズの4艘の船)がほとんど中国の商品(絹、磁器)をつんで日本に来ていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Portuguese vessels (4 small size ships in common each year) used to arrive in Japan bringing Chinese products (silk, porcelain).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Portuguese vessels (4 small size ships in common each year) used to arrive in Japan bringing Chinese products (silk, porcelain).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Portuguese vessels (4-small-size ships in common each year) used to arrive in Japan bringing Chinese products (silk, porcelain).</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースを削除しました。ハイフン補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>日本人はそれをとても待望していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese people were very much expecting for those ships.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese people were very much expecting for those ships.</e>
<cmt>Translation doesn’t make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese people were very much expecting for trading those Chinese products.</e>
<cmt>trading those Chinese productsに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>しかしながら倭寇を懲罰するために中国皇帝にその貿易は禁止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However Chinese emperor prohibited the trade between Japan and Portugal in order to discipline wako.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However the Chinese emperor prohibited trade between Japan and Portugal in order to discipline wako.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However the Chinese emperor prohibited trade between Japan and Portugal in order to discipline wako.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>それゆえポルトガルはアジアの貿易の仲介役を見つけて貿易した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Portuguese tried to find the reconciliatory role between Japan and other countries in Asia.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Portuguese tried to act as a reconciliatory role between Japan and other countries in Asia.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Portuguese tried to seek a country that could act as a reconciliatory role in trading between the Asian countries.</e>
<cmt>訳が違うようです。訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="66">
<j>1557年ポルトガルがマカオを取得し、中国と正式な貿易パートナーとして認められるとポルトガル国家は日本への貿易を制限しだし、最高落札者に日本との交易を認めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1557 when Portugal acquired Macau and was recognized as the formal trade partner with China, Portugal began to control the trade with Japan and recognized the most successful bidder the trade with Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1557 when Portugal acquired Macau and was recognized as a formal trade partner with China, Portugal began to control its trade with Japan and recognized the most successful bidder the trade with Japan.</e>
<cmt>&quot;recognized the most successful bidder the trade with Japan.&quot; doesn’t make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1557 when Portugal acquired Macau and was recognized as a formal trade partner with China, Portugal began to control its trade with Japan and recognized the most successful bidder the trade with Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>協議の結果、1艘の1,000-1,500トンのキャラック船(武装商船大きなジャンク船やガレオン船の2,3倍の大きさ)に毎年排他的に交易する権利が与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the result of conference, an armed merchant ship of 1,000 to 1,500 tons was given the exclusive right for trade each year (an armed merchant ship was 2 to 3 times as large as junk and galleon ships).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the result of this conference, an armed merchant ship of 1,000 to 1,500 tons was given exclusive rights to trade each year (an armed merchant ship was 2 to 3 times as large as junk or galleon ships).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the result of this conference, an armed merchant ship of 1,000 to 1,500 tons was given exclusive rights to trade each year (an armed merchant ship was 2 to 3 times as large as junk or galleon ships).</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>この交易は途中中断しながら1638年まで続けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although interrupted in the middle, this trade lasted until 1638.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although interrupted in the middle, this trade lasted until 1638.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although interrupted in the middle, this trade lasted until 1638.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>キリスト教の司祭を日本に輸入しだした時、その貿易は禁止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Japan began to prohibit priests of Christianity, trade with Portugal was prohibited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Trade with Portugal was finally prohibited after Japan began to prohibit Christian priests from coming to Japan.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Trade with Portugal was finally prohibited after Japan began to prohibit Christian priests from coming to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="70">
<j>オランダ人との貿易</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Trade with Dutch</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Trade with the Dutch</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Trade with the Dutch</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>ポルトガルとの交易は次第に中国のジャンク船との貿易に圧迫され、1592年に朱印船貿易が年に約10隻の割合で始まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Trade with Portugal was gradually overwhelmed by the trade of junk ship by China and in 1592 trading by ships with a shogunal charter for foreign trade began at the rate of 10 ships a year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Trade with Portugal was gradually overwhelmed by trading with junk ships from China and in 1592 trading by ships with a shogunal charter for foreign trade began at the rate of 10 ships a year.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Trade with Portugal was gradually overwhelmed by trading with junk ships from China and in 1592 trading by ships with a shogunal charter for foreign trade began at the rate of 10 ships a year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>1600年からマニラからスペイン船が年に約1隻の割合で到着した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since 1600, Spain ship arrived in Japan from Manila once a year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since 1600, Spanish ships arrived in Japan from Manila once a year.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since 1600, Spanish ships arrived in Japan from Manila once a year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>また1600年からオランダが、1613年からイギリスが貿易した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also since 1600 the Netherlands and since 1613 England began trade with Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also since 1600 the Netherlands and since 1613 England began trade with Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also since 1600 the Netherlands and since 1613 England began trade with Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>1600年リーフデ号が日本に漂着し、ウィリアム・アダムスがイギリス人として初めて日本に到着した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1600 the Liefde was cast up on the coast of Japan and William ADAMS arrived in Japan as the first Englishman.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1600 the Liefde was cast up on the coast of Japan and William ADAMS arrived in Japan as the first Englishman.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1600 the Liefde was cast up on the coast of Japan and William ADAMS arrived in Japan as the first Englishman.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>1605年徳川家康の命でリーフデ号の乗組員の2人がタイ王国のパッターニーのオランダ人に日本と交易するように招待するために送られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1605 on a command of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, 2 members of the Liefde crew were sent to Hollanders in the city of Pattani in Kingdom of Thailand in order to start trade with Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1605 on the order of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, 2 members of the Liefde crew were sent to Hollanders in the city of Pattani in the Kingdom of Thailand in order to start trade with Japan.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1605 on the order of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, 2 members of the Liefde crew were sent to Hollanders in the city of Pattani in the Kingdom of Thailand in order to start trade with Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>パッターニーのオランダ交易所の所長のVictor Sprinckelは南アジアで敵対するポルトガルとの折合いをつけるのに忙しかったので上陸を拒んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Victor Sprinckel, Head of the Netherlands trade office in Pattani in Thailand, declined them to land, because he was too busy to cope with the situation caused by Portugal which was hostile to Netherlands in southern Asia.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Victor Sprinckel, Head of the Netherlands trade office in Pattani in Thailand, refused their landing, as he was too busy to cope with the situation caused by Portugal which was hostile to the Netherlands in southern Asia.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Victor Sprinckel, Head of the Netherlands trade office in Pattani in Thailand, refused their landing, as he was too busy to cope with the situation caused by Portugal which was hostile to the Netherlands in southern Asia.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>しかし、1609年オランダ人のJacques Specxは2艘の船で平戸にたどり着き、ウィリアム・アダムスを通じて家康から貿易許可を戴いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Dutch, Jacques Specx struggled to arrive at Hirato in 1609 and obtained the trade permission from Yeyasu through William ADAMS.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Dutch, Jacques Specx struggled to arrive at Hirato in 1609 and obtained permission to trade from Yeyasu through William ADAMS.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Dutch, Jacques SPECX struggled to arrive at Hirato in 1609 and obtained permission to trade from Ieyasu through William ADAMS.</e>
<cmt>Ieyasu に訂正しました。SPECXに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="78">
<j>江戸時代の始まりは南蛮貿易の終わりと重なり、ヨーロッパ人との経済的、宗教的に交易がある程度の域に達した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The beginning of Edo Period overlapped the end of trade with Spain and Portugal, and in this period the economic and religious relationship with Europeans arrived at certain extent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The beginning of the Edo Period overlapped the end of trade with Spain and Portugal, and in this period the economic and religious relationship with Europeans arrived at certain extent.</e>
<cmt>&quot;with Europeans arrived at certain extent.&quot; doesn’t make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The beginning of the Edo period overlapped the end of trade with Spain and Portugal, and in this period the economic and religious relationship with Europeans arrived at certain extent.</e>
<cmt>period小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>江戸時代始めには日本初のヨーロピアンスタイルの遠洋航海用ガレオン船サン・フアン・バウティスタ号(500トン)が日本の支倉常長使節団をのせてヨーロッパ経由でアメリカに航海した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the beginning of Edo period, Japanese first European style galleon ship for ocean navigation, San Juan Bautista (500 ton) started on a voyage for Europe with Japanese delegation headed by Tsunenaga HASEKURA through America.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the beginning of the Edo period, the first Japanese European style galleon ship for ocean navigation, San Juan Bautista (500 ton) started on a voyage for Europe with a Japanese delegation headed by Tsunenaga HASEKURA through America.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the beginning of the Edo period, the first Japanese European style galleon ship for ocean navigation, San Juan Bautista (500 ton) started on a voyage for Europe with a Japanese delegation headed by Tsunenaga HASEKURA through America.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>この時代、幕府は350艘の、3本マストの武装交易船の朱印船に許可をだした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this age Tokugawa Shogunate gave charters for trade to 350 armed trading ships with 3 masts</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this age Tokugawa Shogunate gave charters for trade to 350 armed trading ships with 3 masts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this age Tokugawa Shogunate gave charters for trade to 350 armed trading ships with 3 masts.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>山田長政のようにアジアで活躍した冒険家も現れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Adventurer such as Nagamasa YAMADA who made a spectacular showing in Asia appeared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Adventurers such as Nagamasa YAMADA who made a spectacular showing in Asia appeared.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Adventurers such as Nagamasa YAMADA who made a spectacular showing in Asia appeared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>その後1638年以降は西洋人としてオランダのみ出島で2世紀に渡り、交易することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After 1638 only Hollanders as Europeans were permitted to trade with Japan at Dejima, Nagasaki for 200 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After 1638 only Hollanders as Europeans were permitted to trade with Japan at Dejima, Nagasaki for 200 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After 1638 only Hollanders as Europeans were permitted to trade with Japan at Dejima, Nagasaki for 200 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="83">
<j>鎖国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National Isolation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National Isolation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National Isolation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="84">
<j>家康の死後、1616年に徳川秀忠は鎖国政策を開始し、25年後に秀忠の後継の徳川家光により鎖国が完了した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Ieyasu in 1616 Hidetada TOKUGAWA began isolation policy and the policy was completed 25 years afterwards by Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, successor of Hidetada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Ieyasu in 1616 Hidetada TOKUGAWA began an isolation policy and the policy was completed 25 years afterwards by Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, the successor of Hidetada.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Ieyasu in 1616 Hidetada TOKUGAWA began an isolation policy and the policy was completed 25 years afterwards by Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, the successor of Hidetada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>このため既存のイギリス、スペイン、ポルトガルとの交易が途絶え、また民間貿易も禁止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of the national isolation, commerce with England, Spain and Portugal who traded with Japan until that time stopped and the commerce with ordinary citizens was also prohibited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of its national isolation, commerce with England, Spain and Portugal who traded with Japan until that time stopped and commerce with ordinary citizens was also prohibited.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of its national isolation, commerce with England, Spain and Portugal who traded with Japan until that time stopped and commerce with ordinary citizens was also prohibited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>貿易相手とその交渉の場も限定され、オランダと中国は長崎・出島、朝鮮は対馬、琉球は薩摩、アイヌは松前藩とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Trade partners and their places for association were also limited: that is, Hollanders and Chinese were approved trade in Nagasaki and Dejima, Koreans were approved trade in Tsushima, Ryukyuans in Satsuma and Ainu tribe in Matsumae Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Trade partners and their places for association were also limited: that is, Hollanders and Chinese were approved trade in Nagasaki and Dejima, Koreans were approved trade in Tsushima, Ryukyuans in Satsuma and Ainu tribe in Matsumae Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Trade partners and their places for association were also limited: that is, Hollanders and Chinese were approved trade in Nagasaki and Dejima, Koreans were approved trade in Tsushima, Ryukyuans in Satsuma and Ainu tribe in Matsumae Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>長崎における貿易では金、銀、銅が日本から輸出され、また中国に対しては海産品も輸出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the trade in Nagasaki, gold, silver and copper products were exported from Japan, and marine products were also exported to China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Trade in Nagasaki included, gold, silver and copper products that were exported from Japan, and marine products that were also exported to China.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Trade in Nagasaki included, gold, silver and copper products that were exported from Japan, and marine products that were also exported to China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>一方で日本には繊維製品などが輸入されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand textile products were imported in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand textile products were imported to Japan.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand textile products were imported to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>その後新井白石により貿易量が制限されるようになるが、田沼意次が政治の中心につくと輸出が奨励されるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards Hakuseki ARAI limited the trade volume, but Okitsugu TANUMA promoted trade after he took political power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterwards Hakuseki ARAI limited the trade volume, but Okitsugu TANUMA promoted trade after he took political power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterwards Hakuseki ARAI limited the trade volume, but Okitsugu TANUMA promoted trade after he took political power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="90">
<j>19世紀の中期には江戸は100万人都市となり、京都と大阪は40万人都市となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the middle of 19th century, Edo became the city with one million population and Osaka and Kyoto, 400,000 population, respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the middle of 19th century, Edo became a city with a one million population and Osaka and Kyoto, having a population of 400,000, respectively.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the middle of 19th century, Edo became a city with a one million population and Osaka and Kyoto, having a population of 400,000, respectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>江戸は米中心の経済であり、税金の徴収のため表記が米で表された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edo had the rice-centered economy and the amount for tax collection was displayed in terms of rice amount.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edo had a rice-centered economy and amount of tax collected was displayed in terms of an amount of rice.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edo had a rice-centered economy and amount of tax collected was displayed in terms of an amount of rice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>例えばその土地に米を生産する事が出来なくてもその経済規模を何万石の米相当と判断して其れに課税をした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example even if they could not produce rice in their land, the economic scale was expressed by the rice amount corresponding to the converged rice worth and the converged rice amount became the standard for taxation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example even if a territory could not produce rice in their land, the economic scale was expressed by the rice amount corresponding to the converged worth of rice and the converged rice amount became the standard for taxation.</e>
<cmt>Translation doesn’t make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example even if a territory could not produce rice in their land, the economic scale was expressed by the rice amount corresponding to the converged worth of rice and the converged rice amount became the standard for taxation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>税率は40パーセントぐらいで他のアジア諸国と比べると格段に高い数値を示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tax rate in Edo era was 40 % on the revenue and this was very high as compared with those in other Asian countries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tax rate in Edo era was 40 % on the revenue and this was very high when compared with those in other Asian countries.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tax rate in Edo era was 40 % on the revenue and this was very high when compared with those in other Asian countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>これにより江戸時代を農民が搾取されていたとする見解がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this situation, there is an opinion that farmers in Edo era were exploited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this situation, there is an opinion that farmers in Edo era were exploited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this situation, there is an opinion that farmers in Edo period were exploited.</e>
<cmt>period に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>が、実は換金作物（大豆、綿、等）には税金がかからず、普通の土地持ちの百姓はそこそこな生活をしていたという見解もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, another opinion says that the cash crop (soybean, cotton, etc.) was not taxed, so farmers having lands of common size could lead a reasonably good life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, another opinion says that the cash crop (soybean, cotton, etc.) was not taxed, so farmers having lands of common size could lead a reasonably good life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, another opinion says that the cash crop (soybean, cotton, etc.) was not taxed, so farmers having lands of common size could lead a reasonably good life.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>大名は米を主に税金として集めたが江戸時代は貨幣経済なので何かするときは換金する必要がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Feudal lords collected mainly rice as taxes, but they had monetary economy in Edo era therefore it was necessary to turn rice into cash.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Feudal lords collected mainly rice as taxes, but they had monetary economy in Edo era therefore it was necessary to turn rice into cash.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Feudal lords collected mainly rice as taxes, but they had monetary economy in Edo period therefore it was necessary to turn rice into cash.</e>
<cmt>period に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>大名は不作時も豊作時も安定した換金が必要となり、1730年に大阪の堂島米会所で世界で初めての先物取引が開始された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whether they had a poor crop or good harvest, it was necessary for feudal lords to have a stabilized conversion into money, therefore in 1730, futures transaction of rice was started in the dojima rice exchange in Osaka first in the world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whether they had a poor crop or good harvest, it was necessary for feudal lords to have a stabilized monetary conversion, therefore in 1730, the world&apos;s first futures transaction of rice was started in the dojima rice exchange in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whether they had a poor crop or good harvest, it was necessary for feudal lords to have a stabilized monetary conversion, therefore in 1730, the world&apos;s first futures transaction of rice was started in the dojima rice exchange in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>いわゆる青田買いである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was so called buying rice before the harvest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was so called buying rice before a harvest.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was so called buying rice before a harvest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>これは1819年のシカゴ・マーカンタイル取引所（現在の穀物先物取引の世界的中心）の設立より100年以上も前のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was a lot of years earlier than the establishment of Chicago mercantile exchange in 1819 (present center in the world for grain futures transaction)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was many years before the establishment of the Chicago mercantile exchange in 1819 (present center in the world for grain futures transaction)</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was many years before the establishment of the Chicago Mercantile Exchange in 1819 (present center in the world for grain futures transaction)</e>
<cmt>Chicago Mercantile Exchangeに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="100">
<j>欧米との再接触</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reopening of contact with Europe and America</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reopening of contact with Europe and America</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reopening of contact with Europe and America</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>開国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Opening of the country to the world</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Opening of the country to the world</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Opening of the country to the world</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="102">
<j>1854年の日米和親条約によりおよそ2世紀にわたる日本の鎖国は解かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to Peace Treaty between Japan and United States in 1854, Japanese isolation policy for 200 years was abolished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the Peace Treaty between Japan and United States in 1854, the Japanese isolation policy that had lasted for 200 years was abolished.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the Peace Treaty between Japan and United States in 1854, the Japanese isolation policy that had lasted for 200 years was abolished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>4年後には日米修好通商条約が締結されるが、この条約によると日本側に関税の自主決定権が与えられていないとされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">4 years afterwards, Treaty of amity and commerce between Japan and United States was concluded, according to this treaty Japan was not approved a tariff autonomy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">4 years later, a Treaty of amity and commerce between Japan and United States was concluded, and according to this treaty Japan was not approved a tariff autonomy.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">4 years later, a Treaty of amity and commerce between Japan and United States was concluded, and according to this treaty Japan was not approved a tariff autonomy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>同様の条約は英仏蘭露とも結ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Treaties of similar contents were concluded also with England, France, Holland and Russia.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Treaties of similar contents were also concluded with England, France, Holland and Russia.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Treaties of similar contents were also concluded with England, France, Holland and Russia.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>これらの不平等条約は半世紀にわたりその後の明治政府を悩ませることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These unequal treaties troubled Meiji Government for a half century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These unequal treaties troubled the Meiji Government for a half century.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These unequal treaties troubled the Meiji Government for a half century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>このときの主な貿易品目は、日本からは生糸や茶が輸出され、各国、とくに最大の貿易相手国となったイギリスからは毛織物や綿織物、軍事用の武器やその原材料となる金属が日本に輸出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the main trade items in this period, Japan exported raw silk thread and tea, and foreign countries, especially England, the largest trade partner of Japan exported wool, cotton fabric, military weapons and metals as raw materials for weapon were exported to Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the main trade items in this period, Japan exported raw silk thread and tea, and foreign countries, especially England, the largest trade partner of Japan exported wool, cotton fabric, military weapons and metals as raw materials for weapon were exported to Japan.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the main trade items in this period, Japan exported raw silk thread and tea, and foreign countries, especially England, the largest trade partner of Japan exported wool, cotton fabric, military weapons and metals as raw materials for weapon were exported to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="107">
<j>日米修好通商条約などの通商条約の締結によって諸外国の銀貨が日本国内で使用できることが定められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the conclusion of commerce treaties with foreign countries including Treaty of amity and commerce between Japan and U.S.A., it came to be possible to use foreign silver coins in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the conclusion of commerce treaties with foreign countries including Treaty of amity and commerce between Japan and U.S.A., it came to be possible to use foreign silver coins in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the conclusion of commerce treaties with foreign countries including Treaty of amity and commerce between Japan and U.S.A., it came to be possible to use foreign silver coins in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>当時日本国内で同じ価値の金と銀との交換比率は幕府によって15と定められていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those days it was decided that the exchange rate of gold to silver was 1:15 by Tokugawa government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those days it was decided that the exchange rate of gold to silver was 1:15 by the Tokugawa government.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those days it was decided that the exchange rate of gold to silver was 1:15 by the Tokugawa government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>だがこの比率は諸外国にくらべて著しく金が割安であり、諸外国ではおおむね115の交換比率が成立していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But in this rate gold was valued very low as compared to the rate in foreign countries where the exchange rate of gold to silver was 1:115.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But in this rate gold was valued very low when compared to the rate in foreign countries where the exchange rate of gold to silver was 1:115.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But in this rate gold was valued very low when compared to the rate in foreign countries where the exchange rate of gold to silver was 1:115.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>このため外国商人は日本へ銀を持ち込んで、金と交換し、上海などで再度銀と交換するだけで巨利を得ることができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore foreign merchants could obtain a lot of profits only by bringing silver into Japan, exchanging silver for gold and exchanging gold for silver again in foreign countries, Shanghai in China for example.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore foreign merchants could obtain a lot of profits by only bringing silver into Japan, exchanging silver for gold and exchanging gold for silver again in foreign countries, such as Shanghai in China for example.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore foreign merchants could obtain a lot of profits by only bringing silver into Japan, exchanging silver for gold and exchanging gold for silver again in foreign countries, such as Shanghai in China for example.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>こうして大量の金貨（小判）が日本から流出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this way large volume of koban (gold coin: former Japanese oval gold coi) were flown out from Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this way large volume of koban (gold coin: former Japanese oval gold coi) were flown out from Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this way large volume of koban (gold coin: former Japanese oval gold coin) were flown out from Japan.</e>
<cmt>coinスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>幕府は1860年に金の含有量を3分の1に圧縮した万延小判を発行し、ようやく金の流出を止めることができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Feudal government issued Manen koban (gold coin in Manen era) and reduced the contained amount of gold in koban (gold coin) to one third, thus being able to stop the outflow of gold from Japan at last.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Feudal government issued Manen koban (gold coin in Manen era) and reduced the amount of gold contained in koban (gold coin) to one third, thus at last stopping the outflow of gold from Japan.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Feudal government issued Manen koban (gold coin in Manen era) and reduced the amount of gold contained in koban (gold coin) to one third, thus at last stopping the outflow of gold from Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>ところが、正貨の貨幣価値が3分の1に下落したこと、また諸外国との貿易の開始によって国内産品が輸出に向けられたことによって、幕末期の日本経済はインフレーションにみまわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Japanese economy in the end of Edo era was visited by inflation due to the reduction of currency value by one third and domestic products being exported through the trade with foreign countries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Japanese economy in the end of Edo era encountered inflation due to the reduction of their currency value by one third and domestic products being exported through trade with foreign countries.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Japanese economy in the end of Edo era encountered inflation due to the reduction of their currency value by one third and domestic products being exported through trade with foreign countries.</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="114">
<j>殖産興業</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Encouragement of New Industry</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Encouragement of New Industry</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Encouragement of New Industry</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="115">
<j>江戸幕府から政権を引き継いだ明治政府が直面した課題は、貿易による外貨獲得と不平等条約の改正であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Problems which Meiji government took over from Edo feudal government were acquisition of foreign currencies and revision of unequal treaty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Meiji government took over issues from the Edo feudal government such as the acquisition of foreign currencies and revision of unequal treaties.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Meiji government took over issues from the Edo feudal government such as the acquisition of foreign currencies and revision of unequal treaties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>1870年（明治3年）政府は工部省を設置、また技術導入のためにお雇い外国人を多数採用し、殖産興業推進のため、鉄道、造船、鉱山、製鉄、電信、灯台など産業振興と産業インフラ整備のための幅広い事業を推進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1870 Meiji government established the ministry of industry, employed many foreign specialists, and promoted new industries and improved infrastructure such as railway, shipbuilding, mine, iron manufacture, telegraph, lighthouse, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1870 Meiji government established the ministry of industry, employed many foreign specialists, and promoted new industries and improved infrastructure such as railway, shipbuilding, mine, iron manufacture, telegraph, lighthouse, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1870 Meiji government established the ministry of industry, employed many foreign specialists, and promoted new industries and improved infrastructure such as railway, shipbuilding, mine, iron manufacture, telegraph, lighthouse, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="117">
<j>当時の日本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan in Those Days</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan in Those Days</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan in Those Days</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="118">
<j>条約改正</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Treaty Revision</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Treaty Revision</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Treaty Revision</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="119">
<j>日本の近代化と世界への進出</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Modernization of Japan and Expansion of Enterprises into the World</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Modernization of Japan and Expansion of Enterprises into the World</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Modernization of Japan and Expansion of Enterprises into the World</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>大戦景気</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Boom after World War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Boom after World War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Boom after World War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="121">
<j>統制経済</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Controlled Economy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Controlled Economy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Controlled Economy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="122">
<j>戦後復興とグローバリゼーション</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Revival after the War and Globalization</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Revival after the War and Globalization</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Revival after the War and Globalization</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Yaojing(id:271362), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Straysheep(id:42448), Forestfarmer(id:59407), 0null0(id:582), Siyajkak(id:9402), Izumin(id:143831), ミッキーマウスのぬいぐるみ(id:80103), Shifumi(id:15485), Shimoxx(id:9332), Point136(id:211299), Takesisaitou(id:156448), Red Star Belgrade(id:25968), Nikka(id:26792), Ariesmarine(id:70919), Binh Giang(id:79801), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>