<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>知行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chigyo (a term concerning territorial control)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chigyo (a term concerning territorial control)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chigyo</e>
<cmt>以下説目が続きますので、英語説明は削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>知行（ちぎょう）とは、日本の中世・近世において、領主が行使した所領支配権を意味する歴史概念。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chigyo is a history-related concept indicating a territory-controlling right executed by territorial lords in the medieval period and early-modern times in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chigyo is a history-related concept indicating a territory-controlling right executed by territorial lords during the medieval period and early-modern times in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chigyo is a history-related concept indicating a territory-controlling right executed by territorial lords during the medieval period and early-modern times in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>平安時代から「知行」の語が使用され始め、以降、各時代ごとに「知行」の意味する範囲は微妙に変化していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Use of the term, chigyo, started in the Heian period, and the range of control indicated by &quot;chigyo&quot; varied depending on each era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Use of the term, chigyo, started during the Heian period, and the range of control indicated by &quot;chigyo&quot; varied depending on each era.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Use of the term, chigyo, started during the Heian period, and the range of control indicated by &apos;chigyo&apos; varied depending on each era.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>日本の歴史上の領主はヨーロッパの農奴制における領主のように無制限に所領の土地と人民を私有財産として所有したのではなく、徴税権・支配権にかかわる一定の権利義務の体系を所持した存在であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Territorial lords in Japanese history were not like those in the serf system in Europe who owned the land and people in his or her territory as his or her private property with no restriction, but possessed a system of certain right and responsibility concerning tax-collecting right and territory-controlling right.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Territorial lords in Japanese history were not like those under the serf system in Europe who owned the land and people in his or her territory as his or her private property without any restrictions, but possessed a system of certain rights and responsibilities concerning tax-collecting and territory-control.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Territorial lords in Japanese history were not like those under the serf system in Europe who owned the land and people in his or her territory as his or her private property without any restrictions, but possessed a system of certain rights and responsibilities concerning tax-collecting and territory-control.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>この体系が知行であり、日本史における領主階層のあり方を理解する上で、知行の概念の理解は欠かせない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chigyo indicates this system, and understanding the concept of chigyo is indispensable for understanding the position of the territorial lord class in the Japanese history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chigyo indicates this system, and understanding the concept of chigyo is indispensable for understanding the position of the territorial lord class in Japanese history.</e>
<cmt>gramamr</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chigyo indicates this system, and understanding the concept of chigyo is indispensable for understanding the position of the territorial lord class in Japanese history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>知行概念の発生</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generation of chigyo concept</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generation of chigyo concept</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generation of chigyo concept</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>9世紀・10世紀頃、統治体制が律令制的な枠組みから、新興階層の富豪層である田堵などに依存した名田と呼ばれる分権的な体制へ変質していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In around the ninth and tenth centuries, the nation-governing system based on a framework like Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) had changed into a decentralized system called myoden (rice field lots in charge of a nominal holder) relying on rich farmers called tato who constituted a new wealthy class.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the ninth and tenth centuries, the nation-governing system based on a framework like the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) had changed into a decentralized system called myoden (rice field lots in charge of a nominal holder) relying on rich farmers called tato who constituted a new wealthy class.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the ninth and tenth centuries, the nation-governing system based on a framework like the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) had changed into a decentralized system called myoden (rice field lots in charge of a nominal holder) relying on rich farmers called tato who constituted a new wealthy class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>11世紀になるとこの流れに、各々の国内の荘園・国衙領への一律的な課税（一国平均役）の動きが加わり、荘園と郡、郷、保に再編成された国衙領を個々の収取単位とする体制（荘園公領制）が成立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Entering the eleventh century, in addition to this trend, the trend of levying tax evenly on shoen (manors) and Kokugaryo (the territory governed by a provincial government office) (called Ikkoku heikinyaku) was also generated, and the system in which tax was collected from shoen and Kokugaryo, which had been reorganized into Gun, Sato (an area within Gun) and Ho (an area within Sato), (called shoen koryo sei) was established.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処郷、保：　これらの読み不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Entering the eleventh century, in addition to this trend, the trend of levying tax evenly on shoen (manors) and Kokugaryo (the territory governed by a provincial government office) (called Ikkoku heikinyaku) was also generated, and the system in which tax was collected from shoen and Kokugaryo, which had been reorganized into Gun, Sato (an area within Gun) and Ho (an area within Sato), (called shoen koryo sei) was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Entering the eleventh century, in addition to this trend, the trend of levying tax evenly on shoen (manors) and Kokugaryo (the territory governed by a provincial government office) (called Ikkoku heikinyaku) was also generated, and the system in which tax was collected from shoen and Kokugaryo, which had been reorganized into Gun, Sato (an area within Gun) and Ho (an area within Sato), (called shoen koryo sei) was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>すると、新たにこれらの収取単位を管理し、紛争処理に携わる「領主」という階層が登場するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then the class of &quot;ryoshu&quot; (territorial lord), who newly managed each unit of these tax-collecting areas and were engaged in handling disputes among people in the areas, appeared.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then the class of &quot;ryoshu&quot; (territorial lord), who newly managed each unit of these tax-collection areas and were engaged in handling disputes among people in the areas, appeared.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then the class of &apos;ryoshu&apos; (territorial lord), who newly managed each unit of these tax-collection areas and were engaged in handling disputes among people in the areas, appeared.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>領主は所領に対して支配権を行使することで、年貢・公事・夫役といった収益を得ていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoshu came to acquire incomes of nengu (land tax), kuji (public duties) and buyaku (labor service) through execution of the right of controlling the areas he managed,</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoshu came to acquire incomes of nengu (land tax), kuji (public duties) and buyaku (labor service) through execution of the right to control areas he managed.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoshu came to acquire incomes of nengu (land tax), kuji (public duties) and buyaku (labor service) through execution of the right to control areas he managed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>このとき、領主が行使した支配権は、知行（ちぎょう）・領知（りょうち）・領掌（りょうしょう）・進止（しんし）などと呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The control right that ryoshu executed here was called chigyo, ryochi, ryoshu or shinshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The control right that ryoshu executed here was called chigyo, ryochi, ryoshu, or shinshi.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The control right that ryoshu executed here was called chigyo, ryochi, ryoshu, or shinshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>ただし、この当時、領主が行使し得た支配権は決して一様ではなく、領主の地位・身分などによって大きな差があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the control right that a ryoshu could execute was not necessarily the same, being largely different depending on the rank and social status.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the control right that a ryoshu could execute was not necessarily the same, being largely different depending upon rank and social status.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the control right that a ryoshu could execute was not necessarily the same, being largely different depending upon rank and social status.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>一口に「知行」と言っても多様なあり方があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, even when the same term of chigyo was used, its real content was not always the same.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, even when the same term of chigyo was used, its real content was not always the same.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, even when the same term of chigyo was used, its real content was not always the same.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>小は個々の荘園や国衙領を分割編成した名田を百姓身分の名主が知行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The smallest power of chigo was that of nanushi (village headman) who used it for myoden of shoen or Kokugaryo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The smallest power of chigo was that of nanushi (village headman) who used it for myoden of shoen or Kokugaryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The smallest power of chigo was that of nanushi (village headman) who used it for myoden of shoen or Kokugaryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>さらに荘園や、郡・郷・保を単位とする国衙領は荘園領主や国司（受領）に任命された荘官・郡司・郷司・保司らが知行して治安維持、租税徴収に当たった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For a shoen or Kokugaryo, which had been organized into Gun, Sato and Ho, shokan (an officer) appointed by the ryoshu of the shoen or Gunji (an officer for Gun), Goji (an officer for Go (Sato)) and Hoji (an officer for Ho), all of whom were appointed by the kokushi (provincial governor) (also called zuryo), executed their respective chigyo right, working for maintaining security and for collecting taxes.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For a shoen or Kokugaryo, which had been organized into Gun, Sato, and Ho, shokan (an officer) appointed by the ryoshu of the shoen or Gunji (an officer for Gun), Goji (an officer for Go - Sato) and Hoji (an officer for Ho), all of whom were appointed by the kokushi (provincial governor) (also called zuryo), executed their respective chigyo right, working for maintaining security and for collecting taxes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For a shoen or Kokugaryo, which had been organized into Gun, Sato, and Ho, shokan (an officer) appointed by the ryoshu of the shoen or Gunji (an officer for Gun), Goji (an officer for Go - Sato) and Hoji (an officer for Ho), all of whom were appointed by the kokushi (provincial governor) (also called zuryo), executed their respective chigyo right, working for maintaining security and for collecting taxes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>この地位にはしだいに武士が任命されることが多くなって鎌倉時代の地頭につながっていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Increasingly more samurai became appointed to these positions, leading to the appearance of the jito (manager and lord of manor) position in the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Increasingly more samurai were appointed to these positions, leading to the appearance of the jito (manager and lord of manor) position during the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Increasingly more samurai were appointed to these positions, leading to the appearance of the jito (manager and lord of manor) position during the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>さらにその上には荘園領主としていくつもの荘園を知行し、また後述の知行国の形で一国の公領もろとも知行する摂関家や官寺に代表される権門が君臨した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, the powerful groups that executed the chigo right for many manors as a ryoshu of shoen or executed the chigyo right for the entire public land in a province as a chigyo-koku (provincial fiefdom) (described later), typically including Sekkan-ke (the families which produced regents) and kanji (state-sponsored temples), reigned over them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the powerful groups that executed the chigo right over many manors as a ryoshu of shoen or executed the chigyo right over the entire public land in a province as a chigyo-koku (provincial fiefdom) (described later), typically including Sekkan-ke (the families which produced regents) and kanji (state-sponsored temples), reigned over them.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the powerful groups that executed the chigo right over many manors as a ryoshu of shoen or executed the chigyo right over the entire public land in a province as a chigyo-koku (provincial fiefdom) (described later), typically including Sekkan-ke (the families which produced regents) and kanji (state-sponsored temples), reigned over them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>知行や領主とはこのように重層的な体制を構成していたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chigyo and ryoshu constituted a multi-tiered system like this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chigyo and ryoshu constituted a multi-tiered system like this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chigyo and ryoshu constituted a multi-tiered system like this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>平安中期頃になると、高級貴族や有力寺社（権門勢家）が、ある国の租税収取権を掌握し、国司を自由に任命する権利を得るようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Entering the middle era of the Heian period, high-class nobles, dominant temples and shrines (or powerful groups in other words) took hold of the right of collecting taxes in a province, becoming to acquire the right to appoint kokushi there freely.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Entering the middle era of the Heian period, high-class nobles, dominant temples and shrines (or powerful groups in other words) took hold of the right to collect taxes in a province, acquiring the right to freely appoint kokushi there.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Entering the middle era of the Heian period, high-class nobles, dominant temples and shrines (or powerful groups in other words) took hold of the right to collect taxes in a province, acquiring the right to freely appoint kokushi there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これは知行権が一国単位に拡大したものであり、こうした国を知行国といった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This indicates that the chigyo right was expanded so as to be executable over an entire province, and a province in such a state was called a chigyo-koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This indicates that the chigyo right was expanded to be executable over an entire province, and a province in such a state was called a chigyo-koku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This indicates that the chigyo right was expanded to be executable over an entire province, and a province in such a state was called a chigyo-koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>知行国は平安後期に急激に増加した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of chigyo-koku increased rapidly in the latter half of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of chigyo-koku increased rapidly during the latter half of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of chigyo-koku increased rapidly during the latter half of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>中世を通して、所領支配を指して知行・領知・領掌・進止などと呼ぶ慣習は続いていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The custom of calling territorial control as chigyo, ryochi, ryosho or shinshi continued throughout the medieval period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The custom of calling territorial control as chigyo, ryochi, ryosho, or shinshi continued throughout the medieval period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The custom of calling territorial control as chigyo, ryochi, ryosho, or shinshi continued throughout the medieval period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>これらの語の指し示す範囲については、大きく2つの見解に分かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concerning the control range indicated by each of these terms, there are largely two different opinions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concerning the control range indicated by each of these terms, there are largely two different opinions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concerning the control range indicated by each of these terms, there are largely two different opinions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>1つは、いずれも領主による所領支配を表していたとする考えである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One is that each of them indicated territorial control by a ryoshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One is that each of them indicated territorial control by a ryoshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One is that each of them indicated territorial control by a ryoshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>もう1つは、中世史料を詳細に検討した結果、進止の語が土地支配を意味するのに対し、知行の語は土地からの収益処分を指すものとした見解である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The other is as follows; As a result of detailed investigations of historical materials concerning the medieval period, it is considered that the term of shinshi indicated land control but that of chigyo the right of getting profits from land.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The other is as follows; As a result of detailed investigations of historical materials concerning the medieval period, it is considered that the term of shinshi indicated land control, but that of chigyo the right of obtaining profits from land.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The other is as follows; As a result of detailed investigations of historical materials concerning the medieval period, it is considered that the term of shinshi indicated land control, but that of chigyo the right of obtaining profits from land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>後者には異論も出されているが、この見解に従えば、中世期の支配・収取のあり方をより具体的に理解することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Opinions denying the latter were proposed, but according to this latter opinion, the state of the national control system and tax-collecting system in the medieval period could be understood more concretely.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Opinions denying the latter were proposed, but according to the latter opinion, the state of the national control and tax-collecting systems during the medieval period could be understood more concretely.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Opinions denying the latter were proposed, but according to the latter opinion, the state of the national control and tax-collecting systems during the medieval period could be understood more concretely.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>知行概念の変質</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Changes in the chigyo concept</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Changes in the chigyo concept</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Changes in the chigyo concept</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>中世期の特徴は、土地の支配権および収益権をめぐって、中央貴族や有力寺社、在地領主・地頭・名主など様々な主体が入り組みながら重層的な権利関係を形成している点にあった（これを職の体系という）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A feature of the medieval period was that, concerning land-controlling right and tax-collecting right, persons in various social statuses, such as nobles in Kyoto, powerful temples and shrines, local ryoshu, jito and nanushi, were related with each other and formed multi-tiered right relationships (this structure called shiki-no-taikei (literally, a job system).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A feature of the medieval period was that, concerning land-controlling rights and tax-collecting rights, persons in various social statuses, such as nobles in Kyoto, powerful temples and shrines, local ryoshu, jito and nanushi, were related with each other and formed multi-tiered right oriented relationships (this structure called shiki-no-taikei (literally, a job system).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A feature of the medieval period was that, concerning land-controlling rights and tax-collecting rights, persons in various social statuses, such as nobles in Kyoto, powerful temples and shrines, local ryoshu, jito and nanushi, were related with each other and formed multi-tiered right oriented relationships (this structure called shiki-no-taikei (literally, a job system)).</e>
<cmt>)補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>しかし、鎌倉時代後期頃から、主に地頭によって、重層的な関係を解消し、一元的な支配体系が指向されるようになっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, entering around the latter half of the Kamakura period, the multi-tiered relationship disappeared mainly due to the appearance of jito, and it was oriented so as to introduce a unified control system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the latter half of the Kamakura period, the multi-tiered relationship disappeared mainly due to the appearance of jito, and it was oriented so as to introduce a unified control system.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the latter half of the Kamakura period, the multi-tiered relationship disappeared mainly due to the appearance of jito, and it was oriented so as to introduce a unified control system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>このような一元的支配を一円知行という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such unified control was called ichien chigyo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such unified control was called ichien chigyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such unified control was called ichien chigyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>こうした動きは室町時代に入ると一層加速していき、守護大名による守護領国制が形成され、さらに戦国時代 (日本)の戦国大名による大名領国制へ発展していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Entering the Muromachi period, such a trend was accelerated, the shugo-ryogoku system (in which shugo (provincial constable) controlled the province) was formed by shugo daimyo (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable), and then entering into the Sengoku period (period of warring states) (in Japan), the daimyo-ryogoku system (the system that a daimyo controlled a feudal domain) was developed by daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) in the Sengoku Period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Muromachi period, such a trend was accelerated, the shugo-ryogoku system (in which shugo, or provincial constable, controlled the province) was formed by shugo daimyo (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable), and then entering into the Sengoku period (period of warring states) (in Japan), the daimyo-ryogoku system (a system whereby a daimyo controlled a feudal domain) was developed by daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) during the Sengoku Period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Muromachi period, such a trend was accelerated, the shugo-ryogoku system (in which shugo, or provincial constable, controlled the province) was formed by shugo daimyo (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable), and then entering into the Sengoku Period (period of warring states) (in Japan), the daimyo-ryogoku system (a system whereby a daimyo controlled a feudal domain) was developed by daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) during the Sengoku Period.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>その中で、様々な主体が担っていた所領支配は、武士の手中へと収まっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In such a trend, the territorial control, having been carried out by persons in various social statuses, became conducted by samurai alone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In such a trend, territorial control, having been carried out by persons in various social statuses, became conducted by samurai alone.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In such a trend, territorial control, having been carried out by persons in various social statuses, became conducted by samurai alone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>それから、「知行」の語は、武士が主君から給付・安堵（保証）された所領を意味するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then the term of &quot;chigyo&quot; became to indicate the territory that a samurai was awarded and protected by his lord.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then the term of &quot;chigyo&quot; came to indicate the territory that a samurai was awarded and was protected by his lord.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then the term of &apos;chigyo&apos; came to indicate the territory that a samurai was awarded and was protected by his lord.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>知行面積＝知行高は、主君が武士に賦課する軍役の基準となり、その知行高の算出は、戦国期においては貫高により表された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The area size of a chigyo, called chigyo-daka, was used as the standard of the amount of the military service that a lord levied on his samurai, and a chigyo-daka was expressed by kandaka (the money corresponding to the amount of rice production based on the area size of the chigyo) in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>知行高の算出は、戦国期においては貫高により表された。：　意味がよく理解できませんでしたので、”知行高は、戦国期においては貫高により表された。”として訳してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The size of a chigyo area, called chigyo-daka, was used as the standard of the amount of military service a lord levied on his samurai, and a chigyo-daka was expressed by kandaka (the money corresponding to the amount of rice production based on the size of the chigyo area chigyo) during the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The size of a chigyo area, called chigyo-daka, was used as the standard of the amount of military service a lord levied on his samurai, and a chigyo-daka was expressed by kandaka (the money corresponding to the amount of rice production based on the size of the chigyo area chigyo) during the Sengoku Period.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>江戸時代になると、知行高は石高で示された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Entering the Edo period, koku-data (the amount of rice to be produced in the chigyo) became used for expressing chigyo-daka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo period, koku-data (the amount of rice to be produced in the chigyo) became used for expressing chigyo-daka.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period, koku-data (the amount of rice to be produced in the chigyo) became used for expressing chigyo-daka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>平和で安定したこの時代、知行高は、厳格な体系を持つ武士内部の身分指標の役割を持つようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period when the society was peaceful and stabilized, chigyo-daka played the role of an index indicating the social status of a samurai within the samurai class where a strict system existed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo period when the society was peaceful and stabilized, chigyo-daka played the role of an index indicating the social status of a samurai within the samurai class where a strict system existed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period when the society was peaceful and stabilized, chigyo-daka played the role of an index indicating the social status of a samurai within the samurai class where a strict system existed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>消滅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Disappearance of chigyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Disappearance of chigyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Disappearance of chigyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>明治維新を迎えると、国家近代化の中で、武士による土地・収取支配は廃止され、知行の概念も消滅することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Entering the Meiji period, the control of land and of collecting taxes by samurai was abolished in the trend of modernizing the nation, and the concept of chigyo disappeared</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Meiji period, the control of land and of collecting taxes by samurai was abolished in the trend of modernizing the nation, and the concept of chigyo disappeared</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Meiji period, the control of land and of collecting taxes by samurai was abolished in the trend of modernizing the nation, and the concept of chigyo disappeared.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), DNCAL(id:120593), Reiruof(id:66113), くっちゃめ(id:86793), Nerimaman(id:61206), Shimoxx(id:9332), Ispar(id:66258), ウミユスリカ(id:9504), Kanbun(id:37114), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>