<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>朝廷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial Court</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Court</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Court</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>朝廷（ちょうてい）とは、天子が政事を行う場所。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial Court is a place where an emperor performs political affairs and tasks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Court was a place where an emperor performs political affairs and tasks.</e>
<cmt>is→was</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Court was a place where an emperor performs political affairs and tasks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>転じて政府のことをさす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, it is a government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, it was a government.</e>
<cmt>is→was</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, it was a government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>中国の朝廷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chinese Imperial Court</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chinese Imperial Court</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chinese Imperial Court</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>中国の朝廷は皇帝を中心とし、丞相などの宦官を含めた中国古来の政府である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chinese Imperial Court - centered an emperor and involved eunuchs filling positions like Chancellor - was the Chinese government of ancient times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chinese Imperial Court was the ancient Chinese government which centered on an emperor and involved eunuchs such as Chancellor and the like.</e>
<cmt>全体を改変しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chinese Imperial Court was the ancient Chinese government which centered on an emperor and involved eunuchs such as Chancellor and the like.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>中国の皇帝は日本の天皇と同じく、建国者（高宗）の男子子孫がこれを継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The emperors of China, as well as of Japan, was succeeded by the male descendants of the founder (Gao Zong (高宗)) of the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The emperors of China, as well as of Japan, was succeeded by the male descendants of the founder (Gao Zong (高宗)) of the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The emperors of China, as well as of Japan, was succeeded by the male descendants of the founder (Gao Zong (高宗)) of the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また中国では国内で戦争が起こりその勝者が皇帝に対し禅譲を要求して皇帝となり国号を変え前皇帝の男子の子孫でない別の者が皇帝となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In China, a winner of a war - not necessarily a son of an emperor - asked an former emperor to transfer his power to him and acceded to the imperial throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In China, a winner of domestic war - not necessarily a son of an emperor - asked an former emperor to transfer his power to him, and acceded to the imperial throne and chaged the name of the country.</e>
<cmt>「国内で」「国号を変え」を訳出しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In China, a winner of domestic war - not necessarily a son of an emperor - asked an former emperor to transfer his power to him, and acceded to the imperial throne and chaged the name of the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その後同じように男子に世襲される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The throne was succeeded as such.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter the throne was succeeded as such.</e>
<cmt>「その後」を訳出</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter the throne was succeeded as such.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>ちなみに中国国内で皇帝の位を帝位と呼び、通常はこれをとることは不義不忠とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The imperial title was called crown (帝位) in China and it was usually considered disloyal to take over it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The imperial title was called crown (帝位) in China and it was usually considered disloyal to take over it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The imperial title was called crown (帝位) in China and it was usually considered disloyal to take over it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし、現在の皇帝に不満がある場合国民などが帝位に着くことを望んだ場合帝位に上る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, a citizen could accede the imperial throne if he did not satisfy with the present emperor and hoped to do so.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, a citizen could accede the imperial throne if he did not satisfy with the present emperor and hoped to do so.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, a citizen could accede the imperial throne if he did not satisfy with the present emperor and hoped to do so.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>しかし例外もありその場合違うものがこの皇帝を倒し善政を敷いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were exceptions too, and in such case, another defeated the emperor and conducted a reign of virtue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were exceptions too, and in such cases, others defeated the emperor and conducted a reign of virtue.</e>
<cmt>in such case, another defeated→in such cases, others</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were exceptions too, and in such cases, others defeated the emperor and conducted a reign of virtue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>ちなみに今は清王朝後、朝廷は存在せず、中国共産党が中国を統治している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial Court has not existed in China after the Qing Dynasty, and now the country is governed by the Chinese Communist Party.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Court has not existed in China after the Qing Dynasty, and now the country is governed by the Chinese Communist Party.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Court has not existed in China after the Qing Dynasty, and now the country is governed by the Chinese Communist Party.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>清王朝最後の皇帝溥儀は満州国の皇帝となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Puyi (溥儀), the last emperor of the Qing Dynasty became the emperor of Manchukuo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Puyi (溥儀), the last emperor of the Qing Dynasty, became the emperor of Manchukuo.</e>
<cmt>コンマを挿入しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Puyi (溥儀), the last emperor of the Qing Dynasty, became the emperor of Manchukuo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>この場合朝廷的体質ではなく明治後の日本の政府のような体質であり朝廷とは呼びづらい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The government of Manchukuo was like the one in Japan after the Meiji period, and it is hardly called the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The character of Manchukuo government was like the one of Japanese government after the Meiji period, and it is hardly called the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>「体質」を訳出しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The character of Manchukuo government was like the one of Japanese government after the Meiji period, and it is hardly called the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>日本の朝廷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese Imperial Court</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese Imperial Court</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese Imperial Court</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>天皇が政治をおこなっていた場所。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the place where an emperor conducted the affairs of state.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the place where an emperor conducted the affairs of state.</e>
<cmt>is→was</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was the place where an emperor conducted the affairs of state.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>もしくは政府のことを指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also refers to the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also refers to the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also refers to the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>古代（奈良時代、平安時代）から中世前期（鎌倉時代）における日本では、天皇を中心とした政治体制が維持されており、国家における天皇が政治を行っていた政府（御所）のことを意味することが多い（ただし、皇位から離れた天皇（太上天皇）が実質の政務を行う院政も「天皇家の当主」を中心としていることでは差異はほとんどない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, from the ancient times (the Nara Period, the Heian Period) to the early Middle Ages (the Kamakura Period), the political system, centered an emperor was kept, and the government often means the government (gosho (Imperial Palace)) in which an emperor carried out politics (Cloister government in wich Daijo Tenno, a retired Emperor, carried out politics, is also similar to the government as such.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, from the ancient times (the Nara Period, the Heian Period) to the early Middle Ages (the Kamakura Period), the political system centered on an emperor was kept, and the Imperial court often means the government (gosho, or the Imperial Palace) in which an emperor carried out politics (however, the Imperial court was similar to Cloister government in wich Daijo Tenno, a retired Emperor, carried out politics).</e>
<cmt>・centered→centered on・the government often means→the Imperial court often means・（）内を改変しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, from the ancient times (the Nara Period, the Heian Period) to the early Middle Ages (the Kamakura Period), the political system centered on an emperor was kept, and the Imperial court often means the government (gosho, or the Imperial Palace) in which an emperor carried out politics (however, the Imperial court was similar to Cloister government in wich Daijo Tenno, a retired Emperor, carried out politics).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>「朝廷」の言葉の由来は、大宝律令が成立し朝廷の政治体制が確立された奈良時代は、政治や会議等は早朝から始められ午前中に開かれていたことによる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial Court is called Chotei (朝廷), the morning court, because in the Nara period, when Taiho Ritsuryo (Taiho Code) was set up and the political system of the Imperial Court was established, the courts were opened in early morning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Court is called Chotei (朝廷) which literally means the morning court; the politics, conferences and the like were held before noon from early in the morning in the Nara period when Taiho Ritsuryo (Taiho Code) was set up and the political system of the Imperial Court was established,</e>
<cmt>・全体を改変しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Court is called Chotei (朝廷) which literally means the morning court; the politics, conferences and the like were held before noon from early in the morning in the Nara period when Taiho Ritsuryo (Taiho Code) was set up and the political system of the Imperial Court was established,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>武家政権の時代においては、征夷大将軍が主宰する政府（幕府）についても「朝廷」と言うことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the period of military government, a bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) was sometimes called &quot;Chotei, the Imperial Court&quot; too.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the period of military government, a bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) was sometimes called &apos;Chotei&apos;, too.</e>
<cmt>・引用符を修正しました・the imperial courtは29列で定義されているので省略しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the period of military government, a bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) was sometimes called &apos;Chotei&apos;, too.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>今日においては「朝廷」という言葉が幕府に対応する言葉としてよく使われるが、これは天皇・貴族（公家政権）と武家（武家政権）を対立した存在として捉えるようになった近世以後の考えからの影響が強い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, the word &quot;Chotei, the Imperial Court&quot; is often used to refer to a bakuhu, because of the point of view after modern times, in which people think of the Emperor/aristocrat (the Kuge (court nobles) Government) and buke (military authority) (military government) opposing one another.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, &apos;Chotei&apos; is often used as the word comparable to a bakuhu; this is strongly influenced by the thoughts after the modern times in which the Emperor/aristocrat (the Government of kuge, or the court nobles) and buke (military government) oppose one another.</e>
<cmt>全体を改変しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, &apos;Chotei&apos; is often used as the word comparable to a bakuhu; this is strongly influenced by the thoughts after the modern times in which the Emperor/aristocrat (the Government of kuge, or the court nobles) and buke (military government) oppose one another.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>実際には鎌倉幕府の摂家将軍や宮将軍、江戸幕府の大政委任論のように、幕府もまた朝廷の実質とは一線を画しつつも、朝廷から分離してその存在を考えることはできないものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a matter of fact, the bakuhu also could not exist without the Imperial Court, while keeping the characteristic of its own, different from the one in the Imperial Court, as Sekke Shogun and Miyashogun (shogun from the Imperial Court) from Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and Taisei-ininron (a theory holding that government powers were delegated to the Shogun by the Tenno) of Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a matter of fact, the bakuhu also could not exist without the Imperial Court while keeping the characteristic of its own which is different from the one in the Imperial Court, such as Sekke Shogun and Miyashogun (shogun from the Imperial Court) from Kamakura bakufu, and Taisei-ininron (a theory holding that government powers were delegated to the Shogun by the Tenno) of Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt>・while keeping the characteristic of its own, different from the one in the Imperial Court→while keeping the characteristic of its own which is different from the one in the Imperial Court・(Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)を削除（前列で説明済）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a matter of fact, the bakuhu also could not exist without the Imperial Court while keeping the characteristic of its own which is different from the one in the Imperial Court, such as Sekke Shogun and Miyashogun (shogun from the Imperial Court) from Kamakura bakufu, and Taisei-ininron (a theory holding that government powers were delegated to the Shogun by the Tenno) of Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>また室町時代初期には、大覚寺統の南朝 (日本)（吉野朝廷）と持明院統の北朝 (日本)とに分かれ対立していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early Muromachi period, the Japanese government was separated into the Southern Dynasty of Daikakuji-to (imperial lineage starting with Emperor Kameyama) and the Northern Dynasty of Jimyoin-to (imperial lineage from Emperor Gofukakusa to Emperor Gokomatsu) and opposing one another.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early Muromachi period, the Japanese government was separated into the Southern Dynasty of Daikakuji-to (imperial lineage starting with Emperor Kameyama) and the Northern Dynasty of Jimyoin-to (imperial lineage from Emperor Gofukakusa to Emperor Gokomatsu) which opposed one another.</e>
<cmt>and opposing→which opposed</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early Muromachi period, the Japanese government was separated into the Southern Dynasty of Daikakuji-to (imperial lineage starting with Emperor Kameyama) and the Northern Dynasty of Jimyoin-to (imperial lineage from Emperor Gofukakusa to Emperor Gokomatsu) which opposed one another.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>この時代を南北朝時代 (日本)という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is called the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is called the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is called the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="22">
<j>明治維新によって、幕府も含めて旧来の朝廷機構は事実上廃止されて（王政復古の大号令）、新しく生まれ変わった行政組織である明治政府が成立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The old Imperial Court system including the bakuhu was virtually abolished - the Decree (of 1867) for the Restoration of Imperial Rule, and the Meiji Government was established as a newly born political system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The old Imperial Court system including the bakuhu was virtually abolished by the Meiji Restoration (the Decree for the Restoration of Imperial Rule), and the Meiji Government was established as a newly born political system.</e>
<cmt>前半を改変しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The old Imperial Court system including the bakuhu was virtually abolished by the Meiji Restoration (the Decree for the Restoration of Imperial Rule), and the Meiji Government was established as a newly born political system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>この時点で前近代的な政治体制である朝廷は終焉を迎えて日本国（あるいは大日本帝国）政府に取って代わったと言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this point, the premodern political system, the Japanese Imperial Court was ended and was replaced by the government of Japanese Nation or the Empire of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this point, the Japanese Imperial Court as the premodern political system was ended and replaced by the government of Japanese Nation (or the Empire of Japan).</e>
<cmt>全体を改変しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this point, the Japanese Imperial Court as the premodern political system was ended and replaced by the government of Japanese Nation (or the Empire of Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Autumn Sky(id:173580), Michey.M(id:906), 平成no牛若丸(id:24527), 経済準学士(id:22656), 0null0(id:582), 水野白楓(id:22811), Tiyoringo(id:70026), Shimoxx(id:9332), Sl(id:20556), 越中掾(id:149423), Gombe(id:27), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>