<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>西・ローゼン協定</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nishi-Rosen Kyotei (Nishi-Rosen Agreement)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nishi-Rosen Kyotei (Nishi-Rosen Agreement)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nishi-Rosen Kyotei (Nishi-Rosen Agreement)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>西・ローゼン協定（にし・ろーぜんきょうてい、）とは、1898年4月25日に大日本帝国とロシア帝国の間で結ばれた、韓国（大韓帝国）についての紛争に関する協定のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nishi-Rosen Kyotei is an agreement on the conflict about the Republic of Korea (the Korean Empire) concluded between the Empire of Japan and the Russian Empire on April 4, 1898.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nishi-Rosen Kyotei was the agreement to settle the dispute over the Republic of Korea (the Korean Empire) signed between Empires of Japan and Russia on April 25, 1898.</e>
<cmt>日付と文法を編集しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nishi-Rosen Kyotei was the agreement to settle the dispute over the Republic of Korea (the Korean Empire) signed between Empires of Japan and Russia on April 25, 1898.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>日清戦争における日本の勝利と、韓国国内政治への影響力の増大により、朝鮮半島への主導権に関する日露の緊張は増大し続けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tension between Japan and Russia about the initiative on the Korean Peninsula continued to run high because of Japan&apos;s victory in the Sino-Japanese War and the increased clout of the domestic politics in the South Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tension between Japan and Russia about the initiative on the Korean Peninsula continued to increase due to Japanese victory in the Sino-Japanese War and the growing Japanese influence on the domestic politics of South Korea.</e>
<cmt>Cloutなどの口語より正式な英語に編集しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tension between Japan and Russia about the initiative on the Korean Peninsula continued to increase due to Japanese victory in the Sino-Japanese War and the growing Japanese influence on the domestic politics of South Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>協定は東京において、日本の外務大臣西徳二郎男爵とロシア帝国の外務大臣ロマン・ローゼン男爵の間で交わされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The agreement was signed in Tokyo by Japanese Foreign Minister Baron Nishi Tokujiro, and Russian Foreign Minister Baron Roman Romanovich Rosen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The agreement was signed in Tokyo between Japanese Foreign Minister Baron Tokujiro NISHI, and Russian Foreign Minister Baron Roman Romanovich Rosen.</e>
<cmt>名字が大文字になっていませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The agreement was signed in Tokyo between Japanese Foreign Minister Baron Tokujiro NISHI, and Russian Foreign Minister Baron Roman Romanovich Rosen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>協定文では、両国は韓国の国内政治への干渉を差し控え、かつ韓国政府の依頼で軍事または財政顧問を送る前に、互いに事前承認を求めることで合意した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They entered the agreement that both nations had to withhold the interference with the national politics in the Republic of Korea and request the pre-approval to each other before they would send the military and financial advisers on requests from the Korean government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The agreement stated that both nations had to withhold from interfering with the national politics of the Republic of Korea and seek each other&apos;s pre-approval before sending the military and financial advisers requested by the Korean government.</e>
<cmt>文章を滑らかにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The agreement stated that both nations had to withhold from interfering with the national politics of the Republic of Korea and seek each other&apos;s pre-approval before sending the military and financial advisers requested by the Korean government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>ロシアは、韓国の商用・経済発展への日本の投資を妨害しないことを誓約し、それにより韓国が日本の勢力範囲になることを明確に認めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Russia clearly recognized that the Republic of Korea became Japan&apos;s sphere of influence by pledging that they would not interrupt Japan&apos;s investing in business and economic development in the South Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Russia clearly recognized that the Republic of Korea will not become Japanese sphere of influence by pledging that they would not interfere with the Japanese business investments and economic development in the South Korea.</e>
<cmt>文章の本来の意味が正反対だったので編集しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Russia clearly recognized that the Republic of Korea will not become Japanese sphere of influence by pledging that they would not interfere with the Japanese business investments and economic development in the South Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>代わりに、日本は満州におけるロシアの勢力範囲を暗黙に認めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Alternatively, Japan gave a tacit nod to the Russian area of influence in Manchuria.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Alternatively, Japan gave a tacit nod to the Russian area of influence in Manchuria.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Alternatively, Japan gave a tacit nod to the Russian area of influence in Manchuria.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Locust-of-abaddon(id:221039), Loveless(id:129239), Aibot(id:104981), Straysheep(id:42448), Chichiii(id:242358), Tatsujin28(id:9300), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>