<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>一国一城令</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Decree of one castle per province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Decree of One Castle Per Province</e>
<cmt>頭文字を大文字に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Decree of One Castle Per Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>一国一城令（いっこくいちじょうれい）は元和 (日本)元年（1615年）閏6月13日に江戸幕府が制定した法令である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Decree of one castle per province was established by the Edo bakufu on June 13, 1615.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The decree of one castle per province was established by the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) on August 7, 1615.</e>
<cmt>The decree of one castle per provinceとし、bakufuの補足追加、旧暦→新暦に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The decree of one castle per province was established by the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) on August 7, 1615.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>一国（この場合の「国」は令制国でもあり、大名の領国（後の藩）のことでもある）に大名が居住あるいは政庁とする一つの城を残してその他の城はすべて廃城にするというものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This decree stipulates disposal of all castles except one castle for feudal lord&apos;s residence or government office in one country (the country here means not only a province but also feudal lord&apos;s territory (subsequent domain)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This decree stipulated disposal of all castles except one castle for feudal lord&apos;s residence or government office in one province (the province here means not only a province but also feudal lord&apos;s territory [subsequent domain]).</e>
<cmt>stipulates→stipulated、country→provinceとし、カッコ表記を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This decree stipulated disposal of all castles except one castle for feudal lord&apos;s residence or government office in one province (the province here means not only a province but also feudal lord&apos;s territory [subsequent domain]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>具体例</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Specific example</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Specific example</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Specific example</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>一つの令制国を複数の大名で分割して領有している場合は各大名ごとに一城とし（例伊予国の大洲城、松山城 (伊予国)、宇和島城等）、一つの大名家が複数の令制国にまたがって領有している場合は各令制国ごとに一城とした（例津藩の津城（伊勢国）、上野城（伊賀国））。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a province was divided to be owned by several feudal lords, each lord was allowed to have one castle (for example, Ozu-jo Castle in Iyo Province, Matsuyama-jo Castle (Iyo Province) and Uwajima-jo Castle, etc.), and when a clan of feudal lord owned territory across a few provinces, they were allowed to have one in one province (for example, Tsu-jo Castle of Tsu Domain (Ise Province) and Ueno-jo Castle (Iga Province)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a province was divided to be owned by several feudal lords, each lord was allowed to have one castle (for example, Ozu-jo Castle, Matsuyama-jo Castle and Uwajima-jo Castle in Iyo Province, etc.), and when a clan of feudal lord owned territory across a few provinces, they were allowed to have one in one province (for example, Tsu-jo Castle [Ise Province] and Ueno-jo Castle [Iga Province] of the Tsu Domain).</e>
<cmt>Ozu-jo Castle in Iyo Province, Matsuyama-jo Castle (Iyo Province) and Uwajima-jo Castle→Ozu-jo Castle, Matsuyama-jo Castle and Uwajima-jo Castle in Iyo Provinceに修正、of the Tsu Domainとし位置を移動、カッコ表記修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a province was divided to be owned by several feudal lords, each lord was allowed to have one castle (for example, Ozu-jo Castle, Matsuyama-jo Castle and Uwajima-jo Castle in Iyo Province, etc.), and when a clan of feudal lord owned territory across a few provinces, they were allowed to have one in one province (for example, Tsu-jo Castle [Ise Province] and Ueno-jo Castle [Iga Province] of the Tsu Domain).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>例外</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Exceptions</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Exceptions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Exceptions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>この法制は画一的に実施されたわけではなく、大藩では大身の一門や家臣が実質上の城を持ち、現実には複数の城を維持している例も見られ、かなり弾力的に運用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This decree was not implemented uniformly but practiced flexibly very much, and when it comes to a large scale domain, families or vassals of high rank or income were the substantial castle owners and, in fact, there were some examples that some of them kept several castles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This decree was not implemented uniformly but practiced flexibly very much, and when it came to a large scale domain, families or vassals of high rank or income were the substantial castle owners and, in fact, there were some examples that some of them kept several castles.</e>
<cmt>comes→cameに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This decree was not implemented uniformly but practiced flexibly very much, and when it came to a large scale domain, families or vassals of high rank or income were the substantial castle owners and, in fact, there were some examples that some of them kept several castles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>毛利家の事例</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mori clan&apos;s cases</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mori clan&apos;s cases</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mori clan&apos;s cases</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>毛利家では周防国、長門国の二令制国で一城というかたちになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mori clan was entitled to have one castle across Suo Province and Nagato Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mori clan was entitled to have one castle across Suo Province and Nagato Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mori clan was entitled to have one castle across Suo Province and Nagato Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>山本博文著「江戸お留守居役の日記」等によると毛利家では長門国の萩城を残して岩国城などを破却し幕府に報告したが幕府の反応は「毛利家は周防国、長門国の二国だから周防国の岩国城まで破却する必要はなかった筈」というものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the book &quot;Journal of House Sitting in Edo&quot; written by Hirofumi YAMAMOTO and other materials, the Mori clan reported to the bakufu after the clan destroyed castles such as Iwakuni-jo Castle while leaving Hagi-jo Castle in Nagato Province, then, the bakufu replied, &quot;Since the Mori clan owns only two provinces, Suo and Nagato, you did not have to destroy Iwakuni-jo Castle in Suo Province, additionally.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the book &apos;Journal of House Sitting in Edo&apos; written by Hirofumi YAMAMOTO and other materials, the Mori clan reported to the bakufu after the clan destroyed castles such as Iwakuni-jo Castle while leaving Hagi-jo Castle in Nagato Province, then, the bakufu replied, &apos;Since the Mori clan owns only two provinces, Suo and Nagato, you did not have to destroy Iwakuni-jo Castle in Suo Province, additionally.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the book &apos;Journal of House Sitting in Edo&apos; written by Hirofumi YAMAMOTO and other materials, the Mori clan reported to the bakufu after the clan destroyed castles such as Iwakuni-jo Castle while leaving Hagi-jo Castle in Nagato Province, then, the bakufu replied, &apos;Since the Mori clan owns only two provinces, Suo and Nagato, you did not have to destroy Iwakuni-jo Castle in Suo Province, additionally.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>幕府への遠慮や毛利家内部の支藩統制上の思惑もあり先走って破却が行われたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that, coupled with humbleness to the bakufu and calculation on the branch domain&apos;s regulation within the clan, the castle was destroyed inadvertently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that, coupled with humbleness to the bakufu and calculation on the branch domain&apos;s regulation within the clan, the castle was destroyed inadvertently.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that, coupled with humbleness to the bakufu and calculation on the branch domain&apos;s regulation within the clan, the castle was destroyed inadvertently.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>その他の例外</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other exceptions</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other exceptions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other exceptions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>このほか仙台藩白石城や熊本藩八代城など大名の家臣でも特に幕府に対して功績があった者の子孫の居城は例外的に廃城の対象外とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, castles such as Shiraishi Castle in Sendai Domain and Yatsushiro Castle in Kumamoto Domain owned by the descendants of those who particularly contributed to the bakufu among vassals of feudal lords were exception to disposal of castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, castles such as Shiraishi-jo Castle in the Sendai Domain and Yatsushiro-jo Castle in the Kumamoto Domain owned by the descendants of those who particularly contributed to the bakufu among vassals of feudal lords were exception to disposal of castle.</e>
<cmt>Shiraishi-jo Castle in the Sendai Domain、Yatsushiro-jo Castle in the Kumamoto Domainとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, castles such as Shiraishi-jo Castle in the Sendai Domain and Yatsushiro-jo Castle in the Kumamoto Domain owned by the descendants of those who particularly contributed to the bakufu among vassals of feudal lords were exception to disposal of castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、仙台藩ではさらに要害などと称して実質上の城を多数維持し続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Sendai Domain also kept many actual castles by calling them fortresses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the Sendai Domain also kept many actual castles by calling them fortresses.</e>
<cmt>the Sendai Domainとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the Sendai Domain also kept many actual castles by calling them fortresses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>秋田藩では大館城と横手城（共に戊辰戦争で焼失）が対象外となり、久保田城と合わせて合計3城を持つことを許された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Akita Domain, Oodate-jo Castle and Yokote-jo Castle (both were burnt down in the Boshin War) were exception to disposal, as a result, the domain was allowed to have three castles in total, which were the above-mentioned two castles along with Kubota-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Akita Domain, Odate-jo Castle and Yokote-jo Castle (both were burnt down in the Boshin War) were exception to disposal, as a result, the domain was allowed to have three castles in total, which were the above-mentioned two castles along with Kubota-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>the Akita Domainとし、Oodate-jo→Odate-joに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Akita Domain, Odate-jo Castle and Yokote-jo Castle (both were burnt down in the Boshin War) were exception to disposal, as a result, the domain was allowed to have three castles in total, which were the above-mentioned two castles along with Kubota-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>これは、大大名であった佐竹氏を秋田に転封する見返りに、政情が不安定だった地区の持ち城を許したとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, some say that castles owned in the districts that were politically unstable were allowed in return for grand feudal lord Satake&apos;s change of the territory to Akita.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, some say that in return for the grand feudal lord Satake clan&apos;s change of the territory to Akita, they were allowed to own castles in the districts that had been politically unstable.</e>
<cmt>意味が明確になるよう一部訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, some say that in return for the grand feudal lord Satake clan&apos;s change of the territory to Akita, they were allowed to own castles in the districts that had been politically unstable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>実施の意義</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Significance of enforcement</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Significance of enforcement</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Significance of enforcement</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>これにより安土桃山時代に3千近くもあったといわれる城が約170まで激減し（陣屋を含めると約300）、結果として家臣団や領民の城下町集住が一層進んだとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, the number of castles which were said nearly as many as 3,000 (about 300 when regional government offices included) in the Azuchi Momoyama period dropped sharply to about 170, and consequently, grouped housing of vassals and domain people in castle towns progressed more.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, the number of castles which were said nearly as many as 3,000 in the Azuchi Momoyama period dropped sharply to about 170 (about 300 when regional government offices included), and consequently, grouped housing of vassals and domain people in castle towns progressed more.</e>
<cmt>(about 300 when regional government offices included)の位置を移動しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, the number of castles which were said nearly as many as 3,000 in the Azuchi Momoyama period dropped sharply to about 170 (about 300 when regional government offices included), and consequently, grouped housing of vassals and domain people in castle towns progressed more.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>大名の勢力（軍事力）を統制して徳川家による全国支配を強化することを目的としており、特に外様大名の多い西国に徹底させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its purpose was to strengthen the nation-wide governance by the Tokugawa by controlling the power (military force) of feudal lords; especially, focusing on the western provinces where there were a lot of nonhereditary feudal lords.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its purpose was to strengthen the nation-wide governance by the Tokugawa family by controlling the power (military force) of feudal lords; especially, focusing on the western provinces where there were a lot of nonhereditary feudal lords.</e>
<cmt>the Tokugawa→the Tokugawa familyとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its purpose was to strengthen the Tokugawa family&apos;s domination of the entire country by regulating the power (military force) of the feudal lords; it was focused in particular on the western provinces, where there were a lot of nonhereditary feudal lords.</e>
<cmt>nation-wide governance by the Tokugawa family→the Tokugawa family&apos;s domination of the entire country</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Jyo81(id:180101), Carkuni(id:79281), BoB774(id:148281), Yonoemon(id:55450), 田無稲子(id:63575), 経済準学士(id:22656), 水野白楓(id:22811), 怪蘇(id:45514), Qje(id:160294), 史跡めぐり(id:95651), らんで(id:58934), Robinhou(id:63040), ブレイズマン(id:183852), 亮来来(id:17212), Suisui(id:69), 酢溜まり氷(id:65987), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>