<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大奥</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">O-oku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">O-oku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">O-oku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大奥（おおおく）とは江戸城に存在した徳川将軍家の子女や正室、奥女中（御殿女中）たちの居所。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">O-oku was a residential place in Edo-jo castle where the Tokugawa Shogun family&apos;s children, lawful wife and oku jochu (working in the domestic quarters of a shogun or feudal lords) (also called palace jochu) resided.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">O-oku was a residential place in Edo-jo castle where the Tokugawa Shogun family&apos;s children, lawful wife and oku jochu (working in the domestic quarters of a shogun or feudal lords) (also called palace jochu) resided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">O-oku was a residential place in Edo-jo castle where the Tokugawa Shogun family&apos;s children, lawful wife and oku jochu (maids working in the domestic quarters of a shogun or feudal lords) (also called goten jochu [palace maids]) resided.</e>
<cmt>奥女中の訳にmaidsという説明を追加しました御殿女中の訳を読み方と意訳に分けました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>初代将軍･徳川家康の時代から、江戸城に「大奥」と呼ばれる区画は存在していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the first shogun, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA regime, there was a section called &quot;O-oku&quot; in Edo-jo castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the first shogun, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA`s regime, there was a section called &quot;O-oku&quot; in Edo-jo castle.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the first Shogun, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA&apos;s regime, there was a section called &quot;O-oku&quot; in Edo-jo castle.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しましたタイトル（将軍）の頭文字を大文字に修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>しかし当時は、政治を行う場である「表」と、城主とその家族の私的な生活の場である「奥」の境界が存在していなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, a border between the &quot;public area&quot; where conducting politics and &quot;private area&quot; where the lord of the castle and his family lived didn&apos;t exist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, a border between the &quot;public area&quot; for conducting politics and the &quot;private area&quot; where the lord of the castle and his family lived didn&apos;t exist.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, a border between the &quot;public area&quot; for conducting politics and the &quot;private area&quot; where the lord of the castle and his family lived didn&apos;t exist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>この境界が江戸城に現れたのは、元和 (日本)4年（1618年）年、2代将軍･徳川秀忠の時代、「大奥法度」を制定した時である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The border was established in Edo-jo castle when the &quot;Act governing O-oku&quot; was introduced in 1618 during the second Shogun, Hidetada TOKUGAWA&apos;s regime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The border was established in Edo-jo castle when the &quot;Act governing O-oku&quot; was introduced in 1618 during the second Shogun, Hidetada TOKUGAWA&apos;s regime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The border was established in Edo-jo castle when the &quot;O-oku Hatto&quot; (Act governing O-oku) was introduced in 1618 during the second Shogun, Hidetada TOKUGAWA&apos;s regime.</e>
<cmt>大奥法度の読みを追加しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>以後、本丸は江戸幕府政庁の「表」、将軍が政務を執る「中奥(奥)」、将軍の私邸「大奥」に区分された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Honmaru (the keep of a castle) of Edo-jo castle was divided into the government office of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) named &quot;Omote&quot;, the Shogun&apos;s office to administrate political affairs named &quot;Nakaoku&quot; and the Shogun&apos;s private residence named &quot;O-oku&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Honmaru (the keep of a castle) of Edo-jo castle was divided into the government office of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) named &quot;Omote&quot;, the Shogun&apos;s office to administrate political affairs named &quot;Nakaoku&quot; and the Shogun&apos;s private residence named &quot;O-oku&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Honmaru (the keep of a castle) of Edo-jo castle was divided into the government office of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) named &quot;Omote&quot;, the Shogun&apos;s office to administrate political affairs named &quot;Nakaoku&quot; and the Shogun&apos;s private residence named &quot;O-oku&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>3代将軍徳川家光乳母･春日局によって組織的な整備がなされていき、こうして現在知られる形の大奥に整えられていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kasuga no Tsubone, a menoto (a woman providing breast-feeding to a highborn baby) of the third Shogun, Iemitsu TOKUGAWA organized O-oku systematically and developed it as known to this day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kasuga no Tsubone, a menoto (a woman providing breast-feeding to a highborn baby) of the third Shogun, Iemitsu TOKUGAWA organized O-oku systematically and developed it as known to this day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kasuga no Tsubone, a menoto (a woman providing breast-feeding to a highborn baby) of the third Shogun, Iemitsu TOKUGAWA organized O-oku systematically and developed it as known to this day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>慶応4年（1868年）4月、江戸城の明け渡しが決定された時に、大奥は終焉を迎える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a decision to surrender Edo-jo castle was made in April, 1868, it was the end of O-oku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a decision to surrender Edo-jo castle was made in April, 1868, it was the end of O-oku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a decision to surrender Edo-jo castle was made in April, 1868, it was the end of O-oku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>開城に伴い、同年4月9日(旧暦)、14代将軍徳川家茂正室･和宮親子内親王と同生母･実成院は清水家邸へ、翌10日には、13代将軍徳川家定正室･天璋院と同生母本寿院が一橋家邸へ引き移った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Along with surrender of Edo-jo castle, the legal wife of the 14th Shogun, Iemochi TOKUGAWA, Imperial Princess Kazunomiya Chikako and her real mother moved to the Shimizu family&apos;s house on May 1, 1868 and the following day, the legal wife of the 14th Shogun, Tenshoin and her real mother Honjuin moved to the Hitotsubashi family&apos;s house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Along with the surrender of Edo-jo castle, the legal wife of the 14th Shogun, Iemochi TOKUGAWA, Imperial Princess Kazunomiya Chikako and her real mother moved to the Shimizu family&apos;s house on May 1, 1868 and the following day, the legal wife of the 14th Shogun, Tenshoin and her real mother Honjuin moved to the Hitotsubashi family&apos;s house.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Along with the surrender of Edo-jo castle, the legal wife of the 14th Shogun Iemochi TOKUGAWA, Imperial Princess Kazunomiya Chikako and his real mother, Jitsujoin moved to the Shimizu family&apos;s house on May 1, 1868 and the following day, the legal wife of the 13th Shogun Iesada TOKUGAWA, Tenshoin and his real mother Honjuin moved to the Hitotsubashi family&apos;s house.</e>
<cmt>誤訳、訳漏れを修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>4月11日、海江田信義、木梨精一郎、水野彦三郎、渡辺清の4人が新政府代表として大手門より入城し、江戸城の引渡しを終了させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 3, Nobuyoshi KAIEDA, Seiichiro KINASHI, Hikosaburo MIZUNO and Kiyoshi WATANABE entered into Edo-jo castle from Otte-mon Gate (Main Gate) as representatives of the new government and completed the surrender of Edo-jo castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 3, Nobuyoshi KAIEDA, Seiichiro KINASHI, Hikosaburo MIZUNO and Kiyoshi WATANABE entered into Edo-jo castle from Otte-mon Gate (Main Gate) as representatives of the new government and completed the surrender of Edo-jo castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 3, Nobuyoshi KAIEDA, Seiichiro KINASHI, Hikosaburo MIZUNO and Kiyoshi WATANABE entered into Edo-jo castle from Ote-mon Gate (Main Gate) as representatives of the new government and completed the surrender of Edo-jo castle.</e>
<cmt>大手門の表記を修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>構造</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structure</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>江戸城内曲輪は、本城(本丸、二の丸、三の丸)、西丸、紅葉山、吹上御庭、西丸下で構成されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edo-jo castle was build up with Honjo (the keep of castle) consisting of Honmaru (inner citadel), Ninomaru (second citadel) and Sannomaru (third citadel), Nishimaru palace, Momiji-yama Mountain, Fukiage garden, Nishinomarushita (西丸下) (residence of the Matsudaira domains).</e>
<cmt>読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edo-jo castle was build up with Honjo (the keep of castle) consisting of Honmaru (inner citadel), Ninomaru (second citadel) and Sannomaru (third citadel), Nishimaru palace, Momiji-yama Mountain, Fukiage garden, Nishinomarushita (西丸下) (residence of the Matsudaira domains).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edo-jo castle was build up with Honjo (the keep of castle) consisting of Honmaru (inner citadel), Ninomaru (second citadel) and Sannomaru (third citadel), Nishinomaru palace, Momiji-yama Mountain, Fukiage garden, Nishinomarushita (西丸下) (residence of the Matsudaira clans).</e>
<cmt>スペルミスを修正しました西丸下の補足説明を修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>この内、大奥が置かれたのは本丸、二丸、西丸の3つの郭である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">O-oku was placed in Honmaru and Nishinomaru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">O-oku was placed in Honmaru and Nishinomaru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">O-oku was placed in Honmaru, Ninomaru and Nishinomaru.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れを修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>本丸は将軍夫妻、二丸は将軍生母やかつての将軍仕えていた側室、西丸は世嗣夫妻や大御所夫妻が住まいとしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honmaru was the resident of shogun&apos;s real mother and concubines who previously worked for a shogun, and Nishinomaru was the residence of a successor couple and the retired shogun&apos;s couple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honmaru was the resident of the shogun&apos;s real mother and concubines who previously worked for a shogun, and Nishinomaru was the residence of the successor couple and the retired shogun couple.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honmaru was the resident of the Shogun and his wives, Ninomaru was the resident of the shogun&apos;s real mother and concubines of former Shogun, and Nishinomaru was the residence of the successor couple and the retired shogun couple.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れを修正しました原文は正しくは「かつての将軍&quot;に&quot;仕えていた側室」であると思われますタイトルの頭文字を大文字に修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>但し本丸の非常時には、二丸や西丸が代わりとして機能した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when Honmaru was in an emergency, Ninomaru and Nishinomaru was functioned as Honmaru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when Honmaru was in an emergency, Ninomaru and Nishinomaru functioned as Honmaru.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when Honmaru was in an emergency, Ninomaru and Nishinomaru functioned as Honmaru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>本丸御殿は、先述したように表、中奥、大奥に区分されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honmaru palace was divided into Omote, Nakaoku, and O-oku as described previously.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honmaru palace was divided into Omote, Nakaoku, and O-oku as described previously.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honmaru palace was divided into Omote, Nakaoku, and O-oku as described previously.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>この内、表と中奥は一続きの御殿であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omote and Nakaoku was a continuous stretch of the palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omote and Nakaoku was a continuous stretch of the palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omote and Nakaoku was a continuous stretch of the palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかし大奥は表･中奥御殿とは切り離されており、銅塀で仕切られていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, O-oku was separated from Omote and Nakaoku palaces by a copper wall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, O-oku was separated from Omote and Nakaoku palaces by a copper wall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, O-oku was separated from Omote and Nakaoku palaces by a copper wall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>中奥と大奥を繋ぐ唯一の廊下が、御鈴廊下である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Osuzuroka (a corridor of bell) was the only corridor connecting Nakaoku and O-oku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Osuzuroka (a corridor of bells) was the only corridor connecting Nakaoku and O-oku.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Osuzuroka (a corridor of bells) was the only corridor connecting Nakaoku and O-oku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>将軍が大奥へ出入りする際に鈴のついた紐を引いて鈴を鳴らして合図を送り、出入り口である「御錠口」の開錠をさせていた事からこの名が付いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This name came from a bell rang by pulling a string attached to the bell to open an entrance named &quot;Ojoguchi&quot; when the shogun visited O-oku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This name came from a bell that was rung by pulling a string attached to the bell to open an entrance named &quot;Ojoguchi&quot; when the shogun visited O-oku.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This name came from a bell that was rung by pulling a string attached to the bell to open an entrance named &quot;Ojoguchi&quot; when the Shogun visited O-oku.</e>
<cmt>タイトルの頭文字を大文字に修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>後に火事等の緊急事態を想定して作られたのが「下御鈴廊下」であるとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that &quot;Shimo osuzuroka&quot;(下御鈴廊下) (second corridor) was built for emergencies like fires.</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that &quot;Shimo osuzuroka&quot;(下御鈴廊下) (second corridor) was built for emergencies like fires.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that &quot;Shimo osuzuroka&quot;(下御鈴廊下) (second corridor) was built for emergencies like fires.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="21">
<j>大奥は大別して広敷向・長局向・御殿向に区画される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">O-oku was broadly divided into Hiroshikimuki, Nagatsubonemuki and Gotenmuki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">O-oku was broadly divided into Hiroshikimuki, Nagatsubonemuki and Gotenmuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">O-oku was broadly divided into Hiroshikimuki, Nagatsubonemuki and Gotenmuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="22">
<j>広敷向</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiroshikimuki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiroshikimuki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiroshikimuki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>広敷は大奥の玄関口である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiroshikimuki was an entrance of O-oku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiroshikimuki was an entrance of O-oku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiroshikimuki was an entrance of O-oku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>広敷には男性の広敷役人（広敷用人）がいたため、御殿との間の錠口、長局との間の七ツ口によって仕切られていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since male officers named Hiroshiki yakunin (yonin) were placed in Hiroshiki, Hiroshikimuki was separated from Gotenmuki by a door called Joguchi and Nagatsubonemuki by a door called Nanatsuguchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since male officers named Hiroshiki yakunin (yonin) were placed in Hiroshiki, Hiroshikimuki was separated from Gotenmuki by a door called Joguchi and Nagatsubonemuki by a door called Nanatsuguchi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since male officers named Hiroshiki yakunin (yonin) were placed in Hiroshiki, Hiroshikimuki was separated from Gotenmuki by a door called Joguchi and Nagatsubonemuki by a door called Nanatsuguchi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>七ツ口は、女中たちの部屋方や商人たちが用いていたが、七ツ時(午後4時)に閉められたためにこの名が付いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nanatsuchuchi was named because this door was closed at Nanatsudoki (4pm in modern time), and servants for jochu and merchants used this door.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nanatsuchuchi was named because this door was closed at Nanatsudoki (4pm in modern times), and servants for jochu and merchants used this door.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nanatsuchuchi was named because this door was closed at Nanatsudoki (4pm in modern times), and servants for jochu and merchants used this door.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="26">
<j>御殿向</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gotenmuki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gotenmuki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gotenmuki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>将軍の寝所である御小座敷、御台所居所、「千鳥之間」、「呉服之間」といった大奥女中詰所などがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gotenmuki consisted of Okozashiki (Shogun&apos;s bed room), the residence of Midaidokoro (wife of a shogun or a highest-ranking nobleman) and the rooms named &quot;Chidori no ma&quot; and &quot;Gofuku no ma&quot; where jochu in O-oku stationed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gotenmuki consisted of Okozashiki (Shogun&apos;s bed room), the residence of Midaidokoro (wife of a shogun or a highest-ranking nobleman) and the rooms named &quot;Chidori no ma&quot; and &quot;Gofuku no ma&quot; where jochu in O-oku were stationed.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gotenmuki consisted of Okozashiki (Shogun&apos;s bed room), the residence of Midaidokoro (wife of a shogun or a highest-ranking nobleman) and the rooms named &quot;Chidori no ma&quot; and &quot;Gofuku no ma&quot; where jochu in O-oku were stationed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>御台所の居所は、時代によって「松御殿」、「新御殿」などと呼ばれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A residence of Midaidokoro was also called &quot;Matsu goten &quot; or &quot;Shin goten&quot; according to the times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A residence of Midaidokoro was also called &quot;Matsu goten &quot; or &quot;Shin goten&quot; according to the times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A residence of Midaidokoro was also called &quot;Matsu goten &quot; or &quot;Shin goten&quot; according to the times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>歴代将軍の位牌がある「御仏間」や「御対面所」も、御殿にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Gobutsuma&quot; was where the successive shoguns&apos; ancestral tablets were placed and &quot;Gotaimensho&quot; was where male visitors were taken.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Gobutsuma&quot; was where the successive shoguns&apos; ancestral tablets were placed and &quot;Gotaimensho&quot; was where male visitors were taken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Gobutsuma&quot; was where the successive Shogun&apos;s ancestral tablets were placed and &quot;Gotaimensho&quot; was where male visitors were taken; those rooms ware also placed in Gotenmuki.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れを修正しましたタイトルの頭文字を大文字に修正しました文法を修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="30">
<j>長局向</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagatsubonemuki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagatsubonemuki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagatsubonemuki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>奥女中たちの2階建ての居所である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two-floors residence for maids in O-oku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two-floors residence for maids in O-oku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two-floors residence for maids in O-oku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>一之側から四之側までの4棟に加え、東長局、御半下部屋があり、格式に応じて一之側が上臈御年寄や御年寄、二之側、三之側がその他のお目見え以上の女中、四之側がお目見え以下の女中たちに配分された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to the four buildings from Ichi no soba (一之側) to Yon no soba (四之側), there were two buildings named Higashi nagatsubone and Ohashitabeya, and joro (high rank women servants in the Imperial Court) Otoshiyori (a lady who controls the servants in O-oku) and Otoshiyori were given Ichi no soba, other jochu in higher rank able to see the shogun were given Ni no soba or San no soba, and lower rank jochu not able to see shogun were given Yon no soba in accordance with their rank.</e>
<cmt>読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to the four buildings from Ichi no soba (一之側) to Yon no soba (四之側), there were two buildings named Higashi nagatsubone and Ohashitabeya, and joro (high rank women servants in the Imperial Court) Otoshiyori (a lady who controls the servants in O-oku) and Otoshiyori were given Ichi no soba, other jochu of higher rank able to see the shogun were given Ni no soba or San no soba, and lower rank jochu not able to see the shogun were given Yon no soba in accordance with their rank.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to the four buildings from Ichi no soba (一之側) to Yon no soba (四之側), there were two buildings named Higashi nagatsubone and Ohashitabeya, and Joro Otoshiyori (high rank women servants who controls the servants in O-oku) and Otoshiyori were given Ichi no soba, other jochu of higher rank able to see the Shogun were given Ni no soba or San no soba, and lower rank jochu not able to see the Shogun were given Yon no soba in accordance with their rank.</e>
<cmt>上臈御年寄の訳が分割されていたので、まとめましたタイトルの頭文字を大文字に修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>大奥女性の身分と立場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Status and position of ladies in O-oku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Status and position of ladies in O-oku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Status and position of ladies in O-oku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>御台所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Midaidokoro</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Midaidokoro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Midaidokoro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="33">
<j>大奥一の女主であり主宰者でもあるのが、将軍正室である「御台所」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Midaidokoro&quot; was Shogun&apos;s lawful wife and the highest rank of mistress in O-oku as well as hostess.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Midaidokoro&quot; was Shogun&apos;s lawful wife and the highest rank of mistress in O-oku as well as hostess.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Midaidokoro&quot; was Shogun&apos;s lawful wife and the highest rank of mistress in O-oku as well as hostess.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>御台所は、公家･宮家･天皇家から迎えるのが慣例となっていた（例外は、11代将軍徳川家斉御台所･広大院と天璋院の2人で、どちらも島津家出身であったが、近衛家に養女となった上で輿入れした）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally a midaidokoro came from a court noble family, a house of an imperial prince or Imperial family (there were two exceptions, Kodaiin and Tenshoin, midaidokoro of the 11th shogun Ienari TOKUGAWA, although they came from Shimazu family, they were adopted by a house of Konoe, and then married with the shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, a midaidokoro came from a court noble family, a house of an imperial prince or the Imperial family (there were two exceptions, Kodaiin and Tenshoin, midaidokoro of the 11th shogun Ienari TOKUGAWA, although they came from the Shimazu family, they were adopted by a house of Konoe, and then married with the shogun).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, a midaidokoro came from a court noble family, a house of an imperial prince or the Imperial family (there were two exceptions, Kodaiin and Tenshoin, midaidokoro of the 11th Shogun Ienari TOKUGAWA, although they came from the Shimazu family, they were adopted by the house of Konoe, and then married with the shogun).</e>
<cmt>タイトルの頭文字を大文字に修正しました文法を修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="35">
<j>江戸時代初期においては大抵の場合、御台所は形式上の主宰者であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the early Edo period, Midaidokoro was a formal hostess in most cases.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early Edo period, Midaidokoro was a formal hostess in most cases.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early Edo period, Midaidokoro was a formal hostess in most cases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>例えば、3代家光夫人･鷹司孝子は夫との仲が極めて険悪で、正式に「御台所」と称することのないまま、結婚後程なくしてその居所を本丸から中丸に移され、大奥の実権はもっぱら春日局らが握っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, since Iemitsu&apos;s third wife, Takako TAKATSUKASA was on extremely bad terms with her husband, she was transferred to her residence from Naka no maru (中丸) from Honmaru before being formally titled &quot;Midaidokoro&quot; and Kasugano tsubone held the real power in O-oku.</e>
<cmt>読み方不明、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, since Iemitsu&apos;s third wife, Takako TAKATSUKASA was on extremely bad terms with her husband, she was transferred to her residence from Naka no maru (中丸) from Honmaru before being formally titled &quot;Midaidokoro&quot; and Kasugano tsubone held the real power in O-oku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, since a wife of the third Shogun Iemitsu, Takako TAKATSUKASA was on extremely bad terms with her husband, she was transferred to her residence from Honmaru to Naka no maru (中丸) before being formally titled &quot;Midaidokoro&quot; and Kasuga no tsubone held the real power in O-oku.</e>
<cmt>誤訳、文法を修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>その立場に変化が現れたのは、6代将軍徳川家宣の時代で、家宣が、御台所･天英院の父･近衛基煕を儀礼指南役として重用し敬意を表した事で、幕府役人はもちろん、大奥の儀礼も整えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The status was changed during the sixth shogun Ienobu TOKUGAWA regime, because Ienobu valued and respected Motohiro KONOE, the father of Midaidokoro, Tenei-in and the officers of the feudal government and O-oku&apos;s rites were maintained.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The status was changed during the sixth shogun Ienobu TOKUGAWA regime, because Ienobu valued and respected Motohiro KONOE, the father of Midaidokoro, Tenei-in and the officers of the feudal government and O-oku&apos;s rites were maintained.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The status was changed during the sixth Shogun Ienobu TOKUGAWA regime, because Ienobu valued and respected Motohiro KONOE, the father of his Midaidokoro, Teneiin, as an instructor of ceremony, and therefore, rites of the officers of the feudal government and O-oku were maintained.</e>
<cmt>タイトルの頭文字を大文字に修正しました訳漏れ、文法を修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>それによって御台所の立場は不動のものとなったが、約100年もの間、御台所不在の期間が続き、その間は先代将軍の正室や将軍子女らが、大奥を主宰した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Midaidokoro&apos;s position was consolidated, but during the Midaidokoro&apos;s absence for about 100 years, the previous shogun&apos;s lawful wife or shogun&apos;s children organized O-oku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Midaidokoro&apos;s position was consolidated, but during the Midaidokoro&apos;s absence for about 100 years, the previous shogun&apos;s lawful wife or shogun&apos;s children organized O-oku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Midaidokoro&apos;s position was consolidated, but during the Midaidokoro&apos;s absence for about 100 years, the previous Shogun&apos;s lawful wife or Shogun&apos;s children organized O-oku.</e>
<cmt>タイトルの頭文字を大文字に修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="39">
<j>生前に官位を賜ったのは</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Midaidokoro granted official court rank during life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Midaidokoro granted official court rank during life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Midaidokoro granted official court rank during life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>4代徳川家綱正室の顕子女王（従三位）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Queen Akiko, the fourth shogun, Ietsuna TOKUGAWA&apos;s lawful wife (Jusani [Junior Third Rank]).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Queen Akiko, the fourth shogun, Ietsuna TOKUGAWA&apos;s lawful wife (Jusani [Junior Third Rank]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Queen Akiko, the fourth Shogun, Ietsuna TOKUGAWA&apos;s lawful wife (Jusani [Junior Third Rank]).</e>
<cmt>タイトルの頭文字を大文字に修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>6代徳川家宣正室の近衛熈子（従一位）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiroko KONOE, the sixth shogun Ienobu TOKUGAWA&apos;s lawful wife (Juichii [Junior First Rank]).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiroko KONOE, the sixth shogun Ienobu TOKUGAWA&apos;s lawful wife (Juichii [Junior First Rank]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiroko KONOE, the sixth Shogun Ienobu TOKUGAWA&apos;s lawful wife (Juichii [Junior First Rank]).</e>
<cmt>タイトルの頭文字を大文字に修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>10代徳川家治正室の倫子女王（従三位）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Queen Rinshi, the tenth shogun Ieharu TOKUGAWA&apos;s lawful wife (Jusani [Junior Third Rank]).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Queen Rinshi, the tenth shogun Ieharu TOKUGAWA&apos;s lawful wife (Jusani [Junior Third Rank]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Queen Rinshi, the 10th Shogun Ieharu TOKUGAWA&apos;s lawful wife (Jusani [Junior Third Rank]).</e>
<cmt>タイトルの頭文字を大文字に修正しました2桁の数字をアラビア数字に修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>11代徳川家斉正室の広大院（従一位）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kodaiin, the eleventh shogun enari TOKUGAWA&apos;s lawful wife (Juichii [Junior First Rank]).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kodaiin, the eleventh shogun enari TOKUGAWA&apos;s lawful wife (Juichii [Junior First Rank]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kodaiin, the 11th Shogun Ienari TOKUGAWA&apos;s lawful wife (Juichii [Junior First Rank]).</e>
<cmt>タイトルの頭文字を大文字に修正しました2桁の数字をアラビア数字に修正しましたスペルミスを修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>12代徳川家慶正室の喬子女王（従三位）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Queen Takako, the twelfth shogun Ieyoshi TOKUGAWA&apos;s lawful wife (Jusani [Junior Third Rank]).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Queen Takako, the twelfth shogun Ieyoshi TOKUGAWA&apos;s lawful wife (Jusani [Junior Third Rank]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Queen Takako, the 12th Shogun Ieyoshi TOKUGAWA&apos;s lawful wife (Jusani [Junior Third Rank]).</e>
<cmt>タイトルの頭文字を大文字に修正しました2桁の数字をアラビア数字に修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>13代徳川家定正室の天璋院（従三位）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenshoin, the thirteenth shogun Iesada TOKUGAWA&apos;s lawful wife (Jusani [Junior Third Rank])..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenshoin, the thirteenth shogun Iesada TOKUGAWA&apos;s lawful wife (Jusani [Junior Third Rank])..</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenshoin, the 13th Shogun Iesada TOKUGAWA&apos;s lawful wife (Jusani [Junior Third Rank]).</e>
<cmt>タイトルの頭文字を大文字に修正しました2桁の数字をアラビア数字に修正しましたピリオドが２つあったので一つ削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>の6人だけで、世嗣となる子供を産んだのは2代徳川秀忠正室の崇源院だけである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only above six Midaidokoro were granted official court rank and only Sugenin, the second shogun Hidetada TOKUGAWA&apos;s lawful wife delivered a successor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only the above six Midaidokoro were granted official court rank and only Sugenin, the second shogun Hidetada TOKUGAWA&apos;s lawful wife delivered a successor.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only the above six Midaidokoro were granted official court rank and only Sugenin, the second Shogun Hidetada TOKUGAWA&apos;s lawful wife delivered a successor.</e>
<cmt>タイトルの頭文字を大文字に修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>御台所は自らの夫が亡くなった場合は出家して本丸から退き、西丸に移って将軍の菩提を弔いながら余生を過ごした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Midaidokoro entered into priesthood after their husbands died and moved from Monmaru to Nishi no maru to spend their rest of life to pray for the repose of their husbands&apos; soul.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Midaidokoro entered into priesthood after their husbands died and moved from Monmaru to Nishi no maru to spend the rest of their lives to pray for the repose of their husbands&apos; soul.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Midaidokoro entered into priesthood after their husbands died and moved from Honmaru to Nishinomaru to spend the rest of their lives to pray for the repose of their husbands&apos; soul.</e>
<cmt>スペルミスをしゅうせいしました西丸の表記を前出のものに統一しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>側室</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concubine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concubine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concubine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="48">
<j>将軍の側室は基本的に将軍付の中臈から選ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basically, shogun&apos;s concubines were selected from the churo (a lady-in-waiting) for the shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Basically, shogun&apos;s concubines were selected from the churo (a lady-in-waiting) for the shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Basically, Shogun&apos;s concubines were selected from the churo (a lady-in-waiting) for the Shogun.</e>
<cmt>タイトルの頭文字を大文字に修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>将軍が目に適った者の名を御年寄に告げると、その日の夕刻には寝間の準備をして寝所である「御小座敷」に待機していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the shogun told name of the churo who suited his taste to the Otoshiyori (the lady who controlled the servants in O-oku), the bed was prepared at &quot;Okozashiki&quot; by that evening, the churo was waiting for the shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the shogun told the name of the churo who suited his taste to the Otoshiyori (the lady who controlled the servants in O-oku), the bed was prepared at &quot;Okozashiki&quot; by that evening, and the churo was waiting for the shogun.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a shogun told the name of a churo who suited his taste to the Otoshiyori (the lady who controlled the servants in O-oku), the bed was prepared at &quot;Okozashiki&quot; by that evening, and the churo was waiting for the shogun.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>御台所付の中臈が将軍の目に適った場合は、将軍付御年寄が御台所付御年寄に掛け合って寝間の準備が行なわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If a churo working for the Midaidokoro was appointed by the Shogun, Otoshiyori to Shogun negotiated with the Otoshiyori to Midaikodoro and prepared the bed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If a churo working for the Midaidokoro was appointed by the Shogun, Otoshiyori to Shogun negotiated with the Otoshiyori to Midaikodoro and prepared the bed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If a churo working for a midaidokoro was appointed by the shogun, Otoshiyori to Shogun negotiated with the Otoshiyori to Midaikodoro and prepared the bed.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="51">
<j>寝間を終えた中臈は「お手つき」と呼ばれ、懐妊して女子を出産すれば「お腹様｣（おはらさま）、男子を出産すれば「お部屋様｣（おへやさま）となり、ようやく正式な側室となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chuyo who slept with the shogun were called &quot;Otetsuki&quot; (person who slept with a shogun) and, if she got pregnant and delivered a girl, she was called &quot;Oharasama&quot;, and if she delivered a boy, she was called &quot;Oheyasama&quot;, and then finally became a concubine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chuyo who slept with the shogun were called &quot;Otetsuki&quot; (person who slept with a shogun) and, if she got pregnant and delivered a girl, she was called &quot;Oharasama&quot;, and if she delivered a boy, she was called &quot;Oheyasama&quot;, and then finally became a concubine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Churo who slept with the shogun were called &quot;Otetsuki&quot; (person who slept with a shogun) and, if she got pregnant and delivered a girl, she was called &quot;Oharasama&quot;, and if she delivered a boy, she was called &quot;Oheyasama&quot;, and then finally became a concubine.</e>
<cmt>スペルミスを修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>さらに我が子が世子となり、やがて将軍ともなれば、落飾した側室でも将軍生母として尼御台（あまみだい、落飾した御台所）をはるかに凌ぐ絶大な権威と権力を持ち得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, if one&apos;s own son became an heir and shogun, even concubines already entered into priesthood could have far more authority and power as the real mother of shogun than Ama Midai (Midaidokoro entered into priesthood).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, if one&apos;s own son became an heir and shogun, even concubines already entered into priesthood could have far more authority and power as the real mother of a shogun than Ama Midai (Midaidokoro entered into priesthood).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, if one&apos;s own son became an heir and Shogun, even concubines already entered into priesthood could have far more authority and power as the real mother of a shogun than Ama Midai (Midaidokoro entered into priesthood).</e>
<cmt>タイトルの頭文字を大文字に修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>五代将軍徳川綱吉の生母・桂昌院はその最たる例で、公家の女子を除いて存命中の女性としては史上空前絶後の従一位に叙せられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fifth shogun Tsunayorshi TOKUGAWA&apos;s real mother, Keishoin was the best example and she was granted juichii (Junior First Rank) as the first female of all time other than the females in the noble court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fifth shogun Tsunayorshi TOKUGAWA&apos;s real mother, Keishoin was the best example and she was granted juichii (Junior First Rank) as the first female of all time other than the females in the noble court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fifth Shogun Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA&apos;s real mother, Keishoin was the best example and she was granted juichii (Junior First Rank) during her lifetime as the first female of all time other than the females in the noble court.</e>
<cmt>タイトルの頭文字を大文字に修正しました訳漏れ、スペルミスを修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="54">
<j>しかし側室や将軍生母の力は時代が下るとともに低下していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the authority of the concubines and shogun&apos;s real mother was declining with the times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the authority of the concubines and shogun&apos;s real mother was declining with the times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the authority of the concubines and Shogun&apos;s real mother were declining with the times.</e>
<cmt>タイトルの頭文字を大文字に修正しました文法を修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>江戸時代後期になると、側室はたとえ我が子が将軍世子であっても自身の地位は一介の女中のそれと同等にとどまり、我が子が将軍になって初めてお上（おかみ、将軍）の最近親として礼遇された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the late Edo period, the concubines&apos; position were the same as a jochu even of her child became the shogun&apos;s heir, after her son became a shogun, she was treated very well as the closest relative of Okami (shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the late Edo period, the concubines&apos; position were the same as a jochu even if her child became the shogun&apos;s heir, and after her son became a shogun, she was treated very well as the closest relative of Okami (shogun).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the late Edo period, the concubines&apos; position were the same as a jochu even if her child became the Shogun&apos;s heir, and only after her son became a shogun, she was treated very well as the closest relative of Okami (Shogun).</e>
<cmt>タイトルの頭文字を大文字に修正しました訳漏れを修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>その他の側室は二丸御殿や桜田御用屋敷で静かに余生を過ごした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other concubines spent the rest of their life in Minomaru palace or Sakurada goyo yashiki (palace) quietly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other concubines spent the rest of their life in Minomaru palace or Sakurada goyo yashiki (palace) quietly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other concubines spent the rest of their life in Ninomaru palace or Sakurada goyo yashiki (palace) quietly.</e>
<cmt>スペルミスを修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>大奥女中</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jochu in O-oku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jochu in O-oku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jochu in O-oku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="57">
<j>大奥に住む女性たちの大部分を占めていたのが女中たちであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of female residents in O-oku was jochu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most female residents in O-oku were jochu.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most female residents in O-oku were jochu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>ちなみに幕府から給金を支給されていた女中たちすべてを「大奥女中」と言い、実際には将軍家の姫君の輿入れ先や息子の養子先の大名家にも存在していたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All jochu received a salary from the government were called &quot;O-oku jochu&quot; and it is said that O-oku jochu were in families where the shogun&apos;s daughter married and the shogun&apos;s son was adopted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All jochu who received a salary from the government were called &quot;O-oku jochu&quot; and it is said that O-oku jochu were in families into which the shogun&apos;s daughters married, and to whom the shogun&apos;s sons were adopted.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All jochu who received a salary from the government were called &quot;O-oku jochu&quot; and it is said that O-oku jochu were also in families into which the shogun&apos;s daughters married, and to whom the shogun&apos;s sons were adopted.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>女中の人数は最盛期で1000人とも3000人とも言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said there were 1,000 to 3,000 jochu were in O-oku at the peak period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said there were 1,000 to 3,000 jochu in O-oku during the peak period.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said there were 1,000 to 3,000 jochu in O-oku during the peak period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="60">
<j>女中は基本的に将軍付と御台所付の女中に大別されているが、役職名は殆ど同じである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basically jochu was divided into two; one working for the shogun, the other was for Midaidokoro, but the name of the position were almost the same.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Basically jochu were divided into two; one working for the shogun, and the other was for Midaidokoro, but the name of the positions were almost the same.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Basically jochu were divided into two; one working for the Shogun, and the other was for Midaidokoro, but the name of the positions were almost the same.</e>
<cmt>タイトルの頭文字を大文字に修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>ただし、格式や権威に関しては将軍付の方が高かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in terms of formality and authority, jochu working for the shogun were higher.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in terms of formality and authority, jochu working for the shogun were higher.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in terms of formality and authority, jochu working for the Shogun were higher.</e>
<cmt>タイトルの頭文字を大文字に修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>また、特定の主人を持たない女中たちを｢詰｣と呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jochu who didn&apos;t have a specific master were called &quot;Tsume&quot; (詰).</e>
<cmt>読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jochu who didn&apos;t have a specific master were called &quot;Tsume&quot; (詰).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jochu who didn&apos;t have a specific master were called &quot;Tsume&quot; (詰).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="63">
<j>序列は時代によって異なるが、江戸時代後期の奥女中の役職は以下の通りであった</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Posts given to oku jochu in the late Edo period were as below, but this varied depending on the period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Posts given to oku jochu in the late Edo period were as below, but this varied depending on the period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Posts given to oku jochu in the late Edo period were as below, but this varied depending on the period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="64">
<j>奥女中のうち、上臈御年寄から御坊主までがお目見え以上と言い、将軍と御台所への目通りを許されていた上級の女中たちである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jochu ranked from Joro otoshiyori to Gobozu were allowed to see the shogun and Midaidokoro, therefore they were upper rank jochu and called &quot;Omemie ijo&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jochu ranked from Joro otoshiyori to Gobozu were allowed to see the shogun and Midaidokoro, therefore they were upper rank jochu and called &quot;Omemie ijo&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jochu ranked from Joro Otoshiyori to Gobozu were allowed to see the Shogun and Midaidokoro, therefore they were upper rank jochu and called &quot;Omemie ijo&quot;.</e>
<cmt>タイトルの頭文字を大文字に修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>女中たちのお禄（手当）は主に切米、合力金、扶持（月々の食料）、湯之木（風呂用の薪）、五菜銀（味噌や塩を買うための銀）、油などの現物が多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Allowance to jochu was mainly in kind like rice, gold, fuchi (monthly provided food), Yunoki (firewood for bath) and Gosaigin (silver for buying miso [bean paste] and salt).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Allowance to jochu was mainly in kind like rice, gold, fuchi (monthly provided food), Yunoki (firewood for bath) and Gosaigin (silver for buying miso [bean paste] and salt).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Allowance to jochu was mainly in kind like rice, gold, fuchi (monthly provided food), Yunoki (firewood for bath), Gosaigin (silver for buying miso [bean paste] and salt), oil and so on.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れを修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>また御年寄になると町屋敷が与えられることもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sometimes machiya (long and narrow wooden row houses) was given to Otoshiyori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sometimes machiya (long and narrow wooden row houses) were given to Otoshiyori.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sometimes machiyashiki (long and narrow wooden row houses) were given to Otoshiyori.</e>
<cmt>スペルミスを修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="67">
<j>奥女中には通常旗本や御家人などの武家出の女性が雇用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally, females from samurai families like hatamoto (direct retainers of the Edo bakufu) and gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods)were employed in O-oku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, females from samurai families like hatamoto (direct retainers of the Edo bakufu) and gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods)were employed in O-oku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, females from samurai families like hatamoto (direct retainers of the Edo bakufu) and gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods)were employed in O-oku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>しかしそれも建前で、時代が下るにつれて裕福な町人出の女性が「行儀見習い」目的に奉公に上がることが多くなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this was a public position, so females from rich townspeople were sent out to O-oku to learn manners in the later period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this was a public position, so females from rich townspeople were sent out to O-oku to learn manners in the later period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this was a public position, so females from rich townspeople were sent out to O-oku to learn manners in the later period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>町人の場合、初めの頃こそは親戚や知り合いの先輩女中の口利きを頼ったり、旗本や御家人の家へいったん養女入りしたりという、迂遠な根回しや手続きを経て大奥入りした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, townspeople needed an intermediary like relatives, acquaintances or senior jochu, or roundabout maneuvering or procedures like adopting their daughters to hatamoto to send their daughters to O-oku.</e>
<cmt>一原文一翻訳の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, townspeople needed an intermediary like relatives, acquaintances or senior jochu, or roundabout maneuvering or procedures like adopting their daughters to hatamoto to send their daughters to O-oku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, townspeople needed an intermediary like relatives, acquaintances or senior jochu, or roundabout maneuvering or procedures like adopting their daughters to hatamoto to send them to O-oku.</e>
<cmt>their daughtersという単語が重複していたので、一部を代名詞に変更しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>しかし後代になって武士と町人の経済力が完全に逆転すると、今度は旗本や御家人の方から持参金付き養女縁組みの話を持ちかけくることも珍しくなくなっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, once the financial strength reversed between samurai and townspeople completely, it was not uncommon that hatamoto and gokenin proposed adoptions with dowries.</e>
<cmt>一原文一翻訳の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, once the financial strength reversed between samurai and townspeople completely, it was not uncommon that hatamoto and gokenin proposed adoptions with dowries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, once the financial strength reversed between samurai and townspeople completely, it was not uncommon that hatamoto and gokenin proposed adoptions with dowries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="71">
<j>「大奥総取締」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A head of O-oku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A head of O-oku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;A head of O-oku&quot;</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて記号を追加しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>大奥を舞台にした小説・舞台・映画・ドラマなどでよく登場するのが、「大奥総取締・〜〜にござりまする」というあの場面。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many scenes in novels, stages, movies and dramas set in O-oku introducing &quot;I am XX, a head of O-oku&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many scenes in novels, stages, movies and dramas set in O-oku introducing &quot;I am XX, a head of O-oku&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many scenes in novels, stages, movies and dramas set in O-oku introducing &quot;I am XX, a head of O-oku&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>特に近年の映画やドラマではこれをよく耳にするようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This words appeared in recent movies and dramas very often.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These words have appeared in recent movies and dramas very often.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These words have appeared in recent movies and dramas very often.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>このため「大奥総取締」は大奥を語る上での不可欠な役職だと思われがちだが、実はそうした名称の役職は大奥に存在しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Head of O-oku tend to be considered the essential posts in O-oku, actually such posts didn&apos;t exist in O-oku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Head of O-oku tend to be considered the essential posts in O-oku, however, actually such posts did not exist in O-oku.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Head of O-oku tend to be considered the essential posts in O-oku, however, actually such posts did not exist in O-oku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>ではこれがまったくの創作上の代物なのかというと、実はそうでもない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, these post weren&apos;t totally fiction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, these posts weren&apos;t totally fiction.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, these posts weren&apos;t totally fiction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>大奥にはどの時代にも奥向き一切を取り締まることを任された取締役の女性が存在したからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because there were ladies who were given the authority to manage all the inner workings of the house in O-oku in this time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because there were ladies who were given the authority to manage all the inner workings of the house in O-oku in this time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because there were ladies who were given the authority to manage all the inner workings of the house in O-oku in this time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="77">
<j>大奥は時代が下るにつれて規模が肥大化し、それに伴って数多くの役職が置かれていったが、その頂点に立つのが上臈御年寄や御年寄といった取締役（統括管理職）だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A scale of O-oku increased later times, many posts were established and at the top of such posts were managers (umbrella administrator) like joro otoshiyori and otoshiyori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The scale of O-oku increased in later times, many posts were established and at the top of such posts were managers (umbrella administrator) like joro otoshiyori and otoshiyori.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The scale of O-oku increased in later times, many posts were established and at the top of such posts were managers (umbrella administrator) like Joro Otoshiyori and Otoshiyori.</e>
<cmt>タイトルの頭文字を大文字に修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>しかしそもそも大奥とは将軍の私的な生活の場であり、将軍とは江戸城における絶対権威者である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, O-oku was a shogun&apos;s private residence and the shogun had absolute authority in Edo-jo castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, O-oku was a shogun&apos;s private residence and the shogun had absolute authority in Edo-jo castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, O-oku was the Shogun&apos;s private residence and the Shogun had absolute authority in Edo-jo castle.</e>
<cmt>タイトルの頭文字を大文字に修正しました文法を修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>いかに大奥が取締役の職掌を制度上定めたとしても、その実際の運用にあたっては結局のところ「お上のご寵愛」という、将軍個人の極めて私的な感情によって左右される要素が介在することを排除できなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even if O-oku determined the authority of the administrator as a rule, the authority given in O-oku depended on the shogun&apos;s private opinion and the O-oku could not stop the Shogun giving authority to his favorite.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even if O-oku determined the authority of the administrator as a rule, the authority given in O-oku depended on the shogun&apos;s private opinion and the O-oku could not stop the Shogun giving authority to his favorite.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even if O-oku determined the authority of the administrator as a rule, the authority given in O-oku depended on the Shogun&apos;s private opinion and the O-oku could not stop the Shogun giving authority to his favorite.</e>
<cmt>タイトルの頭文字を大文字に修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>したがって時代によっては、時の将軍が最も信頼する乳母や側室などが、その将軍の絶対権威のみを背景に、奥向き一切を取り仕切っていた場合もあったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, sometime a wet nurse or concubine of shogun at that time were trusted to administer the inner part of the house based on the shogun&apos;s absolute authority.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, sometime a wet nurse or concubine of the shogun at that time were trusted to administer the inner part of the house based on the shogun&apos;s absolute authority.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, sometime a wet nurse or concubine of the Shogun at that time were trusted to administer the inner part of the house based on the Shogun&apos;s absolute authority.</e>
<cmt>タイトルの頭文字を大文字に修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>これは御鈴廊下を隔てた表向きにおいて、大老や老中といった幕府の機構上の最高責任者がいても、時代によっては将軍が最も寵愛する御側用人がその将軍の権威のみを背景に幕政の諸事万端を司っていたことがあるのと同様である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This happened across Osuzuroka, the political administration, although Tairo (chief minister) and roju (senior councilor) were assigned as chief governmental executives, the shogun&apos;s favorite sobayonin (lord chamberlain) administrated various government matters based on the shogun&apos;s authority.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This happened across Osuzuroka, the political administration, although Tairo (chief minister) and roju (senior councilor) were assigned as chief governmental executives, the shogun&apos;s favorite sobayonin (lord chamberlain) administrated various government matters based on the shogun&apos;s authority.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This happened across Osuzuroka, the political administration, although Tairo (chief minister) and roju (senior councilor) were assigned as chief governmental executives, the shogun&apos;s favorite sobayonin (lord chamberlain) administrated various government matters based on the Shogun&apos;s authority.</e>
<cmt>タイトルの頭文字を大文字に修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="82">
<j>大奥に「大奥総取締」という名称の役職は確かに存在しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Surely there was no post called &quot;a head of O-oku&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Surely there was no post called &quot;a head of O-oku&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Surely there was no post called &quot;a head of O-oku&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>しかし大奥はどの時代も「事実上の大奥総取締」というべき職掌を担った一人の女性によって統括されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, O-oku was administrated by a lady who was in complete control and she was &quot;virtual head of O-oku&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, O-oku was administrated by a lady who was in complete control and she was &quot;virtual head of O-oku&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, O-oku had been administrated by a lady who was in complete control and she was &quot;virtual head of O-oku&quot;.</e>
<cmt>「どの時代も」という部分を出すため、時制を変更しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>この二点を混同しないよう気をつけたい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Don&apos;t confuse these positions</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Don&apos;t confuse these positions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Don&apos;t confuse these positions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>有名な大奥の女性</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Famous O-oku women</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Famous O-oku women</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Famous O-oku women</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="85">
<j>崇源院 - 2代将軍徳川秀忠の御台所、徳川家光の母。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sugen-in - Midaidokoro of the second shogun Hidetada TOKUGAWA and mother of Iemitsu TOKUGAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sugen-in - Midaidokoro of the second shogun Hidetada TOKUGAWA and mother of Iemitsu TOKUGAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sugenin - Midaidokoro of the second Shogun Hidetada TOKUGAWA and mother of Iemitsu TOKUGAWA</e>
<cmt>名前のハイフンを削除しましたタイトルの頭文字を大文字に修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="86">
<j>春日局 - 徳川家光の乳母。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kasuga no tsubone - a wet nurse of Iemitus TOKUGAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kasuga no tsubone - a wet nurse of Iemitus TOKUGAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kasuga no tsubone - a wet nurse of Iemitsu TOKUGAWA</e>
<cmt>スペルミスを修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="87">
<j>鷹司孝子 - 家光の御台所。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takako TAKATSUKASA- Midaidokoro of Iemitsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takako TAKATSUKASA- Midaidokoro of Iemitsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takako TAKATSUKASA- Midaidokoro of Iemitsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="88">
<j>永光院 - 家光の側室。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eikoin - Concubine of Iemitsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eikoin - Concubine of Iemitsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eikoin - Concubine of Iemitsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>春日局の死後、家光より「春日同様」に奥向きを取締まるよう命じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Kasuga no tsubone died, Iemitsu ordered her to administrate the inner part of the house &quot;as Katsuga no tsubone did&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Kasuga no tsubone died, Iemitsu ordered her to administrate the inner part of the house &quot;as Katsuga no tsubone did&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Kasuga no tsubone died, Iemitsu ordered her to administrate the inner part of the house &quot;as Katsuga no tsubone did&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="90">
<j>宝樹院 - 家光の側室、徳川家綱の生母。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hojuin - Concubine of Iemitsu, real mother of Ietsuna TOKUGAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hojuin - Concubine of Iemitsu, real mother of Ietsuna TOKUGAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hojuin - Concubine of Iemitsu, real mother of Ietsuna TOKUGAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="91">
<j>順性院 - 家光の側室、甲府藩主徳川綱重（徳川家宣の実父）の生母。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Junsho-in - Concubine of Iemitsu, real mother of Tsunashige TOKUGAWA (real father of Ienobu TOKUGAWA), a lord of the Kofu domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Junsho-in - Concubine of Iemitsu, real mother of Tsunashige TOKUGAWA (real father of Ienobu TOKUGAWA), a lord of the Kofu domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Junshoin - Concubine of Iemitsu, real mother of Tsunashige TOKUGAWA (real father of Ienobu TOKUGAWA), a lord of the Kofu Domain.</e>
<cmt>名前のハイフンを削除しました藩のイニシャルを大文字にしました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="92">
<j>桂昌院 - 家光の側室、徳川綱吉の生母。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keisho-in - Concubine of Iemitsu, real mother of Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keisho-in - Concubine of Iemitsu, real mother of Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keishoin - Concubine of Iemitsu, real mother of Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA</e>
<cmt>名前のハイフンを削除しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="93">
<j>鷹司信子 - 5代将軍徳川綱吉の御台所。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobuko TAKATSUKASA - Midaidokoro of the fifth shogun Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobuko TAKATSUKASA - Midaidokoro of the fifth shogun Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobuko TAKATSUKASA - Midaidokoro of the fifth Shogun Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>タイトルの頭文字を大文字に修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="94">
<j>瑞春院 - 綱吉の側室。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zuishun-in - Concubine of tsunayoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zuishun-in - Concubine of Tsunayoshi.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zuishunin - Concubine of Tsunayoshi.</e>
<cmt>名前のハイフンを削除しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="95">
<j>右衛門佐局 - 綱吉から奥向きを取締まるよう命じられた上臈御年寄。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uemon no suke no tsubone - Joro otoshiyori that Tsunayoshi ordered to the administrate the inner part of the house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uemon no suke no tsubone - Joro otoshiyori that Tsunayoshi ordered to the administrator of the inner part of the house.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uemon no suke no tsubone - Joro otoshiyori that Tsunayoshi ordered to the administrator of the inner part of the house.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="96">
<j>近衛熙子 - 徳川家宣の御台所。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiroko KONOE - Midaidokoro of Ienobu TOKUGAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiroko KONOE - Midaidokoro of Ienobu TOKUGAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiroko KONOE - Midaidokoro of Ienobu TOKUGAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="97">
<j>月光院 - 徳川家宣の側室、7代将軍徳川家継の生母。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gekkoin - Concubine of Ienobu TOKUGAWA, real mother of the seventh shogun Ietsugu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gekkoin - Concubine of Ienobu TOKUGAWA, real mother of the seventh shogun Ietsugu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gekkoin - Concubine of Ienobu TOKUGAWA, real mother of the seventh Shogun Ietsugu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>タイトルの頭文字を大文字に修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="98">
<j>絵島 - 徳川家継時代に勢力をはった御年寄。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ejima - Otoshiyori who had power during Ietsugu TOKUGAWA regime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ejima - Otoshiyori who had power during the Ietsugu TOKUGAWA regime.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ejima - Otoshiyori who had power during the Ietsugu TOKUGAWA regime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="99">
<j>玉沢 -10代将軍徳川家治の時代に勢力をはった御年寄。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tamasawa (玉沢) - Otoshiyori who had power during Ieharu TOKUGAWA regime.</e>
<cmt>読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tamasawa (玉沢) - Otoshiyori who had power during the Ieharu TOKUGAWA regime.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tamasawa (玉沢) - Otoshiyori who had power during the regime of the 10th Shogun, Ieharu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れを修正しました2桁の数字をアラビア数字に修正しましたタイトルの頭文字を大文字に修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="100">
<j>広大院 - 11代将軍徳川家斉の御台所。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kodaiin - Midaidokoro of the eleventh shogun Ienari TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kodaiin - Midaidokoro of the eleventh shogun Ienari TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kodaiin - Midaidokoro of the 11th Shogun Ienari TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>2桁の数字をアラビア数字に修正しましたタイトルの頭文字を大文字に修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="101">
<j>大崎 (大奥御年寄) - 家斉付御年寄。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Osaki (O-oku Otoshiyori) - Otoshiyori to Ienari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Osaki (O-oku Otoshiyori) - Otoshiyori to Ienari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Osaki (O-oku Otoshiyori) - Otoshiyori to Ienari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>松平定信の老中就任に尽力したが後に対立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was committed to getting Sadanobu MATSUDAIRA post of roju (member of shogun&apos;s council of elders), but later they were opposed each other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was committed to getting Sadanobu MATSUDAIRA the post of roju (member of shogun&apos;s council of elders), but later they were opposed to each other.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was committed to getting Sadanobu MATSUDAIRA the post of roju (member of shogun&apos;s council of elders), but later they were opposed to each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="103">
<j>専行院 - 徳川家斉の側室。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senkoin - Concubine of Ienari TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senkoin - Concubine of Ienari TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senkoin - Concubine of Ienari TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="104">
<j>姉小路 - 12代将軍徳川家慶付き上臈御年寄。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anekoji - Joro Otoshiyori to the twelfth shogun Ieyoshi TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anekoji - Joro Otoshiyori to the twelfth shogun Ieyoshi TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anekoji - Joro Otoshiyori to the 12th Shogun Ieyoshi TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>2桁の数字をアラビア数字に修正しましたタイトルの頭文字を大文字に修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>家慶時代に勢力をはった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She had power during the Ieyoshi regime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She had power during the Ieyoshi regime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She had power during the Ieyoshi regime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="106">
<j>本寿院 - 徳川家慶の側室、13代将軍徳川家定の生母。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honjin - Concubine of Ieyoshi TOKUGAWA, real mother of the thirteenth shogun Iesada TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honjin - Concubine of Ieyoshi TOKUGAWA, real mother of the thirteenth shogun Iesada TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honjuin - Concubine of Ieyoshi TOKUGAWA, real mother of the 13th Shogun Iesada TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>スペルミスを修正しました2桁の数字をアラビア数字に修正しましたタイトルの頭文字を大文字に修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="107">
<j>瀧山 - 徳川家定時代から14代将軍徳川家茂時代の御年寄。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takiyama - Otoshiyori between Iesada TOKUGAWA and the fourteenth shogun Ieshige TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takiyama - Otoshiyori between Iesada TOKUGAWA and the fourteenth shogun Ieshige TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takiyama - Otoshiyori between Iesada TOKUGAWA and the 14th Shogun Ieshige TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>2桁の数字をアラビア数字に修正しましたタイトルの頭文字を大文字に修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="108">
<j>天璋院 - 徳川家定の正室。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenshoin - Lawful wife of Iesada TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenshoin - Lawful wife of Iesada TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenshoin - Lawful wife of Iesada TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="109">
<j>幾島 - 天璋院付の御年寄。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikushima - Otoshiyori to Tenshoin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ikushima - Otoshiyori to Tenshoin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikushima - Otoshiyori to Tenshoin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="110">
<j>実成院 - 徳川家茂の生母。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jitsujoin - Real mother of Iemochi TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jitsujoin - Real mother of Iemochi TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jitsujoin - Real mother of Iemochi TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="111">
<j>和宮親子内親王 - 徳川家茂の御台所。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Princess Kazunomiya Chikako - Midaidokoro of Iemochi TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Princess Kazunomiya Chikako - Midaidokoro of Iemochi TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Princess Kazunomiya Chikako - Midaidokoro of Iemochi TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 月下薄氷(id:47743), 果帆(id:225119), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), 飲んでも飲まれるな(id:120588), Uraios(id:72687), 赤井(id:258378), Kurz(id:1601), Shelling ford 221b(id:35237), Shelling ford(id:35136), みらい(id:14772), Loveless(id:129239), Point136(id:211299), こぶまき(id:38278), サイユ(id:25887), Toki-ho(id:10691), せくそろじすと(id:9002), 翰林硯士(id:99377), Izayohi(id:13095), 目白梅(id:141468), Rosecosmique(id:68611), 与左衛門(id:159462), 松茸(id:27535), Seibuabina(id:37532), 胸肉(id:156651), Happy B.(id:111020), 酢溜まり氷(id:65987), 白拍子花子(id:244805), MDR-SK(id:192066), Rusk(id:9895), Kazukiokumura(id:142935), Tietew(id:4054), Yoriyori(id:67575), VolkovBot(id:105371), ゐ(id:795), 史さん(id:25829), Alexbot(id:157199), Safkan(id:423), NDR(id:5500), 陸奥守(id:27058), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>