<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>平群氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hegri Clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heguri Clan (an ancient powerful local clan based in Heguri County, Yamato Province)</e>
<cmt>用語を変更し、補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heguri Clan (an ancient powerful local clan based in Heguri County, Yamato Province)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>平群氏（へぐりし）は、武内宿禰の後裔と伝えられ、大和国平群郡平群郷（奈良県生駒郡平群町）を本拠地とした古代在地豪族の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hegri clan is said to be a descendant of TAKENOUCHI no Sukune and one of the ancient powerful local clans who was based in Heguri go, Hegurino-kori in Yamato province (present Heguri-cho, Ikoma County, Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Heguri clan is said to be a descendant of TAKENOUCHI no Sukune and one of the ancient powerful local clans based in Heguri no go, Heguri County in Yamato Province (present Heguri Town, Ikoma County, Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Heguri clan is said to be a descendant of TAKENOUCHI no Sukune and one of the ancient powerful local clans based in Heguri no go, Heguri County in Yamato Province (present Heguri Town, Ikoma County, Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>カバネは臣（おみ）、後に朝臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kabane (hereditary title) was Omi and later it was changed to Ason.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kabane (hereditary title) was Omi and later it was changed to Ason.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kabane (hereditary title) was Omi and later it was changed to Ason.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>『日本書紀』の所伝によると、応神朝から軍事氏族としての活躍が見え、履中朝に平群木菟宿禰（へぐりのつくのすくね）が国政に携わるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Nihon Shoki (Chronicles of Japan),&quot; the Heguri clan was very active as a military clan from Emperor Ojin&apos;s Court and HEGURI no Tsuku no Sukune came to participate in the national politics in Emperor Richu&apos;s Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), the Heguri clan was active as a military clan from Emperor Ojin&apos;s Court and HEGURI no Tsuku no Sukune came to participate in the national politics in Emperor Richu&apos;s Court.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), the Heguri clan was active as a military clan from Emperor Ojin&apos;s Court and HEGURI no Tsuku no Sukune came to participate in the national politics in Emperor Richu&apos;s Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>葛城氏没落後の雄略朝以降、木菟の子の平群真鳥（まとり）が「大臣」を歴任して一族の興隆を極めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Emperor Yuryaku&apos;s Court and after the fall of the Katsuragi clan, HEGURI no Matori, a child of Tsuku successively held the position of &quot;minister,&quot; and the family fully enjoyed their prosperity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Emperor Yuryaku&apos;s Court after the fall of the Katsuragi clan, HEGURI no Matori, a child of Tsuku successively held the position of &apos;Oomi&apos; (a highest officer in national politics of the Yamato dynasty) and the clan fully enjoyed their prosperity.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Emperor Yuryaku&apos;s Court after the fall of the Katsuragi clan, HEGURI no Matori, a child of Tsuku successively held the position of &apos;Oomi&apos; (a highest officer in national politics of the Yamato dynasty) and the clan fully enjoyed their prosperity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>しかし、仁賢天皇の崩後、真鳥大臣は日本国王になろうと専横を極めて、国政をほしいままにしたため、天皇家をも凌ぐその勢力を怖れられ、稚鷦鷯太子（後の武烈天皇）の命を受けた大伴金村により、真鳥とその子の平群鮪（しび）は誅殺されたという（498年）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Matori and his child HEGURI no Shibi were said to be killed by Kanamura OTOMO who had an order to kill from Prince Wakasazaki (later Emperor Buretsu) in 498; they were killed because Matori tried to become the king of Japan after the demise of Emperor Ebnin and he was very tyrannical; so Prince Wakasazaki feared that the power Matori held might exceed the power the Imperial family held.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after Emperor Ninken&apos;s death, Matori Oomi, having wanted to be the King of Japan, became tyrannical to govern the nation as he wanted and was feared his power excluding even the Imperial Family, which is considered to be a cause that Kanamura OTOMO by the order of Prince Wakasazaki (later Emperor Buretsu) killed Matori and his son, HEGURI no Shibi in 498.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after Emperor Ninken&apos;s death, Matori Oomi, having wanted to be the King of Japan, became tyrannical to govern the nation as he wanted and was feared his power excluding even the Imperial Family, which is considered to be a cause that Kanamura OTOMO by the order of Prince Wakasazaki (later Emperor Buretsu) killed Matori and his son, HEGURI no Shibi in 498.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>これ以後、平群氏の氏人はしばらく『書紀』から姿を消すが、用明天皇2年（587年）の物部氏討伐将軍として平群神手（かみて）の名が見え、この頃までに大夫選任氏族としての地位を得ていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this, members of the Hegri clan disappear from &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; (The Chronicle of Japan) for a while, but in 587 the name of HEGURI no Kamite appears as the General to subjugate Mononobe clan; by this time the Heguri clan had gained the position to be elected as the grand master.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this, members of the Heguri clan disappear from &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; (The Chronicle of Japan) for a while, but in 587 the name of HEGURI no Kamite appears as the General to subjugate the Mononobe clan; by this time the Heguri clan had gained the position to be elected as daibu (master).</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this, members of the Heguri clan disappear from &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; (The Chronicle of Japan) for a while, but in 587 the name of HEGURI no Kamite appears as the General to subjugate the Mononobe clan; by this time the Heguri clan had gained the position to be elected as daibu (master).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>同13年（684年）10月の八色の姓施行に伴い、改めて朝臣姓を賜る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 684 the Hegri clan was granted kabane (hereditary title) of Ason when the Imperial Court enforced the yakusa no kabane system (eight official titles conferred upon nobles by Emperor Tenmu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November, 684 the Heguri clan was granted kabane (hereditary title) of Ason again when the Imperial Court enforced the yakusa no kabane system (eight official titles conferred upon nobles by Emperor Tenmu).</e>
<cmt>用明天皇13年は存在しないため、西暦「684年」から天武天皇13年として算出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November, 684 the Heguri clan was granted kabane (hereditary title) of Ason again when the Imperial Court enforced the yakusa no kabane system (eight official titles conferred upon nobles by Emperor Tenmu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>奈良時代には平群広成などの官人を輩出したが、その後は没落した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Heguri clan produced government officials such as HEGURI no Hironari in the Nara period, but afterwards the clan went to ruin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Heguri clan produced government officials such as HEGURI no Hironari in the Nara period, but afterwards the clan went to ruin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Heguri clan produced government officials such as HEGURI no Hironari in the Nara period, but afterwards the clan went to ruin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>諸説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various Theories</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various Theories</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various Theories</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>考古学的な見地からは、平群氏の奥津城とされる平群谷古墳群（平群町に所在）の変遷を考えると、同氏の台頭は6世紀中期以前には遡れないという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to archeologists, when they see the changes of the okutsuki (graves of the Heguri clan in ancient times), which is considered to be Heguridani Valley Kofun group (located in present Heguri-cho), the emergence of the Heguri clan cannot be retraced beyond the middle of the sixth century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to archeologists, when they see the changes of Heguridani-kofun Tumulus Cluster (located in present Heguri Town) which is said to be the okutsuki (Shinto tomb) of the Heguri clan, the emergence of the Heguri clan cannot be traced before the middle of the sixth century.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to archeologists, when they see the changes of Heguridani-kofun Tumulus Cluster (located in present Heguri Town) which is said to be the okutsuki (Shinto tomb) of the Heguri clan, the emergence of the Heguri clan cannot be traced before the middle of the sixth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>このことから、平群氏を6世紀後半の神手以降の新興在地豪族と見る説が有力である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on the above fact, a theory that regards the Hegri clan to be a new powerful local clan after HEGURI no Kamite of the later the sixth century is gaining supporters recently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on the above fact, a theory that regards the Heguri clan to be a new powerful local clan after Kamite of the later sixth century is gaining supporters recently.</e>
<cmt>スペル、用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on the above fact, a theory that regards the Heguri clan to be a new powerful local clan after Kamite of the later sixth century is gaining supporters recently.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>従って、真鳥が大臣に就任して専権を振るったという『書紀』の叙述は史実として認められず、平群氏が自氏と同じく武内宿禰の後裔氏族である蘇我氏への対抗意識から故意に作り上げたのだと説明されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, the description in &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; in which Matori took the office as minister and wielded arbitrary power is not accepted as a historical fact; it is explained that the story was intentionally made up by the Heguri clan themselves driven by a feeling of competition to the Soga clan who is considered to be the descendant clan of TAKENOUCHI no Sukune as the Heguri clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, the description in &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; in which Matori took the position of Oomi and wielded arbitrary power is not accepted as a historical fact; it is explained that the story was intentionally made up by the Heguri clan themselves driven by a feeling of competition to the Soga clan who is considered to be the descendant of the same TAKENOUCHI no Sukune as the Heguri clan.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, the description in &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; in which Matori took the position of Oomi and wielded arbitrary power is not accepted as a historical fact; it is explained that the story was intentionally made up by the Heguri clan themselves driven by a feeling of competition to the Soga clan who is considered to be the descendant of the same TAKENOUCHI no Sukune as the Heguri clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>天武天皇10年（681年）の帝紀・旧辞の記定事業に平群子首（こびと）が参画していること、持統天皇5年（691年）に「墓記（纂記）」上進を命じられた諸氏族に平群氏が含まれることは、同氏伝承の成立とも関わって留意されよう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">We should note that in 681 Emperor Tenmu started his project of Teiki (the genealogy of the Imperial Family) and Kyuji (a record of stories current at court) and HEGURI no Kobito participated in this project; also he was included in the various clans asked by the Empress Jito to submit an epitaph in 691; these matters may relate to the formation of the legend of the minister Matori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">We should note, related with the formation of the legend of the clan, that in 681 HEGURI no Kobito participated in the project of Teiki (the genealogy of the Imperial Family) and Kyuji (a record of stories current at court) and also included in the various clans asked to submit an &apos;epitaph&apos; in 691.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">We should note, related with the formation of the legend of the clan, that in 681 HEGURI no Kobito participated in the project of Teiki (the genealogy of the Imperial Family) and Kyuji (a record of stories current at court) and also included in the various clans asked to submit an &apos;epitaph&apos; in 691.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 葉月(id:25674), 越中掾(id:149423), BAKU(id:55205), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>