<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>交替式</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kotaishiki (laws concerning government officers)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kotaishiki (laws concerning government officers)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kotaishiki</e>
<cmt>以下説明が続くので、英語説明は削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>交替式（こうたいしき）は、日本の律令官吏が交替する際の事務引継ぎに関する法規集である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kotaishiki indicates the laws concerning how, when a government officer was replaced with a new officer in the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) in Japan, the matters necessary for continuing the duties of the office should be handed over to the successor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kotaishiki indicates the laws concerns the replacement of a government officer with a new officer under the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) in Japan, matters necessary for continuing the duties of the office and how they should be handed over to the successor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kotaishiki indicates the laws concerns the replacement of a government officer with a new officer under the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) in Japan, matters necessary for continuing the duties of the office and how they should be handed over to the successor.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>勘解由使により編纂・集成され、官吏交替の手続きは交替式に則して行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were collected and compiled by Kageyushi, and the procedure of replacing an officer with another officer was conducted based on Kotaishiki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were collected and compiled by Kageyushi, and the replacement procedure was conducted based on Kotaishiki.</e>
<cmt>wordy, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were collected and compiled by Kageyushi, and the replacement procedure was conducted based on Kotaishiki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>律令制が本格的に施行された8世紀のうちから、官吏、特に国司交替の手続きに関する法令（詔勅・太政官符）を集成した私撰の「交替式」と呼ばれる書物が存在していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In as early as the eight century when the Ritsuryo system was enforced on a large scale, a privately compiled book called &quot;Kotaishiki&quot; existed, in which the laws and regulations concerning the procedures for replacing government officers, in particular, kokushi (provincial governors) (Shochoku (imperial edicts) and Daijokanpu (official documents issued by Daijokan, Grand Council of State)) were collected.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As early as the eight century when the Ritsuryo system was enforced on a large scale, a privately compiled book called &quot;Kotaishiki&quot; existed, in which the laws and regulations concerning the procedures for replacing government officers, in particular, kokushi (provincial governors) (Shochoku - imperial edicts) and Daijokanpu (official documents issued by Daijokan, Grand Council of State) were collected.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As early as the eight century when the Ritsuryo system was enforced on a large scale, a privately compiled book called &apos;Kotaishiki&apos; existed, in which the laws and regulations concerning the procedures for replacing government officers, in particular, kokushi (provincial governors) (Shochoku - imperial edicts) and Daijokanpu (official documents issued by Daijokan, Grand Council of State) were collected.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>しかし、私撰「交替式」には内容の不備も多数あった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the privately compiled &quot;Kotaishiki&quot; included many unsatisfactory items.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, privately compiled &quot;Kotaishiki&quot; included many unsatisfactory items.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, privately compiled &apos;Kotaishiki&apos; included many unsatisfactory items.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>797年（延暦16年）頃に国司交替の際に行政実績を監査する勘解由使が設置された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In around 797, kageyushi was introduced to audit results of the administration when a kokushi (provincial governor) was to be replaced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around 797, kageyushi was introduced to audit results of the administration when a kokushi (provincial governor) was to be replaced.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around 797, kageyushi was introduced to audit results of the administration when a kokushi (provincial governor) was to be replaced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>当時、国司交替に当たって手続きの不備や前任・後任の間の紛争が多発しており、国司交替の手続きを明確化する必要が生じていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, many troubles concerned with replacement of kokushi, such as &quot;the procedures used were inadequate&quot; and disputes between a predecessor and the successor, were caused, making it necessary that the procedure to replace a kokushi should be clarified.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, many problems concerned with the replacement of kokushi, such as &quot;the procedures that were used were inadequate&quot; and disputes between a predecessor and the successor, were caused, making it necessary to clarify the procedures for replacing a kokushi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, many problems concerned with the replacement of kokushi, such as &quot;the procedures that were used were inadequate&quot; and disputes between a predecessor and the successor, were caused, making it necessary to clarify the procedures for replacing a kokushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そして803年（延暦22年）、勘解由使の菅野真道により『撰定交替式』（延暦交替式）が編纂され、桓武天皇の裁可を得て、正式な国司交替の例規として扱われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then SUGANO no Mamichi, a kageyushi, compiled &quot;Sentei kotaishiki&quot; (literally, selected kotaishiki) (Enryaku kotaishiki) (literally, kotaishiki in the Enryaku era), which was approved by Emperor Kanmu and was handled as precedent rules in official replacement of kokushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then SUGANO no Mamichi, a kageyushi, compiled &quot;Sentei kotaishiki&quot; (literally, selected kotaishiki) (Enryaku kotaishiki) (literally, kotaishiki in the Enryaku era), approved by Emperor Kanmu and was handled as the rules covering official replacement of kokushi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then in 803 SUGANO no Mamichi, a kageyushi, compiled &quot;Sentei kotaishiki&quot; (literally, selected kotaishiki) (Enryaku kotaishiki) (literally, kotaishiki in the Enryaku era), approved by Emperor Kanmu and was handled as the rules covering official replacement of kokushi.</e>
<cmt>年号補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>824年（天長元年）以降、国司（外官）だけでなく内官（在京の官吏）も勘解由使の監査対象となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 824 and later, naikan (officers living in Kyoto) in addition to kokushi (officers living outside Kyoto) became also audited by kagyukishi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 824 and later, naikan (officers living in Kyoto) in addition to kokushi (officers living outside Kyoto) were also audited by kagyukishi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 824 and later, naikan (officers living in Kyoto) in addition to kokushi (officers living outside Kyoto) were also audited by kageyushi.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>867年（貞観_(日本)9年）頃、内外官の交替手続きに関する法令を集成した『新定内外官交替式』（貞観交替式）が勘解由使においてまとめられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In around 869, &quot;Shinjo naigekan kotaishiki&quot; (literally, new kotaishiki for officers living in Kyoto as well as those outside Kyoto) (Jogan kotaishiki) (literally, kotaishiki in the Jokan era), in which laws and regulations concerning replacement of officers living in Kyoto as well as those outside Kyoto were collected, was compiled by kageyushi.</e>
<cmt>新定内外官交替式：　読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around 869, &quot;Shinjo naigekan kotaishiki&quot; (literally, new kotaishiki for officers living in Kyoto as well as those outside Kyoto) (Jogan kotaishiki) (literally, kotaishiki in the Jokan era), in which laws and regulations concerning replacement of officers living in Kyoto as well as those outside Kyoto were collected, were compiled by kageyushi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around 869, &quot;Shinjo naigekan kotaishiki&quot; (literally, new kotaishiki for officers living in Kyoto as well as those outside Kyoto) (Jogan kotaishiki) (literally, kotaishiki in the Jokan era), in which laws and regulations concerning replacement of officers living in Kyoto as well as those outside Kyoto were collected, were compiled by kageyushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>以後、内外官の事務引継ぎは同交替式に依ることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this, when a government officer was replaced, the procedure of handing over matters necessary for continuing the office duties were carried out based on this kotaishiki, regardless of whether he lived in or outside Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this, when a government officer was replaced, the procedure of handing over matters necessary for continuing office duties were carried out based on this kotaishiki, regardless of whether he lived in or outside Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this, when a government officer was replaced, the procedure of handing over matters necessary for continuing office duties were carried out based on this kotaishiki, regardless of whether he lived in or outside Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>10世紀前期、律令官制の再構築を図る醍醐天皇が、延喜格式の編纂事業を開始すると、その一環として交替式の再編纂も行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the first half of the tenth century when Emperor Daigo, who tried to reconstruct the organization of government according to the ritsuryo codes, started the work to compile Engi no kyakushiki (regulations and laws of the Engi era), kotaishiki was recompiled in the work as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the first half of the tenth century when Emperor Daigo tried to reconstruct the organization of government according to the ritsuryo codes and started the work to compile Engi no kyakushiki (regulations and laws of the Engi era), kotaishiki was recompiled in the work as well.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the first half of the tenth century when Emperor Daigo tried to reconstruct the organization of government according to the ritsuryo codes and started the work to compile Engi no kyakushiki (regulations and laws of the Engi era), kotaishiki was recompiled in the work as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>編纂作業は911年（延喜11年）に始まり、921年（延喜21年）に『内外官交替式』（延喜交替式）として完成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The compilation work started in 911 and was completed in 921 as &quot;Naigekan kotaishiki&quot; (Engi kotaishiki) (literally, kotaishiki in the Jokan era).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Compilation started in 911 and was completed in 921 as &quot;Naigekan kotaishiki&quot; (Engi kotaishiki) (literally, kotaishiki in the Jokan era).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Compilation started in 911 and was completed in 921 as &quot;Naigekan kotaishiki&quot; (Engi kotaishiki) (literally, kotaishiki in the Jokan era).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>これが最後の交替式となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This became the last kotaishiki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This became the last kotaishiki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This became the last kotaishiki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>なお、施行当時より慣例的に「交替式」と呼ばれてきているが、律令法における格式のおける考え方からすれば、これは「格」にあたるのではないかとする意見もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way, although it was called &quot;kotaishiki&quot; (indicating a kind of &quot;shiki&quot;) from the time it was enforced for the first time, there is also the following opinion: According to the concept of &quot;kyakushiki&quot; (kyaku indicates supplementary laws or regulations, and shiki indicates detailed rules for enforcing them) in the Ritsuryo laws, use of &quot;kyaku&quot; is more appropriate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the way, although it was called &quot;kotaishiki&quot; (indicating a kind of &quot;shiki&quot;) from the time it was enforced for the first time, there is also the following opinion: According to the concept of &quot;kyakushiki&quot; (kyaku indicates supplementary laws or regulations, and shiki indicates detailed rules for enforcing them) in the Ritsuryo laws, use of &quot;kyaku&quot; is more appropriate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the way, although it was called &apos;kotaishiki&apos; (indicating a kind of &apos;shiki&apos;) from the time it was enforced for the first time, there is also the following opinion: According to the concept of &apos;kyakushiki&apos; (kyaku indicates supplementary laws or regulations, and shiki indicates detailed rules for enforcing them) in the Ritsuryo laws, use of &apos;kyaku&apos; is more appropriate.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>各交替式の概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary of each kotaishiki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary of each kotaishiki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary of each kotaishiki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>撰定交替式（延暦交替式）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sentei kotaishiki (Enryaku kotaishiki)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sentei kotaishiki (Enryaku kotaishiki)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sentei kotaishiki (Enryaku kotaishiki)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>成立：803年（延暦22年）、編者：菅野真道ら、1巻41条。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Established in 803; Compiled by SUGANO no Mamichi and others; one volume including 41 articles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Established in 803; Compiled by SUGANO no Mamichi and others; one volume including 41 articles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Established in 803; Compiled by SUGANO no Mamichi and others; one volume including 41 articles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>新定内外官交替式（貞観交替式）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinjo naigekan kotaishiki (Jogan kotaishiki)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinjo naigekan kotaishiki (Jogan kotaishiki)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinjo naigekan kotaishiki (Jogan kotaishiki)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>施行：868年（貞観10年）、編者：南淵年名らか、上下2巻。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enforced in 868; Compiled by MINABUCHI no Toshina and others?; Two volumes, the upper volume and the lower volume.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enforced in 868; Compiled by MINABUCHI no Toshina and others?; Two volumes, the upper volume and the lower volume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enforced in 868; Compiled by MINABUCHI no Toshina and others?; Two volumes, the upper volume and the lower volume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>内外官交替式（延喜交替式）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naigekan kotaishiki (Engi kotaishiki)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naigekan kotaishiki (Engi kotaishiki)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naigekan kotaishiki (Engi kotaishiki)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>成立：921年（延喜21年）、編者：橘清澄ら、1巻192条。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Established in 921; Complied by TACHIBANA no Kiyozumi and others; One volume including 192 articles.</e>
<cmt>橘清澄：　読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Established in 921; Complied by TACHIBANA no Kiyozumi and others; One volume including 192 articles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Established in 921; Complied by TACHIBANA no Kiyozumi and others; One volume including 192 articles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Shimoxx(id:9332), Andee(id:20421), 水野白楓(id:22811), Toto-tarou(id:16648), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>