<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>永正の錯乱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eisho no Sakuran (Eisho Disturbance)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eisho no Sakuran (Eisho Disturbance)</e>
<cmt>fixed spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eisho Disturbance</e>
<cmt>英語のタイトルにしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>永正の錯乱（えいしょうのさくらん）は、戦国時代 (日本)の初期にあたる永正4年（1507年）、室町幕府管領・細川政元が殺害された事件を指し示す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eisho no Sakuran refers to an incident that Masamoto HOSOKAWA, Kanrei (A shogunal deputy) for the Muromachi shogunate, was assassinated in 1507 in the early Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eisho no Sakuran refers to an incident during the early Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) where the Kanrei (shogunal deputy) for the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) named Masamoto HOSOKAWA was assassinated in 1507.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;Muromachi shogunate&quot; to &quot;Muromachi bakufu&quot; and added description to follow the word list; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eisho Disturbance refers to an incident during the early Sengoku period (period of warring states) (Japan) where the kanrei (shogunal deputy) for the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) named Masamoto HOSOKAWA was assassinated in 1507.</e>
<cmt>Eisho Disturbance としました。period　小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>いわゆる細川氏（京兆家）の内訌である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the so-called internal strife of the Hosokawa clan (the Keicho family).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This event was the so-called internal strife of the Hosokawa clan (the Keicho family).</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This event was the so-called internal strife of the Hosokawa clan (the Keicho family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経緯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Details</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Details</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Details</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>細川政元の3人の養子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Three adopted sons of Masamoto HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The three adopted sons of Masamoto HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt>added &quot;The&quot; at the beginning of the section title</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The three adopted sons of Masamoto HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>明応2年（1493年）、管領・細川政元は、10代征夷大将軍・足利義稙を廃立し専制権力を樹立した（明応の政変）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1493, Kanrei Masamoto HOSOKAWA established a dictatorship after eliminating Yoshitane ASHIKAGA, the tenth Seii Taishogun (Barbarian Subduing Generalissimo) (Meio Coup).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1493, the Kanrei Masamoto HOSOKAWA established a dictatorship after overthrowing Yoshitane ASHIKAGA, the Tenth Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) (this incident known as the &quot;Meio Coup&quot;).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;Seii Taishogun&quot; description to match the word list; &quot;eliminating&quot; could easily mean &quot;kill&quot; which is not what happened, as I understand it, so I changed this to &quot;overthrowing&quot;; added description for &quot;Meio Coup&quot; since it was not clear to me why it was here until further reading</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1493, the kanrei Masamoto HOSOKAWA established a dictatorship after overthrowing Yoshitane ASHIKAGA, the tenth seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) (this incident known as the Meio Coup).</e>
<cmt>kanrei, seii taishogun 小文字としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>さて政元には実子は無く、関白・九条政基の末子である細川澄之、細川氏阿波細川氏からの細川澄元、さらに細川氏野州家からは細川高国の3人を迎え養子にしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamoto didn&apos;t have a biological child, and he had adopted three - Sumiyuki HOSOKAWA, the youngest child of Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) Masamoto KUJO, Sumimoto HOSOKAWA from the Awa Hosokawa clan, and Takakuni HOSOKAWA from the Yasu family of the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>「細川氏阿波細川氏」は「阿波細川氏」として訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Masamoto did not have a biological child, he adopted three sons: Sumiyuki HOSOKAWA, the youngest child of the Kanpaku (chief advisor to the Emperor) Masamoto KUJO, Sumimoto HOSOKAWA from the Awa Hosokawa clan and Takakuni HOSOKAWA from the Yasu family of the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Masamoto did not have a biological child, he adopted three sons: Sumiyuki HOSOKAWA, the youngest child of the kanpaku (chief advisor to the Emperor) Masamoto KUJO, Sumimoto HOSOKAWA from the Awa Hosokawa clan and Takakuni HOSOKAWA from the Yasu family of the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>kanpaku　小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>永正3年（1506年）、摂津国守護となった澄元が阿波国勢を率いて入京し、その家宰三好之長が政元に軍事面で重用されるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1506, Sumimoto who became Settsu no kuni Shugo (provincial constable of Settsu Province) entered the capital leading the force of Awa Province, and his Kasai (main retainer) Yukinaga MIYOSHI was given important military posts by Masamoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1506, Sumimoto, who had become the Settsu no kuni Shugo (provincial constable of Settsu Province), entered the capital leading forces from the Awa Province. Upon their arrival, Masamoto gave important military posts to Sumimoto&apos;s Kasai (main retainer) Yukinaga MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>split into two sentences for easier reading; changed the second sentence to active rather than passive; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1506, Sumimoto, who had become the shugo (provincial constable) of Settsu Province, entered the capital leading forces from the Awa Province; upon their arrival, Masamoto gave important military posts to Sumimoto&apos;s kasai (main retainer) Yukinaga MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>摂津国守護　表現を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>すると、これまで政元政権を支えてきた「内衆」とよばれる京兆家重臣（主に畿内有力国人層）と、阿波勢との対立が深まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then senior vassals of the Keicho family (mainly powerful local lords in and around the capital) called &apos;Uchishu&apos; who supported Masamoto&apos;s government, and the force of Awa deepened the confrontation.</e>
<cmt>同上</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This intensified the confrontation between the forces from Awa and the senior vassals of the Keicho family (mainly powerful local lords in and around the capital) called &quot;Uchishu&quot; who had thus far supported Masamoto.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;deepened&quot; to &quot;intensified&quot; for &quot;深まった&quot;; rearranged sentence to read more understandably</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This intensified the confrontation between the forces from Awa and the senior vassals of the Keicho family (mainly powerful local lords in and around the capital) called &apos;uchishu&apos; who had thus far supported Masamoto.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>政元殺害</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Assassination of Masamoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Assassination of Masamoto</e>
<cmt>added &quot;The&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The assassination of Masamoto</e>
<cmt>小タイトルのため、小文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>永正4年（1507年）6月23日、修験道にとりつかれ、度々奇行のあった細川政元は、魔法を修する準備として邸内の湯屋に入ったところ、澄之を擁する内衆の薬師寺長忠・香西元長らに殺害された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 11, 1507, when Masamoto HOSOKAWA, who was possessed with Shugendo (Japanese mountain asceticism-shamanism incorporating Shinto and Buddhist concepts) and often had eccentric behavior, went into the bathhouse in his premises for preparation of acquiring magic, he was assassinated by Nagatada YAKUSHIJI and Motonaga KOZAI, Uchishu with Sumiyuki at their head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 11, 1507, when Masamoto, who often behaved peculiarly and was obsessed with Shugendo (Japanese mountain asceticism-shamanism that incorporated Shinto and Buddhist concepts) went into the bathhouse on his premises in preparation for acquring magic, he was assassinated by the Uchishu members Nagatada YAKUSHIJI and Motonaga KOZAI, lead by Sumiyuki.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;eccentric behavior&quot; to &quot;behaved peculiarly&quot;; fixed to read more understandably</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 11, 1507, when Masamoto, who often behaved peculiarly and was obsessed with Shugendo (Japanese mountain asceticism-shamanism that incorporated Shinto and Buddhist concepts) went into the bathhouse on his premises in preparation for acquiring magic, he was assassinated by the uchishu members Nagatada YAKUSHIJI and Motonaga KOZAI, who supported Sumiyuki.</e>
<cmt>澄之を擁する→supported Sumiyuki としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>さらに翌日、長忠らは澄元・三好之長の屋敷に攻め寄せると、澄元らを近江国に敗走させ、澄之を迎えて家督を継がせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, on the following day, Nagatada made an attack on the residence of Sumimoto and Yukinaga MIYOSHI, then put them to flight to Omi Province, and had Sumiyuki take over as head of the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the following day, Nagatada attacked the residences of Sumimoto and Yukinaga MIYOSHI, making them flee to the Omi Province and had Sumiyuki take over as the head of the family.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;put them to flight&quot; to &quot;making them flee&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the following day, Nagatada attacked the residences of Sumimoto and Yukinaga MIYOSHI, making them flee to the Omi Province and had Sumiyuki take over as the head of the family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>しかしもう一人の養子・高国は、一族の摂津国分郡守護細川政賢や淡路国守護細川尚春、河内国守護畠山義堯と語らい、細川氏（京兆家）の後継者を澄元とすることで合意をみた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However the other adopted son Takakuni talked with Masakata HOSOKAWA, Settsu no kuni Bungunshugo (provincial constable of counties in Settsu Province) and Hisaharu HOSOKAWA, Awaji no kuni Shugo (provincial constable of Awaji Province) in the family, and Yoshitaka HATAKEYAMA, Kawachi no kuni Shugo (provincial constable of Kawachi Province), and they agreed to have Sumimoto as the successor of the Hosokawa clan (the Keicho family).</e>
<cmt>「細川政賢」は登録に３つあり、名前の読みがそれぞれ違うのですが、「Masakata」が正解と思われます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The other adopted son Takakuni, however, conspired with his two relatives, the Settsu no kuni Bungunshugo (provincial constable of the Settsu Province) Masakata HOSOKAWA and the Awaji no kuni Shugo (provincial constable of Awaji Province) Hisaharu HOSOKAWA, as well as the Kawachi no kuni Shugo (provincial constable of Kawachi Province) Yoshitaka HATAKEYAMA. Amongst the four of them, they agreed to make Sumimoto the successor of the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>split into two sentences for easier reading; eliminated (the Keicho family) as this is already written above; fixed grammar to read more understandably</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The other adopted son Takakuni, however, conspired with his two relatives, Masakata HOSOKAWA, the bungunshugo (a provincial constable of a specially given province in gun unit) of Settsu Province, Hisaharu HOSOKAWA, the shugo of Awaji Province and Yoshitaka HATAKEYAMA, the shugo of Kawachi Province; amongst the four of them, they agreed to make Sumimoto the successor of the Hosokawa clan (the Keicho family).</e>
<cmt>役職名などの表現を他の記事と統一しました。既出単語の補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>まず7月28日、薬師寺元一（弟・薬師寺長忠に滅ぼされている）の子・薬師寺万徳丸は、長忠の居城茨木城を攻め落した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First, on September 15, Mantokumaru YAKUSHIJI, a son of Motokazu YAKUSHIJI (he had been destroyed by his brother Nagatada YAKUSHIJI) captured Ibaraki-jo Castle, the residential castle of Nagatada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 15, Mantokumaru YAKUSHIJI, the son of Motokazu YAKUSHIJI (who had been overthrown by his brother Nagatada YAKUSHIJI), captured Ibaraki-jo, the residence of Nagatada.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;destroyed&quot; to &quot;overthrown&quot; for 滅ぼされている; eliminated &quot;castle&quot; after &quot;residential&quot;; changed &quot;residential&quot; to &quot;residence&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 15, Mantokumaru YAKUSHIJI, the son of Motokazu YAKUSHIJI (who had been overthrown by his brother Nagatada YAKUSHIJI), captured Ibaraki-jo Castle, the residence of Nagatada.</e>
<cmt>Castle を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>そして翌29日、細川高国らは香西元長の居城嵐山城を攻め落とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then September 16, the following day, Takakuni HOSOKAWA captured Arashiyama-jo Castle, the residential castle of Motonaga KOZAI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following day, Takakuni HOSOKAWA captured Arashiyama-jo Caste, the residence of Motonaga KOZAI.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;residential castle&quot; to &quot;residence&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following day, Takakuni HOSOKAWA captured Arashiyama-jo Castle, the residence of Motonaga KOZAI.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>8月1日、逃亡先の近江甲賀郡の国人らを味方に引き入れ急ぎ京に戻った三好之長が、細川澄之の最後の砦となっていた遊初軒を高国勢とともに一気に攻め落したため澄之は自害した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 17, Yukinaga MIYOSHI, who won over local lords of Koga-gun Omi Province where he had escaped and hurriedly returned to the capital, captured Yushoken, which was the last bastion of Sumiyuki HOSOKAWA, at once with the force of Takakuni, which made Sumiyuki commit suicide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 17, Yukinaga MIYOSHI, who had escaped to Koga-gun Omi Province where he won the support of the local lords, rushed back to the capital. Together with the Takakuni forces, Yukinaga captured Yushoken in one stroke, causing Sumiyuki HOSOKAWA to commit suicide since it was the last of his strongholds.</e>
<cmt>split into three sentences for easier reading; fixed grammar to read more smoothly; chnaged &quot;bastion&quot; to &quot;stronghold&quot; for &quot;砦&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 17, Yukinaga MIYOSHI, who had escaped to Koga-gun, Omi Province where he won the support of the local lords, rushed back to the capital; together with the Takakuni forces, Yukinaga captured Yushoken in one stroke, causing Sumiyuki HOSOKAWA to commit suicide since it was the last of his strongholds.</e>
<cmt>一文につなげました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>翌2日、澄元は将軍に拝謁し、京兆家の家督と管領職を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 18, the following day, Sumimoto had an audience with Shogun, and he took over as the head of the family and the Kanrei post.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 18, Sumimoto had an audience with the Shogun and succeeded the head of the of the family as well as the post of Kanrei.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 18, Sumimoto had an audience with the shogun and succeeded the head of the family as well as the post of kanrei.</e>
<cmt>ダブっていた単語を削除しました。kanrei, shogun 小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>澄元と高国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumimoto and Takakuni</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sumimoto and Takakuni</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sumimoto and Takakuni</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>ところで明応の政変で追われた前将軍足利義稙（義材、のち義稙）は、明応8年（1499年）以来周防国の大内義興を頼っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former shogun Yoshitada ASHIKAGA (Yoshiki, later known as Yoshitane), who was displaced by Meio Coup, relied on Yoshioki OUCHI in Suo Province from 1499.</e>
<cmt>「足利義稙」はリンク先の語で、サイト上では「足利義尹」なので、そのとおり訳出しました。一原文一訳文の原則の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, the former Shogun Yoshitada ASHIKAGA (Yoshiki, later known as Yoshitane), who was displaced by the Meio Coup, had been relying on Yoshioki OUCHI in Suo Province since 1499.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;relied&quot; to &quot;had been relying&quot;; added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Meio&quot;; changed &quot;from&quot; to &quot;since&quot; before &quot;1499&quot;; added &quot;In a related matter&quot; for &quot;ところで&quot; to help connect this sentence with other events described in this article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, the former shogun Yoshitada ASHIKAGA (Yoshiki, later known as Yoshitane), who was displaced by the Meio Coup, had been relying on Yoshioki OUCHI in Suo Province since 1499.</e>
<cmt>shogun 小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>だが、幕府はその動向を恐れて6月 (旧暦)、義興追討の綸旨を得て安芸国・石見国の国人らに義興追討を命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the feudal government was afraid of their movement, and in July, ordered local lords of the Aki and Iwami Province to hunt down and kill Yoshioki after acquiring rinji (the Emperor&apos;s command) to do so.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shogunate was afraid of their movements, however, and after acquiring a Rinji (Emperor&apos;s command) in July, ordered the local lords of the Aki and Iwami Provinces to hunt down and kill Yoshioki.</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;However&quot; since it did not feel entirely necessary and because the following sentence also contains a &quot;however&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bakufu was afraid of their movements, however, and after acquiring a rinji (Emperor&apos;s command) in July, ordered the local lords of the Aki and Iwami Provinces to hunt down and kill Yoshioki.</e>
<cmt>shogunate→ bakufu　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし永正4年（1507年）末、大内義興は義尹を擁し、軍勢を率いて山口市を発すると、備後国鞆の浦で年を越しつつ入京の時期をうかがった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the end of 1507, Yoshioki OUCHI had Yoshitada with his head and left Yamaguchi city leading the troops, and then looked for the timing to enter the capital, while seeing the old year out at Tomonoura in Bingo Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of 1507, as Yoshioki OUCHI left Yamaguchi City leading his troops with Yoshitada at his side, he saw the year out at Tomonoura in Bingo Province while waiting for a chance to enter the capital,</e>
<cmt>rearranged sentence and fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of 1507, as Yoshioki OUCHI left Yamaguchi City leading his troops with Yoshitada at his side, he saw the year out at Tomonoura in Bingo Province while waiting for a chance to enter the capital,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>この頃、三好之長の専横に反発する畿内の勢力は細川高国の元に結集していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the meantime, the force in and around the capital, that was against the tyranny of Yukinaga MIYOSHI, rallied behind Takakuni HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this time, the forces in kinai (the five provinces in the immediate vicinity of Kyoto) opposing the tyranny of Yukinaga MIYOSHI rallied behind Takakuni HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;in and around the capital&quot; to &quot;kinai&quot; and added description; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this time, the forces in kinai (the five provinces in the immediate vicinity of Kyoto) opposing the tyranny of Yukinaga MIYOSHI rallied behind Takakuni HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>澄元は義興と和議を結ぶために高国を差し向けようとした。だが、逆に高国は伊賀国に出奔した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumimoto tried to send Takakuni to make a compromise with Yoshioki.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sumimoto tried sending Takakuni to make peace negotiations with Yoshioki but Takakuni fled to Iga Province instead.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;compromise&quot; to &quot;peace negotiations&quot; for &quot;和議&quot;; moved &quot;but Takakuni fled to Iga Province instead.&quot; from the following sentence; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sumimoto tried sending Takakuni to make peace negotiations with Yoshioki but Takakuni fled to Iga Province instead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>義尹・義興と結び、摂津の伊丹元扶や丹波国の内藤貞正らの畿内国人を味方につけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, on the contrary, Takakuni fled to Iga Province, and tied up with Yoshiki and Yoshioki and won over local lords in and around the capital including Motosuke ITAMI from Settsu and Sadamasa NAITO from Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt>同上</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakuni made alliances with Yoshiki and Yoshioki and gained the support of the local lords in kinai, including Motosuke ITAMI from Settsu Province and Sadamasa NAITO from Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;tied up&quot; to &quot;made alliances&quot; for &quot;結び&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakuni made alliances with Yoshiki and Yoshioki and gained the support of the local lords in kinai, including Motosuke ITAMI from Settsu Province and Sadamasa NAITO from Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>永正5年（1508年）4月、澄元や11代将軍足利義澄は相次いで近江に逃れ、高国が入京した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May, 1508, Sumimoto and the eleventh shogun Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA fled to Omi in succession, and Takakuni entered the capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May of 1508, Sumimoto and the Eleventh Shogun Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA fled to Omi one after the other and Takakuni entered the capital.</e>
<cmt>fixed date to read more naturally; capitalized &quot;Eleventh Shogun&quot;; &quot;in succession&quot; sounds unnatural to me here, so I changed it to &quot;one after the other&quot; for &quot;相次いで&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May of 1508, Sumimoto and the eleventh shogun Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA fled to Omi one after the other and Takakuni entered the capital.</e>
<cmt>shogun 小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>4月末、義尹・義興は和泉国堺に到着、出迎えた高国が京兆家の家督を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In early June, Yoshiki and Yoshioki arrived at Sakai in Izumi Province, and Takakuni, who received them, took over as the head of the Keicho family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In early June, Yoshiki and Yoshioki were met by Takakuni when they arrived at Sakai in Izumi Province and Takakuni took over as the head of the Keicho family.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;and Takakuni, who received them&quot; to &quot;were met by Takakuni&quot; and fixed grammar accordingly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In early June, Yoshitada and Yoshioki were met by Takakuni when they arrived at Sakai in Izumi Province and Takakuni took over as the head of the Keicho family.</e>
<cmt>yoshiki →yoshitadaとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>6月、前将軍義尹は堺から京に入り、再び将軍となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July, the former shogun Yoshiki entered the capital from Sakai, and became Shogun again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July, the former Shogun Yoshiki entered the capital from Sakai and became Shogun again.</e>
<cmt>eliminated comma after &quot;Sakai&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July, the former shogun Yoshitada entered the capital from Sakai and became shogun again.</e>
<cmt>shogun 小文字にしました。yoshiki →yoshitadaとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>高国は右京大夫・管領となり、大内義興は左京大夫・山城国守護となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakuni became Ukyo no daibu (Master of the Western Capital Offices)/Kanrei, and Yoshioki OUCHI became Sakyo no daibu (Master of the Eastern Capital Offices)/Yamashiro no kuni Shugo (provincial constable of Yamashiro Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakuni became Kanrei and Ukyo no daibu (Master of the Western Capital Offices), and Yoshioki OUCHI became Sakyo no daibu (Master of the Eastern Capital Offices) and Yamashiro no kuni Shugo (provincial constable of Yamashiro Province).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;/&quot; to &quot;and&quot; in both caes; moved location of &quot;Kanrei&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakuni became kanrei and Ukyo no daibu (Master of the Western Capital Offices), and Yoshioki OUCHI became Sakyo no daibu (Master of the Eastern Capital Offices) and shugo of Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>守護　既出のため、補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="24">
<j>この1年の間に、細川氏（京兆家）の家督は政元から澄之、澄元、高国とめまぐるしく入れ替わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the year, the head of the Hosokawa clan (the Keicho family) dizzyingly changed from Masamoto to Sumiyuki, to Sumimoto, and to Takakuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Within one year, the head of the Hosokawa clan (the Keicho family) changed chaotically from Masamoto to Sumiyuki, then to Sumimoto, and then again to Takakuni.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;dizzyingly&quot; to &quot;chaotically&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Within one year, the head of the Hosokawa clan (the Keicho family) changed chaotically from Masamoto to Sumiyuki, then to Sumimoto, and then again to Takakuni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>両細川の乱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two Hosokawas War</e>
<cmt>用語登録にはthe Rebellion of Ryohosokawaで定訳不明となっていましたが、左記の通り訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Two Hosokawas&apos; War</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Two Hosokawas&apos; War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>この擾乱を契機として、京を押さえた細川高国らと、細川澄元・細川晴元・三好氏ら阿波勢との攻防が長期にわたって繰り返された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Triggered by this disturbance, struggles between Takakuni HOSOKAWA capturing the capital, and the force of Awa including Sumimoto HOSOKAWA, Harumoto HOSOKAWA and the Miyoshi clan repeated for a long time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Triggered by these disturbances, battles repeatedly occurred over a prolonged period between the Takakuni HOSOKAWA forces that had gained control of the capital and the Awa forces that included Sumimoto HOSOKAWA, Harumoto HOSOKAWA and the Miyoshi clan.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;this disturbance&quot; to &quot;these disturbances&quot;; changed &quot;struggles&quot; to &quot;battles&quot; for &quot;攻防&quot;; rearranged sentence, fixed grammar and word choices</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Triggered by these disturbances, battles repeatedly occurred over a prolonged period between the Takakuni HOSOKAWA forces that had gained control of the capital and the Awa forces that included Sumimoto HOSOKAWA, Harumoto HOSOKAWA and the Miyoshi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="26">
<j>永正6年（1509年）、細川澄元・三好之長が京侵攻を企てるが、細川高国・大内義興は協同して撃退（如意ケ嶽の戦い）している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1509, Sumimoto HOSOKAWA and Yukinaga MIYOSHI planned to invade the capital, but Takakuni HOSOKAWA and Yoshioki OUCHI cooperated and fought them off (Battle of Nyoigatake).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1509, Sumimoto HOSOKAWA and Yukinaga MIYOSHI attempted to invade the capital, but Takakuni HOSOKAWA and Yoshioki OUCHI fought them off in a cooperative effort (The Battle of Nyoigatake).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;planned&quot; to &quot;attempted&quot; for &quot;企てる&quot;; changed &quot;cooperated and fought them off&quot; to &quot;fought them off in a cooperative effort&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1509, Sumimoto HOSOKAWA and Yukinaga MIYOSHI attempted to invade the capital, but Takakuni HOSOKAWA and Yoshioki OUCHI fought them off in a cooperative effort (The Battle of Nyoigatake).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="27">
<j>同年10月、高国らが近江に侵攻し、澄元・之長は阿波に逃亡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November in the same year, Takakuni invaded Omi, and Sumimoto and Yukinaga fled to Awa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November of the same year, Takakuni&apos;s forces invaded Omi, and Sumimoto and Yukinaga fled to Awa.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;in&quot; to &quot;of&quot;; changed &quot;Takakuni&quot; to &quot;Takakuni&apos;s forces&quot; for &quot;高国ら&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November of the same year, Takakuni&apos;s forces invaded Omi, and Sumimoto and Yukinaga fled to Awa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>之長の子・三好長秀は伊勢に敗走したが、北畠材親に攻められ自害する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagahide MIYOSHI, a son of Yukinaga, fled to Ise, but the attack by Kichika KITABATAKE made him commit suicide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A son of Yukinaga named Nagahide MIYOSHI fled to Ise but committed suicide after being attacked by Kichika KITABATAKE.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A son of Yukinaga named Nagahide MIYOSHI fled to Ise but committed suicide after being attacked by Kichika KITABATAKE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="29">
<j>永正7年（1510年）、高国らが近江に侵攻したが、澄元方を支持する国人の反抗もあって大敗した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1510, Takakuni invaded Omi, but they suffered a crushing defeat due to the resistance by local lords supporting the Sumimoto side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1510, Takakuni&apos;s forces invaded Omi but suffered a crushing defeat due to the resistance they met by local lords who supported the Sumimoto side.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;Takakuni&quot; to &quot;Takakuni&apos;s forces&quot; for &quot;高国ら&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1510, Takakuni&apos;s forces invaded Omi but suffered a crushing defeat due to the resistance they met by local lords who supported the Sumimoto side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="30">
<j>永正8年（1511年）、澄元は細川政賢・細川尚春らと（芦屋河原の合戦）、また河内守護畠山尚順らと（和泉・深井城深井の合戦）合戦に及ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1511, Sumimoto had a battle with Masakata HOSOKAWA and Hisaharu HOSOKAWA (the Battle of Ashiyakawara) and with and Yoshitaka HATAKEYAMA, Shugo of Kawachi (the Battle of Izumi and Fukai).</e>
<cmt>「深井城深井の合戦」は「深井の合戦」で訳しました。一原文一訳文の原則の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1511, Sumimoto engaged in battle with the forces of Masakata HOSOKAWA and Hisaharu HOSOKAWA (The Battle of Ashiyakawara), and then again with the forces of Yoshitaka HATAKEYAMA, the Shugo of Kawachi (The Battle of Izumi and Fukai).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;had a battle&quot; to &quot;engaged in battle with the forces of&quot;; changed &quot;and with&quot; to &quot;and then again with the forces of&quot;; capitalized words in the battle titles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1511, Sumimoto engaged in battle with the forces of Masakata HOSOKAWA and Hisaharu HOSOKAWA (The Battle of Ashiyakawara), and then again with the forces of Yoshitaka HATAKEYAMA, the shugo of Kawachi Province (The Battle of Izumi and Fukai).</e>
<cmt>shugo 小文字としています。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>そして播磨国・備前国守護赤松義村などと連携して京に侵攻する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And he invaded the capital, collaborating with Yoshimura AKAMATSU, Shugo of Harima and Bizen Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sumimoto then invaded the capital in a collaborative effort with Yoshimura AKAMATSU, the Shugo of Harima and Bizen Province.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;And he&quot; to &quot;Sumimoto then&quot;; changed &quot;collaborating with&quot; to &quot;in a collaborative effort with&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sumimoto then invaded the capital in a collaborative effort with Yoshimura AKAMATSU, the shugo of Harima and Bizen Provinces.</e>
<cmt>shugo 小文字としています。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>高国・義興は一時は劣勢に追い込まれ、将軍足利義稙を擁して丹波国に撤退余儀なくされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakuni and Yoshioki lost ground for a while, and they were forced to withdraw to Tanba Province with the shogun Yoshitane ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakuni and Yoshioki were temporarily cornered with inferior numbers and forced to withdraw to Tanba Province with Shogun Yoshitane ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;lost ground for a while&quot; to &quot;were temporarily cornered with inferior numbers&quot; for &quot;一時は劣勢に追い込まれ&quot;; capitalized &quot;Shogun&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakuni and Yoshioki were temporarily cornered with inferior numbers and forced to withdraw to Tanba Province with shogun Yoshitane ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>shogun 小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="33">
<j>しかしこの最中に、阿波勢の擁する前将軍義澄が病死する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the middle of this, the former shogun Yoshizumi the force of Awa had, died of illness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During these events, however, the former Shogun Yoshizumi, who held the forces of Awa, died of illness.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During these events, however, the former shogun Yoshizumi, who held the forces of Awa, died of illness.</e>
<cmt>shogun 小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>8月、高国・義興軍が船岡山合戦に勝利した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September, the army of Takakuni and Yoshioki won at the Battle of Funaokayama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September, the Takakuni and Yoshioki forces were victorious at the Battle of Funaokayama.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;army&quot; to &quot;forces&quot; for &quot;軍&quot;; changed &quot;won&quot; to &quot;victorious&quot; for &quot;勝利&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September, the Takakuni and Yoshioki forces were victorious at the Battle of Funaokayama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>細川政賢は自害し、澄元は阿波に撤退する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masakata HOSOKAWA committed suicide, and Sumimoto withdrew to Awa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masakata HOSOKAWA committed suicide, and Sumimoto withdrew to Awa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masakata HOSOKAWA committed suicide, and Sumimoto withdrew to Awa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="36">
<j>永正14年（1517年）、三好之長は淡路水軍を掌握するため淡路に侵攻し、淡路守護細川尚春は和泉の堺に逃亡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1514, Yukinaga MIYOSHI invaded Awaji to take control of the Awaji Navy, and Hisaharu HOSOKAWA, Shugo of Awaji, fled to Sakai in Izumi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1514, as Yukinaga MIYOSHI invaded Awaji in order to take control of the Awaji Navy, the Shugo of Awaji Hisaharu HOSOKAWA fled to Sakai in Izumi.</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;and&quot; and added &quot;as&quot; before Yukinaga to make this a sentence of cause-and-effect rather than of two incidents</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1517, as Yukinaga MIYOSHI invaded Awaji in order to take control of the Awaji Navy, Hisaharu HOSOKAWA, the shugo of Awaji Province, fled to Sakai in Izumi.</e>
<cmt>shugo 小文字としています。1517年に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="37">
<j>永正15年（1518年）8月、出雲国の尼子氏や安芸の武田氏などが不穏な動きを見せ、麾下の国人の離反も相次いだため、大内義興が周防に帰国する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September, 1518, Yoshioki OUCHI went back to Suo, because the Amago clan in Izumo Province and the Takeda clan in Aki made a threatening move, and the local lords under his command defected from him one after another.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September of 1518, when threatening movements began showing in the Amago Clan of Izumo Province and the Takeda Clan of Aki, Yoshioki OUCHI returned home to Suo (modern day Yamaguchi Prefecture) due to the local lords under his command defecting one after another.</e>
<cmt>added description for Suo (modern day Yamaguchi Prefecture); rearranged sentence to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September of 1518, when threatening movements began showing in the Amago clan of Izumo Province and the Takeda clan of Aki Province, Yoshioki OUCHI returned home to Suo Province (modern day Yamaguchi Prefecture) due to the local lords under his command defecting one after another.</e>
<cmt>clan 小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="38">
<j>永正16年（1519年）5月、細川尚春は澄元に降るが、之長に殺害される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June, 1519, Hisaharu HOSOKAWA surrendered to Sumimoto, but he was killed by Yukinaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June of 1519, Hisaharu HOSOKAWA surrendered to Sumimoto but was killed by Yukinaga.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar in the date; eliminated comma and &quot;he&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June of 1519, Hisaharu HOSOKAWA surrendered to Sumimoto but was killed by Yukinaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="39">
<j>同年11月、澄元・之長らが摂津国兵庫に上陸、瓦林正頼（別名：河原林政頼）の越水城を落とす（越水城の合戦）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December in the same year, Sumimoto and Yukinaga landed in Hyogo in Settsu Province, and captured Koshimizu-jo Castle of Masayori KAWARABAYASHI (瓦林正頼, also known as 河原林政頼) (the Battle of Koshimizu-jo Castle).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During December of the same year, Sumimoto and Yukinaga landed in Hyogo in the Settsu Province and captured Koshimizu-jo Castle, owned by Masayori KAWARABAYASHI (瓦林正頼, also known as 河原林政頼) (The Battle of Koshimizu-jo Castle).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;In&quot; to &quot;During&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During December of the same year, Sumimoto and Yukinaga landed in Hyogo in the Settsu Province and captured Koshimizu-jo Castle, owned by Masayori KAWARABAYASHI (瓦林正頼, also known as 河原林政頼) (The Battle of Koshimizu-jo Castle).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="40">
<j>永正17年（1520年）2月、高国が摂津で澄元・之長に敗れ、将軍義稙は澄元側に通じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February, 1520, Takakuni was defeated by Sumimoto and Yukinaga in Settsu, and the shogun Yoshitane took sides with Sumimoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February of 1520 when Takakuni was defeated by Sumimoto and Yukinaga in Settsu, Shogun Yoshitane took sides with Sumimoto.</e>
<cmt>eliminated commas and fixed to read more smoothly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February of 1520, when Takakuni was defeated by Sumimoto and Yukinaga in Settsu, shogun Yoshitane took sides with Sumimoto.</e>
<cmt>shogun 小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="41">
<j>高国は近江坂本に逃走するが、近江の六角定頼・京極高清、丹波の内藤貞正らの支援を得て5月、京に侵攻し、澄元・之長を破る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakuni fled to Sakamoto in Omi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakuni fled to Sakamoto in Omi, but in May he invaded the capital, defeating Sumimoto and Yukinaga after gaining support in Omi from Sadayori ROKKAKU and Takakiyo KYOGOKU and Sadamasa NAITO from Tanba.</e>
<cmt>combined with the sentence below; rearranged sentences to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakuni fled to Sakamoto in Omi, but in May he invaded the capital, defeating Sumimoto and Yukinaga after gaining support in Omi from Sadayori ROKKAKU and Takakiyo KYOGOKU and Sadamasa NAITO from Tanba.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>之長は高国に拝謁し助命を請うが、細川尚春の養子・細川彦四郎の要求で自害に追い込まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Yukinaga had an audience with Takakuni to beg for his life, he was forced to commit suicide at the request of Hikoshiro HOSOKAWA, an adopted son of Hisaharu HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Yukinaga had an audience with Takakuni to beg for his life, he was forced to commit suicide at the request of Hikoshiro HOSOKAWA, an adopted son of Hisaharu HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Yukinaga had an audience with Takakuni to beg for his life, he was forced to commit suicide at the request of Hikoshiro HOSOKAWA, an adopted son of Hisaharu HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>また、澄元は摂津に追放され、6月、阿波勝瑞城で病死。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And Sumimoto was banished to Settsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sumimoto was banished to Settsu and died of illness in July at Shozui-jo Castle in Awa.</e>
<cmt>combined with the following sentence; fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sumimoto was banished to Settsu and died of illness in July at Shozui-jo Castle in Awa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="44">
<j>永正18年（1521年）3月、高国は対立した将軍義稙を追放し、新たに足利義晴を12代将軍として擁立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April, 1521, Takakuni expelled the shogun Yoshitane, who turned against him, and enthroned Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA as the twelfth shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April of 1521 Takakuni banished Shogun Yoshitane who had turned against him and put up Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA as the twelfth shogun.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;expelled&quot; to &quot;banished&quot; for &quot;追放&quot;; changed &quot;enthroned&quot; to &quot;put up&quot; for &quot;擁立した&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April of 1521, Takakuni banished shogun Yoshitane who had turned against him, and put up Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA as the twelfth shogun.</e>
<cmt>shogun 小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>8月、大永に改元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September, the name of the era changed to Daiei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September the name of the era changed to Daiei.</e>
<cmt>eliminated comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September the name of the era changed to Daiei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>この年、赤松義村の重臣浦上村宗、義村を幽閉ののち暗殺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In that year, Muramune URAGAMI, a senior vassal of Yoshimura AKAMATSU, and Yoshimura himself were assassinated after being incarcerated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the year, Muramane URAGAMI, a senior vassal of Yoshimura AKAMATSU, as well as Yoshimura himself were assassinated after being incarcerated.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;In that year&quot; to &quot;During the year&quot;; changed &quot;and&quot; to &quot;as well as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the year, Muramune URAGAMI, a senior vassal of Yoshimura AKAMATSU, as well as Yoshimura himself were assassinated after being incarcerated.</e>
<cmt>人名を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="47">
<j>大永4年（1524年）10月、高国の重臣香西元盛・柳本賢治らが阿波勢の残党を和泉で破る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November, 1524, Motomori KOZAI and Kataharu YANAGIMOTO, senior vassals of Takakuni defeated the remnants of the force of Awa in Izumi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November of 1524 Takakuni&apos;s senior vassals Motomori KOZAI and Kataharu YANAGIMOTO defeated the remnants of the Awa forces in Izumi.</e>
<cmt>rearranged sentence and fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November of 1524, Takakuni&apos;s senior vassals Motomori KOZAI and Kataharu YANAGIMOTO defeated the remnants of the Awa forces in Izumi.</e>
<cmt>1524の後にカンマを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="48">
<j>大永6年（1526年）7月、丹波守護細川尹賢の讒言により、高国が香西元盛を謀殺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August, 1526, Takakuni murdered Motomori KOZAI, because of a false charge by Tadakata HOSOKAWA, Shugo of Tanba.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August of 1526 Takakuni murdered Motomori KOZAI due to false charges made by the Shugo of Tanba, Tadakata HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;charge&quot; to &quot;charges&quot;; changed &quot;because of&quot; to &quot;due to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August of 1526, Takakuni murdered Motomori KOZAI due to false charges made by the shugo of Tanba Province, Tadakata HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>shugo 小文字としています。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>元盛の兄・波多野稙通・柳本賢治らは阿波の細川晴元・三好元長と連携して丹波で挙兵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tanemichi HATANO, Motomori&apos;s brother, and Kataharu YANAGIMOTO raised an army in Tanba, Collaborating with Harumoto HOSOKAWA and Motonaga MIYOSHI from Awa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motomori&apos;s brother Tanemichi HATANO and Kataharu YANAGIMOTO raised an army in Tanba in a collaborative effort with Harumoto HOSOKAWA and Motonaga MIYOSHI from Awa.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;Collaborating&quot; to &quot;in a collaborative effort&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motomori&apos;s brother Tanemichi HATANO and Kataharu YANAGIMOTO raised an army in Tanba in a collaborative effort with Harumoto HOSOKAWA and Motonaga MIYOSHI from Awa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>高国は細川尹賢を丹波に侵攻させたが敗退。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though Takakuni had Tadakata HOSOKAWA invade Tanba, he was defeated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakuni had Tadakata HOSOKAWA invade Tanba but he was defeated.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;Though&quot; to &quot;but&quot; and used in the middle of the sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakuni had Tadakata HOSOKAWA invade Tanba but he was defeated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="51">
<j>大永7年（1527年）2月、波多野稙通・柳本賢治らが京に侵攻。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March, 1527, Tanemichi HATANO and Kataharu YANAGIMOTO invaded the capital.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March of 1527 Tanemichi HATANO and Kataharu YANAGIMOTO invaded the capital.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;In March, 1527&quot; to &quot;In March of 1527&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March of 1527, Tanemichi HATANO and Kataharu YANAGIMOTO invaded the capital.</e>
<cmt>1527の後にカンマを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>高国・尹賢は桂川で迎え撃つが敗れ、将軍義晴を擁して近江坂本に逃亡（桂川の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakuni and Tadakata countered them at the Katsura-gawa River, but they were defeated, and fled to Sakamoto in Omi with the shogun Yoshiharu (the Battle of Katsura-gawa River).</e>
<cmt>同上</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakuni and Tadakata attacked their forces at the Katsura-gawa River but they were defeated and fled to Sakamoto in Omi with Shogun Yoshiharu (The Battle of Katsura-gawa River).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;countered them&quot; to &quot;attacked their forces&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakuni and Tadakata attacked their forces at the Katsura-gawa River but they were defeated and fled to Sakamoto in Omi with shogun Yoshiharu (The Battle of Katsura-gawa River).</e>
<cmt>shogun 小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>前将軍義稙の養子・足利義維（義晴の弟）を擁する晴元・元長は堺に進出し、京の支配を行う（堺公方）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harumoto and Motonaga, who had Yoshitsuna ASHIKAGA (Yoshiharu&apos;s brother), an adopted son of the former shogun Yoshitane, advanced to Sakai, and governed the capital (Sakaikubo (the municipal government based in Sakai City)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With Yoshitsuna ASHIKAGA, the former Shogun Yoshitane&apos;s adopted son on their side, Harumoto and Motonaga advanced to Sakai and governed the capital (Sakaikubo (the municipal government based in Sakai City)).</e>
<cmt>rearranged sentence to read more smoothly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With Yoshitsuna ASHIKAGA, the former shogun Yoshitane&apos;s adopted son and a younger brother of Yoshiharu on their side, Harumoto and Motonaga advanced to Sakai and governed the capital (Sakaikubo [the municipal government based in Sakai City]).</e>
<cmt>「義晴の弟」を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="54">
<j>享禄元年（1528年）、高国は京奪回を試みるが、晴元に敗れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1528, Takakuni tried to recaptured the capital, but he was defeated by Harumoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1528 Takakuni tried to recapture the capital but was defeated by Harumoto.</e>
<cmt>recaptured→recapture; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1528, Takakuni tried to recapture the capital but was defeated by Harumoto.</e>
<cmt>1528の後にカンマを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>細川尹賢、晴元方に寝返る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadakata HOSOKAWA changed sides to Harumoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadakata HOSOKAWA defected to Harumoto&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;changed sides&quot; to &quot;defected&quot; and fixed grammar accordingly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadakata HOSOKAWA defected to Harumoto&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="56">
<j>享禄3年（1530年）、柳本賢治が播磨出陣中に死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1530, Kataharu YANAGIMOTO died while he was at the front in Harima.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1530 Kataharu YANAGIMOTO died while departing for the front in Harima.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;while he was at the front&quot; to &quot;while departing for the front&quot; for &quot;出陣中に&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1530, Kataharu YANAGIMOTO died while departing for the front in Harima.</e>
<cmt>1530の後にカンマを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>高国は浦上村宗と連携して京に侵攻。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakuni invaded the capital collaborating with Muramune URAGAMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakuni invaded the capital in a collaboritive effort with Muramune URAGAMI.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;collaborating with&quot; to &quot;in a collaboritive effort with&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakuni invaded the capital in a collaborative effort with Muramune URAGAMI.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="58">
<j>享禄4年（1531年）3月、高国は三好元長の反撃を受けて摂津国中嶋の戦いで大敗。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March, 1531, Takakuni suffered a crushing defeat at the Battle of Nakajima in Settsu Province, due to the counterattack of Motonaga MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During March of 1531, Takakuni suffered a crushing defeat at the Battle of Nakajima in Settsu Province due to a counterattack made by Motonaga MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During March of 1531, Takakuni suffered a crushing defeat at the Battle of Nakajima in Settsu Province due to a counterattack made by Motonaga MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="59">
<j>6月、さらに高国は大物崩れで元長に敗れて尼崎市に逃走したが、捕らえられ自害した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, in July, Takakuni was defeated by Motonaga at Daimotsu kuzure (the Battle of Daimotsu) and he fled to Amagasaki City, but he was captured and he committed suicide.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July, Takakuni was defeated again by Motonaga at Daimotsu Kuzure (The Battle of Daimotsu) and fled to Amagasaki City but was captured and committed suicide.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;Further, in July, Takakuni was defeated&quot; to &quot;In July, Takakuni was defeated again&quot;; capitalized &quot;Kuzure&quot;; eliminated comma after &quot;City&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July, Takakuni was defeated again by Motonaga at Daimotsu Kuzure (The Battle of Daimotsu) and fled to Amagasaki City but was captured and committed suicide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>浦上村宗も討死。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Muramune URAGAMI died on the battle field.</e>
<cmt>同上</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Muramune URAGAMI also died in the battle.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;also&quot; to correspond to the &quot;も&quot;; fixed grammar to make this sentence less fragmented</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Muramune URAGAMI also died in the battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="61">
<j>7月、細川尹賢が木沢長政に殺害される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August, Tadakata HOSOKAWA was killed by Nagamasa KIZAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August Tadakata HOSOKAWA was killed by Nagamasa KIZAWA.</e>
<cmt>eliminated comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August, Tadakata HOSOKAWA was killed by Nagamasa KIZAWA.</e>
<cmt>August の後にカンマを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>長政と元長が対立するようになるが、細川晴元は長政を寵愛する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though Nagamasa and Motonaga became opposed to each other, Harumoto HOSOKAWA favored Nagamasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Nagamasa and Motonaga had become opposed to each other, Harumoto HOSOKAWA showed favor for Nagamasa.</e>
<cmt>This sentence seems to lack a connection to anything but I tried to fix the grammar to make it stand alone…</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Nagamasa and Motonaga had become opposed to each other, Harumoto HOSOKAWA showed favor for Nagamasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="63">
<j>天文 (元号)元年（1532年）6月、晴元は本願寺証如や木沢長政と結び、一向一揆に堺の元長を攻めさせる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July, Harumoto allied with Shonyo HONGANJI and Nagamasa KIZAWA, and had the troops of Ikko sect&apos;s revolt attack Motonaga in Sakai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July Harumoto formed an alliance with Shonyo HONGANJI and Nagamasa KIZAWA and had Ikko-ikki (mobs of peasant farmers, monks, Shinto priests and local nobles who rose up against samurai) troops attack Motonaga in Sakai.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;allied&quot; to &quot;formed an alliance&quot;; changed &quot;Ikko sect&apos;s revolt&quot; to &quot;Ikko-ikki troops&quot; and added description from the wiki article based on the group</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July of 1532, Harumoto formed an alliance with Shonyo HONGANJI and Nagamasa KIZAWA and had Ikko-ikki (mobs of peasant farmers, monks, Shinto priests and local nobles who rose up against samurai) troops attack Motonaga in Sakai.</e>
<cmt>1532を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>元長は敗れて自害。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motonaga was defeated, and he committed suicide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motonaga was defeated and committed suicide.</e>
<cmt>eliminated comma and &quot;he&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motonaga was defeated and committed suicide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>晴元は将軍義晴と和睦する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harumoto made peace with the shogun Yoshiharu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Harumoto made peace with Shogun Yoshiharu.</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Shogun&quot;; capitalized &quot;Shogun&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harumoto made peace with shogun Yoshiharu.</e>
<cmt>shogun 小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>この後、享禄・天文の乱が勃発。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Kyoroku-Tenbun no Ran (Kyoroku-Tenbun War) erupted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later on, the Kyoroku-Tenbun no Ran (Kyoroku-Tenbun War) erupted.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;Later&quot; to &quot;Later on&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later on, the Kyoroku-Tenbun War erupted.</e>
<cmt>Kyoroku-Tenbun War としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tiyoringo(id:70026), Yanahan(id:2437), Carkuni(id:79281), ファービィ(id:129184), ブレイズマン(id:183852), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 8888aa8888(id:244382), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>