<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>国免荘</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokumen no sho (a shoen allowed exemption from so or other tribute in bempo or binho system)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokumen no sho (a shoen allowed exemption from so or other tribute in THE bempo or binho system)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokumen no sho</e>
<cmt>タイトルですので、補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>国免荘（こくめんのしょう）は、平安時代後期の荘園のうち、国司によって諸役の免除を受けたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokumen no sho (also referred to as Kokumensho) was a kind of shoen (manor in medieval Japan) in the late Heian period which was exempt from miscellaneous taxes by kokushi (provincial governor.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokumen no sho (also referred to as Kokumensho) was a kind of shoen (manor in medieval Japan) during the late Heian period which was exempt from miscellaneous taxes by kokushi (provincial governor.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokumen no sho (also referred to as Kokumensho) was a kind of shoen (manor in medieval Japan) during the late Heian period which was exempt from miscellaneous taxes by kokushi (provincial governor).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>平安時代後期に入ると、地方統治における国司の権限は強力となり、荒田などの諸役免除などを決定する権限を保持するようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the late Heian period, kokushi became influential in the provincial government and assumed the authority to decide shoekimenjo (exemption of miscellaneous taxes) on Arata (also referred to as Areta; rice field of low grade) and the like.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the late Heian period, kokushi became influential in the provincial government and assumed the authority to decide shoekimenjo (exemption of miscellaneous taxes) on Arata (also referred to as Areta; rice field of low grade) and the like.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the late Heian period, kokushi became influential in the provincial government and assumed the authority to decide shoekimenjo (exemption of miscellaneous taxes) on Arata (also referred to as Areta; rice field of low grade) and the like.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>これを不輸の権 (日本)・不入の権 (日本)を獲得した荘園に対しても適用を拡大しようとしたのが国免荘である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokushi managed to extend his influence even to shoen that had already been granted Fuyu no ken (the right of tax exemption, Japan) and Funyu no ken (the right to keep the tax agents from entering the property, Japan), which had resulted in Kokumen no sho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokushi managed to extend his influence even to shoen that had already been granted Fuyu no ken (the right of tax exemption, Japan) and Funyu no ken (the right to keep the tax agents from entering the property, Japan), which had resulted in Kokumen no sho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokushi managed to extend his influence even to shoen that had already been granted Fuyu no ken (the right of tax exemption, Japan) and Funyu no ken (the right to keep the tax agents from entering the property, Japan), which had resulted in Kokumen no sho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>ただし、これは当該の国司の個人裁量によるものであったから、国司が交代すると無効になる可能性があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since kokushi gave such treatment entirely at his discretion, that exemption could be cancelled by newly assigned kokushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since kokushi gave such treatment entirely at his discretion, that exemption could be cancelled by a newly assigned kokushi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since kokushi gave such treatment entirely at his discretion, that exemption could be cancelled by a newly assigned kokushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>このため、荘園領主たちは更に効力が強い官省符荘や勅免荘への認定を期待するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the lords of shoen wanted their lands to be granted much stronger Kanshofu sho (a shoen enjoying immunity from taxation by virtue of having official documents from both the Council of State and the Ministry of Popular Affairs) or Chokumen sho (imperially exempted manor.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the lords of shoen wanted their lands to be granted a much stronger Kanshofu sho (a shoen enjoying immunity from taxation by virtue of having official documents from both the Council of State and the Ministry of Popular Affairs) or Chokumen sho (imperially exempted manor.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the lords of shoen wanted their lands to be granted a much stronger Kanshofu sho (a shoen enjoying immunity from taxation by virtue of having official documents from both the Council of State and the Ministry of Popular Affairs) or Chokumen sho (imperially exempted manor).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 春秋君(id:174988), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>