<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>守護使不入</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shugoshi funyu (privilege of excluding agents of the shugo, provincial constables)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shugoshi funyu (privilege of excluding agents of the shugo, provincial constables)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shugoshi funyu</e>
<cmt>原文の不要な文字列を削除し、タイトルなので補足も削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>守護使不入（しゅごしふにゅう）とは、鎌倉時代・室町時代において幕府が守護やその役人に対して犯罪者追跡や徴税のために、幕府によって設定された特定の公領や荘園などに立ち入る事を禁じたこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shugoshi funyu&quot; means that in the Kamakura Period and the Muromachi Period, the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) forbade shugo (provincial constables) and their officials to enter some specific koryo (public lands), shoen (manor), and so on, which were specified by the bakufu, for pursuing criminals and collecting taxes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shugoshi funyu&quot; means that in the Kamakura Period and the Muromachi Period, the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) forbade shugo (provincial constables) and their officials from entering some specific koryo (public lands), shoen (manors), and so on, which were specified by the bakufu, when pursuing criminals and collecting taxes.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shugoshi funyu means that in the Kamakura period and the Muromachi period, the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) forbade shugo (provincial constables) and their officials from entering some specific koryo (public lands), shoen (manors), and so on, which were specified by the bakufu, when pursuing criminals and collecting taxes.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>守護不入（しゅごふにゅう）とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shugoshi funyu&quot; is also referred as &quot;shugo funyu&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shugoshi funyu&quot; is also referred to as &quot;shugo funyu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>added &quot;to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shugoshi funyu is also referred to as shugo funyu.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>戦国時代_(日本)には幕府による権限は否定され、代わりに戦国大名が守護・国主の権限の一環としてこれを付与するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States), this privilege which had been granted by the bakufu was denied and instead daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) in the Sengoku Period came to give it to their shugo and kokushu (a landed daimyo) as part of their rights.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States), this privilege which had been granted by the bakufu was denied and instead daimyo (Japanese territorial lords) in the Sengoku Period came to give it to their shugo and kokushu (landed daimyo) as part of their rights.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States), this privilege which had been granted by the bakufu was denied and instead daimyo (Japanese territorial lords) in the Sengoku Period came to give it to their shugo and kokushu (landed daimyo) as part of their rights.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>鎌倉幕府</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamakura bakufu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamakura bakufu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamakura bakufu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>本来、守護には大犯三箇条の義務遂行のため、本人あるいはその代理である役人・使者の国内の公領・荘園への立ち入る権利が認められていたが、鎌倉幕府は国司や領家・本所（権門）との対立を回避するために、国司や領家・本所が守護による干渉を受けない特例地域を設ける事を承認していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally not only shugo but also his officials and emissaries as his agent had been empowered to enter domestic koryo and shoen to perform their duties of Taibon Sankajo (three major tasks of peacekeeping), but the Kamakura bakufu agreed to provide special areas in which kokushi (regional lord), ryoke (a lord of the manor), and honjo (proprietor or guarantor of manor) or kenmon (an influential family) were not interfered by shugo, in order to avoid a confrontation with them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally not only a shugo but also his officials and emissaries acting as his agents had been empowered to enter domestic koryo and shoen to perform their duties of Taibon Sankajo (three major tasks of peacekeeping), but the Kamakura bakufu agreed to provide special areas in which a kokushi (regional lord), ryoke (lord of the manor), honjo (proprietor or guarantor of manor), or kenmon (an influential family) were not interfered with by shugo, in order to avoid a confrontation with them.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally not only a shugo but also his officials and emissaries acting as his agents had been empowered to enter domestic koryo and shoen to perform their duties of Taibon Sankajo (three major tasks of peacekeeping), but the Kamakura bakufu agreed to provide special areas in which a kokushi (regional lord), ryoke (lord of the manor), honjo (proprietor or guarantor of manor), or kenmon (an influential family) were not interfered with by shugo, in order to avoid a confrontation with them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>これは御成敗式目によって一層明確化され、不入地に犯罪者などが逃げ込んだ場合でもその追捕は国司・領家によって行われ、不入地の境界線で守護側に引き渡すと言う原則が成立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This agreement was more clarified by the Goseibai-shikimoku (code of conduct for samurai) and then a principle was established that even when a criminal and others ran into such funyuchi (special areas for excluding shugo), the criminal should be searched by kokushi or ryoke, and handed over to the shugo side on a border line of the funyuchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This agreement was further clarified by the Goseibai-shikimoku (code of conduct for samurai), and then a principle was established that even when a criminal and others ran into such funyuchi (special areas for excluding shugo), the criminal should be searched by kokushi or ryoke, and handed over to the shugo side on a border line of the funyuchi.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This agreement was further clarified by the Goseibai-shikimoku (code of conduct for samurai), and then a principle was established that even when a criminal and others ran into such funyuchi (special areas for excluding shugo), the criminal should be searched by kokushi or ryoke, and handed over to the shugo side on a border line of the funyuchi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>室町幕府</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Muromachi bakufu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Muromachi bakufu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Muromachi bakufu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>室町幕府においては、守護（守護大名）に対して、既存の大犯三箇条に加えて、苅田狼藉検断、使節遵行権、段銭徴収権などの広範な権利が付与されていたが、幕府御家人は、足利将軍家の威光を背景に守護使不入の特権を得て、守護からの段銭徴収を拒絶し、幕府からの段銭要求に対しても幕府への直接納付（京納）が認められて守護からの加重徴収の危険を免れる事を可能とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Muromachi bakufu, extensive rights were given to shugo (or shugo daimyo, shugo that became daimyo, which were Japanese feudal lords) such as Karita Rozeki Kendan (the shugo&apos;s right to suppress provincial warriors who entered shoen unlawfully to harvest rice, and to prosecute and convict them), Shisetsu Jungyo Ken (a right empowered to shugo to implement shisetsu jungyo, in which shugo who received orders from the bakufu sent jungyo-shi, emissaries, to a region and have them execute the orders.) and Tansen Choshu Ken (a right to collect surtax), in addition to the existing Taibon Sankajo, but bakufu gokenin (an immediate vasal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods)who had been granted the shugoshi-funyu privilege backed by authority of the Ashikaga family positioned to accede to the shogunate, refused collection of tansen (surtax) from shugo, and responded to one from the bakufu as direct payment to the bakufu (kyono) was approved, which enabled them to escape from a danger of being surcharged by the shugo.</e>
<cmt>段銭「だんせん」とも読むようです。[http://kotobank.jp/word/%E6%AE%B5%E9%8A%AD] 使節遵行「しせつじゅんぎょう」百科事典マイペディアhttp://kotobank.jp/word/%E4%BD%BF%E7%AF%80%E9%81%B5%E8%A1%8C　京納→京納 [読み方不明]　「京納」の読み方については「日本歴史辞典」「日本史用語辞典」なども参照しましたが、今のところ不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Muromachi bakufu, extensive rights were given to shugo (or shugo daimyo, shugo that became daimyo, which were Japanese feudal lords), such as Karita Rozeki Kendan (the shugo&apos;s right to suppress provincial warriors who entered shoen unlawfully to harvest rice, and to prosecute and convict them), Shisetsu Jungyo Ken (a right empowered to shugo to implement shisetsu jungyo, in which shugo who received orders from the bakufu sent jungyo-shi, emissaries, to a region and have them execute the orders) and Tansen Choshu Ken (a right to collect surtax), in addition to the existing Taibon Sankajo, but bakufu gokenin (an immediate vasal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods) who had been granted the shugoshi-funyu privilege backed by the authority of the Ashikaga family positioned to accede to the shogunate, refused collection of tansen (surtax) from shugo, and responded to one from the bakufu as direct payment to the bakufu (kyono) was approved, which enabled them to escape from a danger of being surcharged by the shugo.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Muromachi bakufu, extensive rights were given to shugo (or shugo daimyo, shugo that became daimyo, which were Japanese feudal lords), such as Karita Rozeki Kendan (the shugo&apos;s right to suppress provincial warriors who entered shoen unlawfully to harvest rice, and to prosecute and convict them), Shisetsu Jungyo Ken (a right empowered to shugo to implement shisetsu jungyo, in which shugo who received orders from the bakufu sent jungyo-shi, emissaries, to a region and have them execute the orders) and Tansen Choshu Ken (a right to collect surtax), in addition to the existing Taibon Sankajo, but bakufu gokenin (an immediate vasal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods) who had been granted the shugoshi-funyu privilege backed by the authority of the Ashikaga family positioned to accede to the shogunate, refused collection of tansen (surtax) from shugo, and responded to one from the bakufu as direct payment to the bakufu (known as kyono) was approved, which enabled them to escape from a danger of being surcharged by the shugo.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>これによって一見すると守護大名の領域に治外法権地域が生まれる事になり、室町幕府の支配系統に障害が生じたかのように見られるが、実態はそれとは反対で守護領国制の強化によって守護大名による領国一円支配を阻止してその勢力拡大を抑制するとともに、特権を受けた御家人層は幕府権力への依存を強めてこの権利を維持しようと図り、幕府にとっては守護大名に対抗するための政治的・経済的・軍事的な基盤を支える支持の形成に効果があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although this could have apparently produced a chigaihoken (extraterritoriality) area in the domains of shugo daimyo and seems to have caused an obstacle in ruling systems of the Muromachi bakufu, in fact contrary to that, by tightening of shugo-ryogoku system (the system that a shugo dominates a manor), it prevented shugo daimyo from executing ryogoku ichien shihai (ruling the whole region of the territory) and suppressed expansion of his power, and at the same time, the privileged gokenin class tried to maintain this privilege by increasing dependence on the bakufu powers, which helped the bakufu form support for political, economic, and military basis to confront the shugo daimyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although this could have apparently produced a chigaihoken (extraterritoriality) area in the domains of shugo daimyo and seems to have caused an obstacle in ruling systems of the Muromachi bakufu, in fact, contrary to that, by tightening of the shugo-ryogoku system (the system that a shugo dominates a manor), it prevented shugo daimyo from executing ryogoku ichien shihai (ruling the whole region of the territory) and suppressed expansion of his power, and at the same time, the privileged gokenin class tried to maintain this privilege by increasing dependence on the bakufu powers, which helped the bakufu form support for political, economic, and military bases to confront the shugo daimyo.</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although this could have apparently produced a chigaihoken (extraterritoriality) area in the domains of shugo daimyo and seems to have caused an obstacle in ruling systems of the Muromachi bakufu, in fact, contrary to that, by tightening of the shugo-ryogoku system (the system that a shugo dominates a manor), it prevented shugo daimyo from executing ryogoku ichien shihai (ruling the whole region of the territory) and suppressed expansion of his power, and at the same time, the privileged gokenin class tried to maintain this privilege by increasing dependence on the bakufu powers, which helped the bakufu form support for political, economic, and military bases to confront the shugo daimyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>戦国時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sengoku Period</e>
<cmt>前出補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>だが、戦国時代_(日本)に入り、幕府の権威は低下して下剋上によって幕府の力に依存せずに自力で領国を形成した戦国大名達はこの特権を否定し始めるとともに、自らの権限としてこれを付与あるいは剥奪を行うようになっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Sengoku Period, however, the authority of the bakufu declined and daimyos in the Sengoku Period who formed their own territories by winning gekokujo (an inverted social order when the lowly reigned over the elite) without dependence on the bakufu&apos;s power not only began to deny the privilege but also grant or despoil it as their own rights.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Sengoku Period, however, the authority of the bakufu declined and daimyos in the Sengoku Period who formed their own territories by winning gekokujo (an inverted social order when the lowly reigned over the elite) without dependence on the bakufu&apos;s power not only began to deny the privilege but also came to grant or despoil it as their own rights.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Sengoku Period, however, the authority of the bakufu declined and Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period) who formed their own territories by winning gekokujo (an inverted social order when the lowly reigned over the elite) without dependence on the bakufu&apos;s power not only began to deny the privilege but also came to grant or despoil it as their own rights.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>更に幕府によって出された守護使不入の規定に従ってきた守護大名の中からも領国の維持を名目に幕府による守護使不入の権利を公然と否定する措置を取るようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also some of the shugo daimyos who had observed the shugoshi funyu rules released by the bakufu came to take measures to deny in public such shugoshi-funyu privilege granted by the bakufu, on the pretext of maintaining their territories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, some of the shugo daimyos who had observed the shugoshi funyu rules released by the bakufu came to take measures to deny in public such shugoshi-funyu privilege granted by the bakufu, on the pretext of maintaining their territories.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, some of the shugo daimyos who had observed the shugoshi funyu rules released by the bakufu came to take measures to deny in public such shugoshi-funyu privilege granted by the bakufu, on the pretext of maintaining their territories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>例えば、明応7年（1498年）、越後国守護上杉房能は、越後国内において守護使不入の主張を認めない事を宣言し、永正年間には駿河国守護今川氏親が幕府の許可を得ずに遠江国守護斯波氏を追って同国を支配して守護使不入地に対しても検地を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1498, for example, Fusayoshi UESUGI, the Governor of Echigo Province, declared that he would not approve to claim shugoshi funyu within the Echigo Province, and during the Eisho era (1504-1521) Ujichika IMAGAWA, the Governor of Suruga Province, expelled the Shiba clan, the Governor of Totomi Province, without permission of the bakufu, ruled the province, and conducted a land survey even in the terrirories specified as shugoshi funyuchi.</e>
<cmt>斯波「しば」http://kotobank.jp/word/%E6%96%AF%E6%B3%A2%E5%AE%B6%E5%85%BC</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1498, for example, Fusayoshi UESUGI, the Governor of Echigo Province, declared that he would not approve to claim shugoshi funyu within Echigo Province, and during the Eisho era (1504-1521) Ujichika IMAGAWA, the Governor of Suruga Province, expelled the Shiba clan, the Governor of Totomi Province, without permission of the bakufu, ruled the province, and conducted a land survey even in the terrirories specified as shugoshi funyuchi.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1498, for example, Fusayoshi UESUGI, the Governor of Echigo Province, declared that he would not approve to claim shugoshi funyu within Echigo Province, and during the Eisho era (1504-1521) Ujichika IMAGAWA, the Governor of Suruga Province, expelled the Shiba clan, the Governor of Totomi Province, without permission of the bakufu, ruled the province, and conducted a land survey even in the territories specified as shugoshi funyuchi.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その後、その子・今川義元は、天文_(日本)22年（1552年）の分国法「今川仮名目録追加」において現在の今川領国の秩序維持を行っているのは足利将軍家ではなく今川氏そのものであることを理由に、幕府権力による守護使不入地を全面否定したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, his son Yoshimoto IMAGAWA completely denied the shugoshi funyuchi specified by the bakufu authority in his bunkokuho (the law individual sengoku-daimyo enforced in their own domain) &apos;Imagawa Kana Mokuroku Tsuika&apos; (expanding on house rules left by Ujichika), published in 1552, on the ground that those who maintain order in the present Imagawa territory are not Ashikaga shogun family, but the Imagawa clan itself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, his son Yoshimoto IMAGAWA completely denied the shugoshi funyuchi specified by the bakufu authority in his bunkokuho (the law individual sengoku-daimyo enforced in their own domain) &apos;Imagawa Kana Mokuroku Tsuika&apos; (expanding on house rules left by Ujichika), published in 1552, on the ground that those who maintain order in the present Imagawa territory are not the Ashikaga shogun family, but the Imagawa clan itself.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, his son Yoshimoto IMAGAWA completely denied the shugoshi funyuchi specified by the bakufu authority in his bunkokuho (the law individual sengoku-daimyo enforced in their own domain) &apos;Imagawa Kana Mokuroku Tsuika&apos; (expanding on house rules left by Ujichika), published in 1552, on the ground that those who maintain order in the present Imagawa territory are not the Ashikaga shogun family, but the Imagawa clan itself.</e>
<cmt>半角クォーテーションにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>これは、今川氏は既に室町幕府の権威によって領国を統治する守護大名ではなく、自らの実力によって領国を統治する戦国大名であることを明確に宣言したものでもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was aslo clear declaration by the Imagawa clan that he was no longer the shugo daimyo who ruled his territory backed by the authority of the Muromachi bakufu, but the daimyo in the Sengoku Period who ruled his own territory with his own capability.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was aslo clear declaration by the Imagawa clan that he was no longer the shugo daimyo who ruled his territory backed by the authority of the Muromachi bakufu, but the daimyo in the Sengoku Period who ruled his own territory with his own capability.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was also clear declaration by the Imagawa clan that he was no longer the shugo daimyo who ruled his territory backed by the authority of the Muromachi bakufu, but the Sengoku daimyo who ruled his own territory with his own capability.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), 味っ子(id:17086), Nalc(id:139567), 伏儀(id:142093), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>