<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大和源氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamato-Genji (Minamoto clan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamato-Genji (Minamoto clan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamato-Genji (Minamoto clan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大和源氏（やまとげんじ）は 清和源氏の一流であり、源満仲の次男の源頼親に始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamato-Genji, a branch of the Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan), was started by MINAMOTO no Yorichika, the second son of MINAMOTO no Mitsunaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamato-Genji, a branch of the Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan), was started by MINAMOTO no Yorichika, the second son of MINAMOTO no Mitsunaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamato-Genji, a branch of the Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan), was started by MINAMOTO no Yorichika, the second son of MINAMOTO no Mitsunaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>頼親は大和国の国司となり同国に勢力を拡大、その過程で興福寺などの南都勢力と武力衝突を起こして流罪となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorichika became the kokushi (provincial governor) of the Province of Yamato, and extended his power across the Province; during this process he fought against the forces of Nanto (southern capital (Nara)), such as Kofuku-ji Temple, and was exiled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yorichika became the kokushi (provincial governor) of the Province of Yamato, and extended his power across the pProvince; during this process he fought against the forces of Nanto (southern capital (Nara)), such as Kofuku-ji Temple, and was exiled.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorichika became the kokushi (provincial governor) of the Province of Yamato, and extended his power across the Province; during this process he fought against the forces of Nanto (southern capital [Nara]), such as Kofuku-ji Temple, and was exiled.</e>
<cmt>pProvince→Province括弧内の括弧を[]に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>しかしその子孫は大和一円に広がり、引き続き南都勢力との抗争を繰り返しながら土着傾向を強めていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, his descendants were scattered throughout the Yamato Province, and were continuously in conflict with the forces of Nanto and were undergoing increasing indigenization.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, his descendants were scattered throughout Yamato Province; they were continuously in conflict with the forces of Nanto but were undergoing increased indigenization.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, his descendants were scattered throughout Yamato Province; they were continuously in conflict with the forces of Nanto but were undergoing increased indigenization.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>中には頼親から五代後の僧信実のように、宿敵であるはずの興福寺の上座となって南都勢力と同化し、同族の大和源氏と抗争する者までも出現した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among them, those who fought on the side of the same family Yamato-Genji appeared in the historical record, like the monk Shinjitsu, fifth generation descendant of Yorichika, who took the seat of honor in Kofuku-ji Temple - their old enemy - and joined with the Nanto forces.</e>
<cmt>信実の読み方ですが、僧侶なので、「しんじつ」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them, those who fought on the side of the same family (Yamato-Genji) appeared in the historical record, such as the monk Shinjitsu, a fifth-generation descendant of Yorichika, who took the seat of honor in Kofuku-ji Temple--their old enemy--and joined the Nanto forces.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them, those who fought on the side of the same family (Yamato-Genji) appeared in the historical record, such as the monk Shinjitsu, a fifth-generation descendant of Yorichika, who took the seat of honor in Kofuku-ji Temple--their old enemy--and joined the Nanto forces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>信実の好敵手であった源親治（宇野親治、同じく頼親から五代後）は、保元元年(1156年)の保元の乱において崇徳上皇方についたため捕虜となるが、南都勢力の伸張を牽制したい後白河天皇の深謀遠慮により、罪を赦されて帰郷を果たしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Hogen War in 1156, MINAMOTO no Chikaharu (Chikaharu UNO), who was also a fifth generation descendant of Yorichika and a worthy opponent of Shinjitsu, supported the retired Emperor Sutoku; for this reason he became a prisoner of war, but due to the farsightedness of the retired Emperor Goshirakawa, who wanted to discourage expansion of the Nanto forces, he was pardoned and returned home.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Hogen War in 1156, MINAMOTO no Chikaharu (Chikaharu UNO), who was also a fifth-generation descendant of Yorichika and a worthy opponent of Shinjitsu, supported the retired Emperor Sutoku; for this reason he became a prisoner of war, but due to the farsightedness of the retired Emperor Goshirakawa, who wanted to discourage the expansion of the Nanto forces, he was pardoned and returned home.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Hogen War in 1156, MINAMOTO no Chikaharu (Chikaharu UNO), who was also a fifth-generation descendant of Yorichika and a worthy opponent of Shinjitsu, supported the retired Emperor Sutoku; for this reason he became a prisoner of war, but due to the farsightedness of the retired Emperor Goshirakawa, who wanted to discourage the expansion of the Nanto forces, he was pardoned and returned home.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>降って治承4年(1180年)に源頼政が以仁王と語らって挙兵した際には、決起を促す諸国の源氏の一群の中に親治とその子達の名前が見え、なおも国内に一勢力を保っていたことが窺える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1180, MINAMOTO no Yorimasa and Prince Mochihito joined forces and raised an army; the names of Chikaharu and his sons appeared among the group of the Minamoto clan that encouraged insurrection in many districts, and this shows that Yamato-Genji still maintained their power within the province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1180, MINAMOTO no Yorimasa and Prince Mochihito joined forces and raised an army; the names of Chikaharu and his sons appeared among the group of the Minamoto clan that encouraged insurrection in many districts, and this shows that Yamato-Genji still maintained their power within the province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1180, MINAMOTO no Yorimasa and Prince Mochihito joined forces and raised an army; the names of Chikaharu and his sons appeared among the group of the Minamoto clan that encouraged insurrection in many districts, and this shows that Yamato-Genji still maintained their power within the province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし治承・寿永の乱において目立った活躍がなかった大和源氏は、これ以降は地方豪族の域を出ることができず、中世を通じて次第に纏まりを失い、諸国に拡散していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Yamato-Genji did not show much military prowess in the Jisho-Juei War and after this war they just continued as a powerful regional clan, and then throughout the middle ages, gradually lost their unity and spread out to other districts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Yamato-Genji didn&apos;t demonstrate much military prowess in the Jisho-Juei War, and subsequently they just continued as a powerful regional clan; throughout the middle ages they gradually lost their unity and spread out to other districts.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Yamato-Genji didn&apos;t demonstrate much military prowess in the Jisho-Juei War, and subsequently they just continued as a powerful regional clan; throughout the middle ages they gradually lost their unity and spread out to other districts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>上述の親治にはじまる大和国の宇野氏をはじめ、織田信雄に仕えた土方雄久の土方氏、肥後国の隈部氏、陸奥国の石川氏、三河国の高木氏、楠木正成を討ち取ったとされる伊予国の大森彦七などが大和源氏の末裔を称している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following clans claimed to be the descendants of Yamato-Genji: the Uno clan from the Province of Yamato, starting from the above-mentioned Chikaharu; the Hijikata clan of Katsuhisa HIJIKATA who served Nobukatsu ODA; the Kumabe clan of Higo Province; the Ishikawa clan of Mutsu Province; the Takagi clan of Mikawa Province; and Hikoshichi OMORI of Iyo Province, who is believed to have slain Masashige KUSUNOKI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following clans claimed to be the descendants of Yamato-Genji: the Uno clan from Yamato Province, starting from the above-mentioned Chikaharu; the Hijikata clan of Katsuhisa HIJIKATA, who served Nobukatsu ODA; the Kumabe clan of Higo Province; the Ishikawa clan of Mutsu Province; the Takagi clan of Mikawa Province; and Hikoshichi OMORI of Iyo Province, who is believed to have slain Masashige KUSUNOKI.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following clans claimed to be the descendants of Yamato-Genji: the Uno clan from Yamato Province, starting from the above-mentioned Chikaharu; the Hijikata clan of Katsuhisa HIJIKATA, who served Nobukatsu ODA; the Kumabe clan of Higo Province; the Ishikawa clan of Mutsu Province; the Takagi clan of Mikawa Province; and Hikoshichi OMORI of Iyo Province, who is believed to have slain Masashige KUSUNOKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 SuperTTS(id:221889), Andee(id:20421), 越中掾(id:149423), BAKU(id:55205), 沢田(id:40580), 編集仁王(id:208160), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>