<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>蘭学</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rangaku (the study of Western sciences)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rangaku (the study of Western sciences)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rangaku (the study of Western sciences)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>蘭学（らんがく）は、江戸時代にオランダを通じて日本に入ってきたヨーロッパの学術・文化・技術の総称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rangaku is a general term for European art and science, culture and skills imported into Japan through the Netherlands in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rangaku is a general term for European art and science, culture and skills imported into Japan through the Netherlands in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rangaku is a general term for European art and science, culture and skills imported into Japan through the Netherlands in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>蘭学の先駆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Early pioneers of Rangaku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Early pioneers of Rangaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Early pioneers of Rangaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>先駆者としては、肥前国長崎生まれの西川如見がおり、長崎で見聞した海外事情を通商関係の観点から記述した『華夷通商考』を著した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the pioneers, Joken NISHIKAWA from Nagasaki, Hizen Province wrote &quot;Kaitsushoko&quot; (Considerations on commerce with foreign countries) which described oveeseas circumstances he learned in Nagasaki from the viewpoint of trade relations.</e>
<cmt>華夷通商考=&quot;Kaitsushoko&quot; (Considerations on commerce with foreign countries)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the pioneers, Joken NISHIKAWA from Nagasaki, Hizen Province wrote &quot;Kaitsushoko&quot; (Considerations on commerce with foreign countries) which described oveeseas circumstances he learned in Nagasaki from the viewpoint of trade relations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the pioneers, Joken NISHIKAWA from Nagasaki, Hizen Province wrote &quot;Kaitsushoko&quot; (Considerations on commerce with foreign countries) which described overseas circumstances he learned in Nagasaki from the viewpoint of trade relations.</e>
<cmt>overseasスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>かれはまた、天文・暦算を林吉右衛門門下の小林義信に学んでおり、その学説は中国の天文学説を主としながらもヨーロッパ天文学説についても深い理解を寄せていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also learned astronomy and calendar from Yoshinobu KOBAYASHI, and his theory, based on Chinese astronomy though, showed great understanding of European astronomy as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also learned astronomy and calendar from Yoshinobu KOBAYASHI, and his theory, based on Chinese astronomy though, showed great understanding of European astronomy as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also learned astronomy and calendar from Yoshinobu KOBAYASHI, and his theory, based on Chinese astronomy though, showed great understanding of European astronomy as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>蘭学の興隆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prosperity of Rangaku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prosperity of Rangaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prosperity of Rangaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>通詞によって学ばれ始め、新井白石が『西洋紀聞』で開明的な海外理解を示し、徳川吉宗が漢訳蘭書の輸入禁止を緩和し、青木昆陽、野呂元丈に蘭語学習を命じ、実学を奨励したのちに盛んになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, interpreters began to study Rangaku, and Hakuseki ARAI demonstrated the enlightened understanding of overseas circumstances in his book &quot;Seiyo kibun&quot; (Western Accounts), and then, Yoshimune TOKUGAWA relaxed the import ban on Chinese translations of Dutch documents, and told Konmei AOKI and Genjo NORO to study Dutch and promoted practical learning, and then, Rangaku started thriving.</e>
<cmt>西洋紀聞= &quot;Seiyo kibun&quot; (Western Accounts)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, interpreters began to study Rangaku, and Hakuseki ARAI demonstrated the enlightened understanding of overseas circumstances in his book &quot;Seiyo kibun&quot; (Western Accounts), and then, Yoshimune TOKUGAWA relaxed the import ban on Chinese translations of Dutch documents, and told Konmei AOKI and Genjo NORO to study Dutch and promoted practical learning, which eventually allowed Rangaku to thrive.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, interpreters began to study Rangaku, and Hakuseki ARAI demonstrated the enlightened understanding of overseas circumstances in his book &quot;Seiyo kibun&quot; (Western Accounts), and then, Yoshimune TOKUGAWA relaxed the import ban on Chinese translations of Dutch documents, and told Konmei AOKI and Genjo NORO to study Dutch and promoted practical learning, which eventually allowed Rangaku to thrive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>江戸時代も後半にさしかかると島津重豪をはじめ、財力ある西国大名の中にも蘭癖大名と呼ばれるほど蘭学に傾倒した者が現れ、その支援によって蘭学がいっそう振興した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the latter half of the Edo period, some wealthy Saigoku Daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in western Japan) including Shigehide SHIMAZU who were so enthusiastic about Rangaku as to be called Ranheki daimyo (daimyo that affects anything Dutch) appeared, and then, Rangaku further developed with the support from those daimyo.</e>
<cmt>蘭癖大名=Ranheki daimyo (daimyo that affects anything Dutch) 定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the latter half of the Edo period, some wealthy Saigoku Daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in western Japan) including Shigehide SHIMAZU were so enthusiastic about Rangaku as to be called Ranheki daimyo (daimyo that affects anything Dutch), and then, Rangaku further developed with the support from these daimyo.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the latter half of the Edo period, some wealthy Saigoku Daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in western Japan) including Shigehide SHIMAZU were so enthusiastic about Rangaku as to be called Ranheki daimyo (daimyo that affects anything Dutch), and then, Rangaku further developed with the support from these daimyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>田沼時代の1774年には、杉田玄白・前野良沢らがオランダの医学書の『ターヘル・アナトミア』を訳して『解体新書』として刊行、志筑忠雄はニュートン力学を研究し、『暦象新書』として訳した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1774 during Tanuma period (when Okitsugu TANUMA led the bakufu), Genpaku SUGITA, Ryotaku MAENO and others translated a Dutch medical textbook, &quot;Ontleedkundige Tafelen&quot; into Japanese and published as &quot;Kaitai Shinsho&quot; (New Book of Anatomy), and Tadao SHIBA studied Newtonian mechanics and published the translation, &quot;Rekisho Shinsho&quot; (New Writings on Calendrical Phenomena).</e>
<cmt>暦象新書=&quot;Rekisho Shinsho&quot; (New Writings on Calendrical Phenomena). 定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1774 during Tanuma period (when Okitsugu TANUMA led the bakufu), Genpaku SUGITA, Ryotaku MAENO and others translated a Dutch medical textbook, &quot;Ontleedkundige Tafelen&quot; into Japanese and published as &quot;Kaitai Shinsho&quot; (New Book of Anatomy), and Tadao SHIBA studied Newtonian mechanics and published the translation, &quot;Rekisho Shinsho&quot; (New Writings on Calendrical Phenomena).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1774 during Tanuma period (when Okitsugu TANUMA led the bakufu), Genpaku SUGITA, Ryotaku MAENO and others translated a Dutch medical textbook, &quot;Ontleedkundige Tafelen&quot; into Japanese and published as &quot;Kaitai Shinsho&quot; (New Book of Anatomy), and Tadao SHIZUKI studied Newtonian mechanics and published the translation, &quot;Rekisho Shinsho&quot; (New Writings on Calendrical Phenomena).</e>
<cmt>志筑忠雄→Tadao SHIZUKI [http://kotobank.jp/word/%E5%BF%97%E7%AD%91%E5%BF%A0%E9%9B%84]</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>平賀源内は蘭学全般を学び、エレキテルの修理や寒暖計などを発明した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gennai HIRAGA learned Rangaku in general and fixed Erekiteru (a hand-operated electric generator) and invented such things as thermometer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gennai HIRAGA learned Rangaku in general and fixed Erekiteru (a hand-operated electric generator) and made inventions such as the thermometer.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gennai HIRAGA learned Rangaku in general and fixed Erekiteru (a hand-operated electric generator) and made inventions such as the thermometer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>出羽国の久保田藩では、源内の蘭画指南により秋田蘭画が興隆をみた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kubota Domain in Dewa Province, under Gennai&apos;s guidance on Ranga (Western painting), Akita Ranga flourished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kubota Domain in Dewa Province, under Gennai&apos;s guidance on Ranga (Western painting), Akita Ranga flourished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kubota Domain, Dewa Province, under Gennai&apos;s guidance on Ranga (Western painting), Akita Ranga flourished.</e>
<cmt>inをコンマに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>幕府天文方では世界地図の翻訳事業がなされ、1810年『新訂万国全図』を刊行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bakufu Tenmonkata (officers in charge of astronomy) started translating maps of the world, and published &quot;Shintei Bankokuzenzu&quot; (A revised World Map) in 1810.</e>
<cmt>新訂万国全図=&quot;Shintei Bankokuzenzu&quot; (A revised World Map)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bakufu Tenmonkata (officers in charge of astronomy) started translating maps of the world, and published &quot;Shintei Bankokuzenzu&quot; (A revised World Map) in 1810.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bakufu Tenmonkata (officers in charge of astronomy) started translating maps of the world, and published &quot;Shintei Bankokuzenzu&quot; (A revised World Map) in 1810.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>伊勢国の商人である大黒屋光太夫は1782年に漂流してアリューシャン列島からロシアへ渡り、10数年を経て帰国を果たした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1782, Kodayu DAIKOKUYA, a merchant in Ise Province, drifted and went to Russia via the Aleutian Islands, and returned to Japan ten years later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1782, Kodayu DAIKOKUYA, a merchant in Ise Province, drifted and went to Russia via the Aleutian Islands, and returned to Japan ten years later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1782, Kodayu DAIKOKUYA, a merchant in Ise Province, drifted and went to Russia via the Aleutian Islands, and returned to Japan ten years later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>彼の豊富な海外知識は桂川甫周が『北槎聞略』としてまとめ、蘭学発展のための刺激にもなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His rich knowledge of overseas was organized by Hoshu KATSURAGAWA into the book titled &quot;Hokusa bunryaku&quot; (Stories about Russia Told by a Repatriated Drifter)</e>
<cmt>北槎聞略=&quot;Hokusa bunryaku&quot; (Stories about Russia Told by a Repatriated Drifter)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His rich knowledge of overseas was organized by Hoshu KATSURAGAWA into the book titled &quot;Hokusa bunryaku&quot; (Stories about Russia Told by a Repatriated Drifter)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His rich knowledge of overseas was organized by Hoshu KATSURAGAWA into the book titled &quot;Hokusa bunryaku&quot; (Stories about Russia Told by a Repatriated Drifter) and encouraged the development of Rangaku.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>辞書としては、ハルマの『蘭仏辞書』をもとにして、1796年に日本最初の蘭和辞典が稲村三伯・宇田川玄随らによって編纂され1798年『ハルマ和解』として刊行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for dictionaries, based on Halma&apos;s &quot;Dutch-French Dictionary&quot;, the first Dutch-Japanese dictionary in Japan was compiled by Sanpaku INAMURA, Genzui UDAGAWA and others in 1796 and published as &quot;Haruma wage&quot; (the Japanese Edition of Halma&apos;s Dictionary&quot; in 1798..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for dictionaries, based on Halma&apos;s &quot;Dutch-French Dictionary&quot;, the first Dutch-Japanese dictionary in Japan was compiled by Sanpaku INAMURA, Genzui UDAGAWA and others in 1796 and published as &quot;Haruma wage&quot; (the Japanese Edition of Halma&apos;s Dictionary&quot; in 1798..</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for dictionaries, based on Halma&apos;s &quot;Dutch-French Dictionary,&quot; the first Dutch-Japanese dictionary in Japan was compiled by Sanpaku INAMURA, Genzui UDAGAWA and others in 1796 and published as &quot;Haruma wage&quot; (the Japanese Edition of Halma&apos;s Dictionary&quot; in 1798.</e>
<cmt>コンマの位置を訂正しました。不要なピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>さらに1833年には大部の『ドゥーフ・ハルマ』が完成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, the voluminous &quot;Doeff-Halma Dictionary&quot; was completed in 1833</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, the voluminous &quot;Doeff-Halma Dictionary&quot; was completed in 1833</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, the voluminous &quot;Doeff-Halma Dictionary&quot; was completed in 1833.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>蘭学受難の時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Trying times for Rangaku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Trying times for Rangaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Trying times for Rangaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>蘭学興隆に伴い、幕府は高橋景保の建議を容れ、1811年に天文方に蛮書和解御用を設けて洋書翻訳をさせたが、これは未完に終わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Rangaku flourished, bakufu adopted a proposal by Kageyasu TAKAHASHI, and established Bansho-wage Goyo (Government Office for Translation of Barbarian Books) and made them translate foreign books, but the project was left unfinished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Rangaku flourished, bakufu adopted a proposal by Kageyasu TAKAHASHI, and established Bansho-wage Goyo (Government Office for Translation of Barbarian Books) and made them translate foreign books, but the project was left unfinished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Rangaku flourished, bakufu adopted a proposal by Kageyasu TAKAHASHI, and established Bansho-wage Goyo (Government Office for Translation of Barbarian Books) and made them translate foreign books, but the project was left unfinished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>文政年間にはフィリップ・フランツ・フォン・シーボルトが日本を訪れ、長崎の郊外に鳴滝塾を開いて高野長英や小関三英などの門下生を教えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Bunsei era, Philipp Franz von Siebold came to Japan and founded his school, Narutaki-juku in the suburbs of Nagasaki and taught pupils including Choei TAKANO and Sanei KOSEKI.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Bunsei era, Philipp Franz von Siebold came to Japan and founded his school, Narutaki-juku in the suburbs of Nagasaki and taught pupils including Choei TAKANO and Sanei KOSEKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Bunsei era, Philipp Franz von SIEBOLD came to Japan and founded his school, Narutaki-juku in the suburbs of Nagasaki and taught pupils including Choei TAKANO and Sanei KOSEKI.</e>
<cmt>SIEBOLDに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>一方、外国からの開国要求を警戒した江戸幕府により、政治・思想面では抑圧が加わり、シーボルト事件、蛮社の獄などの弾圧事件が起こり、続いて蘭書翻訳取締令が出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One the other hand, the Edo bakufu, on the alert for foreign countries calling for the opening of Japan, started to suppress political and ideological activities, and crackdowns such as Siebold Incident and Bansha no goku (Imprisonment of scholars of Western learning) took place, which were followed by the order to restrict translation of foreign books.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the Edo bakufu, on the alert for foreign countries calling for the opening of Japan, started to suppress political and ideological activities, and crackdowns such as Siebold Incident and Bansha no goku (Imprisonment of scholars of Western learning) took place, which were followed by orders to restrict translation of foreign books.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the Edo bakufu, on the alert for foreign countries calling for the opening of Japan, started to suppress political and ideological activities, and crackdowns such as Siebold Incident and Bansha no goku (Imprisonment of scholars of Western learning) took place, which were followed by orders to restrict translation of foreign books.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>洋学へ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yogaku (Western studies)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yogaku (Western studies)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yogaku (Western studies)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>幕末には日本も開国を余儀なくされて英語による英学、ドイツ語による獨逸学などの新たな学問が流入するようになった</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of the Edo period, Japan was forced to open up to the West, and new learning such as German studies in the German language flew into Japan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of the Edo period, Japan was forced to open up to the West, and new learning such as German studies in the German language flew into Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of the Edo period, Japan was forced to open up to the West, and new learning such as German studies in the German language flew into Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>そのために、オランダ以外の欧米諸国から到来した学術をまとめて洋学（ようがく）と呼ぶようになるのが一般的となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, arts and sciences from Western countries other than the Netherlands were generally called Yogaku (Western learning).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, arts and sciences from Western countries other than the Netherlands were generally called Yogaku (Western learning).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, arts and sciences from Western countries other than the Netherlands were generally called Yogaku (Western learning).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>高島秋帆の西洋砲術、江川英龍（太郎左衛門）の韮山反射炉、勝海舟の長崎海軍伝習所など、幕府洋学は軍事的実学性の強いものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bakufu Yogaku such as Western gunnery of Shuhan TAKAHASHI, Nirayama Reverberatory furnace of Hidetatsu (Tarozaemon) EGAWA, and Kaigun Denshu-sho (The Nagasaki Naval Training Center) of Kaishu KATSU were highly practical for military purposes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bakufu Yogaku such as Western gunnery of Shuhan TAKAHASHI, Nirayama Reverberatory furnace of Hidetatsu (Tarozaemon) EGAWA, and Kaigun Denshu-sho (The Nagasaki Naval Training Center) of Kaishu KATSU were highly practical for military purposes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bakufu Yogaku such as Western gunnery of Shuhan TAKASHIMA, Nirayama Reverberatory furnace of Hidetatsu (Tarozaemon) EGAWA, and Kaigun Denshu-sho (The Nagasaki Naval Training Center) of Kaishu KATSU were highly practical for military purposes.</e>
<cmt>高島秋帆→Shuhan TAKASHIMA 訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>蛮書和解御用は、外交文書の翻訳にも当たるようになり、洋学所、1858年設置の蕃書調所と改編される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bansho-wage Goyo started to translate diplomatic documents and was renamed Yogakusho (Institute of Foreign Study), and in 1858, it was reorganized as Bansho shirabesho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bansho-wage Goyo started to translate diplomatic documents and was renamed Yogakusho (Institute of Foreign Study), and in 1858, it was reorganized as Bansho shirabesho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bansho-wage Goyo started to translate diplomatic documents and was renamed Yogakusho (Institute of Foreign Study), and in 1858, it was reorganized as Bansho shirabesho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>洋学研究・教育機関としての蕃書調所は、1862年（文久2）には対象言語をオランダ語から、英語などに拡大した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bansho shirabesho as an institute for studying and educating Western learning increased its object language to include English and other languages in addition to Dutch.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bansho shirabesho as an institute for studying and educating Western learning increased its object language to include English and other languages in addition to Dutch.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bansho shirabesho as an institute for studying and educating Western learning increased its object language to include English and other languages in addition to Dutch in 1862.</e>
<cmt>in 1862補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>1863年に開成所と改称、幕府瓦解により明治新政府に受け継がれ、のちの東京大学等につながる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was renamed Kaiseijo and changed hands to the new Meiji government after the fall of the bakufu and led to the University of Tokyo and other institutes later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was renamed Kaiseijo and changed hands to the new Meiji government after the fall of the bakufu and led to the University of Tokyo and other institutes later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was renamed Kaiseijo in 1863 and changed hands to the new Meiji government after the fall of the bakufu and led to the University of Tokyo and other institutes later.</e>
<cmt>in 1863補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>また諸藩でも、薩摩藩の開成所、集成館や、佐賀藩の蘭学寮設置や反射炉の建設など、独自の洋学が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Several domains practiced unique Yogaku, such as Kaiseijo and Shuseikan in Satsuma Domain, and establishment of Rangakuryo (house of Rangaku) and construction of reverberatory furnace in Saga Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Several domains practiced unique Yogaku, such as Kaiseijo and Shuseikan in Satsuma Domain, and establishment of Rangakuryo (house of Rangaku) and construction of a reverberatory furnace in Saga Domain.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Several domains practiced unique Yogaku, such as Kaiseijo and Shuseikan in Satsuma Domain, and establishment of Rangakuryo (house of Rangaku) and construction of a reverberatory furnace in Saga Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>蘭学塾</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rangaku Juku (Institutes for Rangaku)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rangaku Juku (Institutes for Rangaku)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rangaku Juku (Institutes for Rangaku)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>江戸　大槻玄沢の芝蘭堂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shiran-do of Gentaku OTSUKI in Edo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shiran-do of Gentaku OTSUKI in Edo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shiran-do of Gentaku OTSUKI in Edo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>大坂　緒方洪庵の適塾</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Teki-juku of Koan OGATA in Osaka</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Teki-juku of Koan OGATA in Osaka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Teki-juku of Koan OGATA in Osaka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>長崎　シーボルトの鳴滝塾</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Narutaki-juku of Siebold in Nagasaki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Narutaki-juku of Siebold in Nagasaki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Narutaki-juku of Siebold in Nagasaki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>佐倉　佐藤泰然の順天堂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Juntendo of Taizen SATO in SAKURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Juntendo of Taizen SATO in SAKURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juntendo of Taizen SATO in Sakura.</e>
<cmt>Sakuraに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Ligar(id:12623), Izayohi(id:13095), Oxhop(id:2551), Straysheep(id:42448), 浩(id:70121), Ceridwen(id:36889), MASA(id:2399), Bletilla(id:38919), Naohiro19(id:60119), Lupinoid(id:68), Syatex(id:1501), RekishiEJ(id:43355), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Orcano(id:96391), Tribot(id:186681), Greenland4(id:114494), Escarbot(id:59151), 酢溜まり氷(id:65987), でここ(id:9565), VolkovBot(id:105371), Goki(id:7107), Chlewbot(id:33904), Thijssie!bot(id:111619), BotMultichill(id:132395), 江戸ラー(id:30154), ФК Партизан(id:81003), Dnssgh(id:118255), トホホ川(id:50502), こいつぅ(id:2105), 竹麦魚(id:11012), Edith(id:10112), Suisui(id:69), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>