<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>町役人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">machiyakunin (municipal official)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Machiyakunin (Municipal Official)</e>
<cmt>頭文字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Machiyakunin (Municipal Official)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>町役人（ちょうやくにん・まちやくにん）とは、江戸時代都市部における行政的な組織 (社会科学)である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Machiyakunin refers to an administrative organization in urban areas during the Edo period (social science).</e>
<cmt>・・・（社会科学）である、という言葉は文章全体についての補足のように読めるので文末にそのまま訳をつけました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Machiyakunin,&quot; also pronounced as &quot;choyakunin,&quot; refers to an administrative organization in urban areas which existed during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>用語の説明とわかるように引用符を追加、「ちょうやくにん」の読みを追加、organizationを先行詞とする関係代名詞を追加、「（社会科学）」はリンク先の用語なので削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Machiyakunin,&quot; also pronounced as &quot;choyakunin,&quot; refers to an administrative organization in urban areas which existed during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>町役人の名称や組織については地域によって異なり、江戸では江戸町役人以下町名主などが置かれ、大阪では総年寄以下町年寄などが置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its name and organization differs from region to region; in fact, in Edo, the names such as town headman lower than Edo-cho government official and, in Osaka, those of town toshiyori (head) lower than toshiyori general were used, respectively.</e>
<cmt>toshiyoriの説明として（　）を補足した。江戸町役人以下町名主と総年寄以下町年寄の正式な訳は不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Names for this position and their organizations differed from region to region; in fact, they had chonanushi (town headman) as well as machiyakunin in Edo, and in Osaka, they had similar positions called sodoshiyori and machidoshiyori.</e>
<cmt>全体的に書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Names for this position and their organizations differed from region to region; in fact, they had chonanushi (town headman) as well as machiyakunin in Edo, and in Osaka, they had similar positions called sodoshiyori and machidoshiyori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>そのほか、地域によって町の代表者を町代、検断などと呼ぶこともあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, representative of a town was called chodai, kendan or such in some regions.</e>
<cmt>町代と検断については呼び方のことを述べているので、意味の説明補足していません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, a representative of a town was called chodai, kendan, or such in some regions.</e>
<cmt>冠詞を追加しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, a representative of a town was called chodai, kendan, or such in some regions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また、人数や任期についても地域やその都市によって異なり、特に任期については、数年で交代するところから世襲によるところもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, each city had its own number of officials and term of office, and, especially when it comes to term, they were replaced every few years in some cities while by heredity in other cities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, each city had its own rule about the number of officials and their term of office, and as for the term of office, they were replaced every few years in some regions or cities while the position was hereditary in some other cities.</e>
<cmt>全体的に書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, each city had its own rule about the number of officials and their term of office, and as for the term of office, they were replaced every few years in some regions or cities while the position was hereditary in some other cities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>町役人の職務については、奉行所からの触書を町民に知らせたり、町民からの訴えを奉行所に取り次いだりすることなどであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its duties included informing town people of furegaki (bakufu orders) from a magistrate&apos;s office and submitting people&apos;s appeals to the office.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The duty of a machiyakunin included informing town people of furegaki (bakufu [Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun] orders) from a magistrate&apos;s office and submitting people&apos;s appeals to the office.</e>
<cmt>「町役人の職務」の箇所を変更しました。「幕府」の説明を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The duty of a machiyakunin included informing town people of furegaki (bakufu [Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun] orders) from a magistrate&apos;s office and submitting people&apos;s appeals to the office.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>なお、身分については士分ではなく、町民の身分であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It belonged to not samurai class but townsman.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were townsmen and they were not in the samurai class.</e>
<cmt>全体的に書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were townsmen and they were not in the samurai class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 江口磐世☆(id:168037), 与左衛門(id:159462), Law soma(id:45202), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>