<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>光悦村</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koetsu mura (Koetsu Village)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koetsu mura (Koetsu Village)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koetsu mura (Koetsu Village)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>光悦村（こうえつむら）は、本阿弥光悦らが営んだ江戸時代初期の芸術村。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koetsu mura was an art village managed by Koetsu HONAMI in the early Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koetsu mura was a village that flourished in arts and crafts, and managed by Koetsu HONAMI during the early Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koetsu mura was a village that flourished in arts and crafts, and managed by Koetsu HONAMI during the early Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>本阿弥光悦が、江戸幕府から与えられた、京都の鷹ヶ峰の地に、さまざまな分野の、町衆の文化人や職人、芸術家たちを集めて、独自の文化を築きあげた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koetsu HONAMI gathered artisans and artists from machi-shu (towns people) in various fields in a land of Takagamine, Kyoto, given from Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and built up a unique culture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koetsu HONAMI gathered artisans and artists from machi-shu (towns people) if various fields in in Takagamine, Kyoto, which he received from the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and subsequently build a unique culture.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koetsu HONAMI gathered artisans and artists from machi-shu (towns people) of various fields in Takagamine, Kyoto, which he received from the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and subsequently build a unique culture.</e>
<cmt>if→ofin in→in</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>光悦の屋敷跡は光悦寺（京都市北区鷹峯光悦町）といわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The site of the residence of Koetsu is said to be Koetsu-ji Temple (Takagaminekoetsu-cho, Kita Ward, Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The site of the Koetsus&apos; residence is said to be Koetsu-ji Temple (Takagaminekoetsu-cho, Kita Ward, Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The site of the Koetsus&apos; residence is said to be Koetsu-ji Temple (Takagaminekoetsu-cho, Kita Ward, Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 浩(id:70121), ぱむ(id:24323), Chuta(id:10457), UMBRO(id:100484), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>