<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>私軍</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Watakushiikusa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Watakushiikusa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Watakushiikusa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>私軍（わたくしいくさ・私戦（しせん））とは、近世以前の日本において太政官符や宣旨、幕府の命令などの公的命令によらずして、敵討や自力救済のために行われる小規模な武力行使・戦闘行為。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Watakushiikusa (also called shisen [private warfare]) is a small-scale military/battle action which was conducted for Katakiuchi (revenge) or self-help without an official order such as Daijokanpu (the official documents of the Daijokan, the office of the supreme political leader), senji (imperial decree) or order from bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) in Japan before the early-modern times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Watakushiikusa (also called shisen [private warfare]) is a small-scale military/battle conducted in Japan before the early-modern period for Katakiuchi (revenge) or for self-preservation, without an official order such as Daijokanpu (official documents of Daijokan, which is the office of the supreme political leader), senji (imperial decree) or an order from bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Watakushiikusa (also called shisen [private warfare]) is a small-scale military/battle conducted in Japan before the early-modern period for Katakiuchi (revenge) or for self-preservation, without an official order such as Daijokanpu (official documents of Daijokan, which is the office of the supreme political leader), senji (imperial decree) or an order from bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>今日の歴史学では、「私戦」と呼ばれるのが一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In today&apos;s history it is generally called &apos;shisen (private warfare)&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contemporary historiography it is generally called &apos;shisen&apos; (private warfare).</e>
<cmt>contemporary historiographyに修正しました。括弧をクォーテーションマークの外に出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contemporary historiography it is generally called &apos;shisen&apos; (private warfare).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>西欧におけるフェーデと近い概念があると言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said to be a concept close to Fehde in the western world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said to be a concept close to Fehde in the western world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said to be a concept close to Fehde in the western world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>武士階層は、所領の防衛などのために対立相手に戦いをしかけることがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were cases where a person of the samurai class waged a battle against his opponent for the defense of his shoryo (territory).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were cases where a person of the samurai class waged a battle against his opponent for the defense of his territory.</e>
<cmt>shoryo を削除し () をはずしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were cases where a person of the samurai class waged a battle against his opponent for the defense of his territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>鎌倉時代にはこうした意図的な戦闘行為を故戦（こせん）、それに対する防衛を防戦（ぼうせん）と呼び、これらを一括して「故戦防戦」と呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kamakura period these deliberate conducts of hostilities were called kosen (intentional war) and the actions for defense were called bosen (defensive war), and they were collectively called &apos;kosen-bosen&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kamakura period this deliberate conduct of hostilities was called kosen (intentional war) and defensive action was called bosen (defensive war), and they were collectively known as &apos;kosen-bosen&apos;.</e>
<cmt>数か所修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kamakura period this deliberate conduct of hostilities was called kosen (intentional war) and defensive action was called bosen (defensive war), and they were collectively known as &apos;kosen-bosen&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>中央権力の威信が低下した時代には、所領紛争を法的手段で解決する方法が無力であったために、代わりに自力救済の一環としてこうした戦いがしばしば行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the periods when the dignity of central authority was lowered, legal means to resolve territorial disputes were ineffective, and instead these wars were often waged as a part of self-help.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During periods when the dignity of central authority declined, legal means to resolve territorial disputes were ineffective, and instead these wars were often waged as a form of self-preservation.</e>
<cmt>In を During に修正しました。was を削除しました。他数か所修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During periods when the dignity of central authority declined, legal means to resolve territorial disputes were ineffective, and instead these wars were often waged as a form of self-preservation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>朝廷や幕府はこうした行為を禁じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chotei (Imperial Court) and bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) prohibited these actions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Court and bakufu prohibited these actions.</e>
<cmt>Chotei を削除し、括弧をはずしました。Bakufu は初出ではないので説明は削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Court and bakufu prohibited these actions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>平安時代の朝廷は私軍・私戦によるに対しては一切の黙殺と不干渉の措置を取った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The chotei in the Heian period deliberately ignored all the watakushiikusa and shisen, and adopted a noninterference policy against them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Court in the Heian period deliberately ignored all the watakushiikusa and shisen, and adopted a noninterference policy in relation to them.</e>
<cmt>The chotei を The Imperial Court に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Court in the Heian period deliberately ignored all the watakushiikusa and shisen, and adopted a noninterference policy in relation to them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>平将門の乱において平将門が国司襲撃という公に対する反逆行為に出るまで鎮圧を行わなかったこと（逆に私戦を行って秩序を乱している点では対立する平貞盛なども同一であり、将門の乱初期においては将門に貞盛追討が命じられたこともある）や後三年の役において源義家の配下に恩賞を与えなかった事がその例である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the examples is that the war of TAIRA no Masakado was not suppressed until TAIRA no Masakado staged a rebellious act of attacking the authority who was Kokushi (provincial governor) (although TAIRA no Sadamori on the opposing side was similar in the respect of disturbing the order and at the beginning of the Masakado&apos;s war he was ordered to hunt down and kill Sadamori), and another example is that, for the Go Sannen no Eki (Later Three-Year Campaign), Onsho (reward grants) were not given to the subordinates of MINAMOTO no Yoshiie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the examples is that TAIRA no Masakado&apos;s War was not suppressed until TAIRA no Masakado staged a rebellious act attacking a provincial governor (although TAIRA no Sadamori on the opposing side was similar in that he had disturbed the peace and at the beginning of Masakado&apos;s War he had been ordered to hunt down and kill Sadamori), and another example is that, for the Go Sannen no Eki (Later Three-Year Campaign), reward grants were not given to the subordinates of MINAMOTO no Yoshiie.</e>
<cmt>the war of TAIRA no Masakado を TAIRA no Masakado&apos;s War に修正しました。of を削除しました。War の語頭を大文字にしました。was ordered を had been ordered に修正しました。Onsho を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the examples is that TAIRA no Masakado&apos;s War was not suppressed until TAIRA no Masakado staged a rebellious act attacking a provincial governor (although TAIRA no Sadamori on the opposing side was similar in that he had disturbed the peace and at the beginning of Masakado&apos;s War he had been ordered to hunt down and kill Sadamori), and another example is that, for the Go Sannen no Eki (Later Three-Year Campaign), reward grants were not given to the subordinates of MINAMOTO no Yoshiie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その後、武家政権である鎌倉幕府が成立すると、裁判制度の充実を図るとともにこうした故戦防戦を積極的に抑制する方針に転じ、延慶 (日本)3年（1310年）に刈田狼藉を犯罪と規定するなど私軍・私戦の原因を絶つ政策を採った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, when Kamakura bakufu which was a samurai government was established, a trial system was enhanced and at the same time the active suppression of such kosen-bosen began to be enforced, and the policy of eliminating the causes of watakushiikusa and shisen by means of stipulating Karita-rozeki (to reap rice illegally) as crimes was adopted in1310.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, when Kamakura bakufu (a samurai government) was established, the active suppression of such kosen-bosen came to be enforced in addition to the enhancement of the &apos;trial system,&apos; and a policy of eliminating the causes of watakushiikusa and shisen by means of making Karita-rozeki (to reap rice illegally) a crime was adopted in 1310.</e>
<cmt>began を came に修正しました。途中、文を入れ替えました。Trial system を現在のものと区別化するために &apos;&apos;でとじました。他数か所修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, when Kamakura bakufu (a samurai government) was established, the active suppression of such kosen-bosen came to be enforced in addition to the enhancement of the &apos;trial system,&apos; and a policy of eliminating the causes of watakushiikusa and shisen by means of making Karita-rozeki (to reap rice illegally) a crime was adopted in 1310.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>続いて室町幕府も貞和2年（1346年）を皮切りに度々出され、観応3年（1352年）には、防戦を行った者も理由の如何を問わずに処罰の対象とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequently, starting in 1346 the policy was frequently issued by the Muromachi bakufu, and in 1352 even those who staged defensive wars were called for criminal penalty regardless of the reasons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, starting in 1346 such policies were frequently put in place by the Muromachi bakufu, and in 1352 even those who staged defensive wars were given criminal penalties regardless of their reasons.</e>
<cmt>the policy was frequently issued を such policies were frequently put in place に修正しました。called for を given に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, starting in 1346 such policies were frequently put in place by the Muromachi bakufu, and in 1352 even those who staged defensive wars were given criminal penalties regardless of their reasons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)の永正11年（1514年）と永正13年（1516年）にも同様の禁令が出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Sengoku period, similar bans were issued in 1514 and 1516.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Sengoku period, similar bans were issued in 1514 and 1516.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Sengoku period, similar bans were issued in 1514 and 1516.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>永正13年の禁令は全国的に出され、故戦者が全所領没収ならば防戦者も所領の半分を没収され、更に故戦者が死刑にされた場合には防戦者に対しても全所領没収が課される事になっていた（もっとも、これによって処罰された戦国大名・国人領主などは皆無であったが）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ban issued in 1516 was nationwide, and to confiscate a half of the defender&apos;s territory if the whole territory of the kosen party (offender) is confiscated, and to confiscate the whole of the defender&apos;s territory if the kosen party is sentenced to death (although none of daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) and kokujin ryoshu (local samurai lord) were punished for this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ban in 1516 was issued nationwide; to confiscate half of the defender&apos;s territory if the whole territory of the offender was confiscated, and to confiscate the whole of the defender&apos;s territory if the offender was sentenced to death (although no Japanese territorial lords or local samurai lords were punished in this way).</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ban in 1516 was issued nationwide; to confiscate half of the defender&apos;s territory if the whole territory of the offender was confiscated, and to confiscate the whole of the defender&apos;s territory if the offender was sentenced to death (although no Japanese territorial lords or local samurai lords were punished in this way).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>なお、防戦に対する処罰規定は戦国大名の分国法などにおける喧嘩両成敗の元となったとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, there is a theory that the law that penalized defenses is the origin of Kenka Ryoseibai (in a quarrel both parties are to blame) stipulated in the bunkoku ho (provincial allotment law) of daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, there is a theory that the law penalizing defenses is the origin of the principle of Kenka Ryoseibai (in a quarrel, both parties are to blame), which was stipulated in bunkokuho (the law which individual Japanese territorial lords in the Sengoku period enforced in their own domain).</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, there is a theory that the law penalizing defenses is the origin of the principle of Kenka Ryoseibai (in a quarrel, both parties are to blame), which was stipulated in bunkokuho (the law which individual Japanese territorial lords in the Sengoku period enforced in their own domain).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>日本から私軍・私戦が一掃されるのは豊臣政権の惣無事令施行とその違反者に対する「公儀の軍勢による征伐」（小田原の陣・奥州仕置）によってこの方針の貫徹が行われて以後の事になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The complete elimination of watakushiikusa and shisen was accomplished only after the Toyotomi government&apos;s enforcement of sobuji rei (Peace edicts) and after this policy was carried through by &apos;the punitive expeditions of army of kogi (shogunate)&apos; (Odawara no Jin [The Siege of Odawara] and Oshu-shioki [repression of the Oshu District]).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The complete elimination of watakushiikusa and shisen was accomplished only after the Toyotomi government&apos;s enforcement of sobuji rei (Peace edicts) and after this policy was carried through by &apos;the punitive expeditions of shogunate&apos;s army&apos; (Odawara no Jin [the Siege of Odawara] and Oshu-shioki [the Repression of Oshu District]).</e>
<cmt>by 以降を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The complete elimination of watakushiikusa and shisen was accomplished only after the Toyotomi government&apos;s enforcement of sobuji rei (Peace edicts) and after this policy was carried through by &apos;the punitive expeditions of shogunate&apos;s army&apos; (Odawara no Jin [the Siege of Odawara] and Oshu-shioki [the Repression of Oshu District]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>