<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>赦律</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sharitsu (law on pardon)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sharitsu (law on pardon)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sharitsu (law on pardon)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>赦律（しゃりつ）とは、日本の幕末期の文久2年（1862年）に江戸幕府によって制定された恩赦に関する法令をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sharitsu is a law on pardon, which was enacted by the Edo Shogunate in 1862 during the last period of the Edo era in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sharitsu is a law on pardon, which was enacted by the Edo Shogunate in 1862 during the last period of the Edo era in Japan.</e>
<cmt>enacted byの間の不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sharitsu is a law on pardon, which was enacted by the Edo Shogunate in 1862 during the last period of the Edo era in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>ただし、法令自体の作成は嘉永4年（1851年）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The law itself however was drafted in 1851.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It should be noted, however, that the law had already been drafted in 1851.</e>
<cmt>ただしの訳を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It should be noted, however, that the law had already been drafted in 1851.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>恩赦についての規定は律令法以来、様々な法令に規定されてきたが、具体的な範囲や手続などを定めたの法令としては日本最初のものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ever since the Ritsuryo law, regulations on pardon were regulated by various laws, but this was the first time in Japan that concrete limits and procedures were decided by law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ever since the Ritsuryo law, various laws regulated pardons, but Sharitsu was the first law in Japan that specified limits and procedures of pardons.</e>
<cmt>regulations以下の訳を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ever since the Ritsuryo law, various laws regulated pardons, but Sharitsu was the first law in Japan that specified limits and procedures of pardons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経緯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Circumstances</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Circumstances</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Circumstances</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>江戸幕府において恩赦は征夷大将軍の大権に属して徳川将軍家や皇室などの慶事・凶事・法事などに際して行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo Shogunate the Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) had the supreme power to grant pardon. It was exercised, when either the Tokugawa Shogunate Family or the Imperial Family had an auspicious event, a calamity or held a Buddhist memorial service. It was then executed by the senior councilors (roju), the conference chamber (hyojosho) or the &quot;three municipal administrators&quot; (sanbugyo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo Shogunate the Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) had the supreme power to grant a pardon when either the Tokugawa Shogunate Family or the Imperial Family had an auspicious event, a calamity or held a Buddhist memorial service.</e>
<cmt>英文が3文になっていたので「一原文一訳文の例外対処」を適用しました。原文：「江戸幕府において恩赦は征夷大将軍の大権に属して徳川将軍家や皇室などの慶事・凶事・法事などに際して行われた。」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo Shogunate the Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) had the supreme power to grant a pardon when either the Tokugawa Shogunate Family or the Imperial Family had an auspicious event, a calamity or held a Buddhist memorial service.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>その実施には老中・評定所・三奉行がこれにあたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was then executed by the roju (senior councilors), hyojosho (conference chamber) or sanbugyo (three municipal administrators).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処、原文「その実施には老中・評定所・三奉行がこれにあたった。」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was then executed by the roju (senior councilors), hyojosho (conference chamber) or sanbugyo (three municipal administrators).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>更に徳川将軍家の法事を司った寛永寺・増上寺には恩赦の口添えの権限が与えられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore the temples Kanei-ji and Zojo-ji, which administered the memorial services of the Tokugawa Shogunate Family, obtained the authority to recommend pardon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore the temples Kanei-ji and Zojo-ji, which administered the memorial services of the Tokugawa Shogunate Family, were authorized to recommend a pardon.</e>
<cmt>obtained 以下の訳を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore the temples Kanei-ji and Zojo-ji, which administered the memorial services of the Tokugawa Shogunate Family, were authorized to recommend a pardon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし、恩赦そのものが濫発されたうえ、本来政治とは無関係である寛永寺や増上寺による口添えの存在、しかもその口添えは受刑者の家族しか出来ない事など（独身者には困難である）様々な問題を抱えており、更に個々の受刑者の恩赦の是非は評定所の個別の審議を経たためにその適用基準も曖昧であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But not only was pardon granted arbitrarily, the recommendations of these supposedly apolitical temples Kanei-ji and Zojo-ji, and that only the family of a convict could ask for a recommendation (an unmarried person was in trouble) was problematic in various ways and finally the propriety of each pardon for a convict had to go through individual deliberation at the conference chamber, where the applied criterions were obscure.</e>
<cmt>I translated 独身者 as unmarried, but I think it should be something like &quot;a person, who has no family&quot;</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This system had various problems, however, including that of pardons granted too frequently; of temples Kanei-ji and Zojo-ji that were supposedly apolitical were allowed to recommend pardons; of recommendations that only the family of a convict were allowed to ask for (thus it was hardly possible for convicts who had no relatives); and of obscure criteria for granting a pardon because the conference chamber discussed the propriety of each case separately.</e>
<cmt>全体的に書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This system had various problems, however, including that of pardons granted too frequently; of temples Kanei-ji and Zojo-ji that were supposedly apolitical were allowed to recommend pardons; of recommendations that only the family of a convict were allowed to ask for (thus it was hardly possible for convicts who had no relatives); and of obscure criteria for granting a pardon because the conference chamber discussed the propriety of each case separately.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>明和_(日本)9年の大火で評定所が焼失した時に恩赦に関する資料が失われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1772 the conference chamber (hyojosho) burned down in The Great Fire of Meiwa and all the materials on pardon were lost, in order to compensate the loss, records on pardon, which the Shogun&apos;s retainer of the conference chamber had collected in the Bunka period (1804-1818) were used under the name &quot;Taisharitsu&quot; as reference materials at the conference chamber, but that was not sufficient enough.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1772 the conference chamber (hyojosho) burned down in The Great Fire of Meiwa and all the documents on pardon were lost.</e>
<cmt>文章がつながっていないため、「一原文一訳文の例外対処」を適用しました。分割後の原文「明和9年の大火で評定所が焼失した時に恩赦に関する資料が失われた。」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1772 the conference chamber (hyojosho) burned down in The Great Fire of Meiwa and all the documents on pardon were lost.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>このため、これを補うために文化_(日本)年間に評定所の幕臣がまとめた恩赦の記録が『大赦律』という名称で評定所において参考資料として用いられたが十分なものではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to compensate the loss, the Shogun&apos;s retainers at the conference chamber complied the records on pardon collected in the Bunka period (1804-1818) into &quot;Taisharitsu&quot; and it was used as reference at the conference chamber, but it was not sufficient enough.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処分割後の原文「このため、これを補うために文化年間に評定所の幕臣がまとめた恩赦の記録が『大赦律』という名称で評定所において参考資料として用いられたが十分なものではなかった。」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to compensate the loss, the Shogun&apos;s retainers at the conference chamber complied the records on pardon collected in the Bunka period (1804-1818) into &quot;Taisharitsu&quot; and it was used as reference at the conference chamber, but it was not sufficient enough.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>そこで嘉永4年（1851年）に老中阿部正弘は寺社奉行脇坂安宅（龍野藩）・勘定奉行池田頼方・南町奉行遠山景元（金四郎）に命じて恩赦に関する公式な法令を制定することを命じたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1851 the senior councilor Masahiro ABE called commissioner of shrines and temples Yasuori WAKISAKA (Tatsuno domain), finance commissioner Yoritaka IKEDA and South Edo magistrate Kagemoto TOYAMA (Kinshiro) and ordered them to lay down an official law on pardon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1851 the senior councilor Masahiro ABE called commissioner of shrines and temples Yasuori WAKISAKA (Tatsuno domain), finance commissioner Yoritaka IKEDA and South Edo magistrate Kagemoto TOYAMA (Kinshiro) and ordered them to lay down an official law on pardon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1851 the senior councilor Masahiro ABE called commissioner of shrines and temples Yasuori WAKISAKA (Tatsuno domain), finance commissioner Yoritaka IKEDA and South Edo magistrate Kagemoto TOYAMA (Kinshiro) and ordered them to lay down an official law on pardon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>阿部の意向としては恩赦の公正かつ明確な基準を定めてその濫発を戒め、全ての受刑者にその道を開くことを目的としていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Abe aimed at establishing an impartial and precise standard in order to admonish the arbitrary granting and pave the way for all convicts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Abe aimed at establishing an impartial and precise standard in order to admonish the arbitrary granting and pave the way for an equivalent opportunity for all convicts to be granted a pardon.</e>
<cmt>文末に訳語を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Abe aimed at establishing an impartial and precise standard in order to admonish the arbitrary granting and pave the way for an equivalent opportunity for all convicts to be granted a pardon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>だが、当時の記録を見るともう一つの目的として公事方御定書にはない恩赦の法令を定める事によって同法の事実上の改正を意図していた事が知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One more intention can be known by looking at the records of that time: by establishing a law on pardon, he thought to actually revise the law of the Edo Shogunate, the Kujigata-osadamegaki (literally, &quot;book of rules for public officials&quot;).</e>
<cmt>I used two explanations of Kujigata-osadamegaki to make it clearer.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One more intention can be known by looking at the records of that time: by establishing a law on pardon, Abe intended to actually revise the law of the Edo Shogunate, the Kujigata-osadamegaki (literally, &quot;book of rules for public officials&quot;).</e>
<cmt>「he thought to」をAbe intended toに訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One more intention can be known by looking at the records of that time: by establishing a law on pardon, Abe intended to actually revise the law of the Edo Shogunate, the Kujigata-osadamegaki (literally, &quot;book of rules for public officials&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>元々江戸幕府の法令は戦国時代_(日本)の三河国松平氏の法令であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The law of the Edo Shogunate was originally the law of the Matsudaira clan of Mikawa Province from the Sengoku period. With the subjugation of the land by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA it developed into a law on a nationwide scale. Its content emphasized to suppress crimes by militaristic punishment and intimidation. Objectivism, which argues that crimes occur by accountability, was a strong factor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The law of the Edo Shogunate was originally the law of the Matsudaira clan of Mikawa Province from the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>複数の英文だったので「一原文一訳文の例外対処」を適用しました。分割後の原文「元々江戸幕府の法令は戦国時代の三河国松平氏の法令であった。」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The law of the Edo Shogunate was originally the law of the Matsudaira clan of Mikawa Province from the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>それが徳川家康の天下平定とともに全国規模の法令に発展したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the subjugation of the land by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA it developed into a law on a nationwide scale.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」を適用しました。分割後の原文「それが、徳川家康の天下平定とともに全国規模の法令に発展したものである。」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the subjugation of the land by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA it developed into a law on a nationwide scale.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>その内容も武断的で厳罰と威嚇をもって犯罪を抑圧する事に重点が置かれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its content was based on militarism that emphasized to suppress crimes by punishment and intimidation.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」を適用しました。分割後の原文「その内容も武断的で厳罰と威嚇をもって犯罪を抑圧する事に重点が置かれていた。」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its content was based on militarism that emphasized to suppress crimes by punishment and intimidation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>結果責任によって犯罪の成立が論じられる客観主義的な要素が強かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Objectivism, which judges a crime based on accountability, was a strong factor.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」を適用しました。分割後の原文「結果責任によって犯罪の成立が論じられる客観主義的な要素が強かった。」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Objectivism, which judges a crime based on accountability, was a strong factor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>このため、江戸幕府の刑罰は厳格に傾きがちであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is why punishments of the Edo Shogunate were inclined to be severe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is why punishments of the Edo Shogunate were inclined to be severe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That is why punishments of the Edo Shogunate were inclined to be severe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>しかも家康が用いた法令は祖法でありそれを改正する事自体が、家康と幕府を侮辱する反逆的行為であると考える儒教的・保守的な考え方もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The law of Ieyasu was the ancestral law, changing it could be regarded as a treasonable act, which insults Ieyasu and the Shogunate in the Confucian and conservative point of view. When the Kujigata-osadamegaki was enacted, it was partly moderated, but the law system of the Sengoku period was taken over unaltered till the last days of the Tokugawa Shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The law of Ieyasu was the ancestral law, changing it could be regarded as a treasonable act which insulted Ieyasu and the Shogunate in the Confucian and conservative point of view.</e>
<cmt>複数の英文だったので「一原文一訳文の例外対処」を適用しました。分割後の原文「しかも家康が用いた法令は祖法でありそれを改正する事自体が、家康と幕府を侮辱する反逆的行為であると考える儒教的・保守的な考え方もあった。」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The law of Ieyasu was the ancestral law, changing it could be regarded as a treasonable act which insulted Ieyasu and the Shogunate in the Confucian and conservative point of view.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>公事方御定書制定時に一部は緩和されたものの、戦国時代の法体系がそのまま幕末にまで持ち込まれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Kujigata-osadamegaki was enacted, it was partly moderated, but the law system of the Sengoku period was taken over unaltered till the last days of the Tokugawa Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」を適用しました。分割後の原文「公事方御定書制定時に一部は緩和されたものの、戦国時代の法体系がそのまま幕末にまで持ち込まれていた。」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Kujigata-osadamegaki was enacted, it was partly moderated, but the law system of the Sengoku period was taken over unaltered till the last days of the Tokugawa Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>阿部は改正を論じる自体が保守派の刺激をしかねない公事方御定書の改正を避け、恩赦という形式を用いて公事方御定書が定めた刑罰を減刑するという遠まわしな手法で結果的に公事方御定書の改正を図ろうとしたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Abe avoided a direct reform of the Kujigata-osadamegaki, as even a discussion about reforming it might stir up the conservatives, so he used pardon as a formality to reduce the penalties, which were provided in the Kujigata-osadamegaki and by using such a roundabout method he intended to reform the Kujigata-osadamegaki as a result.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Abe avoided a direct reform of the Kujigata-osadamegaki, as even a discussion about reforming it might stir up the conservatives, so he used pardon as a means of reducing the penalties provided in the Kujigata-osadamegaki, and by using such a roundabout method he intended to reform the Kujigata-osadamegaki as a result.</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースを削除しました。「as a formality to reduce the penalties, which were」の部分を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Abe avoided a direct reform of the Kujigata-osadamegaki, as even a discussion about reforming it might stir up the conservatives, so he used pardon as a means of reducing the penalties provided in the Kujigata-osadamegaki, and by using such a roundabout method he intended to reform the Kujigata-osadamegaki as a result.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="21">
<j>阿部の意向を受けた三人は「大赦律」などを参照にしつつも旧来の問題点を洗い出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On behalf of Abe the three men thoroughly examined customary controversial points while referring to the &quot;Taisharitsu&quot;. A scheme to mitigate actual punishments was incorporated, although former regulations on pardon remained as they were, but they were put together with conventional procedures in the hands of the council chamber. Juveniles younger than fifteen who were formerly given severe punishments like banishment including cases, where they were guilty only because of a relative&apos;s crime (enza) became eligible for pardon right away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On behalf of Abe the three men thoroughly examined customary controversial points while referring to the &quot;Taisharitsu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>複数の英文だったので「一原文一訳文の例外対処」を適用しました。分割後の原文「阿部の意向を受けた三人は「大赦律」などを参照にしつつも旧来の問題点を洗い出した。」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On behalf of Abe the three men thoroughly examined customary controversial points while referring to the &quot;Taisharitsu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>旧来の恩赦規定をそのまま残すものの、より儀式的なものとして手続の主体を評定所に置くとともに、旧来は縁座のケースも含めて15歳以下の未成年にも課されていた追放などの重罰については直ちに恩赦の対象とするなどの事実上の刑罰の緩和策が盛り込まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A scheme to mitigate actual punishments was incorporated, although former regulations on pardon remained as they were, but they were put together with conventional procedures in the hands of the council chamber, and Juveniles younger than fifteen who were formerly given severe punishments like banishment including cases where they were guilty only because of a relative&apos;s crime (enza) became eligible for pardon right away.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」を適用しました。分割後の原文「旧来の恩赦規定をそのまま残すものの、より儀式的なものとして手続の主体を評定所に置くとともに、旧来は縁座のケースも含めて15歳以下の未成年にも課されていた追放などの重罰については直ちに恩赦の対象とするなどの事実上の刑罰の緩和策が盛り込まれた。」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A scheme to mitigate actual punishments was incorporated, although former regulations on pardon remained as they were, but they were put together with conventional procedures in the hands of the council chamber, and Juveniles younger than fifteen who were formerly given severe punishments like banishment including cases where they were guilty only because of a relative&apos;s crime (enza) became eligible for pardon right away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="23">
<j>ところが編纂の翌年の黒船来航などで内外の情勢が混乱して施行が先延ばしされ、続いて阿部や遠山が急死して保守派の井伊直弼が実権を握った事もあって「赦律」は事実上葬り去られてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One year after the compilation started, with the arrival of the black ships, the domestic and foreign situation was in a state of confusion, enforcement got postponed, then Abe and Toyama died suddenly, the conservative Naoskuke II seized the power and the law on pardon was practically consigned to oblivion.</e>
<cmt>1851 law was drawn up 1853 black ships arrive 1855 Toyama dies   1857 Abe dies</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One year after the compilation started, however, the domestic and foreign situation became turbulent due to the arrival of the black ships and it postponed taking the law into effect, then Abe and Toyama died suddenly and the conservative Naosuke II seized the power, and as a result the law on pardon was practically consigned to oblivion.</e>
<cmt>文章のつながりがわかりにくかったので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One year after the compilation started, however, the domestic and foreign situation became turbulent due to the arrival of the black ships and it postponed taking the law into effect, then Abe and Toyama died suddenly and the conservative Naosuke II seized the power, and as a result the law on pardon was practically consigned to oblivion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>ところが、編纂から11年後の文久3年3月に突然施行が命じられたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eleven years after the compilation started, enforcement was suddenly ordered in March, 1862 (the third year of the Bunkyu era).</e>
<cmt>I left Bunky era here, as the next sentence is about the Bunkyu Reform</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eleven years after the compilation started, enforcement was suddenly ordered in March, 1862 (the third year of the Bunkyu era).</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースをとりました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eleven years after the compilation started, enforcement was suddenly ordered in March, 1862 (the third year of the Bunkyu era).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>これについては編纂に参加した脇坂安宅の老中就任との関係や当時のいわゆる文久の改革との関連性が指摘されるが、その経緯については不明のままである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this connection it was pointed out, that Yasuori WAKISAKA, who was installed as senior councilor and participated in the compilation, was relevant to the so-called Bunkyu Reform of that time, but the particulars are still unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is pointed out that this sudden order might be relevant to the appointment of Yasuori WAKISAKA, who participated in the compilation of the law, as the senior councilor and to the so-called Bunkyu Reform of that time, but the particulars are still unknown.</e>
<cmt>編纂参加と老中就任の順序をわかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is pointed out that this sudden order might be relevant to the appointment of Yasuori WAKISAKA, who participated in the compilation of the law, as the senior councilor and to the so-called Bunkyu Reform of that time, but the particulars are still unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>内容</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Content</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Content</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Content</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>まず、当時の刑罰は大まかに死刑と遠島・追放などの長期にわたる放逐を行う刑、そして敲や叱りなど判決と同時にその場において執行される刑に分かれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First of all, punishments at that time were broadly divided into death penalty and long term expulsion like exile to an island and banishment, further there were punishments which were executed locally right after the verdict was passed, like beating and harsh scolding, so in fact pardon was made possible mostly for convicted persons who were exiled to an island or banished. Other possible cases were prisoners on remand. Lost honor could be claimed in the cases of samurai, who were punished with confiscation (kaieki, confiscation of land, stipend, house) and passed away and monks, who were exiled from their sect as punishment. (However only their social status, not their official position or their stipend (rokudaka) could be retrieved).</e>
<cmt>かい-えき【改易】所領や家禄·屋敷を没収すること。江戸時代の刑では蟄居(ちつきよ)より重く、切腹より軽い (広辞苑第四版） It is not clear who could ask to retrieve the lost honor of a dead samurai.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It should be noted first that punishments at that time were broadly divided into the followings: death penalty, long term expulsion like exile to an island and banishment, and punishments which were executed immediately after the verdict was passed, like beating and harsh scolding.</e>
<cmt>複数の英文だったので「一原文一訳文の例外対処」を適用しました。分割後の原文「まず、当時の刑罰は大まかに死刑と遠島・追放などの長期にわたる放逐を行う刑、そして敲や叱りなど判決と同時にその場において執行される刑に分かれていた。」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It should be noted first that punishments at that time were broadly divided into the followings: death penalty, long term expulsion like exile to an island and banishment, and punishments which were executed immediately after the verdict was passed, like beating and harsh scolding.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>実際の恩赦の対象になりえたのは遠島・追放となった受刑者がほとんどであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, those who could actually be pardoned were mostly convicted persons who were exiled to an island or banished.</e>
<cmt>さらに分割しました。分割後の原文「実際の恩赦の対象になりえたのは遠島・追放となった受刑者がほとんどであった。」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, those who could actually be pardoned were mostly convicted persons who were exiled to an island or banished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>この他に未決囚や死亡した改易などの処分を受けた武士や宗門を追放されるなどの処分を受けた僧侶の名誉回復を求めるもの（ただし、処分前の資格を回復するのみで役職・禄高などが回復する訳ではない）を恩赦などを対象とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other possible cases of pardons were prisoners on remand, and claims for lost honor of dead samurai who had been punished with confiscation (kaieki, confiscation of land, stipend, and house) and of monks who were exiled from their sect as punishment (provided that only their religious qualification, not their official position or their stipend (rokudaka), could be retrieved).</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」を適用しました。分割後の原文「この他に未決囚や死亡した改易などの処分を受けた武士や宗門を追放されるなどの処分を受けた僧侶の名誉回復を求めるもの（ただし、処分前の資格を回復するのみで役職・禄高などが回復する訳ではない）を恩赦などを対象とした。」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other possible cases of pardons were prisoners on remand, and claims for lost honor of dead samurai who had been punished with confiscation (kaieki, confiscation of land, stipend, and house) and of monks who were exiled from their sect as punishment (provided that only their religious qualification, not their official position or their stipend (rokudaka), could be retrieved).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>また、一定の期間既に刑を受けている事も用件とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also necessary to serve time for a specified time period.</e>
<cmt>用件-要件</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also necessary to serve time for a specified time period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also necessary to serve time for a specified time period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>所払は11年、江戸払14年、江戸十里四方追放17年、軽追放20年、中追放23年、重追放26年、遠島29年、非人手下10年、武士や僧侶の処分取消は11年という基準が定められ、これを越える服役をして初めて資格を得たのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Convicts were eligible for a pardon, after serving the decided time period, which was: -Banishment from one&apos;s residence (tokorobarai) eleven years. -Banishment from Edo (Edobarai) fourteen years. -Banishment from Edo and its outskirts (Edo Juri Shiho Tsuiho) seventeen years. -Light banishment (Keitsuiho) twenty years. Medium banishment (hutsuiho) twenty-three years. Heavy banishment (Jutsuiho) twenty-six years. Exile to a remote island (ento) twenty-nine years.- Outcast ten years. Rehabilitation for Samurai and Buddhist monks eleven years.</e>
<cmt>For further info on punishments: http://www.geocities.co.jp/HeartLand-Keyaki/5107/page020.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Convicts were eligible for a pardon after serving the specified period of term; namely, 11 years for banishment from one&apos;s residence (tokorobarai); 14 years for banishment from Edo (Edobarai); 17 years for banishment from Edo and its outskirts (Edo Juri Shiho Tsuiho); 20 years for light banishment (Keitsuiho); 23 years for medium banishment (Chutsuiho); 26 years for heavy banishment (Jutsuiho); 29 years for exile to a remote island (ento); 10 years for outcast; and 11 years for rehabilitation for Samurai and Buddhist monks.</e>
<cmt>全角の「、」を訂正しました。箇条書き部分を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Convicts were eligible for a pardon after serving the specified period of term; namely, 11 years for banishment from one&apos;s residence (tokorobarai); 14 years for banishment from Edo (Edobarai); 17 years for banishment from Edo and its outskirts (Edo Juri Shiho Tsuiho); 20 years for light banishment (Keitsuiho); 23 years for medium banishment (Chutsuiho); 26 years for heavy banishment (Jutsuiho); 29 years for exile to a remote island (ento); 10 years for outcast; and 11 years for rehabilitation for Samurai and Buddhist monks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="31">
<j>なお、父の縁座によって処分を受けた子や15歳未満で刑が執行されていない幼年者への恩赦は年限に限らずに恩赦が認められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pardon was granted for children, who were punished because of their father&apos;s guilt (enza) and juveniles under fifteen years old, where the punishment was not enforced yet, regardless of their term.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Pardons were granted for children who were punished because of their father&apos;s guilt (enza) and for juveniles under fifteen years old where the punishment was not enforced yet, regardless of their term.</e>
<cmt>pardonを複数形にし、カンマを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Pardons were granted for children who were punished because of their father&apos;s guilt (enza) and for juveniles under fifteen years old where the punishment was not enforced yet, regardless of their term.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>なお、社会的に影響が小さい事件については短期でも恩赦が認められ（11年必要なケースでは6年など）、また逆に影響が大きいケースでは認められない場合があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pardon was approved after a short time in cases which had little effect on society (for example eleven years required-six years), conversely pardon might not be approved in cases which had a big effect on society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A pardon was approved after a short time in cases which had little effect on society (for example, after six years where the requirement was eleven years); conversely, a pardon might not be approved in cases which had a big effect on society.</e>
<cmt>括弧内の表現を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A pardon was approved after a short time in cases which had little effect on society (for example, after six years where the requirement was eleven years); conversely, a pardon might not be approved in cases which had a big effect on society.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>なお、当時の時代背景を反映して「外国人への犯罪及び外国人と組んで行った犯罪」が恩赦の対象外とされているのは特異な点であると言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also a unique point, which reflects the historical background as pardon did not extend to &quot;crimes on foreigners or crimes committed together with foreigners&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A unique point of this law which reflected the historical background was that a pardon did not extend to &quot;crimes on foreigners or crimes committed together with foreigners.&quot;</e>
<cmt>前半を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A unique point of this law which reflected the historical background was that a pardon did not extend to &quot;crimes on foreigners or crimes committed together with foreigners.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 欅(id:170341), 磯多申紋(id:36455), 嫦娥(id:81469), わずか(id:126848), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>