<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>女戸主</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lady Head of a Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onna Koshu</e>
<cmt>直下のコメントご参照ください</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onna Koshu (Ffemale Head of a Family)</e>
<cmt>()に意味を補足しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>女戸主（おんなこしゅ）は、日本の旧民法で、女性の戸主である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lady head of a family was defined as a female householder according to the Old Civil Codes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onna Koshu was defined as a female head of a family according to the Old Civil Codes of Japan.</e>
<cmt>・原文の「女戸主」と「女性の戸主」は意味としては全く同じで英訳すると&quot;female head of a family&quot;となりますので、一つ目を日本語読みのまま残すこととしました・「日本の」を訳出</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onna Koshu was defined as a female head of a family according to the Old Civil Codes of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>戸主は男性であることが原則であるが、女性であっても家督相続ができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In principle, a head of a family was a man, but a woman was also allowed to succeed the position of family head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In principle, a head of a family was a man, but a woman was also allowed to succeed the position of family head.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In principle, a head of a family was a man, but a woman was also allowed to succeed the position of family head.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>女性の庶子、私生児などが一家を創立することもあり、女戸主もあり得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A lady head of a family was possible because a female illegitimate child or a female child born outside of marriage could establish a family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A female head of a family was possible because a female illegitimate child or a female child born outside of marriage could establish a family.</e>
<cmt>lady→female</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A female head of a family was possible because a female illegitimate child or a female child born outside of marriage could establish a family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="5">
<j>女戸主が隠居するには、年齢は問わないが、ただ完全な能力を持つ相続人が相続の単純承認をすればそれでよかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a lady head of a family wanted to retire, a simple acceptance of the succession by a successor with full ability, regardless of age, was necessary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a female head of a family wanted to retire, only a simple acceptance of the succession by a successor with full ability, regardless of age, was necessary.</e>
<cmt>・lady→female・onlyを補完しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a female head of a family wanted to retire, only a simple acceptance of the succession by a successor with full ability, regardless of age, was necessary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="6">
<j>女戸主が婚姻して他家に入るには、隠居するか、でなければ廃家するほかなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For a lady head of a family to join another family by marriage, she had to retire or abolish the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For a female head of a family to join another family by marriage, she had to retire or abolish the family.</e>
<cmt>lady→female</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For a female head of a family to join another family by marriage, she had to retire or abolish the family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="7">
<j>廃家は一家創立者であれば自由にできた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If she was the founder of a family, she was free to abolish her family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If she was the founder of a family, she was free to abolish her family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If she was the founder of a family, she was free to abolish her family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="8">
<j>原則としては許されない場合でも、女戸主が婚姻するためであれば特に裁判所が許可を得て隠居または廃家ができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even though it was not acceptable as a general rule, she could retire or abolish the house in order to get married, only if she obtained permission specially from the court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even in the case which was not generally acceptable, she could retire or abolish the family in order to get married, only if she obtained permission specially from the court.</e>
<cmt>・この文型ですとitの指すものに関して誤解が生じうるので、文型を変えました・house→family</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even in the case which was not generally acceptable, she could retire or abolish the family in order to get married, only if she obtained permission specially from the court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="9">
<j>女戸主が戸主でいるままで婚姻するときは入夫婚姻といって、夫がその家に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a lady head of a family wanted to stay as the head of her family, her husband married into her family which was called Nyufu marriage.</e>
<cmt>入夫婚姻の定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a female head of a family wanted to marry staying as the head of her family, her husband married into her family which was called Nyufu marriage.</e>
<cmt>・lady→female・「婚姻する」を訳出しました・「入夫」の読みはOKです。ここで一応の定義がされていますので、このままで良いかと思います</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a female head of a family wanted to marry staying as the head of her family, her husband married into her family which was called Nyufu marriage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="10">
<j>入夫婚姻の場合に女戸主が戸主の地位を留保しなければ入夫は当然に戸主となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even in the case of Nyufu marriage, if a lady head of a family did not wish to reserve the position, her husband of course replaced the position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even in the case of Nyufu marriage, if a female head of a family did not wish to reserve the position, her husband of course replaced the position.</e>
<cmt>lady→female</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even in the case of Nyufu marriage, if a female head of a family did not wish to reserve the position, her husband of course replaced the position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="11">
<j>この留保をすれば女戸主は婚姻後も戸主の地位を失わず、夫の財産を使用収益する権利を有したが、婚姻後の共同生活の費用、子女の教育費などは女戸主が負担しなければならなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If she wished to reserve the position, she would not loose the position even after marriage and kept the right to use and profit from her husband&apos;s property, on the other hand, she had to pay expenses, including education fee for their children.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If she wished to reserve the position, she would not lose the position of the family head even after marriage and kept the right to use and profit from her husband&apos;s property, on the other hand, she had to pay expenses including cost of shared living and education fee for their children.</e>
<cmt>・loose→lose・「戸主」を訳出しました・「共同生活の費用」を訳出しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If she wished to reserve the position, she would not lose the position of the family head even after marriage and kept the right to use and profit from her husband&apos;s property, on the other hand, she had to pay expenses including cost of shared living and education fee for their children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 OY-BZ(id:295828), 白文鳥(id:103465), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>