<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>康暦の政変</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Koryaku Coup</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Koryaku Coup</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Koryaku Coup</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>康暦の政変（こうりゃくのせいへん）は、南北朝時代 (日本)の天授 (日本)5年/康暦元年（1379年）に室町幕府の管領・細川頼之が失脚した政変である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Koryaku Coup was a coup d&apos;etat that occurred in the fifth year of Tenju (Southern)/first year of Koryaku (Northern) during the Northern and Southern dynasties era (in Japan), in which the Kanrei, or deputy (de facto leader) of the Muromachi shogunate, Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA, was overthrown and lost his position.</e>
<cmt>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kanrei</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Koryaku Coup was a coup d&apos;etat that occurred in the fifth year of Tenju (Southern)/first year of Koryaku (Northern) during the Northern and Southern dynasties era (in Japan), in which the Kanrei, or deputy (de facto leader) of the Muromachi shogunate, Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA, was overthrown and lost his position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Koryaku Coup was a coup d&apos;etat that occurred in 1379 (the fifth year of Tenju (Southern)/first year of Koryaku (Northern)) during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), in which the Kanrei, or deputy (de facto leader) of the Muromachi Shogunate, Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA, was overthrown and lost his position.</e>
<cmt>1379,補足、年号が話題なので（）補足にしました。南北朝時代は、the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan) としました。Shogunate大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>室町幕府の2代将軍足利義詮の頃には守護同士が対立し、執事の細川清氏などは失脚した後に吉野朝廷に属して京都を奪還するなど幕政は不安定な状態にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the reign of the Muromachi shogunate&apos;s second Shogun, Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA, a conflict had arisen among the group of shugo (Protectors), and after such men as the steward Kiyouji HOSOKAWA were driven out of power, they defected to the Southern Court at Yoshino, who managed to recapture Kyoto, which left the shogunate in a very unstable position.</e>
<cmt>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ashikaga_Yoshiakira</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the reign of the Muromachi shogunate&apos;s second Shogun, Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA, a conflict had arisen among the group of shugo (Protectors), and after such men as the steward Kiyouji HOSOKAWA were driven out of power, they defected to the Southern Court at Yoshino, who managed to recapture Kyoto, which left the shogunate in a very unstable position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the reign of the Muromachi Shogunate&apos;s second Shogun Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA, a conflict had arisen among the group of shugo (Protectors), and after such men as the steward Kiyouji HOSOKAWA were driven out of power, they defected to the Southern Court at Yoshino, who managed to recapture Kyoto, which left the shogunate in a very unstable position.</e>
<cmt>Shogunate大文字にしました。,削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>清氏失脚後には斯波高経、斯波義将親子が政権を持つが、佐々木道誉との対立などから貞治の政変で失脚する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Kiyouji was overthrown, the reins of political power were held by a father-son pair, Takatsune and Yoshimasa SHIBA, but they clashed with Doyo SASAKI, and were themselves driven from power during the Joji coup.</e>
<cmt>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sasaki_Takauji</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Kiyouji was overthrown, the reins of political power were held by a father-son pair, Takatsune and Yoshimasa SHIBA, but they clashed with Doyo SASAKI, and were themselves driven from power during the Joji coup.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Kiyouji was overthrown, the reins of political power were held by a father-son pair, Takatsune and Yoshimasa SHIBA, but they clashed with Doyo SASAKI, and were themselves driven from power during the Joji coup.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>義詮死去の直前には四国地方、中国地方で南朝側と戦っていた細川頼之が佐々木など反斯波氏派の支持を得て管領に就任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Just before Yoshiakira died, Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA, who had been fighting the Southern Court forces on the island of Shikoku and in the Chugoku region (of western Japan), was appointed Kanrei after obtaining the support of SASAKI and others of the anti-SHIBA faction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Just before Yoshiakira died, Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA, who had been fighting the Southern Court forces on the island of Shikoku and in the Chugoku region (of western Japan), was appointed Kanrei after obtaining the support of SASAKI and others of the anti-SHIBA faction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Just before Yoshiakira died, Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA, who had been fighting the Southern Court forces on the island of Shikoku and in the Chugoku region (of western Japan), was appointed Kanrei after obtaining the support of Sasaki and others of the anti-Shiba faction.</e>
<cmt>Sasaki、Shiba に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>頼之は義詮の子で幼少の足利義満を補佐し、半済令の試行や南朝との交渉などの政策を実施するが、旧仏教勢力の比叡山と新興禅宗の南禅寺との対立においては南禅寺派を支持していたため叡山派と対立し、南禅寺の住職春屋妙葩が隠棲して抗議するなど宗教勢力とも対立していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoriyuki acted as advisor and regent to Yoshiakira&apos;s son Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, who was still a child, and carried out policies like experimenting with a new hansei (half-tax) law, which was designed to protect existing land holdings, and he attempted to negotiate with the Southern Court, but he also became embroiled in a religious conflict between Mt. Hiei, the powerful old Buddhist sect, and Nanzenji temple, a center of the rising new Zen sect; he opposed the Mt. Hiei faction because he was supporting the Nanzenji faction, yet he also clashed with Nanzenji&apos;s own powerful religious leaders, as when he opposed chief priest Myoha Shunnoku&apos;s seclusion from public life.</e>
<cmt>(middle of page discusses hanzei law) http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nanboku-ch%C5%8D#The_Kann.C5.8D_Incident_and_the_resurgence_of_the_Southern_Court_in_the_1350.E2.80.99s</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriyuki acted as advisor and regent to Yoshiakira&apos;s son Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, who was still a child, and carried out policies like experimenting with a new hansei (half-tax) law, which was designed to protect existing land holdings, and he attempted to negotiate with the Southern Court, but he also became embroiled in a religious conflict between Mt. Hiei, the powerful old Buddhist sect, and Nanzenji temple, a center of the rising new Zen sect; he opposed the Mt. Hiei faction because he was supporting the Nanzenji faction, yet he also clashed with Nanzenji&apos;s own powerful religious leaders, for example, when he opposed chief priest Myoha Shunnoku&apos;s seclusion from public life.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriyuki acted as advisor and regent to Yoshiakira&apos;s son Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, who was still a child, and carried out policies like experimenting with a new hansei (half-tax) law, which was designed to protect existing land holdings, and he attempted to negotiate with the Southern Court, but he also became embroiled in a religious conflict between Mt. Hiei, the powerful old Buddhist sect, and Nanzen-ji temple, a center of the rising new Zen sect; he opposed the Mt. Hiei faction because he was supporting the Nanzen-ji faction, yet he also clashed with Nanzen-ji&apos;s own powerful religious leaders, for example, when he opposed chief priest Myoha Shunnoku&apos;s seclusion from public life.</e>
<cmt>-補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>1376年には紀伊での南朝方の活動に対して頼之は弟の細川頼元を総大将とし派遣するが鎮圧に失敗し、成長した3代将軍義満は反頼之派の山名氏を派遣させ、また大和での軍事活動には復帰した斯波義将や土岐頼康ら反頼之派に軍勢を与える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1376, Yoriyuki made his younger brother Yorimoto HOSOKAWA supreme military commander and dispatched him to counter the Southern Court&apos;s military maneuvers in the Kii peninsula, but Yorimoto failed to subjugate the area, and the third Shogun, Yoshimitsu, who had now reached adulthood, caused the leader of the Yamana clan, a member of the anti-Yoriyuki faction, to be sent as a replacement; moreover, he granted appointments to others of the anti-Yoriyuki faction, including Yoriyasu TOKI and the rehabilitated Yoshimasa SHIBA, to command military activities in Yamato.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1376, Yoriyuki made his younger brother Yorimoto HOSOKAWA supreme military commander and dispatched him to counter the Southern Court&apos;s military maneuvers in the Kii peninsula, but Yorimoto failed to subjugate the area, and the third Shogun, Yoshimitsu, who had now reached adulthood, had the leader of the Yamana clan, a member of the anti-Yoriyuki faction, to sent as a replacement; moreover, he granted appointments to others of the anti-Yoriyuki faction, including Yoriyasu TOKI and the rehabilitated Yoshimasa SHIBA, to command military activities in Yamato.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1376, Yoriyuki made his younger brother Yorimoto HOSOKAWA supreme military commander and dispatched him to counter the Southern Court&apos;s military maneuvers in the Kii peninsula, but Yorimoto failed to subjugate the area, and the third Shogun Yoshimitsu, who had now reached adulthood, had the leader of the Yamana clan, a member of the anti-Yoriyuki faction, to sent as a replacement; moreover, he granted appointments to others of the anti-Yoriyuki faction, including Yoriyasu TOKI and the rehabilitated Yoshimasa SHIBA, to command military activities in Yamato.</e>
<cmt>,削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>翌77年（天授3年/永和 (日本)3年）には義将の所領内の騒動が頼之の領地であった太田荘（現富山県富山市）に飛び火すると、頼之と斯波派、土岐、山名氏らの抗争は表面化し、頼之派から斯波派に転じる守護も現れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following year, in 1377 (the third year of Tenju (Southern)/third year of Eiwa), when the riotous strife within Yoshimasa&apos;s territory spread like wildfire to Ota estate (modern-day Toyama city in Toyama Pref.), part of Yoriyuki&apos;s territory, the antagonistic dispute between Yoriyuki and the SHIBA faction, TOKI, the YAMANA clan, and others flared out into the open, and some shugo switched from the Yoriyuki faction to the SHIBA faction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following year, in 1377 (the third year of Tenju (Southern)/third year of Eiwa), when riotous strife within Yoshimasa&apos;s territory spread like wildfire to Ota estate (modern-day Toyama city in Toyama Pref.), part of Yoriyuki&apos;s territory, the antagonistic dispute between Yoriyuki and the SHIBA faction, TOKI, the YAMANA clan, and others flared out into the open, and some shugo switched from the Yoriyuki faction to the SHIBA faction.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot; deleted before &quot;riotous&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following year, in 1377, when riotous strife within Yoshimasa&apos;s territory spread like wildfire to Ota estate (modern-day Toyama City in Toyama Pref.), part of Yoriyuki&apos;s territory, the antagonistic dispute between Yoriyuki and the Shiba faction, Toki, the Yamana clan, and others flared out into the open, and some shugo switched from the Yoriyuki faction to the Shiba faction.</e>
<cmt>旧暦削除しました。City大文字にしました。Shiba、Toki、Yamanaとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>反頼之派は義満に対して頼之の排斥、討伐を要請し、近江で反頼之派に転じた佐々木高秀が挙兵すると、鎌倉公方の足利氏満が呼応して軍事行動を起こそうとし上杉憲春に諌死される事件も起こる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The anti-Yoriyuki faction asked Yoshimitsu for permission to expel and subjugate Yoriyuki, and when Takahide SASAKI, who had switched to the anti-Yoriyuki faction, raised an army at Omi, Ujimitsu ASHIKAGA, the Shogun&apos;s representative at Kamakura, prepared to begin military action in response, it also happened that Noriharu UESUGI committed suicide to remonstrate with him about this course of action.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The anti-Yoriyuki faction asked Yoshimitsu for permission to expel and subjugate Yoriyuki, and when Takahide SASAKI, who had switched to the anti-Yoriyuki faction, raised an army at Omi, Ujimitsu ASHIKAGA, the Shogun&apos;s representative at Kamakura, prepared to begin military action in response, it also happened that Noriharu UESUGI committed suicide to remonstrate with him about this course of action.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The anti-Yoriyuki faction asked Yoshimitsu for permission to expel and subjugate Yoriyuki, and when Takahide SASAKI, who had switched to the anti-Yoriyuki faction, raised an army at Omi, Ujimitsu ASHIKAGA, the Shogun&apos;s representative at Kamakura, prepared to begin military action in response, it also happened that Noriharu UESUGI committed suicide to remonstrate with him about this course of action.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>義満は義将らの圧力で高秀や頼康らを赦免すると、義将はじめ反頼之派が軍勢を用いて将軍邸の花の御所を包囲して義満に頼之の罷免を迫る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yoshimitsu pardoned several, including Takahide and Yoriyasu, under pressure from Yoshimasa and others, the anti-Yoriyuki faction, and Yoshimasa first among them, gathered their military forces together and surrounded the Shogun&apos;s flower garden at his estate, insisting that Yoshimitsu dismiss Yoriyuki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yoshimitsu pardoned several, including Takahide and Yoriyasu, under pressure from Yoshimasa and others, the anti-Yoriyuki faction, and Yoshimasa first among them, gathered their military forces together and surrounded the Shogun&apos;s flower garden at his estate, insisting that Yoshimitsu dismiss Yoriyuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yoshimitsu pardoned several, including Takahide and Yoriyasu, under pressure from Yoshimasa and others, the anti-Yoriyuki faction, and Yoshimasa first among them, gathered their military forces together and surrounded the Shogun&apos;s flower garden at his estate, insisting that Yoshimitsu dismiss Yoriyuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>頼之は出家し、自邸を焼いて一族を連れて領国の四国へ下る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoriyuki took the tonsure, burned down his own estate, and went off together with his family to his territories in Shikoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriyuki took the tonsure, burned down his own estate, and went off together with his family to his territories in Shikoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriyuki took the tonsure, burned down his own estate, and went off together with his family to his territories in Shikoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>後任の管領は義将で、春屋妙葩らも復帰する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The successor as kanrei was Yoshimasa, and among others, Myoha Shunnoku returned to public life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The successor as kanrei was Yoshimasa, and among others, Myoha Shunnoku returned to public life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The successor as kanrei was Yoshimasa, and among others, Myoha Shunnoku returned to public life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>四国へ下った頼之は幕府から頼之追討令を受けた伊予の河野氏らと戦い、年末には赦免をうける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoriyuki, after going off to Shikoku, fought with the Kawana clan of Iyo, who had received a shogunal order to hunt him dow nand kill him; at the end of the year, Yoriyuki received a pardon, however.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriyuki, after going off to Shikoku, fought with the Kawana clan of Iyo, who had received a shogunal order to hunt him down and kill him; however, at the end of the year, Yoriyuki received a pardon.</e>
<cmt>corrected typo, revised word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriyuki, after going off to Shikoku, fought with the Kono clan of Iyo Province, who had received a shogunal order to hunt him down and kill him; however, at the end of the year, Yoriyuki received a pardon.</e>
<cmt>Konoに訂正しました。Province補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>弟の細川頼元は管領に就任し、頼之自身もその後幕政の中心に復帰していることから、この政変は頼之からの自立を望んだ義満の提唱によって起こされたものと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But given that his younger brother Yorimotoo HOSOKAWA assumed the position of kanrei, and the fact that Yoriyuki himself was eventually able to stage a political comeback and return to the inner circle of the shogunate, it is thought that this coup may have been instigated by Yoshimitsu, who wished to achieve independence from Yoriyuki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But given that his younger brother Yorimoto HOSOKAWA assumed the position of kanrei, and the fact that Yoriyuki himself was eventually able to stage a political comeback and return to the inner circle of the shogunate, it is thought that this coup may have been instigated by Yoshimitsu, who wished to achieve independence from Yoriyuki.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But given that his younger brother Yorimoto HOSOKAWA assumed the position of kanrei, and the fact that Yoriyuki himself was eventually able to stage a political comeback and return to the inner circle of the shogunate, it is thought that this coup may have been instigated by Yoshimitsu, who wished to achieve independence from Yoriyuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>斯波氏・細川氏両派の抗争を利用し、相互に牽制させて強大化を防いだとも考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that Yoshimitsu played the SHIBA and HOSOKAWA clan factions off against each other, using their mutual antagonism to check them both and keep either from becoming too powerful.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that Yoshimitsu played the SHIBA and HOSOKAWA clan factions off against each other, using their mutual antagonism to check them both and keep either from becoming too powerful.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that Yoshimitsu played the Shiba and Hosokawa clan factions off against each other, using their mutual antagonism to check them both and keep either from becoming too powerful.</e>
<cmt>Shiba、Hosokawaとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>義満はこの後には将軍直轄の軍事力である奉公衆を整備し、1391年の明徳の乱においては山名氏を、1397年の応永の乱においては大内氏を追討して有力守護を弱体化させ、幕府の支配体制を固めていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the coup, Yoshimitsu established the Hokoshu, a Shogunal army directly loyal to him, and succeeded in using it to weaken the two most powerful shugo families, the Yamana clan in 1391 during the Meitoku Rebellion and the Ouchi clan in 1397 by means of the Oei Rebellion, thereby solidifying the shogunate&apos;s control over the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the coup, Yoshimitsu established the Hokoshu, a Shogunal army directly loyal to him, and succeeded in using it to weaken the two most powerful shugo families, the Yamana clan in 1391 during the Meitoku Rebellion and the Ouchi clan in 1397 by means of the Oei Rebellion, thereby solidifying the shogunate&apos;s control over the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the coup, Yoshimitsu established the Hokoshu, a Shogunal army directly loyal to him, and succeeded in using it to weaken the two most powerful shugo families, the Yamana clan in 1391 during the Meitoku Rebellion and the Ouchi clan in 1397 by means of the Oei Rebellion, thereby solidifying the shogunate&apos;s control over the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), Shimoxx(id:9332), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), 竹麦魚(id:11012), Sutou(id:32), Nnh(id:474), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>