<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>水口藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minakuchi Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minakuchi Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minakuchi Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>水口藩（みなくちはん）　滋賀県甲賀市水口町周辺を領した藩。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Minakuchi Domain was han (a basic unit of provincial government during the Edo period) located around in Minakuchi-cho, Koga City, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Minakuchi Domain was a han (a basic unit of provincial government during the Edo period) that governed around Minakuchi-cho, Koga City, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>hanは「領した」とあるため、governにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Minakuchi Domain was a han (a basic unit of provincial government during the Edo period) that governed around Minakuchi-cho, Koga City, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藩庁は水口城。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The government building of the domain was Minakuchi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The government building of the domain was Minakuchi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The government building of the domain was Minakuchi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>天和 (日本)3年（1682年）、賤ヶ岳の七本槍の1人として知られる加藤嘉明の孫で、外様の石見国吉永藩（1万石）藩主・加藤明友が祖父と自身の功により1万石の加増を受け、2万石で近江国水口城主となり立藩。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Minakuchi Domain was founded In 1682; Akitomo KATO, tozama (a outsider feudal lord) of the Yoshinaga Domain in Iwami Province (with a fief yielding 10,000 koku of rice), became the lord of the Minakuchi-jo Castle in Omi Province with 10,000 koku of rice increased to 20,000 in total because of the military exploit of his grandfather, Yoshiaki KATO, known as one of the seven excellent military commanders in Hideyoshi&apos;s army at the battle of Shizugatake (Shizugatake-no-shichihon-yari) and his merits.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Minakuchi Domain was founded in 1682 by Akitomo KATO, a tozama (outsider feudal lord) of the Yoshinaga Domain in Iwami Province (with a fief yielding 10,000 koku of rice), who became the lord of the Minakuchi-jo Castle in Omi Province with 10,000 koku of rice increased to 20,000 in total because of the military exploit by himself and his grandfather, Yoshiaki KATO, known as one of the seven excellent military commanders in Hideyoshi&apos;s army at the battle of Shizugatake (Shizugatake-no-shichihon-yari).</e>
<cmt>・文の途中でｓのでIn→inとしました。・his meritsが離れすぎていてわかりにくいため、修正しました。・「外様」は可算名詞扱いになると思われますので、冠詞を付けました。・Akitomo以降は最初の立藩の説明と情報がつながっているため、英訳もつなげました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Minakuchi Domain was founded in 1682 by Akitomo KATO, a tozama (outsider feudal lord) of the Yoshinaga Domain in Iwami Province (with a fief yielding 10,000 koku of rice), who became the lord of the Minakuchi-jo Castle in Omi Province with 10,000 koku of rice increased to 20,000 in total because of the military exploit by himself and his grandfather, Yoshiaki KATO, known as one of the seven excellent military commanders in Hideyoshi&apos;s army at the battle of Shizugatake (Shizugatake-no-shichihon-yari).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>水口城は造園の名手・小堀遠州の手によるものとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Enshu KOBORI, a master of landscape gardening, oversaw construction on Minakuchi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Enshu KOBORI, a master of landscape gardening, oversaw construction of Minakuchi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>意味は「水口城の築城」ですのでconstruction onはconstruction ofと思われます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Enshu KOBORI, a master of landscape gardening, oversaw construction of Minakuchi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>子の加藤明英は譜代の格式を与えられ、元禄3年（1690年）に寺社奉行から若年寄に昇進し、5000石の加増を受けて元禄8年（1695年）、下野国壬生藩に移封となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akihide KATO, a child of Akitomo, was bestowed the rank of fudai daimyo (hereditary daimyo), and in 1690, promoted to wakadoshiyori (a managerial position in Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)) from jisha-bugyo (magistrate of temples and shrines), transferred to the Mibu Domain in Shimotsuke Province in 1695 with 5,000 koku of rice increased.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akihide KATO, a son of Akitomo, was bestowed the rank of fudai daimyo (hereditary daimyo), and in 1690, promoted to wakadoshiyori (a managerial position in Edo bakufu [Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun]) from jisha-bugyo (magistrate of temples and shrines) and transferred to the Mibu Domain in Shimotsuke Province in 1695 with an increase of 5,000 koku of rice.</e>
<cmt>・childだと「幼い」という意味の「子」ですので、sonとしました。・指示に従って括弧の中の括弧は[　]としました。・transferredの前にandが抜けていましたので加えました。・with～は「5000石から増加」の意味にも取れるため修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akihide KATO, a son of Akitomo, was bestowed the rank of fudai daimyo (hereditary daimyo), and in 1690, promoted to wakadoshiyori (a managerial position in Edo bakufu [Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun]) from jisha-bugyo (magistrate of temples and shrines) and transferred to the Mibu Domain in Shimotsuke Province in 1695 with an increase of 5,000 koku of rice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>替わって能登国能登下村藩より、譜代の鳥居忠英が2万石で入封する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadateru TORII, hereditary daimyo, entered into the Minakuchi Domain with 20,000 koku of rice from the Notoshimomura Domain in Noto Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadateru TORII, hereditary daimyo, entered into the Minakuchi Domain with 20,000 koku of rice from the Notoshimomura Domain in Noto Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadateru TORII, hereditary daimyo, entered into the Minakuchi Domain with 20,000 koku of rice from the Notoshimomura Domain in Noto Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>忠英は正徳 (日本)元年（1711年）、寺社奉行から若年寄に昇進し、正徳2年（1712年）に下野壬生藩に移封となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadateru was promoted to wakadoshiyori from jisha-bugyo in 1711, and transferred to the Mibu Domain in Shimotsuke Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadateru was promoted to wakadoshiyori from jisha-bugyo in 1711, and transferred to the Mibu Domain in Shimotsuke Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadateru was promoted to wakadoshiyori from jisha-bugyo in 1711, and transferred to the Mibu Domain in Shimotsuke Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>同年、入れ替わりに下野壬生藩より加藤明英の嗣子・加藤嘉矩が2万5千石で入封した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, Yoshinori KATO, an heir of Akihide KATO, entered into the domain from the Mibu Domain in Shimotsuke Province with 25,000 koku of rice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, Yoshinori KATO, an heir of Akihide KATO, entered into the domain from the Mibu Domain in Shimotsuke Province with 25,000 koku of rice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, Yoshinori KATO, an heir of Akihide KATO, entered into the domain from the Mibu Domain in Shimotsuke Province with 25,000 koku of rice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>以後、明治維新まで加藤氏が領することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From then on till the Meiji Restoration, the Kato clan had dominated the Minakuchi Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From then on till the Meiji Restoration, the Kato clan had dominated the Minakuchi Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From then on till the Meiji Restoration, the Kato clan had dominated the Minakuchi Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>明治4年（1871年）、廃藩置県により廃藩となり、水口県となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1871, by the act of Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures), the Minakuchi Domain was abolished to establish Minakuchi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1871, by the act of Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures), the Minakuchi Domain was abolished to establish Minakuchi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1871, by the act of Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures), the Minakuchi Domain was abolished to establish Minakuchi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>吉永藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshinaga Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshinaga Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshinaga Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>吉永藩（よしながはん）は、加藤明友が近江水口藩に転封する前に治めていた藩。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yoshinaga Domain was the one which was governed by Akitomo KATO before he was transferred to the Minakuchi Domain in Omi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yoshinaga Domain was a han which had been governed by Akitomo KATO before he was transferred to the Minakuchi Domain in Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>the oneが曖昧なため、修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yoshinaga Domain was a han which had been governed by Akitomo KATO before he was transferred to the Minakuchi Domain in Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>石見国安濃郡吉永（島根県大田市）周辺で1万石を領有し、吉永に陣屋を構えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was located around in Yoshinaga, Ano-gun, Iwami Province (now Ota City, Shimane Prefecture) with 10,000 koku of rice, and jinya (regional government) was settled in Yoshinaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It had been located around Yoshinaga, Ano-gun, Iwami Province (current Ota City, Shimane Prefecture) with 10,000 koku of rice, and jinya (regional government) had been settled in Yoshinaga.</e>
<cmt>・時制を修正しました。・around inはaroundのみでよいと思われます。・「現在の～」はnowよりもcurrentが一般的と思われます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It had been located around Yoshinaga, Ano-gun, Iwami Province (current Ota City, Shimane Prefecture) with 10,000 koku of rice, and jinya (regional government) had been settled in Yoshinaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>寛永20年（1643年）5月、父・加藤明成が会津藩40万石を収公されたが、祖父・嘉明の勲功により家名存続を許され、6月に立藩した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June, 1643, the Yoshinaga Domain was founded; Akitomo&apos;s father, Akinari KATO, who was the lord of the Aizu Domain, had his domain with 400,000 koku of rice confiscated in May, 1643, but continuance of the family name was allowed because of the deed of valor of Akitomo&apos;s grandfather, Akinari KATO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 1643, the Yoshinaga Domain was founded; Akitomo&apos;s father, Akinari KATO, who was the lord of the Aizu Domain, had his domain with 400,000 koku of rice confiscated in June 1643, but continuance of the family name was allowed because of the deed of valor of Akitomo&apos;s grandfather, Akinari KATO.</e>
<cmt>・JuneoおよびMayは数字ではないため、直後のコンマは不要です。・旧暦でしたので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July 1643, the Yoshinaga Domain was founded; Akitomo&apos;s father, Akinari KATO, who was the lord of the Aizu Domain, had his domain with 400,000 koku of rice confiscated in June 1643, but continuance of the family name was allowed because of the deed of valor of Akitomo&apos;s grandfather, Akinari KATO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>しかし40万石を領する大藩からわずか1万石の小藩にまで成り下がったため、家臣団の縮小などを余儀なくされ、藩財政は一気に悪化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because The Kato clan had its large domain with 400,000 koku of rice which it had retained reduced to a small one with only 10,000 koku of rice, it was forced to curtail the vassals, so that the clan&apos;s finance underwent rapid deterioration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the Kato clan had its large domain with 400,000 koku of rice which it had retained reduced to a small one with only 10,000 koku of rice, it was forced to curtail the vassals, so that the clan&apos;s finance underwent rapid deterioration.</e>
<cmt>・文中ですので、The Kato clan→the Kato clanにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the Kato clan had its large domain with 400,000 koku of rice which it had retained reduced to a small one with only 10,000 koku of rice, it was forced to curtail the vassals, so that the clan&apos;s finance underwent rapid deterioration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>このため、会津藩から漆器製造者を招聘し、さらに桐・櫨・梅などの栽培を奨励したりするなど、殖産興業に尽力している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, the Kato clan made great effort to encourage new industry development, such as engaging manufacturer of lacquer ware from the Aizu Domain, promoting to plant paulownia trees, Japanese wax trees, and Japanese apricot trees.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, the Kato clan made great effort to encourage new industry development, such as engaging manufacturer of lacquer ware from the Aizu Domain and promoting to plant paulownia trees, Japanese wax trees, and Japanese apricot trees.</e>
<cmt>promotingの前にandが必要です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, the Kato clan made great effort to encourage new industry development, such as engaging manufacturer of lacquer ware from the Aizu Domain and promoting to plant paulownia trees, Japanese wax trees, and Japanese apricot trees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また、年貢増徴政策なども行なっているが、このために加藤氏が水口藩に移封された後も、天領の中では特に税率の高い地域になったといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, the Kato clan evolved nengu (land tax)-increase policy, so that the domain was said to still be a particularly high-tax area after it was transferred to the Minakuchi Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, the Kato clan evolved nengu (land tax)-increase policy, so that the domain was said to still be a particularly high-tax area after it was transferred to the Minakuchi Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, the Kato clan evolved nengu (land tax)-increase policy, so that the domain was said to still be a particularly high-tax area after it was transferred to the Minakuchi Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>藩の行政機構は小藩になったことから未熟なものとなったとされているが、実情には不明な点も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the small domain made its administrative organization less systematized, but there are many unknown real circumstances.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the small domain made its administrative organization less systematized, but there are many unknown real circumstances.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the small domain made its administrative organization less systematized, but there are many unknown real circumstances.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>明成の死後、第2代藩主の座は加藤明友が相続し、天和2年（1682年）6月、明友は1万石加増の2万石で、水口藩に転封となり、廃藩となって天領（石見銀山領）となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Akinari, Akitomo KATO, who succeeded to the second lord of the domain, was transferred to the Minakuchi Domain with 10,000 koku of rice increased to 20,000 in total in 1682, so that the Yoshinaga domain was abolished to become a shogunal demesne (tenryo of Iwami Ginzan Mine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Akinari, Akitomo KATO, who succeeded to the second lord of the domain, was transferred to the Minakuchi Domain with 10,000 koku of rice increased to 20,000 in total in July 1682, so that the Yoshinaga domain was abolished to become a tenryo (bakufu-owned land of Iwami Ginzan Mine).</e>
<cmt>・訳漏れです（6月)。・「天領」は日本語（英語）の順が正ですので、修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Akinari, Akitomo KATO, who succeeded to the second lord of the domain, was transferred to the Minakuchi Domain with 10,000 koku of rice increased to 20,000 in total in July 1682, so that the Yoshinaga domain was abolished to become a tenryo (bakufu-owned land of Iwami Ginzan Mine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), ドルチェット(id:46458), 210.(id:9838), けんち(id:5147), 0null0(id:582), Reggaeman(id:6214), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>