<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>親王任国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinno-ningoku (provinces whose gubernatorial posts were reserved for imperial princes)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinno-ningoku (provinces whose gubernatorial posts were reserved for imperial princes)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinno-ningoku</e>
<cmt>タイトルのため補足を削除しました。(次文に説明あり)</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>親王任国（しんのうにんごく）とは、親王が国司に任じられた令制国及びその制度を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term Shinno-ningoku means provinces to which imperial princes were appointed as kokushi (provincial governor) as well as such system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term Shinno-ningoku means provinces to which imperial princes were appointed as kokushi (provincial governor) as well as such systems.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term Shinno-ningoku means provinces to which imperial princes were appointed as kokushi (provincial governor) as well as such systems.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>天長3年9月6日 (旧暦)（826年10月10日）、清原夏野の奏上に基づき制定された（『類聚三代格』：親王任国太政官符）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This system was established on October 10, 826 based on sojo (report to the Emperor) made by KIYOHARA no Natsuno (&quot;Ruiju sandaikyaku&quot;: Shinno-ningoku Dajokanpu (the official document issued by Dajokan, Grand Council of the state)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This system was established on October 10, 826 based on sojo (report to the Emperor) made by KIYOHARA no Natsuno (&quot;Ruiju sandaikyaku&quot;: Shinno-ningoku Dajokanpu (the official document issued by Dajokan, Grand Council of the state)).</e>
<cmt>Spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This system was established on October 14, 826 based on sojo (report to the Emperor) made by KIYOHARA no Natsuno (&quot;Ruiju Sandaikyaku&quot;: Shinno-ningoku Daijokanpu (the official document issued by Daijokan, Grand Council of the state)).</e>
<cmt>ユリウス→グレゴリオ暦に修正、&quot;Ruiju Sandaikyaku&quot;とし、Dajokanpu→Daijokanpu、Dajokan→Daijokanに修正 (参照: http://dictionary.goo.ne.jp/leaf/jn/116675/m0u/)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>桓武天皇は非常に多くの皇子・皇女を残し、続く平城天皇及び嵯峨天皇も多くの皇子・皇女に恵まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor Kanmu had many princes/princesses and the following emperors, the Emperor Heijo and the Emperor Saga, also had many princes/princesses.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor Kanmu had many princes/princesses and the following emperors, the Emperor Heijo and the Emperor Saga, also had many princes/princesses.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor Kanmu had many princes/princesses and the following emperors, the Emperor Heijo and the Emperor Saga, also had many princes/princesses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>このため天長3年当時、多数ある親王家を維持する財源と親王に充てるべき官職が不足していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, the government faced, in the 3rd year of Tencho era, a financial problem in supporting many Imperial Prince&apos;s families as well as the shortage of posts to be allocated to Imperial Princes.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, the government faced, in the third year of the Tencho era, a financial problem in supporting many Imperial Prince&apos;s families as well as the shortage of posts to be allocated to Imperial Princes.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, the government faced, in 826, a financial problem in supporting many Imperial Prince&apos;s families as well as the shortage of posts to be allocated to Imperial Princes.</e>
<cmt>in the third year of the Tencho era→in 826に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>清原夏野はこうした課題に加えて、当時親王が八省卿を兼務する慣例が成立していたことに問題があることを指摘した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KIYOHARA no Natsuno pointed out, in addition to the above problems, that the practice of appointing Imperial Princes to hasshokyo (the ministers of eight ministries) was problematic.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KIYOHARA no Natsuno pointed out, in addition to the above problems, that the practice of appointing Imperial Princes to hasshokyo (the ministers of eight ministries) was problematic.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">KIYOHARA no Natsuno pointed out, in addition to the above problems, that the practice of appointing Imperial Princes to hasshokyo (the ministers of eight ministries) was problematic.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そして、こうした問題を解決するため、親王任国の制度を奏上した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to solve these problems, he proposed the Emperor to establish Shinno-ningoku system.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to solve these problems, he proposed the Emperor establish the Shinno-ningoku system.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to solve these problems, he proposed the Emperor establish the Shinno-ningoku system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>当初は淳和天皇の治世だけに限定して始められたが、結局この制度はその後も存続し、平安時代を通じて定着することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although this system initially started as the one which was valid only during the era of the Emperor Junna, it continued to exist and took root throughout the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although this system initially started as one which was valid only during the era of the Emperor Junna, it continued to exist and took root throughout the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although this system initially started as one which was valid only during the era of the Emperor Junna, it continued to exist and took root throughout the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>親王任国に充てられたのは、常陸国、上総国、上野国の3国である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Provinces which were designated as Shinno-ninkoku were Hitachi Province, Kazusa Province and Kozuke Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Provinces which were designated as Shinno-ninkoku were Hitachi Province, Kazusa Province and Kozuke Province.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Provinces which were designated as Shinno-ningoku were Hitachi Province, Kazusa Province and Kozuke Province.</e>
<cmt>ninkoku→ningokuに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>いずれも大国だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All of them were taikoku (major province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All of them were taikoku (major province).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All of them were major provinces.</e>
<cmt>大国→あえて&quot;taikoku&quot;とローマ字表記する必要はないと思われるため、major provincesのみとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>これら3国の国司筆頭官である国守には、必ず親王が補任されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of these three provinces, Imperial Princes were always appointed to their kokushu, the head of provincial governors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of these three provinces, Imperial Princes were always appointed to their kokushu, the head of provincial governors.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of these three provinces, Imperial Princes were always appointed to their kokushu, the head of provincial governors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>親王任国の国守となった親王は「太守」と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Princes who were appointed to the kokushu of Shino-ningoku were called &quot;Taishu&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Princes who were appointed to the kokushu of Shino-ningoku were called &quot;Taishu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Princes who were appointed to the kokushu of Shino-ningoku were called &apos;Taishu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>親王太守の官位は、必然的に他の国守より高かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The court rank of Imperial Prince Taishu was necessarily higher than that of other kokushu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The court rank of Imperial Prince Taishu was necessarily higher than that of other kokushu.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The court rank of Imperial Prince Taishu was necessarily higher than that of other kokushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>通常は従五位上から従六位従六位であるのに対して親王任国の太守は正四位下とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the rank of kokushu was normally from Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade to Junior Sixth Rank, that of Imperial Prince Taishu of Shinno-ningoku was Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the rank of kokushu were normally from Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade to Junior Sixth Rank, that of Imperial Prince Taishu of Shinno-ningoku was Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the rank of kokushu were normally from Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) to Jurokuinoge (Junior Sixth Rank, Lower Grade), that of Imperial Prince Taishu of Shinno-ningoku was Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>「従六位従六位」→ウェブ上では「従六位下」と記載されているためこちらに基づき訳文を修正しました。（原文にはリンク先の単語が表記されているようです）官位を統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>天長3年に初めて3国の太守に任じられたのは、賀陽親王（常陸国太守）、仲野親王（上総国太守）、 葛井親王（上野国太守）で、いずれも桓武天皇の皇子であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those who were firstly appointed to the kokushu of the above three provinces in the 3rd year of Tencho era were Imperial Prince Kaya (Taishu of Hitachi Province), Imperial Prince Nakano (Taishu of Kazusa Province) and Imperial Prince Kadoi (Taishu of Kozuke Province) and all of them were the Emperor Kanmu&apos;s princes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those who were firstly appointed to the kokushu of the above three provinces in the 3rd year of Tencho era were Imperial Prince Kaya (Taishu of Hitachi Province), Imperial Prince Nakano (Taishu of Kazusa Province), and Imperial Prince Kadoi (Taishu of Kozuke Province) and all of them were Emperor Kanmu&apos;s princes.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those who were firstly appointed to the kokushu of the above three provinces in 826 were Imperial Prince Kaya (Taishu of Hitachi Province), Imperial Prince Nakano (Taishu of Kazusa Province), and Imperial Prince Kadoi (Taishu of Kozuke Province) and all of them were Emperor Kanmu&apos;s princes.</e>
<cmt>in the 3rd year of Tencho era→in 826に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>親王太守は、現地へ赴任しない遙任だったため、親王任国での実務上の最高位は、次官の国介（すけ）であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the position of Imperial Prince Taishu was yokan (remote appointment) and Imperial Princes were not required to go to respective provinces, suke, the deputies of Imperial Prince Taishu, were practically the highest position in Shinno-ningoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the position of Imperial Prince Taishu was yokan (remote appointment) and Imperial Princes were not required to go to the respective provinces, suke, the deputies of Imperial Prince Taishu, were practically the highest position in Shinno-ningoku.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the position of Imperial Prince Taishu was yonin (remote appointment) and Imperial Princes were not required to go to the respective provinces, suke, the deputies of Imperial Prince Taishu, were practically the highest position in Shinno-ningoku.</e>
<cmt>yokan→yoninに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>平安中期になり、受領国司が登場した際も、親王任国については介が受領の地位に就き、他国の国守と同列に扱われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When zuryo-kokushi (the head of provincial governors) appeared in the mid-Heian period, suke were appointed to the zuryo of Shinno-ningoku and were treated equally with kokushu of other provinces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When zuryo-kokushi (the head of provincial governors) appeared in the mid-Heian period, suke were appointed to the zuryo of Shinno-ningoku and were treated equally with kokushu of other provinces.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When zuryo-kokushi (the head of provincial governors) appeared in the mid-Heian period, suke were appointed to the zuryo of Shinno-ningoku and were treated equally with kokushu of other provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>なお、親王任国においては、太守の俸禄は太守の収入に、その他の料物については無品親王（官職に就けない内親王含む）に与えられたと考えられているが、詳細は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it is believed that Taishu of Shinno-ningoku received their salary but gave other revenues to Muhon-Shinno (Imperial prince without court rank) (inclusive of Imperial Princesses without official position), the details are not clear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is believed that Taishu of Shinno-ningoku received their salary but gave other revenues to Muhon-Shinno (Imperial prince without court rank) (inclusive of Imperial Princesses without official position), the details are not clear.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is believed that Taishu of Shinno-ningoku received their salary but gave other revenues to Muhon-Shinno (Imperial prince without court rank) (inclusive of Imperial Princesses without official position), the details are not clear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="19">
<j>承平天慶の乱において平将門が新皇として関東八ヶ国の国司を任命した際も、常陸と上総の国司は「常陸国」「上総国」を任命している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Johei and Tengyo War, Taira no Masakado appointed persons to the kokushi of eight provinces in Kanto region in the capacity of the new emperor, but he appointed &quot;Hitachi Province&quot; and &quot;Kazusa Province&quot; to the kokushi of Hitachi and Kazusa respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Johei and Tengyo War, Taira no Masakado appointed persons to the kokushi of eight provinces in the Kanto region in the capacity of the new emperor, but he appointed &quot;Hitachi Province&quot; and &quot;Kazusa Province&quot; to the kokushi of Hitachi and Kazusa respectively.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Johei and Tengyo War, TAIRA no Masakado appointed persons to the kokushi of eight provinces in the Kanto region in the capacity of the new emperor, but he appointed &apos;Hitachi no suke&apos; (assistant governor of Hitachi Province) and &apos;Kazusa no suke&apos; (assistant governor of Kazusa Province) to the kokushi of Hitachi and Kazusa respectively.</e>
<cmt>「常陸国」「上総国」→意味が不明瞭なためウェブで確認したところ「常陸介」「上総介」と記載されており、こちらに基づき訳文を修正しました。Taira no Masakado→TAIRA no Masakadoに修正、シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>叛乱勢力であり親王任国の慣習を守る必要は無いのだが、伝統として定着していたのであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being a rebel, he was not obliged to observe the custom of Shinno-ningoku, but it seems this custom took root as a tradition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Being a rebel, he was not obliged to observe the custom of Shinno-ningoku, but it seems this custom took root as a tradition.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Being a rebel, he was not obliged to observe the custom of Shinno-ningoku, but it seems this custom took root as a tradition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>しかし何故か上野だけは「上野守」を任命している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of Kozuke Province, however, he appointed &quot;Kozuke no kami&quot; (governor of Kozuke Province), though its reason is not cleaonly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of Kozuke Province, however, he appointed &quot;Kozuke no kami&quot; (governor of Kozuke Province), though its reason is not clear.</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of Kozuke Province, however, he appointed &apos;Kozuke no kami&apos; (governor of Kozuke Province), though its reason is not clear.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="22">
<j>時代が下り、後醍醐天皇の建武の新政期には、一時期陸奥国も親王任国とされ、義良親王が陸奥国太守として実際に陸奥国へ赴任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kenmu Restoration period led by the Emperor Godaigo, Mutsu Province was also designated as Shinno-ningoku for a while and Imperial Prince Norinaga actually went to Mutsu Province as the Taishu of Mutsu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kenmu Restoration period led by the Emperor Godaigo, Mutsu Province was also designated as Shinno-ningoku for a while and Imperial Prince Norinaga actually went to Mutsu Province as the Taishu of Mutsu Province.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kenmu Restoration period led by the Emperor Godaigo, Mutsu Province was also designated as Shinno-ningoku for a while and Imperial Prince Norinaga actually went to Mutsu Province as the Taishu of Mutsu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="23">
<j>名目としての親王任国はその後も継続した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinno-ningoku continued to exist nominally ever since.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinno-ningoku continued to exist nominally ever since.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinno-ningoku continued to exist nominally ever since.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>織田信長が「上総介」を僭称し松平忠輝が任官し、本多正純、吉良義央、小栗忠順が「上野介」を任官したのも、名目のみとは言え、「上総守」「上野守」の官職が親王のみにしか許されなかったからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason why Nobunaga ODA called himself &quot;Kazusa no suke&quot;and Tadateru MATSUNAGA was appointed to &quot;Kazusa no suke&quot;, or Masazumi HONDA, Yoshinaka KIRA and Tadamasa OGURI were appointed to &quot;Kozuke no suke&quot; was because the use of &quot;Kazusa no kami&quot; and &quot;Kozuke no kami&quot; was limited to Imperial Princes, though these titles were only nominal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason why Nobunaga ODA called himself &quot;Kazusa no suke&quot;and Tadateru MATSUNAGA was appointed to &quot;Kazusa no suke,&quot; or Masazumi HONDA, Yoshinaka KIRA, and Tadamasa OGURI were appointed to &quot;Kozuke no suke&quot; was because the use of &quot;Kazusa no kami&quot; and &quot;Kozuke no kami&quot; was limited to Imperial Princes, though these titles were only nominal.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason why Nobunaga ODA called himself &apos;Kazusa no suke&apos; and Tadateru MATSUNAGA was appointed to &apos;Kazusa no suke,&apos; or Masazumi HONDA, Yoshinaka KIRA, and Tadamasa OGURI were appointed to &apos;Kozuke no suke&apos; was because the use of &apos;Kazusa no kami&apos; and &apos;Kozuke no kami&apos; was limited to Imperial Princes, though these titles were only nominal.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更、スペース追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 PATMAN(id:145791), Lonicera(id:20638), Shimoxx(id:9332), Richknight(id:141069), Azusayumi7(id:21082), BAKU(id:55205), 水野白楓(id:22811), Hannah(id:15935), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>