<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>八甲田雪中行軍遭難事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Death March of Hakkoda Mountains Incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Death March of Hakkoda Mountains Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Death March of Hakkoda Mountains Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>八甲田雪中行軍遭難事件（はっこうだせっちゅうこうぐんそうなんじけん）は、1月に大日本帝国陸軍第8師団 (日本軍)の歩兵第5連隊が八甲田山で冬季訓練中に遭難した事件。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Death March of Hakkoda Mountains Incident was the incident that the 5th Infantry Regiment of the 8th Imperial Japanese Army (IJA) division was stranded while being on a training exercise on Hakkoda-san Mountain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Death March of Hakkoda Mountains Incident was the incident in which the 5th Infantry Regiment of the 8th Imperial Japanese Army (IJA) division was stranded while on a training exercise on Hakkoda-san Mountain.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Death March of Hakkoda Mountains Incident was the incident in which the fifth Infantry Regiment of the eighth Imperial Japanese Army (IJA) division was stranded while on a training exercise on the Hakkoda-san Mountain.</e>
<cmt>spacing, grammerを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>訓練への参加者210名中199名が死亡する、日本の冬山登山史上もっとも多くの遭難者が発生した事件となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It had the greatest number of missing people in Japanese winter mountain-climbing history, with 199 of 210 who had joined the training died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It had the greatest number of missing people in Japanese winter mountain-climbing history, with 199 of 210 who had joined the training died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It had the greatest number of missing people in Japanese winter mountain-climbing history, with 199 of 210 who had joined the training died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>事件の背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>事件の背景には、日本陸軍が冬季訓練を緊急の課題としていたことが挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan&apos;s considering wintertime training the most urgent task was the background of the incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan&apos;s consideration that wintertime training was to be the most urgent task was the background of the incident.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan&apos;s consideration that wintertime training was to be the most urgent task was the background of the incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>日本陸軍はの日清戦争で冬季寒冷地での戦いに苦戦し、そしてさらなる厳寒地での戦いとなる対ロシア戦を想定し、準備していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese Army was preparing for the battle against Russia in which it would fight in colder region than the Japanese-Sino War, which Japanese Army had had a tough fight in cold climates.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese Army was preparing for the battle against Russia in which it would fight in colder regions than the Japanese-Sino War where the Japanese Army had had a tough fight in cold climates.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese Army was preparing for the battle against Russia in which it would fight in colder regions than the Japanese-Sino War where the Japanese Army had had a tough fight in cold climates.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>こうした想定は、事件から2年後のに日露戦争として現実のものとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such assumption became a reality after 2 years after the incident as Russo-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This assumption became a reality 2 years after the incident, as the Russo-Japanese War began.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This assumption became a reality two years after the incident, as the Russo-Japanese War began.</e>
<cmt>wordingを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>この演習の目的は、ロシア海軍の艦隊が津軽海峡（北海道と青森との間）に入り、青森の海岸沿いの列車が動かなくなった際に、日本海側と太平洋側から、それぞれ移動するための演習であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The aim of that training was to move the troops from the Sea of Japan side and the Pacific side respectively assuming the fleets of Russia navy had entered Tsugaru Straits (between Hokkaido and Aomori) and the train on the coast of Aomori couldn&apos;t have moved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The aim of that training was to move the troops from the Sea of Japan side and the Pacific side respectively assuming the fleets of the Russian navy had entered the Tsugaru Straits (between Hokkaido and Aomori) and the train on the coast of Aomori couldn&apos;t move.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The aim of that training was to move the troops from the Sea of Japan side and the Pacific side respectively assuming the fleets of the Russian navy had entered the Tsugaru Straits (between Hokkaido and Aomori) and the train on the coast of Aomori couldn&apos;t move.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そのルートは「弘前～十和田湖畔～三本木～田代～青森」と「青森～田代～三本木～八戸」の2ルートが考えられ、弘前ルートは弘前第31連隊が、八戸ルートは青森5連隊がそれぞれ受持つ形となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the two route considered was &apos;Hirosaki-Sanbongi-Tashiro-Aomori&apos; and the other was &apos;Aomori-Tashiro-Sanbongi-Hachinohe&apos;, and the 31th Hirosaki Regiment took on the former, the 5th Aomori Regiment the latter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the two routes considered was &apos;Hirosaki-Sanbongi-Tashiro-Aomori&apos; and the other was &apos;Aomori-Tashiro-Sanbongi-Hachinohe&apos;. The 31st Hirosaki Regiment took on the former, the 5th Aomori Regiment the latter.</e>
<cmt>sentence structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the two routes considered was &apos;Hirosaki-the bank of Lake Towada-Sanbongi-Tashiro-Aomori&apos; and the other was &apos;Aomori-Tashiro-Sanbongi-Hachinohe;&apos; the 31st Hirosaki Regiment took on the former and the 5th Aomori Regiment the latter.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ部分を訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>このような形になったのは全くの偶然であり、弘前第31連隊は「雪中行軍に関する服装、行軍方法等」の全般に亘る研究が目的だったのに対し、青森第5連隊は「雪中における軍の展開、物資の輸送の可否」が目的だったとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such allocation was by pure accident, and it appears the aim of the 5th Aomori Regiment was to research &apos;how to deploy the troop in the snow and whether or not it is possible to carry the goods&apos; while that of the 31th Hirosaki Regiment was to research of &apos;the attire for march in snow, the way of marching and others&apos; as a whole.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such allocations were by pure accident, and it appears the aim of the 5th Aomori Regiment was to research &apos;how to deploy the troops in the snow and whether or not it is possible to carry the goods&apos;. While that of the 31st Hirosaki Regiment was to research &apos;the attire for the march in snow, the way of marching and others&apos; as a whole.</e>
<cmt>sentence structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such allocations were by pure accident, and it appears the aim of the 5th Aomori Regiment was to research &apos;how to deploy the troops in the snow and whether or not it is possible to carry the goods,&apos; while that of the 31st Hirosaki Regiment was to research &apos;the attire for march in the snow, the way of marching and others&apos; as a whole.</e>
<cmt>grammerを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>遭難部隊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Missing troop</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Missing troops</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Missing troops</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>遭難したのは、青森市を衛戍地とする歩兵第5連隊第2大隊である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The troop got lost was the 2nd Battalion, 5th Infantry Regiment whose garrison was in Aomori City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The troops that got lost were members of the 2nd Battalion, 5th Infantry Regiment whose garrison was in Aomori City.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The troops that got lost were members of the second Battalion, fifth Infantry Regiment whose garrison was in Aomori City.</e>
<cmt>spellingを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>部隊の指揮を執っていたのは、中隊長で陸軍歩兵大尉の神成文吉（かんなりぶんきち）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Company Commander and Army Infantry Captain Bunkichi KANNARI leaded the troop.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Company Commander and Army Infantry Captain Bunkichi KANNARI led the troops.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Company Commander and Army Infantry Captain Bunkichi KANNARI led the troops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>但し、大隊長で少佐の山口鋠が指揮に関与したとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is said Shin YAMAGUCHI, a Battalion Commander and Major was involved in giving directions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is said Shin YAMAGUCHI, a Battalion Commander and Major was involved in giving directions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is said Shin YAMAGUCHI, a Battalion Commander and Major was involved in giving directions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>神成文吉大尉は、秋田県の出身で、陸軍教導団を経て陸軍歩兵二等軍曹に任官し、順次昇進して陸軍歩兵大尉となった人物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Captain Bunkichi KANNARI was from Akita Prefecture, assigned as a staff sergeant of Army Infantry after trained in Rikugun Kyododan (an academy established to train noncommissioned officers) and became Army Infantry Captain, being promoted sequentially.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Captain Bunkichi KANNARI, from Akita Prefecture, was assigned as a staff sergeant of the Army Infantry after having trained in Rikugun Kyododan (an academy established to train noncommissioned officers) and became Army Infantry Captain, being promoted sequentially.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Captain Bunkichi KANNARI, from Akita Prefecture, was assigned as a staff sergeant of the Army Infantry after having trained in Rikugun Kyododan (an academy established to train noncommissioned officers) and became Army Infantry Captain, being promoted sequentially.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>神成大尉の命を受けて危急を知らせる途上で仮死状態となっていた後藤房之助伍長が1月27日に捜索隊に発見されたことから、遭難の詳細が判明した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The incident became clear when Corporal Fusanosuke GOTO, who was on the way to inform the emergency on Captain Kannari&apos;s command, was found in a state of apparent death by the searching party on January 27.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The incident became clear when Corporal Fusanosuke GOTO who, on Captain Kannari&apos;s command, was on the way to inform of the emergency and was found in a state of apparent death by the search party on January 27.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The incident became clear when Corporal Fusanosuke GOTO who, on Captain Kannari&apos;s command, was on the way to inform of the emergency and was found in a state of apparent death by the search party on January 27.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>5月28日に全遺体が収容された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All bodies of deceased persons were recovered on May 28.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All bodies of the deceased were recovered on May 28.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All bodies of the deceased were recovered on May 28.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>最終的に生存したのは、倉石一大尉（山形）、伊藤格明中尉（山形）、長谷川貞三特務曹長（秋田）、後藤房之助伍長（宮城）、小原忠三郎伍長（岩手）、及川平助伍長（岩手）、村松文哉伍長（宮城）、阿部卯吉一等卒（岩手）、後藤惣助一等卒（岩手）、山本徳次郎一等卒（青森）、阿部寿松一等卒（岩手）、の11人のみであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Final survivors were only 11 persons; Captain Hajime KURAISHI, Lieutenant Masaaki ITO (Yamagata Prefecture), Sergeant Major Teizo HASEGAWA (Akita Prefecture), Corporal Fusanosuke GOTO (Miyagi Prefecture), Corporal Chuzaburo OHARA (Iwate Prefecture), Corporal Heisuke OIKAWA (Iwate Prefecture), Corporal Fumichika MURAMATSU (Miyagi Prefecture), Private First Ukichi ABE (Iwate Prefecture), Private First Sousuke GOTO (Iwate Prefecture), Private First Tokujiro YAMAMOTO (Aomori Prefecture), Private First Hisamatsu ABE (Iwate Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>伊藤格明、長谷川貞三、小原忠三郎、村松文哉(定訳不明。該当する読みが見つかりませんでした。）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Final survivors were only 11 persons; Captain Hajime KURAISHI, Lieutenant Masaaki ITO (Yamagata Prefecture), Sergeant Major Teizo HASEGAWA (Akita Prefecture), Corporal Fusanosuke GOTO (Miyagi Prefecture), Corporal Chuzaburo OHARA (Iwate Prefecture), Corporal Heisuke OIKAWA (Iwate Prefecture), Corporal Fumichika MURAMATSU (Miyagi Prefecture), Private First Ukichi ABE (Iwate Prefecture), Private First Sousuke GOTO (Iwate Prefecture), Private First Tokujiro YAMAMOTO (Aomori Prefecture), Private First Hisamatsu ABE (Iwate Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Final survivors were only 11 persons; Captain Hajime KURAISHI (Yamagata Prefecture), Lieutenant Masaaki ITO (Yamagata Prefecture), Sergeant Major Teizo HASEGAWA (Akita Prefecture), Corporal Fusanosuke GOTO (Miyagi Prefecture), Corporal Chuzaburo OHARA (Iwate Prefecture), Corporal Heisuke OIKAWA (Iwate Prefecture), Corporal Fumichika MURAMATSU (Miyagi Prefecture), Private First Ukichi ABE (Iwate Prefecture), Private First Sosuke GOTO (Iwate Prefecture), Private First Tokujiro YAMAMOTO (Aomori Prefecture), Private First Hisamatsu ABE (Iwate Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ、spellingを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>生存した将兵も、倉石大尉、伊藤中尉、長谷川特務曹長以外の、そのほとんどが凍傷により足や手の切断を余儀なくされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of the survivors were forced to have their legs and arms amputated due to frostbite except Captain Kuraishi, Lieutenant Ito and Sergeant Major Hasegawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of the survivors were forced to have their legs and arms amputated due to frostbite except Captain Kuraishi, Lieutenant Ito and Sergeant Major Hasegawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of the survivors were forced to have their legs and arms amputated due to frostbite except Captain Kuraishi, Lieutenant Ito and Sergeant Major Hasegawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>軽症な方では、及川はアキレス腱と指3本、山本は左足を切断した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As rather mild cases, Oikawa had his Achilles tendon and three fingers amputated and Yamamoto his left leg.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As rather mild cases, Oikawa had his Achilles tendon and three fingers amputated and Yamamoto his left leg.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As rather mild cases, Oikawa had his Achilles tendon and three fingers amputated and Yamamoto his left leg.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>その他は四肢切断であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others had their extremities amputated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others had their extremities amputated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others had their extremities amputated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>また、一番元気だった倉石大尉は日露戦争の黒溝台会戦で1月27日に戦死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Captain Kuraishi, who had been injured most slightly, died in the Battle of Kokkoudai in Russo-Japanese War on January 27.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Captain Kuraishi, who had been injured most slightly, died in the Battle of Kokkoudai in the Russo-Japanese War on January 27.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Captain Kuraishi, who had been injured most slightly, died in the Battle of Kokkodai in the Russo-Japanese War on January 27.</e>
<cmt>spellingを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>伊藤中尉、長谷川特務曹長も重傷を負った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lieutenant Ito and Sergeant Major Hasegawa were seriously injured.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lieutenant Ito and Sergeant Major Hasegawa were seriously injured.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lieutenant Ito and Sergeant Major Hasegawa were seriously injured.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="21">
<j>銅像が立てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bronze statue was built, however, Fusanosuke KONDO himself could hardly see it with embarrassment, though he was told to take a close look at it by Colonel of a regiment at that time.</e>
<cmt>冒頭の　、　は、無いものとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A bronze statue was built. However, Fusanosuke KONDO himself could hardly look at it without embarrassment, though he was told to take a close look at it by the Colonel of a regiment at that time.</e>
<cmt>sentence structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A bronze statue was built.</e>
<cmt>grammer、一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>が、後藤房之助本人は当時の連隊長に「よく見ろ」と言われたが、照れくさくなかなか見ることができなかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Howevr, Fusanosuke KONDO himself could hardly look at it without embarrassment, though he was told to take a close look at it by the Colonel of a regiment at that time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>彼は遭難の話はあまり話したがらず、また、後藤伍長は同じく生き残りの村松伍長と仲が良かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He didn&apos;t want to talk much about the incident and got along well with Corporal Muramatsu, who was also a survivor of the incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He didn&apos;t want to talk much about the incident and got along well with Corporal Muramatsu, who was also a survivor of the incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He didn&apos;t want to talk much about the incident and got along well with Corporal Muramatsu, who was also a survivor of the incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>原因するが岩手と宮城の兵士たちにとっては凄まじい惨劇となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a terrible disaster to the soldiers of Iwate and Miyagi.</e>
<cmt>原因するが（文意不明の為、訳しませんでした。）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a terrible disaster to the soldiers of Iwate and Miyagi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a terrible disaster to the soldiers of Iwate and Miyagi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="25">
<j>後藤伍長は銅像のほか、現在青森県道40号青森田代十和田線の路上に「後藤伍長発見の地」という板が立っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than the bronze statue of Corporal Goto, there stands a plate which read &apos;this is the place where Corporal Goto was found&apos; on the current Aomori Prefectural Highway 40 Aomori Tashiro Towada Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than the bronze statue of Corporal Goto, there stands a plate which reads, &apos;This is the place where Corporal Goto was found.&apos;, on the current Aomori Prefectural Highway 40, Aomori Tashiro Towada Line.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than the bronze statue of Corporal Goto, there stands a plate which reads, &apos;This is the place where Corporal Goto was found.&apos;, on the current Aomori Prefectural Highway 40, Aomori Tashiro Towada Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>ただし、発見の地は銅像よりも数キロ青森よりの場所である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, actual place he was found is a several kilometers nearer Aomori from the statue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the actual place he was found is several kilometers closer to Aomori than the statue.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the actual place he was found is several kilometers closer to Aomori than the statue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>銅像の場所は馬立場付近で、第二露営地と第三露営地の間である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The place of the statue is near Umatateba, between the second camping ground and the third camping ground.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The location of the statue is near Umatateba, between the second camping ground and the third camping ground.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The location of the statue is near Umatateba, between the second camping ground and the third camping ground.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="28">
<j>銅像に向かうスキーのコースは銅像コースと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ski course toward the statue is called the statue course.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ski course toward the statue is called the statue course.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ski course toward the statue is called the statue course.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>同コースでは、2月14日に、死者2人・重軽傷者8人を出す雪崩事故が発生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A snowslide accident in which 2 people were killed and 8 injured was occurred in February 14 on that course.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A snowslide accident in which 2 people were killed and 8 injured occurred on February 14 on this course.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A snowslide accident in which two people were killed and eight injured occurred on February 14 on this course.</e>
<cmt>spellingを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>遭難経緯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The process of the missing</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The process of the missing</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The process of the missing</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>第1日（1月23日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first day (January 23)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first day (January 23)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first day (January 23)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="30">
<j>午前6時に青森連隊駐屯地を出発。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They left Aomori regimental post at 6 a.m.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They left Aomori regimental post at 6 a.m.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They left Aomori regimental post at 6 a.m.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>田茂木野において地元村民が案内役を買ってでるが、これを断り地図と方位磁針のみで厳寒期の八甲田山走破を行うことになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A local villager offered a guide at Tamogino, they declined it, making a journey on midwinter Hakkoda-san Mountain only with a map and compass.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A local villager offered a guide at Tamogino but they declined it, making the journey on midwinter Hakkoda-san Mountain only with a map and compass.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A local villager offered a guide at Tamogino but they declined it, making the journey on midwinter Hakkoda-san Mountain only with a map and compass.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="32">
<j>途中小峠まではさしたる障害もなく進軍できた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They managed to march without so many obstaclesuntil they reached Kotouge (small pass).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They managed to march without so many obstaclesuntil they reached Kotouge (small pass).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They managed to march without so many obstaclesuntil they reached Kotouge (small pass).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>しかし、大峠付近にて天候が悪化し、ソリ隊も遅れはじめたことから、大休止を取った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, they took a long halt near Ootouge (big pass) the weather was getting worse and sledge troop became straggling.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, they took a long halt near Ootouge (big pass) as the weather was getting worse and the sledge troop began straggling.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, they took a long halt near Otouge (big pass) as the weather was getting worse and the sledge troop began straggling.</e>
<cmt>spellingを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>携帯した食料類は凍りついてしまい食事を取らない兵士が大多数を占める事態となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The provisions they had brought was frozen, which forced most of the soldiers to suffer without food.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The provisions they had brought froze, which forced most of the soldiers to suffer without food.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The provisions they had brought froze, which forced most of the soldiers to suffer from no food.</e>
<cmt>grammerを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>装備の不安と天候がさらに悪化することを恐れ、駐屯地への一時帰営を協議したが下士官などの反対により、行軍を続行することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Returning to the post once was discussed due to concerns about equipment and deteriorating weather, however, they continued marching as noncommissioned officers opposed it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Returning to the post was discussed once due to concerns about equipment and deteriorating weather. However, they continued marching even as noncommissioned officers opposed it.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Returning to the post was discussed once due to concerns about equipment and deteriorating weather, however, they continued marching even as noncommissioned officers opposed it.</e>
<cmt>grammerを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="36">
<j>風雪をやり過ごしながら馬立場（大峠より2km）まで進軍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They marched to Umatateba (2 kilometers from Ootoge) passing harmlessly through wind and snow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They marched to Umatateba (2 kilometers from Ootoge) passing harmlessly through wind and snow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They marched to Umatateba (two kilometers from Otoge) passing harmlessly through wind and snow.</e>
<cmt>spellingを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>ここから積雪量が格段に深くなり、行軍速度が落ち、食料と燃料などを積んだソリ部隊は本隊より1時間以上遅れることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From there, snow depth became much deeper, marching speed slowed down, the sledge troop carrying provisions and fuel dropped behind from the main troop more than an hour.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From there, snow became much deeper, marching speed slowed down, and the sledge troop carrying provisions and fuel dropped behind the main troop more than an hour.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From there, snow became much deeper, marching speed slowed down, and the sledge troop carrying provisions and fuel dropped behind the main troop more than an hour.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>神成大尉は第2、第3小隊計88名をソリ隊の応援に向かわせると同時に、設営隊15名を田代方面に斥候を兼ねた先遣隊として先行させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Captain Kannari made the second and the third platoons, 88 people in total, go to help the sledge troop and a construction party, 15 people, go first as an advance troop and patrol toward Tashiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Captain Kannari made the second and the third platoons, 88 people in total, go to help the sledge troop and a construction party, 15 people, go first as an advance troop and patrol toward Tashiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Captain Kannari made the second and the third platoons, 88 people in total, go to help the sledge troop and a construction party, 15 people, go first as an advance troop and patrol toward Tashiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="39">
<j>夜6時、鳴沢付近でソリの放棄を決定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At 6 p.m. the abandonment of sledges was decided near Narusawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At 6 p.m. the abandonment of sledges was decided near Narusawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At 6 p.m. the abandonment of sledges was decided near Narusawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>ソリの荷物については、各隊員が分散して持つこととなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Things on the sled were allocated to soldiers to carry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Things on the sled were allocated to soldiers to carry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Things on the sled were allocated to soldiers to carry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>このとき炊飯用の銅釜を持たされた兵士が一番悲惨だったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said the soldiers assigned to carry copper cookers were most miserable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said the soldiers assigned to carry copper cookers were most miserable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said the soldiers assigned to carry copper cookers were most miserable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>先遣隊として先行していた設営隊も進路を発見できず、道に迷っていたところを偶然にも本隊と合流した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The construction party which was going ahead as an advance troop could not find the track, joining together the main party by accident while being lost.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The construction party which was going ahead as an advance troop could not find the track, joining together the main party by accident while being lost.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The construction party which was going ahead as an advance troop could not find the track, joining together the main party by accident while being lost.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="43">
<j>夜8時過ぎに田代元湯まであと1.5kmの平沢の森まで進出するが、日没により前後不覚となり田代方面への進路も発見できなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After 8 p.m. they reached Hirasawa forest which was 1.5km from Tashiro Motoyu, however, they lost even the track toward Tashiro, being blinded by sundown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After 8 p.m. they reached Hirasawa forest which was 1.5km from Tashiro Motoyu, however, they lost even the track toward Tashiro, being blinded by sundown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After 8 p.m. they reached Hirasawa forest which was 1.5km from Tashiro Motoyu, however, they lost even the track toward Tashiro, being blinded by sundown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>そのため、これ以上の行軍は不可能と判断し雪濠を掘って露営することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, they dig a moat in the snow and camped out, making a decision that it was impossible to march anymore.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, they dug a moat in the snow and camped out, making a decision that it was impossible to march anymore.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, they dug a moat in the snow and camped out, making a decision that it was impossible to march anymore.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>第2日（1月24日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second day (January 24)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second day (January 24)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second day (January 24)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="45">
<j>前日の強行軍が災いし、寒さと疲労を訴える者が続出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many people complained of coldness and fatigue due to the forced march previous day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many people complained of coldness and fatigue due to the forced march the previous day.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many people complained of coldness and fatigue due to the forced march the previous day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>暖を取ろうにも炭火などの燃料が用を成さず、部隊は遭難に近い状態となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fuel such as charcoal fire didn&apos;t work for them to have a warm, and the troop went nearly missing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fuel such as charcoal fire didn&apos;t work for them to have warmth, and the troops nearly went missing.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fuel such as charcoal fire didn&apos;t work for them to have warmth, and the troops nearly went missing.</e>
<cmt>spacingを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>午前2時頃、この事態を重く見た行軍指導部は部隊の帰営を決定する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About 2 a.m. Army officers decided to return to the post, taking the matter seriously.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">About 2 a.m. Army officers decided to return to the post, taking the matter seriously.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">About 2 a.m. Army officers decided to return to the post, taking the matter seriously.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="48">
<j>部隊は馬立場を目指すが午前3時半ごろに鳴沢付近でゴルジュに迷い込み、崖をよじ登ることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The troop started toward Umatateba, however, they were lost into gorge near Narusawa around 3 a.m., forced to climb the cliff.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The troops started toward Umatateba. However, they were lost in a gorge near Narusawa around 3 a.m., forced to climb the cliff.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The troops started toward Umatateba, however, they were lost in a gorge near Narusawa around 3 a.m., forced to climb the cliff.</e>
<cmt>grammerを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>ここで崖を登れず落伍する兵がでてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some soldiers dropped out, unable to climb the cliff.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some soldiers dropped out, unable to climb the cliff.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some soldiers dropped out, unable to climb the cliff.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>この行軍における最初の犠牲者であるが、猛吹雪で誰も確認ができなかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although they were the first victims of this march, nobody could confirm that in such a blizzard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although they were the first victims of this march, nobody could confirm that in such a blizzard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although they were the first victims of this march, nobody could confirm that in such a blizzard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="51">
<j>途中、午前8時半ごろに佐藤特務曹長が田代元湯に至る道を発見したと上層部に進言した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the way, Sergeant Major Sato told the top officers that he had found the track leading to Tashiro Motoyu around 8 a.m.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the way, around 8am, Sergeant Major Sato told the top officers that he had found the track leading to Tashiro Motoyu.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the way, around 8 a.m., Sergeant Major Sato told the top officers that he had found the track leading to Tashiro Motoyu.</e>
<cmt>grammerを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>この進言に基づき山口少佐が独断により佐藤特務曹長の言を採用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Received that, Major Yamaguchi adopted Sergeant Major Sato&apos;s offer on his own authority.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On receiving this news, Major Yamaguchi adopted Sergeant Major Sato&apos;s offer on his own authority.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On receiving this news, Major Yamaguchi adopted Sergeant Major Sato&apos;s offer on his own authority.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>佐藤特務曹長に隊の教導を任せた上で、進路を再び田代に変更した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He changed the course again to Tashiro, leaving the command of the troop to Sergeant Major Sato.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He changed the course again to Tashiro, leaving the command of the troops to Sergeant Major Sato.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He changed the course again to Tashiro, leaving the command of the troops to Sergeant Major Sato.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="54">
<j>駒込川の沢に到達するが、その頃の進軍は全員疲労困憊しており、隊列も整わず統制に支障が出始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They reached the stream of Komagome-gawa River, however, all soldiers were completely exhausted by then, which affected the control, breaking formation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They reached the stream of Komagome-gawa River, however, all soldiers were completely exhausted by then, which affected the control, breaking formation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They reached the stream of Komagome-gawa River, however, all soldiers were completely exhausted by then, which affected the control, breaking formation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>駒込川に至ったことで佐藤特務曹長の進言が誤りだったことに気付く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reaching Komagome-gawa River made them realize what Sergeant Major Sato had told was not correct, however, the way to return was erased completely in the blizzard, making the troop lost their way.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reaching Komagome-gawa River made them realize what Sergeant Major Sato had told was not correct. However, the way to return was erased completely in the blizzard, making the troops lose their way.</e>
<cmt>sentence structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reaching Komagome-gawa River made them realize what Sergeant Major Sato had told was not correct.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>が、もと来た道は吹雪により完全に消されており部隊は完全に前後不覚の状態になり遭難となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the way to return was erased completely in the blizzard, making the troops lose their way.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="57">
<j>再び断崖を登ることになり、ここでも転落落伍者をだした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were forced to climb a cliff again, making also dropouts who fell from it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were forced to climb a cliff again, causing more dropouts who fell.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were forced to climb a cliff again, causing more dropouts who fell.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>駒込川の沢を脱出する際、第4小隊の水野中尉が従卒と共に卒倒の上凍死し、部隊の士気が下がった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lieutenant Mizuno of the 4th platoon fainted down along with his orderly and died while they were escaping from the stream of Komagome-gawa River, which lowered the morale of the troop.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lieutenant Mizuno of the 4th platoon fainted along with his orderly and died while they were escaping from the stream of Komagome-gawa River. This lowered the morale of the troops.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lieutenant Mizuno of the fouth platoon fainted along with his orderly and died while they were escaping from the stream of Komagome-gawa River, which lowered the morale of the troops.</e>
<cmt>grammer,spellingを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="59">
<j>夕方頃に鳴沢付近にて凹地を発見し、ここを露営地とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They found the depression contour near Narusawa in the evening, camping out there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They found the depression contour near Narusawa in the evening, camping out there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They found the depression contour near Narusawa in the evening, camping out there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>部隊は統制が取れない上、雪濠を掘ろうにもそれらの道具を所持していた隊員は全員落伍して行方不明となっており、文字通り吹曝しの露天に露営する状態となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They had to camp out literally windblown outdoor because the soldiers carrying the tools to dig a moat in the snow had dropped out and disappeared, besides, the troop was out of control.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They had to camp out literally in the windblown open because the soldiers carrying the tools to dig a moat in the snow had dropped out and disappeared. Besides, the troop was out of control.</e>
<cmt>sentence structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The troop was out of control and, furthermore, they had to camp out literally in the windblown open because the soldiers carrying the tools to dig a moat in the snow had dropped out and disappered.</e>
<cmt>sentence structureを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>吹雪で体感温度が-50℃近く、また前日よりほとんど不眠不休で絶食状態であるため、ここで多くの将兵が昏倒し、凍死していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many soldiers fell unconscious, frozen to death there due to nearly -50 degrees Celsius of sensory temperature caused by the blizzard and their being sleepless and food-deprived since previous day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many soldiers fell unconscious and froze to death there due to nearly -50 degrees Celsius temperatures. Being sleepless and food-deprived since the previous day also contributed to their deaths.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many soldiers fell unconscious and froze to death there due to nearly -50 degrees Celsius temperatures because sleepless and food-deprived since the previous day also contributed to their deaths.</e>
<cmt>sentence structureを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="62">
<j>一方、青森では帰営予定日時になっても帰営しない行軍隊を迎えに行くため、川和田少尉以下40名が田茂木野まで出迎えに行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, from Aomori side, 40 people including Junior Lieutenant Kawawada went to Tamogino to meet the marching troop, which had not returned after scheduled date and time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, from theAomori side, 40 people including Junior Lieutenant Kawawada went to Tamogino to meet the marching troop, which had not returned by the scheduled date and time.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, from the Aomori side, 40 people including Junior Lieutenant Kawawada went to Tamogino to meet the marching troop, which had not returned by the scheduled date and time.</e>
<cmt>spacing修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>しかし24時まで待ったが消息がなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They waited until 24 o&apos;clock, though there was no word about the troop.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They waited until midnight, though there was no word about the troop.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They waited until midnight, though there was no word about the troop.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>この日は弘前連隊へ転出する松木中尉の送別会を催していたが、出席者は「この場で行軍隊が戻ってきたらうれしい話だな」と話し合っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The farewell party was given on that day for Lieutenant Matsuki, who was moving out to Hirosaki Regiment, and participants were saying &apos;It is good if the marching troop return now.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The farewell party was given on that day for Lieutenant Matsuki, who was moving out to Hirosaki Regiment, and participants were saying &apos;It would be good if the marching troop returned now.&apos;</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The farewell party was given on that day for Lieutenant Matsuki, who was moving out to Hirosaki Regiment, and participants were saying &apos;It would be good if the marching troop returned now.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>第3日（1月25日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The third day (January 25)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The third day (January 25)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The third day (January 25)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="65">
<j>午前3時頃、部隊は馬立場方面を目指して出発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around 3 a.m. the troop started off toward Umatateba.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around 3 a.m. the troop started off toward Umatateba.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around 3 a.m. the troop started off toward Umatateba.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>この時点で死者、行方不明者合わせて40名を超えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dead and the disappeared tallied more than 40 at that point.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dead and the disappeared tallied more than 40 at that point.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dead and the disappeared tallied more than 40 at that point.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>その他の兵士も多くは凍傷にかかっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of the remaining soldiers were frostbitten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of the remaining soldiers were frostbitten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of the remaining soldiers were frostbitten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>コンパスは凍りついて用を成さず、地図を頼りに、ほぼ勘に頼っての行軍となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They marched following their hunches, relying on the map because the compass was frozen and didn&apos;t work.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They marched following their instincts, relying on the map because the compass was frozen and didn&apos;t work.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They marched following their instincts, relying on the map because the compass was frozen and didn&apos;t work.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="69">
<j>途中再び道を見失った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They lost their route again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They lost their route again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They lost their route again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>先頭で教導していた神成大尉は誰ともなく以下のように命令した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You&apos;re dismissed now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You&apos;re dismissed now.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Captain Kannari, who led the troop, at large ordered as follows.</e>
<cmt>「」書きなど原文修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>「ここで部隊を解散する。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You can return to Aomori on your own.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You can return to Aomori on your own.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You&apos;re dismissed now.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「」書きなど原文修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>「各自勝手に青森へ帰るように。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ordered Captain Kannari, who led the troop, at large.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ordered Captain Kannari, who led the troop, at large.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You can return to Aomori on your own.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「」書きなど原文修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>そのため、それまで何とか落伍せずに頑張っていた多くの兵士が、この一言により箍が外れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Which made the soldiers who remained with great effort not to drop out go mad, and many people were frozen to death in this way, taking off their clothes, going into the river yelling &apos;I&apos;ll go down the cliff so that I can reach Aomori&apos;, walking toward trees yelling&apos; I&apos;ll make a raft to down the river to go home.&apos; and fell.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This made many of the soldiers who remained, who had made great efforts not to drop out, go mad. Many people froze to death in this way, taking off their clothes, going into the river yelling, &apos;I&apos;ll go down the cliff so that I can reach Aomori&apos;, or walking toward trees yelling, &apos;I&apos;ll make a raft to go down the river to go home.&apos;</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This made many of the soldiers who remained, who had made great efforts not to drop out, go mad.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>発狂して服を脱ぎ始める者、「この崖を降りれば青森だ!」と叫び川に飛び込む者、「筏を作って川下りをして帰るぞ」と叫び樹に向かって行きそのまま倒れこむ者と、凍死者が続出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many people froze to death in this way, taking off their clothes, going into the river yelling, &apos;I&apos;ll go down the cliff so that I can reach Aomori&apos;, or walking toward trees yelling, &apos;I&apos;ll make a raft to go down the river to go home.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="75">
<j>この彷徨で興津大尉以下約30名が凍死。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That caused 30 people to be frozen to death including Captain Okitsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That caused 30 people to be frozen to death including Captain Okitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That caused 30 people to be frozen to death including Captain Okitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>昨晩の夕方から興津大尉は凍傷にかかっており軽石三蔵らが手当てしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Captain Okitsu had been frostbitten since previous evening and attended by Karuishi SANZO.</e>
<cmt>軽石三蔵（定訳不明、該当する読みが見つかりませんでした。）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Captain Okitsu had been frostbitten since the previous evening and was attended to by Karuishi SANZO.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Captain Okitsu had been frostbitten since the previous evening and was attended to by Karuishi SANZO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>2月12日の発見時には軽石二等卒は興津大尉を覆うように倒れていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When they were found on February 12, Private Karuishi was lying as if to cover Captain Okitsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When they were found on February 12, Private Karuishi was lying as if to cover Captain Okitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When they were found on February 12, Private Karuishi was lying as if to cover Captain Okitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>さらに、長谷川特務曹長など後に生存者として発見される兵士を含む兵士十数名が行方不明となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And more than a dozen soldiers disappeared including those who were found alive later such as Sergeant Major Hasegawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And more than a dozen soldiers disappeared including those who were found alive later such as Sergeant Major Hasegawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And more than a dozen soldiers disappeared including those who were found alive later such as Sergeant Major Hasegawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>長谷川特務曹長は滑落し道に迷っており、彼に従った数名は午後2時頃平沢の炭小屋を発見しそこに滞在していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sergeant Major Hasdgawa slipped drop and got lost, finding a charcoal house in Hirasawa about 2 p.m. and stayed there along with a few people following him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sergeant Major Hasdgawa slipped behind and got lost, finding a charcoal house in Hirasawa about 2 p.m. and stayed there along with a few people following him.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sergeant Major Hasdgawa slipped behind and got lost, finding a charcoal house in Hirasawa about 2 p.m. and stayed there along with a few people following him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>長谷川特務曹長が持っていたマッチで火を起し暖を取った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sergeant Major Hasegawa had a warm with matches, however, they put out the charcoal fire about at 3 a.m. on 26, the next day, afraid of a fire because they were all extremely exhausted, and they never had a warm after that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sergeant Major Hasegawa kept warm with matches. However, they put out the charcoal fire around 3 a.m. on the 26th, the next day, afraid of a fire because they were all extremely exhausted, and they never had warmth after that.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sergeant Major Hasegawa kept warm with matches.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>が全員疲労が激しく翌26日午前3時頃に火事になる可能性を恐れ炭火を消し、その後は暖を取ることは無かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, they put out the charcoal fire around 3 a.m. on the 26th, the next day, afraid of a fire because they were all extremely exhausted, and they never had warmth after that.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>本隊が午前5時30分頃に露営地に戻った頃に山口少佐が人事不省となり、倉石大尉は少佐に遺言を求めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major Yamaguchi fell unconscious when the main troop returned to the camp at 5:30 a.m. and Captain Kuraishi demanded the will of Major.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major Yamaguchi fell unconscious when the main troop returned to the camp at 5:30 a.m. and Captain Kuraishi demanded the command of the Major.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major Yamaguchi fell unconscious when the main troop returned to the camp at 5:30 a.m. and Captain Kuraishi asked the Major to leave a will.</e>
<cmt>grammerを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>後藤伍長には少佐はこの時死んだものと判断された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Corporal Goto assumed that the Major died then.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Corporal Goto assumed that the Major died then.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Corporal Goto assumed that the Major died then.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="84">
<j>午前7時頃、比較的冷静だった倉石大尉は斥候隊を募り、比較的元気な15名が馬立場方面への斥候へ向かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around 7 a.m. Captain Kuraishi, who was relatively calm, collected some soldiers as a patrol troop and 15 people who remained relatively strong started off toward Umatateba.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around 7 a.m. Captain Kuraishi, who was relatively calm, collected some soldiers as a patrol troop and 15 people who remained relatively strong started off toward Umatateba.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around 7 a.m. Captain Kuraishi, who was relatively calm, collected some soldiers as a patrol troop and 15 people who remained relatively strong started off toward Umatateba.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>これにより部隊は少なからずも平静を取り戻した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thanks for that, the troop regained its calmness a little, however, it didn&apos;t last long, and around 10 a.m. a soldier, having seen a tree swinging, screamed &apos;There comes rescue team!&apos;, which made others start screaming &apos;It&apos;s true!&apos; &apos;Mummy!&apos; one after another.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thanks to this, the troop regained its calm a little. However, it didn&apos;t last long, and around 10 a.m. a soldier, having seen a tree swinging, screamed &apos;There comes a rescue team!&apos;, which made others start screaming, &apos;It&apos;s true!&apos;, &apos;Mummy!&apos;, one after another.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thanks to this, the troop regained its calm a little.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>がその状況も長くは続かず、午前10時頃には木が揺れるのを見た1人の兵士が「救助隊が来た!」と叫ぶと、他の者も「本当に来た!」「母ちゃ～ん!」と叫び始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it didn&apos;t last long, and around 10 a.m. a soldier, having seen a tree swinging, screamed &apos;There comes a rescue team!&apos;, which made others start screaming, &apos;It&apos;s true!&apos;, &apos;Mummy!&apos;, one after another.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>倉石大尉は、その状況になる度に春日林太夫喇叭卒に喇叭を吹かせて冷静さを取り戻したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said Captain Kuraishi made Private Trumpet Hayashidayu KASUGA blow a trumpet to calm them down every time they got into such situations.</e>
<cmt>春日林太夫（定訳不明、該当する読みが見つかりませんでした。）喇叭卒(定訳不明です。）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said Captain Kuraishi made Private Trumpet Hayashidayu KASUGA blow a trumpet to calm them down every time they got into such situations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said Captain Kuraishi made Private Trumpet Hayashidayu KASUGA blow a trumpet to calm them down every time they got into such situations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>春日喇叭卒は喇叭が凍結していたため、唇がはがれ翌日凍死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Private Trumpet Kasuga was frozen to death on the following day because the trumpet had been frozen and made his lips fall off.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Private Trumpet Kasuga was frozen to death on the following day because the trumpet had been frozen and made his lips fall off.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Private Trumpet Kasuga was frozen to death on the following day because the trumpet had been frozen and made his lips fall off.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="89">
<j>佐々木霜吉一等卒が帰路を発見した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Private First Shimokichi SASAKI found the way to return.</e>
<cmt>佐々木霜吉（定訳不明、該当する読みが見つかりませんでした。）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Private First Shimokichi SASAKI found the way to return.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Private First Shimokichi SASAKI found the way to return.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>午前11時30分頃高橋斥候長が戻ってきて帰路を発見し田茂木方面へ進軍中との報告をした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around 11:30 a.m. Takahashi, the head of patrol troop, returned and informed that they had found the way home and was marching toward Tashiromogi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around 11:30 a.m., Takahashi, the head of patrol troop, returned and informed them that they had found the way home and were marching toward Tashiromogi.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around 11:30 a.m., Takahashi, the head of patrol troop, returned and informed them that they had found the way home and were marching toward Tashiromogi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>本隊は戻ってきた斥候隊に付いて行き、馬立場に到着した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main troop followed the patrol troop, reaching Umatateba.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main troop followed the patrol troop, reaching Umatateba.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main troop followed the patrol troop, reaching Umatateba.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>ここで渡辺幸之助軍曹らの残りの斥候隊からの報告を待った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They waited the word from other patrol troops including Sergeant Major Konosuke WATANABE, however, they never returned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They waited for word from other patrol troops including Sergeant Major Konosuke WATANABE. However, they never returned.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They waited for word from other patrol troops including Sergeant Major Konosuke WATANABE.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>が、残りの部隊はついに戻らなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, they never returned.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>また、馬立場付近で帰路を発見した佐々木一等卒と高橋伍長は重なり合うようにして凍死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And Private First Sasaki and Corporal Takahashi, who found the way home near Umatateba, were frozen to death lying on top of each other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And Private First Sasaki and Corporal Takahashi, who found the way home near Umatateba, were frozen to death lying on top of each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And Private First Sasaki and Corporal Takahashi, who found the way home near Umatateba, were frozen to death lying on top of each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>夜5時頃倉石大尉が気づいた時には大橋中尉、永井軍医が行方不明となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lieutenant Oohashi and army surgeon Nagai had already disappeared when Captain Kuraishi realized it around 5 p.m.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lieutenant Oohashi and army surgeon Nagai had already disappeared when Captain Kuraishi realized it around 5 p.m.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lieutenant Ohashi and army surgeon Nagai had already disappeared when Captain Kuraishi realized it around 5 p.m.</e>
<cmt>spellingを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>永井軍医や桜井龍造看護長といった医療班は、兵の看護を無理をして続けていたが、その結果本人達も斃れてしまう結果となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The people of medical detachment such as army surgeon Nagai and chief nurse Ryuzo SAKIRAI tried so hard treating other soldiers that they themselves fell in the end.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The people of the medical detachment, such as army surgeon Nagai and chief nurse Ryuzo SAKIRAI, tried so hard treating other soldiers that they themselves fell in the end.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The people of the medical detachment, such as army surgeon Nagai and chief nurse Ryuzo SAKURAI, tried so hard treating other soldiers that they themselves fell in the end.</e>
<cmt>spellingを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>この頃には完全に部隊はばらばらになっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The troop had been broken apart by that point.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The troop had been broken apart by that point.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The troop had been broken apart by that point.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="98">
<j>夜12時頃に、倉石大尉の一隊は山口少佐の一行と合流した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around 12 a.m. the troop of Captain Kuraishi joined the party of Major Yamaguchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around 12 a.m. the troop of Captain Kuraishi joined the party of Major Yamaguchi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around 0 a.m. the troop of Captain Kuraishi joined the party of Major Yamaguchi.</e>
<cmt>grammerを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>この日は馬立場北方の中の森にて露営することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They decided to camp out in the forest of northern Umatateba that day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They decided to camp out in the forest of northern Umatateba that day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They decided to camp out in the forest of northern Umatateba that day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>この日の露営は寒さに堪えかねて、凍死した将兵の背嚢を燃やすなどして何とか寒さを凌ぐものの、それでも大多数の兵士が凍死していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many soldiers were frozen to death as the chill was too severe to camp out that day, though they burned the rucksacks of dead soldiers to scarcely preserve heat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many soldiers were frozen to death as the chill was too severe to camp out that day, though they burned the rucksacks of dead soldiers to scarcely preserve heat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many soldiers were frozen to death as the chill was too severe to camp out that day, though they burned the rucksacks of dead soldiers to scarcely preserve heat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="101">
<j>青森では天候が前日よりも良かったので今日こそは帰ってくるだろうと、小関中尉以下40名は炊飯具を携行して幸畑で粥を作って待っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Aomori 40 people including Lieutenant Kozeki waited them, making rice gruel with rice cooker they had brought with them, thinking the troop will return today because the weather was better than the previous day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Aomori, 40 people including Lieutenant Kozeki, waited for them, making rice gruel with a rice cooker they had brought with them, thinking the troop would return that day because the weather was better than the previous day.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Aomori, 40 people including Lieutenant Kozeki, waited for them, making rice gruel with a rice cooker they had brought with them, thinking the troop would return that day because the weather was better than the previous day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>その一部は田茂木野村の南端でかがり火を作って夜まで待った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of them waited till night, making bonfire at the southern edge of Tamogino village.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of them waited till night, making a bonfire at the southern edge of Tamogino village.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of them waited till night, making a bonfire at the southern edge of Tamogino Village.</e>
<cmt>spellingを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>しかし22時になっても到着しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, they had not returned by 22 o&apos;clock, the people waiting in the barracks send a telegraph to Sanbongi police, thinking the troop might be marching toward Sanbongi, getting no confirmation, they decided to start dispatching rescue teams from the following day on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, they had not returned by 10pm. The people waiting in the barracks sent a telegraph to Sanbongi police, thinking the troop might be marching toward Sanbongi. Receiving no confirmation, they decided to start dispatching rescue teams from the following day on.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, they had not returned by 10 p.m..</e>
<cmt>spelling、一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>屯営では行軍隊が三本木方面に抜けているのでは考え、三本木警察に電報を出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The people waiting in the barracks sent a telegraph to Sanbongi police, thinking the troop might be marching toward Sanbongi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>が確認がとれず、翌日から救援隊を派遣することを決定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Receiving no confirmation, they decided to start dispatching rescue teams from the following day on.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>第4日（1月26日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fourth day (January 26)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fourth day (January 26)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fourth day (January 26)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="106">
<j>明け方頃に出発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They started off at dawn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They started off at dawn.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They started off at dawn.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>この時点で生存している将兵は60～70名となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of surviving soldiers was 60 to 70 at that point.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of surviving soldiers was 60 to 70 at that point.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of surviving soldiers was 60 to 70 at that point.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>部隊の人数は1/3までに減っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of the people in the troop had been decreased to one third.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of the people in the troop had been decreased to one third.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of the people in the troop had been decreased to one third.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>前日の露営で山口少佐が再び人事不省となり、少佐は兵卒に担がれる状態で行軍する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major Yamaguchi fell unconscious while camping out the previous day and marched being carried by soldiers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major Yamaguchi fell unconscious while camping out the previous day and marched being carried by soldiers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major Yamaguchi fell unconscious while camping out the previous day and marched being carried by soldiers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>隊列は乱れに乱れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The file was in a state of chaos, though naturally Captain Kannari and Captain Kuraishi was in the lead, other than that, soldiers followed them regardless of their position or ranks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The file was in a state of chaos, though naturally Captain Kannari and Captain Kuraishi was in the lead, other than that, soldiers followed them regardless of their position or ranks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The file was in a state of chaos.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>先頭は神成大尉、倉石大尉と自然に決まっていたが、それ以外は所属も階級も関係なく、将兵が後から続く形となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naturally, Captain Kannari and Captain Kuraishi were in the lead, but, other than that, soldiers followed them regardless of their positions or ranks.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>神成大尉らは前方高地を偵察する形で前方を行き、倉石大尉は後方を進んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Captain Kannari was in the head reconnoitering a highland ahead and Captain Kuraishi was in the rear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Captain Kannari was in the head reconnoitering a highland ahead and Captain Kuraishi was in the rear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Captain Kannari and others were in the head reconnoitering a highland ahead and Captain Kuraishi was in the rear.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="113">
<j>後藤伍長は目覚めたとき、昨夜自分と共に寝た者が1人もいなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Corporal Goto woke up to find there was no one who had slept along with him left.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Corporal Goto woke up to find there was no one who had slept along with him left.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Corporal Goto woke up to find there was no one who had slept along with him left.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>1人で青森に向かう途中、神成大尉、鈴木少尉、及川伍長らと出会う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He joined Captain Kannari, Junior Lieutenant Suzuki and Corporal Oikawa while going toward Aomori alone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He joined Captain Kannari, Junior Lieutenant Suzuki and Corporal Oikawa while going toward Aomori alone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He joined Captain Kannari, Junior Lieutenant Suzuki and Corporal Oikawa while going toward Aomori alone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>夕方までに、中の森～賽の河原の間（所在不明）に到着。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They reached somewhere between Nakano-mori Forest and Sai-no-kawara (location unidentified) by evening.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They reached somewhere between Nakano-mori Forest and Sai-no-kawara (location unidentified) by evening.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They reached somewhere between Nakano-mori Forest and Sai-no-kawara (location unidentified) by evening.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>露営をするが、暖を取る事も叶わず、将校を中心に周りを兵卒が囲む形で立ったまま休む状態で露営をすることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were forced to camp out standing in a circle, officers in a center and soldiers surrounding them, as they couldn&apos;t even have a warm.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were forced to camp out standing in a circle. Officers were in the center and soldiers surrounded them, as they couldn&apos;t have any warmth.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were forced to camp out standing in a circle, with officers in a center and soldiers surrounding them, as they couldn&apos;t even have a warm.</e>
<cmt>grammerを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="117">
<j>村上一等軍医、三神少尉、下士卒60名の救援隊は屯営を出発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The rescue team consisted of 60 people, First army surgeon Murakami, Junior Lieutenant Mikami and noncommissioned officers, started off the barrack.</e>
<cmt>一等軍医（定訳不明です。）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rescue team consisted of 60 people. First army surgeon Murakami, Junior Lieutenant Mikami and noncommissioned officers, started off from the barrack.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rescue team consisted of First army surgeon Murakami, Junior Lieutenant Mikami and 60 noncommissioned officers, started off the barrack.</e>
<cmt>grammerを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>大峠まで捜索活動を行ったが、この日の気温は-14℃であり、風雪も厳しく、捜索を断念して田茂木野へ引き返した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They returned to Tamogino after searching to Ootouge (big pass) due to the temperature as low as -14 degrees Celsius and harsh wind and snow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They returned to Tamogino after searching to Ootouge (big pass) due to temperatures as low as -14 degrees Celsius, harsh wind and snow.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They returned to Tamogino after searching to Otouge due to temperatures as low as -14 degrees Celsius, harsh wind and snow.</e>
<cmt>spellingを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>第5日（1月27日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fifth day (January 27)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fifth day (January 27)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fifth day (January 27)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="119">
<j>倉石大尉は目の前の道が二手に分かれる場所で神成大尉、今泉見習士官、中野中尉、鈴木少尉らと合流した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Captain Kuraishi joined Captain Kannari, Officers Designate Imaizumi, Lieutenant Nakano and Junior Lieutenant Suzuki where the road ahead split in two.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Captain Kuraishi joined Captain Kannari, Officers Designate Imaizumi, Lieutenant Nakano and Junior Lieutenant Suzuki where the road ahead split in two.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Captain Kuraishi joined Captain Kannari, Officers Designate Imaizumi, Lieutenant Nakano and Junior Lieutenant Suzuki where the road ahead split in two.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>談合し、隊は二手に別れて行動する事になった（四日目とも言われるが倉石大尉は五日目と証言しており恐らくこちらの方が正しい）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They decided to separate into two groups to march different way (it is said to be the fourth day, however, Captain Kuraishi said it was the fifth day and it is likely to be true).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They decided to separate into two groups to march in different directions. (This is said to have been the fourth day, however, Captain Kuraishi said that this was the fifth day and it is likely to be true).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They decided to separate into two groups to march in different directions (This is said to have been the fourth day, however, Captain Kuraishi said that this was the fifth day and it is likely to be true).</e>
<cmt>period</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>真夜中（午前3時頃と推定）に出発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They started off at midnight (presumably around 3 a.m.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They started off in the middle of the night (presumably around 3 a.m.).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They started off in the middle of the night (presumably around 3 a.m.).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>この時点で生存者は30名で倉石大尉と山口少佐を中心とするグループと、神成大尉を中心とするグループに分かれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of the survivors was 30 at that point and they were divided into one group led by Captain Kuraishi and Major Yamaguchi and the other by Captain Kannari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of survivors was 30 at that point and they were divided into two groups. One was led by Captain Kuraishi and Major Yamaguchi and the other by Captain Kannari.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of survivors was 30 at that point and they were divided into two groups; the one was led by Captain Kuraishi and Major Yamaguchi and the other by Captain Kannari.</e>
<cmt>grammerを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="123">
<j>倉石大尉のグループは駒込川方面を進むが、中野中尉をはじめ数名が倒れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The group of Captain Kuraishi marched toward Komagome-gawa River and several people fell including Lieutenant Nakano.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The group of Captain Kuraishi marched toward Komagome-gawa River and several people fell including Lieutenant Nakano.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The group of Captain Kuraishi marched toward Komagome-gawa River and several people fell including Lieutenant Nakano.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>途中青岩付近で沢にはまってしまい、進むことも戻ることもできなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They couldn&apos;t either move through or return, having been caught in a stream on the way.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They could neither move through nor return, having been caught in a stream on the way.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They could neither move through nor return, having been caught in a stream on the way.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="125">
<j>神成大尉のグループは、道自体は比較的正確に進んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many people of the group of Captain Kannari dropped out because, unlike the group of Captain Kuraishi, they faced a blizzard directly, though they choose a right route comparatively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many people in Captain Kannari&apos;s group dropped out because, unlike the group of Captain Kuraishi, they faced a blizzard. Although, they had chosen the correct route, comparatively.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Captain Kannari&apos;s group had chosen the correct route, comparatively.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>が、倉石大尉らと異なり猛吹雪をまともに受けたため落伍者が続出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, many people dropped out because, unlike the group of Captain Kuraishi, they faced a blizzard.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>残り4人の中から鈴木少尉が高地を見に行くと言い、出発したがそのまま帰ってこなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Junior Lieutenant Suzuki, out of the 4 people remaining, left the group saying he was going to reconnoiter a highland, and never to return.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Junior Lieutenant Suzuki, out of the 4 people remaining, left the group saying he was going to reconnoiter a highland, and was never to return.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Junior Lieutenant Suzuki, out of the four people remaining, left the group saying he was going to reconnoiter a highland, and was never to return.</e>
<cmt>spellingを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>3人となりしばらく留まるなかで、及川篤三郎が危篤となり手当ての甲斐なく死亡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokusaburo OIKAWA fell into critical condition and died in spite of the treatment while the 3 of them staying there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokusaburo OIKAWA fell into critical condition and died in spite of the treatment he received while the 3 of them stayed with him.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokusaburo OIKAWA fell into critical condition and died in spite of the treatment he received while the three of them stayed with him.</e>
<cmt>spellingを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>神成大尉と後藤伍長の2人は雪中を進む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Captain Kannari and Corporal Goto marched in the snow, however, Captain Kannari fell down.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Captain Kannari and Corporal Goto marched in the snow. However, Captain Kannari fell down.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Captain Kannari and Corporal Goto marched in the snow.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>が神成大尉が倒れてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Captain Kannari fell down.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>神成大尉は後藤伍長に「田茂木に行って住民を雇い、連隊への連絡を依頼せよ」と命令した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Captain Kannari ordered Corporal Goto &apos;Go to Tamogino and ask the local residents to contact the Regiment&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Captain Kannari ordered Corporal Goto to, &apos;Go to Tamogino and ask the local residents to contact the Regiment&apos;.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Captain Kannari ordered Corporal Goto to, &apos;Go to Tamogino and ask the local residents to contact the Regiment&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>後藤伍長は1人で朦朧とした意識の中で田茂木へ歩き続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Corporal Goto kept walking toward Tamogino in a stupor of exhaustion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Corporal Goto kept walking toward Tamogino in a stupor of exhaustion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Corporal Goto kept walking toward Tamogino in a stupor of exhaustion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="133">
<j>救援隊は捜索活動を再開した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The rescue team resumed the search.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rescue team resumed the search.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rescue team resumed the search.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>今日こそは何としてでも雪中行軍隊と接触しようと、案内人を何とか説得して、大滝平に進んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They moved to Otakidaira persuading the guide that they must meet the marching troop today at any cost.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They moved to Otakidaira persuading the guide that they must meet the marching troop today at any cost.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They moved to Otakidaira persuading the guide that they must meet the marching troop today at any cost.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>午前10時頃、三上中尉率いる小隊が大滝平付近で雪中に立つ後藤伍長を発見した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around 10 a.m. the platoon led by Lieutenant Mikami found Corporal Goto standing in the snow near Otakidaira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around 10 a.m. the platoon led by Lieutenant Mikami found Corporal Goto standing in the snow near Otakidaira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around 10 a.m. the platoon led by Lieutenant Mikami found Corporal Goto standing in the snow near Otakidaira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>本人はこの時のことを「其距離等も詳かに知る能はず、所謂夢中に前進中救援隊のために救われたり」と述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He recalled &apos;I was just walking forward desperately not knowing distance and others, when I was saved by rescue team&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He recalled, &apos;I was just walking forward desperately, not knowing the distance from the others, when I was saved by the rescue team&apos;.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He recalled, &apos;I was just walking forward desperately, not knowing the distance from the others, when I was saved by the rescue team&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>発見時の様子を東奥日報は「直立せしまま身動きもせずキョロキョロせしのみ」と報じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toonippo (local newspaper of Aomori Prefecture) reported the circumstances of finding &apos;He didn&apos;t move, standing upright, just looking around&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toonippo (local newspaper of Aomori Prefecture) reported the circumstances of his discovery as, &apos;He didn&apos;t move, standing upright, just looking around&apos;.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tonippo (local newspaper of Aomori Prefecture) reported the circumstances of his discovery as, &apos;He didn&apos;t move, standing upright, just looking around.&apos;</e>
<cmt>spelling, puctuationを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>また、「遭難始末」では仮死状態で歩哨の如く直立していたと述べられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;Sounan Shimatsusho (report of the disaster)&apos; reported that he was standing upright like a sentry in a state of apparent death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&apos;Sounan Shimatsusho (report of the disaster)&apos; reported that he was standing upright like a sentry in a state of apparent death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sounan Shimatsusho&apos; (report of the disaster) reported that he was standing upright like a sentry in a state of apparent death.</e>
<cmt>grammerを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>ここで雪中行軍隊が遭難したことが判明した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that point, the missing of the marching troop became clear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that point, the disappearance of the marching troop became clear.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that point, the disappearance of the marching troop became clear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="140">
<j>伍長が「神成大尉」と微かに語ったため、付近を捜索するとすぐ先に神成大尉が倒れていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They searched the vicinity as the Corporal had managed to say &apos;Captain Kannari&apos; and found him lying down nearby.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They searched the vicinity as the Corporal had managed to say &apos;Captain Kannari&apos; and found him lying down nearby.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They searched the vicinity as the Corporal had managed to say &apos;Captain Kannari&apos; and found him lying down nearby.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>大尉は全身凍っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was frozen all over.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was frozen all over.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was frozen all over.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>腕に気付け薬を注射しようとしたが、皮膚まで凍っていたため針が折れてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They tried to inject a stimulant into his chest, however, the needle was broken because even his skin was frozen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They tried to inject a stimulant into his chest, however, the needle broke because even his skin was frozen.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They tried to inject a stimulant into his chest, however, the needle broke because even his skin was frozen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>その後口を開けさせ口腔内に針を刺した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They made him open his mouth and injected intraorally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They made him open his mouth and injected intraorally.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They made him open his mouth and injected intraorally.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>何か語ったように見えたが、蘇生せずそのまま凍死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He seemed to say something, however, froze to death without recovering consciousness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He seemed to say something, but, froze to death without recovering consciousness.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He seemed to say something, but, froze to death without recovering consciousness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>及川篤三郎の遺体も発見された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The body of Tokusaburo OIKAWA was also found.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The body of Tokusaburo OIKAWA was also found.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The body of Tokusaburo OIKAWA was also found.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>19時40分、三上少尉が連隊長官舎に駆け込み大滝平で後藤伍長を発見したことと雪中行軍が「全滅の模様」であること、2時間の捜索で「救助隊60余名中、約半数が凍傷で行動不可」となったことを知らせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At 19:40, Junior Lieutenant Mikami run into the official residence of regiment officers and informed that they had found Corporal Goto near Otakidaira, all of the marching troop seem to be dead, and that about the half of 60 people of the rescue team became incapable due to frostbite.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At 19:40, Junior Lieutenant Mikami ran into the official residence of regiment officers and informed them that they had found Corporal Goto near Otakidaira, all of the marching troop seem to be dead, and that about the half of 60 people of the rescue team had become incapacitated due to frostbite.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At 19:40, Junior Lieutenant Mikami ran into the official residence of regiment officers and informed them that they had found Corporal Goto near Otakidaira, all of the marching troop seem to be dead, and that about the half of 60 people of the rescue team had become incapacitated due to frostbite.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="147">
<j>津川青森歩兵第五連隊長中佐はこの報告を聞いて青くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major of the 5th Infantry Regiment of Tsugaru Aomori turned white having heard that news.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major of the 5th Infantry Regiment of Tsugaru Aomori turned white having heard that news.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major of the fifth Infantry Regiment of Tsugaru Aomori turned white having heard that news.</e>
<cmt>spellingを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>その後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="148">
<j>1月27日の夜、倉石大尉らの一隊では今泉三太郎見習士官が下士1名を伴い周りが制止するのも聞かず川に飛び込んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 27, in the group of Captain Kuraishi, Officers Designate Santaro IMAIZUMI jumped into a river along with a noncommissioned officer, though the others tried to stop them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 27, in the group of Captain Kuraishi, Officer Designate Santaro IMAIZUMI jumped into a river along with a noncommissioned officer, though the others had tried to stop them.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At night on January 27, in the group of Captain Kuraishi, Officer Designate Santaro IMAIZUMI jumped into a river along with a noncommissioned officer, though the others had tried to stop them.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>倉石大尉は「川を下っていった」と述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Captain Kuraishi said &apos;He went down the river&apos;, however, it is obvious from what the other survivors said that he jumped into the river, and his body was found on March 9.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Captain Kuraishi said, &apos;He went down the river&apos;. However, it is obvious from what the other survivors said that he had jumped into the river. His body was found on March 9.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Captain Kuraishi said, &apos;He went down the river.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>が、他の生存者の証言から川に飛び込んだのは間違いない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is obvious from what the other survivors said that he had jumped into the river.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="151">
<j>3月9日に下流で遺体となって発見された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His body was found on March 9.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="152">
<j>1月28日には倉石大尉らの一隊では、佐藤特務曹長が下士兵卒を連れ川に飛び込んだが、そのまま凍死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 28, in the group of Captain Kuraishi, Sergeant Major Sato jumped into a river along with a noncommissioned officer and froze to death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 28, in the group of Captain Kuraishi, Sergeant Major Sato jumped into a river along with a noncommissioned officer and froze to death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 28, in the group of Captain Kuraishi, Sergeant Major Sato jumped into a river along with a noncommissioned officer and froze to death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>これに関しても倉石大尉は「連隊に連絡しようとして行ったまま行方不明」と述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Captain Kuraishi also said &apos;He disappeared, going to inform the Regiment&apos; about that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Captain Kuraishi said, &apos;He disappeared, going to inform the Regiment&apos;, about that.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Captain Kuraishi said, &apos;He disappeared, going to inform the Regiment,&apos; about that.</e>
<cmt>punctuationを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="154">
<j>倉石大尉ら4名は崖穴に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 4 of them including Captain Kuraishi went into the cave in a cliff.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 4 of them including Captain Kuraishi went into a cave in a cliff.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The four of them including Captain Kuraishi went into a cave in a cliff.</e>
<cmt>spellingを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>山口少佐がいる川岸の場所と、倉石大尉らのいる場所の二つに別れて兵士がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were two places where divided soldiers stayed, one place was on the riverside, where Major Yamaguchi stayed and the other was where Captain Kuraishi stayed and the latter was better in terms of location.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were two places where divided soldiers stayed. One place was on the riverside, where Major Yamaguchi stayed and the other was where Captain Kuraishi stayed. The latter was better in terms of location.</e>
<cmt>sentence structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were two places where divided soldiers stayed; the one place was on the riverside, where Major Yamaguchi stayed and the other was where Captain Kuraishi stayed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>どちらかといえば倉石大尉らのいる所の方が場所的には良かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The latter was better in terms of location, comparatively.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処、訳漏れ</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>倉石大尉は山口少佐にこちらに来るよう勧めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Captain Kuraishi persuaded Major Yamaguchi to come to his place, however, Major Yamaguchi rejected it saying &apos;I&apos;m dying here&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Captain Kuraishi tried to persuade Major Yamaguchi to move to his place. However, Major Yamaguchi rejected it saying, &apos;I&apos;m dying here&apos;.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Captain Kuraishi tried to persuade Major Yamaguchi to move to his place.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>が、山口少佐は「吾は此処に死せん」として拒否した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Major Yamaguchi rejected it saying, &apos;I&apos;m dying here.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処、punctuationを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>この時点では、比較的動けた山本徳次郎が山口少佐に水を与えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokujiro YAMAMOTO, who was relatively able to move, served water to Major Yamaguchi at that point.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokujiro YAMAMOTO, who was relatively able to move, served water to Major Yamaguchi at that point.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokujiro YAMAMOTO, who was relatively able to move, served water to Major Yamaguchi at that point.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="160">
<j>1月29日に救助部隊が神成大尉の遺体を収容し、各哨所も完成する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 29, the body of Captain Kannari was recovered by the rescue team and each sentry station was completed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 29, the body of Captain Kannari was recovered by the rescue team and each sentry station was completed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 29, the body of Captain Kannari was recovered by the rescue team and each sentry station was completed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="161">
<j>同様に雪中行軍をしていた弘前隊が青森に到着した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same way, Hirosaki Party marching in the snow reached Aomori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same way, the Hirosaki Party marching in the snow reached Aomori.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same way, the Hirosaki Party marching in the snow reached Aomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="162">
<j>1月30日には賽の河原で中野中尉ら36名の遺体発見した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 30, the bodies of 36 people including Lieutenant Nakano were found at Sai-no-kawara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 30, the bodies of 36 people including Lieutenant Nakano were found at Sai-no-kawara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 30, the bodies of 36 people including Lieutenant Nakano were found at Sai-no-kawara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="163">
<j>この場所は倉石大尉らが駒込川の沢に降りていった道に当たる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That place is the road through which Captain Kuraishi and others went down to the stream of Komagomegawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That place is the road through which Captain Kuraishi and others went down to the stream of Komagomegawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That place is the road through which Captain Kuraishi and others went down to the stream of Komagomegawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="164">
<j>「賽の河原」の名前は、以前にもここで凍死した村の人が多くいたために付けられていたといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of Sai-no-kawara (the Children&apos;s limbo) was named because many village people had been also frozen to death there before.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of Sai-no-kawara (the Children&apos;s limbo) was named because many village people had also frozen to death there before.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of Sai-no-kawara (the Children&apos;s limbo) was named because many village people had also frozen to death there before.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>後藤惣介が倉石大尉らの場所に行く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sosuke Goto went to the place where Captain Kuraishi and others were.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sosuke Goto went to the place where Captain Kuraishi and others were.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sosuke Goto went to the place where Captain Kuraishi and others were.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="166">
<j>1月31日午前9時頃、鳴沢北方の炭焼き小屋にいた三浦武雄伍長と阿部卯吉一等卒の2人が救出されるが三浦伍長は救出後に死亡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around 9 a.m. on January 31, Corporal Takeo MIURA and Private First Ukichi ABE, who had been staying in a charcoal making shack in the northern Narusawa, were rescued, though Corporal Miura died after being rescued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around 9 a.m. on January 31, Corporal Takeo MIURA and Private First Ukichi ABE, who had been staying in a charcoal making shack in the northern Narusawa, were rescued, though Corporal Miura died after being rescued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around 9 a.m. on January 31, Corporal Takeo MIURA and Private First Ukichi ABE, who had been staying in a charcoal making shack in the northern Narusawa, were rescued, though Corporal Miura died after being rescued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>小屋で朝まで生きていたというもう1人の遺体も発見した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The other body, which had been a living human until the morning in the shack, was also found.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The other body, which had been alive until the morning in the shack, was also found.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The other body, which had been alive until the morning in the shack, was also found.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="168">
<j>3日目に出発したところまでは覚えているが、それ以降は分からず、気づいたら小屋に飛び込んでいたという内容の証言をしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The rescue team said they remembered starting on the third day and that they just realized they were going into the shack, not knowing what they had done until then.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rescue team said they remembered starting on the third day and that they just realized they were going into the shack, not knowing what they had done until then.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Private First ABE said they remembered starting on the third day and that they just realized they were going into the shack, not knowing what they had done until then.</e>
<cmt>文脈から主語を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="169">
<j>小屋周辺では16名の遺体を発見した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They found 16 bodies around the shack.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They found 16 bodies around the shack.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They found 16 bodies around the shack.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>この際田村少佐は陸軍省に「生存者12名」と誤電報を送る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major Murata send the wrong telegraph to Ministry of War saying &apos;12 survivor&apos;, however he corrected it immediately &apos;2 surviving soldiers and 10 dead bodies&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major Murata sent the wrong telegraph to the Ministry of War saying &apos;12 survivors&apos;. However, he corrected it immediately saying, &apos;2 surviving soldiers and 10 dead bodies&apos;.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major Murata sent the wrong telegraph to the Ministry of War saying &apos;12 survivors.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処、punctuationを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="171">
<j>がすぐさま「生存兵卒2、遺体10」だったと訂正している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he corrected it immediately saying, &apos;2 surviving soldiers and 10 dead bodies.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処、punctuationを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="172">
<j>午前9時頃、倉石大尉らが崖をよじ登りだす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around 9 a.m. Captain Kuraishi and others started to climb the cliff.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around 9 a.m. Captain Kuraishi and others started to climb the cliff.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around 9 a.m. Captain Kuraishi and others started to climb the cliff.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="173">
<j>15時頃、250メートルほど進んだところで倉石大尉、伊藤中尉ら4人が発見され、生存者計9人が発見された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around 15 o&apos;clock, they found 9 survivors, having found Captain Kuraishi, Lieutenant Ito and others where they went forward about 250 meters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around 3pm, they found 9 survivors, having found Captain Kuraishi, Lieutenant Ito and others where they had gone forward about 250 meters.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around 3 p.m., the four including Captain Kuraishi and Lieutenant Ito were found, and as a result, the nine survivors in total were found where they had gone forward about 250 meters.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れに対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="174">
<j>だが、高橋房治伍長、紺野市次郎二等卒は救出後死亡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Corporal Fusaji TAKAHASHI and Private Ichijiro KONNO died after being rescued.</e>
<cmt>紺野市次郎（定訳不明、該当する読みが見つかりませんでした）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Corporal Fusaji TAKAHASHI and Private Ichijiro KONNO died after being rescued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Corporal Fusaji TAKAHASHI and Private Ichijiro KONNO died after being rescued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="175">
<j>この際に救出された山口少佐も病院に収容されたが2月2日に死亡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major Yamaguchi, who was also rescued then, was taken to a hospital and died on February 2.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major Yamaguchi, who was also rescued then, was taken to a hospital and died on February 2.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major Yamaguchi, who was also rescued then, was taken to a hospital and died on February 2.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="176">
<j>山口少佐の死因については、公式発表では心臓麻痺となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His cause of death was cardiac failure in official announcement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His cause of death was cardiac failure in the official announcement.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His cause of death was cardiac failure in the official announcement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="177">
<j>しかしピストル自殺説（小笠原孤酒及び彼に取材した新田次郎が採っている）もあることや「凍傷の指で銃の操作は不可能」として新たな背景を探る松木明知の研究もあり、更なる検証・進展が望まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, further verification and progress were required as there is a theory of his having committed suicide with a gun (Koshu OGASAWARA and Jiro NITTA, who interviewed him, put forward this theory) and other theory by Akitomo MATSUKI that seeks new background saying &apos;It was impossible for his frozen fingers to manipulate a gun&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, further verification and is required as there is a theory of his having committed suicide with a gun (Koshu OGASAWARA and Jiro NITTA, who interviewed him, put forward this theory). Another theory, by Akitomo MATSUKI, that needs more background says, &apos;It was impossible for his frozen fingers to manipulate a gun&apos;.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, further verification is required as there are a theory of his having committed suicide with a gun (Koshu OGASAWARA and Jiro NITTA, who interviewed him, put forward this theory) and another theory, by Akitomo MATSUKI, that needs more background says, &apos;It was impossible for his frozen fingers to manipulate a gun.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammerを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="178">
<j>鳴沢では他に水野忠宜中尉（紀伊新宮藩10代藩主水野忠幹 (紀伊新宮藩主)の長男）以下33名の遺体を発見した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Narusawa, 33 bodies including Lieutenant Tadayoshi MIZUNO (the eldest son of Tadatomo MIZUNO, the 10th lord of Kii-Shingu Domain [the lord of Kii-Shingu Domain]) were found and the body of Junior Lieutenant Suzuki near Otakidaira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At Narusawa, 33 bodies including that of Lieutenant Tadayoshi MIZUNO (the eldest son of Tadatomo MIZUNO, the 10th lord of Kii-Shingu Domain [the lord of Kii-Shingu Domain]) were found. The body of Junior Lieutenant Suzuki was found near Otakidaira.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At Narusawa, 33 bodies including that of Lieutenant Tadayoshi MIZUNO (the eldest son of Tadatomo MIZUNO, the 10th lord of Kii-Shingu Domain [the lord of Kii-Shingu Domain]) were found.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="179">
<j>大滝平付近で鈴木少尉の遺体を発見している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The body of Junior Lieutenant Suzuki was found near Otakidaira.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処、訳漏れ</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="180">
<j>2月1日には賽の河原付近にて数名の、按ノ木森から中ノ森にかけ十数名の遺体を発見した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 1, a several bodies were found near Sai-no-kawara and more than a dozen between Yasunoki-mori Forest and Nakano-mori Forest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 1, several bodies were found near Sai-no-kawara and more than a dozen between Yasunoki-mori Forest and Nakano-mori Forest.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 1, several bodies were found near Sai-no-kawara and more than a dozen between Yasunoki-mori Forest and Nakano-mori Forest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="181">
<j>2月2日11時頃地震が発生し、その際平沢の炭小屋で屋根が崩れその中にいた長谷川特務曹長、阿部寿松一等卒、佐々木正教二等卒、小野寺佐平二等卒の4人の生存者が発見される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around 11 o&apos;clock on February 2, an earthquake occurred, breaking down the roof of the shack in Hirasawa, and 4 survivors; Sergeant Major Hasegawa, Private First Hisamatsu ABE, Private Masanori SASAKI and Private Sahei ONODERA staying in the shack were found.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around 11 o&apos;clock on February 2, an earthquake occurred, breaking down the roof of the shack in Hirasawa, and 4 survivors; Sergeant Major Hasegawa, Private First Hisamatsu ABE, Private Masanori SASAKI and Private Sahei ONODERA who were staying in the shack were found.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around 11 o&apos;clock on February 2, an earthquake occurred, breaking down the roof of the shack in Hirasawa, and four survivors; Sergeant Major Hasegawa, Private First Hisamatsu ABE, Private Masanori SASAKI and Private Sahei ONODERA who were staying in the shack were found.</e>
<cmt>spellingを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="182">
<j>しかし、佐々木二等卒、小野寺二等卒は救出後死亡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Private Sasaki and Private Onodera died after being rescued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Private Sasaki and Private Onodera died after being rescued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Private Sasaki and Private Onodera died after being rescued.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れに対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="183">
<j>15時頃には3日目に隊列を離れていた最後の生存者村松伍長が古館要吉一等卒の遺体と共に田代元湯で発見された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around 15 o&apos;clock, the last survivor Corporal Matsumura, who had been parted from the file since the third day, was found along with the body of Private First Youkichi FURUTACHI at Tashiro Motoyu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around 3pm, the last survivor, Corporal Matsumura, who had parted from the file since the third day, was found along with the body of Private First Youkichi FURUTACHI at Tashiro Motoyu.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around 3 p.m., the last survivor, Corporal Matsumura, who had parted from the file since the third day, was found along with the body of Private First Youkichi FURUTACHI at Tashiro Motoyu.</e>
<cmt>spellingを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="184">
<j>村松伍長は四肢切断の上、一時危篤状態となったがかろうじて回復した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Corporal Matsumura was amputated his extremities and in critical condition at one stage, however, managed to recover.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Corporal Matsumura&apos;s extremities were amputated and he was in critical condition at one stage, however, he managed to recover.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Corporal Matsumura&apos;s extremities were amputated and he was in critical condition at one stage, however, he managed to recover.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>救助活動</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rescue effort</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rescue effort</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rescue effort</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="185">
<j>救助活動は青森連隊、弘前連隊、更には仙台第5砲兵隊も出動した大掛かりな体制になり、延べ1万人が投入された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The rescue effort was large-scale and 10,000 people were put including Aomori Regiment, Hirosaki Regiment and the 5th Sendai Artillery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rescue effort was large-scale and 10,000 people were involved, including the Aomori Regiment, Hirosaki Regiment and the 5th Sendai Artillery.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rescue effort was large-scale and 10,000 people were involved, including the Aomori Regiment, Hirosaki Regiment and the fifth Sendai Artillery.</e>
<cmt>spellingを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="186">
<j>その後、生存者の収容の完了と捜索方法の確立と共に青森連隊独自で行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Aomori Regiment completed accommodating the survivors and established the way of searching on their own.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, the Aomori Regiment accommodated the survivors and established the way of searching on their own.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, the Aomori Regiment continued rescue effort on their own after completing the accommodation of the survivors and the establishment of the way of searching.</e>
<cmt>文脈から「共に」は「伴って」と判断し、修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="187">
<j>救助拠点は、幸畑に資材集散基地、田茂木に捜索本部を置き、そこから哨戒所と呼ばれるベースキャンプを構築、前進させる方法が取られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They put a material distributing base in Kohata and a searching headquarters in Tamogino as the main posts, building base camps called patrol posts, then made them move forward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They put a material distributing base in Kohata and a searching headquarters in Tamogino as the main posts, building base camps called patrol posts, then made them move forward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They put a material distributing base in Kohata and a searching headquarters in Tamogino as the main posts, building base camps called patrol posts, then made them move forward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="188">
<j>哨戒所は大滝平から最初の遭難地点の鳴沢まで合計15箇所設営された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">15 patrol posts in total were set up between Otakidaira and Narusawa, which was the first point the disaster had occurred.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">15 patrol posts in total were set up between Otakidaira and Narusawa, which was the first point the disaster had occurred.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">15 patrol posts in total were set up between Otakidaira and Narusawa, which was the first point the disaster had occurred.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="189">
<j>捜索は、生存者の証言と行軍計画を参照して行軍ルートを割出し、そのルートを重点として、横幅30m（およそ30人一列）になって、其々が所持する長さ10m程の竹棒を雪中に突き刺しながら前進し、少しでも違和感がある手応えを感知するとその下を掘削する方法が採られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The way of searching was like this; determining the marching route according to the story of the survivors and marching plan, making people walk forward along that route in a 30 meters wide line (about 30 people in one line) stabbing a bamboo stick, which was about 10 centimeters long, in the snow, digging up the place where something strange was felt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The method of searching was like this; determining the marching route according to the stoies of the survivors and the marching plans, making people walk forward along that route in a 30 meters wide line (about 30 people in one line) stabbing a 10 meter long stick into the snow, and digging up the places where something strange was felt.</e>
<cmt>Revised 10cm to 10m</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The method of searching was like this; determining the marching route according to the stoies of the survivors and the marching plans, making people walk forward along that route in a 30 meters wide line (about 30 people in one line) stabbing a 10 meter long stick into the snow, and digging up the places where something strange was felt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="190">
<j>この作業は構築した哨戒所を拠点として、日中を6時間程かけて行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such operation was carried out about 6 hours in the daytime with the patrol post as a base, and bodies were accommodated in the patrol post once, moved to searching headquarters later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such operations were carried out for about 6 hours in the daytime with the patrol post as a base. Bodies were accommodated in the patrol post once and moved to searching headquarters later.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such operations were carried out for about six hours in the daytime with the patrol post as a base.</e>
<cmt>spelling、一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="191">
<j>遺体は哨戒所に一旦収容してから、捜索本部に集積した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bodies were accommodated in the patrol post once and moved to searching headquarters later.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="192">
<j>1ヵ月も経過すると、捜索隊員によって雪が踏み固められたり、気温の変化で雪がシャーベット状になり、かなり固くなってしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After 1 month, the snow became hard like sherbet as the snow had been tread down by rescue team and the temperature had changed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After 1 month, the snow had become hard like sherbet as the snow had been tread down by the rescue team and the temperature had changed.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After one month, the snow had become hard like sherbet as the snow had been tread down by the rescue team and the temperature had changed.</e>
<cmt>spellingを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="193">
<j>そのため、竹棒では刺さらなくなり鉄棒で代用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bamboo sticks didn&apos;t work anymore, they substituted iron sticks for them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bamboo sticks didn&apos;t work anymore, so they substituted iron sticks for them.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bamboo sticks didn&apos;t work anymore, so they substituted iron sticks for them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="194">
<j>また、捜索活動初期の頃、北海道からアイヌ人一行を招き、彼等と彼等が所有する猟犬と共に捜索活動を行い、遺体発見でかなりの成果を挙げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early stages of the search, they invited a party of Ainu tribe from Hokkaido, searching with them and their hunting dogs, finding bodies successfully.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early stages of the search, they invited a party of Ainu tribe from Hokkaido, searching with them and their hunting dogs, finding bodies successfully.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early stages of the search, they invited a party of Ainu tribe from Hokkaido, searching with them and their hunting dogs, finding bodies successfully.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="195">
<j>発見された遺体は、1体に数人程度をかけて掘り出して哨戒所に運搬した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A body found was dig up by several people and carried to the patrol post.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A body found was dug up by several people and carried to the patrol post.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A body found was dug up by several people and carried to the patrol post.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="196">
<j>余りに凍りついていたため、粗略に扱うと遺体が関節の部分から粉々に砕けるからであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was frozen to such an extent that it would have fallen apart to pieces from its joints if you had treated it roughly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was frozen to such an extent that it would have fallen apart to pieces from its joints if you had treated it roughly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was frozen to such an extent that it would have fallen apart to pieces from its joints if you had treated it roughly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="197">
<j>哨戒所にて衣服を剥いだ後、直火にて遺体を解凍し、棺に収容して本部まで運搬した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the patrol post, the bodies were stripped off, thawed by direct heat, carried to the headquarters in coffins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the patrol post, the bodies were stripped off, thawed by direct heat, and carried to the headquarters in coffins.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the patrol post, the bodies were stripped off, thawed by direct heat, and carried to the headquarters in coffins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="198">
<j>水中に没した遺体は引揚げ作業が難航し、そのまま流されてしまうものが多数であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of the bodies sunken in the water were drifted away because it was difficult to salvage them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of the bodies sunken in the water had drifted away because it was difficult to salvage them.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of the bodies sunken in the water had drifted away because it was difficult to salvage them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="199">
<j>そのため、幸畑村を流れる駒込川に流出防止の柵を構築し、そこに引っ掛かった遺体から順次収容して行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, they made a bar to prevent the bodies from drifting away in Komagome-gawa River that runs Kohata village and recovered the bodies which were caught on it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, they made a sandbar to prevent the bodies from drifting away in the Komagome-gawa River that runs Kohata village and recovered the bodies which were caught on it.</e>
<cmt>vocabulary</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, they made a sandbar to prevent the bodies from drifting away in the Komagome-gawa River that runs Kohata Village and recovered the bodies which were caught on it.</e>
<cmt>spellingを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="200">
<j>こうして発見された遺体は、最終的に5連隊駐屯所に運ばれ、そこで遺族と面会、確認の後、そこで荼毘に付されるか故郷へ帰っていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bodies recovered in that ways ended up being stored in the 5th Regiment post, where they were cremated or send home after their bereaved family had met and confirmed them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bodies recovered in that way ended up being stored in the 5th Regiment post, where they were cremated or sent home after their bereaved family had met and confirmed them.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bodies recovered in that way ended up being stored in the fifth Regiment post, where they were cremated or sent home after their bereaved family had met and confirmed them.</e>
<cmt>spellingを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>原因</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cause</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cause</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cause</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="201">
<j>原因は諸説あるが、決定的な原因ははっきりしていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The cause of the disaster has not been determined, though there are several theories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The cause of the disaster has not been determined, though there are several theories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The cause of the disaster has not been determined, though there are several theories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="202">
<j>それを踏まえて、現在唱えられている原因を列挙する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The causes accepted widely now are shown below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The causes accepted widely now are shown below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The causes accepted widely now are shown below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="203">
<j>気象条件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Weather condition</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Weather condition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Weather condition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="204">
<j>雪中行軍が行われたのは、冬季によく見られる典型的な西高東低の気圧配置で、未曾有の寒気団が日本列島を襲っていた時で、日本各地で観測史上における最低気温を更新した日でもある（旭川で1月25日、日本最低記録である-41.0℃を記録した）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The march was carried out on the day the lowest temperature since observations had began was recorded around the country (on January 25, -41.1 degrees Celsius, the lowest temperature ever observed in Japan, was recorded in Asahikawa) with typical winter pressure pattern, the high-pressure area lies to the west, and the low-pressure area to the east, and unprecedented cold air mass was covering the Japanese archipelago.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The march was carried out on the day of the lowest temperature ever recorded in the country (on January 25, -41.1 degrees Celsius, the lowest temperature ever observed in Japan, was recorded in Asahikawa). Typical winter pressure patterns such as, the high-pressure area to the west, and the low-pressure area to the east, and an unprecedented cold air mass was covering the Japanese archipelago.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The march was carried out on the day of the lowest temperature ever recorded in the country (on January 25, -41.1 degrees Celsius, the lowest temperature ever observed in Japan, was recorded in Asahikawa) when Typical winter pressure patterns such as, the high-pressure area to the west, and the low-pressure area to the east, and an unprecedented cold air mass was covering the Japanese archipelago.</e>
<cmt>一部変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="205">
<j>青森の気温にしても例年より8～10℃程低かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The temperature in Aomori was 8 to 10 degrees Celsius lower than usual years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The temperature in Aomori was 8 to 10 degrees Celsius lower than usual years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The temperature in Aomori was 8 to 10 degrees Celsius lower than usual years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="206">
<j>行軍隊の遭難した山中の気温は、観測係であった看護兵が記録も残せず死亡したため定かでないが、-20℃以下だったとの推測を青森5連隊が報告書の中で残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 5th Aomori Regiment recorded that the temperature in the mountain on which the troop got lost was less than -20 degrees Celsius, though it&apos;s not clear because the hospital corpsman who was in charge of observation died before leaving a record.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 5th Aomori Regiment recorded that the temperature in the mountain on which the troop got lost was lower than -20 degrees Celsius, though it&apos;s not clear because the hospital corpsman who was in charge of observations died before leaving a record.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fifth Aomori Regiment recorded that the temperature in the mountain on which the troop got lost was lower than -20 degrees Celsius, though it&apos;s not clear because the hospital corpsman who was in charge of observations died before leaving a record.</e>
<cmt>spellingを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="207">
<j>この過酷な気象条件が遭難の一大要因と考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such harsh weather condition is regarded as the biggest factor of the disaster.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such harsh weather conditions is regarded as the biggest factor of the disaster.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such harsh weather conditions are regarded as the biggest factor of the disaster.</e>
<cmt>is → are に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="208">
<j>稚拙な装備</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Poor equipment</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Poor equipment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Poor equipment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="209">
<j>雪中行軍時、将兵の装備は、特務曹長（准士官）以上が「毛糸の外套1着」「毛糸の軍帽」「ネル生地の冬軍服」「軍手1足」「長脚型軍靴」「長靴型雪沓」、下士兵 (日本軍)が「毛糸の外套2着重ね着」「フェルト地の普通軍帽」「小倉生地の普通軍服」「軍手1足」「短脚型軍靴」であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The equipment soldiers had during marching was as follows; &apos; a woolen coat&apos; &apos; a woolen service cap&apos; &apos; a winter military uniform of cotton flannel&apos; &apos; cotton work gloves&apos; &apos;long ammunition boots&apos; &apos;long straw boots for snow&apos; for soldiers whose rank were Sergeant Major or higher and &apos; wearing two woolen coats&apos; &apos; an ordinary felt service cap&apos; &apos; an ordinary military uniform of Ogura fabric&apos; &apos; cotton work gloves&apos; &apos;short ammunition boots&apos; for noncommissioned officers or lower, and those were hardly enough for cold protection in winter mountain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The equipment soldiers had during marching was as follows; &apos; a woolen coat&apos; &apos; a woolen service cap&apos; &apos; a winter military uniform of cotton flannel&apos; &apos; cotton work gloves&apos; &apos;long ammunition boots&apos; &apos;long straw boots for snow&apos;, for soldiers whose ranks were Sergeant Major or higher and &apos; wearing two woolen coats&apos; &apos; an ordinary felt service cap&apos; &apos; an ordinary military uniform of Ogura fabric&apos; &apos; cotton work gloves&apos; &apos;short ammunition boots&apos; for noncommissioned officers or lower. Those were hardly enough for protection from the cold in winter mountains.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The equipment soldiers had during marching was as follows; &apos; a woolen coat&apos; &apos; a woolen service cap&apos; &apos; a winter military uniform of cotton flannel&apos; &apos; cotton work gloves&apos; &apos;long ammunition boots&apos; &apos;long straw boots for snow&apos;, for soldiers whose ranks were Sergeant Major or higher, and &apos; wearing two woolen coats&apos; &apos; an ordinary felt service cap&apos; &apos; an ordinary military uniform of Ogura fabric&apos; &apos; cotton work gloves&apos; &apos;short ammunition boots&apos; for noncommissioned officers or lower.</e>
<cmt>spacing、一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="210">
<j>冬山登山の防寒に対応しているとは言い難い装備であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those were hardly enough for protection from the cold in winter mountains.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="211">
<j>とくに下士官兵卒の防寒装備に至っては、毛糸の外套2枚を渡されただけである（当時の日本陸軍の軍装については軍服 (大日本帝国陸軍)も参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially, noncommissioned officers were gave only two woolen coats as their cold protection equipment (about the military uniform of Japanese Army at that time, see also Military Uniform [Imperial Japanese Army]).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, noncommissioned officers were given only two woolen coats as their cold protection equipment (about the military uniform of Japanese Army at that time, see also Military Uniform [Imperial Japanese Army]).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, noncommissioned officers were given only two woolen coats as their cold protection equipment (about the military uniform of Japanese Army at that time, see also Military Uniform [Imperial Japanese Army]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="212">
<j>倉石大尉はゴム靴を持っていたことが結果として凍傷を防いだと言われるが、これは正月に東京に行った際にたまたま買っていたものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Captain Kuraishi had escaped frostbite thanks to his rubber boots which he had happened to buy when he had been Tokyo at New Year&apos;s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Captain Kuraishi had escaped frostbite thanks to his rubber boots which he had happened to buy when he had been in Tokyo at New Year&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Captain Kuraishi had escaped frostbite thanks to his rubber boots which he had happened to buy when he had been in Tokyo at New Year&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="213">
<j>指揮系統の混乱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The chaotic chain of command</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The chaotic chain of command</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The chaotic chain of command</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="214">
<j>雪中行軍隊の総指揮者は行軍隊隊長の神成大尉であるが、これに山口少佐と若干名の大尉が行軍隊付きとして同行する形になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The officer in total command of the marching troop was Captain Kannari, captain of the troop, and Major Yamaguchi and several Captains came along to attend the troop.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The officer in total command of the marching troop was Captain Kannari, captain of the troop, and Major Yamaguchi and several Captains came along to attend the troop.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The officer in total command of the marching troop was Captain Kannari, captain of the troop, and Major Yamaguchi and several Captains came along to attend the troop.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="215">
<j>責任者は神成大尉ではあるが、階級と本来の職務の関係から行くと山口少佐は上司にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major Yamaguchi was Captain Kannari&apos;s boss in terms of the rank and their relationship in ordinary duty and other Captains came along were commanders of equal rank with Captain Kannari, even though he was the officer in charge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major Yamaguchi was Captain Kannari&apos;s boss in terms of rank and their relationship in ordinary duty. Other Captains who came along were commanders of equal rank with Captain Kannari, even though he was the officer in charge.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major Yamaguchi was Captain Kannari&apos;s boss in terms of rank and their relationship in ordinary duty.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="216">
<j>同行してきた大尉達は神成大尉と同格の指揮官になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other Captains who came along were commanders of equal rank with Captain Kannari, even though he was the officer in charge.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="217">
<j>これが結果として情報伝達の不備、意思決定の不統一になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That resulted in defective transmission of information and disunion in decision-making.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That resulted in defective transmission of information and disunion in decision-making.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That resulted in defective transmission of information and disunion in decision-making.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="218">
<j>極端な情報不足</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Terrible lack of information</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Terrible lack of information</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Terrible lack of information</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="219">
<j>神成大尉が雪中行軍隊の指揮を任されることになったのは、行軍実施の直前である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was just before the march was carried out that they had decided to make Captain Kannari in charge of the marching troop.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was just before the march was carried out that they had decided to make Captain Kannari in charge of the marching troop.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was just before the march was carried out that they had decided to make Captain Kannari in charge of the marching troop.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="220">
<j>それまでの担当者は夫人出産の立会いのため、任を解かれる形となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The person who had been in charge was discharged to attend his wife&apos;s giving a birth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The person who had been in charge was discharged to attend to his wife who was giving a birth.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The person who had been in charge was discharged to attend to his wife who was giving a birth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="221">
<j>その為、実際の雪中行軍に対して神成大尉は何も予備知識を持たないまま準備作業に入るが、準備作業としては、予行演習の日帰り行軍を小峠まで小隊編成で行ったのみである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Captain Kannari started preparation, which was only conducting a single-day march to Kotoge in small troop as a preparatory exercise, without any advance knowledge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Captain Kannari started preparations, which was conducting only a single-day march to Kotoge in small troop as a preparatory exercise, without any advance knowledge.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Captain Kannari started preparations, which was conducting only a single-day march to Kotoge in small troop as a preparatory exercise, without any advance knowledge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="222">
<j>その行軍自体が晴天下で行われた事もあり、冬山登山や雪中行動の基本的リスクの抽出が結果として行われなかったことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That march was carried out on a fine day, which resulted in extracting no basic risk of climbing winter mountain or acting in snow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That march was carried out on a fine day, which resulted in extracting no basic information on the risk of climbing winter mountains or actions in snow.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That march was carried out on a fine day, which resulted in extracting no basic information on the risk of climbing winter mountains or actions in snow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="223">
<j>知識不足</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lack of knowledge</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lack of knowledge</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lack of knowledge</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="224">
<j>雪中行軍参加者のほとんどは岩手県、宮城県の農家の出身者であり、普段冬山などに接する機会がない者たちであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of the soldiers joined the march were from farm families in Iwate Prefecture and Miyagi Prefecture, having had no chance to climb winter mountain before.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of the soldiers who joined the march were from farm families in Iwate Prefecture and Miyagi Prefecture, having had no chance to climb winter mountains before.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of the soldiers who joined the march were from farm families in Iwate Prefecture and Miyagi Prefecture, having had no chance to climb winter mountains before.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="225">
<j>冬の八甲田山のことなど知る由もなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Little did they know about Mt.Hakkoda in winter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Little did they know about Mt.Hakkoda in winter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Little did they know about Mt.Hakkoda in winter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="226">
<j>そのため、防寒の知識は皆無に等しく、雪中行軍をトレッキングと同列に考えている者がほとんどだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, they had little knowledge about cold protection and most of them thought marching in snow and trekking was the same.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, they had little knowledge about cold protection and most of them thought marching in snow and trekking was the same.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, they had little knowledge about cold protection and most of them thought marching in snow and trekking was the same.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="227">
<j>第5連隊では、出発の前日に壮行会が開かれており、深夜まで宴会が行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As to the 5th Regiment, a send-off party was held on the day before departure and banquet was continuing till midnight.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the 5th Regiment, a send-off party was held on the day before departure and the banquet continued until midnight.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the fifth Regiment, a send-off party was held on the day before departure and the banquet continued until midnight.</e>
<cmt>spellingを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="228">
<j>長谷川特務曹長は「田代といっても僅かに5里ばかりで、湯に入りに行くつもりで、たった手ぬぐい1本を持っただけだった」と語っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sergeant Major Hasegawa recalled &apos; I brought only one hand towel like going to dip in a hot spring because Tashiro was just about 5 ri away from there.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sergeant Major Hasegawa recalled &apos; I brought only one hand towel like going to dip in a hot spring because Tashiro was just about 5 ri away from there.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sergeant Major Hasegawa recalled &apos; I brought only one hand towel like going to dip in a hot spring because Tashiro was just about five ri (&quot;ri&quot; is about 3.927km) away from there.&apos;</e>
<cmt>termを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="229">
<j>なお、長谷川は軍銃の皮を足に巻き凍傷を防いでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hasegawa prevented his feet from being frozen by wrapping them with the leather used on a gun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hasegawa prevented his feet from being frozen by wrapping them with the leather used on a gun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hasegawa prevented his feet from being frozen by wrapping them with the leather used on a gun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="230">
<j>遭難始末によれば、&quot;山登り&quot;という事で履物を普段の皮製の軍靴から地下足袋に換えて参加した兵士も何名かいたことが確認されている（氏名までは不詳）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &apos;Sounan Shimatsusho (report of the disaster)&apos;, several soldiers (who they were is unclear) replaced their ordinary leather military boots with tabi socks to climb a mountain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &apos;Sounan Shimatsusho (report of the disaster)&apos;, several soldiers (who they were is unclear) replaced their ordinary leather military boots with tabi socks to climb the mountain.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &apos;Sounan Shimatsusho,&apos; several soldiers (who they were is unclear) replaced their ordinary leather military boots with tabi socks to climb the mountain.</e>
<cmt>termを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="231">
<j>生存者の小原伍長の証言によれば、誰も予備の手袋、靴下を用意しておらず、装備が濡れてしまったら換えはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to survived Corporal Ohara, they had no spare gloves and socks to change when their clothes got wet, and frostbite occurred from the wet part, depriving them of temperature and power, making them being frozen to death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to survivor, Corporal Ohara, they had no spare gloves and socks to change into when their clothes got wet.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to survivor, Corporal Ohara, they had no spare gloves and socks to change into when their clothes got wet.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="232">
<j>そこから凍傷が始まり、体温と体力を奪われ凍死していったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Frostbite occurred from the wet parts, depriving them of temperature and power, and causing them to freeze to death.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Frostbite occurred from the wet parts, depriving them of temperature and power, and causing them to freeze to death.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="233">
<j>小原伍長自身も「もしあの時、予備の軍手、靴下の一組でも余計にあれば自分は足や指を失わなかっただろうし、半分の兵士が助かっただろう」と後年、供述している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Corporal Ohara recalled, he himself &apos; wouldn&apos;t have lost my legs and fingers and half of the soldiers would have been alive, if we had had only one pair of gloves and socks to change.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Corporal Ohara recalled, he himself &apos; wouldn&apos;t have lost my legs and fingers and half of the soldiers would have been alive, if we had had only one pair of gloves and socks to change.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Corporal Ohara recalled, he himself &apos; wouldn&apos;t have lost my legs and fingers and half of the soldiers would have been alive, if we had had only one pair of gloves and socks to change.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="234">
<j>兵卒の生存者は全員山間部の出身で、普段はマタギの手伝いや炭焼きに従事している者達だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All the survivors of nonofficial soldiers were from mountain-ringed region and usually helped Matagi hunter group or doing charcoal making.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All the survivors who were nonofficial soldiers were from mountain-ringed regions and normally helped Matagi hunter groups or worked in charcoal making.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All the survivors who were nonofficial soldiers were from mountain-ringed regions and normally helped Matagi hunter groups or worked in charcoal making.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="235">
<j>彼等は冬山での行動にある程度習熟しており、「足に唐辛子を擦り付けて、足温を安定させる」「足に油紙を巻いて水分の浸入を防ぐ」「肌着と衣服の間に新聞紙を仕込んで、体温の安定化、寒気の遮断をする」「食料（握り飯）に油紙を巻いて凍結を防ぐ」等の独自の耐寒装備をしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were acquainted with winter mountain to some extent and had their original cold protection such as &apos; rubbing red peppers on one&apos;s feet to make the temperature of the feet stable&apos; &apos;wrapping water-resistant paper coated with oil around one&apos;s feet to prevent water from invading&apos; &apos; tucking newspaper between underwear and clothes to make body temperature stable and shut out the cold air&apos; &apos;wrapping water-resistant paper coated with oil around food (rice balls) to prevent them being frozen&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were acquainted with winter mountains to some extent and used their original cold protection techniques such as &apos; rubbing red peppers on one&apos;s feet to make the temperature of the feet stable&apos; &apos;wrapping water-resistant paper coated with oil around one&apos;s feet to prevent water from invading&apos; &apos; tucking newspaper between underwear and clothes to make body temperature stable and shut out the cold air&apos; &apos;wrapping water-resistant paper coated with oil around food (rice balls) to prevent them being frozen&apos;.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were acquainted with winter mountains to some extent and used their original cold protection techniques such as &apos; rubbing red peppers on one&apos;s feet to make the temperature of the feet stable&apos; &apos;wrapping water-resistant paper coated with oil around one&apos;s feet to prevent water from invading&apos; &apos; tucking newspaper between underwear and clothes to make body temperature stable and shut out the cold air&apos; &apos;wrapping water-resistant paper coated with oil around food (rice balls) to prevent them being frozen&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="236">
<j>将校の生存確率が高いのも、兵卒より防寒機能が高い装備が一因と言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that one of the reason why survival probability of the officers is high is because their equipment had better cold protection function than those of nonofficial soldiers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that one of the reasons why the survival probability of the officers was high is because their equipment had better cold protection functions than those of nonofficial soldiers.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that one of the reasons why the survival probability of the officers was high is because their equipment had better cold protection functions than those of nonofficial soldiers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other things</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other things</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other things</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="237">
<j>この事件では雪中行軍した兵士だけではなく、道案内で駆り出された地元の一般人も凍傷などの被害を受けたと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said not only soldiers who marched in snow but local people who gathered as guides were also suffered from frostbite and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that not only soldiers who marched in the snow but local people who gathered as guides also suffered from frostbite and other ailments.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that not only soldiers who marched in the snow but local people who gathered as guides also suffered from frostbite and other ailments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="238">
<j>手厚い補償のあった遭難兵士と違い、道案内の地元民には十分な礼金すら与えられていないと言われ、悲惨さの度合いは兵士以上に高いという意見もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some say that local people who had guided the troop were more miserable than missing soldiers who received handsome compensation, because unlike them, local people weren&apos;t given sufficient reward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some say that local people who had guided the troop were more miserable than missing soldiers who received handsome compensation, because unlike them, local people weren&apos;t given sufficient reward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some say that local people who had guided the troop were more miserable than missing soldiers who received handsome compensation, because unlike them, local people weren&apos;t given sufficient reward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="239">
<j>事件は新田次郎により『八甲田山死の彷徨』としてに小説化され、さらにこの小説を原作としたの映画『八甲田山 (映画)』で一般に広く知られることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The incident became known to public by a novel &quot;Death march on Mount Hakkoda&quot; written by Jiro NITTA and a movie which was based on that novel &quot;Hakkoda (movie)&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The incident became known to the public by a novel, &quot;Death march on Mount Hakkoda&quot; written by Jiro NITTA and a movie which was based on that novel &quot;Hakkoda (movie)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The incident became known to the public by a novel, &quot;Death march on Mount Hakkoda&quot; written by Jiro NITTA and a movie which was based on that novel &quot;Hakkoda-san Mountain.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation, wordingを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="240">
<j>1月、第2次雪中行軍を敢行。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January, the second march in snow was carried out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January, the second march in snow was carried out.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January, the second march in snow was carried out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="241">
<j>参加者全員無事に八甲田山走破に成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All participants succeeded in marching through Hakkoda safe and sound.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All participants succeeded in marching through Hakkoda safe and sound.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All participants succeeded in marching through Hakkoda-san Mountain safe and sound.</e>
<cmt>wordingを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="242">
<j>1月、青森駐屯の第5普通科連隊（陸上自衛隊第9師団 (陸上自衛隊)）が近代装備を用い八甲田山の雪中行軍に成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January, the 5th Infantry Regiment (Japan Ground Self-Defense Force 9th Division[Japan Ground Self-Defense Force]) of Aomori post succeeded in marching in snow on Hakkoda-san Mountain with modern equipment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January, the 5th Infantry Regiment (Japan Ground Self-Defense Force 9th Division[Japan Ground Self-Defense Force]) of Aomori post succeeded in marching in snow on Hakkoda-san Mountain with modern equipment.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January, the fifth Infantry Regiment (Japan Ground Self-Defense Force ninth Division [Japan Ground Self-Defense Force]) of Aomori post succeeded in marching in snow on Hakkoda-san Mountain with modern equipment.</e>
<cmt>spellingを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="243">
<j>7月、レンジャー養成訓練中だった青森駐屯第5普通科連隊の訓練生15人、教官ら8人の計23人が、八甲田温泉近くの田代平牧場入口付近のくぼ地で相次いでガス中毒様の症状で倒れ、12人が病院に運ばれ内3名が死亡する惨事が起きている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July, 15 trainees and 8 instructors, 23 in total, of the 5th Infantry Regiment of Aomori post fell on low-lying depression at the entrance of Tashirodaira farm near Hakkoda hot spring with gas poisoning-like symptom during the training of rangers, and 12 of them were carried to hospital, of whom 3 died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July, 15 trainees and 8 instructors, 23 in total, of the 5th Infantry Regiment of Aomori post fell on a low-lying depression at the entrance of Tashirodaira farm near Hakkoda hot spring with gas poisoning-like symptoms during the training of rangers, and 12 of them were carried to hospital, of whom 3 died.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July, 15 trainees and 8 instructors, 23 in total, of the fifth Infantry Regiment of Aomori post fell on a low-lying depression at the entrance of Tashirodaira farm near Hakkoda hot spring with gas poisoning-like symptoms during the training of rangers, and 12 of them were carried to hospital, of whom 3 died.</e>
<cmt>spellingを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="244">
<j>近年、その死因について多くの説が立てられている山口鋠少佐（大隊長）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many theories about the cause of death of Major Shin YAMAGUCHI recent years, however, his status by birth and career are barely known widely.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There have been many theories about the cause of death of Major Shin YAMAGUCHI in recent years. However, his status by birth and his career are barely known.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There have been many theories about the cause of death of Major Shin YAMAGUCHI in recent years.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="245">
<j>だが、その出自・経歴については広く知られているとは言い難い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, his status by birth and his career are barely known.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="246">
<j>山口（旧姓成澤、養子のため改姓）は安政3年に幕臣の子として生まれ、義兄の英学者・翻訳家の渡部温（『イソップ寓話』の翻訳等で名高い）が沼津兵学校教授を務めていたため、幼時を沼津で過ごす（年少のため入学はせず）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamaguchi (original family name was Narisawa, changed as he was adopted) was born to vassal of the shogun in 1856, growing up in Numadu because his brother-in-law On WATANABE, English scholar and translator, was professor at Numadu Hei School (Yamaguchi was too young to enter).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamaguchi (original family name was Narisawa, changed as he was adopted) was born to a vassal of the shogun in 1856, growing up in Numadu because his brother-in-law On WATANABE, English scholar and translator, was a professor at Numadu Hei School (Yamaguchi was too young to enter).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamaguchi (original family name was Narisawa, changed as he was adopted) was born to a vassal of the shogun in 1856, growing up in Numadu because his brother-in-law On WATANABE, English scholar and translator, was a professor at Numadu Hei School (Numazu officer academy) (Yamaguchi was too young to enter).</e>
<cmt>termを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="247">
<j>後に東京外国語学校（やはり渡部が校長だったことがある）でフランス語を専攻し、そして陸軍士官学校 (日本)から陸軍戸山学校に進む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later he studied French at Tokyo University of Foreign Studies (it&apos;s also because the principal was Watanabe), going from Military academy (Japan) to Army Toyama School.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he studied French at Tokyo University of Foreign Studies (also because the principal was Watanabe), going from the Military academy (Japan) to Army Toyama School.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he studied French at Tokyo University of Foreign Studies (also because the principal was Watanabe), going from the Military academy (Japan) to Army Toyama School.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="248">
<j>日清戦争に従軍した後、青森の前任地は山形（歩兵第32連隊）だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After serving in Japanese-Sino War, his post was Yamagata (the 32th Infantry Regiment) before Aomori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After serving in Japanese-Sino War, his post was Yamagata (the 32th Infantry Regiment) before Aomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After serving in Japanese-Sino War, his post was Yamagata (the 32th Infantry Regiment) before Aomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="249">
<j>なお、謎の多い山口の最期を看取った軍医は山形衛戍病院からの応援者、中原貞衛であり、この点も単なる偶然と言い切れない一面がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The army surgeon who was on Yamaguchi&apos;s bedside when he died mysteriously was Sadae NAKAHARA, who had come from Yamagata Military Hospital, and it was hardly just a coincidence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The army surgeon who was at Yamaguchi&apos;s bedside when he died mysteriously was Sadae NAKAHARA, who had come from Yamagata Military Hospital, and it was hardly a coincidence.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The army surgeon who was at Yamaguchi&apos;s bedside when he died mysteriously was Sadae NAKAHARA, who had come from Yamagata Military Hospital, and it was hardly a coincidence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="250">
<j>いずれにせよ、今後の研究進展によって、既存の小説や映画とは異なった人物像が浮かび上がって来る可能性がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anyway, it is possible his different profiles from that of in the novel and the movie will be revealed by further study.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anyway, it is possible his different profiles from that of the novel and the movie will be revealed by further study.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anyway, it is possible his different profiles from that of the novel and the movie will be revealed by further study.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="251">
<j>この八甲田山雪中行軍遭難事件を聴いた、ノルウェー王国のホーコン7世国王が、、お見舞いとして明治天皇宛にスキー二台を進呈した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Haakon VII of Kingdom of Norway, send two skis to Emperor Meiji as a get-well present, having heard about Death March of Hakkoda Mountains Incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Haakon VII of Kingdom of Norway, sent two skis to Emperor Meiji as a get-well present, having heard about Death March of Hakkoda Mountains Incident.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Haakon VII of Kingdom of Norway, sent two skis to Emperor Meiji as a get-well present, having heard about Death March of Hakkoda Mountains Incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Caspar(id:70378), Kawai(id:5634), 花いちもんめ(id:39081), Ｔａｔｅｍｏｎｏ2(id:90153), Bellcricket(id:37640), The Side(id:69360), 0太郎(id:7375), Anexus6(id:190046), Su-no-G(id:52744), 軽功(id:40602), 玄史生(id:43670), 男の教室(id:62924), 代言人(id:33675), 曾禰越後守(id:183605), Dagon sato(id:12438), エントンカリア(id:148538), こぶまき(id:38278), あおもりくま(id:143606), Sampo(id:1041), Buddy holly(id:182036), Kurokirishima(id:177343), 貿易風(id:85487), ととりん(id:31982), Molemaster(id:206725), Blood on the town(id:102100), ミッドランドライダー(id:40104), Tiyoringo(id:70026), GILIK(id:108047), J8takagi(id:20409), Diw(id:268275), 斎藤勇輝(id:61190), Carkuni(id:79281), 竃馬(id:102733), ZERO13(id:53029), Azzurro t(id:110960), Geogie(id:143809), Route275(id:119236), Rislimric(id:54531), あんも騎士(id:139357), R28Bot(id:177951), Tatata(id:110870), WhisperToMe(id:1202), やすとし(id:63220), Kodai99(id:83937), Naranja-este(id:101503), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>