<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>後南朝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ex-Southern Court</e>
<cmt>「後南朝」ですが、英語の定訳はないようですので、”Ex-Southern Court”としましたが、ほかの選択肢として、”Former Southern Court”もあるかと思います。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ex-Southern Court</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gonancho (Second Southern Court)</e>
<cmt>用語集より、Gonancho (Second Southern Court)としました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>後南朝（ごなんちょう）とは、1392年（元中9年/明徳3年）の南北朝合一後、南朝 (日本)の再建を図った南朝の皇統の子孫や遺臣による南朝復興運動とそれによって樹立された政権、皇室の総称である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ex-Southern Court&quot; (gonancho) is a general term that refers to descendants of the Southern dynasty lineage and its former retainers and their attempts to revive the Southern Court after the two Courts were unified in 1392 (the ninth year of Ganchu/third year of Meitoku), and to the political administrations and the members of the Imperial household involved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ex-Southern Court&quot; (gonancho) is a general term that refers to descendants of the Southern dynasty lineage and their former retainers and their attempts to revive the Southern Court after the two Courts were unified in 1392 (the ninth year of Ganchu/third year of Meitoku), and to the political administrations and the members of the Imperial household who were involved involved.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gonancho (Second Southern Court) is a general term that refers to descendants of the Southern dynasty (Japan) lineage and their former retainers and their attempts to revive the Southern Court after the two Courts were unified in 1392, and to the political administrations and the members of the Imperial household who were involved.</e>
<cmt>用語集より、Gonancho (Second Southern Court)としました。(Japan)補足。旧暦は不要と考え、削除しました。余分なinvolved削除。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>この名称は江戸時代末期に儒学者斎藤拙堂によって付けられたもので、それまで名称は特に決まっていなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This name was coined by the Confucian scholar Setsudo SAITO in the final days of the Edo period; until this point, there was no established name for such activities and groups.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This name was coined by the Confucian scholar Setsudo SAITO in the final days of the Edo period; until that time, there was no established term for such activities and groups.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This name was coined by the Confucian scholar Setsudo SAITO in the final days of the Edo period; until that time, there was no established term for such activities and groups.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>また後南朝という呼び方も戦後広まったもので戦前までは定着してはいなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, the term &quot;ex-Southern Court&quot; (gonancho) didn&apos;t come into common use until after World War II, so up until then the term was not firmly established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, the term &quot;ex-Southern Court&quot; (gonancho) didn&apos;t come into common use until after World War II, so up until then the term was not firmly established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the term &quot;Gonancho (Second Southern Court)&quot; didn&apos;t come into common use until after World War II, so up until then the term was not firmly established.</e>
<cmt>用語集より、Gonancho (Second Southern Court)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Synopsis</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Synopsis</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Synopsis</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>南北朝合一時の約束「明徳の和約」では天皇は北朝 (日本)系（持明院統）と南朝系（大覚寺統）から交代で出す（迭立）ことになっていたが、1412年（応永19年）に北朝系の後小松天皇の次代として後小松上皇の皇子称光天皇が即位したことをきっかけに、北朝系によって天皇位が独占されるようになったのに反抗して起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the &apos;Meitoku Compromise,&apos; the agreement reached when the Northern and Southern Courts were unified, the Imperial throne would alternate between candidates from the (Japanese) Northern dynasty (of the Go-Fukakusa lineage) and the Southern dynasty (of the Kameyama lineage), but in 1412 (the nineteenth year of Oei) Emperor Go-Komatsu of the Northern lineage broke precedent by enthroning his son Prince (Emperor) Shoko as his successor, bidding to monopolize the Imperial throne for the Northern dynasty lineage, which provoked hostility among former Southern Court supporters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the &apos;Meitoku Compromise,&apos; an agreement reached when the Northern and Southern Courts were unified, the Imperial throne would alternate between candidates from the (Japanese) Northern dynasty (of the Go-Fukakusa lineage) and the Southern dynasty (of the Kameyama lineage), but in 1412 (the nineteenth year of Oei) Emperor Go-Komatsu of the Northern lineage broke precedent by enthroning his son Prince (Emperor) Shoko as his successor, in a bid to monopolize the Imperial throne for the Northern dynasty lineage, which provoked hostility among former Southern Court supporters.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the &apos;Meitoku Compromise,&apos; an agreement reached when the Northern and Southern Courts were unified, the Imperial throne would alternate between candidates from the (Japanese) Northern dynasty (of the Gofukakusa lineage) and the Southern dynasty (of the Kameyama lineage), but in 1412 Emperor Gokomatsu of the Northern lineage broke precedent by enthroning his son Prince (Emperor) Shoko as his successor, in a bid to monopolize the Imperial throne for the Northern dynasty lineage, which provoked hostility among former Southern Court supporters.</e>
<cmt>Gofukakusa に訂正しました。旧暦は不要と考え、削除しました。Gokomatsu に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>1414年（応永21年）、4年前に京都を出奔して吉野に潜行していた南朝最後の天皇後亀山天皇とその皇子小倉宮を支持して伊勢国国司の北畠満雅が挙兵したが、室町幕府の討伐を受け和解、上皇は2年後に京に帰った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1414 (Oei 21), the provincial governor of Ise province, Mitsumasa KITABATAKE--financial backer of the last Southern Court Emperor, Go-Kameyama, who had fled from Kyoto four years earlier and traveled incognito to Yoshino, as well as his son Prince Oguranomiya--raised an army in response, but after receiving an order from Go-Kameyama to subjugate the Muromachi shogunate, a peace settlement was reached, and retired Emperor Go-Kameyama returned to Kyoto two years later.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Cloistered Emperor&quot; is also often used in textbooks; from the beginning of this project I&apos;ve translated it as &quot;retired&quot; but they each have advantages and disadvantages.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1414 (Oei 21), the provincial governor of Ise province, Mitsumasa KITABATAKE--financial backer of the last Southern Court Emperor, Go-Kameyama, who had fled from Kyoto four years earlier and traveled incognito to Yoshino, as well as his son Prince Oguranomiya--raised an army in response, but after receiving an order from Go-Kameyama to subjugate the Muromachi shogunate, a peace settlement was reached, and the retired Emperor Go-Kameyama returned to Kyoto two years later.</e>
<cmt>minor grammatical revision</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1414 (Oei 21), the provincial governor of Ise province, Mitsumasa KITABATAKE - financial backer of the last Southern Court Emperor, Gokameyama, who had fled from Kyoto four years earlier and traveled incognito to Yoshino, as well as his son Prince Oguranomiya - raised an army in response, but after receiving an order from Gokameyama to subjugate the Muromachi Shogunate, a peace settlement was reached, and the Retired Emperor Gokameyama returned to Kyoto two years later.</e>
<cmt>旧暦は不要と考え、削除しました。Gokameyama に訂正しました。スペース補足、-削除Shogunate に訂正しました。Retired に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>後亀山上皇の死去から4年後の1428年（正長元年）、嗣子のなかった称光天皇が崩御したために北朝の嫡流は断絶した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1428 (the first year of Seicho), four years after retired Emperor Go-Kameyama died, Emperor Shoko died without an heir, and consequently the principal Northern lineage came to an end.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1428 (the first year of Seicho), four years after retired Emperor Go-Kameyama died, Emperor Shoko died without an heir, and consequently the principal Northern lineage came to an end.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1428, four years after Retired Emperor Gokameyama died, Emperor Shoko died without an heir, and consequently the principal Northern lineage came to an end.</e>
<cmt>旧暦は不要と考え、削除しました。Gokameyama に訂正しました。Retired に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>後小松上皇が北朝の傍流である伏見宮家から彦仁王（後花園天皇）を後継者に選ぼうとしたことをきっかけに、北朝は皇統断絶して皇位継承権を失ったと考える南朝側は激しく反発する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Retired Emperor Go-Komatsu took this opportunity to select Prince Hikohito (Emperor Go-Hanazono) of the Fushiminomiya branch of the Northern lineage to be the successor; in response, the ex-Southern Court faction, which with the Northern dynasty&apos;s Imperial line extinct had expected that the Northern lineage would have lost its authority over matters of Imperial succession, vehemently opposed this decision.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Retired Emperor Go-Komatsu took this opportunity to select Prince Hikohito (Emperor Go-Hanazono) of the Fushiminomiya branch of the Northern lineage to be the successor; in response, the ex-Southern Court faction, which now with the Northern dynasty&apos;s Imperial line extinct, he had expected that the Northern lineage would have lost its authority over matters of Imperial succession, vehemently opposed this decision.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Retired Emperor Gokomatsu took this opportunity to select Prince Hikohito (Emperor Gohanazono) of the Fushiminomiya branch of the Northern lineage to be the successor; in response, the Gonancho faction, which now with the Northern dynasty&apos;s Imperial line extinct, he had expected that the Northern lineage would have lost its authority over matters of Imperial succession, vehemently opposed this decision.</e>
<cmt>Gokomatsu、Gohanazono に訂正しました。ex-Southern Court→Gonanchoとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>北畠満雅は再び小倉宮聖承（後亀山の皇子恒敦の王子）を担いで伊勢国で挙兵、幕府軍と戦って敗死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once again, Mitsumasa KITABATAKE, who was supporting Prince Seisho OGURANOMIYA (the son of Tsuneatsu, himself Go-Kameyama&apos;s son and Imperial prince), raised an army in Ise province, but he was defeated in a battle with shogunal forces and died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once again, Mitsumasa KITABATAKE, who was supporting Prince Seisho OGURANOMIYA (the son of Tsuneatsu, himself Go-Kameyama&apos;s son and Imperial prince), raised an army in Ise province, but he was defeated in a battle with shogunal forces and died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once again, Mitsumasa KITABATAKE, who was supporting Prince Oguranomiya Seisho (the son of Tsuneatsu, himself Gokameyama&apos;s son and Imperial Prince), raised an army in Ise Province, but he was defeated in a battle with shogunal forces and died.</e>
<cmt>Oguranomiya Seisho に訂正しました。Gokameyama に訂正しました。Prince 大文字にしました。Province 大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>この事件をはじめとして、応仁の乱に至るまで、南朝の子孫は反幕勢力に担がれて断続的に活動を続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the time of this incident onward, until the time of the Onin war, the descendants of the Southern Court and dynasty, taken in by various powerful anti-shogunate forces, continued acting intermittently against the Northern dynasty and the shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the time of this incident onward, until the time of the Onin war, the descendants of the Southern Court and dynasty, taken in by various powerful anti-shogunate forces, continued acting intermittently against the Northern dynasty and the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the time of this incident onward, until the time of the Onin War, the descendants of the Southern Court and dynasty, taken in by various powerful anti-shogunate forces, continued acting intermittently against the Northern dynasty and the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>War 大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>1443年（嘉吉3年）には、南朝復興を唱える日野氏傍流の日野有光らの勢力が後花園天皇の暗殺を企てて御所に乱入（暗殺は未遂）、三種の神器の天叢雲剣と八尺瓊勾玉を奪い、南朝皇族の通蔵主・金蔵主兄弟（後亀山の弟の孫）を担いで比叡山に逃れる「禁闕の変」を起こした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1443 (the third year of Kakitsu), Arimitsu HINO, from a branch of the Hino family, who was constantly talking of reviving the Southern Court, sent a force that was planning to assassinate Emperor Go-Hanazono to enter the Imperial palace (the assassination attempt failed), where they stole two of the Three Imperial Regalia of Japan, the Ama-no Murakumo no Tsurugi (the heavenly cloud gathering sword) and the Yasakani no Magatama (the Grand Jewels) before fleeing to Mt. Hiei accompanied by Tsuzoshu and Gonzoshu, brothers of the Southern dynasty lineage (the grandchildren of Go-Kameyama&apos;s younger brother) in what became known as the Kinketsu Incident (or the Incident at the Forbidden Palace).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1443 (the third year of Kakitsu), Arimitsu HINO, from a branch of the Hino family, who was constantly talking of reviving the Southern Court, sent a force that was planning to assassinate Emperor Go-Hanazono to enter the Imperial palace (the assassination attempt failed), where they stole two of the Three Imperial Regalia of Japan, the Ama-no Murakumo no Tsurugi (the heavenly cloud gathering sword) and the Yasakani no Magatama (the Grand Jewels) before fleeing to Mt. Hiei accompanied by Tsuzoshu and Gonzoshu, brothers of the Southern dynasty lineage (the grandchildren of Go-Kameyama&apos;s younger brother) in what became known as the Kinketsu Incident (or the Incident at the Forbidden Palace).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1443 (the third year of Kakitsu), Arimitsu HINO, from a branch of the Hino family, who was constantly talking of reviving the Southern Court, sent a force that was planning to assassinate Emperor Gohanazono to enter the Imperial Palace (the assassination attempt failed), where they stole two of the Three Imperial Regalia of Japan, the Ama no Murakumo no Tsurugi (the heavenly cloud gathering sword) and the Yasakani no Magatama (the Grand Jewels) before fleeing to Mt. Hiei accompanied by Tsuzoshu and Gonzoshu, brothers of the Southern dynasty lineage (the grandchildren of Gokameyama&apos;s younger brother) in what became known as the Kinketsu Incident (or the Incident at the Forbidden Palace).</e>
<cmt>Gohanazono に訂正しました。Palace 大文字にしました。-削除。Gokameyama に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>幕府軍によって変の首謀者たちが討たれ、剣が奪い返された後も神璽は後南朝に持ち去られたままであったが、1457年（長禄元年）に至って、1441年（嘉吉元年）の嘉吉の乱で取り潰された赤松氏の復興を願う赤松家遺臣の石見太郎、丹生屋帯刀、上月満吉らが、大和国・紀伊国国境付近の北山（奈良県吉野郡上北山村か）あるいは三之公（同郡川上村 (奈良県)）に本拠を置いていた後南朝に臣従すると偽って後南朝勢力を襲い、南朝の末裔という自天王・忠義王兄弟を殺害して神璽を奪い返した（長禄の変）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shogunal forces hunted down and executed the ringleaders of the Incident and recaptured the sword, but the Grand Jewel remained with the ex-Southern Court forces who fled; in 1457 (the first year of Choroku), the surviving retainers of the AKAMATSU clan--which had been crushed in the Kakitsu Rebellion of 1441 (the first year of Kakitsu)--including Taro ISHIMI, Tatewaki NIUNOYA, and Mitsuyoshi KOZUKI, wishing to restore the AKAMATSU clan&apos;s fortunes, went to the ex-Southern Court headquarters at Kitayama near the provincial borders of Yamato and Kii provinces (possibly referring to modern-day Kamikitayama village in Yoshino district, Nara Pref.), or perhaps at Sannoko (in Kawakami village of Yoshino district, Nara Pref.), and pretended to become vassals of the ex-Southern Court before turning on them and striking down many of their forces, murdering Princes Jitenno and Tadayoshiten, brothers and Imperial descendants of the Southern Court bloodline, before recapturing the Grand Jewels (in what became known as the Choroku Incident).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shogunal forces hunted down and executed the ringleaders of the Incident and recaptured the sword, but the Grand Jewels remained with the ex-Southern Court forces who fled in 1457 (the first year of Choroku), the surviving retainers of the AKAMATSU clan--which had been crushed in the Kakitsu Rebellion of 1441 (the first year of Kakitsu)--including Taro ISHIMI, Tatewaki NIUNOYA, and Mitsuyoshi KOZUKI, wishing to restore the AKAMATSU clan&apos;s fortunes, went to the ex-Southern Court headquarters at Kitayama near the provincial borders of Yamato and Kii provinces (possibly referring to modern-day Kamikitayama village in Yoshino district, Nara Pref.), or perhaps at Sannoko (in Kawakami village of Yoshino district, Nara Pref.), and pretended to become vassals of the ex-Southern Court before turning on them and striking down many of their forces, murdering Princes Jitenno and Tadayoshiten who were brothers and Imperial descendants of the Southern Court bloodline, before recapturing the Grand Jewels (in what became known as the Choroku Incident).</e>
<cmt>minor revision for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shogunal forces hunted down and executed the ringleaders of the Incident and recaptured the sword, but the Grand Jewels remained with the Gonancho forces who fled in 1457, the surviving retainers of the Akamatsu clan - which had been crushed in the Kakitsu Rebellion of 1441 - including Taro ISHIMI, Tatewaki NIUNOYA, and Mitsuyoshi KOZUKI, wishing to restore the Akamatsu clan&apos;s fortunes, went to the Gonancho headquarters at Kitayama near the provincial borders of Yamato and Kii Provinces (possibly referring to modern-day Kamikitayama village in Yoshino district, Nara Pref.), or perhaps at Sannoko (in Kawakami village of Yoshino district, Nara Pref.), and pretended to become vassals of the Gonancho before turning on them and striking down many of their forces, murdering Princes Jitenno and Tadayoshiten who were brothers and Imperial descendants of the Southern Court bloodline, before recapturing the Grand Jewels (in what became known as the Choroku Incident).</e>
<cmt>ex-Southern Court→Gonanchoとしました。旧暦は不要と考え、削除しました。Akamatsuに訂正しました。-削除、スペース補足。Province大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>両王子は後世の系図では小倉宮の末裔とされているが、同時代史料に証拠はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both princes are listed in later genealogies as being descendants of Oguranomiya, but there is no evidence for this in historical records of the day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both princes are listed in later genealogies as being descendants of Oguranomiya, but there is no evidence for this in historical records of the day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both princes are listed in later genealogies as being descendants of Oguranomiya, but there is no evidence for this in historical records of the day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>後南朝は次第に勢力を失い、応仁の乱において小倉宮の末裔（『大乗院寺社雑事記』には小倉宮の子孫との記述あり）と称し、岡崎前門主という人物の息子が山名宗全により洛中の西陣に迎えられた（これを「西陣の南帝」と呼ぶ）との記録を最後に、歴史上にあらわれなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ex-Southern Court forces gradually lost their power, and during the Onin War were labeled in historical records as descendants of Oguranomiya (in the &quot;Daijoin temple and shrine record of miscellaneous matters&quot; they are listed as offspring of Oguranomiya), while the son of Zenmonshu (Gatekeeper) OKAZAKI being welcomed in the capital&apos;s western district (this son was called &quot;The Southern Emperor of the western district&quot;) by Sozen YAMANA is the last historical mention of them; after this point, they no longer appear in the historical record.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ex-Southern Court forces gradually lost their power, and during the Onin War were labeled in historical records as descendants of Oguranomiya (in the &quot;Daijoin temple and shrine records of miscellaneous matters&quot; they are listed as offspring of Oguranomiya), while the son of Zenmonshu (Gatekeeper) OKAZAKI being welcomed in the capital&apos;s western district (this son was called &quot;The Southern Emperor of the western district&quot;) by Sozen YAMANA is the last historical mention of them; after this point, they no longer appear in historical records.</e>
<cmt>minor grammatical revisions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Gonancho forces gradually lost their power, and during the Onin War were labeled in historical records as descendants of Oguranomiya (in the &quot;Daijoin temple and shrine records of miscellaneous matters&quot; they are listed as offspring of Oguranomiya), while the son of Zenmonshu (Gatekeeper) OKAZAKI being welcomed in the capital&apos;s western district (this son was called &quot;The Southern Emperor of the western district&quot;) by Sozen YAMANA is the last historical mention of them; after this point, they no longer appear in historical records.</e>
<cmt>ex-Southern Court→Gonanchoとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>しかしその後も民間で後南朝の伝説や伝承は残り、貴種流離譚の一つとしてサンカに利用された可能性を滝川政次郎は指摘している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yet even after this point, legends and folklore about the ex-Southern Court forces remained in existence among the common people, and Seijiro TAKIKAWA has pointed out that one of the tales of wandering aristocrats among the Sanka (mountain folk of Japan) may have made use of ex-Southern Court stories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yet even after this point, legends and folklore about the ex-Southern Court forces remained in existence among the common people, and Seijiro TAKIKAWA pointed out that one of the tales of wandering aristocrats among the Sanka (mountain folk of Japan) may have made use of the ex-Southern Court stories.</e>
<cmt>minor grammatical revisions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yet even after this point, legends and folklore about the Gonanch forces remained in existence among the common people, and Seijiro TAKIKAWA pointed out that one of the tales of wandering aristocrats among the Sanka (mountain folk of Japan) may have made use of the Gonancho stories.</e>
<cmt>ex-Southern Court→Gonanchoとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>太平洋戦争後の開放的気分の中で「熊沢天皇」こと熊沢寛道など、自らを正統な天皇の継承者と称する自称天皇たちが現れたとき、その多くは、1911年（明治44年）に明治天皇の裁断によって南朝が正統とされたことを受けて、後南朝の子孫と主張していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the liberal atmosphere after the end of the Second World War, when figures like Hiromichi KUMAZAWA, the so-called &quot;Emperor Kumazawa,&quot; appeared and each claimed that only he himself was the legitimate successor to the Emperor, most of these self-styled Emperors were reacting to the fact that in 1911 (Meiji 44) Emperor Meiji had decided that the Southern lineage was the legitimate one, and came forward claiming to be descendants of the Southern dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the liberal atmosphere after the end of the Second World War, when figures like Hiromichi KUMAZAWA, the so-called &quot;Emperor Kumazawa,&quot; appeared and each claimed that only he himself was the legitimate successor to the Emperor, most of these self-styled Emperors were reacting to the fact that in 1911 (Meiji 44) Emperor Meiji had decided that the Southern lineage was the legitimate one, and came forward claiming to be descendants of the Southern dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the liberal atmosphere after the end of the World War II, when figures like Hiromichi KUMAZAWA, the so-called &apos;Emperor Kumazawa,&apos; appeared and each claimed that only he himself was the legitimate successor to the Emperor, most of these self-styled Emperors were reacting to the fact that in 1911 Emperor Meiji had decided that the Southern lineage was the legitimate one, and came forward claiming to be descendants of the Southern dynasty.</e>
<cmt>World War IIとしました。原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に (Meiji 44)削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Carbuncle(id:346), 玄史生(id:43670), Reggaeman(id:6214), MIsogi(id:20599), 怪蘇(id:45514), ＤＦ．Ｋｉｎｇ(id:48817), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), 大伴宿禰大祐(id:10152), Safkan(id:423), Lkhiutsz(id:209331), Nakaoka7675(id:39645), Mop(id:12061), タビックスJapan(id:52714), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>