<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>和薬種改会所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wayakushu aratame kaisho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wayakushu aratame kaisho (agency for checking the quality of Japanese medicinal materials)</e>
<cmt>統一事項に従ってタイトルの補足説明を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wayakushu aratame kaisho (agency for checking the quality of Japanese medicinal materials)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>和薬種改会所（わやくしゅあらためかいしょ）は、江戸時代に江戸幕府が設置した和薬種の品質管理のための鑑定を行った機関。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wayakushu aratame kaisho was an agency established by the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) during the Edo period, which performed quality control check on domestic (Japanese) materials of medicines.</e>
<cmt>和薬種→domestic (Japanese) materials of medicines と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wayakushu aratame kaisho was an agency established by the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) during the Edo period, which performed quality control check on domestic (Japanese) materials of medicines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wayakushu aratame kaisho was an agency established by the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) during the Edo period, which performed quality control check on domestic (Japanese) materials of medicines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>和薬改所・和薬改会所とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also called Wayaku kaisho or Wayaku aratame kaisho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also called Wayaku kaisho or Wayaku aratame kaisho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also called Wayaku kaisho or Wayaku aratame kaisho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>享保7年（1727年）6月 (旧暦)に江戸伊勢町に設置され、続いて大坂淡路町・堺神明町・京都二条通・駿府にも設置された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was set up in Ise-machi in Edo, in July, 1727, and subsequently placed in Awaji-machi in Osaka, Shinmei-cho in Sakai, Nijo Street in Kyoto and Sunpu as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was set up in Ise-machi in Edo in July 1727 and subsequently placed in Awaji-machi in Osaka, Shinmei-cho in Sakai, Nijo Street in Kyoto and Sunpu as well.</e>
<cmt>不要なコンマがありましたので削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was set up in Ise-machi in Edo in July 1727 and subsequently placed in Awaji-machi in Osaka, Shinmei-cho in Sakai, Nijo Street in Kyoto and Sunpu as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>設置された都市の薬種問屋の代表は事前に江戸に集められ、本草学者丹羽正伯の講習を受けるとともに和薬種取締の基準・方法について意見の提出を求められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The representatives of wholesale drug companies in those cities had been summoned to Edo beforehand, where they attended a lecture by Shohaku NIWA, a scholar of herbalism, and were required to submit their opinions on the standards and measures for controlling domestic materials of medicines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The representatives of wholesale drug companies in those cities had been summoned to Edo beforehand, where they attended a lecture by Shohaku NIWA, a scholar of herbalism, and were required to submit their opinions on the standards and measures for controlling domestic materials of medicines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The representatives of wholesale drug companies in those cities had been summoned to Edo beforehand, where they attended a lecture by Shohaku NIWA, a scholar of herbalism, and were required to submit their opinions on the standards and measures for controlling domestic materials of medicines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>諸国から設置都市に送られてきた和薬種及び都市を通過して他の地域に向かう薬種は全て会所にて検査を受けて薬種の真偽及びその品質を検査した後に検印（焼印もしくは紙札）を得ることが義務付けられた（対象となる薬種が大量の場合は、会所役人が出張して検査した）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All the domestic materials of medicines sent from various districts to the cities where the agency was set up, as well as those sent to other districts passing through the cities, were obligated to receive a seal of approval (a brand or paper tag) after being inspected at kaisho for their genuineness and quality (if the amount of the materials was large, visiting inspection was performed by officials of the kaisho).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All the domestic materials of medicines sent from various districts to the cities where the agency was set up, as well as those sent to other districts passing through the cities, were obligated to receive a seal of approval (a brand or paper tag) after being inspected at kaisho for their genuineness and quality (if the amount of the materials was large, visiting inspection was performed by officials of the kaisho.)</e>
<cmt>統一事項に従ってピリオドは括弧の中に入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All the domestic materials of medicines sent from various districts to the cities where the agency was set up, as well as those sent to other districts passing through the cities, were obligated to receive a seal of approval (a brand or paper tag) after being inspected at kaisho for their genuineness and quality (if the amount of the materials was large, visiting inspection was performed by officials of the kaisho.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>なお、検査の際には「改料」として売主・買主双方から金銭を徴収した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the inspection, fees were collected both from sellers and buyers as &apos;aratameryo&apos; (改料) (inspection fee).</e>
<cmt>「改料」→ &apos;aratameryo&apos;正しい読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the inspection, fees were collected both from sellers and buyers as &apos;aratameryo&apos; (改料) (inspection fee).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the inspection, fees were collected both from sellers and buyers as &apos;aratameryo&apos; (改料) (inspection fee).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>比較的資料が残っている大坂の例を取ると、主たる問屋3名が会所頭取となり交替で会所役人を指揮し、その下に薬種屋仲間に属する121名が原則3名1組として1日交替（全40組）で会所に詰めて会所役人として検査及び改料徴収の任務を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of Osaka, for which relatively many data remains, there were three main warehouse merchants serving as Todori (chiefs) of the kaisho, who took turns in supervising officials of the kaisho, and under them, there were 121 people belonging to Yakushuya nakama (the union of drug sellers), who were divided into groups by basically three people (40 groups in total) and worked at the kaisho every other day as the officials to conduct inspection and collect aratameryo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of Osaka, for which relatively many data remain, there were three main warehouse merchants serving as Todori (chiefs) of the kaisho, who took turns in supervising officials of the kaisho, and under them, there were 121 people belonging to Yakushuya nakama (the union of drug sellers), who were divided into groups by basically three people (40 groups in total) and worked at the kaisho every other day as the officials to conduct inspection and collect aratameryo.</e>
<cmt>・many dataは複数扱いになりますのでremainとしました。・groups by basically three people→groups of basically three peopleが適切と思われます（groups of [数値]という言い回しがあるうえ、divideの主体がthree peopleのようにも読めます）。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of Osaka, for which relatively many data remain, there were three main warehouse merchants serving as Todori (chiefs) of the kaisho, who took turns in supervising officials of the kaisho, and under them, there were 121 people belonging to Yakushuya nakama (the union of drug sellers), who were divided into groups by basically three people (40 groups in total) and worked at the kaisho every other day as the officials to conduct inspection and collect aratameryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>元文3年（1738年）5月 (旧暦)に薬種問屋・薬種屋ら薬種業者が真物を覚えて品質が向上したことを理由に廃止されたが、実際は薬種流通の統制につながる和薬種改会所に対して業者の反感が強かったからと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June, 1738, the kaisho was abolished for the reason that the quality of the materials had been improved as drug traders such as wholesale drug companies or drug sellers had learnt to recognize genuine products; however, the true reason is said to be because there was a strong backlash from the traders against Wayakushu aratame kaisho which would lead to controlling distribution of materials of medicines.</e>
<cmt>廃止された→’会所が’廃止された、と補足して訳しました。品質が向上した→’薬種の’品質が向上した、と補足して訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June 1738, the kaisho was abolished because the quality of the materials improved as drug traders such as wholesale drug companies or drug sellers learnt to recognize genuine products; however, the true reason is said to be that there was a strong backlash from the traders against the possibility of the control of medicinal material distribution by Wayakushu aratame kaisho.</e>
<cmt>・which would lead toの部分は、ここでは制限用法の関係代名詞は不自然に思えます。「和薬種改会所に対しての反感」というより、「統制の可能性への反感」と解釈されますので、そのニュアンスを前に出しました。・The reason is becauseという形は、一般的な文章指南書でもThe reason is thatとした方が適切と言われていますので修正しました。・文頭のJune, 1738は数値が並んでいるわけではないので、コンマは不要と思われます。・for the reason that以降はbecause節にした方が短くなるうえ、時制もシンプルになるので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June 1738, the kaisho was abolished because the quality of the materials improved as drug traders such as wholesale drug companies or drug sellers learnt to recognize genuine products; however, the true reason is said to be that there was a strong backlash from the traders against the possibility of the control of medicinal material distribution by Wayakushu aratame kaisho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>