<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>職分田</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shikibunden (rice fields granted to government officials according to their position).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shikibunden (rice fields granted to government officials according to their position).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shikibunden (rice fields granted to government officials according to their position).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>職分田（しきぶんでん）は、古代東アジアの律令制において、官職についた者へ支給された田である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shikibunden are rice fields that were granted to government officials under the ancient East Asian Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shikibunden are rice fields that were granted to government officials under the ancient East Asian Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shikibunden are rice fields that were granted to government officials under the ancient East Asian Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>中国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>隋・唐の律令では、均田制を採用し、男丁（成人男性）へ一律に口分田と世業田（永業田）を支給することを原則としていたが、それと別に、官職にある者（官人）へ職分田が支給されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ritsuyo code of Sui and Tang dynasties adopted an equal-field system under which kubunden (rice fields given to each farmer under the Ritsuryo system) and inheritable fields were provided to all adult men, and shikibunden were granted separately to government officials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ritsuyo code of Sui and Tang dynasties adopted an equal-field system under which kubunden (rice fields given to each farmer under the Ritsuryo system) and inheritable fields were provided to all adult men, and shikibunden were granted separately to government officials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ritsuyo code of Sui and Tang dynasties adopted an equal-field system under which kubunden (rice fields given to each farmer under the Ritsuryo system) and inheritable fields were provided to all adult men, and shikibunden were granted separately to government officials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>ただし、官職を辞する時には職分田を返納する規定となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The code stipulated that shikibunden had to be returned on leaving government office.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The code stipulated that shikibunden had to be returned on resignation from the governmental position.</e>
<cmt>分かりやすいよう表現を少し変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The code stipulated that shikibunden had to be returned on resignation from the governmental position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>官人らは、支給された職分田の耕作権を、希望する均田農民へ与えて、収穫の一部を私的な租税として徴収していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Government officials (especially of low to medium rank) gave the right to cultivate on shikibunden to peasants who only had fields that were equally allocated, and collected parts of the harvest as private land tax.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Government officials (especially of low to medium ranks) devolved the right to cultivate shikibunden to peasants who only had equally allocated fields, and instead collected part of the harvest as a private land tax.</e>
<cmt>分かりやすいよう単語と表現を少し変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Government officials (especially of low to medium ranks) devolved the right to cultivate shikibunden to peasants who only had equally allocated fields, and instead collected part of the harvest as a private land tax.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>職分田は官人の重要な収入源として機能した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shikibunden functioned as an important income source for government officials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shikibunden functioned as an important income source for government officials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shikibunden functioned as an important income source for government officials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>日本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>日本では、701年制定の大宝律令（大宝令）において、職田（しきでん）と公廨田（くがいでん）の規定が置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, the Taiho Ritsuryo (Taiho code) enacted in 701 stipulated the rules for shikiden (rice fields granted to Dainagon and those with higher ranks) and kugaiden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, the Taiho Ritsuryo (Taiho code) enacted in 701 stipulated the rules for shikiden (rice fields granted to Dainagon and those with higher ranks) and kugaiden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, the Taiho Ritsuryo (Taiho code) enacted in 701 stipulated the rules for shikiden (rice fields granted to Dainagon and those with higher ranks) and kugaiden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>職田は、大納言以上の太政官の官人および郡司へ支給される田地であり、公廨田は、国司および大宰府官人へ支給される田地である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shikiden were rice fields provided to government officials who were Dajokan (Grand Council of State) and held the rank of Dainagon (chief councilor of state) or higher and to Gunji (local magistrates), and kugaiden were rice fields provided to Kokushi (provincial governors) and officials of Dazaifu (local government office in the Kyushu region).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shikiden were rice fields provided to the government officials who were the members of Daijokan (Grand Council of State) and held the ranks of Dainagon (chief councilor of the state) or higher and to Gunji (local magistrates), and kugaiden were rice fields provided to Kokushi (provincial governors) and officials of Dazaifu (local government office in the Kyushu region).</e>
<cmt>「太政官」は機関の名前なので、membersを加えました。後の説明でdaijokanの読みを採用しているので、統一のためこの読みに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shikiden were rice fields provided to the government officials who were the members of Daijokan (Grand Council of State) and held the ranks of Dainagon (chief councilor of the state) or higher and to Gunji (local magistrates), and kugaiden were rice fields provided to Kokushi (provincial governors) and officials of Dazaifu (local government office in the Kyushu region).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>唐令では、職田（職分田）は官職を有する官人へ支給され、公廨田は官庁の収入源として規定されたのに対し、日本の大宝令では、両者とも官人を対象としたものであり、両者間の本質的な差異はなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under Torei (codes in the Tang era), shikiden (or shikibunden) were provided to government officials that held government posts and kogaiden were income source for government institutions, while under the Taiho code, both were provided to government officials and there were no fundamental difference between the two.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under Torei (codes in the Tang era), shikiden (or shikibunden) were provided to the government officials who held governmental posts and kugaiden were a source of revenue for governmental institutions, while under the Taiho code, both were provided to government officials and there were no fundamental difference between the two.</e>
<cmt>スペルミスあり、修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under Torei (codes in the Tang era), shikiden (or shikibunden) were provided to the government officials who held governmental posts and kugaiden were a source of revenue for governmental institutions, while under the Taiho code, both were provided to government officials and there were no fundamental difference between the two.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>職田・公廨田ともに租庸調が免除された不輸租田であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both shikiden and kogaiden were fuyosoden (tax free rice fields) and were exempt from soyocho (taxes in kind or service).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both shikiden and kugaiden were fuyusoden (tax free rice fields) and were exempt from soyocho (taxes in kind or service).</e>
<cmt>スペルミスあり、修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both shikiden and kugaiden were fuyusoden (tax free rice fields) and were exempt from soyocho (taxes in kind or service).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>なお、大宝令以前の職田・公廨田についてはよく判っていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is not enough information on shikiden and kogaiden before the Taiho code.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is not enough information on shikiden and kugaiden before the Taiho code.</e>
<cmt>スペルミスあり、修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is not enough information on shikiden and kugaiden before the Taiho code.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>先行する近江令・飛鳥浄御原令に何らかの規定があった可能性はあるが、両者とも現存しないため、詳細は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a possibility that there were provisions under Omi-Ryo (Omi administrative code) or Asukakiyomihararyo (the legal code of Japanese ancient state) that preceded the Taiho code but since neither exists in print, details are unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a possibility that there were provisions under Omi-Ryo (Omi administrative code) or Asukakiyomihararyo (the legal code of Japanese ancient state) that preceded the Taiho code but since neither exists in print, details are unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a possibility that there were provisions under Omi-Ryo (Omi administrative code) or Asukakiyomihararyo (the legal code of Japanese ancient state) that preceded the Taiho code but since neither exists in print, details are unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>757年に施行された養老律令（養老令）は、職田・公廨田を一本化して、職分田と規定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoro Ritsuryo code (Yoro code) enforced in 757 integrated shikiden and kogaiden into one and established it as shikibunden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yoro ritsuryo code (Yoro code) enacted in 757 integrated shikiden and kugaiden into one and established it as shikibunden.</e>
<cmt>スペルミスあり、修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yoro ritsuryo code (Yoro code) enacted in 757 integrated shikiden and kugaiden into one and established it as shikibunden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>太政官の官人（太政大臣以下、大納言以上）、大宰府官人、地方国司、地方郡司に対して、官職に応じた面積が支給されることに変わりはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The new rule continued to grant rice fields to government officials who were Dajokan (which meant Dajodaijin or lower but Dainagon and or higher), officials of Dazaifu, Kokushi and Gunji according to their government post.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The new rule continued to grant rice fields to the government officials who were the members of Daijokan (which meant Dajodaijin at the highest to Dainagon at the lowest), officials of Dazaifu, Kokushi and Gunji according to their government posts.</e>
<cmt>「太政官」は機関の名前なので、membersを加えました。後の説明でdaijokanの読みを採用しているので、統一のためこの読みに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The new rule continued to grant rice fields to the government officials who were the members of Daijokan (which meant Dajodaijin at the highest to Dainagon at the lowest), officials of Dazaifu, Kokushi and Gunji according to their government posts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>原則として不輸租田とされていたが、郡司への職分田のみ輸租田（田租の対象となる田）とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In principle, such rice fields were fuyusoden but shikibunden provided to Gunjis were yusoden (rice fields subject to rice field tax).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In principle, such rice fields were fuyusoden but shikibunden provided to Gunjis were yusoden (rice fields subject to rice field tax).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In principle, such rice fields were fuyusoden but shikibunden provided to Gunjis were yusoden (rice fields subject to rice field tax).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>郡司への支給面積を見ると、国司と比べて非常に広い面積が支給されていたことが判る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reviewing the size of the fields provided to Gunji, it is clear that they were afforded far larger fields than Kokushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reviewing the size of the fields provided to Gunji, it is clear that they were afforded far larger fields than Kokushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reviewing the size of the fields provided to Gunji, it is clear that they were afforded far larger fields than Kokushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>また、教育を重視する観点から養老令の規定には無い大学寮の諸博士に特に博士職田と称される職分田が支給されていたことが知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is known that in view of the importance placed on education, shikibunden called Hakase-shikiden were provided to various professors in Daigakuryo (Bureau of Education), which was not the case under the Yoro code.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is known that in view of the importance placed on education, shikibunden called Hakase-shikiden were provided to various professors in Daigakuryo (Bureau of Education), which was not the case under the Yoro code.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is known that in view of the importance placed on education, shikibunden called Hakase-shikiden were provided to various professors in Daigakuryo (Bureau of Education), which was not the case under the Yoro code.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>791年には大学博士（明法博士）と明法博士に博士職田の加増が行うが、文章博士・算博士などの他の博士の職田は現状維持とするという内容の太政官符（『類聚三代格』）が出されいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 791, Daijokanpu (an official document of the Daijokan sent to local governments) (&quot;Ruiju sandaikyaku&quot; (statute book written in the Heian Period)) that afforded additional Hakase-shikiden to Daigaku Hakase and Myobo Hakase (Professor of Law) but retained the same distribution for Monjo Hakase (doctor or letters), San Hakase (doctor of numbers) and others was issued.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 791, Daijokanpu (an official document of the Daijokan sent to local governments) (&quot;Ruiju sandaikyaku&quot; [a statute book written in the Heian Period]) that afforded additional Hakase-shikiden to Daigaku Hakase (Professor of Education) and Myobo Hakase (Professor of Law) but retained the same distribution for Monjo Hakase (Professor of Literature and History), San Hakase (Professor of Arithmetic) and other professors was issued.</e>
<cmt>指示書に従い、二重括弧に[]を使用しました。大学博士の大学は、「大学寮:式部省に属して中央官庁の官吏養成に関する教育と事務を管掌した機関」（デジタル大辞泉）とあるので、大学博士はProfessor of Educationとしておきました。他、文章博士はProfessor of Literature and History、算博士はProfessor of Arithmeticとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 791, Daijokanpu (an official document of the Daijokan sent to local governments) (&quot;Ruiju sandaikyaku&quot; [a statute book written in the Heian Period]) that afforded additional Hakase-shikiden to Daigaku Hakase (Professor of Education) and Myobo Hakase (Professor of Law) but retained the same distribution for Monjo Hakase (Professor of Literature and History), San Hakase (Professor of Arithmetic) and other professors was issued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>具体的な始期は不明であるが、その以前から博士職田の支給が行われていた事が判明している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although details are not clear, this shows that Hakase-shikiden were provided before that time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although details are not clear, this shows that Hakase-shikiden had been provided before that time.</e>
<cmt>時制を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although details are not clear, this shows that Hakase-shikiden had been provided before that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="19">
<j>律令制が弛緩する9・10世紀になると、大宰府官人、国司、郡司らは職分田を原資の一つとして、富の蓄積を行っていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the 9th to 10th century, when the Ritsuryo system had become laxed, government officials of Dazaifu, Kokushi, Gunshi and others used shikibunden as principal to accumulate wealth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the 9th to 10th century the Ritsuryo system had become lax, and the officials of Dazaifu, Kokushi, Gunshi and others started to use shikibunden as principal to accumulate wealth.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the 9th to 10th century the Ritsuryo system had become lax, and the officials of Dazaifu, Kokushi, Gunshi and others started to use shikibunden as principal to accumulate wealth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>これにより彼らの中には富豪と呼ばれる者も出現し、農業経営に特化して経済力をつけた田堵（たと）へ成長していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This resulted in some of them becoming millionaires, some of whom went on to become Tato (cultivators) who were those that specialized in farm management and acquired economic power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, some of them became millionaires and some went on to become Tato (cultivators), who specialized in farm management and acquired economic power.</e>
<cmt>削除できる部分を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, some of them became millionaires and some went on to become Tato (cultivators), who specialized in farm management and acquired economic power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Shimoxx(id:9332), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>