<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>攘夷論</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Theory of &apos;Expel the barbarians&apos; (Joi Ron)</e>
<cmt>http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110004709854</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Theory of &apos;expelling the barbarians&apos; (Joi Ron)</e>
<cmt>Expel をexpellingに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Theory of &apos;expelling the barbarians&apos; (Joi Ron)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>攘夷論（じょういろん）は、日本に於いては、江戸時代末期に広まった考えで、夷人（外国人）をしりぞける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The theory of &apos;Expel the barbarians&apos; (Joi ron) was a view that prevailed in Japan during the end of the Edo period and aims to expel foreigners from Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The theory of &apos;expelling the barbarians&apos; (Joi ron) was a view that prevailed in Japan during the end of the Edo period and aims to expel foreigners from Japan.</e>
<cmt>Expel をexpellingに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The theory of &apos;expelling the barbarians&apos; (Joi ron) was a view that prevailed in Japan during the end of the Edo period and aims to expel foreigners from Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>つまり外国人を実力行使で排斥しようという思想。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, the theory supported the expulsion of foreigners from Japan by force.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, the theory supported the expulsion of foreigners from Japan by force.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, the theory supported the expulsion of foreigners from Japan by force.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>元は中国の春秋時代の言葉。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was originally a word used during the Chunqiu era of China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was originally a word used during the Chunqiu era of China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was originally a word used during the Chunqiu era of China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>帝国主義の発想を持つ欧米のアジアへの接近（侵略・進出・植民地化）により、それまでの江戸の天下泰平の世の中（鎖国体制下の社会）を維持したいという発想として盛り上がった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the time of imperialism when Europe and America came in close contact with Asia (invasion, expansion, and colonization), Japan was in the Edo period when it preferred to maintain the peaceful state of society (sakoku society, where foreigners were not allowed to enter the nation).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the time of imperialism when Europe and America came in close contact with Asia (invasion, expansion, and colonization), Japan was in the Edo period when it preferred to maintain the peaceful state of society (sakoku society, where foreigners were not allowed to enter the nation).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This theory was made widely known during the Edo period of Japan so as to maintain its society&apos;s peaceful state (sakoku society, where foreigners were not allowed to enter the nation) as a way to avoid the imperialism of Europe and America, who were, in those days, approaching Asia for the purpose of invasion, expansion, and colonization.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>元々は朱子学を重んじた水戸学から発して全国に尊皇攘夷思想として広まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This theory was originally developed by Mitogaku (the scholarship and academic traditions that arose in the Mito Domain) that highly valued Shushigaku (Neo-Confucianism) and spread nationwide as the thought of Sonno Joi (&apos;Revere the Emperor and expel the barbarians&apos;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This theory was originally developed by Mitogaku (the scholarship and academic traditions that arose in the Mito Domain) that highly valued Shushigaku (Neo-Confucianism) and spread nationwide as the thought of Sonno Joi (&apos;Revere the Emperor and expel the barbarians&apos;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This theory was originally developed by Mitogaku (the scholarship and academic traditions that arose in the Mito Domain) that highly valued Shushigaku (Neo-Confucianism) and spread nationwide as the thought of Sonno Joi (&apos;Revere the Emperor and expel the barbarians&apos;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>だが、それが勤皇思想と結んだ結果において倒幕と言うエネルギーに一転した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, at time when this theory was related to the pro-Imperial thought, it led people to shift to the movement to overthrow the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, at time when this theory was related to the pro-Imperial thought, it led people to shift to the movement to overthrow the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, at time when this theory was related to the pro-Imperial thought, it led people to shift to the movement to overthrow the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>これは一種のすり替えであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it was a kind of manipulative shift of attention.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it was a kind of manipulative shift of attention.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it was a kind of manipulative shift of attention.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>開港以後は、国学 (学問)の発展によって強化されつつあった日本は神国であるというナショナリズムの発想である尊皇論と結びつき、尊皇攘夷論となって諸藩の志士や公卿によって支持された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the opening of the port, the theory of Joi was related to the Sonno ron (theory of &apos;Revere the Emperor&apos;), which was becoming prevalent due to the development of kokugaku (the study of Japanese literature and culture) and was transformed into Sonno joi ron (the theory of Sonno joi); the Sonno ron believed that Japan was the country of god and became origin of the thought of nationalism, and was supported by patriots of various domains and kugyo (court nobles).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the opening of the port, the theory of Joi was related to the Sonno ron (theory of &apos;Revere the Emperor&apos;), which was becoming prevalent due to the development of kokugaku (the study of Japanese literature and culture) and was transformed into Sonno joi ron (the theory of Sonno joi); the Sonno ron believed that Japan was the country of god and became origin of the thought of nationalism, and was supported by patriots of various domains and kugyo (court nobles).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the opening of the port, the theory of Joi was related to the Sonno ron (theory of &apos;Revere the Emperor&apos;), which was becoming prevalent due to the development of kokugaku (the study of Japanese literature and culture) and was transformed into Sonno joi ron (the theory of Sonno joi); the Sonno ron believed that Japan was the country of god and became origin of the thought of nationalism, and was supported by patriots of various domains and kugyo (court nobles).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>しかし薩英戦争や下関戦争において外国艦隊との力の差に直面したことにより、単純な攘夷論に対する批判が生じて、津和野藩の国学者大国隆正らによって唱えられた国内統一を優先して、外国との交易によって富国強兵を図ってでも、諸外国と対等に対峙する力をつけるべきだとする「大攘夷」論が登場した事によって、これを受け入れた攘夷運動の主力であった長州藩・薩摩藩の主張も事実上開国へと転向していくのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as Japan faced the power difference from the foreign fleets during the Anglo-Satsuma War and Shimonoseki War, criticisms to the simple Joi ron arose and was replaced with Dai joi ron started by Takamoasa OKUNI, a scholar of Japanese classical literature in the Tsuwano Domain; Takamosa claimed that unification of the whole nation should be the first priority and should gain power that the country can confront other nations equally even by aiming fukoku kyohei (fortifying the country, strengthening the military) through trades with foreign countries; The Choshu Domain and Satsuma Domain, the major drive of the joi movement, accepted this view and started directing themselves for the opening of the country to the world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as Japan faced the power difference from the foreign fleets during the Anglo-Satsuma War and Shimonoseki War, criticisms to the simple Joi ron arose and was replaced with Dai joi ron started by Takamasa OKUNI, a scholar of Japanese classical literature in the Tsuwano Domain; Takamasa claimed that unification of the whole nation should be the first priority and should gain power that the country can confront other nations equally even by aiming fukoku kyohei (fortifying the country, strengthening the military) through trades with foreign countries; The Choshu Domain and Satsuma Domain, the major drive of the joi movement, accepted this view and started directing themselves for the opening of the country to the world.</e>
<cmt>Takamasaのミススペルを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as Japan faced the power difference from the foreign fleets during the Anglo-Satsuma War and Shimonoseki War, criticisms to the simple Joi ron arose and was replaced with Dai joi ron started by Takamasa OKUNI, a scholar of Japanese classical literature in the Tsuwano Domain; Takamasa claimed that unification of the whole nation should be the first priority and should gain power that the country can confront other nations equally even by aiming fukoku kyohei (fortifying the country, strengthening the military) through trades with foreign countries; The Choshu Domain and Satsuma Domain, the major drive of the joi movement, accepted this view and started directing themselves for the opening of the country to the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>その後も、一部の人々は攘夷運動を進めようとした（草莽）が、明治2年（1869年）に入ると、明治政府は公議所・上局から上げられた「公議輿論」が攘夷は不可能であるという意見であったことを理由に「開国和親」を国是として以後は攘夷を議題としないことを決定（5月28日）した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after that, some ordinary citizens tried to continue the Joi movement, however, for the reason that Kogisho (the lower house) and Jokyoku (a law-making body) judged that joi (expel of the barbarians) is not possible, the Meiji government employed the national policy &quot;opening the country and establishing friendly relations with other countries&quot; (kaikoku washin) in 1869 and decided not to employ joi as an agenda anymore (May 28); furthermore, together with the peasants, the government decided to treat the ordinary citizens who supported the Joi movement as the people who left their own homeland without permission and punished them by the law of Hitogaeshi (the law that forced to send back peasants to their homelands). (In the fifth item in the Gobo no keiji, five public notices, actual regulation was enacted after 1869). http://www.google.co.jp/search?hl=fr&amp;rlz=1T4HPIE_frCA312CA312&amp;&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=NAF9TLTUO8G78gaOnLyeBg&amp;ved=0CBMQBSgA&amp;q=%E5%85%AC%E8%AD%B0%E8%BC%BF%E8%AB%96+kogi+yoron&amp;spell=1</e>
<cmt>Hitogaeshi: http://www.docoja.com/dico/histxtg55.html kaikoku washin http://edoc.hu-berlin.de/japonica-hu/3/naoaki-hiraishi-167/PDF/naoaki.pdf   公議輿論: http://books.google.co.jp/books?id=pXlZoSjXb2QC&amp;pg=PA399&amp;lpg=PA399&amp;dq=governement+by+public+deliberation%E3%80%80kogiyoron&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=GzVnThp-au&amp;sig=SOiTC67YBusz7Y4tOu2ndUPIH5E&amp;hl=ja&amp;ei=MvaHTI7PO4WClAet_5i7Dw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=3&amp;ved=0CCEQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after that, some ordinary citizens tried to continue the Joi movement; however, for the reason that Kogisho (the lower house) and Jokyoku (a law-making body) judged that joi (expelling of the barbarians) is not possible, the Meiji government employed the national policy &quot;opening the country and establishing friendly relations with other countries&quot; (kaikoku washin) in 1869 and decided not to employ joi as an agenda anymore (May 28); furthermore, together with the peasants, the government decided to treat the ordinary citizens who supported the Joi movement as the people who left their own homeland without permission and punished them by the law of Hitogaeshi (the law that forced to send back peasants to their homelands). (In the fifth item in the Gobo no keiji, five public notices, actual regulation was enacted after 1869).</e>
<cmt>「訳漏れ」…から上げられた「公議輿論」が抜けています。howeverの前のコンマをセミコロンに変更しました。expelをexpellingに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after that, some ordinary citizens tried to continue the Joi movement; however, because the kogi-yoron (public deliberation) issued by the Kogisho (the lower house) and the Jokyoku (a law-making body) expressed the judgment that joi (the expelling of the barbarians) was not possible, the Meiji government adopted a national policy of &quot;opening the country up and establishing friendly relations with other countries&quot; (kaikoku washin) in 1869 and decided not to employ joi as part of their agenda anymore (May 28).</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また草莽に対しても出稼ぎの農民とともに勝手に本国より離れたものとして人返しの対象にすることを決定した（五榜の掲示の第5札、実際の取締規定は明治2年以後である）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, together with the peasants, the government decided to treat the ordinary citizens who had supported the Joi movement as people who had left their homeland without permission, punishing them under the law of Hitogaeshi (a law that forced peasants to return to their homelands) (According to the fifth item in the Gobo no keiji (five public notices), the actual regulation was enacted after 1869).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>だが、復古的な攘夷論がこれによって一掃されたわけではなく、大楽源太郎の反乱計画や二卿事件、久留米藩難など明治政府を倒して攘夷を断行しようとする事件が暫くの間継続されることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the revival of the joi ron did not completely disappear; some incidents that tried to decline the Meiji government and force the Joi movement, such as Gentaro DAIRAKU&apos;s rebellion, Nikyo Jiken (The Incidents triggered by two court nobles), and the Kurume Domain continued for a certain period of time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the revival of the joi ron did not completely disappear; some incidents that tried to decline the Meiji government and force the Joi movement, such as Gentaro DAIRAKU&apos;s rebellion, Nikyo Jiken (The Incidents triggered by two court nobles), and the Kurume Domain incident continued for a certain period of time.</e>
<cmt>Kurume Domainの後にincidentを入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the revival of the joi ron did not completely disappear; some incidents that tried to decline the Meiji government and force the Joi movement, such as Gentaro DAIRAKU&apos;s rebellion, Nikyo Jiken (The Incidents triggered by two court nobles), and the Kurume Domain incident continued for a certain period of time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>攘夷運動の代表例</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Examples of the Joi movement (the movement advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Examples of the Joi movement (the movement advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Examples of the Joi movement (the movement advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>下関戦争　長州藩 vs 大英帝国・ フランス・ オランダ・　アメリカ合衆国 連合軍</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shimonoseki War the Choshu Domain vs allied forces of the British Empire, France, Holland, and the USA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shimonoseki War the Choshu Domain vs allied forces of the British Empire, France, Holland, and the USA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shimonoseki War the Choshu Domain vs allied forces of the British Empire, France, Holland, and the USA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>薩英戦争　薩摩藩 vs 英国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Anglo-Satsuma War the Satsuma Domain vs the United Kingdom</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Anglo-Satsuma War the Satsuma Domain vs the United Kingdom</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Anglo-Satsuma War the Satsuma Domain vs the United Kingdom</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Straysheep(id:42448), 悠卯斗(id:46277), らりた(id:1327), Otoshigo(id:80102), MIsogi(id:20599), Taroh(id:63499), 水野白楓(id:22811), 廿粁(id:219234), 花鳥(id:240256), 認定者(id:99098), Shinkansen(id:13703), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>