<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>漏刻博士</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rokoku Hakase (master of clock)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rokoku Hakase (Master of Clock)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rokoku Hakase (Master of Clock)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>漏刻博士（ろうこくはかせ）は、日本律令制において陰陽寮に置かれた博士。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rokoku Hakase was a post appointed by Onmyoryo (a government office that had jurisdiction over calendar preparation, astronomy, divination, etc.) under the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rokoku Hakase was a post appointed by Onmyoryo (a government office that had jurisdiction over calendar preparation, astronomy, divination, etc.) under the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rokoku Hakase was a post appointed by Onmyoryo (a government office that had jurisdiction over calendar preparation, astronomy, divination, etc.) under the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>和訓は「ときつかさ」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese reading of the Chinese characters is &apos;tokitsukasa.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese reading of the Chinese characters is &apos;tokitsukasa.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese reading of the Chinese characters is &apos;tokitsukasa.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>唐名は司辰・契壷司。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tang name is Shishin 契壷司.</e>
<cmt>読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tang name is Shishin 契壷司.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tang name is Shishin 契壷司.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>定員2名で時には権官が置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two officials were appointed to the post, and sometimes one or both were Kenkan (powerful official).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two officials were appointed to the post, and sometimes one or both were Kenkan (powerful officials).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two officials were appointed to the post, and sometimes one or both were Kenkan (powerful officials).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>従七位下相当であるが、五位・六位が任じられた例もある（『職源鈔』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The post was equivalent to Jushichiinoge (Junior Seventh Rank, Lower Grade), but there were examples of Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) or Jurokui (Junior Sixth Rank) being appointed (&quot;Shokugensho&quot; (a history of court officials)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The post was equivalent to Jushichiinoge (Junior Seventh Rank, Lower Grade), but there were examples of Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) or Jurokui (Junior Sixth Rank) being appointed (according to &quot;Shokugensho&quot; (a history of court officials)).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The post was equivalent to Jushichiinoge (Junior Seventh Rank, Lower Grade), but there were examples of Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) or Jurokui (Junior Sixth Rank) being appointed (according to &quot;Shokugensho&quot; (a history of court officials)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>仕丁から選抜された守辰丁（20名）を率いて漏刻を警備するとともに、時刻を計り、定時に守辰丁に命じて陰陽寮内に設置された鐘を撃たせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In charge of 20 Shushincho (workers) selected from forced laborers, the Rokoku Hakase supervised the rokoku (water clock) and at the same time measured the time, and at regular intervals ordered Shushincho to strike a bell installed in the Onmyoryo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In charge of 20 Shushincho (workers) selected from among forced laborers, the Rokoku Hakase supervised the rokoku (water clock) and at the same time measured the time, and at regular intervals ordered Shushincho to strike a bell installed in the Onmyoryo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In charge of 20 Shushincho (workers) selected from among forced laborers, the Rokoku Hakase supervised the rokoku (water clock) and at the same time measured the time, and at regular intervals ordered Shushincho to strike a bell installed in the Onmyoryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>天皇の行幸の際には漏刻博士1名と守辰丁12名が漏刻とともに随従する義務があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During an Imperial visit, one Rokoku Hakase and 12 Shushincho were obliged to join the procession, along with the rokoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During an imperial visit, one Rokoku Hakase and 12 Shushincho were obliged to join the procession, along with the rokoku.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During an imperial visit, one Rokoku Hakase and 12 Shushincho were obliged to join the procession, along with the rokoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>もっとも、漏刻の技術は比較的早くに途絶えたとされ、院政期には賀茂氏・阿倍氏の一員やその推挙する門人のための官職となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is considered that at a relatively early stage the essential skills of the rokoku were no longer needed, and during the Insei period (the period of the government by the retired Emperor), the post became a government post held by members of the Kamo and Abe clans, or followers recommended by them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is considered that at a relatively early stage the essential skills of the rokoku were no longer needed, and during the Insei period (the period of government by the retired Emperor), the post became a government post held by members of the Kamo and Abe clans, or followers recommended by them.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is considered that at a relatively early stage the essential skills of the rokoku were no longer needed, and during the Insei period (the period of government by the retired Emperor), the post became a government post held by members of the Kamo and Abe clans, or followers recommended by them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>菅野季親・菅野季長は漏刻ではなく、年筮の達人として漏刻博士となったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is generally believed that 菅野季親 and 菅野季長were appointed as Rokoku Hakase as a master of nenzei (yearly predications), not rokoku.</e>
<cmt>読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is generally believed that 菅野季親 and 菅野季長were appointed as Rokoku Hakase as a master of nenzei (yearly predications), not rokoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is generally believed that 菅野季親 and 菅野季長were appointed as Rokoku Hakase as a master of nenzei (yearly predications), not rokoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>なお、大宰府・陸奥国（後に出羽国を追加）にも漏刻は設置されたが、博士は置かれずに守辰丁が管理していたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rokoku was also installed in Dazaifu and Mutsu Province (later Dewa Province was added), but Hakase was not appointed and Shushincho seemed to have operated the rokoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rokoku was also installed in the provinces of Dazaifu and Mutsu (later Dewa Province was added), but Hakase was not appointed and Shushincho seemed to have operated the rokoku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rokoku was also installed in the provinces of Dazaifu and Mutsu (later Dewa Province was added), but Hakase was not appointed and Shushincho seemed to have operated the rokoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Straysheep(id:42448), 新アルパカ(id:65850), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>