<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>陸奥守</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mutsu no kami</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mutsu no Kami</e>
<cmt>頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mutsu no Kami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>陸奥守（むつのかみ）は陸奥国の国司の長官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mutsu no kami was the governor of Mutsu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mutsu no kami was the governor of Mutsu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mutsu no kami was the governor of Mutsu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>その官職及び官職にある者をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It meant the post or the one who took the post of it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It meant the post or the one who took the post of it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It meant the post or the one who took the post of it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>行政・司法等、国務一切を総轄する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The job was to control the administration, judiciary and all of the national affairs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The job was to control the administration, judiciary and all of the national affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The job was to control the administration, judiciary and all of the national affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>定員1名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Positions: 1</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The position was limited to one person.</e>
<cmt>原文の内容に沿うよう訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The position was limited to one person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>従五位相当の職。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The grade of the job was equivalent to Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The grade of the job was equivalent to Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The grade of the job was equivalent to Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief History</e>
<cmt>頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>古代・中世</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ancient and the medieval period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ancient and the medieval period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ancient and the medieval period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>陸奥国の国府は現在の宮城県多賀城市にあり、八世紀前半から国司が派遣されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The kokufu (provincial office) of Mutsu Province was in present Tagajo City, Miyagi Prefecture, and governors began to be sent down in the first half of the eighth century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kokufu (provincial office) of Mutsu Province was in present Tagajo City, Miyagi Prefecture, and kokushi (provincial governors) began to be sent down in the first half of the eighth century.</e>
<cmt>国司の表記を修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kokufu (provincial office) of Mutsu Province was in present Tagajo City, Miyagi Prefecture, and kokushi (provincial governors) began to be sent down in the first half of the eighth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>当初は蝦夷対策の重責を担っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first the job assumed the weighty responsibility of taking countermeasure against Ezo (the northerners).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first the job assumed the weighty responsibility of taking countermeasure against Ezo (the northerners).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first the job assumed the weighty responsibility of taking countermeasure against Ezo (the northerners).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>陸奥国は66ヶ国中、日本の北限にあたり（当時は東限と認識されていた）、出羽国と並ぶ辺境の国であると同時に、広大な領域を有する大国でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mutsu Province was the northernmost of 66 provinces in Japan (though it was thought to be the easternmost those days), and was the remote region along with Dewa Province as well as the large country with vast territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mutsu Province was the northernmost of 66 provinces in Japan (though it was thought to be the easternmost in those days), and was the remote region along with Dewa Province as well as the large country with vast territory.</e>
<cmt>those days→in those daysとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mutsu Province was the northernmost of 66 provinces in Japan (though it was thought to be the easternmost in those days), and was the remote region along with Dewa Province as well as the large country with vast territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>陸奥国は、金山や良馬に恵まれる一方、その国司は、朝廷の支配に属さない蝦夷を帰服させ、しばしば離反を繰り返した俘囚を服属させる任務を帯びていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Mutsu Province was a place with good goldmine and breeding of good horses, the governor of it was on a mission of subduing some tribes of Ezo who wouldn&apos;t come under the yoke of the Imperial court, and subsuming other tribes of Ezo who once submitted (Fushu) but often seceded to the Imperial curt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Mutsu Province was a place with good goldmine and breeding of good horses, the governor of it was on a mission of subduing some tribes of Ezo who did not come under the yoke of the Imperial Court, and subsuming other tribes of Ezo who once submitted (Fushu) but often seceded from the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>Imperial court→Imperial Court、wouldn&apos;t→did not、seceded to→seceded fromとし、courtのスペルミス修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Mutsu Province was a place with good goldmine and breeding of good horses, the governor of it was on a mission of subduing some tribes of Ezo who did not come under the yoke of the Imperial Court, and subsuming other tribes of Ezo who once submitted (Fushu) but often seceded from the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>後代まで服属しない蝦夷がいたため、陸奥国の領域は下北半島または津軽地方に及ばなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of some tribes of Ezo who did not submit down to posterity the territory of Mutsu Province didn&apos;t expand to the Shimokita Peninsula or Tsugaru district.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of some tribes of Ezo who did not submit down to posterity, the territory of Mutsu Province did not expand to the Shimokita Peninsula or Tsugaru region.</e>
<cmt>カンマ追加、didn&apos;t→did not、Tsugaru district→Tsugaru regionとし、余分なスペース消去</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of some tribes of Ezo who did not submit down to posterity, the territory of Mutsu Province did not expand to the Shimokita Peninsula or Tsugaru region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>そのため、陸奥国には征夷大将軍や鎮守府将軍が派遣され、平定した地域には陸奥国府と並び鎮守府が置かれ、その長官たる鎮守府将軍は国司と同格とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Seii taishoguns (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) or Chinju-fu shoguns (Commander-in-Chief of the Defense of the North) were dispatched to Mutsu Province and Chinju-fu (army base) was deployed in the subdued area and the Chinju-fu shogun, the chief of it raked with the governor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Seii taishoguns (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) or Chinju-fu shoguns (Commander-in-Chief of the Defense of the North) were dispatched to Mutsu Province and Chinju-fu (army base) was deployed in the subdued area and the Chinju-fu shogun, the chief of it ranked with kokushi.</e>
<cmt>the governor→kokushiとし、rankedのスペルミス修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Seii taishoguns (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) or Chinju-fu shoguns (Commander-in-Chief of the Defense of the North) were dispatched to Mutsu Province and Chinju-fu (army base) was deployed in the subdued area and the Chinju-fu shogun, the chief of it ranked with kokushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>こうして代々の陸奥守には清和源氏や桓武平氏などの軍事貴族が任ぜられることが多く、また陸奥守が鎮守府将軍を兼ねる場合も少なくなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, military aristocrats from Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan) or Kanmu-Heishi (Taira clan) were often assigned as Mutsu no kami successively and they often doubled as Mutsu no kami and Chinju-fu shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, military aristocrats from Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan) or Kanmu-Heishi (Taira clan) were often assigned as Mutsu no kami successively and they often doubled as Mutsu no kami and Chinju-fu shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, military aristocrats from Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan) or Kanmu-Heishi (Taira clan) were often assigned as Mutsu no kami successively and they often doubled as Mutsu no kami and Chinju-fu shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>その好例が河内源氏の棟梁　源頼義とその子、源義家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A good example of this is the case with MINAMOTO no Yoriyoshi, the head of the Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan), and his son MINAMOTO no Yoshiie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A good example of this is the case with MINAMOTO no Yoriyoshi, the head of the Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan), and his son MINAMOTO no Yoshiie.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A good example of this is the case with MINAMOTO no Yoriyoshi, the head of the Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan), and his son MINAMOTO no Yoshiie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>頼義は源氏始祖の源経基以来、父の代まて4代にわたり鎮守府将軍を歴任しており、蝦夷の俘囚長で奥六郡の支配者である安倍氏 (奥州)が国府と対立した際、これを平定するため陸奥守・鎮守府将軍として派遣され、12年の歳月を経て平定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In case of Yoriyoshi, four generations of the Minamoto clan, from the earliest ancestor, MINAMOTO no Tsunemoto to his father, held the post of Chinju-fu shogun, and when the Abe clan (in Oshu, northern Japan), who was the chief of Fushu (subdued Ezo) and the autonomous ruler of Okuroku-gun (six counties in northern Japan), conflicted with Kokufu, Yoriyoshi was also dispatched as Mutsu no kami and Chinju-fu shogun and subdued them in 12 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In case of Yoriyoshi, four generations of the Minamoto clan, from the earliest ancestor, MINAMOTO no Tsunemoto to his father, held the post of Chinju-fu shogun, and when the Abe clan (in Oshu, northern Japan), who was the chief of Fushu (subdued Ezo) and the autonomous ruler of Okuroku-gun (six counties in northern Japan), conflicted with kokufu, Yoriyoshi was also dispatched as Mutsu no kami and Chinju-fu shogun and subdued them in 12 years.</e>
<cmt>表記統一のため、Kokufu→kokufuとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In case of Yoriyoshi, four generations of the Minamoto clan, from the earliest ancestor, MINAMOTO no Tsunemoto to his father, held the post of Chinju-fu shogun, and when the Abe clan (in Oshu, northern Japan), who was the chief of Fushu (subdued Ezo) and the autonomous ruler of Okuroku-gun (six counties in northern Japan), conflicted with kokufu, Yoriyoshi was also dispatched as Mutsu no kami and Chinju-fu shogun and subdued them in 12 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>これを前九年の役という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is called &apos;Zen Kunen no Eki&apos; (Former Nine Years&apos; War).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is called &apos;Zen Kunen no Eki&apos; (Former Nine Years&apos; War).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is called &apos;Zen Kunen no Eki&apos; (Former Nine Years&apos; War).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>その後は、しばらく陸奥は平穏であったが、依然として東北には陸奥国に編入しきれていない蝦夷の領域があり、頼義の遠縁にあたる大和源氏の源頼俊が出羽清原氏の援軍を得て、青森北端までを制圧し、陸奥国府の威光が東北一帯まで及ぶようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that Mutsu was calm for a while but there still remained the area in Ezo which was not annexed to Mutsu Province, so MINAMOTO no Yoritoshi from Yamato-Genji (Minamoto clan), who was remotely related to Yoriyoshi, subdued as far as the northern edge of Aomori with the troops of the Kiyohara clan and the authority of Mutsu kokufu came to range throughout Tohoku area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that Mutsu was calm for a while but there still remained the area in Ezo which was not annexed to Mutsu Province, so MINAMOTO no Yoritoshi from Yamato-Genji (Minamoto clan), who was remotely related to Yoriyoshi, subdued as far as the northern edge of Aomori with the troops of the Kiyohara clan in Dewa Province and the authority of Mutsu kokufu came to range throughout Tohoku area.</e>
<cmt>スペース消去、「出羽」→訳漏れのため訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that Mutsu was calm for a while but there still remained the area in Ezo which was not annexed to Mutsu Province, so MINAMOTO no Yoritoshi from Yamato-Genji (Minamoto clan), who was remotely related to Yoriyoshi, subdued as far as the northern edge of Aomori with the troops of the Kiyohara clan in Dewa Province and the authority of Mutsu kokufu came to range throughout Tohoku area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>この戦いを延久蝦夷合戦という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is called &apos;the Battle against Ezo northerner in the Enkyu era.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is called &apos;the Battle against Ezo northerner in the Enkyu era.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is called &apos;the Battle against Ezo northerner in the Enkyu era.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>その後、頼義の子の源義家も安倍氏の後に奥六郡の支配者となった清原氏の内紛に介入、これを鎮定し、武勲を挙げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Yoriyoshi&apos;s son, MINAMOTO no Yoshiie stepped in an internal strife of the Kiyohara clan, who ruled Okuroku-gun after the Abe clan, suppressed this and performed his deeds of arms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Yoriyoshi&apos;s son, MINAMOTO no Yoshiie stepped in an internal strife of the Kiyohara clan, who ruled Okuroku-gun after the Abe clan, suppressed this and performed his deeds of arms.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Yoriyoshi&apos;s son, MINAMOTO no Yoshiie stepped in an internal strife of the Kiyohara clan, who ruled Okuroku-gun after the Abe clan, suppressed this and performed his deeds of arms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>これを後三年の役という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is called &apos;Gosannen War&apos; (the Later Three Years&apos; War).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is called &apos;Gosannen War&apos; (the Later Three Years&apos; War).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is called &apos;Gosannen War&apos; (the Later Three Years&apos; War).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="20">
<j>後三年の役が平定された後は、奥州藤原氏が奥羽一帯の実質的な支配者となり、陸奥国司は徴税官的側面が強くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Gosannen War was suppressed, the Oshu-Fujiwara clan became the effective ruler of Ou region and the position of the governor of Mutsu Province became more like a revenue agent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Gosannen War was suppressed, the Oshu-Fujiwara clan became the effective ruler of Ou region and the position of kokushi of Mutsu Province became more like a revenue agent.</e>
<cmt>the governor→kokushiとし、余分なスペース消去</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Gosannen War was suppressed, the Oshu-Fujiwara clan became the effective ruler of Ou region and the position of kokushi of Mutsu Province became more like a revenue agent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>三代　藤原秀衡は陸奥守・鎮守府将軍の地位を得たが、敵対心を抱いた頼朝により免官運動がなされ、程なく免官されたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Hidehira, the third head of the Oshu-Fujiwara clan, got the position of Mutsu no kami and Chinju-fu shogun, however, MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, who developed a feeling of hostility toward Hidehira, took actions for Hidehira&apos;s dismissal and soon Hidehira is said to have been dismissed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Hidehira, the third head of the Oshu-Fujiwara clan, got the position of Mutsu no kami and Chinju-fu shogun; however, it is said that MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, who developed a feeling of hostility toward Hidehira, took actions for Hidehira&apos;s dismissal and soon Hidehira was dismissed.</e>
<cmt>, however→; however, it is said that、Hidehira is said to have been dismissed→Hidehira was dismissedとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Hidehira, the third head of the Oshu-Fujiwara clan, got the position of Mutsu no kami and Chinju-fu shogun; however, it is said that MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, who developed a feeling of hostility toward Hidehira, took actions for Hidehira&apos;s dismissal and soon Hidehira was dismissed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="22">
<j>藤原秀衡の死後、奥州藤原氏は源頼朝に討たれ、鎌倉幕府が成立すると、陸奥守は北条氏や安達氏など有力御家人が務める栄職とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After FUJIWARA no Hidehira died, Oshu-Fujiwara was defeated by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo and when Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) was established, Mutsu no kami became the honorable position served by senior vassals such as the Hojo clan or the Adachi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After FUJIWARA no Hidehira died, Oshu-Fujiwara was defeated by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo and when Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) was established, Mutsu no kami became the honorable position served by senior vassals such as the Hojo clan or the Adachi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After FUJIWARA no Hidehira died, Oshu-Fujiwara was defeated by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo and when Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) was established, Mutsu no kami became the honorable position served by senior vassals such as the Hojo clan or the Adachi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="23">
<j>鎌倉幕府滅亡後は、後醍醐天皇の時代には親王任国となっていたため、後の後村上天皇となる義良親王が陸奥国府に入り、北畠顕家が陸奥大介鎮守府大将軍を務め、東北勢を率いて足利尊氏の勢力と大戦を繰り返した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Norinaga, who became the Emperor Gomurakami later, entered Mutsu kokufu, the provincial capital of Mutsu province, which had become shinno ninkoku (the province whose gubernatorial posts were reserved as sinecures for imperial princes) in the time of Emperor Godaigo after the downfall of Kamakura bakufu, and Akiie KITABATAKE, as Mutsu Osuke (Assistant Governor of Mutsu Province) and Chinju-fu daishogun, had mighty battles against the force of Takauji ASHIKAGA leading the force of Tohoku (north) region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Norinaga, who became the Emperor Gomurakami later, entered Mutsu kokufu, the provincial capital of Mutsu Province, which had become shinno ninkoku (the province whose gubernatorial posts were reserved as sinecures for imperial princes) in the time of Emperor Godaigo after the downfall of Kamakura bakufu, and Akiie KITABATAKE, as Mutsu Osuke (Assistant Governor of Mutsu Province) and Chinju-fu daishogun, had mighty battles against the force of Takauji ASHIKAGA leading the force of Tohoku (north) region.</e>
<cmt>provinceの頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Norinaga, who became the Emperor Gomurakami later, entered Mutsu kokufu, the provincial capital of Mutsu Province, which had become shinno ninkoku (the province whose gubernatorial posts were reserved as sinecures for imperial princes) in the time of Emperor Godaigo after the downfall of Kamakura bakufu, and Akiie KITABATAKE, as Mutsu Osuke (Assistant Governor of Mutsu Province) and Chinju-fu daishogun, had mighty battles against the force of Takauji ASHIKAGA leading the force of Tohoku (north) region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="24">
<j>戦国時代には、島津貴久や毛利元就、武田信虎などが任ぜられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Sengoku (civil war) period this position was assigned to Takahisa SHIMAZU, Motonari MORI and Nobutora TAKEDA so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Sengoku period (period of warring states) this position was assigned to Takahisa SHIMAZU, Motonari MORI and Nobutora TAKEDA so on.</e>
<cmt>「戦国時代」の表記を修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Sengoku period (period of warring states) this position was assigned to Takahisa SHIMAZU, Motonari MORI and Nobutora TAKEDA so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>近世</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recent times</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recent times</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recent times</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>伊達政宗以降、武家官位としての陸奥守の職は伊達家当主・仙台藩主に与えられるのが慣例となり、代々伊達氏が世襲し幕末まで続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Masamune DATE it became customary that the position of Mutsu no kami as an official court title for samurai was granted to the family head of the Date family or the load of the Sendai Domain, that is, the position was taken over by the Date clan by heredity till the end of Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Masamune DATE it became customary that the position of Mutsu no kami as an official court title for samurai was granted to the family head of the Date family or the lord of the Sendai Domain, that is, the position was taken over by the Date clan by heredity till the end of Edo period.</e>
<cmt>load→lordに修正、Periodの頭文字を小文字に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Masamune DATE it became customary that the position of Mutsu no kami as an official court title for samurai was granted to the family head of the Date family or the lord of the Sendai Domain, that is, the position was taken over by the Date clan by heredity till the end of Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>一方京都では、これとは別に朝廷によって五位クラスの地下家が陸奥守に任命されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aside from this, another position of Mutsu no kami was assigned to Fifth-ranked Jige-ke (family status of non-noble retainers who were not allowed into the Emperor&apos;s living quarters in the imperial palace) by the Imperial Court in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aside from this, another position of Mutsu no kami was assigned to Fifth-ranked Jige-ke (family status of non-noble retainers who were not allowed into the Emperor&apos;s living quarters in the imperial palace) by the Imperial Court in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aside from this, another position of Mutsu no kami was assigned to Fifth-ranked Jige-ke (family status of non-noble retainers who were not allowed into the Emperor&apos;s living quarters in the imperial palace) by the Imperial Court in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 DCyokohama(id:26779), Shimoxx(id:9332), Kkkdc(id:32227), Hokahoka(id:37244), SSIG33(id:66434), 海衛士(id:19229), Law soma(id:45202), Kamitani(id:30757), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>