<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>解由状</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Geyujo (governmental documents in ancient Japan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Geyujo (government documents in ancient Japan)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Geyujo</e>
<cmt>以下に説明が続くので、英語説明は削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>解由状（げゆじょう）は、古代日本の律令制における、官人交替の際の事務引継ぎ文書である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A geyujo indicates a document that, when an officer in a position was replaced with another person in the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) in ancient Japan, was issued concerning the confirmation of matters necessary for continuing the office duties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A geyujo is a document that, when an officer in a position is replaced with another person under the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) in ancient Japan, was issued confirming the change necessary for continuing office duties.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A geyujo is a document that, when an officer in a position is replaced with another person under the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) in ancient Japan, was issued confirming the change necessary for continuing office duties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>解由（げゆ）ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also called a geyu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also called a geyu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also called a geyu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>平安時代以降、解由状に基づいて行政監査を行う勘解由使が置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Heian period and later, kageyushi who conducted administrative audit based on geyujo was placed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Heian period and later, kageyushi conducted administrative audits based on geyujo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Heian period and later, kageyushi conducted administrative audits based on geyujo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>解由状に関する規定は、根本法令である大宝律令・養老律令には置かれていなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No specification for geyujo was stipulated in the basic laws of Taiho Code and Yoro Code.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No specification for geyujo was stipulated in the basic laws of Taiho Code and Yoro Code.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No specification for geyujo was stipulated in the basic laws of Taiho Code and Yoro Code.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>しかし、ほどなくして、行政の不徹底を防止・監督するため、官人交替のときに前任者と後任者が事務引継ぎを行い、前任の実績に問題がなければ、後任から前任へ事務引継ぎ完了を証明する文書を発給する制度が導入された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, shortly after that, the following system was introduced to supervise administration for making administration conducted more thoroughly: When an officer in a position was replaced with another person, the former officer made a document describing matters necessary for continuing the office duties and handed over them to the new officer, and the new officer issued a certificate showing that he or she accepted a proper document.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, shortly after that, the following system was introduced to supervise administration more thoroughly: When an officer was replaced with another person, the former officer made a document describing matters necessary for continuing office duties and handed it over to the new officer, and the new officer issued a certificate showing that he or she accepted the proper document.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, shortly after that, the following system was introduced to supervise administration more thoroughly: When an officer was replaced with another person, the former officer made a document describing matters necessary for continuing office duties and handed it over to the new officer, and the new officer issued a certificate showing that he or she accepted the proper document.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>この引継ぎ完了の文書が解由状である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The certificate showing the acceptance of such a proper document was a geyujo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The certificate showing the acceptance of such a proper document was a geyujo.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The certificate showing the acceptance of such a proper document was a geyujo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>前任者は、解由状を式部省へ提出して初めて、次の官職に就くことができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only after submitting a geyujo to Shikibu-sho (the Ministry of Ceremonial), the former officer could assume the next official position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only after submitting a geyujo to Shikibu-sho (the Ministry of Ceremonies), is the former officer able to assume the next official position.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only after submitting a geyujo to Shikibu-sho (the Ministry of Ceremonies), is the former officer able to assume the next official position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>もし任務の履行不十分（例：田租徴収の未収納など）により、後任から解由状が発給されない場合は、任務を完全に遂行（例：未納田租の徴収）すれば、解由状が発給されることとなっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The new officer did not issue a geyugo when the predecessor did not complete his duty (for example, land tax had not been collected), and in such a case, a geyujo was issued only after the duty was completed (for example, the necessary land tax had been collected).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The new officer can not issue a geyugo when the predecessor had not yet completed his duty (for example, land tax had not been collected), and in such a case, a geyujo was issued only after the duty was completed (for example, the necessary land tax had been collected).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The new officer can not issue a geyujo when the predecessor had not yet completed his duty (for example, land tax had not been collected), and in such a case, a geyujo was issued only after the duty was completed (for example, the necessary land tax had been collected).</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>解由状の制度の導入時期は明確でないが、天平5年（733年）4月5日、解由制を奨励する詔が発令されている（『続日本紀』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it was not clear when the geyujo system was introduced, a mikotonori (imperial edict) for promoting the geyujo system was issued on May 26, 733 (according to &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan continued)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it was not clear when the geyujo system was introduced, a mikotonori (imperial edict) for promoting the geyujo system was issued on May 26, 733 (according to &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; - Chronicle of Japan continued).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it was not clear when the geyujo system was introduced, a mikotonori (imperial edict) for promoting the geyujo system was issued on May 26, 733 (according to &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; - Chronicle of Japan continued).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>この詔には、天平3年（731年）に解由制の徹底を通達したにも関わらず、後任の到着前に前任国司が帰京したり、後任が解由状を発給しないために前任が次の官職に任命されない、といった状況が発生していたことが記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This mikotonori included the description of the following situations: Although it was instructed to follow the geyu system thoroughly, a former kokushi (provincial governor) at a province returned to Kyoto before his successor arrived at the province, and a former officer at a position could not be appointed to a new position because his successor did not issue a geyujo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This mikotonori included the description of the following situations: Although instructed to follow the geyu system thoroughly, a former kokushi (provincial governor) at a province returned to Kyoto before his successor arrived at the province, and the former officer could not be appointed to the new position because his successor did not issue a geyujo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This mikotonori included the description of the following situations: Although instructed to follow the geyu system thoroughly in 731, a former kokushi (provincial governor) at a province returned to Kyoto before his successor arrived at the province, and the former officer could not be appointed to the new position because his successor did not issue a geyujo.</e>
<cmt>年号補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>そこで、同詔によって、解由状の発行と式部省への提出を再徹底することが通達されたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, this mikotonori was issued for reminding officers that they were responsible for issuing a geyujo and for submitting it to Shikibu-sho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, this mikotonori was issued to remind officers that they were responsible for issuing a geyujo and for submitting it to the Shikibu-sho.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, this mikotonori was issued to remind officers that they were responsible for issuing a geyujo and for submitting it to the Shikibu-sho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>なお、以上のような解由制は、主に国司の事務引継ぎを対象とするものだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The geyu system described above was mostly concerned with kokoshi, or more specifically, handing over a description of matters necessary for continuing the office duties when a new kokushi was appointed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The geyu system described above was mostly concerned with kokoshi, or more specifically, handing over a description of matters necessary for continuing office duties when a new kokushi was appointed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The geyu system described above was mostly concerned with kokushi, or more specifically, handing over a description of matters necessary for continuing office duties when a new kokushi was appointed.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>奈良時代末期から平安時代初期にかけての桓武天皇は、国司の任務遂行の徹底を企図して、延暦元年（782年）、後任が到着して120日経過しても解由状を得られない官司は、厳しい処分を受けることが定められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Kanmu, who was an emperor in the era from towards the end of the Nara period to the early Heian period, attempted to make kokushi perform their duties completely, and regulated in 782 that, if a government officer could not obtain a geyujo even in 120 days after his successor arrived, the officer should be punished severely.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Kanmu, who was an emperor from the end of the Nara period to the early Heian period, attempted to make kokushi perform his duties completely, and regulated in 782 that, if a government officer could not obtain a geyujo even after 120 days from when his successor arrived, the officer should be punished severely.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Kanmu, who was an emperor from the end of the Nara period to the early Heian period, attempted to make kokushi perform his duties completely, and regulated in 782 that, if a government officer could not obtain a geyujo even after 120 days from when his successor arrived, the officer should be punished severely.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>さらに延暦16年（797年）ごろ、解由状の審査に当たる勘解由使が新たに設置された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, the kageyushi position for checking geyujo was introduced in around 797.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the kageyushi position for checking geyujo was introduced in around 797.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the kageyushi position for checking geyujo was introduced in around 797.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>その後、勘解由使は一旦廃止されるが、天長元年（824年）に再設置されると、解由状の制度にも大きな変化が生じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, the kageyushi position was abolished once, but when it was introduced again (in 824), the geyujo system was changed considerably.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, the kageyushi position was once abolished, but when it was introduced again (in 824), the geyujo system was changed considerably.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, the kageyushi position was once abolished, but when it was introduced again (in 824), the geyujo system was changed considerably.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>従前、解由状を必要とするのは国司だけだったが、内官（京都の各官職）も交替の際には解由状の発給が必要となり、勘解由使の監査対象に加えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although formerly a geyujo was necessitated for kokushi alone, naikan (government officials in Kyoto) as well became necessary to have a geyujo issued when they left their positions, and became audited by kageyushi as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although formerly a geyujo was necessitated for kokushi alone, naikan (government officials in Kyoto) as well became necessary to have a geyujo issued when they left their positions, and became audited by kageyushi as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although formerly a geyujo was necessitated for kokushi alone, naikan (government officials in Kyoto) as well became necessary to have a geyujo issued when they left their positions, and became audited by kageyushi as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また、事務引継ぎが不調に終わった場合、解由状の代わりに不与解由状（ふよげゆじょう）を発給することとし、勘解由使の勘判に委ねることが定められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also regulated that, when being unable to accept a description of matters necessary for continuing the office duties, the successor should issue a fuyogeyujo (literally, not giving a geyujo) instead of a geyujo, and the kageyushi should judge the situation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regulations also covered when it was impossible to accept a description of matters necessary for continuing the office duties, in such case, the successor should issue a fuyogeyujo (literally, not giving a geyujo) instead of a geyujo, and the kageyushi should judge the situation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regulations also covered when it was impossible to accept a description of matters necessary for continuing the office duties, in such case, the successor should issue a fuyogeyujo (literally, not giving a geyujo) instead of a geyujo, and the kageyushi should judge the situation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>ところで、平安期当時、前任者が解由状を受理することを受領（ずりょう）といった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way, in the Heian period, the act of a predecessor accepting a geyujo was called &quot;zuryo.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the way, in the Heian period, the act of a predecessor accepting a geyujo was called &quot;zuryo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the way, in the Heian period, the act of a predecessor accepting a geyujo was called &quot;zuryo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>解由状の発給は、赴任地（現地）で行うのが原則だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basically, a geyujo was issued at the site of the office concerned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Basically, a geyujo was issued at the site of the office concerned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Basically, a geyujo was issued at the site of the office concerned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>そのため、遙任ではなく、現地で行政責任を負った国司を受領と呼ぶようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the kokushi who actually lived in his responsible area to control it directly, not the one who lived in Kyoto and controlled his responsible area remotely, became called zuryo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the kokushi who actually lived in his area of responsibility in order to control it directly, not one who lived in Kyoto and remotely controlled responsible area remotely, became called zuryo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the kokushi who actually lived in his area of responsibility in order to control it directly, not one who lived in Kyoto and remotely controlled responsible area remotely, became called zuryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>解由状は、平安前期には有効に機能したと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that geyujo functioned effectively in the first half of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that geyujo functioned effectively during the first half of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that geyujo functioned effectively during the first half of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>しかしながら、平安中期から後期になると、ある官職を特定の家系が相伝する「官司の家職化」が進行していき、内官の解由状は次第に形骸化していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the middle era to the latter half of the Heian period, the trend of an office position monopolized by members of a specific family progressed, making geyujo for naikan ineffective gradually.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the middle to the latter half of the Heian period, the trend of an office position monopolized by members of a specific family progressed, making geyujo for naikan gradually ineffective.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the middle to the latter half of the Heian period, the trend of an office position monopolized by members of a specific family progressed, making geyujo for naikan gradually ineffective.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>さらに、鎌倉時代前期には、受領支配が有名無実化したため、受領の解由状も消滅していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, in the first half of the Kamakura period, control by zuryo became existent in name only and geyujo for zuryo went out of existence as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, in the first half of the Kamakura period, control by zuryo became existent in name only and geyujo for zuryo went out of existence as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, in the first half of the Kamakura period, control by zuryo became existent in name only and geyujo for zuryo went out of existence as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Shimoxx(id:9332), BAKU(id:55205), 水野白楓(id:22811), 怪蘇(id:45514), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>