<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>土一揆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsuchi Uprising (Tsuchi-ikki or Do-ikki)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsuchi Uprising (Tsuchi-ikki or Do-ikki)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuchi Uprising (Tsuchi-ikki or Do-ikki)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>土一揆（つちいっき・どいっき）は、室町時代中期から後期にかけて発生した民衆の政治的要求活動をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsuchi uprising (Tsuchi-ikki or Do-ikki) refers to a political appeal by the masses which occurred from the middle to the late of the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsuchi uprising (Tsuchi-ikki or Do-ikki) refers to a political appeal by the masses which occurred from the middle to the late Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;tsuchi uprising&quot; (called tsuchi-ikki or do-ikki in Japanese) refers to political appeals by the masses which had occurred from the middle to the late Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>室町中期ごろ、商品経済の発達や農業生産の向上、惣結合の強化などに伴い社会情勢が変化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the middle of the Muromachi period, the social situation changed according to development of the commodity economy, improvement of agricultural production, consolidation of So (peasant&apos;s self-governing association), and the like.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the middle of the Muromachi period, the social situation changed according to development of the commodity economy, improvement of agricultural production, consolidation of So (peasant&apos;s self-governing association), and the like.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the middle of the Muromachi period, the social situation changed according to the development of a commodity economy, the improvement of agricultural production, the consolidation of so (peasants&apos; self-governing association), and the like.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>これにより、まず当時の先進地域だった畿内において、民衆が連帯組織＝一揆を形成して、支配者（幕府や守護など）へ政治的な要求を行うようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the wake of the change, at first in the Kinai region (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto) which was an advanced area in those days, the masses formed consolidated organizations (i.e., ikki) to make a political appeal to the ruler (bakufu (feudal government headed by a shogun) or Shugo (provincial constable)).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the wake of the change, first in the Kinai region (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto) which was an advanced area in those days, the masses formed organizations (i.e., ikki) to make a political appeal to their ruler (bakufu - feudal government headed by a shogun, or Shugo - provincial constable).</e>
<cmt>wordiness, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the wake of the change, the masses in the Kinai region (the provinces in the vicinity of the capital which were under direct Imperial rule), which was an advanced area of those days, began to form solidarity organizations (called ikki in Japanese) to make a political appeal to their rulers such as the bakufu (feudal government headed by a shogun) and their shugo (provincial constables).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>これを土一揆という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is called Tsuchi-ikki or Do-ikki (Tsuchi uprising).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was called the Tsuchi-ikki or Do-ikki (Tsuchi uprising).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was called the Tsuchi-ikki or Do-ikki (Tsuchi uprising).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>この頃には、惣村の形成に見られるように、百姓らの自治・連帯意識が非常に高まっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this period, peasants and other commoners began to have intense consciousness of self-governing and solidarity as shown in their formation of Soson (a community consisting of peasant&apos;s self-governing association).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「百姓らの」は「百姓、その他の平民」として訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this period, peasants and other commoners became intensely conscious of self-governing and solidarity, as shown in their formation of Soson (a community consisting of a peasant&apos;s self-governing association).</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this period, the level of awareness of self-governing and solidarity was rapidly raised among peasants and other commoners, as shown in the formation of soson (a community consisting of peasants&apos; self-governing association).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>そうした流れの中で、百姓や地侍、馬借らが広域的に連合する土一揆が発生したと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is now considered that the consciousness caused peasants, jizamurai (local samurai), and bashaku (shipping agents who used horses) to extensively league together and start Tsuchi-ikki.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is now considered that the state of consciousness caused peasants, jizamurai (local samurai), and bashaku (shipping agents who used horses) to extensively come together to start Tsuchi-ikki.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is now considered that the state of consciousness caused peasants, jizamurai (local samurai), and bashaku (shipping agents who used horses) in a wide area to come together to start Tsuchi-ikki.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>土一揆のほとんどは、徳政の実施を要求した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In most cases of Tsuchi-ikki, they appealed for the government to enforce tokusei (the virtuous rule).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In most cases of Tsuchi-ikki, they appealed to the government to enforce tokusei (the virtuous rule).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In most tsuchi-ikki, they appealed to the government to enforce tokusei (which literally means &quot;virtuous rule,&quot; representing cancellations of debts in this case).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>そのため、土一揆を徳政一揆ということもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is why Tsuchi-ikki is sometimes called Tokusei ikki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is why Tsuchi-ikki is sometimes called Tokusei ikki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That is why Tsuchi-ikki is sometimes called Tokusei ikki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>当時、動産・不動産の所有権は、売買などが行われたとしても、本来は元の所有者が保持しているのがあるべき姿だとする観念が存在していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In that period, there was an idea that the right of ownership of movable property and immovable property should be rightfully held by the original owner even if the property had been sold.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In that period, the idea that the right of ownership of movable and immovable properties should be rightfully held by the original owner even if the property had been sold.</e>
<cmt>redundancy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In that period, there was an idea that the right of ownership of movable or immovable property should belong to the original owner of that property even if the property had been sold.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>そして、あるべき姿＝元の所有者へ所有権を戻すことこそ、正しい政治＝徳政であるという思想が広く浸透していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And there was a widely accepted thought: It is the right politics, i.e., tokusei to do what should be done, i.e., returns the right of ownership to the original owner.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And it was widely accepted, the right politics, i.e., for tokusei to do what should be done, i.e., return the right of ownership to the original property owners.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, there was also a widespread idea that returning the right of ownership to the original owner of that property should be realized in the right governance (or tokusei).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>百姓らにとって、そうした徳政を要求することは、当然の権利と認識されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The peasants thought they appeal for the government to enforce tokusei by right.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The peasants thought they could appeal to the government to enforce their right of tokusei.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The peasants thought they could appeal to the government to enforce their right of tokusei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>従って、経済的な困窮が土一揆の主要因だったとは言えない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, poverty is not supposed to have been a primary cause of Tsuchi-ikki.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, poverty is not thought to have been the primary cause of Tsuchi-ikki.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, poverty is not thought to have been the primary cause of Tsuchi-ikki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>天皇や将軍の代替わり時は、徳政を行うべき機会と考えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was considered that it was an occasion for the government to enforce tokusei when the Emperor or the Shogun changes.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was considered an occasion for the government to enforce tokusei when the Emperor or the Shogun changes.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People considered a change of emperors or shogun as a good occasion to enforce tokusei.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>そして、その時には土一揆が発生することが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For that reason, many cases of Tsuchi-ikki broke out at those times.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For that reason, many cases of Tsuchi-ikki arose during such times.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For that reason, many cases of tsuchi-ikki arose at such times.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>次第に土一揆は頻発していき、毎年のように見られるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsuchi-ikki broke out much more frequently thereafter; eventually it occurred every year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsuchi-ikki occurred much more frequently thereafter; eventually it occurred every year.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The frequency of the occurrence of tsuchi-ikki gradually became higher, and eventually it occurred almost every year.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>こうした土一揆の頻発は、幕府権力の弱体化をもたらしていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That frequent occurrence of Tsuchi-ikki undermined the power of the feudal government.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The frequent occurrence of Tsuchi-ikki undermined the power of the feudal government.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The frequent occurrence of tsuchi-ikki undermined the power of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>それでもなお、幕府の対応は鈍かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nevertheless, the government was slow to respond to that situation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nevertheless, the government was slow to respond to the situation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nevertheless, the bakufu was slow to respond to the situation.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>更に実際に鎮圧にあたった守護大名配下の武士の中にも長年の京都滞在に伴い生活が逼迫するものがいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, some of the samurai who were under the command of Shugo daimyo (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable) and actually suppressed the uprisings lived with tight economy due to their lengthened stationing in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, some of the samurai who were under the command of the Shugo daimyo (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable) and actually suppressed the uprisings lived on a tight economy due to their extended stationing in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides, some of the samurai who were under the command of shugo daimyo (Japanese territorial lords as provincial constables) and actually suppressed uprisings fell into financial difficulty due to their longtime stay in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>彼らの多くは、似たような状況下に置かれた農民達に同情的な者も多く、一揆側に寝返る者が現れる始末だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of them were sympathetic to the peasants who were forced to live in the similar conditions, and eventually, some of them even went over to the side of ikki.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of them were sympathetic to the peasants who were forced to live in similar conditions, and eventually, some of them even went over to the side of ikki.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of such samurai were sympathetic to peasants who lived in the similar conditions, and eventually, some of them even went over to the side of ikki.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>そのため幕府が度々諸大名に配下の徹底管理を命じている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The feudal government often ordered the feudal lords to thoroughly supervise the samurai under their command.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The feudal government often ordered the feudal lords to thoroughly supervise the samurai under their command.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bakufu often ordered feudal lords to thoroughly supervise samurai under their command.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>また、応仁の乱直前には都に集結した兵士によって土倉などが荒らされて「私徳政」と称した事件も発生している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Immediately before the Onin War, there was a case occurred in which the warriors who had assembled to the capital robbed doso (or, tokura, tsuchikura; an underground ware house), calling their robbery &quot;Private acts of tokusei, Virtuous Government&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Immediately before the Onin War, samurai warriors assembled in the capital and broke into and robbed the doso (or, tokura, tsuchikura; an underground warehouse), calling their &quot;robbery &quot;Private acts of tokusei, Virtuous Government&quot;.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Immediately before the Onin War, samurai warriors who were assembled in the capital broke into and robbed financial institutions called doso, calling their robberies &apos;shi-tokusei,&apos; which literally means &apos;privately declared tokusei.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>室町幕府は本来、土倉から土倉役、酒屋から酒屋役を徴収していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Muromachi shogunate originally levied the tax for doso (dosoyaku) from doso and the taxes imposed on Sake brewery (Sakaya yaku) from brewery.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Muromachi shogunate originally levied a tax to cover doso (dosoyaku) and taxes imposed on Sake breweries (Sakaya yaku).</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Muromachi bakufu originally collected a tax called doso-yaku from doso and a tax called sakaya-yaku from breweries.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>しかし、徳政令を発布すると、土倉が収益を失うために土倉役を免除しなければならない規定があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was stipulated, however, that the shogunate had to exempt doso from the tax for doso because doso would lose its profits when the government promulgated Tokuseirei (ordering return of land sold and dissolution of debts).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was stipulated, however, that the shogunate had to exempt doso from the tax because it would lose profitability when the government promulgated Tokuseirei (order the return of land sold and the dissolution of debts).</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was stipulated, however, that the bakufu had to exempt doso from doso-yaku because they would lose their profit when the bakufu enforced a tokuseirei (debt cancellation order).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>それで、当初は「徳政禁止」の命令も出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, the government issued a &quot;ban on tokusei &quot;at the begging.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, the government issued a &quot;ban on tokusei. &quot;</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, the bakufu initially issued orders to forbid tokusei.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>だが、一揆はますます増加するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nevertheless, uprisings of ikki kept increasing.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nevertheless, ikki uprisings kept increasing.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nevertheless, the number of ikki uprisings kept increasing.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>果ては幕府自体が財政難を救うためにあえて一揆を黙認して「分一徳政令」（紛争となった債権額の一割を幕府に納付した紛争当事者が自由に処理できるとした徳政令）を出すに至ったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eventually, the government even issued &quot;Buichi Order for the Acts of Virtuous Government&quot; (a tokuseirei that stipulates that a party involved in a conflict and had paid ten percent of the credit amount in dispute to the government can dispose the rest of the credit) by acquiescing ikki in order to be relieved from its own financial pressure.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「自由に処理できる」の主語に「債権額の１割納付した残額」を補い訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eventually, the government even issued a &quot;Buichi Order for the Acts of Virtuous Government&quot; (a tokuseirei that stipulates that a party involved in a conflict who had paid ten percent of the credit amount in dispute to the government can dispose the rest of the credit) by acquiescing ikki in order to be relieved from its own financial pressure.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eventually, the bakufu even issued the &apos;Buichi Tokusei-rei&apos; (Ten Per Cent Debt-relief Edict), in which a party involved in a conflict was allowed to dispose their credit at will if they paid ten percent of the credit amount in dispute to the bakufu, and they acquiesced ikki in order to solve their own financial difficulty.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>このため、土倉や寺院と言った一揆の標的となりそうな者達は自ら自衛のための兵士を雇ってこれを防ぐ他なかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, probable targets of ikki such as doso and temples were forced to hire soldiers for their own protection by themselves.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, probable targets of ikki, like doso and temples, were forced to hire samurai for their own protection.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, probable targets of ikki such as doso and temples had to hire samurai for their own protection.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="28">
<j>1428年の正長の土一揆、1441年の嘉吉の徳政一揆、1454年の享徳の土一揆、1457年の長禄の土一揆、1478年及び1480年の山城土一揆がなどが知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The peasant uprising of Shocho era in 1428, the Tokusei uprising in Kakitsu era in 1441, the peasants&apos; uprising of Kyotoku era in 1454, the peasants&apos; uprising of Choroku era in 1457, and the uprisings in Yamashiro Province in 1478 and 1480 are well-known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The peasant uprising of the Shocho era in 1428, the Tokusei uprising in the Kakitsu era in 1441, the peasants&apos; uprising in the Kyotoku era in 1454, the peasants&apos; uprising of Choroku era in 1457, and the uprisings in Yamashiro Province in 1478 and 1480, are all well-known.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some uprisings are widely known; for example, the peasant uprising of the Shocho era in 1428, the Tokusei uprising of the Kakitsu era in 1441, the peasant uprising of the Kyotoku era in 1454, the peasant uprising of the Choroku era in 1457, the uprising of Yamashiro Province in 1478 and 1480, and so on.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="29">
<j>これに対して国人勢力が中心となって波及したものを国一揆という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrast, the uprising that was mainly affected by the force of kokujin (local samurai) is called the uprising in a province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast, an uprising that was mainly affected by the force of kokujin (local samurai) was called a provincial uprising..</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast, an uprising that was led mainly by a kokujin (local samurai) group was called kuni ikki (provincial uprising).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), Shimoxx(id:9332), Gappei2006(id:69935), Yas(id:739), Ittyon(id:1348), Robert De Smith(id:28533), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>