<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>陣定</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Jin no Sadame (a Heian-era Privy Council)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Jin no Sadame (a Heian-era Privy Council)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jin no Sadame</e>
<cmt>タイトルのため、補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>陣定（じんのさだめ）は、平安時代摂関政治の朝議の形式のひとつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Jin no Sadame was a type of privy council in use by regency governments during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Jin no Sadame was a type of privy council in use by regency governments during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Jin no Sadame was a type of privy council in use by regency governments during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>左右近衛府の陣に公卿の座を設定し、大臣以下の公卿と四位の参議以上の議政官が出席して、政務を討議した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The council, which was limited to those of Kugyo status (the highest echelon of the court nobility), was established at the camp of the Left and Right Divisions of the Inner Palace Guard, and was open only to those Kugyo (noble) of Daijin (Grand Minister) status or lower who were also at least fourth-ranked Sangi (Councillors); at council sessions members would debate government affairs and policies.</e>
<cmt>The original is quite unclear, so I have added a few explanatory comments.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The council, which was limited to those of Kugyo status (the highest echelon of the court nobility), was established at the camp of the Left and Right Divisions of the Inner Palace Guard, and was open only to those Kugyo (noble) of Daijin (Grand Minister) status or lower who were also at least fourth-ranked Sangi (Councillors); at council sessions members would debate government affairs and policies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The council, which was limited to those of Kugyo status (the highest echelon of the court nobility), was established at the camp of the Left and Right Divisions of the Inner Palace Guard, and was open only to those Kugyo (noble) of Daijin (Grand Minister) status or lower and Sangi (Councilors) who held at least the court rank of Shii (Fourth Rank); at council sessions members would debate government affairs and policies.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。一部翻訳を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>近衛府の陣（主として左近衛府側）において招集されたので、会議の場を陣座（じんのざ）又は杖座（じょうざ）と呼称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The council was convened at the camp of the Inner Palace Guard (most often in the area of the Left Division of the Guard), so the council sessions came to be called &quot;Jinnoza&quot; (&quot;meetings at the camp&quot;) or &quot;Joza&quot; (&quot;stave meetings&quot;).</e>
<cmt>I believe it would be best to explain &quot;Joza&quot; also, e.g., &quot;…Joza (&quot;stave meetings&quot;, so named because of the official staffs used by the participants).</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The council was convened at the camp of the Inner Palace Guard (most often in the area of the Left Division of the Guard), so the council sessions came to be called &quot;Jinnoza&quot; (&quot;meetings at the camp&quot;) or &quot;Joza&quot; (&quot;stave meetings&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The council was convened at the camp of the Inner Palace Guard (most often in the area of the Left Division of the Guard), so the council sessions came to be called &quot;Jinnoza&quot; (&quot;meetings at the camp&quot;) or &quot;Joza&quot; (&quot;stave meetings&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>本来は非公式の会合であり、意思決定も統裁合議制に則って行われていたが、次第に実質上の政策決定期間となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally these meetings were informal in nature, and although decisions were made in accordance with the tosai-gogisei (a system under which the role of members was merely to advise the single individual vested with final decision-making power), the Jin no Sadame gradually came to hold substantial sway over government policy-making.</e>
<cmt>There is no satisfactory way to translate &quot;kikan&quot; here, and indeed it seems unnecessary.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally these meetings were informal in nature, and although decisions were made in accordance with the tosai-gogisei (a system under which the role of members was merely to advise the single individual vested with final decision-making power), the Jin no Sadame gradually came to hold substantial sway over government policy-making.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally these meetings were informal in nature, and although decisions were made in accordance with the tosai-gogisei (a system under which the role of members was merely to advise the single individual vested with final decision-making power), the Jin no Sadame gradually became a de facto institution for government policy-making.</e>
<cmt>期間→機関　ではないかと解釈し、左記のようにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>決定は蔵人を通して天皇と摂政または関白に奏聞された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Jin no Sadame made use of Kurodo (Chamberlains) to transmit its decisions to the Emperor and his Sessho (Regent) or Kanpaku (Chief Adviser).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Jin no Sadame made use of Kurodo (Chamberlains) to transmit its decisions to the Emperor and his Sessho (Regent) or Kanpaku (Chief Adviser).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Jin no Sadame made use of Kurodo (Chamberlains) to transmit its decisions to the Emperor and his Sessho (Regent) or Kanpaku (Chief Adviser).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 BAKU(id:55205), Hadrianvs et antinovs(id:187552), 水野白楓(id:22811), Mop(id:12061), 怪蘇(id:45514), 小太刀(id:18154), YAMAARASHI(id:18211), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>