<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>武衛騒動</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buei Sodo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buei Sodo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buei Sodo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>武衛騒動（ぶえいそうどう）とは、寛正6年（1465年）に発生した室町幕府の内紛のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buei Sodo is an internal conflict in the Muromachi shogunate which occurred in 1465.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Buei Sodo was an internal conflict that occurred within the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) in 1465.</e>
<cmt>Reworded to read more naturally and include the correct terminology.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Buei Sodo was an internal conflict that occurred within the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) in 1465.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>将軍家々宰の伊勢貞親は8代将軍足利義政の信任を良いことに、管領家の一つ斯波氏のお家騒動に介入し斯波義敏と斯波義廉の間をとりなして私腹を肥やし、幕政を混乱に陥れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taking advantage of 8th Shogun Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA&apos;s trust on him, the steward of shogun family Sadachika ISE lined his personal purse and caused trouble to the shogunate administration by intervening the internal issue of the Shiba clan (one of Shogun&apos;s Deputies) and by mediating Yoshitoshi SHIBA and Yoshikado SHIBA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taking advantage of the trust placed in him by 8th Shogun Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA&apos;s, shogun family steward Sadachika ISE filled his own pockets and plunged the bakufu into chaos by intervening the internal troubles of the Shiba clan (who served as the Shogun&apos;s Deputies) and by mediating between Yoshitoshi SHIBA and Yoshikado SHIBA.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read professionally and relect meaning of source text.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taking advantage of the trust placed in him by eighth Shogun Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA&apos;s, shogun family steward Sadachika ISE filled his own pockets and plunged the bakufu into chaos by intervening the internal troubles of the Shiba clan among Kanrei families (families in the position of the shogunal deputy) and by mediating between Yoshitoshi SHIBA and Yoshikado SHIBA.</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトし、用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>将軍家々宰の身分でありながら管領家々督に口をはさむ貞親の横暴に激怒した有力者細川勝元と山名宗全は協力して貞親を幕府から追放した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outraged by Yoshimasa&apos;s arrogance, with which he entered the Shogun&apos;s Deputy&apos;s affairs despite his position just as a steward, the magnates Katsumoto HOSOKAWA and Sozen YAMANA got together to banish Yoshimasa from the shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outraged by the arrogance with which Yoshimasa interfered in the Shogun&apos;s Deputy&apos;s affairs despite his position as a mere steward, the leaders Katsumoto HOSOKAWA and Sozen YAMANA came together to banish Yoshimasa from the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read more naturally and use consistent terminology.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Outraged by the arrogance with which Yoshimasa interfered in the Kanrei families&apos; affairs despite his position as a mere steward, the leaders Katsumoto HOSOKAWA and Sozen YAMANA came together to banish Sadachika from the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせ修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>背景に、次期将軍を予定されていた足利義視の排斥問題も絡んでいると伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been told that behind it lies the exclusion of the enticipated next Shogun Yoshimi ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the expulsion of the anticipated successor as shogun, Yoshimi ASHIKAGA, was involved in the events leading up to the dispute.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read more naturally and corrected spelling.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the expulsion of the anticipated successor as shogun, Yoshimi ASHIKAGA, was involved in the events leading up to the dispute.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>のち、勝元と宗全が対立し応仁の乱が勃発すると、貞親は赦免されて復権した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, when Onin war took place due to the conflict between Katsumoto and Sozen, Yoshimasa was pardoned and restored the power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Onin War subsequently broke out due to the conflict between Katsumoto and Sozen, Yoshimasa was pardoned and reinstated..</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read more naturally and use correct terminology.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Onin War subsequently broke out due to the conflict between Katsumoto and Sozen, Sadachika was pardoned and reinstated..</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせ修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mixtures(id:29234), Daranome(id:1429), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), ECLIPSE(id:39342), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>