<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>宮刑</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyukei (castration penalty)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyukei (castration penalty)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyukei (castration penalty)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>宮刑（きゅうけい、castration）は、去勢する刑罰。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyukei (Castration penalty) is a kind of penalty for castrating criminals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyukei (Castration penalty) is a kind of penalty to castrate criminals.</e>
<cmt>toの方が良いかと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyukei (Castration penalty) is a kind of penalty to castrate criminals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>この刑は世界的に実施例があるが、中国におけるものが最も有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The evidences show that this type of penalty existed throughout the globe, while the examples in China are the most well-known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The evidence shows that this type of penalty existed throughout the globe, while the examples in China are the most well-known.</e>
<cmt>evidenceは単数の方が良いと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The evidence shows that this type of penalty existed throughout the globe, while the examples in China are the most well-known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>中国における宮刑</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Castration in China</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Castration in China</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Castration in China</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>中国では腐刑（ふけい）とも呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In China, it was also called &quot;Fukei.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In China, it was also called &quot;Fukei.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In China, it was also called &quot;Fukei.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>主に男性を対象とした刑罰であったが、女性に宮刑を科す場合には、代わりに幽閉して強制労働させたとも言われているが実際に去勢された事例も若干数あったようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This penalty was mostly conducted against male criminals, but it was also applied to female criminals in some cases, sentenced to confinement or forced labour instead; however, it also appears to be true that even female criminals were sterilized in some cases.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This penalty was mostly conducted against male criminals, but it was also applied to female criminals in some cases such as confinement and forced labour instead; however, it also appears to be true that even female criminals were sterilized in some cases.</e>
<cmt>一文にするには長すぎるので、少し削りました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This penalty was mostly conducted against male criminals, but it was also applied to female criminals in some cases such as confinement and forced labour instead; however, it also appears to be true that even female criminals were sterilized in some cases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>宮刑を科された者の多くは、その後宦官となって宮廷に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of the male criminals imposed this penalty later joined the Court as eunuch.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of the male criminals imposed this penalty later joined the Court as eunuchs.</e>
<cmt>male criminalsと言っているので、eunuchは複数です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of the male criminals imposed this penalty later joined the Court as eunuchs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>日本語の俗語で、陰茎または男性器の切断を「羅切」とも言うが、必ずしも宮刑と同義ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japanese slang word, the act of cutting off the penis or genital of a man is called &quot;Rasetsu,&quot; although this act does not necessarily mean the same with the cases of penalty in China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japanese slang word, the act of cutting off the penis or genital of a man is called &quot;Rasetsu,&quot; although this act does not necessarily mean the same with the cases of penalty in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japanese slang word, the act of cutting off the penis or genital of a man is called &quot;Rasetsu,&quot; although this act does not necessarily mean the same with the cases of penalty in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>古代中国では、死刑に次ぐ酷刑として位置付けられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In ancient China, castration penalty was considered as the second most severe penalty next to the death sentence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In ancient China, the castration penalty was considered as the second most severe penalty next to the death sentence.</e>
<cmt>the を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In ancient China, the castration penalty was considered as the second most severe penalty next to the death sentence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>男性には陰茎・睾丸双方を切除する場合と、睾丸のみ切除する場合があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When applied to male criminals, there were the cases of extirpating both penis and testicles, or the case of extirpating testicles only.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When applied to male criminals, there were the cases of extirpating both penis and testicles, or the case of extirpating testicles only.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When applied to male criminals, there were the cases of extirpating both penis and testicles, or the case of extirpating testicles only.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>刑罰として科す場合は前者の場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In cases of conducting castration as a penalty against criminals, the former case was applied more likely.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In cases of conducting castration as a penalty against criminals, the former case was more likely applied.</e>
<cmt>more likelyはapplyの前に来た方が自然だと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In cases of conducting castration as a penalty against criminals, the former case was more likely applied.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>女性には科されなかったとも、生涯幽閉する刑であったとも、実際に膣口を縫い潰したり、卵巣か子宮を切除する場合とがあったとも言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Studies suggest various possibilities regarding the cases of this penalty conducted against female criminals; some suggest that there was no such case of this penalty applied to women; some say this penalty for woman was replaced by the penalty of confinement for life; some mentions about the possible cases that the vagina hole was stitched up, or the ovary or the womb were extracted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Studies suggest various possibilities regarding the cases of this penalty conducted against female criminals; some suggest that there was no such case of this penalty applied to women; some say this penalty for woman was replaced by the penalty of confinement for life; some mentions about the possible cases that the vagina was stitched up, or the ovary or the womb were extracted.</e>
<cmt>Vagina holeはVaginaだけで良いです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Studies suggest various possibilities regarding the use of this penalty against female criminals; some suggest that this penalty was not applied to women; some say this penalty was replaced by the penalty of confinement for life for women; and some mention the possibility that the vagina was stitched up, or the ovaries or womb were extracted.</e>
<cmt>簡潔にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>罪人に対して科されるため、漢代以前には、外性器を切り落とした後も十分な治療もされず、熱した土に首から下を埋めるなどの荒っぽい方法がとられたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since this was the penalty conducted against criminals, they were not treated well after the excision of the genitals, and a rough treatment method was taken by burying them under the heated soil to their neck, which was seen among those castration penalty cases conducted before the Han Dynasty period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since this was the penalty conducted against criminals, they were not treated well after the excision of the genitals, and a rough treatment method was taken by burying them under heated soil to their neck, which was seen among those castration penalty cases conducted before the Han Dynasty period.</e>
<cmt>the heated soilにtheは要らないと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since this was the penalty conducted against criminals, they were not treated well after the excision of the genitals, and a rough treatment method was taken by burying them under heated soil to their neck, which was seen among those castration penalty cases conducted before the Han Dynasty period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>当然死亡率も比較的高かったと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inevitably, the death rate of those criminals received this penalty type could have been high.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inevitably, the death rate of those criminals received this penalty type could have been high.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inevitably, the death rate of those criminals received this penalty type could have been high.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>だが、受刑後に宦官として重用されることが多くなると、後の世には自宮、すなわち自ら性器を切り落として宦官となる人間が増加した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Courts gave important posts to those punished criminals as eunuch to work in the Court, and the number of people who cut off the genital themselves increased in later period in order to become eunuch.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Courts gave important posts to those punished criminals as eunuchs to work in the Court, and the number of people who cut off the genitals by themselves increased in later periods in order to become eunuchs.</e>
<cmt>この場合、eunuchは複数です。themselvesはpossesiveになっていた方がスムーズだと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Courts gave important posts to those punished criminals as eunuchs to work in the Court, and the number of people who cut off the genitals by themselves increased in later periods in order to become eunuchs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>それに伴い、隋代に宮刑は一旦廃止される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seeing this habit becoming popular, the Sui Dynasty abolished this type of penalty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to its popularity, the Sui Dynasty abolished this type of penalty.</e>
<cmt>少しスムーズに書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to its popularity, the Sui Dynasty abolished this type of penalty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>自宮の増加に伴い、完全去勢の方法も洗練されていき、最終的に清代には、死亡率は1%未満になったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Along with the increase in the number of self-extirpated eunuch, the method of the complete removal of the genital parts was invented and refined, decreasing the death rate to less than 1% by the end of the Qing Dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Along with the increase in the number of self-extirpated eunuchs, the method of the complete removal of the genital parts was invented and refined, decreasing the death rate to less than 1% by the end of the Qing Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>この場合eunuchは複数です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Along with the increase in the number of self-extirpated eunuchs, the method of the complete removal of the genital parts was invented and refined, decreasing the death rate to less than 1% by the end of the Qing Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>なお、一旦廃止された宮刑は明代に復活し、政府の高官から塩を作る人夫まで、さまざまな階層の男性がこの刑に処せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once abolished castration penalty was returned in the Ming Dynasty and conducted against the male criminals among wide variety of social classes, from high officials in the government to the labourers of manufacturing salt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once abolished, the penalty of castration was reinstated in the Ming Dynasty and utilized against male criminals among a wide variety of social classes, from high officials in the government to the labourers who produced salt.</e>
<cmt>わかりにくかったので、カンマをいれました。manufactuingでは意味合いが変わってくるので、who produced saltにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once abolished, the penalty of castration was reinstated in the Ming Dynasty and utilized against male criminals among a wide variety of social classes, from high officials in the government to the labourers who produced salt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>性器を切断して生殖能力を奪ってしまえば家系が絶える事になり、先祖に対する供養を人倫の最重要項目に置く儒教においては、宮刑は一種の追放刑として認識されていたとの説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A study mentions that the removal of genital parts to eliminate the virility meant the discontinuation of his family name, which was understood as a total expulsion from his family and severe punishment under the Confucianism valuing the service for the dead as its most important, moral act.</e>
<cmt>原文の意味するところが良くわかりません。「家系が絶たれる」ことが「一種の追放刑」につながっていく理由が説明されていません。「追放刑に処された者は二度と故郷に帰ってくることができず先祖の墓前で直接供養ができない」から、「家系が途絶えると子孫が残らず先祖が供養されない」という宮刑と同等である、というふうに解釈しました。現状では意味が想像上のものになってしまいますので、仕方なく、直訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A study mentions that the removal of genital parts to eliminate the virility meant the discontinuation of his family name, which was understood as a total expulsion from his family and severe punishment under the Confucianism valuing the service for the dead as its most important, moral act.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A study mentions that the removal of genital parts to eliminate the virility meant the discontinuation of his family name, which was understood as a total expulsion from his family and severe punishment under Confucianism, which values the service for the dead as its most important, moral act.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>また、去勢を「腐刑」とも称するのは、その傷口から悪臭を発するからだとする説と、外性器を縛って腐らせる事で去勢する方法があったからだという説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are two possible reasons for the alternative name of the castration penalty, &quot;腐刑&quot; (literally, &quot;rot down penalty&quot;) that the wound of the castrated criminal gave off a bad smell, or there was a method to remove genital parts by tying them to decay themselves by stopping the blood flow.</e>
<cmt>「縛って腐らせる」という内容に「血の流れを止めて」という説明を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are two possible reasons for the alternative name of the castration penalty: &quot;腐刑&quot; (literally, &quot;rot down penalty&quot;) that the wound of the castrated criminal gave off a bad smell, or there was a method to remove genital parts by tying them to decay themselves by stopping the blood flow.</e>
<cmt>二つの理由を記述しているので、最初のpenaltyの後は:にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are two possible reasons for the alternative name of the castration penalty: &quot;腐刑&quot; (literally, &quot;rot down penalty&quot;) that the wound of the castrated criminal gave off a bad smell, or there was a method to remove genital parts by tying them to decay themselves by stopping the blood flow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="19">
<j>宮廷に関係なく、その他朝鮮半島等の地域でも行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outside of the Court, this custom was also conducted in areas such as the Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outside of the Court, this custom was also conducted in areas such as the Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Outside of the Court, this custom was also conducted in areas such as the Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>日本における宮刑</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Castration penalty in Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Castration penalty in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Castration penalty in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>日本における宮刑の法典への記載例としては、「建武式目」の中の宮刑の記述がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an instance of castration penalty described in Japanese code book, &quot;Kenmu Shikimoku.&quot; (&quot;the Rules and Regulations of Kenmu&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an instance of castration penalty described in Japanese code book, &quot;Kenmu Shikimoku&quot; (&quot;the Rules and Regulations of Kenmu&quot;).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドは（）の後です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an instance of castration penalty described in Japanese code book, &quot;Kenmu Shikimoku&quot; (&quot;the Rules and Regulations of Kenmu&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="21">
<j>その方法は、「後太平記」に、男はヘノコを裂き（陰茎や陰嚢を切取る）、女は膣口を縫い潰して塞ぐと記録されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The method of how the penalty was conducted is described in this record that the genital parts (penis or scrotum) of a man were removed, while the vagina hall was stitched up in case of applying this penalty against female criminals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The method of how the penalty was conducted is described in &quot;Go Taiheiki&quot; that the genital parts (penis or scrotum) of a man were removed, while the vagina was stitched up in case of applying this penalty against female criminals.</e>
<cmt>「後太平記」が漏れていました。vaginaにhallは要りません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The method of how the penalty was conducted is described in &quot;Go Taiheiki&quot; that the genital parts (penis or scrotum) of a man were removed, while the vagina was stitched up in case of applying this penalty against female criminals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="22">
<j>実際の執行例としても、土御門天皇の代、1207年（承元元年）に法然の弟子である法本坊行空と安楽坊遵西が、女犯の罪で羅切の刑に処せられたとの、「皇帝紀抄（巻7）」の記録がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The actual incidents were also recorded in &quot;Koutei Kisho, volume. 7&quot; (&quot;Excerpts Imperial Age&quot;) that the pupils of Honen priest, Gyouku and Jyunsai, received the penalty of &quot;Rasetsu&quot; for violating precepts by committing adultery in 1207.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The actual incidents were also recorded in &quot;Kotei Kisho, volume 7&quot; (&quot;Excerpt From the Imperial Age&quot;) that the pupils of Honen priest, Gyouku and Jyunsai, received the penalty of &quot;Rasetsu&quot; for violating precepts by committing adultery in 1207.</e>
<cmt>kouteiはkoteiだと思います。volumeと７の間にピリオドは要りません。Excerp fromの方が自然だと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The actual incidents were also recorded in &quot;Kotei Kisho, volume 7&quot; (&quot;Excerpt From the Imperial Age&quot;) that the pupils of Honen priest, Gyouku and Jyunsai, received the penalty of &quot;Rasetsu&quot; for violating precepts by committing adultery in 1207.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="23">
<j>また、戦争捕虜に対して去勢が行われた例もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, there is also a record regarding this type of penalty conducted against the captives of war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, there is also a record regarding this type of penalty conducted against prisoners of war.</e>
<cmt>戦争捕虜は、POW (prisoners of war) です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, there is also a record regarding this type of penalty conducted against prisoners of war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="24">
<j>本州西部の有力守護大名であった大内義隆が、家臣陶晴賢の謀反によって、1551年（天文 (元号)20年）9月1日、長門大寧寺に攻め滅ぼされたとき、義隆の遺児歓寿丸は、女装して逃げ山中に潜伏したが、翌年捕らえられ、陶晴賢の家臣に男根を切られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a powerful feudal lord of the western Honshu region, Yoshitaka OISHI, was overthrown by the treason of his vassal, Harukata SUE, on September 1, 1551 at Nagato Tainei-ji Temple, the son of Yoshitaka, Kanjyumaru succeeded to escape into the mountains by dressing as a woman, although he was captured next year by the vassal of SUE clan, and was killed on the spot; his penis was cut off and brought to Harutaka as the proof of killing Kanjyumaru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a powerful feudal lord of the western Honshu region, Yoshitaka OISHI, was overthrown by the treason of his vassal, Harukata SUE, on September 1, 1551 at the Nagato Tainei-ji Temple, the son of Yoshitaka, Kanjyumaru succeeded in escaping to the mountains by dressing as a woman, although he was captured the following year by the SUE clan&apos;s vassal, and was killed on the spot; his penis was cut off and brought to Harutaka as the proof of Kanjumaru&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>succeeded in escaping toの方が自然だと思います。By the vassal of SUE clanwby the SUE clan&apos;s vassalに変えました。The proof of Kanjyumaru&apos;s deathの方が自然です。kanjyumaru→kanjumaru</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a powerful feudal lord of the western Honshu region, Yoshitaka OISHI, was overthrown by the treason of his vassal, Harukata SUE, on September 1, 1551 at the Nagato Tainei-ji Temple, the son of Yoshitaka, Kanjyumaru succeeded in escaping to the mountains by dressing as a woman, although he was captured the following year by the SUE clan&apos;s vassal, and was killed on the spot; his penis was cut off and brought to Harutaka as the proof of Kanjumaru&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>山口県の俵山温泉近くにあるその現場には、歓寿丸を哀れんだ村人によって、現在、麻羅観音という神社が造られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the actual spot of the capture of Kanjumaru near Tawarayama Hot Spring in Yamaguchi Prefecture, there is a temple called Mara-kannon Temple built by the villagers who felt sympathy for Kanjumaru.</e>
<cmt>「麻羅観音という神社」とありますが、観音とあることから寺としました。神仏習合で神社なのかもしれませんがそこまでは調べられませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the actual spot of Kanjumaru&apos;s capture near Tawarayama Hot Spring in Yamaguchi Prefecture, there is a temple called Mara-kannon Temple built by the villagers who felt sympathy for Kanjumaru.</e>
<cmt>spot of the capture of Kanjumaruを、spot of Kanjumaru&apos;s captureにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the actual spot of Kanjumaru&apos;s capture near Tawarayama Hot Spring in Yamaguchi Prefecture, there is a temple called Mara-kannon Temple built by the villagers who felt sympathy for Kanjumaru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>現在のアメリカ合衆国における去勢刑</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Castration penalty in the United States today</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Castration penalty in the United States today</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Castration penalty in the United States today</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>アメリカ合衆国の一部の州において、性犯罪者に対して、本人の希望により、あるいは懲役刑との自由選択の形で、去勢刑が行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some states of the United States as of today, castration penalty is conducted for the offenders of sex crime upon request or the selection of penalty type by the criminals, choosing between the castration penalty or the imprisonment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some states within the United States of America today, castration is provided as an alternative to imprisonment and is conducted as a penalty for sex offenders at their request.</e>
<cmt>少しわかりづらかったので、整理しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some states within the United States of America today, castration is provided as an alternative to imprisonment and is conducted as a penalty for sex offenders at their request.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="27">
<j>実施方法は、多くは薬物注射で睾丸を萎縮させる「化学的去勢」といわれる方法を取るが、テキサス州においては、手術による睾丸摘出が実施されており、1997年と2007年の執行例がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The method of the castration is normally the chemical operation by atrophying the testicles with chemical injection, while extraction of testicles in surgical operation was also operated in Texas, in1997 and 2007.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The method of castration is normally a chemical operation by which the testicles atrophied using a chemical injection, while extraction of testicles in surgical operation was also conducted in Texas, in 1997 and 2007.</e>
<cmt>inと1997の間にスペースがありませんでした。文章がわかりづらかったので、整理しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The method of castration is normally a chemical operation by which the testicles atrophied using a chemical injection, while extraction of testicles in surgical operation was also conducted in Texas, in 1997 and 2007.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>宮刑に遭った著名人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A famous persons who received castration penalty</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Famous people who received castration penalty</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Famous people who received castration penalty</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>司馬遷（史記の作者）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shibasen (the writer of &quot;Shi-ki.&quot; (&quot;the history record of the ancient China&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shibasen (the writer of &quot;Shi-ki&quot; [&quot;the history record of the ancient China&quot;])</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shibasen (the writer of &quot;Shi-ki&quot; [the history record of the ancient China])</e>
<cmt>[]内の&quot;&quot;を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>鄭和（捕虜として宮刑を受けたという）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Teiwa (he received the castration penalty as a prisoner of war)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Teiwa (he received the castration penalty as a prisoner of war)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Teiwa (he received the castration penalty as a prisoner of war)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Ligar(id:12623), ٢١٩.١٧٤.١٥٨.٢٢٥(id:83316), Balmung0731(id:99201), Auf(id:633), 水野白楓(id:22811), BuxWV(id:169145), Kamakura(id:472), Tribot(id:186681), Nakaoka7675(id:39645), らりた(id:1327), Mymelo(id:122034), Hissakun(id:51132), SuisuiBot(id:10165), Miya(id:1881), こぶまき(id:38278), Hat shop(id:3993), Emonue(id:11273), せくそろじすと(id:9002), 中二病の端くれ(id:137185), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>