<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>新徴組</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinchogumi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinchogumi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinchogumi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>新徴組（しんちょうぐみ）は、江戸時代後期の文久2年(1862年)に結成された、江戸幕府による警備組織である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinchogumi was a guard organization set up by Edo bakufu (a Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) in 1862 in the late Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinchogumi was a guard organization set up by the Edo bakufu (a Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) in 1862, during the late Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shinchogumi was a security force established by the Edo bakufu (a Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) in 1862, during the late Edo period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>同年2月に江戸で浪士組結成募集が行われ、京都へ上洛した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February of the same year, members of roshi-gumi (an organization of masterless samurai) were recruited in Edo and dispatched to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February of the same year, members of the Roshi-gumi, an organization of masterless samurai, were recruited in Edo and dispatched to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>gp</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February of the same year, members of the Roshi-gumi, an organization of masterless samurais, were recruited in Edo and dispatched to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>samurais　と複数にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>後に清河八郎に率いられて江戸に戻るが、4月に清河が暗殺されると幕府により新徴組として再組織され、主に江戸市中の警戒、海防警備に従事する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, they returned to Edo under the leadership of Hachiro KIYOKAWA, but, when KIYOKAWA was assassinated in April, the roshi-gumi was reorganized by Edo bakufu and assigned to maintain vigilance inside Edo City and its naval defence and guard.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, they returned to Edo under the leadership of Hachiro KIYOKAWA, but when KIYOKAWA was assassinated in April the Roshi-gumi was reorganized by the Edo bakufu and assigned to maintain vigilance inside Edo City and serve as its naval defense and guard.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, they returned to Edo led by Hachiro KIYOKAWA, but after Kiyokawa was assassinated in April, the Roshi-gumi was reorganized as the Shinchogumi by the Edo bakufu, and they maintained vigilance inside Edo City and served as the naval defense and guard.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>屯所は江戸の本所（東京都墨田区）に設置された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were quartered at Honjo in Edo (currently, Sumida Ward, Tokyo.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were quartered at Honjo in Edo (the present-day Sumida Ward, Tokyo).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were quartered at Honjo in Edo (the present-day Sumida Ward, Tokyo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>1864年（元治1）に庄内藩御預かりとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1864, they became in custody of Shonai clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They came under the custody of the Shonai clan in 1864.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They came under the custody of the Shonai clan in 1864.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>大政奉還、王政復古 (日本)により江戸幕府が消滅すると解散。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Edo bakufu ceased to exist by Taisei Hokan (the transfer of power back to the Emperor) and Osei Fukko in Japan (Japanese Restoration of Imperial Rule), they dissolved their organization.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their organization was dissolved when the Edo bakufu ceased to exist by Taisei Hokan (the transfer of power back to the Emperor) and Osei Fukko in Japan (Japanese Restoration of Imperial Rule).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The organization was dissolved when the Edo bakufu ceased to exist by Taisei Hokan (the Return of Political Power to the Emperor) and Osei Fukko (the Restoration of Imperial Rule).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>新選組幹部の沖田総司の義兄、沖田林太郎が組頭を務めているなど、新選組との交流もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They had kept some relationship with Shinsengumi (a group who guarded Kyoto during the end of Tokugawa Shogunate,) since Rintaro OKITA who served as the head of this group was an elder brother in law of Soji OKITA, one of cadres of the Shinsengumi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They had maintained a relationship with the Shinsengumi (a group that guarded Kyoto at the end of the Tokugawa Shogunate), since Rintaro OKITA, who served as the head of this group, was an elder brother-in-law of Soji OKITA, who was among the cadre of the Shinsengumi.</e>
<cmt>gp</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They had a relationship with the Shinsengumi (Tokugawa shogunate police force located in Kyoto), because Rintaro OKITA, who was the headman of this group, was an elder brother-in-law of Soji OKITA, who was one of the senior members of the Shinsengumi.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Osu-mike(id:61051), Reggaeman(id:6214), Tast(id:29478), Ttwo(id:82880), Bellis(id:106036), 土方　誠(id:3651), Maakun(id:16735), Jun Kashiwao(id:156444), 利用者(id:18447), Johncapistrano(id:969), 小太刀(id:18154), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>