<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>青侍</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aosamurai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aosamurai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aosamurai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>青侍（あおさむらい）は、貴族・公家の家政機関に勤仕する侍のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aosamurai was a samurai warrior who serves the nobles and the court nobles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aosamurai were samurai warriors who served nobles and court nobles.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aosamurai were samurai warriors who served domestic governing institution of nobles and court nobles.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>『大鏡』に登場する「なまざむらい」と同義語とされ、『中右記』や『明月記』などの日記類、『今昔物語集』・『古今著聞集』・『平家物語』・『宇治拾遺物語』の物語類などにも登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was considered to be synonym of &apos;Namazamurai&apos; appeared in &quot;Okagami&quot; (Great Mirror; historical tale), and it appeared in diaries such as &quot;Chuyuki&quot; (Diary of a court official) and &quot;Meigetsuki&quot; (Diary of the Full Moon), and stories such as &quot;Konjaku monogatari shu&quot; (Tales of a Time Now Past), &quot;Kokin chosaku shu&quot;, &quot;Heike monogatari&quot; (Tale of the Heike), and &quot;Ujishui monogatari&quot; (Tales of the Uji Collection.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered to be a synonym of &apos;Namazamurai&apos;, which appeared in &quot;Okagami&quot; (Great Mirror; a historical tale), and and in diaries such as &quot;Chuyuki&quot; (Diary of a Court Official) and &quot;Meigetsuki&quot; (Diary of the Full Moon), and stories such as &quot;Konjaku monogatari shu&quot; (Tales of a Time Now Past), &quot;Kokin chosaku shu&quot;, &quot;Heike monogatari&quot; (Tale of the Heike), and &quot;Ujishui monogatari&quot; (Tales of the Uji Collection).</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered to be a synonym of &apos;Namazamurai&apos;, which appeared in &quot;Okagami&quot; (Great Mirror; a historical tale), and in diaries such as &quot;Chuyuki&quot; (The Diary of a Court Official) and &quot;Meigetsuki&quot; (Chronicle of the Bright Moon), and stories such as &quot;Konjaku monogatari shu&quot; (Tales of a Time Now Past), &quot;Kokon chomon ju&quot; (A collection of Tales Heard, Past and Present), &quot;Heike monogatari&quot; (Tale of the Heike), and &quot;Ujishui monogatari&quot; (Tales of the Uji Collection).</e>
<cmt>用語リスト、統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>11世紀の侍階層出現の頃より現れて公家の家政機関に奉仕する役目を担うが、四位・五位へ昇進する諸大夫より下位に置かれて、基本的には六位に置かれていた（稀に五位に昇る者が存在した）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It appeared around the 11th century when the samurai rank system appeared, and it played a role of serving a household institution of the court nobles -- It ranked under shodaibu (the fourth and ffith ranks of nobility), basically placed at the sixth rank (rarely, some rose to the fifth rank.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The position first appeared in around the 11th century when the samurai rank system was created, and it fulfilled the role of serving the household institution of court nobles: it ranked under shodaibu (the fourth and fifth ranks of nobility), mainly placed at the sixth rank (rarely, some rose to the fifth rank).</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The position first appeared in around the 11th century when the samurai rank system was created, and it fulfilled the role of serving the household institution of court nobles, however, it ranked under Shodaibu (aristocracy lower than Kugyo) who would raise to Shii (Fourth Rank) or Goi (Fifth Rank), mainly placed at Rokui (Sixth Rank) (rarely, some rose to Goi).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>六位層は位袍の色が青系の縹であったことから、「青侍」という語が生じたと言われ、また青が持つ“未熟”という意味から年若いあるいは位階の低い侍の意味も有したとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was considered that the word &apos;Aozamurai&apos; originated from the fact that costumes for those at the sixth rank were hanada (medium blue); besides, based on the sense of blue color, &quot;immature&quot;, &apos;Aozamurai&apos; also meant a young or low ranked samurai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is beleived that the word &apos;Aozamurai&apos; originated from the fact that costumes for those at the sixth rank were of hanada (medium blue); besides, based on the connotations of blue, that is to say &quot;immature&quot;, &apos;Aozamurai&apos; also meant a young or low ranking samurai.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that the word &apos;Aozamurai&apos; originated from the fact that costumes for those at Rokui rank were of hanada (medium blue); besides, based on the connotations of blue, that is to say &quot;immature,&quot; &apos;Aozamurai&apos; also meant a young or low ranking samurai.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせ表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="5">
<j>ただし、公家社会において政所及びこれを構成する家司の制度が解体された中世後期に入ると、公家の家臣層も諸大夫と青侍を中心とする家僕に再編成されることになるが、諸大夫を持てない中下層公家では青侍のみで家僕が構成されて公家家政を運営するようになり、青侍と家僕が同義語として扱われる場合もあった（『教言卿記』など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When it turned into the late Medieval period and mandokoro (Administrative Office) and ie no tsukasa (house steward) system that constituted mandokoro were broken in the court, those at the level of vassals of the court nobles were to be rearranged into the retainers mainly including shodaibu and Aozamurai; however, the court nobles at the lower and middle levels who could not have vassals at shodaibu rank had only Aozamurai constituting its vassals and managing their households, whereby Aozamurai and vassals were treated as synonyms in some cases (according to &quot;Noritoki Kyoki&quot; (The Diary of the Noble Noritoki).)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the late Medieval period, with the mandokoro (Administrative Office) and ie no tsukasa (house steward) system that constituted mandokoro being broken up by the court, those of the court nobles at the level of vassals were to be reassigned to retainers, mainly including shodaibu and Aozamurai; however, the court nobles at the lower and middle levels who could not have vassals at shodaibu rank had only Aozamurai constituting their vassals and managing their households, whereas Aozamurai and vassals were treated as synonyms in some cases according to &quot;Noritoki Kyoki&quot; (The Diary of the Noble Noritoki).</e>
<cmt>Word order, word choice, grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the late Medieval period, with the mandokoro (Administrative Office) and Ie no tsukasa (house steward) system that constituted mandokoro being broken up by the court, those of the court nobles at the level of vassals were to be reassigned to retainers, mainly including shodaibu and Aozamurai; however, the court nobles at the lower and middle levels who could not have vassals at shodaibu rank had only Aozamurai constituting their vassals and managing their households, whereas Aozamurai and vassals were treated as synonyms in some cases (according to &quot;Noritoki Kyo ki&quot; [The Diary of Noritoki YAMASHINA]).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせ、表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)には天皇や摂関などが身分が低い者に対して命令を下すための奉書を発給する際にこれを承った弁官などが自己の青侍に命じて奉書を発給させた青侍奉書が存在したことが知られている（『親長卿記』・『宣胤卿記』・『実隆公記』など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was known that, in the Sengoku period (the Age of Warring States), when the Emperor or the Regeant was to issue hosho paper (edict paper) to make a command on low ranked people, benkan (council of state) who received the order commanded his own Aozamurai to issue the hosho paper, which was called Aozamurai hosho (according to diaries &quot;Chikanaga kyoki&quot;, &quot;Nobutane kyoki&quot;, &quot;Sanetaka koki&quot;.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was known that, in the Sengoku Period (the Age of Warring States), when the Emperor or the Regent was to issue hosho paper (edict paper) to make a command regarding low ranked people, the benkan (Council of State) who received the order commanded his own Aozamurai to issue the hosho paper, which was called Aozamurai hosho (according to the diaries &quot;Chikanaga kyoki&quot;, &quot;Nobutane kyoki&quot; and &quot;Sanetaka koki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was known that, in the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States), when the Emperor or Sekkan (regents and advisers) was to issue hosho paper (edict paper) to make a command regarding low ranked people, the benkan (Council of State) who received the order commanded his own Aozamurai to issue the hosho paper, which was called Aozamurai hosho (according to the diaries &quot;Chikanaga Kyo ki&quot; [The Diary of Chikanaga KANROJI], &quot;Nobutane Kyo ki [The Diary of Nobutane NAKANOMIKADO] and &quot;Sanetaka ko ki&quot; [The Diary of Sanetaka SANJONISHI]).</e>
<cmt>用語集、統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>