<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>分国法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bunkokuho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bunkokuho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bunkokuho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>分国法（ぶんこくほう）は、戦国時代 (日本)に戦国大名が領国内を統治するために制定した法律規範である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bunkokuho is a law which was established by warlords in the Sengoku period to govern their domains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bunkokuho is a law established by warlords during the Sengoku period to govern their domains.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bunkokuho is a law established by warlords during the Sengoku period to govern their domains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>分国とは中世における一国単位の知行を指す語であり、知行国に始まる概念であるが、室町時代中期以降に守護大名や国人一揆による一国単位の領国化が進み、分国支配が形成されていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bunkoku is a term for lordship (chigyo) over one county in the middle age and was originated from chigyo-koku, which developed into control of one county by shugo daimyo or kokujin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bunkoku is a term for lordship (chigyo) over one county in the middle ages and was originated from chigyo-koku, which developed into the control of one county by shugo daimyo or kokujin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bunkoku is a term for lordship (chigyo) over one county in the middle ages and was originated from chigyo-koku, which developed into the control of one county by shugo daimyo or kokujin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>そうした分国支配の一環として、領国内の武士・領民を規制するために分国法が定められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As part of control over one county, Bunkokuho was established to control warriors and farmers in its county.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As part of control over one county, Bunkokuho was established to control warriors and farmers within its county.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As part of control over one county, Bunkokuho was established to control warriors and farmers within its county.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>分国法には、先行武家法である御成敗式目および建武式目の影響が見られるが、一方では、自らの分国支配の実情を反映した内容となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bunkokuho was influenced by Goseibai Shikimoku and Kenmu Shikimoku while its contents reflected actual conditions of control over one county.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bunkokuho was influenced by Goseibai Shikimoku and Kenmu Shikimoku while its contents reflected the actual conditions of control over one county.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bunkokuho was influenced by Goseibai Shikimoku and Kenmu Shikimoku while its contents reflected the actual conditions of control over one county.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>分国法が規定する主な事項には、領民支配、家臣統制、寺社支配、所領相論、軍役、などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main items Bunkokuho regulated were control over farmers, discipline for retainers, control over temples and shrines, lawsuits on lands, military service and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Main items that Bunkokuho regulated were control over farmers, discipline for retainers, control over temples and shrines, lawsuits about land, military service, and so on.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Main items that Bunkokuho regulated were control over farmers, discipline for retainers, control over temples and shrines, lawsuits about land, military service, and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), NoriBeat(id:2074), MMH(id:31208), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Shimoxx(id:9332), Tomika(id:43050), Suisui(id:69), Krex38(id:44492), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>