<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>石核石器</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Core stone tools</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Core stone tools</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Core stone tools</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>石核石器（せっかくせっき）とは、原石（母岩）から剥片をはがし取ったあとにのこった石核と呼ばれる芯材からつくった石器。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Core stone tools were made from the core part of the stone (known as core), which appears after flakes have been removed from ore (country rock).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Core stone tools are made from the core part of the stone (known as stone core), which appears after flakes have been removed from ore (country rock).</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Core stone tools are made from the core part of the stone (known as stone core), which appears after flakes have been removed from ore (country rock).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>打製石器としては打製石斧、砥石などの各一部があるのみで、磨製石器としては、石棒、石剣、石刀、青竜刀形石器、御物石器、装飾石器、石冠、岩偶、玉類など各種の祭祀具や調理加工に用いた石皿、凹石（一部）、磨石（一部）などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for chipped stone tools, only some parts of chipped stone axes and grinding stones have been discovered, and as for ground stoneware, various tools for religious service have been discovered, including stone rods, stone daggers, stone swords, stone tools in the shape of Chinese broadswords, gyobutsu (Imperial treasures) made from stone, decorative stoneware, stone crowns, stone figures and beads, as well as cooking tools like stone plates, concave stones (partial) and mill stones (partial).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for chipped stone tools, only some parts of chipped stone axes and grinding stones have been discovered, and as for ground stone tools, various tools for religious service have been discovered, including stone rods, stone daggers, stone swords, stone tools in the shape of Chinese broadswords, gyobutsu (Imperial treasures) made from stone, decorative stoneware, stone crowns, stone figures and beads, as well as cooking tools like stone plates, concave stones (partial) and mill stones (partial).</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for chipped stone tools, only some parts of chipped stone axes and grinding stones have been discovered, and as for ground stone tools, various tools for religious service have been discovered, including stone rods, stone daggers, stone swords, stone tools in the shape of Chinese broadswords, gyobutsu (Imperial treasures) made from stone, decorative stoneware, stone crowns, stone figures and beads, as well as cooking tools like stone plates, concave stones (partial) and mill stones (partial).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), Greenland4(id:114494), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>