<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>明保野亭事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akebonotei Jiken (Akebonotei Incident)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akebonotei Jiken (Akebonotei Incident)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akebonotei Jiken (Akebonotei Incident)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>明保野亭事件（あけぼのていじけん）は、幕末の京都において発生した、長州系浪士捕縛活動においての誤報に起因する土佐藩士傷害・切腹と、それに伴う会津藩士自刃事件である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akebonotei Jiken, which occurred in Kyoto at the end of Edo period, was an incident of wounding and forcing a retainer of Tosa domain along with committing suicide of a retainer of Aizu domain with his sword, resulted from wrong information in an operation of arresting lordless samurai of Choshu domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akebonotei Jiken, which occurred in Kyoto at the end of the Edo period, was an incident where a retainer of the Tosa domain was wounded and committed suicide, together with a retainer of the Aizu domain who also committed suicide with his own sword, which resulted from mis-information during an operation to arrest masterless samurai from the Choshu domain.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akebonotei Jiken, which occurred in Kyoto at the end of the Edo period, was an incident where a retainer of the Tosa clan was wounded and committed suicide, together with a retainer of the Aizu clan who also committed suicide with his own sword, which resulted from mis-information during an operation to arrest masterless samurai from the Choshu clan.</e>
<cmt>domain→clan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経緯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Details</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Details</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Details</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>1864年6月10日 (旧暦)（1864年7月13日）に、幕府の命により池田屋事件の残党の捕縛を命じられた新選組が、同日に東山区の料亭・明保野（あけぼの、曙とも）に長州系浪士が潜伏するとの情報を得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 13, 1864, Shinsengumi received an order from the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) to arrest the remnants of those at the Ikedaya Incident, and on the same day, Shinsengumi got information that lordless samurai of Choshu domain were hidden in the restaurant Akebono (which was written 明保野, あけぼの, or 曙) in Higashiyama Ward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 13, 1864, Shinsengumi received an order from the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) to arrest the remnants of those at the Ikedaya Incident, and on the same day, Shinsengumi received information that masterless samurai of Choshu domain were hidden in the restaurant Akebono (which was written 明保野, あけぼの, or 曙) in Higashiyama Ward.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 13, 1864, Shinsengumi (a group who guarded Kyoto during the end of Tokugawa Shogunate) received an order from the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) to arrest the remnants of those at the Ikedaya Incident, and on the same day, Shinsengumi received information that masterless samurai of Choshu clan were hidden in the restaurant Akebono (which was written 明保野 or 曙) in Higashiyama Ward.</e>
<cmt>新撰組の説明補足あけぼの→削除domain→clan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>武田観柳斎率いる新選組隊士15名と、前日より応援として派遣されていた会津藩士20名のうち5名が共に捕縛に向かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fifteen members of Shinsengumi led by Kanryusai TAKEDA and five out of twenty retainers of Aizu domain who had been dispatched the day before for supporting Shinsengumi went to arrest the lordless samurai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fifteen members of Shinsengumi led by Kanryusai TAKEDA and five out of twenty retainers of Aizu domain who had been dispatched the day before for supporting Shinsengumi went to arrest the masterless samurai.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fifteen members of Shinsengumi led by Kanryusai TAKEDA and five out of twenty retainers of Aizu clan who had been dispatched the day before for supporting Shinsengumi went to arrest the masterless samurai.</e>
<cmt>domain→clan数字が文の最初に来ているので、スペルアウトし、他の数字も統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>現場で会津藩家中の柴司が、座敷にいた武士を制止しようとしたところ相手が逃げ出したため、取り押えようと追跡のうえ槍で傷を負わせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the scene, when Tsukasa SHIBA, a retainer of Aizu domain, tried to control samurai in a guest room, the samurai escaped there, which prompted SHIBA to pursue and wound the samurai with the spear in an effort to catch the samurai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When at the scene, Tsukasa SHIBA, a retainer of Aizu domain, tried to control the samurai in a guest room, the samurai escaped, which prompted SHIBA to pursue and wound the samurai with a spear in an effort to catch the samurai.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When at the scene, Tsukasa SHIBA, a retainer of Aizu clan, tried to control the samurai in a guest room, the samurai escaped, which prompted SHIBA to pursue and wound the samurai with a spear in an effort to catch the samurai.</e>
<cmt>domain→clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>直後に相手が浪士ではなく土佐藩士麻田時太郎（時次郎、とする説もある）と判明したため、その場で解放した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soon after, the samurai was found Tokitaro ASADA (Tokijiro, in another opinion), a retainer of Tosa domain, and not the lordless samurai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon after, the samurai was found to be Tokitaro ASADA (Tokijiro, in another opinion), a retainer of Tosa domain, and not a masterless samurai.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon after, the samurai was found to be Tokitaro ASADA (Tokijiro, in another opinion), a retainer of Tosa clan, and not a masterless samurai; therefore, he was released on the spot.</e>
<cmt>domain→clan「その場で解放した」追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>当初、柴の行為に問題無しとして念のため会津藩から医師と謝罪の使者を送り、これに対し土佐藩側も最初に名乗らなかった麻田にも落ち度があると理解を示していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, SHIBA&apos;s action was passed and the Aizu clan dispatch a doctor and a messenger of apologee to Tosa clan, and the Tosa clan responded that by mentioning that ASADA was also blamed for not giving his name at the beginning.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, SHIBA&apos;s action was passed and the Aizu clan dispatched a doctor and a messenger to apologizeto the Tosa clan. The Tosa clan responded by mentioning that ASADA was also to blame for not having mentioned his name in the beginning.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, Shiba&apos;s action was passed and the Aizu clan dispatched a doctor and a messenger to apologize to the Tosa clan; the Tosa clan responded by mentioning that Asada was also to blame for not having mentioned his name in the beginning.</e>
<cmt>SHIBA→ShibaASADA→AsadaNCが２文に分けているのを繋げました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし、翌6月11日 (旧暦)に麻田が「士道不覚悟」として藩により切腹させられたことにより、若い土佐藩士たちが「片手落ち」だと激昂し、会津・土佐の関係に亀裂が入りかねない事態へと発展した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 11 (old calendar), however, ASADA was forced to commit Seppuku by the Tosa clan for Shido-fukakugo (disobeying Bushido (the code of the samurai)), which infuriated young retainers of Tosa clan who clamored that the punishment was too &quot;unfair&quot; loudly enough to harm the relationship between the Aizu clan and the Tosa clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「士道不覚悟」の定訳が不明です。また、意味も確証がありませんが、インターネット検索を基にした説明文を括弧内に付しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 11 (old calendar), however, ASADA was forced to commit seppuku by the Tosa clan for Shido-fukakugo (disobeying Bushido (the code of the samurai)), which infuriated young retainers of Tosa clan who clamored that the punishment was &quot;unfair,&quot; their dissent was serious enough to harm the relationship between the Aizu clan and the Tosa clan.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 11 (old calendar), however, ASADA was forced to commit seppuku by the Tosa clan for Shido-fukakugo (disobeying Bushido (the code of the samurai)), which infuriated young retainers of Tosa clan who clamored that the punishment was &apos;unfair,&apos; their dissent was serious enough to harm the relationship between the Aizu clan and the Tosa clan.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>結局6月12日 (旧暦)に柴司が謝罪の意で切腹し、両者の関係悪化は回避された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At last on June 12 (old calendar), Tsukasa SHIBA committed Seppuku for expressing apologee, preventing the relationship between the Aizu clan and the Tosa clan from damaged.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At last on June 12 (old calendar), Tsukasa SHIBA committed seppuku as a gesture of apology, preventing the relationship between the Aizu clan and the Tosa clan from being damaged.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At last on June 12 (old calendar), Tsukasa SHIBA committed seppuku as a gesture of apology, preventing the relationship between the Aizu clan and the Tosa clan from being damaged.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>事件の意味</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meaning of the Incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meaning behind the Incident</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meaning behind the Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>当時、土佐藩は藩主山内容堂のもと公武合体を支持しており、会津藩との関係も良好であったが、内部には土佐勤王党など倒幕を目論む勢力もあり、その中で起きた傷害事件はまさに両藩の関係に水を差すものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those days, under the rule of the lord Yodo YAMAUCHI, the Tosa clan supported kobu-gattai (integration of the imperial court and the shogunate) and kept good relationship with the Aizu clan, but also had such power as Tosa kinnoto (loyalist clique of Tosa) which aimed to overthrow the bakufu; therefore, in that circumstances, the injury incident cast a shadow over the relationship between the two clans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those days, under the rule of the lord Yodo YAMAUCHI, the Tosa clan supported kobu-gattai (integration of the imperial court and the shogunate) and kept a good relationship with the Aizu clan, but also had power as Tosa kinnoto (loyalist clique of Tosa) which aimed to overthrow the bakufu; therefore, under those circumstances, the incident cast a shadow over the relationship between the two clans.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those days, under the rule of the lord Yodo YAMAUCHI, the Tosa clan supported kobu-gattai (integration of the imperial court and the shogunate) and kept a good relationship with the Aizu clan, but also had power as Tosa kinnoto (loyalist clique of Tosa) which aimed to overthrow the bakufu; therefore, under those circumstances, the incident cast a shadow over the relationship between the two clans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>柴司は自らの職務を遂行したのみであったが、自ら犠牲となる事で両者の関係悪化を食い止めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Tsukasa SHIBA merely did his duty, he prevented the relationship between the two clans from damaged at the cost of his life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Tsukasa SHIBA merely did his duty, he prevented the relationship between the two clans from being damaged, despite it costing his life.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Tsukasa SHIBA merely did his duty, he prevented the relationship between the two clans from being damaged, despite it costing his life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>明保野亭について</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About the restaurant Akebonotei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">About the restaurant Akebonotei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">About the restaurant Akebonotei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>この事件の舞台となった明保野亭は当時、他にも多く見られた様に料亭と旅宿を兼ねており、倒幕の志士による密議にも多く利用されていたことが事件の背景にあったと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akebonotei where the incident took place was served as both restaurant and hotel like other restaurants did in those days was also frequently used by the royalists who aimed at overthrowing the bakufu in their closed session, which was in the context of the incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Like other restaurants in tnhose days, Akebonotei served as both restaurant and hotel and was also frequently used by royalists who aimed to overthrow the bakufu in their closed sessions, which was the context of the incident.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Like other restaurants in those days, Akebonotei served as both restaurant and hotel and was also frequently used by royalists who aimed to overthrow the bakufu in their closed sessions, which was the context of the incident.</e>
<cmt>tnhose→thosehotel の後のスペース短縮</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また、土佐の坂本龍馬の常宿の1つと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that Ryoma SAKAMOTO regularly used Akebonotei as inn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that Ryoma SAKAMOTO regularly used Akebonotei as his inn.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that Ryoma SAKAMOTO regularly used Akebonotei as his inn.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>なお、明保野亭は現在も東山区清水三年坂（産寧坂）に石碑と共に店舗が現存するが、当時は現在よりもやや北東位置にあったとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akebonotei is still running businesses with a stone monument by it in Sannen-zaka Slpoe (or Sanei-zaka Slope), Kiyomizu, Higashiyama Ward, which is said that the original sight was in the slightly northeastern place than now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akebonotei still runs businesses, and a stone monument stands by it in Sannen-zaka Slpoe (or Sanei-zaka Slope), Kiyomizu, Higashiyama Ward, which is said to be the original site, however in truth, the original site was located slightly northeast of the current location.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akebonotei still runs businesses, and a stone monument stands by it in Sannen-zaka Slope (or Sannei-zaka Slope), Kiyomizu, Higashiyama Ward, however, the original site is said to be been located slightly northeast of the current location.</e>
<cmt>slpoe→slopeSanei-zaka→Sannei-zaka&quot;which is said to be the original site&quot;という表現は原文にないので削除し、それに従って&quot;in truth&quot;も削除し、&quot;was&quot;を&quot;is said to have been&quot;としましたのでご確認願います。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), 戊辰龍馬(id:10371), Miyuki h(id:84952), Izayohi(id:13095), カリン酒(id:175842), Reggaeman(id:6214), R28Bot(id:177951), Nonomura(id:72557), おきた(id:18906), Maakun(id:16735), Klesha(id:203751), Kagetudo(id:163875), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>