<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>五人組 (日本史)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gonin-gumi (five-household group) (Japanese history)</e>
<cmt>共有用語辞典には&apos;gonin-gumi&apos; としか載っていないのですが、これでは意味不明かと思いますので(five-household group)を補充しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gonin-gumi (five-household group) (Japanese history)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gonin-gumi (five-household group) (Japanese history)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>日本史の五人組（ごにんぐみ）とは、江戸時代に領主の命令により組織された隣保制度。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japanese history, the Gonin-gumi, or five-household group system was a system of the community association organized under the command of the feudal lord.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japanese history, the Gonin-gumi, or the five-household group system, was a system of the community association organized under the command of a feudal lord.</e>
<cmt>・systemは可算名詞ですので、theを付けました。・wasの前には挿入句を閉じるコンマが必要です。・領主は特定されていないため不定冠詞にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japanese history, the Gonin-gumi, or the five-household group system, was a system of the community association organized under the command of a feudal lord.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>武士の間にも軍事目的の五人組が作られたが、百姓・町人のものが一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Gonin-gumi were established among some samurai groups for military purpose, however, mostly the system was applied to peasants, tradesmen and artisans.</e>
<cmt>江戸時代の町人は商人と職人のことなので単語を分割しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Gonin-gumi were established among some samurai groups for military purpose; however, mostly the system was applied to peasants, tradesmen and artisans.</e>
<cmt>howeverは接続詞ではないため、直前のコンマをセミコロンに変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Gonin-gumi were established among some samurai groups for military purpose; however, mostly the system was applied to peasants, tradesmen and artisans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>五人与（ぐみ）・五人組合などとも呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also referred to as 五人与(Gonin-gumi, homonym, five-household party) or &apos;Gonin-kumiai&apos; (five-household union).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also referred to as 五人与(Gonin-gumi, or five-household party) or &apos;Gonin-kumiai&apos; (five-household union).</e>
<cmt>五人与は指しているものは同じなので、homonym(同音異義語)ではないと思います。Homonymを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also referred to as 五人与(Gonin-gumi, or five-household party) or &apos;Gonin-kumiai&apos; (five-household union).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>変遷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>制度の起源は、古代律令制下の五保制（五保の制）といわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This system is considered to have started as the &apos;Goho-sei system,&apos; an administration system in the ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) in ancient times.</e>
<cmt>コンマは統一事項どおりクォーテーションの中に入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This system is considered to have started as the &apos;Goho-sei system,&apos; an administration system in the ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) in ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>時代が流れ、1597年（慶長2年）豊臣秀吉が治安維持のため、下級武士に五人組・庶民に十人組を組織させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, in 1597, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI organized the Gonin-gumi, or five-members groups consisted of lower-ranking samurai, and the jyunin-gumi, or ten-household groups consisted of common people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, in 1597, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI organized the Gonin-gumi, or five-member groups, consisting of lower-ranking samurai, and the jyunin-gumi, or ten-household groups, consisting of common people.</e>
<cmt>・「five-members」は「five-member」が正です。・consistは自動詞なのでconsisting ofに変えました。・groupsの後にはそれぞれ挿入句を閉じるコンマが必要です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, in 1597, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI organized the Gonin-gumi, or five-member groups, consisting of lower-ranking samurai, and the jyunin-gumi, or ten-household groups, consisting of common people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>江戸幕府もキリシタン禁制や浪人取締りのために秀吉の制度を継承した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Edo shogunate also took over this Hideyoshi&apos;s system to crack down Christians and regulate ronin(masterless samurai).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Edo shogunate also took over Hideyoshi&apos;s system to crack down on Christians and regulate ronin (masterless samurai).</e>
<cmt>・crack downは熟語としてonが必要です。・Hideyoshi&apos;sで特定してあるためthisは不要と思われます。・roninの後にスペースがなかったため入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Edo shogunate also took over Hideyoshi&apos;s system to crack down on Christians and regulate ronin (masterless samurai).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>さらに一般的な統治の末端組織として運用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, they operated the system for general administration by terminal organizations.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, they operated the groups as terminal organizations for general administration.</e>
<cmt>「末端組織による統治」ではなく、「五人組などのgroupを末端組織として運用した」ということだと思いますので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, they operated the groups as terminal organizations for general administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>五人組制度は村では惣百姓、町では地主・家持を近隣ごとに五戸前後を一組として編成し、各組に組頭などと呼ばれる代表者を定めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Gonin-gumi system consisted of groups of five members that were landholders in the village, and landlords/house owners in the town, including appointed group leaders called &apos;Kumigashira&apos;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Gonin-gumi system consisted of groups of five members who were landholders in a village, and landlords/house owners in a town, including appointed group leaders called &apos;Kumigashira.&apos;</e>
<cmt>・統一事項に従ってピリオドはクォーテーションマークの中に入れました。・that were landholdersは人についての関係代名詞なのでwho were landholdersに修正しました。・村と町は特定されていないため不定冠詞としました。・villageの後の余分なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Gonin-gumi system consisted of groups of five members who were landholders in a village, and landlords/house owners in a town, including appointed group leaders called &apos;Kumigashira.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>そして名主・庄屋の統率下に組織化したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, the system was organized under the control of the Nanushi/Shoya, the headman of the village.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, the groups were organized under Nanushi/Shoya, the headman of the village.</e>
<cmt>・組織化されたのは制度ではなくgroupsだと思われます。・under一語で「統率下」を表せると思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, the groups were organized under Nanushi/Shoya, the headman of the village.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>これは連帯責任・相互監察・相互扶助の単位であり、領主はこの組織を利用して治安維持・村（町）の中の争議の解決・年貢の確保・法令の伝達周知の徹底をはかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was the unit for collective responsibility, mutual monitoring, and mutual aid, and the feudal lord operated these organizations for law and order, the solution of conflicts in the village (town), collecting land tax, and notification of acts to everyone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the unit for collective responsibility, mutual monitoring, and mutual aid, and the feudal lord operated these organizations for law and order, resolving conflicts in the village (town), collecting land tax, and notifying everyone of acts.</e>
<cmt>意味の明確化とパラレリズムのためにoperated these organizations forの後はing形で統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the unit for collective responsibility, mutual monitoring, and mutual aid, and the feudal lord operated these organizations for law and order, resolving conflicts in the village (town), collecting land tax, and notifying everyone of acts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また町村ごとに遵守する法令と組ごとの人別および各戸当主・村役人の連判を記した五人組帳という帳簿が作成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Every village and town had their own acts to comply, a census register for every group, and a book referred to as &apos;Gonin-gumi cho&apos; sealed by every group leader and the village official.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Every village and town had their own acts to comply with, a census register for every group, and a book referred to as &apos;Gonin-gumi cho&apos; sealed by every group leader and the village official.</e>
<cmt>complyは自動詞のためwithを付けました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Every village and town had their own acts to comply with, a census register for every group, and a book referred to as &apos;Gonin-gumi cho&apos; sealed by every group leader and the village official.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>実態は、逃散したりして潰れた家や実際の住民構成とはかけ離れた内容が五人組帳に記載されていた場合があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Actually, missing family who had run away, or quite different, far from actual family structure were occasionally registered in the Gonin-gumi cho.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In reality, however, some Gonin-gumi cho contained missing families who had run away or family composition that was different from reality.</e>
<cmt>文法的に間違いがあり、意味が通じないため、書き直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In reality, however, some Gonin-gumi cho contained missing families who had run away or family composition that was different from reality.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また年貢滞納をはじめとする村の中の争議は、村請制の下では五人組ではなく村落規模で合議・責任処理されるのが普通であった</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the village, under the murauke system (village-wide, collective responsibility for tax payment), most of the conflicts such as tax delinquency were discussed and handled by the whole village instead of the Gonin-gumi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In villages under the murauke system (village-wide, collective responsibility system for tax payment), most conflicts such as tax delinquency were discussed and handled by the whole village instead of the Gonin-gumi.</e>
<cmt>・村は特定されていないため無冠詞複数形にしました。・conflictも特定されていないため、most conflictsとしました。・村請制の説明はsystemとresponsibilityが同格に扱われていて不自然なためresponsibility systemとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In villages under the murauke system (village-wide, collective responsibility system for tax payment), most conflicts such as tax delinquency were discussed and handled by the whole village instead of the Gonin-gumi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>そのため効果としては疑問がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it was doubtful about the effectiveness of the Gonin-gumi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, there is a doubt about the effectiveness of the Gonin-gumi.</e>
<cmt>表現が不自然なためdoubtfulをdoubtにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, there is a doubt about the effectiveness of the Gonin-gumi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また、村によっては一つの村内で領主が家ごとに別々（相給）になっているケースがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some villages, every family had its feudal lord, (it was referred to as Aikyu).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「領主が家ごとに別々」という記述は説明として少し誤りがあるようなのですが、（家ごとではなく、一つの村の分割された区分ごとに領主がいる）指示書に従って原文のまま訳してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some villages, every family had its feudal lord, (it was referred to as Aikyu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some villages, every family had its feudal lord, (it was referred to as Aikyu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>その場合には領主が編成する五人組と村が居住区域をもって定めた五人組（「郷五人組」）が並存するという現象も生じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In that case, the Gonin-gumi organized by the feudal lord and another Gonin-gumi (&apos;Go-gonin gumi&apos; (the Gonin-gumi of the dwelling)) made by the village based on their settlements existed in parallel.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In that case, the Gonin-gumi organized by the feudal lord and another Gonin-gumi (&apos;Go-gonin gumi&apos; [the Gonin-gumi of the dwelling]) made by the village based on their settlements existed at the same time.</e>
<cmt>・統一事項に従って、丸括弧の中の括弧は[]にしました。・in parallelは英語としてここでは意味を成さないため、at the same timeとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In that case, the Gonin-gumi organized by the feudal lord and another Gonin-gumi (&apos;Go-gonin gumi&apos; [the Gonin-gumi of the dwelling]) made by the village based on their settlements existed at the same time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>しかし五人組制度が存在することによって、間接的に名主・庄屋の権威を裏付け、住民の生活を制約すると同時に町村の自治とりまとめを強化することには役立った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Gonin-gumi system indirectly helped to give Nanushi/Shoya authority, control the life of the citizens, and reinforce autonomy of the villeages and towns.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Gonin-gumi system indirectly helped to give Nanushi/Shoya authority, control the life of the citizens, and reinforce autonomy of the villages and towns.</e>
<cmt>villeagesはスペルミスのようです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Gonin-gumi system indirectly helped to give Nanushi/Shoya authority, control the life of the citizens, and reinforce autonomy of the villages and towns.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>近代的自治法の整備とともに五人組は法制的には消滅したが、第二次世界大戦中の隣組にその性格は受け継がれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Along with development of the modern self-governing laws, the Gonin-gumi disappeared as a legal system, however, tonarigumi (neighborhood association (established in Japan in 1940)) system during World War 2 took over its characteristics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Along with development of the modern self-governing laws, the Gonin-gumi disappeared as a legal system; however, the tonarigumi (neighborhood association [established in Japan in 1940]) system during World War II took over its characteristics.</e>
<cmt>・統一事項に従って、丸括弧の中の括弧は[]にしました。・統一用語ではWorld War 2→World War IIが正です。・howeverは接続詞ではないため、直前のコンマはセミコロンにしました。・systemは可算名詞のため定冠詞を付けました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Along with development of the modern self-governing laws, the Gonin-gumi disappeared as a legal system; however, the tonarigumi (neighborhood association [established in Japan in 1940]) system during World War II took over its characteristics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Extrahitz(id:26245), Dakara930(id:122892), 江口磐世☆(id:168037), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), Bue(id:237847), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>