<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>朝野群載</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Choya Gunsai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Choya Gunsai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Choya Gunsai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>朝野群載（ちょうやぐんさい）は平安時代の詩文・宣旨・官符・書札等各種文書を分類して算博士・三善為康が編纂したもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Choya gunsai was edited by MIYOSHI no Tameyasu, San hakase (Doctor of Numbers), who classified monjo (written materials) n the Heian period such as prose and poetry, imperial decrees, official documents from the Dajokan (Great Council of State).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Choya gunsai was edited by MIYOSHI no Tameyasu, San hakase (Doctor of Numbers), who classified monjo (written materials) n the Heian period such as prose and poetry, imperial decrees, official documents from the Dajokan (Great Council of State).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Choya gunsai was edited by MIYOSHI no Tameyasu, San hakase (Doctor of Numbers), who classified monjo (written materials) n the Heian period such as prose and poetry, imperial decrees, official documents from the Dajokan (Great Council of State).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>1116年（永久 (元号)4）成立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was completed in 1116.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was completed in 1116.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was completed in 1116.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>しかしその後の増補があり、最終的には保延年間（1135～41）の成立と推定される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it was enlarged in later years, so that the final completion is estimated to be from 1135 to 1141.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it was enlarged in later years, so that the final completion is estimated to be from 1135 to 1141.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it was enlarged in later years, so that the final completion is estimated to be from 1135 to 1141.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>元は30巻であったが、10、14、18、19、23、24、25、29、30の9巻は現存しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The original book consisted of thirty volumes; however, the volumes 10, 14, 18, 19, 23, 24, 25, 29, and 30 do not exist today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The original book consisted of thirty volumes; however, the volumes 10, 14, 18, 19, 23, 24, 25, 29, and 30 do not exist today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The original book consisted of thirty volumes; however, the volumes 10, 14, 18, 19, 23, 24, 25, 29, and 30 do not exist today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>分類は、文筆・朝儀・神祇官・太政官・摂籙家・公卿家・別奏・功労・廷尉・内記・紀伝・陰陽道・暦道・天文道・医道・仏事・太宰府・異国・雑文・凶事・諸国雑事・諸国公文・諸国功過の各項目であるが、これは現存する部分についてであり、失われた9巻にどのような分類が含まれていたのかは不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The classification includes such items as literary art, chogi, the kugyo family, Jingikan (Department of Divinities), Daijokan (Grand Council of State), the Kugyo family (kugyo means a Court noble), besso, achievements, teii (Chinese name of police), naiki (secretary of the Ministry of Central Affairs), kiden, Onmyodo (yin-yang philosophy), rekido (the study of the calendar), tenmondo (astrology), ido (medical ethics), Buddhist service, Dazaifu foreign countries, miscellaneous writings, shokoku-zatsuji, shokoku-kobun and shokoku koka, however, these items are about existing parts, therefore, it is unknown what kinds of classification were included in the missing eight volumes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The classification includes such items as literary art, chogi (ceremony at Imperial Court), Jingikan (Department of Divinities), Daijokan (Grand Council of State), the Setsuroku family (the family which produced the Regent and the Chief Adviser to the Emperor), the Kugyo family (kugyo means a Court noble), besso, achievements, teii (Chinese name of police), naiki (secretary of the Ministry of Central Affairs), kiden (biographical books), Onmyodo (yin-yang philosophy), rekido (the study of the calendar), tenmondo (astrology), ido (medical ethics), Buddhist service, Dazaifu (local government office in Kyushu region), foreign countries, miscellaneous writings, misfortunes, shokoku-zatsuji (miscellaneous matters of various districts), shokoku-kumon (official documents of various districts) and shokoku koka (merits and demerits of various districts), however, these items are about existing parts, therefore, it is unknown what kinds of classification were included in the missing nine volumes.</e>
<cmt>訳抜けおよび誤りを修正し、調査して判明した分のみ説明を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The classification includes such items as literary art, chogi (ceremony at Imperial Court), Jingikan (Department of Divinities), Daijokan (Grand Council of State), the Setsuroku family (the family which produced the Regent and the Chief Adviser to the Emperor), the Kugyo family (kugyo means a Court noble), besso, achievements, teii (Chinese name of police), naiki (secretary of the Ministry of Central Affairs), kiden (biographical books), Onmyodo (yin-yang philosophy), rekido (the study of the calendar), tenmondo (astrology), ido (medical ethics), Buddhist service, Dazaifu (local government office in Kyushu region), foreign countries, miscellaneous writings, misfortunes, shokoku-zatsuji (miscellaneous matters of various districts), shokoku-kumon (official documents of various districts) and shokoku koka (merits and demerits of various districts), however, these items are about existing parts, therefore, it is unknown what kinds of classification were included in the missing nine volumes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>上記の内容からも判るとおり、本書は詩文集としてより、諸司の事務に関わるものを多く含み、文書集としての性格が強い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As easily understood from the above, this book, including many affairs of hoshi (officials), has more characteristics as collected monjo (written material) than as a poetry miscellany.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As easily understood from the above, this book, including many affairs of shoshi (officials), has more characteristics as collected monjo (written material) than as a poetry miscellany.</e>
<cmt>スペルミスを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As easily understood from the above, this book, including many affairs of shoshi (officials), has more characteristics as collected monjo (written material) than as a poetry miscellany.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また編者三善為康が身近な「反故」を集めたと自ら述べているように、編者が生きた平安時代末期の史料が特に多く収録されていることから、平安時代中紀以降末期にかけての律令政治の実態を伝える貴重な文書集となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the editor, MIYOSHI no Tameyasu himself stated that he had collected scraps of paper, the book, including many historical materials especially in the end of Heian period when he lived, makes itself a valuable collection of monjo that reports realities of government according to the Ritsuryo code from the middle to the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the editor, MIYOSHI no Tameyasu himself stated that he had collected &apos;hogo&apos; (scraps of paper), the book, including many historical materials especially in the end of Heian period when he lived, makes itself a valuable collection of monjo that reports realities of government according to the Ritsuryo code from the middle to the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>「反故」は括弧書きになっているため、残したほうが良いと考え、追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the editor, MIYOSHI no Tameyasu himself stated that he had collected &apos;hogo&apos; (scraps of paper), the book, including many historical materials especially in the end of Heian period when he lived, makes itself a valuable collection of monjo that reports realities of government according to the Ritsuryo code from the middle to the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>昭和13年に黒板勝美が編集した『新訂増補国史大系』（吉川弘文館）第29上巻に収録される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">n 1938 it was included in the 29th volume of &quot;Enlarged New Edition of the Summa Japanese History&quot; compiled by Katsumi KUROSAKA (Yoshikawa Kobunkan Inc.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1938, it was included in the 29th volume of &quot;Enlarged New Edition of the Summa Japanese History&quot; compiled by Katsumi KUROSAKA (Yoshikawa Kobunkan Inc.).</e>
<cmt>スペルミスを修正し、読点を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1938, it was included in the 29th volume of &quot;Enlarged New Edition of the Summa Japanese History&quot; compiled by Katsumi KUROSAKA (Yoshikawa Kobunkan Inc.).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Ktmchi(id:113301), Libertas(id:40611), 玄史生(id:43670), Championship2006(id:38664), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>