<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>哲学館事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tetsugakukan incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tetsugakukan incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tetsugakukan incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>哲学館事件（てつがくかんじけん・てつがっかんじけん）とは1902年に東洋大学（現在の東洋大学）で発生した事件である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tetsugakugan incident was occurred at Toyo University (current Toyo University) in 1902.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tetsugakugan incident occurred at Toyo University (current Toyo University) in 1902.</e>
<cmt>wasを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tetsugakugan incident occurred at Toyo University (current Toyo University) in 1902.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>明治期の初め、学校の卒業と同時に無試験で教員になることができたのは国立の学校のみで私立にはその権利がなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the first period of Meiji era, students of national university could become a teacher at the same time as graduation without taking the examination, but those of private school had no rights of that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the first period of Meiji era, national university students were certified to be teachers at the time of graduation without taking an examination, but not private university students.</e>
<cmt>全体的に語句等変更しました。※以下、「学校」と表記されていますが、universityと訳出してあります。（哲学館も東洋大学の前身であるため)。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the first period of Meiji era, national university students were certified to be teachers at the time of graduation without taking an examination, but not private university students.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>しかし、哲学普及のために教育者を育成することを目標としていた私立哲学館の井上円了は私立学校にも卒業生に対して無資格で教員となることができるよう、1890年から当時の文部科学省に対して陳情を行っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However Enryo INOUE of the private school Tetsugakukan who had a purpose to train educators for the popularization of Philosophy lobbied the Ministry of Education at that time from 1890 to admit private university students to become a teacher without certification.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However Enryo INOUE of Tetsugakukan (a private university), who aimed to train educators for popularization of philosophy requested continuously from 1890 the Ministry of Education to admit private university students to become a teacher without certification.</e>
<cmt>全体的に語句等変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However Enryo INOUE of Tetsugakukan (a private university), who aimed to train educators for popularization of philosophy requested continuously from 1890 the Ministry of Education to admit private university students to become a teacher without certification.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>文部省からなかなか良い返事をもらえなかった井上は、慶應義塾大学（現在の慶應義塾大学）、國學院大學（現在の國學院大學）、早稲田大学（現在の早稲田大学）と私立学校の連合を組んで再度陳情を行い、1899年に中等学校の教員免許について、卒業と同時に無試験で認可されることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">INOUE could not receive a good response from the Ministry of Education, so that he made a combination of private universities with Keio University, Kokugakuin University, and Waseda University to lobby again, then finally in 1899, it was allowed to take teacher&apos;s license for the secondary school at the same time as graduation without taking an examination.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">INOUE could not receive a good response from the Ministry of Education, then he formed a combination of private universities with Keio University, Kokugakuin University, and Waseda University, then finally in 1899 graduates of private university were allowed to have secondary school teacher&apos;s license without an examination.</e>
<cmt>全体的に語句等変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">INOUE could not receive a good response from the Ministry of Education, then he formed a combination of private universities with Keio University, Kokugakuin University, and Waseda University, then finally in 1899 graduates of private university were allowed to have secondary school teacher&apos;s license without an examination.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>1902年にはこの4校で最初の卒業生が誕生し、私立学校ではじめての無試験教員が誕生するはずであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was supposed that the first graduates and the teachers without taking the examination would be born from these 4 universities in 1902.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1902, students graduated from those four schools and they were supposed to become first teachers without taking examination after graduation of private universities.</e>
<cmt>全体的に語句等変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1902, students graduated from those four schools and they were supposed to become first teachers without taking examination after graduation of private universities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>しかし、哲学館の卒業試験を検定した視学官隈本有尚が中島徳蔵の出題した内容を問題視した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, school inspector Aritaka KUMAMOTO who examined the final examination of Tetsugakukan, pointed a problem of the contents which Tokuzo NAKAJIMA made.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Aritaka KUMAMOTO who examined the graduation exam of Tetsugakukan, pointed out a problem regarding the contents which Tokuzo NAKAJIMA prepared.</e>
<cmt>全体的に語句等変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Aritaka KUMAMOTO who examined the graduation exam of Tetsugakukan, pointed out a problem regarding the contents which Tokuzo NAKAJIMA prepared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>この内容はミュアヘッドの書物の一節からとられたもので「動機が善ならば弑逆（親など目上の人を殺すこと）も許されるであろうか」という課題である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The contents were extracted one passage from the book written by Muirhead, and the question was &apos;If the motive was virtue, would it be allowed to kill superiors such as parents?&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The content was from one passage of the book written by Muirhead, and the question was &apos;If the motive is good, would it be excusable to kill superiors such as parents?&apos;</e>
<cmt>全体的に語句等変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The content was from one passage of the book written by Muirhead, and the question was &apos;If the motive is good, would it be excusable to kill superiors such as parents?&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>これに対して学生が「許される」としたため、哲学館の教育方針は「目上を殺してよいということは天皇も殺してよいということだ。この思想は国体を危うくする恐れがある」という見解をまとめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As one student answered &apos;Yes, it would be allowed&apos;, the education policy of Tetsugakukan concluded its opinion that &apos;if it is possible to kill the superiors, it would be possible to kill the Emperor. This thought would invite danger to the fundamental character.&apos;</e>
<cmt>内容が続いていたので次の文とまとめました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As one student answered &apos;Yes it would be excusable&apos;, the views on the education policy of Tetsugakukan was summarized as follows: &apos;if it is excusable to kill superiors, it would be excusable to kill an Emperor and this thought would endanger the fundamental character of the nation&apos;.</e>
<cmt>全体的に語句等変更しました。空欄の列は削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As one student answered &apos;Yes it would be excusable&apos;, the views on the education policy of Tetsugakukan was summarized as follows: &apos;if it is excusable to kill superiors, it would be excusable to kill an Emperor and this thought would endanger the fundamental character of the nation&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その結果、文部省は哲学館の教員免許無試験認可を取り消すこととした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Ministry of Education cancelled to admit to get teaching license without taking the examination at Tetsugakukan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Ministry of Education cancelled to give teaching license to graduates of Tetsugakukan without an examination.</e>
<cmt>全体的に語句等変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Ministry of Education cancelled to give teaching license to graduates of Tetsugakukan without an examination.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>この事件は私立学校における教育の自由や学問の自由に関する議論となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This incident expanded to the discussion on the freedom of education and learning at private schools.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This incident provoked controversy on the freedom of education and learning at private schools.</e>
<cmt>expanded to the discussion→provoked controversyに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This incident provoked controversy on the freedom of education and learning at private schools.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>当時の新聞紙上では私学の自由を犯すものであるという見解が出る一方で、そもそもこの思想を教授した方法に問題があったのではないかという擁護論も交わされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the newspaper at that time some opinion was that would prevent the freedom of private schools, but on the other hand, there was an opinion to protect that originally there was a problem in the way to teach the thought.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the newspaper at that time there were opinions that the measure would hamper freedom of private schools, but on the other hand, some people supported the measure because they thought there might have been a problem in the way to teach the thought.</e>
<cmt>全体的に語句等変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the newspaper at that time there were opinions that the measure would hamper freedom of private schools, but on the other hand, some people supported the measure because they thought there might have been a problem in the way to teach the thought.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>こうした状況は帝国議会でも問題となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These situation became the problem at the Imperial Diet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The topic was discussed at the Imperial Diet as well.</e>
<cmt>become the problem→was discussed に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The topic was discussed at the Imperial Diet as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>ミュアヘッドも文部省の見解に対してイギリスから反論するなど、日英間の国際問題となりかけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Muirhead opposed from England to the opinion of Ministry of Education, it mostly became the international matter between England and Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Muirhead opposed to the opinion of Ministry of Education from Britain, the incident was about to be an international incident between England and Japan.</e>
<cmt>全体的に語句等変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Muirhead opposed to the opinion of Ministry of Education from Britain, the incident was about to be an international incident between England and Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>この後、哲学館は東洋大学となり、1928年に大学令による大学となるが、申請をしたにもかかわらず他の大学に比べて認可が遅れた（早稲田大学や國學院大學などは1920年に認可）のは哲学館事件が尾を引いたからではないかと当時の新聞は論説を書いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, Tetsugakukan became Toyo University, and became university under the order of university in 1928, but the admission was delayed, in spite of giving the application, compared to other universities (Waseda University and Kokugakuin University were admitted in 1920), so the newspapers at that time wrote the opinion that the delay was caused by the Tetsugakukan incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterwards, Tetsugakukan became Toyo University, and became university under Acts of Universities in 1928, but the approbation was delayed compared to other universities (Waseda and Kokugakuin University were authorized in 1920), there was an opinion on a newspaper that the Tetsugakukan incident affected the delay.</e>
<cmt>全体的に語句等変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterwards, Tetsugakukan became Toyo University, and became university under Acts of Universities in 1928, but the approbation was delayed compared to other universities (Waseda and Kokugakuin University were authorized in 1920), there was an opinion on a newspaper that the Tetsugakukan incident affected the delay.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また、公文書の開示結果、1920年に既に認可できる要件は整っていたが、この事件が影響して認可できないという内容が残されていることが判り、東洋大学が遅れた存在ではなかったことが証明された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And as a result of the disclosing of an official document, the contents were recorded saying that the requirements were ready to admit Toyo University in 1920, but it could not be done because of the incident, so that this record proved that Toyo University was not the one delayed from others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a disclosed official document, the requirements to be authorized as Toyo University were ready in 1920 but the approbation was delayed due to the incident, so this record proved that Toyo University didn&apos;t lag behind others.</e>
<cmt>全体的に語句等変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a disclosed official document, the requirements to be authorized as Toyo University were ready in 1920 but the approbation was delayed due to the incident, so this record proved that Toyo University didn&apos;t lag behind others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>哲学館事件は現在でも日本の教育史では大きなトピックとなっており、松本清張の「小説東京帝国大学」（1969年、新潮社）などのように小説や論説の題材として使用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tetsugakukan incident is a big topic in the current educational history in Japan, it is used as a theme of novels and editorials, such as &apos;novel Tokyo Imperial University&apos; (published in 1969, by Shinchosha Publishing Co., Ltd.;) written by Seicho Matsumoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tetsugakukan incident is an important topic in educational history in Japan, it is used as a theme of novels and editorials, for example&apos;Novel Tokyo Imperial University&apos; (published in 1969, by Shinchosha Publishing Co., Ltd.;) written by Seicho Matsumoto.</e>
<cmt>全体的に語句等変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tetsugakukan incident is an important topic in educational history in Japan, it is used as a theme of novels and editorials, for example&apos;Novel Tokyo Imperial University&apos; (published in 1969, by Shinchosha Publishing Co., Ltd.;) written by Seicho Matsumoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Ihsanan(id:30330), Straysheep(id:42448), 秋の虹(id:18259), Enowiki(id:18580), 経済準学士(id:22656), Littlesetuna(id:252328), ToyoMaster(id:91542), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>