<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>久米田の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The battle of Kumeda</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The battle of Kumeda</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The battle of Kumeda</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>久米田の戦い（くめだのたたかい）は永禄5年(1562年)3月5日、和泉国八木村 (大阪府)郷の久米田寺周辺（現大阪府岸和田市）に布陣する三好義賢に対し、畠山高政が攻め入った日本の合戦。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The battle of Kumeda was a battle occurred in Japan in which Takamasa HATAKEYAMA attacked Yoshitaka MIYOSHI who lined up around Kumeda-dera Temple (present Kishiwada City, Osaka Prefecture) in Yagi-mura, Izumi Province (Osaka) on March 5, 1562.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The battle of Kumeda was a battle that took place in Japan in which Takamasa HATAKEYAMA attacked Yoshitaka MIYOSHI who lined up around Kumeda-dera Temple (present Kishiwada City, Osaka Prefecture) in Yagi-mura, Izumi Province (Osaka) on March 5, 1562.</e>
<cmt>自然な表現となるよう修正致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The battle of Kumeda was a battle that took place in Japan in which Takamasa HATAKEYAMA attacked Yoshitaka MIYOSHI who lined up around Kumeda-dera Temple (present Kishiwada City, Osaka Prefecture) in Yagi-mura, Izumi Province (Osaka) on March 5, 1562.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>両軍併せて17,000から50,000の兵力が激突し、三好義賢はこの合戦にて戦死を遂げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Total of 17,000 through 50,000 soldiers fought against each other, and Yoshitaka MIYOSHI died in the battlefield.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A total of 17,000 to 50,000 soldiers of the two armies fought against each other, and Yoshitaka MIYOSHI died in in this battle.</e>
<cmt>自然な表現となるよう修正致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A total of 17,000 to 50,000 soldiers of the two armies fought against each other, and Yoshitaka MIYOSHI died in in this battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>三好氏没落の遠因となった合戦とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This battle is thought to be an underlying cause of the fall of the Miyoshi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This battle is thought to be an underlying cause of the fall of the Miyoshi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This battle is thought to be an underlying cause of the fall of the Miyoshi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>第13代将軍足利義輝を擁した三好長慶に反発した畿内の守護大名である六角義賢や畠山高政らは互いに手を組み、京を含めた畿内において反三好的な行動を度々おこす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitaka ROKKAKU and Takamasa HATAKEYAMA, who were both shugo daimyo (shugo, which were Japanese provincial military governors, that became daimyo, which were Japanese feudal lords) and were against Nagayoshi MIYOSHI, who backed up the 13th shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA, joined hands and caused many anti-Miyoshi actions in Kinai, including Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitaka ROKKAKU and Takamasa HATAKEYAMA, who were both shugo daimyo (shugo, which were Japanese provincial military governors, that became daimyo, which were Japanese feudal lords) were against Nagayoshi MIYOSHI, who supported the 13th shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA, and they joined hands and caused many anti-Miyoshi movements in Kinai, including Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>自然な表現となるよう修正致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitaka ROKKAKU and Takamasa HATAKEYAMA, who were both shugo daimyo (shugo, which were Japanese provincial military governors, that became daimyo, which were Japanese feudal lords) were against Nagayoshi MIYOSHI, who supported the 13th shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA, and they joined hands and caused many anti-Miyoshi movements in Kinai, including Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>長慶の弟である十河一存の死を契機として、高政は安見宗房、遊佐教光らを伴い岸和田城へ攻め入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taking advantage of the death of Kazumasa SOGO, younger brother of Nagayoshi, Takamasa, along with Munefusa YASUMI and Norimitsu YUSA, attacked the Kishiwada-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taking the death of Kazumasa SOGO who was a younger brother of Nagayoshi as an opportunity, Takamasa attacked the Kishiwada-jo Castle along with Munefusa YASUMI and Norimitsu YUSA.</e>
<cmt>自然な表現となるよう修正致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taking the death of Kazumasa SOGO who was a younger brother of Nagayoshi as an opportunity, Takamasa attacked the Kishiwada-jo Castle along with Munefusa YASUMI and Norimitsu YUSA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>一方、六角義賢は慈照寺の北、勝軍地蔵山城へ攻め入り、三好軍を挟撃する布陣で臨んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, Yoshitaka ROKKAKU attacked the Shogun Jizo San-jo Castle which was located in the north of Jisho-ji Temple; Takamasa and Yoshitaka took a pincer movement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Yoshitaka ROKKAKU attacked the Shogun Jizo San-jo Castle which was located in the north of Jisho-ji Temple; Takamasa and Yoshitaka took a pincer movement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Yoshitaka ROKKAKU attacked the Shogun Jizo San-jo Castle which was located in the north of Jisho-ji Temple; Takamasa and Yoshitaka took a pincer movement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>これに対し長慶は、畠山軍への備えに河内高屋城に拠る三好義賢を、六角軍へは三好義興をあてた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In response to this, Nagayoshi had Yoshitaka MIYOSHI who was positioned in the Kawachi Takaya-jo Castle fight against the Hatakeyama&apos;s army and had Yoshioki MIYOSHI fight against the Rokkaku&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In response to this, Nagayoshi had Yoshitaka MIYOSHI who was positioned in the Kawachi Takaya-jo Castle fight against the Hatakeyama&apos;s army, and had Yoshioki MIYOSHI fight against the Rokkaku&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>自然な表現となるよう修正致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response to this, Nagayoshi had Yoshitaka MIYOSHI who was positioned in the Kawachi Takaya-jo Castle fight against the Hatakeyama&apos;s army, and had Yoshioki MIYOSHI fight against the Rokkaku&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>自身は飯盛山城から両軍の総指揮を執った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagayoshi acted as the commander of the both armies in the Imoriyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagayoshi acted as the commander for both armies in the Imoriyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>自然な表現となるよう修正致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagayoshi acted as the commander for both armies in the Imoriyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>戦況</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The war situation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The war situation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The war situation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>『細川両家記』によれば1562年3月5日、三好義賢が布陣していた久米田に畠山高政、安見宗房らの軍勢が攻め入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the &quot;Hosokawa ryoke ki&quot; (Record of the two houses of Hosokawa), on March 5, 1562, an army of Takamasa HATAKEYAMA and Munefusa YASUMI attacked Kumeda, where Yoshitaka MIYOSHI lined up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Hosokawa ryoke ki&quot; (Record of the two houses of Hosokawa), on March 5, 1562, an army of Takamasa HATAKEYAMA and Munefusa YASUMI attacked Kumeda, where Yoshitaka MIYOSHI was taking position.</e>
<cmt>自然な表現となるよう修正致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Hosokawa ryoke ki&quot; (Record of the two houses of Hosokawa), on March 5, 1562, an army of Takamasa HATAKEYAMA and Munefusa YASUMI attacked Kumeda, where Yoshitaka MIYOSHI was taking position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>三好側は篠原長房らの将兵が打って出ており、激戦の末、戦局は次第に三好側へと傾いていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the Miyoshi side, officers and soldiers, including Nagafusa SHINOHARA, fought and after the severe fight, the Miyoshi side was dominating.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Officers and soldiers including Nagafusa SHINOHARA, fought from the Miyoshi side, and after a fierce battle, the Miyoshi side came to dominate the tide of the war.</e>
<cmt>自然な表現となるよう修正致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Officers and soldiers including Nagafusa SHINOHARA, fought from the Miyoshi side, and after a fierce battle, the Miyoshi side came to dominate the tide of the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>総攻撃をかけたい三好側は三好康長、三好政康らが一挙に打って出た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Miyoshi side wanted to mount a full-scale attack, and Yasunaga MIYOSHI and Masayasu MIYOSHI made an attack at the same time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Miyoshi side wanted to mount a full-scale attack, and Yasunaga MIYOSHI and Masayasu MIYOSHI made an attack all at once.</e>
<cmt>自然な表現となるよう修正致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Miyoshi side wanted to mount a full-scale attack, and Yasunaga MIYOSHI and Masayasu MIYOSHI made an attack all at once.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>そのため、一時三好義賢の近辺が100騎前後の手薄となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, there were only 100 horsemen around Yoshitaka MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Yoshitaka MIYOSHI was shorthanded at one time with about 100 horsemen around him.</e>
<cmt>自然な表現となるよう修正致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Yoshitaka MIYOSHI was shorthanded at one time with about 100 horsemen around him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>畠山高政はこの期を逃さず根来衆をもって本陣へ突撃し、午後4時頃、三好義賢を討ち取った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takamasa HATAKEYAMA took this opportunity and attacked the headquarters along with Negoroshu (a group of armed priests in Negoro-ji Temple), and killed Yoshitaka MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takamasa HATAKEYAMA took this opportunity and attacked the headquarters along with Negoroshu (a group of armed priests in Negoro-ji Temple), and killed Yoshitaka MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takamasa HATAKEYAMA took this opportunity and attacked the headquarters along with Negoroshu (a group of armed priests in Negoro-ji Temple), and killed Yoshitaka MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>戦後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the war</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the war</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the war</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>畠山高政は三好義賢を討ち取り、飯盛山城を攻撃し長慶を脅かした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takamasa HATAKEYAMA killed Yoshitaka MIYOSHI and threatened Nagayoshi by attacking the Imoriyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takamasa HATAKEYAMA killed Yoshitaka MIYOSHI and threatened Nagayoshi by attacking the Imoriyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takamasa HATAKEYAMA killed Yoshitaka MIYOSHI and threatened Nagayoshi by attacking the Imoriyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>しかし、続く教興寺の戦いにおいて戦局を立て直した三好軍の前に敗北を喫し、三好長慶の覇権を覆すことはできなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Takamasa lost against the Miyoshi&apos;s army which rebuilt the course of war at the following battle of Kyoko-ji Temple, and could not take over the hegemony by Nagayoshi MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Takamasa was defeated in the subsequent Battle of Kyoko-ji Temple by the Miyoshi&apos;s army that restored the state of the war, and could not take over the hegemony by Nagayoshi MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>自然な表現となるよう修正致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Takamasa was defeated in the subsequent Battle of Kyoko-ji Temple by the Miyoshi&apos;s army that restored the state of the war, and could not take over the hegemony by Nagayoshi MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし、信頼できる補佐役を失った三好氏はまもなく内紛に悩まされるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Miyoshi clan, which lost faithful assistants at the battle, came to suffer from internal conflicts.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Miyoshi clan, which lost faithful assistants in the battle, came to suffer from internal conflicts.</e>
<cmt>自然な表現となるよう修正致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Miyoshi clan, which lost faithful assistants in the battle, came to suffer from internal conflicts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>長慶の病没後、これに乗じて実権を回復せんとした将軍足利義輝を暗殺してしまい（永禄の変）、自身の支配の正当性を大きく揺るがしてしまうことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Nagayoshi died by illness, the Miyoshi clan assassinated shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA who tried to take back the real power (Eiroku Incident), and the Miyoshi clan lost the rightness of their control.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Nagayoshi died from an illness, the Miyoshi clan assassinated shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA who tried to take back the real power (Eiroku Incident), and the Miyoshi clan greatly shook their own righteousness to control.</e>
<cmt>自然な表現となるよう修正致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Nagayoshi died from an illness, the Miyoshi clan assassinated shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA who tried to take back the real power (Eiroku Incident), and the Miyoshi clan greatly shook their own righteousness to control.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 赤井彗星(id:18381), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>