<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>戊午の密勅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bogo no micchoku (a secret imperial decree)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bogo no Mitchoku (a secret imperial decree)</e>
<cmt>micchoku→Mitchokuに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bogo no Mitchoku (a secret imperial decree)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>戊午の密勅（ぼごのみっちょく）は1858年9月14日（安政5年8月8日 (旧暦)）に孝明天皇が水戸藩に勅書（勅諚）を下賜した事件である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bogo no micchoku is an incident that Emperor Komei gave a chokusho (imperial decree) to the Mito Domain on September 14, 1858.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bogo no mitchoku is an incident that Emperor Komei gave a chokusho (imperial decree) to the Mito Domain on September 14, 1858.</e>
<cmt>micchoku→mitchokuに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bogo no mitchoku is an incident that Emperor Komei gave a chokusho (imperial decree) to the Mito Domain on September 14, 1858.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「戊午」は下賜された安政5年の干支が戊午（つちのえ・うま）であったことに由来し、「密勅」とは正式な手続（関白九条尚忠の裁可）を経ないままの下賜であったことによる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Bogo&quot; is derived from Bogo (also called tsuchinoe, uma), the zodiac sign of that year when the chokusho was given, and &quot;micchoku&quot; or a secret Imperial command means that the document was given without going through the official procedure which required to obtain approbation from Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor), Hisatada KUJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Bogo&quot; is derived from Bogo (also called tsuchinoe, uma), the zodiac sign of that year when the chokusho was given, and &quot;mitchoku&quot; or a secret Imperial command means that the document was given without going through the official procedure which required to obtain approbation from Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor), Hisatada KUJO.</e>
<cmt>micchoku→mitchokuに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Bogo&quot; is derived from Bogo (also called tsuchinoe, uma), the zodiac sign of that year when the chokusho was given, and &quot;mitchoku&quot; or a secret Imperial command means that the document was given without going through the official procedure which required to obtain approbation from Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor), Hisatada KUJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>密勅は万里小路正房より水戸藩京都留守居役鵜飼吉左衛門に下り、吉左衛門の子　鵜飼幸吉の手によって水戸藩家老　安島帯刀を介して水戸藩主徳川慶篤に伝えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The micchoku was passed from Naofusa MADENOKOJI to Kichizaemon UGAI, the Kyoto rusuiyaku (a person representing the master during his absence) of the MIto Domain, and Kokichi UGAI, the son of Kichizaemon, passed it to Yoshiatsu TOKUGAWA, the lord of the Mito Domain, via Tatewaki AJIMA, Karo (chief retainer) of the Mito Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The mitchoku was passed from Naofusa MADENOKOJI to Kichizaemon UGAI, the Kyoto rusuiyaku (a person representing the master during his absence) of the Mito Domain, and Kokichi UGAI, the son of Kichizaemon, passed it to Yoshiatsu TOKUGAWA, the lord of the Mito Domain, via Tatewaki AJIMA, Karo (chief retainer) of the Mito Domain.</e>
<cmt>micchoku→mitchoku、MIto→Mitoに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The mitchoku was passed from Naofusa MADENOKOJI to Kichizaemon UGAI, the Kyoto rusuiyaku (a person representing the master during his absence) of the Mito Domain, and Kokichi UGAI, the son of Kichizaemon, passed it to Yoshiatsu TOKUGAWA, the lord of the Mito Domain, via Tatewaki AJIMA, Karo (chief retainer) of the Mito Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>幕府には数日後に禁裏付の大久保一翁を通じて伝えられたが、江戸より水戸に先着することを図っての時期であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Micchoku was conveyed to the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) through Ichio OKUBO, an assistant to Kinri (the Imperial Palace) several days later, but it was such a time-sensitive situations when the micchoku was delivered to Mito earlier than to Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The mitchoku was conveyed to the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) through Ichio OKUBO, an assistant to Kinri (the Imperial Palace) several days later, but it was such a time-sensitive situations when the mitchoku was delivered to Mito earlier than to Edo.</e>
<cmt>Micchoku→The mitchoku、micchoku→mitchokuとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The mitchoku was conveyed to the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) through Ichio OKUBO, an assistant to Kinri (the Imperial Palace) several days later, but it was such a time-sensitive situations when the mitchoku was delivered to Mito earlier than to Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>水戸藩以外の徳川御三家、御三卿などには秘匿されていたが、写しは関白以外の摂家を通じて縁家の大名に送付された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The micchoku was kept secret from Tokugawa gosanke and gosankyo (three privileged branches of Tokugawa family) other than the Mito Domain but the copies of it were sent to other related daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) through Sekke (line of regents and advisers) except Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The mitchoku was kept secret from the Tokugawa gosanke and gosankyo (three privileged branches of Tokugawa family) other than the Mito Domain but the copies of it were sent to other related daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) through Sekke (line of regents and advisers) except Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>micchoku→mitchokuに修正、the Tokugawa gosanke and gosankyoとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The mitchoku was kept secret from the Tokugawa gosanke and gosankyo (three privileged branches of Tokugawa family) other than the Mito Domain but the copies of it were sent to other related daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) through Sekke (line of regents and advisers) except Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>内容</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Contents of the micchoku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Contents of the mitchoku</e>
<cmt>micchoku→mitchokuに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Contents of the mitchoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>勅許なく日米修好通商条約(安政五カ国条約)に調印したことへの呵責と、詳細な説明の要求。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Condemnation against signing the Treaty of Amity and Commerce between the United States and Japan (five-parties treaty in Ansei period) without an imperial sanction and demand a through explanation on it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Condemnation against signing the Treaty of Amity and Commerce between the United States and Japan (five-parties treaty in the Ansei era) without an imperial sanction and demand a through explanation on it.</e>
<cmt>in Ansei period→in the Ansei eraに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Condemnation against signing the Treaty of Amity and Commerce between the United States and Japan (five-parties treaty in the Ansei era) without an imperial sanction and demand a through explanation on it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>御三家および諸藩は幕府に協力して公武合体の実を成し、幕府は攘夷推進の幕政改革を遂行せよとの命令。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Order that Tokugawa gosanke and other domains shall realize kobu-gattai, the union of the imperial Court and the Shogunate, in cooperation with the bakufu, and the bakufu shall accelerate to reform the shogunate government to promote the expulsion of foreigners.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Order that the Tokugawa gosanke and other domains shall realize kobu-gattai, the union of the Imperial Court and the shogunate, in cooperation with the bakufu, and the bakufu shall accelerate to reform the shogunate government to promote the expulsion of foreigners.</e>
<cmt>the Tokugawa gosanke、imperial Court→Imperial Court、Shogunate→shogunateとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Order that the Tokugawa gosanke and other domains shall realize kobu-gattai, the union of the Imperial Court and the shogunate, in cooperation with the bakufu, and the bakufu shall accelerate to reform the shogunate government to promote the expulsion of foreigners.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>上記2つの内容を諸藩に廻達せよという副書。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The micchoku had a rider which demanded to deliver the above two contents to other domains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The mitchoku had a rider which demanded to deliver the above two contents to other domains.</e>
<cmt>micchoku→mitchokuに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The mitchoku had a rider which demanded to deliver the above two contents to other domains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>以上の3つに要約することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The contents of the micchoku can be summarized as above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The contents of the mitchoku can be summarized as above.</e>
<cmt>micchoku→mitchokuに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The contents of the mitchoku can be summarized as above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>幕府の臣下であるはずの水戸藩へ朝廷から直接勅書が渡されたということは幕府が蔑ろにされ威信を失墜させられたということであったため、幕府は勅条の内容を秘匿し、大老井伊直弼による安政の大獄を起こす引き金となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fact that the chokusho was delivered directly from the Imperial Court to the Mito Domain that was regarded as a vassal of the bakufu meant that the bakufu was ignored and lost its dignity, so the bakufu kept the contents of the document confidential, which led to trigger the Ansei no Taigoku (suppression of extremists by the Shogunate) by Naosuke II, Tairo (chief minister).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fact that the chokusho was delivered directly from the Imperial Court to the Mito Domain that was regarded as a vassal of the bakufu meant that the bakufu was ignored and lost its dignity, so the bakufu kept the contents of the document confidential, which led to trigger the Ansei no Taigoku (suppression of extremists by the bakufu) by Naosuke II, Tairo (chief minister).</e>
<cmt>the Shogunate→the bakufuとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fact that the chokusho was delivered directly from the Imperial Court to the Mito Domain that was regarded as a vassal of the bakufu meant that the bakufu was ignored and lost its dignity, so the bakufu kept the contents of the document confidential, which led to trigger the Ansei no Taigoku (suppression of extremists by the bakufu) by Naosuke II, Tairo (chief minister).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>とりわけ、鵜飼吉左衛門から安島帯刀宛への書簡には井伊直弼暗殺の秘事が記されていたとされ、幕府にその内容が漏洩したことで安政の大獄ではより厳重な処分となったといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especcially, the letter from Kichizaemon UGAI to Tatewaki AJIMA was said that it contained the secret conspiracy to assassinate Naosuke II, and the leakage of its contents resulted in receiving stricter punishment in the Ansei no Taigoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especcially, the letter from Kichizaemon UGAI to Tatewaki AJIMA was said that it contained the secret conspiracy to assassinate Naosuke II, and the leakage of its contents resulted in receiving stricter punishment in the Ansei no Taigoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especcially, the letter from Kichizaemon UGAI to Tatewaki AJIMA was said that it contained the secret conspiracy to assassinate Naosuke II, and the leakage of its contents resulted in receiving stricter punishment in the Ansei no Taigoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>水戸藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mito Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mito Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mito Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>もともと、斉昭の藩主就任以来、水戸藩では斉昭に忠実な天狗党と幕府との関係を重視する諸生党の対立が激しかったが、密勅の対応をめぐり、さらに確執を深めることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, since Nariaki TOKUGAWA had assumed the the lord of the domain, Tenguto who were royal to Nariaki had been in fierce conflict with Shoseito who emphasized the relationship with the bakufu, and the feud between them were intencified over how to handle this micchoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, since Nariaki TOKUGAWA had assumed the lord of the domain, the Tenguto (the Tengu faction) who were royal to Nariaki had been in fierce conflict with the Shoseito (the Shosei faction) who emphasized the relationship with the bakufu, and the feud between them were intencified over how to handle this mitchoku.</e>
<cmt>the the→the、micchoku→mitchokuに修正、Tenguto→the Tenguto (the Tengu faction)、Shoseito→the Shoseito (the Shosei faction)としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, since Nariaki TOKUGAWA had assumed the lord of the domain, the Tenguto (the Tengu faction) who were royal to Nariaki had been in fierce conflict with the Shoseito (the Shosei faction) who emphasized the relationship with the bakufu, and the feud between them were intencified over how to handle this mitchoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>密勅の返納に反対する藩士は城下を離れて街道を封鎖し脱藩、後に井伊直弼の襲撃を計画する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Feudal retainers of domain left the castle town and blocked roads and left the domain, and later organized an attack against Naosuke II.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Feudal retainers of the domain left the castle town and blocked roads and left the domain, and later organized an attack against Naosuke II.</e>
<cmt>domain→the domainとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Feudal retainers of the domain left the castle town and blocked roads and left the domain, and later organized an attack against Naosuke II.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>桜田門外の変および天狗党の乱を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Refer to the Sakuradamongai Incident and Tenguto no Ran (Rebellion of Tenguto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Refer to the Sakuradamongai no Hen (The Incident Outside the Sakurada-mon Gate) and the Tenguto no Ran (Rebellion of the Tenguto).</e>
<cmt>Sakuradamongai Incidentとありますが、「桜田門外」の意味を明確にするため、Sakuradamongai no Hen (The Incident Outside the Sakurada-mon Gate)としました。（参照: http://books.google.co.jp/books?id=wQZIAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=sakuradamongai-no-hen&amp;dq=sakuradamongai-no-hen&amp;hl=ja&amp;ei=Gy5qTI3hDpDgugPg-KCDAQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCoQ6AEwAA)the Tengutoとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Refer to the Sakuradamongai no Hen (The Incident Outside the Sakurada-mon Gate) and the Tenguto no Ran (Rebellion of the Tenguto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), ドラムスコ(id:40234), 左近将監(id:169081), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), たね(id:10372), Samiadon(id:13976), 砂の妖精(id:24382), Tom-spring(id:42457), Point136(id:211299), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Maakun(id:16735), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>