<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>公儀</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kogi (Shogunate)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kogi (Shogunate)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kogi</e>
<cmt>説明があるのでShogunateは不要と考え削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>公儀（こうぎ/くうぎ）とは、中世・近世において公権力を指して用いた言葉。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kogi is the term used for &quot;official authority&quot; in the middle and early modern ages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kogi is the term used for &quot;official authority&quot; in the middle and early modern ages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kogi (also referred to as Kugi) is the term used for &quot;official authority&quot; in the middle and early modern ages.</e>
<cmt>「（くうぎ）」追記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>本来、公家という言葉が「おおやけ」すなわち朝廷及び天皇を指していたが、領主制による私的支配に由来する新たな公権力である武家政権成立後に武家である幕府及び征夷大将軍と区別するために公儀という言葉も用いられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, the word &quot;Kuge&quot; meant &quot;Oyake&quot; or the Imperial Court and the Emperor, but after the establishment of the &quot;Buke&quot;, or military administration and the new official authority that arose through private management in the manorial system, the word &quot;Kogi was used to differentiate from the &quot;Buke&quot;, the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, the word &quot;Kuge&quot; meant &quot;Oyake&quot; or the Imperial Court and the Emperor, but after the establishment of the &quot;Buke&quot;, or military administration and the new official authority that arose through private management in the manorial system, the word &quot;Kogi was used to differentiate from the &quot;Buke&quot;, the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, the word &quot;Kuge&quot; meant &quot;Oyake&quot; or the Imperial Court and the Emperor, but after the establishment of the &quot;Buke&quot;, or military administration and the new official authority that arose through private management in the manorial system, the word &quot;Kogi&quot; was used to differentiate from the &quot;Buke&quot;, the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;).</e>
<cmt>&quot;Kogi→&quot;Kogi&quot;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>やがて、南北朝時代 (日本)に入ると、北朝 (日本)を擁する室町幕府（武家側）と南朝 (日本)の吉野朝廷（公家側）の対立によって、自己が所属する公権力側を「公儀」と呼ぶようになり、その結果幕府や将軍に対しても公儀が用いられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eventually, in the Period of Northern and Southern Dynasties (Japan), due to the conflict between the Muromachi bakufu (buke) which supported the Northern Dynasty and the Yoshino Court (kuge), both sides called their official authority &quot;Kogi&quot;, which led to the use of Kogi towards the bakufu and shogun as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eventually, in the Period of Northern and Southern Dynasties (Japan), due to the conflict between the Muromachi bakufu (buke) which supported the Northern Dynasty and the Yoshino Court (kuge), both sides called their official authority &quot;Kogi&quot;, which led to the use of Kogi towards the bakufu and shogun as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eventually, in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), due to the conflict between the Muromachi bakufu (buke) which supported the Northern Court and the Yoshino Court (kuge), both sides called their official authority &quot;Kogi&quot;, which led to the use of Kogi towards the bakufu and shogun as well.</e>
<cmt>南北朝時代の定訳Dynasty→Court&quot;the Period of Northern and Southern Courts&quot;→&quot;the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan)&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="4">
<j>豊臣政権末期の政情不安定期に公権力を漠然と公儀と呼ぶ慣習が生まれ、江戸時代に入ると統一政権で諸領主権力間の唯一の利害調整機関となった江戸幕府を指して公儀と呼ばれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kogi became the general term for official authority in the period of governmental instability in towards the end of the Toyotomi administration, and in the Ido Period, Kogi started to indicate the Edo bakufu which was do only unified authority that mediated the power struggles among the feudal lords.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kogi became the general term for official authority in the period of governmental instability in towards the end of the Toyotomi administration, and in the Ido Period, Kogi started to indicate the Edo bakufu which was do only unified authority that mediated the power struggles among the feudal lords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kogi became the general term for official authority in the period of governmental instability in towards the end of the Toyotomi administration, and in the Edo Period, Kogi started to indicate the Edo bakufu which was the only unified authority that mediated the power struggles among the feudal lords.</e>
<cmt>Ido→Edodo→the</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>ただし、地域領主である藩などを指して公儀と呼ぶ習慣も残り、幕府のことを「公儀の公儀」と認めて特に大公儀（おおこうぎ）とも呼ぶようになったのは寛永以後と言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the tradition to call the local landlord, or &quot;han&quot; (feudal domains) as &quot;Kogi&apos; remained and to recognize the bakufu as &quot;the kogi of kogi&quot;, it was especially called &quot;O-kogi&quot; (great official authority) after the Kanei Era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the tradition to call the local landlord, or &quot;han&quot; (feudal domains) as &quot;Kogi&apos; remained and to recognize the bakufu as &quot;the kogi of kogi&quot;, it was especially called &quot;O-kogi&quot; (great official authority) after the Kanei Era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the tradition to call the local landlord, or clan as Kogi remained and to recognize the bakufu as &apos;the kogi of kogi&apos;, it was especially called O-kogi (great official authority) after the Kanei Era.</e>
<cmt>“han” (feudal domains)→clan“the kogi of kogi”→&apos;the kogi of kogi&apos;Kogi と O-kogi の &quot; &quot; 削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>ただし、当時の公私関係は曖昧であり、一般民衆及び下位権力から見て上位権力は公儀であったが、上位権力から見て一般民衆及び下位権力は領主としての私的支配によって結び付けられた「わたくし」の存在であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the relationship between public and private was ambiguous at that time, and although the upper authorities were &quot;Kogi&quot; from the viewpoint of the common people and lower authorities, the upper authorities view the common people and lower authorities as &quot;Watakushi (private)&quot; and as the landlord, connected by private dominance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the relationship between public and private was ambiguous at that time, and although the upper authorities were &quot;Kogi&quot; from the viewpoint of the common people and lower authorities, the upper authorities view the common people and lower authorities as &quot;Watakushi (private)&quot; and as the landlord, connected by private dominance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the relationship between public and private was ambiguous at that time, and although the upper authorities were Kogi from the viewpoint of the common people and lower authorities, the upper authorities viewed the common people and lower authorities as Watakushi (private) and as the landlord, connected by private dominance.</e>
<cmt>view→viewed&quot; &quot; 削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また、世間とは公（上位）と私（下位）が交錯する世界であり、そこに対しても（上位権力をも対象に含むことから）公儀と呼称する場合もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Seken (the world)&quot; was a place where Oyake (higher rank) and Watakushi (lower rank) mixed and in some cases it was also called Kogi (because it included the upper authorities).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Seken (the world)&quot; was a place where Oyake (higher rank) and Watakushi (lower rank) mixed and in some cases it was also called Kogi (because it included the upper authorities).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seken (the world) was a place where Oyake (higher rank) and Watakushi (lower rank) mixed and in some cases it was also called Kogi (because it included the upper authorities).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot; 削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>今日でも「世間」・「世間体」のことを公儀と呼ぶ用法が残っているのもその名残であるとも言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even now, the use of Kogi to mean &quot;Seken (the world)&quot; or &quot;Sekentai (decency)&quot; is a vestige of such usage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even now, the use of Kogi to mean &quot;Seken (the world)&quot; or &quot;Sekentai (decency)&quot; is a vestige of such usage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even now, the use of Kogi to mean &apos;Seken (the world)&apos; or &apos;Sekentei (decency)&apos; is a vestige of such usage.</e>
<cmt>Sekentai→Sekentei&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Areare(id:119960), タランチュラ(id:125720), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>