<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>日仏協約</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Franco-Japanese treaty</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Franco-Japanese treaty</e>
<cmt>原文の意味をより分かりやすくために訳文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Franco-Japanese treaty</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>日仏協約（にちふつきょうやく）とは、1907年6月10日にパリにおいて日本・フランス両国間で締結された条約。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Franco-Japanese treaty is a treaty concluded in Paris between Japan and France on June 10, 1907.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Franco-Japanese treaty is a treaty concluded in Paris between Japan and France on June 10, 1907.</e>
<cmt>原文の意味をより分かりやすくために訳文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Franco-Japanese treaty is a treaty concluded in Paris between Japan and France on June 10, 1907.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>駐フランス大使栗野慎一郎とフランス外相ステファン・ピションの間で調印され、アジアにおける両国の利益と安全保護を約束した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was signed by a taishi (commander-in-chief) to France, Shinichiro KURINO and French Foreign Minister, Stephin PICHON and insured a blessing and safety protection of the countries in Asia.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was signed by the Japanese ambassador to France, Shinichiro KURINO and French Foreign Minister, Stephin PICHON and insured profit and safety in Asia for both countries.</e>
<cmt>原文の意味をより分かりやすくために訳文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was signed by the Japanese ambassador to France, Shinichiro KURINO and French Foreign Minister, Stephin PICHON and insured profit and safety in Asia for both countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>これによってフランスは日本との関係を相互的最恵国待遇に引き上げることを同意する代わりに日本はフランスのインドシナ半島支配を容認して、ベトナム人留学生による日本を拠点とした独立運動（ドンズー運動）を取り締まることを約束した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By this, France agreed to apply the most favored nation status to Japan and instead, Japan allowed the occupation of Indochina by France, committed to crack down on Dokuryu (zen priest) movement by Vietnamese students which had its foothold in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the treaty, France agreed to give Japan exclusive favors, and in return Japan would recognize France&apos;s authority over Indochina and committed to cracking down on the independence movement (also called the Donzu movement) by Vietnamese students within Japan.</e>
<cmt>原文の意味をより分かりやすくために訳文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the treaty, France agreed to give Japan exclusive favors, and in return Japan would recognize France&apos;s authority over Indochina and committed to cracking down on the independence movement (also called the Donzu movement) by Vietnamese students within Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また、両国は清国の独立を保全するとともに清国内におけるお互いの勢力圏を認め合った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The countries also protected Dokuryu (zen priest) of Qing and as a result approved their influence areas to each other within Qing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The countries also guaranteed the independence of Qing, while at the same time recognizing each other&apos;s authority over different provinces within it.</e>
<cmt>原文の意味をより分かりやすくために訳文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The countries also guaranteed the independence of Qing, while at the same time recognizing each other&apos;s authority over different provinces within it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>これによってフランスは広東省・広西省・雲南省を、日本は満州と蒙古、それに秘密協定によって福建省を自国の勢力圏として相手国側に承認させたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By this, France made Japan approve Guangdong, Guanxi and Yunnan Province as its influence areas and Japan did the same for Manchuria and Menggu as well as Fujian Province by concluding a non-disclosure agreement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Through this treaty, both countries agreed to recognize France&apos;s authority over Guangdong, Guanxi and Yunnan Province, and Japan&apos;s authority over Manchuria and Menggu, and Fujian Province, the latter through a confidential agreement.</e>
<cmt>原文の意味をより分かりやすくために訳文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Through this treaty, both countries agreed to recognize France&apos;s authority over Guangdong, Guanxi and Yunnan Province, and Japan&apos;s authority over Manchuria and Menggu, and Fujian Province, the latter through a confidential agreement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>なお、フランス側が議会・世論対策のために自国マスコミに交渉内容をリークしたために、清国側からの抗議を受ける事態も生じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As France revealed the contents of the treaty to its mass media for the congress and taisaku (one of the examination for adopting government officials under the Ritsuryo legal codes), it even brought up the state of affairs where France was protested by Qing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When France leaked the contents of the treaty to the media to deal with congress and to boost public opinion, there was an outcry from the Qing dynasty.</e>
<cmt>原文の意味をより分かりやすくために訳文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When France leaked the contents of the treaty to the media to deal with congress and to boost public opinion, there was an outcry from the Qing dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また、この協定によって同年に日露協約を締結した日本は三国協商陣営の事実上の一員に加わることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan who concluded Japanese Russian treaty by the agreement in the same year became a member of the Entente camp of San Guo (Three Kingdoms) as a matter of fact.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan also concluded the Japanese-Russian Treaty in the same year and joined the Triple Entente.</e>
<cmt>原文の意味をより分かりやすくために訳文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan also concluded the Japanese-Russian Treaty in the same year and joined the Triple Entente.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>1941年の日本軍による仏印進駐によって事実上無効となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The treaty was invalidated by the occupation of Indochina by the Japanese army in 1941.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The treaty was declared void when Japenese troops entered and were stationed in French-occupied Indochina.</e>
<cmt>原文の意味をより分かりやすくために訳文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The treaty was declared void when Japenese troops entered and were stationed in French-occupied Indochina.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Straysheep(id:42448), SK(id:64397), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>