<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>1918年米騒動</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rice riots in 1918</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rice riots in 1918</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rice riots in 1918</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>1918年米騒動（1918ねんこめそうどう）とは、近世から近代にかけての日本における米価格急騰にともなう暴動。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The rice riots in 1918 were riots that lasted from the early-modern times to modern times due to a sharp rise in rice prices in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rice riots in 1918 were riots due to a sharp rise in rice prices in which lasted in prewar Japan from the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>日本での「近世」「近代」に言い換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rice riots in 1918 were riots due to a sharp rise in rice prices in which lasted in prewar Japan from the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>米価の暴騰</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sharp rise in rice prices</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sharp rise in rice prices</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sharp rise in rice prices</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>1914年の第一次世界大戦開始の直後に暴落した米価は、周りの物価が少しずつ上昇していく中で、約3年半の間ほぼ変わらない値段で推移していたが、1918年（大正7年）の中ごろから急激に上昇しはじめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A rice price which tumbled down just after the First World War had begun in 1914 was about the same for three and a half years although prices of other things gradually rose, however, from mid-1918, it started sharply rising.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A rice price which tumbled down just after the First World War had begun in 1914 was about the same for three and a half years although prices of other things gradually rose, however, from mid-1918, it started sharply rising.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A rice price which tumbled down just after the First World War had begun in 1914 was about the same for three and a half years although prices of other things gradually rose, however, from mid-1918, it started sharply rising.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>大阪堂島の堂島米会所の記録によれば、1918年の1月に1石15円だった米価は、6月には20円を超え、翌月7月17日には30円を超えるという異常事態になっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the record of Dojima rice exchange in Dojima, Osaka Prefecture, the rice price that had been 15 yen per 1 koku (about 180 liter; an old unit showing volume) in January, 1918 rose above 20 yen in June and then 30 yen on July 17, which was an abnormal circumstance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the record of Dojima rice exchange in Dojima, Osaka Prefecture, the rice price that had been 15 yen per 1 koku (about 180 liter; an old unit showing volume) in January, 1918 rose above 20 yen in June and then 30 yen on July 17, which was an abnormal circumstance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the record of Dojima rice exchange in Dojima, Osaka Prefecture, the rice price that had been 15 yen per 1 koku (about 180 liter; an old unit showing volume) in January, 1918 rose above 20 yen in June and then 30 yen on July 17, which was an abnormal circumstance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>（当時の一般社会人の月収が18円-25円）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Monthly income of the general public at that time was 18 yen to 25 yen.)</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Monthly income of the general public at that time was 18 yen to 25 yen.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>7月末から8月初めにかけては各地の取引所で立会い中止が相次ぎ、地方からの米の出回りが減じ、8月7日には白米小売相場は1升50銭に暴騰した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The retail price of polished rice soared to 50 sen (One sen is 1/100 of one yen) per 1 sho (1.8 liter) on August 7 since sessions on exchanges in various places were cancelled from the end of July to the beginning of August and the rice supply from the country was reduced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The retail price of polished rice soared to 50 sen (One sen is 1/100 of one yen) per 1 sho (1.8 liter) on August 7 since sessions on exchanges in various places were cancelled from the end of July to the beginning of August and the rice supply from the countryside was reduced.</e>
<cmt>「地方からの」をfrom the countrysideに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The retail price of polished rice soared to 50 sen (One sen is 1/100 of one yen) per 1 sho (1.8 liter) on August 7 since sessions on exchanges in various places were cancelled from the end of July to the beginning of August and the rice supply from the countryside was reduced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>この背景には資本主義の急速な発展が指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is pointed out that it was caused by the rapid development of capitalism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is pointed out that it was caused by the rapid development of capitalism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is pointed out that it was caused by the rapid development of capitalism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>第一次世界大戦の影響による好景気（大戦景気）は都市部の人口増加、工業労働者の増加をもたらしたほか、養蚕業などによる収入の増加があった農家は、これまでのムギやヒエといった食生活から米を食べる生活に変化していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The booming economy affected by the First World War (War economy) caused not only population growth of urban areas and increase of industrial laborers but also change of a diet that farmers whose income was increased by sericultural industry and so on started to eat rice, not barley or barnyard millet that they had used to have.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The booming economy affected by the First World War (War economy) caused not only population growth of urban areas and an increase of industrial laborers but also a change of a diet that farmers whose income was increased by sericultural industry and so on started to eat rice, not barley or barnyard millet that they had used to have.</e>
<cmt>increaseとchangeに冠詞を補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The booming economy affected by the First World War (War economy) caused not only population growth of urban areas and an increase of industrial laborers but also a change of a diet that farmers whose income was increased by sericultural industry and so on started to eat rice, not barley or barnyard millet that they had used to have.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>このように、農業界からの人材流出と米の消費量の増加が続いた事に加え、大戦の影響によって米の輸入量が減少した事も重なり、米価暴騰の原因となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, the sharp rise in rice prices was caused by decrease in the amount of rice imports due to the influence of the War in addition to the loss of personnel from the farming industry and the increase in consumption of rice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, the sharp rise in rice prices was caused by decreased amount of imported rice due to the influence of the War in addition to the loss of personnel from the farming industry and the increase in consumption of rice.</e>
<cmt>decrease in the amount ofをdecreased amount ofに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, the sharp rise in rice prices was caused by decreased amount of imported rice due to the influence of the War in addition to the loss of personnel from the farming industry and the increase in consumption of rice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>国の対応</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Measurements taken by the government</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Measurements taken by the government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Measurements taken by the government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>米価格が高騰することにより、地主や商人は米を投機へまわすようになり、次第に売り惜しみや買い占めが発生しはじめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the rice price soared, landlords and merchants started to speculate in rice and gradually withholding of rice and the buyout occurred.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the rice price soared, landlords and merchants started to speculate in rice and gradually withholding of rice and the buyout occurred.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the rice price soared, landlords and merchants started to speculate in rice and gradually withholding of rice and the buyout occurred.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>事態を重く見た仲小路廉農商務省 (日本)は1917年9月1日に「暴利取締令」を出し、米、鉄、石炭、綿、紙、染料、薬品の買い占め、売り惜しみを禁止したが、効果はなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ren NAKASHOJI, the minister of Agriculture and Commerce, who took the matter seriously issued the &apos;Bori (Excessive profits) act&apos; on September 1, 1917 and prohibited to buy up and withhold rice, iron, coal, cotton, paper, dye and medicines but was not successful.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ren NAKASHOJI, the minister of Agriculture and Commerce, who took the matter seriously, issued the &apos;Bori (Excessive profits) act&apos; against cornering and speculative stocking of rice, iron, coal, cotton, paper, dye and medicines on September 1, 1917 but it was not successful.</e>
<cmt>後半を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ren NAKASHOJI, the minister of Agriculture and Commerce, who took the matter seriously, issued the &apos;Bori (Excessive profits) act&apos; against cornering and speculative stocking of rice, iron, coal, cotton, paper, dye and medicines on September 1, 1917 but it was not successful.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>常軌を逸した商魂を表わす口語の動詞「ぼる」「ぼられる」（暴る、暴られる）は、この暴利取締令の「暴利」に由来する（広辞苑）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The colloquial verbs &apos;boru (rip off)&apos; and &apos;borareru (ripped off) expressing the extraordinary commercially-minded behavior derives from the &apos;bori&apos; of this Bori act. (From Kojien dictionary)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The colloquial verbs &apos;boru (rip off)&apos; and &apos;borareru (ripped off)&apos; expressing the extraordinary commercially-minded behavior derive from the &apos;bori&apos; of this Bori act (From Kojien dictionary).</e>
<cmt>動詞の人称を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The colloquial verbs &apos;boru (rip off)&apos; and &apos;borareru (ripped off)&apos; expressing the extraordinary commercially-minded behavior derive from the &apos;bori&apos; of this Bori act (From Kojien dictionary).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>1918年4月には「外米管理令」が公布され、三井物産、鈴木商店など指定七社による外国米の大量輸入が実施されたが、米価引下げには至らなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April, 1918, the &apos;Foreign Rice Regulations Ordinance&apos; was issued and mass of foreign rice was imported by the seven designated companies such as Mitsui &amp; Co., Ltd. and Suzuki&apos;s, however, the rice price did not drop.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April, 1918, the &apos;Foreign Rice Regulations Ordinance&apos; was issued and mass of foreign rice was imported by the seven designated companies including Mitsui &amp; Co., Ltd. and Suzuki &amp; Co., however, the rice price did not drop.</e>
<cmt>「鈴木商店など」を言い換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April, 1918, the &apos;Foreign Rice Regulations Ordinance&apos; was issued and mass of foreign rice was imported by the seven designated companies including Mitsui &amp; Co., Ltd. and Suzuki &amp; Co., however, the rice price did not drop.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>社会不安</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Social anxiety</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Social anxiety</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Social anxiety</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>米価の暴騰は一般市民の生活を苦しめ、新聞が連日米の価格高騰を知らせ煽った事もあり、社会不安を増大させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sharp rise in rice prices made ordinary citizens&apos; lives hard and grew the social anxiety since the newspapers reported the rise in rice prices daily and fueled it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sharp rise in rice prices made ordinary citizens&apos; lives hard and grew the social anxiety since the newspapers reported the rise in rice prices daily and fueled it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sharp rise in rice prices made ordinary citizens&apos; lives hard and grew the social anxiety since the newspapers reported the rise in rice prices daily and fueled it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>寺内正毅内閣総理大臣は1918年5月の地方長官会議にて国民生活難に関して言及したが、その年の予算予算編成において救済事業奨励費はわずか35,000円のみであり、寺内の憂慮を反映した予算編成になっているとは言えなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prime minister Masatake TERAUCHI had mentioned the hard living of citizens at the provincial governor meeting held in 1918 but Grant-in-Aid for relief work in budgeting of that year was only 35,000 yen, so his worry was not particularly reflected to the budgeting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Prime minister Masatake TERAUCHI had mentioned the hard living of citizens at the provincial governor meeting held in 1918, the grant-in-aid for the relief work in budgeting of that year was only 35,000 yen and his worry was not particularly reflected to the budgeting.</e>
<cmt>Althoughを補足し、「救済事業奨励費」を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Prime minister Masatake TERAUCHI had mentioned the hard living of citizens at the provincial governor meeting held in 1918, the grant-in-aid for the relief work in budgeting of that year was only 35,000 yen and his worry was not particularly reflected to the budgeting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>この為、警察の増加をもって社会情勢の不安を抑え込む方針が取られ、それまで5,300人であった巡査を3,000人増員するという措置が取られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, the policy to quell fears of the social situation by increasing the number of police officers was taken and 3,000 patrol officers were added to the 5,300 officers already existing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, the policy to quell fears of the social situation by increasing the number of police officers was adopted and 3,000 patrol officers were added to the 5,300 officers already existing.</e>
<cmt>takenをadoptedに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, the policy to quell fears of the social situation by increasing the number of police officers was adopted and 3,000 patrol officers were added to the 5,300 officers already existing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>労働者の労働基本権日本における労働基本権すらなかったこの時代、厳しい抑圧と、苦しい生活に喘ぐ一般庶民の怒りの矛先は、次第に高所得者、とくに米問屋や商人に向けられるようになっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In times like that when there was not even basic labor rights, the common people who struggled against hard suppression and living directed their anger to high-income people, especially rice warehouse merchants and merchants gradually.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In times like that when there were not even basic labor rights in Japan, the common people who struggled against hard suppression and living directed their anger to high-income people, especially rice marketers and merchants gradually.</e>
<cmt>Webでは「労働者の団結権すらなかったこの時代」で始まっていますが、この原文に即して訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In times like that when there were not even basic labor rights in Japan, the common people who struggled against hard suppression and living directed their anger to high-income people, especially rice marketers and merchants gradually.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>シベリア出兵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dispatch of troops to Siberia</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dispatch of troops to Siberia</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dispatch of troops to Siberia</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>米価が徐々に上昇していく中、寺内内閣は1918年8月2日、対外政策としてシベリア出兵を宣言した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the rice price was gradually rising, Terauchi cabinet announced the dispatch of troops to Siberia as foreign policy on August 2, 1918.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the rice price was gradually rising, the Terauchi Cabinet announced the dispatch of troops to Siberia as the foreign policy on August 2, 1918.</e>
<cmt>定冠詞を補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the rice price was gradually rising, the Terauchi Cabinet announced the dispatch of troops to Siberia as the foreign policy on August 2, 1918.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>この宣言は流通業者や商人などが戦争特需における物資高騰を狙い、売り惜しみをさらに加速させていくという状況を発生させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This announcement caused the situation which distributors and merchants sought steep price rise of goods by war-time special procurements and further accelerated the withholding.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This announcement caused the situation which distributors and merchants sought steep price rise of goods by war-time special procurements and further accelerated the withholding.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This announcement caused the situation which distributors and merchants sought steep price rise of goods by war-time special procurements and further accelerated the withholding.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>事実、神戸市米会所における相場では7月2日に1升34銭3厘だった相場が8月1日には40銭5厘、8月9日は60銭8厘と急騰している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, in the market price at Kobe City rice exchange, the price which had been 34 sen 3 rin (one-hundredth) per 1 sho on July 2 soared to 40 sen 5 rin on August 1 and to 60 sen 8 rin on August 9.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, in the market price at Kobe City rice exchange, the price which had been 34 sen 3 rin (one-hundredth) per 1 sho on July 2 soared to 40 sen 5 rin on August 1 and to 60 sen 8 rin on August 9.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, in the market price at Kobe City rice exchange, the price which had been 34 sen 3 rin (one-hundredth) per 1 sho on July 2 soared to 40 sen 5 rin on August 1 and to 60 sen 8 rin on August 9.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>また、時を前後して富山県での騒動が発生していることなどから、シベリア出兵と米騒動の直接的な因果関係を指摘するものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, since a riot occurred in Toyama Prefecture coincidentally, some pointed out the direct consequence between the dispatch of troops to Siberia and the rice riot.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, since a riot occurred in Toyama Prefecture coincidentally, some pointed out the direct consequence between the dispatch of troops to Siberia and the rice riot.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, since a riot occurred in Toyama Prefecture coincidentally, some pointed out the direct consequence between the dispatch of troops to Siberia and the rice riot.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>米騒動の発生</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Occurrence of the rice riot</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Occurrence of the rice riot</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Occurrence of the rice riot</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>1918年7月22日の夜間、富山県下新川郡魚津町の魚津港に、北海道への米の輸送を行うため、「伊吹丸」が寄航。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At night on July 22, 1918, &apos;Ibukimaru&apos; ship made a port call to Uozu Port in Uozu town, Shimoniikawa District, Toyama Prefecture to transport rice to Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At night on July 22, 1918, &apos;Ibukimaru&apos; ship made a port call at Uozu Port in Uozu town, Shimoniikawa County, Toyama Prefecture to transport rice to Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt>「郡」をCountyに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At night on July 22, 1918, &apos;Ibukimaru&apos; ship made a port call at Uozu Port in Uozu town, Shimoniikawa County, Toyama Prefecture to transport rice to Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>伊吹丸への荷積みを行っていた十二銀行の倉庫前へ魚津町の主婦ら十数人が集まり、米の船積みを中止し、住民に販売するよう求める嘆願がなされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dozens of housewives and others who lived in Uozu town gathered in front of a warehouse of Juni Bank where loading to Ibukimaru was done, and pleaded to cancel the loading of rice and sell it to people.</e>
<cmt>「十二銀行」読み・定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">More than a dozen housewives and others who lived in Uozu town gathered in front of a warehouse of Juni Bank where Ibukimaru had been loaded, and they pleaded to cancel the loading of rice and sell it to people.</e>
<cmt>「十数人」「荷積み」を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">More than a dozen housewives and others who lived in Uozu town gathered in front of a warehouse of Juni Bank where Ibukimaru had been loaded, and they pleaded to cancel the loading of rice and sell it to people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>この時は巡回中の警官によって解散させられたが、住民らは集会をはじめるなど、米の販売を要望する人数はさらに増加していき、翌月8月3日には中新川郡水橋町で200名弱の町民が集結し、米問屋や資産家に対し米の移出を停止し、販売するよう嘆願した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, they had been broken up by patrolling officers, but people started to have meetings and the number of people who demanded to sell rice increased further, and moreover, on August 3, under 200 residents gathered in Mizuhashi-machi town, Nakaniikawa District and asked rice warehouse merchants and wealthy people to stop transporting rice and sell it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They had been broken up by patrolling officers at that time, but people started to have meetings and the number of people who demanded to sell rice increased further, and moreover, nearly 200 residents gathered in Mizuhashi-machi town, Nakaniikawa County on August 3 to ask rice marketers and wealthy people to stop transporting rice and sell it.</e>
<cmt>「200名弱」をnearly 200 residentsに、「郡」をCountyに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They had been broken up by patrolling officers at that time, but people started to have meetings and the number of people who demanded to sell rice increased further, and moreover, nearly 200 residents gathered in Mizuhashi-machi town, Nakaniikawa County on August 3 to ask rice marketers and wealthy people to stop transporting rice and sell it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="24">
<j>8月6日にはこの運動はさらに激しさを増し、水橋町、滑川市の住民も巻き込み、1,000名を超える事態となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 6, the movement increasingly escalated and the number of people who joined it became over 1,000 involving residents in Mizuhashi-machi town and Namegawa City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 6, the movement increasingly escalated and over 1,000 people including residents in Mizuhashi-machi town and Namerikawa City joined it.</e>
<cmt>後半を簡略化しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 6, the movement increasingly escalated and over 1,000 people including residents in Mizuhashi-machi town and Namerikawa City joined it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>住民らは米の移出を実力行使で阻止し、当時1升40銭から50銭の相場だった米を35銭で販売させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They prevented the rice transportation by force and forced to sell rice, which had been from 40 sen to 50 sen at that time, for 35 sen per 1 sho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They prevented the rice transportation by force and forced a sale of rice, which had been from 40 sen to 50 sen per 1 sho at that time, for 35 sen.</e>
<cmt>後半を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They prevented the rice transportation by force and forced a sale of rice, which had been from 40 sen to 50 sen per 1 sho at that time, for 35 sen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="26">
<j>この件は地方新聞を通じ、全国の新聞に「越中女一揆」として報道された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This movement was reported as &apos;Uprising of women in Ecchu Province&apos; in nationwide newspaper via local paper.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This movement was reported as &apos;Uprising of women in Ecchu Province&apos; in nationwide newspaper via local paper.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This movement was reported as &apos;Uprising of women in Ecchu Province&apos; in nationwide newspaper via local paper.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>米騒動の始まりであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was the beginning of the rice riots.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the beginning of the rice riots.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the beginning of the rice riots.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>騒動の広がり</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Spread of the riots</e>
<cmt>記入するセルが違います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Spread of the riots</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>米価の暴騰はとどまりを見せず、1918年8月1日には1石35円を超え、同5日には40円を超え、9日には50円を超えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sharp rise in rice prices never stopped and it rose above 35 yen per 1 koku on August 1, 1918, 40 yen on August 5 and to over 50 yen on August 9.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sharp rise in rice prices never stopped and it rose above 35 yen per 1 koku on August 1, 1918, 40 yen on August 5 and to over 50 yen on August 9.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sharp rise in rice prices never stopped and it rose above 35 yen per 1 koku on August 1, 1918, 40 yen on August 5 and to over 50 yen on August 9.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>8月10日には京都市と名古屋市を皮切りに全国の主要都市で米騒動が発生する形となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 10, rice riots broke out in major cities, starting with Kyoto City and Nagoya City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 10, rice riots broke out in major cities, starting with Kyoto City and Nagoya City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 10, rice riots broke out in major cities, starting with Kyoto City and Nagoya City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>米騒動は移出の取りやめ、安売りの哀願から始まり、要求は次第に寄付の強要、打ちこわしに発展した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Initially, they asked to cancel the transportation of rice and to sell cheap but gradually they enforced a donation and the riots grew into Uchikowashi (it refers to an act where people destroyed residences of privileged merchants or officials who were involved in misgovernment).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially, the rice riots started to ask to cancel the transportation of rice and to sell it cheap, but gradually led to the enforcement of donation and grew into Uchikowashi (it refers to an act where people destroyed residences of privileged merchants or officials who were involved in misgovernment).</e>
<cmt>主語をthe rice riotsにして訳し換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially, the rice riots started to ask to cancel the transportation of rice and to sell it cheap, but gradually led to the enforcement of donation and grew into Uchikowashi (it refers to an act where people destroyed residences of privileged merchants or officials who were involved in misgovernment).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>10日夜に名古屋鶴舞公園において米価問題に関する市民大会が開かれるとの噂が広まり、約20,000人の群集が集結した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rumors got out that a citizens&apos; rally about a rice price issue was held in Tsuruma Park of Nagaya City at night on 10 and approximately 20,000 people gathered there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As it was rumored that a citizens&apos; rally about a rice price issue was held in Tsuruma Park of Nagoya City on the night of the 10th, approximately 20,000 people gathered there.</e>
<cmt>前半を言い換え、スペルミスを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As it was rumored that a citizens&apos; rally about a rice price issue was held in Tsuruma Park of Nagoya City on the night of the 10th, approximately 20,000 people gathered there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>同じく京都では柳原において騒動が始まり、米問屋を打ちこわすなどして1升30銭での販売を強要した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, a riot started in Yanagihara, Kyoto City and they destroyed rice warehouse merchants and forced to sell rice for 30 sen per 1 sho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, a riot started in Yanagihara, Kyoto City, which destroyed rice warehouse merchants and forced a sale of rice for 30 sen per 1 sho.</e>
<cmt>後半を言い換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, a riot started in Yanagihara, Kyoto City, which destroyed rice warehouse merchants and forced a sale of rice for 30 sen per 1 sho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="33">
<j>こうした「値下げを強要すれば安く米が手に入る」という実績は瞬く間に市から市へと広がり、8月17日頃からは都市部から町や農村へ、そして8月20日までにほぼ全国へ波及した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus this achievement which was &apos;if we enforce price reduction, we can get rice at a low price&apos; spread from city to city immediately, and from around August 17, riots spread from urban areas to town or agricultural community and then reached almost everywhere in the country by August 20.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus this achievement which was &apos;if we enforce price reduction, we can get rice at a low price&apos; spread from city to city immediately, and from around August 17, riots spread from urban areas to town or agricultural community and then reached almost everywhere in the country by August 20.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus this achievement which was &apos;if we enforce price reduction, we can get rice at a low price&apos; spread from city to city immediately, and from around August 17, riots spread from urban areas to town or agricultural community and then reached almost everywhere in the country by August 20.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>騒動は次第に米問屋から炭坑へと場所を移し、9月12日の三井三池炭鉱の騒動終了まで、50日間を数えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The riots gradually moved from rice warehouse merchants to coal mines and it took 50 days until the riot in Mitsui Miike coal mine ended on September 12.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The riots gradually moved from rice warehouse merchants to coal mines and it took 50 days until the riot in Mitsui Miike coal mine ended on September 12.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The riots gradually moved from rice warehouse merchants to coal mines and it took 50 days until the riot in Mitsui Miike coal mine ended on September 12.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>炭坑への飛び火</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Spillover to coal mines</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Spillover to coal mines</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Spillover to coal mines</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="35">
<j>8月17日以降には米騒動は山口県や北九州の炭坑騒動へ飛び火する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After August 17, the rice riots spilled over to coal mines riots in Yamaguchi Prefecture and Kitakyushu region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After August 17, the rice riots spilled over to coal mines riots in Yamaguchi Prefecture and Kitakyushu region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After August 17, the rice riots spilled over to coal mines riots in Yamaguchi Prefecture and Kitakyushu region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>山口県沖の山炭坑、福岡県峰地炭坑などにおいて炭坑夫の賃上げ要求が暴動に転化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Demands for higher wages by coal miners in Okinoyama coal mine off the coast of Yamaguchi Prefecture, Minechi coal mine of Fukuoka Prefecture and so on changed to riots.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Demands for higher wages by coal miners in Okinoyama coal mine of Yamaguchi Prefecture, Minechi coal mine of Fukuoka Prefecture and so on changed into riots.</e>
<cmt>「沖の山炭坑」を言い換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Demands for higher wages by coal miners in Okinoyama coal mine of Yamaguchi Prefecture, Minechi coal mine of Fukuoka Prefecture and so on changed into riots.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>沖の山炭坑の騒動は付近住民を加えた数千人規模の騒動に発展し、米問屋、屋敷の打ちこわしや遊廓への放火などが起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The riot in Okinoyama coal mine developed into a riot of several thousand people including local residents and Uchikowashi of rice warehouse merchants and residences and arson to brothels took place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the riot in Okinoyama coal mine developed into a riot of several thousand people including local residents, Uchikowashi of rice warehouse merchants and residences and arsons to brothels took place.</e>
<cmt>Whileで言い換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the riot in Okinoyama coal mine developed into a riot of several thousand people including local residents, Uchikowashi of rice warehouse merchants and residences and arsons to brothels took place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>出動した軍隊に対してもダイナマイトで対抗するなど、死者13名を数える惨事となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It became a disaster which killed over 13 people since they countered the armies who were called out with dynamite.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It became a disaster which killed over 13 people since they countered the armies who were called out with dynamite.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It became a disaster which killed over 13 people since they countered the armies who were called out with dynamite.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>騒動の発生地域・参加人員と軍隊出動、検挙者の処遇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Area where riots occurred, participants and call-out of armies and treatment of people under arrest</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Area where riots occurred, participants and call-out of armies and treatment of people under arrest</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Area where riots occurred, participants and call-out of armies and treatment of people under arrest</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="39">
<j>「米騒動」や「米騒擾」などと呼ばれた約50日間に渡る一連の騒動は最終的に、1道3府37県の計369ヶ所にのぼり、参加者の規模は数百万人を数え、出動した軍隊は3府23県にわたり10万人以上が投入された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A series of riots for about 50 days called &apos;Rice riot&apos; or &apos;Rice civil disorder&apos; eventually occurred in 369 prefectures in total, and millions of participants were counted, the armies were called out to 26 prefectures in total and more than 100,000 soldiers were put.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A series of riots for about 50 days called &apos;Rice riot&apos; or &apos;Rice civil disorder&apos; eventually occurred in 369 places of 41 prefectures in total, for which millions of participants were counted, the armies were called out to 26 prefectures in total and more than 100,000 soldiers were put.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A series of riots for about 50 days called &apos;Rice riot&apos; or &apos;Rice civil disorder&apos; eventually occurred in 369 places of 41 prefectures in total, for which millions of participants were counted, the armies were called out to 26 prefectures in total and more than 100,000 soldiers were put.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>呉市では、海軍陸戦隊が出動し、民衆と対峙するなか、銃剣で刺されたことによる死者が少なくとも２名でたことが報告されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kure City, it was reported that Naval Landing Forces were called out and when they confronted the people, at least 2 people died by stabbing with a bayonet drill.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was reported that at least 2 people were killed by a bayonet in Kure City while Naval Landing Forces were called out and facing the people,</e>
<cmt>簡略化しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was reported that at least 2 people were killed by a bayonet in Kure City while Naval Landing Forces were called out and facing the people,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>検挙された人員は25,000人を超え、8253名が検事処分を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of people who had been arrested were over 25,000 and 8,253 people faced punishment by the prosecutor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of people who had been arrested were over 25,000 and 8,253 people of them faced punishment by the prosecutor.</e>
<cmt>8,253 people of themとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of people who had been arrested were over 25,000 and 8,253 people of them faced punishment by the prosecutor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>また7786名が起訴され、第一審での無期懲役が12名、10年以上の有期刑が59名を数えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, 7,786 people were charged, as a result, 12 people were sentenced to life in prison in the first instance and 59 people were sentenced to imprisonment for more than 10 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, among 7,786 people who were charged, 12 people were sentenced to life in prison in the first instance and 59 people were sentenced to imprisonment for more than 10 years.</e>
<cmt>前半を言い換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, among 7,786 people who were charged, 12 people were sentenced to life in prison in the first instance and 59 people were sentenced to imprisonment for more than 10 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>米騒動には統一的な指導者は存在しなかったが、一部民衆を扇動したとして和歌山県で2名が死刑の判決を受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was no unified leader in rice riots, however, 2 people got a death penalty in Wakayama Prefecture for encouraging some people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there was no unified leader in rice riots, 2 people got a death penalty in Wakayama Prefecture for encouraging some people.</e>
<cmt>Althoughで言い換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there was no unified leader in rice riots, 2 people got a death penalty in Wakayama Prefecture for encouraging some people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>被差別部落との関わり</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Involvement with discriminated communities called buraku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Involvement with discriminated communities called buraku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Involvement with discriminated communities called buraku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="44">
<j>米騒動での検事処分者は8185人におよび、被差別部落からはそのうちの1割を超える処分者が出た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of people who faced punishment by a prosecutor were 8,185 in rice riots and more than 10 percent of them were from the discriminated communities called buraku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of people who faced punishment by a prosecutor were 8,185 in rice riots and more than 10 percent of them were from the discriminated communities called buraku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of people who faced punishment by a prosecutor were 8,185 in rice riots and more than 10 percent of them were from the discriminated communities called buraku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>1割は人口比率に対して格別に多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 10 percent was large in particular against the population ratio.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 10 percent was large in particular against the population ratio.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 10 percent was large in particular against the population ratio.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>これは被差別部落民が米商の投機買いによる最大の被害者層であったからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is because people from discriminated communities called buraku were the heaviest sufferers by speculative buying of rice merchants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because people from discriminated communities called buraku were the heaviest sufferers by speculative buying of rice merchants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because people from discriminated communities called buraku were the heaviest sufferers by speculative buying of rice merchants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>処分は死刑をも含む重いものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The punishment was harsh and included a death penalty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The punishment was harsh and included a death penalty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The punishment was harsh and included a death penalty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>1920年、事態を重く見た原敬内閣は部落改善費5万円を計上し、部落改善のための最初の国庫支出を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1920, Takashi HARA cabinet budgeted 50,000 yen for buraku (hamlet) improvement cost and did first treasury payment to improve the buraku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1920, the Takashi HARA Cabinet budgeted 50,000 yen for buraku (hamlet) improvement cost and did first treasury payment to improve the buraku.</e>
<cmt>定冠詞を補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1920, the Takashi HARA Cabinet budgeted 50,000 yen for buraku (hamlet) improvement cost and did first treasury payment to improve the buraku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>同年、内務省は省内に社会局を設置し、府県などの地方庁にも社会課を設けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, Ministry of Interior established Department of Social Affairs in the ministry and also Division of Social Affairs in intendance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, Ministry of Interior established Department of Social Affairs in the ministry and also Division of Social Affairs in intendance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, Ministry of Interior established Department of Social Affairs in the ministry and also Division of Social Affairs in intendance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>軍人の参加、警官による暴動への加担</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Participation of military men and support in riots by police officers</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Participation of military men and support in riots by police officers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Participation of military men and support in riots by police officers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="50">
<j>呉市では、水兵が騒動に参加して検挙された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kure City, sailors were arrested since they participated in the riots.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kure City, sailors were arrested since they participated in the riots.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kure City, sailors were arrested since they participated in the riots.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>また、一部の地域では制止すべき警官が暴動を黙認した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, in some regions, police officers who should have stopped riots tolerated the riots.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, in some regions, police officers who should have stopped riots tolerated the riots.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, in some regions, police officers who should have stopped riots tolerated the riots.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>政府対応</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Governmental response</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Governmental response</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Governmental response</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="52">
<j>政府は8月13日に1000万円の国費を米価対策資金として支出する事を発表し、各都道府県に向けて米の安売りを実施させたが、騒動の結果、米価が下落したとの印象があるとの理由から8月28日にはこの指令を撤回し、安売りを打ち切った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 13, the government announced that they would spend the national treasury of 10 million yen as money for rice price and ordered each local government to sell rice at a cheap price, but took the order back and stopped the discount on August 28 since they judged that the rice price seemed to drop as a result of riots.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 13, the government announced that they would spend the national treasury of 10 million yen as money for rice price and ordered each local government to sell rice at a cheap price, but took the order back and stopped the discount on August 28 since they judged that the rice price seemed to drop as a result of riots.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 13, the government announced that they would spend the national treasury of 10 million yen as money for rice price and ordered each local government to sell rice at a cheap price, but took the order back and stopped the discount on August 28 since they judged that the rice price seemed to drop as a result of riots.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>結果として発表時の4割程度の支出に留まり、米価格の下落には至らず、1918年末には米騒動当時の価格まで上昇したが、国民の実質収入増加によって騒動が再発することはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, as only about 40 percent of 10 million yen were spent, the rice price did not drop and soared to the price during the rice riots at the end of 1918, however, riots never occurred again since people&apos;s actual income had increased.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As only about 40 percent of the announced budget were eventually spent, the rice price did not drop but rose to the price during the rice riots in the end of 1918, but riots never occurred any more since people&apos;s actual income had increased.</e>
<cmt>As節内を変更し、howeverをbutに置き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As only about 40 percent of the announced budget were eventually spent, the rice price did not drop but rose to the price during the rice riots in the end of 1918, but riots never occurred any more since people&apos;s actual income had increased.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>全国中等学校優勝野球大会の中止</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cancellation of National junior-high school baseball tournament</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cancellation of National junior-high school baseball tournament</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cancellation of National junior-high school baseball tournament</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="54">
<j>この騒動は、全国高等学校野球選手権大会にも影響を及ぼした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The riot also affected the national junior-high school baseball tournament.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The riot also affected the national high school baseball tournament.</e>
<cmt>junior-high schooljをhigh schoolに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The riot also affected the national high school baseball tournament.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>8月11日に神戸市で始まった騒動により、当時の会場だった鳴尾球場に程近い鈴木商店で焼き打ち事件が発生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Triggered by the riot which had started in Kobe City on August 11, a torching incident occurred at Suzuki&apos;s very close to Naruo stadium which was the venue of the tournament at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Triggered by the riot which had started in Kobe City on August 11, a torching incident occurred at Suzuki &amp; Co. which was very close to Naruo stadium which was the venue of the tournament at that time.</e>
<cmt>「鈴木商店」を言い換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Triggered by the riot which had started in Kobe City on August 11, a torching incident occurred at Suzuki &amp; Co. which was very close to Naruo stadium which was the venue of the tournament at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>周辺の治安も大幅に悪化し、8月14日からの開催予定だった第4回全国中等学校優勝野球大会は一旦延期された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As public security around there significantly deteriorated, the national junior-high school baseball tournament scheduled for August 14 was put off once.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As public security in the area significantly deteriorated, the national junior-high school baseball tournament scheduled for August 14 was put off once.</e>
<cmt>「周辺の」を言い換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As public security in the area significantly deteriorated, the national junior-high school baseball tournament scheduled for August 14 was put off once.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>その後も治安改善の見通しが立たなかったため、8月16日に大会の中止が決定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cancellation of the tournament was determined on August 16 since it was uncertain when the public security could be improved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cancellation of the tournament was determined on August 16 since it was uncertain when the public security could be improved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cancellation of the tournament was determined on August 16 since it was uncertain when the public security could be improved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>騒動の起こった都市</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cities where riots occurred</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cities where riots occurred</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cities where riots occurred</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="58">
<j>『米騒動の研究』- 井上清、渡部徹編より、発生した都市を日付順に並べた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cities where riots occurred are listed by date as below based on &apos;A study of rice riots&apos; edited by Kiyoshi INOUE and Toru WATANABE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cities where riots occurred are listed by date as below based on &quot;A study of rice riots&quot; edited by Kiyoshi INOUE and Toru WATANABE.</e>
<cmt>&quot;&quot;に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cities where riots occurred are listed by date as below based on &quot;A study of rice riots&quot; edited by Kiyoshi INOUE and Toru WATANABE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="59">
<j>8月11日大阪市、神戸市</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 11, Osaka City and Kobe City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 11, Osaka City and Kobe City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 11, Osaka City and Kobe City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>8月13日東京市、福島市、豊橋市、岐阜市、大津市、富山市、高岡市、金沢市、福井市、和歌山市、堺市、尼崎市、姫路市、岡山市、尾道市、呉市、広島市、鳥取市、高松市、丸亀市、高知市</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 13, Tokyo City, Fukushima City, Toyohashi City, Gifu City, Otsu City, Toyama City, Takaoka City, Kanazawa City, Fukui City, Wakayama City, Sakai City, Amagasaki City, Himeji City, Okayama City, Onomichi City, Kure City, Hiroshima City, Tottori City, Takamatsu City, Marugame City and Kochi City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 13, Tokyo City, Fukushima City, Toyohashi City, Gifu City, Otsu City, Toyama City, Takaoka City, Kanazawa City, Fukui City, Wakayama City, Sakai City, Amagasaki City, Himeji City, Okayama City, Onomichi City, Kure City, Hiroshima City, Tottori City, Takamatsu City, Marugame City and Kochi City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 13, Tokyo City, Fukushima City, Toyohashi City, Gifu City, Otsu City, Toyama City, Takaoka City, Kanazawa City, Fukui City, Wakayama City, Sakai City, Amagasaki City, Himeji City, Okayama City, Onomichi City, Kure City, Hiroshima City, Tottori City, Takamatsu City, Marugame City and Kochi City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>8月14日浜松市、岡崎市、奈良市、福山市</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 14, Hamamatsu City, Okazaki City, Nara City and Fukuyama City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 14, Hamamatsu City, Okazaki City, Nara City and Fukuyama City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 14, Hamamatsu City, Okazaki City, Nara City and Fukuyama City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>8月15日仙台市、若松市、横浜市、横須賀市、甲府市、津市、松山市、門司市</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 15, Sendai City, Wakamatsu City, Yokohama City, Yokosuka City, Kofu City, Tsu City, Matsuyama City and Moji City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 15, Sendai City, Wakamatsu City, Yokohama City, Yokosuka City, Kofu City, Tsu City, Matsuyama City and Moji City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 15, Sendai City, Wakamatsu City, Yokohama City, Yokosuka City, Kofu City, Tsu City, Matsuyama City and Moji City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>8月16日下関市、小倉市</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 16, Shimonoseki City and Kokura City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 16, Shimonoseki City and Kokura City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 16, Shimonoseki City and Kokura City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>8月17日新潟市、長岡市、長野市</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 17, Niigata City, Nagaoka City and Nagano City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 17, Niigata City, Nagaoka City and Nagano City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 17, Niigata City, Nagaoka City and Nagano City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>8月20日佐世保市、熊本市、松江市、大垣市</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 20, Sasebo City, Kumamoto City, Matsue City and Ogaki City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 20, Sasebo City, Kumamoto City, Matsue City and Ogaki City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 20, Sasebo City, Kumamoto City, Matsue City and Ogaki City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>言論弾圧</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suppression of free speech</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suppression of free speech</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suppression of free speech</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="66">
<j>米騒動の報道に際し、各種新聞は民衆の行動を好意的に報じると共に、根本的な原因は民衆の要求を無視し続けた政府にあるとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding press report of rice riots, each newspaper reported the people&apos;s behavior positively and also that the underlying cause was the government since they had continued to ignore people&apos;s demands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding press report of rice riots, each newspaper reported the people&apos;s behavior positively and also that the underlying cause was the government since they had continued to ignore people&apos;s demands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding press report of rice riots, each newspaper reported the people&apos;s behavior positively and also that the underlying cause was the government since they had continued to ignore people&apos;s demands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>一方政府は事件が広がったのは新聞が誇大に報道したためであるとし、8月7日に『高岡新報』を発禁処分にしたのをはじめ、8月14日には米騒動に関する一切の報道を禁じる記事差止命令を報道各社へ通達した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrast, the government insisted that the movements were spread since newspaper had reported them exaggeratedly, so they shut down &quot;Takaoka Shinpo&quot; (newspaper) on August 7 and issued an injunction against articles which banned any reports about the rice riots to media organizations on August 14.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast, the government insisted that the movements were spread since newspaper had reported them exaggeratedly, so they shut down &quot;Takaoka Shinpo&quot; (newspaper) on August 7 and issued an injunction against articles about the rice riots to media organizations on August 14.</e>
<cmt>不要箇所を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast, the government insisted that the movements were spread since newspaper had reported them exaggeratedly, so they shut down &quot;Takaoka Shinpo&quot; (newspaper) on August 7 and issued an injunction against articles about the rice riots to media organizations on August 14.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="68">
<j>東京春秋会（新聞社複数社で結成された連合）はこのような政府の処分に対し取り消しを要求し、水野錬太郎内務大臣 (日本)は「内務省 (日本)発表の公報情報のみ掲載を認める」と柔化させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokyo Shunju Kai (a combination made up of various newspaper companies) demanded a retraction of this punishment by the government, as a result, Rentaro MIZUNO, prewar Minister of Home Affairs, relaxed the ban that &apos;only official information announced by prewar Ministry of Home Affairs could be published&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokyo Shunju Kai (a combination made up of various newspaper companies) demanded a retraction of this punishment by the government, as a result, Rentaro MIZUNO, prewar Minister of Home Affairs, relaxed the ban that &apos;only official information announced by prewar Ministry of Home Affairs could be published&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokyo Shunju Kai (a combination made up of various newspaper companies) demanded a retraction of this punishment by the government, as a result, Rentaro MIZUNO, prewar Minister of Home Affairs, relaxed the ban that &apos;only official information announced by prewar Ministry of Home Affairs could be published&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>しかし、政府発表情報があまりに事実と反していた事から春秋会はさらに抗議を続け、報道禁止令を撤廃させる事に成功している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the information announced by the government was quite far from the truth, therefore, Tokyo Shunju Kai continued to lodge a protest and finally succeeded in abolishment of the injunction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the information announced by the government was quite far from the truth, therefore, Tokyo Shunju Kai continued to lodge a protest and finally succeeded in abolishment of the injunction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the information announced by the government was quite far from the truth, therefore, Tokyo Shunju Kai continued to lodge a protest and finally succeeded in abolishment of the injunction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="70">
<j>一連の寺内内閣の言論弾圧に対し新聞社は激しく抗議し、言論報道の自由に関する運動に発展していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Newspaper companies made a vigorous protest against a series of suppression of free speech by Terauchi cabinet and it gradually developed into the movement about freedom of press.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Newspaper companies made a vigorous protest against a series of suppression of free speech by the Terauchi Cabinet and it gradually developed into the movement about freedom of press.</e>
<cmt>「内閣」を大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Newspaper companies made a vigorous protest against a series of suppression of free speech by the Terauchi Cabinet and it gradually developed into the movement about freedom of press.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>平民宰相の誕生</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The advent of Commoner Prime Minister</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The advent of Commoner Prime Minister</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The advent of Commoner Prime Minister</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="71">
<j>米騒動の影響を受け、世論は寺内内閣の退陣を求めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Public opinion demanded resignation of Terauchi cabinet under the influence of rice riots.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Public opinion demanded resignation of the Terauchi Cabinet under the influence of rice riots.</e>
<cmt>「内閣」を大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Public opinion demanded resignation of the Terauchi Cabinet under the influence of rice riots.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>寺内は8月31日に山縣有朋に辞意を告げ、9月21日に正式に辞表を提出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Terauchi expressed to Aritomo YAMAGATA his intention to resign on August 31 and submitted his letter of resignation officially on September 21.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TERAUCHI offered his resignation to Aritomo YAMAGATA on August 31 and submitted his letter of resignation officially on September 21.</e>
<cmt>前半を簡略化しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TERAUCHI offered his resignation to Aritomo YAMAGATA on August 31 and submitted his letter of resignation officially on September 21.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>山県は西園寺公望に組閣を命じたが西園寺はこれを固辞し、原敬を推薦した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamagata ordered Kinmochi SAIONJI to form a government but Saionji refused firmly and recommended Takashi HARA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">YAMAGATA ordered Kinmochi SAIONJI to form a government but SAIONJI refused it firmly and recommended Takashi HARA.</e>
<cmt>苗字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">YAMAGATA ordered Kinmochi SAIONJI to form a government but SAIONJI refused it firmly and recommended Takashi HARA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>そして9月27日に原に組閣が命じられ、日本で初の本格的な政党内閣である原内閣が誕生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hara was ordered to form a government on September 27 and Hara cabinet which was the first full-scale party cabinet in Japan was launched.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">HARA was ordered to form a government on September 27 and the Hara Cabinet which was the first full-scale party cabinet in Japan was launched.</e>
<cmt>苗字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">HARA was ordered to form a government on September 27 and the Hara Cabinet which was the first full-scale party cabinet in Japan was launched.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>爵位を持たない衆議院議員を首相とする初の内閣となったということで、民衆からは「平民宰相」と呼ばれ、歓迎された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was called &apos;Commoner Prime Minister&apos; and welcomed by the people since it was the first cabinet whose prime minister was a member of the House of Representatives who did not have the peerage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was called &apos;Commoner Prime Minister&apos; and welcomed by the people since it was the first cabinet whose prime minister was a member of the House of Representatives who did not have the peerage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was called &apos;Commoner Prime Minister&apos; and welcomed by the people since it was the first cabinet whose prime minister was a member of the House of Representatives who did not have the peerage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 奈緒(id:33238), Los688(id:12316), Straysheep(id:42448), Nnh(id:474), 経済準学士(id:22656), 0null0(id:582), Cprobot(id:97843), Makeboy(id:53882), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), BAKU(id:55205), 柑橘類(id:112137), Johncapistrano(id:969), でここ(id:9565), 氷鷺(id:73707), 赤井彗星(id:18381), Sevenseas(id:27322), IwaimBot(id:190695), Shimoxx(id:9332), Yasushi1964(id:129670), Yosemite(id:5808), Etoa(id:20987), Taichi(id:20605), Juqipedia(id:188816), MIK(id:61548), 蒼海牧菜(id:78923), Complex01(id:10454), ZZZ(id:9462), Tantal(id:74335), Ryo-Osaki(id:48671), Memosa(id:131221), 北方1号(id:153712), Muneohouse(id:179394), Akaloli(id:141644), ないです(id:68294), Hno3(id:56786), Trek011(id:7105), 青心(id:173433), SieBot(id:126695), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>