<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>対外硬</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taigaiko (a concept to pursue a forceful diplomacy)</e>
<cmt>対外硬→Taigaiko (a concept to pursue a forceful diplomacy)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taigaiko (a concept to pursue a forceful diplomacy)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taigaiko (a concept to pursue a forceful diplomacy)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>対外硬（たいがいこう）とは、国際社会における日本国家の現状を対外的に危機的状況と考え、国際協調を否定して、国家の自主・独立を重んじて軍事力をも視野においた強硬的な外交でのみによってこの危機を打開できるとする思想・主張のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taigaiko was the idea or concept that considered the situation of Japan in the international community as the critical externally, and only the forceful diplomacy including the military force which denies the international corporation, and values national independence can defuse a crisis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taigaiko was the idea or concept that considered the situation of Japan in the international community as the critical externally, and only the forceful diplomacy including the military force which denies the international cooperation, and values national independence can defuse a crisis.</e>
<cmt>強調 corporation → cooperation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taigaiko was the idea or concept that considered the situation of Japan in the international community as the critical externally, and only the forceful diplomacy including the military force which denies the international cooperation, and values national independence can defuse a crisis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>こうした考えを支持する人々・党派を対外硬派（たいがいこうは）と呼び、明治後期の条約改正から日清戦争・日露戦争、韓国併合の時期に最も盛んであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People or parties who support those ideas were called &apos;Taigaiko Group&apos; and they were at their highest since the revision of treaty in the end of the Meiji Period, through the Japanese-Sino War, Japanese-Russo War, and annexation of Korea.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People or parties who support those ideas were called &apos;Taigaiko Group&apos; and they were at peak over the period from the revision of treaty in the end of the Meiji Period to the Japanese-Sino War, Japanese-Russo War, and annexation of Korea.</e>
<cmt>最も盛んであった at their highest → at peak, 明治後期の条約改正から日清戦争・日露戦争、韓国併合の時期に since the revision of treaty in the end of the Meiji Period, through the Japanese-Sino War, Japanese-Russo War, and annexation of Korea. → over the period from the revision of treaty in the end of the Meiji Period to the Japanese-Sino War, Japanese-Russo War, and annexation of Korea.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People or parties who support those ideas were called &apos;Taigaiko Group&apos; and they were at peak over the period from the revision of treaty in the end of the Meiji Period to the Japanese-Sino War, Japanese-Russo War, and annexation of Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>明治政府に反対する勢力がナショナリズムの元に党派を超えて大衆を結集させて政府を攻撃する際のスローガンとして活用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The opposition forces against the Meiji government used the ideas of Taigaiko as the slogan when they organized people across parties in the name of nationalism and attacked the government.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The opposition forces against the Meiji government used the ideas of Taigaiko as the slogan when they organized people across parties in the name of nationalism and attacked the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The opposition forces against the Meiji government used the ideas of Taigaiko as the slogan when they organized people across parties in the name of nationalism and attacked the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>その原点は、幕末の攘夷論や明治初期の征韓論などに求めることも可能であるが、直接的な原因としては、明治政府が条約改正に際して採った欧化政策とそれに対する反発としての国粋主義の高揚が上げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin can be considered the principle of excluding foreigners in the end of the Edo Period or Seikanron (debate on subjugation of Korea) in the early Meiji Period, however, the direct causes were that a policy of Europeanization at the revision of a treaty by the Meiji government and a nationalist fervor against the Europeanization.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin can be considered the principle of excluding foreigners in the end of the Edo Period or Seikanron (debate on subjugation of Korea) in the early Meiji Period, however, the direct causes were that a policy of Europeanization at the revision of a treaty by the Meiji government and a nationalist fervor against the Europeanization.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin can be considered the principle of excluding foreigners in the end of the Edo Period or Seikanron (debate on subjugation of Korea) in the early Meiji Period, however, the direct causes were that a policy of Europeanization at the revision of a treaty by the Meiji government and a nationalist fervor against the Europeanization.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>いわゆる日本主義者が、『日本 (新聞)』を舞台に政府の外交方針と自由民権運動の民力休養路線の双方を批判して、強硬的な外交政策による不平等条約解消とその裏付けとなる軍事力の拡張を主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So-called &apos;Japanese nationalist&apos; criticized the line of reducing the national burden which were the government diplomatic policies and the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement in &quot;Japan (newspaper)&quot; and advocated dissolution of unequal treaty with the forceful diplomacy and to expand the military force.</e>
<cmt>日本主義者→Japanese nationalism定訳不明民力休養路線→line of reducing the national burden定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So-called &apos;Japanese nationalist&apos; criticized the line of reducing the national burden which were the government diplomatic policies and the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement in &quot;Japan (newspaper)&quot; and advocated dissolution of unequal treaty with the forceful diplomacy and to expand the military force.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So-called &apos;Japanese nationalist&apos; criticized the line of reducing the national burden which were the government diplomatic policies and the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement in &quot;Japan (newspaper)&quot; and advocated dissolution of unequal treaty with the forceful diplomacy and to expand the military force.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>この路線を奉じる安部井磐根・佐々友房・神鞭知常らは1893年に大日本協会を結成して、「条約励行・自主外交・対清強硬」を掲げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iwane ABEI, Tomofusa SASSA, Tomotsune KOMUCHI who advocated this line organized a Dainihon (Japan) Association in 1893, and set &apos;treaty enforcement, autarkic foreign policy, and stern approach toward Qing (China) &apos;.</e>
<cmt>大日本協会→Dainihon (Japan) Association定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iwane ABEI, Tomofusa SASSA, Tomotsune KOMUCHI who advocated this line organized a Dainihon (Japan) Association in 1893, and set &apos;treaty enforcement, autarkic foreign policy, and stern approach toward Qing (China) &apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iwane ABEI, Tomofusa SASSA, Tomotsune KOMUCHI who advocated this line organized a Dainihon (Japan) Association in 1893, and set &apos;treaty enforcement, autarkic foreign policy, and stern approach toward Qing (China) &apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>これに対して東洋自由党・同盟倶楽部・立憲改進党・国民協会_(日本)・政務調査会_(明治時代の政党)の5党派がこれに呼応して、「日英通商航海条約締結の反対」・「清国への早期開戦」を掲げて共闘を約した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">East Liberal Party, Alliance Club, the Constitutional Progressive Party, National Association (Japan), and Policy Affairs Research Council (political party in the Meiji Period) were allied and advocated &apos;Opposition to the Anglo-Japanese Treaty of Commerce and Navigation&apos; and &apos;Quick Start of War against Qing&apos; and form a united.</e>
<cmt>東洋自由党→East Liberal Party同盟倶楽部→Allinace Club国民協会→National Association政務調査会→Policy Affairs Research Councilいずれも定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">East Liberal Party, Alliance Club, the Constitutional Progressive Party, National Association (Japan), and Policy Affairs Research Council (political party in the Meiji Period) were allied and advocated &apos;Opposition to the Anglo-Japanese Treaty of Commerce and Navigation&apos; and &apos;Quick Start of War against Qing&apos; and form a united.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">East Liberal Party, Alliance Club, the Constitutional Progressive Party, National Association (Japan), and Policy Affairs Research Council (political party in the Meiji Period) were allied and advocated &apos;Opposition to the Anglo-Japanese Treaty of Commerce and Navigation&apos; and &apos;Quick Start of War against Qing&apos; and form a united.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>この6党を対外硬六派（たいがいこうろっぱ、略して「硬六派」とも）と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those six parties were called &apos;Taigaiko Roppa&apos; (forceful six parties) (&apos;Ko Roppa&apos; for short).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those six parties were called &apos;Taigaiko Roppa&apos; (forceful six parties) (&apos;Ko Roppa&apos; for short).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those six parties were called &apos;Taigaiko Roppa&apos; (forceful six parties) (&apos;Ko Roppa&apos; for short).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>こうした動きは世論を日清開戦論へと動かす契機にはなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those movements triggered to mobilize the public opinion to the start of the Japanese-Sino War.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those movements triggered to lead the public opinion to the start of the Japanese-Sino War.</e>
<cmt>世論を日清開戦論へと動かす　mobilize the public opinion to the start of the Japanese-Sino War → lead the public opinion to the start of the Japanese-Sino War.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those movements triggered to lead the public opinion to the start of the Japanese-Sino War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし、これらの政党は対外政策では一定の一致をみていたものの、国内政策では国粋主義的な大日本協会や国民協会から自由民権運動の中でも急進派である東洋自由党まで幅広い勢力を含んでいたために、政府あるいは衆議院第2党の自由党 (明治)あるいは後に同党と伊藤博文系官僚勢力が合同した立憲政友会に対する批判でしか一致をみなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although these political parties agreed certain points in external policy, in the internal policy these parties, which included nationalistic Dainihon Association, National Association, and the East Liberal Party which was a leftist among the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement, agreed each other only with the criticism against the government, the Liberal Party which was the first party of House of Representatives (in Meiji Period), or the Rikken seiyukai (a political party organized by Hirobumi ITO) which the Liberal Party and the government bureaucratic in the side of Hirobumi ITO were united.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although these political parties agreed certain points in external policy, in the internal policy these parties, which included nationalistic Dainihon Association, National Association, and the East Liberal Party which was a leftist among the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement, agreed each other only in the point of criticism against the government, the Liberal Party which was the second party of House of Representatives (in Meiji Period), or the Rikken seiyukai (a political party organized by Hirobumi ITO) which was established from the alliance of the Liberal Party and the governmental bureaucratic in the side of Hirobumi ITO.</e>
<cmt>衆議院第2党の自由党 the Liberal Party which was the first party of House of Representatives → the Liberal Party which was the second party of House of Representatives 批判でしか一致をみなかった。agreed each other only with the criticism → agreed each other only in the point of criticism　同党と伊藤博文系官僚勢力が合同した立憲政友会　which the Liberal Party and the government bureaucratic in the side of Hirobumi ITO were united.　→ which was established from the alliance of the Liberal Party and the governmental bureaucratic in the side of Hirobumi ITO.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although these political parties agreed certain points in external policy, in the internal policy these parties, which included nationalistic Dainihon Association, National Association, and the East Liberal Party which was a leftist among the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement, agreed each other only in the point of criticism against the government, the Liberal Party which was the second party of House of Representatives (in Meiji Period), or the Rikken seiyukai (a political party organized by Hirobumi ITO) which was established from the alliance of the Liberal Party and the governmental bureaucratic in the side of Hirobumi ITO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>実際にこの勢力の主流は後の進歩党 (明治)・憲政本党・立憲国民党・憲政会と続く「反自由党」・「反政友会」の第2党勢力の母胎となっていくのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main current of this force became a parent organization of &apos;Anti Liberal Party&apos; and &apos;Anti Seiyu Party&apos; which were second party force to continue to latter-day Shinpo-to Party (Progressive Party) (in Meiji), Kensei honto Party, Rikken Kokumin-to Party, Kenseikai political Party.</e>
<cmt>憲政本党→Kensei honto Party</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main current of this force became a parent organization of &apos;Anti Liberal Party&apos; and &apos;Anti Seiyu Party&apos; which were second party force to continue to latter-day Shinpo-to Party (Progressive Party) (in Meiji), Kensei honto Party, Rikken Kokumin-to Party, Kenseikai political Party.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main current of this force became a parent organization of &apos;Anti Liberal Party&apos; and &apos;Anti Seiyu Party&apos; which were second party force to continue to latter-day Shinpo-to Party (Progressive Party) (in Meiji), Kensei honto Party, Rikken Kokumin-to Party, Kenseikai political Party.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>日清戦争後に一時的に沈静化していた対外硬の再燃が始まるのは、北清事変後のロシア帝国による満州駐留であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The beginning of reactivation of Taigaiko which had receded temporarily after the Japanese-Sino War was due to the military presence in Manchuria by the Russia Empire after The Boxer Rebellion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The beginning of reactivation of Taigaiko which had receded temporarily after the Japanese-Sino War was due to the military presence in Manchuria by the Russia Empire after The Boxer Rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The beginning of reactivation of Taigaiko which had receded temporarily after the Japanese-Sino War was due to the military presence in Manchuria by the Russia Empire after The Boxer Rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>旧摂関家の当主であった近衛篤麿（近衛文麿の父）を擁した対露同志会を始めとして、七博士建白事件における日露開戦論の高まり、戦後のポーツマス条約締結に反対する民衆による日比谷焼討事件など、対外硬派の影響によるところが大きい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was due to the influence of Taigaiko group such as, the anti Russia comradeship with Atsumaro KONOE (the father of Fumimaro KONOE) who was the family head of the former Sekkan-ke (the families which produced regents), the fervor of theory of outbreak of Japanese -Russo War in the Incident of Shichihakase Kenpaku (movement of outbreak of Japanese-Russo War by seven doctors), and the Hibiya Incendiary Incident by the people who were against Treaty of Portsmouth.</e>
<cmt>対露同志会→anti Russia comradeship七博士建白事件→Shichihakase Kenpaku (movement of outbreak of Japanese-Russo War by seven doctors)定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What were largely due to the influence of Taigaiko group are the anti Russia comradeship with Atsumaro KONOE (the father of Fumimaro KONOE) who was the family head of the former Sekkan-ke (the families which produced regents), the fervor of theory of outbreak of Japanese -Russo War in the Incident of Shichihakase Kenpaku (movement of outbreak of Japanese-Russo War by seven doctors), and the Hibiya Incendiary Incident by the people who were against Treaty of Portsmouth.</e>
<cmt>対外硬派の影響によるところが大きい。It was due to the influence of Taigaiko group such as → What were largely due to the influence of Taigaiko group are</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What were largely due to the influence of Taigaiko group are the anti Russia comradeship with Atsumaro KONOE (the father of Fumimaro KONOE) who was the family head of the former Sekkan-ke (the families which produced regents), the fervor of theory of outbreak of Japanese -Russo War in the Incident of Shichihakase Kenpaku (movement of outbreak of Japanese-Russo War by seven doctors), and the Hibiya Incendiary Incident by the people who were against Treaty of Portsmouth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また、戦後には大韓帝国の併合を積極的に唱えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the Taigaiko group promulgated annexation of the Korean Empire after war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And the Taigaiko group promulgated annexation of the Korean Empire after war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And the Taigaiko group promulgated annexation of the Korean Empire after war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>ところが、日比谷焼討事件に対する評価が対外硬派を分裂の方向に向かわせることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the opinions of Hibiya Incendiary Incident turned the Taigaiko group to split.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the opinions on Hibiya Incendiary Incident turned the Taigaiko group to split.</e>
<cmt>the opinions of → the opinions on</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the opinions on Hibiya Incendiary Incident turned the Taigaiko group to split.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>自由民権運動の流れを汲みこの動きを評価する人々は、1905年に国民倶楽部を結成して「内に立憲主義、外に帝国主義」という標語を掲げて、普通選挙を行って正しい国民の声を政治に反映させることが国家の自主・独立の確立に必要であると主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The people who valued the movement following the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement united the National Club in 1905 and set a slogan which said &apos;Constitutionalism internally, and imperialism externally&apos;, then advocated that it was necessary for the national independence to reflect the right people&apos;s voice in politics with a popular election.</e>
<cmt>国民倶楽部→National Club</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The people who valued the movement following the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement united the National Club in 1905 and set a slogan which said &apos;Constitutionalism internally, and imperialism externally&apos;, then advocated that it was necessary for the national independence to reflect the right people&apos;s voice in politics with a popular election.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The people who valued the movement following the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement united the National Club in 1905 and set a slogan which said &apos;Constitutionalism internally, and imperialism externally&apos;, then advocated that it was necessary for the national independence to reflect the right people&apos;s voice in politics with a popular election.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>だが、逆に国粋主義の流れを汲みこの動きを国内における危機と見た人々は既に1900年に近衛篤麿が結成していた国民同盟会（1902年解散）の流れを汲む諸派に結集して、国家主義の強化と国民への統制強化によって国民が一致団結して自主・独立を追求すべきであると唱えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the people who took the movement following the nationalism as a crisis, united the group following the People&apos;s Alliance (dissolved in 1902) set up by Atsumaro KONOE in 1900, and they advocated that it was necessary to pursue independence with united the nation by strengthening of the nationalism and strengthening to control the people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the people who followed the nationalism and took this movement as a crisis, united the group following the People&apos;s Alliance (dissolved in 1902) set up by Atsumaro KONOE in 1900, and they advocated that it was necessary for people to pursue independence with united the nation by strengthening of the nationalism and reinforcement of control over the people.</e>
<cmt>逆に国粋主義の流れを汲みこの動きを国内における危機と見た人々 the people who took the movement following the nationalism as a crisis → the people who followed the nationalism and took this movement as a crisis　国民への統制強化　strengthening to control the people → reinforcement of control over the people</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the people who followed the nationalism and took this movement as a crisis, united the group following the People&apos;s Alliance (dissolved in 1902) set up by Atsumaro KONOE in 1900, and they advocated that it was necessary for people to pursue independence with united the nation by strengthening of the nationalism and reinforcement of control over the people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="18">
<j>この路線対立は、その後の辛亥革命や対米移民問題、第1次世界大戦などで対外硬が度々再燃して、結果的には対外的にはその方向に向かいながらも、「対外硬」という言葉が色褪せる原因となっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the confrontation between two groups, the Taigaiko was reactivated due to the Xinhai Revolution, the immigration issue against the United States, or the First World War, and although they set off in the same direction externally, the word of &apos;Taigaiko&apos; faded away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the confrontation between two groups, the Taigaiko was reactivated due to the Xinhai Revolution, the immigration issue against the United States, or the First World War, and although they were led to the same direction externally, the word of &apos;Taigaiko&apos; faded away.</e>
<cmt>その方向に向かいながらも they set off in the same direction → they were led to the same direction</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the confrontation between two groups, the Taigaiko was reactivated due to the Xinhai Revolution, the immigration issue against the United States, or the First World War, and although they were led to the same direction externally, the word of &apos;Taigaiko&apos; faded away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 柴崎力栄(id:306719), KH－editor(id:125369), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>