<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>滝川事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takigawa Incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takigawa Incident</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takigawa Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>滝川事件（たきがわじけん）は、1933（昭和8）年に京都帝国大学で発生した思想弾圧事件。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Takigawa incident was a crackdown on freedom of thought that occurred at the Kyoto Imperial University in 1933.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Takigawa incident was a crackdown on freedom of thought that occurred at the Kyoto Imperial University in 1933.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Takigawa Incident was a crackdown on freedom of thought that occurred at the Kyoto Imperial University in 1933.</e>
<cmt>Takigawa Incidentとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>京大事件とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also called the Kyodai Incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also called the Kyodai Incident</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also called the Kyodai (Kyoto University) Incident.</e>
<cmt>Kyodai→Kyodai (Kyoto University)とし、ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経緯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Progress</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Progress</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Progress</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>事件の発端</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Beginning of the incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Beginning of the incident</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Beginning of the incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>事件は、京都帝国大学法学部の瀧川幸辰教授が、1932年10月中央大学法学部で行った講演「『復活』を通して見たるトルストイの刑法観」の内容（レフ・トルストイの思想について「犯罪は国家の組織が悪いから出る」などと説明）が無政府主義的として文部省および司法省内で問題化したことに端を発する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The incident started when a lecture, &quot;Tolstoy&apos;s view on penal law through his novel, Resurrection&quot; in October 1932 by Professor Yukitoki TAKIGAWA of the Faculty of Law, Kyoto Imperial University explained in his talk that &quot;Criminal offenses occur when organization of the national governmental is bad&quot;, which was considered problematic by the Ministry of Education and Ministry of Law as being anarchist.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The incident started when a lecture, &quot;Tolstoy&apos;s view on penal law through his novel, Resurrection&quot; in October 1932 by Professor Yukitoki TAKIGAWA of the Faculty of Law, Kyoto Imperial University explained in his talk that &quot;Criminal offenses occur when organization of the national governmental is bad,&quot; which was considered problematic by the Ministry of Education and Ministry of Law as being anarchist.</e>
<cmt>Spacing, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The incident started when a lecture, &apos;Tolstoy&apos;s view on penal law through his novel, &quot;Resurrection&quot;&apos; in October 1932 by Professor Yukitoki TAKIGAWA of the Faculty of Law, Kyoto Imperial University explained in his talk that &apos;Criminal offenses occur when organization of the national governmental is bad,&apos; which was considered problematic by the Ministry of Education and Ministry of Law as being anarchist.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション表記修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>この時点では宮本英雄法学部長が文部省に釈明し問題にはならなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this point, the dean of the Faculty of Law, Hideo MIYAMOTO apologized to the Ministry of Education and this was not a problem.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this point, the dean of the Faculty of Law, Hideo MIYAMOTO apologized to the Ministry of Education and this was not a problem.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this point, the dean of the Faculty of Law, Hideo MIYAMOTO apologized to the Ministry of Education and this was not a problem.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>ところが1933年3月になり日本共産党員およびその同調者とされた裁判官・裁判所職員が検挙される「司法官赤化事件」が起こり状況は一変することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in March 1933, the situation changed drastically when the &quot;Communist Judiciary Incident&quot; occurred and Japanese Communist Party members and judges and court staff who were sympathetic to the party were arrested.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in March 1933, the situation changed drastically when the &quot;Communist Judiciary Incident&quot; occurred and Japanese Communist Party members and judges and court staff who were sympathetic to the party were arrested.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in March 1933, the situation changed drastically when the &apos;Communist Judiciary Incident&apos; occurred and Japanese Communist Party members and judges and court staff who were sympathetic to the party were arrested.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション表記修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>この事件をきっかけに蓑田胸喜ら原理日本社の右翼、および菊池武夫 (陸軍軍人)（貴族院 (日本)）や宮澤裕（衆議院・立憲政友会所属）らの国会議員は、司法官赤化の元凶として帝国大学法学部の「赤化教授」の追放を主張、司法試験委員であった滝川を非難した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to this incident, Muneki MINODA and others from the right wing group, Genri Nihonsha, Takeo KIKUCHI (army veteran)(House of Peers (Japan)), Yu MIYAZAWA (House of Representatives, affiliated with Riken seiyukai) and other Diet members proposed the exile of &quot;Red (communist) Professors&quot; in the Faculty of Law in imperial universities as the cause of communist judges and accused Takigawa, who was a member of the bar test board.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to this incident, Muneki MINODA and others from the right wing group, Genri Nihonsha, Takeo KIKUCHI (army veteran)(House of Peers (Japan)), Yu MIYAZAWA (House of Representatives, affiliated with Riken seiyukai) and other Diet members proposed the exile of &quot;Red (communist) Professors&quot; in the Faculty of Law in imperial universities as the cause of communist judges and accused Takigawa, who was a member of the bar test board.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to this incident, Muneki MINODA and others from the right wing group, Genri Nihonsha, Takeo KIKUCHI (army veteran) (House of Peers (Japan)), Yu MIYAZAWA (House of Representatives, affiliated with Rikken Seiyukai) and other Diet members proposed the exile of &apos;Red (communist) Professors&apos; in the Faculty of Law in imperial universities as the cause of communist judges and accused Takigawa, who was a member of the bar test board.</e>
<cmt>カッコの後のスペース追加、Riken seiyukai→Rikken Seiyukaiに修正、クォーテーション表記修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>滝川の処分と京大法学部の抵抗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The punishment of Takiwgawa and the resistance by the Faculty of Law, Kyodai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The punishment of Takiwgawa and the resistance by the Faculty of Law, Kyodai.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The punishment of Takiwgawa and the resistance by the Faculty of Law, Kyoto University</e>
<cmt>Kyodai→Kyoto Universityとし、ピリオド削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>1933年4月、内務省 (日本)は滝川の著書『刑法講義』『刑法読本』に対し、その中の内乱罪、姦通罪に関する見解（後者については妻にだけ適用されることを批判した）などを理由として発売禁止処分を下した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ministry of Internal Affairs (Japan) ruled in April 1933 that Takigawa&apos;s books &quot;Keiho Kogi&quot;&quot;Keiho Dokuhon&quot; were not allowed to be for sale because of his stance on insurrection crimes and adultery (which he criticized because it was only applicable to the wife).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ministry of Internal Affairs (Japan) ruled in April 1933 that Takigawa&apos;s books &quot;Keiho Kogi&quot; and &quot;Keiho Dokuhon&quot; were not allowed to be for sale because of his stance on insurrection crimes and adultery (which he criticized because it was only applicable to the wife).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ministry of Internal Affairs (Japan) ruled in April 1933 that Takigawa&apos;s books &quot;Keiho Kogi&quot; and &quot;Keiho Dokuhon&quot; were not allowed to be for sale because of his stance on insurrection crimes and adultery (which he criticized because it was only applicable to the wife).</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーションを半角に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>翌5月には齋藤内閣の鳩山一郎文部大臣が小西重直京大総長に滝川の罷免を要求した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May of the following year, Ichiro HATAYAMA, Minister of Education in the Saito Cabinet made a demand to Shigenao KONISHI, Dean of Kyoto University, that Takigawa was fired</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May of the following year, Ichiro HATAYAMA, Minister of Education in the Saito Cabinet made a demand to Shigenao KONISHI, Dean of Kyoto University, to fire Takigawa.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May of the following year, Ichiro HATOYAMA, Minister of Education in the Saito Cabinet made a demand to Shigenao KONISHI, Dean of Kyoto University, to fire Takigawa.</e>
<cmt>Ichiro HATAYAMA→Ichiro HATOYAMAに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>京大法学部教授会および小西総長は文相の要求を拒絶したが、同月26日、文部省は文官分限令により滝川の休職処分を強行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The board of professors at the Faculty of Law, Kyoto University and Dean Konishi refused the Minister of Education&apos;s demands and on the twenty-sixth of the same month, the Ministry of Education forced a decision on Takigawa&apos;s suspension from work through the Bunkanbungen law (ordinance on the status of civil servants).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The board of professors at the Faculty of Law, Kyoto University and Dean Konishi refused the Minister of Education&apos;s demands and on the 26th of the same month, the Ministry of Education forced a decision on Takigawa&apos;s suspension from work through the Bunkanbungen law (ordinance on the status of civil servants).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The board of professors at the Faculty of Law, Kyoto University and Dean Konishi refused the Minister of Education&apos;s demands and on the 26th of the same month, the Ministry of Education forced a decision on Takigawa&apos;s suspension from work through the Bunkanbungen law (ordinance on the status of civil servants).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>滝川の休職処分と同時に、京大法学部は教授31名から副手に至る全教官が辞表を提出して抗議の意思を示したが、大学当局および他学部は法学部教授会の立場を支持しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time as Takigawa&apos;s suspension, all law faculty staff, from the 31 professors to the technicians, submitted their resignation as a sign of protest, but the University itself and other faculties did not support the stance of the board of law faculty professors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time as Takigawa&apos;s suspension, all law faculty staff, from 31 professors to the technicians, submitted their resignation as a sign of protest, but the University itself and other faculties did not support the stance of the board of law faculty professors.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time as Takigawa&apos;s suspension, all law faculty staff, from 31 professors to the technicians, submitted their resignation as a sign of protest, but the University itself and other faculties did not support the stance of the board of law faculty professors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>小西総長は辞職に追い込まれ、7月に後任の松井元興総長（博士 (理学)、のちに立命館大学学長）が就任したことから事件は急速に終息に向かうこととなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dean Konishi was forced to resign and with the appointment of Motooki MATSUI as dean (D.Sc., later Ritsumeikan University dean), the incident quickly headed towards a conclusion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dean Konishi was forced to resign and with the appointment of Motooki MATSUI as dean (D.Sc., later Ritsumeikan University dean), the incident quickly headed towards a conclusion.</e>
<cmt>Spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dean Konishi was forced to resign and with the appointment of Motooki MATSUI as dean (D.Sc., later Ritsumeikan University dean), the incident quickly headed towards a conclusion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>すなわち松井総長は、辞表を提出した教官のうち滝川および佐々木惣一（のちに立命館大学学長）、宮本英雄、森口繁治、末川博（のちに立命館大学学長・総長）、宮本英脩の6教授のみを免官とし、それ以外の辞表を却下した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dean Matsui accepted the resignation of 6 professors, Takigawa, Soichi SASAKI (later Ritsumeikan University dean), Hideo MIYAMOTO, Shigeji MORIGUCHI, Hiroshi SUEKAWA (later Risumeikan University dean) and Hidenaga MIYAMAOTO, and rejected the resignation of all others.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dean Matsui accepted the resignation of 6 professors, Takigawa, Soichi SASAKI (later Ritsumeikan University dean), Hideo MIYAMOTO, Shigeji MORIGUCHI, Hiroshi SUEKAWA (later Risumeikan University dean) and Hidenaga MIYAMAOTO, and rejected the resignation of all others.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dean Matsui accepted the resignation of six professors, Takigawa, Soichi SASAKI (later Ritsumeikan University dean), Hideo MIYAMOTO, Shigeji MORIGUCHI, Hiroshi SUEKAWA (later Risumeikan University dean) and Hidenaga MIYAMOTO, and rejected the resignation of all others.</e>
<cmt>&quot;6&quot;をスペルアウト、Hidenaga MIYAMAOTO→Hidenaga MIYAMOTOに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>さらに鳩山文相との間で「滝川の処分は非常特別のものであり、教授の進退は文部省に対する総長の具状によるものとする」という「解決案」を提示した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also submitted a &quot;solution&quot; to Minister of Education Hatayama that &quot;Takigawa&apos;s shobun is an extraordinary case, and the suspension of professors is decided by the Dean with the guidance of the Ministry of Education&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also submitted a &quot;solution&quot; to Minister of Education Hatayama that &quot;Takigawa&apos;s shobun is an extraordinary case, and the suspension of professors is decided by the Dean with the guidance of the Ministry of Education.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also submitted a &apos;solution&apos; to Minister of Education Hatoyama that &apos;The punishment of Takiwgawa is an extraordinary case, and the suspension of professors is decided by the Dean with the guidance of the Ministry of Education.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Hatayama→Hatoyama、Takigawa&apos;s shobun→The punishment of Takiwgawaに修正、 クォーテーション表記修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>この結果法学部教官は、解決案により要求が達成されたとして辞表を撤回した残留組（中島玉吉、末広重雄、牧健二など）と、辞表を撤回せず解決案を拒否した辞職組に分裂し、前記6教授以外に恒藤恭（のちの大阪市立大学初代学長）および田村徳治の教授2名、助教授5名、専任講師以下8名が辞職という形で事件は決着した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, law faculty staff became divided into those who decided that their demands had been reached by the solution and retracted their resignations and stayed (Tamakichi NAKAJIMA, Shigeo SUEHIRO, Kenji MAKI, etc.), and those who resigned because they did not retract their resignations and refused the solution, who were the aforementioned 6 professors, 2 professors, Kyo TSUNETO (later the first president of Osaka Prefectural University) and Tokuji TAMURA, 5 associate professors and 8 lecturers and the incident was concluded.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, law faculty staff became divided into those who decided that their demands had been reached by the solution and retracted their resignations and stayed (Tamakichi NAKAJIMA, Shigeo SUEHIRO, Kenji MAKI, etc.), and those who resigned because they did not retract their resignations and refused the solution, who were the aforementioned 6 professors, 2 professors, Kyo TSUNETO (later the first president of Osaka Prefectural University) and Tokuji TAMURA, 5 associate professors and 8 lecturers and the incident was concluded.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, law faculty staff became divided into those who decided that their demands had been reached by the solution and retracted their resignations and stayed (Tamakichi NAKAJIMA, Shigeo SUEHIRO, Kenji MAKI, etc.), and those who resigned because they did not retract their resignations and refused the solution, who were the aforementioned six professors, two professors, Kyo TSUNETO (later the first president of Osaka Prefectural University) and Tokuji TAMURA, five associate professors and eight lecturers and the incident was concluded.</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウト</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>（年末には残留組に近かったとされる宮本英脩が復職した）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(In the end of the year, Hidenaga MIYAMOTO, who was close to those who stayed, returned to work).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(At the end of the year, Hidenaga MIYAMOTO, who was close to those who stayed, returned to work).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(At the end of the year, Hidenaga MIYAMOTO, who was close to those who stayed, returned to work).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>学内外の支援運動</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Support from within and outside the university</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Support from within and outside the university</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Support from within and outside the university</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>京大法学部の学生は教授会を支持し、全員が退学届けを提出するなど処分に抗議する運動を起こした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The students of the Faculty of Law in Kyoto University supported the board of professors and started a movement to protest the punishment by all students submitting a leave from studies.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The students of the Faculty of Law in Kyoto University supported the board of professors and started a movement to protest the punishment by having all students submitting a leave from studies.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The students of the Faculty of Law in Kyoto University supported the board of professors and started a movement to protest the punishment by having all students submitting a leave from studies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>他学部の学生もこれに続いた（このとき文学部の大学院生・学生のグループで活躍したのが中井正一、久野収、花田清輝、高木養根らである）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The students in other faculties also followed (Masaichi NAKAO, Osamu HISANO, Kiyoteru HANADA, Yoshine TAKAGI and others who were active in groups for graduate and undergraduate students in the Faculty of Letters).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The students in other faculties also followed (Masaichi NAKAO, Osamu HISANO, Kiyoteru HANADA, Yoshine TAKAGI and others who were active in groups for graduate and undergraduate students in the Faculty of Letters).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The students in other faculties also followed (Masakazu NAKAI, Osamu KUNO, Kiyoteru HANADA, Yasumoto TAKAGI and others who were active in groups for graduate and undergraduate students in the Faculty of Letters).</e>
<cmt>人物名の読みの誤りを訂正 *Masaichi NAKAO→Masakazu NAKAI、Osamu HISANO→Osamu KUNO、Yoshine TAKAGI→Yasumoto TAKAGI</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>さらに東京大学など他大学の学生も呼応し、7月には16大学の参加により「大学自由擁護連盟」、さらに文化人200名が参加する「学芸自由同盟」が結成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other university students such as Tokyo University also supported the movement and the &quot;Daigaku Jiyu Yogo renmei (Association for University Freedom&quot; with 16 participating universities and the &quot;Gakugei Jiyu Domei (Arts Freedom Association)&quot;formed by 200 cultural leaders were established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other university students such as Tokyo University also supported the movement and the &quot;Daigaku Jiyu Yogo renmei (Association for University Freedom&quot; with 16 participating universities and the &quot;Gakugei Jiyu Domei (Arts Freedom Association)&quot; formed by 200 cultural leaders were established.</e>
<cmt>Spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other university students such as Tokyo University also supported the movement and the &apos;Daigaku Jiyu Yogo Renmei&apos; (Association for University Freedom) with 16 participating universities and the &apos;Gakugei Jiyu Domei&apos; (Arts Freedom Association) formed by 200 cultural leaders were established.</e>
<cmt>カッコ不足分追加、Daigaku Jiyu Yogo Renmeiとし、シングルクォーテーションに変更、位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>『中央公論』『改造 (雑誌)』などの総合雑誌、『大阪朝日新聞』などの新聞は京大を支援し文部省を批判する論説を多く掲載した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">General opinion magazines such as &quot;Chuo Koron&quot;&quot;Kaizo(magazine)&quot; and newspapers such as &quot;Osaka Asahi Shinbun&quot; supported Kyoto University and published many editorials criticizing the Ministry of Education.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">General opinion magazines such as &quot;Chuo Koron,&quot; &quot;Kaizo(magazine),&quot; and newspapers such as &quot;Osaka Asahi Shinbun&quot; supported Kyoto University and published many editorials criticizing the Ministry of Education.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">General opinion magazines such as &quot;Chuo Koron,&quot; &quot;Kaizo,&quot; and newspapers such as &quot;Osaka Asahi Shinbun&quot; supported Kyoto University and published many editorials criticizing the Ministry of Education.</e>
<cmt>Kaizo(magazine)→Kaizoのみとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>しかし大学の夏期休暇などもあり学内の抗議運動は終息、自由擁護連盟も弾圧により解体した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, with the summer break at university, the protest movement within the university ended and the Jiyu Yogo Renmei was dissolved because of pressure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, with the summer break at university, the protest movement within the university ended and the Jiyu Yogo Renmei was dissolved because of pressure.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, with the summer break at university, the protest movement within the university ended and the Jiyu Yogo Renmei was dissolved because of pressure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>学芸自由同盟も翌年には活動停止状態となったが、前記の中井、久野などこの運動に参加した学生のなかから『土曜日 (雑誌)』『学生評論』『世界文化』など反ファシズムを標榜する雑誌メディアが生まれ、自由主義的文化運動は「非常時」下でなおも命脈を保った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Gakugei Jiyu Domei also ceased its activities the next year but students such as the aforementioned Nakai and Hisano who participated in this movement started magazines supporting anti-fascism such as &quot;Doyobi (Saturaday&quot;, &quot;Gakusei Hyoron (Student Editorials)&quot;&quot;Sekai Bunka (World Culture)&quot; and even under &quot;emergency situation(war period)&quot;, the liberal cultural movement continued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Gakugei Jiyu Domei also ceased its activities the next year but students such as the aforementioned Nakai and Hisano who participated in this movement started magazines supporting anti-fascism such as &quot;Doyobi (Saturaday),&quot; &quot;Gakusei Hyoron (Student Editorials),&quot; &quot;Sekai Bunka (World Culture),&quot; and even under &quot;emergency situation (war period),&quot; the liberal cultural movement continued.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Gakugei Jiyu Domei also ceased its activities the next year but students such as the aforementioned Nakai and Kuno who participated in this movement started magazines supporting anti-fascism such as &quot;Doyobi&quot; (Saturaday), &quot;Gakusei Hyoron&quot; (Student Editorials), &quot;Sekai Bunka&quot; (World Culture), and even under &apos;emergency situation (war period),&apos; the liberal cultural movement continued.</e>
<cmt>Hisano→Kunoに修正、クォーテーションの位置を移動、一部半角・シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>事件のその後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the incident</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>滝川事件に関連して京都帝大を辞職した教官のうち、18名が立命館大学に教授・助教授などの形で移籍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the staff who quit Kyoto Imperial University over the Takigawa Incident, 18 of them transferred to Ritsumeikan University as professors, associate professors, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the staff who quit Kyoto Imperial University over the Takigawa Incident, 18 of them transferred to Ritsumeikan University as professors, associate professors, etc.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the staff who quit Kyoto Imperial University over the Takigawa Incident, 18 of them transferred to Ritsumeikan University as professors, associate professors, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>結果、立命館をはじめ京大以外の関西圏大学法学部の発展を促すことにもなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the end, it led to the development of law faculties within the Kansai area other than Kyoto University such as Ritsumeikan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end, it led to the development of law faculties within the Kansai area other than Kyoto University such as Ritsumeikan.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end, it led to the development of law faculties within the Kansai area other than Kyoto University such as Ritsumeikan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>しかしその後、京大の残留教官による説得に応じ京大に復帰する教官（黒田覚、佐伯千仭ら6名）が現れ、滝川および筋を通して復帰しなかった人々（宮本英雄、末川、恒藤、田村ら）との間に感情的なしこりを残した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, some staff members answered the call from staff who stayed at Kyoto University and returned (6 members such as Satori KURODA and CHIHIRO SAEKI) and this led to estrangement with Takigawa and those who did not return under principle (Hideo MIYAMOTO, Suekawa, Tsuneto, Tamura, etc).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, some staff members answered the call from staff who stayed at Kyoto University and returned (6 members such as Satori KURODA and CHIHIRO SAEKI) and this led to estrangement with Takigawa and those who did not return under principle (Hideo MIYAMOTO, Suekawa, Tsuneto, Tamura, etc).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, some staff members answered the call from staff who stayed at Kyoto University and returned (six members such as Satoru KURODA and Chihiro SAEKI) and this led to estrangement with Takigawa and those who did not return under principle (Hideo MIYAMOTO, Suekawa, Tsuneto, Tamura, etc).</e>
<cmt>&quot;6&quot;をスペルアウト、Satori KURODA→Satoru KURODA、CHIHIRO SAEKI→Chihiro SAEKIに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>このことは第二次世界大戦後の京大法学部の再建に大きな影を落としたといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is said to have cast a dark shadow upon the rebuilding of the Faculty of Law in Kyoto University after World War II.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is said to have cast a dark shadow upon the rebuilding of the Faculty of Law in Kyoto University after World War II.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is said to have cast a dark shadow upon the rebuilding of the Faculty of Law in Kyoto University after World War II.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>すなわち戦後、連合国軍最高司令官総司令部の方針により滝川は京大に復帰したが、他の「辞職組」教官らは復帰しなかった（ただし恒藤は戦後に兼任教官として短期間在任）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, the GHQ allowed Takigawa to return to Kyoto University but other staff who resigned did not return (however, Tsuneto returned for a short period with a joint appointment in the post-war years).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, the GHQ allowed Takigawa to return to Kyoto University but other staff who resigned did not return (however, Tsuneto returned for a short period with a joint appointment in the post-war years).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, the GHQ allowed Takigawa to return to Kyoto University but other staff who resigned did not return (however, Tsuneto returned for a short period with a joint appointment in the post-war years).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>また滝川を法学部長とし、法学部再建の全権を委ねる旨密約がなされ、黒田法学部長は解任され、佐伯ら前記「復帰組」教官らは辞職した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There also was a secret pact that made Takigawa head of the Faculty of Law and have all the rights to rebuild the faculty, which led to the Kuroda who was faculty head being fired and the staff who returned such as Saeki resigning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There also was a secret pact that made Takigawa head of the Faculty of Law and have all the rights to rebuild the faculty, which led to Kuroda who was faculty head being fired and the staff who returned such as Saeki resigning.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There also was a secret pact that made Takigawa head of the Faculty of Law and have all the rights to rebuild the faculty, which led to Kuroda who was faculty head being fired and the staff who returned such as Saeki resigning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="28">
<j>なお、鳩山一郎が戦後連合国軍最高司令官総司令部の公職追放指令を受けたのは、かつて文相として滝川の処分を強行したことに関係があるといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the forced punishment of Takigawa was one of the reasons why Ichiro HATAYAMA was banished from official positions by the GHQ in the post-war years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the forced punishment of Takigawa was one of the reasons why Ichiro HATAYAMA was banished from official positions by the GHQ in the post-war years.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the forced punishment of Takigawa was one of the reasons why Ichiro HATOYAMA was banished from official positions by the GHQ in the post-war years.</e>
<cmt>Ichiro HATAYAMA→Ichiro HATOYAMAに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>事件の意義</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meaning of the incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meaning of the incident</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meaning of the incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>久野収はこの事件の特色について、「危険思想の内容がもはや共産主義やマルクス主義といった嫌疑にあるのではなく…国家に批判的な態度を取る学者たちの思想内容に及んできた」点にあると回顧しており、言論弾圧の対象が従来の共産主義思想から自由主義的な言論へと拡大することとなった大きな転機であることを強調している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Osamu HISANO recollects that the characteristic of this incident was &apos;Dangerous ideology was not only communism and Marxism, but started to include the content of thinking of academics who took a critical stance against the government&quot; and emphasizes that this was a big step when the target of freedom of speech changed from communism to liberalism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Osamu HISANO recollects that the characteristic of this incident was &apos;Dangerous ideology was not only communism and Marxism, but started to include the content of thinking of academics who took a critical stance against the government&quot; and emphasizes that this was a big step when the target of freedom of speech changed from communism to liberalism.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Osamu KUNO recollects that the characteristic of this incident was &apos;Dangerous ideology was not only communism and Marxism, but started to include the content of thinking of academics who took a critical stance against the government&apos; and emphasizes that this was a big step when the target of freedom of speech changed from communism to liberalism.</e>
<cmt>Osamu HISANO→Osamu KUNOに修正、片方のクォーテーションをシングルに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="30">
<j>また、文部省が京大総長の具状を待たずに分限委員会を開き滝川の休職処分を決定したことは、京大における沢柳事件（1913年 - 1914年）以来、「教授会自治」として認められていた慣行（総長の具状は教授会の同意を必要とするというもの）を無視するものであったうえに帝国大学官制にすら違反する可能性があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The decision for Takigawa&apos;s extended leave by the Bungen board of the Ministry of Education without waiting for the explanation from the President of Kyodai ignored the tradition of &quot;Ruling by the Board of Professors&quot; that was established by the Sawayanagi Incident(1913-1914) at Kyoto University (the explanation of the president requires the consent of the board of professors) and may have possibly been against the Imperial University Rules.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The decision for Takigawa&apos;s extended leave by the Bungen board of the Ministry of Education without waiting for an explanation from the President of Kyodai ignored the tradition of &quot;Ruling by the Board of Professors&quot; that was established by the Sawayanagi Incident(1913-1914) at Kyoto University (the explanation of the president requires the consent of the board of professors) and may have possibly been against the Imperial University Rules.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The decision for Takigawa&apos;s extended leave by the Bungen (change in employment status) board of the Ministry of Education without waiting for an explanation from the President of Kyoto University ignored the tradition of &apos;Ruling by the Board of Professors&apos; that was established by the Sawayanagi Incident (1913-1914) at Kyoto University (the explanation of the president requires the consent of the board of professors) and may have possibly been against the Imperial University Rules.</e>
<cmt>Bungenの補足追加 (参照: http://waei.hounavi.jp/je_word_%E5%88%86%E9%99%90.php)、Kyodai→Kyoto Universityとし、クォーテーション表記修正、スペース追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>斎藤実や鳩山文相が当時語っていたように、政府当局が処分を強行した意図は、「大学自治の総本山」と見られていた京大を強力な国家権力のもとに屈服させるという点にあったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Minoru SAITO and Minister of Education HATAYAMA talked at that time, the reason why the government used force was to place Kyoto University, which was thought to be the &quot;stronghold of university freedom&quot;, under the strong power of the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Minoru SAITO and Minister of Education HATAYAMA talked at that time, the reason why the government used force was to place Kyoto University, which was thought to be the &quot;stronghold of university freedom,&quot; under the power of the government.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Minoru SAITO and Minister of Education Hatoyama talked at that time, the reason why the government used force was to place Kyoto University, which was thought to be the &apos;stronghold of university freedom,&apos; under the power of the government.</e>
<cmt>HATAYAMA→Hatoyamaに修正、クォーテーション表記修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="32">
<j>立命館大学『学園通信校友版』「百二十年の歴史を訪ねて」によると、同省は滝川を弾圧すると末川が反対に乗り出すことを予想し、むしろ弾圧の本命を末川としていたとする説もあることを紹介している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the Ritsumeikan University&apos;s &quot;Gakuen Tsushin Koyu edition, Revisiting the 120 years of History&quot;, the ministry assumed that accusing Takigawa would make put Suekawa in the opposition and that there is a theory that Suekawa was the real target of oppression.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the Ritsumeikan University&apos;s &quot;Gakuen Tsushin Koyu edition, Revisiting the 120 years of History,&quot; the ministry assumed that accusing Takigawa would put Suekawa in the opposition and that there is a theory that Suekawa was the real target of oppression.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the Ritsumeikan University&apos;s &quot;Gakuen Tsushin Koyu edition, Revisiting the 120 years of History,&quot; the ministry assumed that accusing Takigawa would put Suekawa in the opposition and that there is a theory that Suekawa was the real target of oppression.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>その末川は「この事件は滝川個人に加えられた弾圧ではなく、日本の学問の自由と大学自治に加えられた弾圧だったから京大事件と呼ぶべきだ」と繰り返し語っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suekawa repeatedly said that &quot;This incident was not oppression of Takigawa as an individual but should be called Kyodai Incident because this was oppression of academic freedom and university freedom in Japan&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suekawa repeatedly said that &quot;This incident was not oppression of Takigawa as an individual but should be called the Kyodai Incident because this was oppression of academic freedom and university freedom in Japan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suekawa repeatedly said that &apos;This incident was not oppression of Takigawa as an individual but should be called the Kyodai Incident because this was oppression of academic freedom and university freedom in Japan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="34">
<j>「第2次滝川事件」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Second Takigawa Incident&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Second Takigawa Incident&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Second Takigawa Incident&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>1955年6月、新制京都大学で発生した学生による滝川幸辰総長への「暴行」事件は、「第2次滝川事件」と称されることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June 1955, the &quot;attack&quot; incident by students at the new system Kyoto University against President Yukitoki TAKIGAWA is sometimes called the &quot;Second Takigawa Incident&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June 1955, the &quot;attack&quot; incident by students at the new system Kyoto University against President Yukitoki TAKIGAWA is sometimes called the &quot;Second Takigawa Incident.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June 1955, the &apos;attack&apos; incident by students at the new system Kyoto University against President Yukitoki TAKIGAWA is sometimes called the &apos;Second Takigawa Incident.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションをシングル・半角に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>この事件は学生自治会である同学会が、当時京大総長に在任（1953年 – 1957年）していた滝川に対し創立記念祭行事の開催を求めており、その実施方法をめぐる両者の協議が決裂した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This incident occurred when Takigawa was Dean of Kyoto University (1953-1957) and the Dogaku-kai (student unioni) asked for a ceremony to commemorate the establishment of the university but discussions about the ceremony details between the two parties did not reach a conclusion.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This incident occurred when Takigawa was Dean of Kyoto University (1953-1957) and the Dogaku-kai (student union) asked for a ceremony to commemorate the establishment of the university but discussions about the ceremony details between the two parties did not reach a conclusion.</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This incident occurred when Takigawa was Dean of Kyoto University (1953-1957) and the Dogaku-kai (student union) asked for a ceremony to commemorate the establishment of the university but discussions about the ceremony details between the two parties did not reach a conclusion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>その直後再交渉を求める学生が総長を監禁したため警官隊が導入されたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The students kept the President hostage demanding renegotiation and the police were introduced.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The students kept the President hostage demanding renegotiation and the police were introduced.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The students kept the President hostage demanding renegotiation and the police were introduced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>この結果同学会は解散させられ、中心人物と目された学生2名が逮捕起訴された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Dogaku-kai was forced to dismantle and two students who were considered the leaders were arrested and charged.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, the Dogaku-kai was forced to dismantle and two students who were considered the leaders were arrested and charged.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, the Dogaku-kai was forced to dismantle and two students who were considered the leaders were arrested and charged.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>同年9月に開かれた被告2名の初公判では、被告側の弁護人として11名の弁護士（この中には先述の佐伯千仭が含まれている）のほか、田畑茂二郎ら3名の法学部教官が特別弁護人として参加した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the first court hearing held in September of that year, 11 lawyers participated as the defendant&apos;s lawyers (including the aforementioned Chihiro SAEKI) along with 3 other law faculty staff such as Shigejiro TAHATA as special lawyers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the first court hearing held in September of that year, 11 lawyers participated as the defendant&apos;s lawyers (including the aforementioned Chihiro SAEKI) along with 3 other law faculty staff such as Shigejiro TAHATA as special lawyers.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the first court hearing of the two defendants held in September of that year, 11 lawyers participated as the defendants&apos; lawyers (including the aforementioned Chihiro SAEKI) along with 3 other law faculty staff such as Shigejiro TAHATA as special lawyers.</e>
<cmt>「被告2名の」→訳漏れのため訳出対応し、defendant&apos;s→defendants&apos;としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>滝川はこの3教官に対し罷免を示唆しつつ公の場で繰り返し非難を行い、結局のところ3人全員が特別弁護人を辞退した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takigawa hinted that the three staff members could be fired and repeatedly criticized them in public, and in the end, all three declined the position of special lawyer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takigawa hinted that the three staff members could be fired and repeatedly criticized them in public, and in the end, all three declined the position of special lawyer.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takigawa hinted that the three staff members could be fired and repeatedly criticized them in public, and in the end, all three declined the position of special lawyer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>このことは滝川総長自らがかつての主張を覆し教授会の人事権を否定したものとされ、戦後の滝川に反動的な人物とのイメージを付け加えることになったという者もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This led to an impression of Takigawa as a reactionary person in the post-war years because he was viewed as reversing his previous opinion of the board of professors having the right of deciding on personnel matters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This led to an impression of Takigawa as a reactionary person in the post-war years because he was viewed as reversing his previous opinion of the board of professors having the right of deciding on personnel matters.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This led to an impression of Takigawa as a reactionary person in the post-war years because he was viewed as reversing his previous opinion of the board of professors having the right of deciding on personnel matters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>公判自体は滝川自身の監禁に対する証言の曖昧さもあって、1959年大阪高等裁判所での控訴判決により確定し、被告2名のうち1名の暴行罪のみを認定した（両名の不退去罪および傷害罪は無罪となった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because there were unclear points in Takigawa&apos;s testimony of his capture during the hearing, the sentence was decided after an appeal to the Osaka Higher Court in 1959, with one of the two defendants being accused of assault (both were acquitted of forcible detainment and inflicting bodily injury)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because there were unclear points in Takigawa&apos;s testimony of his capture during the hearing, the sentence was decided after an appeal to the Osaka Higher Court in 1959, with one of the two defendants being accused of assault (both were acquitted of forcible detainment and inflicting bodily injury).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because there were unclear points in Takigawa&apos;s testimony of his capture during the hearing, the sentence was decided after an appeal to the Osaka Higher Court in 1959, with one of the two defendants being accused of assault (both were acquitted of forcible detainment and inflicting bodily injury).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>事件をモデルとした作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pieces of work that used this incident as a model</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Pieces of work that used this incident as a model</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Pieces of work that used this incident as a model</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="43">
<j>この事件（およびゾルゲ事件）をモデルとした映画が、黒澤明監督の戦後第1作『わが青春に悔なし』（1946年）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The movie &quot;Waga seishun in kuinashi&quot; (1946), which was Akira KUROSAWA&apos;s first piece after the war, used this incident (together with Sorge Incident) as a model.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The movie &quot;Waga seishun in kuinashi&quot; (1946), which was Akira KUROSAWA&apos;s first piece after the war, used this incident (together with the Sorge Incident) as a model.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The movie &quot;Waga Seishun ni Kuinashi&quot; (No Regrets for Our Youth) (1946), which was Akira KUROSAWA&apos;s first piece after the war, used this incident (together with the Sorge Incident) as a model.</e>
<cmt>Waga seishun in kuinashi→Waga Seishun ni Kuinashiに修正、英語表記追加、クォーテーション表記修正 (参照: http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0039090/)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>滝川をモデルとしたとおぼしき八木原教授を大河内伝次郎、その娘・幸枝を原節子が演じている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Professor Yagihara, loosely based on Takigawa, was acted by Denjiro OKAWACHI and his daughter Sachie was depicted by Setsuko HARA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Professor Yagihara, loosely based on Takigawa, was acted by Denjiro OKAWACHI and his daughter Sachie was depicted by Setsuko HARA.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Professor Yagihara, loosely based on Takigawa, was acted by Denjiro OKOCHI and his daughter Sachie was depicted by Setsuko HARA.</e>
<cmt>Denjiro OKAWACHI→Denjiro OKOCHIに訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>大河内の教え子でのちに幸枝と結婚する人物として尾崎秀実をモデルにした野毛隆吉（藤田進が演じている）が登場するが、もちろん実在の尾崎はこの事件とは無関係である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakichi NOGE (played by Susumu FUJITA), who was Okawachi&apos;s student and later marries Sachie was based on Hidemitsu OZAKI, but of course the real Ozaki is unrelated to this incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakichi NOGE (played by Susumu FUJITA), who was Okawachi&apos;s student and later marries Sachie was based on Hidemitsu OZAKI, but of course the real Ozaki is unrelated to this incident.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakichi NOGE (played by Susumu FUJITA), who was Okochi&apos;s student and later marries Sachie was based on Hotsumi OZAKI, but of course the real Ozaki is unrelated to this incident.</e>
<cmt>Okawachi→Okochi、Hidemitsu OZAKI→Hotsumi OZAKIに訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>さらに学生によるデモ行進のシーンもあるが、実際には戦前のこの時期に学生デモが認められることはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a scene involving a demonstration march by students, but a student demonstration in this pre-war period would not have actually been allowed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a scene involving a demonstration march by students, but a student demonstration in this pre-war period would not have actually been allowed.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a scene involving a demonstration march by students, but a student demonstration in this pre-war period would not have actually been allowed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="47">
<j>近年ではかわぐちかいじの漫画作品『ジパング (かわぐちかいじ)』に「滝川事件に連座して京大理学部を免職になり、日本軍の原子爆弾計画に関与する科学者」という設定の倉田万作（モデルは『世界文化』同人として検挙されたことがあり、戦時期には理化学研究所を中心とする日本の原子爆弾開発に関わっていた物理学者・武谷三男であると思われる）が登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent years, the manga work of Kawaguchi Kaiji &quot;Jipang&quot; set Mansaku KURATA (the model is thought to be the physicist Mitsuo TAKETANI,who was involved in developing a nuclear bomb in Japan during the war period at Rikagaku Kenkyujo who had also been arrested as a member of &quot;Sekai Dojin&quot;) as a &quot;scientist who was working in the nuclear bomb plan of the Japanese army and was fired from the Faculty of Science in Kyoto University in relation with the Takigawa Incident&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent years, the manga work of Kawaguchi Kaiji &quot;Jipang&quot; set Mansaku KURATA (the model is thought to be the physicist Mitsuo TAKETANI, who was involved in developing a nuclear bomb in Japan during the war period at Rikagaku Kenkyujo who had also been arrested as a member of &quot;Sekai Dojin&quot;) as a &quot;scientist who was working on the nuclear bomb plan of the Japanese army and was fired from the Faculty of Science at Kyoto University in relation with the Takigawa Incident.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent years, the manga work of Kaiji KAWAGUCHI &quot;Jipang&quot; set Mansaku KURATA (the model is thought to be the physicist Mitsuo TAKETANI, who was involved in developing a nuclear bomb in Japan during the war period at Rikagaku Kenkyujo who had also been arrested as a member of &quot;Sekai Bunka&quot;) as a &apos;scientist who was working on the nuclear bomb plan of the Japanese army and was fired from the Faculty of Science at Kyoto University in relation with the Takigawa Incident.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Kawaguchi Kaiji→Kaiji KAWAGUCHI、&quot;Sekai Dojin&quot;→&quot;Sekai Bunka&quot;に修正、一部シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>滝川事件は法学部のみの処分で決着し、理学部とはほとんど関係のない事件であるので、この人物設定は歴史的な意味では正確さを欠くものともいえるが、「思想信条を理由に大学教員が弾圧された戦前の事件」としては象徴的な意味を今なお持っていることを示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The punishment related to the Takigawa Incident was concluded within the Faculty of Law and has almost nothing to do with the Faculty of Science, and although this character setting is inaccurate historically, it shows that the &quot;incident was the oppression of thinking and ideology of pre-war university staff&quot; has a figurative meaning to this day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The punishment related to the Takigawa Incident was concluded within the Faculty of Law and has almost nothing to do with the Faculty of Science, and although this character setting is inaccurate historically, it shows that the &quot;incident was the oppression of thinking and ideology of pre-war university staff&quot; has a figurative meaning to this day.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The punishment related to the Takigawa Incident was concluded within the Faculty of Law and has almost nothing to do with the Faculty of Science, and although this character setting is inaccurate historically, it shows that the &apos;incident was the oppression of thinking and ideology of pre-war university staff&apos; has a figurative meaning to this day.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Straysheep(id:42448), Tomchiukc(id:5469), たね(id:10372), Nonomura(id:72557), Tcyiswalk(id:7279), Jazzy(id:3202), Uraios(id:72687), 縹色の空(id:106156), Huugo(id:61491), 朝彦(id:9407), Kenpei(id:11349), 玄史生(id:43670), 下総大納言(id:43461), 代言人(id:33675), ジャビ(id:88014), まったけ(id:130042), Point136(id:211299), しようこ(id:89598), Component(id:146478), Longlongsummer(id:211232), M3HR(id:45797), Chuta(id:10457), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>