<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>高階氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takashina Clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takashina Clan (the clan of which the first son of Emperor Tenmu, Prince Takechi [Takechi no Miko] was the ancestor)</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takashina Clan (the clan of which the first son of Emperor Tenmu, Prince Takechi [Takechi no Miko] was the ancestor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>高階氏（たかしなし）は、天武天皇の長子、高市皇子を祖とする氏族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takashina clan is the clan in which the first son of Emperor Tenmu, Prince Takeuchi, is the ancestor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takashina clan is the clan of which the first son of Emperor Tenmu, Prince Takechi, was the ancestor.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takashina clan is the clan of which the first son of Emperor Tenmu, Prince Takechi, was the ancestor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>長屋王の変の際、父・長屋王（母：御名部皇女）と共に自害した桑田王の子・磯部王が助命され、その孫の峯緒王が承和 (日本)11年（844年）に臣籍降下して高階真人を賜る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuwata no Okimi killed himself together with his father Prince Nagaya (mother: Minabe no himemiko) at the time of Nagaya no Hen (Conspiracy of Nagayao); Prince Isobe, the son of Kuwata no Okimi, was spared his life and Prince Mineo, the grandson of Prince Isobe left the Imperial Family and was granted the hereditary title of TAKASHINA Mahito in 844.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Conspiracy of Nagayao occurred, Prince Isobe, a son of Prince Kuwata [Kuwata no Miko] who killed himself with his father Prince Nagaya (his mother Minabe no Himemiko), was spared his life and Prince Mineo, a grandson of Prince Isobe became subjects of the state to be granted the hereditary title of TAKASHINA Mahito in 844.</e>
<cmt>用語を合わせ、表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Conspiracy of Nagayao occurred, Prince Isobe, a son of Prince Kuwata [Kuwata no Miko] who killed himself with his father Prince Nagaya (his mother Minabe no Himemiko), was spared his life and Prince Mineo, a grandson of Prince Isobe became subjects of the state to be granted the hereditary title of TAKASHINA Mahito in 844.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>他に桑田王の異母兄弟である安宿王（母は藤原不比等の娘藤原長娥子）なども高階真人姓を賜ったが、いずれも早い段階で断絶した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Prince Asukabe who was the brother of Kuwata no Okimi by different mother (the mother was FUJIWARA no Nagako, daughter of FUJIWARA no Fuhito) and some others were also granted the hereditary title of TAKASHIMA no Mahito; however, the lineage of all of them ended at early stage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Asukabe who was a paternal half-brother of Prince Kuwata (his mother was FUJIWARA no Nagako, a daughter of FUJIWARA no Fuhito) and some others were also granted the hereditary title of TAKASHIMA no Mahito; however, each lineage ended at early stage.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせ、用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Asukabe who was a paternal half-brother of Prince Kuwata (his mother was FUJIWARA no Nagako, a daughter of FUJIWARA no Fuhito) and some others were also granted the hereditary title of TAKASHIMA no Mahito; however, each lineage ended at early stage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>峯緒は伊勢権守となり、斎宮・恬子内親王に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mineo became Ise Province&apos;s provincial governor and served Saigu Tenshi Naishinno.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mineo became Ise no Gon no kami (Provisional Governor of Ise Province) and served Saigu (Imperial Princess appointed to serve the deities of the Ise-jingu Shrine), Imperial Princess Tenshi (also known as Imperial Princess Yasuko).</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。原文には 「伊勢国」とありましたが、リンク先の単語のようです。ウェブで確認すると用語が「伊勢権守」となっており、本来はこちらの用語を使用していると思われますので、こちらを訳出し、原文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mineo became Ise no Gon no kami (Provisional Governor of Ise Province) and served Saigu (Imperial Princess appointed to serve the deities of the Ise-jingu Shrine), Imperial Princess Tenshi (also known as Imperial Princess Yasuko).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>一説によれば、内親王と在原業平が密通して生まれた男児を引き取り、高階師尚と名付け、自らの跡を嗣がせたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to some people, Saigu Teishi Naishinno and ARIWARA no Narihira committed adultery and the son was born and Mineo adopted this child and named him as TAKASHIMA no Morohisa and made the child his successor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to some people, Mineo adopted a boy named TAKASHIMA no Morohisa, who was born between the Imperial Princess and ARIWARA no Narihira by adultery, and had him succeed Mineo.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to some people, Mineo adopted a boy named TAKASHIMA no Morohisa, who was born between the Imperial Princess and ARIWARA no Narihira by adultery, and had him succeed Mineo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>以後、高階氏の人々は伊勢神宮に参拝することを控えるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People of Takashina clan came to refrain from going and worshipping at Ise-jingu Shrine afterward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People of the Takashina clan came to refrain from going and worshipping at Ise-jingu Shrine afterward.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People of the Takashina clan came to refrain from going and worshipping at Ise-jingu Shrine afterward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>尤も、この「師尚隠し子説」は事実無根という説も根強い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, some people consistently think this &apos;Moronao being illegitimate child&quot; theory is absolutely groundless.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, some people consistently think this &apos;Moronao being illegitimate child&apos; theory is absolutely groundless.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, some people consistently think this &apos;Moronao being illegitimate child&apos; theory is absolutely groundless.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>高階成忠の時に、娘・高階貴子が藤原道隆の正室となり一条天皇の中宮・藤原定子を産んでにわかに繁栄する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time of TAKASHINA no Naritada, his daughter TAKASHINA no Kishi became the legal wife of FUJIWARA no Michitaka and bore a daughter FUJIWARA no Teishi, who later became the Empress of Emperor Ichijo and the Takashina clan enjoyed sudden prosperity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time of TAKASHINA no Naritada, when his daughter TAKASHINA no Kishi became the legal wife of FUJIWARA no Michitaka and bore a daughter FUJIWARA no Teishi, who later became the chugu (the second consort of an emperor) of Emperor Ichijo, the Takashina clan enjoyed sudden prosperity.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time of TAKASHINA no Naritada, when his daughter TAKASHINA no Kishi became the legal wife of FUJIWARA no Michitaka and bore a daughter FUJIWARA no Teishi, who later became the chugu (the second consort of an emperor) of Emperor Ichijo, the Takashina clan enjoyed sudden prosperity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし、定子の生んだ敦康親王の即位は藤原道長に妨害され、成忠の子孫は中関白家と共に没落する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, enthronement of the Imperial Prince Atsuyasu whom Teishi bore was interfered by FUJIWARA no Michinaga and the descendants of Naritada fell along with the Nakanokanpaku family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, enthronement of the Imperial Prince Atsuyasu whom Teishi bore was interfered by FUJIWARA no Michinaga and the descendants of Naritada fell along with the Nakanokanpaku family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, enthronement of the Imperial Prince Atsuyasu whom Teishi bore was interfered by FUJIWARA no Michinaga and the descendants of Naritada fell along with the Nakanokanpaku family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>藤原行成が高階氏の血を引く敦康親王の即位は、伊勢神宮の怒りを買うと進言したことが大きな要因となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yukinari advised Imperial family that the enthronement of Imperial Prince Atsuyasu, to whom blood of Takashina clan is flown, will cause the anger of Ise Jingu Shrine; this advice became a big factor in excluding Atsuyasu from enthronement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The advice of FUJIWARA no Yukinari that the enthronement of Imperial Prince Atsuyasu, to whom blood of the Takashina clan was flown, would cause the anger of Ise-Jingu Shrine, was strong trigger for it.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The advice of FUJIWARA no Yukinari that the enthronement of Imperial Prince Atsuyasu, to whom blood of the Takashina clan was flown, would cause the anger of Ise-Jingu Shrine, was strong trigger for it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>成忠の弟・高階敏忠の系統は道長に接近して、受領として勢力を築く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The lineage of Naritada&apos;s younger brother TAKASHINA no Toshitada approached Michinaga, and built power as zuryo (provincial governor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lineage of Naritada&apos;s younger brother TAKASHINA no Toshitada approached Michinaga, and built power as zuryo (provincial governor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lineage of Naritada&apos;s younger brother TAKASHINA no Toshitada approached Michinaga, and built power as zuryo (provincial governor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>欲大弐と呼ばれた高階成章、白河法皇の近臣として法勝寺の造営を行った高階為家・高階為章親子などが代表である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The representative people in this lineage include TAKASHINA no Nariakira who was called Yokudaini, TAKASHINA no Tameie who executed construction of Hossho-ji Temple as a trusted vassal of the Cloistered Emperor Shirakawa, and the father and son of TAKASHINA no Tameie and TAKASHINA no Tameakira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The representative people in this lineage include TAKASHINA no Nariakira who was called Yoku-daini (Senior Assistant Governor General of desire), TAKASHINA no Tameie and his son TAKASHINA no Tameakira who executed construction of Hossho-ji Temple as a trusted vassals of the Cloistered Emperor Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The representative people in this lineage include TAKASHINA no Nariakira who was called Yoku-daini (Senior Assistant Governor General of desire), TAKASHINA no Tameie and his son TAKASHINA no Tameakira who executed construction of Hossho-ji Temple as a trusted vassals of the Cloistered Emperor Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>後白河天皇院政期にも後白河側近の大蔵省・高階泰経、寵妃・高階栄子が活躍する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the period when the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa was in power, the close adviser TAKASHINA no Yasutsune of the ministry of the Treasury, a favorite mistress TAKASHINA no Eishi were active.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the period when the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa was in power, the close adviser TAKASHINA no Yasutsune of the ministry of the Treasury, a favorite mistress TAKASHINA no Eishi were active.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the period when the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa was in power, the close adviser TAKASHINA no Yasutsune of the ministry of the Treasury, a favorite mistress TAKASHINA no Eishi were active.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>その後は有力者を輩出できず没落、南北朝時代 (日本)期の高階寛経を最後に、公卿が出なくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After these people, influential people ceased to come from the Takashana clan and the clan fell to obscurity; a last influential person was TAKASHINA no Hirotsune in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts in Japan; after him no court nobles came from the Takashina clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After them, the clan didn&apos;t have influential people then fell to obscurity; after TAKASHINA no Hirotsune in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts in Japan, no court nobles came from the Takashina clan.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After them, the clan didn&apos;t have influential people then fell to obscurity; after TAKASHINA no Hirotsune in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts in Japan, no court nobles came from the Takashina clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし代々足利家執事をつとめた高氏 が高階氏から出ているように、武家としてはその後も大いに繁栄している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as a military family, the clan has been very prosperous; for example, the Ko clan who has been the steward of the Ashikaga family for generations came from the Takashina clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as a samurai family, the clan has been very prosperous; for example, the Ko clan who has been the steward of the Ashikaga family for generations came from the Takashina clan.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as a samurai family, the clan has been very prosperous; for example, the Ko clan who has been the steward of the Ashikaga family for generations came from the Takashina clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>室町幕府の執事である高師直や織田信長、豊臣秀吉に仕え大名となった堀尾吉晴も高階氏の末裔とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KO no Muronao who was the steward of Muromachi Shogunate and Yoshiharu HORIO who served Nobunaga ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and became daimyo is to be said the descendant of Takashina clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KO no Muronao who was the steward of Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and Yoshiharu HORIO who served Nobunaga ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and became daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) were to be said the descendant of the Takashina clan.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせ、用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">KO no Muronao who was the steward of Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and Yoshiharu HORIO who served Nobunaga ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and became daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) were to be said the descendant of the Takashina clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Sakura-no-kuni(id:115977), 松茸(id:27535), Nate(id:165259), Alljal(id:46858), こぶまき(id:38278), Nalc(id:139567), Andee(id:20421), 越中掾(id:149423), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>