<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>御教書</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Migyosho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Migyosho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Migyosho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>御教書（みぎょうしょ、みきょうしょ）とは平安時代後期から室町時代にかけて、従三位以上及びそれに准じる地位にある人の家司が主の意思を奉じて発給した古文書の形態。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Migyosho (or Mikyosho) was the style of ancient documents issued, during the period from the late Heian period to Muromachi period, by Keishi (household superintendant) of people of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) or upper for the purpose of conveying their masters&apos; intention.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the late Heian period to the Muromachi period, a Migyosho (or Mikyosho) was a form of ancient document issued by a Keishi (household superintendant) with a court rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) or higher used for conveying the intentions of their masters.</e>
<cmt>rearranged sentence and fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Migyosho (or Mikyosho) was a form of ancient document issued by a Keishi (household superintendant) with a court rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) or higher used for conveying the intentions of their masters from the late Heian period to the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>&quot;From the late Heian period to the Muromachi period&quot;の位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>三位以下の公家や守護大名クラスの武士の家司・家僕が主の意思を奉じて発給した同形式の文書は奉書という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Documents of the same style issued by keishi/kaboku (servant) of nobilities whose rank was lower than Third Rank or shugodaimyo (military governor) for the purpose of conveying their masters&apos; intention was called hosho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Documents with the same style issued by Keishi or Kaboku (servant) of nobilities with a rank lower than Jusanmi or Shugodaimyo (military governor) used for conveying their masters&apos; intention was called hosho.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;Third Rank&quot; to &quot;Jusanmi&quot;; capitalized &quot;Shugodaimyo&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Documents with the same style issued by Keishi or Kaboku (servant) of nobilities with a rank lower than Jusanmi or Shugodaimyo (military governor) used for conveying their masters&apos; intention was called hosho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>形式論的には綸旨・院宣・令旨と同じ形態である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a matter of formal logic, its style was same with that of rinji (Imperial order), inzen (decree from the retired Emperor) and ryoji (orders issued by princes, empresses etc.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a matter of formality, Migyosho were written in the same style as Rinji (Imperial order), Inzen (decree from the Retired Emperor) and Ryoji (orders issued by princes, empresses etc.).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;formal logic&quot; to &quot;formality&quot; for &quot;形式論&quot;; made a more definite subject; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a matter of formality, Migyosho were written in the same style as Rinji (Imperial order), Inzen (decree from the Retired Emperor) and Ryoji (orders issued by princes, empresses etc.).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>形のうえでは私信であるが、身分の高い人物は直接自分では書かず、近臣に書かせるのが通例であるため、通常家司が書いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it was a private letter as a matter of style, it was usually written by keishi because it was common for people of high rank to get their close aides to write on behalf of them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although they were written in the style of a private letter, they were customarily written by a Keishi since it was common for those with high rank to have their close aides write on their behalf.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;usually&quot; to &quot;customarily&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although they were written in the style of a private letter, they were customarily written by a Keishi since it was common for those with high rank to have their close aides write on their behalf.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>そのため、差出人も家司であるが、必要に応じて主が袖判を加える事もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, its sender was also keishi and when necessary, the master added sodeban (signature) to it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, the sender was also a Keishi and the master would add their sodeban (signature) when necessary.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally; capitalized &quot;Keishi&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, the sender was also a Keishi and the master would add their sodeban (signature) when necessary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>文末に「仰旨如此」、「者依仰執達如件」、「由被仰下候」など、文意が主の意思である事を強調した文言が付けられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of text, a phrase emphasizing the fact that a letter was written according to master&apos;s intention, such as &quot;The above is what he said&quot;etc., was written.</e>
<cmt>「仰旨如此」、「者依仰執達如件」、「由被仰下候」はほぼ同意と思われ、区別して翻訳することも困難ですので、左記の通り一括して意訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of one of these documents, a phrase emphasizing that a letter was written in accordance with the intention of a master was added, such as, &quot;The statements above were made by him/her.&quot;</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of one of these documents, a phrase emphasizing that a letter was written in accordance with the intention of a master was added, such as, &apos;The statements above were made by him/her.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>下文が訴訟の判決、裁許状など効力が永久的になる正式文書であるのに対し、御教書は通達や緊急の命令などで、文書としての格は劣るものとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While kudashibumi (document issued by a superior or office) was an official document which was effective indefinitely, such as court ruling or license proof, Migyosho was a notice or emergency order and its status as a document was inferior to kudashibumi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a Migyosho was a notice or emergency order, its status as a document was inferior to a Kudashibumi (a document issued by a superior or office), which was an official document and effective indefinitely as a court ruling, license proof, etc..</e>
<cmt>rearrnaged sentence to read more naturally; changed &quot;such as&quot; to &quot;etc&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a Migyosho was a notice or emergency order, its status as a document was inferior to a Kudashibumi (a document issued by a superior or office), which was an official document and effective indefinitely as a court ruling, license proof, etc.</e>
<cmt>余分なピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>現存する最古の御教書は、永久 (元号)4年（1116年）10月12日 (旧暦)に藤原忠実により発給された文書である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The oldest Migyosho in existence was the one which was issued by FUJIWARA no Tadazane on October 12, 1116 (old calendar).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The oldest Migyosho still in existence was issued by FUJIWARA no Tadazane on October 12, 1116 (old calendar).</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;was the one which&quot; since it was wordy and unecessary; added &quot;still&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The oldest Migyosho still in existence was issued by FUJIWARA no Tadazane on November 25, 1116.</e>
<cmt>旧暦→新暦に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>摂家当主の御教書は「殿下御教書」と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Migyosho issued by the head of sekke (five top Fujiwara families whose members were eligible for the positions of sessho and kanpaku) was called &quot;Denka Migyosho&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Migyosho issued by the head of the Sekke (the top five Fujiwara families whose members were eligible for the positions of Sessho and Kanpaku) were called &quot;Denka Migyosho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>capitalized &quot;Sekke&quot; &quot;Sessho&quot; and &quot;Kanpaku&quot;; fixed period placement; added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Sekke&quot;; changed &quot;was&quot; to &quot;were&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Migyosho issued by the head of the Sekke (the top five Fujiwara families whose members were eligible for the positions of Sessho and Kanpaku) were called &apos;Denka Migyosho.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>源頼朝は下文・下知状・御教書を発給文書の三本柱として武家様文書の基礎を作った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minamoto no Yoritomo established the base of bukeyo monjo (a samurai-style document) consisted of three kinds of documents, namely kudashibumi, gejijo (a document issued by shogun&apos;s vassal for the purpose of conveying shogun&apos;s order) and Migyosho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minamoto no Yoritomo established the base of bukeyo monjo (a samurai-style document) which consisted of three kinds of documents. These were the Kudashibumi, Gejijo (a document issued by a vassal of the Shogun for conveying Shogun orders) and Migyosho.</e>
<cmt>capitalized &quot;Kudashibumi&quot; &quot;Gejijo&quot; and &quot;Shogun&quot;; split into two sentences for easier reading and fixed grammar accordingly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minamoto no Yoritomo established the base of bukeyo monjo (a samurai-style document) which consisted of three kinds of documents; these were the Kudashibumi, Gejijo (a document issued by a vassal of the Shogun for conveying Shogun orders) and Migyosho.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドで二文に分かれていますが、原文の分割が困難なため、セミコロンでつなぎました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>ただし、文治元年（1185年）4月27日 (旧暦)に従二位に昇進する以前は奉書と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Provided, however, that documents issued by Yoritomo prior to his promotion to Junii (Junior Second Grade) on April 27, 1185 (old calendar) were called hosho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Documents issued by Yoritomo prior to his promotion to Junii (Junior Second Rank) on April 27, 1185 (old calendar), however, were called hosho.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;Grade&quot; to &quot;Rank&quot; to follow the word list; changed &quot;Provided, however&quot; to &quot;however&quot; and used later in the sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Documents issued by Yoritomo prior to his promotion to Junii (Junior Second Rank) on June 4, 1185, however, were called hosho.</e>
<cmt>旧暦→新暦に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>頼朝没後も御教書は鎌倉幕府の公的意思を通達する手段として用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Yoritomo, Migyosho was used as the method of informing the official intention of Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Yoritomo, the Kamakura bakufu used Migyosho as the method for passing on information of official intentions.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;was&quot; to &quot;were&quot;; changed to sentence to active rather than passive; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Yoritomo, the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) used Migyosho as the method for passing on information of official intentions.</e>
<cmt>bakufuの補足追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>次第に御教書の使用頻度が増え、下文・下知状は衰える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gradually, use frequency of Migyosho increased while that of kudashibumi and gechijo decreased.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The frequency in which Migyosho were used gradually increased as the use of Kudashibumi and Gejijo decreased.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally; changed &quot;Gechijo&quot; to &quot;Gejijo&quot; for consistency</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The frequency in which Migyosho were used gradually increased as the use of Kudashibumi and Gejijo decreased.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>室町時代にはいると、御教書は下文・下知状を駆逐して幕府が発給する最上格の文書形式となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Muromachi period, Migyosho drove out kudashibumi and gejijo and became the highest ranking document style among documents issued by bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Muromachi period, Migyosho drove out Kudashibumi as well as Gejijo and became the highest ranking document style among documents issued by the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;In&quot; to &quot;During&quot;; capitalized &quot;Kudashibumi&quot; and &quot;Gejijo&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Muromachi period, Migyosho drove out Kudashibumi as well as Gejijo and became the highest ranking document style among documents issued by the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>しかし、それに伴って現れた私信である直状形式の御内書などが次第に広く用いられるようになり、御教書はやがて使われなくなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, gonaisho (official document) adopting the style of jikijo (a private document) came to be used around that time and Migyosho gradually fell into disuse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as Gonaisho (an official document) adopted the style of Jikijo (a private document) and came to be more wildey used, Migyosho gradually fell into disuse.</e>
<cmt>capitalized &quot;Gonaisho&quot; and &quot;Jikijo&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as Gonaisho (an official document) adopted the style of Jikijo (a private document) and came to be more wildey used, Migyosho gradually fell into disuse.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>今谷明は、足利義満が明に「日本国王」に冊封されたことを重視して、以降の義満の御教書を「国王御教書」と呼んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akira IMATANI emphasized the fact that Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA was conferred the title of &quot;King of Japan&quot; by the emperor of Ming and called Yoshimitsu&apos;s Migyosho &quot;King Migyosho&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In emphasis of the fact that Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA was conferred the title of &quot;King of Japan&quot; by the Emperor of Ming, Akira IMATANI called Yoshimitsu&apos;s Migyosho &quot;Migyosho of a King.&quot;</e>
<cmt>rearranged sentence to read more naturally and fixed grammar accordingly; capitalized &quot;Emperor&quot;; changed &quot;King Migyosho&quot; to &quot;Migyosho of a King&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In emphasis of the fact that Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA was conferred the title of &apos;King of Japan&apos; by the Emperor of Ming, Akira IMATANI called Yoshimitsu&apos;s Migyosho &apos;Migyosho of a King.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), Nalc(id:139567), 伏儀(id:142093), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), 怪蘇(id:45514), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>