<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>銀座 (歴史)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ginza (History)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ginza (History)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ginza (History)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>銀座(ぎんざ)とは、中近世の日本の政権において貨幣の鋳造および銀地金の買売を担った場所に与えられた呼称である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ginza is a name used for mints in the medieval and modern ages of Japan, where coins were manufactured and silver bullion was bought and sold.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ginza is a name used for mints in the medieval and modern ages of Japan, where coins were manufactured and silver bullion was bought and sold.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ginza is a name used for mints in the medieval and modern ages of Japan, where coins were manufactured and silver bullion was bought and sold.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>銀座は豊臣秀吉が大坂に常是座（じょうぜざ）を設けたことに始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ginza originates from the establishment of Joizeza in Osaka by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, where 20 silversmiths of Sakai and Kyoto were summoned to work for standardization of coinage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ginza originates from the establishment of Joizeza in Osaka by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI. 20 silversmiths from Sakai and Kyoto were summoned to Osaka to work for standardization of coinage.</e>
<cmt>needed editing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ginza originates from the establishment of Joizeza in Osaka by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>銀貨の統一に向けて堺市、京都の銀吹屋20人を集めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">20 silversmiths from Sakai and Kyoto were summoned to Osaka to work for standardization of coinage.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>その他、戦国時代 (日本)より現れた両替商兼銀細工師である銀屋（ぎんや）が各地で極印銀を鋳造し、銀座はこうした業者から成立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ginza was also formed by &quot;ginya,&quot; money changers who were also silver craftsmen and minted hallmarked silver coins in various parts of the country, starting in the Sengoku Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ginza was also formed by &quot;ginya,&quot; money changers who were also silver craftsmen and minted hallmarked silver coins in various parts of the country, starting in the Sengoku Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ginza was also formed by &quot;ginya,&quot; money changers who were also silver craftsmen and minted hallmarked silver coins in various parts of the country, starting in the Sengoku Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>例えば加賀藩では銀細工師集団である金沢市銀座があり江戸時代の初期にかけて領国貨幣である極印銀を鋳造した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kaga domain, for example, the Kanazawa city ginza had a group of silversmiths, who minted silver coins hallmarked as domain currency in the early Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kaga domain, for example, the Kanazawa city ginza had a group of silversmiths, who minted silver coins hallmarked as domain currency in the early Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kaga domain, for example, the Kanazawa city ginza had a group of silversmiths, who minted silver coins hallmarked as domain currency in the early Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>このような各地銀座が江戸時代まで続いた理由は、銀の海外流出などにより慶長丁銀が地方まで充分に行き渡らなかったことに起因する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The presence of ginza in various parts of the country until the Edo Period was caused by the shortage of Keicho chogin coins in areas outside Edo, due silver being exported out of the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The presence of ginza in various parts of the country until the Edo Period was caused by the shortage of Keicho chogin coins in areas outside Edo, due silver being exported out of the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The presence of ginza in various parts of the country until the Edo Period was caused by the shortage of Keicho chogin coins in areas outside Edo, due silver being exported out of the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>銀座といえば主に徳川家康が開いた江戸幕府の銀座が知られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The most famous ginza is the ginza of the Edo shogunate that was opened by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, which was an organization of commoners who were granted license from the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The most famous was the Edo shogunate ginza that was opened by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA. That was an organization of commoners who were granted license from the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>needed editing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The most famous was the Edo shogunate ginza that was opened by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>これは徳川家により特許された御用達町人による組織であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That was an organization of commoners who were granted license from the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>当時の主な通貨のうちの銀貨の鋳造が行われたこと、この場所以外での貨幣鋳造が厳しく取り締まられたこと、などにより「銀・座」の名が付けられたと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name &quot;gin (silver)&quot; and &quot;za (place)&quot; is believed to originate from the fact that a mint chiefly issuing silver coins was located there and also that minting such coins in other areas was strictly controlled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name &quot;gin (silver)&quot; and &quot;za (place)&quot; is believed to originate from the fact that a mint chiefly issuing silver coins was located there and also that minting such coins in other areas was strictly controlled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name &quot;gin (silver)&quot; and &quot;za (place)&quot; is believed to originate from the fact that a mint chiefly issuing silver coins was located there and also that minting such coins in other areas was strictly controlled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>銀座は極印打および包封を行う常是役所（じょうぜやくしょ）、および座人が会同する銀座役所（ぎんざやくしょ）よりなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ginza consisted of the jouze-yakusho, the office in charge of printing hallmarks of authenticity and wrapping minted coins, and ginza-yakusho where the officers of the ginza assembled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ginza consisted of the jouze-yakusho, the office in charge of printing hallmarks of authenticity and wrapping minted coins, and ginza-yakusho where the officers of the ginza assembled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ginza consisted of the jouze-yakusho, the office in charge of printing hallmarks of authenticity and wrapping minted coins, and ginza-yakusho where the officers of the ginza assembled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>常是役所は京都は湯浅作兵衛の長男である大黒作右衛門、江戸は次男である大黒長左衛門が銀改役となり以後世襲制となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The jouze-yakusho post was hereditary, with Sakuemon DAIKOKU, the eldest son of Sakuemon YUASA, assuming the post in Kyoto and Saemon DAIKOKU, the second son of the same, in charge of silver mint inspection as gin-aratameyaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The jouze-yakusho post was hereditary, with Sakuemon DAIKOKU, the eldest son of Sakuemon YUASA, assuming the post in Kyoto and Saemon DAIKOKU, the second son of the same, in charge of silver mint inspection as gin-aratameyaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The jouze-yakusho post was hereditary, with Sakuemon DAIKOKU, the eldest son of Sakuemon YUASA, assuming the post in Kyoto and Saemon DAIKOKU, the second son of the same, in charge of silver mint inspection as gin-aratameyaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>慶應2年（1866年）、幕府が改税約書によりイギリス、フランス、アメリカ合衆国、オランダ四ヵ国と交わした自由造幣局設立の確約を受け、慶應4年（1868年）4月17日、明治維新は金座および銀座を接収した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the pledge to establish a free currency minting bureau in the amended tariff treaty the Edo shogunate concluded with Britain, France, the United States and Holland in 1866, the ginza and the kinza were closed with the Meiji Restoration on April 17, 1868, and the currency office established under Dajokan (Grand Council of State) minted 2-bu gold coins and 1-bu silver coins at the former kinza and ginza but closed on February 5, 1869.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With a pledge to establish a free currency minting bureau in the amended tariff treaty that the Edo shogunate concluded with Britain, France, the United States and Holland in 1866, the ginza and the kinza were closed with the Meiji Restoration on April 17, 1868. The currency office established under Dajokan (Grand Council of State) minted 2-bu gold coins and 1-bu silver coins at the former kinza and ginza but it closed on February 5, 1869.</e>
<cmt>needed editing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With a pledge to establish a free currency minting bureau in the amended tariff treaty that the Edo shogunate concluded with Britain, France, the United States and Holland in 1866, the ginza and the kinza were closed with the Meiji Restoration on April 17, 1868.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>同月21日、太政官に設立された貨幣司（かへいし）は旧金座、銀座で二分金および一分銀などを鋳造し、明治2年（1869年）2月5日に廃止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 21, the currency office established under Dajokan (Grand Council of State) minted 2-bu gold coins and 1-bu silver coins at the former kinza and ginza but it closed on February 5, 1869.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処、同月21日→訳漏れ</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>伏見・銀座町</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fushimi-ginza-cho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fushimi-ginza-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fushimi-ginza-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>関ヶ原の戦いに勝利した徳川家康は、日本国内の覇権を意識し、1601年(慶長6年)、京都伏見区の伏見城下に貨幣鋳造所を設立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his triumph in the Battle of Sekigahara, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA set up a mint near Fushimi Castle in Fushimi-ku, Kyoto, in 1601 and ordered the Sakai money changer Sakubei YUASA to supervise the operation, which was headed Yoshikata SUEYOSHI (Kanbei Yoshikata HIRANO (SUEYOSHI) and his son Yoshiyasu (Saemon Yoshiyasu SUEYOSHI) of the powerful merchant clan of Hirano-go, Sumiyoshi-gun, Settsu Province (present-day Hirano-ku, Osaka City), along with Tojiro HIRANO and Kuemon HIRANO of the same clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his triumph in the Battle of Sekigahara, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA set up a mint near Fushimi Castle in Fushimi-ku, Kyoto, in 1601. There, he ordered the Sakai money changer Sakubei YUASA to supervise the operation, which was headed Yoshikata SUEYOSHI (Kanbei Yoshikata HIRANO (SUEYOSHI) and his son Yoshiyasu (Saemon Yoshiyasu SUEYOSHI). They were a powerful merchant clan of Hirano-go, Sumiyoshi-gun, Settsu Province (present-day Hirano-ku, Osaka City), along with the Tojiro HIRANO and Kuemon HIRANO of the same clan.</e>
<cmt>needed editing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his triumph in the Battle of Sekigahara, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA set up a mint near Fushimi Castle in Fushimi-ku, Kyoto, in 1601.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>堺の両替商、湯浅作兵衛に命じて取り仕切らせ、頭役には、末吉氏の末吉利方(平野(末吉)勘兵衛利方)と子の末吉吉康（吉安）(末吉孫左衛門吉康)がなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There, he ordered the Sakai money changer Sakubei YUASA to supervise the operation, which was headed Yoshikata SUEYOSHI (Kanbei Yoshikata HIRANO (SUEYOSHI) and his son Yoshiyasu (Saemon Yoshiyasu SUEYOSHI).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>彼らは摂津国住吉郡平野郷(大阪市平野区)の豪商で、同族の平野藤次郎、平野九右衛門も頭役となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were a powerful merchant clan of Hirano-go, Sumiyoshi-gun, Settsu Province (present-day Hirano-ku, Osaka City), along with the Tojiro HIRANO and Kuemon HIRANO of the same clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>極印方の湯浅作兵衛は徳川家より大黒常是（だいこくじょうぜ）という姓名を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the officer in charge of stamping hallmarks, Sakubei YUASA was granted the new family name DAIKOKUJOUZE from the Tokugawa family and from then on stamped the name &quot;Jouze&quot; on newly minted coins as hallmark and wrapped them with official seals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the officer in charge of stamping hallmarks, Sakubei YUASA was granted the new family name DAIKOKUJOUZE from the Tokugawa family. From then on he stamped the name &quot;Jouze&quot; on newly minted coins as a hallmark and wrapped them with official seals.</e>
<cmt>needed editing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the officer in charge of stamping hallmarks, Sakubei YUASA was granted the new family name DAIKOKUJOUZE from the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これ以降大黒常是家は鋳造された銀貨に「常是」の略号を刻印して銀貨の極印・包装を担当した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From then on he stamped the name &quot;Jouze&quot; on newly minted coins as a hallmark and wrapped them with official seals.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>このため、銀座で出された銀貨の包みを常是包と呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, the wrapping used for silver coins issued at the Ginza was called Jouze-zutsumi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, the wrapping used for silver coins issued at the Ginza was called Jouze-zutsumi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, the wrapping used for silver coins issued at the Ginza was called Jouze-zutsumi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="20">
<j>徳川幕府の中枢が移るに従い駿府にも銀座が設けられ、さらに慶長13年（1608年）に伏見銀座は京都両替町、続いて慶長17年（1612年）に駿河銀座は江戸新両替町に移された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The location of the ginza moved with the transition of power of the Tokugawa shogunate, with ginza created in Sunpu, followed by Fushimi-ginza in Kyoto Ryogae-cho in 1608 and Suruga-ginza in Edo Shinryogae-cho in 1612, marking the full transition of minting function to Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The location of the ginza moved with the transition of power of the Tokugawa shogunate, with ginza created in Sunpu, followed by Fushimi-ginza in Kyoto Ryogae-cho in 1608 and Suruga-ginza in Edo Shinryogae-cho in 1612. This marked the full transition of minting function to Edo.</e>
<cmt>needed editing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The location of the ginza moved with the transition of power of the Tokugawa shogunate, with ginza created in Sunpu, followed by Fushimi-ginza in Kyoto Ryogae-cho in 1608 and Suruga-ginza in Edo Shinryogae-cho in 1612.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>銀座の貨幣鋳造機能は江戸に全て移された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This marked the full transition of minting function to Edo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>駿府・銀座</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sunpu-ginza</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sunpu-ginza</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sunpu-ginza</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>慶長11年（1606年）徳川家康が隠居の地、駿府城築城と同時進行に設立したとされる銀座である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sunpu-ginza was created alongside the construction of Sunpu Castle, where Ieyasu TOKUGAWA retired in 1606, and has manned in alternate shifts by zajin officers and jouze inspectors from Kyoto-ginza since 1611.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sunpu-ginza was created alongside the construction of Sunpu Castle, where Ieyasu TOKUGAWA retired in 1606. It has been manned in alternate shifts by zajin officers and jouze inspectors from Kyoto-ginza since 1611.</e>
<cmt>needed editing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sunpu-ginza was established in 1606 alongside the Sunpu-jyo Castle, where Ieyasu TOKUGAWA lived after his retirement, and the ginza was manned in alternate shifts by zajin officers and jouze inspectors from Kyoto-ginza since 1611.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>慶長16年（1611年）より京都銀座より座人および常是役人が勤番交代で詰めたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been manned in alternate shifts by zajin officers and jouze inspectors from Kyoto-ginza since 1611.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>主に駿府城の蓄財としての分銅銀、丁銀を鋳造することが目的であったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The objective is believed to be the minting of silver ingots and chogin silver that had been stored in Sunpu Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The objective is believed to be the minting of silver ingots and chogin silver that had been stored in Sunpu Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The objective is believed to be the minting of silver ingots and chogin silver that had been stored in Sunpu Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>慶長17年（1612年）に駿府銀座の機能は江戸へ移転したが、この地は現在静岡市葵区両替町として名残を有する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The functions of Sunpu-ginza moved to Edo in 1612, but the name remains in the location as Ryogae-cho, Aoi-ku, Shizuoka City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The functions of Sunpu-ginza moved to Edo in 1612, but the name remains in the location as Ryogae-cho, Aoi-ku, Shizuoka City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The functions of Sunpu-ginza moved to Edo in 1612, but the name remains in the location as Ryogae-cho, Aoi-ku, Shizuoka City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>京都・銀座</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto-ginza</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto-ginza</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto-ginza</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>慶長13年（1608年）、伏見銀座より移転し、京都の室町通と烏丸通の中間、二条通から三条通までの四町（二条下ル、押小路通下ル、御池通下ル、姉小路通下ル）に亘って拝領して設立され、この地を両替町通と称するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto-ginza was created with the move from Fushimi-ginza in 1608 to the location between Muromachi-dori Street and Karasuma-dori Street and across 4 town blocks south of Nijo-dori Street, Oshikoji-dori Street, Oike-dori Street and Aneyakoji-dori Street, which came to be known as Ryogaecho-dori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto-ginza was created with the move from Fushimi-ginza in 1608 to the location between Muromachi-dori Street and Karasuma-dori Street and across 4 town blocks south of Nijo-dori Street, Oshikoji-dori Street, Oike-dori Street and Aneyakoji-dori Street, which came to be known as Ryogaecho-dori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto-ginza was created with the move from Fushimi-ginza in 1608 to the location between Muromachi-dori Street and Karasuma-dori Street and across 4 town blocks south of Nijo-dori Street, Oshikoji-dori Street, Oike-dori Street and Aneyakoji-dori Street, which came to be known as Ryogaecho-dori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>この各地銀座所在地の両替町という名称は諸国の銀山より産出される灰吹銀を、銀座が公鋳の丁銀を以って買い入れることを南鐐替（なんりょうがえ）と称したことによる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name Ryogae-cho found in various ginzas is due to the fact that cupellated silver from various silver mines in the country was purchased by each ginza with the officially minted chogin silver, and this trade was named Nangyo-gin silver exchange.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name Ryogae-cho found in various ginzas is due to the fact that cupellated silver from various silver mines in the country was purchased by each ginza with the officially minted chogin silver, and this trade was named Nangyo-gin silver exchange.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name Ryogae-cho found in various ginzas is due to the fact that cupellated silver from various silver mines in the country was purchased by each ginza with the officially minted chogin silver, and this trade was named Nangyo-gin silver exchange.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>京都銀座では常是屋敷は両替町御池の北東側角にあり、銀座役所はその北側に隣接していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kyoto-ginza, the Jouze estate is located at the northeastern corner of Ryogaecho-oike, with the ginza office adjoining it to the north--an area arrangement that was applied also in Edo-ginza.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kyoto-ginza, the Jouze estate is located at the northeastern corner of Ryogaecho-oike, with the ginza office adjoining it to the north. This arrangement was adopted by Edo-ginza.</e>
<cmt>needed editing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kyoto-ginza, the Jouze estate is located at the northeastern corner of Ryogaecho-oike, with the ginza office adjoining it to the north.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>江戸銀座の町割りもこれに準ずるものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This arrangement was adopted by Edo-ginza.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="30">
<j>銀座移転前のこの地は染物屋が多く集居していたが、西洞院通蛸薬師通付近に替地を与えられ立ち退いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the ginza was set up, the area had a high concentration of cloth-dyeing shops, which moved to replacement land granted near Nishinotoin-dori and Takoyakushi-dori streets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the ginza was set up, the area had a high concentration of cloth-dyeing shops, which moved to replacement land granted near Nishinotoin-dori and Takoyakushi-dori streets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the ginza was set up, the area had a high concentration of cloth-dyeing shops, which moved to replacement land granted near Nishinotoin-dori and Takoyakushi-dori streets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="31">
<j>銀遣いの上方にあることから丁銀鋳造の中心地となり、駿河、後に江戸とともに貨幣鋳造を担い、これは寛政12年（1800年）の銀座改革まで続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Located in the Osaka area where coinage was used heavily, it became the center of Chogin silver minting and continued to operate alongside other ginzas in Sunpu and later in Edo, until the ginza reform in 1800.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Located in the Osaka area where coinage was used heavily, it became the center of Chogin silver minting and continued to operate alongside other ginzas in Sunpu and later in Edo, until the ginza reform in 1800.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Located in the Osaka area where coinage was used heavily, it became the center of Chogin silver minting and continued to operate alongside other ginzas in Sunpu and later in Edo, until the ginza reform in 1800.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>大坂・銀座</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Osaka-ginza</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Osaka-ginza</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Osaka-ginza</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="32">
<j>慶長13年（1608年）（慶長11年との説も有り確定的でない）大坂高麗橋東一丁目両替町に設立された銀座は、主に生野銀山および石見銀山からの灰吹銀および大坂銅吹所における粗銅からの絞銀を集積して京都の銀座に送る役割を果たした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ginza located in Ryogaecho, Koraibashi-higashi 1-chome, Osaka, was established in 1608 (or 1606, according to another report) for the purpose of gathering cupellated silver from Ikuno and Iwami silver mines and silver extracted from silver ore at the Osaka Dobukijo refinery and sending them to the ginza in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ginza located in Ryogaecho, Koraibashi-higashi 1-chome, Osaka, was established in 1608 (or 1606, according to another report) for the purpose of gathering cupellated silver from Ikuno and Iwami silver mines and silver extracted from silver ore at the Osaka Dobukijo refinery and sending them to the ginza in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ginza located in Ryogaecho, Koraibashi-higashi 1-chome, Osaka, was established in 1608 (or 1606, according to another report) for the purpose of gathering cupellated silver from Ikuno and Iwami silver mines and silver extracted from silver ore at the Osaka Dobukijo refinery and sending them to the ginza in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>銀遣いである商業の中心地にあって京都銀座の出見世（でみせ）としての機能を果たした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Located in the center of commerce where silver coins were used, the ginza served as an outlet for Kyoto-ginza</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Located in the center of commerce where silver coins were used, the ginza served as an outlet for Kyoto-ginza</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Located in the center of commerce where silver coins were used, the ginza served as an outlet for Kyoto-ginza</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>江戸・銀座</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edo-ginza</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edo-ginza</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edo-ginza</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>銀座歴史を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">See the history of Ginza.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">See the history of Ginza.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">See the history of Ginza.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>慶長17年（1612年）に駿府銀座より移転し、通町京橋 (東京都中央区)より南へ四町までを拝領して、既に江戸金座が本両替町と呼ばれていたことから、この地を新両替町と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sunpu-ginza was moved Edo in 1612, to occupy the 4 town blocks south of Torimachi Kyobashi (Chuo-ku Tokyo), which was then called Shin-ryogae-cho, because there already was Hon-ryogae-cho where Edo-kinza was located.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sunpu-ginza was moved Edo in 1612, to occupy the 4 town blocks south of Torimachi Kyobashi (Chuo-ku Tokyo), which was then called Shin-ryogae-cho, because there already was Hon-ryogae-cho where Edo-kinza was located.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sunpu-ginza was moved Edo in 1612, to occupy the 4 town blocks south of Torimachi Kyobashi (Chuo-ku Tokyo), which was then called Shin-ryogae-cho, because there already was Hon-ryogae-cho where Edo-kinza was located.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>京都の銀座より座人が一年毎に勤番交代を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ginza was run by mind officials from the ginza in Kyoto, alternating shifts once every year.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ginza was run by mind officials from the ginza in Kyoto, alternating shifts once every year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ginza was run by officials from the ginza in Kyoto, alternating shifts once every year.</e>
<cmt>mind削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>現在この地は銀座二丁目にあたり、「銀座」は繁華街の代名詞となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The location is what is now Ginza 2-chome and became synonymous with major shopping districts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The location is what is now Ginza 2-chome and became synonymous with major shopping districts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The location is what is now Ginza 2-chome and became synonymous with major shopping districts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="38">
<j>明和年間以前は銀座は専ら丁銀および豆板銀すなわち秤量銀貨を鋳造した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before Meiwa Period, the ginza minted coins was based on weight, such as Chogin silver and mameitagin silver.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before Meiwa Period, the ginza minted coins was based on weight, such as Chogin silver and mameitagin silver.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before Meiwa Period, the ginza minted coins was based on weight, such as Chogin silver and mameitagin silver.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>だが、明和2年（1765年）9月の五匁銀発行を皮切りに明和9年(1772年)9月の南鐐二朱銀発行以降は計数銀貨の鋳造が主流となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, currency based on value stamped on the coin became mainstream with the issue of Gomommegin in September 1765, followed by others such as the Nangyo nishu-gin of September 1772.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, currency based on value stamped on the coin became mainstream with the issue of Gomommegin in September 1765, followed by others such as the Nangyo nishu-gin of September 1772.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, currency based on value stamped on the coin became mainstream with the issue of Gomommegin in September 1765, followed by others such as the Nangyo nishu-gin of September 1772.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="40">
<j>加えて明和5年（1768年）から寛永通寳真鍮當四文 (通貨単位)銭の鋳造を請負い、これ以降、文久永宝に至るまで四文銭の鋳造は銀座の指導監督のもと行われることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ginza later became responsible for minting the Kan&apos;ei Tsuho shinchu-yonmon (currency unit) coin from 1768, marking the start of yonmon coin minting under the supervision of the ginza until the Bunkyu and Eiho periods</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ginza later became responsible for minting the Kan&apos;ei Tsuho shinchu-yonmon (currency unit) coin from 1768, marking the start of yonmon coin minting under the supervision of the ginza until the Bunkyu and Eiho periods</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ginza later became responsible for minting the Kan&apos;ei Tsuho shinchu-yonmon (currency unit) coin from 1768, marking the start of yonmon coin minting under the supervision of the ginza until the Bunkyu and Eiho periods</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="41">
<j>寛政12年（1800年）6月、江戸銀座において不正行為が発覚したことを機に、銀改役の大黒長左衛門八代目常房は家職放免の上、永蟄居を命じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the exposure of illegalities at Edo-ginza in June 1800, the silver coin inspection officer Chozaemon VIII Tsunefusa of the DAIKOKU family was dismissed and ordered to lifetime house arrest, subsequently replaced by Sakuemon IX Tsuneaki of the same family summoned to Edo from Kyoto-ginza and henceforth serving as inspection officer for both ginzas in Kyoto and Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the exposure of illegalities at Edo-ginza in June 1800, the silver coin inspection officer Chozaemon VIII Tsunefusa of the DAIKOKU family was dismissed and placed under house arrest for life. Subsequently, he replaced by Sakuemon IX Tsuneaki of the same family summoned to Edo from Kyoto-ginza and henceforth serving as inspection officer for both ginzas in Kyoto and Edo.</e>
<cmt>needed editing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the exposure of illegalities at Edo-ginza in June 1800, the silver coin inspection officer Chozaemon VIII Tsunefusa of the DAIKOKU family was dismissed and placed under house arrest for life.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>その後京都銀座から大黒作右衛門九代目常明が江戸へ招致され、京都および江戸両座の銀改役を兼任することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, he replaced by Sakuemon IX Tsuneaki of the same family summoned to Edo from Kyoto-ginza and henceforth serving as inspection officer for both ginzas in Kyoto and Edo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>この銀座粛正の後、座人は15人に縮小され、同年11月に日本橋蛎殻町（現在の日本橋人形町）に移転される事が申し渡され、南鐐二朱判鋳造が再開された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After reorganization of the ginza, the number of officers was reduced to 15, and the mint was ordered to be moved to Nihonbashi-kakigaara-cho (present-day Nihonbashi Ningyocho) for resumption of Nanryo nishuban coins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After reorganization of the ginza, the number of officers was reduced to 15, and the mint was ordered to be moved to Nihonbashi-kakigaara-cho (present-day Nihonbashi Ningyocho) for resumption of Nanryo nishuban coins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After reorganization of the ginza, the number of officers was reduced to 15, and the mint was ordered to be moved to Nihonbashi-kakigaara-cho (present-day Nihonbashi Ningyocho) for resumption of Nanryo nishuban coins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>移転は翌享和元年（1801年）7月に完了した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The move was completed in July 1801.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The move was completed in July 1801.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The move was completed in July 1801.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>それ以降、貨幣鋳造は江戸銀座に集約され、京都、大坂の銀座は貨幣吹替えの際の旧銀貨の回収、引換を行なった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, minting was consolidated at Edo-ginza, with the ginzas in Kyoto and Osaka in charge of recovering and exchanging old currency in case of new issue and of purchasing silver buillon and wrapping and sealing silver coins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, minting was consolidated at Edo-ginza, with the ginzas in Kyoto and Osaka in charge of recovering and exchanging old currency for new issues. They were also in charge of purchasing silver bullion and wrapping and sealing silver coins.</e>
<cmt>needed editing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, minting was consolidated at Edo-ginza, with the ginzas in Kyoto and Osaka in charge of recovering and exchanging old currency for new issues.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>銀地金の買上および銀貨の包封などの役割りにとどまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were also in charge of purchasing silver bullion and wrapping and sealing silver coins.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>長崎・銀座</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagasaki-ginza</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagasaki-ginza</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagasaki-ginza</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="47">
<j>慶長19年（1614年）（設立時期は諸説あり確定的でない）に長崎市芊（すすき）原、後に大村町、島原町北入込に設立された銀座は、主に銀の海外への不正持ち出しの監視、良質灰吹銀輸出の防止の役割を果たし、京の銀座より銀見役および銀座手代が一年毎に交代派遣された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagasaki-ginza reportedly established in 1614 (exact date unknown) in Susukihara in Nagasaki City and later in Omuracho, Shimabaracho and Kitairikomi operated chiefly to prevent illegal export of silver and prevent outflow of quality cupellated silver and was staffed by a silver inspector or ginza assistant manager dispatched alternately for one-year assignments.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagasaki-ginza reportedly established in 1614 (exact date unknown) in Susukihara in Nagasaki City and later in Omuracho, Shimabaracho and Kitairikomi operated chiefly to prevent illegal export of silver and prevent outflow of quality cupellated silver and was staffed by a silver inspector or ginza assistant manager dispatched alternately for one-year assignments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagasaki-ginza reportedly established in 1614 (exact date unknown) in Susukihara in Nagasaki City and later in Omuracho, Shimabaracho and Kitairikomi operated chiefly to prevent illegal export of silver and prevent outflow of quality cupellated silver and was staffed by a silver inspector or ginza assistant manager dispatched alternately for one-year assignments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="48">
<j>銀山から山出しされた灰吹銀は原則として銀座が買上、丁銀に鋳造することになっていたが、灰吹銀を銀座に売り渡さず直接長崎に送り利益を得る者が続出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although cupellated silver coming from silver mines was purchased by the ginza as a rule for minting into Chogin silver, many sought to make profits by shipping the ore directly to Nagasaki rather than selling it to the ginza.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although cupellated silver coming from silver mines was purchased by the ginza as a rule for minting into Chogin silver, many sought to make profits by shipping the ore directly to Nagasaki rather than selling it to the ginza.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although cupellated silver coming from silver mines was purchased by the ginza as a rule for minting into Chogin silver, many sought to make profits by shipping the ore directly to Nagasaki rather than selling it to the ginza.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>そのため幕府は慶長14年（1609年）に灰吹銀輸出を禁止、慶長銀で決済するよう定め、監視を強めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, the shogunate banned cupellated silver export in 1609, enforced trade in Keicho silver and strengthened surveillance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, the shogunate banned cupellated silver export in 1609, enforced trade in Keicho silver and strengthened surveillance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, the shogunate banned cupellated silver export in 1609, enforced trade in Keicho silver and strengthened surveillance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>しかし銅を20%含有する、より品位の低い慶長銀により決済しなければならないというものは、外国人にとって甚だ迷惑なものであり、上銀に精錬し直さなければならなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, foreign traders found the Keicho silver, containing 20% lead and lower in quality, extremely troublesome because it required refining into quality silver, leading to the creation of forged Daikoku coins with fake Keiko stamp impression from good cupellated silver and used for export and to smuggling of a substantial amount of silver out of the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, foreign traders found the Keicho silver, containing 20% lead and lower in quality, extremely troublesome because it required refining into quality silver. This lead to the creation of forged Daikoku coins with fake Keiko stamp impressions made from good cupellated silver. They were used for exporting and smuggling substantial amounts of silver out of the country.</e>
<cmt>needed editing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, foreign traders found the Keicho silver, containing 20% lead and lower in quality, extremely troublesome because it required refining into quality silver.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>良質灰吹銀に偽造の慶長銀の極印を打ち「似せ大黒」を作成し、輸出するといったことも行われ、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This lead to the creation and export of forged Daikoku coins with fake Keiko stamp impressions made from good cupellated silver.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処　”輸出する・・・”の記述が和文と合わないため変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>相当量の灰吹銀が監視の目を逃れて不正に持ち出され流出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Substantial amounts of cupellated silver were illegally smuggled out in secret and flowed out of the country.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処,&quot;監視の目を逃れて不正に&quot;訳漏れ</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="53">
<j>寛政12年の銀座改革に伴い廃止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ginza was abolished with the ginza reform of 1801.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ginza was abolished with the ginza reform of 1801.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ginza was abolished with the ginza reform of 1801.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>丁銀の鋳造法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chogin silver minting method</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chogin silver minting method</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chogin silver minting method</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="54">
<j>銀貨鋳造の吹元銀には大別して二通りの形式があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cupellated silver minting was divided largely into two types.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cupellated silver minting was divided largely into two types.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cupellated silver minting was divided largely into two types.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>一つは諸国の私領銀山より産出される灰吹銀および世上流通の灰吹銀を買い上げ、丁銀に吹き立て利益の一部を運上する、買灰吹銀（かいはいふきぎん）（寄銀）による自家営業形式。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One was Kaihaifukigin, private operation based on purchase of cupellated silver from silver mines located in private properties and of silver available in the marketplace to forge Chogin silver for income from part of the revenues.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One was Kaihaifukigin, private operation based on purchase of cupellated silver from silver mines located in private properties and of silver available in the marketplace to forge Chogin silver for income from part of the revenues.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One was Kaihaifukigin, private operation based on purchase of cupellated silver from silver mines located in private properties and of silver available in the marketplace to forge Chogin silver for income from part of the revenues.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>もう一つは石見、生野、佐渡金山などの天領にある銀山から上納される、公儀灰吹銀（こうぎはいふきぎん）（御銀）を預り丁銀に吹き立てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The other was the official minting with shogunate-property cupellated silver from shogunate-owned silver mines in Iwami, Ikuno and Sado Kinzan for minting Chogin silver.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The other was the official minting with shogunate-property cupellated silver from shogunate-owned silver mines in Iwami, Ikuno and Sado Kinzan for minting Chogin silver.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The other was the official minting with shogunate-property cupellated silver from shogunate-owned silver mines in Iwami, Ikuno and Sado Kinzan for minting Chogin silver.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>その鋳造高に対する3%を分一銀（ぶいちぎん）として銀座が受け取り、残りを上納する御用達形式があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">3% of the mint volume was granted to the ginza as its share (buichi-gin) and the rest shipped to the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">3% of the mint volume was granted to the ginza as its share (buichi-gin) and the rest shipped to the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">3% of the mint volume was granted to the ginza as its share (buichi-gin) and the rest shipped to the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>なお元禄以降の貨幣吹替えの際、回収された旧貨幣を吹元とする場合の取り扱いは御用達形式に準じるものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The official minting method was adopted for the reminting of recovered older silver coins at currency changes that took place in the Genroku Period and thereafter.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The official minting method was adopted for the reminting of recovered older silver coins at currency changes that took place in the Genroku Period and thereafter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The official minting method was adopted for the reminting of recovered older silver coins at currency changes that took place in the Genroku Period and thereafter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>釻場（ませば）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maseba</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maseba</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maseba</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="59">
<j>吹元銀として、幕府御金蔵より渡す灰吹銀、回収された古銀、銀座が買い上げた灰吹銀などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Silver used for minting consisted of cupellated silver from the shogunate reserves, recovered old coins and cupellated silver purchased by the ginza.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Silver used for minting consisted of cupellated silver from the shogunate reserves, recovered old coins and cupellated silver purchased by the ginza.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Silver used for minting consisted of cupellated silver from the shogunate reserves, recovered old coins and cupellated silver purchased by the ginza.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>釻とは灰吹銀の意味である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;mase&quot; of maseba means cupellated silver.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;mase,&quot; which comes from the word maseba, means cupellated silver.</e>
<cmt>needed editing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;mase,&quot; which comes from the word maseba, means cupellated silver.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>吹元銀は釻場（ませば）で質量を改め、銀見役により品位が改められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cupellated silver was reassessed of its silver content at the maseba and its quality determined by the silver inspector. Those determined to have 95% silver content or higher (gobu-ire) were used without refining</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cupellated silver was reassessed of its silver content at the maseba and its quality determined by the silver inspector. Those determined to have 95% silver content or higher (gobu-ire) were used without refining</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cupellated silver was reassessed of its silver content at the maseba and its quality determined by the silver inspector.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>五分入れ（銀95%）の品位以上のものはそのまま用いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those determined to have 95% silver content or higher (gobu-ire) were used without refining.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処,　ピリオド付加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>それ以下のものは精錬し直して、最上位の一割入れとし、規定の割合に銅を組み合わせて秤量し取組みが行われ箱に入れ封印し、銀見役から常是手代へ引き継ぐ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others were refined again and reclassified as top-quality ichiwari-ire, mixing the silver with lead in the statutory proportion, weighed, stored in boxes, sealed and handed from the silver inspector (ginmiyaku) to the jouze-tedai (assistant manager).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others were refined again and reclassified as top-quality ichiwari-ire, mixing the silver with lead in the statutory proportion, weighed, stored in boxes, sealed and handed from the silver inspector (ginmiyaku) to the jouze-tedai (assistant manager).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others were refined again and reclassified as top-quality ichiwari-ire, mixing the silver with lead in the statutory proportion, weighed, stored in boxes, sealed and handed from the silver inspector (ginmiyaku) to the jouze-tedai (assistant manager).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>吹所（ふきしょ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukisho (mint)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukisho (mint)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukisho (mint)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="64">
<j>吹立は常是吹所で行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minting was done at the jouze-fukisho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minting was done at the jouze-fukisho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minting was done at the jouze-fukisho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>取り組みの行われた地金を12貫を一吹として留鉢（坩堝）にいれ吹鎔かし常是手代湯入役が鉄柄杓で汲み上げ熱湯を張った丁銀および豆板銀の型に流し込んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Coins were minted in batches of 12 kan (approx. 45 kg), with the ore placed in a tomebashi (skull crucible) for melting and next collected by the yuiriyaku in a steel ladle for pouring into Chogin or mameitagin molds containing hot water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Coins were minted in batches of 12 kan (approx. 45 kg), with the ore placed in a tomebashi (skull crucible) for melting and next collected by the yuiriyaku in a steel ladle for pouring into Chogin or mameitagin molds containing hot water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Coins were minted in batches of 12 kan (approx. 45 kg), with the ore placed in a tomebashi (skull crucible) for melting and next collected by the yuiriyaku in a steel ladle for pouring into Chogin or mameitagin molds containing hot water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>形の良否により選別され、合格したものは数量および目方が改められた後、常是極印役に引き継ぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Coins were screened by quality in shape, with coins that passed inspection counted and weighed and later sent to the jouze-gokuinyaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Coins were screened by quality in shape, with coins that passed inspection counted and weighed and later sent to the jouze-gokuinyaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Coins were screened by quality in shape, with coins that passed inspection counted and weighed and later sent to the jouze-gokuinyaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="67">
<j>常是極印役により極印打ちが行われ、さらに焼鈍しが行われた後、梅酢に漬けられ、表面の銅を溶解して銀色が整えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The jouze-gokuinyaku stamped hallmarks on the coins, annealed, immersed in plum vinegar, and the lead on the surface dissolved to refine the silver color.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The coins were stamped with the jouze-gokuinyaku hallmark, annealed, immersed in plum vinegar, and any lead on the surface was dissolved to refine the silver color.</e>
<cmt>needed editing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The coins were stamped with the jouze-gokuinyaku hallmark, annealed, immersed in plum vinegar, and any lead on the surface was dissolved to refine the silver color.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>丁銀は200枚ずつ、豆板銀は500匁ずつ包み、座人封で銀座に廻した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chogin silver coins were packed in units of 200 and mameitagin coins in 500 mon and were sealed by the zanin officers for shipping to the ginza.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chogin silver coins were packed in units of 200 and mameitagin coins in 500 mon and were sealed by the zanin officers for shipping to the ginza.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chogin silver coins were packed in units of 200 and mameitagin coins in 500 mon and were sealed by the zanin officers for shipping to the ginza.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>糺吹所（ただしふきしょ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadashifukisho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadashifukisho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadashifukisho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="69">
<j>鋳造された丁銀の銀品位が正しいか否かを検査するため、常是手代立会いの下、鉛を加えて吹き戻され灰吹法により含有銀量が改められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to confirm the silver quality of the minted Chogin coins, lead was added for reminting, with jouze-tedai (assistant manager) standing as witness, with the cupellation method to alter silver content.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to confirm the silver quality of the minted Chogin coins, lead was added for reminting, with jouze-tedai (assistant manager) standing as witness, with the cupellation method to alter silver content.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to confirm the silver quality of the minted Chogin coins, lead was added for reminting, with jouze-tedai (assistant manager) standing as witness, with the cupellation method to alter silver content.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>これを糺吹（ただしふき）と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was called the tadashi-fuki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was called the tadashi-fuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was called the tadashi-fuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="71">
<j>丁銀100匁当りの含有上銀の許容誤差は慶長銀および享保丁銀0.3匁、元禄丁銀0.8匁、宝永丁銀1.11匁、永字銀1.33匁、三ツ宝銀1.51匁、四ツ宝銀1.7匁、および元文丁銀1.5匁であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The error margin in silver content for 100 mon of Chogin coins was 0.3 mon for Keicho gin and Kyoho chogin, 0.8 for Genroku chogin, 1.11 for Eiho chogin, 1.33 for Eiji gin, 1.51 for Mitsuhou gin, 1.7 for Yotsuhou gin and 1.5 for Genbun chogin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The error margin in silver content for 100 mon of Chogin coins was 0.3 mon for Keicho gin and Kyoho chogin, 0.8 for Genroku chogin, 1.11 for Eiho chogin, 1.33 for Eiji gin, 1.51 for Mitsuhou gin, 1.7 for Yotsuhou gin and 1.5 for Genbun chogin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The error margin in silver content for 100 mon of Chogin coins was 0.3 mon for Keicho gin and Kyoho chogin, 0.8 for Genroku chogin, 1.11 for Eiho chogin, 1.33 for Eiji gin, 1.51 for Mitsuhou gin, 1.7 for Yotsuhou gin and 1.5 for Genbun chogin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>寛政12年（1800年）の銀座改革により勘定奉行による統制が強化され「御勘定附切り」となり、それ以降、文政丁銀から糺吹は必要なしと判断され廃止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the ginza reform of 1800, control by the kanjo-bugyo was strengthened, placing coin minting an operation directly done by the shogunate and making tadashifuki no longer necessary from the Bunsei chogin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the ginza reform of 1800, control by the kanjo-bugyo was strengthened, placing coin minting an operation directly done by the shogunate and making tadashifuki no longer necessary from the Bunsei chogin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the ginza reform of 1800, control by the kanjo-bugyo was strengthened, placing coin minting an operation directly done by the shogunate and making tadashifuki no longer necessary from the Bunsei chogin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>仕立場（したてば）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shitateba</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shitateba</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shitateba</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="73">
<j>仕上げは丁銀を加熱した梅酢に漬け、取り出した後、磨き水洗いした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chogin coins were finished by immersing in plum vinegar and next polished and washed with water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chogin coins were finished by immersing in plum vinegar and next polished and washed with water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chogin coins were finished by immersing in heated plum vinegar and next polished and washed with water.</e>
<cmt>Heated 追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>仕上げた丁銀および豆板銀は500匁毎にまとめられ、常是が包封した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The finished Chogin and mameitagin coins were packaged in quantities of 500 mon and sealed by the jouze.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The finished Chogin and mameitagin coins were packaged in quantities of 500 mon and sealed by the jouze.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The finished Chogin and mameitagin coins were packaged in quantities of 500 mon and sealed by the jouze.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Ligar(id:12623), As6022014(id:214263), ZassouTori(id:136771), Ignis(id:28979), 水野白楓(id:22811), Matangohouse(id:312713), 一言虎児(id:100290), Junger(id:10282), 沢田(id:40580), BAKU(id:55205), Gombe(id:27), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>