<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>明法勘文</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myobo kanmon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myobo kanmon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myobo kanmon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>明法勘文（みょうぼうかんもん）とは、明法博士ら明法道の学者（明法家）が、諮問に対する解答として勘申した文書（勘文）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myobo kanmon is kanmon (report) prepared by scholars of Myobodo (study of Codes) (Myobo-ke) including Myobo hakase to respond to consultation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myobo kanmon is kanmon (report) prepared by scholars (Myobo-ke) of Myobodo (study of Codes) including Myobo hakase to respond to consultation.</e>
<cmt>(Myobo-ke)をscholarsの後に移動しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myobo kanmon is kanmon (report) prepared by scholars (Myobo-ke) of Myobodo (study of Codes) including Myobo hakase to respond to consultation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>主として朝廷・院庁より個々の事件・問題に対する律令格式などによる法的解釈を諮問された場合の解答として行われるが、天皇や公卿などからの個別の質問や自問答による解答なども含まれる場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is mainly responses to the Imperial Court and In no cho (Retired Emperor&apos;s Office) asking for legal interpretation of Laws of codes and ethics (conduct) concerning specific accidents and problems, but sometimes it contains answers to specific questions from the Emperor and Kugyo (the top court officials) and self-answered questions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is mainly responses to the Imperial Court and In no cho (Retired Emperor&apos;s Office) asking for legal interpretation of Laws of codes and ethics (conduct) concerning specific accidents and problems, but sometimes it contains answers to specific questions from the Emperor and Kugyo (the top court officials) and self-answered questions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is mainly responses to the Imperial Court and In no cho (Retired Emperor&apos;s Office) asking for legal interpretation of Laws of codes and ethics (conduct) concerning specific accidents and problems, but sometimes it contains answers to specific questions from the Emperor and Kugyo (the top court officials) and self-answered questions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>通常は天皇や太政官の意向を受けた宣旨が外記局もしくは弁官局の史 (律令制)より明法博士に下され、それに対して勘文の形式で解答を出すことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Normally an imperial decree intended by the Emperor or Daijokan (Grand Council of State) was handed down via recorders of gekikyoku (Secretaries&apos; Office of the Council of State) or Benkankyoku (Controllers&apos; Office) to Myobo hakase, who replied in the form of kanmon.</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Normally an imperial decree intended by the Emperor or Daijokan (Grand Council of State) was handed down via recorders of gekikyoku (Secretaries&apos; Office of the Council of State) or Benkankyoku (Controllers&apos; Office) to Myobo hakase, who replied in the form of kanmon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Normally an imperial decree intended by the Emperor or Daijokan (Grand Council of State) was handed down via recorders of gekikyoku (Secretaries&apos; Office of the Council of State) or Benkankyoku (Controllers&apos; Office) to Myobo hakase, who replied in the form of kanmon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>当初は「明法曹司」などと呼ばれる明法博士の教授団（組織）に対して下される形式が取られたが、9世紀以後には明法博士個人に対して出されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first such an imperial decree was formally handed down to an instruction group of Myobo hakase called &quot;Myobo-zoshi&quot; but after the ninth century it was handed down to Myobo hakase personally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first such an imperial decree was formally handed down to an instruction group of Myobo hakase called &apos;Myobo-zoshi&apos; but after the ninth century it was handed down to Myobo hakase personally.</e>
<cmt>指示書に従い、ダブルクォーテーションをシングルクォーテションに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first such an imperial decree was formally handed down to an instruction group of Myobo hakase called &apos;Myobo-zoshi&apos; but after the ninth century it was handed down to Myobo hakase personally.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション調整</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>勘文の範囲は刑事・民事を問わず行われ、後には明法道とは直接関係のない問題についても勘申が行われる場合もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The scope of kanmon covered both criminal and civil affairs, and later reports on matters which were not directly related to Myobodo were sometimes submitted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The scope of kanmon covered both criminal and civil affairs, and later reports on matters which were not directly related to Myobodo were sometimes submitted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The scope of kanmon covered both criminal and civil affairs, and later reports on matters which were not directly related to Myobodo were sometimes submitted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>なお、10世紀に入ると、官人の犯罪に関する裁判の権能が太政官の陣定に移された関係上、犯罪の罪名や処罰に関する明法勘文が大きな部分を占めて、特に「罪名勘文」（ざいみょうかんもん）とも呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the tenth century, when the capacity for trials concerning government officials&apos; crimes was moved to Jin no sadame (ancient cabinet council) of Daijokan, kanmon concerning the charge and penalty of a crime accounted for the large majority of Myobo kanmon, so they were especially called &quot;Zaimyo kanmon&quot; (kanmon for charges).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the tenth century, when the authority related to trials of government officials&apos; crimes was moved to Jin no sadame (ancient cabinet council) of Daijokan, kanmon concerning charges and penalties of crime accounted for the large majority of Myobo kanmon, so they were especially called &apos;Zaimyo kanmon&apos; (kanmon for charges).</e>
<cmt>capacityをauthorityに変更しました。特定ではなく、一般的な犯罪の罪名処罰に関わるという意味なのでthe charge and penalty of a crime を左記のように変更しました。指示書に従い、ダブルクォーテーションをシングルクォーテションに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the tenth century, when the authority related to trials of government officials&apos; crimes was moved to Jin no sadame (ancient cabinet council) of Daijokan, kanmon concerning charges and penalties of crime accounted for the large majority of Myobo kanmon, so they were especially called &apos;Zaimyo kanmon&apos; (kanmon for charges).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション調整</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>日本最古の明法勘文は、『法曹類林』所収の大宝律令選任令の解釈に関するもので、当時は明法博士の官職が存在していなかったために、律令編纂に関与して令官を兼ねていた大納言藤原不比等と式部卿葛野王が回答している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The oldest Myobo kanmon in Japan is the one concerning interpretation of Regulations for selection of Taiho Ritsuryo (Taiho Code) included in &quot;Hosoruirin,&quot; and was replied by FUJIWARA no Fuhito, Dainagon (Major Counselor) and FUJIWARA no Fuhito, Shikibukyo, who were involved in compilation of Taiho Code and also served as Ryokan, because there was no government post of Myobo hakase in those days.</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The oldest Myobo kanmon in Japan is the one concerning interpretation of Regulations for selection of Taiho Ritsuryo (Taiho Code) included in &quot;Hosoruirin,&quot; and was replied by FUJIWARA no Fuhito, Dainagon (Major Counselor) and Kadono no Okimi, Shikibukyo, who were involved in compilation of Taiho Code and also served as Ryokan, because there was no government post of Myobo hakase in those days.</e>
<cmt>二度目のFUJIWARA no Fuhitoは 正しくはKadono no Okimiであるのでそのように変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The oldest Myobo kanmon in Japan is the one concerning interpretation of Regulations for selection of Taiho Ritsuryo (Taiho Code) included in &quot;Hosoruirin,&quot; and was replied by FUJIWARA no Fuhito, Dainagon (Major Counselor) and Kadono no Okimi, Shikibukyo, who were involved in compilation of Taiho Code and also served as Ryokan, because there was no government post of Myobo hakase in those days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、明法博士による勘文に関する最古の記録は『続日本紀』天平宝字2年9月8日（丁丑/758年10月14日）条の国司交替に関する勘文を最古とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the oldest kanmon by Myobo hakase that is recorded is the one concerning the replacement of Kokushi in the article of October 14, 758 of &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the oldest record of kanmon created by Myobo is the one concerning the replacement of Kokushi in the article of October 14, 758 of &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued).</e>
<cmt>より自然な表現にするため、the oldest kanmon by Myobo hakase that is recorded の部分を左記のように変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the oldest record of kanmon created by Myobo is the one concerning the replacement of Kokushi in the article of October 14, 758 of &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また、『続日本後紀』承和 (日本)13年11月14日 (旧暦)（壬子/846年12月6日）条に引載されたいわゆる「善愷事件」（弁官伴善男が、弁官局で長年行われてきた慣例上の行政処理を僧尼令違反であるとして同僚弁官5名全員を告発した事件）における大判事讃岐永直・明法博士御輔長道・左大史川枯勝成による3通の勘文が知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Three kanmon written by daihanji (judge) SANUKI no Naganao, Myobo hakase 御輔長道 and Sadaishi (senior recorder of the left) 川枯勝成 in the so-called &quot;Zengai Jiken&quot;(described in the article of December 6, 846 of &quot;Shoku Nihon Koki&quot; (Later Chronicle of Japan Continued)), in which benkan Yoshio TOMONO accused all of his five fellow benkan of violating Soni ryo (Regulations for Monks and Nuns) in their customary public administration which had been implemented for many years, are well known.</e>
<cmt>読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Three kanmon written by daihanji (judge) SANUKI no Naganao, Myobo hakase 御輔長道 and Sadaishi (senior recorder of the left) 川枯勝成 in the so-called &apos;Zengai Jiken&apos;(described in the article of December 6, 846 of &quot;Shoku Nihon Koki&quot; (Later Chronicle of Japan Continued)), in which benkan Yoshio TOMONO accused all of his five fellow benkan of violating Soni ryo (Regulations for Monks and Nuns) in their customary public administration which had been implemented for many years, are well known.</e>
<cmt>指示書に従い、‘Zengai Jiken’のダブルクォーテーションをシングルクォーテションに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Three kanmon written by daihanji (judge) SANUKI no Naganao, Myobo hakase 御輔長道 and Sadaishi (senior recorder of the left) 川枯勝成 in the so-called &apos;Zengai Jiken&apos;(described in the article of December 6, 846 of &quot;Shoku Nihon Koki&quot; (Later Chronicle of Japan Continued)), in which benkan Yoshio TOMONO accused all of his five fellow benkan of violating Soni ryo (Regulations for Monks and Nuns) in their customary public administration which had been implemented for many years, are well known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>平安時代中期には明法勘文の文体が凡そ定型化されていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the mid Heian period, buntai (literary style) of Myobo kanmon was generally fixed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the mid Heian period, buntai (literary style) of Myobo kanmon was generally fixed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the mid Heian period, buntai (literary style) of Myobo kanmon was generally fixed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>まず、冒頭に勘申すべき事柄を「勘申～事」と記した上で次行より本文が開始される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the beginning the matter to be reported is written in a sentence, &quot;Kanjin *** no koto,&quot; and the body text starts at the second sentence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the beginning, the matter to be reported is written in a sentence, &quot;Kanjin *** no koto,&quot; and the body text starts in the next line.</e>
<cmt>beginningにコンマをいれ、second sentenceをnext lineに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the beginning, the matter to be reported is written in a sentence, &quot;Kanjin... no koto,&quot; and the body text starts in the next line.</e>
<cmt>記号変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>最初は勘申の元となった宣旨本文を引用する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First, the body text of an imperial decree to which kanmon replies is cited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First, the body text of an imperial decree to which kanmon replies is cited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First, the body text of an imperial decree to which kanmon replies is cited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>続いて勘申の根拠となる律令格式の本文を引用する（これは断獄律断罪引律令格式条によって規定されている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Next, the body text of Laws of codes and ethics (conduct) upon which kanmon is based is cited (this is stipulated in Laws of codes and ethics (conduct) concerning conviction of 断獄律).</e>
<cmt>読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Next, the body text of Laws of codes and ethics (conduct) upon which kanmon is based is cited (this is stipulated in Laws of codes and ethics (conduct) concerning conviction of 断獄律).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Next, the body text of Laws of codes and ethics (conduct) upon which kanmon is based is cited (this is stipulated in Laws of codes and ethics (conduct) concerning conviction of 断獄律).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また、後には勅撰の律令注釈書である『律集解』・『令集解』本文からも引用も同様の書式で行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The text body of &quot;Ritsu-no-shuge&quot; and &quot;Ryonoshuge,&quot; commentaries compiled by Imperial command, is cited in the same format.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The text body of &quot;Ritsu-no-shuge&quot; and &quot;Ryonoshuge,&quot; commentaries compiled by Imperial command, is cited in the same format.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The text body of &quot;Ritsu-no-shuge&quot; and &quot;Ryonoshuge,&quot; commentaries compiled by Imperial command, is cited in the same format.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>その後に「勘決」と呼ばれる勘申者の見解・結論が記された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Next, the proposer&apos;s comment and conclusion, which are called &quot;Kanketsu,&quot; are shown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Next, the proposer&apos;s comment and conclusion, which are called &apos;Kanketsu&apos;are shown.</e>
<cmt>指示書に従い、ダブルクォーテーションをシングルクォーテションに変更しました。またKanketsuの後のコンマを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Next, the proposer&apos;s comment and conclusion, which are called &apos;Kanketsu&apos; are shown.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション調整</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>こうした勘文は陣定・院評定などの会議資料として用いられた他、『法曹類林』や『政事要略』以下多くの明法家の著書に採録され、後には公家法の法源の1つとして扱われる場合もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such kanmon were used as conference materials in Jin no sadame and In no hyojo (consultation under the government by the retired Emperor), included in many works by Myobo-ke such as &quot;Hosoruirin&quot; and &quot;Seiji yoryaku,&quot; and later treated as one of the sources of court noble laws.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such kanmon were used as conference materials in Jin no sadame and In no hyojo (consultation under the government by the retired Emperor) and included in many works by Myobo-ke such as &quot;Hosoruirin&quot; and &quot;Seiji yoryaku,&quot; and later treated as one of the sources of court noble laws.</e>
<cmt>includedの前のコンマを削除し、andを入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such kanmon were used as conference materials in Jin no sadame and In no hyojo (consultation under the government by the retired Emperor) and included in many works by Myobo-ke such as &quot;Hosoruirin&quot; and &quot;Seiji yoryaku,&quot; and later treated as one of the sources of court noble laws.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>こうした明法勘文は、朝廷・院庁の政治的権威が京都とその周辺部で堅持されていた南北朝時代 (日本)の頃までは盛んに作成されていたが、以後政治的権力の失墜とともに明法道も衰退し、明法勘文が作成されることはほとんど無くなったとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myobo kanmon had been actively created by the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), when the political power of the Imperial Court and In no cho was well retained in and around Kyoto, but Myobodo declined with the downfall of such political power and Myobo kanmon were no longer created.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myobo kanmon had been actively created by the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), when the political power of the Imperial Court and In no cho was well retained in and around Kyoto, but Myobodo declined with the downfall of such political power and Myobo kanmon were no longer created.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myobo kanmon had been actively created by the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), when the political power of the Imperial Court and In no cho was well retained in and around Kyoto, but Myobodo declined with the downfall of such political power and Myobo kanmon were no longer created.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>