<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>教部省</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyobusho (Ministry of Religion)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyobusho (Ministry of Religion)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyobusho (Ministry of Religion)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>教部省（きょうぶしょう）は明治初期の太政官制度のもと、宗教統制による国民教化の目的で設置された中央官庁組織である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyobusho (Ministry of Religion) is the central government authority organization founded for the purpose of national edification by controlling religion, under Dajokan System (the system of Great Council of State) established in early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyobusho (Ministry of Religion) is the central governmental organ founded for the purpose of national edification by controlling religion under Dajokan System (the system of Great Council of State) established in the early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>不自然な表現、文法を直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyobusho (Ministry of Religion) is the central governmental organ founded for the purpose of national edification by controlling religion under Dajokan System (the system of Great Council of State) established in the early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>明治5年3月14日 (旧暦)（1872年4月21日）に神祇省を改組し、民部省社寺掛を併合する形で設置。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 21, 1872, the Meiji government reorganized Jingisho (Ministry of Divinities) by merging the department with the Department of shrines and temples of Minbusho. (Ministry of Popular Affairs)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 21, 1872, the Meiji government reorganized Jingisho (Ministry of Divinities) by merging the department with the Department of shrines and temples of Minbusho (Ministry of Popular Affairs).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 21, 1872, the Meiji government reorganized Jingisho (Ministry of Divinities) by merging the department with the Department of shrines and temples of Minbusho (Ministry of Popular Affairs).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>神祇官内に設置された宣教使の神道と儒教を基本とした国民教導が失敗したことを受け、当時最大の宗教勢力であった仏教、特に浄土真宗の要請によって神・儒・仏の合同布教体制が敷かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the failure of Shintoism instructed by Shinto Missionaries division set up inside of the department of Jingikan (officer of the institution for dedicating to religious ceremony) and the edification based on the ideas of Confucianism, Buddhism, the largest religious group of the days, and particularly its Jodo Shinshu Sect (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) requested government to jointly propagate Religion in Japan, including Shintoism, Confucianism and Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the failure of Shintoism instructed by the Shinto Missionary division set up inside of the department of Jingikan (officers of the institution for dedicating to religious ceremony) and the edification based on the ideas of Confucianism, Buddhism, the largest religious group of the days, and particularly its Jodo Shinshu Sect (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) requested the government to jointly propagate three religions in Japan, including Shintoism, Confucianism and Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>冠詞を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the failure of Shintoism instructed by the Shinto Missionary division set up inside of the department of Jingikan (officers of the institution for dedicating to religious ceremony) and the edification based on the ideas of Confucianism, Buddhism, the largest religious group of the days, and particularly its Jodo Shinshu Sect (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) requested the government to jointly propagate three religions in Japan, including Shintoism, Confucianism and Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>キリスト教の（半ば黙認という形での）禁制解除、社寺に於ける女人結界の解除など近代宗教政策を実施する一方で、神祇官が為し得なかった国民教化を実現する為に教導職制度を設け、大教院による国民教化・大教宣布運動を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Kyobusho implemented the cancellation of ban on Christianity (in reality a tacit permission) and the prohibition against woman entering a sacred area at temples and shrines, it also established a system called evangelist system, and propagated the Imperial Edict (of 1870) for Establishment of Shinto under Daikyoin (Great Teaching Institute) in order to realize the edification and enlightenment of citizens after the failure of Jingikan department.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While implementing modernistic religious policies including the cancellation of a ban on Christianity (in reality a tacit permission) and the prohibition against woman entering a sacred area at temples and shrines, Kyobusho also established a system called the kyodoshoku (evangelist) system, and propagated national edification and the Imperial Edict (of 1870) for Establishment of Shinto under Daikyoin (Great Teaching Institute) in order to realize the edification and enlightenment of citizens after the failure of the Jingikan department.</e>
<cmt>「近代宗教政策」の「国民強化」訳が抜けているので補いました。冠詞を補いました。Kyodoshokuという語は残しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While implementing modernistic religious policies including the cancellation of a ban on Christianity (in reality a tacit permission) and the prohibition against woman entering a sacred area at temples and shrines, Kyobusho also established a system called the kyodoshoku (evangelist) system, and propagated national edification and the Imperial Edict (of 1870) for Establishment of Shinto under Daikyoin (Great Teaching Institute) in order to realize the edification and enlightenment of citizens after the failure of the Jingikan department.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>教導職は半官半民の任命制であり、神官・神職、僧侶などの宗教家を始め、落語家や歌人、俳人なども教導職に任命された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Evangelist was a semi-governmental appointment position, as he was not only assigned from those religious groups of Shinto priests and Buddhist monks, but also from Rakugo story teller, Waka poet, Haiku poet, etc..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kyodoshoku was a semi-governmental appointive position, and not only members of religious groups such as Shinto priests and Buddhist monks but also Rakugo story tellers, Waka poets, Haiku poets, etc. were appointed to the position.</e>
<cmt>kyodoshokuの語を使いました。文法修正、及び分かりやすくするため文章後半を書き直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kyodoshoku was a semi-governmental appointive position, and not only members of religious groups such as Shinto priests and Buddhist monks but also Rakugo story tellers, Waka poets, Haiku poets, etc. were appointed to the position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>国民教化をより具体的に行う為、教導職の全国統括機関である大教院、各府県単位の統括を行なう中教院が設置され、全国に小教院が置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For concretely operating the edification of the citizens, Daikyoin (Great Teaching Institute) as the national unification organization of evangelists, and Chukyoin (Intermediate Teaching Institute) as the Prefectural unification organization of evangelists, and Shokyoin (Small Teaching Institute) for nation-wide network of the teaching institute were established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to edify citizens more specifically, Daikyoin (Great Teaching Institute) as the national organization to supervise kyodoshoku and Chukyoin (Intermediate Teaching Institute) as the prefectural organization to supervise kyodoshoku were established, and Shokyoin (Small Teaching Institute) were set up in many places all over the country.</e>
<cmt>分かりやすくするため、表現を変更、一部書き直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to edify citizens more specifically, Daikyoin (Great Teaching Institute) as the national organization to supervise kyodoshoku and Chukyoin (Intermediate Teaching Institute) as the prefectural organization to supervise kyodoshoku were established, and Shokyoin (Small Teaching Institute) were set up in many places all over the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかしながら、当時新進であった神道勢力と旧来よりの勢力を保っていた浄土真宗との深刻な意見対立によって実績は揚がらぬまま、浄土真宗の大教院離脱を経て、明治10年（1877年）1月11日に廃止、機能は社寺局へ移された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the organization could not achieve significant result because of the critical conflict between the newly-up-and-coming Shintoism influence and Jodo Shinshu Buddhism Sect with more conventional influence, and Jodo Shinshu broke away from Daikyoin, which led to the abolition of Kyobusho on January 11, 1877, while its functionality was succeeded by the Bureau of shrines and temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Kyobusho could not achieve significant results because of the critical conflict between the up-and-coming Shintoism group and the Jodo Shinshu Buddhist sect group that had kept its long-established power, and eventually the Jodo Shinshu sect broke away from Daikyoin, which led to the abolition of Kyobusho on January 11, 1877 while its functions were transferred to the Bureau of shrines and temples.</e>
<cmt>分かりやすくするため一部書き直しました。The organization はkyobushoで置き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Kyobusho could not achieve significant results because of the critical conflict between the up-and-coming Shintoism group and the Jodo Shinshu Buddhist sect group that had kept its long-established power, and eventually the Jodo Shinshu sect broke away from Daikyoin, which led to the abolition of Kyobusho on January 11, 1877 while its functions were transferred to the Bureau of shrines and temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>教部省を巡る問題</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The issues over Kyobusho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The issues over Kyobusho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The issues over Kyobusho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>神祇官・宣教使の宣教政策の失敗を受けて出来上がった教部省であったが、最終的には廃止という結果となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the ministry was established after the failure of Jingikan and its Shinto Missionaries, consequently the department was abolished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was established after the failure of Jingikan and its Shinto Missionaries, but consequently it also ended up with abolition.</e>
<cmt>主語はitで置き換えました。「最終的には」などの意味が良く伝わるよう、若干表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was established after the failure of Jingikan and its Shinto Missionaries, but consequently it also ended up with abolition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その原因として当時の宗教行政の混乱が挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason of this result can be found in the confusion over administrating religious influences.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason for this can be found in the confusion over administration of religions.</e>
<cmt>言葉の使用を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason for this can be found in the confusion over administration of religions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>政府は当初、伝統宗教の権威と地盤を以ってキリスト教防御と維新後の新体制を国民に教導する考えであったが、近代国家の樹立の為には政教分離と信教の自由を国家の基本方針として盛り込むことは避けられず、また西洋諸国との外交関係に於いてキリスト教の禁制解除は不可欠となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, Meiji government intended to defend citizens from the influence of Christianity, and edify its new organizations and systems of the new government renewed after Meiji Restoration by the power and the constituency of traditional religious groups; however, the separation of religion and politics, and the freedom of religious belief was the essential policy of establishing a modernized nation, and the lift of ban on Christianity was indispensable for the diplomatic relationship with the Western countries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, the Meiji government intended to keep citizens away from the influence of Christianity and to educate them on the new systems made by the new government renewed after the Meiji Restoration with authority and foundations of the Japanese traditional religion; however, the separation of religion and politics and the freedom of religion were essential policies in order to establish a modernized nation, and the cancellation of a ban on Christianity was indispensable to maintain the diplomatic relationships with Western countries.</e>
<cmt>文法修正、及び分かりやすくするため、表現を一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, the Meiji government intended to keep citizens away from the influence of Christianity and to educate them on the new systems made by the new government renewed after the Meiji Restoration with authority and foundations of the Japanese traditional religion; however, the separation of religion and politics and the freedom of religion were essential policies in order to establish a modernized nation, and the cancellation of a ban on Christianity was indispensable to maintain the diplomatic relationships with Western countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、学制の整備によって宣教政策の目的が達成されるとの観点から、政府は教部省の存在自体を懐疑的に捉える結末となり、上記の混乱によって既存の宗教勢力は右往左往することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Meiji government considered the establishment of the educational system throughout Japan could substitute the purpose of edification policy, thus the existence of Kyobusho itself became sceptical for the government; as the result, the existing religious groups rushed around in confusion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the Meiji government considered that the establishment of the educational system throughout Japan could satisfy the purpose of national edification at the same time and thus became skeptical of Kyobusho, and these inconsistencies made the existing religious groups rush around in confusion.</e>
<cmt>文法修正、及び分かりやすくするため、表現を一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the Meiji government considered that the establishment of the educational system throughout Japan could satisfy the purpose of national edification at the same time and thus became skeptical of Kyobusho, and these inconsistencies made the existing religious groups rush around in confusion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>そのような混乱の中、神仏分離で劣勢に立たされていた仏教勢力、特に明治維新に際して倒幕運動を支援した浄土真宗は巧みな政治工作によって教部省を政府に樹立させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Within such confusion, the Buddhist group in the inferior position under the movement of separating Buddhism and Shintoism, especially Jodo Shinshu Sect who supported the movement to overthrow the Shogunate promoted an ingenious political maneuver to successfully persuaded the government to establish Kyobusho.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In such confusion, the Buddhist group that had been put in the inferior position under the movement of separation of Buddhism and Shintoism, especially the Jodo Shinshu sect that had supported the movement to overthrow the shogunate, promoted ingenious political maneuvers and successfully persuaded the government to establish Kyobusho.</e>
<cmt>文法修正、及び分かりやすくするため、表現を一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In such confusion, the Buddhist group that had been put in the inferior position under the movement of separation of Buddhism and Shintoism, especially the Jodo Shinshu sect that had supported the movement to overthrow the shogunate, promoted ingenious political maneuvers and successfully persuaded the government to establish Kyobusho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>一向宗宗名論争（浄土真宗が公式に否認している「一向宗」を宗派名として強要しようとした問題）を機に浄土真宗内部からも政府への反発が高まってきたこともあり、教部省の施策が暗礁に乗り上げると政教分離の観点から脱退するといった動きを見せた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the dispute of Ikko Sect issue (the issue that government attempted to enforce Jodo Shinshu Sect for accepting the Ikko group of Buddhism to be nominated as an actual sect even though Jodo Shinshu had officially denied it) repelled the member of Jodo Shinshu against the government, and Jodo Shinshu Sect left Kyobusho from the view of the separation of religion and politics, after the policy of Kyobusho reached a deadlock.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, triggered by the dispute over naming of the Ikko sect (the issue that government attempted to enforce the name of &apos;Ikko&apos; as an official name on the Jodo Shinshu sect even though the sect had officially rejected it), the repugnance against the government grew within the Jodo Shinshu sect, and the Jodo Shinshu sect withdrew from Kyobusho after the policy of Kyobusho reached a deadlock on the basis of the separation of religion and politics.</e>
<cmt>意味が正確に訳されていない部分があるので（前半～中半）、全体的に書き直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, triggered by the dispute over naming of the Ikko sect (the issue that government attempted to enforce the name of &apos;Ikko&apos; as an official name on the Jodo Shinshu sect even though the sect had officially rejected it), the repugnance against the government grew within the Jodo Shinshu sect, and the Jodo Shinshu sect withdrew from Kyobusho after the policy of Kyobusho reached a deadlock on the basis of the separation of religion and politics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>大教院神殿問題</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The issue on Daikyoin Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The issue on Daikyoin Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The issue on Daikyoin Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>教導職の全国統括機関であった大教院は東京芝にある増上寺内に設置された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daikyoin organization that unifies the evangelists throughout the nation was established within Zojo-ji Temple located in Shiba, Tokyo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daikyoin, the national organization to supervise kyodoshoku (evangelists), was established in Zojo-ji Temple located in Shiba, Tokyo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>前述の訳に合わせて変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daikyoin, the national organization to supervise kyodoshoku (evangelists), was established in Zojo-ji Temple located in Shiba, Tokyo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>大教院の設置は仏教主導で行われた事もあり、増上寺の施設献納も自発的なものだったが、神道勢力が主導権を握りはじめると、献納を拒否する動きをみせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the establishment of Diakyoin was led under the leadership of Buddhism influence, the contribution of Zojo-ji Temple for providing its facilities to Daikyoin was voluntary, but once Shintoism influence began to take control of the administration of Daikyoin, Zojo-ji Temple denied the voluntary contribution.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the establishment of Daikyoin was led by the leadership of the Buddhist power, Zojo-ji Temple voluntarily offered to provide its facilities for Daikyoin at first, but once Shinto power began to take control of the administration of Daikyoin, Zojo-ji Temple tried to retract its initial proposal.</e>
<cmt>スペルミス、文法ミス、及び表現の一部を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the establishment of Daikyoin was led by the leadership of the Buddhist power, Zojo-ji Temple voluntarily offered to provide its facilities for Daikyoin at first, but once Shinto power began to take control of the administration of Daikyoin, Zojo-ji Temple tried to retract its initial proposal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし、増上寺の献納は予定通り進められ、なかば強引に増上寺本堂は大教院として召し上げられ、大教院神殿の拝殿として用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the contribution request to Zojo-ji Temple was pushed accordingly to the previous plan to almost forcefully taken as an offering for the haiden (a worship hall at a Shinto shrine) of Daikyoin Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the plan of the contribution of the facilities of Zojo-ji Temple was pursued according to schedule, and the main hall of the temple was almost forcefully taken away and used as the haiden (a worship hall at a Shinto shrine) of Daikyoin Shrine.</e>
<cmt>文法ミス、及び分かりやすいよう一部表現を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the plan of the contribution of the facilities of Zojo-ji Temple was pursued according to schedule, and the main hall of the temple was almost forcefully taken away and used as the haiden (a worship hall at a Shinto shrine) of Daikyoin Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>更には神殿で行なわれる祭祀に教導職である僧侶の参列と拝礼を義務付けた為に仏教勢力の一部を激しく怒らせる結果となった（又、その反面に幟を掲げるなどして熱烈な祝福を示した僧侶もいた）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Kyobusho enforced the requirement to evangelist Buddhist monks for the attendance and the ritual bow at the rituals performed at the shrine, therefore a certain group of Buddhist was vigorously opposed against the enforced requirements. (on the other hand, some Buddhist monks fervently celebrated it by setting up a flag)</e>
<cmt>ここでの幟がどのようなものか不明ですので、直訳のままとして説明を欠いています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Kyobusho enforced attendance and religious services at rituals performed at the shrine on the Buddhist priests who were Kyodoshoku, which made part of Buddhist power furious (on the other hand, some Buddhist priests fervently celebrated them by setting up a flag).</e>
<cmt>文法ミス、及び分かりやすいよう一部表現を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Kyobusho enforced attendance and religious services at rituals performed at the shrine on the Buddhist priests who were Kyodoshoku, which made part of Buddhist power furious (on the other hand, some Buddhist priests fervently celebrated them by setting up a flag).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>その後、仏堂の中に神社が設けられた事に反発した廃仏主義者の旧薩摩藩士によって明治7年（1874年）1月1日に放火され、旧増上寺本堂は全焼したが神体はかろうじて助け出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 1, 1874, a former Satsuma domain member whose belief was to abolish Buddhism, set a fire on the facility for opposing against the fact that a shrine was set up within temple facility, and the former Zojo-ji Temple Hondo (main hall) was totally burned down while its shintai (a sacred object) was managed to be evacuated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 1, 1874, a former Satsuma clan member, who believed in the abolition of Buddhism, set fire to Zojo-ji Temple opposing a shrine set up in the temple, and thus the main hall of former Zojo-ji Temple was totally burned down while its shintai (a sacred object) was barely saved.</e>
<cmt>文法ミス、及び分かりやすいよう一部表現を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 1, 1874, a former Satsuma clan member, who believed in the abolition of Buddhism, set fire to Zojo-ji Temple opposing a shrine set up in the temple, and thus the main hall of former Zojo-ji Temple was totally burned down while its shintai (a sacred object) was barely saved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>この神体は芝東照宮に一時奉遷され、神道勢力が新たに設置した神道事務局の神殿に遷された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This shintai was temporary moved to Shiba Tosho-gu Shrine, and later it was moved to the shrine of the Secretariat of Shinto established by Shinto group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This shintai was temporarily placed in Shiba Tosho-gu Shrine, and afterward moved in the shrine in the Secretariat of Shinto later set up by the Shinto group.</e>
<cmt>文法ミス、及び分かりやすいよう一部表現を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This shintai was temporarily placed in Shiba Tosho-gu Shrine, and afterward moved in the shrine in the Secretariat of Shinto later set up by the Shinto group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>教部卿など</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The minister of Kyobusho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The minister of Kyobusho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The minister of Kyobusho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>教部卿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoubu kyo (The minister of Kyobusho)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoubu kyo (The minister of Kyobusho)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoubu kyo (The minister of Kyobusho)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>嵯峨実愛（1872年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanenaru SAGA (1872)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanenaru SAGA (1872)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanenaru SAGA (1872)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>大木喬任（1872年 - 1873年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takato OKI (1872 - 1873)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takato OKI (1872 - 1873)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takato OKI (1872 - 1873)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>教部大輔</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyobu taifu (The vice-minister of Kyobusho)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyobu taifu (The vice-minister of Kyobusho)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyobu taifu (The vice-minister of Kyobusho)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>福羽美静（前任神祇大輔　-1872年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bisei FUKUBA (- 1872; former Jingi Taifu (the vice-minister of the institution for dedicating to religious ceremony)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bisei FUKUBA (former Jingi Taifu [the vice-minister of the institution for dedicating to religious ceremony]) (- 1872)</e>
<cmt>二重括弧に[]を使いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bisei FUKUBA (former Jingi Taifu [the vice-minister of the institution for dedicating to religious ceremony]) (- 1872)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>宍戸璣（1872年 - 1877年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iwane SHISHIDO (1872 - 1877)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iwane SHISHIDO (1872 - 1877)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iwane SHISHIDO (1872 - 1877)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>教導職</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyodoshoku (evangelist)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyodoshoku (evangelist)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyodoshoku (evangelist)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>大教正・・・長官</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daikyosei (director general of Daikyoin)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daikyosei (the director general of Daikyoin)</e>
<cmt>冠詞を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daikyosei (the director general of Daikyoin)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>中教正</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chukyosei (director general of Chukyoin)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chukyosei (the director general of Chukyoin)</e>
<cmt>冠詞を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chukyosei (the director general of Chukyoin)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>少教正</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoukyousei (director of Shokyoin)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shokyosei (the director of Shokyoin)</e>
<cmt>ローマ字表記ミスがありました。冠詞を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shokyosei (the director of Shokyoin)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 エル・トポ(id:43117), 神祇官(id:99217), Njt(id:11249), Tomzo(id:16777), Nnh(id:474), 新アルパカ(id:65850), Kstigarbha(id:13376), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>