<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>古代日本の戸籍制度</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Family registration system in ancient Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family registration system in ancient Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family registration system in ancient Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>古代の戸籍制度とは、飛鳥時代に撰定・編纂された律令による人民把握のための戸籍をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Family registration systems in ancient times refer to family registers for taking hold of people under the Ritsuryo codes selected and edited in the Asuka period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family registration systems in ancient times refer to family registers for keeping tabs on people under the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) where were codes selected and compiled in the Asuka period.</e>
<cmt>&quot;taking hold of people&quot; &gt; &quot;keeping tabs on people&quot;; changed &quot;Ritsuryo codes&quot; to &quot;Ritsuryo system&quot; and added description in parenthesis; edited &gt; compiled (編纂された); added &quot;codes&quot; after description</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family registration systems in ancient times refer to family registers for keeping tabs on people under the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) where were codes selected and compiled in the Asuka period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>その主なものに、庚寅年籍（こういんのねんじゃく）や庚午年籍（こうごのねんじゃく）があげられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major systems include Koin no Nenjaku (the first completed registers) and Kogo no Nenjaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major systems include the Koin no Nenjaku (the first completed register) and the Kogo no Nenjaku.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Koin&quot; and &quot;Kogo&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major systems include the Koin no Nenjaku (the first completed register) and the Kogo no Nenjaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>古代の戸籍は死亡帳などとして、正倉院に残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Family registers in ancient times are left as Shibo-cho (record of the dead), etc. in Shosoin Treasure House.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family registers from ancient times are left as Shibo-cho (a record of the dead), etc. in the Shosoin Treasure House.</e>
<cmt>in &gt; from; added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Shosoin&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family registers from ancient times are left as Shibo-cho (a record of the dead), etc. in the Shosoin Treasure House.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また近年、漆紙文書のかたちで秋田城や多賀城、下野国国府跡など地方の城柵や官衙から、戸籍木簡としては周防国国府などで出土しており、赤外線による解読作業がおこなわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently family registers were excavated from local josaku (official defense sites) and kanga (government offices) such as Akita-jo Castle, Taga-jo Castle and the remains of the provincial capital of Shimotsuke in the form of urushigami monjo (Lacquer documents), and from the provincial capital of Suo in the form of koseki mokkan (narrow, long, and thin pieces of wood strung together that were used to write family register), and are being deciphered with the use of infrared ray.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family registers have been recently excavated from local josaku (official defense sites) and kanga (government offices) such as Akita-jo Castle, Taga-jo Castle and the remains of the provincial capital of Shimotsuke in the form of urushigami monjo (Lacquer documents); as well as from the provincial capital of Suo in the form of koseki mokkan (narrow, long and thin pieces of wood strung together that were used to write family registers), and are being deciphered with an infrared ray.</e>
<cmt>moved &quot;recently&quot; to before &quot;excavated&quot;; changed comma to semi-colon after (Lacquer documents); eliminated comma after &quot;long&quot;; register &gt; registers; with the use of infrared ray &gt; with an infrared ray</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family registers have been recently excavated from local josaku (official defense sites) and kanga (government offices) such as Akita-jo Castle, Taga-jo Castle and the remains of the provincial capital of Shimotsuke in the form of urushigami monjo (Lacquer documents); as well as from the provincial capital of Suo in the form of koseki mokkan (narrow, long and thin pieces of wood strung together that were used to write family registers), and are being deciphered with an infrared ray.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>戸籍のはじまり</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Beginnings of family registers</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first family registers</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first family registers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>造籍に関する古い例としては、下記が挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An old example of having a new family register is described</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Old examples of family registers</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Old examples of family registers are as follows.</e>
<cmt>原文に「下記が挙げられる。」を追加are as follows 追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>540年（欽明天皇元年）八月の条「秦人（はたひと）・漢人（あやひと）等、諸蕃（しょばん）より投化せる者を招集して、国群に安置し、戸籍に編貫す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">in the article of August, 540, which says &quot;Those who have been naturalized from Shoban (clans coming from foreign lands), such as Hatahito (Hata people) and the Han (Chinese), were assembled, placed according to kokugun (provinces and districts) and their family registers were edited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An article from August of 540 describes, &quot;Those who have been naturalized from Shoban (clans coming from foreign lands), such as Hatahito (Hata people) and the Han (Chinese), were assembled, placed according to kokugun (provinces and districts) and their family registers were edited.</e>
<cmt>in the article of August, 540, which says &gt; An article from August of 540 describes,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An article from August of 540 describes, &quot;Those who have been naturalized from Shoban (clans coming from foreign lands), such as Hatahito (Hata people) and the Han (Chinese), were assembled, placed according to kokugun (provinces and districts) and their family registers were edited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>秦人の戸数七千五十三戸、大蔵掾（おおくらのじょう）を以て、秦伴造（はたのとものみやつこ）となす」（『日本書紀』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were 7,053 families of Hatahito, and Okura no jo (an officer in charge of the large storehouse) was made into Hatano Tomo no Miyatsuko&quot;(&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan)),</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were 7,053 Hatahito families and an Okura no jo (an officer in charge of the large storehouse) became a Hatano Tomo no Miyatsuko&quot;(&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; [Chronicles of Japan]).</e>
<cmt>7,.530 families of Hatahito &gt; 7,530 Hatahito families; added &quot;an&quot; before &quot;Okura&quot;; added &quot;a&quot; before &quot;Hatano&quot;; changed ending comma into a period</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were 7,053 Hatahito families and an Okura no jo (an officer in charge of the large storehouse) became a Hatano Tomo no Miyatsuko&quot;(&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; [Chronicles of Japan]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>とあり、6世紀の中頃、欽明朝頃には、まず渡来人を戸籍によって支配したことが窺われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">and it is presumed that at first toraijin (people from overseas, especially from China and Korea, who settled in early Japan and introduced Continental culture to the Japanese) were controlled with the use of family registers in the Kinmei dynasty, around the middle of the 6th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is presumed that around the middle of the 6th century during the Kinmei Dynasty that the toraijin (people from overseas, especially from China and Korea, who settled in early Japan and introduced Continental culture to the Japanese) were the first to be controlled with the use of family registers.</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;and&quot;; rearranged sentence to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is presumed that around the middle of the 6th century during the Kinmei Dynasty that the toraijin (people from overseas, especially from China and Korea, who settled in early Japan and introduced Continental culture to the Japanese) were the first to be controlled with the use of family registers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="10">
<j>569年（欽明30）の春正月に、詔で吉備国の白猪屯倉（しらいのみやけ）では、年齢が十歳あまりに達しているのに、籍に漏れているために賦課を免ぜられている者が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January, spring of 569, an edict stated that many people were exempt from paying tax in spite of the fact that they were more than ten years old because they were not listed in the family register in Shirai no Miyake, the Kibi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the spring of 569, an edict stated that many people were exempt from paying taxes even if they were older than ten years old because they were not listed in the family register in Shirai no Miyake, Kibi Province.</e>
<cmt>I do not understand if &quot;春正月&quot; is the &quot;first month of 欽明３０&quot; therefore it was &quot;spring.&quot; Since &quot;January&quot; and &quot;spring&quot; occur at different times on the Gregorian calendar, I eliminated &quot;January.&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the spring of 569, an edict stated that many people were exempt from paying taxes even if they were older than ten years old because they were not listed in the family register in Shirai no Miyake, Kibi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>膽津（いつ）を遣わして田部の丁籍を検定せよと述べた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The edict ordered to send Itsu (a person&apos;s name) for inspection of the block register of tabe (a group of peasants set for the cultivation of miyake, Imperial-controlled territory in ancient times).</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The edict ordered a man named Itsu to inspect the block register of tabe (a group of peasants set for the cultivation of miyake, Imperial-controlled territory in ancient times).</e>
<cmt>added &quot;a man named&quot; before &quot;Itsu&quot; and deleted (a person&apos;s name);</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The edict ordered a man named Itsu to inspect the block register of tabe (a group of peasants set for the cultivation of miyake, Imperial-controlled territory in ancient times).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>4月になって、膽津は詔に述べられているとおりによく丁（よほろ）を調査して籍を定め、田戸を編成したので、その功をほめて白猪史（しらいのふひと）の姓を賜い、田令（たづかい）に任じた（『日本書紀』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April Itsu conducted an exhaustive investigation into yohoro (one liable to corvee service in early times) as ordered by the edict, established registers and organized farmland registers, so that the emperor granted him a family name, Shirai no Huhito, as a compliment to his achievement and appointed him tazukai (a superintendent of the miyake). (&quot;Nihonshoki&quot;)</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Itsu followed the edict in April by conducting an exhaustive investigation into the yohoro (people liable to be in corvee service in early times) where he established registers and organized farmland registers, the emperor granted him the family name Shirai no Huhito as a reward for his achievement and appointed him as tazukai (a superintendent of the miyake) (&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; [Chronicles of Japan]).</e>
<cmt>added comma after &quot;April&quot;; added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;yohoro&quot;; changed &quot;one&quot; to &quot;people&quot;; added &quot;to be in&quot; before &quot;corvee&quot;; compliment &gt; reward; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Itsu followed the edict in April by conducting an exhaustive investigation into the yohoro (people liable to be in corvee service in early times) where he established registers and organized farmland registers, the emperor granted him the family name Shirai no Fuhito as a reward for his achievement and appointed him as tazukai (a superintendent of the miyake) (&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; [Chronicles of Japan]).</e>
<cmt>HuhitoをFuhitoに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="13">
<j>丁籍は、課役を負担する成年男子のみを記載した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Block registers listed only adult males who were allocated labor duty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Block registers listed only adult males who were allocated to labor duty.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;to&quot; before &quot;labor&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Block registers listed only adult males who were allocated to labor duty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>田戸は、田部を編成して丁籍よりも正確な戸籍を造ったのか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maybe farmland registers were created out of tabe in order to make more correct family registers than block registers?</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is speculated that farmland registers were created out of tabe in order to make family registers more accurate than block registers.</e>
<cmt>Maybe &gt; It is speculated that; ? &gt;.; correct &gt; accurate; rearranged sentence to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is speculated that farmland registers were created out of tabe in order to make family registers more accurate than block registers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="15">
<j>はじめに籍を造っただけで、後は定期的に籍を作成することもなかったらしいので、このような不具合が生じたらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is presumed that such a problem arose because registers were established only once instead of being created on a regular basis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is presumed that such a problem arose because registers were established only once instead of being created on a regular basis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is presumed that such a problem arose because registers were established only once instead of being created on a regular basis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="16">
<j>さらに574年（敏達天皇3）十月の条に、大臣（おおおみ）の蘇我馬子（そがのうまこ）を吉備に遣わし、白猪屯倉と田部とを増益して、その田部の名籍を膽津に授けたとある（『日本書紀』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, according to the article of October 574, SOGA no Umako, O-omi, was sent to Kibi in order to increase profits from Shirai no Miyake and tabe, and Meiseki (card showing official rank, name and age) of the tabe was granted to Itsu. (&quot;Nihonshoki&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, according to an article from October 574, SOGA no Umako, O-omi, was sent to Kibi in order to increase profits from Shirai no Miyake and tabe, and a Meiseki (a card showing official rank, name and age) of the tabe was granted to Itsu (&quot;Nihonshoki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>the article of October &gt; an article from October; added &quot;a&quot; before &quot;Meiseki&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, according to an article from October 574, SOGA no Umako, O-omi, was sent to Kibi in order to increase profits from Shirai no Miyake and tabe, and a Meiseki (a card showing official rank, name and age) of the tabe was granted to Itsu (&quot;Nihonshoki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="17">
<j>名籍は、胆津が新しく造ったものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meiseki was newly created by Itsu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meiseki was newly created by Itsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meiseki was newly created by Itsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>後の戸籍・計帳に近いものか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Is it like family registers and keicho (the yearly tax registers) in later years?</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is speculated that Meiseki were similar to family registers and keichi (yearly tax registers), which were created in later years.</e>
<cmt>changed this from a question into a statement, adding &quot;It is speculated&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is speculated that Meiseki were similar to family registers and keicho (yearly tax registers), which were created in later years.</e>
<cmt>keichiをkeichoに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="19">
<j>これらは渡来系集団や屯倉の田部などの造籍であり、すべての人民の律令制の戸籍制とは異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are new family registers of groups of toraijin or tabe in miyake (Imperial-controlled territory), and different from the family registration system for all the people on the basis of the ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These were new family registers for groups of toraijin or tabe in miyake (Imperial-controlled territory), and different from the family registration system for all the people based on the ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>They are &gt; These were; on the basis of the ritsuryo &gt; based on the ritsuryo; eliminated description in parenthesis since it is given above</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These were new family registers for groups of toraijin or tabe in miyake (Imperial-controlled territory), and different from the family registration system for all the people based on the ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="20">
<j>庚午（こうご）の年籍</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kogo no Nenjaku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kogo no Nenjaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kogo no Nenjaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>日本で最初の全国的な戸籍は、「庚午年籍」であるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kogo Nenjaku&quot; is said to be the first national family registration system in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kogo Nenjaku&quot; is said to be the first national family registration system in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kogo Nenjaku&quot; is said to be the first national family registration system in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>しかし現存しておらず、全国的に全ての階層の人民を対象にして造籍したのかどうかも疑われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this system does not exist any longer, so it is doubtful whether family registers of all ranks of people were created on a national basis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This system no longer exists, however, so it is doubtful if family registers for all ranks of people were created on a national basis.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This system no longer exists, however, so it is doubtful if family registers for all ranks of people were created on a national basis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>つまり、氏や姓を持つ首長や豪族の民までも把握できたのかと言うことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, it is doubtful whether people controlled by chiefs and Gozoku (local ruling families) who had a family or clan name were also grasped.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, it is doubtful that tabs were also kept on people controlled by chiefs and Gozoku (local ruling families) who had a family or clan name.</e>
<cmt>whether &gt; that; grasped &gt; kept tabs on (把握); fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, it is doubtful that tabs were also kept on people controlled by chiefs and Gozoku (local ruling families) who had a family or clan name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="24">
<j>646年（大化2）大化改新の詔を発布して今後の政治改革の方針を示した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 646 Taika kaishin no Mikotonori (Taika Reforms Edict) was issued for the purpose of announcing political reform policies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 646, the Taika kaishin no Mikotonori (Taika Reforms Edict) was issued for announcing political reform policies.</e>
<cmt>added comma after &quot;646&quot;; added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Taika&quot;; fixed spacing after parenthesis; eliminated &quot;the purpose of&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 646, the Taika no kaishin no Mikotonori (Taika Reforms Edict) was issued for announcing political reform policies.</e>
<cmt>Taika kaishin　を Taika no kaishinに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>（しかし、今日では改新の詔は後世作られたものとするのが通説である。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(It is, however, a commonly accepted theory that Taika kaishin no Mikotonori was devised in later years.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(However, it is a commonly accepted theory that the Taika Reforms Edict was created in later years.)</e>
<cmt>Taika kaishin no Mikotonori &gt; Taika Reforms Edict; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(However, it is a commonly accepted theory that the Taika Reforms Edict was created in later years.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="26">
<j>『日本書紀』には670年（天智9）二月条に「戸籍を造り、盗賊と浮浪者とを断ず」とみえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; states that &quot;family registers were created and robbers and vagrants were regulated&quot; in its article of February 670.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In an article from February of 670 in the &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; it is stated that &quot;family registers were created and robbers and vagrants were regulated.&quot;</e>
<cmt>rearranged sentence and fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In an article from February of 670 in the &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; it is stated that &quot;family registers were created and robbers and vagrants were regulated.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>畿内はもちろん、西は九州から東は常陸国・上野国（こうづけ）まで造籍の実施されたことを示す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It demonstrates that family registers were established not only in the Kinai region (provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara) but also from Kyushu in the west to Hitachi and Kozuke Provinces in the east.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It indicates that family registers were established not only in the Kinai region (provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara) but also from Kyushu in the west to Hitachi and Kozuke Provinces in the east.</e>
<cmt>deomonstrates &gt; indicates (示す);</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It indicates that family registers were established not only in the Kinai region (provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara) but also from Kyushu in the west to Hitachi and Kozuke Provinces in the east.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>氏姓制を確定する台帳の機能を果たしたものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that family registers served as a ledger for ascertaining the system of clans and hereditary titles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that family registers served as a ledger for ascertaining the system of clans and hereditary titles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that family registers served as a ledger for ascertaining the system of clans and hereditary titles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="29">
<j>647年（大化3）から664年（天智3）までの間に一括投棄された飛鳥京跡の木簡に「白髪部五十戸、◎十口」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mokkan (narrow strips of wood on which an official message is written) in the remains of Asuka-kyo which was dumped in a lump during the period from 647 to 664 has a sentence written on it: &quot;Shirakabe 50 families, ??? Tens units.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is writing on a bundle of mokkan (narrow strips of wood used for official messages) that were found abandoned in the remains of Asuka-kyo between 647 and 664 that says: &quot;Shirakabe 50 families, ??? Tens units.&quot;</e>
<cmt>rearranged sentence and fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is writing on a bundle of mokkan (narrow strips of wood used for official messages) that were found abandoned in the remains of Asuka-kyo between 647 and 664 that says: &quot;Shirakabe 50 families, ??? Tens units.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>◎は五と思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is presumed that &quot;???&quot; was &quot;five.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;???&quot; is an unreadable character, but it is presumed to be the number &quot;five.&quot;</e>
<cmt>extended the sentence to read more understandably</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;???&quot; is an unreadable character, but it is presumed to be the number &quot;five.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>五十戸を単位として行政的に把握する試みが進められていたことを示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This sentence demonstrates that an attempt was being made by administrative officers to comprehend the population in terms of fifty families.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This indicates that an attempt was being made by administrative officers to comprehend the population by fifty-family units.</e>
<cmt>in terms of fifty familes &gt; by fifty family units; fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This indicates that an attempt was being made by administrative officers to comprehend the population by fifty-family units.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>この統一的造籍・行政的村落把握を実施するには、体系的な法が必要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Systematic laws are required in order to conduct such unified creation of family registers and administrative comprehension of villages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Systematic laws are required in order to conduct such a unification of family registers and administrative comprehension of villages.</e>
<cmt>unified creation &gt; unification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Systematic laws are required in order to conduct such a unification of family registers and administrative comprehension of villages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>弘仁格式序に「天智天皇元年に至り、令二十二巻を制す、世人所謂近江朝廷之令也」と伝えるが、近江令は存在しなかったとみられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is stated in the preface of Konin kyakushiki code (amendments to penal and administrative law compiled in 820) that &quot;Twenty-two volumes of administrative codes were completed in the First Year of Emperor Tenmu, which are called Omi-chotei-no-ryo (The Administrative Code of the Omi Court),&quot; but it is believed that Omi-Ryo (Omi Administrative Code) did not exist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is stated in the preface of the Konin kyakushiki code (amendments to penal and administrative law compiled in 820) that &quot;Twenty-two volumes of administrative codes were completed in the First Year of Emperor Tenmu called Omi-chotei-no-ryo (The Administrative Code of the Omi Court),&quot; but it is believed that the Omi-Ryo (Omi Administrative Code) did not exist.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Konin&quot;; eliminated comma after &quot;Tenmu&quot;; eliminated &quot;which are called&quot;; eliminated extra space after &quot;Court)&quot;; added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Omi-Ryo&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is stated in the preface of the Konin kyakushiki code (amendments to penal and administrative law compiled in 820) that &quot;Twenty-two volumes of administrative codes were completed in the First Year of Emperor Tenmu called Omi-chotei-no-ryo (The Administrative Code of the Omi Court),&quot; but it is believed that the Omi-Ryo (Omi Administrative Code) did not exist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="34">
<j>庚寅（こういん）の年籍</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koin no Nenjaku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koin no Nenjaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koin no Nenjaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="35">
<j>681年（天武10）に飛鳥浄御原令の編纂が開始され、689年（持統3）になってようやく飛鳥浄御原令ができあがった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Asuka Kiyomihara Code started to be compiled in 681 and was completed at last in 689.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Compilation of the Asuka Kiyomihara Code began in 681 and was completed in 689.</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;at last&quot;; fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Compilation of the Asuka Kiyomihara Code began in 681 and was completed in 689.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>その戸令（こりょう）に基づいて690年（持統4）に全国的な戸籍の庚寅年籍が作成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the basis of this Code of Households, Koin no Nenjaku, the national family register, was established in 690.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the basis of this Code of Households, the national family register &apos;Koin no Nenjaku&apos; was established in 690.</e>
<cmt>added &apos; around &quot;Koin no Nenjaku&quot;; rearranged sentence to reduce commas</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the basis of this Code of Households, the national family register &apos;Koin no Nenjaku&apos; was established in 690.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>現存しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It does not exist any longer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It does not exist any longer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It does not exist any longer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="38">
<j>同戸籍は、その後の六年に一度作成するという「六年一造」の造籍の出発点になっただけでなく、五十戸一里を基準に行政的に戸を編成して、その戸内の家族（戸口）の名・年齢・戸主との続柄などを詳述したことによって、個々の家族構成を直接的に把握することを可能にし、それを基に班田収授を行い、人頭課税をする台帳の機能も果たした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This registration system not only served as a starting point of &quot;rokunen-ichizo&quot;(one creation in six years) in which family registers were created every six years thereafter but also made it possible to see the direct picture of composition of each household by organizing households in terms of fifty households in ichi-ri on an administrative basis and describing each family member&apos;s name, age and relation to the household head in detail, and served as a ledger on which to conduct Handen Shuju (a regulation of land ownership) and jinto kazei (poll taxation).</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This registration system not only served as a starting point of &quot;rokunen-ichizo&quot; (literally, &quot;one creation in six years) in which family registers were created every six years thereafter, but also made it possible to see the direct composition of each household by organizing households in terms of fifty households in ichi-ri on an administrative basis and describing each family member&apos;s name, age and relation to the household head in detail, and served as a ledger to conduct Handen Shuju (a regulation of land ownership) and jinto kazei (poll taxation).</e>
<cmt>added &quot;literally&quot; before &quot;one creation in six years&quot;; added comma after &quot;thereafter&quot;; eliminated &quot;picture of&quot; before &quot;composition&quot;; eliminated &quot;on which&quot; after &quot;ledger&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This registration system not only served as a starting point of &quot;rokunen-ichizo&quot; (literally, &quot;one creation in six years) in which family registers were created every six years thereafter, but also made it possible to see the direct composition of each household by organizing households in terms of fifty households in ichi-ri on an administrative basis and describing each family member&apos;s name, age and relation to the household head in detail, and served as a ledger to conduct Handen Shuju (a regulation of land ownership) and jinto kazei (poll taxation).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>また、良賤身分を定める原簿の機能を付随するようになったようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the function as an original record on which to determine grandness of each person&apos;s status seems to have been added to this registration system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The function as an original record to determine each person&apos;s status seems to have been added to this registration system.</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;In addition&quot;; eliminated &quot;grandness&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The function as an original record to determine each person&apos;s status seems to have been added to this registration system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>また、年齢別人口構成や家族形態などを具体的に知ることが出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore this system provides concrete information on the age structure of population and family forms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This system provides concrete information on the age structure of populations and family forms.</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;Furthermore&quot;; population &gt; populations;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This system provides concrete information on the age structure of populations and family forms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="41">
<j>令に則った戸籍を介して個別に人身を把握して、個別人身支配が始まったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Domination over individuals was started by comprehending individuals via family registers organized in accordance with laws.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Governing individuals began by keeping tabs on individuals via family registers organized in accordance with laws.</e>
<cmt>Domination over individuals &gt; Governing individuals; was started &gt; began; comprehending &gt; keeping tabs on;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Governing individuals began by keeping tabs on individuals via family registers organized in accordance with laws.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="42">
<j>人民を地域により編成するという作業はほぼ完了し、692年（持統2）には、庚寅年籍に基づく口分田の班給が、畿内で開始された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Organization of people according to areas was almost completed, and in 692 kubunden (the farm land given to each farmer in the Ritsuryo system) started to be distributed in the Kinai region on the basis of Koin no Nenjaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Organizing people according to area was nearly complete, and in the year 692, kubunden (farm land given to each farmer in the Ritsuryo system) began to be distributed in the Kinai region on the basis of Koin no Nenjaku.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Organizing people according to area was nearly complete, and in the year 692, kubunden (farm land given to each farmer in the Ritsuryo system) began to be distributed in the Kinai region on the basis of Koin no Nenjaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>同時に全国でも班田収授法（はんでんしゅうじゅほう）が施行されたと推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is presumed that at the same time Handen Shuju ho (the law of periodic reallocations of rice land) was put in force all over Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is presumed that the Handen Shuju ho (the law of periodic reallocations of rice land) was put in force all over Japan at the same time.</e>
<cmt>moved &quot;at the same time&quot; to the end of the sentence;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is presumed that the Handen Shuju ho (the law of periodic reallocations of rice land) was put in force all over Japan at the same time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="44">
<j>因みに、戸籍と同じように、律令時代の人口（人頭）を知ることの出来る史料として、計帳がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For comparison, another example of historic materials which provide as much information on population in the Ritsuryo period as family registers is keicho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a comparison, the keicho is another example of historic material that provides as much information on populations in the Ritsuryo period as family registers.</e>
<cmt>For comparison &gt; As a comparison; added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;keicho&quot;; moved &quot;the keicho&quot; toward the beginning of the sentence;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a comparison, the keicho is another example of historic material that provides as much information on populations in the Ritsuryo period as family registers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="45">
<j>計帳と課役</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keicho and distribution of assignments</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keicho and distribution of assignments</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keicho and distribution of assignments</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="46">
<j>計帳は、課役を徴収するための基本台帳である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keicho is a basic ledger on which to levy duties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keicho is a basic ledger to levy duties.</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;on which&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keicho is a basic ledger to levy duties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>毎年作成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was prepared every year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was prepared every year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was prepared every year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>そこには人口、性別、年齢から一人ひとりの身体的特徴までが里長（郷長）によって書き上げられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Satoosa (village chief) wrote in population as well as each individual&apos;s gender, age and bodily characteristics in keicho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Satoosa (village chief) wrote in the population as well as each individual&apos;s gender, age and bodily characteristics in the keicho.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;The&quot; before &quot;Satoosa&quot; &quot;population&quot; and &quot;keicho&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Satoosa (village chief) wrote in the population as well as each individual&apos;s gender, age and bodily characteristics in the keicho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>国ごとにまとめられて租庸調（ちょう）・庸（よう）・雑徭（ぞうよう）、軍役など、課役賦課の基本台帳とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keicho was organized for each Province and was made a basic ledger on which to levy duties including Soyocho (a tax system, corvee), Yo (Labor or alternative goods), zoyo (irregular corvee) and military service.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The keicho was organized for each province and was a basic ledger to levy duties, including Soyocho (a tax system, corvee), Yo (Labor or alternative goods), zoyo (irregular corvee) and military service.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;The&quot; before &quot;keicho&quot;; made &quot;province&quot; lowercase; eliminated &quot;made a&quot;; eliminated &quot;on which&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The keicho was organized for each province and was a basic ledger to levy duties, including Soyocho (a tax system, corvee), Yo (Labor or alternative goods), zoyo (irregular corvee) and military service.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="50">
<j>計帳の作成には、三段階あり、三種の文書が出来上がった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are three steps in creation of keicho, from which three types of documents are completed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were three steps in the creation of a keicho from which three types of documents were completed.</e>
<cmt>changed to past tense; eliminated comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were three steps in the creation of a keicho from which three types of documents were completed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>一を手実（しゅじつ）、二を歴名（れきみょう）、三を目録という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first is shujitsu, the second is rekimyo and the third is mokuroku (catalogue).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first was called shujitsu, the second was rekimyo and the third is mokuroku (catalogue).</e>
<cmt>is &gt; was called; is &gt; was</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first was called shujitsu, the second was rekimyo and the third is mokuroku (catalogue).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="52">
<j>手実とは、戸主が作成し、毎年六月末日までに京職（きょうしき）や国司に提出する申告書である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shujitsu is an application form prepared by the household head and submitted to Kyoshiki (the Capital Bureau) or kokushi (provincial governors) before the 30th of the 6th month every year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shujitsu was an application form prepared by the household head and submitted to the Kyoshiki (the Capital Bureau) or kokushi (provincial governors) before the 30th of the 6th month every year.</e>
<cmt>is &gt; was; added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Kyoshiki&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shujitsu was an application form prepared by the household head and submitted to the Kyoshiki (the Capital Bureau) or kokushi (provincial governors) before the 30th of the 6th month every year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>戸主以下全戸口の姓名・年齢・続柄を書き上げた文書である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a document which includes the name, age and relation of all the individuals (including the household head).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a document that included the name, age and relationships of all the individuals (including the household head).</e>
<cmt>is &gt; was; relation &gt; relationships;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a document that included the name, age and relationships of all the individuals (including the household head).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>当時の識字層からみて、郡司や里長が手実の作成を代行する場合も多かったであろうと推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Considering literate people in those days, it is presumed that gunji (district managers) and satoosa often prepared shujitsu for household heads.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In consideration of the literacy rate of the time, it is presumed that the gunji (district managers) and satoosa often prepared shujitsu for household heads.</e>
<cmt>Considering literate people in those days &gt; In consideration of the literacy rate of the time</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In consideration of the literacy rate of the time, it is presumed that the gunji (district managers) and satoosa often prepared shujitsu for household heads.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>この手実に基づき、官司では歴名・目録が作成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rekimyo and mokuroku were prepared by government officials on the basis of this shujitsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rekimyo and mokuroku were prepared by government officials on the basis of shujitsu.</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;this&quot; before &quot;shijitsu&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rekimyo and mokuroku were prepared by government officials on the basis of shujitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="56">
<j>歴名はちょうど戸籍のように、各戸の手実の内容を一里（五十戸）分列挙して、一巻の帳簿に編成したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rekimyo is an account book which lists the contents of shujitsu of ichi-ri (fifty households) as family registers do.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rekimyo were account books that listed the contents of shujitsu of ichi-ri (fifty households), similar to family registers.</e>
<cmt>changed to past tense; added comma after (fifty households); as family registers do &gt; similar to family registers</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rekimyo were account books that listed the contents of shujitsu of ichi-ri (fifty households), similar to family registers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>各戸ごとに負担すべき調庸額が記録され、おそらく里全体の調庸額も記録され、前年との戸口の異同が詳細に示されていた点が戸籍と異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is different from family registers in that it records the amount of choyo (taxes in tribute and labor under the ritsuryo system) to be borne by each household and probably the amount of choyo for the whole ri, and provides detailed information on comparison of household members with the previous year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rekimyo are different from family registers in that they record the amount of choyo (taxes in tribute and labor under the ritsuryo system) to be borne by each household and probably the amount of choyo for the whole ri, and they provide detailed information on a comparison of household members from the previous year.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rekimyo are different from family registers in that they record the amount of choyo (taxes in tribute and labor under the ritsuryo system) to be borne by each household and probably the amount of choyo for the whole ri, and they provide detailed information on a comparison of household members from the previous year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="58">
<j>目録は、具体的な戸の内容を記載していない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mokuroku does not include the concrete contents of households.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mokuroku do not include the specifics of households.</e>
<cmt>does &gt; do; concrete &gt; specifics (具体的); eliminated &quot;contents&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mokuroku do not include the specifics of households.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>数字だけの統計文書である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a statistical document consisting only of figures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a statistical document consisting only of figures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a statistical document consisting only of figures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>一国及び各郡の戸数・口数が課役負担の有無を基準として詳細に集計され、前年度との異同、及びその年の調・庸額が示される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of households and that of members for each Province and district are calculated minutely according to whether duties are borne or not, and comparison with data of the previous year as well as the amount of choyo for that year is shown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of households and members for each province and district are minutely calculated according to whether duties are borne or not, and comparisons are shown with data of the previous year as well as the amount of choyo for that year.</e>
<cmt>made &quot;province&quot; lowercase; calculated minutely &gt; minutely calculated; is shown &gt; are shown; moved &quot;are shown&quot; to earlier in the sentence;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of households and members for each province and district are minutely calculated according to whether duties are borne or not, and comparisons are shown with data of the previous year as well as the amount of choyo for that year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>令規定に毎年八月末日までに京に進上するべく義務づけられた計帳とはこの目録を指し、京都ではこれによって毎年の歳入予定を知るとともに、全国の口数、特に課口数を掌握していたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keicho which was required by regulation of laws to be submitted to Kyoto no later than the end of the eighth month every year is this mokuroku, and Kyoto comprehended the planned revenue for each year and the number of households (especially households bearing duties) throughout Japan with the use of mokuroku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These mokuroku were keicho that were required by law to be submitted to Kyoto no later than the end of the eighth month every year, and Kyoto planned the revenue for each year and for the number of households (especially households bearing duties) throughout Japan with mokuroku.</e>
<cmt>moved &quot;this mokuroku&quot; to the beginning of the sentence; This mokuroku &gt; These mokuroku; eliminated &quot;by regulation of; laws &gt; law; eliminated &quot;comprehended&quot;; eliminated &quot;the use of&quot; before &quot;mokuroku&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These mokuroku were keicho that were required by law to be submitted to Kyoto no later than the end of the eighth month every year, and Kyoto planned the revenue for each year and for the number of households (especially households bearing duties) throughout Japan with mokuroku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>なお歴名の作成・京に進上の規定は令にはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was no provision in laws concerning creation and submission to Kyoto of rekimyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was no provision in laws concerning the creation and submission to Kyoto for rekimyo.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;creation&quot;; of rekimyo &gt; for rekimyo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was no provision in laws concerning the creation and submission to Kyoto for rekimyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="63">
<j>成年男子の21歳～60歳までを正丁（せいてい）といい、課役の対象となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Adult males between 21 and 60 years of age are called seitei and required to bear duties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Adult males between twenty-one and sixty years of age were called seitei and required to bear duties.</e>
<cmt>21 &gt; twenty-one; 60 &gt; sixty; are &gt; were</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Adult males between twenty-one and sixty years of age were called seitei and required to bear duties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="64">
<j>調は、その地域の特産物で、一定量の絹、あしぎぬ、糸、綿、布などの繊維製品、塩、鰒、海藻、堅魚などの海産物や鉄、それに調副物として油、染料、海産物、山の幸など、様々な物品から成っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cho is special local products of the area, consisting of a variety of goods including a certain amount of fiber products such as silk, thick silk fabric, threads, cotton and cloth, marine products such as salt, abalone, seaweeds and katauo (solid dried fish), iron, and Cho no sowaritsumono (the subordinate tax to cho (a tax paid by tribute)) such as oil, dyes, marine products and mountain vegetables.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cho were the special local products of an area that consisted of a variety of goods, including fiber products such as silk, thick silk fabric, threads, cotton and cloth, marine products such as salt, abalone, seaweed and katauo (solid dried fish), iron, as well as Cho no sowaritsumono (the subordinate tax to cho [a tax paid by tribute]) such as oil, dyes, marine products and mountain vegetables.</e>
<cmt>Cho is &gt; Cho were; added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;special&quot;; the area &gt; an area; eliminated comma after &quot;area&quot; and added &quot;that&quot; in its place; consisting &gt; consisted; added comma after &quot;goods&quot;; seaweeds &gt; seaweed; and &gt; as well as; changed parenthesis inside the parenthesis to brackets; eliminated &quot;a certain amount of&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cho were the special local products of an area that consisted of a variety of goods, including fiber products such as silk, thick silk fabric, threads, cotton and cloth, marine products such as salt, abalone, seaweed and katauo (solid dried fish), iron, as well as Cho no sowaritsumono (the subordinate tax to cho [a tax paid by tribute]) such as oil, dyes, marine products and mountain vegetables.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="65">
<j>庸は、年10日京都へ出て使役される歳役の代納物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yo is the substitute for labor in Kyoto for ten days a year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yo was the substitute for labor in Kyoto for ten days a year.</e>
<cmt>is &gt; was</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yo was the substitute for labor in Kyoto for ten days a year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="66">
<j>戸籍と紙背文書</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Family registers and shihai monjo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family registers and shihai monjo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family registers and shihai monjo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>戸籍は令に拠れば30年の保管が行われた後に廃棄されることとなっていたが、当時の紙は大変貴重品であったために、実際には廃棄されずに他の官司や官寺などに回されて、裏面を再利用するのが一般的であった（紙背文書）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the Code, family registers were to be stored for thirty years and then scrapped, but in fact they were not scrapped and it was common to send them to other government officials and kanji (state-sponsored temples) and to reuse the other side of them (shihai monjo) because paper was so valuable in those days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the Code, family registers were to be stored for thirty years and then discared, but instead of being thrown away, it was common to send them to other government officials and kanji (state-sponsored temples) to use the other side (shihai monjo) since paper was so valuable in those days.</e>
<cmt>scrapped &gt; discarded; scrapped &gt; thrown away; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the Code, family registers were to be stored for thirty years and then discared, but instead of being thrown away, it was common to send them to other government officials and kanji (state-sponsored temples) to use the other side (shihai monjo) since paper was so valuable in those days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>東大寺正倉院に保管された文書（正倉院文書）の中にはこうした戸籍を再利用したものが含まれており、正倉院の宝物そのものとは別の意味で歴史学者に多くの貴重な情報を提供している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of the documents stored in Todai-ji Temple Shosoin (Shoso-in monjo (documents of Shoso-in)) were written on the reused family registers, and so they provide a lot of valuable information to historians in a sense different from treasures in Shosoin themselves.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A number of the documents stored in Todai-ji Temple Shosoin (Shoso-in monjo [documents of Shoso-in]) are written on reused family registers and provide a great deal of valuable information to historians in a different sense from the other treasures in the Shosoin.</e>
<cmt>Some &gt; A number; () &gt; []; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A number of the documents stored in Todai-ji Temple Shosoin (Shoso-in monjo [documents of Shoso-in]) are written on reused family registers and provide a great deal of valuable information to historians in a different sense from the other treasures in the Shosoin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="32">
<sen id="69">
<j>戸籍の関係年表</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chronology of events related to family registers</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chronology of events related to family registers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chronology of events related to family registers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="33">
<sen id="70">
<j>681年（天武10）飛鳥浄御原律令の編纂を開始する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 681 compilation of Asuka Kiyomihara Code was started.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 681, compilation of the Asuka Kiyomihara Code began.</e>
<cmt>added comma after 681; added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Asuka&quot;; was started &gt; began</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 681, compilation of the Asuka Kiyomihara Code began.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="34">
<sen id="71">
<j>689年（持統3）諸司に令一部二十二巻（飛鳥浄御原令）をわかつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 689 twenty-two volumes of one code (Asuka Kiyomihara Code) were distributed among shoshi (officials).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 689, twenty-two volumes of one code (Asuka Kiyomihara Code) were distributed among shoshi (officials).</e>
<cmt>added comma after 689;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 689, twenty-two volumes of one code (Asuka Kiyomihara Code) were distributed among shoshi (officials).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>八月、戸籍の作成、浮浪人を取り締まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August, family registers were created and vagrants were regulated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August, family registers were created and vagrants were regulated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August, family registers were created and vagrants were regulated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="35">
<sen id="73">
<j>690年（持統4）九月、戸令により庚寅年籍を造る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September 690, Koin no Nenjaku was established under the Code of Households.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September 690, Koin no Nenjaku was established under the Code of Households.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September 690, Koin no Nenjaku was established under the Code of Households.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="36">
<sen id="74">
<j>691年（持統5）三月、良・賤身分を区別する規定を定める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March 691, rules for distinguishing grandness of individual&apos;s status were set.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March 691, rules were set for distinguishing the status of individuals.</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;grandness&quot;; fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March 691, rules were set for distinguishing the status of individuals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>四月、開放された奴婢の身分を庚寅年籍で確定する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April, the status of freed slaves was ascertained in Koin no Nenjaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April, the status of freed slaves was ascertained in Koin no Nenjaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April, the status of freed slaves was ascertained in Koin no Nenjaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>十月陵戸の制を定める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October the system of Ryoko (Imperial tomb guards, one kind of senmin) was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October, the system of Ryoko (Imperial tomb guards, one kind of senmin) was established.</e>
<cmt>added comma after &quot;October&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October, the system of Ryoko (Imperial tomb guards, one kind of senmin) was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="37">
<sen id="77">
<j>692年（持統2）畿内で口分田の班給を開始する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 692, distribution of kubunden was started in the Kinai region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 692, distribution of kubunden was started in the Kinai region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 692, distribution of kubunden was started in the Kinai region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>全国的にも行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also conducted throughout Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also conducted throughout Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also conducted throughout Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>九月、班田大夫を四畿内に遣わす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September, handen taifu (master of the allotted farmland) was sent to Shikinai (four provinces close to the Capital: Yamato, Yamashiro, Settsu, Kawachi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September, the handen taifu (master of the allotted farmland) was sent to Shikinai (four provinces close to the Capital: Yamato, Yamashiro, Settsu, Kawachi).</e>
<cmt>added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;handen&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September, the handen taifu (master of the allotted farmland) was sent to Shikinai (four provinces close to the Capital: Yamato, Yamashiro, Settsu, Kawachi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="38">
<sen id="80">
<j>693年（持統7）一月、百姓に黄色衣、奴に黒衣を着させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 693, peasants were made to wear in yellow, and yakko (varlet) in black.</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January 693, peasants were to wear yellow, and yakko (attendants) were to dress in black.</e>
<cmt>varlet &gt; attendants; fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January 693, peasants were to wear yellow, and yakko (attendants) were to dress in black.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>三月、桑・紵・梨・栗などの栽培を奨励し、五穀の助けとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March, cultivation of mulberries, flax, pears and chestnuts was promoted in order to add to the five main cereals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March, cultivation of mulberries, flax, pears and chestnuts was promoted in order to add to the five main cereals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March, cultivation of mulberries, flax, pears and chestnuts was promoted in order to add to the five main cereals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="39">
<sen id="82">
<j>694年（持統8）藤原京に都を移す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 694 the capital was moved to Fujiwara-kyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 694, the capital was moved to Fujiwara-kyo.</e>
<cmt>added comma after 694</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 694, the capital was moved to Fujiwara-kyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="40">
<sen id="83">
<j>697年（文武元）持統天皇譲位し、文武天皇即位する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 697 Emperor Jito abdicated from the throne and Emperor Monmu ascended the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 697, Emperor Jito abdicated from the throne and Emperor Monmu ascended the throne.</e>
<cmt>added comma after 697;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 697, Emperor Jito abdicated from the throne and Emperor Monmu ascended the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="41">
<sen id="84">
<j>700年（文武4）三月、王臣に令文を読習させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March 700, vassals were made to learn letter of the law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March 700, vassals were obligated to learn the letter of the law.</e>
<cmt>made &gt; obligated; added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;letter&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March 700, vassals were obligated to learn the letter of the law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>律条を撰定する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ritsujo (law of itemized form) was selected.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ritsujo (law of itemized form) was selected.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ritsujo (law of itemized form) was selected.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>諸国の牧地を定め、牛馬を放牧する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pasture lands were specified in various Provinces and cows and horses were sent to graze there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Pasture lands were specified in various provinces for cows and horses to graze.</e>
<cmt>made &quot;provinces&quot; lowercase; fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Pasture lands were specified in various provinces for cows and horses to graze.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>六月、刑部親王・藤原不比等等に、大宝律令を撰定させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June, Imperial Prince Osakabe, FUJIWARA no Fuhito and others were ordered to select Taiho Ritsuryo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June, Imperial Prince Osakabe, FUJIWARA no Fuhito and others were ordered to select Taiho Ritsuryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June, Imperial Prince Osakabe, FUJIWARA no Fuhito and others were ordered to select Taiho Ritsuryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="42">
<sen id="88">
<j>701年（大宝元）六月、新令によって政治を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June 701, politics were carried out under the new code.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June 701, politics were carried out under the new code.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June 701, politics were carried out under the new code.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>八月、律令の選定を完成する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August, selection of Ritsuryo was completed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August, selection of Ritsuryo was completed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August, selection of Ritsuryo was completed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>明法博士を西海道以外の六道に派遣し、新令を講義させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myoho hakase (Professor of Law) was sent to the six main roads except for Saikaido in order to give a lecture about the new code.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myoho hakase (Professors of Law) were sent to the six main roads, except for Saikaido, in order to give lectures about the new code.</e>
<cmt>added comma after &quot;roads&quot; and &quot;Saikaido&quot;; a lecture &gt; lectures</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myoho hakase (Professors of Law) were sent to the six main roads, except for Saikaido, in order to give lectures about the new code.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="43">
<sen id="91">
<j>702年（大宝2）大宝律を天下にわかつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 702 Taiho Code was made public.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 702, the Taiho Code was made public.</e>
<cmt>added comma after 702; added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Taiho&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 702, the Taiho Code was made public.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>七月、新律を講義する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June, lectures were given about the new laws.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June, lectures were given about the new laws.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June, lectures were given about the new laws.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>十月、大宝律令を諸国に領下する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October, Taiho Ritsuryo was distributed among Provinces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October, Taiho Ritsuryo was distributed among the provinces.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;provinces&quot;; made &quot;provinces&quot; lowercase;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October, Taiho Ritsuryo was distributed among the provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>十二月、持統太上天皇没する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December, Jito Daijo-tenno (the ex-Emperor Jito) passed away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December, Jito Daijo-tenno (the ex-Emperor Jito) passed away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December, Jito Daijo-tenno (the ex-Emperor Jito) passed away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="44">
<sen id="95">
<j>703年（大宝3）庚午年籍を戸籍の原簿とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 703, Kogo no Nenjaku was made an original record of family registers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 703, Kogo no Nenjaku was made an original record of family registers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 703, Kogo no Nenjaku was made an original record of family registers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="45">
<sen id="96">
<j>706年（慶雲3）田租の法を定め、町別十五束（成斤の束）にする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 706, the law on denso (rice field tax) was established and fifteen bundles (成斤の束) were demanded for each town.</e>
<cmt>読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 706, the law on denso (rice field tax) was established and each town was required to supply fifteen bundles (成斤の束).</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 706, the law on denso (rice field tax) was established and each town was required to supply fifteen bundles (成斤の束).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="46">
<sen id="97">
<j>710年（和銅3）平城京に遷都する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 710 the capital was moved to Heijo-kyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 710, the capital was moved to Heijo-kyo.</e>
<cmt>added comma after &quot;710&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 710, the capital was moved to Heijo-kyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="47">
<sen id="98">
<j>711年（和銅4）諸司に律令を励行させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 711 shoshi was ordered to enforce Ritsuryo rigorously.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 711, shoshi was ordered to enforce Ritsuryo rigorously.</e>
<cmt>added comma after &quot;711&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 711, shoshi was ordered to enforce Ritsuryo rigorously.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="48">
<sen id="99">
<j>713年（和銅6）度量・調庸・義倉等に関する五条の事を定める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 713 five articles were established concerning scales and measures, choyo and giso (stockpiling warehouse).</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 713, five articles were established concerning scales and measures, choyo and giso (stockpiling warehouses).</e>
<cmt>added comma after &quot;713&quot;; warehouse &gt; warehouses;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 713, five articles were established concerning scales and measures, choyo and giso (stockpiling warehouses).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>四月、丹後国・美作国・大隅国の三国を建てる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April, three provinces (Tango, Mimasaka and Osumi Provinces) were established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April, three provinces (Tango, Mimasaka and Osumi) were established.</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;Provinces&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April, three provinces (Tango, Mimasaka and Osumi) were established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>五月、郡・郷名に好字をつけさせる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May, the names of districts and go&apos;s were made to bear koji (letters signified good meaning and often used for person&apos;s name or place name).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May, the names of districts and go&apos;s became obligated to bear koji (letters which signified a positive meaning and often used for a person&apos;s name or place name).</e>
<cmt>were made to &gt; became obligated to; added &quot;which&quot; before &quot;signified&quot;; good &gt; positive; added &quot;a&quot; before &quot;person&apos;s&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May, the names of districts and go&apos;s became obligated to bear koji (letters which signified a positive meaning and often used for a person&apos;s name or place name).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="49">
<sen id="102">
<j>715年（和銅8）五月、逃亡三ヶ月以上の浮浪人に、逃亡地で調庸を課する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May 715, choyo was levied on vagrants who had been escaping for more than three months at the place to which they had fled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May 715, choyo was levied on vagrants who had been running from their duties for more than three months at the place to which they had fled.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;from their duties&quot;; escaping &gt; running</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 715, choyo was levied on vagrants who had been running from their duties for more than three months at the place to which they had fled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="50">
<sen id="103">
<j>715年（霊亀元）九月、里を郷に改め、郷を二・三の里に分ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September 715, sato was turned into go and go was divided into a few sato.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September 715, sato was turned into go and go was divided into a few sato.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September 715, sato was turned into go and go was divided into a few sato.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="51">
<sen id="104">
<j>717年（霊亀3）四月、百姓の違法の出家を禁じ、行基の活動を禁圧する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 717, peasants were prohibited from unlawfully becoming a priest, and Gyoki&apos;s activities were suppressed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 717, peasants were prohibited from unlawfully becoming a priests, and Gyoki&apos;s activities were suppressed.</e>
<cmt>priest &gt; priests;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 717, peasants were prohibited from unlawfully becoming a priests, and Gyoki&apos;s activities were suppressed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>五月、太計帳・青苗簿・輸租帳などの式を諸国に領下する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May, formalities of 太計帳, seibyobo (the register of standing crops) and yusocho (the field-tax report, same meaning of socho) were distributed among provinces.</e>
<cmt>読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May, formalities of 太計帳, seibyobo (the register of standing crops) and yusocho (the field-tax report, same meaning of socho) were distributed among provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May, formalities of 太計帳, seibyobo (the register of standing crops) and yusocho (the field-tax report, same meaning of socho) were distributed among provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>五月、能登国・安房国・石城国・石背国の四国を建てる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May, four provinces (Noto, Awa, Iwaki and Iwase Provinces) were established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May, four provinces (Noto, Awa, Iwaki and Iwase) were established.</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;Provinces&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May, four provinces (Noto, Awa, Iwaki and Iwase) were established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>国別の衛士数を定める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of eji (guards) for each province was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of eji (guards) for each province was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of eji (guards) for each province was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>この年、藤原不比等らに命じて、律令を撰定する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this year FUJIWARA no Fuhito was ordered to select Ritsuryo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this year, FUJIWARA no Fuhito was ordered to select Ritsuryo.</e>
<cmt>added comma after &quot;year&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this year, FUJIWARA no Fuhito was ordered to select Ritsuryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>（養老律令）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Yoro Code)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Yoro Code)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Yoro Code)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="52">
<sen id="110">
<j>719年（養老3）天下の民戸に陸田を給する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 719 fields were distributed among minko (private houses) all over Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 719, fields were distributed among minko (private houses) all over Japan.</e>
<cmt>added comma after &quot;719&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 719, fields were distributed among minko (private houses) all over Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Izayohi(id:13095), Non-stop24(id:10471), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), ヤマト(id:8425), 水野白楓(id:22811), Shikire(id:1623), Hiyragi(id:230078), Yanahan(id:2437), Shimoxx(id:9332), 210.(id:9838), Namazu-tron(id:135120), Greenland4(id:114494), Chuta(id:10457), Johncapistrano(id:969), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>