<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>延喜格</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Engikyaku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Engikyaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Engikyaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>延喜格（えんぎきゃく）は、平安時代の延喜7年（907年）11月_(旧暦)に完成し、翌年12月の宣旨によって施行された格式。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Engikyaku, a collection of amendments to and enforcement regulations for Ritsuryo (basic national laws), was completed in November 907 during the Heian Period and put into force by a senji (written order of the Emperor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Engikyaku, a collection of amendments to and enforcement regulations for Ritsuryo (basic national laws), was completed in November 907 during the Heian Period and put into force by a senji (written order of the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Engikyaku, a collection of amendments to and enforcement regulations for Ritsuryo (basic national laws), was completed in November 907 (old calendar) during the Heian period and put into force by a senji (written order of the Emperor) in December of the following year (old calendar).</e>
<cmt>(old calendar) 補足in December of the following year (old calendar)補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>当初は10巻であったが、間もなく臨時格2巻が追加されて全12巻となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Engikyaku at first consisted of 10 volumes, but two extraordinary volumes were soon added to make the total number of volumes 12.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Engikyaku at first consisted of 10 volumes, but two additional volumes were soon added to make the total number of volumes 12.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Engikyaku at first consisted of 10 volumes, but two additional volumes were soon added to make the total number of volumes 12.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>「貞観格」を継いで貞観_(日本)11年（869年）より延喜7年（907年）までの39年間の詔勅・太政官符のうち編纂当時に実際に行われていた重要なものを取捨選択して各省毎に配列した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Succeeding Jogankyaku, Engikyaku is a selected collection of particularly important ones which had been in actual effect at the time of its compilation out of Jogankyaku, so chosen as to comprise imperial edicts and Daijokanbu (official documents issued by Daijokan, the Grand Council of State) during the 39 years from 869 until 907, with its contents classified by ministry.</e>
<cmt>律令制下の太政官は、明治時代の太政官と異なり、だいじょうかんと読むのが普通だと思います。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Succeeding Jogankyaku, Engikyaku is a selected collection of particularly important volumes which had been in actual effect at the time of its compilation out of Jogankyaku, so chosen as to comprise imperial edicts and Daijokanbu (official documents issued by Daijokan, the Grand Council of State) during the 39 years from 869 until 907, while its contents were classified by ministry.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Succeeding Jogankyaku, Engikyaku is a selected collection of particularly important volumes which had been in actual effect at the time of its compilation out of Jogankyaku, so chosen as to comprise imperial edicts and Daijokanbu (official documents issued by Daijokan, the Grand Council of State) during the 39 years from 869 until 907, while its contents were classified by ministry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>編纂者を直接示す記録は無いが、臨時格を追加したときに編纂に関与した人物として左大臣藤原時平が総裁を務め、藤原定国（大納言・右近衛大将）・三善清行（文章博士）・大蔵春行（民部大輔）・藤原善経（明法博士）が挙げられており、「延喜格」本文の編纂もほぼ同じ人員構成であったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there is no record directly identifying the compilers, the names of persons cited as having participated in the compilation of the extraordinary volumes include FUJIWARA no Tokihira, Sadaijin (minister of the left), serving as the editor-in-chief, FUJIWARA no Sadakuni (Dainagon or Chief Councilor of the State and Ukone no Taisho or the Chief of Ukonefu, (Guard Department)), Kiyotsura MIYOSHI, Monjo-hakase (teacher of Chinese poetry and history under the Ritsuryo system), Haruyuki OKURA (Minbutaifu,, executive officer of the Ministry of Popular Affairs) and FUJIWARA no Yoshitsune, (Myoho-hakase, teacher of the law under the Ritsuryo system), and the compiling staff of the main volumes of Engikyaku is assumed to have consisted of substantially the same persons.</e>
<cmt>近衛は、この文脈では「こんえ」と読むようです（広辞苑）。清行：広辞苑では「きよつら」。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there is no record directly identifying the compilers, the names of persons cited as having participated in the compilation of the extraordinary volumes include FUJIWARA no Tokihira, Sadaijin (minister of the left), serving as the editor-in-chief, FUJIWARA no Sadakuni (Dainagon or Chief Councilor of the State and Ukone no Taisho or the Chief of Ukonefu, (Guard Department)), Kiyotsura MIYOSHI, Monjo-hakase (teacher of Chinese poetry and history under the Ritsuryo system), Haruyuki OKURA (Minbutaifu,, executive officer of the Ministry of Popular Affairs) and FUJIWARA no Yoshitsune, (Myoho-hakase, teacher of the law under the Ritsuryo system), and the staff which compiled the main volumes of Engikyaku are assumed to have consisted mainly of the same persons.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there is no record directly identifying the compilers, the names of persons cited as having participated in the compilation of the extraordinary volumes include FUJIWARA no Tokihira, Sadaijin (minister of the left), serving as the editor-in-chief, FUJIWARA no Sadakuni (Dainagon (chief councilor of state) and Ukone no Taisho or the Chief of Ukonefu, (Guard Department)), Kiyotsura MIYOSHI, Monjo-hakase (teacher of Chinese poetry and history under the Ritsuryo system), Haruyuki OKURA (Minbutaifu, executive officer of the Ministry of Popular Affairs) and FUJIWARA no Yoshitsune, (Myoho-hakase, teacher of the law under the Ritsuryo system), and the staff which compiled the main volumes of Engikyaku are assumed to have consisted mainly of the same persons.</e>
<cmt>コンマ削除&quot;Dainagon or Chief Councilor of the State&quot;→&quot;Dainagon (chief councilor of state)&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>編纂に当たっては「弘仁格」・貞観格に既出のもの、編纂当時に廃止されていたものは掲載せず、文章が長すぎるものは削り、以前の格で内容が不十分あるいは不明確であったものは書き加え、更に一部が使われていない場合には該当部分を削除するなどの修正が施されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In compiling the new collection, such corrections were made as excluding items already taken up in Koninkyaku or Jogyankyaku and those already abolished at the time of compilation, shortening too long sentences, supplementing insufficient or unclear statements in any earlier Kyaku and, where some rules were partially out of use, clearing the pertinent rules of those unused parts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In compiling the new collection, such corrections were made as excluding items already taken up in Koninkyaku or Jogyankyaku and those already abolished at the time of compilation, shortening too long sentences, supplementing insufficient or unclear statements in any earlier Kyaku and, where some rules were partially out of use, clearing the pertinent rules of those unused parts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In compiling the new collection, such corrections were made as excluding items already taken up in Koninkyaku or Jogyankyaku and those already abolished at the time of compilation, shortening too long sentences, supplementing insufficient or unclear statements in any earlier Kyaku and, where some rules were partially out of use, clearing the pertinent rules of those unused parts.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>「延喜格」の原文は残されていないが、『類聚三代格』や惟宗允亮の『政事要略』にその多くが引用されており、その相当部分の内容を窺い知る事が出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the original text of Engikyaku is lost, many of its passages are quoted in Ruiju Sandaikyaku (a statute book written in the Heian Period) and Seiji Yoryaku (examples of political affairs in the Heian Period) written by KOREMUNE no Tadasuke to enable present-day students to guess substantial contents of the text.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the original text of Engikyaku is lost, many of its passages are quoted in Ruiju Sandaikyaku (a statute book written in the Heian Period) and Seiji Yoryaku (examples of political affairs in the Heian Period) written by KOREMUNE no Tadasuke to enable present-day students to guess substantial contents of the text.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the original text of Engikyaku is lost, many of its passages are quoted in &quot;Ruiju Sandaikyaku&quot; (a statute book written in the Heian period) and &quot;Seiji Yoryaku&quot; (examples of political affairs in the Heian period) written by KOREMUNE no Tadasuke to enable present-day students to guess substantial contents of the text.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>巻次構成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Allocation of Contents to Individual Volumes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Allocation of Contents to Individual Volumes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Allocation of Contents to Individual Volumes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>巻一 神祇官・中務省</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 1: Department of Worship and Ministry of Central Affairs</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 1: Department of Worship and Ministry of Central Affairs</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 1: Department of Worship and Ministry of Central Affairs</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>巻二・巻三 式部省</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volumes 2 and 3: Ministry of Ceremonies</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volumes 2 and 3: Ministry of Ceremonies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volumes 2 and 3: Ministry of Ceremonies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>巻四・巻五 治部省</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volumes 4 and 5: Ministry of Civil Administration</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volumes 4 and 5: Ministry of Civil Administration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volumes 4 and 5: Ministry of Civil Administration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>巻六・巻七 民部省</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volumes 6 and 7: Ministry of Popular Affairs</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volumes 6 and 7: Ministry of Popular Affairs</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volumes 6 and 7: Ministry of Popular Affairs</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>巻八 兵部省</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 8: Ministry of Military Affairs</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 8: Ministry of Military Affairs</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 8: Ministry of Military Affairs</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>巻九 刑部省・大蔵省・宮内省・弾正台・京職</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 9: Ministry of Justice, Ministry of Finance, Imperial Household Department, Imperial Prosecuting and Investigating Office and Kyoshoku (Administrative Agency of Kyoto)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 9: Ministry of Justice, Ministry of Finance, Imperial Household Department, Imperial Prosecuting and Investigating Office and Kyoshoku (Administrative Agency of Kyoto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 9: Ministry of Justice, Ministry of Finance, Imperial Household Department, Imperial Prosecuting and Investigating Office and Kyoshoku (Administrative Agency of Kyoto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>巻十 雑格（その他）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 10: Zakkyaku (Miscellaneous)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 10: Zakkyaku (Miscellaneous)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 10: Zakkyaku (Miscellaneous)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>巻十一・巻十二 臨時格（追加分）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volumes 11 and 12: Rinjikyaku (Extraordinary Volumes) (Supplements)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volumes 11 and 12: Rinjikyaku (Extraordinary Volumes) (Supplements)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volumes 11 and 12: Rinjikyaku (Extraordinary Volumes) (Supplements)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 踏蹟(id:51201), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>