<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>田堵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tato (田堵)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tato (田堵)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tato</e>
<cmt>漢字削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>田堵（たと）は、日本の平安時代に荘園・国衙領の田地経営をおこなった有力百姓層である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tato means wealthy farmer class who managed rice fields belonged to shoen (manor) or kokugaryo (rice fields governed by provincial government office) in Japan&apos;s Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tato means the wealthy farmer class that managed rice fields belonging to shoen (manor) or kokugaryo (rice fields governed by provincial government office) during Japan&apos;s Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tato means the wealthy farmer class that managed rice fields belonging to shoen (manor) or kokugaryo (rice fields governed by provincial government office) during Japan&apos;s Heian period.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>田刀、田頭とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tato (田堵) is also written in Chainese character as &quot;田刀&quot; or &quot;田頭&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tato (田堵) is also written in Chinese characters as &quot;田刀&quot; or &quot;田頭&quot;.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tato (田堵) is also written in Chinese characters as &quot;田刀&quot; or &quot;田頭.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>貞観_(日本)元年（895年）12月付の元興寺領近江国愛智荘（えちのしょう）の検田帳に「田刀」とあるのが初見である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;田刀&quot; first appeared in kenden-cho (note of Cadastral Surveys) of Echinosho, Omi Province owned by Ganko-ji Temple, as of December 895.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;田刀&quot; first appeared in kenden-cho (note of Cadastral Surveys) of Echinosho, Omi Province owned by Ganko-ji Temple, as of December 895.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &apos;田刀&apos; first appeared in kenden-cho (note of Cadastral Surveys) of Echinosho, Omi Province owned by Ganko-ji Temple, as of December 895.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>田堵の堵は、垣を意味する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A chinese character &quot;堵&quot; included in &quot;田堵&quot; means a fence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The chinese character &quot;堵&quot; included in &quot;田堵&quot; means a fence.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Chinese character &quot;堵&quot; included in &quot;田堵&quot; means a fence.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>9世紀～10世紀ごろに律令制の解体が進展していくと、百姓の中に他から田地を借りて耕作し、富を蓄積する富豪層が出現した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on ritsuryo code) began to dissolve around the 9th-10th century, some farmers amassed wealth by cultivating rice fields which they rented from others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on ritsuryo code) began to dissolve around the ninth-tenth century, some farmers amassed wealth by cultivating rice fields which they rented from others.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on ritsuryo code) began to dissolve around the ninth-tenth century, some farmers amassed wealth by cultivating rice fields which they rented from others.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>これが田堵である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These people were called Tato.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These people were called Tato.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These people were called Tato.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>田堵には、古来の郡司一族に出自する在地豪族や、土着国司などの退官した律令官人を出自とする者が多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of Tato were local powerful clans, who were the descendants of Gunji (local magistrate) in the ancient times, or ex-officials such as native provisional governors.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many Tato were local powerful clans, who were the descendants of Gunji (local magistrate) during ancient times, or ex-officials such as native provisional governors.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many Tato were local powerful clans, who were the descendants of Gunji (local magistrate) during ancient times, or ex-officials such as native provisional governors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>彼らは、蓄積した富をもって、墾田開発・田地経営などの営田活動を進めたり、他の百姓への出挙を行ったりして、より一層、富を集積し、一般の零細な百姓層を隷属化して成長していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With amassed wealth in hand, they further accumulated wealth by developing and managing additional lands or subjecting other petty farmers by lending rice seeds to them.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With amassed wealth in hand, they further accumulated wealth by developing and managing additional land or subjected other petty farmers by lending rice seeds to them.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With amassed wealth in hand, they further accumulated wealth by developing and managing additional land or subjected other petty farmers by lending rice seeds to them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>そして、まず国衙領において、公田から名田への再編成が行われると、田堵が名田経営を請け負う主体に位置づけられるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, when koden (rice fields administered directly by a ruler) located in kokugaryo was reorganized into myoden (rice fields owned by a nominal holder), Tato became the persons who undertook the management of myoden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, when koden (rice fields administered directly by a ruler) located in kokugaryo was reorganized into myoden (rice fields owned by a nominal holder), Tato became the persons who undertook the management of myoden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, when koden (rice fields administered directly by a ruler) located in kokugaryo was reorganized into myoden (rice fields owned by a nominal holder), Tato became the persons who undertook the management of myoden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>さらに、荘園にも名田化が波及すると、荘園内の名田経営も田堵が請け負うようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, when the movement of reorganization into myoden reached to shoen, Tato undertook the management of myoden located inside shoen as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, when reorganization into myoden reached shoen, Tato undertook the management of myoden located inside shoen as well.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, when reorganization into myoden reached shoen, Tato undertook the management of myoden located inside shoen as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>こうして田堵は、荘園・公領経営に深く携わるようになっていき、荘官や名主の地位を得るのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, Tato were deeply engaged in the management of shoen/koryo (public land) and eventually gained the status of shokan (an officer governing shoen) or myoshu (owner of rice fields).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, Tato were deeply engaged in the management of shoen/koryo (public land) and eventually gained the status of shokan (an officer governing shoen) or myoshu (owner of rice fields).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, Tato were deeply engaged in the management of shoen/koryo (public land) and eventually gained the status of shokan (an officer governing shoen) or myoshu (owner of rice fields).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>田堵は、荘園公領制の成立に非常に大きな役割を果たしたといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It may be said that Tato played a big role in the process of establishing shoen koryo sei (The system of Public Land and Private Estates).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It may be said that Tato played a large role in the process of establishing shoen koryo sei (The system of Public Land and Private Estates).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It may be said that Tato played a large role in the process of establishing shoen koryo sei (The system of Public Land and Private Estates).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>田堵は、その経営規模によって、大名田堵（だいみょうたと）や小名田堵（しょうみょうたと）などと呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Depending on the scale of land under their management, they were called either Daimyo Tato or Shomyo Tato.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Depending upon the scale of land under their management, they were called either Daimyo Tato or Shomyo Tato.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Depending upon the scale of land under their management, they were called either Daimyo Tato or Shomyo Tato.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>11世紀に成立した『新猿楽記』という世相を映し出した書物には、以下の内容の記載があり、田堵の実情をよく知ることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">We can learn the reality of Tato from the following descriptions included in &quot;Shinsarugakuki&quot;, a book written in the 11th century which reflected the social conditions at the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">We can learn the reality of Tato from the following descriptions included in the &quot;Shinsarugakuki,&quot; a book written in the eleventh century reflecting the social conditions at the time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">We can learn the reality of Tato from the following descriptions included in the &quot;Shinsarugakuki,&quot; a book written in the eleventh century reflecting the social conditions at the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>「出羽権介の田中豊益は、農業経営を専門とし、数町の田地を経営する大名田堵である。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Dewa gon no suke (Deputy governor of Dewa Province) Toyomasu TANAKA is a specialist of agricultural management and at the same time, he is Daimyo Tato who manages several hectares of rice field.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Dewa gon no suke (Deputy governor of Dewa Province) Toyomasu TANAKA is a specialist in agricultural management and at the same time, he is Daimyo Tato who manages several hectares of rice fields.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dewa gon no suke (Deputy governor of Dewa Province) Toyomasu TANAKA is a specialist in agricultural management and at the same time, he is Daimyo Tato who manages several hectares of rice fields.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>「ひでりに備えて、農具や用水の整備にいそしんで農民の育成にあたり、種播期には農民の作業をうまく指揮する。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He nurtures farmers while preparing for drought by maintaining farming tools and irrigation channels and leads farmers well at the time of their sowing seeds&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He nurtures farmers while preparing for drought by maintaining farming tools and irrigation channels and leads farmers well when it&apos;s time to sow their seeds&quot;.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He nurtures farmers while preparing for drought by maintaining farming tools and irrigation channels and leads farmers well when it&apos;s time to sow their seeds.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 S kitahashi(id:10307), Shimoxx(id:9332), Straysheep(id:42448), 春秋君(id:174988), ウミユスリカ(id:9504), 水野白楓(id:22811), UMBRO(id:100484), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>