<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>安政の大獄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ansei no Taigoku (suppression of extremists by the Shogunate)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ansei no Taigoku (suppression of extremists by the Shogunate)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ansei no Taigoku (suppression of extremists by the Shogunate)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>安政の大獄（あんせいのたいごく）とは、安政5年（1858年）から翌年にかけて江戸幕府が行なった弾圧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ansei no Taigoku was an oppression conducted by the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) between 1858 and 1859.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ansei no Taigoku was an act of suppression conducted by the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) between 1858 and 1859.</e>
<cmt>oppression&gt;act of suppression</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ansei no Taigoku was an act of suppression conducted by the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) between 1858 and 1859.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>幕府の大老井伊直弼や老中間部詮勝らは、勅許を得ないまま日米修好通商条約に調印し、また徳川家茂を将軍継嗣に決定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tairo (chief minister), Naosuke II and roju (member of shogun&apos;s council of elders), Akikatsu MANABE signed the Treaty of Amity and Commerce between the United States and Japan without obtaining Imperial sanction and decided to put forward Iemochi TOKUGAWA as a Shogun successor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tairo (chief minister), Naosuke II and roju (member of shogun&apos;s council of elders), Akikatsu MANABE signed the Treaty of Amity and Commerce between the United States and Japan without obtaining Imperial sanction and decided to put forward Iemochi TOKUGAWA as successor to the Shogun.</e>
<cmt>tairo&gt;the tairo. shogun successor&gt;successor to the shogun</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tairo (chief minister), Naosuke II and roju (member of shogun&apos;s council of elders), Akikatsu MANABE signed the Treaty of Amity and Commerce between the United States and Japan without obtaining Imperial sanction and decided to put forward Iemochi TOKUGAWA as successor to the Shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>安政の大獄とは、これらの諸策に反対する者たちを弾圧した事件である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ansei no Taigoku was the oppression of people who were against such policies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ansei no Taigoku was the oppression of people who were against such policies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ansei no Taigoku was the oppression of people who were against such policies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>弾圧されたのは尊皇攘夷や一橋派の大名・公卿・志士（活動家）らで、連座した者は100人以上にのぼった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">More than 100 people, including daimyos (Japanese feudal lords), Kugyo (high court nobles) and patriots supporting Sonno Joi (slogan advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners) and Hitotsubashi group (group supporting Yoshinobu from the Hitotsubashi-Tokugawa family), were implicated by Ansei no Taigoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">More than 100 people, including daimyos (Japanese feudal lords), Kugyo (high court nobles), patriots supporting Sonno Joi (slogan advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners) and the Hitotsubashi group (group supporting Yoshinobu from the Hitotsubashi-Tokugawa family), were implicated in Ansei no Taigoku.</e>
<cmt>implicated by&gt;implicated in</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">More than 100 people, including daimyos (Japanese feudal lords), Kugyo (high court nobles), patriots supporting Sonno Joi (slogan advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners) and the Hitotsubashi group (group supporting Yoshinobu from the Hitotsubashi-Tokugawa family), were implicated in Ansei no Taigoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>なお、形としては第13代将軍・徳川家定が「台命」（たいめい＝将軍の命令）を発して本項で述べる全ての処罰を行なったことになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a formality, the 13th Shogun, Iesada TOKUGAWA issued Taimei (order from Shogun) and carried out all punishments described in this section.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a formality, the 13th Shogun, Iesada TOKUGAWA issued a Taimei (Shogunal order) and carried out the punishments described below.</e>
<cmt>order from shougn&gt;shogunal order. in this section&gt;below</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a formality, the 13th Shogun, Iesada TOKUGAWA issued a Taimei (Shogunal order) and carried out the punishments described below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>そうでもしなければ譜代大名に過ぎない井伊直弼が自分の目上に当たる朝廷・徳川一門を処罰することはできなかったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otherwise, Naosuke II, the only fudai daimyo (a daimyo as a hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family), could not punish his superiors like the Imperial Court and the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Had Iesada not done so, Naosuke II, the only fudai daimyo (a daimyo as a hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family), would have been unable to punish his superiors, such as the Imperial Court and the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>other&gt;had iesada not done so. could not&gt;would ahve been unable to</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Had Iesada not done so, Naosuke II, the only fudai daimyo (a daimyo as a hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family), would have been unable to punish his superiors, such as the Imperial Court and the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経緯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>江戸時代後期の日本には外国船が相次いで来航した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the late Edo period, many foreign ships arrived in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the late Edo period, many foreign ships arrived in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the late Edo period, many foreign ships arrived in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>中国がアヘン戦争に敗北すると日本国内でも対外的危機意識が高まり、幕閣では海防問題が議論される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After China lost the Opium War, foreign risk awareness increased in Japan and the cabinet officials of the Shogunate discussed the coastal defense issue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After China lost the Opium War, the awareness of foreign risk rose in Japan and cabinet officials of the Shogunate discussed the issue of coastal defense.</e>
<cmt>risk awareness&gt;awareness of risk. defense issue&gt;issue of defense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After China lost the Opium War, the awareness of foreign risk rose in Japan and cabinet officials of the Shogunate discussed the issue of coastal defense.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>老中・阿部正弘が幕政改革を行ない、1854年にアメリカ合衆国と日米和親条約を、ロシアとは日露和親条約を締結した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Roju, Masahiro Abe carried out the reformation of the shogunate government and entered into the treaty between the United States of America and the Empire of Japan with USA and the treaty between the Russian Empire and the Empire of Japan with Russia in 1854.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Roju Masahiro Abe carried out the reformation of the shogunate government and entered into the America-Japan Treaty of Amity and Friendship and a treaty between the Russian Empire and the Empire of Japan in 1854.</e>
<cmt>roju,&gt;the roju. America-Japan Treaty of Amity and Friendship http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Convention_of_Kanagawa</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Roju Masahiro ABE carried out the reformation of the shogunate government and entered into the America-Japan Treaty of Amity and Friendship and a treaty between the Russian Empire and the Empire of Japan in 1854.</e>
<cmt>ABE大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>嘉永6年（1853年）に第12代将軍徳川家慶が死去し、第13代将軍に家慶の四男・徳川家定が就任するが、病弱で男子を儲ける見込みが無かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1853, the 12th shogun, Ieyoshi TOKUGAWA died and the fourth son of Ieyoshi, Iesada TOKUGAWA ascended to be the 13th Shogun, but Iesada was in poor health and had no hope to have a son.</e>
<cmt>一原文一翻訳の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1853, the 12th shogun, Ieyoshi TOKUGAWA died and his fourth son, Iesada TOKUGAWA ascended to be the 13th Shogun, but was in poor health and had no hope to have a son.</e>
<cmt>the fourth son of Ieyoshi&gt;his fourth son.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1853, the 12th shogun, Ieyoshi TOKUGAWA died and his fourth son, Iesada TOKUGAWA ascended to be the 13th Shogun, but was in poor health and had no hope to have a son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>このため将軍継嗣問題が起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This caused the Shogun successor issue.</e>
<cmt>一原文一翻訳の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This have rise the Shogun successor crisis.</e>
<cmt>caused&gt;gave rise. issue&gt;crisis</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This have rise the Shogun successor crisis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>前水戸藩主徳川斉昭の七男・一橋慶喜は英明との評判が高く、これを支持し諸藩との協調体制を望む一橋派と、血統を重視し、現将軍に血筋の近い紀州藩主徳川慶福（後の徳川家茂）を推す保守路線の南紀派とに分裂し、激しく対立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The successor issue divided the domains in two; one was the Hitotsubashi family supporting the seventh son of Nariaki TOGUKAWA, previous lord of the Mito Domain, Yoshinobu HITOTSUBASHI with great a reputation for intelligence, and the other was Nanki group, conservative and regarding blood line as important and supporting Yoshitomi TOKUGAWA (later Iemochi TOKUGAWA), the lord of the Kishuu domain, who had a close genealogy with the current Shogun, and the two groups were in fierce conflict with each other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The successor issue divided the domains into two factions in fierce conflict with each other; one was the Hitotsubashi family supporting the seventh son of Nariaki TOGUKAWA, Yoshinobu HITOTSUBASHI, the previous lord of Mito Domain with great a reputation for intelligence.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The successor issue divided the domains into two factions in fierce conflict with each other: One was the Hitotsubashi family supporting Yoshinobu HITOTSUBASHI who had a great reputation for intelligence and was the seventh son of Nariaki TOGUKAWA, the previous lord of Mito Domain; and the other was the conservative Nanki group supporting Yoshitomi TOKUGAWA (later Iemochi TOKUGAWA) who had a close genealogy with the current Shogun and was the lord of the Kishu Domain because of regarding blood line as important.</e>
<cmt>分割不可と考え、一文に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>この頃、米国総領事タウンゼント・ハリスが通商条約・調印を幕府に迫っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, Townsend HARRIS, the council general of USA urged the Japanese government to enter into the Treaty of Amity and Commerce.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, Townsend HARRIS, the USA council general, urged the Japanese government to enter into the Treaty of Amity and Commerce.</e>
<cmt>council general of USA&gt;USA council general</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, Townsend HARRIS, the USA council general, urged the Japanese government to enter into the Treaty of Amity and Commerce.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>老中・堀田正睦は朝廷の権威を借りて事態の打開を図ろうとしたが、梅田雲浜ら在京の尊攘派の工作もあり、孝明天皇から勅許を得ることは出来なかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Roju, Masayoshi HOTTA tried to break the deadlock by using his authority in the Imperial court, he could not obtain Imperial sanctions from Emperor Komei since a member of the sonjo party (royalists), Unpin UMEDA and other members stayed in Kyoto prevented it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the Roju Masayoshi HOTTA tried to break the deadlock by using his authority in the Imperial court, he could not obtain Imperial sanctions from Emperor Komei since members of the sonjo (royalist) party in Kyoto including Unpin UMEDA prevented it.</e>
<cmt>a member and other members&gt;members. staying in Kyoto &gt;in Kyoto</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the Roju Masayoshi HOTTA tried to break the deadlock by using his authority in the Imperial Court, he could not obtain Imperial sanctions from Emperor Komei since members of the sonjo (royalist) party in Kyoto including Unpin UMEDA prevented it.</e>
<cmt>Court大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>安政5年（1858年）4月、南紀派の井伊が大老に就任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April, 1858, Ii in the Nanki group became Tairo (chief minister).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April, 1858, Ii from the Nanki group became Tairo (chief minister).</e>
<cmt>in&gt;from</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April, 1858, Ii from the Nanki group became Tairo (chief minister).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>井伊は無勅許の条約調印と、家茂の将軍継嗣指名を断行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ii signed the Treaty without Imperial sanction and appointed Iemochi as the heir to the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ii signed the Treaty without Imperial sanction and appointed Iemochi as the heir to the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ii signed the Treaty without Imperial sanction and appointed Iemochi as the heir to the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>水戸老公徳川斉昭は、一旦は謹慎していたものの復帰、藩政を指揮して水戸藩主徳川慶篤（斉昭の長男）を動かし、尾張藩主徳川慶勝、福井藩主松平慶永らと連合した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Roko (polite address for elderly nobleman) in Mito domain, Nariaki TOKUGAWA retired once, but retuned to the administration of the domain and motivated Yoshiatsu TOKUGAWA (the first son of Nariaki), the lord of Owari domain to unite Yoshikatsu TOKUGAWA, the lord of Owari domain and Yoshinaga MATSUDAIRA, the lord of Fukui domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An elderly nobleman of Mito domain, Nariaki TOKUGAWA had previously retired, but retuned to domain administration and pushed the Mito lord Yoshiatsu TOKUGAWA (the first son of Nariaki), to unite Lords Yoshikatsu TOKUGAWA of Owari domain and Yoshinaga MATSUDAIRA of Fukui domain.</e>
<cmt>本文によると、徳川慶篤は水戸藩主であるそうですので、the Mito lord Yoshiatsu TOKUGAWAに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An elderly nobleman of Mito Domain, Nariaki TOKUGAWA had previously retired, but retuned to domain administration and pushed the Mito lord Yoshiatsu TOKUGAWA (the first son of Nariaki), to unite Lords Yoshikatsu TOKUGAWA of Owari Domain and Yoshinaga MATSUDAIRA of Fukui Domain.</e>
<cmt>Domain大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>彼らは条約調印は止むを得ないが、「違勅調印」を不敬だとして、井伊を詰問するために不時登城（定式登城日以外の登城）した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They insisted that they had to sign the Treaty, but as signing it without Imperial sanction would be a great impropriety towards the imperial family, they went to the castle in an untimely fashion (go to the castle on undesignated date) in order to question Ii closely.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They realised there was no choice but to sign the Treaty, however as signing it without Imperial sanction would be a great impropriety towards the Imperial family, they made an unscheduled visit to the castle (dates for visiting normally had to be designated) in order to consult with Ii.</e>
<cmt>insisted they had to&gt;realised there was no choice but to. in an untimely fashion&gt;unscheduled. undesigned date&gt;dates for visiting normally had to be designated</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They realized there was no choice but to sign the Treaty, however as signing it without Imperial sanction would be a great impropriety towards the Imperial family, they made an unscheduled visit to the castle (dates for visiting normally had to be designated) in order to consult with Ii.</e>
<cmt>realizedスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>井伊は不時登城を理由に、彼らを隠居謹慎などに処した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ii removed them from headships of their families and suspended them from office because of their appearance in the castle on an undesignated date.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ii removed them from their positions as heads of their families and suspended them from office because of their appearance in the castle on an undesignated date.</e>
<cmt>headships&gt;their positions as heads</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ii removed them from their positions as heads of their families and suspended them from office because of their appearance in the castle on an undesignated date.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="20">
<j>薩摩藩主の島津斉彬は井伊に反発し、藩兵5千を率いて上洛することを計画したが、同年7月に鹿児島で急死したため出兵計画は頓挫する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Nariakira SHIMAZU, the lord of Satsuma domain offended Ii and planned to march on the capital with 5,000 domain soldiers, he died suddenly in July on that year,.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Nariakira SHIMAZU, the lord of Satsuma domain opposed Ii and planned to march on the capital with 5,000 domain soldiers, he died suddenly in July on that year.</e>
<cmt>offended&gt;opposed</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Nariakira SHIMAZU, the lord of Satsuma Domain opposed Ii and planned to march on the capital with 5,000 domain soldiers, he died suddenly in July on that year.</e>
<cmt>Domain大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>斉彬死後の薩摩藩の実権は、御家騒動で斉彬と対立して隠居させられた島津斉興が掌握した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Nariakira, Narioki SHIMAZU who had been forced to retire due to conflict over family troubles with Nariakira, held power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Nariakira, Narioki SHIMAZU who had been forced to retire due to conflict with Nariakira over family issues, seized power.</e>
<cmt>troubles&gt;issues. held.seized</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Nariakira, Narioki SHIMAZU who had been forced to retire due to conflict with Nariakira over family issues, seized power.</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>1859年8月には朝廷工作を行なっていた水戸藩らに対して戊午の密勅が下され、ほぼ同じ時期、幕府側の同調者であった関白・九条尚忠が辞職に追い込まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August, 1859, the government gave a secret imperial decree to the Mito domain who carried out covert action against the Imperial court, and the chief adviser to the Emperor, Hisataka KUJO who was an associate of the government side was forced to resign his position about the same time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August, 1859, the government gave a secret Imperial decree to Mito domain (who had been carrying out covert action against the Imperial court), and at roughly the same time the chief adviser to the Emperor, Hisataka KUJO who was a government sympathiser was forced to resign his position.</e>
<cmt>associate&gt;sympthasiser</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August, 1859, the government gave a secret Imperial decree to Mito Domain (who had been carrying out covert action against the Imperial Court), and at roughly the same time the chief adviser to the Emperor, Hisataka KUJO who was a government sympathizer was forced to resign his position.</e>
<cmt>sympathizerスペル訂正しました。Domain大文字にしました。Court大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>このため9月に老中間部詮勝、京都所司代酒井忠義 (若狭国小浜藩主)らが上洛し、近藤茂左衛門、梅田雲浜らを逮捕したことを皮切りに激しい弾圧が始まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Roju, Akikatsu MANABE and Kyoto shoshidai (The Kyoto deputy), Tadaaki SAKAI (the lord of Obama domain of Wakasa province) went to Kyoto and arrested Mosaemon KONDO and Unpin UMEDA, this was the beginning of vigorous oppression.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Roju Akikatsu MANABE and Kyoto deputy Tadaaki SAKAI (who was also the lord of Obama domain of Wakasa province) went to Kyoto and arrested Mosaemon KONDO and Unpin UMEDA, heralding the start of intense oppression.</e>
<cmt>who was alsoを入れ、this was the beginning&gt;heralding the start. vigorous&gt;intense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Roju Akikatsu MANABE and Kyoto deputy Tadaaki SAKAI (who was also the lord of Obama Domain of Wakasa Province) went to Kyoto and arrested Mozaemon KONDO and Unpin UMEDA, heralding the start of intense oppression.</e>
<cmt>Domain、Province大文字にしました。近藤茂左衛門→Mozaemon KONDO</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="24">
<j>京都で捕縛された志士たちは江戸に送致され、江戸伝馬町の獄などで詮議を受けた後、切腹・死罪など酷刑に処せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Royalists arrested in Kyoto were sent to Edo, questioned in prisons in Edo Denmacho town and sentenced to severe punishments like Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) and capital punishment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Royalists arrested in Kyoto were sent to Edo, questioned in prisons in Edo&apos;s Denmacho quarter and sentenced to severe punishments like Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) and capital punishment.</e>
<cmt>edo denmacho town&gt; edo&apos;s denmacho quarter.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Royalists arrested in Kyoto were sent to Edo, questioned in prisons in Denma-cho, Edo and sentenced to severe punishments like Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) and capital punishment.</e>
<cmt>in Denma-cho, Edo　に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>幕閣でも川路聖謨や岩瀬忠震らの非門閥の開明派幕臣が処罰され、謹慎などの処分となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the cabinet officials of the Shogunate, Toshiakira KAWAJI and Tadanari IWASE, shogun&apos;s retainer from poor lineage in Kaimei group were subject to punishment such as being confined at home.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even Shogunate cabinet officials Toshiakira KAWAJI and Tadanari IWASE, Kaimei group shogunal retainers of poor lineage, were subject to punishment such as house arrest.</e>
<cmt>開明派＞定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even Shogunate cabinet officials Toshiakira KAWAJI and Tadanari IWASE, Kaimei group shogunal retainers of poor lineage, were subject to punishment such as house arrest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>この際、寛典論を退けて厳刑に処すことを決したのは井伊直弼と言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Naosuke II dismissed lenient treatment and decided to severely punish any opponents at this time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Naosuke II dismissed the very concept of lenient treatment and decided to severely punish any opponents at this time.</e>
<cmt>lenient treatment&gt;the very concept of lenient treatment</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Naosuke II dismissed the very concept of lenient treatment and decided to severely punish any opponents at this time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="27">
<j>安政7年（1860年）3月3日、桜田門外の変において井伊が殺害された後、弾圧は収束する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Ii was murdered at the Sakuradamongai Incident on March 3, 1860, the oppression was concluded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Ii&apos;s murder during the Sakuradamongai Incident on March 3, 1860, the oppression ceased.</e>
<cmt>was murdered&gt;&apos;s murder. at&gt;during. was concluded&gt;ceased.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Ii&apos;s murder during the Sakuradamongai Incident on March 3, 1860, the oppression ceased.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="28">
<j>文久2年（1862年）5月　勅命により、一橋慶喜が将軍後見職に、松平春嶽が政事総裁職に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May, 1862, Yoshinobu HITOTSUBASHI assumed Shogun-kokenshoku (one of three major posts of Edo bakufu), and Shungaku MATSUDAIRA assumed the president of political affairs in accordance with an Imperial order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In accordance with an Imperial order in May, 1862, Yoshinobu HITOTSUBASHI assumed the role of Shogun-kokenshoku (one of three major posts of Edo bakufu), and Shungaku MATSUDAIRA became president of political affairs.</e>
<cmt>順番を変え、assumed&gt;assumed the role. assumed&gt;became</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In accordance with an Imperial order in May, 1862, Yoshinobu HITOTSUBASHI assumed the role of Shogun-kokenshoku (one of three major posts of Edo bakufu), and Shungaku MATSUDAIRA became president of political affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="29">
<j>慶喜と春嶽は井伊直弼が行なった大獄は甚だ専断であったとして下記を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshinobu and Shungaku ordered the following since suppression by Naosuke Ii was extreme at his own discretion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshinobu and Shungaku criticised Naosuke Ii&apos;s suppression as an extreme, arbitrary display of power, and ordered the following:</e>
<cmt>順番を変え、at his own discretion&gt;arbitrary display of power</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshinobu and Shungaku criticised Naosuke Ii&apos;s suppression as an extreme, arbitrary display of power, and ordered the following:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>井伊家に対し10万石削減の追罰</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A reduction of 100,000 koku (a unit of volume: rice 1-koku is 180.39 liter, lumber 1-koku is 0.278 cubic meter) for the Ii family was an additional punishment,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As additional punishment fro the Ii family, a reduction of 100,000 koku (a unit of volume: 1 koku equals 180.39 litres of rice, or 0.278 cubic metres of lumber.)</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As additional punishment fro the Ii family, a reduction of 100,000 koku (a unit of volume: 1 koku equals 180.39 liters of rice, or 0.278 cubic meters of lumber.)</e>
<cmt>litersスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>弾圧の取調べをした者の処罰</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Punishment for investigators during the oppression,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Punishment for investigators during the oppression,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Punishment for investigators during the oppression</e>
<cmt>カンマを削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>大獄で幽閉されていた者の釈放</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Releasing people confined during the oppression,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The release of those confined during the oppression,</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The release of those confined during the oppression</e>
<cmt>カンマを削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>桜田門外の変・坂下門外の変における尊攘運動の遭難者を和宮降嫁の祝賀として大赦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The amnesty of Sonno Joi after the Sakuradamongai Incident and Sakashita mongai Incident for the celebration of Kazunomiya koka (the marriage of Kazunomiya Imperial princess to an ordinary person)</e>
<cmt>遭難者では意味が通らないと思いますので、推進者と訳出しました。下のセルに”行なった。”と一文がありましたが、本欄に追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An amnesty to be carried out for the victims who supported Sonno Joi during the Sakuradamongai and Sakashita mongai Incidents as part of the celebrations for Kazunomiya koka (the marriage of the Kazunomiya Imperial princess to an commoner.)</e>
<cmt>順番を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An amnesty to be carried out for the victims who supported Sonno Joi during the Sakuradamongai and Sakashita mongai Incidents as part of the celebrations for Kazunomiya koka (the marriage of the Kazunomiya Imperial princess to an commoner.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="34">
<j>幕閣では一橋派が復活し、文久の改革が行なわれ、将軍家茂と皇女・和宮の婚儀が成立して公武合体路線が進められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the cabinet official of the shogunate, the Hitotsubashi family came back into power, and Bunkyu Reform was carried out, Shogun Iemochi married with Imperial princess Kazunomiya, and reconciliation between the imperial court and the shogunate was advanced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the shogun&apos;s cabinet officials, the Hitotsubashi family came back into power, the Bunkyu Reform was carried out, Shogun Iemochi married the Imperial princess Kazunomiya, and a reconciliation between the imperial court took place.</e>
<cmt>in the &gt;as for the.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the shogun&apos;s cabinet officials, the Hitotsubashi family came back into power, the Bunkyu Reform was carried out, Shogun Iemochi married the Imperial princess Kazunomiya, and a reconciliation between the imperial court took place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="35">
<j>安政の大獄は幕府の規範意識の低下や人材の欠如を招き、反幕派による尊攘活動を激化させ、幕府滅亡の遠因ともなったとも言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ansei no Taigoku caused a decrease in morality, a shortfall in human resources in the shogunate and intensified Sonno activities by the anti shogunate group, and it is said these were underlying cause in the fall of the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ansei no Taigoku lead to a decrease in general awareness and a shortfall in human resources in the shogunate, plus intensified Sonno activities by the anti-shogunate group, and it is said these were underlying causes in the fall of the government.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ansei no Taigoku lead to a decrease in general awareness and a shortfall in human resources in the shogunate, plus intensified Sonno activities by the anti-shogunate group, and it is said these were underlying causes in the fall of the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 DCyokohama(id:26779), 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Higashi(id:8842), Trudi3194(id:283128), J-ishikawa(id:74471), Albambot(id:195288), Hat2867(id:67840), MelancholieBot(id:31942), Nonomura(id:72557), Extrahitz(id:26245), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Legs(id:15473), ShikiH(id:181574), Hatch(id:46448), 彩華1226(id:64711), Kurz(id:1601), パの字(id:34188), Jugger90(id:17088), A6M4(id:14155), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Boa(id:20845), 玄史生(id:43670), ヤマト(id:8425), Nobchim(id:21792), シャさん(id:43303), おきた(id:18906), Yas(id:739), Maakun(id:16735), Yosemite(id:5808), きまま(id:183217), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>