<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>類聚符宣抄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ruiju fusensho (a collection of official documents)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ruiju fusensho (a collection of official documents)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ruiju Fusensho</e>
<cmt>Ruiju Fusenshoとし、カッコ内の補足削除 (次文に説明あり)</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>類聚符宣抄（るいじゅうふせんしょう）は、天平9年（737年）から寛治7年（1093年）までの間の太政官符･宣旨･解状を、部目別に分類して編集した法令集である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ruiju fusensho is a collection of official documents where Daijokanpu (official documents issued by Daijokan, Grand Council of State), imperial decrees and gebumi (reports to upper-class persons) from 737 to 1093 were classified and compiled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ruiju fusensho is a collection of official documents where Daijokanpu (official documents issued by Daijokan, Grand Council of State), imperial decrees and gebumi (reports to upper-class persons) from 737 to 1093 were classified and compiled.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ruiju fusensho is a collection of official documents where Daijokanpu (official documents issued by Daijokan, Grand Council of State), imperial decrees and gebumi (reports to upper-class persons) from 737 to 1093 were classified and compiled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>別名『左丞抄』。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called &quot;Sajosho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>左丞抄：　読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called &quot;Sajosho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called &quot;Sajosho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>編者・成立年代について、平安時代末期の保安 (元号)2年（1121年）、3年に書写された最古の写本（現宮内庁書陵部所蔵）が、小槻氏に永く秘蔵されていたことから、小槻氏によって編纂され、本書収録の最も新しい年次の文書が寛治7年正月19日の宣旨であるため、寛治7年から保安2年までの間に成立したと従来考えられてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its oldest manuscript (now kept in Imperial Household Archives) copied in 1121 to 1122, towards the end of the Heian period, was kept secretly by the Ozuki clan for a long time, with the latest document included there concerned with an imperial decree issued on February, 1093, and therefore, it has been considered that the document was complete between 1093 and 1121.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its oldest manuscript (now kept in the Imperial Household Archives) copied in 1121 to 1122, towards the end of the Heian period, was kept secretly by the Ozuki clan for a long time, with the latest document included there concerned with an imperial decree issued on February, 1093, and therefore, it has been considered that the document was completed between 1093 and 1121.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its oldest manuscript (now kept in the Imperial Household Archives) copied in 1121 to 1122, towards the end of the Heian period, was kept secretly by the Ozuki clan for a long time, with the latest document included there concerned with an imperial decree issued on 23 February, 1093, and therefore, it has been considered that the document was completed between 1093 and 1121.</e>
<cmt>on February, 1093→on 23 February, 1093に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>しかし、本書の特徴・内容から、平安時代後期の実務官僚であった源経頼（宇多源氏）が、公務遂行の為に編まれたとする新説が提示された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, a new theory was proposed saying that MINAMOTO no Tsuneyori (Uda-Genji (Minamoto clan)), a governmental official responsible for practical works, compiled it for necessities for carrying out his official duties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, a new theory was proposed saying that MINAMOTO no Tsuneyori (Uda-Genji (Minamoto clan)), a governmental official responsible for practical works, compiled it for necessities for carrying out his official duties.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, a new theory was proposed saying that MINAMOTO no Tsuneyori (Uda-Genji (Minamoto clan)), a governmental official responsible for practical works, compiled it for necessities for carrying out his official duties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>この説の場合、本書の編纂は長暦3年（1039年）に経頼が歿したため、未完成のまま中断したとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to this theory, it is said that the compilation of this book was stopped before its completion, because Tsuneyori died in 1039.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to this theory, it is said that the compilation of this book was stopped before its completion, because Tsuneyori died in 1039.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to this theory, it is said that the compilation of this book was stopped before its completion, because Tsuneyori died in 1039.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>とすると、前記の如く、本書収録の最新年次の文書は寛治7年の宣旨であるため、長暦3年説を採用すると矛盾が生じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the latest document included there is an imperial decree issued on February, 1093, as described before, contradicting the theory that its compilation ended in 1039.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the latest document included there is an imperial decree issued on February, 1093, as described before, contradicting the theory that its compilation ended in 1039.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the latest document included there is an imperial decree issued in 1093, as described before, contradicting the theory that its compilation ended in 1039.</e>
<cmt>原文に基づき、on February, 1093→in 1093としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし、長暦3年から寛治7年の間の文書は、全て女院号についての文書16通であり、それらは、本書の最古の写本が成立した保安2年までに増補されたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this point, it is considered that, because all of the documents between 1039 and 1093 are concerned with nyoingo (a title of respect given to close female relatives of the Emperor or a woman of comparable standing), they were augmented later by 1121 when the latest manuscript was completed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this point, it is considered that, because all of the documents between 1039 and 1093 are concerned with nyoingo (a title of respect given to close female relatives of the Emperor or a woman of comparable standing), they were augmented later in 1121 when the latest manuscript was completed.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this point, it is considered that, because all of the documents between 1039 and 1093 are concerned with nyoingo (a title of respect given to close female relatives of the Emperor or a woman of comparable standing), they were augmented later in 1121 when the latest manuscript was completed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>なお、本書は新訂増補国史大系（吉川弘文館）第27巻に収録されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This book is recorded in vol. 27 of &quot;Shintei zoho kokushi taikei&quot; (Newly revised and enlarged survey of Japanese history) (published by Yoshikawa Kobunkan Inc.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This book is recorded in vol. 27 of &quot;Shintei zoho kokushi taikei&quot; (Newly revised and enlarged survey of Japanese history) (published by Yoshikawa Kobunkan Inc.).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This book is recorded in vol. 27 of Shintei Zoho Kokushi Taikei (Newly revised and enlarged survey of Japanese history) (published by Yoshikawa Kobunkan Inc.).</e>
<cmt>Shintei Zoho Kokushi Taikeiとし、原文表記に合わせクォーテーション削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Carkuni(id:79281), 伊集院聖(id:53199), 蘇民(id:87832), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>