<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>伝馬</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenma</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenma</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenma</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>伝馬（てんま）または伝馬制（- せい）とは、古代から近世までの日本に見られた使者や物資を馬で運ぶ交通制度、またはその馬。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A tenma refers to a transportation system from ancient times to the early modern times in Japan that carried envoys or goods, or to a horse used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A tenma refers to a transportation system from ancient times to the early modern times in Japan that carried envoys or goods, or to a horse used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A tenma refers to a transportation system from ancient times to the early modern times in Japan that carried envoys or goods, or to a horse used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>古代においては、7世紀後半頃に律令制の中央・地方間の情報伝達システムとして伝馬制が整備された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About in the latter half of the seventh century in ancient times, the tenma system was improved as a system of transmission of information between the capital and local regions in the ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">About in the latter half of the seventh century in ancient times, the tenma system was improved as a system of transmission of information between the capital and local regions in the ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">About in the latter half of the seventh century in ancient times, the tenma system was improved as a system of transmission of information between the capital and local regions in the ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>その後、おそらく10世紀以降に古代伝馬制は廃れたが、中世に至り荘園領主や地頭らが居住地と自領を結ぶ伝馬を置きはじめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequently, presumably from the tenth century on, the ancient tenma system went out of use, however, in the Middle Ages lords of manors and jito (agents in charge of manors of their lords) began to post tenma (post horses) that shuttled between their residences and own domains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, presumably from the tenth century on, the ancient tenma system went out of use, however, in the Middle Ages, lords of manors and jito (agents in charge of manors of their lords) began to post tenma (post horses) that shuttled between their residences and own domains.</e>
<cmt>読点を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, presumably from the tenth century on, the ancient tenma system went out of use, however, in the Middle Ages, lords of manors and jito (agents in charge of manors of their lords) began to post tenma (post horses) that shuttled between their residences and own domains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)には、戦国大名らが自領内の街道に宿場を設け、本城と支城などを連絡する伝馬を設置した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Warring States period (Japan) warring lords posted shukuba (post stations) along highways in their domains and tenma that shuttled between their main castles and branch castles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) (Japan), warring lords posted shukuba (post stations) along highways in their domains and tenma that shuttled between their main castles and branch castles.</e>
<cmt>読点を追加しました。用語集に従い、「戦国時代」の訳を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) (Japan), warring lords posted shukuba (post stations) along highways in their domains and tenma that shuttled between their main castles and branch castles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>近世に入ると、江戸幕府は諸街道を整備し、各宿場に伝馬を常設させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early Modern times the Edo bakufu improved highways across Japan and posted tenma at each shukuba.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early Modern times, the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) improved highways across Japan and posted tenma at each shukuba.</e>
<cmt>読点、「江戸幕府」の説明を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early Modern times, the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) improved highways across Japan and posted tenma at each shukuba.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>古代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ancient Times</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ancient Times</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ancient Times</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>古代律令制における交通制度は駅伝制と総称されるが、主に駅制、伝馬制、伝制の3システムに分けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Transportation systems under the ancient ritsuryo system were generally known as ekiden-sei (the transportation system of the ritsuryo system), classified mainly into three systems such as Eki-sei, Tenma-sei and Den-sei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Transportation systems under the ancient ritsuryo system were generally known as ekiden-sei and classified mainly into three systems: Eki-sei, Tenma-sei and Den-sei.</e>
<cmt>「駅伝制」について二重の説明になるため（　）内の説明を削除しました。またsuch asを：に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Transportation systems under the ancient ritsuryo system were generally known as ekiden-sei and classified mainly into three systems: Eki-sei, Tenma-sei and Den-sei.</e>
<cmt>スペース調整</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>駅制は中央と地方との間相互の緊急情報伝達を主眼としたシステムであり、そのため中央から地方へのびる幹線道路たる駅路と駅路沿いの駅家が整備され、情報伝達者は駅鈴を携帯し、駅家に各5 - 20匹置かれた駅馬を利用して駅路上を通行していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Eki-sei transportatin system being intended mainly for transmission of urgent information between the capital and local regions, ekiro (highways) from the capital and local regions and umaya (facilities for providing houses, foods, etc.) along ekiro were maintained, and informants, carrying an ekirei bell and using one of five to twenty ekiba (horses for transportation of official travellers) kept in an Umaya, passed through ekiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Eki-sei transportation system being intended mainly for transmission of urgent information between the capital and local regions, ekiro (highways) from the capital and local regions and umaya (facilities for providing houses, foods, etc.) along ekiro were maintained, and informants, carrying an ekirei bell and using one of five to twenty ekiba (horses for transportation of official travelers) kept in an Umaya, passed through ekiro.</e>
<cmt>スペルミスを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Eki-sei transportation system being intended mainly for transmission of urgent information between the capital and local regions, ekiro (highways) from the capital and local regions and umaya (facilities for providing houses, foods, etc.) along ekiro were maintained, and informants, carrying an ekirei bell and using one of five to twenty ekiba (horses for transportation of official travelers) kept in an Umaya, passed through ekiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>伝馬制は駅制と異なり、使者を中央から地方へ送迎することを主目的としていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike the Eki-sei system, the tenma system was intended mainly for envoys sent from the capital to local regions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike the Eki-sei system, the tenma system was mainly intended for envoys sent from the capital to local regions.</e>
<cmt>語順を一部修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike the Eki-sei system, the tenma system was mainly intended for envoys sent from the capital to local regions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>中央から地方へ派遣される使者は、伝符を携行し、郡家ごとに5匹ずつ置かれた伝馬を乗り継ぎ目的地へ到達した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A convoy sent from the capital to local regions, carrying a denpu (permit for using tenma) and changing tenma at each gunke (public office) that kept five tenma, reached his destination.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A envoy sent from the capital to local regions, carrying a denpu (permit for using tenma) and changing tenma at each gunke (public office) that kept five tenma, reached his destination.</e>
<cmt>語句に誤りがあったため、修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A envoy sent from the capital to local regions, carrying a denpu (permit for using tenma) and changing tenma at each gunke (public office) that kept five tenma, reached his destination.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>使者の位階に対応して使用可能な馬の数が決められていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Corresponding to his ikai (court rank), he could use a fixed number of tenma.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Corresponding to his ikai (court rank), he was able to use a fixed number of tenma.</e>
<cmt>文法の誤りを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Corresponding to his ikai (court rank), he was able to use a fixed number of tenma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>伝符に使者の位階を示す刻みがつけられ、それにより判別可能であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The denpu had a carving showing the rank of the envoy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The denpu had a carving showing the rank of the envoy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The denpu had a carving showing the rank of the envoy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>使者の宿泊や食糧などは、郡家が負担することとなっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Envoys&apos; lodgings and foods and so on were in charge of a gunke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Envoys&apos; lodgings, foods and so on were in charge of a gunke.</e>
<cmt>語彙の使用法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Envoys&apos; lodgings, foods and so on were in charge of a gunke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>伝馬制は当初、特命任務を帯びた使者を中央から地方へ派遣するための制度として想定されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, the tenma-sei system was presumed to have been a system to send an envoy with a special commission from the capital to local regions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, the tenma system was presumed to have been a system to send an envoy with a special commission from the capital to local regions.</e>
<cmt>用語がこの列以前の表記と異なっていたため、修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, the tenma system was presumed to have been a system to send an envoy with a special commission from the capital to local regions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>実際例としては、覓珠玉使、中宮職促稲使、検舶使、流人、流人部領使などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, magishugyoku-shi (envoy), chugushoku-sokuto-shi, kenpaku-shi, runin (exiles), runin-kotori-shi and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, magishugyoku-shi (envoy), chugushoku-sokuto-shi, kenpaku-shi, runin (exiles), runin-kotori-shi and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, magishugyoku-shi (envoy), chugushoku-sokuto-shi, kenpaku-shi, runin (exiles), runin-kotori-shi and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>しかし、律令制初期から、新任国司の赴任交通手段として伝馬を利用する事例が見られ始めると、平安時代初期までに、伝馬制は新任国司赴任のための専用制度になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, from the early ritsuryo system, some cases of new kokushi (local governors) using tenma as a transportation means to their new posts began to appear, leading to the exclusive use of the tenma system by new kokushi going to their new posts by the early Heian period..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, from the early ritsuryo system, some cases of new kokushi (local governors) using tenma as a transportation means to their new posts began to appear, leading to the exclusive use of the tenma system by new kokushi going to their new posts by the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドが2つついていたので削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, from the early ritsuryo system, some cases of new kokushi (local governors) using tenma as a transportation means to their new posts began to appear, leading to the exclusive use of the tenma system by new kokushi going to their new posts by the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>10世紀初めに編纂された『延喜式』に伝馬を置く郡が列挙されているが、新任国司の通過路線に限定して伝馬が設置されるようになったことがわかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Engi-shiki law compiled in the early tenth century listed provinces where tenma were posted, which made it known that tenma were posted only along passing routes of new kokushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Engi-shiki law&quot; compiled in the early tenth century listed provinces where tenma were posted, which made it known that tenma were posted only along passing routes of new kokushi.</e>
<cmt>括弧を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Engi-shiki law&quot; compiled in the early tenth century listed provinces where tenma were posted, which made it known that tenma were posted only along passing routes of new kokushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>中世</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Medieval Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Medieval Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Medieval Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>近世</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Early Modern Age</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Early Modern Age</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Early Modern Age</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>地名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Place Names</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Place Names</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Place Names</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>主に近世の伝馬所（問屋場）に発祥した伝馬地名が各所に残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Place names including the word tenma still remain in various places where tenmajo (post stations) mainly in modern-times, were set.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Place names including the word tenma still remain in various places where mainly modern tenmajo (post stations) were set.</e>
<cmt>読みやすくするため語句および語順を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Place names including the word tenma still remain in various places where mainly modern tenmajo (post stations) were set.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>（詳細→伝馬町）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(For details =&gt; Denma-cho)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(For details =&gt; Denma-cho)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(For details -&gt; Denma-cho)</e>
<cmt>記号を変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Shimoxx(id:9332), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>