<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>アラハバキ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Arahabaki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Arahabaki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Arahabaki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>アラハバキ（荒覇吐、荒吐、荒脛巾）信仰は、東北地方一帯に見られる民俗信仰。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Arahabaki belief is a folk belief found in the Tohoku region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Arahabaki belief is a folk belief found in the Tohoku region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Arahabaki belief is a folk belief found in the Tohoku region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>その起源は不明な点が多く、「まつろわぬ民」であった日本東部の民・蝦夷（えみし、えびす、えぞ）がヤマト王権・朝廷により東北地方へと追いやられながらも守り続けた伝承とする説が唱えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many aspects of its origin is unknown and there is a theory that says it was a tradition that the people of western Japan, the Emishi (Ebisu, Ezo), who were considered &quot;Matsurowanu people&quot;, preserved while they were being driven into the Tohoku region by the Yamato government/imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many aspects of its origin are unknown and there is a theory that says it was a tradition that the people of western Japan, the Emishi (Ebisu, Ezo), who were considered &quot;Matsurowanu people,&quot; preserved while they were being driven into the Tohoku region by the Yamato government/imperial court.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many aspects of its origin are unknown and there is a theory that says it was a tradition that the people of eastern Japan, the Emishi (Ebisu, Ezo), who were considered &apos;Matsurowanu tami&apos; (people who do not obey) preserved while they were being driven into the Tohoku region by the Yamato government/Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>まつろわぬ民→people who do not obey と補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>歴史的経緯や信憑性については諸説ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are various theories regarding the history and believability.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various theories regarding the history and believability.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various theories regarding the history and believability.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>縄文神の一種という説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a theory that says it is a type of Jomon god.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a theory that says it is a type of Jomon god.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a theory that says it is a type of Jomon god.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また、古史古伝・偽史的な主張と結びつけられることも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also often tied up with ancient history, folklore and false history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also often tied up with ancient history, folklore, and false history.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also often tied up with ancient history, folklore, and false history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>アラハバキを祀る神社は東北地方に多く見られるが、関東以南でもみることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shrines dedicated to Arahabaki are common in the Tohoku region, but are also found south of the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shrines dedicated to Arahabaki are common in the Tohoku region, but are also found south of the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shrines dedicated to Arahabaki are common in the Tohoku region, but are also found south of the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>ただしそれは主祭神としてではなく、門客神（もんきゃくじん）として祀られているケースが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, these shrines in many cases do not enshrine Arahabaki as the main god, but as a Monkyakujin (guest god).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, these shrines in many cases do not enshrine Arahabaki as the main god, but as a Monkyakujin (guest god).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, these shrines in many cases do not enshrine Arahabaki as the main god, but as a Monkyakujin (guest god).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>門客神とは、神社の門に置かれた「客人神（まろうどがみ）」のことで、「客人神」は地主神がその土地を奪われて、後からやって来た日本神話に登場する神々と立場を逆転させられて、客神となったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monkyakujin means &quot;Maroudogami (guest god)&quot; placed at the gate of the shrine and &quot;Maroudogami&quot; are usually the local god whose land had been taken away by the later gods that feature in Japanese myths and are placed into the inferior guest god position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Monkyakujin means &quot;Maroudogami (guest god)&quot; placed at the gate of the shrine and &quot;Maroudogami&quot; are usually the local god whose land had been taken away by the later gods that feature in Japanese myths and are placed into the inferior guest god position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Monkyakujin means &apos;Maroudogami&apos; (guest god) placed at the gate of the shrine and &apos;Maroudogami&apos; is usually the local god whose land had been taken away by the later gods that feature in Japanese myths and is placed into the inferior guest god position.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>アラハバキが「客人神」として祀られているケースは、例えば埼玉県大宮にある「氷川神社」で見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cases where Arahabaki enshrined as a &quot;Maroudogam&quot;i for example is the &quot; Hikawa-jinja Shrine&quot; in Omiya, Saitama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One case where Arahabaki is enshrined as a &quot;Maroudogami&quot; for example is the &quot; Hikawa-jinja Shrine&quot; in Omiya, Saitama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One case where Arahabaki is enshrined as a &apos;Maroudogami&apos; for example is the &apos;Hikawa-jinja Shrine&apos; in Omiya, Saitama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>この摂社は「門客人神社」と呼ばれるが、元々は「荒脛巾（あらはばき）神社」と呼ばれていたとのことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This shrine is called the &quot;Monkyaku-jinja shrine&quot; but originally was called &quot;Arahabaki-jinja Shrine&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This shrine is called the &quot;Monkyaku-jinja shrine&quot; but was originally called &quot;Arahabaki-jinja Shrine.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This sessha (auxiliary shrine [dedicated to a deity close-related to that of a main shrine]) is called the &apos;Monkyaku-jinja Shrine&apos; but was originally called &apos;Arahabaki-jinja Shrine.&apos;</e>
<cmt>摂社　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>蛇神説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Snake god theory</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Snake god theory</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Snake god theory</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>吉野裕子によると、「ハバキ」の「ハハ」は蛇の古語であるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Yuko YOSHINO, the &quot;Haha&quot; in &quot;Habaki&quot; is an ancient word for snake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Yuko YOSHINO, the &quot;Haha&quot; in &quot;Habaki&quot; is an ancient word for snake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Yuko YOSHINO, the &apos;Haha&apos; in &apos;Habaki&apos; is an ancient word for snake.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>「ハハキ」とは「蛇木（ははき）」あるいは「竜木（ははき）」であり、直立する樹木は蛇に見立てられ、古来祭りの中枢にあったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hahaki&quot; means &quot;snake tree&quot; or &quot;dragon tree&quot; and straight trees were originally the center of festivals and were portrayed as snakes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hahaki&quot; means &quot;snake tree&quot; or &quot;dragon tree&quot; and straight trees were originally the center of festivals and were portrayed as snakes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word &apos;Hahaki&apos; means &apos;snake tree&apos; or &apos;dragon tree&apos; and straight trees were originally the center of festivals and were portrayed as snakes.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>また、伊勢神宮には「波波木（ははき）神」が祀られているが、その祀られる場所は内宮の東南、つまり「辰巳」の方角、その祭祀は6、9、12月の18日（これは土用にあたる）の「巳の刻」に行われるというのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Ise Jingu, a &quot;Hahaki-kami&quot; is enshrined in a shrine that is positioned southwest from the inner shrine, in other words, the &quot;tatsumi&quot; direction and ceremonies are conducted on the Eighteenth of June, September and December (Doyo days) at the &quot;hour of Mi&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At Ise Jingu, a &quot;Hahaki-kami&quot; is enshrined in a shrine that is positioned southwest from the inner shrine, in other words, the &quot;tatsumi&quot; direction and ceremonies are conducted on the Eighteenth of June, September and December (Doyo days) at the &quot;hour of Mi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At Ise Jingu Shine, a &apos;Hahaki-kami&apos; is enshrined in a shrine that is positioned southwest from the inner shrine, in other words, the &apos;tatsumi&apos; direction, and ceremonies are conducted on the 18th of June, September and December (Doyo days) at the &apos;hour of Mi&apos; (around 10 am).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。巳の刻→around 10 am と補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>「辰」＝「竜」、「巳」＝「蛇」だから、蛇と深い関わりがあると容易に想像がつく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tatsu&quot;&quot; means dragon and &quot;Mi&quot; means snake, so it is easy to imagine that it has a strong relation with snakes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Tatsu&quot;&quot; means dragon and &quot;Mi&quot; means snake, so it is easy to imagine that it has a strong relation with snakes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since &apos;Tatsu&apos; means &apos;dragon&apos; and &apos;Mi&apos; means &apos;snake,&apos; it is easy to imagine that it has a strong relation with snakes.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>ちなみに、「波波木神」が後に「顕れる」という接頭語が付いて、「顕波波木神」になったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It became &quot;hahaki-kami&quot; with the prefix for &quot;to appear&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It became &quot;hahaki-kami&quot; with the prefix for &quot;to appear.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It became &apos;Arahabaki-kami&apos;, in which &quot;Hahaki-kami&apos; is later added by the prefix for &apos;to appear&apos; (ara).</e>
<cmt>翻訳を一部補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>塞の神説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sae no kami theory</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sae no kami theory</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sae no kami theory</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>宮城県にある多賀城跡の東北にアラハバキ神社がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a Arahabaki-jinja Shrine located northwest of the remains of Taga-jo Castle in Miyagi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a Arahabaki-jinja Shrine located northwest of the remains of Taga-jo Castle in Miyagi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a Arahabaki-jinja Shrine located northwest of the remains of Taga-jo Castle in Miyagi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>多賀城とは、奈良・平安期の朝廷が東北地方に住んでいた蝦夷を制圧するために築いた拠点である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taga-jo Castle was the base built by the Nara and Heian period court to control the Emishi living in the Tohoku region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taga-jo Castle was the base built by the Nara and Heian period court to control the Emishi living in the Tohoku region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taga-jo Castle was the base built by the Nara and Heian period court to control the Emishi living in the Tohoku region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>谷川健一によれば、これは朝廷が外敵から多賀城を守るためにアラハバキを祀ったとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Kenichi TANIGAWA, it is said that Arahabaki enshrined by the court to protect Taga-jo Castle from enemies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Kenichi TANIGAWA, it is said that Arahabaki was enshrined by the court to protect Taga-jo Castle from enemies.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Kenichi TANIGAWA, it is said that Arahabaki was enshrined by the court to protect Taga-jo Castle from enemies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>朝廷にとっての外敵とは当然蝦夷である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Obviously the court&apos;s enemy is the Emishi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Obviously the court&apos;s enemy were the Emishi.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Obviously the court&apos;s enemy were the Emishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>つまりこれはアラハバキに「塞の神」としての性格があったためと述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, he explains that Arahabahi had a characteristic of being a &quot;sae no kami (god that prevents intrusion)&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, he explains that Arahabahi had the characteristic of being a &quot;sae no kami (god that prevents intrusion).&quot;</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, he explains that Arahabaki had the characteristic of being a &apos;sae no kami&apos; (god that prevents intrusion).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="21">
<j>さらに谷川によると、朝廷の伝統的な蝦夷統治の政策は、「蝦夷をもって蝦夷を制す」であったそうで、もともと蝦夷の神であったアラハバキを多賀城を守るための塞の神として配し、蝦夷を撃退しようとしていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, according to Tanigawa, the traditional Emishi control strategy of the court was &quot;use the Emishi to control the Emishi&quot;, and they used Arahabaki, which was originally an Emishi god, to protect Taga-jo Castle as a sae no kami and tried to ward off Emishi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, according to Tanigawa, the traditional Emishi control strategy of the court was &quot;use the Emishi to control the Emishi,&quot; and they used Arahabaki, which was originally an Emishi god, to protect Taga-jo Castle as a sae no kami and tried to ward off the Emishi.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, according to Tanigawa, the traditional Emishi control strategy of the court was &apos;use the Emishi to control the Emishi,&apos; and they used Arahabaki, which was originally an Emishi god, to protect Taga-jo Castle as a sae no kami and tried to ward off the Emishi.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>製鉄の神説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iron production god theory</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iron production god theory</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iron production god theory</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>先の、多賀城跡近くにあるアラハバキ神社には鋏が奉納され、さらに鋳鉄製の灯篭もあるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Arahabaki-jinja Shrine near Taga-jo Castle as mentioned above had shears as an offering and also lanterns made from cast iron.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Arahabaki-jinja Shrine near Taga-jo Castle as mentioned above had shears as an offering and also lanterns made from cast iron.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Arahabaki-jinja Shrine near Taga-jo Castle as mentioned above had shears as an offering and also lanterns made from cast iron.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>また多賀城の北方は砂金や砂鉄の産出地であるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To the north of Taga-jo Castle were places that produce gold sand and iron sand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To the north of Taga-jo Castle were places that produced gold sand and iron sand.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To the north of Taga-jo Castle were places that produced gold sand and iron sand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="24">
<j>先のアラハバキを客人神として祀る氷川神社であるが、出雲の流れを汲むという（出雲の斐川にあった杵築神社から移った）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hikawa-jinja Shrine mentioned earlier for enshrining Arahabaki as a guest god is of the Izumo branch (transferred from Kitsuki-jinja Shrine located at Hikawa River of Izumo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hikawa-jinja Shrine mentioned earlier for enshrining Arahabaki as a guest god is of the Izumo branch (transferred from Kitsuki-jinja Shrine located at Hikawa River of Izumo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hikawa-jinja Shrine mentioned earlier for enshrining Arahabaki as a guest god is of the Izumo branch (transferred from Kitsuki-jinja Shrine located at Hi-kawa River of Izumo).</e>
<cmt>Hi-kawa River としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>出雲といえば日本の製鉄発祥の地である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Izumo is the place were iron production started in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Izumo is the place were iron production started in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Izumo is the place were iron production started in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>また氷川神社の祀官は鍛冶氏族である物部氏の流れを組むとのことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The monks at Hikawa-jinja Shrine are said to be a branch of Mononobe clan, who were the clan of blacksmiths.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The monks at Hikawa-jinja Shrine are said to be a branch of the Mononobe clan, who were a clan of blacksmiths.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The monks at Hikawa-jinja Shrine are said to be a branch of the Mononobe clan, who were a clan of blacksmiths.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>氷川神社のある埼玉県は古代製鉄産業の中心地でもあるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saitama Prefecture, where Hikawa-jinja Shrine is located, was the center of iron production industry in ancient times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saitama Prefecture, where Hikawa-jinja Shrine is located, was the center of iron production industry in ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saitama Prefecture, where Hikawa-jinja Shrine is located, was the center of iron production industry in ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>但し、音韻的に斐川は「シカワ」から転訛したものであり、氷川は「ピカワ」から転訛したものであることから、全く繋がりはないとの説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there is also a theory that phonologically Hikawa came from &quot;Shikawa&quot; and Hikawa came from &quot;Bikawa&quot; and the two have no relation at all.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there is also a theory that phonologically Hikawa came from &quot;Shikawa&quot; and Hikawa came from &quot;Bikawa&quot; and the two have no relation at all.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there is also a theory that phonologically Hikawa came from &apos;Shikawa&apos; and Hikawa came from &apos;Bikawa&apos; and the two have no relation at all.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="29">
<j>またこの大宮を中心とする氷川神社群（三ツ星である氷川神社、中氷川神社、女氷川神社に調神社、宗像神社、越谷の久伊豆神社まで含めたもの）はオリオン座の形、つまりカムド（神門）の形に並んでおり、脇を流れる荒川を天の川とすれば、ちょうど天を映した形になっている点は注目に値する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also worthwhile to note that the Hikawa-jinja Shrine group in Omiya (the three stars, Hikawa-jinja, Nakahikawa-jinja, Onnahikawa-jinja and Tsukijinja-Shrine, Munakata-jinja Shrine and Hisaizujinja Shrine in Koshigaya_ are aligned in the shape of the constellation Orion, or Kamudo(god&apos;s gate) and if the Ara-kawa River that follow beside them is considered as the Milky Way, it seems to depict the skies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also worthwhile to note that the Hikawa-jinja Shrine group in Omiya (the three stars, Hikawa-jinja, Nakahikawa-jinja, Onnahikawa-jinja and Tsukijinja-Shrine, Munakata-jinja Shrine and Hisaizujinja Shrine in Koshigaya are aligned in the shape of the constellation Orion, or Kamudo(god&apos;s gate) and if the Ara-kawa River that follow beside them is considered as the Milky Way, it seems to depict the skies.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also worthwhile to note that the shrines in Hikawa-jinja Shrine group in Omiya (the three stars, Hikawa-jinja, Nakahikawa-jinja and Onnahikawa-jinja shrines, along with Tsuki-jinja Shrine, Munakata-jinja Shrine and Hisaizu-jinja Shrine in Koshigaya) are aligned in the shape of the constellation Orion, or Kamudo (god&apos;s gate) and if the Ara-kawa River that follow beside them is considered as the Milky Way, it seems to depict the skies.</e>
<cmt>神社の表現などを統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>さらにこの氷川神社群は秩父神社群（北斗七星（＝アメノトリフネ、ウケフネ）の形に並んでいる）と比企郡ときがわ町の萩日吉神社において一点で交わり一対一で対応している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, this Hikawa-jinja Shrine group is located on the other side of the Chichibu-jinja Shrine group (aligned in the shape of the Bid Dipper=Amenotorihune, Ukehune) crossing the Hagihichi-jinjja Shrine in Hiki-gun, Tokigawa-cho.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, this Hikawa-jinja Shrine group is located on the other side of the Chichibu-jinja Shrine group (aligned in the shape of the Big Dipper=Amenotorihune, Ukehune) crossing the Hagihichi-jinjja Shrine in Hiki-gun, Tokigawa-cho.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, this Hikawa-jinja Shrine group is located on the other side of the Chichibu-jinja Shrine group (aligned in the shape of the Big Dipper = Amenotorifune, Ukefune) crossing the Hagihiyoshi-jinja Shrine in Tokigawa-cho, Hiki-gun.</e>
<cmt>神社名を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>このことは、あるいは（その測量技術の精度の高さもあることから）古代朝鮮道教との強いつながりを窺わせる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This suggests a strong relation with ancient Korean Dokyo because of the highly accurate measurement technology.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This suggests a strong relation with ancient Korean Dokyo because of the highly accurate measurement technology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This suggests a strong relation with ancient Korean Dokyo because of the highly accurate measurement technology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>氷川神社が延喜式に掲載されている古社であり、かつ、氷川神社の主祭神がスサノオになった（＝元々主祭神であったアラハバキ神が客人神になった）のは江戸幕府の政治的意図によるものであることからすれば、出雲と氷川の繋がりの話は、大和朝廷による蝦夷（含、渡来人）支配の一過程であると捉えたほうがよさそうである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Hikawa-jinja Shrine is an old establishment listed in the &quot;the Engishiki&quot; (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers) and the main god of Hikawa-jinja became Susanoo (in other words, the original main god Arahabaki became the guest god) only because of political reasons of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), the story on the link between Izumo and Hikawa may be taken as part of the process of Emeishi (including Toraijin (people from overseas, especially from China and Korea, who settled in early Japan and introduced Continental culture to the Japanese)) control by the Yamato court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Hikawa-jinja Shrine is an old establishment listed in the &quot;the Engishiki&quot; (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers) and the main god of Hikawa-jinja became Susanoo (in other words, the original main god Arahabaki became the guest god) only because of political reasons of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), the story on the link between Izumo and Hikawa may be taken as part of the process of Emeishi (including Toraijin (people from overseas, especially from China and Korea, who settled in early Japan and introduced Continental culture to the Japanese)) control by the Yamato court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Hikawa-jinja Shrine is an old establishment listed in the &quot;the Engishiki&quot; (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers) and the main god of Hikawa-jinja Shrine became Susanoo (in other words, the original main god Arahabaki became the guest god) only because of political reasons of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), the story on the link between Izumo and Hikawa may be taken as part of the process of Emishi (including Toraijin [people from overseas, especially from China and Korea, who settled in early Japan and introduced Continental culture to the Japanese]) control by the Yamato Court.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="33">
<j>近江雅和によると、アラハバキから変容したとされる門客人神の像は、片目で祀られていることが多いという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Masakazu OE, the gate guest god figure said to have transformed from Arahabaki often has only one eye.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Masakazu OE, the gate guest god figure said to have transformed from Arahabaki often has only one eye.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Masakazu OMI, the gate guest god figure said to have transformed from Arahabaki often has only one eye.</e>
<cmt>おうみ　と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>片目は製鉄神の特徴とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having one eye is said to be a characteristic of the god of iron production.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having one eye is said to be a characteristic of the god of iron production.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having one eye is said to be a characteristic of the god of iron production.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>また近江は、「アラ」は鉄の古語であるということと、山砂鉄による製鉄や、その他の鉱物採取を実態としていた修験道はアラハバキ信仰を取り入れ、「ハバキ」は山伏が神聖視する「脛巾」に通じ、アラハバキはやがて「お参りすると足が良くなる」という「足神」様に変容していったと述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, Oe explains that &quot;Ara&quot; is an acient word for iron and Shugendo (Japanese mountain asceticism-shamanism incorporating Shinto and Buddhist concepts), which was actually involved in iron production using mountain iron sand and collecting other minerals,incorporated Arahabaki beliefs, and &quot;Habaki&quot; is related with the &quot;Habaki (shin guard)&quot; which Yamabushi consider holy and therefore Arahabaki eventually transformed into a &quot;god of feet&quot; and considered that &quot;your legs get better if you worship at the shrine&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, Oe explains that &quot;Ara&quot; is an ancient word for iron and Shugendo (Japanese mountain asceticism-shamanism incorporating Shinto and Buddhist concepts), which was actually involved in iron production using mountain iron sand and collecting other minerals, incorporated Arahabaki beliefs, and &quot;Habaki&quot; is related to the &quot;Habaki (shin guard)&quot; which Yamabushi consider holy and therefore Arahabaki eventually transformed into a &quot;god of feet&quot; and considered that &quot;your legs get better if you worship at the shrine.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, Omi explains that &apos;Ara&apos; is an ancient word for iron and Shugendo (Japanese mountain asceticism-shamanism incorporating Shinto and Buddhist concepts), which was actually involved in iron production using mountain iron sand and collecting other minerals, incorporated Arahabaki beliefs, and &apos;Habaki&apos; is related to the &apos;Habaki&apos; (shin guard) which Yamabushi (a mountain priest) considers holy and therefore Arahabaki eventually transformed into a &apos;god of feet,&apos; considering &apos;your legs get better if you worship at the shrine.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を補足しました。&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="36">
<j>なお、真弓常忠は先述の「塞の神」について、本来は「サヒ（鉄）の神」の意味だったと述べていて、「塞の神」と製鉄の神がここで結びついてくる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tunetada MAYUMI explains that the aforementioned &quot;sae no kami&quot; originally meant &quot;Sahi (iron) no kami&quot; and here &quot;sae no kami&quot; and the god of iron production is linked.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tunetada MAYUMI explains that the aforementioned &quot;sae no kami&quot; originally meant &quot;Sahi (iron) no kami&quot; and here &quot;sae no kami&quot; and the god of iron production is linked.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunetada MAYUMI explains that the aforementioned &apos;sae no kami&apos; originally meant &apos;Sahi (iron) no kami&apos; and here &apos;sae no kami&apos; and the god of iron production is linked.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>四天王寺との関係説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Relation with Shitenno-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Relation with Shitenno-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Relation with Shitenno-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="37">
<j>聖徳太子が物部守屋との仏教受容をめぐる戦いを制し建てた、日本初の大寺である大阪市の四天王寺について、アラハバキ及び縄文系との関わりが指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been suggested that Shitenno-ji in Osaka City, which was the first large temple built in Japan by TAISHI Shotoku when he battled and defeated Moriya MONONOBE over accepting Buddhism, has a relationship with Arahabaki and Jomon culture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been suggested that Shitenno-ji in Osaka City, which was the first large temple built in Japan by TAISHI Shotoku when he battled and defeated Moriya MONONOBE over accepting Buddhism, has a relationship with Arahabaki and Jomon culture.</e>
<cmt>Spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been suggested that Shitenno-ji Temple in Osaka City, which was the first large temple built in Japan by Prince Shotoku when he battled and defeated MONONOBE no Moriya over accepting Buddhism, has a relationship with Arahabaki and Jomon culture.</e>
<cmt>人名の読みを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="38">
<j>四天王寺の地の元来の地名は「荒墓邑」(アラバキ？)であり、場所は縄文系説が言われる物部氏の地に立てたと伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The original place name of Shitenoji was &quot;Arabaki?&quot; and it is said to have been the land of Mononobe clan who were considered as the branch of Jomon culture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The original place name of Shitenoji was &quot;Arabaki?&quot; and it is said to have been the land of the Mononobe clan who were considered as the branch of Jomon culture.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The original place name of Shitennoji was presumably &apos;Arabaki&apos; and it is said to have been the land of the Mononobe clan who were considered as the branch of Jomon culture.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。?をpresumably としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="39">
<j>現四天王寺の北側に磐船神社(饒速日命の降臨地)が元々あったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iwahune-jinja Shrine(place were Nigihayanomikoto arrived) is said to have located at the north side of the present Shitenno-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iwahune-jinja Shrine (place where Nigihayanomikoto arrived) is said to have been located at the north side of the present Shitenno-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iwafune-jinja Shrine (place where Nigihaya no mikoto descended to earth) is said to have been located at the north side of the present Shitenno-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。Nigihaya no mikoto としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>物部氏は饒速日命を始祖とする一族であるから、この四天王寺の地は本来、物部発祥の聖地であったと考えてよさそうである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Considering the fact that the Mononobe clan consider their founding father as Nigihayanomikoto, the land where Shiteno-ji is located seems to be originally the holy place where Mononobe clan started.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Considering the fact that the Mononobe clan consider their founding father as Nigihayanomikoto, the land where Shiteno-ji is located seems to be originally the holy place where the Mononobe clan started.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Considering the fact that the Mononobe clan consider their founding father as Nigihaya no mikoto, the land where Shitenno-ji Temple is located seems to be originally the holy place where the Mononobe clan started.</e>
<cmt>Nigihaya no mikoto としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 もね～るmoner(id:28477), Toroia(id:31889), TMPU(id:199045), Nnh(id:474), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Michey.M(id:906), Cprobot(id:97843), MIO(id:31681), Shimoxx(id:9332), Bit(id:2197), 佐目(id:65316), Clinamen(id:42894), Mt3(id:118081), Gombe(id:27), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>