<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>兵農分離</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heinobunri (a separation of the warriors class from the soil)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heinobunri (a separation of the warrior class from the soil)</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heinobunri</e>
<cmt>タイトルのため、補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>兵農分離（へいのうぶんり）とは、安土桃山から江戸時代にかけて推し進められた武士階級以外の武装解除を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heinobunri indicates the disarming the classes pushed forward during the period from Azuchi Momoyama through Edo period except for samurai (warrior) class.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heinobunri indicates the disarming of the classes pushed forward during the period from the Azuchi Momoyama through Edo periods except for the samurai (warrior) class.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heinobunri indicates the disarming of the classes pushed forward during the period from the Azuchi-Momoyama through Edo periods except for the samurai (warrior) class.</e>
<cmt>Azuchi-Momoyama としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>のち徳川家が国政を管掌する途上において、武士と他の階級を明確に区別した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, in the process of Tokugawa family taking control of the national administration, samurai class and other classes were separated precisely.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, in the process of the Tokugawa family taking control of the national administration, the samurai class and other classes were separated precisely.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, in the process of the Tokugawa family taking control of the national administration, the samurai class and other classes were separated precisely.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>そして武士を最上位に置く体制を確立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And it led to establishing the system of samurai class being put on the top of hierarchy.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And it led to establishing the system of the samurai class being put on top of the hierarchy.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And it led to establishing the system of the samurai class being put on top of the hierarchy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>日本の中世期においては、幕府の地頭、御家人、その郎党といった正規の武士以外に地侍（土豪）、野伏、農民等も武装していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the medieval period of Japan, not only regular samurai who were jito (land steward appointed by the central military government to each of the estates (shoen) into which the countryside was divided), gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods) and other roto (retainers) but also jizamurai (local samurai (or dogo:loclal ruling family)), nobushi (unofficial warrior hidden in a forest and farmers were armed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the medieval period of Japan, not only regular samurai who were jito (land steward appointed by the central military government to each of the estates (shoen) into which the countryside was divided), gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods) and other roto (retainers) but also jizamurai (local samurai (or dogo: local ruling family)), nobushi (unofficial warrior hidden in a forest) and farmers were armed.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the medieval period of Japan, not only regular samurai who were jito (land steward appointed by the central military government to each of the estates [shoen] into which the countryside was divided), gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods) and other roto (retainers) but also jizamurai (local samurai [or dogo: local ruling family]), nobushi (unofficial warrior hidden in a forest) and farmers were armed.</e>
<cmt>括弧内の括弧を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>武士は律令時代の武装開拓農場主を出自としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Samurai originated in the armed farmers in Ritsuryo period who developed and cultivated their own land.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Samurai originated in the armed farmers in the Ritsuryo period who developed and cultivated their own land.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Samurai originated in the armed farmers in the Ritsuryo period who developed and cultivated their own land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>農場主が小作人の子弟を郎党として戦時の体制を構成していたため、兵と農は不離あるいは同義語に近い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the farmers took the system in wartime, having younger people of their roto armed, hei (samurai) and no (farmers) were inseparable or close to a synonym.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the farmers took the system in wartime, having younger people of their roto armed, hei (samurai) and no (farmers) were inseparable or close to a synonym.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the farmers took the system in wartime, having younger people of their tenant farmers armed, hei (samurai) and no (farmers) were inseparable or close to a synonym.</e>
<cmt>小作人→tenant farmers としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また治安維持を担う政府が形骸化していたために流通業者も武装しなければならなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, as the government that was supposed to take the duties of maintaining security had become dead letter, distributors also had to be armed themselves.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, as the government that was supposed to take the duties of maintaining security had become useless, distributors also had to be armed themselves.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, as the government that was supposed to take the duties of maintaining security had become useless, distributors also had to be armed themselves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>このため、農業系武士の代表が鎌倉幕府の御家人たちであるならば、商業系武士の代表としては運輸業者であったといわれる楠木正成等が挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this, while the typical example of samurai originated in farmers were gokenin in Kamakura bakufu, the typical example of samurai originated in merchants were Masashige KUSUNOKI who is said to have been a distributor and others.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this, while the typical example of samurai who originated in farmers were gokenin in the Kamakura bakufu, the representative of samurai who originated in merchants was Masashige KUSUNOKI who is said to have been a distributor and others.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this, while the typical example of samurai who originated in farmers were gokenin in the Kamakura bakufu, the representative of samurai who originated in merchants was Masashige KUSUNOKI who is said to have been a distributor and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>つまり武装を必要としない江戸時代の安定を見るまでは、あらゆる階層が武装していたと考えるほうがよい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is, it is better to think that all the classes had been armed until the society was stabilized in Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is, it is better to think that all the classes had been armed until the society was stabilized in Edo period.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That is, it is better to think that all the classes had been armed until the society was stabilized in Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>元々、兵農分離は戦国大名の必要性から始まっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, heinobunri started by the necessity of daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) in the Sengoku (warring) period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, heinobunri started by the necessity of daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) in the Sengoku (warring) period.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, heinobunri started by the necessity of Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period).</e>
<cmt>戦国大名　表現を変更しました。 (daimyo [Japanese territorial lord] in the Sengoku period [period of warring states])→Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>すなわち、継続的に戦闘が行われる戦国期においては、戦国大名はいつでも、迅速に、また長期的に政略的・軍事的要地に精兵を動員できるようにしたかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This means that during the Sengoku period when the battles were conducted continuously, Sengoku daimyo wanted to mobilize their strongest warriors to politically and militarily important places anytime, swiftly and over the long term.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This means that during the Sengoku period when the battles were conducted continuously, Sengoku daimyo wanted to mobilize their strongest warriors to politically and militarily important places anytime, swiftly and over the long term.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This means that during the Sengoku period when the battles were conducted continuously, Sengoku daimyo wanted to mobilize their strongest warriors to politically and militarily important places anytime, swiftly and over the long term.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>だが、室町期以前のような家来達が所領に在住する地方領主制では、召集するのに時間が掛かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the system in Muromachi period or before that the retainers lived in their territory, it took a long time for daimyo to call out their retainers.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the system in the Muromachi period or before where the retainers lived in their territory, it took a long time for daimyo to call out their retainers.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the system in the Muromachi period or before where the retainers lived in their territory, it took a long time for daimyo to call out their retainers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また、彼らの郎党には半士半農の者もおり、農繁期の動員に対して不満をもたれるといった問題もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, as among their retainers, some of them were half warrior half farmer, the local lords had a problem that their retainers would have complaints against the mobilization during the busy farming season.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, as among their retainers, some of them were half warrior half farmer, the local lords had a problem that their retainers would have complaints against mobilization during the busy farming season.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, as among their retainers, some of them were half warrior half farmer, the local lords had a problem that their retainers would have complaints against mobilization during the busy farming season.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>このため大内氏や三好氏などは京に軍を進めることには成功したが、その覇権を維持することはできなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this problem, Ouchi clan and Miyoshi clan were able to move their army to Kyoto and attain the hegemony, but unable to maintain it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this problem, the Ouchi clan and Miyoshi clan were able to move their army to Kyoto and attain the hegemony, but unable to maintain it.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this problem, the Ouchi clan and Miyoshi clan were able to move their army to Kyoto and attain the hegemony, but unable to maintain it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>これに対し、家臣を城下に集めて専任の常備軍（この常備軍は西洋軍事史で規定されるそれとは全くの別物である事に注意）とすれば、上記の要求を満たせる上、兵の錬度、武具の質も上げることができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrast, if the feudal lords gathered their vassals around their castles and set them as full-time regular army, they were able to meet the needs mentioned above and to improve soldiers&apos; skillfulness and the quality of arms. (notice: in this case the regular army mentioned here is totally different from the one stipulated in the history of military in the Western countries.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast, if the feudal lords gathered their vassals around their castles and set them as a full-time regular army, they were able to meet the needs mentioned above and to improve soldiers&apos; skillfulness and the quality of arms. (notice: in this case the regular army mentioned here is totally different from the one stipulated in the history of military in the Western countries.)</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast, if the feudal lords gathered their vassals around their castles and set them as a full-time regular army, they were able to meet the needs mentioned above and to improve soldiers&apos; skillfulness and the quality of arms (notice: in this case the regular army mentioned here is totally different from the one stipulated in the history of military in the Western countries).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを括弧の外に移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>一方、家臣を城下に集中させれば、それ以外の者が武力をもつことは安定した支配への脅威となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, if the lords gathered their vassals and had them live around the castles, the citizens&apos; armament besides their soldiers would be a threat to the lords.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, if the lords gathered their vassals and had them live around the castles, the citizens&apos; armament besides their soldiers would be a threat to the lords.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, if the lords gathered their vassals and had them live around the castles, the citizens&apos; armament besides their soldiers would be a threat to the lords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>このため、その武装を禁じる、これが兵農分離である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the lords banned the citizens&apos; armament, which is heinobunri.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the lords banned the citizens&apos; armament, which is heinobunri.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the lords banned the citizens&apos; armament, which is heinobunri.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>有力な戦国大名の下で、これらの施策は一部行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These measures were partly conducted under the powerful daimyo in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These measures were partly conducted under the powerful daimyo in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These measures were partly conducted under the powerful daimyo in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>ただし国人・地侍等の既得権授益層の解体を意味するため、最終的に徹底しされるのは、豊臣秀吉の天下統一後である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as the measures meant to dissolve the class such as kokujin (local lord) and jizamurai who had had vested interest, it was after the unification of the whole country by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI that heinobunri was thoroughly accomplished.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as the measures meant to dissolve the classes such as kokujin (local lord) and jizamurai who had had vested interests, it was after the unification of the whole country by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI that heinobunri was thoroughly accomplished.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as the measures meant to dissolve the classes such as kokujin (local lord) and jizamurai who had had vested interests, it was after the unification of the whole country by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI that heinobunri was thoroughly accomplished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="20">
<j>兵農分離による家臣の城下への集住は、楽市楽座とともに、城下町発展の大きな要因となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having their vassals move and live around the castles became a big factor for the castles to develop besides rakuichi-rakuza (free markets and open guilds).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having their vassals move and live around the castles became a big factor for the castles to develop besides rakuichi-rakuza (free markets and open guilds).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having their vassals move and live around the castles became a big factor for the castles to develop besides rakuichi-rakuza (free markets and open guilds).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="21">
<j>具体的な政策として検地、刀狩、海賊禁止令が施行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the specific policy measures, kenchi (land survey), katanagari (sword hunt) and kaizoku kinshirei (ban on piracy) were conducted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As specific policy measures, kenchi (land survey), katanagari (sword hunt) and kaizoku kinshirei (ban on piracy) were conducted.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As specific policy measures, kenchi (land survey), katanagari (sword hunt) and kaizoku kinshirei (ban on piracy) were conducted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>これらは、土地の支配関係を明らかにし、武士以外の武装権を剥奪するものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These measures were to clearly define the relation of the land holding and to deprive the citizens other than samurai of the right to arm.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These measures were to clearly define the relation of land holding and to deprive the citizens other than samurai of the right to bear arms.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These measures were to clearly define the relation of land holding and to deprive the citizens other than samurai of the right to bear arms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>また、海上においては海賊勢力を解体して大名の水軍武士と漁民に分離するものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, they were to dismantle the pirates&apos; power and separate suigun (navy) samurai from fisher men.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, they were to dismantle the pirates&apos; power and separate suigun (navy) samurai from fisher men.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, they were to dismantle the pirates&apos; power and separate suigun (navy) samurai from fisher men.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="24">
<j>江戸時代に入るとこの方針は一層強化された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Into Edo period, the policy measures were further strengthened.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Into the Edo period, the policy measures were further strengthened.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Into the Edo period, the policy measures were further strengthened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>支配階層を武士として、それ以外の農民、職人、商人はその下に入る階層として厳密に区別された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The social class in Japan was precisely divided into four classes, putting the samurai at the top as ruling class, and farmers, craftsmen and merchants being the lower classes in order that should be put under samurai class.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The social class in Japan was precisely divided into four classes, putting the samurai at the top as the ruling class and farmers, craftsmen, and merchants into lower classes in order to put them under the samurai class.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The social class in Japan was precisely divided into four classes, putting the samurai at the top as the ruling class and farmers, craftsmen, and merchants into lower classes in order to put them under the samurai class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>原則、身分の移動は行えなくなったが、江戸中期以降、この体制は再び崩れ始める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In principal, the citizens were not allowed to change their social status, but in the mid Edo period and later this system began to collapse again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In principal, the citizens were not allowed to change their social status, but in the mid Edo period and later this system began to collapse again.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In principal, the citizens were not allowed to change their social status, but in the mid Edo period and later this system began to collapse again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Zorac(id:28001), Straysheep(id:42448), 越中掾(id:149423), BAKU(id:55205), こおりやんま(id:108912), 酢溜まり氷(id:65987), 水野白楓(id:22811), 彩華1226(id:64711), HI(id:72996), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>