<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>上方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamigata</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamigata</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamigata</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>上方（かみがた・かみかた）は、江戸時代に、大坂や京都を初めとする畿内を呼んだ名称である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamigata is a name used in the Edo period to call Kinai including Osaka and Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamigata is a name used in the Edo period referring to Kinai including Osaka and Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamigata is a name used in the Edo period referring to Kinai including Osaka and Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>広義では、畿内を初めとする近畿地方一帯を指す語としても使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a broad sense, it is also used to call the Kinki area including Kinai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a broad sense, it is also used to refer to the Kinki area including Kinai.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a broad sense, it is also used to refer to the Kinki area including Kinai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>天皇の住む都を「上」とする事から用いられ、特に江戸幕府は三河国以西の畿内（大和国・山城国・摂津国・河内国・和泉国）三州（近江国・丹波国・播磨国）を、「上方筋」と定義した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The city where the emperor lived was called &quot;kami&quot; and the Edo government defined as &quot;Kamigatasuji&quot; Kinai west of the Mikawa County (the Yamato, Yamashiro, Settsu, Kawachi and Izumi Counties) and Sanshu (the Omi, Tanba and Harima Counties).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The city where the emperor lived was called &quot;kami&quot; and the Edo government was defined as &quot;Kamigatasuji&quot; Kinai west of the Mikawa County (the Yamato, Yamashiro, Settsu, Kawachi and Izumi Counties) and Sanshu (the Omi, Tanba and Harima Counties).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The city where the emperor lived was called &apos;kami&apos; and the Edo government defined Kinai, west of the Mikawa Province (the Yamato, Yamashiro, Settsu, Kawachi and Izumi Provinces) and Sanshu (the Omi, Tanba and Harima Provinces) as &apos;Kamigatasuji.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一部、翻訳を変更しました。County→Province</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>政治的な中心である江戸に対し、古くからの文化的な中心地・先進地域を指す語として用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edo was the political center while Kamigata was the ancient cultural center or culturally developed area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edo was the political center while Kamigata was the ancient cultural center or culturally developed area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edo was the political center while Kamigata was the ancient cultural center or culturally developed area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="5">
<j>また、上方と呼ばれる地域における文化は上方文化とも呼ばれ、代表的なものに上方舞、上方落語、上方浮世絵、上方歌、上方言葉がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The culture in the area which was called Kamigata was called Kamigata culture such as Kamigata dance, Kamigata rakugo, Kamigata Ukiyo-e, Kamigata language.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The culture in the area called Kamigata was called Kamigata culture such as Kamigata dancing, Kamigata rakugo, Kamigata Ukiyo-e, Kamigata language.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The culture in the area called Kamigata was called Kamigata culture such as Kamigata dancing, Kamigata rakugo, Kamigata Ukiyo-e, Kamigata language.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="6">
<j>徳川時代中期以降になると、文化の東漸にともない次第に関東へも洗練された先進的な上方文化が下り、化政期になって漸く江戸特有の文化が開花を見るに至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the middle Tokugawa period, refined and advanced Kamigata culture had spread to east gradually and the culture specific to Edo flowered in the Kasei era</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the middle of the Tokugawa period, refined and advanced Kamigata culture spread gradually east and culture specific to Edo flowered in the Kasei era</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the middle of the Tokugawa period, refined and advanced Kamigata culture spread gradually east and culture specific to Edo flowered in the Kasei era</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Rusk(id:9895), Starbacks(id:1018), Straysheep(id:42448), Aney(id:10520), Maxima m(id:28947), Point136(id:211299), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Yas(id:739), Kyoww(id:126965), ウラヌス(id:25954), ウィキ豊(id:82961), Johncapistrano(id:969), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>