<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>秋田蘭画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akita Ranga (Akita Dutch-style painting)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akita Ranga (Akita Dutch-style painting)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akita Ranga (Akita Dutch-style painting)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>秋田蘭画（あきたらんが）とは、江戸時代における絵画のジャンルのひとつで、久保田藩（秋田藩）主や藩士を担い手とした、西洋画の手法を取り入れた構図と純日本的な画材を使用した和洋折衷絵画である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akita Ranga is a genre of painting in a semi-Western style in the Edo period, which was composed by the technique of Western paintings and used traditional Japanese drawing materials, adopted by the Lord and statesmen of the Kubota clan (the Akita clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akita Ranga is a genre of Japanese painting in a semi-Western style from the Edo period that was adopted by the lord and statesmen of the Kubota clan (the Akita clan). Paintings in this style were composed using techniques of Western paintings with traditional Japanese drawing materials.</e>
<cmt>split into two sentences, moving the end of the original into the first sentence; made &quot;lord&quot; lowercase; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akita Ranga is a genre of Japanese painting in a semi-Western style from the Edo period that was adopted by the lord and statesmen of the Kubota clan (the Akita clan); paintings in this style were composed using techniques of Western paintings with traditional Japanese drawing materials.</e>
<cmt>一文につなげました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>秋田派ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Akita school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called the School of Akita.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;Akita school&quot; to &quot;the School of Akita&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called the School of Akita.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>安永 (元号)年間（1772年－1781年）に久保田藩で成立したが、後継者もなく天明年間（1781年－1789年）には廃れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was established by the Kubota clan between 1772 and 1781 and became out of use between 1781 and 1789 because there were no successors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The genre was established by the Kubota clan between 1772 and 1781, but died out between 1781 and 1789 due to a lack of successors.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The genre was established by the Kubota clan between 1772 and 1781, but died out between 1781 and 1789 due to a lack of successors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>しかし、その極端な遠近法は後代の浮世絵にも大きな影響を与えたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However it is said that the extreme perspective largely affected ukiyoe (a woodblock print depicting everyday life of the common people) later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is said that the extremity of its method of perspective had a large effect on later art known as ukiyoe (woodblock prints depicting everyday life of the common people).</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is said that the extremity of its method of perspective had a large effect on later art known as ukiyoe (woodblock prints depicting everyday life of the common people).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>代表的な画家に、藩士小田野直武（1750年－1780年）、藩主佐竹曙山（1748年－1785年）、その一族佐竹義躬（1749年－1800年）がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The major painters are Naotake ODANO, a statesman (1750-1780) and Shozan SATAKE, the Lord (1748-1785) and his family Yoshimi SATAKE (1749-1800).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major Akita Ranga painters were a statesman named Naotake ODANO (1750-1780), a feudal lord named Shozan SATAKE (1748-1785) and a member of his family named Yoshimi SATAKE (1749-1800).</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major Akita Ranga painters were a statesman named Naotake ODANO (1750 - 1780), a feudal lord named Shozan SATAKE (1748 - 1785) and a member of his family named Yoshimi SATAKE (1749 - 1800).</e>
<cmt>生没年にスペースを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>特徴と背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Characteristics and background</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Characteristics and Background</e>
<cmt>capitalized &quot;Background&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Characteristics and background</e>
<cmt>小タイトルのため、一部小文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>秋田蘭画の多くは、絹本着色で掛幅という東洋画の伝統的な形態をとりながらも、画題のうえでは洋風の風景画や静物画を、技法のうえでは陰影法や大気遠近法など西洋絵画の手法を多く採り入れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because many of the Akita Ranga paintings adopted not only the traditional style of Oriental paintings in silk cloth and Kakehaba (mesh count in a row) but also the subjects of Western landscapes and still-life paintings and the techniques of Western paintings largely such as shadow method and atmospheric perspective, it was often painted in oblong composition that strong colored flowers, birds, still lives were in near distances and landscapes like waterfront or only light colors without any objects for distance perspective were in background.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many Akita Ranga paintings used traditional Eastern styles of painting by using silk fabric colors and Kakehaba (Japanese pigments) while adopting Western painting techniques. These included Western-style themes, such as landscapaes and still-lifes, and used such techniques as shadowing and aerial perspective. Works were often in oblong composition, in many cases with flowers, birds and still objects painted in the foreground in deep colors, and landscapes, such as waterfronts, painted in the background, or nothing but light colors to denote a feeling of distance.</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;Because&quot;; changed &quot;paintings in silk&quot; to &quot;silk fabric colors&quot; for &quot;絹本着色&quot;; changed &quot;mesh count in a row&quot; to &quot;Japanese pigments&quot; for description of &quot;掛幅&quot;; changed &quot;atmospheric perspective&quot; to &quot;aerial perspective&quot; since google searches kept changing the former to the latter; changed &quot;it&quot; to &quot;works&quot; for &quot;作品&quot;; split into three sentences for easier reading; fixed grammar to be more understandable</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many Akita Ranga paintings used traditional Eastern styles of painting by using silk fabric colors and Kakehaba (Japanese pigments) while adopting Western painting techniques, which included Western-style themes, such as landscapes and still-lifes, and used such techniques as shadowing and aerial perspective.</e>
<cmt>セルを二つに分け、英文のそのように変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>近景に濃彩の花鳥や静物を描き、遠景には水辺などの風景、あるいは何も描かずに淡い色彩で距離感を示している場合が多く、縦長構図の作品が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The works were often in oblong composition, in many cases with flowers, birds and still objects painted in the foreground in deep colors, and landscapes, such as waterfronts, painted in the background, or nothing but light colors to denote a feeling of distance.</e>
<cmt>セルを二つに分け、英文のそのように変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、舶載顔料であるプルシアンブルーが取り入れられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also an imported color, Prussian blue was adopted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prussian blue was also adopted as an imported color.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prussian blue was also adopted as an imported color.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>秋田蘭画流行の背景には、徳川吉宗の蘭学奨励、当時の南蘋（なんびん）派の流行、および博物趣味の広まりがあると指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was pointed out that the backgrounds of popularity of Akita Ranga were the encouragement of Dutch studies by Yoshimune TOKUGAWA, the popularity of Nanbin school and increasing interests to natural history at the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been pointed out that the popularity of Akita Ranga backgrounds spread from Yoshimune TOKUGAWA&apos;s Dutch study promotions, the popularity of the Nanbin School and hobbyists of natural history of the time.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been pointed out that the popularity of Akita Ranga spread from Yoshimune TOKUGAWA&apos;s Dutch study promotions, the popularity of the Nanbin School and hobbyists of natural history of the time.</e>
<cmt>backgrounds を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>秋田蘭画も南蘋派の影響を受けており、その意味からは和漢洋の折衷体から独自の境地を見い出した画派といえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akita Ranga was also affected by Nanbin school, which means it was a unique painting style created by mixing Japanese, Chinese and Western styles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akita Ranga was also influenced by the Nanbin School, meaning that it was a unique painting style created by mixing Japanese, Chinese and Western styles.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;affected&quot; to &quot;influenced&quot; for &quot;影響を受けており&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akita Ranga was also influenced by the Nanbin School, meaning that it was a unique painting style created by mixing Japanese, Chinese and Western styles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>日本における西洋画は、当初、蘭学の一分野として輸入された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Western paintings were originally imported as a part of Dutch studies in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Western paintings were originally imported as a part of Dutch studies in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Western paintings were originally imported as a part of Dutch studies in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>そのため西洋画の技法研究も、蘭学者である平賀源内が外国人からの直接の指導を受けることなく、書物の挿画の模写などを通して独学で行っており、余技の域を出ないものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore the techniques of Western paintings were studied by Gennai HIRAGA, a scholar of Dutch studies by copying illustrations of books in his own way without any direct guidance from Westerners, as the result it was no better than paining as a hobby.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The techniques of Western paintings were studied by Gennai HIRAGA, a scholar of Dutch studies, by copying the illustrations in books. Since he painted in his own way without any direct guidance from Westerners, his study of the art was no better than painting as a hobby.</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;Therefore&quot; at the beginning of the sentence; split into two sentences for easier reading; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The techniques of Western paintings were studied by Gennai HIRAGA, a scholar of Dutch studies, by copying the illustrations in books, and since he painted in his own way without any direct guidance from Westerners, his study of the art was no better than painting as a hobby.</e>
<cmt>一文につなげました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>一方、久保田藩は財政再建のための方策として鉱山開発に着目しており、安永2年（1773年）7月、源内を鉱山技術者として藩に招聘した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the Kubota clan focused on mine development as a measure to reconstruct its finance and in July, 1773 they invited Gennai as a mine engineer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August of 1773 (安永2年7月), the Kubota clan, who were focused on mine development as a measure to reconstruct their finances, invited Gennai to be a mine engineer.</e>
<cmt>&quot;On the other hand&quot; does not feel natural here, so I eliminated it entirely; fixed grammar to read more naturally; according to &lt;http://maechan.net/kanreki/&gt; 安永2年7月 is August 1773, not July 1773</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the meantime, the Kubota clan, who were focused on mine development as a measure to reconstruct their finances, invited Gennai to be a mine engineer in August of 1773.</e>
<cmt>安永2年7月　を削除しました。In the meantime を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>伝説では、源内が阿仁町に向かうため角館城下の酒造業者五井家に泊まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to legend, when Gennai stayed at Goi family&apos;s house, a brewer in Kakunodate castle town on the way to Ani-machi, he was impressed by a screen painting and called Naotake, the artist and asked him &apos;Try to paint the offering rice cake looking from up&apos; and Naotake painted just a double circle, so he said &apos;it is unclear if it is the tray or the rice cake&apos; and he taught Naotake the shadow method immediately.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to legend, Gennai stayed the night at the home of a brewer named Goi who lived in the castle town of Kakunodate on the way to Ani-machi. Impressed by a screen painting in the home, Gennai summoned the artist named Naotake and said to him, &quot;Try to paint the rice cake offering as if looking at it from above.&quot; When Naotake painted only a double circle, Gennai exclaimed, &quot;I cannot tell if that is the tray or the rice cake,&quot; and immediately taught him a method of painting with shadows.</e>
<cmt>split into three sentences for easier reading; changed &quot;called&quot; to &quot;summoned&quot;; fixed to read more understandably and naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a legend, Gennai stayed the night at the home of Goi family, a sake a brewer who lived in the castle town of Kakunodate, on the way to Ani-machi.</e>
<cmt>セルを二つに分け、英文のそのように変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>その際、宿の屏風絵に感心した源内がその絵の作者だという直武を呼び、「供物餅を上から描いてみなさい」と直武に描かせてみせたところ、二重丸を描いた直武に「それではお盆なのか餅なのか分からない」と言い、即座に陰影法を教えたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Impressed by a screen painting in the home, Gennai summoned the artist named Naotake and said to him, &apos;Try to paint the rice cake offering as if looking at it from above,&apos; and when Naotake painted only a double circle, Gennai exclaimed, &apos;I cannot tell if that is the tray or the rice cake,&apos; and immediately taught him a method of painting with shadows.</e>
<cmt>セルを二つに分け、英文のそのように変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>このとき直武は24歳、それに対し源内は満45歳であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naotake was 24 years old, while Gennai was 45 years old at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time, Naotake was twenty four years old and Gennai was forty five years old.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;at that time&quot; to &quot;At the time&quot; and put at the beginning of the sentence; changed &quot;24&quot; to &quot;twenty-four&quot; and &quot;45&quot; to &quot;forty-five&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time, Naotake was 24 years old and Gennai was 45 years old.</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>源内が阿仁や大館の検分を終えて藩主佐竹曙山（義敦）に拝謁したのちの同年10月29日に久保田を出発、江戸へ戻った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he inspected Ani and Odate, he had an audience with the Lord, Shozan (Yoshiatsu) SATAKE and then left Kubota on October 29 of the same year and went back to Edo and soon after that, Naotake was promoted to &apos;the agent of products under Gennai&apos; and &apos;the collector (selector) of copper mine products&apos; and left Kakunodate for Edo on December 1 and stayed with Gennai for a while.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After inspecting Ani and Odate and having an audience with the feudal lord Shozan (Yoshiatsu) SATAKE, Gennai left the Kubota domain on December 12 of the same year (安永2年10月29日) and returned to Edo. Soon afterwards, Naotake was promoted to &quot;product agent under Gennai&quot; and &quot;collector (selector) of copper mine products.&quot; He departed from Kakunodate for Edo on January 12, 1774 (安永2年12月1日) and lodged with Gennai.</e>
<cmt>run-on sentence split into three sentences for easier reading; changed dates according to &lt;http://maechan.net/kanreki/&gt; and added Japanese dates in parenthesis;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After inspecting Ani and Odate and having an audience with the feudal lord Shozan (Yoshiatsu) SATAKE, Gennai left the Kubota domain on December 12 of the same year and returned to Edo.</e>
<cmt>安永2年12月1日　を削除しました。文章を分けました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>後を追うようなかたちで直武は藩の「源内手、産物他所取次役」ないし「銅山方産物取立役（吟味役）」に抜擢され、12月1日に角館より江戸へ出立して源内のところに寄寓した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon afterwards, Naotake was promoted to &apos;product agent under Gennai&apos; and &apos;collector (selector) of copper mine products,&apos; and he departed from Kakunodate for Edo on January 12, 1774 and lodged with Gennai.</e>
<cmt>文章を分けました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>それまで直武は佐竹北家の家臣（陪臣）であったので、この抜擢により本藩直臣へと立身したことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before that Naotake was a vassal (a retainer of a vassal) of the Satake Kita family, so he was promoted to a direct vassal of the clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since up until that time Naotake had been a vassal (retainer of a vassal) of the Satake Kita family, he was promoted to a direct vassal of the clan.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;Before that&quot; to &quot;Up until that time&quot; for &quot;それまで&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since up until that time Naotake had been a vassal (retainer of a vassal) of the Northern House of the Satake clan, this appointment promoted him to a direct vassal of the main clan.</e>
<cmt>佐竹北家　表現を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>江戸寄寓中の1774年、直武は『解体新書』の挿画を描いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he was staying at Edo for a while in 1774, Naotake drew paintings for &quot;Kaitai Shinsho (New Text on Anatomy)&quot; and also copied Western books such as &quot;Dobutsu Zufu (Zoological Encyclopedia)&quot; written by Jonston to learn the technique of three-dimensional effect by shadowing on painting animals such as lion, snake, horse which had been stereotyped in Oriental paintings and he painted &apos;Toeizan Shinobazu no Ike Zu&apos; (important cultural property), &apos;Totaiso Kacho Sansui Zu&apos; (important cultural property at Akita Museum of Modern Art), &apos;Totaiso Zu&apos; (at Akita Senshu Museum of Art), &apos;Enoshima Zu&apos; (at The Museum Yamato Bunkakan) and also it is said that he taught the techniques to Kokan SHIBA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During his stay in Edo in 1774, Naotake drew paintings for &quot;Kaitai Shinsho&quot; (New Text on Anatomy). He also copied Western books, including Jonston&apos;s &quot;Dobutsu Zufu&quot; (Zoological Encyclopedia) in order to learn techniques of drawing in three dimensions by using shadow effects. Animals he painted included lions, snakes and horses, which had been a stereotype of Oriental paintings. His paintings include &quot;Toeizan Shinobazu no Ike Zu&quot; (now deemed important cultural property), &quot;Totaiso Kacho Sansui Zu&quot; (important cultural property at the Akita Museum of Modern Art), &quot;Totaiso Zu&quot; (at the Akita Senshu Museum of Art) and &quot;Enoshima Zu&quot; (at the Museum of Yamato Bunkakan). It is also said that Naotake taught his techniques to Kokan SHIBA.</e>
<cmt>split into five sentences…; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During his stay in Edo in 1774, Naotake drew paintings for &quot;Kaitai Shinsho&quot; (New Text on Anatomy).</e>
<cmt>セルを三つに分け、英文のそのように変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>また、ヨンストン著『動物図譜』などの洋書を模写することによって、従来の東洋画では定型化されていた獅子やヘビ、ウマなどの動物表現についても、陰影をつけて立体感をあらわす方法を学んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, by copying Western books including Jonston&apos;s &quot;Dobutsu Zufu&quot; (Zoological Encyclopedia), he learned techniques of drawing animals such as lions, snakes and horses, which had been a stereotype of Oriental paintings, in three dimensions by using shadow effects.</e>
<cmt>セルを分けたことに伴い、翻訳を一部変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>「東叡山不忍池図」（重要文化財）、「唐太宗・花鳥山水図」（重要文化財、秋田県立近代美術館所蔵）、「唐太宗図」（秋田市立千秋美術館所蔵）、「江ノ島図」（大和文華館所蔵）などを描くとともに、司馬江漢にも技法を伝授したといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His paintings include &apos;Toeizan Shinobazu no Ike Zu&apos; (A View of Shinobazuno-ike Pond in Toeizan) (an important cultural property), &apos;Totaiso Kacho Sansui Zu&apos; (Totaiso [a Chinese emperor] and a View of Flowers, Birds, Hills, and Water) (an important cultural property at the Akita Museum of Modern Art), &apos;Totaiso Zu&apos; (a painting of Totaiso, a Chinese emperor) (at the Akita Senshu Museum of Art) and &apos;Enoshima Zu&apos; (A View of Enoshima) (at the Museum of Yamato Bunkakan), and it is also said that Naotake taught his techniques to Kokan SHIBA.</e>
<cmt>セルを分けたことに伴い、翻訳を一部変更しました。&quot; → &apos;　としました。作品名の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="23">
<j>直武の絵画における弟子としては、蘭癖大名として知られる熊本藩主細川重賢とも交流のあった藩主佐竹曙山、北家当主（角館城代）佐竹義躬、藩士田代忠国・荻津勝孝・菅原寅吉、久保田藩御用絵師菅原虎三などがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naotake&apos;s disciples of painting were Shozan SATAKE, the Lord who was known as hot-tempered Lord and communicating with Shigekata HOSOKAWA, the Lord of the Kumamoto clan and Yoshimi SATAKE, the family head of Satake Kita family (the chief retainer of Kakunodate) and statesmen such as Tadakuni TASHIRO, Katsutaka OGITSU, Torakichi SUGAWARA and TORAZO Sugawara, a painter of the Kubota clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shozan SATAKE, a feudal lord known for his hot temper and for his association with the lord of the Kumamoto clan Shigakata HOSOKAWA, Yoshimi SATAKE, the family head of the Satake Kita family (the chief retainer of Kakunodate), as well as statesmen including Tadakuni TASHIRO, Katsutaka OGITSU, Torakichi SUGAWARA and TORAZO Sugawara, a painter of the Kubota clan, were all among Naotake&apos;s painting disciples.</e>
<cmt>since the list of names involves long descriptions in two two cases, it seemed the only way to make it work was to put &quot;among Naotake&apos;s painting disciples&quot; at the very end</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shozan SATAKE, a feudal lord known for his association with the lord of the Kumamoto clan Shigekata HOSOKAWA who was known for his hot temper, Yoshimi SATAKE, the family head of the Northern House of the Satake clan (the Keeper of Kakunodate-jo Castle), as well as statesmen including Tadakuni TASHIRO, Katsutaka OGITSU, Torakichi SUGAWARA and Torazo SUGAWARA, a painter of the Kubota clan, were all among Naotake&apos;s painting disciples.</e>
<cmt>北家→佐竹北家　と解釈し、Northern House of the Satake clan　としました。角館城代→the Keeper of Kakunodate-jo Castle　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>秋田蘭画は、君臣間の一種のサロン的雰囲気のなかで広まっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akita Ranga became popular in a kind of salon atmosphere among the lords and vassals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akita Ranga became popular in a kind of salon atmosphere among the lords and vassals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akita Ranga became popular in a kind of salon atmosphere among the lords and vassals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="25">
<j>特に曙山は平賀源内や薩摩藩主島津重豪から絶賛されるほどの画才にめぐまれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially Shozan was highly praised by Gennai HIRAGA and Shigehide SHIMAZU, the Lord of the Satsuma clan for his painting talent and painted &apos;Matsu ni Karadori Zu&apos; (important cultural property at private collection), &apos;Kakitsubata ni Hasami Zu&apos; (at Kobe City Museum), &apos;Take ni Buncho Zu&apos; (at Akita Senshu Museum of Art), &apos;Kozan Hukei Zu&apos; and also wrote the first theory of Western painting in Japan such as &quot;Gaho Koryo (Summary of Painting Laws)&quot; and &quot;Gazu Rikai (Understanding of Painting)&quot; in September, 1778, which became the theoretical prop of Akita Ranga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shozan in particular was highly praised by Gennai HIRAGA and the lord of the Satsuma clan Shigehide SHIMAZU for his painting talent. Shozan&apos;s paintings include &quot;Matsu ni Karadori Zu&quot; (important cultural property in a private collection), &quot;Kakitsubata ni Hasami Zu&quot; (at Kobe City Museum), &quot;Take ni Buncho Zu&quot; (at Akita Senshu Museum of Art), and &quot;Kozan Hukei Zu.&quot; In addition, he also wrote the first books on theories of Western-style painting in Japan, such as &quot;Gaho Koryo&quot; (Summary of Painting Laws) and &quot;Gazu Rikai&quot; (Understanding Painting) in September of 1778. These books became the theoretical fulcrum point of Akita Ranga.</e>
<cmt>split into four sentences; changed &quot;prop&quot; to &quot;fulcrum point&quot; for &quot;支柱&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shozan in particular was highly praised by Gennai HIRAGA and the lord of the Satsuma clan Shigehide SHIMAZU for his painting talent.</e>
<cmt>セルを三つに分け、英文のそのように変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>曙山の作品として、「松に唐鳥図」（重要文化財、個人蔵）、「燕子花にハサミ図」（神戸市立博物館所蔵）、「竹に文鳥図」（秋田市立千秋美術館所蔵）、「湖山風景図」などの絵画がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shozan&apos;s paintings include &apos;Matsu ni Karadori Zu&apos; (A Painting of Foreign-bred Bird on Pine) (an important cultural property in a private collection), &apos;Kakitsubata ni Hasami Zu&apos; (A Painting of Rabbit-ear Iris and Scissors) (at Kobe City Museum), &apos;Take ni Buncho Zu&apos; (A Painting of a Paddy Bird on a Bamboo) (at Akita Senshu Museum of Art), and &apos;Kozan Fukei Zu&apos; (A View of a Mountain and a Lake).</e>
<cmt>セルを三つに分け、英文のそのように変更しました。作品名　補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>そのほかに1778年9月『画法綱領』、『画図理解』という日本最初の西洋画論ともいえる理論書を執筆しており、これは秋田蘭画の理論的支柱となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, he also wrote the first books on theories of Western-style painting in Japan, such as &quot;Gaho Koryo&quot; (Summary of Painting Laws) and &quot;Gazu Rikai&quot; (Understanding Painting) in September of 1778, which became the theoretical fulcrum point of Akita Ranga.</e>
<cmt>セルを三つに分け、英文のそのように変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>また、膨大な数のスケッチを『佐竹曙山写生帖』（秋田市立千秋美術館所蔵）に収めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also included his enormous numbers of sketches in &quot;Satake Shozan Shaseicho&quot; (at Akita Senshu Museum of Art).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An enormous amount of his sketches were dedicated in &quot;Satake Shozan Shaseicho&quot; (at Akita Senshu Museum of Art).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;included&quot; to &quot;dedicated&quot; for &quot;収めている&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An enormous amount of his sketches were dedicated in &quot;Satake Shozan Shaseicho&quot; (at Akita Senshu Museum of Art).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="29">
<j>ところが、安永8年（1779年）の末に、直武は突然謹慎を申し渡され、翌年5月には死去してしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, at the end of 1779, Naotake was suddenly ordered to refrain from making public appearances and in May, the next year he died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of 1779, however, Naotake was suddenly ordered to refrain from making public appearances and died in June of the following year (安永9年5月).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;May&quot; to &quot;June&quot; in accordance with &lt;http://maechan.net/kanreki/&gt; and added Japanese date in parenthesis; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of 1779, however, Naotake was suddenly ordered to refrain from making public appearances and died in June of the following year.</e>
<cmt>安永9年5月　削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>源内の刃傷事件との関係を指摘する説もあるが、詳細は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some people say that there was a relationship with the affair involving bloodshed by Gennai, but the detail is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an additional theory indicating an incident of bloodshed involving Gennai but the details are unknown.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;Some people say&quot; to &quot;There is an additional theory&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an additional theory indicating an incident of bloodshed involving Gennai but the details are unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>それから5年後に曙山も亡くなると、秋田蘭画は下火となり、しだいに廃れたが、同画の系統・画流は司馬江漢に受けつがれ、さらに洋風化して須賀川の亜欧堂田善にも影響をおよぼしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Shozan also died 5 years later, Akita Ranga became not very popular any longer and out of use gradually, but the lineage and style were inherited to Kokan SHIBA and westernized further and affected Denzen AODO from Sukagawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Shozan died five years later, Akita Ranga lost its popularity and gradually fell out of practice. However, its lineage and style were inherited by Kokan SHIBA, becoming further westernized and also came to have an influence on Denzen AODO from Sukagawa.</e>
<cmt>split into two sentences for easier reading and fixed grammar accordingly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Shozan died five years later, Akita Ranga lost its popularity and gradually fell out of practice; however, its lineage and style were inherited by Kokan SHIBA, becoming further westernized and also came to have an influence on Denzen AODO from Sukagawa.</e>
<cmt>一文につなげました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>秋田蘭画の紹介</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Introduction of Akita Ranga</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Introduction of Akita Ranga</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Introduction of Akita Ranga</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="32">
<j>秋田蘭画を広く世に紹介した人物として、直武と同郷の日本画家で明治末年頃から昭和初期にかけて活躍した平福百穂がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The one who brought Akita Ranga to a wide audience was Hyakusui HIRAFUKU, a Japanese-style painter from the same prefecture as Naotake and he played an active role from the end of Maiji period to the early Showa period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The person to bring Akita Ranga to a wide audience was Hyakusui HIRAFUKU. He was a Japanese-style painter from the same prefecture as Naotake and had great success from the end of the Meiji period to the early Showa period.</e>
<cmt>Maiji→Meiji; split into two sentences for easier reading; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The person to bring Akita Ranga to a wide audience was Hyakusui HIRAFUKU, who was a Japanese-style painter from the same prefecture as Naotake and had great success from the end of the Meiji period to the early Showa period.</e>
<cmt>一文につなげました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>1930年（昭和5年）、百穂は『日本洋画曙光』という大型版画集のなかで秋田蘭画を紹介している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1930 Hyakusui introduced Akita Ranga in a large-paper edition of art collection book, &quot;Nihon Yoga Shoko (dawn of Japanese and Western paintings)&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1930, Hyakusui introduced Akita Ranga with a large paper edition of an art collection book called &quot;Nihon Yogo Shoko&quot; (The Dawn of Japanese and Western Paintings).</e>
<cmt>added comma after year; eliminated hyphen between &quot;large-paper&quot;; fixed grammar; moved quotation marks to not include the description in parenthesis; capitalized English title</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1930, Hyakusui introduced Akita Ranga with a large paper edition of an art collection book called &quot;Nihon Yoga Shoko&quot; (The Dawn of Japanese and Western Paintings).</e>
<cmt>Yogo →Yoga に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>また、百穂はアララギ派の歌人でもあり、以下の短歌7首を詠んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hyakusui was also a poet of Araragi school and wrote 7 tankas as follows;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hyakusui was also a poet of the Araragi School and wrote the following seven tanka.</e>
<cmt>changed semi-colon to a period; capitalized &quot;School&quot;; changed &quot;7&quot; to &quot;seven&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hyakusui was also a poet of the Araragi School and wrote the following seven tanka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="35">
<j>みちのくの　出羽の太守と 生れけむ　この君にして　描ける　阿蘭陀絵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You were born as the Lord of Dewa in Michinoku, that&apos;s why you can paint Dutch painting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You were born as the Lord of Dewa in Michinoku, that&apos;s why you can paint Dutch paintings.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;painting&quot; to &quot;paintings&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You were born as the Lord of Dewa in Michinoku, that&apos;s why you can paint Dutch paintings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>この君の　ゑがきける絵は　おほらかなり　蘭法にならひ　吾が国ぶりの絵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The paintings of the Lord are magnanimous with the Dutch techniques and Japanese style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The paintings of the Lord are magnanimous with Dutch techniques and Japanese style.</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Dutch&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The paintings of the Lord are magnanimous with Dutch techniques and Japanese style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>丹念に　ゑがきける絵に　落款の　曙山と大きく　おらんだ文字の印</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This carefully painted picture has the artist&apos;s signature and seal of Shozan in Dutch letters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This carefully painted picture has the artist&apos;s signature and seal of Shozan in Dutch letters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This carefully painted picture has the artist&apos;s signature and seal of Shozan in Dutch letters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>いちはやく　おらんだぶりを　画（えが）きしは　吾が郷人（くにびと）よ　小田野直武</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The one who adopted Dutch style painting first was my countryman, Naotake ODANO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The one who adopted Dutch style painting first was my countryman, Naotake ODANO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The one who adopted Dutch style painting first was my countryman, Naotake ODANO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>明暗を　とりてゑがける　ふりにし絵　珍笑（うづゑ）ましもよ　そのおらんだぶり</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The painting is realistic with contrast between light and shadow and the Dutch style makes me laugh on the value.</e>
<cmt>不明：「ふりにし絵」と「珍笑（うづゑ）ましもよ」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The painting is realistic with its contrast between light and shadow; the value of Dutch style makes me laugh.</e>
<cmt>added semi-colon to separate seemingly different thoughts; moved the location of &quot;the value&quot; to the middle of the sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The painting is realistic with its contrast between light and shadow; the value of Dutch style makes me laugh.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>細密（こまごま）に　ゑがきたる絵は　真白なる　兎に笹の　かげをおとせる</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The painting is so detailed that it can be seen shadows of arrow bamboo on the white rabbit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The painting is so detailed that the shadows of arrow bamboo can be seen on the white rabbit.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more grammatically</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The painting is so detailed that the shadows of arrow bamboo can be seen on the white rabbit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>壮（わか）くして　逝きにし人の　阿蘭陀絵は　世に稀なれや　くりかへしみつ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Dutch-style painting of the one who died at an early age is rare in the world and I&apos;m looking at it repeatedly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Dutch-style painting made by one who died at an early age is rare in this world and I look at it repeatedly.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more grammatically</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Dutch-style painting made by one who died at an early age is rare in this world and I look at it repeatedly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 663highland(id:18755), Point136(id:211299), Opponent(id:720), Straysheep(id:42448), Greenland4(id:114494), Law soma(id:45202), アト(id:193073), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>