<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>京都大学吉田寮</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshida dormitory of Kyoto University</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshida dormitory of Kyoto University</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshida dormitory of Kyoto University</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>京都大学学生寄宿舎吉田寮（きょうとだいがくがくせいきしゅくしゃよしだりょう）とは、京都大学の寄宿舎のひとつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshida dormitory of Kyoto University is one of Kyoto University&apos;s dormitories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshida dormitory of Kyoto University is one of Kyoto University&apos;s dormitories.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshida dormitory of Kyoto University is one of Kyoto University&apos;s dormitories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>木構造 (建築)二階建（三棟）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are three two-storied woodon buildings. (construction) (three buildings)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are three two-storied wooden buildings (construction) (three buildings).</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are three two-storied wooden buildings (construction) (three buildings).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>日本四大自治寮のひとつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of the four major autonomous student dormitories in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is one of the four major autonomous student dormitories in Japan.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is one of the four major autonomous student dormitories in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>施設の概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Facilities</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Facilities</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Facilities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>吉田寮は本学吉田キャンパス吉田南構内と隣接している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshida dormitory is adjacent to Yoshida-minami campus of Kyoto University&apos; Yoshida campus.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshida dormitory is adjacent to Yoshida-minami campus of Kyoto University Yoshida campus.</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshida dormitory is adjacent to Yoshida-minami campus of Kyoto University Yoshida campus.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>本寮は、北寮・中寮・南寮の三棟がE字型に並ぶ配置をしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dormitory consists of three buildings, the north building, the center building and the south building, and they are placed in E-shape.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dormitory consists of three buildings, the north building, the center building and the south building, and they are placed in an E-shape.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dormitory consists of three buildings, the north building, the center building and the south building, and they are placed in an E-shape.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>各棟2階建てでそれぞれ約40部屋（和室8畳～10畳26室、和室6畳～7.5畳95室）ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each one is a two-storied building with about forty rooms (26 Japanese-style rooms of 8 - 10 mats (about 14 ㎡-18㎡)) and 95 Japanese-style rooms of 6-7.5 mats (about 11㎡ - 13 ㎡))</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each one is a two-storied building with about forty rooms (26 Japanese-style rooms of 8 - 10 mats (about 14m2-18m2)) and 95 Japanese-style rooms of 6-7.5 mats (about 11m2 - 13m2)).</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each one is a two-storied building with about forty rooms (26 Japanese-style rooms of 8 - 10 mats [about 14 -18 square meters]) and 95 Japanese-style rooms of 6 - 7.5 mats [about 11 - 13 square meters]).</e>
<cmt>m2→square meters としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>この他の施設は、管理棟、居住スペースとして使われているプレハブ、洗濯場、シャワー室、旧食堂などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are other facilities such as an administration building, a pre-fabricated building which is being used for living space, a laundry, a shower room and a former dining room etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are other facilities such as an administration building, a pre-fabricated building which is being used for living space, laundry, a shower room and a former dining room etc.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are other facilities such as an administration building, a pre-fabricated building which is being used for living space, laundry, a shower room and a former dining room etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>寄宿料は「京都大学における学生納付金に関する規程（平成16年達示第63号）」により、月額400円と定められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monthly boarding fee is \400 based on &quot; Regulation on the payments of the students of Kyoto University (Instruction No.63 issued in 2006)&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Monthly boarding fee is \400 based on &quot;Regulation on the payments of the students of Kyoto University (Instruction No. 63 issued in 2006)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Monthly boarding fee is 400 yen based on &apos;Regulation on the payments of the students of Kyoto University (Instruction No. 63 issued in 2006).&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>なお、寄宿料のほか、水道光熱費、自治会費を別途徴収する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to a boarding fee, students should pay utilities expenses and a membership fee of dormitory council.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to a boarding fee, students pay utility expenses and a membership fee for dormitory council.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to a boarding fee, students pay utility expenses and a membership fee for dormitory council.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief history</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>他記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>竣工は1913年（大正2年）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dormitory was constructed in 1913.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dormitory was constructed in 1913.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dormitory was constructed in 1913.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>旧制第三高等学校 (旧制)の学生寄宿舎の廃材を利用して建設された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was constructed using scrap wood of the dormitory of former Third High School.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was constructed using scrap wood of the dormitory of the former Third High School.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was constructed using scrap wood of the dormitory of the former Third High School.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>木造2階建てで、北寮、中寮、南寮と呼ばれる3棟および関連施設からなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It consists of three two-storied wooden buildings, which are called the north building, the center building and the south building respectively, and other related facilities.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It consists of three two-storied wooden buildings, which are called the north building, the center building and the south building respectively, and other related facilities.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It consists of three two-storied wooden buildings, which are called the north building, the center building and the south building respectively, and other related facilities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>東京大学駒場寮が閉寮した現在、現存する最古の大学寄宿舎である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, it is the oldest existent university&apos;s dormitory since Komaba dormitory of Tokyo University was already abolished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present, it is the oldest existing university dormitory since Komaba dormitory of Tokyo University was already abolished.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present, it is the oldest existing university dormitory since Komaba dormitory of Tokyo University was already abolished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>1897年（明治30年）の京都大学創立当時から、学生寄宿舎が設けられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a student domitory at the time when Kyoto University was established in 1897.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a student dormitory at the time when Kyoto University was established in 1897.</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a student dormitory at the time when Kyoto University was established in 1897.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>翌1898年（同31年）、1889年（同22年）竣工の（旧制）第三高等学校の学生寄宿舎が譲り受けられ、1913年にその材木を再利用して現在の吉田寮が建築された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto University took over in 1898 the dormitory of former Third High School, which was constructed in 1889, and newly constructed existent Yoshida dormitory using its scrap wood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto University took over in 1898 the dormitory of the former Third High School, which was constructed in 1889, and the newly constructed existing Yoshida dormitory using its scrap wood.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto University took over in 1898 the dormitory of the former Third High School, which was constructed in 1889, and newly constructed the existing Yoshida dormitory in 1913 using its scrap wood.</e>
<cmt>文法を一部修正しました。1913 を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>1941年（昭和16年）に中寮の一部を焼失したが、すぐに再建された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the center building was burned down in 1941, it was reconstructed soon after.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the center building was burned down in 1941, it was reconstructed soon after.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the center building was burned down in 1941, it was reconstructed soon after.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>1959年（昭和34年）、60年には民間の労働者寄宿舎が本学の学生寄宿舎に転用され、従来からの建物が吉田東寮、転用された建物が吉田西寮と呼ばれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1959 and 1960, a dormitory for private workers was converted to the dormitory of Kyoto University, and then- existing building and newly converted building were called Yoshida East dormitory and Yoshida West dormitory respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1959 and 1960, a dormitory for private workers was converted to a dormitory of Kyoto University, and the then- existing building and newly converted building were called Yoshida East dormitory and Yoshida West dormitory respectively.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1959 and 1960, a dormitory for private workers was converted to a dormitory of Kyoto University, and the then- existing building and newly converted building were called Yoshida East dormitory and Yoshida West dormitory respectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="18">
<j>国立大学の寄宿舎・学生寮を廃止する全国的な流れの中で、薬学部構内にあった吉田西寮は取り壊された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshida West dormitory, which was located inside the pharmaceutical department&apos;s campus, was abolished in keeping with the national tendency to abolish national universities&apos; dormitories.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshida West dormitory, which was located inside the pharmaceutical department&apos;s campus, was abolished in keeping with the national tendency to abolish national universities&apos; dormitories.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshida West dormitory, which was located inside the pharmaceutical department&apos;s campus, was abolished in keeping with the national tendency to abolish national universities&apos; dormitories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>一方、学生らの反対運動（後述）により吉田東寮は現在でも存続し、京大生とその家族など約180名が生活している（京都大学の定める定員は147名）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Yoshida East dormitory has continued to exist up to the present thanks to the opposition movement conducted by the students of the time (to be mentioned later), and about 180 persons, including the students of Kyoto University as well as their families, are living in the dormitory (pre-fixed number of personnel determined by Kyoto University is 147).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Yoshida East dormitory has continued to exist until the present thanks to the opposition movement conducted by the students of the time (to be mentioned later), and about 180 persons, including the students of Kyoto University as well as their families, are living in the dormitory (the predetermined number of personnel determined by Kyoto University is 147).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Yoshida East dormitory has continued to exist until the present thanks to the opposition movement conducted by the students of the time (to be mentioned later), and about 180 persons, including the students of Kyoto University as well as their families, are living in the dormitory (the predetermined number of personnel determined by Kyoto University is 147).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>吉田東寮は単に「吉田寮」と改称され、現在に至っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshida East dormitory was renamed &quot;Yoshida dormitory&quot; and has continued to exist up to the present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshida East dormitory was renamed &quot;Yoshida dormitory&quot; and has continued to exist up to the present.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshida East dormitory was renamed &apos;Yoshida dormitory&apos; and has continued to exist up to the present.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="21">
<j>1996年（平成8年）10月31日、近接していた学生集会所（サークル棟）向かいの建物からの失火が原因とされる火災で旧食堂の西側を焼失した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 31, 1966, west side of the former dining room was burnt down due to an accidental fire occurred in the building situated on the opposite of student meeting place (building for club activities).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 31, 1966, the west side of the former dining room was burnt down due to an accidental fire occurring in the building situated on the opposite of the student meeting place (building for club activities).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 31, 1996, the west side of the former dining room was burnt down due to an accidental fire occurring in the building situated on the opposite of the student meeting place (building for club activities).</e>
<cmt>1996に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>一時は老朽化を理由に停止していたが、現在焼け残った旧食堂は吉田寮の各種催・ライブ・演劇などのイベント会場としての貸し出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former dining room was once closed because it became too old, but currently it is now used for the place for various events of Yoshida dormitory as well as concerts or theatrical performances.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former dining room was once closed because it became too old, but currently it is now used as a place for various events of the Yoshida dormitory as well as concerts or theatrical performances.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former dining room was once closed because it became too old, but currently it is now used as a place for various events of the Yoshida dormitory as well as concerts or theatrical performances.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="23">
<j>2007年1月16日未明、近接する学生集会所の1階からぼやが発生し、階段下の収納庫付近2平方メートルが焼けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A small fire started at dawn on 16 January 2007 on the first floor of the adjacent student meeting building and 2㎡ of shed situated under the staircase burned due to this fire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A small fire started at dawn on January 16, 2007 on the first floor of the adjacent student meeting building and 2m2 of shed situated under the staircase burned due to this fire.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A small fire started at dawn on January 16, 2007 on the first floor of the adjacent student meeting building and two square meters of shed situated under the staircase burned due to this fire.</e>
<cmt>two square meters としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>サークル関係者と吉田寮の寮生らが初期消火を行い、消防車が到着してから火は20分ほどで消しとめられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People of club activities as well as the students of Yoshida dormitory engaged in the initial firefighting activities and a fire was put out within 20 minutes after the arrival of fire engines.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People of club activities as well as the students of Yoshida dormitory engaged in the initial firefighting activities and the fire was put out within 20 minutes after the arrival of fire engines.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People of club activities as well as the students of Yoshida dormitory engaged in the initial firefighting activities and the fire was put out within 20 minutes after the arrival of fire engines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>けが人は出なかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were no causalities.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were no causalities.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were no causalities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="26">
<j>2009年4月25日、産経新聞紙上で松本紘総長が「寮自治会と建て替えに向けた話し合いを開始した」と公表。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 25, 2009, the president of Kyoto University Hiroshi MATSUMOTO announced on the Sankei Shimbun saying &quot;the university started a consultation with the dormitory council concerning the reconstruction of Yoshida dormitory&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 25, 2009, the president of Kyoto University Hiroshi MATSUMOTO announced in the Sankei Shimbun saying &quot;the university started a consultation with the dormitory council concerning the reconstruction of Yoshida dormitory.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 25, 2009, the president of Kyoto University Hiroshi MATSUMOTO announced in the Sankei Shimbun saying &apos;the university started a consultation with the dormitory council concerning the reconstruction of Yoshida dormitory.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>閉寮反対運動</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The opposition movement against the clousure of dormitory</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The opposition movement against the closure of dormitory</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The opposition movement against the closure of dormitory</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="27">
<j>京都大学では1970年代になって全国的に学生運動が退潮期に入っても、なお学生寮（自治寮）や一部の学部自治会、京都大学西部講堂などを拠点として運動が一定の勢力を保ち続け、「日本のガラパゴス」と呼ばれる状況を呈していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1970&apos;s when student movements declined around the nation, student movements at Kyoto university were still active using dormitories (autonomous dormitories), some college councils and the west auditorium of Kyoto university as the base of their activity, and such situation was dubbed &quot;Japanese Galapagos&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the 1970&apos;s when student movements declined around the nation, student movements at Kyoto university were still active using dormitories (autonomous dormitories), some college councils and the west auditorium of Kyoto university as the base of their activity, and such situations were dubbed &quot;Japanese Galapagos.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the 1970&apos;s when student movements declined around the nation, student movements at Kyoto University were still active using dormitories (autonomous dormitories), some college councils and the west auditorium of Kyoto University as the base of their activity, and such situations were dubbed &apos;Japanese Galapagos.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。Kyoto University としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="28">
<j>京大当局は70年代後半になってこれらの運動基盤の解体に着手した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the late 70&apos;s, the authority of Kyoto university stated to destroy such bases of movements.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the late 70&apos;s, the authority of Kyoto university stated to destroy such bases of movements.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the late 70&apos;s, the authority of Kyoto University stated to destroy such bases of movements.</e>
<cmt>Kyoto University としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>1977年（昭和52年）の「竹本処分」強行を経て、沢田敏男総長時代には吉田寮など学生寮の閉鎖に向け「学生寮の正常化」政策を進めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After forcing through &quot;Takemoto shobun&quot; (dismissal of associate professor Takemoto) in 1977, the president Toshio SAWADA implemented the policy of &quot;normalization of student dormitories&quot; with the aim of abolishing student dormitories including Yoshida dormitory.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After forcing through &quot;Takemoto shobun&quot; (dismissal of associate professor Takemoto) in 1977, the president Toshio SAWADA implemented the policy of &quot;normalization of student dormitories&quot; with the aim of abolishing student dormitories including Yoshida dormitory.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After forcing through &apos;Takemoto shobun&apos; (dismissal of associate professor Takemoto) in 1977, the president Toshio SAWADA implemented the policy of &apos;normalization of student dormitories&apos; with the aim of abolishing student dormitories including Yoshida dormitory.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="30">
<j>そして1982年12月、寮生側との協議や意見聴取などのないまま、評議会によって「吉田寮の在寮期限を昭和61年3月31日とする」（原文ママ）との決定がなされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December 1982, the university council decided, without consultation with the members of dormitory or hearing their opinions, that &quot;the time limit for staying at Yoshida dormitory is March 31, 1986&quot; (so in original).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December 1982, the university council decided, without consultation with the members of the dormitory or hearing their opinions, that &quot;the time limit for staying at Yoshida dormitory is March 31, 1986&quot; (so in original).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December 1982, the university council decided, without consultation with the members of the dormitory or hearing their opinions, that &apos;the time limit for staying at Yoshida dormitory is March 31, 1986&apos; (so in original).</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>これに対し、在寮生で構成する吉田寮自治会を中心に卒寮生も含めた廃寮反対運動が高まり、自主入寮選考の成功で寮生数は減少するどころか増加した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the rise in the opposition movement against the above decision conducted by the council of Yoshida dormitory and the graduates, however, the number of dormitory residents increased, instead of decrease, thanks to the success of autonomous selection of residents.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the rise in the opposition movement against the above decision conducted by the council of Yoshida dormitory and the graduates, however, the number of dormitory residents increased, instead of decreased, thanks to the success of autonomous selection of residents.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the rise in the opposition movement against the above decision conducted by the council of Yoshida dormitory and the graduates, however, the number of dormitory residents increased, instead of decreased, thanks to the success of autonomous selection of residents.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>そのため、「在寮期限」到来時には多数の寮生が居住するという事態に至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, many students still lived in the dormitory at the time of the above &quot;time limit&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, many students still lived in the dormitory at the time of the above &quot;time limit.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, many students still lived in the dormitory at the time of the above &apos;time limit.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>その一方で教養部自治会のように大学側の主張に同意する自治会が現れるなど、一時は思想や運動方針の相違に起因する自治会同士の対立も発生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the meantime, some councils, such as the council of the department of liberal art, conceded the decision of the university, and confrontation among councils arising from the difference in philosophy or policy for movements also became apparent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the meantime, some councils, such as the council of the department of liberal arts, conceded the decision of the university, and confrontation among councils arising from differences in philosophy or policy for movements also became apparent.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the meantime, some councils, such as the council of the department of liberal arts, conceded the decision of the university, and confrontation among councils arising from differences in philosophy or policy for movements also became apparent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="34">
<j>西島安則総長時代の1989年（平成元年）春、京大当局（河合隼雄学生部長）と吉田寮自治会の間で合意が成立し、西寮の取り壊しなどと引き換えに事実上「在寮期限」は撤廃さた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1989 when Yasunori NISHIJIMA was the president, the authority of Kyoto university (dean of students Hayao KAWAI) and the council of Yoshida dormitory agreed to demolish the west building in exchange for the abolition of &quot;time limit&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1989 when Yasunori NISHIJIMA was the president, the authority of Kyoto university (dean of students Hayao KAWAI) and the council of Yoshida dormitory agreed to demolish the west building in exchange for the abolition of the &quot;time limit.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1989 when Yasunori NISHIJIMA was the president, the authority of Kyoto University (dean of students Hayao KAWAI) and the council of Yoshida dormitory agreed to demolish the west building in exchange for the abolition of the &apos;time limit.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。Kyoto University としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>その結果、吉田寮はその後も京都大学の学生寮として存続することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Yoshida dormitory has since continued to exist as the student dormitory of Kyoto University.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Yoshida dormitory has since continued to exist as the student dormitory of Kyoto University.</e>
<cmt>Spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Yoshida dormitory has since continued to exist as the student dormitory of Kyoto University.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>新寮建て替え問題</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Construction of new dormitory</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Construction of a new dormitory</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Construction of a new dormitory</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="36">
<j>1995年（平成7年）の阪神・淡路大震災を経て、近年本寮の耐久性、耐震性について学内外から疑問を持たれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Great Hanshin-Awaji Earthquake occurred in 1995, questions have been raised from the people both inside and outside of the university about the durability and quake resistance of the dormitory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Great Hanshin-Awaji Earthquake occurred in 1995, questions have been raised from the people both inside and outside of the university about the durability and quake resistance of the dormitory.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Great Hanshin-Awaji Earthquake occurred in 1995, questions have been raised from the people both inside and outside of the university about the durability and quake resistance of the dormitory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>そこで、2005年（平成17年）には本寮の耐震調査の予算が承認され、外部の有識者による耐震調査が断続的に行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A budget for seismic-resistance evaluation was approved in 2005 and the evaluations were conducted by outside experts intermittently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A budget for seismic-resistance evaluation was approved in 2005 and the evaluations were conducted by outside experts intermittently.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A budget for seismic-resistance evaluation was approved in 2005 and the evaluations were conducted by outside experts intermittently.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="38">
<j>2006年（平成18年）、本寮の存続に関わる大きな動きが起こる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An important movement concerning the continued existence of the dormitory occurred in 2006.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An important movement concerning the continued existence of the dormitory occurred in 2006.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An important movement concerning the continued existence of the dormitory occurred in 2006.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="39">
<j>2月、吉田寮執行部は前年の耐震調査の結果を踏まえ、2006年度の総長裁量予算枠に吉田寮食堂の補修を申請する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on the results of seismic-resistance evaluation conducted in the previous year, executives of Yoshida dormitory requested in February to include the renovation cost of dormitory&apos;s dining room in the presidential discretionary budget of 2006.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on the results of seismic-resistance evaluation conducted in the previous year, executives of Yoshida dormitory requested in February to include the renovation cost of dormitory&apos;s dining room in the presidential discretionary budget of 2006.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on the results of seismic-resistance evaluation conducted in the previous year, executives of Yoshida dormitory requested in February to include the renovation cost of dormitory&apos;s dining room in the presidential discretionary budget of the academic year 2006.</e>
<cmt>2006年度→the academic year 2006としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>しかし6月になってその申請が却下されていることが判明、執行部は他の予算による請求の道を模索した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June, however, it was revealed that this request was turned down and executives pursued other ways to secure a budget.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June, however, it was revealed that this request was turned down and executives pursued other ways to secure a budget.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June, however, it was revealed that this request was turned down and executives pursued other ways to secure a budget.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="41">
<j>8月、本学学生センターは「学生関連施設のための予算を獲得できるので、吉田寮の建て替え予算を申請しないか」という旨の提案を吉田寮に行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August, the student center of Kyoto Uuniversity made a proposal to the executives of Yoshida dormitory saying &quot;as we will be able to secure the budget for the improvement of students&apos; facilities, why don&apos;t you request the budget for reconstructing Yoshida dormitory ?&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August, the student center of Kyoto university made a proposal to the executives of Yoshida dormitory saying &quot;as we will be able to secure the budget for the improvement of students&apos; facilities, why don&apos;t you request the budget for reconstructing Yoshida dormitory?&quot;</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August, the student center of Kyoto University made a proposal to the executives of Yoshida dormitory saying &apos;as we will be able to secure the budget for the improvement of students&apos; facilities, why don&apos;t you request the budget for reconstructing Yoshida dormitory?&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。Kyoto University としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>この提案は吉田寮側の事情もあり一度は断られたが、学生センターはこの事案を実質水面下で進めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the above proposal was once declined by Yoshida dormitory, the student center pressed forward with this case behind the closed doors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the above proposal was once declined by Yoshida dormitory, the student center pressed forward with this case behind closed doors.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the above proposal was once declined by Yoshida dormitory, the student center pressed forward with this case behind closed doors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="43">
<j>9月末から10月上旬にかけて学生センター職員が二度にわたって吉田寮を訪問した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the end of September to early October, officers of the student center visited Yoshida dormitory twice.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the end of September to early October, officers of the student center visited Yoshida dormitory twice.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the end of September to early October, officers of the student center visited Yoshida dormitory twice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>その際、上記の建て替え予算案を提出する用意があり、吉田寮が立て替えを受諾するか否か、その回答期限が10月23日であると告げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In these meeting, they informed that the student center is prepared to submit the budget for reconstruction, and requested Yoshida dormitory to reply by October 23 whether or not it accepts the reconstruction.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In these meeting, they informed that the student center was prepared to submit the budget for reconstruction, and requested Yoshida dormitory to reply by October 23 whether or not it would accept the reconstruction.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In these meeting, they informed that the student center was prepared to submit the budget for reconstruction, and requested Yoshida dormitory to reply by October 23 whether or not it would accept the reconstruction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>これを受けて吉田寮では、受諾の可否とその際の交渉条件について昼夜議論がなされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshida dormitory&apos;s residents discussed by day and night about the pros and cons of the proposal as well as the conditions of negotiation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshida dormitory&apos;s residents discussed day and night about the pros and cons of the proposal as well as the conditions of the negotiation.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshida dormitory&apos;s residents discussed day and night about the pros and cons of the proposal as well as the conditions of the negotiation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="46">
<j>そして10月23日、学内において建て替え問題に関する団交が開かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A mass bargaining session on the problem of reconstruction was held on October 23.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A mass bargaining session on the problem of reconstruction was held on October 23.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A mass bargaining session on the problem of reconstruction was held on October 23.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>大学側からは責任者として東山紘久副学長以下数名、吉田寮側からは寮生・学生・利用者ら80人が出席した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">University vice-president Hirohisa HIGASHIYAMA, a responsible person, and other several officers attended as the representatives of the university and 80 persons, including the residents of dormitory, students and other users, attended as the people of Yoshida dormitory side.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">University vice-president Hirohisa HIGASHIYAMA, a responsible person, and several other officers attended as representatives of the university and 80 persons, including the residents of the dormitory, students, and other users, attended as people of the Yoshida dormitory side.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">University vice-president Hirohisa HIGASHIYAMA, a responsible person, and several other officers attended as representatives of the university and 80 persons, including the residents of the dormitory, students, and other users, attended as people of the Yoshida dormitory side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>2時間半に及ぶ交渉を行ったが結局合意が得られず、同年度における吉田寮建て替え予算の提出は見送られることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In spite of two and a half hours of negotiation, no agreements were reached and the submission of the budget for reconstruction of Yoshida dormitory in 2006 was given up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In spite of two and a half hours of negotiation, no agreements were reached and the submission of the budget for reconstruction of Yoshida dormitory in 2006 was not reached.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In spite of two and a half hours of negotiation, no agreements were reached and the submission of the budget for reconstruction of Yoshida dormitory in the academic year 2006 was not reached.</e>
<cmt>同年度　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="49">
<j>2008年10月1日、松本紘総長就任にともない、教育・学生・国際（教育） 担当の副学長として西村周三氏が就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the wake of the inauguration of Hiroshi MATSUMOTO as the president of Kyoto University, Shuzo NISHIMURA was appointed on October 1, 2008 to the vice-president in charge of education, student affairs and international affairs (education).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the wake of the inauguration of Hiroshi MATSUMOTO as the president of Kyoto University, Shuzo NISHIMURA was appointed on October 1, 2008 to the vice-president in charge of education, student affairs and international affairs (education).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the wake of the inauguration of Hiroshi MATSUMOTO as the president of Kyoto University, Shuzo NISHIMURA was appointed on October 1, 2008 to the vice-president in charge of education, student affairs and international affairs (education).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>その後行われた、寮自治会と大学当局との話し合いの場で、これまで得ていた確約の引き継ぎを求める寮自治会に対し、西村氏は吉田寮の早急な建て替えを提案する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a meeting in which the council of dormitory and the authority of university participated, Nishimura proposed to reconstruct Yoshida dormitory as soon as possible while the council of dormitory requested him to keep previous promise.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a meeting in which the council of the dormitory and the university authority participated, Nishimura proposed to reconstruct Yoshida dormitory as soon as possible while the council of the dormitory requested him to keep previous promises.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a meeting in which the council of the dormitory and the university authority participated, Nishimura proposed to reconstruct Yoshida dormitory as soon as possible while the council of the dormitory requested him to keep previous promises.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="51">
<j>2009年4月20日、大学当局は寮自治会に「吉田南最南部地区再整備・基本方針（案）」を提出。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 20, 2009, the authority of Kyoto University submitted to the council of dormitory &quot;the basic policy for the redevelopment of the southernmost area in Yoshida (draft)&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 20, 2009, the authority of Kyoto University submitted to the council of the dormitory &quot;the basic policy for the redevelopment of the southernmost area in Yoshida (draft).&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 20, 2009, the authority of Kyoto University submitted to the council of the dormitory &apos;the basic policy for the redevelopment of the southernmost area in Yoshida (draft).&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>4月24日には、大学当局が吉田寮の建て替えに関する基本方針についての説明会が開催され、吉田寮側からは60名ほどの参加者があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The authority of Kyoto University convened on April 24 a meeting to explain the basic policy for reconstruction and about 60 persons of Yoshida dormitory side participated in this meeting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The authority of Kyoto University convened on April 24 a meeting to explain the basic policy for reconstruction and about 60 persons of the Yoshida dormitory side participated in this meeting.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The authority of Kyoto University convened on April 24 a meeting to explain the basic policy for reconstruction and about 60 persons of the Yoshida dormitory side participated in this meeting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>入寮選考と入寮資格の拡大</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Selection for entering the dormitory and easing of the requirements for entering</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Selection for entering the dormitory and easing of the requirements for entering</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Selection for entering the dormitory and easing of the requirements for entering</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="53">
<j>吉田寮の入寮選考は吉田寮自治会によって行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Selection for entering the dormitory is conducted by the council of Yoshida dormitory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Selection for entering the dormitory is conducted by the council of Yoshida dormitory.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Selection for entering the dormitory is conducted by the council of Yoshida dormitory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>年に二度、春と秋に入寮選考期間が設けられ、自治会組織である「入寮選考委員会」が選考を担当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The period of selection is set twice a year in spring and in autumn and &quot;dormitory-entering selection committee&quot;, an organization of the council of dormitory, is in charge of selection.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The period of selection is set twice a year in spring and in autumn and a &quot;dormitory-entering selection committee,&quot; an organization of the council of the dormitory, is in charge of selection.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The period of selection is set twice a year in spring and in autumn and a &apos;dormitory-entering selection committee,&apos; an organization of the council of the dormitory, is in charge of selection.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="55">
<j>吉田寮では、前述の閉寮反対運動に関連して、入寮対象者を拡大していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshida dormitory has eased the requirements for entering as a part of the above-mentioned opposition movement against the closure of dormitory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshida dormitory has eased the requirements for entering as a part of the above-mentioned opposition movement against the closure of dormitory.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshida dormitory has eased the requirements for entering as a part of the above-mentioned opposition movement against the closure of dormitory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="56">
<j>1985年、それまでの男子学部学生のみという入寮資格を拡大し、女子学生の受け入れを開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it used to permit only male undergraduates to enter the dormitory, it started to accept female students from 1985.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it used to permit only male undergraduates to enter the dormitory, it started to accept female students from 1985.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it used to permit only male undergraduates to enter the dormitory, it started to accept female students from 1985.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="57">
<j>1990年度からは留学生の受け入れ、1991年度からは大学院生・聴講生・研究生・医療技術短期大学生（現在の医学部保健学科）を含めた全ての京大生を入寮募集の対象とするようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It started to accept foreign students from 1990, and from 1991, it started to allow all students of Kyoto University, including postgraduates, auditing students, junior college students of medical technology (health sciences course in the Medical department), to apply for entering the dormitory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It started to accept foreign students from 1990, and from 1991, it started to allow all students of Kyoto University, including postgraduates, auditing students, junior college students of medical technology (health sciences course in the Medical department), to apply for entering the dormitory.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It started to accept foreign students from the academic year 1990, and from the academic year 1991, it started to allow all students of Kyoto University, including graduate students, postgraduates, auditing students, junior college students of medical technology (health sciences course in the Medical department), to apply for entering the dormitory.</e>
<cmt>大学院生　を追加しました。年度　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="58">
<j>さらに1994年度、「京都大学学生との同居の切実な必要性」が認められる者（身障者とその介護者、親子、夫婦等）も入寮募集の対象となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, &quot;persons who keenly need to live with the students of Kyoto University&quot; (the handicapped and their support persons, parent and children, a couple etc.) were allowed to apply for entering the dormitory in 1994.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, &quot;persons who keenly need to live with the students of Kyoto University&quot; (the handicapped and their support persons, parent and children, a couple etc.) were allowed to apply for entering the dormitory in 1994.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, &apos;persons who keenly need to live with the students of Kyoto University&apos; (the handicapped and their support persons, parent and children, a couple etc.) were allowed to apply for entering the dormitory in the academic year 1994.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。年度　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="59">
<j>入寮資格の拡大に伴い、入寮希望者は増加し、近年の寮生数は京都大学の定める定員147名を大きく上回ることとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the number of applicants increased after the requirements for entering were eased, current number of residents far exceeds 147, the quota decided by Kyoto university.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the number of applicants increased after the requirements for entering were eased, the current number of residents far exceeds 147, the quota decided by Kyoto university.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the number of applicants increased after the requirements for entering were eased, the current number of residents far exceeds 147, the quota decided by Kyoto University.</e>
<cmt>Kyoto University としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>そのため、本来個室として運用されてきた部屋を相部屋にせざるを得なくなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, rooms originally used as an individual room are being shared by two persons now.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, rooms originally used as individual rooms are being shared by two persons now.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, rooms originally used as individual rooms are being shared by two persons now.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="61">
<j>ちなみに、京都大学寄宿舎規程によれば、「学部学生に限り入舎させる」（寄宿舎規程第3条）との記述がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, a description stating &quot;only undergraduates are allowed to enter a dormitory&quot; is seen in the regulation for the student dormitory of Kyoto university (article 3 of the regulation for the student dormitory).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, a description stating &quot;only undergraduates are allowed to enter the dormitory&quot; is seen in the regulation for the student dormitory of Kyoto university (article 3 of the regulation for the student dormitory).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, a description stating &apos;only undergraduates are allowed to enter the dormitory&apos; is seen in the regulation for the student dormitory of Kyoto University (article 3 of the regulation for the student dormitory).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。Kyoto University としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>しかし、受験生用の募集要項や、京都大学の公式サイトによれば「本学学生」が入寮資格を持つことになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the guidelines for the students taking an entrance exam and official web-site of Kyoto university, however, &quot;students of the university&quot; are qualified to enter dormitories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the guidelines for the students taking an entrance exam and official web-site of Kyoto university, however, &quot;students of the university&quot; are qualified to enter dormitories.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the guidelines for the students taking an entrance exam and official web-site of Kyoto University, however, &apos;students of the university&apos; are qualified to enter dormitories.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。Kyoto University としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>これはつまり、大学当局も入寮資格の拡大を公式に追認しているということである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above means that the authority of university officially confirmed the easing of the requirements for entering the dormitory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above means that the authority of the university officially confirmed the easing of the requirements for entering the dormitory.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The above means that the authority of the university officially confirmed the easing of the requirements for entering the dormitory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>事実、吉田寮や熊野寮が自主的に入寮資格拡大を行わなかった場合、女子学生（女子寮）や院生（室町寮）の受け入れ先はほぼ無いに等しい状態だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a matter of fact, if Yoshida dormitory and Kumano dormitory hadn&apos;t eased the requirements on an autonomous basis, there might have been no facilities to accept female students (dormitory for female) and postgraduates (Muromachi dormitory).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a matter of fact, if Yoshida dormitory and Kumano dormitory hadn&apos;t eased the requirements on an autonomous basis, there might have been no facilities to accept female students (dormitory for females) and postgraduates (Muromachi dormitory).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a matter of fact, if Yoshida dormitory and Kumano dormitory hadn&apos;t eased the requirements on an autonomous basis, there might have been no facilities to accept female students (dormitory for females) and graduate students (Muromachi dormitory).</e>
<cmt>院生→graduate students としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>また、経済的に困窮した留学生も行き場を失っていた可能性がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, foreign students who were in distress might have faced difficulty in finding affordable lodging.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, foreign students who were in distress might have faced difficulty in finding affordable lodging.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, foreign students who were in distress might have faced difficulty in finding affordable lodging.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>著名な出身者</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Famous persons who once lived in the dormitory</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Famous persons who once lived in the dormitory</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Famous persons who once lived in the dormitory</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="66">
<j>谷川徹三（1922年卒・哲学） 西田幾太郎を慕って入学、後に哲学者になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tetsuzo TANIGAWA (class of 1922, philosophy) : he entered the university adoring Ikutaro NISHIDA and later became a philosopher.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tetsuzo TANIGAWA (class of 1922, philosophy) : he entered the university adoring Ikutaro NISHIDA and later became a philosopher.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tetsuzo TANIGAWA (class of 1922, philosophy) : He entered the university adoring Ikutaro NISHIDA and later became a philosopher.</e>
<cmt>コロンの後の文章を大文字から始めました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>宗教的宇宙観に基づく諸民族の世界連邦を提唱した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He advocated the world confederation of various ethnic groups based on the religious view of the universe.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He advocated the world confederation of various ethnic groups based on the religious view of the universe.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He advocated the world confederation of various ethnic groups based on the religious view of the universe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>国際連合教育科学文化機関や平和運動など幅広い活躍を行い、法政大学総長も務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was engaged in wide-ranging activities, such as those of United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization and peace movement, and also served as the president of Hosei university.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was engaged in wide-ranging activities, such as those of the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization and peace movement, and also served as the president of Hosei university.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was engaged in wide-ranging activities, such as those of the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization and peace movement, and also served as the president of Hosei University.</e>
<cmt>University 大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>詩人の谷川俊太郎は息子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shuntaro TANIGAWA, a poet, is his son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shuntaro TANIGAWA, a poet, is his son.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shuntaro TANIGAWA, a poet, is his son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>入学時は一高の一年先輩の三木清の下宿に転がり込んだが、後に入寮。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He initially lived in the lodging of Kiyoshi MIKI, who was one year ahead of Tanigawa at former First School, as a free-loading lodger, but later entered the dormitory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He initially lived in the lodging of Kiyoshi MIKI, who was one year ahead of Tanigawa at the former First School, as a free-loading lodger, but later entered the dormitory.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He initially lived in the lodging of Kiyoshi MIKI, who was one year ahead of Tanigawa at the former First School, as a free-loading lodger, but later entered the dormitory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>寮時代は、寮にいた友人らと盛んに議論を交わした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While he lived in the dormitory, he often discussed with his friends.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While he lived in the dormitory, he often discussed with his friends.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While he lived in the dormitory, he often discussed with his friends.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="72">
<j>鰺坂二夫（1932年卒・哲学） 日本教育学会の会長も務めた教育学者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsugio AJISAKA (class of 1932, philosophy) : he was a scholar of pedagogy who served as the chairman of The Japan society for the study of education.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsugio AJISAKA (class of 1932, philosophy) : he was a scholar of pedagogy who served as the chairman of The Japan society for the study of education.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsugio AJISAKA (class of 1932, philosophy): He was a scholar of pedagogy who served as the chairman of The Japan Society for the Study of Education.</e>
<cmt>コロンの後の文章を大文字から始めました。日本教育学会→The Japan Society for the Study of Education と大文字にしました。コロンの前のスペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="73">
<j>上野淳一（1934年卒・経済） 父の上野精一から1970年に朝日新聞社社長を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Junichi UENO (class of 1934, economics) : he succeeded in 1970 the president of Asahi Shimbun Company from his father Seiichi UENO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Junichi UENO (class of 1934, economics) : he succeeded in 1970 the president of the Asahi Shimbun Company from his father Seiichi UENO.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Junichi UENO (class of 1934, economics): He succeeded in 1970 the president of the Asahi Shimbun Company from his father Seiichi UENO.</e>
<cmt>コロンの後の文章を大文字から始めました。コロンの前のスペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>1945年に戦争責任で朝日新聞の取締役を辞任し、小学校教師、大学事務官、最高裁判官秘書などを経たのち7年後に朝日新聞社に復帰。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He resigned from the position of director of Asahi Shimbun Company in 1945 due to responsibility for the war, and returned to Asahi Shimbun Company after working as an elementary school teacher, a clerk of university and a secretary of supreme court judge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He resigned from the position of director of the Asahi Shimbun Company in 1945 due to responsibility for the war, and returned to the Asahi Shimbun Company after working as an elementary school teacher, a clerk for the university and a secretary of a supreme court judge.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He resigned from the position of director of the Asahi Shimbun Company in 1945 due to responsibility for the war, and returned to the Asahi Shimbun Company seven years later after working as an elementary school teacher, a clerk for the university and a secretary of a supreme court judge.</e>
<cmt>７年後　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>後に上野は寮生活について次のように述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He later told about his life in the dormitory as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He later told about his life in the dormitory as follows.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He later told about his life in the dormitory as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>「非常に良かった。先輩も良かったし、学生は全国の旧制高校から来ていてとても仲が良かった」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;It was very good. My seniors were good persons, and all of us were good friends as the graduates of old-education-system high schools around the nation.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;It was very good. My seniors were good persons, and all of us were good friends as the graduates of the old-education-system high schools around the nation.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was very good. My seniors were good persons, and all of us were good friends as the graduates of the high schools under the old system of education around the nation.</e>
<cmt>全国の旧制高校→high schools under the old system of education around the nation　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>「共同通信の松方三郎が友人でね。私の部屋がみんなのたまり場だった」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Saburo MATSUKATA of Kyodo News Service was my friend. Many friends used to gather in my room.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Saburo MATSUKATA of Kyodo News Service was my friend. Many friends used to gather in my room.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saburo MATSUKATA of Kyodo News Service was my friend. Many friends used to gather in my room.</e>
<cmt>文頭のクォーテーションマークを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="78">
<j>桐栄良三（1943年卒・化工） ケミカルプロセスの権威で、日本学術会員も務め、1996年に勲二等旭日重光賞を受賞。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryozo TOEI (class of 1943, chemical engineering) : being an authority of chemical process, he was a member of Science Council of Japan and awarded &quot;Kunnito Kyokujitsu Jukosho&quot; (a kind of decoration).</e>
<cmt>勲二等旭日重光賞→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryozo TOEI (class of 1943, chemical engineering) : being an authority on chemical processing, he was a member of the Science Council of Japan and awarded &quot;Kunnito Kyokujitsu Jukosho&quot; (a kind of decoration).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryozo TOEI (class of 1943, chemical engineering) : Being an authority on chemical processing, he was a member of the Science Council of Japan and awarded &quot;Kunnito Kyokujitsu Jukosho&quot; (Second Class, the gold and silver star of order of the rising sun) in 1996.</e>
<cmt>勲二等旭日重光賞　補足を追加しました。1996を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="79">
<j>永井道雄（1944年卒・哲学） 教育社会学者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michio NAGAI (class of 1944, philosophy) : he was a educational sociologist.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michio NAGAI (class of 1944, philosophy) : he was a educational sociologist.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michio NAGAI (class of 1944, philosophy): He was a educational sociologist.</e>
<cmt>コロンの後の文章を大文字から始めました。コロンの前のスペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>国民的基盤に立った大学改革を唱えて東京工業大学教授を辞職し、朝日新聞論説委員になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He resigned from his post, a professor of Tokyo Institute of Technology, advocating the need of university reform based on people and became the editorial writer of Asahi Shimbun Company.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He resigned from his post, a professor of the Tokyo Institute of Technology, advocating the need for university reform based on people and became an editorial writer for Asahi Shimbun Company.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He resigned from his post, a professor of the Tokyo Institute of Technology, advocating the need for university reform based on people and became an editorial writer for Asahi Shimbun Company.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>1974年、民間人の登用の目玉として三木内閣の文部大臣に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1974, he was appointed to the Minister for Education of the Miki cabinet as a symbol of the policy of appointing civilians to ministerial posts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1974, he was appointed to the Minister for Education of the Miki cabinet as a symbol of the policy of appointing civilians to ministerial posts.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1974, he was appointed to the Minister for Education of the Miki cabinet as a symbol of the policy of appointing civilians to ministerial posts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>国立大学協会会長・岡本道雄京大総長とともに共通一次試験導入に取り組んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He strived to introduce the common first-stage exam along with Michio OKAMOTO, the president of Kyoto university as well as the president of the Japan Association of National Universities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He strived to introduce the common first-stage exam along with Michio OKAMOTO, the president of Kyoto university as well as the president of the Japan Association of National Universities.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He strived to introduce the preliminary standard university entrance examination along with Michio OKAMOTO, the president of Kyoto University as well as the president of the Japan Association of National Universities.</e>
<cmt>共通一次試験→the preliminary standard university entrance examination　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="83">
<j>檜学（1945年卒・医学） 島根医科大学医学部教授を経て学長に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Manabi HINOKI (class of 1945, medicine) : he was a professor of Shimane University Faculty of Medicine and later served as the president of the university.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Manabi HINOKI (class of 1945, medicine) : he was a professor at the Shimane University Faculty of Medicine and later served as the president of the university.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Manabi HINOKI (class of 1945, medicine): He was a professor at the Shimane University Faculty of Medicine and later served as the president of the university.</e>
<cmt>コロンの後の文章を大文字から始めました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>平衡神経科の第一人者として心身症とめまいの関係を解明した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the leading person of the study of the vestibular nerve and he clarified the linkage between psychosomatic illness and dizziness.</e>
<cmt>平衡神経科→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the leading person of the study of the vestibular nerve and he clarified the linkage between psychosomatic illness and dizziness.</e>
<cmt>Spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the leading person of the study of the vestibular nerve and he clarified the linkage between psychosomatic illness and dizziness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>寮時代は戦争の真っ最中で、檜は次のように振りかえっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The time when he lived in the dormitory was in the middle of the war, and he recalled as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The time when he lived in the dormitory was in the middle of the war, and he recalled as follows.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The time when he lived in the dormitory was in the middle of the war, and he recalled as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>「いつ兵隊にとられるか分からない。戦場に行けば必ず死が待っている。そういった緊迫した状態で学問に打ち込んでいた。寄宿舎の連中は皆そうだった。それだけにお互いの連帯感は強かった」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;I didn&apos;t know when I was to be called up for military service. Being called up inevitably led to my death. I concentrated on my study in such tense atmosphere. So did all of my colleagues in the dormitory. For that reason alone, we had a strong sense of solidarity.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;I didn&apos;t know when I was to be called up for military service. Being called up inevitably led to my death. I concentrated on my study in such a tense atmosphere. So did all of my colleagues in the dormitory. For that reason alone, we had a strong sense of solidarity.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I didn&apos;t know when I was to be called up for military service. Being called up inevitably led to my death. I concentrated on my study in such a tense atmosphere. So did all of my colleagues in the dormitory. For that reason alone, we had a strong sense of solidarity.</e>
<cmt>文頭のクォーテーションマークを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="87">
<j>松浦玲（1953年卒・放学、文学部国文）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rei MATSUURA (class of 1953, expelled from the university, department of literature, national literature)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rei MATSUURA (class of 1953, expelled from the university, department of literature, national literature)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rei MATSUURA (class of 1953, expelled from the university, department of literature, national literature)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>小室直樹（1955年卒・理学部数学科） 大学卒業後は東京大学、マサチューセッツ工科大学、ハーバード大学などで学んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naoki KOMURO (class of 1955, physics department, mathematics course) : after graduation, he studied at Tokyo university, Massachusetts Technology of Institutes and Harvard University.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naoki KOMURO (class of 1955, physics department, mathematics course) : after graduation, he studied at Tokyo university, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, and Harvard University.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naoki KOMURO (class of 1955, science department, mathematics course): After graduation, he studied at Tokyo University, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, and Harvard University.</e>
<cmt>コロンの後の文章を大文字から始めました。理学→science としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>年収100万円で学問三昧の暮らしを送ったが、1980年に栄養失調でダウン。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He concentrated on his study while earning 1M\ a year, but fell ill in 1980 due to malnutrition.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He concentrated on his study while earning 1M\ a year, but fell ill in 1980 due to malnutrition.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He concentrated on his study while earning one million yen a year, but fell ill in 1980 due to malnutrition.</e>
<cmt>one million yen としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>友人のすすめで生活費稼ぎに書いた「ソビエト帝国の逆襲」がベストセラーになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being exhorted by friends, he wrote a bestseller &quot;The Soviet Empire Strikes Back&quot; in order to earn his living.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Being exhorted by friends, he wrote a bestseller &quot;The Soviet Empire Strikes Back&quot; in order to earn a living.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Being exhorted by friends, he wrote a bestseller &apos;The Soviet Empire Strikes Back&apos; in order to earn a living.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>さらに田中角栄の礼賛で有名になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He further became famous by praisng Kakuei TANAKA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He further became famous by praising Kakuei TANAKA.</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He further became famous by praising Kakuei TANAKA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>大学では有名な学生で「小室将軍」と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a well-known student in the university and was dubbed &quot;Komuro shogun&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a well-known student in the university and was dubbed &quot;Komuro shogun.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a well-known student in the university and was dubbed &apos;Komuro shogun.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>1952年に「スターリンを殺せ、再軍備賛成」と主張して京大弁論部を除名させられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was dismissed from the debating club of Kyoto University in 1952 because of his remarks saying &quot;Kill Stalin, Agree Rearmament&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was dismissed from the debating club of Kyoto University in 1952 because of his remarks saying &quot;Kill Stalin, Agree Rearmament.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was dismissed from the debating club of Kyoto University in 1952 because of his remarks saying &apos;Kill Stalin, Agree Rearmament.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>その後、寮の自室に軍事問題研究会の看板を掲げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, he put up the sign of &quot;Military affairs study group&quot; on the door of his room in the dormitory.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, he put up a sign saying &quot;Military affairs study group&quot; on the door of his room in the dormitory.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, he put up a sign saying &quot;Military affairs study group&quot; on the door of his room in the dormitory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="95">
<j>岩見隆夫（1958年卒・法学） 毎日新聞社で、政治部記者としてロッキード事件や日韓癒着の取材で活躍。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takao IWAMI (class of 1958, law) : he was a political reporter of Mainichi Newspaper Co., Ltd., and took an active part in the report on Lockheed scandal and a collusive relationship between Japan and Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takao IWAMI (class of 1958, law) : he was a political reporter for Mainichi Newspaper Co., Ltd., and took an active part in the report on the Lockheed scandal and a collusive relationship between Japan and Korea.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takao IWAMI (class of 1958, law): He was a political reporter for Mainichi Newspaper Co., Ltd., and took an active part in the report on the Lockheed scandal and a collusive relationship between Japan and Korea.</e>
<cmt>コロンの後の文章を大文字から始めました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>サンデー毎日編集長を経て、役員待遇編集局顧問を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served as the chief editor of Mainichi Weekly News as well as the executively-treated advisor of the editorial office.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served as the chief editor of Mainichi Weekly News as well as the executive advisor of the editorial office.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served as the chief editor of Mainichi Weekly News as well as the executive advisor of the editorial office.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="97">
<j>室田武（1967年卒・理学） 大学卒業後は経済学に転じ、一橋大学や同志社大学教授を務めて「エコロジーの経済学」を提唱した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeshi MUROTA (class of 1967, physics) : after graduation, he studied economics, served as a professor of Hitotsubbashi University and Doshiha University, and advocated &quot;economics of ecology&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takeshi MUROTA (class of 1967, physics) : after graduation, he studied economics, served as a professor at Hitotsubbashi University and Doshiha University, and advocated &quot;economics of ecology.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeshi MUROTA (class of 1967, science): After graduation, he studied economics, served as a professor at Hitotsubashi University and Doshisha University, and advocated &apos;economics of ecology.&apos;</e>
<cmt>理学→science としました。Hitotsubashi, Doshisha としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="98">
<j>若狭雅信（1972年卒・言語） 在学中に同人誌で創作活動を始め、1977年に高城修三の筆名による「榧の木祭り」で芥川賞を受賞。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masanobu WAKASA (class of 1972, linguistics) : he started to write novels for dojinshi (publication aimed at a particular hobby group) when he was a student, and his novel &quot;Kayanokimatsuri&quot;, which was written under his pen name Shuzo TAKI, won Akutagawa Award in 1977.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masanobu WAKASA (class of 1972, linguistics) : he started to write novels for dojinshi (publications aimed at a particular hobby group) when he was a student, and his novel &quot;Kayanokimatsuri,&quot; which was written under his pen name Shuzo TAKI, won the Akutagawa Award in 1977.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masanobu WAKASA (class of 1972, linguistics): He started to write novels for dojinshi (publications aimed at a particular hobby group) when he was a student, and his novel &apos;Kayanokimatsuri,&apos; which was written under his pen name Shuzo TAKI, won the Akutagawa Award in 1977.</e>
<cmt>コロンの後の文章を大文字から始めました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>1968年後期の寮自治会委員長として学生部封鎖や総長団交を推進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the chairman of dormitory council in the latter half of 1968 and spearheaded a blockade of the office of student affaires department as well as negotiations with the president of university.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the chairman of the dormitory council in the latter half of 1968 and spearheaded a blockade of the office of the student affairs department as well as negotiations with the president of the university.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the chairman of the dormitory council in the latter half of 1968 and spearheaded a blockade of the office of the student affairs department as well as negotiations with the president of the university.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="100">
<j>篠原資明（1975年卒・美学）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motoaki SHINOHARA (class of 1975, aesthetics)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motoaki SHINOHARA (class of 1975, aesthetics)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motoaki SHINOHARA (class of 1975, aesthetics)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>市田良彦（1980年卒・経済） 社会思想学者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihiko ICHIDA (class of 1980, economics) : he is a scholar of social thought.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihiko ICHIDA (class of 1980, economics) : he is a scholar of social thought.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihiko ICHIDA (class of 1980, economics): He is a scholar of social thought.</e>
<cmt>コロンの後の文章を大文字から始めました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>大阪女子大学を経て神戸大学教授。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After serving as a professor of Osaka Women&apos;s University, he is now a professor of Kobe University.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After serving as a professor for Osaka Women&apos;s University, he is now a professor at Kobe University.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After serving as a professor for Osaka Women&apos;s University, he is now a professor at Kobe University.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>在学中は全学自治会同学会の委員長として竹本処分闘争以降の京大学生運動を導いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he was a student, he spearheaded the student movement at Kyoto University after &quot;Takemoto shobun&quot; struggle as the chairman of national student association.</e>
<cmt>全学自治会同学会→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he was a student, he spearheaded the student movement at Kyoto University after &quot;Takemoto shobun&quot; struggle as the chairman of the national student association.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he was a student, he spearheaded the student movement at Kyoto University after &quot;Takemoto shobun&quot; struggle as the chairman of the national student association.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>委員長時代に「つるし上げた」縁で、上田正昭名誉教授を大阪女子大学の学長にかつぎあげた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He pressed emeritus professor Masaaki UEDA into serving as the president of Osaka Women&apos;s University because he had a connection with Ueda since the time when he, as the then chairman, teased Ueda with sharp questions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He pressed emeritus professor Masaaki UEDA into serving as the president of Osaka Women&apos;s University because he had a connection with Ueda since the time when he, as the then chairman, teased Ueda with sharp questions.</e>
<cmt>Spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He pressed emeritus professor Masaaki UEDA into serving as the president of Osaka Women&apos;s University because he had a connection with Ueda since the time when he, as the then chairman, teased Ueda with sharp questions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="105">
<j>徳永信一（1985年卒・法） 大阪HIV訴訟弁護団の一人として裁判を支えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinichi TOKUNAGA (class of 1985, law) : he supported Osaka HIV-tainted blood litigation as a member of defense lawyers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinichi TOKUNAGA (class of 1985, law) : he supported Osaka HIV-tainted blood litigation as a member of the defense lawyers.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinichi TOKUNAGA (class of 1985, law): He supported Osaka HIV-tainted blood litigation as a member of the defense lawyers.</e>
<cmt>コロンの後の文章を大文字から始めました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="106">
<j>色平哲郎（1989年卒・医） 卒業後は地域医療の世界に飛び込む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tetsuro IROHIRA (class of 1989, medicine) : he entered the world of community medicine after graduation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tetsuro IROHIRA (class of 1989, medicine) : he entered the world of community medicine after graduation.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tetsuro IROHIRA (class of 1989, medicine): He entered the world of community medicine after graduation.</e>
<cmt>コロンの後の文章を大文字から始めました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>地域医療のNGOの立場からマスコミからコメントを求められることも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He often provides opinions to mass media from the stndpoint of NGO of community medicine.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He often provides opinions to mass media from the standpoint of a NGO for community medicine.</e>
<cmt>Typo, Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He often provides opinions to mass media from the standpoint of a NGO for community medicine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>所在地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Adress</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Address</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Address</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="108">
<j>京都府京都市左京区吉田近衛町69番地。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">69, Yoshida Konoe-cho, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">69, Yoshida Konoe-cho, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">69, Yoshida Konoe-cho, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="109">
<j>※2004年度（平成16年度）より京都大学が国立大学法人となるのに伴い、住所は吉田近衛町官有地から地番がつけられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">* Since 2004, when Kyoto University was reorganized into national university corporation, the adrees was changed from Yoshida Konoe-cho kaneichi (national kand) to the above one (lot number was added).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">* Since 2004, when Kyoto University was reorganized into a national university corporation, the address was changed from Yoshida Konoe-cho kaneichi (national kind) to the one above (lot number was added).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">* Since the academic year 2004, when Kyoto University was reorganized into a national university corporation, the address was changed from Yoshida Konoe-cho kaneichi (national kind) to the one above (lot number was added).</e>
<cmt>2004年度　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 U m(id:58731), Straysheep(id:42448), PANYNJ(id:38638), 江口磐世☆(id:168037), Hougi(id:175007), Suzuki1985(id:92126), Kalz(id:92749), Newtype(id:185412), TEy(id:32722), Jazzy(id:3202), 秋の虹(id:18259), Kayoko(id:25755), Yoshinaga(id:45391), MDR-SK(id:192066), Su-no-G(id:52744), Opponent(id:720), Kokada jnet(id:84730), 朝彦(id:9407), ＮｉＫｅ(id:7512), KAMUI(id:9330), 曾禰越後守(id:183605), Baba(id:2635), 日本一弱い男(id:92046), Nakanohitonadoinai(id:227365), Point136(id:211299), Asami(id:26168), Akinoniji(id:56111), Toujin1985(id:86543), Habu(id:18076), 小太刀(id:18154), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>