<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>高輪談判</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takanawa negotiation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takanawa negotiation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takanawa negotiation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>高輪談判（たかなわだんぱん）とは、明治2年7月12日（1869年8月19日）に、東京高輪において開催された明治政府首脳とイギリス・フランス・アメリカ合衆国・イタリア・北ドイツ連邦の5ヶ国の駐日公使による会談。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Takanawa negotiation was a conference held by the the head of the Meiji Government and the ambassadors of England, France, United States of America, Italy, and Germany, in Takanawa, Tokyo Prefecture on August 19, 1869.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Takanawa negotiation was a conference held by the the head of the Meiji Government and the ambassadors of England, France, United States of America, Italy, and Germany, in Takanawa, Tokyo Prefecture on August 19, 1869.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Takanawa negotiation was a conference held by the the head of the Meiji Government and the ambassadors of England, France, United States of America, Italy, and Germany, in Takanawa, Tokyo Prefecture on August 19, 1869.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>この会談で日本が官民の（二分金を中心とした）贋貨の回収と近代貨幣制度の導入を国際公約とすることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this conference, the collection of counterfeit coins of Japanese citizens (centered around nifun gane) and the international promise of the introduction of the modern currency system were decided.</e>
<cmt>二分金の適訳が見つからなかったので、nifun ganeとしてあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this conference, the collection of counterfeit coins of Japanese citizens (centered around nibukin) and the introduction of the modern currency system were decided as international commitments.</e>
<cmt>「国際公約とすることになった」のは贋貨の回収と制度導入の二つだと思います。国際公約　international promise → international commitments   二分金 nifun gane → nibukin (日本語の読み方が間違っています）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this conference, the collection of counterfeit coins of Japanese citizens (centered around nibukin) and the introduction of the modern currency system were decided as international commitments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>また、新貨条例や造幣局 (日本)設置のきっかけとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, this lead to the New Currency Act and the set up of the Mint (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, this led to the New Currency Act and the set up of the Mint (Japan).</e>
<cmt>Further → Furthermore, lead → led</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, this led to the New Currency Act and the set up of the Mint (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>明治の悪贋貨問題</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meiji&apos;s bad counterfeit money problem</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meiji&apos;s bad counterfeit money problem</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meiji&apos;s bad counterfeit money problem</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>開国以後、江戸幕府は金の海外流出を食い止めるために金貨の質を落としたが、そのために物価は上昇、社会は混乱し、欧米商人も経済的な打撃を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Japan opened it&apos;s country to the world, the Edo bakufu lowered the quality of gold coins to stop the flow of gold to foreign countries, but because of this, prices rose, the society was in confusion, and European and American merchants also took a hard hit economically.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Japan opened its country to the world, the Edo bakufu lowered the quality of gold coins to stop the outflow of gold to foreign countries, but because of this, prices rose, the society was in confusion, and European and American merchants also took a hard hit economically.</e>
<cmt>it&apos;s → its, 流出　flow → outflow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Japan opened its country to the world, the Edo bakufu lowered the quality of gold coins to stop the outflow of gold to foreign countries, but because of this, prices rose, the society was in confusion, and European and American merchants also took a hard hit economically.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>このため、慶応3年5月13日（1866年6月25日）に欧米諸国は江戸幕府と改税約書を結び、内外貨幣の等価交換とその安定化のために万延年間に定められた現行の貨幣水準を当面維持し、将来的には国際水準に見合った貨幣制度を導入することを約束させられたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, on June 25, 1866, Western countries and the Edo bakufu tied a kaietsuyakusho, promising to maintain the current currency level fixed during the Manen years (end of the Edo period) for the moment for the equivalent exchange of domestic and overseas currency and it&apos;s stabilization, and that in the future Japan would adopt a currency system that corresponds with the international level.</e>
<cmt>改税約書の適訳が見つからなかったので、kaietsuyakushoとしてあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, on June 25, 1866, Western countries and the Edo bakufu concluded a kaizeiyakusho, promising to maintain the current currency level fixed during the Manen era (end of the Edo period) for the moment for the equivalent exchange of domestic and overseas currency and it&apos;s stabilization, and that in the future Japan would adopt a currency system that corresponds with the international level.</e>
<cmt>改税約書を結び tied a kaietsuyakusho → concluded a kaizeiyakusho　（日本語の読み方が間違っています), 万延年間 Manen years → Manen era   it&apos;s → its</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, on June 25, 1866, Western countries and the Edo bakufu concluded a kaizeiyakusho, promising to maintain the current currency level fixed during the Manen era (end of the Edo period) for the moment for the equivalent exchange of domestic and overseas currency and it&apos;s stabilization, and that in the future Japan would adopt a currency system that corresponds with the international level.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>だが、当時幕府財政は破綻寸前であり、改税約書が結ばれた当時には既に幕府はこれよりも質を落として貨幣を発行し続けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the financial affairs of the bakufu at the time was on the verge of collapse, and by the time the kaietsuyakusho was tied, the bakufu lowered the quality of coins even more and continued issuing them.</e>
<cmt>改税約書の適訳が見つからなかったので、kaietsuyakushoとしてあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the financial affairs of the bakufu at the time were on the verge of collapse, and by the time the kaizeiyakusho was concluded, the bakufu had already lowered the quality of coins even more and continued issuing them.</e>
<cmt>was → were, kaietsuyakusho was tied → kaizeiyakusho was concluded （日本語の読み方が間違っています), the bakufu lowered → the bakufu had already lowered</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the financial affairs of the bakufu at the time were on the verge of collapse, and by the time the kaizeiyakusho was concluded, the bakufu had already lowered the quality of coins even more and continued issuing them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>やがて戊辰戦争が始まると、外国より武器を輸入するための戦費調達を目的として奥羽越列藩同盟の会津藩・仙台藩・二本松藩・久保田藩などが贋貨を鋳造し始め、続いて薩摩藩・土佐藩・芸州藩・宇和島藩・佐土原藩・郡山藩などの官軍諸藩もこれに続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Boshin War eventually started, the Oetsu-reppan alliance: the Aizu, Sendai, Nihonmatsu, Kubota, and other domains started coining counterfeit money, followed by Imperial army domains such as Satsuma, Tosa, Geishu, Uwajima, Sadowara, and Gunyama Domain, for the purpose of providing the war costs of importing weapons from overseas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Boshin War eventually started, the Oetsu-reppan alliance: the Aizu, Sendai, Nihonmatsu, Kubota, and other domains started coining counterfeit money, followed by Imperial army domains such as Satsuma, Tosa, Geishu, Uwajima, Sadowara, and Gunyama Domain, for the purpose of raising capital to import weapons from overseas.</e>
<cmt>外国より武器を輸入するための戦費調達を目的として　for the purpose of providing the war costs of importing weapons from overseas → for the purpose of raising capital to import weapons from overseas.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Boshin War eventually started, the Oetsu-reppan alliance: the Aizu, Sendai, Nihonmatsu, Kubota, and other domains started coining counterfeit money, followed by Imperial army domains such as Satsuma, Tosa, Geishu, Uwajima, Sadowara, and Gunyama Domain, for the purpose of raising capital to import weapons from overseas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>さらには加賀藩や筑前藩、久留米藩などの、戦争に積極的とはいえなかった藩までが贋貨を鋳造するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, domains such as Kaga, Chikuzen, and Kurume Domain who did not actively participate in the war also started coining counterfeit money.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, domains such as Kaga, Chikuzen, and Kurume Domain who did not actively participate in the war also started coining counterfeit money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, domains such as Kaga, Chikuzen, and Kurume Domain who did not actively participate in the war also started coining counterfeit money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>特に当時の欧米を中心とした通貨制度の主流が金本位制であったこと、当時の小判の形状が対外的な運搬・流通などに不便であったことから、代わりに対外決済の分野で最もよく使われていた二分金の贋貨鋳造が盛んに行われ、中には銀貨に金鍍金を施した贋貨とほとんど変わりのないものまで出現した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially because at the time, the currency system centered around Europe and America was the main gold standard system, along with the fact that the shape of the koban (former Japanese oval gold coin) of this period was inconvenient for external transport and settlement, instead, the coining of counterfeit nifungane, which was the most used in the field of external settlement, was done frequently to the extent that some counterfeit money that pretty much applied a gold plate over silver coins appeared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially because at the time, the currency system centered around Europe and America was mainly the gold standard system, along with the fact that the shape of the koban (former Japanese oval gold coin) of this period was inconvenient for external transport and circulation, instead, the coining of counterfeit nibukin, which was the most used in the field of external settlement, was done frequently, and even gilded silver coins which were not so different from the forfeit coins appeared.</e>
<cmt>主流が金本位制 the main gold standard system → mainly the gold standard system, 流通 settlement → circulation, 二分金 nifungane → nibukin (日本語の読み方が間違っています） 中には銀貨に金鍍金を施した贋貨とほとんど変わりのないものまで出現した。to the extent that some counterfeit money that pretty much applied a gold plate over silver coins appeared. → even gilded silver coins which were not so different from the forfeit coins appeared.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially because at the time, the currency system centered around Europe and America was mainly the gold standard system, along with the fact that the shape of the koban (former Japanese oval gold coin) of this period was inconvenient for external transport and circulation, instead, the coining of counterfeit nibukin, which was the most used in the field of external settlement, was done frequently, and even gilded silver coins which were not so different from the forfeit coins appeared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>そして明治政府もまた、明治元年4月から翌年2月にかけて幕府から接収した金座_(歴史)・銀座_(歴史)において、質の劣る金貨を約381万両、銀貨を約224万両、合計約605万両を鋳造した（これは一応政府が発行した公式通貨であるが、政府自らが規定した貨幣としての基準を満たしていないという点では贋貨となんら変わりがない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Meiji Government seized the kin-za (an organization in charge of casting and appraising of gold during the Edo period) and the gin-za (an organization in charge of casting and appraising of silver during the Edo period) also coined around 381 thousand ryo low quality gold coins, around 224 thousand ryo silver coins, for a total amount of around 605 thousand ryo during April 1868 to the February of next year (this was more or less, the official currency issued by the government, but by the terms that the government did not satisfy the standard for currency they themselves made as a rule, it was not much different from counterfeits).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Meiji Government took over the kin-za (an organization in charge of casting and appraising of gold during the Edo period) and the gin-za (an organization in charge of casting and appraising of silver during the Edo period) from Shogunate, also coined around 3.81 million ryo low quality gold coins, around 2.24 million ryo silver coins, for a total amount of around 6.05 million ryo from April 1868 to the February of next year (this was more or less, the official currency issued by the government, but from the point of view that it didn&apos;t meet the monetary standard defined by the government itself, it was not much different from counterfeits).</e>
<cmt>「訳漏れ」・・・幕府から  接収 seized → took over, 明治元年4月から during April 1868 → from April 1868 政府自らが規定した貨幣としての基準を満たしていないという点では by the terms that the government did not satisfy the standard for currency they themselves made as a rule → from the point of view that it didn&apos;t meet the monetary standard defined by the government itself    　約381万両 around 381 thousand ryo → around 3.81 million ryo 　　約224万両 around 224 thousand ryo → around 2.24 million ryo 　約605万両 around 605 thousand ryo → around 6.05 million ryo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Meiji Government took over the kin-za (an organization in charge of casting and appraising of gold during the Edo period) and the gin-za (an organization in charge of casting and appraising of silver during the Edo period) from Shogunate, also coined around 3.81 million ryo low quality gold coins, around 2.24 million ryo silver coins, for a total amount of around 6.05 million ryo from April 1868 to the February of next year (this was more or less, the official currency issued by the government, but from the point of view that it didn&apos;t meet the monetary standard defined by the government itself, it was not much different from counterfeits).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>諸藩の鋳造額は不明だが、公式に届け出たものでは芸州藩は約19.6万両、久留米藩は約3万両、土佐藩は約5.1万両、薩摩藩は公式には明かさなかったものの、吉井友実が藩の会計係に問い詰めた上での推計は約150万両とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The amount coined for many domains are unknown, but the amount reported officially is: for the Geishu Domain, around 196 thousand ryo, for the Kurume Domain, around 30 thousand ryo, for the Tosa Domain, around 51 thousand ryo, and the Satsuma Domain did not officially disclose the amount, but the estimated amount after Tomozane YOSHII pressed the domain&apos;s accountant was around 1500 thousand ryo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The amount coined for many domains are unknown, but the amount reported officially is: for the Geishu Domain, around 196 thousand ryo, for the Kurume Domain, around 30 thousand ryo, for the Tosa Domain, around 51 thousand ryo, and the Satsuma Domain did not officially disclose the amount, but the estimated amount after Tomozane YOSHII pressed the domain&apos;s accountant was around 1.5 million ryo.</e>
<cmt>約150万両 around 1500 thousand ryo → around 1.5 million ryo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The amount coined for many domains are unknown, but the amount reported officially is: for the Geishu Domain, around 196 thousand ryo, for the Kurume Domain, around 30 thousand ryo, for the Tosa Domain, around 51 thousand ryo, and the Satsuma Domain did not officially disclose the amount, but the estimated amount after Tomozane YOSHII pressed the domain&apos;s accountant was around 1.5 million ryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>もちろん、実際には内乱に乗じた他の諸藩や民間でも同様の贋貨作りが行われており、明治2年3月に外国官（後の外務省）より公議所に対して3,000万両の贋貨が外国商人の手に落ちたという「風説」があると報告されている（「問題四条」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of course in reality, many other domains and people took advantage of the civil war and had counterfeit money made similarly, and a rumor was reported by the Foreign Office (the later Ministry of Foreign Affairs) to the public chamber that 3,000 thousand counterfeit ryo fell into the hands of foreign merchants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of course in reality, many other domains and people took advantage of the civil war and had counterfeit money made similarly, and a rumor was reported by the Foreign Office (the later Ministry of Foreign Affairs) to the public chamber that 30 million counterfeit ryo fell into the hands of foreign merchants.</e>
<cmt>3,000万両 3,000 thousand counterfeit ryo → 30 million counterfeit ryo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of course in reality, many other domains and people took advantage of the civil war and had counterfeit money made similarly, and a rumor was reported by the Foreign Office (the later Ministry of Foreign Affairs) to the public chamber that 30 million counterfeit ryo fell into the hands of foreign merchants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>つまり、当時の政府もその具体額は把握しておらず、将来的にも全容を明らかにするのは困難である（3,000万両は過大であるとしても、現在明らかになっているだけで800万両近くあり、それを遥かに上回る金額の悪貨・贋貨が発行されたと考えられる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, the government at the time also did not know the concrete amount of fake money coined, and even in the future, uncovering the whole truth would be difficult (even if 30,000 thousand ryo is exaggerated, the amount made clear presently is still close to 800 thousand ryo, and much more bad money and counterfeit money is thought to have been issued.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, the government at the time also did not know the concrete amount of fake money coined, and even in the future, uncovering the whole truth would be difficult (even if 30 million ryo is exaggerated, the amount made clear presently is still close to 8 million ryo, and much more bad money and counterfeit money is thought to have been issued.)</e>
<cmt>3,000万両 3,000 thousand ryo → 30 million ryo, 　　800万両 800 thousand ryo → 8 million ryo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, the government at the time also did not know the concrete amount of fake money coined, and even in the future, uncovering the whole truth would be difficult (even if 30 million ryo is exaggerated, the amount made clear presently is still close to 8 million ryo, and much more bad money and counterfeit money is thought to have been issued.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>大隈重信と諸外国との交渉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Negotiations between Shigenobu Okuma and several foreign countries</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Negotiations between Shigenobu Okuma and several foreign countries</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Negotiations between Shigenobu Okuma and several foreign countries</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>大量の贋貨（政府発行の悪貨を含む）の流通は物価を不安定化させ経済にも悪影響を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The circulation of great amounts of counterfeit money (including bad money issued by the government) made the prices destabilize and was a bad influence on the economy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The circulation of great amounts of counterfeit money (including bad money issued by the government) made the prices destabilize and gave a bad influence on the economy.</e>
<cmt>was a bad influence → gave a bad influence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The circulation of great amounts of counterfeit money (including bad money issued by the government) made the prices destabilize and gave a bad influence on the economy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>特に一般の商人や民衆には金銀貨の真贋を見分けることは難しく、外国商人の中にも贋貨を入手して損害を受ける者も出た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Particularly, the general merchants and people had a hard time distinguishing real gold and silver coins from the fake, and there were foreign merchants who also acquired counterfeit money, suffering damage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Particularly, it was difficult for general merchants and people to distinguish real gold and silver coins from the fake, and there were foreign merchants who also acquired counterfeit money and suffered damage.</e>
<cmt>一般の商人や民衆には金銀貨の真贋を見分けることは難しく the general merchants and people had a hard time distinguishing real gold and silver coins from the fake →it was difficult for general merchants and people to distinguish real gold and silver coins from the fake</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Particularly, it was difficult for general merchants and people to distinguish real gold and silver coins from the fake, and there were foreign merchants who also acquired counterfeit money and suffered damage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>これに不満を抱いたのがイギリス公使であったハリー・パークスである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The man who was dissatisfied with this was England minister, Harry Parkes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The man who was dissatisfied with this was England minister, Harry Parkes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The man who was dissatisfied with this was England minister, Harry Parkes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>パークスは薩摩藩・長州藩を支援して明治政府の成立に協力していた経緯があるだけに、政府が極秘で改税約書に違反した悪貨を鋳造していることに気づいていたが、これを放置しておくことは日本と貿易を行うイギリス商人の利益に反することであると考えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having the background of cooperating with the formation of the Meiji Government by supporting the Satsuma and Choshu Domain, Parkes realized that the Meiji Government was breaking the kaietsuyakusho and secretly coining bad money, but thought that leaving this matter alone would go against the profit of English merchants who were trading with Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having the background of cooperating with the formation of the Meiji Government by supporting the Satsuma and Choshu Domain, Parkes realized that the Meiji Government was breaking the kaizeiyakusho and secretly coining bad money, but thought that leaving this matter alone would go against the profit of English merchants who were trading with Japan.</e>
<cmt>改税約書 kaietsuyakusho → kaizeiyakusho　（日本語の読み方が間違っています)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having the background of cooperating with the formation of the Meiji Government by supporting the Satsuma and Choshu Domain, Parkes realized that the Meiji Government was breaking the kaizeiyakusho and secretly coining bad money, but thought that leaving this matter alone would go against the profit of English merchants who were trading with Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>従って、内乱が終結した後には直ちに明治政府が通貨改革を行うことを望んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, he hoped that the Meiji Government would carry out a currency reform immediately after the civil war ended.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, he hoped that the Meiji Government would carry out a currency reform immediately after the civil war ended.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, he hoped that the Meiji Government would carry out a currency reform immediately after the civil war ended.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>明治2年1月7日、パークスの呼びかけでフランス・アメリカ・イタリア・ドイツの各国公使が相次いで新政府に対して「新政府（明治政府）が改税約書に違反した通貨を鋳造しているという噂があるために通貨の相場が暴落して商人たちが損害を受けている」として贋貨一掃のための措置を採る事を要求した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 7, 1869, with the call of Parkes, ministers from France, America, Italy, and Germany successively demanded the new Japanese Government to take measures to wipe out the counterfeit money because &quot;since there are rumors that the new government (Meiji Government) are coining money that goes against the kaietsuyakusho, the market place for money is crashing and merchants are suffering damage.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 7, 1869, with the call of Parkes, ministers from France, America, Italy, and Germany successively demanded the new Japanese Government to take measures to wipe out the counterfeit money because &quot;since there are rumors that the new government (Meiji Government) are coining money that goes against the kaizeiyakusho, the market place for money is crashing and merchants are suffering damage.&quot;</e>
<cmt>改税約書 kaietsuyakusho → kaizeiyakusho　（日本語の読み方が間違っています)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 7, 1869, with the call of Parkes, ministers from France, America, Italy, and Germany successively demanded the new Japanese Government to take measures to wipe out the counterfeit money because &apos;since there are rumors that the new government (Meiji Government) are coining money that goes against the kaizeiyakusho, the market place for money is crashing and merchants are suffering damage.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot; → &apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>明治政府は突然の要求に驚いたが取りあえず外国官副知事の小松清廉（帯刀・薩摩藩家老）に対応をさせようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Meiji Government was surprised with the sudden demand, but tried to make the vice foreign prefectural governor, Kiyokado KOMATSU (Tatewaki, a chief retainer of Satsuma Domain), deal with the problem for the time being.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Meiji Government was surprised with the sudden demand, but tried to make the vice foreign prefectural governor, Kiyokado KOMATSU (Tatewaki, a chief retainer of Satsuma Domain), deal with the problem for the time being.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Meiji Government was surprised with the sudden demand, but tried to make the vice foreign prefectural governor, Kiyokado KOMATSU (Tatewaki, a chief retainer of Satsuma Domain), deal with the problem for the time being.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>ところが、その小松が病に倒れてしまった（翌年36歳で急死）ために、病床の小松が代役として推挙したのが肥前藩出身の大隈重信であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, because KOMATSU became sick (suddenly died next year, at the age of 36), the man who KOMATSU recommended as his substitute was Shigenobu OKUMA from the Hizen Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, because KOMATSU became sick (suddenly died next year, at the age of 36), the man who KOMATSU recommended as his substitute was Shigenobu OKUMA from the Hizen Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, because KOMATSU became sick (suddenly died next year, at the age of 36), the man who KOMATSU recommended as his substitute was Shigenobu OKUMA from the Hizen Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="22">
<j>大隈は直ちに外国官副知事兼参与に任じられ、更に会計官（後の大蔵省）への出向（1月12日）が命じられたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">OKUMA was immediately appointed to vice foreign prefectural governor and counselor, and still more, he was ordered (January 12) to be sent to the finance office (the later Ministry of Finance).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">OKUMA was immediately appointed to vice foreign prefectural governor and counselor, and still more, he was ordered (January 12) to be sent to the finance office (the later Ministry of Finance).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OKUMA was immediately appointed to vice foreign prefectural governor and counselor, and still more, he was ordered (January 12) to be sent to the finance office (the later Ministry of Finance).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>だが、明治天皇の東京行幸を目前に控えて大隈は直ちに京都からパークスのいる横浜市に動くことは出来ず、大隈は外国官知事伊達宗城（宇和島藩）らと協議の結果2月5日に内外に向けて近いうちに新貨幣を発行することを発表し、パークスには神奈川県知事を兼務していた外国官判事寺島宗則が宥めるように指示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as Emperor Meiji&apos;s Tokyo Gyoko (Emperor&apos;s going out to Tokyo) was nearing, OKUMA could not immediately move from Kyoto to Yokohama City where Parkes was, so he and others such as foreign governor Munenari DATE (Uwajima Domain) had a conference, resulting in an announcement to Japan and foreign countries on February 5, that they would issue new currency in the near future, and for Parkes, he instructed officer of Foreign Affairs Council Munenori TERASHIMA, who was also the governor of Kanagawa Prefecture, to appease.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as Emperor Meiji&apos;s Tokyo Gyoko (Emperor&apos;s going out to Tokyo) was nearing, OKUMA could not immediately move from Kyoto to Yokohama City where Parkes was, so he and others such as foreign governor Munenari DATE (Uwajima Domain) had a conference, resulting in an announcement to Japan and foreign countries on February 5, that they would issue new currency in the near future, and for Parkes, he instructed officer of Foreign Affairs Council Munenori TERASHIMA, who was also the governor of Kanagawa Prefecture, to appease.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as Emperor Meiji&apos;s Tokyo Gyoko (Emperor&apos;s going out to Tokyo) was nearing, OKUMA could not immediately move from Kyoto to Yokohama City where Parkes was, so he and others such as foreign governor Munenari DATE (Uwajima Domain) had a conference, resulting in an announcement to Japan and foreign countries on February 5, that they would issue new currency in the near future, and for Parkes, he instructed officer of Foreign Affairs Council Munenori TERASHIMA, who was also the governor of Kanagawa Prefecture, to appease.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>だが、これがパークスを怒らせて1月22日と2月21日に改めて政府に事情説明を求める書簡を送っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this angered Parkes, and he sent a letter to the government on January 22 and 23 seeking an explanation for the circumstance again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this angered Parkes, and he sent a letter to the government on January 22 and 23 seeking an explanation for the circumstance again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this angered Parkes, and he sent a letter to the government on January 22 and 23 seeking an explanation for the circumstance again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>そこで2月30日に伊達の名において各国公使に対して政府は現在の通貨（公式にはそれが改税約書違反の悪貨とは認めなかった）を今後は鋳造せずに新貨幣の準備が整うまでは太政官札で対応していくこと、太政官以外の組織・個人はたとえ諸侯であっても貨幣を鋳造するものは処罰の対象となることを通知したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here, in the name of DATE, the government notified minsters from each country that Japan will not coin the current currency from now on (they did not formally recognize this as bad money violating the kaietsuyakusho), that the daijokan money would be used until the preparations for the new currency is completed, and that if organizations and individuals besides the daijokan coin currency, they will be subject to punishment, even if they are lords.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Here, in the name of DATE, the government notified minsters from each country that Japan will not coin the current currency from now on (they did not formally recognize this as bad money violating the kaizeiyakusho), that the daijokan money would be used until the preparations for the new currency is completed, and that if organizations and individuals besides the daijokan coin currency, they will be subject to punishment, even if they are lords.</e>
<cmt>改税約書 kaietsuyakusho → kaizeiyakusho　（日本語の読み方が間違っています)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Here, in the name of DATE, the government notified minsters from each country that Japan will not coin the current currency from now on (they did not formally recognize this as bad money violating the kaizeiyakusho), that the daijokan money would be used until the preparations for the new currency is completed, and that if organizations and individuals besides the daijokan coin currency, they will be subject to punishment, even if they are lords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>だが、実際には当時（版籍奉還以前）の明治政府は諸藩に対して命令を下す権限を持っておらず（従って明治政府の命令である太政官布告ではなく、要請に近い太政官達が出されていた）、特に薩摩・土佐両藩は「戦勝国」の立場を利用してその後も贋貨を鋳造続けたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in reality, the Meiji Government at the time (before the return of lands and people to the emperor) did not have the authority to give orders to various domains (therefore the notice of Daijokan [Grand Council of State], which was more of a request, was issued instead of the edict of Daijokan, which was a command from the Meiji Government), and particularly the Satsuma and Tosa Domains used their position as a &quot;victor country&quot; and still continued to coin counterfeit money.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in reality, the Meiji Government at the time (before the return of lands and people to the emperor) did not have the authority to give orders to various domains (therefore the notice of Daijokan [Grand Council of State], which was more of a request, was issued instead of the edict of Daijokan, which was a command from the Meiji Government), and particularly the Satsuma and Tosa Domains used their position as a &quot;victor country&quot; and still continued to coin counterfeit money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in reality, the Meiji Government at the time (before the return of lands and people to the emperor) did not have the authority to give orders to various domains (therefore the notice of Daijokan [Grand Council of State], which was more of a request, was issued instead of the edict of Daijokan, which was a command from the Meiji Government), and particularly the Satsuma and Tosa Domains used their position as a &quot;victor country&quot; and still continued to coin counterfeit money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>また、会計官では不換紙幣としての太政官札の企画を推進してきた副知事の由利公正が従来の財政問題を巡る路線対立に加えて、外交問題から太政官札の位置付け変更に踏み込んだ通貨改革の流れに発展してきたことに対する不満から辞意を表明していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, Kosei YURI, the vice prefectural governor who promoted the the plan of the Daijokan money as the fiat money at the finance office, expressed his will to resign because of his dissatisfaction with the opposition lines over the traditional financial affairs problem, along with his dissatisfaction that the problem was developing from diplomatic issues into a problem along the flow of the currency reform, which had changed its position.</e>
<cmt>太政官札の適訳が見つからなかったので、daijokan moneyとしてあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Kosei YURI, the vice prefectural governor who promoted the the plan of the Dajokan-satsu as the inconvertible paper currency at the finance office, expressed his will to resign because of his dissatisfaction with the confrontation on the existing financial issues along with his dissatisfaction with the circumstances that the diplomatic issue had grown into a monetary reform which even involved the change of position of Dajokan-satsu.</e>
<cmt>Further → Furthermore　太政官札 → Dajokan-satsu (用語集より）　不換紙幣　fiat money → inconvertible paper currency （用語集より） 従来の財政問題を巡る路線対立 the opposition lines over the traditional financial affairs problem → confrontation on the existing financial issues　外交問題から太政官札の位置付け変更に踏み込んだ通貨改革の流れに発展してきたこと the problem was developing from diplomatic issues into a problem along the flow of the currency reform, which had changed its position　→ the diplomatic issue had grown into a monetary reform which even involved the change of position of Dajokan-satsu.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Kosei YURI, the vice prefectural governor who promoted the the plan of the Dajokan-satsu as the inconvertible paper currency at the finance office, expressed his will to resign because of his dissatisfaction with the confrontation on the existing financial issues along with his dissatisfaction with the circumstances that the diplomatic issue had grown into a monetary reform which even involved the change of position of Dajokan-satsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>更にこうした一連の遣り取りが内外に伝わると2月28日には横浜居留地の商人たちが会合を開いて明治政府に贋貨によって生じた損害賠償を求める事を決議し、更に一部の商人が今後の回収に期待して暴落した贋貨を買い占めるなど様々な思惑が動き出し始めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, when this series of exchange spread around Japan and foreign countries, merchants of Yokohama settlement held a meeting on February 28, and decided to seek compensation from the Meiji Government for the damage caused by counterfeit money, and on top of this, people began to move on their various ideas, like how some merchants started to buy up the counterfeit money which had slumped anticipating the next recall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, when this series of exchange spread around Japan and foreign countries, people began to move on their various ideas, for example, merchants of Yokohama settlement held a meeting on February 28, and decided to seek compensation from the Meiji Government for the damage caused by counterfeit money, or some merchants started to buy up the counterfeit money which had slumped anticipating the next recall.</e>
<cmt>Further → Furthermore 「など様々な思惑が動き出し始めていた」は、「損害賠償を求める動き」と「贋貨の買占め」の両方だと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, when this series of exchange spread around Japan and foreign countries, people began to move on their various ideas, for example, merchants of Yokohama settlement held a meeting on February 28, and decided to seek compensation from the Meiji Government for the damage caused by counterfeit money, or some merchants started to buy up the counterfeit money which had slumped anticipating the next recall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="29">
<j>3月18日に東京に入った大隈は各国公使と会談する一方で、贋貨整理案の策定を急いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">OKUMA, who entered Tokyo on March 18, talked with ministers of each country while hurrying to work out the counterfeit money disposal plan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">OKUMA, who entered Tokyo on March 18, talked with ministers of each country while hurrying to work out the counterfeit money disposal plan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OKUMA, who entered Tokyo on March 18, talked with ministers of each country while hurrying to work out the counterfeit money disposal plan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>その結果、太政官の許可を得次第、3月30日（末日）をもって「新通貨の発行決定・金札（太政官札）を正貨同様の通用（等価化）・金札相場の廃止」という第1弾の新方針を布告する準備が整うまでに至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, they went as far as preparing the first declaration of their plan &quot;decision to issue new currency, using the kinsatsu (daijokan money) as the same as a specie, and the abolition of the market price of kinsatsu&quot; on March 30, once permission from the Daijokan (Grand Council of State) was received.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, they went as far as preparing for the first proclamation of their new policy such as &quot;decision to issue new currency, using the kinsatsu (Dajokan-satsu) as the same as a specie (in equal value), and the abolition of the market price of kinsatsu&quot; on March 30, once permission from the Daijokan (Grand Council of State) was received.</e>
<cmt>第1弾の新方針を布告する準備が整う preparing the first declaration of their plan → preparing for the first proclamation of their new policy　（等価化）→ (in equal value)　</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, they went as far as preparing for the first proclamation of their new policy such as &apos;decision to issue new currency, using the kinsatsu (Dajokan-satsu) as the same as a specie (in equal value), and the abolition of the market price of kinsatsu&apos; on March 30, once permission from the Daijokan (Grand Council of State) was received.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot; → &apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>ところが、布告前日の29日になって太政官より反対論が出されて布告は中止されて、正式決定を前提として大阪に布告文を送付している途中であった飛脚が東京に呼び戻されることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, on the day before the declaration, the 29th, an opposing argument by the Daijokan was released so the declaration was canceled, and the express messenger who was in the middle of sending the declaration letter to Osaka, with the assumption that this declaration would be a formal decision, was called back to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, on the day before the declaration, the 29th, an opposing argument by the Daijokan was released so the declaration was canceled, and the express messenger who was in the middle of sending the declaration letter to Osaka, with the assumption that this declaration would be a formal decision, was called back to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, on the day before the declaration, the 29th, an opposing argument by the Daijokan was released so the declaration was canceled, and the express messenger who was in the middle of sending the declaration letter to Osaka, with the assumption that this declaration would be a formal decision, was called back to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>反対の中心人物は明治政府の実力者大久保利通であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main person who was against the declaration was Toshimichi OKUBO, a formidable member of the Meiji Government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main person who was against the declaration was Toshimichi OKUBO, a powerful figure of the Meiji Government.</e>
<cmt>実力者 a formidable member → a powerful figure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main person who was against the declaration was Toshimichi OKUBO, a powerful figure of the Meiji Government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>この日、大久保が岩倉具視に対して送った書簡に「町人という者は浅墓なものなので、少しお上がハキハキと申し付ければ、如何様にも従うものである （要旨）。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On a letter OKUBO sent to Tomomi IWAKURA on this day, it said &quot;townspeople are foolish people, so if the emperor instructs them a little clearly, they will follow even if it was a hoax.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On a letter OKUBO sent to Tomomi IWAKURA on this day, it said &quot;townspeople are foolish people, so if the Okami (political authorities) instructs them a little clearly, they will follow even if it was a hoax.</e>
<cmt>「お上」は次のセルにも出てくるのですが、Okami (political authorities) とした方が意味が統一すると思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On a letter OKUBO sent to Tomomi IWAKURA on this day, it said &apos;townspeople are foolish people, so if the Okami (political authorities) instructs them a little clearly, they will follow even if it was a hoax. (the gist)&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理&quot; &quot; → &apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>このように、商人は「お上」の命に唯々諾々と従う存在であるのだから、政治的基盤が未だ脆弱で「お上」としての権威を十分に持っているとは言えない明治政府が慌てて貨幣改革を行うことによって、万が一命令が行き渡らずに「お上」（＝明治政府）に対する「万民の信」の無さと無力ぶりを内外に示すことになっては政権の崩壊につながると考え、通貨改革を不要不急のことと捉えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(the gist)&quot; like it says above, merchants were people who obediently followed the emperor&apos;s orders, so OKUBO thought that if the Meiji Government, which was still feeble and did not have enough authority as the &quot;emperor,&quot; reformed the currency in a flurry, by doing so if in the worst case scenario, the orders did not get across, this would reveal the lack of &quot;people&apos;s trust&quot; in the &quot;emperor&quot; (= Meiji Government) and their powerlessness to their own country and foreign countries, which would lead to the collapse of the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the gist)&quot; like it says above, merchants were people who obediently followed the Okami (political authorities)&apos;s orders, so OKUBO thought that if the Meiji Government, which was still feeble and did not have enough authority as the &quot;Okami (political authorities)&quot; reformed the currency in a flurry, by doing so if in the worst case scenario, the orders did not get across, this would reveal the lack of &quot;people&apos;s trust&quot; in the &quot;Okami (political authorities)&quot; (= Meiji Government) and their powerlessness to their own country and foreign countries, which would lead to the collapse of the government, therefore he considered the monetary reform was nonessential and nonurgent.</e>
<cmt>「訳漏れ」・・・通貨改革を不要不急のことと捉えていた。 「お上」 emperor, &quot;emperor&quot; (= Meiji Government) → Okami (political authorities)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Like it says above, merchants were people who obediently followed the Okami (political authorities)&apos;s orders, so OKUBO thought that if the Meiji Government, which was still feeble and did not have enough authority as the &apos;Okami&apos; (political authorities) reformed the currency in a flurry, by doing so if in the worst case scenario, the orders did not get across, this would reveal the lack of &apos;people&apos;s trust&apos; in the &apos;Okami&apos; (political authorities) (Meiji Government) and their powerlessness to their own country and foreign countries, which would lead to the collapse of the government, therefore he considered the monetary reform was nonessential and nonurgent.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理&quot; &quot; → &apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>更に大久保は当時はまだ表にする事は避けていたものの、贋貨整理の過程で自分の出身である薩摩藩が秘かに贋貨を作っていた事実が内外に明らかになった時の反響を危惧していたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, OKUBO was still avoiding to reveal this at the time, but he was apprehensive about the response when the fact was made clear that during the disposing process of counterfeit money, his own domain, the Satsuma Domain was secretly making counterfeit money was made.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, OKUBO was still avoiding to reveal this at the time, but he was apprehensive about the response when the fact was made clear during the disposing process of counterfeit money that his own domain, the Satsuma Domain, was secretly making counterfeit money.</e>
<cmt>when the fact was made clear that during the disposing process of counterfeit money の that の位置を修正。文末の was made は不要なため削除。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, OKUBO was still avoiding to reveal this at the time, but he was apprehensive about the response when the fact was made clear during the disposing process of counterfeit money that his own domain, the Satsuma Domain, was secretly making counterfeit money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="36">
<j>この状況に大隈は落胆し、30日に現職在任のままで兼務していた会計官副知事（由利の後任）を辞任することも考えるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">OKUMA was disappointed with this situation, and on the 30th, he began to think about resigning his post as a finance office vice prefectural governor, which he held along with his present post.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">OKUMA was disappointed with this situation, and on the 30th, he began to think about resigning his post as a finance office vice prefectural governor (successor to Yuri), which he held along with his present post.</e>
<cmt>「訳漏れ」・・・（由利の後任）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OKUMA was disappointed with this situation, and on the 30th, he began to think about resigning his post as a finance office vice prefectural governor (successor to Yuri), which he held along with his present post.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>この危機を救ったのは病気静養中で東京にいなかった木戸孝允であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takayoshi KIDO, who was not in Tokyo because he was resting because of illness, was the one who saved this crisis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takayoshi KIDO, who was not in Tokyo because he was resting because of illness, was the one who saved this crisis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takayoshi KIDO, who was not in Tokyo because he was resting because of illness, was the one who saved this crisis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>木戸はこの事情を知って、4月17日付で吉井友実に託して大久保に送った手紙において、貨幣の流通の現状は「全身不随」であり、このような状況を放置しては大政一新（明治維新）はままならないこと、そして遠回しながら薩摩藩が自ら贋貨製造の事実を明らかにしなければ、維新における薩摩藩の名声は地に落ちることになると説いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KIDO found out about these circumstances, and on a letter dated April 17 which he entrusted Tomozane YOSHII and sent to OKUBO, he explained that the present situation of the currency circulation is &quot;totally paralyzed,&quot; and that if this situation is left alone the Imperial Rule Restoration (Meiji Restoration) would not go as they wanted, along with indirectly saying that if the Satsuma Domain did not reveal by themselves the fact that they were manufacturing counterfeit money, the Satsuma Domain&apos;s reputation regarding the restoration would be ruined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KIDO found out about these circumstances, and on a letter dated April 17 which he entrusted Tomozane YOSHII and sent to OKUBO, he explained that the present situation of the currency circulation is &quot;totally paralyzed,&quot; and that if this situation is left alone the Imperial Rule Restoration (Meiji Restoration) would not go as they wanted, along with indirectly saying that if the Satsuma Domain did not reveal by themselves the fact that they were manufacturing counterfeit money, the Satsuma Domain&apos;s reputation regarding the restoration would be ruined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">KIDO found out about these circumstances, and on a letter dated April 17 which he entrusted Tomozane YOSHII and sent to OKUBO, he explained that the present situation of the currency circulation is &apos;totally paralyzed,&apos; and that if this situation is left alone the Imperial Rule Restoration (Meiji Restoration) would not go as they wanted, along with indirectly saying that if the Satsuma Domain did not reveal by themselves the fact that they were manufacturing counterfeit money, the Satsuma Domain&apos;s reputation regarding the restoration would be ruined.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot; → &apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>続いて2日後には岩倉具視にも別に書簡を送り、通貨改革を行なわなければ却って「万民の信」を失い、外国からは不正の汚名を着せられることになるとして、大久保に対する説得と大隈への助力を求めたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two days following this, KIDO sent a separate letter to Tomomi IWAKURA, asking him to persuade OKUBO and helping OKUMA, saying that if the currency reform is not put through, the &quot;people&apos;s trust&quot; will be lost and Japan would be branded by foreign countries with fraud.</e>
<cmt>セル５４と５５は一つの文章のはずです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two days following this, KIDO sent a separate letter to Tomomi IWAKURA, asking him to persuade OKUBO and helping OKUMA, saying that if the currency reform is not put through, the &quot;people&apos;s trust&quot; will be lost and Japan would be branded by foreign countries with fraud.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two days following this, KIDO sent a separate letter to Tomomi IWAKURA, asking him to persuade OKUBO and helping OKUMA, saying that if the currency reform is not put through, the &quot;people&apos;s trust&quot; will be lost and Japan would be branded by foreign countries with fraud.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>ここにおいて大久保も事の重大さを認識して、吉井や鹿児島市滞在中の西郷隆盛ら薩摩藩出身者と相談した上で大久保個人による形式で薩摩藩への建白書を提出して「皇国（日本）の安危興亡」を救うために「御国（薩摩藩）」が身を犠牲にすることで「天下に大義を唱える」ことが可能となることを論じて、直ちに贋貨鋳造を取りやめて事実を明らかにすることで、薩摩藩が他藩に対して優位に立てると主張したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here, OKUBO became aware of the importance of the matter, and after consulting people from the Satsuma Domain such as YOSHII and Takamori SAIGO who was staying in Kagoshima City, OKUBO presented a petition individually, arguing that when the &quot;Satsuma Domain&quot; sacrifices it&apos;s life to save the &quot;empire&apos;s (Japan) crisis,&quot; then it becomes possible to &quot;advocate great moral causes to the world&quot; and he also insisted that by stopping the coining of counterfeit money and revealing the truth, the Satsuma Domain would be able to have an advantage over other domains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Here, OKUBO became aware of the importance of the matter, and after consulting people from the Satsuma Domain such as YOSHII and Takamori SAIGO who was staying in Kagoshima City, OKUBO presented a petition individually, arguing that when &quot;your domain (the Satsuma Domain)&quot; sacrifices its life to save the &quot;empire&apos;s (Japan) crisis,&quot; then it becomes possible to &quot;preach the justice to the world&quot; and he also insisted that by stopping the coining of counterfeit money and revealing the truth, the Satsuma Domain would be able to have an advantage over other domains.</e>
<cmt>it&apos;s life → its life, 　　「御国（薩摩藩）」　&quot;Satsuma Domain&quot;→&quot;your domain (the Satsuma Domain)&quot; 　「天下に大義を唱える」 &quot;advocate great moral causes to the world&quot; → &quot;preach the justice to the world&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Here, OKUBO became aware of the importance of the matter, and after consulting people from the Satsuma Domain such as YOSHII and Takamori SAIGO who was staying in Kagoshima City, OKUBO presented a petition individually, arguing that when &apos;your domain (the Satsuma Domain)&apos; sacrifices its life to save the &apos;empire&apos;s (Japan) crisis,&apos; then it becomes possible to &apos;preach the justice to the world&apos; and he also insisted that by stopping the coining of counterfeit money and revealing the truth, the Satsuma Domain would be able to have an advantage over other domains.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot; → &apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>また、先に中止させた大隈による通貨改革の布告への反対を撤回したため、改めて4月29日をもって交付されることとなったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, because OKUBO withdrew his opposition to the currency reform declaration by OKUMA which he had canceled before, the reform was rescheduled to be issued on April 29.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, because OKUBO withdrew his opposition to the currency reform declaration by OKUMA which he had canceled before, the reform was rescheduled to be issued on April 29.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, because OKUBO withdrew his opposition to the currency reform declaration by OKUMA which he had canceled before, the reform was rescheduled to be issued on April 29.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="42">
<j>以後、大隈（4月17日会計官副知事専任、7月6日大蔵省発足により大蔵大輔に移行）を主導として通貨改革に関する様々な布告が出されることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, various declarations concerning the currency reform was put out with OKUMA (on April 17 he became a full-time finance office vice prefectural governor, and on July 6, he was inaugurated by the ministry of finance and changed to Okura no taifu [a senior assistant minister of the Ministry of Treasury]) as the main leader.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterwards, various declarations concerning the currency reform were put out with OKUMA (on April 17 he became a full-time finance office vice prefectural governor, and on July 6, he transferred to Okura no taifu [a senior assistant minister of the Ministry of Treasury] due to the establishment of Ministry of finance) as the main leader.</e>
<cmt>was → were   大蔵省発足により大蔵大輔に移行 he was inaugurated by the ministry of finance and changed to Okura no taifu → he transferred to Okura no taifu due to the establishment of Ministry of finance</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterwards, various declarations concerning the currency reform were put out with OKUMA (on April 17 he became a full-time finance office vice prefectural governor, and on July 6, he transferred to Okura no taifu [a senior assistant minister of the Ministry of Treasury] due to the establishment of Ministry of finance) as the main leader.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>以下はその主なものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following are the main aspects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following are the main aspects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following are the main aspects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="44">
<j>4月29日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 29th</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 29th</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 29th</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>－新通貨の発行決定・金札（太政官札）を正貨同様の通用（等価化）・金札相場の廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">-Decision to issue new currency, using the Kinshasa (Daijokan money) as the same as a specie, and the abolition of the market price of kinsatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Decision to issue new currency, using the Kinsatsu (Dajokan-satsu) as the same as a specie (in equal value), and the abolition of the market price of kinsatsu.</e>
<cmt>Kinshasha → Kinsatsu, （等価化）→ (in equal value)　太政官札 → Dajokan-satsu (用語集より）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Decision to issue new currency, using the Kinsatsu (Dajokan-satsu) as the same as a specie (in equal value), and the abolition of the market price of kinsatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="46">
<j>5月2日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May 2nd</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">May 2nd</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 2nd</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>－金札・正貨の交換を禁じ（等価であるため）、「太政官札」の呼称を禁じる（太政官以外に通貨発行機関が存在するとの誤解を与えるため）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">-Forbid the exchange of kinsatsu/specie money (because they are equivalent), and forbid the naming &quot;Daijokan money&quot; (because this would lead to a misunderstanding that a machine that issues currency besides the Daijokan exists).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Forbid the exchange of kinsatsu/specie money (because they are equivalent), and forbid the naming &quot;Dajokan-satsu&quot; (because this would lead to a misunderstanding that another organization that issues currency besides the Daijokan exists).</e>
<cmt>太政官札 → Dajokan-satsu (用語集より）   機関 a machine → another organization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Forbid the exchange of kinsatsu/specie money (because they are equivalent), and forbid the naming &apos;Dajokan-satsu&apos; (because this would lead to a misunderstanding that another organization that issues currency besides the Daijokan exists).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot; → &apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="48">
<j>5月28日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May 28th</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">May 28th</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 28th</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>－金札の発行量を現状の3,250万両に留めて増刷を停止する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">-Keep the amount of issued kinsatsu to the present 3,250 thousand ryo, and stop additional printing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keep the amount of issued kinsatsu to the present 32.5 million ryo, and stop additional printing.</e>
<cmt>3,250万両 3,250 thousand ryo → 32.5 million ryo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keep the amount of issued kinsatsu to the present 32.5 million ryo, and stop additional printing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>両替商・その他商人は贋金による取引を一切禁じる（贋金が鋳造・流通している事実を内外に正式に公表する）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Money-exchange business and other exchanges by merchants using counterfeit money is strictly forbidden (the fact that Japan was coining and circulating counterfeit money would be announced to Japan and foreign countries).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Money-exchange business and other exchanges by merchants using counterfeit money is strictly forbidden (the fact that Japan was coining and circulating counterfeit money would be announced to Japan and foreign countries).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Money-exchange business and other exchanges by merchants using counterfeit money is strictly forbidden (the fact that Japan was coining and circulating counterfeit money would be announced to Japan and foreign countries).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>明治5年までに新通貨を発行して金札との交換を行うまでの間、金札の流通を妨げてはならない（金札が新通貨発行までの正貨の代替となるため）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The circulation of kinsatsu must be prevented until the new currency is issued and is exchanged with the kinsatsu in 1872 (this is because the kinsatsu was a substitution of the specie until the new currency was issued).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The circulation of kinsatsu must not be prevented until the new currency is issued and is exchanged with the kinsatsu by 1872 (this is because the kinsatsu was a substitution of the specie until the new currency was issued).</e>
<cmt>妨げてはならない must be prevented → must not be prevented    明治5年までに in 1872 → by 1872</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The circulation of kinsatsu must not be prevented until the new currency is issued and is exchanged with the kinsatsu by 1872 (this is because the kinsatsu was a substitution of the specie until the new currency was issued).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="52">
<j>6月6日（太政官達）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 6th (Daijokan tasshi [proclamation by the Grand Council of State])</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 6th (Daijokan tasshi [proclamation by the Grand Council of State])</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 6th (Daijokan tasshi [proclamation by the Grand Council of State])</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>－三都府（東京・京都・大阪）にある金札を回収して各府藩県に対して禄高1万石あたり2,500両分を6・7月の2回に分けて交付するので、それに相当する正貨を所定期間までに会計官に納付すること（この場合の「正貨」には贋金が混じっている事を黙認している）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- Since kinsatsu in the three prefectures (Tokyo/Kyoto/Osaka) was toD81 be collected, and each prefecture would be issued 2,500 ryo for each stipend of ten thousand Goku crop yields, split between June and July, the specie which corresponds to this is to be payed to the finance office by the appointed time (it was silently accepted that the &quot;specie&quot; in this case had counterfeit money mixed in it).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since kinsatsu in the three prefectures (Tokyo/Kyoto/Osaka) was to be collected, and each prefecture would be issued 2,500 ryo for each stipend of ten thousand Goku crop yields, in twice of June and July, the specie which corresponds to this is to be payed to the finance office by the appointed time (it was silently accepted that the &quot;specie&quot; in this case had counterfeit money mixed in it).</e>
<cmt>6・7月の２回に分けて split between June and July→ in twice of June and July 　payed → paid 不要な文字&apos;D81&apos;を削除。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since kinsatsu in the three prefectures (Tokyo/Kyoto/Osaka) was to be collected, and each prefecture would be issued 2,500 ryo for each stipend of ten thousand Goku crop yields, in twice of June and July, the specie which corresponds to this is to be payed to the finance office by the appointed time (it was silently accepted that the &apos;specie&apos; in this case had counterfeit money mixed in it).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot; → &apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="54">
<j>6月17日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 17th</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 17th</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 17th</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>－版籍奉還</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- return of lands and people to the emperor</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">- return of lands and people to the emperor</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">- return of lands and people to the emperor</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="56">
<j>さて、この2月30日の新政府からの通告以後、一旦は相場が安定してきたために明治政府の方針を見守ることにしていたパークスは、大隈の予想以上の急激な方針とその後の独自調査で予想以上に莫大な量が流通していることが判明した諸藩による贋貨が版籍奉還後に「新政府とは無関係である」と切り捨てられる事を憂慮していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Now, since after the notification by the new government on February 30, the market price was steady for awhile, Parkes decided to watch over the Meiji Government&apos;s policies, but after seeing that OKUMA&apos;s policy was more sudden than expected and after finding out through independent investigations that the amount of money circulating was bigger than expected, he became worried that the counterfeit money by the domains would be discarded after the return of lands and people to the emperor saying that &quot;it is unrelated to the new government.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Now, since after the notification by the new government on February 30, the market price was steady for a while, Parkes decided to watch over the Meiji Government&apos;s policies, but after seeing that OKUMA&apos;s policy was more sudden than expected and after finding out through independent investigations that the amount of counterfeit money circulated by various domains was bigger than expected, he became worried that those things would be discarded after the return of lands and people to the emperor saying that &quot;it is unrelated to the new government.&quot;</e>
<cmt>awhile → a while, 諸藩による　by various domains, 憂慮事項は予想以上の贋貨流通と大隈の急激な方針の２点だと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Now, since after the notification by the new government on February 30, the market price was steady for a while, Parkes decided to watch over the Meiji Government&apos;s policies, but after seeing that OKUMA&apos;s policy was more sudden than expected and after finding out through independent investigations that the amount of counterfeit money circulated by various domains was bigger than expected, he became worried that those things would be discarded after the return of lands and people to the emperor saying that &apos;it is unrelated to the new government.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot; → &apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>特にイギリスは幕末以来薩摩藩と多額の取引を行っており、その際に支払われた贋金が無効と言う事になれば、イギリスの商人や企業が打撃を受け、日本の貿易は大混乱に陥る事を警戒したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">England in particular had traded large amounts of money with the Satsuma Domain since the end of Edo period, and Parkes was cautious about the possibility that if the counterfeit money payed during this time was to become invalid, English merchants and businesses would suffer losses, and Japanese trade would fall into great confusion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">England in particular had traded large amounts of money with the Satsuma Domain since the end of Edo period, and Parkes was cautious about the possibility that if the counterfeit money paid during this time was to become invalid, English merchants and businesses would suffer losses, and Japanese trade would fall into great confusion.</e>
<cmt>payed → paid</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">England in particular had traded large amounts of money with the Satsuma Domain since the end of Edo period, and Parkes was cautious about the possibility that if the counterfeit money paid during this time was to become invalid, English merchants and businesses would suffer losses, and Japanese trade would fall into great confusion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>そこでパークスは他の4国公使と協議して、7月6日に明治政府に対して覚書を送付して、政府が大隈の方針を貫徹出来るのか、そして諸藩が発行した贋貨について政府がどうするのかを確認するための協議を政府側と持つことを希望することを通知したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here, Parkes consulted with ministers of the other four countries, and on July 6, he sent a memorandum to the Meiji Government notifying their request for the government to hold a conference to confirm that the government would be able to carry out Okuma&apos;s policy, and also confirm what the government was going to do about the counterfeit money that the domains issued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Here, Parkes consulted with ministers of the other four countries, and on July 6, he sent a memorandum to the Meiji Government notifying their request for the government to hold a conference to confirm that the government would be able to carry out Okuma&apos;s policy, and also confirm what the government was going to do about the counterfeit money that the domains issued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Here, Parkes consulted with ministers of the other four countries, and on July 6, he sent a memorandum to the Meiji Government notifying their request for the government to hold a conference to confirm that the government would be able to carry out Okuma&apos;s policy, and also confirm what the government was going to do about the counterfeit money that the domains issued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>高輪談判と新通貨制度への移行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shift towards the Takanawa negotiation and new currency system</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takanawa negotiation and shift to new currency system</e>
<cmt>「移行」するのは「新通貨制度」だと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takanawa negotiation and shift to new currency system</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>高輪談判</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takanawa negotiation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takanawa negotiation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takanawa negotiation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="59">
<j>7月10日、東京に置かれた英国大使館を外務省への改編に伴って外務卿に就任した澤宣嘉と同じく大蔵省への改編に伴って大蔵大輔に就任した大隈がパークスを訪問する形式で予備会談が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 10, a preliminary meeting in the form of Nobuyoshi SAWA, who assumed the position of chief of Foreign Ministry accompanying the reorganization of the English Embassy placed in Tokyo to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, along with OKUMA, who similarly assumed the position of Okura no taifu (senior assistant minister of the Minister of Treasury) accompanying the reorganization of the Ministry of Finance, visiting Parkes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 10, a preliminary meeting was held in the form of visit Parkes in British Embassy in Tokyo by Nobuyoshi SAWA, who assumed the position of chief of Foreign Ministry accompanying the reorganization to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, along with OKUMA, who similarly assumed the position of Okura no taifu (senior assistant minister of the Minister of Treasury) accompanying the reorganization to the Ministry of Finance.</e>
<cmt>「東京に置かれた英国大使館を」「パークスを訪問する形式で予備会談が行われた」の意味だと思いますが、trans 1では「英国大使館が外務省に改編した」という意味で英訳されていました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 10, a preliminary meeting was held in the form of visit Parkes in British Embassy in Tokyo by Nobuyoshi SAWA, who assumed the position of chief of Foreign Ministry accompanying the reorganization to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, along with OKUMA, who similarly assumed the position of Okura no taifu (senior assistant minister of the Minister of Treasury) accompanying the reorganization to the Ministry of Finance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>これに続いて7月12日に高輪接遇所において正式な会談が開催された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following this, a formal conference was held in Takanawa setsugusho on July 12.</e>
<cmt>接遇所の適訳が見つからなかったので、setsugushoとしてあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following this, a formal conference was held in Takanawa setsugusho on July 12.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following this, a formal conference was held in Takanawa setsugusho on July 12.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>これを「高輪談判」と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is called the &quot;Takanawa negotiation.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is called the &quot;Takanawa negotiation.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is called the &apos;Takanawa negotiation.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot; → &apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>日本側からは太政官の最高責任者であった右大臣三条実美・大納言岩倉具視・外務卿澤宣嘉・大蔵大輔大隈重信・外務大輔寺島宗則が出席し、伊藤博文がこれを補佐した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Japan, the highest officials of Daijokan, Minister of the Right Sanetomi Sanjo, chief councilor of state Tomomi IWAKURA, chief of Foreign Ministry Nobuyoshi SAWA, Okura no taifu (senior assistant minister of the Ministry of Treasury) Shigenobu Okuma, and Gaimu-taifu (post of Foreign Ministry) Munenori Terashima attended, and Hirobumi ITO was the assistant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Japan, the highest officials of Daijokan, Minister of the Right Sanetomi Sanjo, chief councilor of state Tomomi IWAKURA, chief of Foreign Ministry Nobuyoshi SAWA, Okura no taifu (senior assistant minister of the Ministry of Treasury) Shigenobu Okuma, and Gaimu-taifu (post of Foreign Ministry) Munenori Terashima attended, and Hirobumi ITO was the assistant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Japan, the highest officials of Daijokan, Minister of the Right Sanetomi Sanjo, chief councilor of state Tomomi IWAKURA, chief of Foreign Ministry Nobuyoshi SAWA, Okura no taifu (senior assistant minister of the Ministry of Treasury) Shigenobu Okuma, and Gaimu-taifu (post of Foreign Ministry) Munenori Terashima attended, and Hirobumi ITO was the assistant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>対する公使側はパークス（イギリス）・オウトレ（フランス）・ロバート・ヴァン・ヴォールクンバーグ（アメリカ）・コント・デ・ラ・ツール（イタリア）・マックス・フォン・ブライト（ドイツ）であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ministers on the other side were Parkes (England), (France), Robert Van Valkenburg (America), (Italy), and Max von Sydow (Germany).</e>
<cmt>オウトレ　と　コント・デ・ラ・ツール　の英語のスペルを調べてみましたけどわかりませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ministers on the other side were Parkes (England), オウトレ (France), Robert Van Valkenburg (America), コント・デ・ラ・ツール (Italy), and Max von ブライト (Germany).</e>
<cmt>マックス・フォン・ブライト（ドイツ）を Max von Sydow (Germany) と英訳していますが、Sydow は間違いですので、その部分はカタカナで残しました。また、 オウトレ と　コント・デ・ラ・ツール については空白になっていましたので、わかりやすいようカタカナで残しておきました。（私も調べましたが見つかりませんでした。）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ministers on the other side were Parkes (England), オウトレ (France), Robert Van Valkenburg (America), コント・デ・ラ・ツール (Italy), and Max von ブライト (Germany).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="64">
<j>現在残されている談判に記した記録によれば、談判は終始パークスの独断場であり、明治政府が改税約書違反の悪貨を鋳造し、諸藩が贋貨を鋳造していたとする事実を示す証拠を次々と突きつけていった（一部記録によると政府側の要領を得ない回答に興奮して、傍にあったコップを叩き割ってしまったとされている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the records written down during the negotiation that remains today, the negotiation was entirely in the hands of Parkes from start to finish, and he confronted the government with evidence indicating the fact that the Meiji Government coined bad money violating the kaietsuyakusho, and that domains coined counterfeit money (according to a part of the records, Parkes became worked up over an answer by the government which was off the point, and hit and broke a cup near him).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the records written down during the negotiation that remains today, the negotiation was entirely in the hands of Parkes from start to finish, and he confronted the government with evidence indicating the fact that the Meiji Government coined bad money violating the kaizeiyakusho, and that domains coined counterfeit money (according to a part of the records, Parkes became worked up over an answer by the government which was off the point, and hit and broke a cup near him).</e>
<cmt>改税約書 kaietsuyakusho → kaizeiyakusho　（日本語の読み方が間違っています)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the records written down during the negotiation that remains today, the negotiation was entirely in the hands of Parkes from start to finish, and he confronted the government with evidence indicating the fact that the Meiji Government coined bad money violating the kaizeiyakusho, and that domains coined counterfeit money (according to a part of the records, Parkes became worked up over an answer by the government which was off the point, and hit and broke a cup near him).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>明治政府は最後まで体面上悪貨鋳造の事実を認めることを拒否したが、複数の藩が贋貨を鋳造していた事実を認めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Meiji Government refused to admit the fact that they coined bad money until the end for the sake of appearance, but they did admit the fact that several domains had coined counterfeit money.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Meiji Government refused to admit the fact that they coined bad money until the end for the sake of appearance, but they did admit the fact that several domains had coined counterfeit money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Meiji Government refused to admit the fact that they coined bad money until the end for the sake of appearance, but they did admit the fact that several domains had coined counterfeit money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>その後、通貨改革によって正貨・贋貨を問わず全ての現行貨幣を引き揚げて早急に（既に大隈より明治5年11月までという案が出されていた）に引き換えを行うこと、応急措置として外国人の所持する二分金（実は一番問題となっていた政府及び諸藩発行の悪貨・贋貨でもあった）の検査を行って、封包を行って検印を施し、それを行ったものについてはたとえ贋貨であっても正貨と等価による納税または交換を認めることを了承させられたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this, the Japanese government was forced to consent with pulling out all current currency, regardless of it being specie or counterfeit (it was already proposed by OKUMA that this would be done by May 11), and exchanging it, and as a temporary measure, the nifungane owned by foreigners (this bad money/counterfeit issued by the government and domains was the biggest problem) were to be examined and encapsulated, put a stamp of approval, and handed out, and those that went though this were to be accepted as tax payment or exchange equivalent to the specie even if it was counterfeit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this, the Japanese government was forced to consent to pulling out all current currency, regardless of it being specie or counterfeit (it was already proposed by OKUMA that this would be done by May 11), and exchanging it immediately, and as a temporary measure, the nibukin owned by foreigners (this bad money/counterfeit issued by the government and domains was the biggest problem) were to be examined, encapsulated, put a stamp of approval, and handed out, and those that went though this were to be accepted as tax payment or exchange equivalent to the specie even if it was counterfeit.</e>
<cmt>二分金 nifun gane → nibukin (日本語の読み方が間違っています） consent with → consent to</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this, the Japanese government was forced to consent to pulling out all current currency, regardless of it being specie or counterfeit (it was already proposed by OKUMA that this would be done by May 11), and exchanging it immediately, and as a temporary measure, the nibukin owned by foreigners (this bad money/counterfeit issued by the government and domains was the biggest problem) were to be examined, encapsulated, put a stamp of approval, and handed out, and those that went though this were to be accepted as tax payment or exchange equivalent to the specie even if it was counterfeit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>その一方で、パークスが談判を仕切ったためにフランス公使によって出された損害賠償要求は事実上無視され、大隈の通貨改革についての異論は公使達からも三条・岩倉ら太政官首脳からも出されること無く、内外からの承認を得る形となり、結果的には明治政府による自主的な通貨改革そのものについては、大隈案に沿った形での方針が認められることになったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, because Parkes ran the negotiation, the claim for loss put out by the French minister was virtually ignored, and objections of OKUMA&apos;s currency reform did not occur by the ministers or the heads of the Daijokan, such as SANJYO and IWAKURA, leading to an agreement from both Japan and foreign countries, and as a result the independent currency reform by the Meiji Government itself was accepted to take the shape of a policy in accordance to OKUMA&apos;s proposal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, because Parkes ran the negotiation, the claim for loss put out by the French minister was virtually ignored, and objections to OKUMA&apos;s currency reform did not occur by the ministers or the heads of the Daijokan, such as SANJYO and IWAKURA, leading to an agreement from both Japan and foreign countries, and as a result the independent currency reform by the Meiji Government itself was accepted to take the shape of a policy in accordance with OKUMA&apos;s proposal.</e>
<cmt>objections of OKUMA&apos;s currency reform → objections to OKUMA&apos;s currency reform, 　　in accordance to → in accordance with</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, because Parkes ran the negotiation, the claim for loss put out by the French minister was virtually ignored, and objections to OKUMA&apos;s currency reform did not occur by the ministers or the heads of the Daijokan, such as SANJYO and IWAKURA, leading to an agreement from both Japan and foreign countries, and as a result the independent currency reform by the Meiji Government itself was accepted to take the shape of a policy in accordance with OKUMA&apos;s proposal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>その後、7月19日に場所と出席者はそのままで再度開催されたものの、それは前回決定された事項の具体的な実施要綱についての説明など細部の調整のみで終了している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, on July 19, the conference was held again at the same place with the same participants, but this ended with only adjustments of details such as concrete explanations of the implementation guidelines for matters decided during the last conference.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterwards, on July 19, the conference was held again at the same place with the same participants, but this ended with only adjustments of details such as concrete explanations of the implementation guidelines for matters decided during the last conference.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterwards, on July 19, the conference was held again at the same place with the same participants, but this ended with only adjustments of details such as concrete explanations of the implementation guidelines for matters decided during the last conference.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>通貨改革と贋貨処理</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Currency reform and counterfeit money disposal</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currency reform and counterfeit money disposal</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Currency reform and counterfeit money disposal</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="69">
<j>とりあえず、大隈の通貨改革は明治政府の方針、そして国際公約として認められたが、その実現までにはまだ4つの課題があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">OKUMA&apos;s currency reform was recognized as the Meiji Government&apos;s policy along with as an international pledge for the moment, but to be realized, there were four problems.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">OKUMA&apos;s currency reform was recognized as the Meiji Government&apos;s policy along with as an international pledge for the moment, but to be realized, there were four problems.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OKUMA&apos;s currency reform was recognized as the Meiji Government&apos;s policy along with as an international pledge for the moment, but to be realized, there were four problems.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="70">
<j>高輪談判で合意した外国人保有二分金の真贋調査（検勘）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The examination of the genuineness or spuriousness of nifungane held by foreigners, as agreed at the Takanawa negotiation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The examination of the genuineness or spuriousness of nibukin held by foreigners, as agreed at the Takanawa negotiation.</e>
<cmt>二分金 nifun gane → nibukin (日本語の読み方が間違っています）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The examination of the genuineness or spuriousness of nibukin held by foreigners, as agreed at the Takanawa negotiation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="71">
<j>贋貨を発行した諸藩に対する処分の実施の是非。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The enforcement of punishment for the domains which issued counterfeit money, by all means.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rights and wrongs of enforcement of punishment for the domains which issued counterfeit money.</e>
<cmt>是非　The rights and wrongs</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rights and wrongs of enforcement of punishment for the domains which issued counterfeit money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="72">
<j>贋貨と正貨の交換比率と期限の決定。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The decision of the time limit and exchange rate of the counterfeit and specie money.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The decision of the time limit and exchange rate of the counterfeit and specie money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The decision of the time limit and exchange rate of the counterfeit and specie money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="73">
<j>新しい通貨制度の決定とそれを実施するための新たな造幣施設の建設。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The decision of the new currency system, and the construction of a new facility to enforce this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The decision of the new currency system, and the construction of a new mint to enforce this.</e>
<cmt>造幣施設 facility → mint</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The decision of the new currency system, and the construction of a new mint to enforce this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>開港場・開市場での検勘</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Authenticity testing at open ports and open markets.</e>
<cmt>検勘の適訳が見つからなかったので、KENKANとしてあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Authenticity testing at open ports and open markets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Authenticity testing at open ports and open markets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="74">
<j>19日の会談終了後、澤と大隈・伊藤は直ちに久世治作・上野景範・花房義質ら若手官僚と東京の有力両替商からなるチームを編成して全国の開港場・開市場で外国人の保有二分金の検勘を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the conference ended on the 19th, SAWA, OKUMA, and ITO immedieatly organize a team with young bereaucracy and influential money exchangers in Tokyo, and started the kenkan of foreigner&apos;s nifungane at open ports and markets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the conference ended on the 19th, SAWA, OKUMA, and ITO immediately organized a team with young bureaucracy and influential money exchangers in Tokyo, and started conducting authenticity tests on foreigner&apos;s nibukin at open ports and markets.</e>
<cmt>二分金 nifun gane → nibukin (日本語の読み方が間違っています）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the conference ended on the 19th, SAWA, OKUMA, and ITO immediately organized a team with young bureaucracy and influential money exchangers in Tokyo, and started conducting authenticity tests on foreigner&apos;s nibukin at open ports and markets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>東京・横浜の外国人に対しては21日に各国公使を通じて提出させた二分金の検勘を23日より開始して、東京では同日中、日本屈指の貿易港であった横浜でも25日までに終わらせることに成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For foreigners in Tokyo and Yokohama, the kenkan of the nifungane they handed in through ministers of each country started on the 23rd, and the officials succeeded in finishing on the same day in Tokyo, and even in Yokohama, which was the Japan&apos;s leading trading port, they managed to finish by the 25th.</e>
<cmt>検勘</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For foreigners in Tokyo and Yokohama, the authenticity test for the nibukin they handed in through ministers of each country started on the 23rd, and the officials succeeded in finishing on the same day in Tokyo, and even in Yokohama, which was the Japan&apos;s leading trading port, they managed to finish by the 25th.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For foreigners in Tokyo and Yokohama, the authenticity test for the nibukin they handed in through ministers of each country started on the 23rd, and the officials succeeded in finishing on the same day in Tokyo, and even in Yokohama, which was the Japan&apos;s leading trading port, they managed to finish by the 25th.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>大阪と神戸では25日に提出・26日に検勘、長崎では27日に提出・28日に検勘、新潟では8月3日に検勘、最後の函館では8月12日に検勘が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Osaka and Kobe, the money was handed in on the 25th, and went through the authenticity test on the 26th, in Nagasaki, the money was handed in on the 27th, and went though the authenticity test on the 28th, and in Niigata, the authenticity test was on August 3, and lastly, in Hakodate the authenticity test was on August 12.</e>
<cmt>検勘</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Osaka and Kobe, the money was handed in on the 25th, and went through the authenticity test on the 26th, in Nagasaki, the money was handed in on the 27th, and went though the authenticity test on the 28th, and in Niigata, the authenticity test was on August 3, and lastly, in Hakodate the authenticity test was on August 12.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Osaka and Kobe, the money was handed in on the 25th, and went through the authenticity test on the 26th, in Nagasaki, the money was handed in on the 27th, and went though the authenticity test on the 28th, and in Niigata, the authenticity test was on August 3, and lastly, in Hakodate the authenticity test was on August 12.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>これによって各国の公使や商人達に明治政府の本気ぶりを見せるとともに海外に流出した贋二分金を日本に再度持ち込ませて検勘を受けさせる時間的余裕を与えなかったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Through this, the Meiji Government showed the ministers and merchants from other countries that they were serious, along with not giving them time to bring in counterfeit nifungane which spilled abroad to Japan again to have it go through kenkan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Through this, the Meiji Government showed the ministers and merchants from other countries that they were serious, along with not giving them time to bring back counterfeit nibukin which spilled abroad to Japan again to have it go through the authenticity test.</e>
<cmt>二分金 nifun gane → nibukin (日本語の読み方が間違っています） bring in → bring back</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Through this, the Meiji Government showed the ministers and merchants from other countries that they were serious, along with not giving them time to bring back counterfeit nibukin which spilled abroad to Japan again to have it go through the authenticity test.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>封包した贋の二分金は9月より翌年3月にかけて各開港場・開市場で順次正貨に引き換えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Encapsulated counterfeit nifungane were exchanged for the specie money one by one at each open port and market from September to March of the next year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Encapsulated counterfeit nibukin were exchanged for the specie money one by one at each open port and market from September to March of the next year.</e>
<cmt>二分金 nifun gane → nibukin (日本語の読み方が間違っています）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Encapsulated counterfeit nibukin were exchanged for the specie money one by one at each open port and market from September to March of the next year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>外国商人達は日本側のこうした強硬なやり方に不満を抱いたものの、公使達がこれを受け入れていること、正貨との等価交換によって不十分ながらも補償を受けられたと判断されたことで損害賠償などを求める動きは一応収束することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Foreign merchants were discontent with these drastic measures, but concluded movements such as asking for compensation for loss for the present since the ministers had accepted these measures, and also since they judged that it was not enough, but they still received compensation through equivalent exchange with specie money.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Foreign merchants were discontent with these drastic measures, but the movements such as asking for compensation for loss were put an end, because the ministers had accepted these measures, and also because, although they judged that it was not enough, they still received compensation through equivalent exchange with specie money.</e>
<cmt>収束する conclude → put an end</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Foreign merchants were discontent with these drastic measures, but the movements such as asking for compensation for loss were put an end, because the ministers had accepted these measures, and also because, although they judged that it was not enough, they still received compensation through equivalent exchange with specie money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>贋貨発行藩に対する処分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Punishment for domains which issued counterfeit money</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Punishment for domains which issued counterfeit money</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Punishment for domains which issued counterfeit money</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="80">
<j>8月24日、薩摩藩が「自訴状」を提出、続いて9月初旬には土佐藩もこれに続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 24, the Satsuma Domain submitted a &quot;Jishoujyo&quot; and in the following September the Tosa Domains followed.</e>
<cmt>自訴状の適訳が見つからなかったので、jishoujyoとしてあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 24, the Satsuma Domain submitted a &quot;Jisojo&quot; and in the following September the Tosa Domains followed.</e>
<cmt>「自訴状」 &quot;Jishoujyo&quot; → &quot;jisojo&quot; （日本語の読み方が間違っています）　</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 24, the Satsuma Domain submitted a &apos;Jisojo&apos; and in the following September the Tosa Domains followed.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot; → &apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>これを受けて大久保や西郷、土佐藩出身のの佐々木高行らは、薩摩・土佐両藩が自ら自首したこと、両藩は私利私欲のためではなく、維新実現のための軍備調達の必要からやむを得ず行ったことであるとして両藩への恩赦を求めたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Receiving this, OKUBO and SAIGO, and Takayui SASAKI from the Tosa Domain asked for pardon for both countries as the Satsuma and Tosa Domains surrendered their self, and as both domains unavoidably issued counterfeit money, not for self-interest, but because of the necessity for armament supplies to realize the restoration,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In response to this, OKUBO and SAIGO, and Takayuki SASAKI from the Tosa Domain asked for pardon for both countries, as the Satsuma and Tosa Domains surrendered themselves, and as both domains unavoidably issued counterfeit money, not for self-interest, but because of the necessity for armament supplies to realize the restoration,</e>
<cmt>これを受けて Receiving this → In response to this, their self → themselves</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response to this, OKUBO and SAIGO, and Takayuki SASAKI from the Tosa Domain asked for pardon for both countries, as the Satsuma and Tosa Domains surrendered themselves, and as both domains unavoidably issued counterfeit money, not for self-interest, but because of the necessity for armament supplies to realize the restoration,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>だが、調査によって贋貨鋳造の事実が無い事が確認されていた長州藩や肥前藩出身者は、自分達は苦労の末に軍費を自前で調達したのに薩摩や土佐が違法手段で調達していたという事実に反発して、両藩から罰金を取ってそれを贋貨と正貨の引換の原資に充てるべきであると主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, people from domains that were confirmed of having no truth in coining counterfeit money due to investigation, such as those from the Choshu or Hizen Domains, repelled at the truth that they supplied war expenditures at their own expense after sustained effort, while the Satsuma and Tosa Domains supplied them with illegal methods, and insisted that a penalty should be taken from both domains and that this should allot to the government funds for the exchange of counterfeit and specie money.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, people from domains that were confirmed of having no truth in coining counterfeit money due to investigation, such as those from the Choshu or Hizen Domains, were offended by the fact that they supplied war expenditures at their own expense after sustained effort, while the Satsuma and Tosa Domains supplied them with illegal methods, and insisted that a penalty should be taken from both domains and that this should allot to the government funds for the exchange of counterfeit and specie money.</e>
<cmt>事実に反発して repelled at the truth that → were offended by the fact that</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, people from domains that were confirmed of having no truth in coining counterfeit money due to investigation, such as those from the Choshu or Hizen Domains, were offended by the fact that they supplied war expenditures at their own expense after sustained effort, while the Satsuma and Tosa Domains supplied them with illegal methods, and insisted that a penalty should be taken from both domains and that this should allot to the government funds for the exchange of counterfeit and specie money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>だが、9月13日に薩摩藩からの自訴状が集議院（公議所の後身）で明らかにされると、諸藩の代表からは薩摩や土佐が自らの不祥事を告白した潔さを評価して穏便な処分を求める意見が相次いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when the jishoujyo from the Satsuma Domain was made known at shugiin on September 13, opinions from domains&apos; representatives succeeded which asked for a gentle punishment appraising the honorable way the Satsuma and Tosa Domains confessed their misconduct voluntarily.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when the jisojo from the Satsuma Domain was made known at shugiin on September 13, opinions from domains&apos; representatives came up one after another asking for a gentle punishment appraising the honorable way the Satsuma and Tosa Domains confessed their misconduct voluntarily.</e>
<cmt>「自訴状」 &quot;Jishoujyo&quot; → &quot;jisojo&quot; （日本語の読み方が間違っています）　 「N/C check」：意見が相次いだ succeeded → came up one after another</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when the jisojo from the Satsuma Domain was made known at shugiin on September 13, opinions from domains&apos; representatives came up one after another asking for a gentle punishment appraising the honorable way the Satsuma and Tosa Domains confessed their misconduct voluntarily.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>更に贋貨鋳造を行っていたその他の藩からも後日政府によって摘発された場合の後難を恐れて自訴状を出す藩が相次いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, other domains which were coining counterfeit money successively submitted a jishoujyo, fearing future problems that would occur in the case that they were exposed by the government later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, other domains which were coining counterfeit money successively submitted a jisojo, fearing future problems that would occur in the case that they were exposed by the government later.</e>
<cmt>「自訴状」 &quot;Jishoujyo&quot; → &quot;jisojo&quot; （日本語の読み方が間違っています）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, other domains which were coining counterfeit money successively submitted a jisojo, fearing future problems that would occur in the case that they were exposed by the government later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>そこで翌明治3年4月29日に政府はそれまでに自訴状を提出した藩の贋貨鋳造を赦免し、またそれ以外の藩でも箱館戦争終結以前の贋貨鋳造行為に関してはかつて明治政府と戦った斗南藩（旧会津藩）なども含めてその罪を不問にするとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently, on April 29, 1870, the government pardoned the domains that handed in the jishoujyo before then, and also decided to overlook the crime regarding the coining of counterfeit money before the end of the Hakodate War for the other domains, including the Tonami Domain (the old Aizu Domain).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, on April 29, 1870, the government pardoned the domains that had handed in the jisojo before then, and also decided to overlook the coining of counterfeit money done by the other domains before the end of the Hakodate War, including the Tonami Domain (the old Aizu Domain) which used to fight with the Meiji government.</e>
<cmt>「自訴状」 &quot;Jishoujyo&quot; → &quot;jisojo&quot; （日本語の読み方が間違っています）, 「訳漏れ」・・・かつて明治政府と戦った</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, on April 29, 1870, the government pardoned the domains that had handed in the jisojo before then, and also decided to overlook the coining of counterfeit money done by the other domains before the end of the Hakodate War, including the Tonami Domain (the old Aizu Domain) which used to fight with the Meiji government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>この時点でほとんどの藩は贋貨作りを中止している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By this time, most domains had stopped making counterfeit money.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By this time, most domains had stopped making counterfeit money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By this time, most domains had stopped making counterfeit money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>ところが、筑前藩のみはこの後も金札（太政官札）の偽造に切り替えて贋貨作りを継続し続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Chikuzen Domain alone still continued to make counterfeit money by switching to forgery of the kinsatsu (Daijokan money) afterwards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Chikuzen Domain alone still continued to make counterfeit money by switching to forgery of the kinsatsu (Dajokan-satsu) even afterwards.</e>
<cmt>太政官札 → Dajokan-satsu (用語集より）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Chikuzen Domain alone still continued to make counterfeit money by switching to forgery of the kinsatsu (Dajokan-satsu) even afterwards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>明治4年7月2日（廃藩置県の12日前）、その事実が発覚した筑前藩は黒田孝高以来の福岡城47万石を没収されて事実上改易されてしまうのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 2, 1871 (12 days before the abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures), the Chikuzen Domain, which was discovered, had to forfeit their Fukuoka-jo Castle 47 thousand koku since Yoshitaka KURODA, and was confiscated in reality.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 2, 1871 (12 days before the abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures), the Chikuzen Domain, which was discovered, had to forfeit their Fukuoka-jo Castle 47 thousand koku since Yoshitaka KURODA, and was virtually changed its rank.</e>
<cmt>事実上改易されて was confiscated in reality → was virtually changed its rank</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 2, 1871 (12 days before the abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures), the Chikuzen Domain, which was discovered, had to forfeit their Fukuoka-jo Castle 47 thousand koku since Yoshitaka KURODA, and was virtually changed its rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>贋貨・悪貨の交換問題</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The problem of exchanging counterfeit and bad money.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The problem of exchanging counterfeit and bad money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The problem of exchanging counterfeit and bad money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="89">
<j>さて、先の検勘の際に強引な日程を組んだ背景には、外国との関係の都合上贋貨と正貨の等価交換をやむなく認めたものの、実際に全ての贋貨を同じように正貨と等価で引き換えた場合には明治政府の財政が破綻するのは目に見えていたからであり、その額をなるべく抑制したいという明治政府と貿易関係の維持のために政府の崩壊に至る事態は避けたいと考える外国公使との思惑の一致があったからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Now, behind the reason for putting together such an aggressive agenda for the kenkan was that while they unavoidably accepted the equivalent exchange of counterfeit and specie money on the account of their relationship with foreign countries, it was clearly visible that if they exchanged counterfeit money with specie money for an equivalent price, the financial affairs of the Meiji Government would collapse, so the motives of both sides, the Meiji Government&apos;s desire to repress this amount as much as possible, and the foreign minister&apos;s desire to avoid a situation where the government collapses for the sake of keeping the trade relationship with the Meiji Government matched.</e>
<cmt>検勘</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Now, in the background of scheduling such a tight agenda for the kenkan, there were some reasons that while they unavoidably accepted the equivalent exchange of counterfeit and specie money taking into account of their relationship with foreign countries, it was clearly visible that if they exchanged all counterfeit money with specie money for an equivalent price, the financial affairs of the Meiji Government would collapse, so the Meiji Government wanted to suppress this amount as much as possible, on the other hand, the foreign ministers also wanted to avoid a situation where the government collapses so that they could keep the trade relationship with the Meiji Government, so the motives of both sides were matched.</e>
<cmt>先の検勘の際に強引な日程を組んだ背景には behind the reason for putting together such an aggressive agenda for the kenkan → in the background of scheduling such a tight agenda for the kenkan　　</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Now, the main reason behind the scheduling of such a tight agenda for the authenticity testing was that, while the exchange of equivalent amounts of counterfeit for specie was accepted as unavoidable given the government&apos;s relationship with foreign countries, it was clear that if all the counterfeit money was exchanged for specie of an equivalent price, the Meiji Government would face financial ruin, so the Meiji Government wanted to keep this amount to a minimum; at the same time, the foreign ministers of Japan&apos;s trading partners wanted to avoid a situation in which the government might collapse so as to ensure that they could maintain their trade relationships with the Meiji Government, so the motives of both sides coincided.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="90">
<j>7月22日に太政官布告が出され、人民は10月末までに官に贋貨を提出するように命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 22, the edict of Daijokan was put out, which ordered citizens to submit counterfeit money to officials by the end of October.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 22, the edict of Daijokan was put out, which ordered citizens to submit counterfeit money to officials by the end of October.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 22, the edict of Daijokan was put out, which ordered citizens to submit counterfeit money to officials by the end of October.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>だが、一般の人々には正貨と贋貨の区別をつける方法が無く（そもそも簡単に区別がつけられるのであれば、外国人に対する検勘は必要がないことになる）、かつ贋貨の方が大量に出回っているために全く意味が無かったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there was no method for regular people to make a distinction between a specie and counterfeit money (if there was a way to make this distinction, there would have been no reason to go through an authenticity test for foreigners in the first place), and besides, large amounts of counterfeit money were circulating so it was pointless.</e>
<cmt>検勘</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there was no method for regular people to make a distinction between a specie and counterfeit money (if there was a way to make this distinction, there would have been no reason to go through an authenticity test for foreigners in the first place), and besides, large amounts of counterfeit money were circulating so it was pointless.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there was no method for regular people to make a distinction between a specie and counterfeit money (if there was a way to make this distinction, there would have been no reason to go through an authenticity test for foreigners in the first place), and besides, large amounts of counterfeit money were circulating so it was pointless.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>8月11日に大蔵省と民部省が合併されて大蔵省が財政の全権を掌握できるようになると、大隈や伊藤を中心に整理のための方策が検討されることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 11, the Ministry of Finance and Ministry of Popular Affairs merged, and the Ministry of Finance became able to control financial affairs with absolute authority, so plans were examined for an organization by this, centered around OKUMA and ITO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 11 when the Ministry of Finance and Ministry of Popular Affairs merged into the Ministry of Finance to be able to control financial affairs with absolute authority, measurements for putting the things in order were planned to be examined by Okuma and Ito as leaders.</e>
<cmt>大隈や伊藤を中心に整理のための方策が検討されることになった。plans were examined for an organization by this, centered around OKUMA and ITO → On August 11 when the Ministry of Finance and Ministry of Popular Affairs merged into the Ministry of Finance to be able to control financial affairs with absolute authority, measurements for putting the things in order were planned to be examined by Okuma and Ito as leaders.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 11 when the Ministry of Finance and Ministry of Popular Affairs merged into the Ministry of Finance to be able to control financial affairs with absolute authority, measurements for putting the things in order were planned to be examined by Okuma and Ito as leaders.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>大隈や伊藤は当初、贋金貨100両に対する実際の価値を20両前後と見て、それに多少上乗せをして25両で引き換えることを考えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the beginning, OKUMA and ITO thought of looking at 100 counterfeit ryo as around 20 ryo in reality, and adding a little more to this, and exchanging it for 25 ryo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the beginning, OKUMA and ITO evaluated that 100 counterfeit ryo had around 20 ryo worth actually, so added a little more to this to exchange it for 25 ryo.</e>
<cmt>贋金貨100両に対する実際の価値を20両前後と見て looking at 100 counterfeit ryo as around 20 ryo in reality → evaluated that 100 counterfeit ryo had around 20 ryo worth actually</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the beginning, OKUMA and ITO evaluated that 100 counterfeit ryo had around 20 ryo worth actually, so added a little more to this to exchange it for 25 ryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>だが、これに対してたちまち政府内で反発が噴出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, objections exploded in the government instantly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, objections exploded in the government instantly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, objections exploded in the government instantly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>一般の人民は自分の持っている通貨の真贋を見極められないのに、ある日突然それは贋金だからとその価値を4分の1にされたら人々は大混乱に陥り、各地で一揆や打ちこわしなどの騒ぎに発展する危険性がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was danger that the general public would fall into great confusion if they were suddenly told that what they had was counterfeit money and was only worth ¼ of the real value, especially since they could not tell apart their currency from counterfeit or specie, and this could develop into to an uproar such as uprisings or vandalism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was danger that the general public would fall into great confusion if they were suddenly told that what they had was counterfeit money and was only worth ¼ of the real value, especially since they could not tell apart their currency from counterfeit or specie, and this could develop into to an uproar such as uprisings or vandalism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was danger that the general public would fall into great confusion if they were suddenly told that what they had was counterfeit money and was only worth ¼ of the real value, especially since they could not tell apart their currency from counterfeit or specie, and this could develop into to an uproar such as uprisings or vandalism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>今の明治政府にはこうした一揆や打ちこわしを鎮圧するだけの十分な力はなく、一歩間違えれば政府は崩壊すると言うのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Meiji Government at this time did not have enough power to suppress these kinds of uprisings or vandalism and one wrong move could lead to a collapse of the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Meiji Government at this time did not have enough power to suppress these kinds of uprisings or vandalism and one wrong move could lead to a collapse of the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Meiji Government at this time did not have enough power to suppress these kinds of uprisings or vandalism and one wrong move could lead to a collapse of the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>特に政府が頼りにしていた薩摩藩・土佐藩が自前の贋貨を大量に自己の領民に流通させている可能性があることもその危惧を高めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That the Satsuma and Tosa Domains which the government depended on, were especially circulating large amounts of counterfeit money to their people, raised the uneasiness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Particularly since the Satsuma and Tosa Domains which the government depended on, might have been circulating large amounts of counterfeit money to their people, it further raised its uneasiness.</e>
<cmt>流通させている可能性があることも might have been circulating</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Particularly since the Satsuma and Tosa Domains which the government depended on, might have been circulating large amounts of counterfeit money to their people, it further raised its uneasiness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>長州藩出身の広沢真臣が薩摩や土佐などの贋貨鋳造藩から罰金を徴収してそれを引換の元手にすることで40両前後にまで引き上げる案も出されたものの、前述のように穏便な処置を望む意見が占める中では実現は困難と思われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A proposal to collect a fine from domains which coined counterfeit money such as Satsuma and Tosa, and using this as a fund for the exchange, and raising the price to around 40 ryo was put out by Saneomi HIROSAWA from the Choshu Domain, but this was thought to be difficult to realize as most opinions desired a gentle punishment, like written above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A proposal to collect a fine from domains which coined counterfeit money such as Satsuma and Tosa, and using this as a fund for the exchange, and raising the price to around 40 ryo was put out by Saneomi HIROSAWA from the Choshu Domain, but this was thought to be difficult to realize as most opinions desired a gentle punishment, like written above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A proposal to collect a fine from domains which coined counterfeit money such as Satsuma and Tosa, and using this as a fund for the exchange, and raising the price to around 40 ryo was put out by Saneomi HIROSAWA from the Choshu Domain, but this was thought to be difficult to realize as most opinions desired a gentle punishment, like written above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="99">
<j>やがて、政府内で長い協議の末、10月24日に以下の太政官布告が出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the end, after a long conference within the government, the following edict of Daijokan was put out on October 24.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end, after a long conference within the government, the following edict of Daijokan was put out on October 24.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end, after a long conference within the government, the following edict of Daijokan was put out on October 24.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="100">
<j>「悪金ノ儀ハ、兼テ御布令ノ通、府藩県ニテ取調十月中ニ可申出筈ノ所、此度引換ノ道被為立、銀台ノ分ハ格別ノ訳ヲ以百両ニ付先金札三十両ニ御引換被成下、追テ総員数銘々持分等巨細御取調ノ上、猶御詮議ノ品モ可有之候条、御趣意ノ程厚ク相心得可申候......（以下略）」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">「悪金ノ儀ハ、兼テ御布令ノ通、府藩県ニテ取調十月中ニ可申出筈ノ所、此度引換ノ道被為立、銀台ノ分ハ格別ノ訳ヲ以百両ニ付先金札三十両ニ御引換被成下、追テ総員数銘々持分等巨細御取調ノ上、猶御詮議ノ品モ可有之候条、御趣意ノ程厚ク相心得可申候......（以下略）」</e>
<cmt>「意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">「悪金ノ儀ハ、兼テ御布令ノ通、府藩県ニテ取調十月中ニ可申出筈ノ所、此度引換ノ道被為立、銀台ノ分ハ格別ノ訳ヲ以百両ニ付先金札三十両ニ御引換被成下、追テ総員数銘々持分等巨細御取調ノ上、猶御詮議ノ品モ可有之候条、御趣意ノ程厚ク相心得可申候......（以下略）」</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">「悪金ノ儀ハ、兼テ御布令ノ通、府藩県ニテ取調十月中ニ可申出筈ノ所、此度引換ノ道被為立、銀台ノ分ハ格別ノ訳ヲ以百両ニ付先金札三十両ニ御引換被成下、追テ総員数銘々持分等巨細御取調ノ上、猶御詮議ノ品モ可有之候条、御趣意ノ程厚ク相心得可申候......（以下略）」</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="101">
<j>これによって贋金100両を金札30両に引き換える事を表明するとともに事情によっては将来的に上乗せされる可能性がある事を仄めかす内容とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hereby, along with expressing the exchange of 100 counterfeit ryo to kinsatsu 30 ryo, the content hinted at the possibility of adding more in the future according to the situation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hereby, along with expressing the exchange of 100 counterfeit ryo to kinsatsu 30 ryo, the content hinted at the possibility of adding more in the future according to the situation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hereby, along with expressing the exchange of 100 counterfeit ryo to kinsatsu 30 ryo, the content hinted at the possibility of adding more in the future according to the situation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>これを受けて11月より順次引換が開始されたが、目標としていた年内完了には至らず、翌3年3月2日、同12月15日と期限を延長しても処理が追いつかなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, exchange of money began in November, but this did not finish by the end of year as aimed, and even when the deadline was pushed to March 2, 1870 and December 15 of the same year, the disposal of counterfeit money did not catch up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, exchange of money began in November, but this did not finish by the end of year as aimed, and even when the deadline was pushed to March 2, 1870 and December 15 of the same year, the disposal of counterfeit money did not catch up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, exchange of money began in November, but this did not finish by the end of year as aimed, and even when the deadline was pushed to March 2, 1870 and December 15 of the same year, the disposal of counterfeit money did not catch up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>そのため、明治4年1月25日に引換を打ち切り、以後は金銀混合の地金として時価で扱うものとする太政官布告が出された（ただし、同年中は希望者には引換は継続されている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, an edict of Daijokan canceling the exchange of money on January 15, 1871, and from this date on, dealing with counterfeit money as the market price of a metal that is a mixture of gold and silver was put out (however, for those who wished to do so the exchange would continue during the year).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, an edict of Daijokan was issued to announce that the exchange of money would be terminated as of January 15, 1871, and that from this date on, the counterfeit money would be dealt with at the market price of a ground metal mixed of gold and silver (however, the exchange continued during the year only for the people who wished).</e>
<cmt>太政官布告が出された an edict of Daijokan canceling → an edict of Daijokan was issued to announce that</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, an edict of Daijokan was issued to announce that the exchange of money would be terminated as of January 15, 1871, and that from this date on, the counterfeit money would be dealt with at the market price of a ground metal mixed of gold and silver (however, the exchange continued during the year only for the people who wished).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>だが、前述の外国人に対する等価引換が34万両、太政官布告による引換が判明分だけで157万両であり、現在判明している政府発行の悪質な金貨（事実上の贋貨）が381万両であるから、それよりも遥かに少ないことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as mentioned above, the equivalent exchange for the foreigners was 34 thousand ryo, but even for just the discovered</e>
<cmt>この文章の最後の一文がどこにかかるのかはっきりせず、完了していません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the amount by the exchange in equal value for foreigners was 340 thousand ryo as mentioned above, and the amount by the exchange following the edict of Daijokan, which had become clear was 1.57 million ryo, while the amount of the bad quality gold coins (actually counterfeit coins) issued by the government, which is recognized today is 3.81 million ryo, so the former ones are much smaller than the latter.</e>
<cmt>校正者による翻訳。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the amount by the exchange in equal value for foreigners was 340 thousand ryo as mentioned above, and the amount by the exchange following the edict of Daijokan, which had become clear was 1.57 million ryo, while the amount of the bad quality gold coins (actually counterfeit coins) issued by the government, which is recognized today is 3.81 million ryo, so the former ones are much smaller than the latter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>結局は海外への流出分も含めて実質的には明治初期の混乱に乗じて殆どが切り捨てられて地金扱いされたのが実態であったとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the end, the situation was thought to be that counterfeit money, including those that circulated abroad, were mostly thrown away and handled as metal, in essence, under the cover of the confusion during the beginning of the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end, the situation was thought to be that counterfeit money, including those that circulated abroad, were mostly thrown away and handled as metal, in essence, under the cover of the confusion during the beginning of the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end, the situation was thought to be that counterfeit money, including those that circulated abroad, were mostly thrown away and handled as metal, in essence, under the cover of the confusion during the beginning of the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>新貨条例制定と造幣寮の設置</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The set up of the New Currency Regulation System and the Mint Dorm</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The set up of the New Currency Regulation System and the Mint Dorm</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The set up of the New Currency Regulation System and the Mint Dorm</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="106">
<j>その一方で大隈は近代的な貨幣制度を実施する計画を進めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, OKUMA was proceeding the plan to enforce the modern currency system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, OKUMA was proceeding the plan to enforce the modern currency system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, OKUMA was proceeding the plan to enforce the modern currency system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>造幣施設の建設計画は由利公正が会計官副知事の時代より進めていたが、大隈が大蔵省設置とともに造幣寮を置いて井上馨を造幣頭に任命（明治2年8月18日）して以後本格化し、大阪市に造幣工場の建設が進められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The construction plan for the mint facility was proceeded by Kosei YURI, from the time he was a finance office vice prefectural governor, but it begin in earnest after OKUMA placed a Mint Dorm along with setting up the Ministry of Finance and appointing Kaoru INOUE to the position of mint head, and the construction of a mint factory proceeded.</e>
<cmt>造幣頭はmint headとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The construction plan for the mint facility was proceeded by Kosei YURI, from the time he was a finance office vice prefectural governor, but it began in earnest after OKUMA placed a Mint Dorm along with setting up the Ministry of Finance and appointing Kaoru INOUE to the position of mint head, and the construction of a mint factory was proceeded in Osaka City.</e>
<cmt>begin → began, the construction of a mint factory proceeded. → the construction of a mint factory was proceeded in Osaka City.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The construction plan for the mint facility was proceeded by Kosei YURI, from the time he was a finance office vice prefectural governor, but it began in earnest after OKUMA placed a Mint Dorm along with setting up the Ministry of Finance and appointing Kaoru INOUE to the position of mint head, and the construction of a mint factory was proceeded in Osaka City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="108">
<j>途中、火災による遅延があったものの、明治3年9月に工場は完成し、明治4年2月15日より仮稼動を開始した（4月4日本格稼動）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a delay due to fire along the way, but the factory was completed in September 1870, and started temporary operating on February 15, 1871 (full-scale operating started on April 4).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a delay due to fire along the way, but the factory was completed in September 1870, and started temporary operating on February 15, 1871 (full-scale operating started on April 4).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a delay due to fire along the way, but the factory was completed in September 1870, and started temporary operating on February 15, 1871 (full-scale operating started on April 4).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>続いて5月10日（1871年6月17日）には円 (通貨)を基本単位とし、通貨の補助単位として「銭」「厘」を導入して、1円100銭、1銭10厘とする新貨条例が公布され、日本は近代的な貨幣制度への第一歩を踏み出すことになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 17 of the following year, the yen (currency) was made the basic unit, the &quot;zeni&quot; and &quot;rin&quot; were introduced as the supplementary unit, the New Currency Act was proclaimed, making 1 yen 100 zeni, and 1 zeni 10 ri, and Japan took it&apos;s first step towards a modern currency system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 17, 1871 of the following year, the yen (currency) was made the basic unit, the &quot;sen&quot; and &quot;ri&quot; were introduced as the supplementary unit, the New Currency Act was proclaimed, making 1 yen 100 sen, and 1 sen 10 ri, and Japan took its first step towards a modern currency system.</e>
<cmt>「銭」zeni → sen</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 17, 1871 of the following year, the yen (currency) was made the basic unit, the &quot;sen&quot; and &quot;ri&quot; were introduced as the supplementary unit, the New Currency Act was proclaimed, making 1 yen 100 sen, and 1 sen 10 ri, and Japan took its first step towards a modern currency system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), BoB774(id:148281), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), Greenland4(id:114494), 水野白楓(id:22811), Complex01(id:10454), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>