<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>駅逓司</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ekitei-Shi (government office in charge of transportation and communication)</e>
<cmt>『駅逓司』に定訳は有りませんので、括弧をつけて意味を付記しました。以下、本文は体制の変化とそれによる名称の変化を記述していると思われるので、名称をローマ字表記し、初出の場合にはその意味を括弧を付けて付記します。また同じ部署が、『寮・局・省』と変化したことを明確にするため、敢えてハイフンをつけて&quot;-Ryo, -Kyoku, -Sho&quot;としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ekitei-Shi (government office in charge of transportation and communication)</e>
<cmt>&quot;(&quot;後のスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ekitei-Shi (government office in charge of transportation and communication)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>駅逓司（えきていし）とは、慶応4年4月21日_(旧暦)（明治元年・1868年6月11日）に設置された交通通信担当官司。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ekitei-Shi is a government office in charge of transportation and communication, formed on June 11, 1868.</e>
<cmt>官司→C列の対訳・定訳では &quot;government official&quot; とありますが、この文章に置いては、全体の流れから役人ではなく、役所を指すのではないかと思います。従って、&quot;government office&quot;と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ekitei-Shi is a government office in charge of transportation and communication, formed on June 11, 1868.</e>
<cmt>過去の、なのでisをwasとします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ekitei-Shi is a government office in charge of transportation and communication, formed on June 11, 1868.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>後に駅逓寮（えきていりょう）・駅逓局（えきていきょく）と改称され、後の逓信省の元になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was later renamed as Ekitei-Ryo/Ekitei-Kyoku and became the former body of Teishin-Sho (Ministry of Communication).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was later renamed as Ekitei-Ryo/Ekitei-Kyoku and became the former body of Teishin-Sho (Ministry of Communication).</e>
<cmt>&quot;(&quot;後のスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was later renamed as Ekitei-Ryo/Ekitei-Kyoku and became the former body of Teishin-Sho (Ministry of Communication).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>政体書に基づいて会計官が設置された際にその下に設置された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was established under Kaikei-Kan (Ministry of Finance), when Kaikei-Kan was created based on the Constitution of 1868.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was established under Kaikei-Kan (Ministry of Finance), when Kaikei-Kan was created based on the Constitution of 1868.</e>
<cmt>&quot;(&quot;後のスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was established under Kaikei-Kan (Ministry of Finance), when Kaikei-Kan was created based on the Constitution of 1868.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>翌年民部省設置とともに移動され、事実上の「大蔵民部省」の一翼を担う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Next year, it was moved with Minbu-Sho (Ministry of Popular Affairs), and played a part in vertual Okura-and-Minbu-Sho (which actually remained as two separate ministries in the government organization - Minbu-Sho and Okura-Sho (Ministry of Finance) -, but virtually functioned as one)</e>
<cmt>大蔵民部省は定訳がありませんでしたので、意味を括弧の中に訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Next year, it was moved with Minbu-Sho (Ministry of Popular Affairs), and played a part in virtual Okura-and-Minbu-Sho (which actually remained as two separate ministries in the government organization - Minbu-Sho and Okura-Sho (Ministry of Finance) -, but virtually functioned as one)</e>
<cmt>&quot;(&quot;後のスペースを削除しました。Vertual&gt;&gt;virtualのスペルミスです。訳文中の不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Next year, it was moved with Minbu-Sho (Ministry of Popular Affairs), and played a part in virtual Okura-and-Minbu-Sho (which actually remained as two separate ministries in the government organization - Minbu-Sho and Okura-Sho (Ministry of Finance) -, but virtually functioned as one)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>1871年3月1日 (旧暦)（新暦4月20日）、駅逓司の前島密・杉浦譲らによって郵便制度が開始された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 20th, 1871, the postal system was launched by officials from Ekitei-Shi, including Hisoka MAEJIMA and Jo SUGIURA.</e>
<cmt>旧暦・新暦併用に意味はありませんので、新暦のみ訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 20, 1871, officials from Ekitei-Shi, including Hisoka MAEJIMA and Jo SUGIURA, launched the postal system.</e>
<cmt>日付表記を修正しました。受動態から修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 20, 1871, officials from Ekitei-Shi, including Hisoka MAEJIMA and Jo SUGIURA, launched the postal system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>同年民部省が大蔵省に統合されて8月に駅逓寮に昇格した（1877年1月の寮→局制の移行に伴い、駅逓局と改称）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, Minbu-Sho was integrated with Okura-Sho, and elevated to be Ekitei-Ryo (according to the change of the government system from Ryo to Kyoku in Juanuary 1877, it changed its name to Ekitei-Kyoku).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, Minbu-Sho was integrated with Okura-Sho, and elevated to be Ekitei-Ryo (according to the change of the government system from Ryo to Kyoku in January 1877, it changed its name to Ekitei-Kyoku).</e>
<cmt>&quot;(&quot;と&quot;with&quot;後の不要なスペースを削除しました。Juanuary &gt;&gt; Januaryのスペルミスです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, Minbu-Sho was integrated with Okura-Sho, and elevated to be Ekitei-Ryo (according to the change of the government system from Ryo to Kyoku in January 1877, it changed its name to Ekitei-Kyoku).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>郵便制度は1875年1月には為替制度（郵便為替）、5月には貯金業務（郵便貯金）を加えてその重要性は高まっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The importance of the postal system has increased as it added exchange system (postal money order) in January 1875 and banking service (postal savings) in May.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The importance of the postal system has increased as it added exchange system (postal money order) in January 1875 and banking service (postal savings) in May.</e>
<cmt>&quot;()&quot;前後の不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The importance of the postal system has increased as it added exchange system (postal money order) in January 1875 and banking service (postal savings) in May.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>なお、幕藩体制の助郷制度の廃止による交通制度の改革も駅逓司の所管であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also a part of Ekitei-Shi&apos;s responsibility to reform the transportation system, which was caused by the abolition of Sukego system (tax system imposed to villages based on their amount of crop, and paid in labor. Villages designated as Sukego had to provide laborers,horses and sometimes sailors to help their neighboring post-station town) in the shogunate system.</e>
<cmt>『助郷制度』→ここではこの制度が税制であったことを記す必要があると思いましたので、定訳とは多少異なりますが内容を訳出して括弧内に付記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also a part of Ekitei-Shi&apos;s responsibility to reform the transportation system, which was caused by the abolition of Sukego system (tax system imposed to villages based on their amount of crop, and paid in labor; villages designated as Sukego had to provide laborers, horses and sometimes sailors to help their neighboring post-station town) in the shogunate system.</e>
<cmt>&quot;()&quot;前後の不要なスペースを削除しました。訳文中にピリオドが2つあるので、&quot;;&quot;と置き換えました。訳文中の改行を削除しました。訳文中の不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also a part of Ekitei-Shi&apos;s responsibility to reform the transportation system, which was caused by the abolition of Sukego system (tax system imposed to villages based on their amount of crop, and paid in labor; villages designated as Sukego had to provide laborers, horses and sometimes sailors to help their neighboring post-station town) in the shogunate system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>その一方で1874年に大蔵省から分離した内務省 (日本)、1881年に内務省から分離した農商務省 (日本)に移管され、1885年に駅逓局そのものが新設の逓信省として独立することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Ekitei-Kyoku itself became independent as a newly established Teishin-Sho in 1885, after it had been moved to Naimu-Sho (prewar Ministry of Home Affairs), which had separated from Okura-Sho in 1874 and then to No-Shomu-Sho (Ministry of Agriculture and Commerce), which had separated from Naimu-Sho in 1881.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Ekitei-Kyoku itself became independent as a newly established Teishin-Sho in 1885, after it had been moved to Naimu-Sho (prewar Ministry of Home Affairs), which had separated from Okura-Sho in 1874, and then to No-Shomu-Sho (Ministry of Agriculture and Commerce), which had separated from Naimu-Sho in 1881.</e>
<cmt>&quot;()&quot;前後の不要なスペースを削除しました。And then の前に&quot;,&quot;を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Ekitei-Kyoku itself became independent as a newly established Teishin-Sho in 1885, after it had been moved to Naimu-Sho (prewar Ministry of Home Affairs), which had separated from Okura-Sho in 1874, and then to No-Shomu-Sho (Ministry of Agriculture and Commerce), which had separated from Naimu-Sho in 1881.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Loafer(id:270948), 水野白楓(id:22811), Complex01(id:10454), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>