<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>弥生時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yayoi period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yayoi period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yayoi period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>弥生時代（やよいじだい）は、北海道・沖縄諸島を除く日本列島における時代区分の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yayoi period is one of periodization in the Japanese Archipelago excluding Hokkaido and Okinawa Islands.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yayoi period is one of periodizations in the Japanese Archipelago excluding Hokkaido and Okinawa Islands.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yayoi period is one of periodizations in the Japanese Archipelago excluding Hokkaido and Okinawa Islands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>縄文時代に後続し、古墳時代に先行する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yayoi period follows Jomon period and precedes Kofun period (tumulus period).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yayoi period follows the Jomon period and precedes the Kofun period (tumulus period).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yayoi period follows the Jomon period and precedes the Kofun period (tumulus period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>およそ紀元前10世紀中頃（ただしこの年代には異論もある）から3世紀中頃までにあたる時代の名称である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the period approximately between the middle of the tenth century B.C. (though there are some objection to this date) to the middle of the third century.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the period approximately between the middle of the tenth century B.C. (though there are some objections to this date) to the middle of the third century.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the period approximately between the middle of the 10th century B.C. (though there are some objections to this date) to the middle of the 3rd century.</e>
<cmt>tenth→10th,third→3rd と修正しました。（用語統一：その他「31項」に従い）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>具体的には、稲作技術導入によって日本での水稲耕作が開始された時代である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In specific term, it is the period when a paddy-rice cultivations started in Japan by introduction of rice cropping techniques.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In specific terms, it is the period when rice-paddy cultivation started in Japan by introduction rice cropping techniques.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In specific terms, it is the period when rice-paddy cultivation started in Japan by introduction rice cropping techniques.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>弥生時代は、水稲耕作による稲作の技術をもつ集団が列島外から北部九州に移住することによって始まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yayoi period had started as a group of people with the paddy-rice cultivation techniques immigrated from outside the Japanese Archipelago to the northern Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yayoi period started when a group of people with rice-paddy cultivation techniques immigrated from outside the Japanese Archipelago to northern Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yayoi period started when a group of people with rice-paddy cultivation techniques immigrated from outside the Japanese Archipelago to northern Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>（しかし、1994年、縄文末期に属する岡山県総社市の南溝手遺跡（みなみみぞていせき）の土器片中からプラント・オパール（イネ科植物の葉などの細胞成分）が発見された。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(However, in 1994, plant opals (cell components (from leaves etc) of gramineous plants) were found inside the fragments of earthware from Minamimizote site located in Soja City, Okayama Prefecture, which was classified as a site from the end of Jomon period.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(However, in 1994, plant opals or cell components, from leaves, etc., of gramineous plants were found inside the fragments of earthware from the Minamimizote site located in Soja City, Okayama Prefecture, which was classified as a site from the end of the Jomon period.)</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(However, in 1994, plant opals or cell components, from leaves, etc., of gramineous plants were found inside the fragments of earthware from the Minamimizote site located in Soja City, Okayama Prefecture, which was classified as a site from the end of the Jomon period.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>（さらに同県真庭市美甘（みかも）姫笹原の4500年前の土器にもプラントオパールが発表された。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Moreover, plant opals were also found from earthware of 4500 years ago from Himesasahara site in Mikamo, Maniwa City, Okayama Prefecture.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処「姫笹原」とありますが、前文（元同文）とのつながりから、「姫笹原遺跡」を指すものととり、そのように訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Moreover, plant opals were also found from earthware of 4,500 years ago from the Himesasahara site in Mikamo, Maniwa City, Okayama Prefecture.)</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Moreover, plant opals were also found from earthware of 4,500 years ago from the Himesasahara site in Mikamo, Maniwa City, Okayama Prefecture.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>(2005年には岡山県灘崎町の縄文時代前期（約6000年前）の地層から大量のプラントオパールが見つかり、少なくとも約3500年前からすでに陸稲（熱帯ジャポニカ米）による稲作が行われていたとする学説が数多く発表された。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(In 2005, large amounts of plant opals were found from a stratum of the early Jomon period (approximately 6000 years ago) in Nadasaki-cho, Okayama Prefecture, and many theories stating that the rice cultivation with a rice plant grown in a dry field (tropical Japonica rice) was practiced at least from 3500 years ago, were proposed.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(In 2005, large amounts of plant opals were found from a stratum of the early Jomon period, approximately 6,000 years ago, in Nadasaki-cho, Okayama Prefecture, and many theories stating that rice cultivation with a rice plant grown in a dry field (tropical Japonica rice) was practiced at least from 3,500 years ago, were proposed.)</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(In 2005, large amounts of plant opals were found from a stratum of the early Jomon period [approximately 6,000 years ago], in Nadasaki-cho, Okayama Prefecture, and many theories stating that rice cultivation with a rice plant grown in a dry field [tropical Japonica rice] was practiced at least from 3,500 years ago, were proposed.)</e>
<cmt>カッコを補い、また、カッコ内のカッコを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>(また水稲である温帯ジャポニカについても縄文晩期には導入されていたともいわれ、現在では弥生時代のはじまりと定義される稲作開始時期自体が確定できない状態である。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Also it is said that temperate Japonica rice, a paddy-rice plant, had already been introduced at the end of Jomon period and the starting time of rice cultivation, which is defined as the beginning of Yayoi period, cannot be confirmed at the moment.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Also it is said that temperate Japonica rice, a paddy-rice plant, had already been introduced at the end of the Jomon period and the starting time of rice cultivation, defined as the beginning of the Yayoi period, cannot be confirmed at the moment.)</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Also it is said that temperate Japonica rice, a paddy-rice plant, had already been introduced at the end of the Jomon period and the starting time of rice cultivation, defined as the beginning of the Yayoi period, cannot be confirmed at the moment.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>名称</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>「弥生」という名称は、1884年（明治17年）に東京府本郷向ヶ岡弥生町（現在の東京都文京区弥生 (文京区)）の貝塚で発見された土器が発見地に因み弥生式土器と呼ばれたことに由来する（なお、その後の都市化の進展などもあって正確な発見地は特定できなくなっている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name &apos;Yayoi&apos; derived from Yayoi earthware, which was named after the place of discovery, as it was earthwares found at shell mounds in Yayoi-cho, Mukougaoka, Hongo, Tokyo Prefecture (Present Yayoi, Bunkyo Ward, Tokyo) in 1884 (precise location of discovery cannot be identified because of the later urbanization increase.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name &apos;Yayoi&apos; is derived from Yayoi earthware, named after the place of discovery, as it was earthware found at shell mounds in Yayoi-cho, Mukougaoka, Hongo, Tokyo Prefecture (Present Yayoi, Bunkyo Ward, Tokyo) in 1884 (precise location of discovery cannot be identified because of the later increase in urbanization.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name &apos;Yayoi&apos; is derived from Yayoi earthware, named after the place of discovery, as it was earthware found at shell mounds in Yayoi-cho, Mukogaoka, Hongo, Tokyo Prefecture (present Yayoi, Bunkyo Ward, Tokyo) in 1884 (Precise location of discovery cannot be identified because of the later increase in urbanization.)</e>
<cmt>Mukougaoka→Mukogaoka と修正しました。Present→present,precise→Precise と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>当初は、弥生式土器の使われた時代ということで「弥生式時代」と呼ばれ、その後徐々に「式」を省略する呼称が一般的となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first it was called &apos;Yayoi-shiki period&apos;, implying a period that used Yayoi earthware but later &apos;-shiki&apos; was omitted gradually and the name Yayoi became the general term.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first it was called &apos;Yayoi-shiki period&apos;, implying a period that used Yayoi earthware but later &apos;-shiki&apos; was gradually omitted and the name Yayoi became the general term.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first it was called &apos;Yayoi-shiki period,&apos; implying a period that used Yayoi earthware but later &apos;-shiki&apos; was gradually omitted and the name Yayoi became the general term.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>なお余談だが、弥生時代の名称の起源となった、弥生町で出土した一群の土器は、現在の土器編年上では古墳時代前期に属するとの説が有力になりつつある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, today&apos;s most convincing theory classifies the earthwares excavated from Yayoi-cho, which was the origin of the name Yayoi period, as earthware of the early Kofun (tumulus period) period in present earthware chronology.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, today&apos;s most convincing theory classifies the earthwares excavated from Yayoi-cho, which was the origin of the name Yayoi period, as earthware of the early Kofun (tumulus period) period in present earthware chronology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, today&apos;s most convincing theory classifies the earthwares excavated from Yayoi-cho, which was the origin of the name Yayoi period, as earthware of the early Kofun (tumulus period) period in present earthware chronology.</e>
<cmt>スペースを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>紀元前5世紀中頃に、大陸から北部九州へと水稲耕作技術を中心とした生活体系が伝わり、九州、四国、本州に広がった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around the fifth century B.C., life style with the paddy-rice cultivations was introduced from the continent to northern Kyushu, and it spread to Kyushu, Shikoku and to Honshu (the main island of Japan).</e>
<cmt>大陸=the continentと訳しています。Chinese Continentと取れるのですが、ドキュメント中に東南アジアも含まれるような記述があるので、中国/中国大陸とない場合は、the continent と訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the fifth century B.C., life style of rice-paddy cultivation was introduced from the continent to northern Kyushu, and it spread to Kyushu, Shikoku, and Honshu (the main island of Japan).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the fifth century B.C., life style of rice-paddy cultivation was introduced from the continent to northern Kyushu, and it spread to Kyushu, Shikoku, and Honshu (the main island of Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>初期の水田は、福岡市博多区にある板付遺跡や、佐賀県唐津市の菜畑遺跡、福岡県曲り田遺跡、福岡県野多目遺跡などで水田遺跡や大陸系磨製石器、炭化米等の存在が北部九州地域に集中して発見されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Early paddy field remains including continental ground stoneware and carbonized rice were concentrated and discovered in northern Kyushu region, such as Itazuke site located at Hakata Ward, Fukuoka City, Nabatake site located at Karatsu City, Saga Prefecture, Magarita site located at Fukuoka Prefecture and Notame site located at Fukuoka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>origianalの文章の主語があいまいです。「初期の水田は、」はその後の文中にある水田遺跡とあわせて考え、初期の水田遺跡や…と訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Early paddy field remains including continental ground stoneware and carbonized rice were concentrated and discovered in the northern Kyushu region, such as the Itazuke site located at Hakata Ward, Fukuoka City, Nabatake site located at Karatsu City, Saga Prefecture, Magarita site located at Fukuoka Prefecture and Notame site located at Fukuoka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Early paddy field remains including continental ground stoneware and carbonized rice were concentrated and discovered in the northern Kyushu region, such as the Itazuke site located at Hakata Ward, Fukuoka City, Nabatake site located at Karatsu City, Saga Prefecture, Magarita site located at Fukuoka Prefecture and Notame site located at Fukuoka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>弥生時代のはじまりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the beginning of Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the beginning of the Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was the beginning of the Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>近年になって水稲である温帯ジャポニカは縄文晩期には導入されていたことが判明しつつある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent years, some evidence shows that the temperate Japonica-rice, a paddy-rice plant, was introduced by the end of Jomon period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent years, some evidence shows that the temperate Japonica-rice, a rice-paddy plant, was introduced by the end of Jomon period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent years, some evidence shows that the temperate Japonica-rice, a rice-paddy plant, was introduced by the end of Jomon period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>さらに近年の放射性炭素年代測定により弥生時代の始まりが少なくとも紀元前10世紀まで遡る可能性が出てきている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, there is a possibility of the start of Yayoi period to go back to tenth century B.C. by recent radiocarbon dating.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, there is a possibility of the start of the Yayoi period going back to the tenth century B.C. by recent radiocarbon dating.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, there is a possibility of the start of the Yayoi period going back to at least the 10th century B.C. by recent radiocarbon dating.</e>
<cmt>tenth→10th と修正しました。at least を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>また、イネの伝来ルートについても従来は朝鮮ルートが有力視されていたが、遼東半島や朝鮮北部での水耕田跡が近代まで見つからないこと、朝鮮半島での確認された炭化米が紀元前2000年が最古であり畑作米の確認しか取れない点、極東アジアにおける温帯ジャポニカ種（水稲）/熱帯ジャポニカ種（陸稲）の遺伝分析において、朝鮮半島を含む中国東北部から当該遺伝子の存在が確認されないことなどの複数の証左から、水稲は大陸からの直接伝来ルート（対馬暖流ルート・東南アジアから南方伝来ルート等）による伝来である学説が有力視されつつある（従来の説とは逆に水稲は日本から朝鮮半島へ伝わった可能性も考えられている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, although Korean route was traditionally regarded as a likely introduction route for rice, the theory stating that paddy-rice plant was introduced through the direct introduction route from the continent (Tsushima Warm Current route/Southern introduction route from South East Asia) is now regarded as very likely from the several facts that remains of paddy-rice fields are not discovered in Liaodong Peninsula and northern Korea until site of modern times, the oldest carbonated rice found in Korean Peninsula only goes back to 2000 B.C., the only a rice plant grown in a dry field are confirmed from the time, and genetic analysis of temperate Japonica rice (a paddy-rice plant)/tropical Japonica rice (a rice plant grown in a dry field) in the Far East Asia shows no evidence of concerned genes from Korean Peninsula and North East China (contrary to traditional theory, there is a possibility that paddy-rice plant had been introduced to Korean Peninsula from Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, although the Korean route was traditionally regarded as a likely introduction route for rice, the theory stating that rice-paddy plants were introduced through the direct introduction route from the continent (Tsushima Warm Current route/Southern introduction route from South East Asia) is now regarded as very likely from the several facts that remains of rice-paddy fields were not discovered in the Liaodong Peninsula and northern Korea until sites of modern times, the oldest carbonated rice found in the Korean Peninsula only goes back to 2000 B.C., the only a rice plants grown in a dry field were confirmed from that time, and genetic analysis of temperate Japonica rice (a rice-paddy plant)/tropical Japonica rice (a rice plant grown in a dry field) in Far East Asia shows no evidence of concerned genes from Korean Peninsula nor from North East China (contrary to traditional theory, there is a possibility that rice-paddy plants had been introduced into Korean Peninsula from Japan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, although the Korean route was traditionally regarded as a likely introduction route for rice, the theory stating that rice-paddy plants were introduced through the direct introduction route from the continent (Tsushima Warm Current route/Southern introduction route from South East Asia) is now regarded as very likely from the several facts that remains of rice-paddy fields were not discovered in the Liaodong Peninsula and northern Korea until sites of modern times, the oldest carbonated rice found in the Korean Peninsula only goes back to 2000 B.C., the only a rice plants grown in a dry field were confirmed from that time, and genetic analysis of temperate Japonica rice (a rice-paddy plant)/tropical Japonica rice (a rice plant grown in a dry field) in Far East Asia shows no evidence of concerned genes from Korean Peninsula nor from North East China (Contrary to traditional theory, there is a possibility that rice-paddy plants had been introduced into Korean Peninsula from Japan.)</e>
<cmt>カッコ部分、ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="19">
<j>紀元前10世紀後半に北部九州に伝わった水田稲作は、近畿南部に伝播するまでに300～400年、南関東までは実に700～800年ほど経過している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Paddy-rice cultivation that was introduced around the end of tenth century B.C. took 300 to 400 years to spread to Southern Kinki region and 700 to 800 years to spread to Southern Kanto region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rice-paddy cultivation that was introduced around the end of tenth century B.C. and took 300 to 400 years to spread to the Southern Kinki region and 700 to 800 years to spread to the Southern Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rice-paddy cultivation that was introduced around the end of 10th century B.C. and took 300 to 400 years to spread to the Southern Kinki region and 700 to 800 years to spread to the Southern Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>tenth→10th と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>昭和56年(1981)、弥生時代中期の遺跡が青森県南津軽郡田舎館村垂柳遺跡から広範囲に整然とした水田区画が見つかっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1981, remains of large-scale-well-ordered paddy field section from the middle of Yayoi period were found in Tareyanagi site located in Inakadate Village, Minamitsugaru-gun, Aomori Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>originalの文、特に主語があいまいです。弥生時代中期の、広範囲で整然とした水田区画の遺跡が、と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1981, remains of large-scale-well-ordered paddy field sections from the middle of the Yayoi period were found in the Tareyanagi site located in Inakadate Village, Minamitsugaru-gun, Aomori Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1981, remains of large-scale-well-ordered paddy field sections from the middle of the Yayoi period were found in the Tareyanagi site located in Inakadate Village, Minamitsugaru-gun, Aomori Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>その後、弥生時代前期には東北へと伝播し、青森県弘前市砂沢遺跡では小規模な水田跡が発見され、中期には、中央高地の松本平、信濃川流域までひろがった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Paddy-rice cultivation had spread to Tohoku region in the early Yayoi period that a small remains of paddy field was discovered in Sunazawa site located in Hirosaki City, Aomori Prefecture, and it had spread to Matsumotodaira in Chuokochi and the Shinano River area in the middle of Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rice-paddy cultivation had spread to the Tohoku region during the early Yayoi period and a small remains of a rice-paddy field was discovered in the Sunazawa site located in Hirosaki City, Aomori Prefecture, and it had spread to Matsumotodaira in Chuokochi and the Shinano River area during the middle of the Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rice-paddy cultivation had spread to the Tohoku region during the early Yayoi period and a small remains of a rice-paddy field was discovered in the Sunazawa site located in Hirosaki City, Aomori Prefecture, and it had spread to Matsumoto-daira Basin in Chuokochi (Central Highlands) and the Shinano-gawa River area during the middle of the Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>(Central Highlands) を補い補強しました。Matsumotodaira→Matsumoto-daira Basin, Shinano River→Shinano-gawa River と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>中部地方の高地にひろがるまでには200年という期間がかかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It took 200 years to spread to highland in Chubu region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It took 200 years to spread to the highlands in the Chubu region.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It took 200 years to spread to the highlands in the Chubu region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>その理由の一つに感光性のモミが日照時間の短い中部高地では育たないということがあげられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the reasons for taking such long years is that photosensitive paddy does not grow in Chubu highland where hours of sunlight are short.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the reasons for taking such a long time was that photosensitive rice does not grow in the Chubu highland where hours of sunlight are short.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the reasons for taking such a long time was that photosensitive rice does not grow in the Chubu highland where hours of sunlight are short.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="24">
<j>水稲農耕は、かなりな速さで日本列島を縦断し伝播波及したといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Paddy-rice cultivation quickly spread across the Japanese Archipelago.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rice-paddy cultivation quickly spread across the Japanese Archipelago.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rice-paddy cultivation quickly spread across the Japanese Archipelago.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="25">
<j>田を作った人々は、弥生土器を作り、多くの場合竪穴住居に住み、倉庫として掘立柱建物や貯蔵穴を作った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People who created paddy field made Yayoi earthware, many cases lived in pit-type dwellings and built dug-standing pillar building and storage pit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People who created paddy fields made Yayoi earthware, in many cases lived in pit-type dwellings and built a dug-standing pillar building and a storage pit.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People who created paddy fields made Yayoi earthware, in many cases lived in pit-type dwellings and built a dug-standing pillar building and a storage pit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>集落は、居住する場所と墓とがはっきりと区別するように作られ、居住域の周囲にはしばしば環濠集落が掘削された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Settlement had clear division between living area and graves, and village surrounded by a moat were excavated around the area of living.</e>
<cmt>「居住域の周囲にはしばしば環濠集落が掘削された」ではなく、「居住域の周囲にはしばしば堀が掘削された」ではないでしょうか？（堀にかこまれた居住域＝環濠集落）訳はoriginalどおりです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Settlements had clear divisions between the living area and graves, and the village surrounded by a moat were excavated around the area of living.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Settlements had clear divisions between the living area and graves, and the village surrounded by a moat were excavated around the area of living.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="27">
<j>道具は、工具や耕起具、調理具などに石器を多く使ったが、次第に石器にかえて徐々に鉄器を使うようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stone tools were used for implements, agriculture cultivation tool and cookware, but gradually shifted to ironware from stoneware.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stone tools were used for implements, agriculture cultivation tool and cookware, but gradually shifted to ironware from stoneware.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stone tools were used for implements, agriculture cultivation tool and cookware, but gradually shifted to ironware from stoneware.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>青銅器は当初武器として、その後は祭祀具として用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bronze ware was originally used as a weapon and was later used as a religious service tools.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bronze ware was originally used as a weapon and was later used as a religious service accessories.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bronze ware was originally used as a weapon and was later used as a religious service accessories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>また、農具や食膳具などとして木器もしばしば用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also wooden tools are often used as farming equipments and dinning tools.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also wooden tools were often used as farming equipment and dinning utensils.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also wooden tools were often used as farming equipment and dinning utensils.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="30">
<j>弥生時代には農業、特に水稲農耕の採用によって穀物の備蓄が可能になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Yayoi period, adaptation of farming, especially paddy-rice cultivation, enabled accumulation of grain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Yayoi period, adaptation of farming, especially rice-paddy cultivation, enabled the accumulation of grain.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Yayoi period, adaptation of farming, especially rice-paddy cultivation, enabled the storage of grain.</e>
<cmt>accumulation→storage と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>このことから、余剰作物の生産と蓄積がすすみ、これが富に転化することにより、持てるものと持たざるもの、ひいては貧富の差や上下関係が生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, production and accumulation of surplus crops increased and it had changed to wealth, which created the haves and the have-nots leading to the disparity between rich and poor and superior-inferior relationship.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, production and accumulation of surplus crops increased and it had changed to wealth, which created the haves and the have-nots leading to the disparity between rich and poor and a superior-inferior relationship.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, production and storage of surplus crops increased and it changed to wealth, which created the haves and the have-nots leading to the disparity between rich and poor and a superior-inferior relationship.</e>
<cmt>accumulation→storage と修正しました。（「蓄積＝たくさんたくわえること」から）,it had changed→it changed と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="32">
<j>また、水稲耕作技術の導入により、開墾や用水の管理などに大規模な労働力が必要とされるようになり、集団の大型化が進行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also groups became large sized by introduction of paddy-rice cultivation techniques, as cultivation and management of agricultural water required large labor force.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also groups became large sized by introduction of rice-paddy cultivation techniques, as cultivation and management of agricultural water required a large labor force.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also groups became large sized by the introduction of rice-paddy cultivation techniques, as the cultivation and management of agricultural water required a large labor force.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>大型化した集団同士の間には、富や耕作地、水利権などをめぐって戦いが発生したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that battles between large groups over the wealth, cultivation land and water supply had occurred.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that battles between large groups over wealth, cultivated land, and water supply had occurred.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that battles between large groups over wealth, cultivated land, and water supply occurred.</e>
<cmt>had を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="34">
<j>このような争いを通じた集団の統合・上下関係の進展の結果、やがて各地に小さなクニが生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of integration of groups and progression of superior-inferior relationship in the battles, small provinces were created in various regions.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of the integration of groups and the progression of a superior-inferior relationship during battles, small provinces were created in various regions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of the integration of groups and the progression of a superior-inferior relationship during battles, small provinces were created in various regions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>1世紀中頃に倭奴国王印が後漢から、3世紀中葉には邪馬台国の女王（卑弥呼）が魏 (三国)に朝貢し、倭の王であることを意味する金印を授けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the middle of first century, Wa no na no kokuo in (the oldest known seal in Japan) was sent to Japan from the Later Han Dynasty and in middle of third century, the queen of Yamatai-Koku Kingdom (Himiko) paid tribute to Wei dynasty (Three States Period) and presented with golden seal which implies the king of Wa (Japan).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the middle of the first century, Wa no na no kokuo in (the oldest known seal in Japan) was sent to Japan from the Later Han Dynasty and in middle of third century, the queen of Yamatai-Koku Kingdom (Himiko) paid tribute to Wei dynasty (Three States Period) and presented with golden seal which implies the king of Wa (Japan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the middle of the first century, Wa no na no kokuo in (the oldest known seal in Japan) was sent to Japan from the Later Han Dynasty and in middle of third century, the queen of Yamatai-Koku Kingdom (Himiko) paid tribute to Wei dynasty (Three States Period) and presented with golden seal which implies the king of Wa (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="36">
<j>なお、この頃以降の日本は、大陸からは倭と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The continents had called Japan &apos;Wa&apos; from this period onwards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The continent had called Japan &apos;Wa&apos; from this period onwards.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The continent had called Japan &apos;Wa&apos; from this period onwards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="37">
<j>一方、南西諸島と樺太・北海道には水田が作られず、南西諸島では貝塚時代、ついでグスク時代、樺太・北海道では続縄文時代、ついで擦文時代（さつもん）が続いた（また、本州東北地方では、青森県垂柳遺跡のように弥生時代前期の水田の事例もあるものの、一般的には中期後半前後まで水稲農耕は完全に受容されたとはいえず、北海道に準じ続縄文文化が展開したとの見方もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, paddy fields did not spread in Nansei Islands and Sakhalin/Hokkaido, therefore Shell mound period then Gusuku period followed after Jomon period in Nansei Islands and Post Jomon period then Satsumon period followed after Jomon period in Sakhalin/Hokkaido (although there was a example of paddy field in the early Yayoi period shown in Tareyanagi site in Aomori Prefecture, paddy-rice cultivation also did not widely spread in Tohoku region in Honshu until the middle to the late Yayoi period and some theory views that Post Jomon period followed like Hokkaido).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, rice-paddies did not spread in the Nansei Islands and Sakhalin/Hokkaido, therefore, the Shell mound period and then the Gusuku period followed the Jomon period in the Nansei Islands and Post Jomon period then Satsumon period followed after the Jomon period in Sakhalin/Hokkaido (although there was an example of a rice-paddy during the early Yayoi period shown in the Tareyanagi site in Aomori Prefecture, rice-paddy cultivation also did not widely spread in Tohoku region in Honshu until the middle to the late Yayoi period and some theoretical views that Post Jomon period followed like in Hokkaido).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, rice-paddies did not spread in the Nansei Islands and Sakhalin/Hokkaido, therefore, the Shell mound period and then the Gusuku period followed the Jomon period in the Nansei Islands and Post Jomon period then Satsumon period followed after the Jomon period in Sakhalin/Hokkaido (Although there was an example of a rice-paddy during the early Yayoi period shown in the Tareyanagi site in Aomori Prefecture, rice-paddy cultivation also did not widely spread in Tohoku region in Honshu until the middle to the late Yayoi period and some theoretical views that Post Jomon period followed as in Hokkaido.)</e>
<cmt>カッコ部分、ピリオドの位置を修正しました。like→as と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="38">
<j>併合の記載があるまで、以後の記述は、九州・四国・本州を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Below statements are referred to Kyushu, Shikoku and Honshu until annexation is stated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The statements below referr to Kyushu, Shikoku, and Honshu until annexation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The statements below refer to Kyushu, Shikoku, and Honshu until annexation.</e>
<cmt>referr→refer と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>南西諸島の歴史については、沖縄県の歴史他奄美諸島の歴史、先島諸島先島の歴史も参照のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">See History of Okinawa Prefecture, History of Amami Islands and History of Sakishima Islands for history of Nansei Islands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">See History of Okinawa Prefecture, Amami Islands, and Sakishima Islands for the history of the Nansei Islands.</e>
<cmt>redundant, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">See History of Okinawa Prefecture, Amami Islands, and Sakishima Islands for the history of the Nansei Islands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="40">
<j>弥生時代後期・終末期の2、3世紀ごろは、やや冷涼な気候であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the second to third century, around the latter to the end of Yayoi period, was slightly cool climate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the second to third century, around the end of the Yayoi period, the climate was slightly cool.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the second to third century, around the end of the Yayoi period, the climate was slightly cool.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="41">
<j>また、3世紀は海退期であり、海が退いていき沼や湖が干上がり、その底に溜まっていた粘土の上に河が運んできた砂が溜まっていく時期であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also the third century was a regression period when the seawater receded and sand carried by rivers deposited over clay layer at the bottom of dried up ponds and lakes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also the third century was a period of regression when the seawater receded and sand carried by rivers was deposited over the clay layer at the bottom of dried up ponds and lakes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also the third century was a period of regression when the seawater receded and sand carried by rivers was deposited over the clay layer at the bottom of dried up ponds and lakes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>時期区分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classification of the period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classification of the period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classification of the period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="42">
<j>弥生時代の始まりをいつの時点とすべきかは、諸説ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are various theories for the start of Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various theories about the start of the Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various theories about the start of the Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="43">
<j>そもそも弥生時代とは、弥生式土器が使われている時代という意味であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally Yayoi period meant for the period that used Yayoi earthware.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally the Yayoi period meant the period that used Yayoi earthenware.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally the Yayoi period meant the period that used Yayoi earthenware.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>ところが、弥生式土器には米、あるいは水稲農耕技術体系が伴うことが徐々に明らかになってきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However the fact that Yayoi earthware required rice or paddy-rice cultivation techniques were gradually came to known.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However the fact that Yayoi earthenware required rice or rice-paddy cultivation techniques gradually came to be known.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However the fact that Yayoi earthenware required rice or rice-paddy cultivation techniques gradually came to be known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>すると、弥生時代とは、水稲農耕による食料生産に基礎を置く農耕社会であって、前段階である縄文時代（狩猟採集社会）とはこの点で区別されるべきだとする考え方が主流になっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then a point of view that Yayoi period was a agrarian society based on food production by paddy-rice cultivation and should be distinguished from its previous period, Jomon period (a hunting and gathering society), became the mainstream.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then the point of view that the Yayoi period was an agrarian society based on food production by rice-paddy cultivation and should be distinguished from previous periods, Jomon period (a hunting and gathering society), became mainstream.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then the point of view that the Yayoi period was an agrarian society based on food production by rice-paddy cultivation and should be distinguished from previous periods, Jomon period (a hunting and gathering society), became mainstream.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="46">
<j>そのような中、福岡市板付遺跡において、夜臼式土器段階の水田遺構が発見された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While such arguments were going on, ancient structural remnants of paddy field at Yusu earthware stage was discovered in Itazuke site located in Fukuoka City.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While such arguments were going on, ancient structural remnants of paddy fields at the Yusu earthenware stage was discovered at the Itazuke site located in Fukuoka City.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While such arguments were going on, ancient structural remnants of paddy fields at the Yusu earthenware stage was discovered at the Itazuke site located in Fukuoka City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>従来縄文時代晩期後半と考えられていた夜臼式土器期において、すでに水稲農耕技術が採用されており、この段階を農耕社会としてよいという考えが提出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yusu earthware stage was originally considered as the latter half of the last of Jomon period, but an opinion stating that the stage was at agrarian society was submitted, as the period already adapted paddy-rice cultivation techniques.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yusu earthenware stage was originally considered the latter half of the last Jomon period, but an opinion stating that the stage was an agrarian society was submitted, as the period already adapted rice-paddy cultivation techniques.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yusu earthenware stage was originally considered the latter half of the last Jomon period, but an opinion stating that the stage was an agrarian society was submitted, as the period already adapted rice-paddy cultivation techniques.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="48">
<j>その後、縄文時代と弥生時代の差を何に求めるべきかという本質的な論争が研究者の間で展開され、集落の形態や墓の形態、水田の有無、土器・石器など物質文化の変化など様々な指標が提案された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, an essential subject of what would be the difference between Jomon and Yayoi period, was argued between researchers and various indicators were proposed, including forms of settlement, forms of grave, presence or absence of paddy field and changes in artifacts such as earthware and stoneware.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, the essential subject of the difference between the Jomon and Yayoi periods, was argued between researchers and various indicators were proposed, including forms of settlement, forms of graves, presence or absence of paddy fields and changes in artifacts such as earthenware and stoneware.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, the essential subject of the difference between the Jomon and Yayoi periods, was argued between researchers and various indicators were proposed, including forms of settlement, forms of graves, presence or absence of paddy fields and changes in artifacts such as earthenware and stoneware.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="49">
<j>現在ではおおよそ、水稲農耕技術を安定的に受容した段階以降を弥生時代とするという考えが定着している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Presently Yayoi period is roughly classified as a stage after a stable adaptation of paddy-rice cultivation techniques.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Presently the Yayoi period is roughly classified as a stage after the stable adaptation of rice-paddy cultivation techniques.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Presently the Yayoi period is roughly classified as a stage after the stable adaptation of rice-paddy cultivation techniques.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>従って、弥生時代前期前半より以前に（夜臼式土器に代表されるような刻目突帯文土器と総称される一群の土器形式に示された）水稲農耕技術を伴う社会が（少なくとも北部九州地域には）成立していたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, society with paddy-rice cultivation techniques (at least in northern Kyushu) existed before the first half of early Yayoi period (shown in a form of earthwares celled Kizamimetottaimon earthware such as Yusu earthware).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, a society with rice-paddy cultivation techniques (at least in northern Kyushu) existed before the first half of the early Yayoi period (shown in a form of earthenware called Kizamimetottaimon earthenware such as Yusu earthenware).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, a society with rice-paddy cultivation techniques (at least in northern Kyushu) existed before the first half of the early Yayoi period (Shown in a form of earthenware called Kizamimetottaimon earthenware such as Yusu earthenware.)</e>
<cmt>カッコ部分、ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>従来縄文時代晩期後半とされてきたこの段階について、近年ではこれを弥生時代早期と呼ぶようになりつつある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Traditionally this stage was classified as the latter half of the last of Jomon period, but now it is called the earlier Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Traditionally this stage was classified as the latter half of the last of Jomon period, but it is now called the earlier Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Traditionally this stage was classified as the latter half of the last of Jomon period, but it is now becoming to be called the earlier Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>becoming to be を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>なお土器についた穀物圧痕の研究が進み、稲作技術は、遅くとも縄文時代後期までには列島にもたらされていたことが分かっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A research on grain impressions on earthware progressed and it is known that rice-cropping techniques was introduced to Japan Archipelago by the end of Jomon period at latest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Research on grain impressions on earthware progressed and it is known that rice-cropping techniques were introduced to Japan Archipelago by the end of the Jomon period at the latest.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Research on grain impressions on earthware progressed and it is known that rice-cropping techniques were introduced to Japan Archipelago by the end of the Jomon period at the latest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="53">
<j>また、水稲農耕の導入についても北部九州の一部地域では縄文晩期前半にまでさかのぼる可能性が指摘されているが、明確な遺構が発見されておらず、推測の域を出ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also a possibility that the adaptation of paddy-rice cultivation in a part of northern Kyushu to go back to the first half of last of Jomon period is indicated but clear evidence of ancient structural remnants are not yet discovered and is still a speculation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also the possibility that the adaptation of rice-paddy cultivation in parts of northern Kyushu that go back to the first half of the last of Jomon period is indicated, but clear evidence of ancient structural remnants have not yet been discovered and is still speculation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also the possibility that the adaptation of rice-paddy cultivation in parts of northern Kyushu that go back to the first half of the last of Jomon period is indicated, but clear evidence of ancient structural remnants have not yet been discovered and is still speculation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="54">
<j>弥生時代の時期区分は、従来、前期・中期・後期の3期に分けられていたが、近年では上記の研究動向をふまえ、早期・前期・中期・後期の4期区分論が主流になりつつある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yayoi period was originally divided to 3 periods, which were early period, middle period and end period, but recently Yayoi period is divided to 4 periods, which are earlier period, early period, middle period and end period, based on above stated researches.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yayoi period was originally divided to three periods; the early period, middle period, and the end period, but recently the Yayoi period is divided to four periods; the earlier period, early period, middle period, and end period, based on the above stated research.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yayoi period was originally divided to three periods; the early period, middle period, and the end period, but recently the Yayoi period is divided to four periods; the earlier period, early period, middle period, and end period, based on the above stated research.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>また、北部九州以外の地域では（先I～）I～Vの5(6)期に分ける方法もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also a method to divide Yayoi period into 5 (or 6) periods, which are I (pre I) to V, in outside northern Kyushu region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also a way to divide Yayoi period into five (or six) periods, which are I (pre I) to V, outside the northern Kyushu region.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also a way to divide the Yayoi period into five (or six) periods, which are I (pre I) to V, outside the northern Kyushu region.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>（早期は先I期）前期はI期、中期はII～IV期、後期はV期にそれぞれ対応する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each period is equivalent to (Earlier period to pre I period) early period to I period, middle period to II to IV periods and end period to V period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each period is equivalent to (Earlier period to pre I period) early period to I period, middle period to II to IV periods and end period to the V period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each period is equivalent to (Earlier period to pre I period) early period to I period, middle period to II to IV periods and end period to the V period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>（早期は紀元前5世紀半ば頃から）前期は紀元前3世紀頃から、中期は紀元前1世紀頃から、後期は1世紀半ば頃から3世紀の半ば頃まで続いたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Earlier period started from the middle of fifth century B.C.) early period started from the third century B.C., middle period started from the first century B.C., end period started from the first century and lasted until the middle of third century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The Earlier period started from the middle of fifth century B.C.) early period started from the third century B.C., middle period started from the first century B.C., end period started from the first century and lasted until the middle of third century.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The Earlier period started from the middle of fifth century B.C.) early period started from the third century B.C., middle period started from the first century B.C., end period started from the first century and lasted until the middle of third century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="58">
<j>最近になって、国立歴史民俗博物館の研究グループによる放射性炭素年代測定を活用した一連の研究成果により、弥生時代の開始期を大幅に繰り上げるべきだと主張する説がでてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently, there is a theory insisting to move back the start date of Yayoi period dramatically, based on radioactive carbon dating research results shown by a research group from National Museum of Japanese History.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently, there is a theory insisting on moving back to the start date of the Yayoi period dramatically, based upon radioactive carbon dating research results shown by a research group from National Museum of Japanese History.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently, there is a theory insisting on moving back to the start date of the Yayoi period dramatically, based upon radioactive carbon dating research results shown by a research group from the National Museum of Japanese History.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>これによると、早期のはじまりが約600年遡り紀元前1000年頃から、前期のはじまりが約500年遡り紀元前800年頃から、中期のはじまりが約200年遡り紀元前400年頃から、後期のはじまりが紀元50年頃からとなり、古墳時代への移行はほぼ従来通り3世紀中葉となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the theory, start of earlier period moves back approximately 600 years and starts around 1000 B.C., starts of early period moves back approximately 500 years and starts around 800 B.C., starts of middle period moves back approximately 200 years and starts 400 B.C., starts of end period is at 50 B.C. and transition to Kofunperiod is at the middle of third century, which is conventional.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the theory, the start of the earlier period is moved back approximately 600 years and starts around 1000 B.C., the start of the early period is moved back approximately 500 years and starts around 800 B.C., the start of the middle period is moved back approximately 200 years and starts around 400 B.C., the start of the end period is at 50 B.C. and the transition to the Kofun period is in the middle of the third century, which is conventional.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the theory, the start of the earlier period is moved back approximately 600 years and starts around 1000 B.C., the start of the early period is moved back approximately 500 years and starts around 800 B.C., the start of the middle period is moved back approximately 200 years and starts around 400 B.C., the start of the end period is at 50 B.C. and the transition to the Kofun period is in the middle of the third century, which is conventional.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="60">
<j>政治</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Politics</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Politics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Politics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>戦乱の時代－環濠集落と高地性集落－</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">War-torn era - Moat Setttlement and Upland Settlements -</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">War-torn era - Moat Setttlement and Upland Settlements -</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">War-torn era - Moat Settlement and Upland Settlements -</e>
<cmt>Setttlement→Settlement と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>弥生時代は、前代（縄文時代）とはうってかわって、集落・地域間の戦争が頻発した時代であったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrast to previous period (Jomon period), it is believed that battles between settlements and regions occurred frequently in Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast to the previous period (Jomon period), it is believed that battles between settlements and regions occurred frequently during the Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast to the previous period (Jomon period), it is believed that battles between settlements and regions occurred frequently during the Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="63">
<j>集落の周りに濠をめぐらせた環濠集落や、低地から100m以上の比高差を持つような山頂部に集落を構える高地性集落などは、集落間の争いがあったことの証拠とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moat settlements that have a moat around the settlement and upland settlements that were located at top of the mountain with more than 100m in its height are said to be the evidence of battles between settlements.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moat settlements that have a moat around the settlement and upland settlements that were located at top of the mountain more than 100m in height are said to be evidence of battles between settlements.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moat settlements that have a moat around the settlement and upland settlements that were located at top of the mountain more than 100m in height are said to be evidence of battles between settlements.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>また、武器の傷をうけたような痕跡のある人骨（受傷人骨）の存在なども、戦乱の裏づけとして理解されてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Weapons wounds on the recovered human bones (a human bone with trauma) also supported the evidence of wars.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Weapon wounds on the recovered human bones (a human bone with trauma) also supported the evidence of war.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Weapon wounds on the recovered human bones (a human bone with trauma) also supported the evidence of war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="65">
<j>しかし、近年ではこうした一面的な理解に対する反論も多く、未だ定説となるに至っていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However there are many objections to the one-sided point of view and has not yet become an established theory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However there are many objections to this one-sided point of view and it has not yet become an established theory.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However there are many objections to this one-sided point of view and it has not yet become an established theory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="66">
<j>弥生時代前期の墓には、人骨の胸から腰にかけての位置から十五本の石鏃が出土した例がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A human bone with 15 Sekizoku (a flint arrowhead) at chest to waist area was excavated from a grave of early Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A human bone with fifteen Sekizoku (a flint arrowhead) at chest to waist area was excavated from an early Yayoi period grave.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A human bone with 15 Sekizoku (a flint arrowhead) at chest to waist area was excavated from an early Yayoi period grave.</e>
<cmt>fifteen→15 と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="67">
<j>このように、多くの石鏃が胸部付近に集中して見つかる墓の事例は、瀬戸内海を中心とする西日本一帯に比較的多く見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cases of graves that yielded human bones with many Sekizoku around chest area are often found in western Japan, around in Seto Inland Sea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cases of graves that yielded human bones with many Sekizoku around chest area are often found in western Japan, around the Seto Inland Sea.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cases of graves that yielded human bones with many Sekizoku around chest area are often found in western Japan, around the Seto Inland Sea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>以前には、こうした例は、戦闘の際に矢を何本も射込まれて、やっと倒れた人物と解釈されることが多く、「英雄」などとも呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Previously, these examples were interpreted as a person who fell in a battle after being shot many arrows and the person was called a &apos;Hero&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Previously, these examples were interpreted as a person who fell in a battle after being shot with many arrows and the person was called a &apos;Hero.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Previously, these examples were interpreted as a person who fell in a battle after being shot with many arrows and the person was called a &apos;Hero.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="69">
<j>しかしながら近年では、矢を特定の部位に集中して射込まれていることの不自然さから、むしろ埋葬の際に副葬品として鏃を胸のあたりに埋納した、あるいは何らかの儀礼的行為の際の犠牲（生け贄）となって胸に矢を射込まれたなどといった解釈も現れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, because of its unnaturalness of arrowhead concentrating in a specific area, recently new interpretations are arising such as; arrowheads were buried as burial goods, or a person was shot arrows as a sacrifice (sacrificial offering) in some kind of rituals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, because of the unnaturalness of arrowheads being concentrated in a specific area, new recent interpretations are arising such as; arrowheads were buried as burial goods, or a person was shot with arrows as a sacrifice (sacrificial offering) in some kind of ritual.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, because of the unnaturalness of arrowheads being concentrated in a specific area, new recent interpretations are arising such as; arrowheads were buried as burial goods, or a person was shot with arrows as a sacrifice (sacrificial offering) in some kind of ritual.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="70">
<j>また、北部九州では、前期から中期にかけて銅剣・銅戈・石剣・石戈の切っ先が棺内から出土することが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, tip of bronze swords, doka (bronze halberds for ritual), stone swords, and stone halberds are excavated from a coffin of the early to middle Yayoi period in northern Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>銅戈：bronze dagger-axe　となっているのですが、戈とは、ピッケル状の長柄武器で、銅戈（どうか）の訳はbronze halberd（斧槍の意)となっています。用語集のdagger-axeでは、斧は当てはまるのですが、daggerは短剣を意味するので、長柄武器とはなりません。ただ、銅矛の訳もbronze halberdとなっており、日本では銅戈は戦闘ではなく祭祀用であったため、銅戈：doka (bronze halberd for ritual)とした方がよいのではないかと思います。以下、銅戈：doka (bronze halberd for ritual)と訳します。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, the tip of bronze swords, doka (bronze halberds for ritual), stone swords, and stone halberds were excavated from a coffin of the early to the middle Yayoi period in northern Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the tip of bronze swords, doka (bronze halberds for ritual), stone swords, and stone halberds are often excavated from a coffin of the early to the middle Yayoi period in northern Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>were→are often と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="71">
<j>こうした例は、従来、武器を人体に刺突した際に先端が折れて体内に残ったものと解釈されてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These examples are previously thought as a remains of weapon breaking off when stabbing a human body.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These examples are previously thought of as remains of a weapon breaking off when stabbing the human body.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Up to now, these examples are thought of as remains of a weapon breaking off when stabbing the human body.</e>
<cmt>previously→up to now　to 修正しました。（「従来＝以前から今まで」ということから）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>しかし、これも、武器の先端を折りとって副葬品として棺内に埋納するという風習があったのではないかといった反論がだされており、決着はついていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However there is a counterargument that there could be a custom to burry tip of weapons as burial goods inside the coffin and the argument has not yet seen a settlement.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However there is a counter argument that there could be a custom to burry tip of weapons as burial goods inside the coffin and the argument has not yet been settled.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However there is a counter argument that there could be a custom to bury tip of weapons as burial goods inside the coffin and the argument has not yet been settled.</e>
<cmt>burry→bury と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="73">
<j>さらに、佐賀県吉野ヶ里遺跡や福岡県筑紫野隈・西小田遺跡などでは、中期前葉の男性甕棺数が女性の倍にも達する事実は男性が戦闘に参加する機会が多いことを示すと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, the fact that number of kamekan (earthenware jar-coffin) for male excavated in Yoshinogari site at Saga Prefecture and Kuma/Nishioda site at Chikushi City, Fukuoka Prefecture is double the number of female&apos;s, which is interpreted as male had more occasion joining in the battle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, the fact that a number of kamekan (earthenware jar-coffin) for males excavated at the Yoshinogari site at Saga Prefecture and Kuma/Nishioda site at Chikushi City, Fukuoka Prefecture is double the number of female&apos;s, which is interpreted as the males had more occasion to join in battle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the fact that a number of kamekan (earthenware jar-coffin) for males excavated at the Yoshinogari site at Saga Prefecture and Kuma/Nishioda site at Chikushi City, Fukuoka Prefecture is double the number of female&apos;s, which is interpreted as the males had more occasion to join in battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>甕棺内に頭部を除く全身が埋葬されていたと考えられる事例が見つかっており、しばしば戦闘の際に敵に頭部を切り取られた死者を連れ帰り、埋葬したものと理解されているが、このような例が本当に戦闘の犠牲者なのか、それとも何らかの儀礼的行為によるものなのかは実際のところは未だ論証されていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in some cases, kamekan with whole body except the head part were excavated, and these were interpreted as a enemy took the victim&apos;s head from the battle field and the victim&apos;s body was taken back to settlement for burial, however it is not proved if they really were a victim of a battle, or if it was a result of some ritual.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also in some cases, kamekan with whole body except the head part were excavated, and these were interpreted as an enemy taking the victim&apos;s head from the battle field and the victim&apos;s body was taken back to the settlement for burial, however it is not proven if they really were victims of a battle, or if it was the result of some ritual.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also in some cases, kamekan with whole body except the head part were excavated, and these were interpreted as an enemy taking the victim&apos;s head from the battle field and the victim&apos;s body was taken back to the settlement for burial, however it is not proven if they really were victims of a battle, or if it was the result of some ritual.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="75">
<j>これに対して、受傷人骨の中でも、明らかに武器によってつけられたと考えられる傷のある人骨の存在は、戦闘の存在を示す証拠として扱うことが可能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among these human bones with trauma, there are human bones with clear sign of weapon trauma and they are treated as the evidence of existence of battles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among these human bones with trauma, there are human bones with a clear sign of weapon trauma and they are treated as the evidence of the existence of battles.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among these human bones with trauma, there are human bones with a clear sign of weapon trauma and they are treated as the evidence of the existence of battles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="76">
<j>例えば、額から右眼にかけて致命的な傷痕があり、更に右手首を骨折していた人骨が見つかっているが、右手首の骨折は、攻撃から身を守る際につけられる、防御創と呼ばれる種類の傷としては一般的なもので、争いによる受傷者である可能性は極めて高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, a human bone with fatal wound across the forehead to right eye and broken right wrist, which is a typical defensive wound happens when defending body from an attack, was excavated, and it is very likely that the person was wounded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, a human bone with fatal wound across the forehead to right eye and broken right wrist, which is a typical defensive wound thqt happens when defending from attack, was excavated, and it is very likely that the person was wounded.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, a human bone with fatal wound across the forehead to right eye and broken right wrist, which is a typical defensive wound that happens when defending from attack, was excavated, and it is very likely that the person was wounded by fighting.</e>
<cmt>thqt→that と修正しました。「争いによる」を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>また、人骨に武器の切っ先が嵌入している事例も、北部九州を中心に数例が確認されているが、これらは武器による受傷人骨であることが明らかである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also there are several cases with tip of weapons impacted human bones in northern Kyushu, and they are clearly the human bones with weapon trauma.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also there are several cases with tip of weapons impacted human bones in northern Kyushu, and they are clearly human bones showing weapon trauma.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also there are several cases with tip of weapons impacted human bones in northern Kyushu, and they are clearly human bones showing weapon trauma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="78">
<j>このような受傷人骨の例は縄文時代にもないわけではないが、弥生時代には前代と比べて明らかに数が増加しており、縄文時代と比べて戦闘が頻繁に起こったことは確実といえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are these types of human bones with trauma from Jomon period, however number of the cases clearly increased in Yayoi period and definitely the battles were more frequent compared to Jomon period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are these types of human bones with trauma from the Jomon period, however the number of cases clearly increased during the Yayoi period and definitely the battles were more frequent compared to the Jomon period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are these types of human bones with trauma from the Jomon period, however the number of cases clearly increased during the Yayoi period and definitely the battles were more frequent compared to the Jomon period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="79">
<j>また、戦闘の証拠とされる上記のような事例のうち、武器の切っ先が棺内から出土する例、頭部がない人骨、あるいは人骨に残る受傷例などは、前期後半～中期前半の北部九州地域、特に福岡県小郡市を中心とした地域に多く認められることが特徴的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among above descried evidence of battles, cases with tip of weapon in the coffin, human bone without head and bone trauma are often found from the latter half of early period to the first half of middle period in northern Kyushu region, especially in regions around Ogori City, Fukuoka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the above described evidence of battles, cases with a tip of a weapon in the coffin, human bones without a head and bone trauma are often found from the latter half of the early period to the first half of middle period in the northern Kyushu region, especially in regions around Ogori City, Fukuoka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>spelling, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the above described evidence of battles, cases with a tip of a weapon in the coffin, human bones without a head and bone trauma are often found from the latter half of the early period to the first half of middle period in the northern Kyushu region, especially in regions around Ogori City, Fukuoka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="80">
<j>弥生前期後半から中期前半は、西日本の多くの地域で集落が可耕地に乏しい丘陵上へと一斉に進出することが指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many settlements in western Japan area are said to have moved up hills, where lacked large cultivation area, at once in the latter half of early period to the first half of middle period in Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many settlements in western Japan are said to have been moved up hill, that lacked large cultivation areas, at once in the latter half of early period to the first half of middle period in Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many settlements in western Japan are said to have been moved up hill, that lacked large cultivation areas, at once in the latter half of early period to the first half of middle period in Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>各地域において弥生集団が急激な人口の増加を背景に可耕地の拡大を求めた時期であるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is suspected that many settlements sought for more cultivation area in each region, due to the rapid increase in population of Yayoi group.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is suspected that many settlements sought more cultivation areas in each region, due to the rapid increase in population of the Yayoi group.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is suspected that many settlements sought more cultivation areas in each region, due to the rapid increase in population of the Yayoi group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="82">
<j>この可耕地の拡大が原因となって、各地で土地と水に絡む戦いが頻発したものと考えられ、中でも北部九州における受傷人骨の多さは、こうした争いが頻発した証拠と考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This expansion in cultivation area caused many battles over land and water in various regions, especially number of human bones with trauma found in northern Kyushu support frequent occurrence of the battles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This expansion in cultivation areas caused many battles over land and water in various regions, especially number of human bones with trauma found in northern Kyushu support the frequent occurrence of battles.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This expansion in cultivation areas caused many battles over land and water in various regions, especially the number of human bones with trauma found in northern Kyushu provide the evidence of the frequent occurrence of battles.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。support→provide the evidence of を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>なお、中期後半以降は受傷人骨や切先が棺内から出土する例は減少する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Excavation of human bones with trauma and tip of weapon in the coffin decrease on and after the latter half of middle period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Excavation of human bones with trauma and tips of weapons in the coffin decreased on and after the latter half of middle period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Excavation of human bones with trauma and tips of weapons in the coffin decreased on and after the latter half of middle period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="84">
<j>環濠集落は、このような集団同士の争いに備えた防衛集落であったと考えられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moat settlement was believed to be a defensive settlement against the battles between groups.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A moat settlement was believed to be a defense against battles between groups.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A moat settlement was believed to be a defense against battles between groups.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="85">
<j>しかし、環濠集落の出現は、未だ戦闘の証拠がほとんどない弥生時代早期にさかのぼること（福岡県江辻遺跡、同那珂遺跡群など）、受傷人骨などの事例から戦乱が頻発したと考えられる前期後半～中期前半、特に中期初頭以降の北部九州ではむしろ環濠集落の事例は少ないこと、しばしば環濠を掘削する際に排出された土を利用して環濠の外側に盛り土をした痕跡のある事例が報告されているが、環濠の外側に盛り土をすることによって、外敵を有利にしてしまう（外敵は、盛り土を矢避けにしたり、盛り土の上から攻撃できる）ことなどから、環濠集落と戦乱とを直接的に関連づける、すなわち環濠集落を防衛集落と考える研究者は最近では少なくなってきている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, recently not many researchers consider moat settlements as a defensive settlements and directly relate moat settlements with wars, because of several reasons such as; emergence of moat settlement goes back to earlier Yayoi period when there are very little evidence of battles (Etsuji site and Nakai sites in Fukuoka Prefecture), less moat settlements are excavated from northern Kyushu in the latter half of early period to first half of middle period, especially beginning of middle period when frequent wars thought to have occurred from evidence of human bones with trauma, and a banking were created outside the moat in some cases using soil dug up to make the moat, which gives advantage to enemies (enemies can use bank as shield against arrows and also can attack from top of the bank).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, recently not many researchers consider moat settlements as defensive and directly related with wars, for several reasons such as; the emergence of moat settlement goes back to earlier Yayoi period when there was very little evidence of battles (Etsuji site and Nakai sites in Fukuoka Prefecture), less moat settlements are excavated from northern Kyushu in the latter half of early period to first half of middle period, especially beginning of middle period when frequent wars were thought to have occurred from the evidence of human bones with trauma, and banks were created outside the moat in some cases using soil dug up to make the moat, which gives an advantage to the enemy (enemy can use the bank as a shield against arrows and also can attack from the top of a bank).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, recently not many researchers consider moat settlements as defensive and directly related with wars, for several reasons such as; the emergence of moat settlement goes back to earlier Yayoi period when there was very little evidence of battles (Etsuji site and Nakai sites in Fukuoka Prefecture), less moat settlements are excavated from northern Kyushu in the latter half of early period to first half of middle period, especially beginning of middle period when frequent wars were thought to have occurred from the evidence of human bones with trauma, and banks were created outside the moat in some cases using soil dug up to make the moat, which gives an advantage to the enemy (Enemy can use the bank as a shield against arrows and also can attack from the top of a bank.)</e>
<cmt>カッコ部分、ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>それよりは、環濠を掘削するという大規模な土木作業を共同で行うことによって共同体の結束を高めることが目的であったとか、環濠によって集団を囲い込むことによって集団意識を高めることが目的であったなどといった議論も提出されてきている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are other opinions such as large scale public work, like digging up moat, was practiced to tighten the union of the community, or to create and increase group consciousness by enclosing the group.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are other opinions such as large scale public work, like digging a moat, was practiced to tighten the union of the community, or to create and increase group consciousness by enclosing the group.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are other opinions such as large scale public work, such as digging a moat, was practiced to tighten the union of the community, or to create and increase group consciousness by enclosing the group.</e>
<cmt>like→such as と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="87">
<j>しかしながら、弥生時代後期の高地性集落にしばしば環濠が掘削されていること、環濠内に逆茂木（さかもぎ）と呼ばれる防御施設が設置された事例が認められる（愛知県朝日遺跡など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However moat was often dug in upland settlement in the end of Yayoi period and Sakamogi (fence made of thorny or steeple branches to prevent entry of an enemy) was placed at moat in some cases (Asahi site at Aichi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However a moat was often dug in an upland settlement during the end of the Yayoi period and Sakamogi (fence made of thorny or steeple branches to prevent entry of an enemy) were placed at the moat in some cases (Asahi site at Aichi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However a moat was often dug in an upland settlement during the end of the Yayoi period and Sakamogi (fence made of thorny or steeple branches to prevent entry of an enemy) were placed at the moat in some cases (Asahi site at Aichi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>このことから、環濠自体に防御的な機能を持たせた事例が存在することもまた明らかであり、環濠の性格については地域・時期によって異なる意味づけを持たせるべきではないかといった主張は説得力がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These indicate that some moat was equipped with defending facilities and an opinion insisting that function of moat should be considered depending on region and period is very persuasive.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These indicate that some moats were equipped with defending facilities and an opinion insisting that the function of the moat should be considered depending upon the region and period is very persuasive.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These indicate that some moats were equipped with defending facilities and an opinion insisting that the function of the moat should be considered depending upon the region and period is very persuasive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="89">
<j>一方、やはり古くから防衛集落と目されてきた集落の類型として、高地性集落が挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, upland settlements are long considered as a type of defensive settlement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, upland settlements have been long considered a type of defensive settlement.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, upland settlements have been long considered a type of defensive settlement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="90">
<j>高地性集落は、弥生時代中期後半～末（IV期後半～末）、そして後期中葉～末（V期中葉～末）に瀬戸内沿岸から大阪湾にかけて頻繁に見られるもので、弥生時代の一般的な集落からみて遙かに高い場所（平地からの比高差が50～300メートル以上）に営まれている集落のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upland settlements are often found at Setouchi seacoast to Osaka Bay in the latter to end of middle of Yayoi period (the latter to end of IV period) and middle to end of end period (the middle to end of V period) and they are settlements located at very high ground compared to general settlement in Yayoi period (50 to 300 meters high compared to flatland).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upland settlements are often found along the Setouchi seacoast to Osaka Bay in the latter to end of the middle of the Yayoi period (the latter to the end of IV period) and middle to the end of the end period (the middle to the end of the V period) and they are settlements located at very high ground compared to general settlement in the Yayoi period (50 to 300 meters high compared to flatland).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upland settlements are often found along the Setouchi seacoast to Osaka Bay in the latter to end of the middle of the Yayoi period (the latter to the end of IV period) and middle to the end of the end period (the middle to the end of the V period), and they are settlements located at very high ground compared to general settlement in the Yayoi period (50 to 300 meters high compared to flatland).</e>
<cmt>カンマを補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="91">
<j>北部九州から北陸・中部・東海地域などといった広い範囲に分布する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They distribute widely across northern Kyushu to Hokuriku, Chubu and Tokai region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are distributed widely across northern Kyushu to Hokuriku, Chubu and Tokai region.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are distributed widely across northern Kyushu to Hokuriku, Chubu and Tokai regions.</e>
<cmt>region→regions と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>1970年代までは、畿内IV期がおおよそ北部九州の後期前半、畿内V期が後期後半に併行するとされ、実年代では紀元50年～250年ごろに比定されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinai IV period was considered to parallel the first half of end period in northern Kyushu and Kinai V period was considered to parallel the latter half of end period, and identified as 50 to 250 A.D. in actual chronology untill 1970s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kinai IV period was considered to parallel the first half of the end period in northern Kyushu and the Kinai V period was considered to parallel the latter half of the end period, and identified as 50 to 250 A.D. in actual chronology untill 1970s.</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kinai IV period was considered to parallel the first half of the end period in northern Kyushu and the Kinai V period was considered to parallel the latter half of the end period, and identified as 50 to 250 A.D. in actual chronology until 1970s.</e>
<cmt>untill→until と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="93">
<j>史書にある、いわゆる倭国大乱は、各種の史書に記載された年代がおおよそ2世紀後半～末に当たり、当時の年代観ではおおよそ畿内IV期末～V期前半期に該当していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History books describes Wakoku War had occurred around the latter to the end of the second century and it is around the end of Kinai IV period to the early V period in the period&apos;s view.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History books describe that the Wakoku War had occurred around the end of the second century and it is around the end of the Kinai IV period to the early V period in view of the period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History books describe that the Wakoku War had occurred around the end of the second century and it is around the end of the Kinai IV period to the early V period in view of the period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="94">
<j>このため、高地性集落の盛行は倭国大乱を原因とするものだという理解が主流であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore Wakoku War was considered as reason for the prosper of upland settlemets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore the Wakoku War was considered as a reason for the prospering of upland settlements.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore the Wakoku War was considered as a reason for the prospering of the upland settlements.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>しかし、畿内と九州の年代の併行関係が是正された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However parallel relationship of Kinai and Kyushu periods were corrected.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However the parallel relationship of the Kinai and Kyushu periods were corrected.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However the parallel relationship of the Kinai and Kyushu periods were corrected.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>倭国大乱は畿内V期後半～末に該当し、畿内IV期の高地性集落とは時代的に整合的でないとされ、これらは倭国大乱とは無関係とする意見が主流を占めるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to correction, Wakoku War comes under the latter to end of Kinai V period, which has no periodical consistency with upland settlement, and theory stating upland settlement was not related to Wakoku War became the mainstream.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a correction, the Wakoku War comes under the latter to end of the Kinai V period, which has no periodical consistency with upland settlements, and theory stating upland settlements were not related to the Wakoku War, became the mainstream.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a correction, the Wakoku War comes under the latter to end of the Kinai V period, which has no periodical consistency with upland settlements, and theory stating upland settlements were not related to the Wakoku War, became the mainstream.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="32">
<sen id="97">
<j>このため、畿内IV期の高地性集落については、この時期に史書には記載されない戦乱があったという主張の他に、背景に戦乱を想定する必要はないという意見も見られるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, as for upland settlements in Kinai IV period, there is some opinion insisting that there were wars not described in history book in the period, as well as an opinion insisting that there is no need to assume wars for its background.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, as for upland settlements in the Kinai IV period, there is some opinion insisting that there were wars not described in history books during the period, as well as an opinion insisting that there is no need to assume wars for its background.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, as for upland settlements in the Kinai IV period, there is some opinion insisting that there were wars not described in history books during the period, as well as an opinion insisting that there is no need to assume wars for its background.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>特に後者の場合、見晴らしがよい立地に住むことで、海上交通の見張り役となっていたとか、畑作を主とする生活をしていた集団であって水田耕作に有利な低地に住む必要がなかったなどといったさまざまな議論が行われており、未だ決着はついていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The argument has not yet seen a settlement, especially the latter argues that living in location with wide view enabled to watch marine traffic, or it was a group mainly lived off with dry field farming and they did not need to live in low-lying ground, which is profitable for paddy-rice cultivation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The argument has not yet seen a settlement, especially the latter argues that living in a location with a wide view enabled the monitoring of watch marine traffic, or it was a group that mainly lived off dry field farming and they did not need to live on a low-lying ground, which is profitable for rice-paddy cultivation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The argument has not yet seen a settlement, especially the latter argues that living in a location with a wide view enabled the monitoring of watch marine traffic, or it was a group that mainly lived off dry field farming and they did not need to live on a low-lying ground, which is profitable for rice-paddy cultivation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="33">
<sen id="99">
<j>一方、後期後半期の近畿の高地性集落（大阪府和泉市観音寺山遺跡、同高槻市古曾部遺跡などは環濠を巡らす山城）については、その盛行期が、上述の理由から北部九州・畿内ともおおよそ史書に記載された倭国大乱の年代とほぼ一致することから、これらを倭国大乱と関連させる理解が主流を占めているようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, upland settlements in Kinki region in the latter half of end period (Kannonjiyama site at Izumi City, Osaka Prefecture and Kosobe site at Takatsuki City, Osaka Prefecture are mountain castle with moat) are considered to hold some relationship to Wakoku War, as its prospered period in both northern Kyushu and Kinai matches to the period of Wakoku War described in history book, after the correction of period described earlier.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, upland settlements in the Kinki region in the latter half of the end period (Kannonjiyama site at Izumi City, Osaka Prefecture and Kosobe site at Takatsuki City, Osaka Prefecture are mountain castle with moat) are considered to hold some relationship to the Wakoku War, as its prospered period in both northern Kyushu and Kinai matches to the period of Wakoku War described in history books, after the correction of the period described earlier.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, upland settlements in the Kinki region in the latter half of the end period (Kannonjiyama site at Izumi City, Osaka Prefecture and Kosobe site at Takatsuki City, Osaka Prefecture are mountain castle with moat) are considered to hold some relationship to the Wakoku War, as its prospered period in both northern Kyushu and Kinai matches to the period of Wakoku War described in history books, after the correction of the period described earlier.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="34">
<sen id="100">
<j>倭国大乱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wakoku War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wakoku War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wakoku War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>魏志倭人伝には、卑弥呼が邪馬台国を治める以前は、諸国が対立し互いに攻め合っていたという記述がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gishiwajinden (literally, an &apos;Account of the Wa&apos; in &quot;The History of the Wei Dynasty&quot;) describes that there were conflicts between various districts before Himiko rules Yamatai-Koku kingdom.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gishiwajinden (literally, an &apos;Account of the Wa&apos; in &quot;The History of the Wei Dynasty&quot;) describes that there were conflicts between various districts before Himiko ruled the Yamatai-Koku kingdom.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gishiwajinden (literally, an &apos;Account of the Wa&apos; in &quot;The History of the Wei Dynasty&quot;) describes that there were conflicts between various districts before Himiko ruled the Yamatai-Koku kingdom.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>また、後漢書東夷伝には、桓帝 (漢)・霊帝 (漢)の治世の間、倭国が多いに乱れたという記述がある（倭国大乱）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dongyi zhuan (the record of the encounters with eastern barbarians) in Gokanjo (Historical records of the Later Han Dynasty) describes Wakoku (Japan) was at troubled state (Wakoku War) while time of the Emperor Ling (Han dynasty) to Emperor Huan (Han dynasty).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dongyi zhuan (the record of encounters with the eastern barbarians) in Gokanjo (Historical records of the Later Han Dynasty) describes Wakoku (Japan) was in a troubled state (Wakoku War) during the time of Emperor Ling (Han dynasty) to Emperor Huan (the Han dynasty).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dongyi zhuan (the record of encounters with the eastern barbarians) in Gokanjo (Historical records of the Later Han Dynasty) describes Wakoku (Japan) was in a troubled state (Wakoku War) during the time of the Emperor Ling (Han dynasty) to the Emperor Huan (the Han dynasty).</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="35">
<sen id="103">
<j>近年、畿内の弥生時代IV・V期の年代観の訂正により、これらはおおよそ弥生時代後期後半 - 末（V期後半 - VI期）に併行するという考えが主流になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of recent chronological correction to Yayoi IV/V period in Kinai, the description is now considered to fall under the latter to end of end of Yayoi period (latter V period to VI period).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of recent chronological corrections to the Yayoi IV/V period in Kinai, the description is now considered to fall under the latter to the end of the Yayoi period (latter V period to VI period).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of recent chronological corrections to the Yayoi IV/V period in Kinai, the description is now considered to fall under the latter to the end of the Yayoi period (latter V period to VI period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>この時期には、畿内を中心として北部九州から瀬戸内、あるいは山陰から北陸、東海地域以東にまで高地性集落が見られること、環濠集落が多く見られることなどから、これらを倭国大乱の証拠であるとする考え方はほぼ定説となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These are many upland settlements and moat settlements are found around Kinai to northern Kyushu, Setouchi, Sanin, Hokuriku, Tokai region and east, and it is an established theory that these are the evidence of Wakoku War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These are many upland settlements and moat settlements are found around Kinai to northern Kyushu, Setouchi, Sanin, Hokuriku, Tokai region, and east, and it is an established theory that these are evidence for the Wakoku War.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These are many upland settlements and moat settlements are found around Kinai to northern Kyushu, Setouchi, Sanin, Hokuriku, Tokai region, and east in this period, and it is an established theory that these are evidence for the Wakoku War.</e>
<cmt>in this period を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="36">
<sen id="105">
<j>しかしながら、前代に比べて武器の発達が見られず、特に近接武器が副葬品以外ではほとんど認められないこと、受傷人骨の少なさなどから、具体的な戦闘が頻発していたと主張する研究者はあまり多くない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, not many researchers insist occurrence of actual battles as there are little development in weapon compared to previous generation, especially very few weapons for close combat are found apart from burial goods and few human bones with trauma are excavated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, not many researchers insist on the occurrence of actual battles as there was little development in weapons compared to the previous generation, especially very few weapons for close combat are found apart from burial goods and few human bones with trauma were excavated.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, not many researchers insist on the occurrence of actual battles as there was little development in weapons compared to the previous generation, especially very few weapons for close combat are found apart from burial goods and few human bones with trauma were excavated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>倭国大乱がどのような争いであったのかは未だ具体的に解明されていないのが現状である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No clear picture about Wakoku War has been unraveled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No clear picture about Wakoku War has been unraveled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No clear picture about the Wakoku War has been unraveled.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="37">
<sen id="107">
<j>邪馬台国畿内説では、北部九州勢力が大和へと移動したことを示す物的証拠は考古学的にはほとんど認められないのが実情である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For Yamatai-Koku kingdom in Kinai theory, there is no archeological material evidence to show northern Kyushu powers migration to Yamato.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For Yamatai-Koku kingdom in Kinai theory, there is no archeological material evidence to show that northern Kyushu powers migrated to Yamato.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For Yamatai-Koku kingdom in Kinai theory, there is no archeological material evidence to show that northern Kyushu powers migrated to Yamato.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>近年ではむしろ北部九州勢力が中心となって、鉄などの資源の入手や大陸からの舶載品などを全国に流通させていた物流システムを畿内勢力が再編成し直そうとして起こった戦いであったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From recent year&apos;s point of view, the battle occurred because of Kinai power tried to reorganize the logistics system, which was originally taken initiative by northern Kyushu power who took lead in acquisition and nation-wide distribution of raw materials including iron and shipped goods from the continent.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently the point of view is the battle occurred because of the Kinai power trying to reorganize a logistics system, originally taking initiative of the northern Kyushu power who took the lead in acquisition and nation-wide distribution of raw materials including iron and shipped goods from the continent.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently the point of view is the battle occurred because of the Kinai power trying to reorganize a logistics system, originally taking initiative of the northern Kyushu power who took the lead in acquisition and nation-wide distribution of raw materials including iron and shipped goods from the continent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>一方、邪馬台国九州説では、弥生時代後期中葉以降に至っても瀬戸内地域では鉄器の出土量は北部九州と比べて明らかに少なく、また、鉄器製作技術は北部九州と比べて格段に低かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For Yamatai-Koku kingdom in Kyushu theory, on the other hand, amount of ironware excavated from Setouchi region even after the middle of the end of Yayoi period were very limited compared to northern Kyushu, and level of ironware manufacturing technique was very low comapred to northern Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the Yamatai-Koku kingdom in Kyushu theory, on the other hand, the amount of ironware excavated from the Setouchi region even after the middle of the end of the Yayoi period was very limited when compared to northern Kyushu, and the level of ironware manufacturing technique was very low comapred to northern Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the Yamatai-Koku kingdom in Kyushu theory, on the other hand, the amount of ironware excavated from the Setouchi region even after the middle of the end of the Yayoi period was very limited when compared to northern Kyushu, and the level of ironware manufacturing technique was very low compared to northern Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>comapred→compared と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>倭国大乱の原因については、古事記等の西遷の記述と結びつけ、北部九州勢力が大和へと移動してヤマト朝廷を建てたとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cause of Wakoku War was related to description of Seisen in Kojiki (The Records of Ancient Matters) and it is said that northern Kyushu power moved to Yamato, where they built Yamato Chotei (Imperial Court).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cause of the Wakoku War was related to description of Seisen in the Kojiki (The Records of Ancient Matters) and it is said that the northern Kyushu power moved to Yamato, where they built Yamato Chotei (the Imperial Court).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cause of the Wakoku War was related to description of Seisen in the Kojiki (The Records of Ancient Matters) and it is said that the northern Kyushu power moved to Yamato, where they built Yamato Chotei (the Imperial Court).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="38">
<sen id="111">
<j>地域勢力と大型墳丘墓の出現</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regional power and emergence of large-scale funkyubo (grave mound)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regional power and the emergence of large-scale funkyubo (grave mound)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regional power and the emergence of large-scale funkyubo (grave mound)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>時代が下るにつれ、大型集落が小型集落を従え、集落内で首長層が力を持ってきたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later in the period, large settlements subdued smaller settlements and a chief and upper ranks started to seize power in the settlement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later in the period, large settlements subdued smaller settlements and the chief and upper ranks started to seize power in the settlement.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that later in the period, large settlements subdued smaller settlements and the chief and upper ranks started to seize power in the settlement.</e>
<cmt>「と考えられている」を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="39">
<sen id="113">
<j>首長層は弥生時代の墓制墳丘墓に葬られるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The chief and upper ranks were buried in a grave mound in the burial system of Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The chief and upper ranks were buried in a grave mound in the burial system of the Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The chief and upper ranks were buried in a grave mound in the burial system of the Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>このことは身分差の出現を意味する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This imply emergence of class difference.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This implies the emergence of class difference.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This implies the emergence of class difference.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="40">
<sen id="115">
<j>弥生時代後期になると墓制の地域差が顕著となっていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The burial system became notably different between regions at the end of Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The burial system became notably different between regions at the end of the Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The burial system became notably different between regions at the end of the Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="41">
<sen id="116">
<j>近畿周辺では方形低墳丘墓がつくられ、山陰（出雲）から北陸にかけては弥生時代の墓制が、瀬戸内地方では大型墳丘墓がそれぞれ営まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The square-shaped low funkyubo (grave mound) was created around Kinki region, the burial system of Yayoi period was practiced in Sanin to Hokuriku, and large-scale grave mound was created in Setouchi region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The square-shaped low funkyubo (grave mound) was created around the Kinki region, the burial system of the Yayoi period was practiced in Sanin to Hokuriku, and a large-scale grave mound was created in the Setouchi region.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The square-shaped low funkyubo (grave mound) was created around the Kinki region, the burial system of the Yayoi period was practiced in Sanin (Izumo) to Hokuriku, and a large-scale grave mound was created in the Setouchi region.</e>
<cmt>「（出雲）」を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="42">
<sen id="117">
<j>吉備地域</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kibi region</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kibi region</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kibi region</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>瀬戸内地方のなかでも吉備と呼ばれる岡山県と広島県東部の地域では、弥生時代後期の最大級の墳丘墓は、岡山県倉敷市の楯築墳丘墓（最大長約80メートル）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among Setouchi region, areas around Okayama Prefecture and Western Hiroshima Prefecture called Kibi hold grave mound of the largest scale in the end of Yayoi period, Tatetsuki Grave Mound (80 meters at longest point) in Kurashiki City, Okayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the Setouchi region, areas around Okayama Prefecture and Western Hiroshima Prefecture called Kibi holds grave mounds of the largest scale from the end of Yayoi period, Tatetsuki Grave Mound (eighty meters at longest point) in Kurashiki City, Okayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the Setouchi region, areas around Okayama Prefecture and Western Hiroshima Prefecture called Kibi holds grave mounds of the largest scale from the end of Yayoi period, Tatetsuki Grave Mound (80 m at longest point) in Kurashiki City, Okayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>eighty meters→80 m と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>この地域では首長の葬送儀礼には、特殊器台形土器と特殊壺形土器が数多く使用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many tokushu-kidai (ceremonial vessel stand) shaped earthwares and tokushu tsubo (ceremonial jar) shaped earthwares were used in the burial ritual of the chief in this region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many tokushu-kidai (ceremonial vessels stand) shaped earthwares and tokushu tsubo (ceremonial jar) shaped earthenware were used in the burial ritual of the chief in this region.</e>
<cmt>spelling, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many tokushu-kidai (ceremonial vessels stand) shaped earthwares and tokushu tsubo (ceremonial jar) shaped earthenware were used in the burial ritual of the chief in this region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>これらの土器は、吉備地方で発生し、美作国・備前国・備中国・備後国の地域に分布し、その発達の中心は、備中南部の平野であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These earthware emerged in Kibi region and spread to Mimasaka Province, Bizen Province, Bicchu Province and Bingo Province, where the earthware matured mainly in Hirano in southern Bicchu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These earthenware emerged in the Kibi region and spread to Mimasaka Province, Bizen Province, Bicchu Province and Bingo Province, where the earthenware matured mainly in Hirano in southern Bicchu.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These earthenware emerged in the Kibi region and spread to Mimasaka Province, Bizen Province, Bicchu Province and Bingo Province, where the earthenware matured mainly in Hirano in southern Bicchu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>そして、これらの地域の周辺地域では使用されていないのが特徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The characteristics are that the earthwares are not used in surrounding area of the region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Characteristically the earthenware are not used in surrounding area of the region.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Characteristically the earthenware are not used in surrounding area of the region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="43">
<sen id="122">
<j>山陰地域</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanin region</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanin region</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanin region</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>中国山地の三次で発生したと推定され、出雲地域で発達した四隅突出型の墳丘墓（大きなものは約45メートル×約35メートル）が現れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Funkyubo in Sanin is presumed to have emerged in Sanji in Chugoku Sanchi (Chugoku Range) and yosumi tosshutsugata funkyubo (square grave mounds with four corners protruding outward) (approximately 45 meters x 35 meters in large size), which was developed in Izumo region, appeared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Funkyubo in Sanin is presumed to have emerged in Sanji in Chugoku Sanchi (Chugoku Range) and yosumi tosshutsugata funkyubo (square grave mounds with four corners protruding outward) (approximately fourty-five meters x thirty-five meters in large size), appeared in the Izumo region.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Funkyubo in Sanin is presumed to have emerged in Miyoshi in Chugoku Sanchi (Chugoku Range) and yosumi tosshutsugata funkyubo (square grave mounds with four corners protruding outward) (approximately 45 m x 35 m in large size), appeared in the Izumo region.</e>
<cmt>Sanji→Miyoshi （「三次＝みよし」と確認しました）,fourty-five meters→45 m,thirty-five meters→35 m と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>これらは後の古墳時代に匹敵する土木建築を駆使したもので、その分布は山陰の出雲地方や北陸の能登半島にまで拡がっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These used construction works equivalent to Kofun period and it spread to Izumo region in Sanin to Noto Peninsula in Hokuriku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These used construction equivalent to that seen in the Kofun period and it spread to the Izumo region in Sanin to Noto Peninsula in Hokuriku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These used construction equivalent to that seen in the Kofun period later and it spread to the Izumo region in Sanin to Noto Peninsula in Hokuriku.</e>
<cmt>later を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>出雲地域に存在する安来・西谷の両墳丘墓集積地には特殊器台形土器と特殊壺形土器し、出雲と吉備の両地域に同盟関係が生まれていたことを示していると考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokushu-kidai (ceremonial vessel stand) shaped earthwares and tokushu tsubo (ceremonial jar) shaped earthwares were excavated from concentrated distribution center of Yasugi Grave Mound and Nishidani Grave Mound, which indicate Izumo and Kibi region formed an alliance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokushu-kidai (ceremonial vessel stand) shaped earthenware and tokushu tsubo (ceremonial jar) shaped earthenware were excavated from a concentrated distribution center of Yasugi Grave and Nishidani Grave Mounds, which indicate Izumo and the Kibi region formed an alliance.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokushu-kidai (ceremonial vessel stand) shaped earthenware and tokushu tsubo (ceremonial jar) shaped earthenware were excavated from a concentrated distribution center of Yasugi Grave and Nishidani Grave Mounds, which indicate Izumo and the Kibi region formed an alliance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="44">
<sen id="126">
<j>これらの墓の特徴が寄り集まって後代の古墳（前方後円墳など）の形成につながったとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These characteristics of grave mound came together and lead to Kofun (tumulus) (such as large keyhole-shaped tomb mound) in later period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These characteristics of the grave mound came together and led to the Kofun (tumulus) (such as large keyhole-shaped tomb mound) in a later period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These characteristics of the grave mound came together and led to the Kofun (tumulus) (such as large keyhole-shaped tomb mound) in a later period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="45">
<sen id="127">
<j>弥生時代の地域勢力は、北部九州・吉備・山陰・近畿・三遠（東海）・関東の勢力に大別することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regional powers in Yayoi period can be divided into powers of northern Kyushu, Kibi, Sanin, Kinki, Sanen (Tokai) and Kanto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regional powers in the Yayoi period can be divided into powers of northern Kyushu, Kibi, Sanin, Kinki, Sanen (Tokai), and Kanto.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regional powers in the Yayoi period can be divided into powers of northern Kyushu, Kibi, Sanin, Kinki, Sanen (Tokai), and Kanto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="46">
<sen id="128">
<j>時代の進行とともに連合していき、一つの勢力が出来ていった、と考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that smaller groups combined to form one power as period went forward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that smaller groups combined to form one power as period went forward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that smaller groups combined to form one power as period went forward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="47">
<sen id="129">
<j>水田農耕発展のために農地の拡大と農具となる鉄の獲得のため、また地域間の交易をめぐる争いのために戦いが起こり時代が進行していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Period forwarded with battles over commerse between regions as well as battles over acquisition of cultivation land and iron for farming equipment, for development of paddy-rice cultivation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Period forwarded with battles over commerce between regions as well as battles over acquisition of cultivation land and iron for farming equipment, for development of rice-paddy cultivation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Period forwarded with battles over commerce between regions as well as battles over acquisition of cultivation land and iron for farming equipment, for development of rice-paddy cultivation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>近畿では、環濠集落は、弥生前期末に現れ、中期以降に普及した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kinki region, moat settlement emerged at the end of early Yayoi period and spread on and after the middle period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kinki region, moat settlement emerged at the end of the early Yayoi period and spread on and after the middle period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kinki region, moat settlement emerged at the end of the early Yayoi period and spread on and after the middle period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="48">
<sen id="131">
<j>人々の生活</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life of people</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life of people</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Life of people</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>道具類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tools</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tools</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tools</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>弥生時代の道具類を材質から分類すると、大きく石器、木器・青銅器・鉄器・土器などに分けることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tools used in Yayoi period can be divided with its materials, which were; stoneware, woodenware, bronze-ware, ironware and earth-were.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tools used in the Yayoi period can be divided into materials, like; stoneware, woodenware, bronze-ware, ironware, and earthenware.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tools used in the Yayoi period can be divided into materials, such as; stoneware, woodenware, bronze-ware, ironware, and earthenware.</e>
<cmt>like→such as と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="49">
<sen id="134">
<j>石器には、縄文文化より伝わった打製石器を中心とする一群と、朝鮮半島無文土器文化より伝わった磨製石器の一群（大陸系磨製石器）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were two types of stoneware;chipped stone tool passed down from Jomon culture and ground stoneware (continental ground stoneware) introduced from Mumun pottery culture in Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were two types of stoneware; chipped stone tools passed down from the Jomon culture and ground stoneware (continental ground stoneware) introduced from the Mumun pottery culture on the Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were two types of stoneware; chipped stone tools passed down from the Jomon culture and ground stoneware (continental ground stoneware) introduced from the Mumun pottery culture on the Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="50">
<sen id="135">
<j>打製石器は、石鏃やスクレイパー（削器・掻器）など、狩猟具（武器）・利器として用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chipped stone tools were used as hunting tool and a sharp-edged tool such as Sekizoku (a flint arrowhead) and scraper.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chipped stone tools were used as hunting tools and sharp-edged tools such as Sekizoku (a flint arrowhead) and scraper.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chipped stone tools were used as hunting tools and sharp-edged tools such as Sekizoku (a flint arrowhead) and scraper.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="51">
<sen id="136">
<j>石材としてはサヌカイトなどの安山岩系の岩石や黒曜石などが主に用いられ、縄文時代からの製作技術を受け継いで作られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanukite, Anzangan rock (andesite) and kokuyoseki (obsidian) were often used for the material, and it was manufactured with manufacturing method passed down from Jomon period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanukite, Anzangan rock (andesite) and kokuyoseki (obsidian) were often used as material, and it was manufactured with a method passed down from Jomon period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanukite, Anzangan rock (andesite) and kokuyoseki (obsidian) were often used as material, and it was manufactured with a method passed down from Jomon period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>一方、水稲農耕の流入とともに流入した大陸系磨製石器と呼ばれる石器群には、蛤刃磨製石斧や抉入片刃石斧といった工具や、石包丁や石鎌などといった農具がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, there were stoneware called continental ground stoneware that came into Japan with introduction of paddy-rice cultivation, such as tools, including Hamaguribamasei stone axe and Eguriirikataba, stone axe, and farming equipments, including ishi-bocho (a stone implement, sickle) and stone stickle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, there was stoneware called continental ground stoneware that came into Japan with introduction of rice-paddy cultivation, such as tools, including Hamaguribamasei stone axe and Eguriirikataba, stone axe, and farming equipment, including ishi-bocho (a stone implement, sickle) and stone stickle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, there was stoneware called continental ground stoneware that came into Japan with introduction of rice-paddy cultivation, such as tools, including Hamaguribamasei stone axe and Eguriirikataba, stone axe, and farming equipment, including ishi-bocho (a stone implement, sickle) and stone stickle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>水稲農耕技術の受容にともなう開墾や耕起、収穫に用いられる道具として、弥生時代になって新たに導入された道具類である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These were new types of tools adapted in Yayoi period and they were used tools for cultivation and harvest, as paddy-rice cultivation techniques spread.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These were new types of tools adapted in the Yayoi period and they used tools for cultivation and harvest, as rice-paddy cultivation techniques spread.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These were new types of tools adapted in the Yayoi period and they used tools for cultivation and harvest, as rice-paddy cultivation techniques spread.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="52">
<sen id="139">
<j>青銅器は大陸から北部九州に伝えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bronze-ware was introduced from the continent to northern Kyushu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bronze-ware was introduced from the continent to northern Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bronze-ware was introduced from the continent to northern Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>北部九州を中心とする地域では銅矛や銅剣・銅戈などの武器形青銅器が、一方畿内を中心とする地域では銅鐸がよく知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Weapon type bronze ware such as bronze halberd, doka (bronze halberd for ritual) and bronze sword are well known in northern Kyushu region, and dotaku (a bell-shaped bronze vessel) is known from Kinai region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Weapon type bronze ware such as bronze halberd, doka (bronze halberd for rituals) and bronze swords are well known in the northern Kyushu region, and dotaku (a bell-shaped bronze vessel) is known from the Kinai region.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Weapon type bronze ware such as bronze halberd, doka (bronze halberd for rituals) and bronze swords are well known in the northern Kyushu region, and dotaku (a bell-shaped bronze vessel) is known from the Kinai region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="53">
<sen id="141">
<j>北部九州や山陰、四国地方などに主に分布する銅矛や銅剣、銅戈などは、前期末に製品が持ち込まれるとともに、すぐに生産も開始された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bronze halberd doka (bronze halberd for ritual), and bronze sword that were distributed mainly in northern Kyushu, Sanin and Shikoku region were introduced at the end of early period and the manufacturing started right after that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bronze halberd doka (bronze halberd for rituals), and bronze swords distributed mainly in northern Kyushu, Sanin and the Shikoku region were introduced at the end of early period and manufacturing started right after that.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bronze halberd, doka (bronze halberd for rituals), and bronze swords distributed mainly in northern Kyushu, Sanin and the Shikoku region were introduced at the end of early period and manufacturing started right after that.</e>
<cmt>カンマを補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="54">
<sen id="142">
<j>一方銅鐸も半島から伝わったと考えられるが、持ち込まれた製品と列島で作られた製品とは形態にやや差があり、列島での生産開始過程はよくわからない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, although dotaku is thought to have introduced from Korean Peninsula, there were a difference in forms of introduced product and manufactured product, and the process of manufacturing in Japan Archipelago is not known.</e>
<cmt>半島＝Korean Peninsulaと訳しています。ドキュメント内に他にも半島とするものがあるため、（能登半島など）明らかに朝鮮半島を指すものはKorean Peninsulaとしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, although dotaku is thought to have been introduced from the Korean Peninsula, there was a difference in forms of introduced and manufactured products, and the process of manufacturing in Japan Archipelago is not known.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, although dotaku is thought to have been introduced from the Korean Peninsula, there was a difference in forms of introduced and manufactured products, and the process of manufacturing in Japan Archipelago is not known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>出現当初の銅剣や銅矛など武器形青銅器は、所有者の威儀を示す象徴的なものであると同時に、刃が研ぎ澄まされていたことなどから実際に戦闘に使われる実用武器としても使われていた可能性が高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Weapon type bronze ware such as bronze sword and bronze halberd were a dignity symbol of owner at the time of emergence, as well as it is possible that they were used as actual weapons, as its edge was sharpened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Weapon type bronze ware bronze swords and bronze halberds were a dignity symbol of the owner at the time of emergence, and it is possible that they were used as actual weapons, as its edge was sharpened.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Weapon type bronze ware bronze swords and bronze halberds were a dignity symbol of the owner at the time of emergence, and it is possible that they were used as actual weapons, as its edge was sharpened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="55">
<sen id="144">
<j>この段階の武器形青銅器は墓に副葬されることが一般的で、個人の所有物として使われていたことがわかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Weapon type bronze ware was usually buried as burial goods, which indicate that they were used as a property of individual.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Weapon type bronze ware was usually buried as burial goods, which indicate that they were used as the property of the individual.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Weapon type bronze ware at that time was usually buried as burial goods, which indicate that they were used as the property of the individual.</e>
<cmt>「この段階の」を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="56">
<sen id="145">
<j>弥生時代中期前半以降、銅剣・銅矛・銅戈などの武器形青銅器は、徐々に太く作られるようになったと理解できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On and after the first half of middle of Yayoi period, manufactured weapon type bronze ware such as bronze sword, doka (bronze halberd for ritual) and bronze halberd gradually increased its thickness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On and after the first half of the middle of the Yayoi period, manufactured weapon type bronze ware such as bronze sworsd, doka (bronze halberd for ritual) and bronze halberds gradually increased in thickness.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In and after the first half of the middle of the Yayoi period, manufactured weapon type bronze ware such as bronze swords, doka (bronze halberd for ritual) and bronze halberds gradually increased in thickness.</e>
<cmt>On→In,sworsd→swords と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="57">
<sen id="146">
<j>一方、銅鐸は出現当初から祭祀に用いられたと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, dotaku is believed to be a tool for rituals from the time of emergence.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, dotaku is believed to be a tool for rituals from the time of emergence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, dotaku is believed to be a tool for rituals from the time of emergence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="147">
<j>しかし、時代が下るにつれて徐々に大型化するとともに、つるす部分が退化することから、最初は舌を内部につるして鳴らすものとして用いられたが、徐々に見るものへと変わっていったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, dotaku became larger and part for hanging was lost as period went forward, therefore it became an object for viewing whereas originally it was a bell with metal parts hanged inside for ringing.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, dotaku became larger and part for hanging was lost as period went forward, therefore it became an object for viewing whereas originally it was a bell with metal parts hung inside for ringing.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, dotaku became larger and part for hanging was lost as period went forward, therefore it became an object for viewing whereas originally it was a bell with metal parts hung inside for ringing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="58">
<sen id="148">
<j>また、鏡も弥生時代前期末に渡来し、中期末以降列島でも生産されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bronze mirror was also introduced at the end of early Yayoi period and the manufacture in Japan Archipelago started on and after the middle period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処青銅器項目のおそらく銅鏡を指すものですので、bronze mirrorと訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bronze mirrors were also introduced at the end of the early Yayoi period and the manufacture in the Japan Archipelago started on and after the middle period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bronze mirrors were also introduced at the end of the early Yayoi period and the manufacture in the Japan Archipelago started on and after the middle period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>墓に副葬されたり意図的に分割されて（破鏡）祭祀に用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were buried as a burial good and also they were intentionally divided (hakyou (broken mirror)) for ritual use.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were buried as a burial good and were also intentionally divided (hakyou - broken mirror) for ritual use.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were buried as a burial good and were also intentionally divided (hakyo - broken mirror) for ritual use.</e>
<cmt>hakyou→hakyo と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="59">
<sen id="150">
<j>このように、大型の青銅器は出現当初をのぞいてほとんどが祭祀に用いられるものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In these manners, most of large bronze wares were used for rituals, except for the time of emergence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In these manners, most of large bronze ware were used for rituals, except for the time of emergence.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In these manners, most of large bronze ware were used for rituals, except for the time of emergence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="60">
<sen id="151">
<j>このほかに鋤先などの農具やヤリガンナなどの工具、鏃などの小型武器などもみられるが、大型の青銅器に比べて非常に少量である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are very few, but some smaller bronze wares are also excavated, such as tip of a spade as a farming equipment, a Japanese-style plane with long handle as a tool, and smaller weapons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are very few, but some smaller bronze ware were also excavated, such as the tip of a spade used as farming equipment, a Japanese-style plane with long handle as a tool, and smaller weapons.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are very few, but some smaller bronze ware were also excavated, such as the tip of a spade used as farming equipment, a Japanese-style plane with long handle as a tool, and an arrowhead as smaller weapon.</e>
<cmt>「鏃」を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="61">
<sen id="152">
<j>青銅器は、最初期のごく一部の例（半島から流入した武器形青銅器などの一部を研ぎ出すことにより製作される事例がわずかに存在する）をのぞき、鋳型に溶けた金属を流し込むことにより生産された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Apart from few examples in the very initial stage (few examples of bronze ware manufactured by grinding weapon type bronze ware imported from Korean Peninsula), bronze ware were manufactured by pouring metal into a mold.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Apart from a few examples in the very initial stage (few examples of bronze ware manufactured by grinding weapon type bronze ware imported from Korean Peninsula), bronze ware was manufactured by pouring metal into a mold.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Apart from a few examples in the very initial stage (few examples of bronze ware manufactured by grinding weapon type bronze ware imported from Korean Peninsula), bronze ware was manufactured by pouring metal into a mold.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="62">
<sen id="153">
<j>青銅器の鋳型は、列島での初現期にあたる弥生時代前期末～中期前半期のものは主に佐賀県佐賀市から小城市にかけての佐賀平野南西部に多く見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of molds for bronze ware in its time of emergence, which was around the end of early Yayoi period to the first half of middle of Yayoi period, were found mainly in south west part of Saga plain, around Saga City and Ogi City, Saga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of the molds for bronze ware in its time of emergence, around the end of the early Yayoi period to the first half of the middle Yayoi period, were found mainly in south west part of the Saga plain, around Saga City, and Ogi City, Saga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of the molds for bronze ware in its time of emergence, around the end of the early Yayoi period to the first half of the middle Yayoi period, were found mainly in south west part of the Saga plain, around Saga City, and Ogi City, Saga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="63">
<sen id="154">
<j>中期後半までに青銅器の生産は福岡県福岡市那珂・比恵遺跡群や春日市須玖遺跡群などで集中的に行われるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the latter half of middle period, bronze wares were intensively manufactured in Nakai and Hie sites at Fukuoka City, Fukuoka Prefecture and in Suku sites.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the latter half of middle period, bronze ware was intensively manufactured in Nakai and Hie sites at Fukuoka City, Fukuoka Prefecture and in Suku sites.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the latter half of middle period, bronze ware was intensively manufactured in Nakai and Hie sites at Fukuoka City, Fukuoka Prefecture and in Suku sites in Kasuga City.</e>
<cmt>「春日市」を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="64">
<sen id="155">
<j>平形銅剣をのぞくほとんどの武器形青銅器はこれらの遺跡群で集中的に生産されたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of weapon type bronze wares were intensively manufactured in these sites, except for flat bronze sword.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most weapon type bronze ware were intensively manufactured in these sites, except for the flat bronze sword.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most weapon type bronze ware were intensively manufactured in these sites, except for the flat bronze sword.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="65">
<sen id="156">
<j>一方、銅鐸の生産は近畿地方などで行われたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, dotaku was manufactured in Kinki region.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, dotaku was manufactured in the Kinki region.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, dotaku was manufactured in the Kinki region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>しかし、北部九州ほど青銅器生産の証拠が集中して発見される遺跡は未だ見つかっておらず、その生産体制や流通体制などには未解明の部分が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However a site with concentrated evidence of bronze ware manufacturing, like the ones in northern Kyushu, has not yet been found and its manufacturing and distribution system remain unsolved.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However sites with concentrated evidence of bronze ware manufacturing, like those in northern Kyushu, have not yet been found and its manufacturing and distribution system remain unsolved.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However sites with concentrated evidence of bronze ware manufacturing, such as those in northern Kyushu, have not yet been found and its manufacturing and distribution system remain unsolved.</e>
<cmt>like→such as と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="66">
<sen id="158">
<j>鉄器の初現は弥生時代早期とされ、弥生時代中期前半までには北部九州で工具を中心に一般化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ironware emerged in the earlier Yayoi period and it became widespread around northern Kyushu mainly as tools, by the first half of middle of Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ironware emerged in the earlier Yayoi period and it became widespread around northern Kyushu mainly as tools, by the first half of middle of Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ironware emerged in the earlier Yayoi period and it became widespread around northern Kyushu mainly as tools, by the first half of middle of Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>後期以降に西日本全域に拡散するとともに、武器や農具としても採用されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They spread across western Japan and adapted as weapons and farming equipments on and after the end of Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They spread across western Japan and were adapted as weapons and farming equipment on and after the end of the Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They spread across western Japan and were adapted as weapons and farming equipment on and after the end of the Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="67">
<sen id="160">
<j>鉄器は耐久性や刃の鋭さから主に利器として、特に工具や農具（収穫具）として用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ironware was mainly used as sharp-edged tool, especially implement and farming equipment (harvesting equipment) from its durability and sharpness of edge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ironware was mainly used for sharp-edged tools, especially implements and farming equipment (harvesting equipment) because of its durability and sharpness of edge.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ironware was mainly used for sharp-edged tools, especially implements and farming equipment (harvesting equipment) because of its durability and sharpness of edge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="161">
<j>出現当初は鍛造鉄斧の断片を研ぎ出して小型の工具などとして使っていたが、中期前半までには北部九州で袋状鉄斧と呼ばれる列島製の鉄斧が出現し、徐々に西日本一帯へと波及していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Smaller tools, which were manufactured by grinding a fragment of forged iron axe, were in use at the time of its emergence, but Japan made iron axe called Fukurojo-Teppu (literally &apos;bag-shaped iron axe&apos;, hollow structured iron axe) emerged in northern Kyushu by the first half of middle period and it gradually spread around western Japan.</e>
<cmt>鍛造=forgingの方が適切であると思います。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Smaller tools, manufactured by grinding a fragment of forged iron axe, were in use at the time of its emergence, but Japan made an iron axe called Fukurojo-Teppu (literally &apos;bag-shaped iron axe&apos;, hollow structured iron axe) emerged in northern Kyushu by the first half of middle period and it gradually spread around western Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Smaller tools, manufactured by grinding a fragment of forged iron axe, were in use at the time of its emergence, but Japan made an iron axe called Fukurojo-Teppu (literally &apos;bag-shaped iron axe,&apos; hollow structured iron axe) emerged in northern Kyushu by the first half of middle period and it gradually spread around western Japan.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>このほかに小刀（刀子）や鉄族、ノミ状工具などの存在が知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, a short sword (Tosu (small knife)) and a chisel shaped tool are known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, a short sword (Tosu - small knife) and a chisel shaped tool are known.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, a short sword (Tosu - small knife) and a chisel shaped tool are known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="68">
<sen id="163">
<j>ただし、この時期の鉄器は鉄素材を半島から輸入して製作されており、列島で製鉄が見られるのは古墳時代後期以降と考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However ironware in this period were made from iron imported from peninsula and iron making in Japan Archipelago is said have started after the end of Kofun period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However ironware during this period were made from iron imported from the peninsula and iron making in Japan Archipelago is said have started after the end of the Kofun period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However ironware during this period were made from iron imported from the peninsula and iron making in Japan Archipelago is said have started after the end of the Kofun period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="69">
<sen id="164">
<j>弥生時代における鉄器の生産には、材料となる鉄を切り・折り取り、刃を磨き出すことによって作られる鏨切り技法と、鍛造により形を作り出す鍛造技法があることがわかっている（ごく一部の例について、鋳造により作られた可能性が示唆されているが、鉄を溶かすためにはきわめて高温の操業に耐えうる炉が必要であり、弥生時代にこのような技術が存在したかどうかは疑問視されている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are two types of ironware manufacturing methods in Yayoi period; a cold chisel cutting method that cut/break off iron material and grind to sharpen its edge, and forging method that create shapes by forging (although a very few cases are suspected with a possibility of casting method, a furnace that can withstand operation at high temperature is required to melt iron and it is questionable if there was such technology in Yayoi period).</e>
<cmt>鍛造=forgingの方が適切であると思います。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are two types of ironware manufacturing methods during the Yayoi period; a cold chisel cutting method that cuts/breaks off iron material and grind to sharpen its edge, and a forging method that create shapes by forging (although a very few cases are suspected with a possibility of the casting method, a furnace that can withstand operation at high temperature is required to melt iron and it is questionable if there was such technology during the Yayoi period).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are two types of ironware manufacturing methods during the Yayoi period; a cold chisel cutting method that cuts/breaks off iron material and grind to sharpen its edge, and a forging method that create shapes by forging (Although a very few cases are suspected with a possibility of the casting method, a furnace that can withstand operation at high temperature is required to melt iron and it is questionable if there was such technology during the Yayoi period.)</e>
<cmt>カッコ部分、ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="70">
<sen id="165">
<j>北部九州、特に福岡市周辺地域では弥生時代中期前半までに鍛造技法による鉄器の生産が開始された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ironware manufacturing by forging had started by the first half of middle of Yayoi period in northern Kyushu, especially in surrounding area of Fukuoka City.</e>
<cmt>鍛造=forgingの方が適切であると思います。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ironware manufacturing by forging had started by the first half of the middle of the Yayoi period in northern Kyushu, especially in surrounding area of Fukuoka City.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ironware manufacturing by forging had started by the first half of the middle of the Yayoi period in northern Kyushu, especially in surrounding area of Fukuoka City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="71">
<sen id="166">
<j>一方、同じ北部九州でも八女市などの周辺地域では弥生時代後期になっても鏨切りによる鉄器生産が一般的であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, ironware manufacturing by a cold chisel cutting was common in surrounding area of Yame City, also in northern Kyushu, even in the end of Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, ironware manufacturing by cold chisel cutting was common in surrounding area of Yame City, also in northern Kyushu, even at the end of the Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, ironware manufacturing by cold chisel cutting was common in surrounding area of Yame City, also in northern Kyushu, even at the end of the Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="72">
<sen id="167">
<j>瀬戸内地方でも、弥生時代後期までには鍛造による鉄器生産が伝播していたが、技術的には北部九州のそれよりも明らかに低い水準にあり、同時に鏨切りによる鉄器製作も普遍的に行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, although ironware manufacturing by forging was introduced to Setouchi region by the end of Yayoi period, technology was clearly lower than that of northern Kyushu and ironware manufacturing by a cold chisel cutting was practiced in general.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, although ironware manufacturing by forging was introduced to the Setouchi region by the end of the Yayoi period, technology was clearly lower than that of northern Kyushu and ironware manufacturing by cold chisel cutting was practiced in general.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, although ironware manufacturing by forging was introduced to the Setouchi region by the end of the Yayoi period, technology was clearly lower than that of northern Kyushu and ironware manufacturing by cold chisel cutting was practiced in general.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="73">
<sen id="168">
<j>弥生時代後期には、玄界灘沿岸地域の遺跡から鉄器が大量に出てくるが、瀬戸内海沿岸各地方や近畿地方の遺跡からはごくわずかしか出てこない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many ironware from the end of Yayoi period were excavated from site in the coastal area of the Genkai-nada Sea, but very little are excavated from sites in the coastal area of the Seto Inland Sea and Kinki region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many ironware from the end of the Yayoi period were excavated from sites along the coastal areas of the Genkai-nada Sea, but very little were excavated from sites along the coastal areas of the Seto Inland Sea and Kinki region.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A large amount of ironware from the end of the Yayoi period were excavated from sites along the coastal areas of the Genkai-nada Sea, but very little were excavated from sites along the coastal areas of the Seto Inland Sea and Kinki region.</e>
<cmt>Many→A large amount of と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="169">
<j>つまり玄界灘沿岸地域が鉄資源入手ルートを独占していたと推定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is suspected that the coastal area of the Genkai-nada Sea monopolized the route of iron acquisition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is suspected that the coastal area of the Genkai-nada Sea monopolized the route of iron acquisition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is suspected that the coastal area of the Genkai-nada Sea monopolized the route of iron acquisition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>それゆえに、鉄資源の入手ルートの支配権を巡って戦争が起こったのではないかと考えられているが、今はまだ考古学的に立証することができない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, a war might have broke out over the control of iron acquisition route, but it is not archaeologically proved yet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, a war may have broken out over the control of the iron acquisition route, but it is not archaeologically proved yet.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, a war may have broken out over the control of the iron acquisition route, but it is not archaeologically proved yet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="171">
<j>戦争が起こったと仮定すれば、近畿地方の大和勢力を中心に、広域の政治連合、例えば邪馬台国連合のような同盟ができあがっていたとことが想定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Assuming that there was a war, formation of a wide area political alliance, such as Yamatai-Koku kingdom alliance, centering on powers of Yamato is also assumed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Assuming that there was a war, formation of a wide area political alliance, such as the Yamatai-Koku kingdom alliance, centering on powers of Yamato is also assumed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Assuming that there was a war, the formation of a wide area political alliance, such as the Yamatai-Koku kingdom alliance, centering on powers of Yamato in Kinki region is also assumed.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。Kinki region を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="74">
<sen id="172">
<j>土器は、弥生土器と呼ばれる、低温酸化炎焼成の素焼き土器が用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For earthware, bisque (fired pottery) earthware, which was fired in low temperature oxidative flame, called Yayoi earthware was used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For earthenware, bisque (fired pottery) earthenware, which was fired in low temperature oxidative flames, called Yayoi earthenware was used.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For earthenware, bisque (fired pottery) earthenware, which was fired in low temperature oxidative flames, called Yayoi earthenware was used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="75">
<sen id="173">
<j>縄文時代の縄文土器と比べて装飾が少ないとしばしばいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yayoi earthware is often described as less decorative compared to Jomon earthware.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yayoi earthenware is often described as less decorative compared to Jomon earthenware.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yayoi earthenware is often described as less decorative compared to Jomon earthenware.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="174">
<j>実際に装飾が少ないのは前期段階の土器と中期以降の西日本、特に北部九州の土器で、そのほかの地域・時代の土器にはしばしば多様な装飾が施される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In actual fact, only earthware in the early period and earthware from on and after the middle period in western Japan, especially in northern Kyushu, are less decorative, but earthware from other region and period often have various decorations.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In actual fact, only earthenware in the early period and earthenware from during and after the middle period in western Japan, especially in northern Kyushu, is less decorative, but earthenware from other regions and periods often have various decorations.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In actual fact, only earthenware in the early period and earthenware from during and after the middle period in western Japan, especially in northern Kyushu, is less decorative, but earthenware from other regions and periods often have various decorations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="76">
<sen id="175">
<j>器種として主要なものに甕・壷・高坏があり、特に壷は縄文時代には一般化しなかった器種で、弥生時代になって米が主要な食糧となったため、貯蔵容器として定着したと理解されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For type of wares, there were mainly a jar, a pot and a small one-legged tray for one person, especially a pot was not a general ware in Jomon period and it is believed that pots became widespread for storage container, as rice became the main food supply.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For types of wares, there were mainly jars, pots and a small one-legged tray for one person, especially the pot was not general ware during the Jomon period and it is believed that pots became widespread as storage container, as rice became the main food supply.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For types of wares, there were mainly jars, pots and a small one-legged tray for one person, especially the pot was not general ware during the Jomon period and it is believed that pots became widespread as storage container, as rice became the main food supply.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="77">
<sen id="176">
<j>土器の生産は集落ごとに行われ、集落ごとに自給自足によりまかなわれたと漠然と考えられているが、土器生産に関する遺構はほとんど事例がない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Earthware was manufactured in each settlement and it is vaguely believed that material was self-sufficient in each settlement but there is hardly any case of ancient structural remnants for earthware manufacturing found.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Earthenware was manufactured in each settlement and it is vaguely believed that material was self-sufficient in each settlement, but there was hardly any case of ancient structural remnants for earthenware manufacturing found.</e>
<cmt>spelling, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Earthenware was manufactured in each settlement and it is vaguely believed that the material was self-sufficient in each settlement, but there was hardly any case of ancient structural remnants for earthenware manufacturing found.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="78">
<sen id="177">
<j>最近、土器の焼成失敗品や、強い熱を受けたために器壁が薄くはじけるように割れた土器に注目して、大規模な集落で土器が集中的に生産された可能性が提起された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently earthware of firing failure and earthware with cracked surface from high temperature are studied and possibility of intensive earthware manufacturing in large-scale settlement was raised.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently earthenware of firing failure and earthware with a cracked surface from high temperature are being studied and the possibility of intensive earthenware manufacturing in large-scale settlements were raised.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently earthenware of firing failure and earthware with a cracked surface from high temperature are being studied and the possibility of intensive earthenware manufacturing in large-scale settlements were raised.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="79">
<sen id="178">
<j>また、土器の形態は地域性をきわめてよく表すため、その特徴に着目して他地域から搬入された可能性の高い土器と在地の土器とを峻別し、土器はこれまで思われていたよりもずっと多量に移動している可能性が指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the fact that form of earthware strongly shows regionality, earthware manufactured in local land and earthware suspected to have brought in from other region was compared and there is a possibility of movement of larger amount of earthware than previously assumed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the fact that the form of earthenware strongly shows regionality, earthenware manufactured on local land and earthenware suspected to have been brought in from other regions were compared and there is a possibility of movement of larger amounts of earthenware than previously assumed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the fact that the form of earthenware strongly shows regionality, earthenware manufactured on local land and earthenware suspected to have been brought in from other regions were compared and there is a possibility of the movement of larger amounts of earthenware than previously assumed.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="80">
<sen id="179">
<j>木器は主に食膳具や耕起具として使われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Woodenware was used as dinning ware and cultivation tool.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Woodenware was used as dinning ware and as cultivation tools.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Woodenware was used as dinning ware and as cultivation tools.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="180">
<j>特に食膳具には漆を塗ったり細かな装飾を施すなどした優品が多いが、木器は腐るために良好な状態で出土する例はまれであり、詳しいことは未だよくわかっていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there are many excellent pieces of work in dinning tools, which are lacquer -covered and have fine decoration, it is rare for woodenware to excavate in good condition as they are easy to rot, and details are still not known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there are many excellent pieces of work in dinning utensils, which are lacquered and have fine decorations, it is rare for woodenware to be excavated in good condition as they easily rot, and the details are still not known.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there are many excellent pieces of work in dinning utensils, which are lacquered and have fine decorations, it is rare for woodenware to be excavated in good condition as they easily rot, and the details are still not known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="81">
<sen id="181">
<j>集落</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Settlement</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Settlements</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Settlements</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="182">
<j>弥生時代の集落には様々な例があるが、一般的に発見されるものとして、居住施設としての竪穴住居、貯蔵施設としての貯蔵穴や掘立柱建物、ゴミ捨て場や土器の焼成など様々な用途に使われたと考えられる土坑（不定形の穴）、集落の周りを巡らせたり集落内部を区画するように掘られた溝（環濠や区画溝など）の遺構がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are several examples of settlement in Yayoi period and common examples of ancient structural remnants are; tateanajukyo (a pit dwelling house) as a dwelling, dug-standing pillar building and storage pit for storage facility, doko (a pit) (non-uniform shaped hole/pit) for various purposes such as garbage pit and firing of earthware, a ditch surrounding settlement and section in the settlement (a moat and a sectional ditch).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are several examples of settlements in the Yayoi period and common examples of ancient structural remnants are; tateanajukyo (a pit dwelling house) as a dwelling, dug-standing pillar building and storage pit for storage facility, doko (a pit) (non-uniform shaped hole/pit) for various purposes such as garbage pit and firing of earthenware, a ditch surrounding settlement and section in the settlement (a moat and a sectional ditch).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are several examples of settlements in the Yayoi period and common examples of ancient structural remnants are; tateanajukyo (a pit dwelling house) as a dwelling, dug-standing pillar building and storage pit for storage facility, doko (a pit) (non-uniform shaped hole/pit) for various purposes such as garbage pit and firing of earthenware, a ditch surrounding settlement and section in the settlement (a moat and a sectional ditch).</e>
<cmt>スペースを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="82">
<sen id="183">
<j>弥生時代の人々の住居には、主として竪穴住居が使われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People in Yayoi period used tateanajukyo (a pit dwelling house) for a dwelling.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People in the Yayoi period used tateanajukyo (a pit dwelling house) for a dwelling.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People in the Yayoi period used tateanajukyo (a pit dwelling house) for a dwelling.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="184">
<j>平面形態は円形・方形が主流で、長方形・隅丸方形がそれに次ぐ位置を占めるが、地域によって多様な様相を示す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Round shape and a square are popular for ground shapes, and a rectangle and a square with round edge follow after that but they show differences in each region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Round and a square shapes are popular for ground shapes, and a rectangle and a square with round edges follow after that but they show differences in each region.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Round and a square shapes are popular for ground shapes, and a rectangle and a square with round edges follow after that but they show differences in each region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="83">
<sen id="185">
<j>早期の北部九州の住居には、縄文時代晩期の系譜を引き継ぐと考えられる平面方形のもののほかに、平面円形で中央に浅い皿状のくぼみを持ち、その両脇に小さな穴（柱穴か）を1対持つ特徴的な形態の住居が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A dwelling with square ground shape that carries on tradition from last period of Jomon period and a dwelling with distinctive shape, which have round ground shape with a bowl like shallow concavity at center and a pair of small hole (could be holes for pillars) at the side of the concavity, both from earlier period are found in northern Kyushu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A dwelling with square ground shape that carries on the tradition from last period of the Jomon period and a dwelling with a distinctive shape, which has a round ground shape with a bowl like shallow concavity at center and a pair of small hole (could be holes for pillars) at the side of the concavity, both from earlier period are found in northern Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A dwelling with square ground shape that carries on the tradition from last period of the Jomon period and a dwelling with a distinctive shape, which has a round ground shape with a bowl like shallow concavity at center and a pair of small hole (could be holes for pillars) at the side of the concavity, both from earlier period are found in northern Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="84">
<sen id="186">
<j>この形態の円形住居は、同時期の朝鮮半島南部に広く分布している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This type of round dwelling is widely distributed in south of Korean Peninsula in the same time period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This type of round dwelling is widely distributed in the south Korean Peninsula during the same time period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This type of round dwelling is widely distributed in the south Korean Peninsula during the same time period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="187">
<j>韓国忠清南道扶余郡松菊里遺跡で最初に注目されたことから、「松菊里型住居」ともよばれる（ただしこの名称は日本国内に限定して使用され、韓国考古学界ではむしろ「松菊里類型」という用語は住居跡の形態のみでなく土器や石器組成を含めた文化総体の名称として用いられることが一般的となっている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is called &apos;Shokikurigata dwelling&apos; as it was first recognized in Shokikuri site in Fuyo District, Sud Chungcheong, Republic of Korea (however the name is only used in Japan, and the term &apos;Shokikuri type-&apos; are used not only for shape of dwelling, but to whole cultural description including form of earthware and stoneware in Korean archaeologist society).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is called &apos;Shokikurigata dwelling&apos; as it was first recognized at the Shokikuri site in Fuyo District, Sud Chungcheong, Republic of Korea (however the name is only used in Japan, and the term &apos;Shokikuri type-&apos; are used not only for shape of dwelling, but to whole cultural description including form of earthenware and stoneware in Korean archaeological society).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is called &apos;Shokikurigata dwelling&apos; as it was first recognized at the Shokikuri site in Fuyo District, Sud Chungcheong, Republic of Korea (However the name is only used in Japan, and the term &apos;Shokikuri type-&apos; are used not only for shape of dwelling, but to whole cultural description including form of earthenware and stoneware in Korean archaeological society.)</e>
<cmt>カッコ部分、ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="85">
<sen id="188">
<j>この松菊里型住居は、縄文時代後・晩期に西日本一帯でしばしば見られる円形プランの住居跡とともに、弥生時代前期から中期にかけて主流となる円形住居の祖形となったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dwelling (habitation) site from the end to last of Jomon period around western Japan and &apos;Shokikurigata dwelling&apos; became original forms of round plan dwellings that became the main stream in early to middle of Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dwelling (habitation) site from the end to last of Jomon period around western Japan and &apos;Shokikurigata dwelling&apos; became original forms of round plan dwellings that became main stream in the early to middle Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is assumed that the dwelling (habitation) site from the end to last of Jomon period around western Japan and &apos;Shokikurigata dwelling&apos; became original forms of round plan dwellings that became main stream in the early to middle Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>「考えられている」という部分を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="86">
<sen id="189">
<j>弥生時代中期には、住居のプランは北部九州から西日本一帯で円形プランのものが卓越した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In middle of Yayoi period, a round plan dwelling excelled in styles of dwelling plan around northern Kyushu to western Japan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the middle of the Yayoi period, a round plan dwelling excelled in styles of dwelling plans around northern Kyushu to western Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the middle of the Yayoi period, a round plan dwelling excelled in styles of dwelling plans around northern Kyushu to western Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="190">
<j>一部に隅丸方形のものが見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A square with round edge type is also found.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A square with round edge type is also found.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A square with round edge type is also found.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="191">
<j>しかし、弥生時代後期にはいると西日本一帯で突如として平面プランが方形あるいは長方形へと変化し、次第に長方形へと統一されていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, flat plan suddenly changed to a square or a rectangle around western Japan in the end of Yayoi period, and gradually standardized to a rectangle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the flat plan suddenly changed to a square or a rectangle around western Japan at the end of the Yayoi period, and gradually standardized to a rectangle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the flat plan suddenly changed to a square or a rectangle around western Japan at the end of the Yayoi period, and gradually standardized to a rectangle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="87">
<sen id="192">
<j>このほか、南部九州には「花弁型住居」と呼ばれる特異な平面プランの住居跡が分布した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a unique type of flat plan dwelling site called &apos;Petal shaped dwelling&apos; distributed in southern Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a unique type of flat plan dwelling site called &apos;Petal shaped dwelling&apos; distributed in southern Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a unique type of flat plan dwelling site called &apos;Petal shaped dwelling&apos; distributed in southern Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>is→was と修正しました。（”分布した”とあることから）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="193">
<j>また兵庫県西部（播磨）地域には円形住居の床面中央部に1O（イチマル）土坑と呼ばれる特殊な遺構を持つ例が分布するなど、竪穴住居の形態には多様な地域性があり、注目される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also there is various regionality in tateanajukyo (a pit dwelling house), such as a round shaped dwelling with special ancient structural remnants called 10 (read; &apos;Ichimaru&apos;) pit at center of its floor, in western Hyogo Prefecture (Harima).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also there is the various regionality in tateanajukyo (a pit dwelling house), such as a round shaped dwelling with special ancient structural remnants called ten (read; &apos;Ichimaru&apos;) pit at center of its floor, in western Hyogo Prefecture (Harima).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also there is the various regionality in tateanajukyo (a pit dwelling house), such as a round shaped dwelling with special ancient structural remnants called 10 (read; &apos;Ichimaru&apos;) pit at center of its floor, in western Hyogo Prefecture (Harima).</e>
<cmt>ten→10 と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="88">
<sen id="194">
<j>弥生時代の住居としては竪穴住居が出土例の大半を占めるが、このほかに平地式住居や掘立柱建物が想定される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although majority of dwelling excavated from Yayoi period was tateanajukyo (a pit dwelling house), flat-land dwellings and dug-standing pillar building are also assumed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the majority of dwellings excavated from the Yayoi period was tateanajukyo (a pit dwelling house), flat-land dwellings and dug-standing pillar buildings are also assumed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the majority of dwellings excavated from the Yayoi period was tateanajukyo (a pit dwelling house), flat-land dwellings and dug-standing pillar buildings are also assumed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="89">
<sen id="195">
<j>しかし、平地式住居の場合、生活面が削平されて（けずられて）しまうと生活の痕跡の大半が失われてしまうことから、住居として把握することがきわめて困難になってしまうため、これまでに把握された平地式住居の具体的な例はきわめて少ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However flat-land dwellings lose most of the evidence of living when living surface is scraped and it is very difficult to recognize it as a dwelling therefore very few of clear example of flat-land dwellings was discovered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However flat-land dwellings loses most of the evidence of living when living surface is scraped and it is very difficult to recognize it as a dwelling therefore very few clear examples of flat-land dwellings have been discovered.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However flat-land dwellings loses most of the evidence of living when living surface is scraped and it is very difficult to recognize it as a dwelling therefore very few clear examples of flat-land dwellings have been discovered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="90">
<sen id="196">
<j>また、掘立柱建物の場合後述する倉庫などとの区別が平面プランだけでは区別できないため、これも確実な住居の例は指摘されていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also it is difficult to distinguish dug-standing pillar building and other warehouse only from flat plans, therefore there is no clear example of dwellings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also it is difficult to distinguish dug-standing pillar building and other warehouses only from flat plans so, there are no clear examples of dwellings.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also it is difficult to distinguish dug-standing pillar building and other warehouses mentioned later only from flat plans so, there are no clear examples of dwellings.</e>
<cmt>「後述する」を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="91">
<sen id="197">
<j>弥生時代には、主に米を貯蔵する倉庫が発達した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Warehouse for storage, especially for rice had developed in Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Warehouse for storage, especially for rice developed in the Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Warehouse for storage, especially for rice developed in the Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="92">
<sen id="198">
<j>早期には北部九州など一部の集落に掘立柱建物の倉庫が半島から伝播する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dug-standing pillar building was introduced from Korean Peninsula to few settlement in northern Kyushu in earlier period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dug-standing pillar buildings were introduced from the Korean Peninsula to a few settlements in northern Kyushu during the earlier period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dug-standing pillar buildings were introduced from the Korean Peninsula to a few settlements in northern Kyushu during the earlier period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="199">
<j>しかし、前期までに地下式の倉庫が主流となり、掘立柱建物はほとんど見られなくなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However underground warehouse became the mainstream by the early period and dug-standing pillar building almost disappeared.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However the underground warehouse became mainstream by the early period and dug-standing pillar building almost disappeared.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However the underground warehouse became mainstream by the early period and dug-standing pillar building almost disappeared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="93">
<sen id="200">
<j>地下式倉庫は円形のものが主流で、しばしば方形・長方形のものが見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Underground warehouse commonly had round shape and sometimes had square or rectangular shape.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Underground warehouses commonly had a round shape and sometimes had square or rectangular shapes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Underground warehouses commonly had a round shape and sometimes had square or rectangular shapes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="201">
<j>いずれも断面形態がフラスコ状を呈する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They all have flask-like cross-sectional form.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They all have flask-like cross-sectional forms.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They all have flask-like cross-sectional forms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="202">
<j>これらは「貯蔵穴」と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These are called &apos;Storage pit&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These are called &apos;Storage pits.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These are called &apos;Storage pits.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="94">
<sen id="203">
<j>中期前半から中葉にかけて、掘立柱建物の倉庫が西日本一帯に展開する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dug-standing pillar building warehouse spread around western Japan between the first half of middle period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dug-standing pillar building warehouses spread around western Japan between the first half of the middle period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dug-standing pillar building warehouses spread around western Japan between the first half to the middle period.</e>
<cmt>of→to と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="95">
<sen id="204">
<j>主な形態のものは柱間が1間×2間の規模のもので、これに1間×1間、1間×3間などのバリエーションが加わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The structure commonly had size of hashirama (bay, space or distance between two pillars) of 1ken (unit of distance between two pillars) x 2ken, and some had different variations such as 1ken x 1ken or 1ken x 3ken.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The structure commonly had size of hashirama (bay, space or distance between two pillars) of 1ken (unit of distance between two pillars) x 2ken, and some had different variations such as 1ken x 1ken or 1ken x 3ken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The structure commonly had size of hashirama (bay, space or distance between two pillars) of 1 ken (unit of distance between two pillars) x 2 ken, and some had different variations such as 1 ken x 1 ken or 1 ken x 3 ken.</e>
<cmt>スペースを修正しました、</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="205">
<j>この倉庫の様相は弥生時代を通じておおよそ変化はなく継続する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This warehouse style continues through out Yayoi period without much change.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This warehouse style continues throughout the Yayoi period without much change.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This warehouse style continues throughout the Yayoi period without much change.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="96">
<sen id="206">
<j>弥生時代末から古墳時代初頭になると、2間×2間の総柱式の建物が出現し、これが主要な倉庫の形態となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around the end of Yayoi period to the beginning of Kofun period (tumulus period), Sobashira-shiki building (dug-standing pillar building with a pillar per ken (unit of distance between two pillars), grid type structure) with size of 2ken x2ken emerged, and this became the main structure of warehouse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the end of the Yayoi period to the beginning of the Kofun period (tumulus period), Sobashira-shiki building (dug-standing pillar building with a pillar per ken (unit of distance between two pillars), grid type structure) with size of 2ken x 2ken emerged, and this became the main structure of a warehouse.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the end of the Yayoi period to the beginning of the Kofun period (tumulus period), Sobashira-shiki building (dug-standing pillar building with a pillar per ken (unit of distance between two pillars), grid type structure) with size of 2 ken x 2 ken emerged, and this became the main structure of a warehouse.</e>
<cmt>スペースを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="97">
<sen id="207">
<j>墓制</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The burial system</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The burial system</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The burial system</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="98">
<sen id="208">
<j>弥生時代の墓制を示す用語として、支石墓、墳丘墓、周溝墓などといった埋葬施設の外部施設（上部構造）を示す区分と、甕棺墓、土壙墓、木棺墓、石棺墓などといった個々の埋葬施設本体の形状（下部構造）を示す区分がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are two classification in terminology used in the burial system of Yayoi period, which are; terms describing outside facility of burial facility (upper structure) such as shisekibo (a dolmen), funkyubo (grave mound or tumulus) and shukobo (burial mound surrounded by moat), and terms describing individual shapes of actual burial facility (lower structure) such as kamekanbo (earthenware jar-coffin grave), dokobo (hole-shaped grave), mokkanbo (wooden coffin grave) and sekkanbo (stone coffin grave).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are two classifications in terminology used in the burial system of the Yayoi period, which are; terms describing outside facility of burial facility (upper structure) such as shisekibo (a dolmen), funkyubo (grave mound or tumulus) and shukobo (burial mound surrounded by a moat), and terms describing individual shapes of actual burial facility (lower structure) such as kamekanbo (earthenware jar-coffin grave), dokobo (hole-shaped grave), mokkanbo (wooden coffin grave) and sekkanbo (stone coffin grave).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are two classifications in terminology used in the burial system of the Yayoi period, which are; terms describing outside facility of burial facility (upper structure) such as shisekibo (a dolmen), funkyubo (grave mound or tumulus) and shukobo (burial mound surrounded by a moat), and terms describing individual shapes of actual burial facility (lower structure) such as kamekanbo (earthenware jar-coffin grave), dokobo (hole-shaped grave), mokkanbo (wooden coffin grave) and sekkanbo (stone coffin grave).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="209">
<j>いずれも、半島より渡来した要素と縄文文化より受け継いだ要素からなり、地域によって墓地の構成に様々な特色が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All were formed with elements passed down from Jomon culture and elements brought from Korean Peninsula, and there were various characteristics of grave components in each region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All were formed with elements passed down from the Jomon culture and elements brought from the Korean Peninsula, and there were various characteristics of grave components in each region.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All were formed with elements passed down from the Jomon culture and elements brought from the Korean Peninsula, and there were various characteristics of grave components in each region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="99">
<sen id="210">
<j>甕棺墓は、縄文時代後・晩期の埋甕習俗を下敷きとし、半島から伝来した壷形土器を埋葬容器として採用することにより成立したと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamekanbo was based on the manners and customs of maiyou (custom of burial in Jomon period, dead body etc was placed inside a pot and buried) in the end to last Jomon period, and was completed by adapting jar-shaped vessel from Korean Peninsula as a container for burial.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamekanbo was based on the manners and customs of maiyou (custom of burial during the Jomon period, dead body, etc. was placed inside a pot and buried) in the end to last Jomon period, and was completed by adapting a jar-shaped vessel from the Korean Peninsula as a container for burial.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamekanbo was based on the manners and customs of maiyo (custom of burial during the Jomon period, dead body, etc. was placed inside a pot and buried) in the end to last Jomon period, and was completed by adapting a jar-shaped vessel from the Korean Peninsula as a container for burial.</e>
<cmt>maiyou→maiyo と修正しました。スペースを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="211">
<j>北部九州弥生時代前～中期の代表的な墓制である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the typical burial system in the early to middle Yayoi period in northern Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the typical burial system in the early to middle Yayoi period in northern Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was the typical burial system in the early to middle Yayoi period in northern Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="100">
<sen id="212">
<j>前期前半段階には壷形土器をそのまま大型化した埋葬容器が使用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Simply enlarged jar-shaped vessel was used for a container for burial in the first half of early Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Simply an enlarged jar-shaped vessel was used for a container for burial during the first half of the early Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Simply an enlarged jar-shaped vessel was used for a container for burial during the first half of the early Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="213">
<j>しかし、前期末までには埋葬専用容器として独自の形状を持ったものが成立し、その形状は壷形土器から甕形土器へと移行する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However earthware with original shape especially for a burial container came into being by the end of early period and the shape shifted to maiyou earthware from jar-shaped vessel.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However earthenware with its original shape, especially as a burial container, came into being by the end of early period and the shape shifted to maiyou earthenware from a jar-shaped vessel.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However earthenware with its original shape, especially as a burial container, came into being by the end of early period and the shape shifted to maiyou earthenware from a jar-shaped vessel.</e>
<cmt>スペースを修正しました、</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="101">
<sen id="214">
<j>中期には北部九州各地で少しずつその形態を変えながらも基本的には同じ形質的特徴を共有する成人用大型甕棺が北部九州に定着する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the middle period, the earthware slightly changed its shape but a large kamekan (earthenware jar-coffin) for adult, which had the same basic characters as previous earthware, was established in northern Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the middle period, the earthenware slightly changed its shape, but a large kamekan (earthenware jar-coffin) for adult, which had the same basic characters as previous earthware, was established in northern Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>grammer</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the middle period, the earthenware slightly changed its shape, but a large kamekan (earthenware jar-coffin) for adult, which had the same basic characters as previous earthware, was established in northern Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="215">
<j>それとともに、小児・乳幼児用に日常容器として使われる通常のサイズの甕形土器が埋葬容器として一般的に使われるようになり、甕棺墓制が確立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then standard sized kamegata earthware, which was used as daily container, started to be used as a burial container for child and infant; the kamekan (earthenware jar-coffin) burial system had been established.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then standard sized kamegata earthenware, used as a daily container, started to be used as a burial container for children and infants; the kamekan (earthenware jar-coffin) burial system had been established.</e>
<cmt>grammer</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then standard sized kamegata earthenware, used as a daily container, started to be used as a burial container for children and infants; the kamekan (earthenware jar-coffin) burial system came to be established.</e>
<cmt>had been→came to be と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="102">
<sen id="216">
<j>同時に、成人用大型甕棺に付属する蓋として、大型の鉢形土器が成立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, a pot type earthware emerged as a lid of a large kamekan for adult.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, a pot type earthenware emerged as a lid of a large kamekan for an adult.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, a pot type earthenware emerged as a lid of a large kamekan for an adult.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="103">
<sen id="217">
<j>甕棺墓は成人用甕棺が二つ合わせ口として組み合わされるものが一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamekanbo (earthenware jar-coffin grave) were generally structured with two large kamekan for adult with both rims put together to seal.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamekanbo (earthenware jar-coffin grave) were generally structured with two large kamekan for adults with both rims put together to seal.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamekanbo (earthenware jar-coffin grave) were generally structured with two large kamekan for adults with both rims put together to seal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="218">
<j>このほかにこの鉢形の甕棺専用蓋が用いられるものも多く、また木製や石製の蓋が使われることも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, a pot type earthware for a rid of kamekan was often used, as well as wooden or stone rid.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, a pot type earthenware for a kamekan lid was often used, as well as wooden or stone lid.</e>
<cmt>spelling, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, a pot type earthenware dedicated to a kamekan lid was often used, as well as wooden or stone lid.</e>
<cmt>「専用」を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="104">
<sen id="219">
<j>甕棺墓制は後期には急速に衰退して石蓋土壙墓・箱式石棺墓などに取って代わられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The kamekan burial system quickly declined in the end period and was replaced by hole-shaped grave with stone lid and hakoshiki-sekkanbo (box-shaped stone coffin grave).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kamekan burial system quickly declined in the end period and was replaced by hole-shaped grave with stone lid and hakoshiki-sekkanbo (box-shaped stone coffin grave).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kamekan burial system quickly declined in the end period and was replaced by hole-shaped grave with stone lid and hakoshiki-sekkanbo (box-shaped stone coffin grave).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="220">
<j>糸島地域のみで細々と継続するほかは旧甕棺墓制分布域で散発的に認められるのみとなり、古墳時代までには消滅する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Apart from Itoshima region where the custom was barely remained in, it was sporadically seen in a pre kamekan burial system distribution range and finally the custom disappeared by Kofun period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Apart from the Itoshima region where the custom barely remained, it was sporadically seen in a pre kamekan burial system distribution range and finally the custom disappeared by the Kofun period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Apart from the Itoshima region where the custom barely remained, it was sporadically seen in a former kamekan burial system distribution range and finally the custom disappeared by the Kofun period.</e>
<cmt>pre→former と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="221">
<j>主たる分布域は北部九州地域でも筑前・筑後国・肥前東部域であり、この周辺地域では副次的な墓制として分布する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main distribution range was northern Kyushu, especially Chikuzen, Chikugo Province and eastern Hizen region, and the custom was distributed as a secondary burial system in the surrounding area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Main distribution range was northern Kyushu, especially Chikuzen, Chikugo Province and the eastern Hizen region, and the custom was distributed as a secondary burial system in the surrounding area.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Main distribution range was northern Kyushu, especially Chikuzen, Chikugo Provinces and the eastern Hizen region, and the custom was distributed as a secondary burial system in the surrounding area.</e>
<cmt>Province→Provinces と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="105">
<sen id="222">
<j>木棺墓は、明確な出自は明らかになってはいないものの縄文文化には認められない墓制であることから半島から渡来した墓制と考えられている埋葬様式の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although clear place of origin for mokkanbo (wooden coffin grave) was not yet known, it is a burial system not found in Jomon culture therefore it is considered as a burial system introduced from Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is clear the place of origin for mokkanbo (wooden coffin grave) was not yet known, it is a burial system not found in the Jomon culture therefore it is considered as a burial system introduced from the Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is clear the place of origin for mokkanbo (wooden coffin grave) is not yet known, it is a burial system not found in the Jomon culture therefore it is considered as a burial system introduced from the Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>was→is と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="106">
<sen id="223">
<j>弥生時代の木棺墓の大半は組合式と呼ばれるもので、一般的には、底板・両側板・両小口板・蓋板の計6枚の板材を組み合わせ、あらかじめ掘削された土坑の中に棺を作るものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Majority of mokkanbo was called kumiaishiki (unit style), which were generally made combining 6 boards, a bottom board, two side boards, two end boards, and a lid board, and the coffin was made inside dug out hole.</e>
<cmt>組合式の読みについては推察です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Majority of mokkanbo was called kumiaishiki (unit style), which were generally made by combining six boards, a bottom board, two side boards, two end boards, and a lid board, and the coffin was placed inside a dug out hole.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Majority of mokkanbo was called kumiaishiki (unit style), which were generally made by combining six boards, a bottom board, two side boards, two end boards, and a lid board, and the coffin was placed inside a dug out hole.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="107">
<sen id="224">
<j>しばしば小口板などが石材に置き換わる例がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stones often replaced end boards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stones often replaced end boards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stones often replaced end boards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="108">
<sen id="225">
<j>板材の組み合わせ方には、両側板が小口板を挟み込む形式のものと小口板が両側板を挟み込む形式のものとがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were two different ways of combination of boards, which are two sideboards holding two end boards in between, or two end boards holding two sideboards in between.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were two different ways of combining the boards, which are two sideboards holding two end boards in between, or two end boards holding two sideboards in between.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were two different ways of combining the boards, which are two sideboards holding two end boards in between, or two end boards holding two sideboards in between.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="226">
<j>これが被葬者の出自集団を表すとする論があるが、証明されてはいない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a theory stating that the difference shows buried person&apos;s birth group, but it is not proved yet.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a theory stating that the difference shows buried person&apos;s birth group, but it is not proven yet.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a theory stating that the difference shows buried person&apos;s birth group, but it is not proven yet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="109">
<sen id="227">
<j>弥生時代前期末までには広く（北部九州をのぞく）西日本地域で主たる墓制として採用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mokkanbo was widespread in western Japan region (except in northern Kyushu) as a main burial system until the end of early Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mokkanbo was widespread in the western Japan region (except in northern Kyushu) as the main burial system until the end of the early Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mokkanbo was widespread in the western Japan region (except in northern Kyushu) as the main burial system until the end of the early Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="228">
<j>特に畿内などでは土壙墓とともに中期の方形周溝墓の主体部として採用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially in Kinai, mokkanbo and hole-shaped grave were adapted as a core of hokei shukobo (burial mound surrounded by square moat) in middle period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially in Kinai, mokkanbo and hole-shaped graves were adapted as a core of hokei shukobo (burial mound surrounded by square moat) in middle period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially in Kinai, mokkanbo and hole-shaped graves were adapted as a core of hokei shukobo (burial mound surrounded by square moat) in middle period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="110">
<sen id="229">
<j>弥生時代後期にはやはり石蓋土壙墓や箱式石棺墓などに取って代わられ、衰退する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mokkanbo also declined and was replaced by a hole-shaped grave with stone lid and hakoshiki-sekkanbo (box-shaped stone coffin grave) in the end of Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mokkanbo also declined and was replaced by a hole-shaped grave with a stone lid and hakoshiki-sekkanbo (box-shaped stone coffin grave) at the end of the Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mokkanbo also declined and was replaced by a hole-shaped grave with a stone lid and hakoshiki-sekkanbo (box-shaped stone coffin grave) at the end of the Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="230">
<j>また、特殊な木棺墓として、丸木をくりぬいたものを上下に合わせたような特殊な形状をした木棺墓が特に弥生時代早期～前期前半期に特徴的に認められる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unique mokkanbo with shape of two hollow out logs put together at rims were confirmed specially in earlier period to the first half of early Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unique mokkanbo with the shape of two hollowed out logs put together at the rims were confirmed specially in the earlier period to the first half of the early Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unique mokkanbo with the shape of two hollowed out logs put together at the rims were confirmed specially in the earlier period to the first half of the early Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="111">
<sen id="231">
<j>土壙墓、特に素掘りの土壙墓は、縄文時代に一般的な墓制であり、弥生時代にもしばしば認められる墓制である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hole-shaped grave, especially an excavation without shoring, was a common burial system in Jomon period and also often seen in Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hole-shaped grave, especially an excavation without shoring, was a common burial system in the Jomon period and also often seen in the Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hole-shaped grave, especially an excavation without shoring, was a common burial system in the Jomon period and also often seen in the Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="112">
<sen id="232">
<j>しかし、縄文時代の土壙墓と弥生時代の（特に西日本の）土壙墓とはその形状に差があり、後者の方が全長が長い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However there is a difference in the shape of hole-shaped grave in Jomon period and Yayoi period (especially in western Japan), and hole-shaped grave in Yayoi period had longer length.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However there is a difference in the shape of hole-shaped graves in the Jomon and Yayoi periods (especially in western Japan), and hole-shaped graves in the Yayoi period was longer in length.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However there is a difference in the shape of hole-shaped graves in the Jomon and Yayoi periods (especially in western Japan), and hole-shaped graves in the Yayoi period was longer in length.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="233">
<j>これは、埋葬姿勢の差異に由来するものと考えられる（縄文時代の土壙墓には屈葬が多く認められる一方、弥生時代の土壙墓は伸展葬が一般的である）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was due to the difference in burial posture (crouched burial are often found in hole-shaped grave in Jomon period, on the other hand full-length burial was common in hole-shaped grave in Yayoi period).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was due to the difference in burial posture (crouched burial are often found in a hole-shaped grave during the Jomon period, on the other hand full-length burial was common in a hole-shaped grave during the Yayoi period).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was due to the difference in burial posture (Crouched burial are often found in a hole-shaped grave during the Jomon period, on the other hand full-length burial was common in a hole-shaped grave during the Yayoi period.)</e>
<cmt>カッコ部分、ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="113">
<sen id="234">
<j>弥生時代に新たに現れる土壙墓の形式の一つに、蓋を板石で覆う石蓋土壙墓があり、弥生時代後期に広く西日本全域で一般化する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A hole-shaped grave with stone lid was a type of a hole-shaped grave emerged in Yayoi period and it became widespread throughout the western Japan in the end of Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A hole-shaped grave with a stone lid was a type of a hole-shaped grave that emerged during the Yayoi period and it became widespread throughout western Japan at the end of the Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A hole-shaped grave with a stone lid was a type of a hole-shaped grave that emerged during the Yayoi period and it became widespread throughout western Japan at the end of the Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="235">
<j>箱式石棺墓との関連性も考えられる（箱式石棺墓の蓋石以外を省略すると石蓋土壙墓となるため）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Relationship between a hakoshiki-sekkanbo (box-shaped stone coffin grave) is also considered (hakoshiki-sekkanbo becomes hole-shaped grave with stone lid if all other part except lid is omitted).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Relationship between a hakoshiki-sekkanbo (box-shaped stone coffin grave) is also considered (hakoshiki-sekkanbo becomes a hole-shaped grave with stone lid if all other parts except the lid is omitted).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Connection between a hakoshiki-sekkanbo (box-shaped stone coffin grave) is also considered (Hakoshiki-sekkanbo becomes a hole-shaped grave with stone lid if all other parts except the lid is omitted.)</e>
<cmt>Relationship→Connection と修正しました。カッコ部分、ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="114">
<sen id="236">
<j>中国との通交</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amity with China</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amity with China</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amity with China</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="237">
<j>中国との通交は渡来系弥生人に遡ることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amity with China goes back to Yayoi man who were immigrants to ancient Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amity with China goes back to Yayoi men who were immigrants to ancient Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amity with China goes back to Yayoi men who were immigrants to ancient Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="115">
<sen id="238">
<j>近年、DNAの研究が進み、渡来系弥生人の多くは中国大陸の長江流域、山東省付近から来たと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recent year&apos;s progress in DNA research unraveled that many of Yayoi man who were immigrants to ancient Japan came from the basin of the Yangtze River and area around Shandong Province in the Chinese continent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recent progress in DNA research unraveled that many Yayoi men who were immigrants to ancient Japan came from the basin of the Yangtze River and an area around Shandong Province on the Chinese continent.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recent progress in DNA research unraveled that many Yayoi men who were immigrants to ancient Japan came from the basin of the Yangtze River and an area around Shandong Province on the Chinese continent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="116">
<sen id="239">
<j>更に遡ると現在の中国の青海省付近にまで遡ることができるという調査結果がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some research results shows that it is possible to go back further to areas around present Qinghai Province in China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some research results show that it is possible to go back further to areas around the present Qinghai Province in China.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some research results show that it is possible to go back further to areas around the present Qinghai Province in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="117">
<sen id="240">
<j>稲作については、弥生米のDNA（SSR多型）分析によって、朝鮮半島には存在しない水稲の品種が確認されており、朝鮮半島経由のルートとは異なる、中国中南部から直接渡来したルートが提唱されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for rice cultivation, DNA (SSR polymorphism) analysis of Yayoi rice confirmed a paddy-rice variety that does not exist in Korean Peninsula and theory of direct introduction route from central and south China is proposed, not a route through Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for rice cultivation, DNA (SSR polymorphism) analysis of Yayoi rice confirmed a paddy-rice variety that does not exist on the Korean Peninsula and theory of a direct introduction route from central and south China is proposed, not a route through the Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for rice cultivation, DNA (SSR polymorphism) analysis of Yayoi rice confirmed a paddy-rice variety that does not exist on the Korean Peninsula, and theory of a direct introduction route from central and south China is proposed, not a route through the Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>カンマを補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="118">
<sen id="241">
<j>また近年、渡来系弥生人のDNAとお酒に弱い人の遺伝子の関連性が調査されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also a relationship between genes from a person who cannot drink much alcohol and DNA of Yayoi man who was a immigrants to ancient Japan has been researched in recent years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also a relationship between genes from a person who cannot drink much alcohol and DNA of a Yayoi man who was an immigrant to ancient Japan has been researched in recent years.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also a relationship between genes from a person who cannot drink much alcohol and DNA of a Yayoi man who was an immigrant to ancient Japan has been researched in recent years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="119">
<sen id="242">
<j>弥生時代の開始についてはかつて中国の春秋戦国時代の混乱と関連付ける考えがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There used to be a theory that related the beginning of Yayoi period with disturbance of the Spring and Autumn period and the Warring States period in China.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There used to be a theory that related the beginning of the Yayoi period with disturbance of the Spring and Autumn periods and the Warring States period in China.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There used to be a theory that related the beginning of the Yayoi period with disturbance of the Spring and Autumn periods and the Warring States period in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="243">
<j>しかし弥生時代の開始年代を繰り上げる説に関連してこれを否定するか、あるいは殷から周への政変に関連付ける考えが検討されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in connection with a theory to moving up the beginning date of Yayoi period, whether or not to reject the previous theory, or to relate new date with political changes of Yin Dynasty to Zhou Dynasty have been considered.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in connection with a theory to moving up the beginning date of the Yayoi period, whether or not to reject the previous theory, or to relate a new date with political changes of the Yin Dynasty to the Zhou Dynasty has been considered.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in connection with a theory to moving up the beginning date of the Yayoi period, whether or not to reject the previous theory, or to relate a new date with political changes of the Yin Dynasty to the Zhou Dynasty has been considered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="120">
<sen id="244">
<j>中国の史書では、後漢の『論衡』が周代の倭に関する知識を伝え、ついで漢書が前漢代のこととして倭人が多数の国に分かれて住んでおり、使節を送ってくると記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Chinese history books, &quot;Ronko (Lunheng)&quot; written in The Later Han Dynasty tells knowledge about Wa in Zhou period, and Historical records of the Han Dynasty tells about Wa in the age of the former Han dynasty, such as; people of Wa are living in many separated provinces and they sent envoy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Chinese history books, &quot;Ronko (Lunheng)&quot; written in The Later Han Dynasty provides knowledge about Wa in the Zhou period, and Historical records of the Han Dynasty explains about Wa in the age of the former Han dynasty, such as; people of Wa are living in many separated provinces and they sent an envoy.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Chinese history books, &quot;Ronko&quot; (Lunheng) written in The Later Han Dynasty provides knowledge about Wa in the Zhou period, and historical records of the Han Dynasty explains about Wa in the age of the former Han dynasty, such as; people of Wa were living in many separated provinces and they sent an envoy.</e>
<cmt>クォーツ部分を修正しました。Historical→historical,are→were と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="121">
<sen id="245">
<j>『後漢書』（南北朝時代、432年成立）には、57年に倭奴国王が後漢光武帝から漢委奴国王印を授かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;History of the Later Han Dynasty&quot; (the period of the Northern and Southern Dynasties, established in 432) describes that Wano Nano Kokuo (the King of Japan) received Kanno Wano Nano Kokuo Kinin (the Golden Seal of the King of Japan, Chinese Colony) from Kobu-tei (Emperor Guangwu) of The Later Han Dynasty in 57.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;History of the Later Han Dynasty&quot; (the period of the Northern and Southern Dynasties, established in 432) describes that Wano Nano Kokuo (the King of Japan) received Kanno Wano Nano Kokuo Kinin (the Golden Seal of the King of Japan, Chinese Colony) from Kobu-tei (Emperor Guangwu) of The Later Han Dynasty in 57.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;History of the Later Han Dynasty&quot; (the period of the Northern and Southern Dynasties, established in 432) describes that Wano Nano Kokuo (the King of Japan) received Kanno Wano Nano Kokuo Kinin (the Golden Seal of the King of Japan, Chinese Colony) from Kobu-tei (Emperor Guangwu) of The Later Han Dynasty in 57.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="246">
<j>また107年には倭国王帥升（または倭面土國王帥升）が生口を後漢へ献じたことが見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also Suisho the King of Wa (倭国王帥升) (also written as 倭面土國王帥升) sent seiko (slave) to The Later Han Dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also Suisho the King of Wa (倭国王帥升) (also written as 倭面土國王帥升) sent seiko (slave) to The Later Han Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also Suisho the King of Wa (倭国王帥升) (also written as 倭面土國王帥升) sent seiko (slave) to The Later Han Dynasty in 107.</e>
<cmt>「107年」を補いました。「倭国王帥升」、「倭面土國王帥升」の読みは不明です。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="122">
<sen id="247">
<j>三国志の『魏志倭人伝』は、3世紀の倭国の状況を詳しく記し、邪馬台国の卑弥呼女王が統治していたことなどを伝えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Gishiwajinden (literally, an &apos;Account of the Wa&apos; in &quot;The History of the Wei Dynasty&quot;)&quot; from Sangokushi (Annals of the Three Kingdoms) describes state of Wakoku in the third century in detail that Queen Himiko ruled over Yamatai-Koku kingdom.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Gishiwajinden (literally, an &apos;Account of the Wa&apos; in &quot;The History of the Wei Dynasty&quot;)&quot; from Sangokushi (Annals of the Three Kingdoms) describes state of Wakoku in the third century in detail that Queen Himiko ruled over the Yamatai-Koku kingdom.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Gishiwajinden&quot; (literally, an &apos;Account of the Wa&apos; in &quot;The History of the Wei Dynasty&quot;) from Sangokushi (Annals of the Three Kingdoms) describes state of Wakoku in the third century in detail that Queen Himiko ruled over the Yamatai-Koku kingdom.</e>
<cmt>クォーツ部分を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="123">
<sen id="248">
<j>中国の三国時代の呉と倭国が公的に交渉を行った文献は全くないが、遺物としては呉の年号を記す画文帯神獣鏡が二面存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there is no evidence of an official negotiation between Wakoku and Wu in Three Kingdoms period, two Gabuntai Shinjukyo Mirror (Mirror with figures of duties and sacred animals) with name of era in Wu exist as a relic.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there is no evidence of an official negotiation between Wakoku and Wu in the Three Kingdoms period, two Gabuntai Shinjukyo Mirror (Mirror with figures of duties and sacred animals) with the name of the era in Wu exists as a relic.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there is no evidence of an official negotiation between Wakoku and Wu in the Three Kingdoms period, two Gabuntai Shinjukyo Mirror (Mirror with figures of duties and sacred animals) with the name of the era in Wu exists as a relic.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="124">
<sen id="249">
<j>山梨県西八代郡市川三郷町（旧三珠町）の鳥居原塚古墳出土の赤烏（せきう）元年(238)の紀年銘をもつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One was excavated from Toriibarakitsunezuka Tumulus in Ichikawa Misatocho (previous Mitamacho), Nishiyatsushiro district, Yamanashi Prefecture and it has an inscription about counting years of Sekiu Gannen (year 1) Year (in 238).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One was excavated from Toriibarakitsunezuka Tumulus in Ichikawa Misatocho (previous Mitamacho), Nishiyatsushiro district, Yamanashi Prefecture and it has an inscription about counting years of Sekiu Gannen (year 1) Year (in 238).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One was excavated from Toriibarakitsunezuka Tumulus in Ichikawa Misatocho (former Mitamacho), Nishiyatsushiro district, Yamanashi Prefecture and it has an inscription about counting years of Sekiu Gannen (year 1) Year (in 238).</e>
<cmt>previous→former と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="125">
<sen id="250">
<j>兵庫県宝塚市安倉古墳（あくらこふん）出土の赤烏七年(244)の紀年銘をもつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another was excavated from Akura Tumulus in Takarazuka City, Hyogo Prefecture and it has an inscription about counting years of year 7 in Sekiu (in 244).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another was excavated from Akura Tumulus in Takarazuka City, Hyogo Prefecture and it has an inscription about counting years of year 7 in Sekiu (in 244).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another was excavated from Akura Tumulus in Takarazuka City, Hyogo Prefecture and it has an inscription about counting years of year seven in Sekiu (in 244).</e>
<cmt>7→seven と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>弥生人の特徴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Characteristics of Yayoi man</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Characteristics of Yayoi man</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Characteristics of Yayoi man</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="251">
<j>弥生人の特徴は、縄文人と比較すると、顔立ちは、面長で、眼窩は鼻の付け根が扁平で上下に長く丸みを帯びていて、のっぺりとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Compared to Jomon man, characteristics of Yayoi man were; a lightly elongated face with flat orbital cavity at nose, and have flat and undefined feature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Compared to Jomon man, characteristics of Yayoi man were; a slightly elongated face with a flat orbital cavity at nose, and have flat and undefined features.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Compared to Jomon man, characteristics of Yayoi man were; a slightly elongated face with a flat orbital cavity at nose, and have flat and undefined features.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="252">
<j>また、平均身長も162～163センチぐらいで、縄文人よりも数センチ高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their average height was 162cm to 163cm, which were several centimeters taller.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their average height was 162cm to 163cm, which was several centimeters taller.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their average height was 162 cm to 163 cm, which was several centimeters taller.</e>
<cmt>スペースを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="253">
<j>これらの特徴は、現代日本人に近いという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These features are close to Japanese people in modern age.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These features are close to Japanese people in the modern age.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These features are close to Japanese people in the modern age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="254">
<j>しかし、これらの人骨資料のほとんどは、北部九州・山口・島根県の日本海沿岸にかけての遺跡から発掘されたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, most of these human bone materials were excavated from sites in the coastal areas of Sea of Japan, including northern Kyushu, Yamaguchi and Shimane Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, most of these human bone materials were excavated from sites in the coastal areas of the Sea of Japan, including northern Kyushu, Yamaguchi, and Shimane Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, most of these human bone materials were excavated from sites in the coastal areas of the Sea of Japan, including northern Kyushu, Yamaguchi, and Shimane Prefectures.</e>
<cmt>Prefecture→Prefectures と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="255">
<j>近年、福岡県糸島半島の新町遺跡で大陸墓制である支石墓から発見された人骨は縄文的習俗である抜歯が施されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently a human bone was excavated from shisekibo (a dolmen), which is a continental burial system, in Shinmachi site in Itoshima Peninsula, Fukuoka Prefecture, and tooth extraction had been performed to the human bone, which was a manners and customs of Jomon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently a human bone was excavated from shisekibo (a dolmen), which is a continental burial system, in Shinmachi site in Itoshima Peninsula, Fukuoka Prefecture, and tooth extraction had been performed to the human bone, that was the manner and custom of Jomon.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently a human bone was excavated from shisekibo (a dolmen), which is a continental burial system, in Shinmachi site in Itoshima Peninsula, Fukuoka Prefecture, and tooth extraction had been performed to the human bone, that was the manner and custom of Jomon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="256">
<j>長崎県大友遺跡の支石墓群から多くの縄文的な人骨が発見されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of Jomon like human bones were excavated from group of shisekibo in Otomo site in Nagasaki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of Jomon like human bones were excavated from a group of shisekibo at the Otomo site in Nagasaki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of Jomon like human bones were excavated from a group of shisekibo at the Otomo site in Nagasaki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="257">
<j>さらに瀬戸内地方の神戸市新方遺跡からの人骨も縄文的形質を備えているという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, human bones excavated from Shinpo site located in Kobe City in Setouchi region also showed some Jomon characteristics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, human bones excavated from the Shinpo site located in Kobe City in the Setouchi region also showed some Jomon characteristics.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, human bones excavated from the Shinpo site located in Kobe City in the Setouchi region also showed some Jomon characteristics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="258">
<j>ただ、福岡市の雀居（ささい）遺跡や奈良盆地の唐古・鍵遺跡の前期弥生人は、渡来系の人骨だと判定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, earlier period Yayoi man excavated from Sasai site in Fukuoka City and Karako-Kagi site in Nara Basin was confirmed as bones of immigrants to ancient Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, earlier period Yayoi man excavated from the Sasai site in Fukuoka City and the Karako-Kagi site in the Nara Basin was confirmed as bones of immigrants to ancient Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, earlier period Yayoi men excavated from the Sasai site in Fukuoka City and the Karako-Kagi site in the Nara Basin were confirmed as bones of immigrants to ancient Japan.</e>
<cmt>man→men,was→were と修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="259">
<j>つまり、最初に渡来人が来たと考えられている北部九州や大陸系渡来人が移住した可能性のある瀬戸内・近畿地方でさえ、弥生時代初期の遺跡からは渡来系の人と判定される人骨の出土数は少ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other word, excavated number of human bones confirmed as immigrants to ancient Japan are very rare in sites from early Yayoi period, even in northern Kyushu where it is said immigrants to ancient Japan first entered, and in Setouchi and Kinki region where it is believed continental immigrants to ancient Japan migrated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, the number of excavated human bones confirmed as immigrants to ancient Japan are very rare in sites from the early Yayoi period, even in northern Kyushu where it is said immigrants to ancient Japan first entered, and in the Setouchi and Kinki region where it is believed continental immigrants to ancient Japan migrated.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, the number of excavated human bones confirmed as immigrants to ancient Japan are very rare in sites from the early Yayoi period, even in northern Kyushu where it is said immigrants to ancient Japan first entered, and in the Setouchi and Kinki region where it is believed continental immigrants to ancient Japan migrated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="260">
<j>水田稲作の先進地帯でも、渡来系の人々ではなく、縄文人が水稲耕作を行ったのではないか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jomon man may have started paddy-rice cultivation in area of advanced paddy-rice cultivation, not immigrants to ancient Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jomon man may have started rice-paddy cultivation in area of advanced rice-paddy cultivation, not the immigrants to ancient Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jomon man may have started rice-paddy cultivation in area of advanced rice-paddy cultivation, not the immigrants to ancient Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="261">
<j>絶対多数の縄文人と少数の大陸系渡来人との協同のうちに農耕社会へと移行したと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that history moved to agrarian society in cooperation between Jomon man of an absolute majority and few continental immigrants to ancient Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that history moved to an agrarian society in cooperation between Jomon man of an absolute majority and few continental immigrants to ancient Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that history moved to an agrarian society in cooperation between Jomon man of an absolute majority and few continental immigrants to ancient Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="262">
<j>現代の遺跡発掘調査</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Present excavation and research of sites</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Present excavation and research of sites</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Present excavation and research of sites</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="263">
<j>熊本県玉名市の両迫間日渡（りょうはざまひわたし）遺跡で、弥生時代後期のものとみられる水田跡の一部が発見された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A part of paddy field remains from the end of Yayoi period was discovered in Ryohazamahiwata site in Tamana City, Kumamoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Part of paddy field remains from the end of Yayoi period was discovered in Ryohazamahiwata site in Tamana City, Kumamoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Part of paddy field remains from the end of Yayoi period was discovered in Ryohazamahiwata site in Tamana City, Kumamoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="264">
<j>あぜ道（約幅1メートル）には土の流失を防ぐため多数の杭が打ち込まれており、足跡も約50カ所見つかっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many stakes were put up at side of a path (approximately 1 meter width) between paddy field to stop soil from being carried out, and about 50 foot prints are also found.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many stakes were put up at side of a path (approximately one meter width) between paddy field to stop soil from being carried out, and about fifty foot prints were also found.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many stakes were put up at the side of a path (approximately 1 m width) between paddy field to stop soil from being carried out, and about 50 foot prints were also found.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。one meter→1 m,fifty→50 と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="265">
<j>あぜ道からは土器片や割れた木製の鍬などが見つかっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fragments of earthware and broken wooden hoe were excavated from a path between paddy field.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fragments of earthenware and a broken wooden hoe were excavated from a path between paddy fields.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fragments of earthenware and a broken wooden hoe were excavated from the path between paddy fields.</e>
<cmt>a→the と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="266">
<j>（熊本県教育委員会2005年11月11日発表）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Kumamoto Prefecture Education Board, November 11, 2005)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Kumamoto Prefecture Education Board, November 11, 2005)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Kumamoto Prefecture Education Board, November 11, 2005)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), おじゃ(id:70348), Okome(id:98), Eskimbot(id:29676), Shikire(id:1623), Suhuitoburaito(id:286325), のぶしょう(id:36242), Tribot(id:186681), Suginamin(id:120015), Gombe(id:27), でここ(id:9565), Commonsenses(id:11185), A-Taul(id:41790), 俊(id:14924), 秀の介(id:490), Gbr3(id:6539), Point136(id:211299), Shimoxx(id:9332), Gowish(id:11130), Cismon(id:16714), Excavator(id:25917), もね～るmoner(id:28477), Mnd(id:15140), Carbuncle(id:346), Balmung0731(id:99201), Tiyoringo(id:70026), Metallic(id:23775), Hokuto7(id:18100), ごまふあざ(id:36855), はるひ(id:59079), MDR-SK(id:192066), Petty(id:43013), Interregnum(id:25269), Thijs!bot(id:69644), SilvonenBot(id:190970), Crystaltear(id:72425), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Tietew(id:4054), ヤマト(id:8425), SuisuiBot(id:10165), Kouchiumi(id:19253), ＮｉＫｅ(id:7512), Oga(id:116), Alexbot(id:157199), TANUKI(id:28527), Elthy(id:5957), Suisui(id:69), 権田原(id:11079), Jade0416(id:104181), Nog(id:53565), Tamaka(id:191522), Reggaeman(id:6214), MIsogi(id:20599), TuvicBot(id:64131), 黄金もち(id:102311), Doskoi 8(id:1070), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), Mintleaf(id:2216), Robert De Smith(id:28533), BAKU(id:55205), やきとり(id:126941), Dondokken(id:246411), Kinori(id:443), 怪蘇(id:45514), 16toki(id:60127), Rei-bot(id:94097), 寂華(id:83725), スミス16号(id:189050), Tomika(id:43050), Piasu9(id:134995), Yosemite(id:5808), Dora(id:1122), TARBOT(id:73059), LERK(id:4460), Higashi(id:8842), Lonicera(id:20638), Izayohi(id:13095), Forestfarmer(id:59407), Auf(id:633), 安室黎(id:296739), Law soma(id:45202), 水野白楓(id:22811), Kalz(id:92749), Web.dweller(id:153933), Yanahan(id:2437), Setu(id:88), Godaigo(id:133481), Sachio340(id:35305), Thijssie!bot(id:111619), Yoshino(id:24150), Fievarsty(id:201483), SieBot(id:126695), Binh Giang(id:79801), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>