<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>三職推任問題</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Three-post endorsement problem</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Three-post endorsement problem</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanshoku suinin mondai (the question of the three alternative positions</e>
<cmt>三職推任問題の定訳</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>三職推任問題（さんしょくすいにんもんだい）とは、天正10年（1582年）4月25日 (旧暦)、5月4日 (旧暦)両日付けの勧修寺晴豊の日記『晴豊公記（天正十年夏記）』の記事の解釈を巡る日本の歴史上の論争である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanshoku suinin mondai (三職推任問題) (three-post endorsement problem) is a controversy in relation to the interpretation of the articles in Haretoyo KAJUJI&apos;s diary &quot;Haretoyo-koki (summer in the tenth year of Tensho)&quot; (晴豊公記) dated April 25 (old calendar) and May 4 (old calendar) of 1582 (in the tenth year of Tensho).</e>
<cmt>「晴豊公記」→&quot;Haretoyo-koki&quot;(晴豊公記）[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanshoku suinin mondai (三職推任問題) (three-post endorsement problem) is a controversy in relation to the interpretation of the articles in Haretoyo KAJUJI&apos;s diary &quot;Haretoyo-koki (summer in the tenth year of Tensho)&quot; (晴豊公記) dated April 25 (old calendar) and May 4 (old calendar) of 1582 (in the tenth year of Tensho).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanshoku suinin mondai is a controversy in relation to the interpretation of the articles in Haretoyo KAJUJI&apos;s diary &quot;Haretoyo-koki (summer in the 10th year of Tensho)&quot; dated April 25 (old calendar) and May 4 (old calendar) of 1582.</e>
<cmt>既出のため説明削除漢字削除of the→of thetenth→10th文末の(in the tenth year of Tensho) 削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>織田信長は天正6年（1578年）4月に、右大臣兼右近衛大将を辞官して後、何らの官職に就いていなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga ODA held no official title after resigning as Udaijin (Minister of the Right) and Ukone no daisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) in April, 1578.</e>
<cmt>右近衛大将→Ukone no daisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards)[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga ODA held no official title after resigning as Udaijin (Minister of the Right) and Ukone no daisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) in April, 1578.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga ODA held no official title after resigning as Udaijin (Minister of the Right) and Ukone no daisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) in May (April in old lunar calendar), 1578.</e>
<cmt>April→May (April in old lunar calendar) に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>天正10年5月に至り、朝廷から武田征伐の戦勝祝賀として信長に、太政大臣、関白、征夷大将軍の三職いずれかに推任しようとする動きがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May, 1582, there was a move in the Imperial Court to endorse Nobunaga for one of the three posts, Grand Minister, Chancellor, or Seiitaishogun (commander-in-chief of the expeditionary force against the barbarians) as a reward of his subjugation of Takeda.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May, 1582, there was a move in the Imperial Court to endorse Nobunaga for one of the three posts, Grand Minister, Chancellor, or Seiitaishogun (commander-in-chief of the expeditionary force against the barbarians) as a reward for his subjugation of Takeda.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June (May in old lunar calendar), 1582, there was a move in the Imperial Court to endorse Nobunaga for one of the three posts, Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state), Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor), or Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) as a reward for his subjugation of Takeda.</e>
<cmt>太政大臣、関白、征夷大将軍の定訳May→June (May in old lunar calendar)に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>本論争は直接的には、この動きを信長の強制と見るか否かを争うものであるが、その論を立脚点とした織田政権の将来構想や本能寺の変の背景に対する考察を含むものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The point of the argument is whether the move was forced by Nobunaga or not, and also the issues include considerations to the grand plan of Oda administration and the background of the Honnoji Incident, which could be derived from the main argument.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The point of the argument is whether the move was forced by Nobunaga or not, while other issues which could be derived from the main argument include considerations to the grand plan of the Oda administration and the background of the Honnoji Incident,</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The point of the argument is whether the move was forced by Nobunaga or not, while other issues which could be derived from the main argument include considerations to the grand plan of the Oda administration and the background of the Honnoji Incident.</e>
<cmt>最後のカンマをピリオドに訂正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>本文</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Excerpts from the diary</e>
<cmt>「本文」だけではわかりにくいので，内容にそって訳しました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Excerpts from the diary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Excerpts from the diary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>廿五日（中略）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Twenty-fifth (snip)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Twenty-fifth (snip)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On 25th (snip)</e>
<cmt>日付なのでonを加え数字表記としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>村井所へ参候。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I called on Murai&apos;s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I called on Murai&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I called on Murai&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>安土へ女はうしゆ御くたし候て、太政大臣か関白か将軍か、御すいにん候て可然候よし被申候。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was mentioned (written as &apos;被申候&apos;) that an envoy with court ladies should be sent to Nobunaga in Azuchi to inform him that he should be endorsed for Grand Minister, Chancellor, or Shogun.</e>
<cmt>主語が分からないのが当論争の原因なので意図的に受動態にしました．</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was mentioned (written as &apos;被申候&apos;) that an envoy with court ladies should be sent to Nobunaga in Azuchi to inform him that he should be endorsed for Grand Minister, Chancellor, or Shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was mentioned (written as &apos;被申候&apos;) that an envoy with court ladies should be sent to Nobunaga in Azuchi to inform him that he should be endorsed for Daijo-daijin, Kanpaku, or Shogun.</e>
<cmt>Grand Minister, Chancellor　表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>その由申入候。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So I reported.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So I reported.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So I reported.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>四日（中略）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fourth (snip)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fourth (snip)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On 4th (snip)</e>
<cmt>日付表記、変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="10">
<j>のふなかより御らんと申候こしやうもちて、いかやうの御使のよし申候。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga had his pageboy called &apos;Oran&apos; to ask the envoy about the business.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga had his pageboy call &apos;Oran&apos; to ask the envoy about the business.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga had his pageboy, Oran ask the envoy about the business.</e>
<cmt>ＮＣの文では意味が違うので訂正。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="11">
<j>関東打はたされ珎重間、将軍ニなさるへきよしと申候へハ、又御らんもつて御書あかる也。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I congratulated on his victory in Kanto and said that Nobunaga should be the Shogun, and then Oran came back with Nobunaga&apos;s note.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I congratulated him on his victory in Kanto and said that Nobunaga should be Shogun, and then Oran came back with Nobunaga&apos;s note.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I congratulated him on his victory in Kanto and said that Nobunaga should be Shogun, and then Oran came back with Nobunaga&apos;s note.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>解釈</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Interpretation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Interpretation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Interpretation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>従来伝承されていた『晴豊公記』は、天正10年4月分から同年9月分が欠けていたが、1968年（昭和43年）岩沢愿彦が内閣文庫（現国立公文書館）にあった『天正十年夏記』が『晴豊公記』断簡であることを発表した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Haretoyo-koki&quot; that had been handed down had missing pages of April to September in 1582, but in 1968 Yoshihiko IWASAWA released that &quot;The Record of Summer in 1582&quot; (天正十年夏記) he found out in Naikaku-bunko (literally, &quot;Library of the Cabinet,&quot; National Archives of Japan now) was a fragment of &quot;Haretoyo-koki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>『天正十年夏記』→&quot;The Record of Summer in 1582&quot;(天正十年夏記）[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Haretoyo-koki&quot; that had been handed down had missing pages from April to September in 1582, but in 1968 Yoshihiko IWASAWA released &quot;The Record of Summer in 1582&quot; (天正十年夏記) he found in Naikaku-bunko (literally, &quot;Library of the Cabinet,&quot; National Archives of Japan now) which was a fragment of &quot;Haretoyo-koki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Haretoyo-koki&quot; that had been handed down had missing pages from May to September in 1582, but in 1968 Yoshihiko IWASAWA released &quot;The Record of Summer in 1582&quot; he found in Naikaku-bunko (literally, &quot;Library of the Cabinet,&quot; National Archives of Japan now) which was a fragment of &quot;Haretoyo-koki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>漢字削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>岩沢の解釈では、「太政大臣、関白、将軍の三職いずれかに推任するのがよい」と言った主体を天皇の意向を受けた晴豊としており、以後もこの解釈を受け、信長はこの天皇の意向を突っぱねたとする説が通説化していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iwasawa&apos;s interpretation of the line &apos;he should be endorsed for Grand Minister, Chancellor, or Shogun&apos; was that it was Haretoyo who said it in line with the Emperor&apos;s wish, and later this interpretation prevailed to form a common belief that Nobunaga refused the Emperor&apos;s wish.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iwasawa&apos;s interpretation of the line &apos;he should be endorsed for Grand Minister, Chancellor, or Shogun&apos; was that it was Haretoyo who said it in line with the Emperor&apos;s wish, and later this interpretation prevailed to form a common belief that Nobunaga refused the Emperor&apos;s wish.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iwasawa&apos;s interpretation of the line &apos;he should be endorsed for Daijo daijin, Kanpaku, or Shogun&apos; was that it was Haretoyo who said it in line with the Emperor&apos;s wish, and later this interpretation prevailed to form a common belief that Nobunaga refused the Emperor&apos;s wish.</e>
<cmt>Grand Minister, Chancellor 表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>ところが、歴史研究家の立花京子が晴豊の日記全体の「被申候」使用例を分析した結果、村井貞勝の言葉と解釈し、独断専行を嫌う信長に無断で貞勝が発言するはずがないとし、信長の将軍任官の意向を踏まえたものであったと主張したことにより、歴史学者の間で賛否両論の論争となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Kyoko TACHIBANA, a researcher of history, studied usages of &apos;被申候&apos;in other passages of whole Haretoyo&apos;s diary to conclude it was what Sadakatsu MURAI said, and she argued that Sadakatsu would never say such a thing without Nobunaga&apos;s permission because Nobunaga disliked his followers&apos; arbitrary decisions or executions, and that he represented Nobunaga&apos;s wish to gain the post, which led to controversies of pros and cons among historians.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Kyoko TACHIBANA, a researcher of history, studied usages of &apos;被申候&apos;in other passages across Haretoyo&apos;s diary and concluded it was what Sadakatsu MURAI said, arguing that Sadakatsu would never say such a thing without Nobunaga&apos;s permission because Nobunaga disliked his followers&apos; arbitrary decisions or executions, and that he represented Nobunaga&apos;s wish to gain the post, which led to controversies of pros and cons among historians.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Kyoko TACHIBANA, a researcher of history, studied usages of &apos;被申候&apos;in other passages across Haretoyo&apos;s diary and concluded it was what Sadakatsu MURAI said, arguing that Sadakatsu would never say such a thing without Nobunaga&apos;s permission because Nobunaga disliked his followers&apos; arbitrary decisions or executions, and that he represented Nobunaga&apos;s wish to gain the post, which led to controversies of pros and cons among historians.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また立花説では、5月4日付けの記事にある「将軍になるべき」との晴豊の言葉を朝廷公式の意向であったとし、「御らん」（森成利）を派遣した信長の意図を真意を隠しわざと当惑して見せたものとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tachibana&apos;s interpretation also claims that Haretoyo&apos;s words &apos;should be the Shogun&apos; in the article of May 4 were official intention of the Imperial Court, and Nobunaga intentionally expressed his false embarrassment concealing his true meaning by having &apos;Oran&apos; (Naritoshi MORI) meet the envoy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tachibana&apos;s interpretation also claims that Haretoyo&apos;s words &apos;should be the Shogun&apos; in an article on May 4 were the official intention of the Imperial Court, and Nobunaga intentionally expressed his false embarrassment concealing his true meaning by having &apos;Oran&apos; (Naritoshi MORI) meet the envoy.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tachibana&apos;s interpretation also claims that Haretoyo&apos;s words &apos;should be the Shogun&apos; in an article on May 4 (old calendar) were the official intention of the Imperial Court, and Nobunaga intentionally expressed his false embarrassment concealing his true meaning by having &apos;Oran&apos; (Naritoshi MORI) meet the envoy.</e>
<cmt>May 4→May 4 (old calendar)に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>立花はこの解釈に基づき、三職推任を信長の勝利と位置づけ、朝廷が拒めなかったものとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on this interpretation, Tachibana concluded that the three-post endorsement indicated Nobunaga&apos;s victory over the Imperial Court which was unable to decline.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on this interpretation, Tachibana concluded that the three-post endorsement indicated Nobunaga&apos;s victory over the Imperial Court which it was unable to veto.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on this interpretation, Tachibana concluded that Sanshoku suinin indicated Nobunaga&apos;s victory over the Imperial Court which it was unable to veto.</e>
<cmt>the three-post endorsement→Sanshoku suinin</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>今谷明は立花説の解釈に立脚しながら、信長は朝廷の権威に屈服し中世的権力関係を指向せざるをえなかったとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akira IMATANI, supporting Tachibana&apos;s theory, presented that Nobunaga bowed down to the Imperial Court&apos;s authority because he had to keep the medieval relationship of power with the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akira IMATANI, supporting Tachibana&apos;s theory, presented that Nobunaga bowed down to the Imperial Court&apos;s authority because he had to keep the medieval relationship of power with the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akira IMATANI, supporting Tachibana&apos;s theory, presented that Nobunaga bowed down to the Imperial Court&apos;s authority because he had to keep the medieval relationship of power with the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>また、橋本政宣は、信長が就任を受けたのは征夷大将軍ではなく、太政大臣であったとする見解を出している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masanobu HASHIMOTO presented that Nobunaga accepted the post of the Grand Minister instead of Seiitaishogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masanobu HASHIMOTO presented that Nobunaga accepted the post of the Grand Minister instead of Seiitaishogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masanobu HASHIMOTO presented that Nobunaga accepted the post of Daijo daijin instead of Seii taishogun.</e>
<cmt>the Grand Minister→Daijo daijinSeiitaishogun→Seii taishogun</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>これは、2月に太政大臣に就任したばかりである近衛前久が5月に突如辞任していること、本能寺の変後の7月17日_(旧暦)に羽柴秀吉から毛利輝元に宛てられた手紙において、秀吉が信長のことを「大相国」と呼んでいるが、信長に対する太政大臣贈官が宮中で論じられたのは同年10月の事であること、加えてその結果出された贈官の宣命には「重而太政大臣」の語句があり、これを太政大臣の辞令が出されたのが2度目であると解釈して、1度目の辞令を三職推任問題の時に既に太政大臣就任の内諾を信長から得たことにより、非公式な内定が出されていたと解している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He thinks that informal decision of appointing Nobunaga as the Grand Minister had been already made after confirming his informal consent when Haretoyo talked about the three-post endorsement based on the following facts: Sakihisa KONOE, who assumed the Grand Minister in February, abruptly resigned in May; Hideyoshi called Nobunaga &apos;Daishokoku&apos; (the Grand Minister) in his letter to Terumoto MORI on July 17 after the Honnoji Incident, while the formal discussion at court on granting a posthumous title of the Grand Minister to Nobunaga was in October; and the subsequently issued Emperor&apos;s order of the posthumous title for Nobunaga contained a word &apos;choji Dajodaijin&apos; (重而太政大臣) (the Grand Minister again), which Hashimoto believed meant the second appointment of Nobunaga as Grand Minister.</e>
<cmt>推定仮訳では，「重而太政大臣」→choji Dajodaijin (重而太政大臣) (the Grand Minister again)[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He thinks that the informal decision of appointing Nobunaga as the Grand Minister had been already made after confirming his informal consent when Haretoyo talked about the three-post endorsement based on the following facts: Sakihisa KONOE, who assumed the Grand Minister in February, abruptly resigned in May; Hideyoshi called Nobunaga &apos;Daishokoku&apos; (the Grand Minister) in his letter to Terumoto MORI on July 17 after the Honnoji Incident, while the formal discussion at court on granting a posthumous title of the Grand Minister to Nobunaga was in October; and the subsequently issued Emperor&apos;s order of the posthumous title for Nobunaga contained a word &apos;choji Dajodaijin&apos; (重而太政大臣) (the Grand Minister again), which Hashimoto believed meant the second appointment of Nobunaga as Grand Minister.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He thinks that the informal decision of appointing Nobunaga as Daijo daijin had been already made after confirming his informal consent when Haretoyo talked about Sanshoku suinin mondai based on the following facts: Sakihisa KONOE, who assumed Daijo daijin in March (February in old lunar calendar), abruptly resigned in June (May in old lunar calendar); Hideyoshi called Nobunaga &apos;Daishokoku&apos; (the Grand Minister) in his letter to Terumoto MORI on August 15 (July 17 in old lunar calendar) after the Honnoji Incident, while the formal discussion at court on granting a posthumous title of Daijo daijin to Nobunaga was in October; and the subsequently issued Emperor&apos;s order of the posthumous title for Nobunaga contained a word &apos;choji Dajodaijin&apos; (重而太政大臣) (the Grand Minister again), which Hashimoto believed meant the second appointment of Nobunaga as Daijo daijin.</e>
<cmt>the Grand Minister→Daijo daiinthe three-post endorsement→Sanshoku suinin mondaiFebruary→March (February in old lunar calendar)に変更しました。May→June (May in old lunar calendar)に変更しました。July 17→August 15 (July 17 in old lunar calendar)に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="20">
<j>しかしながら堀新 (歴史学者)から出された反論では、同日記の5月4日 (旧暦)付けの記事や、『誠仁親王消息』などの資料から、三職いずれかなどという曖昧な推任をしたのは誰も信長の真意を理解していなかったための行動であり、貞勝と信長との間にこの件に関する打ち合わせをした形跡がないことなどから、三職推任は信長の意向とは言えず、5月4日の晴豊の言葉も晴豊個人の見解であるとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shin HORI (a historian) argued against these interpretations that Haretoyo expressed his own opinion on May 4 at that time and the three-post endorsement had nothing do to with Nobunaga&apos;s intention, because: the article of the diary dated May 4 and &quot;Message from Imperial Prince Sanehito&quot; (誠仁親王消息) suggest that such an unspecific three-post endorsement came from the situation that no one knew what Nobunaga wanted; and nothing suggests Nobunaga and Sadakatsu had talked about this matter.</e>
<cmt>『誠仁親王消息』→&quot;Message from Imperial Prince Sanehito&quot;(『誠仁親王消息』)[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shin HORI (a historian) argued against these interpretations that Haretoyo expressed his own opinion on May 4 at that time and the three-post endorsement had nothing do to with Nobunaga&apos;s intention, because: the article of the diary dated May 4 and &quot;Message from Imperial Prince Sanehito&quot; (誠仁親王消息) suggest that such an unspecific three-post endorsement came from a situation where no one knew what Nobunaga wanted; and nothing suggests Nobunaga and Sadakatsu had talked about this matter.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shin HORI (a historian) argued against these interpretations that Haretoyo expressed his own opinion on May 4 (old calendar) at that time and Sanshoku suinin had nothing do to with Nobunaga&apos;s intention, because: the article of the diary dated May 4 and &quot;Message from Imperial Prince Sanehito&quot; (誠仁親王消息) suggest that such an unspecific Sanshoku suinin came from a situation where no one knew what Nobunaga wanted; and nothing suggests Nobunaga and Sadakatsu had talked about this matter.</e>
<cmt>May 4→May 4 (old calendar)the three-post endorsement→Sanshoku suinin</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>堀説では、信長は天下統一まで任官できないとして右大臣兼右近衛大将を辞官しており統一前に任官する理由が立たないことを指摘し、信長には任官の意思はなく、律令体制に留まらず中華皇帝を指向していたと推察できるともしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hori pointed out that Nobunaga had resigned as Minister of the Right and Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards because he would not take any official post until his unification of the whole country, and Hori also said Nobunaga probably did not want any official post, and instead he had the aim of becoming an emperor outside the Ritsuryo system (the system of centralized government established in the beginning of the eighth century).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hori pointed out that Nobunaga had resigned as Minister of the Right and Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards because he would not take any official post until his unification of the whole country, and Hori also said Nobunaga probably did not want any official post, and instead he had the aim of becoming an emperor outside the Ritsuryo system (the system of centralized government established in the beginning of the eighth century).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hori pointed out that Nobunaga had resigned as Minister of the Right and Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards because he would not take any official post until his unification of the whole country, and Hori also said Nobunaga probably did not want any official post, and instead he had the aim of becoming an emperor outside the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code).</e>
<cmt>律令体制の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="22">
<j>小和田哲男は堀と同様の解釈をとりながら、5月4日以降に将軍任官を考えたのではないかとの見解を示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tetsuo OWADA with the same interpretation as Hori&apos;s presented that Nobunaga probably thought of accepting the title of the Shogun after May 4.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tetsuo OWADA with the same interpretation as Hori&apos;s presented that Nobunaga probably thought of accepting the title of the Shogun after May 4.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tetsuo OWADA with the same interpretation as Hori&apos;s presented that Nobunaga probably thought of accepting the title of the Shogun after May 4 (old calendar).</e>
<cmt>May 4→May 4 (old calendar)に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="23">
<j>この論争は2007年現在も継続しており、いまだ定説と見なされる見解は確定していない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This controversy was still under way as of 2007 without reaching any settlement with an accepted theory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This controversy was still under way as of 2007 without reaching any settlement over an accepted theory.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This controversy was still under way as of 2007 without reaching any settlement over an accepted theory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Anton21(id:158479), Ikedat76(id:34218), 水野白楓(id:22811), Law soma(id:45202), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>