<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>天満屋事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenmanya Incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenmanya Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenmanya Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>天満屋事件（てんまやじけん）は、海援隊 (浪士結社)士/陸援隊士らが京都油小路通の旅籠・天満屋を襲撃して、紀州藩士三浦安を襲い、新選組と戦った事件である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tenmanya Incident was an incident in which members of Kaientai (an association of roshi (masterless samurai) organized by Ryoma SAKAMOTO) (Roshi association) and Rikuentai (an association of roshi organized by Shintaro NAKAOKA) assaulted a hatago (inn with meals) on Aburanokoji-dori Street, Kyoto called Tenmanya, attacking Yasushi MIURA, who was a feudal retainer of Kishu Domain, and fought a battle against Shinsengumi (a group who guarded Kyoto during the end of Tokugawa Shogunate).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tenmanya Incident was an incident in which members of Kaientai (an association of roshi (masterless samurai) organized by Ryoma SAKAMOTO) (Roshi association) and Rikuentai (an association of roshi organized by Shintaro NAKAOKA) assaulted a hatago (inn with meals) on Aburanokoji-dori Street, Kyoto called Tenmanya, attacking Yasushi MIURA, who was a feudal retainer of the Kishu Domain, and fought a battle against Shinsengumi (group that guarded Kyoto during the end of Tokugawa Shogunate).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tenmanya Incident was an incident in which members of Kaientai (an association of roshi (masterless samurai) organized by Ryoma SAKAMOTO) (Roshi association) and Rikuentai (an association of roshi organized by Shintaro NAKAOKA) assaulted a hatago (inn with meals) on Aburanokoji-dori Street, Kyoto called Tenmanya, attacking Yasushi MIURA, who was a feudal retainer of the Kishu Domain, and fought a battle against Shinsengumi (group that guarded Kyoto during the end of Tokugawa Shogunate).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経緯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Circumstances</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Circumstances</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Circumstances</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>陸奥宗光は、当時有力な佐幕論者であった紀州藩士三浦休太郎が大垣藩井田五蔵らと共謀して京都にて不穏な動きをしていること、また、坂本龍馬、中岡慎太郎の暗殺（近江屋事件）が、伊呂波丸事件にて龍馬に恨みを持つ紀州藩が黒幕であるとの話を聞いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Munemitsu MUTSU heard that Kyutaro MIURA, a feudal retainer of Kishu Domain, who was an influential supporter of the bakufu, together with Itsuzo IDA of Ogaki Domain and others were plotting something threatening and that the Kishu Clan was the mastermind of the assassinations of Ryoma SAKAMOTO and Shintaro NAKAOKA (Omiya Incident), which occurred in retaliation for Iroha Maru Incident from which they had a grudge against Ryoma.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Munemitsu MUTSU heard that Kyutaro MIURA, a feudal retainer of the Kishu Domain, who was an influential supporter of the bakufu, together with Itsuzo IDA of the Ogaki Domain and others were plotting something threatening and that the Kishu Clan was the mastermind of the assassinations of Ryoma SAKAMOTO and Shintaro NAKAOKA (Omiya Incident), which occurred in retaliation for the Iroha Maru Incident from which they had a grudge against Ryoma.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Munemitsu MUTSU heard that Kyutaro MIURA, a feudal retainer of the Kishu Domain, who was an influential supporter of the bakufu, together with Itsuzo IDA of the Ogaki Domain and others were plotting something threatening in Kyoto and that the Kishu clan was the mastermind of the assassinations of Ryoma SAKAMOTO and Shintaro NAKAOKA (Omiya Incident), which occurred in retaliation for the Iroha Maru Incident from which they had a grudge against Ryoma.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>紀州藩公用人であった三浦休太郎を討つことを海援隊士/陸援隊士らと計画する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He planned to kill Kyutaro MIURAl, who was a koyonin of the Kishu Clan, with members of Kaientai and Rikuentai.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He planned to kill Kyutaro MIURAl, who was a koyonin of the Kishu Clan, with members of Kaientai and Rikuentai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He planned to kill Kyutaro MIURA, who was a koyonin of the Kishu clan, with members of Kaientai and Rikuentai.</e>
<cmt>用語統一人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>危険を感じた紀州藩は、会津藩を通して新選組に三浦の警護を依頼した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kishu Clan, which sensed the danger, asked Shinsengumi through the Aizu Clan to protect MIURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kishu Clan, which sensed the danger, asked Shinsengumi through the Aizu Clan to protect MIURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kishu clan, which sensed the danger, asked Shinsengumi through the Aizu Clan to protect Miura.</e>
<cmt>用語統一人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>天満屋で三浦休太郎の護衛に新選組の斎藤一、大石鍬次郎ら7名がついた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Tenmanya, Kyutaro MIURA had as his bodyguard seven Shinsengumi members including Hajime SAITO and Kuwajiro OISHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At Tenmanya, Kyutaro MIURA had as his bodyguard seven Shinsengumi members including Hajime SAITO and Kuwajiro OISHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At Tenmanya, Kyutaro MIURA had as his bodyguard seven Shinsengumi members including Hajime SAITO and Kuwajiro OISHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>慶応3年12月7日 (旧暦)（1868年1月1日）、海援隊/陸援隊士ら総勢16名(15名とも)が、三浦休太郎、新選組らが天満屋2階にて酒宴を行っていたところを襲い、出会い頭に、十津川郷士の中井庄五郎が「三浦氏は其許か」というなり斬りつけ、三浦休太郎は、頬頤を負傷する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 1st, 1868, 16 members in total (or another theory has 15 members) of Kaientai and Rikuentai assaulted Kyutaro MIURA and Shinsengumi, who were having drinks on the second floor of Tenmanya, and Shogoro NAKAI, who was a samurai from Totsugawa area in Nara, slashed at Kyutaro MIURA, injuring him on his cheek and jaw, as he bumped into MIURA, asking &apos;Are you MIURA?&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 1st, 1868, 16 members in total (or another theory has 15 members) of Kaientai and Rikuentai assaulted Kyutaro MIURA and Shinsengumi, who were having drinks on the second floor of Tenmanya, and Shogoro NAKAI, who was a samurai from the Totsugawa area in Nara, slashed Kyutaro MIURA, injuring him on his cheek and jaw, as he bumped into MIURA, asking &apos;Are you MIURA?&apos;.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 1, 1868, 16 members in total (or another theory has 15 members) of Kaientai and Rikuentai assaulted Kyutaro MIURA and Shinsengumi, who were having drinks on the second floor of Tenmanya, and Shogoro NAKAI, who was a samurai from the Totsugawa area in Nara, slashed Kyutaro MIURA, injuring him on his cheek and jaw, as he bumped into MIURA, asking &apos;Are you MIURA?&apos;.</e>
<cmt>日付表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その後、入り乱れるが、燈火を消し、暗闇での戦闘となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following this, they fell in confusion but someone turned the lamp off and they fought in the dark.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following this, they fell in confusion but someone turned the lamp off and they fought in the dark.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following this, they fell in confusion but someone turned the lamp off and they fought in the dark.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>斎藤は後から斬りかかられ命を落としそうになったが梅戸勝之進（平隊士）が斎藤を守った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SAITO was slashed from behind and was on the verge of losing his life: however, Katsunoshin UMEDO (Hira taishi (common soldier)) saved him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SAITO was slashed from behind and was on the verge of losing his life: however, Katsunoshin UMEDO (Hira taishi (common soldier)) saved him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saito was slashed from behind and was on the verge of losing his life: however, Katsunoshin UMEDO (Hira taishi (common soldier)) saved him.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>変を聞きつけた新選組、紀州藩が援助に向かうが、着いた頃には、陸奥らは素早くその場を引き揚げていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinsengumi and the Kishu Clan, who heard about the attack, went to help them but when they arrived there MUTSU and the others had already left the scene.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinsengumi and the Kishu Clan, who heard about the attack, went to help them but when they arrived there MUTSU and the others had already left the scene.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinsengumi and the Kishu clan, who heard about the attack, went to help them but when they arrived there Mutsu and the others had already left the scene.</e>
<cmt>用語統一人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>この事件で襲撃側では中井庄五郎が死亡、負傷者2-3名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During this incident, Shogoro NAKAI died and a few others were injured on the attacker&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this incident, Shogoro NAKAI died and a few others were injured on the attacker&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this incident, Shogoro NAKAI died and a few others were injured on the attacker&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>新選組側は宮川信吉と舟津釜太郎が死亡、重傷1名、負傷者3名を出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinsengumi lost Nobukichi MIYAGAWA and Kamataro FUNAZU, and four others were injured, including one seriously.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinsengumi lost Nobukichi MIYAGAWA and Kamataro FUNAZU, and four others were injured, including one seriously.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinsengumi lost Nobukichi MIYAGAWA and Kamataro FUNAZU, and four others were injured, including one seriously.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>紀州側は、三浦は頬頤に傷を負い、三宅精一、関甚之助も軽傷を負った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the Kishu Clan, MIURA got injured on his cheek and jaw, and Seiichi MIYAKE and Jinnosuke SEKI were lightly hurt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the Kishu Clan, MIURA got injured on his cheek and jaw, and Seiichi MIYAKE and Jinnosuke SEKI were lightly hurt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the Kishu clan, Miura got injured on his cheek and jaw, and Seiichi MIYAKE and Jinnosuke SEKI were lightly hurt.</e>
<cmt>用語統一人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>京都市下京区油小路正面通の跡地には石碑が建てられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a stone monument of this incident on the alley of Aburakoji Shomen-dori Street, Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a stone monument of this incident on the alley of Aburakoji Shomen-dori Street, Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a stone monument of this incident on the alley of Aburakoji Shomen-dori Street, Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Lemon pie(id:66842), 目白梅(id:141468), Grooving(id:82884), Boa(id:20845), 松茸(id:27535), おきた(id:18906), Tast(id:29478), Maakun(id:16735), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>