<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>山城国一揆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Uprising in Yamashiro Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Uprising in Yamashiro Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Uprising in Yamashiro Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>山城国一揆（やましろのくにいっき）は、1485年（文明 (日本)17年）、山城国（現在の京都府南部）南半の上三郡（久世郡、綴喜郡、相楽郡）で起きた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamashiro no kuniikki (the uprising in Yamashiro Province) occurred in three southern counties (Kuse-gun, Tsuzuki-gun and Soraku-gun) of Yamashiro Province (currently the southern part of Kyoto Prefecture) in 1485.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamashiro no kuniikki (the uprising in Yamashiro Province) occurred in three southern counties (Kuse-gun, Tsuzuki-gun and Soraku-gun) of Yamashiro Province (currently the southern part of Kyoto Prefecture) in 1485.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamashiro no kuniikki (the uprising in Yamashiro Province) occurred in three southern counties (Kuse-gun, Tsuzuki-gun and Soraku-gun) of Yamashiro Province (currently the southern part of Kyoto Prefecture) in 1485.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>国人や農民が協力し、守護大名畠山氏の政治的影響力を排除し、以後8年間自治を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokujin (local samurai) and farmers cooperated to eliminate the political influence of the Shugo Daimyo (Military Governor) of the Hatakeyama clan, and governed by themselves for the next eight years.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokujin (local samurai) and farmers cooperated to eliminate the political influence of the Shugo Daimyo (Military Governor) of the Hatakeyama clan, and governed themselves for the next eight years.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Local samurais and farmers cooperated to eliminate the political influence of the shugo daimyo (military governor) of the Hatakeyama clan, and functioned as self-governing community for the succeeding eight years.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>山城国一揆の性格</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Characteristics of the uprising in Yamashiro Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Characteristics of the uprising in Yamashiro Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Characteristics of the uprising in Yamashiro Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>一般的に国人が起こした一揆のことを国一揆という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An uprising started by kokujin (local samurai) is generally called kuniikki (an uprising in a province).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An uprising started by kokujin (local samurai) is generally called kuniikki (an uprising in a province).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kuniikki&quot; (an uprising in a province) is an uprising staged by local samurais in general.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。Kuniikki にダブルクォーテーションを追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>山城国一揆は惣の農民らが参加している点で厳密には国一揆ではなく惣国一揆とでも言うべきものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Strictly speaking, the uprising in Yamashiro should be called as sokokuikki, not kuniikki, because the uprising was started by farmers in so (so village, which is a community consisting of peasants&apos; self-governing association).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Strictly speaking, the uprising in Yamashiro should be called sokokuikki, not kuniikki, because the uprising was started by farmers in so (so village, which is a community consisting of peasants&apos; self-governing association).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Strictly speaking, the uprising in Yamashiro Province was not a &quot;kuniikki&quot; but a &quot;sokoku ikki&quot;, because the uprising was started by farmers belonging to so (a community organized by a self-governing association of farmers).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。kuniikki および sokoku ikki にダブルクォーテーションを追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>山城国一揆の成立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The formation of the uprising in Yamashiro Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The formation of the uprising in Yamashiro Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of the uprising in Yamashiro Province</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>応仁の乱が終結した後も各地で守護大名同士の小競り合いは続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after the end of the Onin War, Shugo Daimyo (Military Governor) had continuous skirmishes with each other in various places.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after the end of the Onin War, Shugo Daimyo (Military Governor) had continuous skirmishes with each other in various places.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after the Onin War, the shugo daimyo had continuous skirmishes with each other throughout regions.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>南山城でも例外ではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minami-Yamashiro is not an exception.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minami-Yamashiro is not an exception.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minami-Yamashiro was not an exception.</e>
<cmt>過去形にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>畠山氏は跡目争いから畠山義就と畠山政長が争いを続けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Hatakeyama clan, Yoshinari HATAKEYAMA and Masanaga HATAKEYAMA continued to fight with each other because of a dispute about the succession.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Hatakeyama clan, Yoshinari HATAKEYAMA and Masanaga HATAKEYAMA continued to fight with each other due to a dispute over succession.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the Hatakeyama clan, Yoshinari HATAKEYAMA and Masanaga HATAKEYAMA had been at war with each other for a dispute over a matter of succession.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>1478年の畠山氏任命まで、本来、山城国には、名目上の守護しか置かれていなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only Shugo (Military Governor) had long been nominally appointed in Yamashiro Province until 1478 when the Hatakeyama clan was appointed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only Shugo (Military Governor) had long been nominally appointed in Yamashiro Province until 1478 when the Hatakeyama clan was appointed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until the time when the Hatakeyama clan was appointed in 1478, only a nominally appointed Shugo had served Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし同年後は本格的な領国化を目指す動きが盛んになっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, a movement for full territorialization became active.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, a movement for full territorialization became active.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the appointment of the Hatakeyama clan, however, a movement to become a fully independent territory started to intensify.</e>
<cmt>領国化はto become a fully independent territoryと訳しました。FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その中で繰り広げられた長年にわたる戦いで国人衆や農民は疲弊した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In such a movement, kokujin (local samurai) and farmers became impoverished due to the long-standing fight.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During such movements, kokujin (local samurai) and farmers became impoverished due to the long-standing fight.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, local samurais and farmers of the province became impoverished due to the long-standing fights.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>そして山城国一揆の土壌が整うこととなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Everything was ready for them to start an uprising in Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Everything was in place for the start of an uprise in Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such a circumstance prepared the backdrop for the uprising in Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>1485年、南山城の国人衆や農民らが宇治の平等院に集まり評定を持った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1485, local samurai and farmers in Minami-Yamashiro gathered in the Uji Byodoin Temple to conduct a conference.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1485, local samurai and farmers in Minami-Yamashiro gathered in the Uji Byodoin Temple to conduct a conference.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1485, local samurais and farmers in Minami-Yamashiro gathered in Byodoin Temple in Uji to conduct a conference.</e>
<cmt>一部表現を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>この評定で「国中掟法」を取り決め、両畠山氏の影響を排除し、南山城の自治を行うことを決めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the conference, they stipulated an autonomous law called Kunijuokite, and decided to eliminate the influence of both HATAKEYAMAs, and to govern by themselves in Minami-Yamashiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the conference, they stipulated an autonomous law called Kunijuokite, and decided to eliminate the influence of both HATAKEYAMAs, and to govern themselves in Minami-Yamashiro.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the conference, they stipulated an autonomous law called &quot;Kunijuokite&quot;, and decided to eliminate the influence of both HATAKEYAMAs in order for Minami-Yamashiro to become a self-governing community.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。ダブルクォーテーションを全角から半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>国人衆により政治がおこなわれ、南山城は惣国とよばれる政治形態となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a new regime, local samurai conducted the affairs of the province, and Minami-Yamashiro was called Sokoku (a federation of so villages).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the new regime, local samurai conducted the affairs of the province, and Minami-Yamashiro was called Sokoku (a federation of so villages).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The new regime of Minami-Yamashiro, where the local samurais conducted the affairs of the province, assumed a political form called &quot;Sokoku&quot; (a federation of so villages).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。Sokoku にダブルクォーテーションを追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>山城国一揆の崩壊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Collapse of the uprising in Yamashiro Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Collapse of the uprising in Yamashiro Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The end of the uprising in Yamashiro Province</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>室町幕府では、幕府のお膝元である山城国が有力守護の支配下に入る事を望んでいなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Government of Muromachi did not like Yamashiro Province, which was under the direct jurisdiction of the government, to be put under the direct control of an influential military governor.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Government of Muromachi did not like Yamashiro Province, which was under the direct jurisdiction of the government, to be put under the direct control of an influential military governor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) did not wish Yamashiro Province, which had been put under the direct jurisdiction of the government, to be taken over by and to be put under the direct control of an influential feudal lord.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>そのため、管領細川政元らは、この動きに対して静観の姿勢を取った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So, Shogunal Deputy Masamoto HOSOKAWA and others took a firm position against the movement.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So, Shogunal Deputy Masamoto HOSOKAWA and others took a firm position against the movement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For that reason, the Shogunal Deputy Masamoto HOSOKAWA and others remained a silent observer of the movement in Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="20">
<j>国人衆による政治は、国人と農民の対立、また国人同士の対立を生むことになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Politics administrated by local samurai created a conflict between local samurai and farmers, and a conflict among local samurai.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Politics administrated by local samurai created a conflict between local samurai and farmers, and a conflict among local samurai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The self-governance administrated by local samurais created conflicts between local samurais and farmers, as well as conflicts among themselves.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。themselv を themselves. に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>惣国は崩壊の兆しを見せ始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Sokoku (a federation of so villages) started showing signs of collapse.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Sokoku (a federation of so villages) started showing signs of collapse.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As such, the sokoku was starting to show signs of collapse.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>特に明応の政変による幕府内部の混乱は幕府有力者達による山城国人衆への切り崩し工作となって現れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially governmental disorder brought by the Coup of Meio prompted the government leaders to wipe out the local samurai of Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Governmental disorder brought by the Coup of Meio prompted the government leaders to wipe out the local samurai of Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The disorder within the bakufu brought by the Coup of Meio prompted the bakufu leaders to wipe out the local samurais of Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>1493年（明応2年）には自ら自治を放棄する集会を開き惣国は解体され、新しい守護の伊勢貞陸の支配下に入ることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1493, Sokoku held a rally to abandon its autonomy and disorganize itself, and it was put under the rule of Sadamichi ISE, a newly appointed Shugo Daimyo (Military Governor),</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some local samurai who opposed this resisted and locked themselves in Inayazuma-jo Castle. But they were defeated, and the uprising in Yamashiro Province ended completely.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1493, the sokoku held a meeting to abandon its autonomy and the organization was dismantled; the community was then put under the rule of Sadamichi ISE, a newly appointed shugo.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。「守護」 shugo daimyo のdaimyoを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>これに反対する一部の国人衆は稲屋妻城に立てこもって抵抗した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some local samurai who opposed to this resisted and locked themselves in Inayazuma-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some local samurai who opposed this resisted and locked themselves in Inayazuma-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some local samurais who opposed to this outcome resisted and locked themselves in protest inside the Inayazuma-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>しかし彼らは敗れ、ここに山城国一揆は完全に終結を見ることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But they were defeated, and the uprising in Yamashiro Province ended completely.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But they were defeated, and the uprising in Yamashiro Province ended completely.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were defeated, however, and the uprising in Yamashiro Province came to a complete end.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="26">
<j>研究・史料</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Research and historical materials</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Research and historical materials</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Research and historical materials</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>1912年に三浦周行が、論文「戦国時代の国民議会」でこの一揆を取り上げて以後、広く知られるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since 1912 when Hiroyuki MIURA covered the uprising in his research paper titled &quot;National Assembly in the Age of Civil War,&quot; the uprising started to draw attention widely.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since 1912 when Hiroyuki MIURA covered the uprising in his research paper titled &quot;National Assembly in the Age of Civil War,&quot; the uprise started to draw wide attention.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Hiroyuki MIURA presented this uprising in his research titled &quot;National Assembly in the Age of Civil War&quot; in 1912, the uprising in Yamashiro Province became widely-known.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。ダブルクォーテーションを全角から半角に修正しました。「でこの一揆」の訳漏れのため、this uprising in を追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), Oxhop(id:2551), 赤井彗星(id:18381), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Nnh(id:474), たね(id:10372), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), Extrahitz(id:26245), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>