<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>室町時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Muromachi Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Muromachi Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Muromachi Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>室町時代（むろまちじだい、1336年 - 1573年）は、室町幕府が存在した時代を指す日本の歴史の時代区分の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Muromachi period (1336-1573) is a period of Japanese history spanning the length of time the Muromachi bakufu (shogunate) was in existence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Muromachi period (1336-1573) is a period of Japanese history spanning the length of time the Muromachi bakufu (shogunate) was in existence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Muromachi period (1336-1573) is a period of Japanese history spanning the length of time the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) was in existence.</e>
<cmt>(shogunate)→(Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>名称は、京都の室町通に幕府が置かれていたことに由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name &quot;Muromachi&quot; was taken from Muromachi-dori (street) in Kyoto, which is where the bakufu was based.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name &quot;Muromachi&quot; was taken from Muromachi-dori (street) in Kyoto, which is where the bakufu was based.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name &quot;Muromachi&quot; was taken from Muromachi-dori (street) in Kyoto, which is where the bakufu was based.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>室町将軍家をはじめとする足利氏が政権を掌握していた時期であることから足利時代とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The period is sometimes also called the Ashikaga period, so named because during this period it was the Ashikaga clan--the most powerful Muromachi shogunal family--who held the reins of power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The period is sometimes also called the Ashikaga period, so named because during this period it was the Ashikaga clan--the most powerful Muromachi shogunal family--who held the reins of power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The period is sometimes also called the Ashikaga period, so named because during this period it was the Ashikaga clan--the most powerful Muromachi shogunal family--who held the reins of power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>1336年、足利尊氏が後醍醐天皇の南朝に対して北朝を擁立し室町幕府を開いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1336, Takauji ASHIKAGA, in opposition to the Southern Court of Emperor Go-Daigo, created the Northern Court and formed the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1336, Takauji ASHIKAGA, in opposition to the Southern Court of Emperor Go-Daigo, created the Northern Court and formed the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1336, Takauji ASHIKAGA, in opposition to the Southern Court of Emperor Godaigo, created the Northern Court and formed the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt>天皇表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>二つの朝廷が対立する南北朝時代 (日本)は1392年まで続き、北朝に統一された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nanbokucho period, during which two courts simultaneously existed, lasted until 1392, whereupon the Southern Court was unified into the Northern Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nanbokucho period, during which two courts simultaneously existed, lasted until 1392, whereupon the Southern Court was unified into the Northern Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), during which two courts simultaneously existed, lasted until 1392, whereupon the Southern Court was unified into the Northern Court.</e>
<cmt>南北朝表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>ここで最終的に武家が優位に立ったが、幕府の財政軍事基盤は弱かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it was at this point that the warrior clans finally reached the pinnacle of power, the bakufu&apos;s own financial and military power base was rather weak.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it was at this point that the warrior clans finally reached the pinnacle of power, the bakufu&apos;s own financial and military power base was rather weak.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it was at this point that the warrior clans finally reached the pinnacle of power, the bakufu&apos;s own financial and military power base was rather weak.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>この期間の政治体制は、中央政権たる室町幕府が上位に立ち、地域権力たる守護大名が幕府の監督下にありつつも、両者が相互補完的に政治的経済的支配を展開する室町幕府-守護体制として理解されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Muromachi bakufu, as the central administrative authority, enjoyed a preeminent position above everyone else, but the political system during the period was characterized more by the shugo daimyo, somewhat analogous to feudal barons in their control over their respective provincial areas, and though they were nominally under the direction of the bakufu, in practice the bakufu and the system of daimyo can be understood to have ruled jointly, with each mutually complementing the other in exercising and developing political and economic control.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Muromachi bakufu, as the central administrative authority, enjoyed a preeminent position above everyone else, but the political system during the period was characterized more by the shugo daimyo, somewhat analogous to feudal barons in their control over their respective provincial areas, and though they were nominally under the direction of the bakufu, in practice the bakufu and the system of daimyo can be understood to have ruled jointly, with each mutually complementing the other in exercising and developing political and economic control.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Muromachi bakufu, as the central administrative authority, enjoyed a preeminent position above everyone else, but the political system during the period was characterized more by the shugo daimyo, somewhat analogous to feudal barons in their control over their respective provincial areas, and though they were nominally under the direction of the bakufu, in practice the bakufu and the system of daimyo can be understood to have ruled jointly, with each mutually complementing the other in exercising and developing political and economic control.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>15世紀後半の応仁の乱ないし明応の政変以降は戦国時代 (日本)とも呼ばれ、それまでの「幕府 - 守護体制」が崩壊するとともに、各地に地域国家が並立するようになり、また、荘園公領制が崩壊した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Starting in the latter half of the fifteenth century, with the Onin war and the Meio Coup, a roughly hundred-year era known as the Sengoku (Warring States) period began; during this period, the bakufu-daimyo system in place up until this point collapsed, and all the various provinces essentially became independent states unto themselves, while the shoen-koryo (private estates and public territory) system of land ownership disintegrated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Starting in the latter half of the fifteenth century, with the Onin war and the Meio Coup, a roughly hundred-year era known as the Sengoku (Warring States) period began; during this period, the bakufu-daimyo system in place up until this point collapsed, and all the various provinces essentially became independent states unto themselves, while the shoen-koryo (private estates and public territory) system of land ownership disintegrated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Starting in the latter half of the fifteenth century, with the Onin War and the Meio Coup, a roughly hundred-year era known as the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) began; during this period, the bakufu-daimyo system in place up until this point collapsed, and all the various provinces essentially became independent states unto themselves, while the shoen-koryo (private estates and public territory) system of land ownership disintegrated.</e>
<cmt>the Sengoku (Warring States) period→the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States)統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>戦乱が続く時代だったが内外の通商は盛んで、農業・工業ともに技術が向上した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Despite being a period of continuous warfare and turmoil, both domestic and overseas trade flourished, and significant technological advances were made in both agriculture and industry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Despite being a period of continuous warfare and turmoil, both domestic and overseas trade flourished, and significant technological advances were made in both agriculture and industry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Despite being a period of continuous warfare and turmoil, both domestic and overseas trade flourished, and significant technological advances were made in both agriculture and industry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>この頃、西方では倭寇が朝鮮や中国を襲った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was from this time that Japanese pirates, known as &quot;Wako,&quot; in western Japan began raiding the coasts of Korea and China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was from this time that Japanese pirates, known as &quot;Wako,&quot; in western Japan began raiding the coasts of Korea and China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was from this time that Japanese pirates, known as &quot;Wako,&quot; in western Japan began raiding the coasts of Korea and China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概観</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Overview of the Muromachi period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Overview of the Muromachi period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Overview of the Muromachi period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>広義には足利尊氏が1336年（建武 (日本)3年）に建武式目を制定し、1338年に正式に京都に幕府を開いてから、15代将軍足利義昭が1573年に織田信長によって追放されるまでの235年間の足利将軍の存続期間を指すのが一般的であるが、前期を南北朝時代 (日本)、後期を戦国時代 (日本)とそれぞれ区分して、南北朝合一から明応の政変（あるいは応仁の乱）までを狭義の室町時代とする場合も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the broadest sense, the term &quot;Muromachi period&quot; refers to the 235-year span during which the country was at least nominally ruled by an Ashikaga Shogun, beginning when Takauji ASHIKAGA enacted the Kemmu Code in 1336 before formally creating the bakufu in Kyoto in 1338, and ending when Nobunaga ODA exiled the fifteenth Shogun, Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, in 1573; however, both the early and late stages of the Muromachi period can also be classified as the Nanbokucho and Sengoku periods, respectively, so many favor a narrower definition of the Muromachi period, in which it is limited to the span from the unification of the two courts (in 1392) until the outbreak of the Meio Coup (in 1492, or alternatively the outbreak of the Onin war in 1467).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the broadest sense, the term &quot;Muromachi period&quot; refers to the 235-year span during which the country was at least nominally ruled by an Ashikaga Shogun, beginning when Takauji ASHIKAGA enacted the Kemmu Code in 1336 before formally creating the bakufu in Kyoto in 1338, and ending when Nobunaga ODA exiled the fifteenth Shogun, Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, in 1573; however, both the early and late stages of the Muromachi period can also be classified as the Nanbokucho and Sengoku periods, respectively, so many favor a narrower definition of the Muromachi period, in which it is limited to the span from the unification of the two courts (in 1392) until the outbreak of the Meio Coup (in 1492, or alternatively the outbreak of the Onin war in 1467).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the broadest sense, the term &quot;Muromachi period&quot; refers to the 235-year span during which the country was at least nominally ruled by an Ashikaga Shogun, beginning when Takauji ASHIKAGA enacted the Kenmu Code in 1336 before formally creating the bakufu in Kyoto in 1338, and ending when Nobunaga ODA exiled the fifteenth Shogun, Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, in 1573; however, both the early and late stages of the Muromachi period can also be classified as the Northern and Southern Courts (Nanbokucho) (Japan) and Sengoku periods, respectively, so many favor a narrower definition of the Muromachi period, in which it is limited to the span from the unification of the two courts (in 1392) until the outbreak of the Meio Coup (in 1492, or alternatively the outbreak of the Onin War in 1467).</e>
<cmt>南北朝表記次のセルの用語と合わせるため、例外的に(Nanbokucho) を補足スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>狭義の室町時代については、時代的に一体化している南北朝時代と併せて南北朝・室町時代と総称されることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concerning this narrower definition of the Muromachi period, some prefer to combine the two period names, Nanbokucho and Muromachi, to create a general term, the &quot;Nanbokucho-Muromachi period.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concerning this narrower definition of the Muromachi period, some prefer to combine the two period names, Nanbokucho and Muromachi, to create a general term, the &quot;Nanbokucho-Muromachi period.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concerning this narrower definition of the Muromachi period, some prefer to combine the two period names, Nanbokucho and Muromachi, to create a general term, the &quot;Nanbokucho-Muromachi period.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>3代将軍足利義満が京都室町に花の御所を造営し歴代将軍が住んだ事から、足利将軍の事を室町殿（むろまちどの）と呼び、後に幕府を室町幕府、時代を室町時代と呼ぶようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The third Shogun, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, had a shogunal palace, the Hana no Gosho (Flower Palace) built for himself on Muromachi street in Kyoto, and successive generations of Shogun continued living there, leading to the Ashikaga Shoguns being called &quot;Muromachi-dono&quot; (the Lord of Muromachi), which led in turn to the bakufu being called the &quot;Muromachi bakufu,&quot; and the period the &quot;Muromachi period.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The third Shogun, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, had a shogunal palace, the Hana no Gosho (Flower Palace) built for himself on Muromachi street in Kyoto, and successive generations of Shogun continued living there, leading to the Ashikaga Shoguns being called &quot;Muromachi-dono&quot; (the Lord of Muromachi), which led in turn to the bakufu being called the &quot;Muromachi bakufu,&quot; and the period the &quot;Muromachi period.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The third Shogun, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, had a shogunal palace, the Hana no Gosho (Flower Palace) built for himself on Muromachi street in Kyoto, and successive generations of Shogun continued living there, leading to the Ashikaga Shoguns being called &quot;Muromachi-dono&quot; (the Lord of Muromachi), which led in turn to the bakufu being called the &quot;Muromachi bakufu,&quot; and the period the &quot;Muromachi period.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>なお、この時代はまだ「幕府」という名称は武家政権を指す言葉としては定着しておらず、当時の人々は室町政権を「室町幕府」という名詞で呼んだことはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In actuality, the term &quot;bakufu&quot; to indicate a military government had not yet been established during this period, meaning that no one during the Muromachi period actually called the Muromachi government the &quot;Muromachi bakufu.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In actuality, the term &quot;bakufu&quot; to indicate a military government had not yet been established during this period, meaning that no one during the Muromachi period actually called the Muromachi government the &quot;Muromachi bakufu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In actuality, the term &apos;bakufu&apos; to indicate a military government had not yet been established during this period, meaning that no one during the Muromachi period actually called the Muromachi government the &quot;Muromachi bakufu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>室町時代は、3代征夷大将軍足利義満の時代の全盛を除いて戦乱と無秩序の時代であったが、鎌倉時代以前には見られない、出自不明の農民・商人層の社会進出を可能とし、日本史上、初めて人間の顔が見える人物を登場させた時代でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aside from the golden age of prosperity reached under the third Sei-i taishogun (Shogun) Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, the Muromachi period was fraught with wars and disorder, but on the other hand, not since before the Kamakura period had there been such opportunity for common people of obscure origins, farmers and tradesmen, to advance socially, and among all the eras of Japanese history, the Muromachi period was the first to produce notable people whose faces and lives appear in clear focus to later eyes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aside from the golden age of prosperity reached under the third Sei-i taishogun (Shogun) Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, the Muromachi period was fraught with wars and disorder, but on the other hand, not since before the Kamakura period had there been such opportunity for common people of obscure origins, farmers and tradesmen, to advance socially, and among all the eras of Japanese history, the Muromachi period was the first to produce notable people whose faces and lives appear in clear focus to later eyes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aside from the golden age of prosperity reached under the third seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, the Muromachi period was fraught with wars and disorder, but on the other hand, not since before the Kamakura period had there been such opportunity for common people of obscure origins, farmers and tradesmen, to advance socially, and among all the eras of Japanese history, the Muromachi period was the first to produce notable people whose faces and lives appear in clear focus to later eyes.</e>
<cmt>Sei-i taishogun (Shogun)→seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>室町時代は一般的に旧勢力の没落と新勢力の興隆の時代として捉えることができる（→下克上）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Muromachi period can also be perceived, in general, as an era in which the ancient bastions of power collapsed and new powers rose to prosperity (via gekokujo, the phenomenon of &quot;the lower overthrowing the higher&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Muromachi period can also be perceived, in general, as an era in which the ancient bastions of power collapsed and new powers rose to prosperity (via gekokujo, the phenomenon of &quot;the lower overthrowing the higher&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Muromachi period can also be perceived, in general, as an era in which the ancient bastions of power collapsed and new powers rose to prosperity (via gekokujo, the phenomenon of &quot;the lower overthrowing the higher&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>その初期、古代的な天皇親政を理想とする後醍醐天皇と現状重視の尊氏を中心とした勢力が対立した（南北朝時代 (日本)）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In its early years, the period was characterized in particular by the conflict between Emperor Go-Daigo, who dreamed of reinstituting the ancient custom of direct Imperial rule, and Takauji, who placed more emphasis on preserving the status quo (this being the essence of the Nanbokucho period).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In its early years, the period was characterized in particular by the conflict between Emperor Go-Daigo, who dreamed of reinstituting the ancient custom of direct Imperial rule, and Takauji, who placed more emphasis on preserving the status quo (this being the essence of the Nanbokucho period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In its early years, the period was characterized in particular by the conflict between Emperor Godaigo, who dreamed of reinstituting the ancient custom of direct Imperial rule, and Takauji, who placed more emphasis on preserving the status quo (this being the essence of the Northern and Southern Courts).</e>
<cmt>南北朝表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>その後、義満の時代に国内は安定したものの、応仁の乱をへて全国動乱の時代（戦国時代）を迎え荘園公領制が崩壊して新秩序が成立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, while in Yoshimitsu&apos;s time the country was pacified, following the Onin war the entire country became engulfed in strife (the Sengoku period) and as the shoen-koryo system fell apart, a new system came into existence to replace it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, while in Yoshimitsu&apos;s time the country was pacified, following the Onin war the entire country became engulfed in strife (the Sengoku period) and as the shoen-koryo system fell apart, a new system came into existence to replace it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, while in Yoshimitsu&apos;s time the country was pacified, following the Onin War the entire country became engulfed in strife (the Sengoku period) and as the shoen-koryo system fell apart, a new system came into existence to replace it.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>概説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">General outline</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">General outline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>&quot;General outline&quot; -&gt; &quot;Summary&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>室町幕府成立から足利義満時代まで</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The period from the establishment of the Muromachi bakufu to the time of Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The period from the establishment of the Muromachi bakufu to the time of Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The period from the establishment of the Muromachi bakufu to the time of Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>足利尊氏が後醍醐天皇の建武の新政を打倒し、持明院統の光明天皇より征夷大将軍の宣下を受け正式に幕府を開く一方、後醍醐天皇は京都を脱出して吉野に吉野朝廷を開き、北朝と南朝が両立する南北朝時代がはじまる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji ASHIKAGA crushed Emperor Go-Daigo&apos;s Kemmu Restoration, and after being appointed Shogun by Emperor Kogon of the Jimyoin lineage, he formally established his bakufu (shogunate); Emperor Go-Daigo, on the other hand, escaped from Kyoto and established a new imperial court at Yoshino, ushering in the Nanbokucho period--the period during which both the Northern and Southern Courts existed simultaneously.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji ASHIKAGA crushed Emperor Go-Daigo&apos;s Kemmu Restoration, and after being appointed Shogun by Emperor Kogon of the Jimyoin lineage, he formally established his bakufu (shogunate); Emperor Go-Daigo, on the other hand, escaped from Kyoto and established a new imperial court at Yoshino, ushering in the Nanbokucho period--the period during which both the Northern and Southern Courts existed simultaneously.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji ASHIKAGA crushed Emperor Godaigo&apos;s Kenmu Restoration, and after being appointed Shogun by Emperor Kogon of the Jimyoin lineage, he formally established his bakufu; Emperor Godaigo, on the other hand, escaped from Kyoto and established a new imperial court at Yoshino, ushering in the Northern and Southern Courts period--the period during which both the Northern and Southern Courts existed simultaneously.</e>
<cmt>天皇表記スペル (shogunate)削除南北朝表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>南朝は後醍醐の死後に衰微するが、足利家内部の対立が全国規模に広がる観応の擾乱が起こると南朝は息を吹き返した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Go-Daigo&apos;s death (in 1339) the Southern Court&apos;s power and influence waned, but internecine strife within the Ashikaga family led to the Kanno Disturbance, which eventually widened in scope to engulf the entire country, and this brought the Southern Court a reprieve, revitalizing it.</e>
<cmt>Including the date here is important in helping to explain how and why the history of the period unfolded as it did.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Go-Daigo&apos;s death (in 1339) the Southern Court&apos;s power and influence waned, but internecine strife within the Ashikaga family led to the Kanno Disturbance, which eventually widened in scope to engulf the entire country, and this brought the Southern Court a reprieve, revitalizing it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Godaigo&apos;s death (in 1339) the Southern Court&apos;s power and influence waned, but internecine strife within the Ashikaga family led to the Kanno Disturbance, which eventually widened in scope to engulf the entire country, and this brought the Southern Court a reprieve, revitalizing it.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>そして、2代将軍足利義詮の時代には幕府内部の権力抗争により細川清氏などの有力守護大名が南朝に降ったり、九州では足利直冬が幕府に反抗したり、後醍醐の皇子である懐良親王が中国の明朝より「日本国王」として冊封を受けて南朝勢力を拡大するなど、南北朝の抗争は3代将軍足利義満が南北朝合体を行うまで続く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And then, during the time of the second Shogun, Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA, a power struggle within the bakufu prompted several influential shugo daimyo, including Kiyouji HOSOKAWA, to defect to the Southern Court, while in Kyushu Tadafuyu ASHIKAGA raised arms against the bakufu and the imperial prince Kaneyoshi, Go-Daigo&apos;s son and heir, received an official missive, in which he was called the &apos;King of Japan,&apos; from the Ming court of China; these and other events served to boost the Southern Court&apos;s power and prestige, which allowed the Southern Court to continue its resistance until the third Shogun, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, unified the Northern and Southern Courts (in 1392).</e>
<cmt>I feel it&apos;s important to include the date at which such a seminal event as the unification happened.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And then, during the time of the second Shogun, Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA, a power struggle within the bakufu prompted several influential shugo daimyo, including Kiyouji HOSOKAWA, to defect to the Southern Court, while in Kyushu Tadafuyu ASHIKAGA raised arms against the bakufu and the imperial prince Kaneyoshi, Go-Daigo&apos;s son and heir, received an official missive, in which he was called the &apos;King of Japan,&apos; from the Ming court of China; these and other events served to boost the Southern Court&apos;s power and prestige, which allowed the Southern Court to continue its resistance until the third Shogun, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, unified the Northern and Southern Courts (in 1392).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And then, during the time of the second Shogun, Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA, a power struggle within the bakufu prompted several influential shugo daimyo, including Kiyouji HOSOKAWA, to defect to the Southern Court, while in Kyushu Tadafuyu ASHIKAGA raised arms against the bakufu and the Imperial Prince Kaneyoshi, Godaigo&apos;s son and heir, received an official missive, in which he was called the &apos;King of Japan,&apos; from the Ming court of China; these and other events served to boost the Southern Court&apos;s power and prestige, which allowed the Southern Court to continue its resistance until the third Shogun, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, unified the Northern and Southern Courts (in 1392).</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>足利義満・義持時代と幕府権力の確立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bakufu&apos;s grip on power tightens during Yoshimitsu and Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA&apos;s reigns</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bakufu&apos;s grip on power tightens during Yoshimitsu and Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA&apos;s reigns</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bakufu&apos;s grip on power tightens during Yoshimitsu and Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA&apos;s reigns</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>2代将軍足利義詮が死去すると、管領細川頼之は3代将軍足利義満を補佐して執政をはじめ、楠木正儀を寝返らせるなど対南朝工作や九州の南朝勢力排除のための今川貞世派遣、内政においては新興の禅宗である南禅寺と旧仏教勢力の比叡山との対立問題の対応や半済の実施などを行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the second Shogun, Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA, died, the Kanrei (regent) Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA give his support and advice to Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, the third Shogun, and helped usher in a new administration, and engineered Masanori KUSUNOKI&apos;s defection and other anti-Southern Court efforts as well as dispatched Sadayo IMAGAWA to Kyushu as part of a push to eliminate the Southern Court&apos;s forces there, while in domestic, nonmilitary affairs, he crafted a response to the problematic conflict between Nanzenji temple, which represented the new Zen sect, and Mt. Hiei, representing the old guard of influential Buddhist temples, and also implemented the hanzei (half-tax).</e>
<cmt>・　()の説明は三省堂・大辞林の「半済」項目一部を訳したものです。・　日本語で単に「比叡山」という場合、「延暦寺」が省略された形であり、山より寺院を指すと思われるので、比叡山の対訳には「延暦寺」まで含めました。(比叡山延暦寺のウェブページhttp://www.hieizan.or.jp/enryakuji/econt/index.htmlでは単に&quot;Hieizan Enryakuji&quot;となっていました）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the second Shogun, Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA, died, the Kanrei (regent) Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA gave his support and advice to Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, the third Shogun, and helped usher in a new administration, and engineered Masanori KUSUNOKI&apos;s defection and other anti-Southern Court efforts as well as dispatching Sadayo IMAGAWA to Kyushu as part of a push to eliminate the Southern Court&apos;s forces there, while in domestic, nonmilitary affairs, he crafted a response to the problematic conflict between Nanzenji temple, which represented the new Zen sect, and Mt. Hiei, representing the old guard of influential Buddhist temples, and also implemented the hanzei (half-tax).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the second Shogun, Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA, died, the Kanrei (regent) Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA gave his support and advice to Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, the third Shogun, and helped usher in a new administration, and engineered Masanori KUSUNOKI&apos;s defection and other anti-Southern Court efforts as well as dispatching Sadayo IMAGAWA to Kyushu as part of a push to eliminate the Southern Court&apos;s forces there, while in domestic, nonmilitary affairs, he crafted a response to the problematic conflict between Nanzen-ji Temple, which represented the new Zen sect, and Mt. Hiei, representing the old guard of influential Buddhist temples, and also implemented the hanzei (half-tax).</e>
<cmt>寺表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>1379年には斯波氏のクーデターで細川頼之が失脚させられる康暦の政変と呼ばれる政変が起き、後任には斯波義将が就任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But in 1379, the Shiba clan launched a coup d&apos;etat, which came to be called the Koryaku coup, and as a result Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA lost his influence, replaced as Kanrei by Yoshimasa SHIBA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But in 1379, the Shiba clan launched a coup d&apos;etat, which came to be called the Koryaku coup, and as a result Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA lost his influence, replaced as Kanrei by Yoshimasa SHIBA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But in 1379, the Shiba clan launched a coup d&apos;etat, which came to be called the Koryaku Coup, and as a result Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA lost his influence, replaced as Kanrei by Yoshimasa SHIBA.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>義満は奉公衆と呼ばれる軍事力を整え、有力守護大名の山名氏や大内氏を挑発してそれぞれ明徳の乱、応永の乱で追討し、将軍権力を固めて、南北朝合一を行い天皇に迫る権力を確立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimitsu also formed an auxiliary military force, called the Hokoshu, and worked to provoke two influential shugo daimyo families, the Yamana clan in the Meitoku Rebellion and the Ouchi clan in the Oei Rebellion, successfully suppressing both, and thereby strengthened the power of the bakufu, managing to unify the Northern and Southern Courts and eventually superceding the emperor&apos;s authority.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimitsu also formed an auxiliary military force, called the Hokoshu, and worked to provoke two influential shugo daimyo families, the Yamana clan in the Meitoku Rebellion and the Ouchi clan in the Oei Rebellion, successfully suppressing both, and thereby strengthened the power of the bakufu, managing to unify the Northern and Southern Courts and eventually superceding the emperor&apos;s authority.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimitsu also formed an auxiliary military force, called the Hokoshu, and worked to provoke two influential shugo daimyo families, the Yamana clan in the Meitoku Rebellion and the Ouchi clan in the Oei Rebellion, successfully suppressing both, and thereby strengthened the power of the bakufu, managing to unify the Northern and Southern Courts and eventually superceding the emperor&apos;s authority.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>足利義満が急死すると、4代将軍の足利義持は斯波義将に補佐され、義満に対する太上天皇の追号を辞退し、勘合貿易での明との通商を一時停止するなど義満の政策を否定し幕政を守旧的なものに改める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA suddenly died, the fourth Shogun, Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA, was supported by Yoshimasa SHIBA, and refused to bestow the posthumous name of Emperor Daijo on Yoshimitsu; he also repudiated Yoshimitsu&apos;s policies, for example by temporarily halting the tally trade with Ming China, and sought to return the bakufu government to a more conservative stance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA suddenly died, the fourth Shogun, Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA, was supported by Yoshimasa SHIBA, and refused to bestow the posthumous name of Emperor Daijo on Yoshimitsu; he also repudiated Yoshimitsu&apos;s policies, for example by temporarily halting the tally trade with Ming China, and sought to return the bakufu government to a more conservative stance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA suddenly died, the fourth Shogun, Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA, was supported by Yoshimasa SHIBA, and refused to bestow the posthumous name of Emperor Daijo on Yoshimitsu; he also repudiated Yoshimitsu&apos;s policies, for example by temporarily halting the tally trade with Ming China, and sought to return the bakufu government to a more conservative stance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>これは貴族色が強まった義満晩年の政策に反感を抱く武士達の不満に応えたものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These measures were in response to the discontent felt by many warriors toward the policies, heavily favorable to the nobility, enacted by Yoshimitsu in his final years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These measures were in response to the discontent felt by many warriors toward the policies, which heavilty favored the nobility, enacted by Yoshimitsu in his final years.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These measures were in response to the discontent felt by many warriors toward the policies, which heavily favored the nobility, enacted by Yoshimitsu in his final years.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>1423年に実子の足利義量に将軍職を譲るが義量が早世し、さらに義持自身も後継者を決めないまま死去する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1423, he handed the position of Shogun over to his own child Yoshikazu ASHIKAGA, but Yoshikazu died young, and Yoshimochi himself died before he was able to choose a successor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1423, he handed the position of Shogun over to his own child Yoshikazu ASHIKAGA, but Yoshikazu died young, and Yoshimochi himself died before he was able to choose a successor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1423, he handed the position of Shogun over to his own child Yoshikazu ASHIKAGA, but Yoshikazu died young, and Yoshimochi himself died before he was able to choose a successor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>6代将軍は籤引きで選ばれる事とされ、義満の子で僧門に入っていた義円が還俗して将軍足利義教が将軍となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the end the sixth Shogun was chosen by lots: Gien, who was a child of Yoshimitsu that had joined the priesthood, returned to secular life and became Shogun Yoshinori ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end the sixth Shogun was chosen by lots: Gien, who was a child of Yoshimitsu that had joined the priesthood, returned to secular life and became Shogun Yoshinori ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end the sixth Shogun was chosen by lots: Gien, who was a child of Yoshimitsu that had joined the priesthood, returned to secular life and became Shogun Yoshinori ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>足利義教時代から応仁の乱まで</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The period from the reign of Yoshinori ASHIKAGA to the Onin War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The period from the reign of Yoshinori ASHIKAGA to the Onin War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The period from the reign of Yoshinori ASHIKAGA to the Onin War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>足利義満が南北朝合一を達成し幕府権力を絶大にしたものの、義満急死後は大名合議制に戻り相対的に将軍の権力も低下した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA had succeeded in unifying the two courts and solidifying the central power and authority of the bakufu, after his sudden death, the country returned to the old oligarchic daimyo system, and the power of the Shogun waned by comparison.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA had succeeded in unifying the two courts and solidifying the central power and authority of the bakufu, after his sudden death, the country returned to the old oligarchic daimyo system, and the power of the Shogun waned by comparison.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA had succeeded in unifying the two courts and solidifying the central power and authority of the bakufu, after his sudden death, the country returned to the old oligarchic daimyo system, and the power of the Shogun waned by comparison.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>更に民衆による土一揆の発生や後南朝による南朝再興運動など、幕府にとってはかつてない事態に遭遇するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, the bakufu encountered new problems never before seen, including the peasants&apos; uprisings that began to occur and efforts to restore the Southern Court by gonancho (former Southern Court forces).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, the bakufu encountered new problems never before seen, including the peasants&apos; uprisings that began to occur and efforts to restore the Southern Court by gonancho (former Southern Court forces).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the bakufu encountered new problems never before seen, including the peasants&apos; uprisings that began to occur and efforts to restore the Southern Court by gonancho (former Southern Court forces).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>そのような中で諸大名にとっても領国統治の必要上、将軍のこれ以上の権威の低下は避けたいとの思惑もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amidst such circumstances, even the daimyo wanted to avoid any further weakening of the bakufu&apos;s authority, since this authority was necessary for them to rule over their own territories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amidst such circumstances, even the daimyo wanted to avoid any further weakening of the bakufu&apos;s authority, since this authority was necessary for them to rule over their own territories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amidst such circumstances, even the daimyo wanted to avoid any further weakening of the bakufu&apos;s authority, since this authority was necessary for them to rule over their own territories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>比叡山座主であった足利義教がくじ引きで将軍になると、土岐氏・赤松氏・大内氏らの有力守護大名の後継争いに積極的に干渉し将軍権力の強化に努めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, the head priest of Enryakuji on Mt. Hiei, was chosen by lot to become Shogun, powerful daimyo families like the Toki, Akamatsu, and Ouchi clans actively interfered in the shogunal succession, trying to shore up the shogunal authority.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, the head priest of Enryakuji on Mt. Hiei, was chosen by lot to become Shogun, powerful daimyo families like the Toki, Akamatsu, and Ouchi clans actively interfered in the shogunal succession, trying to shore up the shogunal authority.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, the head priest of Enryakuji on Mt. Hiei, was chosen by lot to become Shogun, powerful daimyo families like the Toki, Akamatsu, and Ouchi clans actively interfered in the shogunal succession, trying to shore up the shogunal authority.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>更に幕府に反抗的だった鎌倉公方足利持氏を永享の乱で、その残党を結城合戦で討伐すると全国に足利将軍に表向きに刃向かう勢力は無くなり、一見社会は安定に向かうかに見えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Yoshinori defeated the Kubo (Commander) of Kamakura, Mochiuji ASHIKAGA, who had rebelled against the bakufu, in the Eikyo Rebellion, and the remnants of his faction in the battle of Musashino, thereby ridding the country of any force that could openly strike down the Ashikaga Shogun, at first glance restoring peace and stability to society.</e>
<cmt>（）内の説明は、三省堂大辞林の「鎌倉公方」項目を訳したものです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Yoshinori defeated the Kubo (Commander) of Kamakura, Mochiuji ASHIKAGA, who had rebelled against the bakufu, in the Eikyo Rebellion, and the remnants of his faction in the battle of Musashino, thereby ridding the country of any force that could openly strike down the Ashikaga Shogun, at first glance restoring peace and stability to society.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Yoshinori defeated the Kubo (Commander) of Kamakura, Mochiuji ASHIKAGA, who had rebelled against the bakufu, in the Eikyo Rebellion, and the remnants of his faction in the Yuki War, thereby ridding the country of any force that could openly strike down the Ashikaga Shogun, at first glance restoring peace and stability to society.</e>
<cmt>battle of Musashino→Yuki War</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>だが、余りにも強硬な政治姿勢が人々に「恐怖政治」との反発を抱かせ、やがて赤松満祐により義教が暗殺された（嘉吉の乱）をきっかけに将軍の力は衰えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But his mercilessly political stance caused a backlash among many, who harbored resentment against his &quot;reign of terror,&quot; and in the end he was assassinated by Mitsusuke AKAMATSU (in the Kakitsu Rebellion), which led to a steep decline in shogunal power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But his mercilessly political stance caused a backlash among many, who harbored resentment against his &quot;reign of terror,&quot; and in the end he was assassinated by Mitsusuke AKAMATSU (in the Kakitsu Rebellion), which led to a steep decline in shogunal power.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But his mercilessly political stance caused a backlash among many, who harbored resentment against his &apos;reign of terror,&apos; and in the end he was assassinated by Mitsusuke AKAMATSU (in the Kakitsu Rebellion), which led to a steep decline in shogunal power.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="35">
<j>その後は幼少の将軍が続いたため有力大名による合議で国が運営された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From that point on, the rank of Shogun was held by a series of young boys, and the actual administration of the country was run by a council of powerful daimyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From that point on, the rank of Shogun was held by a series of young boys, and the actual administration of the country was run by a council of powerful daimyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From that point on, the rank of Shogun was held by a series of young boys, and the actual administration of the country was run by a council of powerful daimyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>8代将軍・足利義政は芸術や建築に関しては優れた才覚の持ち主であったものの、政治的関心には乏しく、自然と政治は将軍の正室・日野富子や将軍側近、有力大名らによる権力抗争の場と化し、関東で鎌倉公方の復活を巡って生じた享徳の乱が発生しても、十分な対策を打とうとはしなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The eighth Shogun, Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, while exceptionally gifted in the arts and in architectural design, had little interest in politics, so it naturally fell to his lawful wife Tomiko HINO, his inner circle of advisors, and the most powerful daimyo to rule and to solve disputes over authority; and upon the outbreak of the Kyotoku Rebellion, in which some sought to revive the fortunes of the Kubo of Kamakura, they failed to respond with sufficient force.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The eighth Shogun, Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, while exceptionally gifted in the arts and in architectural design, had little interest in politics, so it naturally fell to his lawful wife Tomiko HINO, his inner circle of advisors, and the most powerful daimyo to rule and to solve disputes over authority; and upon the outbreak of the Kyotoku Rebellion, in which some sought to revive the fortunes of the Kubo of Kamakura, they failed to respond with sufficient force.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The eighth Shogun, Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, while exceptionally gifted in the arts and in architectural design, had little interest in politics, so it naturally fell to his lawful wife Tomiko HINO, his inner circle of advisors, and the most powerful daimyo to rule and to solve disputes over authority; and upon the outbreak of the Kyotoku Rebellion, in which some sought to revive the fortunes of the Kubo of Kamakura, they failed to respond with sufficient force.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="37">
<j>義政は子供に恵まれなかったために弟の足利義視を養子として後継者にする予定であったが、富子に息子・足利義尚が生まれると、後継者を巡って義視支持派と義尚支持派が対立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimasa was not fortunate enough to have any sons, so he adopted his younger brother Yoshimi ASHIKAGA and appointed him his heir, but when Tomiko gave birth to a son, Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA, two rival factions, the faction supporting Yoshimi and the one supporting Yoshihisa, came into conflict.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimasa was not fortunate enough to have any sons, so he adopted his younger brother Yoshimi ASHIKAGA and appointed him his heir, but when Tomiko gave birth to a son, Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA, two rival factions, the faction supporting Yoshimi and the one supporting Yoshihisa, came into conflict.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimasa was not fortunate enough to have any sons, so he adopted his younger brother Yoshimi ASHIKAGA and appointed him his heir, but when Tomiko gave birth to a son, Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA, two rival factions, the faction supporting Yoshimi and the one supporting Yoshihisa, came into conflict.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>前者は管領・細川勝元を後者は有力大名の山名持豊（宗全）を中心に擁して対立を深めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dispute intensified due to the actions of two opposing Kanrei (regents), the earlier being Katsumoto HOSOKAWA and the later being the powerful daimyo Mochitoyo YAMANA (Sozen).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dispute intensified due to the actions of two opposing Kanrei (regents), the earlier being Katsumoto HOSOKAWA and the later being the powerful daimyo Mochitoyo YAMANA (Sozen).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dispute intensified due to the actions of two opposing Kanrei (regents), the former being Katsumoto HOSOKAWA and the latter being the powerful daimyo Mochitoyo YAMANA (Sozen).</e>
<cmt>前者、後者修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>更に管領を輩出する畠山氏・斯波氏でも家督相続を巡る争いが発生して将軍後継者争いと連動を始めたことから問題は複雑化していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The conflict deepened still more after disputes arose within both the Hatakeyama and the Shiba clans, both families that had produced many Kanrei, over who should succeed to the headship of the clan, these new struggles combining with and further exacerbating the ongoing fight over the shogunal succession.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The conflict deepened still more after disputes arose within both the Hatakeyama and the Shiba clans, both families that had produced many Kanrei, over who should succeed to the headship of the clan, these new struggles combining with and further exacerbating the ongoing fight over the shogunal succession.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The conflict deepened still more after disputes arose within both the Hatakeyama and the Shiba clans, both families that had produced many Kanrei, over who should succeed to the headship of the clan, these new struggles combining with and further exacerbating the ongoing fight over the shogunal succession.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="40">
<j>やがて、両者の対立は全国の大名の兵力（享徳の乱の最中の関東を除く）を政治の中心地である京都に結集して遂に大規模な軍事衝突を引き起こしたこれが応仁の乱である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eventually, the conflict between each side led to all the daimyo in the country (except for daimyo from the Kanto during the Kyotoku Rebellion) concentrating their military forces in Kyoto, the governmental capital, until at last, with these large-scale armies in such proximity, armed conflict was inevitable, and the Onin war began.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eventually, the conflict between each side led to all the daimyo in the country (except for daimyo from the Kanto during the Kyotoku Rebellion) concentrating their military forces in Kyoto, the governmental capital, until at last, with these large-scale armies in such proximity, armed conflict was inevitable, and the Onin war began.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eventually, the conflict between each side led to all the daimyo in the country (except for daimyo from the Kanto during the Kyotoku Rebellion) concentrating their military forces in Kyoto, the governmental capital, until at last, with these large-scale armies in such proximity, armed conflict was inevitable, and the Onin War began.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>だが、大規模な軍事衝突にも関わらず、参加諸大名の士気は低く、かと言って勝利の際の利益配分を期待しなかったわけではないため、結果的に首都で延々と11年間も決着が付かない軍事衝突を断続的に行う事になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yet despite the enormous size of the armies involved, morale among the various participating daimyo was low; this wasn&apos;t to say that they weren&apos;t hoping to be rewarded if their side was victorious, but as a result of this situation, inconclusive and intermittent fighting ravaged the capital for the next eleven years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yet despite the enormous size of the armies involved, morale among the various participating daimyo was low; this wasn&apos;t to say that they weren&apos;t hoping to be rewarded if their side was victorious, but as a result of this situation, inconclusive and intermittent fighting ravaged the capital for the next eleven years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yet despite the enormous size of the armies involved, morale among the various participating daimyo was low; this wasn&apos;t to say that they weren&apos;t hoping to be rewarded if their side was victorious, but as a result of this situation, inconclusive and intermittent fighting ravaged the capital for the next eleven years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>そのため、義政がこれ以上の政治参加に倦んで義尚に突然将軍を譲って引退しても、また両軍の総大将である細川勝元・山名宗全が相次いで病死しても諸大名は兵を撤退させることは無かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This only caused Yoshimasa to lose what little interest he had left in politics, prompting him suddenly to relinquish the position of Shogun to Yoshihisa and retire, but the conflict between the two armies continued, and even after the successive natural deaths by illness of each army&apos;s supreme commanders, Katsumoto HOSOKAWA and Sozen YAMANA, the various daimyo did not withdraw their forces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This only caused Yoshimasa to lose what little interest he had left in politics, prompting him suddenly to relinquish the position of Shogun to Yoshihisa and retire, but the conflict between the two armies continued, and even after the successive natural deaths by illness of each army&apos;s supreme commanders, Katsumoto HOSOKAWA and Sozen YAMANA, the various daimyo did not withdraw their forces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This only caused Yoshimasa to lose what little interest he had left in politics, prompting him suddenly to relinquish the position of Shogun to Yoshihisa and retire, but the conflict between the two armies continued, and even after the successive natural deaths by illness of each army&apos;s supreme commanders, Katsumoto HOSOKAWA and Sozen YAMANA, the various daimyo did not withdraw their forces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>兵を撤退させる事になったのは、余りの長い戦争に耐え切れなくなった領国で不穏な動きが相次いだからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The daimyo did not actually withdraw their soldiers until successive uprisings and unrest broke out in their home territories due to war weariness from the cost of having to support a war for so long.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The daimyo did not actually withdraw their soldiers until successive uprisings and unrest broke out in their home territories due to war weariness from the cost of having to support a war for so long.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The daimyo did not in fact withdraw their soldiers until successive uprisings and unrest broke out in their home territories due to war weariness from the cost of having to support a war for so long.</e>
<cmt>actually -&gt; &quot;in fact&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="44">
<j>結果、応仁の乱は首都・京都を焦土としただけで何ら勝敗を決することなく終結したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hence, the Onin war ended without any sort of conclusive victory for either side; the only thing it had accomplished was the near-total destruction of the capital, Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hence, the Onin war ended without any sort of conclusive victory for either side; the only thing it had accomplished was the near-total destruction of the capital, Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hence, the Onin War ended without any sort of conclusive victory for either side; the only thing it had accomplished was the near-total destruction of the capital, Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>だが、この乱をきっかけにした戦闘は応仁の乱終結後も地方へと拡大し、関東の享徳の乱も更に10年近く戦いが継続された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the armed conflict that began in the Onin war spread out to more rural areas and continued even after the fighting petered out in the capital, and in the Kanto, the Kyotoku Incident extended the bloodshed for almost ten additional years after the Onin war ended.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the armed conflict that began in the Onin war spread out to more rural areas and continued even after the fighting petered out in the capital, and in Kanto, the Kyotoku Incident extended the bloodshed for almost ten additional years after the Onin war ended.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the armed conflict that began in the Onin War spread out to more rural areas and continued even after the fighting petered out in the capital, and in Kanto, the Kyotoku Incident extended the bloodshed for almost ten additional years after the Onin War ended.</e>
<cmt>スペルスペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="46">
<j>この争いによって幕府の政治的・経済的基盤は崩壊して将軍の権威は名目のみと化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Through this fighting, the political and economic foundation of the bakufu collapsed, and the once-powerful Shogun transformed into a mere figurehead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Through this fighting, the political and economic foundation of the bakufu collapsed, and the once-powerful Shogun transformed into a mere figurehead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Through this fighting, the political and economic foundation of the bakufu collapsed, and the once-powerful Shogun transformed into a mere figurehead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>だが、新将軍・義尚は若くして病死し、引退した父・義政も銀閣をはじめとする慈照寺の造営に余生を費やして、芸術の世界にのみ生きた（とはいえ、義政の芸術保護が後の東山文化発展の基礎となり、後々の日本文化に大きな影響を与えた事は否定できない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But the new Shogun, Yoshihisa, died of illnes while still young, and his retired father Yoshimasa devoted his remaining years to construction projects at Jishoji temple, notably the building known as Ginkaku (the Silver Pavillion), focusing his attention entirely on the world of artistic endeavor (and indeed, Yoshimasa&apos;s patronage of the arts became the foundation of the flourishing artistic culture of the Higashiyama area, and no one can deny he had a profound influence on later developments in Japanese culture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But the new Shogun, Yoshihisa, died of illnes while still young, and his retired father Yoshimasa devoted his remaining years to construction projects at Jishoji temple, notably the building known as Ginkaku (the Silver Pavillion), focusing his attention entirely on the world of artistic endeavor (and indeed, Yoshimasa&apos;s patronage of the arts became the foundation of the flourishing artistic culture of the Higashiyama area, and no one can deny he had a profound influence on later developments in Japanese culture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But the new Shogun, Yoshihisa, died of illness while still young, and his retired father Yoshimasa devoted his remaining years to construction projects at Jisho-ji Temple, notably the building known as Ginkaku (the Silver Pavilion), focusing his attention entirely on the world of artistic endeavor (and indeed, Yoshimasa&apos;s patronage of the arts became the foundation of the flourishing artistic culture of the Higashiyama area, and no one can deny he had a profound influence on later developments in Japanese culture.)</e>
<cmt>寺表記)補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="48">
<j>また、皮肉にもこれまで将軍の権威をないがしろにしてきた諸大名も将軍の権威が本当に失われてしまった事でそこに由来していた守護としての統治権そのものの権威までが失われてしまい、配下であった守護代や国人衆による下克上、更には加賀一向一揆や山城国一揆に代表される民衆の一揆からもその領国支配を脅かされるようになっていくのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, somewhat ironically, the very daimyo that had begun by making light of the Shogun&apos;s authority found that when that shogunal authority was truly lost, their own authority and sovereignty as shugo (governors) vanished, and many were overthrown by their deputies or by commoners from their provinces in the phenomenon known as gekokujo (the lower overthrowing the higher); worse yet, peasant uprisings and religious leagues, of which the Kaga Ikko Ikki (a religious league of commoners in Kaga) and a similar Ikki in Yamashiro province are representative examples, began to threaten the lords&apos; control over their lands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, somewhat ironically, the very daimyo that had begun by making light of the Shogun&apos;s authority found that when that shogunal authority was truly lost, their own authority and sovereignty as shugo (governors) vanished, and many were overthrown by their deputies or by commoners from their provinces in the phenomenon known as gekokujo (the lower overthrowing the higher); worse yet, peasant uprisings and religious leagues, of which the Kaga Ikko Ikki (a religious league of commoners in Kaga) and a similar Ikki in Yamashiro province are representative examples, began to threaten the lords&apos; control over their lands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, somewhat ironically, the very daimyo that had begun by making light of the Shogun&apos;s authority found that when that shogunal authority was truly lost, their own authority and sovereignty as shugo (governors) vanished, and many were overthrown by their deputies or by commoners from their provinces in the phenomenon known as gekokujo (the lower overthrowing the higher); worse yet, peasant uprisings and religious leagues, of which the Kaga Ikko Ikki (a religious league of commoners in Kaga) and a similar Ikki in Yamashiro Province are representative examples, began to threaten the lords&apos; control over their lands.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>戦乱の拡大と室町幕府の崩壊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wars and rebellions spread and the Muromachi bakufu collapses</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Spread of Wars and rebellions spread and the collapse of the Muromachi bakufu</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The spread of wars and rebellions and the collapse of the Muromachi bakufu</e>
<cmt>spread 削除語頭のみ大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="49">
<j>応仁の乱で将軍の権威は完全に失墜し幕府の権力は衰退したが、将軍の軍事的な実権はある程度保たれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Onin war completely eclipsed shogunal authority and stripped the bakufu of much of its power, but the Shogun was able to hold onto some measure of de facto authority through his military power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Onin war completely eclipsed shogunal authority and stripped the bakufu of much of its power, but the Shogun was able to hold onto some measure of de facto authority through his military power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Onin War completely eclipsed shogunal authority and stripped the bakufu of much of its power, but the Shogun was able to hold onto some measure of de facto authority through his military power.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>乱のあと、将軍の権威に変わる形で管領細川政元が絶大的な権力者として台頭するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the war, the Shogun&apos;s former authority transferred to the Kanrei Masamoto HOSOKAWA, who rose to prominence as a figure of tremendous power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the war, the Shogun&apos;s former authority transferred to the Kanrei Masamoto HOSOKAWA, who rose to prominence as a figure of tremendous power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the war, the Shogun&apos;s former authority transferred to the Kanrei Masamoto HOSOKAWA, who rose to prominence as a figure of tremendous power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>義尚の死後、将軍の座は義視の子・足利義稙が継承していたが、義材と対立した政元は、義材と結ぶ元管領畠山政長を討つと、明応の政変を引き起こして義材を追放して足利義澄を新将軍に擁立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following Yoshihisa&apos;s death, the position of Shogun passed to Yoshimi&apos;s son Yoshitane (more commonly known as &quot;Yoshiki&quot;) ASHIKAGA, but when Masamoto, who was embroiled in a conflict with Yoshiki, struck down the former Kanrei Masanaga HATAKEYAMA, who was allied with Yoshiki, the Meio Coup began; Yoshiki was driven into exile and Yoshizane ASHIKAGA was installed as the new Shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following Yoshihisa&apos;s death, the position of Shogun passed to Yoshimi&apos;s son Yoshitane (more commonly known as &quot;Yoshiki&quot;) ASHIKAGA, but when Masamoto, who was embroiled in a conflict with Yoshiki, struck down the former Kanrei Masanaga HATAKEYAMA, who was allied with Yoshiki, the Meio Coup began; Yoshiki was driven into exile and Yoshizane ASHIKAGA was installed as the new Shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following Yoshihisa&apos;s death, the position of Shogun passed to Yoshimi&apos;s son Yoshitane (more commonly known as &quot;Yoshiki&quot;) ASHIKAGA, but when Masamoto, who was embroiled in a conflict with Yoshiki, struck down the former Kanrei Masanaga HATAKEYAMA, who was allied with Yoshiki, the Meio Coup began; Yoshiki was driven into exile and Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA was installed as the new Shogun.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)の始まりは長らく応仁の乱がきっかけとされてきたが、今日では明応の政変をきっかけにして戦国時代が始まったとする説が有力になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The view that the Sengoku (Warring States) period began with the Onin war was the dominant one for a long time, but recently the view holding that the Sengoku period began with the Meio Coup has become more prevalent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The view that the Sengoku (Warring States) period began with the Onin war was the dominant one for a long time, but recently the view holding that the Sengoku period began with the Meio Coup has become more prevalent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The view that the Sengoku period began with the Onin War was the dominant one for a long time, but recently the view holding that the Sengoku period began with the Meio Coup has become more prevalent.</e>
<cmt>(Warring States)削除スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="53">
<j>家臣である管領が将軍を廃したこの事件によって政元は細川京兆家による管領職の世襲化と独占状態を確立し、さらに将軍の廃立権をも手中に収めたのだが、その天下も長くは続かなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With this coup, in which the Kanrei, a retainer of the Shogun, deposed the Shogun, Masamoto managed to create a hereditary monopoly over the position of Kanrei for his Keicho branch of the Hosokawa clan, and moreover arrogated to himself the right to depose and appoint the Shogun, but such a state of affairs did not continue for long.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With this coup, in which the Kanrei, a retainer of the Shogun, deposed the Shogun, Masamoto managed to create a hereditary monopoly over the position of Kanrei for his Keicho branch of the Hosokawa clan, and moreover arrogated to himself the right to depose and appoint the Shogun, but such a state of affairs did not continue for long.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With this coup, in which the Kanrei, a retainer of the Shogun, deposed the Shogun, Masamoto managed to create a hereditary monopoly over the position of Kanrei for his Keicho branch of the Hosokawa clan, and moreover arrogated to himself the right to depose and appoint the Shogun, but such a state of affairs did not continue for long.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>自らの後継者を巡る家中の内紛で殺害されたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was assassinated by members of his own family over who would be chosen as his successor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was assassinated by members of his own family over who would be chosen as his successor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was assassinated by members of his own family over who would be chosen as his successor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>以後、政元の養子である細川澄元と細川高国が後継管領を巡って争いを始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, the two candidates seeking to inherit the position of Kanrei, Masamoto&apos;s adopted sons Sumimoto and Takakuni HOSOKAWA, began to fight over who would be chosen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, the two candidates seeking to inherit the position of Kanrei, Masamoto&apos;s adopted sons Sumimoto and Takakuni HOSOKAWA, began to fight over who would be chosen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, the two candidates seeking to inherit the position of Kanrei, Masamoto&apos;s adopted sons Sumimoto and Takakuni HOSOKAWA, began to fight over who would be chosen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>これを知った前将軍義稙（義材改め）は、大内義興とともに上洛、細川高国の出迎えを受けて将軍位に復した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the former Shogun, Yoshitane (Yoshiki), learned of this internecine struggle in the Hosokawa clan, he marched on the capital together with Yoshioki OUCHI, and after receiving a welcome from Takakuni HOSOKAWA, he reclaimed his former position as Shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the former Shogun, Yoshitane (Yoshiki), learned of this internecine struggle in the Hosokawa clan, he marched on the capital together with Yoshioki OUCHI, and after receiving a welcome from Takakuni HOSOKAWA, he reclaimed his former position as Shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the former Shogun, Yoshitane (Yoshiki), learned of this internecine struggle in the Hosokawa clan, he marched on the capital together with Yoshioki OUCHI, and after receiving a welcome from Takakuni HOSOKAWA, he reclaimed his former position as Shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>だが、大内義興が本国情勢によって帰国すると、高国は亡命先で没した義澄の遺児足利義晴を新将軍に擁立して義稙と澄元連合軍を破った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But when Yoshioki OUCHI was forced to return to his home provinces due to unrest there, Takakuni took Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA, the orphan son of Yoshizumi, who had died in exile, and raised him up as the new Shogun, defeating the combined armies of Yoshitane and Sumimoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But when Yoshioki OUCHI was forced to return to his home provinces due to unrest there, Takakuni took Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA, the orphan son of Yoshizumi, who had died in exile, and raised him up as the new Shogun, defeating the combined armies of Yoshitane and Sumimoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But when Yoshioki OUCHI was forced to return to his home provinces due to unrest there, Takakuni took Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA, the orphan son of Yoshizumi, who had died in exile, and raised him up as the new Shogun, defeating the combined armies of Yoshitane and Sumimoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="58">
<j>最終的に澄元の子・細川晴元が高国を倒し、義晴を新将軍と認めその管領になる事で20年以上にわたる内紛に終止符を打った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the end, Takakuni was crushed by Sumimoto&apos;s son Harumoto HOSOKAWA, who forced all to acknowledge Yoshiharu as the new Shogun and took the position of Kanrei for himself, thereby putting an end to the internecine strife that had plagued the Hosokawa clan for over twenty years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end, Takakuni was crushed by Sumimoto&apos;s son Harumoto HOSOKAWA, who forced all to acknowledge Yoshiharu as the new Shogun and took the position of Kanrei for himself, thereby putting an end to the internecine strife that had plagued the Hosokawa clan for over twenty years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end, Takakuni was crushed by Sumimoto&apos;s son Harumoto HOSOKAWA, who forced all to acknowledge Yoshiharu as the new Shogun and took the position of Kanrei for himself, thereby putting an end to the internecine strife that had plagued the Hosokawa clan for over twenty years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>結局、一連の内紛で幕府そのものが衰微し京都周辺を収めるだけの地方政府へと転落し、辛うじて守護に代わって全国に割拠した戦国大名への権威付け機関としての存在感を示すだけのものと化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But as a result of this series of internal squabbles, the bakufu itself had fallen into decline, and was now capable of exerting control only over the area immediately surrounding Kyoto, transforming into an institution that just barely managed to take the place of the shugo and survive as the titular authority over the Sengoku-period daimyo who each struggled to defend his authority over his own territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But as a result of this series of internal squabbles, the bakufu itself had fallen into decline, and was now capable of exerting control only over the area immediately surrounding Kyoto, transforming into an institution that just barely managed to take the place of the shugo and survive as the titular authority over the Sengoku-period daimyo who each struggled to defend his authority over his own territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But as a result of this series of internal squabbles, the bakufu itself had fallen into decline, and was now capable of exerting control only over the area immediately surrounding Kyoto, transforming into an institution that just barely managed to take the place of the shugo and survive as the titular authority over the Sengoku-period daimyo who each struggled to defend his authority over his own territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="60">
<j>だが、晴元が政権獲得の最終段階で功臣・三好元長を殺害した事が後年大きく裏目に出る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Harumoto&apos;s murder of the meritorious retainer Motonaga MIYOSHI, who had climbed to the highest rungs of power within the government, had a profound backlash in later years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Harumoto&apos;s murder of the meritorious retainer Motonaga MIYOSHI, who had climbed to the highest rungs of power within the government, had a profound backlash in later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Harumoto&apos;s murder of the meritorious retainer Motonaga MIYOSHI, who had climbed to the highest rungs of power within the government, had a profound backlash in later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>元長の子である三好長慶兄弟が晴元に対して挙兵、晴元を追放して将軍足利義輝を傀儡化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagayoshi (Chokei) MIYOSHI, Motonaga&apos;s son, raised an army along with his brothers to hunt down Harumoto, who was driven into exile, while the Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA was converted into a mere puppet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagayoshi (Chokei) MIYOSHI, Motonaga&apos;s son, raised an army along with his brothers to hunt down Harumoto, who was driven into exile, while the Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA was converted into a mere puppet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagayoshi (Chokei) MIYOSHI, Motonaga&apos;s son, raised an army along with his brothers to hunt down Harumoto, who was driven into exile, while the Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA was converted into a mere puppet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>長慶は晴元の後任に傀儡の管領を立ててその職権を奪い、相伴衆の一員として幕政の全権を掌握した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chokei raised another puppet up to be Harumoto&apos;s successor as Kanrei, meanwhile usurping the Kanrei&apos;s authority himself, and managed personally to seize the full power and authority of the shogunal government from his position as one of the Shobanshu (Shogunal advisor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chokei raised another puppet up to be Harumoto&apos;s successor as Kanrei, meanwhile usurping the Kanrei&apos;s authority himself, and managed personally to seize the full power and authority of the shogunal government from his position as one of the Shobanshu (Shogunal advisor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chokei raised another puppet up to be Harumoto&apos;s successor as Kanrei, meanwhile usurping the Kanrei&apos;s authority himself, and managed personally to seize the full power and authority of the shogunal government from his position as one of the Shobanshu (Shogunal advisor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>だが、その晩年には重臣の松永久秀に実権を奪われて病没した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But in his later years he was robbed of any actual power by his chief retainer Hisahide MATSUNAGA, and died of illness soon after.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But in his later years he was robbed of any actual power by his chief retainer Hisahide MATSUNAGA, and died of illness soon after.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But in his later years he was robbed of any actual power by his chief retainer Hisahide MATSUNAGA, and died of illness soon after.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="64">
<j>この状況を見た将軍・義輝は上杉謙信（関東管領）をはじめとする親将軍家の戦国大名の支援を受けながら、将軍権威の再建に努めるが、その矢先松永一派のクーデター（永禄の変）によって暗殺された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shogun Yoshiteru observed these events and resolved, even as he accepted the support of Sengoku daimyo families closely allied with the Shogun, especially Kenshin UESUGI (the Kanrei of the Kanto region), to try to wrest back the power and prestige of the office of Shogun, only to be assassinated during a coup d&apos;etat (known as the Matsunaga Coup) by the faction led by Matsunaga, who was the primary target of Yoshiteru&apos;s efforts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shogun Yoshiteru observed these events and resolved, even as he accepted the support of Sengoku daimyo families closely allied with the Shogun, especially Kenshin UESUGI (the Kanrei of the Kanto region), to try to wrest back the power and prestige of the office of Shogun, only to be assassinated during a coup d&apos;etat (known as the Matsunaga Coup) by the faction led by Matsunaga, who was the primary target of Yoshiteru&apos;s efforts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shogun Yoshiteru observed these events and resolved, even as he accepted the support of Sengoku daimyo families closely allied with the Shogun, especially Kenshin UESUGI (the Kanrei of the Kanto region), to try to wrest back the power and prestige of the office of Shogun, only to be assassinated during a coup d&apos;etat (known as the Eiroku Incident) by the faction led by Matsunaga, who was the primary target of Yoshiteru&apos;s efforts.</e>
<cmt>Matsunaga Coup修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>その弟・足利義昭は管領斯波氏の元家臣織田信長の支援を受けて上洛して松永らを降伏させて将軍に就任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiteru&apos;s younger brother Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA--supported by Nobunaga ODA, a former vassal of the Kanrei Shiba clan--entered the capital and forced Matsunaga and his followers to capitulate before being appointed Shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiteru&apos;s younger brother Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA--supported by Nobunaga ODA, a former vassal of the Kanrei Shiba clan--entered the capital and forced Matsunaga and his followers to capitulate before being appointed Shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiteru&apos;s younger brother Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA--supported by Nobunaga ODA, a former vassal of the Kanrei Shiba clan--entered the capital and forced Matsunaga and his followers to capitulate before being appointed Shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>だが、やがて「天下布武」を唱えて新秩序形成を目指す信長と旧来の将軍・幕府中心の秩序の再建を目指す義昭は敵対し、1573年に義昭は信長によって京都を追放されて幕府組織は信長の築いた政治機構に解体・吸収された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But eventually, Nobunaga, who aimed to create a new system of government consistent with his motto of &quot;Tenka fubu&quot; (warriors rule all under heaven), and Yoshiaki, who was trying to revitalize the old system of Shogun and bakufu, were bound to become enemies, and in 1573 Yoshiaki was driven out of Kyoto by Nobunaga, and with this, the bakufu system was dismantled and absorbed into a new governmental system created by Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But eventually, Nobunaga, who aimed to create a new system of government consistent with his motto of &quot;Tenka fubu&quot; (warriors rule all under heaven), and Yoshiaki, who was trying to revitalize the old system of Shogun and bakufu, were bound to become enemies, and in 1573 Yoshiaki was driven out of Kyoto by Nobunaga, and with this, the bakufu system was dismantled and absorbed into a new governmental system created by Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But eventually, Nobunaga, who aimed to create a new system of government consistent with his motto of &apos;Tenka fubu&apos; (warriors rule all under heaven), and Yoshiaki, who was trying to revitalize the old system of Shogun and bakufu, were bound to become enemies, and in 1573 Yoshiaki was driven out of Kyoto by Nobunaga, and with this, the bakufu system was dismantled and absorbed into a new governmental system created by Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="67">
<j>その後も義昭は征夷大将軍職を解任されていない事を盾に各地で幕府再建運動を行うが、信長、そして豊臣秀吉による新秩序形成の勢いを前には全くの無力であり、義昭の京都追放の時点をもって室町幕府および室町時代の終期と看做されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, using the fact that Yoshiaki had never officially been dismissed from the post of Sei-i taishogun (Shogun) as a pretext, movements did arise in various provinces to restore the bakufu to power, but against the momentum of the new governmental structure created by Nobunaga and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, such efforts were entirely fruitless, and so the Muromachi bakufu--and the Muromachi period itself--is considered to have ended at the point Yoshiaki was driven from Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, using the fact that Yoshiaki had never officially been dismissed from the post of Sei-i taishogun (Shogun) as a pretext, movements did arise in various provinces to restore the bakufu to power, but against the momentum of the new governmental structure created by Nobunaga and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, such efforts were entirely fruitless, and so the Muromachi bakufu--and the Muromachi period itself--is considered to have ended at the point Yoshiaki was driven from Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, using the fact that Yoshiaki had never officially been dismissed from the post of Seii taishogun as a pretext, movements did arise in various provinces to restore the bakufu to power, but against the momentum of the new governmental structure created by Nobunaga and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, such efforts were entirely fruitless, and so the Muromachi bakufu--and the Muromachi period itself--is considered to have ended at the point Yoshiaki was driven from Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>(Shogun)削除ハイフン削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>→地方情勢については戦国時代 (日本)を参照</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For more information on circumstances in the provinces, see the article on the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For more information on circumstances in the provinces, see the article on the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For more information on circumstances in the provinces, see the article on the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>経済と社会</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Economy and society of the Muromachi period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Economy and society of the Muromachi period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Economy and society of the Muromachi period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>農業</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Agriculture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Agriculture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Agriculture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="69">
<j>鎌倉時代から農業生産力が向上する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Agricultural production began to increase starting in the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Agricultural production began to increase starting in the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Agricultural production began to increase starting in the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>西日本から関東地方に波及した二毛作の技術や牛馬耕、水車などを利用した灌漑施設の整備や肥料の発達などは生産力を向上させ、さらに農業技術の進歩で集約的・多角的な農業を行い、自立農民の成長を促して郷村制の成立をもたらす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">New agricultural techniques were gradually introduced to the Kanto from western Japan, including irrigation techniques that utilized the planting two crops a year, oxen and horses to plow, and water wheels, as well as increased production and use of manure fertilizer, leading to improved crop production; moreover, more concentrated and diverse agricultural efforts were launched thanks to advances in agricultural technology, which led to the development of a system of villages that spurred the growth of self-reliance among farmers.</e>
<cmt>（）内は三省堂・大辞林の「郷村」項目一部を訳したものです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">New agricultural techniques were gradually introduced to the Kanto from western Japan, including irrigation techniques that utilized the planting of two crops a year, oxen and horses to plow, and water wheels, as well as increased production and use of manure fertilizer, leading to improved crop production; moreover, more concentrated and diverse agricultural efforts were launched thanks to advances in agricultural technology, which led to the development of a system of villages that spurred the growth of self-reliance among farmers.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">New agricultural techniques were gradually introduced to the Kanto from western Japan, including irrigation techniques that utilized the planting of two crops a year, oxen and horses to plow, and water wheels, as well as increased production and use of manure fertilizer, leading to improved crop production; moreover, more concentrated and diverse agricultural efforts were launched thanks to advances in agricultural technology, which led to the development of a system of villages that spurred the growth of self-reliance among farmers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>手工業原料となる胡麻や桑、楮なども栽培される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Plants that served as the raw materials in handicraft industries, including sesame, mulberry, and paper mulberry (kaji), also started to be cultivated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Plants that served as the raw materials in handicraft industries, including sesame, mulberry, and paper mulberry (kaji), also started to be cultivated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Plants that served as the raw materials in handicraft industries, including sesame, mulberry, and paper mulberry (kaji), also started to be cultivated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>また、それまでは輸入に頼るのみであった木綿の栽培も16世紀頃から三河国地方において栽培されはじめる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And starting in the sixteenth century or thereabouts, cotton, which heretofore had had to be imported, began to be cultivated locally in Mikawa province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And starting in the sixteenth century or thereabouts, cotton, which heretofore had had to be imported, began to be cultivated locally in Mikawa province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And starting in the sixteenth century or thereabouts, cotton, which heretofore had had to be imported, began to be cultivated locally in Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>手工業</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Handicrafts</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Handicrafts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Handicrafts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="73">
<j>農民の自立が進むと、それまで宮廷に属していた工人も解放されて自立し、手工業が一般的に行われ市場が成立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As farmers made progress towards political independence, artisans also were freed from the control of the imperial court--which had dominated their livelihoods until this point--and achieved independence, leading to the general proliferation of handicrafts and the establishment of markets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As farmers made progress towards political independence, artisans also were freed from the control of the imperial court--which had dominated their livelihoods until this point--and achieved independence, leading to the general proliferation of handicrafts and the establishment of markets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As farmers made progress towards political independence, artisans also were freed from the control of the imperial court--which had dominated their livelihoods until this point--and achieved independence, leading to the general proliferation of handicrafts and the establishment of markets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>日用品や農具、織物や紙など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Products included everyday items, farming tools, textiles, and paper.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Products included everyday items, farming tools, textiles, and paper.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Products included everyday items, farming tools, textiles, and paper.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>今日各地方の特産物と呼ばれるものは室町時代が起源であるものも多く、京都の西陣では明から輸入した生糸を利用して高級織物である西陣織がつくられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of the products considered specialties of specific prefectures today have their origins in the Muromachi period, including Nishijin silks, luxury items that were made in the Nishijin district of Kyoto from raw silk imported from Ming China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of the products considered specialties of specific prefectures today have their origins in the Muromachi period, including Nishijin silks, luxury items that were made in the Nishijin district of Kyoto from raw silk imported from Ming China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of the products considered specialties of specific prefectures today have their origins in the Muromachi period, including Nishijin silks, luxury items that were made in the Nishijin district of Kyoto from raw silk imported from Ming China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>商業</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Commerce and trade</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Commerce and trade</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Commerce and trade</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="76">
<j>農業生産力の向上や手工業の独立は市場を成立させ、都市や交通の要地とされる場所では市場が発達した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Increased agricultural production and the growing independence of artisans caused markets to spring up and expand in places ideally situated for commerce between or within cities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Increased agricultural production and the growing independence of artisans caused markets to spring up and expand in places ideally situated for commerce between or within cities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Increased agricultural production and the growing independence of artisans caused markets to spring up and expand in places ideally situated for commerce between or within cities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>鎌倉時代の三斎市から月に6回定期的に開かれる六斎市など定期市や、都市部での見世棚をもった常設の店舗に、特定商品のみの卸売市場、卸売業を営む問屋も発生する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Market types ranged from the Kamakura-period Sansai markets, which were held three times a month, to Rokusai markets that were held regularly, six times a month, and in urban areas many types of stores sprang up, ranging from permanent shops with display shelves to wholesale markets and wholesale stores that sold only one specific product.</e>
<cmt>(）内はそれぞれ、三省堂・大辞林「三斎市」「六斎市」項目の一部を訳したものです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Market types ranged from the Kamakura-period Sansai markets, which were held three times a month, to Rokusai markets that were held regularly, six times a month, and in urban areas many types of stores sprang up, ranging from permanent shops with display shelves to wholesale markets and wholesale stores that sold only one specific product.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Market types ranged from the Kamakura-period Sansai markets, which were held three times a month, to Rokusai markets that were held regularly, six times a month, and in urban areas many types of stores sprang up, ranging from permanent shops with display shelves to wholesale markets and wholesale stores that sold only one specific product.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>行商人は連雀商人と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Traveling peddlers were called &quot;renjaku merchants&quot; (so named for their use of renjaku, a wooden frame for carrying goods on one&apos;s back).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Traveling peddlers were called &quot;renjaku merchants&quot; (so named for their use of renjaku, a wooden frame for carrying goods on one&apos;s back).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Traveling peddlers were called &quot;renjaku merchants&quot; (so named for their use of renjaku, a wooden frame for carrying goods on one&apos;s back).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>平安時代あたりから公家や寺社を本所として販売の独占権や関税の免除などの特権を得る座と呼ばれる閉鎖的な商業独占体制は、成長する戦国大名によって自営営業を許す楽市楽座によって廃止の方向へ向かう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From about the Heian period onwards, there was an insular, monopolistic system of commerce centered around the za (guilds), under which each za had exclusive rights to sell their products tax-free to specific noblemen and/or temples and shrines, but with the free market, open guild system introduced thanks to the rise of the sengoku daimyo, who started to allow independent (i.e., non-guild) businesses to be created, progress was made towards ending the oppressive guild system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From about the Heian period onwards, there was an insular, monopolistic system of commerce centered around the za (guilds), under which each za had exclusive rights to sell their products tax-free to specific noblemen and/or temples and shrines, but with the free market, open guild system introduced thanks to the rise of the sengoku daimyo, who started to allow independent (i.e., non-guild) businesses to be created, progress was made towards ending the oppressive guild system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From about the Heian period onwards, there was an insular, monopolistic system of commerce centered around the za (guilds), under which each za had exclusive rights to sell their products tax-free to specific noblemen and/or temples and shrines, but with the free market, open guild system introduced thanks to the rise of the sengoku daimyo, who started to allow independent (i.e., non-guild) businesses to be created, progress was made towards ending the oppressive guild system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>経済</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Muromachi economy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Muromachi economy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Muromachi economy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="80">
<j>標準貨幣は永楽通宝であったが、室町幕府は貨幣を鋳造せずに日明貿易で明銭を輸入して流通させていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The standard currency in use during the period was the Eiraku tsuho (Chinese Ming-dynasty copper coins); the Muromachi bakufu never minted its own coins, instead importing these Ming copper coins by means of Japan&apos;s trade with Ming China and then having them circulate.</e>
<cmt>（）内は三省堂・大辞林の「永楽銭」項目一部を訳したものです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The standard currency in use during the period was the Eiraku tsuho (Chinese Ming-dynasty copper coins); the Muromachi bakufu never minted its own coins, instead importing these Ming copper coins by means of Japan&apos;s trade with Ming China and then having them circulate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The standard currency in use during the period was the Eiraku tsuho (Chinese Ming-dynasty copper coins); the Muromachi bakufu never minted its own coins, instead importing these Ming copper coins by means of Japan&apos;s trade with Ming China and then having them circulate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>流通貨幣は不足しており私鋳銭など悪貨が流通しており、幕府は度々撰銭令で悪銭を指定し、流通貨幣との交換比率も定めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But the coins in circulation were insufficient, leading to the circulation of both privately minted and bad currency (which contained less than the full amount of copper), which prompted the bakufu to issue a series of laws singling out low-quality coins and banning them from use; the bakufu also set an exchange rate between the different currencies in circulation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But the coins in circulation were insufficient, leading to the circulation of both privately minted and bad currency (which contained less than the full amount of copper), which prompted the bakufu to issue a series of laws singling out low-quality coins and banning them from use; the bakufu also set an exchange rate between the different currencies in circulation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But the coins in circulation were insufficient, leading to the circulation of both privately minted and bad currency (which contained less than the full amount of copper), which prompted the bakufu to issue a series of laws singling out low-quality coins and banning them from use; the bakufu also set an exchange rate between the different currencies in circulation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>都市</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cities during the Muromachi period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cities during the Muromachi period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cities during the Muromachi period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="82">
<j>市場の成立や交通の整備は都市の発展を促す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The founding of and subsequent commerce at markets spurred cities to grow and develop.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The founding of and subsequent commerce at markets spurred cities to grow and develop.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The founding of and subsequent commerce at markets spurred cities to grow and develop.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>また、室町時代には伊勢詣や西国33ヵ所など寺社参りが流行し、応仁の乱の戦火などは各種都市の発達をもたらした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, during the Muromachi period the pilgrimage to the Grand Shrine at Ise, as well as the pilgrimage to the Thirty-Three Temples in Kinki with a statue of Avalokitesvara, were very much in vogue, and combined with the construction opportunities afforded by the fighting and conflagrations of the Onin War, this contributed to the growth and development of a wide variety of urban areas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, during the Muromachi period the pilgrimage to the Grand Shrine at Ise, as well as the pilgrimage to the Thirty-Three Temples in Kinki with a statue of Avalokitesvara, were very much in vogue, and combined with the construction opportunities afforded by the fighting and conflagrations of the Onin War, this contributed to the growth and development of a wide variety of urban areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, during the Muromachi period the pilgrimage to the Grand Shrine at Ise, as well as the pilgrimage to the Thirty-Three Temples in Kinki with a statue of Avalokitesvara, were very much in vogue, and combined with the construction opportunities afforded by the fighting and conflagrations of the Onin War, this contributed to the growth and development of a wide variety of urban areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>また、守護大名は城下町を整備。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, shugo daimyo began establishing and building castle towns.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, shugo daimyo began establishing and building castle towns.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, shugo daimyo began establishing and building castle towns.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>堺市（大阪府堺市）や博多（福岡県福岡市）などでは会合衆を中心に自治的な都市運営を行っており、応仁の乱以後は武装して防衛をしており自治的性格をもっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cities like Sakai (part of the Osaka metropolitan area today) and Hakata (the modern-day city of Fukuoka in Fukuoka Prefecture) were free cities self-governed largely by the egoshu, associations of merchants, and beginning with the Onin war, such cities armed themselves and bolstered their defensive capabilities, developing quite an autonomous, free spirit.</e>
<cmt>()内は三省堂・大辞林の「会合衆」項目一部を訳したものです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cities like Sakai (part of the Osaka metropolitan area today) and Hakata (the modern-day city of Fukuoka in Fukuoka Prefecture) were free cities self-governed largely by the egoshu, associations of merchants, and beginning with the Onin war, such cities armed themselves and bolstered their defensive capabilities, developing quite an autonomous, free spirit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cities like Sakai (part of the Osaka metropolitan area today) and Hakata (the modern-day Fukuoka City, Fukuoka Prefecture) were free cities self-governed largely by the egoshu, associations of merchants, and beginning with the Onin War, such cities armed themselves and bolstered their defensive capabilities, developing quite an autonomous, free spirit.</e>
<cmt>地名の表記スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>中世の代表的自治都市である堺は宣教師も「東洋のベニス」と評価する文書を残しており、織田信長に屈服するまで自治を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakai, a representative example of the free cities in the medieval period, was rated by missionaries in some surviving accounts as &quot;the Venice of the East,&quot; and continued its autonomy until it was later forced to capitulate to Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakai, a representative example of the free cities in the medieval period, was rated by missionaries in some surviving accounts as &quot;the Venice of the East,&quot; and continued its autonomy until it was later forced to capitulate to Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakai, a representative example of the free cities in the medieval period, was rated by missionaries in some surviving accounts as &apos;the Venice of the East,&apos; and continued its autonomy until it was later forced to capitulate to Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>同じく自治的性格を持っていのは、一向宗の寺院を中心に形成された寺内町である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A similar style of autonomy could be seen in the character of Jinaicho (temple towns), religious communities that coalesced around temples of the Ikko sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A similar style of autonomy could be seen in the character of Jinaicho (temple towns), religious communities that coalesced around temples of the Ikko sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A similar style of autonomy could be seen in the character of Jinaicho (temple towns), religious communities that coalesced around temples of the Ikko sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>代表的寺内町には摂津国石山（大阪府）や越前国吉崎御坊（福井県）、富田林市（大阪府富田林市）などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Representative examples of Jinaicho included those in Ishiyama of Settsu province (modern-day Osaka), in Yoshizaka Mibo of Echizen province (Fukui Prefecture today), and in the city of Tondabayashi (present-day Tondabayashi city in Osaka).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Representative examples of Jinaicho included those in Ishiyama of Settsu province (modern-day Osaka), in Yoshizaka Mibo of Echizen province (Fukui Prefecture today), and in the city of Tondabayashi (present-day Tondabayashi city in Osaka).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Representative examples of Jinaicho included those in Ishiyama of Settsu Province (modern-day Osaka Prefecture), in Yoshizaki Mibo of Echizen Province (Fukui Prefecture today), and in the city of Tondabayashi (present-day Tondabayashi City, Osaka).</e>
<cmt>Prefecture補足スペル地名の表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>同じく信長による一向一揆平定で解体する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once again, it was Nobunaga that quelled the Ikko Ikki (popular religious uprisings) and dismantled the Jinaicho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once again, it was Nobunaga that quelled the Ikko Ikki (popular religious uprisings) and dismantled the Jinaicho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once again, it was Nobunaga that quelled the Ikko Ikki (popular religious uprisings) and dismantled the Jinaicho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>交通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Transportation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Transportation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Transportation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="90">
<j>貨幣経済の浸透や庶民の成長による地方都市の発達、遠隔地の商品流通や年貢輸送のために街道が整備され、地方文化の交流も活発になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the dissemination of the money-based economy and (economic) growth among the commoners, provincial cities also began to develop, and the highways were maintained to boost circulation of goods and trade in remote areas and facilitate the collection of the annual taxes, which led to lively cultural exchanges in rural culture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the dissemination of the money-based economy and (economic) growth among the commoners, provincial cities also began to develop, and the highways were maintained to boost circulation of goods and trade in remote areas and facilitate the collection of the annual taxes, which led to lively cultural exchanges in rural culture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the dissemination of the money-based economy and (economic) growth among the commoners, provincial cities also began to develop, and the highways were maintained to boost circulation of goods and trade in remote areas and facilitate the collection of the annual taxes, which led to lively cultural exchanges in rural culture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>陸上交通では馬借、車借などの陸上輸送業者、海上交通では廻船を用いて輸送や委託販売を行う中継業者の問丸が活躍する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Land-based trade relied on ground transportation traders like bashaku (who used packhorses) and shashaku (who used carriages), while sea-based trade was dependent on monmaru (shipping agents), relay traders who utilized light trading vessels to transport goods or items sold via consignment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Land-based trade relied on ground transportation traders like bashaku (who used packhorses) and shashaku (who used carriages), while sea-based trade was dependent on monmaru (shipping agents), relay traders who utilized light trading vessels to transport goods or items sold via consignment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Land-based trade relied on ground transportation traders like bashaku (who used packhorses) and shashaku (who used carriages), while sea-based trade was dependent on monmaru (shipping agents), relay traders who utilized light trading vessels to transport goods or items sold via consignment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>港や街道の要所には幕府や寺社、地方領主らにより関所が設置され、関銭や津料を徴収していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Barriers and checkpoints were erected by the bakufu or by influential temples, shrines, or local lords at key points around ports and on highways, collecting tolls (sekisen) for land and customs (tsuryo) for sea travel and trade.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Barriers and checkpoints were erected by the bakufu or by influential temples, shrines, or local lords at key points around ports and on highways, collecting tolls (sekisen) for land and customs (tsuryo) for sea travel and trade.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Barriers and checkpoints were erected by the bakufu or by influential temples, shrines, or local lords at key points around ports and on highways, collecting tolls (sekisen) for land and customs (tsuryo) for sea travel and trade.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>京都七関など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Examples of such checkpoints include Kyoto&apos;s seven barrier stations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Examples of such checkpoints include Kyoto&apos;s seven barrier stations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Examples of such checkpoints include Kyoto&apos;s seven barrier stations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="94">
<j>日本の交通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Transportation within Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Transportation within Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Transportation within Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>対外関係</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">International relations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">International relations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">International relations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>倭寇と西洋人来航</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Wako (Japanese pirates) and the arrival of Westerners</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Wako (Japanese pirates) and the arrival of Westerners</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Wako (Japanese pirates) and the arrival of Westerners</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="95">
<j>室町時代には倭寇と呼ばれる無国籍海上勢力が活動し、14世紀の倭寇は前期倭寇、15世紀の倭寇は後期倭寇と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pirates who held no allegiance to any state, called Wako (Japanese pirates), were active during the Muromachi period; the term &quot;early Wako&quot; is used to describe such pirates in the fourteenth century, while &quot;later Wako&quot; refers to Wako of the fifteenth century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Pirates who held no allegiance to any state, called Wako (Japanese pirates), were active during the Muromachi period; the term &quot;early Wako&quot; is used to describe such pirates in the fourteenth century, while &quot;later Wako&quot; refers to Wako of the fifteenth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Pirates who held no allegiance to any state, called Wako (Japanese pirates), were active during the Muromachi period; the term &quot;early Wako&quot; is used to describe such pirates in the fourteenth century, while &quot;later Wako&quot; refers to Wako of the fifteenth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>倭寇は朝鮮半島や中国沿岸部、東南アジアにわたる東アジア地域で活動し、海賊行為や密貿易などを行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Wako were active throughout East Asia, especially along the coasts of China and the Korean peninsula, and were involved in acts of piracy and smuggling.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Wako were active throughout East Asia, especially along the coasts of China and the Korean peninsula, and were involved in acts of piracy and smuggling.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Wako were active throughout East Asia, along the coasts of China and the Korean peninsula to Southeast Asia, and were involved in acts of piracy and smuggling.</e>
<cmt>especially削除to Southeast Asia補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>さらに世界史的には大航海時代を迎えており、ポルトガルやイスパニアなどのヨーロッパ人も東アジアで活動を広めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, this period witnessed, in terms of international history, the dawning of the age of exploration, which meant that Europeans, notably the Portugese and the Spanish, began to be active in East Asia.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, this period witnessed, in terms of international history, the dawning of the age of exploration, which meant that Europeans, notably the Portugese and the Spanish, began to be active in East Asia.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, this period witnessed, in terms of international history, the dawning of the age of exploration, which meant that Europeans, notably the Portuguese and the Spanish, began to be active in East Asia.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>日明関係</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan&apos;s relations with Ming China</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan&apos;s relations with Ming China</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan&apos;s relations with Ming China</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="98">
<j>勘合貿易で倭寇と区別 博多、堺市、坊津（鹿児島県南さつま市坊津町）から出航し、寧波で勘合符を照査させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Licensed trade missions--to be distinguished from smuggling and piracy by Wako--set sail from Hakata, Sakai, and Bonotsu (today&apos;s Bonotsu-machi in the city of Satsuma of Kagoshima Prefecture), and goods were checked and inspected upon arrival in Ningbo, China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Licensed trade missions--to be distinguished from smuggling and piracy by Wako--set sail from Hakata, Sakai, and Bonotsu (today&apos;s Bonotsu-machi in the city of Satsuma of Kagoshima Prefecture), and goods were checked and inspected upon arrival in Ningbo, China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Licensed trade missions--to be distinguished from smuggling and piracy by Wako--set sail from Hakata, Sakai, and Bonotsu (today&apos;s Bonotsu-machi, Satsuma City, Kagoshima Prefecture), and goods were checked and inspected upon arrival in Ningbo, China.</e>
<cmt>住所表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="99">
<j>足利義持が一時停止するが、足利義教が再開。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA did temporarily halt trade with China, but Yoshinori ASHIKAGA resumed it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA did temporarily halt trade with China, but was resumed by Yoshinori ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA did temporarily halt trade with China, but was resumed by Yoshinori ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>細川氏と大内氏が実権を巡り衝突（寧波の乱）して、以後大内氏が貿易の実権を握った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hosokawa and Ouchi clans clashed over who would hold true authority over the trade (in what was called the Ningbo Turmoil); following this, the Ouchi clan managed to seize de facto control over the China trade.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hosokawa and Ouchi clans clashed over who would hold true authority over the trade (in what was called the Ningbo Turmoil); following this, the Ouchi clan managed to seize de facto control over the China trade.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hosokawa and Ouchi clans clashed over who would hold true authority over the trade (in what was called the Ningbo Turmoil); following this, the Ouchi clan managed to seize de facto control over the China trade.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>日朝関係</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan&apos;s relations with Korea</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan&apos;s relations with Korea</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan&apos;s relations with Korea</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="101">
<j>朝鮮王朝との国交と貿易。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Diplomatic relations and trade between Japan and the Korean royal dynasty</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Diplomatic relations and trade between Japan and the Korean royal dynasty</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Diplomatic relations and trade between Japan and the Korean royal dynasty</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>足利義満は倭寇を取り締まり朝鮮との交易。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA brings the Wako under control and begins dealings with Korea</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA brings the Wako under control and begins dealings with Korea</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA brings the Wako under control and begins dealings with Korea</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="103">
<j>朝鮮通信使・・・足利義満からの使者と国書に対する返礼で1375年に足利義満に対して信（よしみ）を通わす使者として派遣されたのが始まりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Embassies from Korea: after an envoy and royal missive was sent to Korea by Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, a reply was dispatched to Yoshimitsu via an emissary from Shin (Yoshimi) in 1375, thereby opening official communications.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Embassies from Korea: after an envoy and royal missive was sent to Korea by Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, a reply was dispatched to Yoshimitsu via an emissary from Shin (Yoshimi) in 1375, thereby opening official communications.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Embassies from Korea: after an envoy and royal missive was sent to Korea by Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, a reply was dispatched to Yoshimitsu via an emissary from Shin (Yoshimi) in 1375, thereby opening official communications.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>15世紀半ごろまで続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These relations continued into the middle of the fifteenth century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These relations continued into the middle of the fifteenth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These relations continued into the middle of the fifteenth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="105">
<j>応永の外寇・・・1419年（応永26年）におきた朝鮮による対馬襲撃</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Oei Gaiko (the Foreign Raiders of the Oei era): the 1419 (Oei 26) raid on Tsushima island by Korean raiders.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Oei Gaiko (the Foreign Raiders of the Oei era): the 1419 (Oei 26) raid on Tsushima island by Korean raiders.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Oei Gaiko (the Foreign Raiders of the Oei era): the 1419 (Oei 26) raid on Tsushima island by Korean raiders.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="106">
<j>三浦の乱・・・三浦（乃而浦（鎮海市）、富山浦（釜山市）、塩浦）に定住する日本人が反乱。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sanpo Disturbance: an insurrection by the Japanese settlers living in Sanpo (the city of Naijiho, today known as Jinhae city) and Fuzanho (the city of Busan, or Shiho).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sanpo Disturbance: an insurrection by the Japanese settlers living in Sanpo (the city of Naijiho, today known as Jinhae city) and Fuzanho (the city of Busan, or Shiho).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sanpo Disturbance: an insurrection by the Japanese settlers living in Sanpo (the city of Naijiho, today known as Jinhae city) and Fuzanho (the city of Busan, or Shiho).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="107">
<j>日朝関係史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The history of Japan-Korea relations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The history of Japan-Korea relations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The history of Japan-Korea relations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>琉球</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ryukyu islands</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ryukyu islands</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ryukyu islands</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="108">
<j>1492年に中山王尚氏が三山を統一して琉球王国を建国すると、明朝の冊封を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Sho clan, the royal family of Chuzan (the middle mountain), unified the Sanzan (Three Mountains) and established the Ryukyu Kingdom in 1492, they received an official seal from the Ming court of China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Sho clan, the royal family of Chuzan (the middle mountain), unified the Sanzan (Three Mountains) and established the Ryukyu Kingdom in 1492, they received an official seal from the Ming court of China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Sho clan, the royal family of Chuzan (the middle mountain), unified the Sanzan (Three Mountains) and established the Ryukyu Kingdom in 1492, they received an official seal from the Ming court of China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>国家の経済を貿易に頼る琉球王国は明のほか、朝鮮、マラッカ王国やパタニ王国、安南やアユタヤー王朝などの東南アジアにも及ぶ広範囲で独自の中継貿易を行っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to Ming China, on whom the Ryukyu kingdom was dependent economically and for trade, the kingdom was also involved in a unique form of transit trade throughout a wide swathe of East Asia, including Korea, the kingdom of Malacca (modern-day Malaysia), the Pattani kingdom, and the kingdoms of Annam (today&apos;s Vietnam) and Ayutthaya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to Ming China, on whom the Ryukyu kingdom was dependent economically and for trade, the kingdom was also involved in a unique form of transit trade throughout a wide swathe of East Asia, including Korea, the kingdom of Malacca (modern-day Malaysia), the Pattani kingdom, and the kingdoms of Annam (today&apos;s Vietnam) and Ayutthaya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to Ming China, on whom the Ryukyu Kingdom was dependent economically and for trade, the kingdom was also involved in a unique form of transit trade throughout a wide swathe of East Asia, including Korea, the kingdom of Malacca (modern-day Malaysia), the Pattani Kingdom, and the kingdoms of Annam (today&apos;s Vietnam) and Ayutthaya.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>1414年には将軍足利義持が琉球王の献上物に対する返礼の書状を贈っており、1441年には足利義教が琉球を薩摩国の島津氏の属国とする事を認めており、さらに幕府には琉球奉行が設置されて貿易の統制を行おうとしており、室町時代には琉球が「日本」として認識されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1414, the Shogun Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA responded to the tributory gifts sent to him from the Ryukyu kingdom with an official letter, while in 1441, Yoshinori ASHIKAGA declared the Ryukyu islands to be a vassal state of the Shimazu clan, lords of Satsuma province; furthermore, the bakufu created the office of Ryukyu Hoko (shogunal magistrate of the Ryukyus) in an attempt to exert control over Ryukyu trade, meaning that it was during the Muromachi period that the Ryukyus began to be seen as part of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1414, the Shogun Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA responded to the tributory gifts sent to him from the Ryukyu kingdom with an official letter, while in 1441, Yoshinori ASHIKAGA declared the Ryukyu islands to be a vassal state of the Shimazu clan, lords of Satsuma province; furthermore, the bakufu created the office of Ryukyu Hoko (shogunal magistrate of the Ryukyus) in an attempt to exert control over Ryukyu trade, meaning that it was during the Muromachi period that the Ryukyus began to be seen as part of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1414, the Shogun Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA responded to the tributary gifts sent to him from the Ryukyu Kingdom with an official letter, while in 1441, Yoshinori ASHIKAGA declared the Ryukyu islands to be a vassal state of the Shimazu clan, lords of Satsuma Province; furthermore, the bakufu created the office of Ryukyu Hoko (shogunal magistrate of the Ryukyus) in an attempt to exert control over Ryukyu trade, meaning that it was during the Muromachi period that the Ryukyus began to be seen as part of Japan.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>北方世界</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Events to the north</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Events to the north</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Events to the north</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="111">
<j>鎌倉時代末期には蝦夷の反乱が鎌倉幕府を揺るがし、幕府滅亡後には安東氏が十三湊を本拠地に栄えるが、やがて南部氏の興隆により没落する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the closing days of the Kamakura period, a revolt by the people of Ezo had thrown the Kamakura bakufu into turmoil, and after the bakufu&apos;s collapse, the Ando clan had created flourishing strongholds out of thirteen ports, but eventually the Ando clan was brought to ruin by the rising fortunes of the Nanbu clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the closing days of the Kamakura period, a revolt by the people of Ezo had thrown the Kamakura bakufu into turmoil, and after the bakufu&apos;s collapse, the Ando clan had created flourishing strongholds out of thirteen ports, but eventually the Ando clan was brought to ruin by the rising fortunes of the Nanbu clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the closing days of the Kamakura period, a revolt by the people of Ezo had thrown the Kamakura bakufu into turmoil, and after the bakufu&apos;s collapse, the Ando clan had created flourishing strongholds out of thirteen ports, but eventually the Ando clan was brought to ruin by the rising fortunes of the Nanbu clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>蝦夷地（北海道）ににおいては和人（本土人）の居住勢力が広まり、土着のアイヌ民族との衝突が起こる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The power and influence of ethnic Japanese (wajin) in Ezo (modern-day Hokkaido) began to spread, leading to a clash with the native inhabitants, the Ainu people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The power and influence of ethnic Japanese (wajin) in Ezo (modern-day Hokkaido) began to spread, leading to a clash with the native inhabitants, the Ainu people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The power and influence of ethnic Japanese (wajin) in Ezo (modern-day Hokkaido) began to spread, leading to a clash with the native inhabitants, the Ainu people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>1457年にアイヌの酋長であるコシャマイン率いる部族が蜂起して、蠣崎氏や武田信広らと戦う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1457, the Ainu tribes, led by the great Ainu chieftain Kosamaynu, rose in revolt, engaging in battle with the Kakizaki clan and with Nobuhiro TAKEDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1457, the Ainu tribes, led by the great Ainu chieftain Kosamaynu, rose in revolt, engaging in battle with the Kakizaki clan and with Nobuhiro TAKEDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1457, the Ainu tribes, led by the great Ainu chieftain Kosamaynu, rose in revolt, engaging in battle with the Kakizaki clan and with Nobuhiro TAKEDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="114">
<j>文化・芸術</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cultural and artistic accomplishments</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cultural and artistic accomplishments</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cultural and artistic accomplishments</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="20">
<tit>
<j>北山文化・東山文化</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kitayama versus Higashiyama culture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kitayama versus Higashiyama culture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kitayama versus Higashiyama culture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="115">
<j>室町時代は、義満の時代と義政の時代に特徴的な文化が栄え、北山文化・東山文化と呼ばれることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two distinct cultures flourished during the Muromachi period, the Kitayama culture of Yoshimitsu&apos;s day and the Higashiyama culture of Yoshimasa&apos;s time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two distinct cultures flourished during the Muromachi period, the Kitayama culture of Yoshimitsu&apos;s day and the Higashiyama culture of Yoshimasa&apos;s time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two distinct cultures flourished during the Muromachi period, the Kitayama culture of Yoshimitsu&apos;s day and the Higashiyama culture of Yoshimasa&apos;s time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>南北朝時代の活力が背景にあり、3代将軍義満の時代（北山文化）は中央集権的で公家文化と武家文化の影響や中国文化の影響があるのに対し、8代将軍義政の時代（東山文化）は庶民的で「侘び・寂び」という禅宗などの影響が強いのが特色といわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Given the energy and vitality of the Nanbokucho period, the (Kitayama) culture during the reign of the third Shogun, Yoshimitsu, was centralized and authoritarian, influenced both by aristocratic and warrior culture and by Chinese culture, while by contrast, the (Higashiyama) culture during the reign of the eighth Shogun, Yoshimasa, was based in commoner culture and was heavily influenced by Zen Buddhism, for example in the twin aesthetic principles of wabi-sabi (the beauty and pathos of loneliness, simplicity, and imperfection).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Given the energy and vitality of the Nanbokucho period, the (Kitayama) culture during the reign of the third Shogun, Yoshimitsu, was centralized and authoritarian, influenced both by aristocratic and warrior culture and by Chinese culture, while by contrast, the (Higashiyama) culture during the reign of the eighth Shogun, Yoshimasa, was based in commoner culture and was heavily influenced by Zen Buddhism, for example in the twin aesthetic principles of wabi-sabi (the beauty and pathos of loneliness, simplicity, and imperfection).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Given the energy and vitality of the Northern and Southern Court period, the (Kitayama) culture during the reign of the third Shogun, Yoshimitsu, was centralized and authoritarian, influenced both by aristocratic and warrior culture and by Chinese culture, while by contrast, the (Higashiyama) culture during the reign of the eighth Shogun, Yoshimasa, was based in commoner culture and was heavily influenced by Zen Buddhism, for example in the twin aesthetic principles of wabi-sabi (the beauty and pathos of loneliness, simplicity, and imperfection).</e>
<cmt>Nanbokucho→Northern and Southern Court</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>応仁の乱での京都の荒廃を機に地方伝播し、惣村や都市の発達により成長していた庶民にも文化が浸透していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taking advantage of the fact that the capital, Kyoto, lay in ruins, culture began to spread out into the provinces, and even disseminated down to the commoners, who had been advancing socially thanks to the development and growth of soson (peasant villages) and new urban areas in the provinces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taking advantage of the fact that the capital, Kyoto, lay in ruins, culture began to spread out into the provinces, and even disseminated down to the commoners, who had been advancing socially thanks to the development and growth of soson (peasant villages) and new urban areas in the provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taking advantage of the fact that the capital, Kyoto, lay in ruins as a result of Onin War, culture began to spread out into the provinces, and even disseminated down to the commoners, who had been advancing socially thanks to the development and growth of soson (peasant villages) and new urban areas in the provinces.</e>
<cmt>as a result of Onin War補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>茶の湯・能楽・書院造など今日、文化の原型と考えられているものがこの時代に確立された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many aspects of Japanese culture today considered iconic of Japan, including the tea ceremony, Noh theater, and shoinzukuri (a traditional Japanese architectural style) were created during this period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many aspects of Japanese culture today considered iconic of Japan, including the tea ceremony, Noh theater, and shoinzukuri (a traditional Japanese architectural style) were created during this period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many aspects of Japanese culture today considered iconic of Japan, including the tea ceremony, Noh theater, and shoinzukuri (a traditional Japanese architectural style) were created during this period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="21">
<tit>
<j>建築・庭園</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Architecture and gardens</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Architecture and gardens</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Architecture and gardens</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="119">
<j>建築では、義満が北山に建造した鹿苑寺は寝殿造と禅宗仏殿を融合させたもので、北山文化を代表する建築である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In terms of architectural design, Rokuonji (Kinkakuji) temple, which Yoshimitsu had built in the Kitayama region of Kyoto, was a blend of palatial Heian style and Zen Buddhist style architecture, and as such is an excellent example of Kitayama culture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In terms of architectural design, Rokuonji (Kinkakuji) temple, which Yoshimitsu had built in the Kitayama region of Kyoto, was a blend of palatial Heian style and Zen Buddhist style architecture, and as such is an excellent example of Kitayama culture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In terms of architectural design, Rokuon-ji (Kinkaku-ji) Temple, which Yoshimitsu had built in the Kitayama region of Kyoto, was a blend of palatial Heian style and Zen Buddhist style architecture, and as such is an excellent example of Kitayama culture.</e>
<cmt>寺表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>義政の建てた慈照寺は禅宗仏殿に書院造を合わせた建築。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jishoji (Ginkakuji) temple, which Yoshimasa had built, is a combination of Zen Buddhist with shoinzukuri-style architecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jishoji (Ginkakuji) temple, which Yoshimasa had built, is a combination of Zen Buddhist with shoinzukuri-style architecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jisho-ji (Ginkaku-ji) Temple, which Yoshimasa had built, is a combination of Zen Buddhist with shoinzukuri-style architecture.</e>
<cmt>寺表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>また慈照寺内の東求堂同仁斎は四畳半の座敷で、初期書院造といわれ、和風建築の原型になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Within Jishoji temple, the room called the Togudo Dojinsai was a four and a half tatami mat room; it is in what has been called early shoinzukuri-style, and is a prototypical example of Japanese-style architecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Within Jishoji temple, the room called the Togudo Dojinsai was a four and a half tatami mat room; it is in what has been called early shoinzukuri-style, and is a prototypical example of Japanese-style architecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Within Jisho-ji Temple, the room called the Togudo Dojinsai was a four and a half tatami mat room; it is in what has been called early shoinzukuri-style, and is a prototypical example of Japanese-style architecture.</e>
<cmt>寺表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="22">
<tit>
<j>連歌・茶の湯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Renga and the tea ceremony</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Renga and the tea ceremony</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Renga and the tea ceremony</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="122">
<j>上句と下句を連ねていく和歌である連歌は鎌倉時代から発達し、室町時代に最盛を迎える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Renga poetry, a form of waka where the first and last stanzas of the poem are linked together, had been growing in popularity beginning in the Kamakura period, but in the Muromachi period it entered a golden age.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Renga poetry, a form of waka where the first and last stanzas of the poem are linked together, had been growing in popularity beginning in the Kamakura period, but in the Muromachi period it entered a golden age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Renga poetry, a form of waka where the first and last stanzas of the poem are linked together, had been growing in popularity beginning in the Kamakura period, but in the Muromachi period it entered a golden age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>宗祇や二条良基、宗長や心敬らの連歌師が出現し、大名や公家僧侶が寺社に集まり連歌会が催された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Renga masters like Sogi, Yoshimoto NIJO, Socho and Shinkei appeared, and daimyo as well as nobles began to gather at temples and shrines for renga parties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Renga masters like Sogi, Yoshimoto NIJO, Socho and Shinkei appeared, and daimyo as well as nobles began to gather at temples and shrines for renga parties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Renga masters like Sogi, Yoshimoto NIJO, Socho and Shinkei appeared, and daimyo as well as nobles began to gather at temples and shrines for renga parties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>連歌は貴族から一般民衆の間にまで広まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Renga eventually spread from the nobility down into the general (commoner) public.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Renga eventually spread from the nobility down into the general (commoner) public.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Renga eventually spread from the nobility down into the general (commoner) public.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>茶の湯は、南北朝時代に行われていた闘茶や茶寄合が、東山時代に村田珠光により侘び茶が開始され、戦国時代に千利休が完成させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding the tea ceremony, the tocho (tea leaf contests) and cha yoriai (tea parties) held in the Nanbokucho period developed, thanks to Shuko MURATA, into wabicha (a tea ceremony characterized by an affecting rusticity and simplicity) in the Higashiyama period, which was perfected by Sen no Rikyu in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding the tea ceremony, the tocho (tea leaf contests) and cha yoriai (tea parties) held in the Nanbokucho period developed, thanks to Shuko MURATA, into wabicha (a tea ceremony characterized by an affecting rusticity and simplicity) in the Higashiyama period, which was perfected by Sen no Rikyu in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding the tea ceremony, the tocho (tea leaf contests) and cha yoriai (tea parties) held in the Northern and Southern Court period developed, thanks to Shuko MURATA, into wabicha (a tea ceremony characterized by an affecting rusticity and simplicity) in the Higashiyama period, which was perfected by Sen no Rikyu in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>Nanbokucho→Northern and Southern Court</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="23">
<tit>
<j>絵画・彫刻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Painting and sculpture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Painting and sculpture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Painting and sculpture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="126">
<j>絵画では東山時代に画僧である明兆・如拙・周文らを経て雪舟が水墨画を完成させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In terms of painting, the Higashiyama period saw the emergence of Sesshu, who surpassed monk-painters like Mincho, Josetsu, and Shubun and perfected the art of ink painting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In terms of painting, the Higashiyama period saw the emergence of Sesshu, who surpassed monk-painters like Mincho, Josetsu, and Shubun and perfected the art of ink painting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In terms of painting, the Higashiyama period saw the emergence of Sesshu, who surpassed monk-painters like Mincho, Josetsu, and Shubun and perfected the art of ink painting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>狩野元信は水墨画と大和絵の技法を融合させ、のちに狩野派と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motonobu KANO blended techniques for both ink and yamato-e (classical Japanese-themed) painting, founding what would become known to later generations as the Kano school of painting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motonobu KANO blended techniques for both ink and yamato-e (classical Japanese-themed) painting, founding what would become known to later generations as the Kano school of painting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motonobu KANO blended techniques for both ink and yamato-e (classical Japanese-themed) painting, founding what would become known to later generations as the Kano school of painting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>彫刻ではそれまでの仏教彫刻に加えて、能面彫刻が作られるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for sculpture, a new sculptural form, the Noh mask style of sculpture, was developed in addition to Buddhist sculpture, the dominant sculptural mode heretofore.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for sculpture, a new sculptural form, the Noh mask style of sculpture, was developed in addition to Buddhist sculpture, the dominant sculptural mode heretofore.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for sculpture, a new sculptural form, the Noh mask style of sculpture, was developed in addition to Buddhist sculpture, the dominant sculptural mode heretofore.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="24">
<tit>
<j>能楽・狂言</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noh theater and Kyogen (Noh farce)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noh theater and Kyogen (Noh farce)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noh theater and Kyogen (Noh farce)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="129">
<j>足利義満の保護を受けた観阿弥・世阿弥元清の親子が鎌倉時代から行われていた猿楽・田楽を能楽として大成させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanami and his son Motokiyo ZEAMI, who both enjoyed the patronage of Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, were able to take the Sarugaku (a style of comedy) and Dengaku (a musical, rhythmic ritual dancing concerned with rice) that had existed from the Kamakura period and perfect them into Noh theater.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanami and his son Motokiyo ZEAMI, who both enjoyed the patronage of Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, were able to take the Sarugaku (a style of comedy) and Dengaku (a musical, rhythmic ritual dancing concerned with rice) that had existed from the Kamakura period and perfect them into Noh theater.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanami and his son Motokiyo ZEAMI, who both enjoyed the patronage of Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, were able to take the Sarugaku (a style of comedy) and Dengaku (a musical, rhythmic ritual dancing concerned with rice) that had existed from the Kamakura period and perfect them into Noh theater.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>世阿弥は「風姿花伝」で芸道論を著す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zeami published his theories on the performing arts in his &quot;Fushi kaden.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zeami published his theories on the performing arts in his &quot;Fushi kaden.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zeami published his theories on the performing arts in his &apos;Fushi kaden.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>対話劇である狂言も成立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also created the Kyogen, a type of dialogue-driven comedy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also created the Kyogen, a type of dialogue-driven comedy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also created the Kyogen, a type of dialogue-driven comedy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="132">
<j>民衆文化</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Commoner culture during the Muromachi period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Commoner culture during the Muromachi period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Commoner culture during the Muromachi period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="133">
<j>室町時代は惣村の成立や都市の発達により庶民が文化の担い手になってくる時代でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Muromachi period can be described as the era in which, thanks to the establishment of the soson (peasant villages) and the development and growth of urban areas, the cultural mantle passed to commoners.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Muromachi period can be described as the era in which, thanks to the establishment of the soson (peasant villages) and the development and growth of urban areas, the cultural mantle passed to commoners.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Muromachi period can be described as the era in which, thanks to the establishment of the soson (peasant villages) and the development and growth of urban areas, the cultural mantle passed to commoners.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>庶民の間では短編の読み物集である御伽草子が読まれ、狂言や小唄、幸若舞などの庶民芸能が流行する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the common people, otogizoshi (fairy-tales), collections of short tales, were available to be read, while Kyogen, ko&apos;uta (ballads) and kowakamai (a type of dance) were all popular forms of entertainment for commoners.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the common people, otogizoshi (fairy-tales), collections of short tales, were available to be read, while Kyogen, ko&apos;uta (ballads) and kowakamai (a type of dance) were all popular forms of entertainment for commoners.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the common people, otogizoshi (fairy-tales), collections of short tales, were available to be read, while Kyogen, kouta (ballads) and kowakamai (a type of dance) were all popular forms of entertainment for commoners.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>食文化では、味噌、醤油、豆腐など日本料理の基本要素が出揃った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In terms of culinary culture, the Muromachi period saw the emergence of many of the most important and iconic staples of Japanese cuisine, including miso paste, soy sauce, and tofu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In terms of culinary culture, the Muromachi period saw the emergence of many of the most important and iconic staples of Japanese cuisine, including miso paste, soy sauce, and tofu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In terms of culinary culture, the Muromachi period saw the emergence of many of the most important and iconic staples of Japanese cuisine, including miso paste, soy sauce, and tofu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>醤油を除き、中国から伝わっていた要素で、室町時代の商工業発達によって普及した（醤油の普及はやや遅れ、関西では江戸時代初期、江戸では中期）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the exception of soy sauce (which had not widely proliferated throughout western Japan until the early Edo period nor spread into Edo itself until the mid-Edo period), these were items that had been introduced from China and then disseminated thanks to the commercial and industrial growth seen during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the exception of soy sauce (which had not widely proliferated throughout western Japan until the early Edo period nor spread into Edo itself until the mid-Edo period), these were items that had been introduced from China and then disseminated thanks to the commercial and industrial growth seen during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the exception of soy sauce (which had not widely proliferated throughout western Japan until the early Edo period nor spread into Edo itself until the mid-Edo period), these were items that had been introduced from China and then disseminated thanks to the commercial and industrial growth seen during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="25">
<tit>
<j>学問と思想</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Academic scholarship and philosophies</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Academic scholarship and philosophies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Academic scholarship and philosophies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="26">
<tit>
<j>学問</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Scholarship</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Scholarship</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Scholarship</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="137">
<j>室町時代の学問の担い手は主に禅僧や公家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Academic scholarship during the Muromachi period was more or less limited to Zen monks and the nobility.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Academic scholarship during the Muromachi period was more or less limited to Zen monks and the nobility.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Academic scholarship during the Muromachi period was more or less limited to Zen monks and the nobility.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>京都の五山を中心に禅僧の間で漢文学や朱子学の研究が行われ、五山文学と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Research into both Chinese literature and neo-Confucianism was conducted mainly in the Gozan (the five great Zen temples) of Kyoto, leading to the appelation &quot;Gozan literary scholarship.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Research into both Chinese literature and neo-Confucianism was conducted mainly in the Gozan (the five great Zen temples) of Kyoto, leading to the appelation &quot;Gozan literary scholarship.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Research into both Chinese literature and neo-Confucianism was conducted mainly in the Gozan (the five great Zen temples) of Kyoto, leading to the appellation &quot;Gozan literary scholarship.&quot;</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>五山は幕府の保護を受け、日明貿易を行う足利義満の外交的顧問役でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Gozan temples enjoyed the patronage of the bakufu, and actually served as advisors and diplomats for Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA in the trade between Japan and Ming China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Gozan temples enjoyed the patronage of the bakufu, and actually served as advisors and diplomats for Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA in the trade between Japan and Ming China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Gozan temples enjoyed the patronage of the bakufu, and in fact served as advisors and diplomats for Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA in the trade between Japan and Ming China.</e>
<cmt>actually -&gt; &quot;in fact&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>無力化した公家は有職故実や和歌、古典の研究を行い、一条兼良や東常縁、三条西実隆などの公家より古典文化が守られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The now effectively powerless nobility busied themselves by researching the intricacies of court practices, waka poetry, and the old classics of literature, and indeed, it is thanks to the efforts of aristocrats like Kaneyoshi ICHIJO, Tsuneyori TO, and Sanetaka SANJONISHI that the classical canon was preserved.</e>
<cmt>有職故実の対訳は、三省堂・大辞林「有職故実」項目からの訳出です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The now effectively powerless nobility busied themselves by researching the intricacies of court practices, waka poetry, and classical literature, and indeed, it is thanks to the efforts of aristocrats like Kaneyoshi ICHIJO, Tsuneyori TO, and Sanetaka SANJONISHI that the classical canon was preserved.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The now effectively powerless nobility busied themselves by researching the intricacies of court practices, waka poetry, and classical literature, and indeed, it is thanks to the efforts of aristocrats like Kaneyoshi ICHIJO, Tsuneyori TO, and Sanetaka SANJONISHI that the classical canon was preserved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>応仁の乱で京都が荒廃すると、公家や禅僧は地方に移り、学問や文化の地方波及や庶民化が進む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Kyoto was reduced to ruins during the Onin war, nobles and Zen monks relocated to the countryside, further spreading scholarship and culture in the provinces and advancing commoner culture as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Kyoto was reduced to ruins during the Onin war, nobles and Zen monks relocated to the countryside, further spreading scholarship and culture in the provinces and advancing commoner culture as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Kyoto was reduced to ruins during the Onin War, nobles and Zen monks relocated to the countryside, further spreading scholarship and culture in the provinces and advancing commoner culture as well.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>関白一条兼良は越前国朝倉氏のもとへ身を寄せ、子は土佐国中村に土着して土佐一条氏となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kanpaku (chief imperial advisor) Kaneyoshi ICHIJO moved into the household of the Asakura clan in Echizen province, while his son settled permanently in Nakamura of Tosa province, thereby founding the Tosa branch of the ICHIJO clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kanpaku (chief imperial advisor) Kaneyoshi ICHIJO moved into the household of the Asakura clan in Echizen province, while his son settled permanently in Nakamura of Tosa province, thereby founding the Tosa branch of the ICHIJO clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kanpaku (chief imperial advisor) Kaneyoshi ICHIJO moved into the household of the Asakura clan in Echizen Province, while his son settled permanently in Nakamura of Tosa Province, thereby founding the Tosa branch of the ICHIJO clan.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>桂庵玄樹は肥後国及び薩摩国に招かれ、現地で朱子学の一派である薩南学派を開くが江戸時代には衰亡南村梅軒は土佐に招かれて、同じく朱子学の一派の海南学派を開く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genju KEIAN was invited to come to both Higo and then Satsuma provinces, leading him to found the Satsunangaku school, a school of Neo-Confucianism, there in the countryside, which fell into decline during the Edo period; Baiken MINAMIMURA was invited to Tosa, where he created the Bainangaku school, which was also a school of Neo-Confucianism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genju KEIAN was invited to come to both Higo and then Satsuma provinces, leading him to found the Satsunangaku school, a school of Neo-Confucianism, there in the countryside, which fell into decline during the Edo period; Baiken MINAMIMURA was invited to Tosa, where he created the Bainangaku school, which was also a school of Neo-Confucianism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genju KEIAN was invited to come to both Higo and then Satsuma provinces, leading him to found the Satsunangaku school, a school of Neo-Confucianism, there in the countryside, which fell into decline during the Edo period; Baiken MINAMIMURA was invited to Tosa, where he created the Kainangaku school, which was also a school of Neo-Confucianism.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="144">
<j>また、この頃関東では、上杉憲実により足利学校が再興される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And in the Kanto during this same period, Norizane UESUGI worked to restore the Ashikaga Academy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And in the Kanto during this same period, Norizane UESUGI worked to restore the Ashikaga Academy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And in the Kanto during this same period, Norizane UESUGI worked to restore the Ashikaga Academy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>大内氏や堺、奈良の商人の間でも独自の出版が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ouchi clan as well as the merchants of Sakai and Nara began to produce their own unique publications.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ouchi clan as well as the merchants of Sakai and Nara began to produce their own unique publications.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ouchi clan as well as the merchants of Sakai and Nara began to produce their own unique publications.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="146">
<j>日本の中世文学史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The history of medieval literature in Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The history of medieval literature in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The history of medieval literature in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="27">
<tit>
<j>宗教・思想</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Religious and philosophical developments</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Religious and philosophical developments</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Religious and philosophical developments</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="147">
<j>禅宗は武家層にも広く広まり、武家の保護を受けた禅の五山が定められるなど仏教を通じて武家文化と貴族文化が融合するなど、室町文化に影響する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zen Buddhism spread widely among the warrior class, and influenced the development of Muromachi culture vis-a-vis the decisions and so forth regarding Buddhism made by the Gozan temples--which were under the patronage of the military families--and thereby managed to combine warrior and aristocratic culture together.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zen Buddhism spread widely among the warrior class, and influenced the development of Muromachi culture vis-a-vis the decisions and so forth regarding Buddhism made by the Gozan temples--which were under the patronage of the military families--and thereby managed to combine warrior and aristocratic culture together.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zen Buddhism spread widely among the warrior class, and influenced the development of Muromachi culture vis-a-vis the decisions and so forth regarding Buddhism made by the Gozan temples--which were under the patronage of the military families--and thereby managed to combine warrior and aristocratic culture together.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>都市部では日蓮宗が広まり、京都では日親が布教活動を行い、町衆は信徒的な団結力で土一揆に対して戦う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nichiren sect started to spread in urban areas while the monk Nisshin began proselytizing work in Kyoto, and the townspeople combined forces into large groups of believers and struggling with the secular Do&apos;ikki (land-based bands of peasants).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nichiren sect started to spread in urban areas while the monk Nisshin began proselytizing work in Kyoto, and the townspeople combined forces into large groups of believers and struggling with the secular Do&apos;ikki (land-based bands of peasants).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nichiren sect started to spread in urban areas while the monk Nisshin began proselytizing work in Kyoto, and the townspeople combined forces into large groups of believers and struggling with the secular Doikki (land-based bands of peasants).</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>1536年には日蓮宗は比叡山延暦寺と衝突して天文法華の乱と呼ばれる騒動となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1536 the Nichiren sect came into conflict with Enryakuji on Mt. Hiei, leading into the Tenbun Hokke no Ran (The Lotus War of the Tenbun era).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1536 the Nichiren sect came into conflict with Enryakuji on Mt. Hiei, leading into the Tenbun Hokke no Ran (The Lotus War of the Tenbun era).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1536 the Nichiren sect came into conflict with Enryaku-ji Temple on Mt. Hiei, leading into the Tenbun Hokke no Ran (The Lotus War of the Tenbun era).</e>
<cmt>寺表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>庶民の間では曹洞宗が広まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the common people, the Soto school of Zen Buddhism flourished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the common people, the Soto school of Zen Buddhism flourished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the common people, the Soto school of Zen Buddhism flourished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="151">
<j>浄土真宗の蓮如が再興した本願寺教団は、講と呼ばれる信徒集団を形成し、応仁の乱の後には守護大名に取って代わった戦国大名に匹敵する勢力になり、一向宗とも呼ばれるようになり、信仰の下に団結して守護大名の勢力と対抗する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The religious establishment at Honganji temple, which had been revived by Rennyo, of the Jodo Shinshu (True Pure Land sect), began to form large groups of laymen followers, called (Buddhist) &quot;lecture meetings,&quot; and after the Onin war, these groups rivaled the Sengoku daimyo, who had supplanted the shugo daimyo, in strength; they began to be referred to as the Ikko sect, and united by faith, fell into opposition with the power and influence of the shugo daimyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The religious establishment at Honganji temple, which had been revived by Rennyo, of the Jodo Shinshu (True Pure Land sect), began to form large groups of laymen followers, called (Buddhist) &quot;lecture meetings,&quot; and after the Onin war, these groups rivaled the Sengoku daimyo, who had supplanted the shugo daimyo, in strength; they began to be referred to as the Ikko sect, and united by faith, fell into opposition with the power and influence of the shugo daimyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The religious establishment at Hongan-ji Temple, which had been revived by Rennyo, of the Jodo Shinshu (True Pure Land sect), began to form large groups of laymen followers, called (Buddhist) &quot;lecture meetings,&quot; and after the Onin War, these groups rivaled the Sengoku daimyo, who had supplanted the shugo daimyo, in strength; they began to be referred to as the Ikko sect, and united by faith, fell into opposition with the power and influence of the shugo daimyo.</e>
<cmt>寺表記スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>加賀国一揆や山城国一揆等の一向一揆は守護大名を打倒し、織田信長などは徹底的に弾圧し、大坂の本願寺が落とされて以降は沈静する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The popular uprisings (ikki) in the provinces of Kaga and Yamashiro crushed the daimyo in those provinces, leading Nobunaga ODA and others to ruthlessly and utterly suppress them; once Honganji in Osaka had fallen, however, such uprisings ceased and the country became tranquil again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The popular uprisings (ikki) in the provinces of Kaga and Yamashiro crushed the daimyo in those provinces, leading Nobunaga ODA and others to ruthlessly and utterly suppress them; once Honganji in Osaka had fallen, however, such uprisings ceased and the country became tranquil again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The popular uprisings (ikki) in the provinces of Kaga and Yamashiro crushed the daimyo in those provinces, leading Nobunaga ODA and others to ruthlessly and utterly suppress them; once Hongan-ji Temple in Osaka had fallen, however, such uprisings ceased and the country became tranquil again.</e>
<cmt>寺表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>信長は日蓮宗の僧と浄土宗の僧と論争をさせる（安土宗論）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga worked to provoke a controversy between the monks of the Nichiren and Jodo sects (which came to be known as the Azuchi religious dispute).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga worked to provoke a controversy between the monks of the Nichiren and Jodo sects (which came to be known as the Azuchi religious dispute).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga worked to provoke a controversy between the monks of the Nichiren and Jodo sects (which came to be known as the Azuchi religious dispute).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="154">
<j>神道では、吉田兼倶が吉田神道を創始する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding Shinto, Kanetomo YOSHIDA created a fusion of religions known as Yoshida Shinto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding Shinto, Kanetomo YOSHIDA created a fusion of religions known as Yoshida Shinto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding Shinto, Kanetomo YOSHIDA created a fusion of religions known as Yoshida Shinto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="155">
<j>1549年にはヨーロッパからキリスト教がフランシスコ・ザビエルなどによってもたらされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1549, Christian missionaries, notably St. Francis Xavier, arrived from Europe and began spreading Christianity as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1549, Christian missionaries, notably St. Francis Xavier, arrived from Europe and began spreading Christianity as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1549, Christian missionaries, notably St. Francis Xavier, arrived from Europe and began spreading Christianity as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="156">
<j>日本の仏教の室町時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buddhism in Japan during the Muromachi period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buddhism in Japan during the Muromachi period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddhism in Japan during the Muromachi period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="28">
<tit>
<j>史書</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History books written during the period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History books written during the period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History books written during the period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="157">
<j>「増鏡」は四鏡の最後の史書で、後鳥羽天皇の即位から1333年に配流となっていた後醍醐天皇が京都に帰還するまでの宮廷社会の動向を記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Masukagami&quot; is the last of the four &quot;kagami&quot; history books (books with the word &quot;kagami,&quot; or &quot;mirror,&quot; in the title), and covers the period from Emperor Go-Toba&apos;s enthronement to Emperor Go-Daigo&apos;s triumphant return to Kyoto from exile in 1333, focusing on trends within courtly society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Masukagami&quot; is the last of the four &quot;kagami&quot; history books (books with the word &quot;kagami,&quot; or &quot;mirror,&quot; in the title), and covers the period from Emperor Go-Toba&apos;s enthronement to Emperor Go-Daigo&apos;s triumphant return to Kyoto from exile in 1333, focusing on trends within courtly society.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Masukagami&quot; is the last of the four &quot;kagami&quot; history books (books with the word &quot;kagami,&quot; or &quot;mirror,&quot; in the title), and covers the period from Emperor Go-Toba&apos;s enthronement to Emperor Go-Daigo&apos;s triumphant return to Kyoto from exile in 1333, focusing on trends within courtly society.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>「太平記」は後醍醐天皇の即位から細川頼之が管領に就任するまでの南北朝時代を扱っており、軍記物語の性格が強く室町時代から江戸時代にかけて太平記よみと呼ばれる物語僧によって庶民にも語られていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Taiheiki&quot; (Record of the Great Peace) describes the Nanbokucho period, from Emperor Go-Daigo&apos;s enthronement to Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA&apos;s appointment as Kanrei; characterized by its strong stylistic similarities to war chronicles, it also gained popularity among the commoners through the reciting of tales by monks from the Muromachi period through to the Edo period, and was so often recited that such readings aloud, regardless of the title of the work being read, came to be called &quot;Taiheiki readings.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Taiheiki&quot; (Record of the Great Peace) describes the Nanbokucho period, from Emperor Go-Daigo&apos;s enthronement to Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA&apos;s appointment as Kanrei; characterized by its strong stylistic similarities to war chronicles, it also gained popularity among the commoners through the reciting of tales by monks from the Muromachi period through to the Edo period, and was so often recited that such readings aloud, regardless of the title of the work being read, came to be called &quot;Taiheiki readings.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;Taiheiki&apos; (Record of the Great Peace) describes the Northern and Southern Court period, from Emperor Godaigo&apos;s enthronement to Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA&apos;s appointment as Kanrei; characterized by its strong stylistic similarities to war chronicles, it also gained popularity among the commoners through the reciting of tales by monks from the Muromachi period through to the Edo period, and was so often recited that such readings aloud, regardless of the title of the work being read, came to be called &apos;Taiheiki readings.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;Nanbokucho→Northern and Southern Court天皇表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>「梅松論」は足利尊氏の正当性を強調して書かれた史書であるが、成立は太平記よりも早く、資料性は高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Baishoron&quot; is a historical work written with special emphasis on supporting the legitimacy of Takauji ASHIKAGA&apos;s rise to power, but it was completed faster than the Taiheiki and relied on a rich assortment of documents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Baishoron&quot; is a historical work written with special emphasis on supporting the legitimacy of Takauji ASHIKAGA&apos;s rise to power, but it was completed faster than the Taiheiki and relied on a rich assortment of documents.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;Baishoron&apos; is a historical work written with special emphasis on supporting the legitimacy of Takauji ASHIKAGA&apos;s rise to power, but it was completed faster than the Taiheiki and relied on a rich assortment of documents.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>「神皇正統記」は、南北朝時代に南朝の北畠親房が関東で勢力を集めるために南朝の正統性を神代から記した所で、のちの皇国史観に繋がるイデオロギー的性格の強い史書であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Jinno shotoki&quot; (Record of the Imperial Succession) was a work written by Chikafusa KITABATAKE and argues for the legitimacy of the Southern Court line of succession, that it was unbroken since the age of myth, in an attempt to drum up support for the Southern Court in the Kanto; in later times, it was to have a powerful influence on ideologues trying to promote a historiography view of Japan as divine and Emperor-centered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Jinno shotoki&quot; (Record of the Imperial Succession) was a work written by Chikafusa KITABATAKE and argues for the legitimacy of the Southern Court line of succession, that it was unbroken since the age of myth, in an attempt to drum up support for the Southern Court in the Kanto; in later times, it was to have a powerful influence on ideologues trying to promote a historiography view of Japan as divine and Emperor-centered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;Jinno shotoki&apos; (Record of the Imperial Succession) was a work written by Chikafusa KITABATAKE and argues for the legitimacy of the Southern Court line of succession, that it was unbroken since the age of myth, in an attempt to drum up support for the Southern Court in the Kanto; in later times, it was to have a powerful influence on ideologues trying to promote a historiographic view of Japan as divine and Emperor-centered.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="161">
<j>「難太平記」は今川貞世が著した史書で、太平記の誤りを訂正しつつ、今川氏の事績を中心に書かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Nantaiheiki&quot; (Defects of the Taiheiki) is a historical work written by Sadayo IMAGAWA in which he attempts to correct the errors in the Taiheiki, though its primary focus is on the achievements of the Imagawa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Nantaiheiki&quot; (Defects of the Taiheiki) is a historical work written by Sadayo IMAGAWA in which he attempts to correct the errors in the Taiheiki, though its primary focus is on the achievements of the Imagawa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;Nantaiheiki&apos; (Defects of the Taiheiki) is a historical work written by Sadayo IMAGAWA in which he attempts to correct the errors in the Taiheiki, though its primary focus is on the achievements of the Imagawa clan.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>「明徳記」は1391年の明徳の乱の経過が書かれている、「応永記」には1399年の応永の乱や南北朝合体の記述が、「永享記」には永享の乱を中心とした関東の情勢が、「応仁記」には足利義政の治世から応仁の乱の様子が記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Meitokuki&quot; (Chronicle of the Meitoku Era) records the events and aftermath of the Meitoku Rebellion, while the &quot;Oeiki&quot; (Chronicle of the Oei Era) describes the Oei Rebellion and the unification of the Northern and Southern courts; the &quot;Eikyoki&quot; focuses on the situation in the Kanto, especially vis-a-vis the Eikyo Rebellion, whereas the &quot;Oninki&quot; records the circumstances of the period from Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA&apos;s reign up until the Onin war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Meitokuki&quot; (Chronicle of the Meitoku Era) records the events and aftermath of the Meitoku Rebellion, while the &quot;Oeiki&quot; (Chronicle of the Oei Era) describes the Oei Rebellion and the unification of the Northern and Southern courts; the &quot;Eikyoki&quot; focuses on the situation in the Kanto, especially vis-a-vis the Eikyo Rebellion, whereas the &quot;Oninki&quot; records the circumstances of the period from Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA&apos;s reign up until the Onin war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;Meitokuki&apos; (Chronicle of the Meitoku Era) records the events and aftermath of the Meitoku Rebellion, while the &apos;Oeiki&apos; (Chronicle of the Oei Era) describes the Oei Rebellion and the unification of the Northern and Southern courts; the &apos;Eikyoki&apos; focuses on the situation in the Kanto, especially vis-a-vis the Eikyo Rebellion, whereas the &apos;Oninki&apos; records the circumstances of the period from Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA&apos;s reign up until the Onin War.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="163">
<j>また、江戸幕府が幕末に編纂した史書として「後鑑」があり、1333年から1597年に至るまでの史実を編年体で記し、各項目に出典となった各種資料を直截採録する形式となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also a historical work, the &quot;Nochi kagami&quot; (Later Mirror), that was compiled by the Edo bakufu during the Bakumatsu period (the mid-eighteenth century), which describes the events from 1333 through 1597 in chronological order; the book very straightforwardly reveals each of the historical sources consulted for each event described.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also a historical work, the &quot;Nochi kagami&quot; (Later Mirror), that was compiled by the Edo bakufu during the Bakumatsu period (the mid-eighteenth century), which describes the events from 1333 through 1597 in chronological order; the book very straightforwardly reveals each of the historical sources consulted for each event described.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also a historical work, the &apos;Nochi kagami&apos; (Later Mirror), that was compiled by the Edo bakufu during the Bakumatsu period (the mid-eighteenth century), which describes the events from 1333 through 1597 in chronological order; the book very straightforwardly reveals each of the historical sources consulted for each event described.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tomzo(id:16777), Okome(id:98), MIsogi(id:20599), 0null0(id:582), Ojigiri(id:329), 鹿両性証明(id:71252), Eskimbot(id:29676), Lilium auratum(id:13615), Doskoi 8(id:1070), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Rai koku(id:1661), Damdamdamd(id:109603), Mintleaf(id:2216), アスカ(id:9205), でここ(id:9565), Kurz(id:1601), ぎゅうひ(id:9206), らりた(id:1327), AlnoktaBOT(id:135808), Gakuinryou(id:9665), A-Taul(id:41790), Whiteapple(id:1178), 俊(id:14924), Kinori(id:443), 秀の介(id:490), Rei-bot(id:94097), Loveless(id:129239), Chobot(id:20846), Tamago915(id:11009), Shimoxx(id:9332), 百楽天(id:5266), 左近衛少将(id:124441), Yas(id:739), あなひろ(id:45821), 李(id:10582), Yosemite(id:5808), TARBOT(id:73059), G(id:21), Pinball1973(id:33613), YonaBot(id:125006), Forestfarmer(id:59407), しるふぃ(id:11247), 水野白楓(id:22811), Law soma(id:45202), PixelBot(id:166734), Yanahan(id:2437), Rusk(id:9895), Xandi(id:36691), Nidarin(id:6420), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), オタスケマン(id:117461), ゐ(id:795), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), トホホ川(id:50502), 伏儀(id:142093), Corwin(id:973), けんち(id:5147), Chuta(id:10457), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>