<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>民法典論争</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoten Ronso (Disputes over Legal Codes)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minpoten Ronso (Disputes over the Civil Code)</e>
<cmt>Hoten &gt; MinpotenLegal Codes &gt; the Civil Code</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minpoten Ronso (Disputes over the Civil Code)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>民法典論争（みんぽうてんろんそう）とは、1889年（明治22年）から1892年（明治25年）の日本において、旧民法（明治23年法律第28号、第98号）の施行を延期するか断行するかを巡り展開された論争。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minpoten Ronso (disputes over the legal code provided for basic stipulation related to Civil Code) were the disputes whether to postpone or carry out the effectuation of the Old Civil Code (Act No.28, No.29 of 1890) in Japan from 1889 to 1892).</e>
<cmt>*.旧民法 the Old Civil Codeが良いのでは＊民法典→Minpoten (legal code (provides→provided) for basic stipulation related to Civil Code</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minpoten Ronso (disputes over the legal code provided for basic stipulation related to Civil Code) was the disputes whether to postpone or carry out the effectuation of the Old Civil Code (Act No.28, No.29 of 1890) in Japan from 1889 to 1892).</e>
<cmt>were &gt; was</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minpoten Ronso (disputes over the legal code provided for basic stipulation related to Civil Code) was the disputes whether to postpone or carry out the effectuation of the Old Civil Code (Act No.28, No.29 of 1890) in Japan from 1889 to 1892).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>なお、この論争と同時期に刑法典・商法典を巡る論争も行われて、旧刑法の全面改正と旧商法の施行延期が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Disputes over the Penal Code/Commercial Code were also made at the same time, and the Old Penal Code was totally revised and the effectuation of the Old Commercial Code was postponed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Disputes over the Penal Code and the Commercial Code were also made at the same time, and the Old Penal Code was totally revised and the effectuation of the Old Commercial Code was postponed.</e>
<cmt>the Penal Code/Commercial Code &gt; the Penal Code and the Commercial Code全角スペースを半角スペースにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Disputes over the Penal Code and the Commercial Code were also made at the same time, and the Old Penal Code was totally revised and the effectuation of the Old Commercial Code was postponed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>このため、3つの法典を巡る論争をまとめて「法典論争（ほうてんろんそう）」と呼称する事がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason the disputes over the three legal codes were sometimes referred to collectively as &quot;hoten ronso (a dispute/disputes over legal codes)&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason the disputes over the three legal codes were sometimes referred to collectively as &apos;hoten ronso (disputes over legal codes)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &gt; &apos;「a dispute /」を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason the disputes over the three legal codes were sometimes referred to collectively as &apos;hoten ronso (disputes over legal codes)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>刑法典・商法典の論争については、それぞれ刑法・商法の項目を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As to disputes over the Penal Code/Commercial Code, see Penal Code/Commercial Code, respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As to disputes over the Penal Code and the Commercial Code, see Penal Code or Commercial Code, respectively.</e>
<cmt>the Penal Code/Commercial Code &gt; the Penal Code and the Commercial Codesee Penal Code/Commercial Code &gt; see Penal Code or Commercial Code</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As to disputes over the Penal Code and the Commercial Code, see Penal Code or Commercial Code, respectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>旧民法の制定まで</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until the time of Enactment of the Old Civil Code</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until the Time of Enactment of the Old Civil Code</e>
<cmt>time &gt; Time</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until the Time of Enactment of the Old Civil Code</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>民法典が存在しなかった東アジア世界</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">East Asia Where No Civil Code Existed</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">East Asia Where No Civil Code Existed</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">East Asia Where No Civil Code Existed</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>近代以前の日本においても民事裁判は存在したが、体系的な民法典はついに作成される事はなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even in pre-modern Japan civil trials did exist, however, a systematic Minpoten (the legal code provided for basic stipulation related to Civil Code) was never prepared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even in pre-modern Japan civil trials did exist, however, a systematic Minpoten was never prepared.</e>
<cmt>ここでは「民法典」は初出ではないので、説明を割愛しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even in pre-modern Japan civil trials did exist, however, a systematic Minpoten was never prepared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>そもそも日本を含めた東アジア文化圏においては、民衆は政治的に無権利であり、法的に許されたわずかな権利も支配者の統治・命令の絶対性を前提としたものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To begin with, in the East Asian cultural area including Japan the people had no political rights and even only a few rights legally approved were premised on the absolutism of administration/orders of a ruler.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To begin with, in the East Asian cultural area including Japan the people had no political rights and even only a few rights legally approved were premised on the absolutism of administration and orders of a ruler.</e>
<cmt>administration/orders &gt; administration and orders</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To begin with, in the East Asian cultural area including Japan the people had no political rights and even only a few rights legally approved were premised on the absolutism of administration and orders of a ruler.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>従って、古代の律令法には刑法にあたる「律」と行政法にあたる「令」は存在しても民法にあたる法律は存在しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the ancient ritsuryo law had &quot;ryo&quot; for the penal code, &quot;rei&quot; for the administrative law, but not law for the civil code.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the ancient Ritsuryo law had &apos;ritsu&apos; for the penal code, &apos;ryo&apos; for the administrative law, but not law for the civil code.</e>
<cmt>ritsuryo &gt; Ritsuryo &quot;ryo&quot; for the penal code, &quot;rei&quot; for the administrative law, &gt; &apos;ritsu&apos; for the penal code, &apos;ryo&apos; for the administrative law,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the ancient Ritsuryo law had &apos;ritsu&apos; for the penal code, &apos;ryo&apos; for the administrative law, but not law for the civil code.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>こうした考え方は商工業が盛んになって民事的な訴訟が増加した幕藩体制になっても基本的には変わらず、その司法制度は専ら刑事裁判の遂行のためのものであり、民衆が自己の権利として裁判を請求することは出来なかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such an idea did not change basically even in the shogunate system when civil suits increased due to activated trade and craft and the judiciary system was entirely for performances of criminal trials, so that the people could not ask for trials as their own rights.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such an idea did not change basically even in the shogunate system when civil suits increased due to activated trade and craft, and the judiciary system was entirely for performances of criminal trials, so that the people could not ask for trials as their own rights.</e>
<cmt>craftの後に, を追加しました。無駄なスペースを削除しました。for performances　&gt; for performances文末のスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such an idea did not change basically even in the shogunate system when civil suits increased due to activated trade and craft, and the judiciary system was entirely for performances of criminal trials, so that the people could not ask for trials as their own rights.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>民事上の問題が生じた場合には当事者間の話し合い（相対）による解決が付かない場合にのみ「お上からの恩恵」として仲裁に乗り出すという名目で民事裁判が行われたものであり、民衆を法的に救済する制度ではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only in cases of civil problems which could not be solved by discussion (vis-a-vis) between the people concerned, civil trials were made in the name of arbitration as &quot; favor from the authorities&quot;, therefore, these trials were not an institution that would give the people legal aids.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only in cases of civil problems which could not be solved by discussion (vis-a-vis) between the people concerned, civil trials were made in the name of arbitration as &apos;favor from the authorities&apos;, therefore, these trials were not an institution that would give the people legal aids.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &gt; &apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only in cases of civil problems which could not be solved by discussion (vis-a-vis) between the people concerned, civil trials were made in the name of arbitration as &apos;favor from the authorities&apos;, therefore, these trials were not an institution that would give the people legal aids.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>だが、欧米列強との交渉が始まると、日本に民法典が無いことが列強による治外法権を正当化させる理由の一つに挙げられて、幕末から明治初期の日本において、不平等条約条約改正という政治的課題の一つとして民法典の整備が急務とされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when negotiations were started beween Japan and the allied western powers, the fact that Japan lacked minpoten became one reason to justify exterritoriality of the western powers, so that in Japan from the end of the Edo period to the early Meiji period, the preparation of Minpoten was an urgent matter as one of political tasks to revise unequal treaties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when negotiations were started beween Japan and the allied western powers, the fact that Japan lacked Minpoten became one reason to justify exterritoriality of the western powers, so that in Japan from the end of the Edo period to the early Meiji period, the preparation of Minpoten was an urgent matter as one of political tasks to revise unequal treaties.</e>
<cmt>minpoten &gt; Minpoten</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when negotiations were started beween Japan and the allied western powers, the fact that Japan lacked Minpoten became one reason to justify exterritoriality of the western powers, so that in Japan from the end of the Edo period to the early Meiji period, the preparation of Minpoten was an urgent matter as one of political tasks to revise unequal treaties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>明治初期の民法典構想</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Vision of Minpoten in the Early Meiji Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Vision of Minpoten in the Early Meiji Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Vision of Minpoten in the Early Meiji Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>幕末には箕作麟祥や栗本鋤雲ら開明派の幕臣がフランスのナポレオン法典（フランス民法典）を範にして求める事を提案したが江戸幕府の滅亡によって実現しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the late Edo period some of shougun&apos;s retainers of Kaimei-ha (a group of people who advocated enlightenment) including Rinsho MITSUKURI, Joun kURIMOTO and others proposed preparing minpoten on a model of Code Napoleon (French Minpoten), but the proposal was not realized because of the downfall of the Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the late Edo period some of shougun&apos;s retainers of Kaimei-ha Group (a group of people who advocated enlightenment) including Rinsho MITSUKURI, Joun kURIMOTO and others proposed preparing Minpoten on a model of Code Napoleon (French Civil Code), but the proposal was not realized because of the downfall of the Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt>Kaimei-ha &gt; Kaimei-ha Groupminpoten &gt; MinpotenFrench Minpoten &gt; French Civil Code</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the late Edo period some of shougun&apos;s retainers of Kaimei-ha Group (a group of people who advocated enlightenment) including Rinsho MITSUKURI, Joun kURIMOTO and others proposed preparing Minpoten on a model of Code Napoleon (French Civil Code), but the proposal was not realized because of the downfall of the Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>それでも、箕作は新政府の仕官後の1874年に5年間の歳月をかけてその邦訳を完成させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Still, MITSUKURI completed its Japanese translation in 1874, spending five years after serving the new government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Still, MITSUKURI completed its Japanese translation in 1874, spending five years after serving the new government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Still, MITSUKURI completed its Japanese translation in 1874, spending five years after serving the new government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>その頃、司法卿江藤新平は箕作麟祥によるナポレオン法典の邦訳を支援して、同法典の直輸入の検討も含めた早期の民法制定を指示して、太政官や司法省を中心に何度か民法の案が作成された（1870年の「民法決議」、1872年の「皇国民法仮規則」、同年の「司法省民法全議」、1873年の「民法仮規則」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About that time Shinpei ETO, the administrator of Ministry of Justice, who supported Rinsho MITSUKURI to translate Code Napoleon, gave an instruction of enacting Civil Code as early as possible including reviews of direct import of Code Napoleon and some drafts of Civil Code were made mainly by the Daijokan (Grand Council of State) and the Ministry of Justice (&quot;Minpo Ketsugi&quot; in 1870, &quot;Kokoku Minpo Kari Kisoku&quot; in 1872,&quot;Shihosho Minpo Zengi&quot; in the same year&quot; and &quot;Minpo Kari Kisoku&quot; in 1873).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">About that time Shinpei ETO, the administrator of Ministry of Justice, who supported Rinsho MITSUKURI to translate Code Napoleon, gave an instruction of enacting Civil Code as early as possible including reviews of direct import of Code Napoleon and some drafts of Civil Code were made mainly by the Daijokan (Grand Council of State) and the Ministry of Justice (&apos;Minpo Ketsugi&apos; in 1870, &apos;Kokoku Minpo Kari Kisoku&apos; in 1872, &apos;Shihosho Minpo Zengi&apos; in the same year, and &apos;Minpo Kari Kisoku&apos; in 1873).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &gt; &apos;以下の用語は英訳がありませんが、よろしいでしょうか？　「民法決議」　「皇国民法仮規則」　「司法省民法全議」　「民法仮規則」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">About that time Shinpei ETO, who was the administrator of the Ministry of Justice and supported Rinsho MITSUKURI in translating the Code Napoleon, issued an instruction for the enactment of the Civil Code as early as possible; the Civil Code included reviews of the direct import of the Code Napoleon, and some drafts of the Civil Code were made mainly by the Daijokan (Grand Council of State) and the Ministry of Justice (these included the &apos;Minpo Ketsugi&apos; (Civil Law resolution) in 1870, &apos;Kokoku Minpo Kari Kisoku&apos; (Tentative Rule of Imperial Civil Law) in 1872, &apos;Shihosho Minpo Zengi&apos; (all Justice Department resolutions on Civil Law) in 1872, and &apos;Minpo Kari Kisoku&apos; (Tentative Rule of Civil Law) in 1873).</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>やがて、1878年に箕作麟祥と牟田口通照を中心となって民法草案が完成された（「明治11年民法草案」という）が、時の司法卿大木喬任はナポレオン法典の丸写しのような内容に不満を抱いたために採用されることは無かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before long Rinsho MITSUKURI and Michiteru MUTAGUCHI completed a draft of Civil Code (called Minpo Soan in 1878), however, Takato OKI, the then Minister of Justice was dissatisfied with its content like a copied version of Code Napoleon and rejected its adoption.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before long Rinsho MITSUKURI and Michiteru MUTAGUCHI completed a draft of Civil Code (called &apos;Minpo Soan in 1878&apos;), however, Takato OKI, the then Minister of Justice was dissatisfied with its content like a copied version of Code Napoleon and rejected its adoption.</e>
<cmt>called Minpo Soan in 1878 &gt; called &apos;Minpo Soan in 1878&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before long Rinsho MITSUKURI and Michiteru MUTAGUCHI completed a draft of Civil Code (called &apos;Minpo Soan in 1878&apos;), however, Takato OKI, the then Minister of Justice was dissatisfied with its content like a copied version of Code Napoleon and rejected its adoption.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>その間にも遅々として進まない司法省の草案作成に業を煮やした内務省 (日本)（戸籍などを扱う）や農商務省 (日本)（物権・債権の早期定義付けを求めた）からは、独自に民法草案の研究を開始する動きが見られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the meantime the Ministry of Home Affairs (Japan) (that dealt with registers and so on) and the Ministry of Agriculture (Japan) (that asked for early definitions of real rights/credit obligations), getting exasperated at the slow progress of the draft making by the Ministry of Justice, showed their own movement of studying the draft of Civil Code.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the meantime the Ministry of Home Affairs (Japan) (that dealt with registers and so on) and the Ministry of Agriculture (Japan) (that asked for early definitions of real rights and credit obligations), getting exasperated at the slow progress of the draft making by the Ministry of Justice, showed their own movement of studying the draft of Civil Code.</e>
<cmt>real rights/credit obligations &gt; real rights and credit obligations文末のスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the meantime the Ministry of Home Affairs (Japan) (that dealt with registers and so on) and the Ministry of Agriculture (Japan) (that asked for early definitions of real rights and credit obligations), getting exasperated at the slow progress of the draft making by the Ministry of Justice, showed their own movement of studying the draft of Civil Code.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>旧民法の制定</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enactment of Old Civil Code</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enactment of Old Civil Code</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enactment of Old Civil Code</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>そのため大木は、1880年にいわゆる御雇外国人として明治初期における日本の法学教育や立法などに功績を挙げたフランス人法学者ギュスターヴ・エミール・ボアソナードを中心に新しい民法草案の作成を指示した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For that purpose OKI gave an instruction mainly to Gustave Emile BOISSONADE, a French jurist, who made a great contribution to law education and lawmaking in Japan, to prepare a draft of New Civil Code.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For that purpose Oki gave an instruction mainly to Gustave Emile BOISSONADE, a French jurist, who made a great contribution to law education and lawmaking in Japan in 1880, to prepare a draft of new Civil Code.</e>
<cmt>OKI &gt; OkiNew Civil Code &gt; new Civil Code「1880年」の訳が抜けていたので追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For that purpose Oki gave an instruction mainly to Gustave Emile BOISSONADE, a French jurist, who made a great contribution to law education and lawmaking in Japan in 1880, to prepare a draft of new Civil Code.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>彼はフランス人ではあったが、ナポレオン法典の直輸入には反対してあくまでも日本国内の事情にも配慮した民法典を作成すべきであると主張していた（大木もこの考えに同意して、この年と1883年に民事法に纏わる全国的な慣習法調査が行われて「（全国）民事慣例類集」として編纂された）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he was a Frenchman, he disagreed to the direct import of Code Napoleon, and asserted that minpoten should include considerations of the domestic situation in Japan (OKI agreed to the idea, and in the same year and in 1883 &quot;Zenkoku Minji Kanrei-shu&quot; was complied based on the nationwide research of customary law related to Civil Code.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he was a Frenchman, he disagreed to the direct import of Code Napoleon, and asserted that Minpoten should include considerations of the domestic situation in Japan (Oki agreed to the idea, and in the same year and in 1883 &apos;Zenkoku Minji Kanreirui-shu&apos; (national civil customary) was complied based on the nationwide research of customary law related to Civil Code.</e>
<cmt>minpoten &gt; MinpotenOKI &gt; Oki&quot; &gt; &apos;&apos;Zenkoku Minji Kanrei-shu&apos; &gt; &apos;Zenkoku Minji Kanreirui-shu&apos; (national civil customary) 文末のスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he was a Frenchman, he disagreed to the direct import of Code Napoleon, and asserted that Minpoten should include considerations of the domestic situation in Japan (Oki agreed to the idea, and in the same year and in 1883 &apos;Zenkoku Minji Kanreirui-shu&apos; (national civil customary) was complied based on the nationwide research of customary law related to Civil Code.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>やがて10年近い年月をかけて作成された草案（ただし、現行民法典の親族、相続に相当する部分については、日本人が作成した草案）を元に、旧民法が起案・制定され、1890年に2回に分けて公布された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before long the draft of the Old Civil Code based on the draft which took nearly ten years of preparation (however, articles corresponding to relatives and heirs in the present Civil Code were written by Japanese) was prepared/enacted and was made public in twice in 1890.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before long the draft of the Old Civil Code based on the draft which took nearly 10 years of preparation (however, articles corresponding to relatives and heirs in the present Civil Code were written by Japanese) was prepared and enacted and was made public in twice in 1890.</e>
<cmt>ten　&gt; 10prepared / enacte　d &gt; prepared and enacted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before long the draft of the Old Civil Code based on the draft which took nearly 10 years of preparation (however, articles corresponding to relatives and heirs in the present Civil Code were written by Japanese) was prepared and enacted and was made public in twice in 1890.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>民法典論争</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Disputes over the Civil Code</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Disputes over the Civil Code</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Disputes over the Civil Code</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>しかし、条約改正を目的としていたことや帝国議会開設前に編纂完了をしていたこと等の事情から十分な審議を尽くされなかったため、施行断行派と施行延期派との論争が始まり、延期派から様々な批判が展開されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, sufficient discussions were not made because the Civil Code was aimed at revising treaties and had completed the compilation before the Imperial Diet was established; therefore, disputes between Seko-dankoha (people who advocated carrying it out) and Seko-enkiha (people who advocated postponing the enforcement) began and the latter developed various criticisms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, sufficient discussions were not made because the Civil Code was aimed at revising treaties and had completed the compilation before the Imperial Diet was established; therefore, disputes between Seko-danko-ha Group (people who advocated carrying it out) and Seko-enki-ha Group (people who advocated postponing the enforcement) began and the latter developed various criticisms.</e>
<cmt>Seko-dankoha &gt; Seko-danko-ha GroupSeko-enkiha &gt; Seko-enki-ha Group</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, sufficient discussions were not made because the Civil Code was aimed at revising treaties and had completed the compilation before the Imperial Diet was established; therefore, disputes between Seko-danko-ha Group (people who advocated carrying it out) and Seko-enki-ha Group (people who advocated postponing the enforcement) began and the latter developed various criticisms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>学術的な視点からは、旧民法が自然法思想に立脚していたことに対して、法の歴史性・民族性を強調した歴史法学からの批判、内容的なものとしては、日本古来の家族制度を始めとする日本の伝統・習慣にそぐわないという批判があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From an academic viewpoint the fact that the Old Civil Code was based on the thought of natural law, there arose criticisms from historical jurisprudence emphasizing a historical/racial nature of law, which included criticisms that the content of the Code would not fit Japanese tradition and customs including Japanese traditional family system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From an academic viewpoint the fact that the Old Civil Code was based on the thought of natural law, there arose criticisms from historical jurisprudence emphasizing a historical and racial nature of law, which included criticisms that the content of the Code would not fit Japanese tradition and customs including Japanese traditional family system.</e>
<cmt>historical and racial</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From an academic viewpoint the fact that the Old Civil Code was based on the thought of natural law, there arose criticisms from historical jurisprudence emphasizing a historical and racial nature of law, which included criticisms that the content of the Code would not fit Japanese tradition and customs including Japanese traditional family system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="21">
<j>公布前の1889年（明治22年）5月、東大法学部出身者で組織されるイギリス法系の法学士会は春季総会において『法典編纂ニ関スル意見書』を発表するとともに、拙速な法典編纂を改めるべきであることを内閣や枢密院 (日本)に働きかけることを議決した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May, 1889 before the publication, the British Law Hogakushikai Association consisting of graduates from the University of Tokyo Faculty of Law presented &quot;Hoten Hensan ni Kansuru Ikensho (written opinions on Compiling Legal Codes &quot;in its spring assembly and decided that they should appeal to the Cabinet and the Sumitsu-in (Privy Council) to correct rapid compilation of legal codes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May, 1889 before the publication, the British Law Hogakushi-kai Association consisting of graduates from the University of Tokyo Faculty of Law presented &quot;Hoten Hensan ni Kansuru Ikensho (written opinions on Compiling Legal Codes&quot; in its spring assembly and decided that they should appeal to the Cabinet and the Sumitsu-in (Privy Council) to correct rapid compilation of legal codes.</e>
<cmt>無駄なスペースを削除しました。Association consisting of graduates &gt; Association consisting of graduatesHogakushikai &gt; Hogakushi-kai文末のスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May, 1889 before the publication, the British Law Hogakushi-kai Association consisting of graduates from the University of Tokyo Faculty of Law presented &quot;Hoten Hensan ni Kansuru Ikensho (written opinions on Compiling Legal Codes&quot; in its spring assembly and decided that they should appeal to the Cabinet and the Sumitsu-in (Privy Council) to correct rapid compilation of legal codes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>この意見書ならびに議決の影響で民法や商法の施行をめぐる議論が活発化したことから、この意見書並びに議決が実質的に民法典論争（商法も含）のきっかけである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the fact that this written opinion and the influence of the decision activated the discussions on Civil Code and the Commercial Code, the written opinion and were substantially triggered the minpoten ronso (including the Commercial Code).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the fact that this written opinion and the influence of the decision activated the discussions on the Civil Code and the Commercial Code, the written opinion and were substantially triggered the Minpoten Ronso (including the Commercial Code).</e>
<cmt>Civil Code &gt; the Civil Codeminpoten ronso &gt; Minpoten Ronso</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the fact that this written opinion and the influence of the decision activated the discussions on the Civil Code and the Commercial Code, the written opinion and were substantially triggered the Minpoten Ronso (including the Commercial Code).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>この時期発表された著名な論文として、施行延期派のものは増島六一郎の『法学士会ノ意見ヲ論ズ』、江木衷の『民法草案財産編批評』がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Well-known theses published then by the seko-enkiha included &quot;Hogakushi Kai no Iken-wo Ronzu&quot; by Rokuichiro MASUJIMA and &quot;Minpo Soan Zaisan Hen Hihyo&quot;. by Makoto EGI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Well-known theses published then by Seko-enki-ha Group included &quot;Hogakushi Kai no Iken-wo Ronzu&quot; by Rokuichiro MASUJIMA and &quot;Minpo Soan Zaisan Hen Hihyo&quot; by Makoto EGI.</e>
<cmt>the seko-enkiha &gt; Seko-enki-ha Group以下の用語は英訳がありませんが、よろしいでしょうか？&quot;Hogakushi Kai no Iken-wo Ronzu&quot;&quot;Minpo Soan Zaisan Hen Hihyo&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Well-known theses published at that time by the Seko-enki-ha Group included &quot;Hogakushi Kai no Iken-wo Ronzu&quot; (Discussing opinions from the School of Law Alumni Association) by Rokuichiro MASUJIMA and &quot;Minpo Soan Zaisan Hen Hihyo&quot; (Critique on property ownership under the draft Civil Law) by Makoto EGI.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>一方施行断行派のものでは磯部四郎の『法理精華ヲ読ム』、井上操の『法律編纂ノ可否』がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, theses by seko-dankouha included &quot;Horiseika wo Yomu&quot;by Shiro ISOBE and &quot;Horitsu Hensan no Kahi&quot; by Masao INOUE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, theses by Seko-danko-ha Group included &quot;Horiseika wo Yomu&quot; by Shiro ISOBE and &quot;Horitsu Hensan no Kahi&quot; by Masao INOUE.</e>
<cmt>seko-dankouha &gt; Seko-danko-ha Group以下の用語は英訳がありませんが、よろしいでしょうか？『法理精華ヲ読ム』『法律編纂ノ可否』</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, theses by the Seko-danko-ha Group included &quot;Horiseika wo Yomu&quot; (Reading the Hori Seika law school Journal) by Shiro ISOBE and &quot;Horitsu Hensan no Kahi&quot; (The pros and cons of compiling laws) by Masao INOUE.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="25">
<j>1890年（明治23年）11月、第一回帝国議会が開かれ、産業界から商法の施行が早すぎ対応がとれないとの理由で「商法実施延期請願書」が出されると、帝国議会は1891年（明治24年）1月1日施行予定の商法を民法と同じ1893年（明治26年）1月1日施行に延期することを決定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November, 1980, the first Imperial Diet was opened, and when &quot;Shoho Jisshi Enki Seigansho (petition for postponing the effectuation of the Commercial Code)&quot; was submitted because they could not correspond to its too early effectuation, the Imperial Diet decided to postpone the enforcement of the Commercial Code in January 1 to January 1, 1893, the same day of the effectuation of the Civil Code.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November, 1980, the first Imperial Diet was opened, and when &apos;Shoho Jisshi Enki Seigansho (petition for postponing the effectuation of the Commercial Code)&apos; was submitted because they could not correspond to its too early effectuation, the Imperial Diet decided to postpone the enforcement of the Commercial Code in January 1, 1991 to January 1, 1893, the same day of the effectuation of the Civil Code.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &gt; &apos;January 1 to January 1, 1893 &gt; January 1, 1991 to January 1, 1893</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November, 1980, the first Imperial Diet was opened, and when &apos;Shoho Jisshi Enki Seigansho (petition for postponing the effectuation of the Commercial Code)&apos; was submitted because they could not correspond to its too early effectuation, the Imperial Diet decided to postpone the enforcement of the Commercial Code in January 1, 1991 to January 1, 1893, the same day of the effectuation of the Civil Code.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>商法の施行延期が決定されたことで論争はさらに勢いを増し、1891年、穂積八束が『民法出デテ忠孝亡ブ』という論文を発表し、「我国ハ祖先教ノ国ナリ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The decision of postponing the enforcement of the Commercial Code activated the disputes, and in 1891 Yatsuka HOZUMI in his thesis &quot;Minho Idete Chuko Horobu&quot;, saying, &quot;Our country worships ancestors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The decision of postponing the enforcement of the Commercial Code activated the disputes, and in 1891 Yatsuka HOZUMI in his thesis &quot;Minho Idete Chuko Horobu&quot;, saying, &apos;Our country worships ancestors.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Our country &gt; &apos;Our country</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The decision to postpone the enforcement of the Commercial Code led to disputes, and in 1891 Yatsuka HOZUMI said the following in his thesis &quot;Minho Idete Chuko Horobu&quot; (As civil laws are being introduced, loyalty and filial duty are being lost): &apos;Our country worships ancestors.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>家制ノ郷ナリ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a home of a family system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a home of a family system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a home of a family system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>権力ト法トハ家ニ生マレタリ」「家長権ノ神聖ニシテ犯スベカラザルハ祖先ノ霊ノ神聖ニシテ犯スベカラザルヲ以ッテナリ」と説き、法による権利義務関係を否定し、日本伝統の家父長制度を否定する婚姻を基調とした家族法を批判した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The authority and law were born in a family.&quot;, and &quot;the authority of a head of a family is holy and inviolable just as the spirits of our ancestors are holy and inviolable&quot;, neglected a right-duty relation by law and criticized the family law based on marriage which denied Japanese traditional patriarchal authority.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The authority and law were born in a family.&apos;, and &apos;the authority of a head of a family is holy and inviolable just as the spirits of our ancestors are holy and inviolable&apos;, neglected a right-duty relation by law and criticized the family law based on marriage which denied Japanese traditional patriarchal authority.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &gt; &apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The authority and law were born in a family.&apos;, and &apos;the authority of a head of a family is holy and inviolable just as the spirits of our ancestors are holy and inviolable&apos;, neglected a right-duty relation by law and criticized the family law based on marriage which denied Japanese traditional patriarchal authority.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>この論文はそのタイトルのため最も注目を集め、民法典論争の象徴ともいえる論文である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This thesis is the one that attracted the most attention because of the title, and may be said to symbolize the disputes over the Civil Code.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This thesis is the one that attracted the most attention because of the title, and may be said to symbolize the disputes over the Civil Code.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This thesis is the one that attracted the most attention because of the title, and may be said to symbolize the disputes over the Civil Code.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="30">
<j>施行を翌年に控えた1892年（明治25年）、法典論争はピークに達し、施行延期派は天皇制に絡めて日本の伝統を基にした論陣をはり個人主義的な施行断行派を批判し、施行断行派はフランス法的自然法思想と市民法理論をもって反論を加えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1892, one year before the effectuation, the dispute over legal codes reached its peak: Seko-dankoha, taking a firm stand on Japanese tradition related to the Emperor system, criticized individualistic Seko-enkiha, while Seko-dankoha put up an argument with the thought of French law-like natural law and the civil code theory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1892, one year before the effectuation, the dispute over legal codes reached its peak: Seko-danko-ha Group, taking a firm stand on Japanese tradition related to the Emperor system, criticized individualistic Seko-enki-ha Group, while Seko-danko-ha Group put up an argument with the thought of French law-like natural law and the civil code theory.</e>
<cmt>Seko-dankoha &gt; Seko-danko-ha GroupSeko-enkiha &gt; Seko-enki-ha Group</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1892, one year before the effectuation, the dispute over legal codes reached its peak: Seko-danko-ha Group, taking a firm stand on Japanese tradition related to the Emperor system, criticized individualistic Seko-enki-ha Group, while Seko-danko-ha Group put up an argument with the thought of French law-like natural law and the civil code theory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>また論争は法律論にとどまらず資本主義経済の矛盾の問題、国家思想や国体の位置づけなどにも及び、商法典論争と相まって一種の政治対立の様相さえ呈するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, the disputes, ranging from legal theories to contradictions of capitalist economy, national ideology and positioning of the national structure and so on and combined with the disputes over the Commercial Code, came to present a kind of political confrontation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, the disputes, ranging from legal theories to contradictions of capitalist economy, national ideology and positioning of the national structure and so on and combined with the disputes over the Commercial Code, came to present a kind of political confrontation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the disputes, ranging from legal theories to contradictions of capitalist economy, national ideology and positioning of the national structure and so on and combined with the disputes over the Commercial Code, came to present a kind of political confrontation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>しかし、松方デフレ等の影響で没落した農家・地主たちや疲弊した地方を尻目に官営事業の払下げで急速に力をつけてきた政商資本家の台頭という資本主義経済における自由競争の負の部分が顕在化しつつあった当時の状況や、大日本帝国憲法では天皇制を定め、近代天皇制国家の形成が進められていたことから、施行延期派を支持する声が段々と強まるようになっていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, more and more people supported the seko-kaikaku-ha, because of the then situation that in spite of peasants/landowners who were brought to ruin and local regions impoverished by Matsukata Deflation, and the appearance of businessmen with political ties who were rapidly increasing power by getting government properties cheaply, a negative part of free competition in capitalist economy, and the fact that in the Constitution of the Empire of Japan the Emperor system was adopted and the formation of the modern Emperor-system nation was on going,.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, more and more people supported the Seko-enki-ha Group, because of the then situation that in spite of peasants and landowners who were brought to ruin and local regions impoverished by Matsukata Deflation, and the appearance of businessmen with political ties who were rapidly increasing power by getting government properties cheaply, a negative part of free competition in capitalist economy, and the fact that in the Constitution of the Empire of Japan the Emperor system was adopted and the formation of the modern Emperor-system nation was on going.</e>
<cmt>seko-kaikaku-ha &gt; Seko-enki-ha Grouppeasants/landowners &gt; peasants and landownersgoing,. &gt; going.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, more and more people supported the Seko-enki-ha Group, because of the then situation that in spite of peasants and landowners who were brought to ruin and local regions impoverished by Matsukata Deflation, and the appearance of businessmen with political ties who were rapidly increasing power by getting government properties cheaply, a negative part of free competition in capitalist economy, and the fact that in the Constitution of the Empire of Japan the Emperor system was adopted and the formation of the modern Emperor-system nation was on going.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="33">
<j>そして同年5月、第三回帝国議会において民法典論争は政治的な決着がはかられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May of the same year a political settlement of the minpoten ronso was made in the third Imperial Diet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May of the same year a political settlement of the Minpoten Ronso was made in the third Imperial Diet.</e>
<cmt>minpoten ronso &gt; Minpoten Ronso</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May of the same year a political settlement of the Minpoten Ronso was made in the third Imperial Diet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>貴族院 (日本)議員田村保によって民法商法施行延期法案が貴族院に出され、断行派議員と延期派議員との間でも激しい論戦が繰り広げられたが、同案は圧倒的多数で貴族院を通過、衆議院でも賛成多数で可決するに至りここに民法典論争は決着をみた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A bill of postponing the effectuation of the Civil/Commercial Codes were submitted by Tamotsu TAMURA, a member of the House of Peers, which caused heated arguments as to whether to carry it out or postpone it, but the bill passed the House of Peers by an overwhelming majority and the House of Representatives by a majority: Finally the minpoten ronso saw its settlement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A bill of postponing the effectuation of the Civil Code and the Commercial Code were submitted by Tamotsu TAMURA, a member of the House of Peers, which caused heated arguments as to whether to carry it out or postpone it, but the bill passed the House of Peers by an overwhelming majority and the House of Representatives by a majority: Finally the Minpoten Ronso saw its settlement.</e>
<cmt>文末のスペースを削除しました。Civil/Commercial Codes &gt; Civil Code and the Commercial Codeminpoten ronso &gt; Minpoten Ronso</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A bill of postponing the effectuation of the Civil Code and the Commercial Code were submitted by Tamotsu TAMURA, a member of the House of Peers, which caused heated arguments as to whether to carry it out or postpone it, but the bill passed the House of Peers by an overwhelming majority and the House of Representatives by a majority: Finally the Minpoten Ronso saw its settlement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="35">
<j>その後新設された法典調査会で、穂積陳重、富井政章、梅謙次郎が旧民法の修正を基本としつつ、ドイツ民法の草案や各国の民法をも参照して、現行の民法（明治29年法律第89号）が起草された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequently in a newly-established Investigation Committee of Codes, Nobushige HOZUMI, Masaakira TOMII and Kenjiro UME, focusing corrections of the Old Civil Code and referring to the draft of the German Civil Code, drafted the present Civil Code (Act No.89, 1896).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently in a newly-established Investigation Committee of Codes, Nobushige HOZUMI, Masaakira TOMII and Kenjiro UME, focusing corrections of the Old Civil Code and referring to the draft of the German Civil Code, drafted the present Civil Code (Act No.89, 1896).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently in a newly-established Investigation Committee of Codes, Nobushige HOZUMI, Masaakira TOMII and Kenjiro UME, focusing corrections of the Old Civil Code and referring to the draft of the German Civil Code, drafted the present Civil Code (Act No.89, 1896).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="36">
<j>この論争の意義については、かつては学問的な論争と考えられていたが、実際には言いがかり的な論争も多く、中心は政治的・派閥的な争いとする見方も強い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The significance of the disputes was once regarded as an academic one, however, in fact, there were so many arguments just for objection that many people take the disputes mainly as political/sectional conflicts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The significance of the disputes was once regarded as an academic one; however, in fact, there were so many arguments just for objection that many people take the disputes mainly as political and sectional conflicts.</e>
<cmt>political/sectional &gt; political and sectionalone, &gt; one;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The significance of the disputes was once regarded as an academic one; however, in fact, there were so many arguments just for objection that many people take the disputes mainly as political and sectional conflicts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="37">
<j>当時、旧民法賛成派であったのが明治法律学校(現明治大学)や和仏法律学校(現法政大学)であり、反対派であったのが東京帝国大学(現東京大学)やイギリス法律学校(現中央大学)である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, supporters of the Old Civil Code included Meiji Law School (now Meiji University) and Japanese-French Law School (now Hosei University), while the nonsupporters included Tokyo Imperial University (now Tokyo University) and English Law School (now Chuo University).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, supporters of the Old Civil Code included Meiji Law School (now Meiji University) and Japanese-French Law School (now Hosei University), while the opponents included Tokyo Imperial University (now Tokyo University) and English Law School (now Chuo University).</e>
<cmt>nonsupporters &gt; opponents</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, supporters of the Old Civil Code included Meiji Law School (now Meiji University) and Japanese-French Law School (now Hosei University), while the opponents included Tokyo Imperial University (now Tokyo University) and English Law School (now Chuo University).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Izayohi(id:13095), Straysheep(id:42448), 水野白楓(id:22811), Complex01(id:10454), Krp(id:15909), Andee(id:20421), Giniro(id:39859), Kurz(id:1601), PPP(id:22924), BBG(id:124711), Swkz(id:10914), Misola(id:36747), ペトチザン(id:19878), Hukidera(id:87796), くにゃこ(id:38684), M3HR(id:45797), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>