<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>京都見廻組</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto mimawarigumi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto mimawarigumi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto mimawarigumi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>京都見廻組（きょうとみまわりぐみ）は、江戸時代末期（幕末期）に幕臣によって結成された、京都治安維持の組織。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto mimawarigumi was an organization for maintaining the public order in Kyoto, which was formed by the shogun&apos;s retainers at the end of Edo Period (end of Edo period).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto mimawarigumi was an organization for maintaining public order in Kyoto, which was formed by the shogun&apos;s retainers at the end of the Edo Period (end of Edo period).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto mimawarigumi was an organization for maintaining public order in Kyoto, which was formed by the shogun&apos;s retainers at the end of the Edo Period (end of Edo period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>元治元年(1864年)、江戸幕府は京都守護職配下として蒔田廣孝と松平康正を京都見廻役に任命した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1864, the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) appointed Hirotaka MAITA and Yasumasa MATSUDAIRA to Kyoto Mimawariyaku under the command of the Kyoto shugoshoku (Military governor of Kyoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1864, the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) appointed Hirotaka MAITA and Yasumasa MATSUDAIRA to Kyoto Mimawariyaku under the command of the Kyoto shugoshoku (Military governor of Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1864, the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) appointed Hirotaka MAITA and Yasumasa MATSUDAIRA to Kyoto Mimawariyaku under the command of the Kyoto shugoshoku (Military governor of Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>そしてその配下として旗本、御家人を組織して京都見廻組が創設された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, the Kyoto mimawarigumi was founded with hatamoto (direct retainer of the shogun) and gokenin (immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods) placed under the Kyoto Mimawariyaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterwards, the Kyoto mimawarigumi was founded with hatamoto (direct retainer of the shogun) and gokenin (immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods) placed under the Kyoto Mimawariyaku.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterwards, the Kyoto mimawarigumi was founded with hatamoto (direct retainer of the shogun) and gokenin (immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods) placed under the Kyoto Mimawariyaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>詰所は二条城の側に置かれたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the station was set by the Nijo-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the station was set by the Nijo-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the station was set by the Nijo-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>それぞれの見廻役が配下の組を持ち、それぞれ見廻役の官職名から相模守組（蒔田廣孝）と出雲守組（松平康正）と呼ばれ、各200名ほどの組員を指揮した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The two Mimawariyaku respectively formed brigades under their command which were named after the official titles of the commanders as the Sagami no kami (governor of Sagami Province) brigade (Hirotaka MAITA) and the Izumo no kami (governor of Izumo Province) brigade (Yasumasa MATSUDAIRA) with about 200 soldiers commanded respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The two Mimawariyaku respectively formed brigades under their command which were named after the official titles of the commanders as the Sagami no kami (governor of Sagami Province) brigade (Hirotaka MAITA) and the Izumo no kami (governor of Izumo Province) brigade (Yasumasa MATSUDAIRA) with about 200 soldiers under their command.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The two Mimawariyaku respectively formed brigades under their command which were named after the official titles of the commanders as the Sagami no kami (governor of Sagami Province) brigade (Hirotaka MAITA) and the Izumo no kami (governor of Izumo Province) brigade (Yasumasa MATSUDAIRA) with about 200 soldiers under their command.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>見廻組は新選組と共に一般犯罪者ではなく、反幕府勢力の取り締まりを専門に行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Along with Shinsengumi, Mimawarigumi specialized in clamping down the counterforce of the bakufu, not offenders.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Along with Shinsengumi, Mimawarigumi specialized in clamping down on those forces which opposed the bakufu, and not offenders.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Along with Shinsengumi (a group who guarded Kyoto during the end of Tokugawa Shogunate), Mimawarigumi specialized in clamping down on those forces which opposed the bakufu, and not offenders.</e>
<cmt>新撰組の説明補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>見廻組は主に御所、二条城周辺といった官庁街を管轄とし、新撰組は祇園や三条といった町人町、歓楽街を管轄とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mimawarigumi mainly covered the government office district including the imperial palace and the neighbor of the Nijo-jo Castle, while Shinsengumi covered the towns for merchant class and the amusement centers such as Gion and Sanjo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mimawarigumi mainly covered the government office district including the imperial palace and the area around the Nijo-jo Castle, while Shinsengumi covered towns for merchant class and amusement centers such as Gion and Sanjo.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mimawarigumi mainly covered the government office district including the imperial palace and the area around the Nijo-jo Castle, while Shinsengumi covered towns for merchant class and amusement centers such as Gion and Sanjo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>そのためか、新撰組と共同戦線をとったことはあまり無かったらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Probably for that reason, Shinsengumi and Mimawarigumi are said to have seldom formed a common front.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, it is highly unlikely that Shinsengumi and Mimawarigumi had the chance to establish a common front.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, it is highly unlikely that Shinsengumi and Mimawarigumi had the chance to establish a common front.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>相模組与頭の佐々木只三郎、渡辺吉太郎、高橋安二郎、桂早之助、土肥仲蔵、桜井大三郎、今井信郎らが坂本龍馬暗殺の実行犯として有力とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadasaburo SASAKI, who was Kumigashira (the leader) of the Sagami no kami brigade, and Kichitaro WATANABE, Yasujiro TAKAHASHI, Hayanosuke KATSURA, Nakazo DOHI, Daizaburo SAKURAI, and Nobuo IMAI were regarded as very likely perpetrators of the assassination of Ryoma SAKAMOTO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadasaburo SASAKI, who was Kumigashira (the leader) of the Sagami no kami brigade, and Kichitaro WATANABE, Yasujiro TAKAHASHI, Hayanosuke KATSURA, Nakazo DOHI, Daizaburo SAKURAI, and Nobuo IMAI were regarded as likely perpetrators of the assassination of Ryoma SAKAMOTO.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadasaburo SASAKI, who was Kumigashira (the leader) of the Sagami no kami brigade, and Kichitaro WATANABE, Yasujiro TAKAHASHI, Hayanosuke KATSURA, Nakazo DOHI, Daizaburo SAKURAI, and Nobuo IMAI are regarded as likely perpetrators of the assassination of Ryoma SAKAMOTO.</e>
<cmt>ＳＡＫＡＭＯＴＯ→SAKAMOTOwere→are　ご確認願います。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tanuki Z(id:612), 土方　誠(id:3651), Maakun(id:16735), Kamakura(id:472), Reggaeman(id:6214), 怪蘇(id:45514), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>