<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>元慶の乱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gangyo War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Gangyo War</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Gangyo War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>元慶の乱（がんぎょうのらん）は平安時代に起きた俘囚（蝦夷）の反乱である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Gangyo War was a rebellion by the Ifu, or less assimilated Emishi (unassimilated northerners) under the rule of the Imperial Court, in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>原文には、「俘囚」 とありますが、「俘囚」はリンク先の単語のようです。ウェブで確認すると用語は「夷俘」となっており、本来はこちらの用語を使用していると思われますので、こちらを訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Gangyo War, which occurred in the Heian period, was a rebellion by the Ifu, or less assimilated Emishi (unassimilated northerners) under the rule of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Gangyo War, which occurred in the Heian period, was a rebellion by the Ifu, or less assimilated Emishi (unassimilated northerners) under the rule of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>朝廷の苛政に対して出羽国の夷俘が蜂起して秋田城を襲った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ifu in Dewa Province revolted against the misrule by the Imperial Court and attacked Akita-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ifu in Dewa Province revolted against the misrule by the Imperial Court and attacked Akita-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ifu in Dewa Province revolted against the misrule by the Imperial Court and attacked Akita-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>官軍は苦戦して鎮圧は難航したが、藤原保則が寛政によって鎮撫して終息した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial forces faced an uphill battle and had difficulty subduing the rebels, but FUJIWARA no Yasunori pacified and ended the rebellion by the kansei (sympathetic policies).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The imperial forces faced an uphill battle and had difficulty subduing the rebels, but FUJIWARA no Yasunori pacified the rebels and ended the rebellion through the use of kansei (sympathetic policies).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The imperial forces faced an uphill battle and had difficulty subduing the rebels, but FUJIWARA no Yasunori pacified the rebels and ended the rebellion through the use of kansei (sympathetic policies).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経緯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Details</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Details</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Details</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>元慶年間の初頭、干ばつにより全国的に飢饉に襲われ、各地で不動倉が開かれ、賑給が実施された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Early in the first year of the Gangyo era, drought caused famine nationwide, and consequently, the fudoso (emergency grain storage) in many parts of the country was opened in order for the Imperial Court to provide food to the poor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Early in the first year of the Gangyo era, drought caused famine nationwide, and consequently the fudoso (emergency grain storage) in many parts of the country was opened in order for the Imperial Court to provide food to the poor.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Early in the first year of the Gangyo era, drought caused famine nationwide, and consequently the fudoso (emergency grain storage) in many parts of the country was opened in order for the Imperial Court to provide food to the poor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>直接記録に残ってはいないが、東北地方も例外ではなかったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed, although there is no written record of this, that the Tohoku region was not an exception to this disaster, either.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed, although there is no written record of this, that the Tohoku region was not spared the effects of the disaster.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed, although there is no written record of this, that the Tohoku region was not spared the effects of the disaster.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>それに秋田城司による年来の苛政が重なり、夷俘の不満は頂点に達した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to this disaster, years of misrule by the lord of Akita-jo Castle finally caused Ifu&apos;s frustration to reach a boiling point.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to this disaster, years of misrule by the lord of Akita-jo Castle had brought the Ifu&apos;s frustration to the boiling point.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to this disaster, years of misrule by the lord of Akita-jo Castle had brought the Ifu&apos;s frustration to the boiling point.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>元慶2年（878年）3月、夷俘が蜂起して秋田城を急襲した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March in the second year of the Gangyo era (the year 878), the Ifu rose in revolt and ambushed Akita-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March in the second year of the Gangyo era (878), the Ifu rose in revolt and ambushed Akita-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March in the second year of the Gangyo era (878), the Ifu rose in revolt and ambushed Akita-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>秋田城司介良岑近は防戦しかねて逃亡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chikashi YOSHIMINE, the lord of Akita-jo Castle, had difficulty defending the castle and escaped.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chikashi YOSHIMINE, the lord of Akita-jo Castle, had difficulty defending the castle and was forced to escape.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikashi YOSHIMINE, the lord of Akita-jo Castle, had difficulty defending the castle and was forced to escape.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>夷俘は周辺に火を放ち、出羽守藤原興世も逃亡してしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ifu set fire around the castle, and then, even Dewa no Kami (Governor of Dewa Province), FUJIWARA no Okiyo fled, too.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ifu set fire around the castle, and then even Dewa no Kami (Governor of Dewa Province), FUJIWARA no Okiyo was forced to flee.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ifu set fire around the castle, and then even Dewa no Kami (Governor of Dewa Province), FUJIWARA no Okiyo was forced to flee.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>4月、出羽守よりの急使を受けた朝廷は、下野国と上野国にそれぞれ1000ずつの徴兵を命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April, the Imperial Court, which received an emergency messenger from Dewa no Kami, ordered Shimotsuke Province and Kozuke Province to each deploy one thousand soldiers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April the Imperial Court, which had received an emergency messenger from Dewa no Kami, ordered Shimotsuke and Kozuke provinces to each deploy 1,000 soldiers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April the Imperial Court, which had received an emergency messenger from Dewa no Kami, ordered Shimotsuke and Kozuke provinces to each deploy 1,000 soldiers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>19日には最上郡郡司擬大領の伴貞道が戦死する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gidairyo (Deputy Administrator) of the gunji (district government official) in Mogami-gun, TOMO no Sadamichi died in the battle on 19th.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TOMO no Sadamichi, Gidairyo (Deputy Administrator) of the gunji (district government official) in Mogami-gun, died in the battle on 19th.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TOMO no Sadamichi, Gidairyo (Deputy Administrator) of the gunji (district government official) in Mogami-gun, died in the battle on 19th.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>5月、朝廷は藤原梶長を押領使に任じて陸奥国より騎兵1000、歩兵2000を派遣して鎮圧に向かわせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May, the Imperial Court appointed FUJIWARA no Kajinaga to Oryoshi (military officer to subdue a rebellion) and deployed one thousand horse soldiers and two thousand foot soldiers from Mutsu Province to suppress the rebellion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May the Imperial Court appointed FUJIWARA no Kajinaga to Oryoshi (military officer to subdue a rebellion) and deployed 1,000 soldiers on horseback and 2,000 foot soldiers from Mutsu Province in order to suppress the rebellion.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May the Imperial Court appointed FUJIWARA no Kajinaga to Oryoshi (military officer to subdue a rebellion) and deployed 1,000 soldiers on horseback and 2,000 foot soldiers from Mutsu Province in order to suppress the rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>出羽掾藤原宗行、文室有房、小野春泉の出羽兵2000もこれに合流する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two thousands soldiers of the Dewa army led by Dewa no Jo, or the third-ranking official of the kokushi (provincial governors) in Dewa Province, FUJIWARA no Muneyuki as well as FUNYA no Arifusa and ONO no Haruizumi joined the forces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two thousand soldiers of the Dewa army led by FUJIWARA no Muneyuki, who was Dewa no Jo, or the third-ranking official of the kokushi (provincial governors) in Dewa Province, along with FUNYA no Arifusa and ONO no Haruizumi, joined the forces.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2,000 soldiers of the Dewa army led by FUJIWARA no Muneyuki, who was Dewa no Jo, or the third-ranking official of the kokushi (provincial governors) in Dewa Province, along with FUNYA no Arifusa and ONO no Haruizumi, joined the forces.</e>
<cmt>Two thousand → 2,000</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>6月、夷俘の軍勢が大挙して再度秋田城を襲い、官軍は大敗を喫して、藤原梶長も陸奥国へ逃げ帰ってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June, Ifu&apos;s forces attacked Akita-jo Castle again in droves and completely defeated the Imperial forces, causing FUJIWARA no Kajinaga to flee to Mutsu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June the Ifu&apos;s forces attacked Akita-jo Castle again in droves and completely defeated the imperial forces, causing FUJIWARA no Kajinaga to flee to Mutsu Province.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June the Ifu&apos;s forces attacked Akita-jo Castle again in droves and completely defeated the imperial forces, causing FUJIWARA no Kajinaga to flee to Mutsu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>城中の甲冑300領、米700石、衾（寝具）100条、馬1500匹が夷俘の有に帰した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ifu got hold of 300 armor, 700 goku (unit for crop yield) of rice, 100 fusuma (Japanese-style bedding) and 1500 horses, all of which had been left in the castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ifu seized 300 coats of armor, 700 goku (unit of crop yield) of rice, 100 fusuma (Japanese-style bedding) and 1,500 horses, all of which had been left in the castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ifu seized 300 coats of armor, 700 goku (unit of crop yield) of rice, 100 fusuma (Japanese-style bedding) and 1,500 horses, all of which had been left in the castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>反乱は拡大して秋田城下の12村（上津野、火内、榲淵、野代、河北、腋本、方口、大河、堤、姉刀、方上、焼岡）が夷俘の支配に落ち、出羽北部ではわずか3村（添河、覇別、助川）の俘囚だけが出羽国に属していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The rebellion spread and the twelve villages near Akita-jo Castle (Kazuno, Hinai, Sugibuchi, Noshiro, Kawakita, Wakimoto, Katakuchi, Okawa, Tsutsumi, Aneto, Katagami and Yakeoka) were occupied by the Ifu; in northern Dewa, only the Fushu (assimilated Emishi) in the three villages of Soekawa, Habetsu and Sukekawa belonged to Dewa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rebellion spread, and the 12 villages near Akita-jo Castle (Kazuno, Hinai, Sugibuchi, Noshiro, Kawakita, Wakimoto, Katakuchi, Okawa, Tsutsumi, Aneto, Katagami and Yakeoka) were occupied by the Ifu; in northern Dewa only the Fushu (assimilated Emishi) in the three villages of Soekawa, Habetsu and Sukekawa belonged to Dewa Province.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rebellion spread, and the 12 villages near Akita-jo Castle (Kazuno, Hinai, Sugibuchi, Noshiro, Kawakita, Wakimoto, Katakuchi, Okawa, Tsutsumi, Aneto, Katagami and Yakeoka) were occupied by the Ifu; in northern Dewa only the Fushu (assimilated Emishi) in the three villages of Soekawa, Habetsu and Sukekawa belonged to Dewa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>さらに津軽・渡嶋の蝦夷も蜂起した蝦夷を支援する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, the Emishi in Tsugaru and Watarishima supported the Emishi in revolt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, the Emishi in Tsugaru and Watarishima supported the Emishi in revolt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the Emishi in Tsugaru and Watarishima supported the Emishi in revolt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>5月、朝廷は左中弁藤原保則を出羽権守に任じて討伐にあたらせることとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May, the Imperial Court appointed Sachuben (Middle Controller of the Left), FUJIWARA no Yasunori to Dewa no Gon no Kami (Provincial Governor of Dewa Province) to subdue the rebellion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May the Imperial Court appointed Sachuben (Middle Controller of the Left) FUJIWARA no Yasunori to Dewa no Gon no Kami (Provincial Governor of Dewa Province) in order to subdue the rebellion.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May the Imperial Court appointed Sachuben (Middle Controller of the Left) FUJIWARA no Yasunori to Dewa no Gon no Kami (Provincial Governor of Dewa Province) in order to subdue the rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>保則は備中国、備前国の国司として善政をうたわれた人物であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasunori had been known for governing Bicchu and Bizen Provinces properly as their kokushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasunori had been known for governing Bicchu and Bizen provinces effectively as their kokushi.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasunori had been known for governing Bicchu and Bizen provinces effectively as their kokushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>保則は小野春風の起用を願い、6月、春風は鎮守府将軍に任命される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He requested the appointment of ONO no Harukaze, and in June, Harukaze was appointed to Shogun of the chinju-fu (military government post to subdue the Emishi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He requested the appointment of ONO no Harukaze, and in June Harukaze was appointed as the shogun of the chinju-fu (military government post to subdue the Emishi).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He requested the appointment of ONO no Harukaze, and in June Harukaze was appointed as the shogun of the chinju-fu (military government post to subdue the Emishi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>陸奥介坂上好蔭（坂上田村麻呂の曾孫）とともに出羽国へ向かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasunori left for Dewa Province along with Mutsu no Suke (Deputy Governor of Mutsu Province) and a great-grandson of SAKANOUE no Tamuramaro, SAKANOUE no Yoshikage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasunori left for Dewa Province along with Mutsu no Suke (Deputy Governor of Mutsu Province) and a great-grandson of SAKANOUE no Tamuramaro, SAKANOUE no Yoshikage.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasunori left for Dewa Province along with Mutsu no Suke (Deputy Governor of Mutsu Province) and a great-grandson of SAKANOUE no Tamuramaro, SAKANOUE no Yoshikage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>この時点で俘囚3人が陣営に来て、雄物川以北を朝廷の直接支配が及ばない「己地」となすことを要求した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this point, three Ifu visited the base of the Imperial forces and demanded that the regions to the north of the Omono-gawa River be out of the direct influence from the Imperial Court and be called &apos;kochi (己地).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that point three Ifu visited the base of the imperial forces and demanded that the regions to the north of the Omono-gawa River be out of the direct influence from the Imperial Court and be called &apos;kochi (己地).&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that point three Ifu visited the base of the imperial forces and demanded that the regions to the north of the Omono-gawa River be out of the direct influence from the Imperial Court and be called &apos;kochi (己地).&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="23">
<j>保則は文室有房、上野国押領使南淵秋郷に命じて上野国兵600人と俘囚300人をもって夷俘に備えさせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasunori ordered FUNYA no Arifusa and Oryoshi of Kozuke Province, MINABUCHI no Akisato to prepare for the Ifu with 600 soldiers of Kozuke Province and 300 Fushu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasunori ordered FUNYA no Arifusa and MINABUCHI no Akisato, Oryoshi of Kozuke Province, to prepare for the Ifu with 600 soldiers of Kozuke Province and 300 Fushu.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasunori ordered FUNYA no Arifusa and MINABUCHI no Akisato, Oryoshi of Kozuke Province, to prepare for the Ifu with 600 soldiers of Kozuke Province and 300 Fushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>これら軍事的措置をすませたうえで、朝廷の不動穀を賑給して懐柔にあたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After preparing military measures, he supplied the Imperial Court&apos;s fudokoku (crops stored for emergency) to the poor Ifu in the regions to appease them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After preparing military measures, he supplied the Imperial Court&apos;s fudokoku (crops stored for emergency) to the poor Ifu in the regions as a means to appease them.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After preparing military measures, he supplied the Imperial Court&apos;s fudokoku (crops stored for emergency) to the poor Ifu in the regions as a means to appease them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>保則の寛大な施策の一環である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was a part of his sympathetic policies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was a part of his sympathetic policies.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was a part of his sympathetic policies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>また、保則の手持ちの兵力が寡兵であるため常陸国、武蔵国の兵2000を動員する許可を朝廷に求めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, Yasunori requested for the deployment of 2000 soldiers from Hitachi and Musashi Provinces because the soldiers under him were outnumbered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, Yasunori requested the deployment of 2,000 soldiers from Hitachi and Musashi provinces because the soldiers under him were outnumbered.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, Yasunori requested the deployment of 2,000 soldiers from Hitachi and Musashi provinces because the soldiers under him were outnumbered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="27">
<j>8月、夷俘の集団が次々と秋田城下に来て降伏してきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August, one after another band of the Ifu came to the castle town of Akita-jo Castle to surrender.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August, one after another band of the Ifu came to the castle town of Akita-jo Castle and surrendered.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August, one after another band of the Ifu came to the castle town of Akita-jo Castle and surrendered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>寛政の噂が広まり、夷俘の敵意が和らいだためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was because the rumor of the kansei (sympathetic policies) had spread and thus reduced Ifu&apos;s hostility.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was because the rumor of the kansei (sympathetic policies) had spread and thus reduced the Ifu&apos;s hostility.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was because the rumor of the kansei (sympathetic policies) had spread and thus reduced the Ifu&apos;s hostility.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>保則は来降を許したが、元慶3年（879年）1月、朝廷は討伐の強行を命じてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasunori accepted Ifu&apos;s surrender, but in January of the third year of the Gangyo era (the year 879), the Imperial Court ordered him to suppress the Ifu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasunori accepted the Ifu&apos;s surrender, but in January of the third year of the Gangyo era (879) the Imperial Court ordered him to suppress the Ifu.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasunori accepted the Ifu&apos;s surrender, but in January of the third year of the Gangyo era (879) the Imperial Court ordered him to suppress the Ifu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>これに対して保則は出羽国の現状を報告して、寛大な政策をおこなって苛政によって逃亡した夷俘の還住を促すことこそ上策であると意見した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In response to this, he reported about the status of Dewa Province and stated the opinion that adopting a sympathetic policy to urge the Ifu, who had fled from their homes due to the misrule, to return to their homes would be a better strategy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In response he reported on the status of Dewa Province and stated the opinion that it would be better to adopt a sympathetic policy to urge the Ifu--who had fled from their homes due to misrule--to return to their homes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response he reported on the status of Dewa Province and stated the opinion that it would be better to adopt a sympathetic policy to urge the Ifu, who had fled from their homes due to misrule, to return to their homes.</e>
<cmt>「--」→,</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>朝廷はこの意見を容れて3月、征夷の軍を解いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial Court accepted his opinion and disbanded the Imperial forces against the Emishi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Court accepted his opinion and disbanded the forces against the Emishi.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Court accepted his opinion and disbanded the forces against the Emishi in March.</e>
<cmt>「in March」を補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>異説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other speculations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other speculations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other speculations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="32">
<j>元慶の乱は朝廷側の蝦夷に対する懐柔政策が功を奏して、蝦夷は降伏したとするが、これに異を唱える人もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some people disputed the idea that appeasement policy of the Imperial side towards the Emishi led to their surrender in the Gangyo War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some people have disputed the idea that appeasement policy of the imperial side toward the Emishi led to their surrender in the Gangyo War.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people have disputed the idea that appeasement policy of the imperial side toward the Emishi led to their surrender in the Gangyo War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="33">
<j>まず、広範囲の蝦夷をまとめて、自分たちの要求を朝廷側に文書にして提出するなど、反乱を指導した人物がいるはずであるが、この人物が朝廷側の多数の犠牲者(焼山での戦いだけで500人以上が死亡あるいは捕虜になったという)にもかかわらず彼らの名前が明確に記録されていないなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First, although there should have been the masterminds of the rebellion who united the widely spread Emishi and submitted the petition in writing to the Imperial Court, their names were not clearly recorded on the list of a large number of casualties (more than five hundred people were killed or captured in the battle of Mt. Yake-yama alone.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First, although there should have been masterminds of the rebellion who united the widely dispersed Emishi and submitted a written petition to the Imperial Court, their names weren&apos;t clearly recorded on the list of a large number of casualties (more than 500 people were killed or captured in the battle of Mt. Yake-yama alone).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First, although there must have been rebellion ringleaders who had united the widely dispersed Emishi and presented a written petition to the Imperial Court, their names weren&apos;t clearly recorded on the long list of casualties (more than 500 people were killed or captured in the battle of Mt. Yake-yama alone).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。#削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>(一応首謀者とされる2人の「首」は蝦夷側から提出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &apos;heads&apos; of two supposed masterminds were at least offered by the Emishi side.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &apos;heads&apos; of two supposed masterminds were at least offered by the Emishi side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;heads&apos; of two supposed ringleaders were at least offered by the Emishi side.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。#削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>しかし、これは朝廷側が独自に処分できなかったことを意味している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This means, however, that the Imperial Court itself was unable to punish them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this means the Imperial Court was unable to punish them.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this means the Imperial Court was unable to punish them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>これだけの被害なら、アテルイのように必ず文書に残っているはずという主張もある。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some people also indicate that in such an incident with a large number of victims as this, written records should have always been left as in the case of Aterui.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some people also indicate that in such an incident with a large number of victims as this, written records should have always been left, as in the case of Aterui.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people also indicate that in such an incident with a large number of victims as this, written records should have always been left, as in the case of Aterui.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>また915年北東北に2000年来最大の自然災害である十和田湖火山の大噴火が起きるが、この噴火あるいはそれに続く広範囲の自然災害が全く文書で記述されていないこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, the eruption of the volcano in Lake Towada-ko, the largest disaster in two millennia, occurred in the northern Tohoku region in 915, but, nothing about the eruption or a series of natural disasters after it had been documented.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, the eruption of the volcano in Lake Towada-ko--the largest disaster in two millennia--occurred in the northern Tohoku region in 915, but nothing about the eruption or a series of natural disasters after it had been documented.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, the eruption of the volcano in Lake Towada-ko (the largest disaster in two millennia) occurred in the northern Tohoku region in 915, but nothing about the eruption or a series of natural disasters after it had been documented.</e>
<cmt>「--」→()</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>などから、この元慶の乱は事実上蝦夷側の要求が通り、雄物川以北は蝦夷側の支配する地区となり、朝廷が手を出せなくなってしまったのではないかとする人もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For these reasons, some even assume that in the Gangyo War, the request of the Emishi side was practically granted, and that the Emishi took over the reins of the region to the north of the Omono-gawa River, which even the Imperial Court could no longer touch.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For these reasons, some even assume that in the Gangyo War the request of the Emishi side was practically granted, and that the Emishi took over the reins of the region to the north of the Omono-gawa River, which even the Imperial Court could no longer touch.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For these reasons, some even assume that in the Gangyo War the request of the Emishi side was practically granted, and that the Emishi took over the reins of the region to the north of the Omono-gawa River, which even the Imperial Court could no longer touch.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>同時期に仙北郡で極めて大規模な城柵として使わたのにも関わらず、記録が全く残っていない払田柵跡にあった施設で中央から監視しに来た人を接待したのではないかとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another theory maintains that there has been no record of facilities at the site of the Hotta no saku (fort in Hotta), though they had formed an extremely large fort, because officials sent from the central government to monitor the region were entertained in those facilities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another theory maintains that there has been no record of facilities at the site of the Hotta no saku (fort in Hotta), though they had constructed an extremely large fort, because officials sent from the central government to monitor the region were entertained in those facilities.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another theory maintains that there has been no record of facilities at the site of the Hotta no saku (fort in Hotta), though they had constructed an extremely large fort, because officials sent from the central government to monitor the region were entertained in those facilities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>いずれにせよ、全く記録に残っていない払田柵の存在は当時のこの地区の人が中央の管理とは別に比較的自由に行動できたことを示す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In either case, the presence of the Hotta no saku without any record indicates that people in the region at that time were able to act relatively freely irrelevant of the control of the central government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In either case, the presence of the Hotta no saku without any record indicates that people in the region at that time were able to act with relative freedom, irrespective of the control of the central government.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In either case, the presence of the Hotta no saku without any record indicates that people in the region at that time were able to act with relative freedom, irrespective of the control of the central government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="41">
<j>元慶の乱が始まる直前に、秋田城の対北海道蝦夷の饗給の増大は、出羽国の財政を圧迫するまでに問題化していたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Right before the Gangyo War, increase in the cost of Akita-jo Castle to appease the Emishi in Hokkaido had become a problem up to the extent to which pressure was put on the finance of Dewa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Immediately before the Gangyo War, the increase in the cost of Akita-jo Castle to appease the Emishi in Hokkaido had become a problem, to the extent that the finances of Dewa Province were put under pressure.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Immediately before the Gangyo War, the increase in the cost of Akita-jo Castle to appease the Emishi in Hokkaido had become a problem, to the extent that the finances of Dewa Province were put under pressure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>また乱の収束後、元慶の乱時に国家側と対立した地域には、9世紀末から10世紀にかけて秋田十二林窯、青森五所川原窯などが相次いで出現した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the rebellion was over, furthermore, the Akita Junibayashi kama kiln and the Aomori Goshogawara kama kiln were built one after another from the end of the ninth century to the tenth century in the regions where people fought against the central government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, once the rebellion was over the Akita Junibayashi kama kiln and the Aomori Goshogawara kama kiln were built in succession from the end of the ninth century to the tenth century in the regions where people fought against the central government.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, once the rebellion was over the Akita Junibayashi kama kiln and the Aomori Goshogawara kama kiln were built in succession from the end of the ninth century to the tenth century in the regions where people fought against the central government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>これらは秋田城が独占していた対北海道蝦夷貿易がこの地区の新興階層の手に移行したことを示唆しているとする人もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This shows, according to some, that trade with the Emishi in Hokkaido which Akita-jo Castle had monopolized was taken over by the emerging class of people in these regions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to some, this shows that trade with the Emishi in Hokkaido, which Akita-jo Castle had monopolized, was taken over by the emerging class of people in these regions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to some, this shows that trade with the Emishi in Hokkaido, which Akita-jo Castle had monopolized, was taken over by the emerging class of people in these regions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>十和田湖火山噴火に伴う洪水から高台に逃げ出した集落からは、専門に鉄製品を作っていた集落も発掘されており(大館市)蝦夷は鉄を朝廷側から得る必要も無かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The settlement specializing in producing iron products was found in Odate City from the settlements that had escaped from the flood caused by the eruption of the volcano in Lake Towada-ko; this demonstrates that the Emishi did not need to obtain even iron from the side of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The settlement specializing in iron products was found in Odate City from the settlements that had escaped the flood caused by the eruption of the volcano in Lake Towada-ko, thus demonstrating that the Emishi didn&apos;t need to obtain even iron from the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The settlement specializing in iron products was found in Odate City from the settlements that had escaped the flood caused by the eruption of the volcano in Lake Towada-ko, thus demonstrating that the Emishi didn&apos;t need to obtain even iron from the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>影響とその後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Influences and consequences</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Influences and consequences</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Influences and consequences</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="45">
<j>藤原保則は武力によらず寛政によって反乱の鎮撫に成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yasunori succeeded in pacifying the rebellion, not by force, but by the kansei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Yasunori succeeded in pacifying the rebellion, not by force but through the use of kansei.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yasunori succeeded in pacifying the rebellion, not by force but through the use of kansei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>一方でこれは、朝廷の力が低下して坂上田村麻呂の時代のように武力によって夷俘を制圧できなくなっていたことも意味していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This, on the other hand, showed that the weakened Imperial Court could no longer subdue the Ifu by force unlike the days of SAKANOUE no Tamuramaro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This, however, showed that the weakened Imperial Court could no longer forcibly subdue the Ifu as it could in the days of SAKANOUE no Tamuramaro.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This, however, showed that the weakened Imperial Court could no longer forcibly subdue the Ifu as it could in the days of SAKANOUE no Tamuramaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>夷俘は降伏したが朝廷による苛政をくつがえし、力を示したことで一定の成功を収めたと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that although they surrendered, the Ifu accomplished their mission to some degree by ending the misrule by the Imperial Court and proving their power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that although they had surrendered, the Ifu accomplished their mission to some degree by ending the misrule by the Imperial Court and demonstrating their power.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that although they had surrendered, the Ifu accomplished their mission to some degree by ending the misrule by the Imperial Court and demonstrating their power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="48">
<j>乱後、秋田城は保則の手により再建された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akita-jo Castle was restored by Yasunori after the rebellion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akita-jo Castle was restored by Yasunori after the rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akita-jo Castle was restored by Yasunori after the rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>出羽国司次官である介が受領官に格上げされると共に、秋田城常駐となり軍事機能も強化された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The position of Suke, Deputy Governor of the kokushi in Dewa Province, was promoted to that of Zuryo (Provincial Governor), and the position was permanently stationed at Akita-jo Castle, enhancing its military capabilities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The position of Suke, Deputy Governor of the kokushi in Dewa Province, was promoted to that of Zuryo (Provincial Governor), and the position was permanently stationed at Akita-jo Castle, enhancing its military capabilities.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The position of Suke, Deputy Governor of the kokushi in Dewa Province, was promoted to that of Zuryo (Provincial Governor), and the position was permanently stationed at Akita-jo Castle, enhancing its military capabilities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>これは後に秋田城介と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The position was later called Akitajo no Suke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The position was later called Akitajo no Suke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The position was later called Akitajo no Suke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>玉造麻呂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAMATSUKURI Maro</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAMATSUKURI Maro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAMATSUKURI Maro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="51">
<j>北秋田市の胡桃舘遺跡から1967年発掘されていた木簡に「月料給出物名張」とされるものがあると2005年発表された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 2005, it was announced that one of the wooden tablets unearthed from the Kurumidate site in 1967 is inscribed with the words &apos;Getsuryo-kyushutsubutsu-meicho&apos; (月料給出物名張), or roughly meaning monthly supply ledger.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 2005 it was announced that one of the wooden tablets unearthed from the Kurumidate site in 1967 is inscribed with the words &apos;Getsuryo-kyushutsubutsu-meicho&apos; (月料給出物名張), which basically means a monthly supply ledger.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 2005 it was announced that one of the wooden tablets unearthed from the Kurumidate site in 1967 is inscribed with the words &apos;Getsuryo-kyushutsubutsu-meicho&apos; (月料給出物名張), which basically means a monthly supply ledger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>これによると、この木簡には「玉造麻呂」などの名前が記されており、それぞれに「米三合」などの数量が書かれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the announcement, the tablet is also inscribed with names such as &apos;TAMATSUKURI no Maro,&apos; each accompanied by quantities such as &apos;Kome Sango&apos; (6 oz. rice).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the announcement, the tablet is also inscribed with names such as &apos;TAMATSUKURI no Maro,&apos; each accompanied by quantities such as &apos;Kome Sango&apos; (six ounces of rice).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the announcement, the tablet is also inscribed with names such as &apos;TAMATSUKURI no Maro,&apos; each accompanied by quantities such as &apos;Kome Sango&apos; (six ounces of rice).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>玉造は元慶の乱の時に、政府側についた蝦夷の名字であるため、この915年十和田火山の噴火によって埋没した遺跡との関係があるのではないかと指摘された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tamatsukuri is a family name of the Emishi who sided with the Imperial government during the Gangyo War, and accordingly, it is pointed out that the family might have connected with the site buried by the eruption of the volcano in Lake Towada-ko in 915.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tamatsukuri is a family name of the Emishi who had sided with the Imperial government during the Gangyo War, and accordingly it is pointed out that the family might have connected with the site buried by the eruption of the volcano in Lake Towada-ko in 915.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tamatsukuri is a family name of the Emishi who had sided with the Imperial government during the Gangyo War, and accordingly it is pointed out that the family might have connected with the site buried by the eruption of the volcano in Lake Towada-ko in 915.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kiyok(id:76023), FCTR3(id:246533), Cyuuritsu Na Shitenn(id:102276), Reggaeman(id:6214), Law soma(id:45202), 怪蘇(id:45514), 味っ子(id:17086), YOSHI438(id:174755), らんで(id:58934), 小者(id:172526), Hotsuregua(id:99069), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>