<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>遣明船</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenminsen (envoy ships dispatched to Ming China)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenminsen (envoy ships dispatched to Ming China)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenminsen</e>
<cmt>以下説明が続くので、英語説明を削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>遣明船（けんみんせん）は室町時代の応永11年（1404年）から天文 (元号)16年（1547年）まで約1世紀半で17次（のべ84隻）に渡り、日明貿易（勘合貿易）に用いられた船のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenminsen means ships dispatched to Ming China in the Muromachi period for 17 times (the total number of ships was 84) during the period of one and a half centuries from 1404 to 1547 for the purpose of Nichi-Ming trade (the trade between Japan and the Ming Dynasty, China) (Kango trade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenminsen means ships dispatched seventeen times to Ming China in the Muromachi period seventeen times (the total number of ships was eighty-four) during the period of one and a half centuries from 1404 to 1547 for the purpose of Nichi-Ming trade (trade between Japan and the Ming Dynasty, China) (Kango trade).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenminsen means ships dispatched seventeen times to Ming China in the Muromachi period (the total number of ships was eighty-four) during the period of one and a half centuries from 1404 to 1547 for the purpose of Nichi-Ming trade (trade between Japan and the Ming Dynasty, China) (Kango trade).</e>
<cmt>seventeen times 削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日明貿易には、両国により正式の渡航船であることを証明する勘合符が用いられたことから、勘合船とも呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These ships were also called Kangosen since both government issued a certificate called Kangofu in order to prove the visiting ships were lawfully registered ships for Nichi-Ming trade.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These ships were also called Kangosen since both governments issued a certificate called Kangofu in order to prove the visiting ships were lawfully registered ships for Nichi-Ming trade.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These ships were also called Kangosen since both governments issued a certificate called Kangofu in order to prove the visiting ships were lawfully registered ships for Nichi-Ming trade.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>足利義満は、応永8年（1401年）に僧の祖阿と博多商人の肥富を派遣し、明との交易を申し入れ、明の使者から「永楽の勘合符」を得て、勘合貿易が始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kango trade started in 1401 when Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA proposed to start the trade with Ming by dispatching a Buddhist monk Soa and a merchant in Hakata Koitomi and received &quot;Eiraku kangofu&quot; from the envoy of Ming.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kango trade started in 1401 when Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA proposed to start the trade with Ming by dispatching a Buddhist monk Soa and a merchant in Hakata Koitomi and received &quot;Eiraku kangofu&quot; from the envoy of Ming.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kango trade started in 1401 when Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA proposed to start the trade with Ming by dispatching a Buddhist monk Soa and a merchant in Hakata Koitomi and received &apos;Eiraku kangofu&apos; from the envoy of Ming.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>遣明船は当初、幕府が直接船主となり運航していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, bakufu was the shipowner of Kenminsen and directly operated them.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, the bakufu was the shipowner of Kenminsen and directly operated them.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, the bakufu was the shipowner of Kenminsen and directly operated them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>幕府の力がしだいに弱まるようになると有力寺社（相国寺、三十三間堂など）や有力守護大名（細川氏、大内氏など）が船主となり、これに博多や堺の商人、瀬戸内海の町、水夫が結びついて貿易を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the power of bakufu gradually declined, influential temples/shrines (Shoku-ji Temple, Sanjusangendo Temple etc) or influential shogo-daimyo (territorial lords as provincial constables) (the Hosokawa clan, the Ouchi clan etc.) became the shipowners and did trade in corporation with merchants in Hakata and Sakai as well as sailors in the towns located in the coastal region of Seto Inland Sea.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the power of bakufu gradually declining, influential temples/shrines (Shoku-ji Temple, Sanjusangendo Temple etc) or influential shogo-daimyo (territorial lords as provincial constables) (the Hosokawa clan, the Ouchi clan etc.) became the shipowners and traded in corporation with merchants in Hakata and Sakai as well as sailors in the towns located in the coastal region of Seto Inland Sea.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the power of bakufu gradually declining, influential temples/shrines (Shokoku-ji Temple, Sanjusangendo Temple etc) or influential shugo-daimyo (territorial lords as provincial constables) (the Hosokawa clan, the Ouchi clan etc.) became the shipowners and traded in corporation with merchants in Hakata and Sakai as well as sailors in the towns located in the coastal region of Seto Inland Sea.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>最終的には貿易の主導権を巡り細川氏と大内氏は争い、大永3年（1523年）には寧波で衝突（寧波の乱）し、大内氏は貿易を独占することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hosokawa clan and Ouchi clan competed for seizing the initiative of trade, clashed at Neiha in 1523 and finally the Ouchi clan monopolized the trade.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hosokawa clan and Ouchi clan competed to seize the initiative of trade, clashed at Neiha in 1523 and finally the Ouchi clan monopolized the trade.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hosokawa clan and Ouchi clan competed to seize the initiative of trade, clashed at Neiha in 1523 and finally the Ouchi clan monopolized the trade.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>結果、大内氏の本拠である山口は応仁の乱で荒廃した京都よりはるかに繁栄することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Yamaguch, the base of the Ouchi clan, prospered far more than Kyoto that was devastated by the Onin War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Yamaguchi, the base of the Ouchi clan, prospered far more than Kyoto that was devastated by the Onin War.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Yamaguchi, the base of the Ouchi clan, prospered far more than Kyoto that was devastated by the Onin War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>規模</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Scale</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Scale</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Scale</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>1406年に帰国した第二次遣明船は6～7隻と記録が残っており、1410に足利義持が中止するまでの初期6回の遣明船の船団規模は同程度であったと推定される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the record is existent that the number of ships of second Kenminsen fleet returned to Japan in ? was 6 to 7, it is presumed that the scale of six Kenminsen fleets which visited Ming until Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA ceased dispatching in ? was in the same range.</e>
<cmt>原文から年号が欠落しております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the record exists that the number of ships of the second Kenminsen fleet returned to Japan in ? was six to seven, it is presumed that the scale of six Kenminsen fleets which visited Ming until Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA ceased dispatching them in ? was within the same range.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the record exists that the number of ships of the second Kenminsen fleet returned to Japan in 1406 was six to seven, it is presumed that the scale of six Kenminsen fleets which visited Ming until Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA ceased dispatching them in 1410 was within the same range.</e>
<cmt>年号を原文、訳文に補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>21年の中断を経て、足利義教が1432に再開し、1550までに11次51隻（このうち、幕府所有船は7隻で、朝廷船1隻、残りは守護大名、寺社所有船であった）が渡航している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After 21 years of interruption, Yoshinori Ashikaga resumed the operation in ? and 11 fleets or 51 ships (7 ships were owned by bakufu, one was owned by the Imperial Court and the rest were owned by shugo-daimyo or temples/shrines) visited Ming until ?.</e>
<cmt>原文から年号が欠落しております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After twenty-one years of interruption, Yoshinori Ashikaga resumed the operation in ? and eleven fleets or fifty-one ships (seven ships were owned by the bakufu, one was owned by the Imperial Court and the rest were owned by theshugo-daimyo or temples/shrines) visited Ming until ?.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After twenty-one years of interruption, Yoshinori ASHIKAGA resumed the operation in 1432 and eleven fleets or fifty-one ships (seven ships were owned by the bakufu, one was owned by the Imperial Court and the rest were owned by the shugo-daimyo or temples/shrines) visited Ming until 1550.</e>
<cmt>人名修正年号を原文、訳文に補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>1468に足利義政の命令で明に渡った禅僧の天与清啓が記録した『戊子入明記』によると、遣明船は700～1700石の大型船で150人程度の乗員（内水夫50人）であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Boshi Nyuminki &quot; written by Zen monk Tenyo Seikei, who visited Ming in ? at the behest of Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, large ships, whose size were 700 to 1700 goku (a unit of ship size), were used for Kenminsen and 150 persons (including 50 sailors) were on board.</e>
<cmt>原文から年号が欠落しております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Boshi Nyuminki &quot; written by Zen monk Tenyo Seikei, who visited Ming in ? at the behest of Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, large ships, whose size were 700 to 1700 goku (a unit of ship size), were used for Kenminsen and 150 persons (including fifty sailors) were on board.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Boshi Nyuminki&quot; written by Zen monk Tenyo Seikei, who visited Ming in 1468 at the behest of Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, large ships, whose size were 700 to 1700 goku (a unit of ship size), were used for Kenminsen and 150 persons (including fifty sailors) were on board.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、『入明諸要例』では同次遣明船について500～2500石の船が門司、富田、上関、柳井、尾道、鞆、田島、因島、牛窓に配されたとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Nyumin shoyorei&quot;, ships of 500 to 2500 goku were on standby at Moji, Tomita, Kamiseki, Yanai, Onomichi, Tomo, Tajima, Innoshima and Ushimado respectively for the same fleet of Kenminsen.</e>
<cmt>入明諸要例 - 読み、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Nyumin shoyorei,&quot; ships of 500 to 2500 goku were on standby at Moji, Tomita, Kamiseki, Yanai, Onomichi, Tomo, Tajima, Innoshima and Ushimado respectively for the same fleet of Kenminsen.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Nyumin shoyorei,&quot; ships of 500 to 2500 goku were on standby at Moji, Tomita, Kamiseki, Yanai, Onomichi, Tomo, Tajima, Innoshima and Ushimado respectively for the same fleet of Kenminsen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>いずれにせよ、遣明船には相当の大型船が用いられたと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At any rate, it is considered that relatively large ships were used for Kenminsen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At any rate, it is considered that relatively large ships were used for Kenminsen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At any rate, it is considered that relatively large ships were used for Kenminsen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>応仁の乱以後には3隻、人員300人に限定される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Onin War, the scale of Kenminsen was limited to three ships and 300 persons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Onin War, the scale of Kenminsen was limited to three ships and 300 persons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Onin War, the scale of Kenminsen was limited to three ships and 300 persons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>航海術</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Navigation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Navigation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Navigation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>遣明船は、季節風を利用して航海を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenminsen sailed using seasonal winds.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenminsen sailed using seasonal winds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenminsen sailed using seasonal winds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>春又は秋の東北の季節風に乗って大陸へ渡り、5月以降、西南西の季節風に乗り、日本へ帰国した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ships left for the Asian continent in Spring or Autumn using a northeast seasonal wind and returned to Japan after May using a west-southwest seasonal wind.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ships left for the Asian continent in Spring or Autumn using a northeast seasonal winds and returned to Japan after May using a west-southwest seasonal winds.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ships left for the Asian continent in Spring or Autumn using a northeast seasonal winds and returned to Japan after May using a west-southwest seasonal winds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>宋 (王朝)代には磁鉄鉱から永久磁石を作るようになり、羅針盤の発見も済んでおり、永正の航海書にも「磁石の針」との言及があることから、遣明船は原始的コンパスを利用した航海を行っていたと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Judging from the fact that the production of permanent magnet made of magnetite began in the age of the Sung dynasty, compass was already invented by that time and the term &quot;magnetic pointer&quot; is seen in the navigation book written in the Eisho era, it is considered that Kenminsen sailed using primitive compass.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Judging from the fact that the production of permanent magnets made of magnetite began in the age of the Sung dynasty, the compass was already invented by that time and the term &quot;magnetic pointer&quot; is seen in the navigation book written in the Eisho era, it is considered that Kenminsen sailed using a primitive compass.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Judging from the fact that the production of permanent magnets made of magnetite began in the age of the Sung Dynasty, the compass was already invented by that time and the term &apos;magnetic pointer&apos; is seen in the navigation book written in the Eisho era, it is considered that Kenminsen sailed using a primitive compass.</e>
<cmt>用語統一&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>航路は堺、兵庫から瀬戸内海を通り、下関、博多を経由し東シナ海を直線的に横断して寧波を目指した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Staring from Sakai or Hyogo, Kenminsen passed Seto Inland Sea, stopped at Shimonoseki or Hakata and sailed for Neiha by traversing the East China Sea in a linear fashion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Starting from Sakai or Hyogo, Kenminsen passed the Seto Inland Sea, stopped at Shimonoseki or Hakata and sailed for Neiha by traversing the East China Sea in a linear fashion.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Starting from Sakai or Hyogo, Kenminsen passed the Seto Inland Sea, stopped at Shimonoseki or Hakata and sailed for Neiha by traversing the East China Sea in a linear fashion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>細川氏と大内氏の対立が深まると、細川氏は大内氏の山口の側を通る瀬戸内航路を避け、土佐の浦戸、下田、南九州の油津、坊津を経由して寧波に行く航路をとった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the confrontation between the Hosokawa clan and Ouchi clan became serious, the Hosokawa clan avoided to take the route of Seto Inland Sea which passed near Yamaguchi, the base of the Ouchi clan, and instead took the route to sail for Neiha via Urado and Shimoda in Tosa Province and Aburatsu and Bonotsu in southern Kyushu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the confrontation between the Hosokawa clan and Ouchi clan became serious, the Hosokawa clan avoided taking the Seto Inland Sea route that passed near Yamaguchi, the base of the Ouchi clan, and instead took the route to sail for Neiha via Urado and Shimoda in Tosa Province and Aburatsu and Bonotsu in southern Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the confrontation between the Hosokawa clan and Ouchi clan became serious, the Hosokawa clan avoided taking the Seto Inland Sea route that passed near Yamaguchi, the base of the Ouchi clan, and instead took the route to sail for Neiha via Urado and Shimoda in Tosa Province and Aburatsu and Bonotsu in southern Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>船体構造</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The structure of the hull</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The structure of the hull</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The structure of the hull</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>遣明船は遣唐使船と異なり、専用船を新造したわけではなく、国内の民間の廻船（商船）の借り入れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike the case of Kentoshisen (envoy ships dispatched to Tang, China), ships of Kenminsen were not the ones that were newly built for exclusive use but the rented private ships (merchant ships).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike the case of Kentoshisen (envoy ships dispatched to Tang, China), ships of Kenminsen were not the ones that were newly built for exclusive use but the rented private ships (merchant ships).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike the case of Kentoshisen (envoy ships dispatched to Tang, China), ships of Kenminsen were not the ones that were newly built for exclusive use but the rented private ships (merchant ships).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>遣明船として遠洋航海用に艤装品を充実させ、外交使節や有力商人などの居室用の屋形を増設するなど大規模改修を行って用いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These rented ships were used for Kenminsen after conducting major renovation such as the installation of hull fittings suitable for ocean navigation and the expansion of cabins for diplomatic envoys or influential merchants.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These rented ships were used for Kenminsen after conducting major renovation such as the installation of hull fittings suitable for ocean navigation and the expansion of cabins for diplomatic envoys or influential merchants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These rented ships were used for Kenminsen after conducting major renovation such as the installation of hull fittings suitable for ocean navigation and the expansion of cabins for diplomatic envoys or influential merchants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="21">
<j>船体構造は木を刳（く）り貫いて造られる航（かわら：船底部）の部材（刳船部材）を板材に置き換え、両角に重木（おもき）というL型の丈夫な部材を用い、数枚の棚板を重ね継ぎして、多数の船梁（ふなばり）で補強した、棚板造りの構造であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The structure of hull was Tanaita (shelf boards) structure using sawn timber as the component of Kawara (the components for the bottom of a ship), instead of the ones hollowed from a tree trunk, L-shaped strong components called Omoki for both sides and several layered Tanaita reinforced by many Funabari (beams fitted horizontally between the planks on the hull of a ship for preventing water pressure).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The structure of the hull was Tanaita (shelf boards) structure using sawn timber as the component of Kawara (the components for the bottom of a ship), instead of the ones hollowed from a tree trunk, L-shaped strong components called Omoki for both sides and several layered Tanaita reinforced by many Funabari (beams fitted horizontally between the planks on the hull of a ship to withstand water pressure).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The structure of the hull was Tanaita (shelf boards) structure using sawn timber as the component of Kawara (the components for the bottom of a ship), instead of the ones hollowed from a tree trunk, L-shaped strong components called Omoki for both sides and several layered Tanaita reinforced by many Funabari (beams fitted horizontally between the planks on the hull of a ship to withstand water pressure).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>棚板構成は、根棚・中棚・上棚の三階造りと中棚のない二階造りが基本となり、大型船では中棚を二段にした四階造りのものも存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basic structure of Tanaita was either three layered structure consists of Nedana (the components to structure the lowest part of a ship), Chudana (the components to structure the middle part of a ship) and Uedana (the components to structure the upper part of a ship) or two layered structure without Chudana and in the case of large ships, four layered structure with two layered Chudana was also seen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Basic structure of Tanaita was either three layered structure consists of Nedana (the components to structure the lowest part of a ship), Chudana (the components to structure the middle part of a ship) and Uedana (the components to structure the upper part of a ship) or two layered structure without Chudana and in the case of large ships, four layered structure with two layered Chudana was also seen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Basic structure of Tanaita was either three layered structure consists of Nedana (the components to structure the lowest part of a ship), Chudana (the components to structure the middle part of a ship) and Uedana (the components to structure the upper part of a ship) or two layered structure without Chudana and in the case of large ships, four layered structure with two layered Chudana was also seen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>船首形状は多様で、伊勢船の戸立（とだて）造り、弁才船の水押（みよし）造り、上部を箱造り下部を水押造りとする二形（ふたなり）船の折衷形式がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shape of bows varied widely depending on ships and Todate style of Ise ships, Miyoshi style of Bensai ships and the blending style of Futanari ships, whose upper side was box style and lower side was Miyoshi style, were seen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shape of bows varied widely depending on ships and Todate style of Ise ships, Miyoshi style of Bensai ships and the blending style of Futanari ships, whose upper side was box style and lower side was Miyoshi style, were seen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shape of bows varied widely depending on ships and Todate style of Ise ships, Miyoshi style of Bensai ships and the blending style of Futanari ships, whose upper side was box style and lower side was Miyoshi style, were seen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>いかりは鉄製のものが用いられ、巻き上げる装備もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iron anchor was used along with a winch.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iron anchors were used along with a winch.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iron anchors were used along with a winch.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>これらの船体構造は和製大型帆船のはしりで、近世の北前船や菱垣廻船・樽廻船などに受け継がれていくことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such structure of the hull was the original model of Japanese large sailing ships and was succeeded by kitamae-bune (cargo ships that sailed the Japan Sea during the Edo period), Higaki-kaisen (a kind of cargo vessels) and Taru-kaisen (a kind of cargo vessels) in the pre-modern times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such structure of the hull was the original model of Japanese large sailing ships and was succeeded by kitamae-bune (cargo ships that sailed the Japan Sea during the Edo period), Higaki-kaisen (a kind of cargo vessel) and Taru-kaisen (a kind of cargo vessels) in pre-modern times.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such structure of the hull was the original model of Japanese large sailing ships and was succeeded by kitamae-bune (cargo ships that sailed the Japan Sea during the Edo period), Higaki-kaisen (a kind of cargo vessel) and Taru-kaisen (a kind of cargo vessels) in pre-modern times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>積荷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cargo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cargo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cargo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>輸出品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Exported goods</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Exported goods</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Exported goods</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>刀剣、槍、鎧、扇、屏風などの工芸品、硫黄、銅などの鉱産物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Handicrafts such as swords, spears, armours, fans and folding screens as well as mineral products such as sulfur and copper.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Handicrafts such as swords, spears, armour, fans and folding screens as well as mineral products such as sulfur and copper.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Handicrafts such as swords, spears, armor, fans and folding screens as well as mineral products such as sulfur and copper.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>中でも莫大な量を占めたのが刀剣で、年間3万～4万本輸出された年があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Swords accounted for the large portion of export and their annual export sometimes reached to 30,000 to 40,000.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Swords accounted for the large portion of export and their annual export sometimes reached to 30,000 to 40,000.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Swords accounted for the large portion of export and their annual export sometimes reached to 30,000 to 40,000.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>輸入品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">imported goods</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">imported goods</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imported goods</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>当時の日本で貨幣経済の中心をなした宋・元・明などの銅銭（永楽銭など）、絹、羅、紗などの織物、生糸、薬材、書画、工芸品。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Copper coins (such as Eiraku-sen) of Sung, Yuan and Ming which were the basis of money economy in Japan, textile such as silk, lightweight fabric and gauze, raw silk thread, medicine, calligraphic works/ paintings and handicrafts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Copper coins (such as Eiraku-sen) of Sung, Yuan and Ming which were the basis of money economy in Japan, textile such as silk, lightweight fabric and gauze, raw silk thread, medicine, calligraphic works/ paintings and handicrafts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Copper coins (such as Eiraku-sen) of Sung, Yuan and Ming which were the basis of money economy in Japan, textile such as silk, lightweight fabric and gauze, raw silk thread, medicine, calligraphic works/ paintings and handicrafts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>禅僧の往来による、宋学、医術、印刷術、陶芸、水墨画などの大陸文化</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Continent culture introduced by Zen monks such as the Sung Study(Neo-Confucian), medicine, printing art, ceramic art and ink-wash painting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Continent culture introduced by Zen monks such as the Sung Study(Neo-Confucian), medicine, printing art, ceramic art and ink-wash painting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Continent culture introduced by Zen monks such as the Sung Study (Neo-Confucian), medicine, printing art, ceramic art and ink-wash painting.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Izayohi(id:13095), Komatta(id:52309), 経済準学士(id:22656), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>