<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>長州征討</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Choshu Conquest</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Choshu Conquest</e>
<cmt>タイトルなので定冠詞Theを取りました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Choshu Conquest</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>長州征討（ちょうしゅうせいとう）とは、江戸時代後期に江戸幕府と長州藩の間で2次に渡って行われた戦いである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Choshu Conquest was battles between the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and Choshu clan that occurred twice in the latter half of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Choshu Conquest was the battle between the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and the Choshu clan, which was fought twice in the latter half of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>表現を若干変えました。Choshu clan→the Choshu clanbattles between... that occurred twice →the battle..., which was fought twice </cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Choshu Conquest was the battle between the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and the Choshu clan, which was fought twice in the latter half of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>長州征伐、長州出兵、幕長戦争、征長の役、長州戦争などとも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also known as Choshu Subjugation, dispatch of troops to Choshu, mission of conquering of Choshu or the Choshu War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called Choshu Subjugation, Dispatch of troops to Choshu, Mission of conquering of Choshu or Choshu War, etc.</e>
<cmt>各固有名詞の語頭を大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called Choshu Subjugation, Dispatch of troops to Choshu, Mission of conquering of Choshu or Choshu War, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>第二次の長州征討は第二次幕長戦争とも、また幕府軍が4方から攻めたため、長州側では四境戦争と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second Choshu Conquest is also known as the second Baku-cho War, or if it is viewed from the Choshu side, it is called Shikyo War (Four Borders War), as the army of bakufu attacked Choshu from four directions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second Choshu Conquest is also known as the second Bakucho War (Bakufu-Choshu War), or if it is viewed from the Choshu side, it is called Shikyo War (Four Borders War), as the bakufu army attacked Choshu from four directions.</e>
<cmt>the army of the bakufu→the bakufu armyBaku-cho War→Bakucho War (Bakufu-Choshu War)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second Choshu Conquest is also known as the second Bakucho War (Bakufu-Choshu War), or if it is viewed from the Choshu side, it is called Shikyo War (Four Borders War), as the bakufu army attacked Choshu from four directions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>第二次征伐の失敗によって幕府の武力が張子の虎であることが知れ渡ると同時に長州藩と薩摩藩への干渉能力がほぼ無くなる結果を招いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The failure of the second conquest made it public knowledge that the military power of the bakufu is a paper tiger, and as a result the bakufu had almost lost the power to interfere in the Choshu Domain and the Satsuma Domain.</e>
<cmt>用語集では張子の虎＝hariko no tora (papier-mache tigers of which neck swing)となっていますが、この場合「paper tiger」の方が一般的かと思います。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The failure of the second conquest made it public knowledge that the military power of the bakufu was a paper tiger, and as a result, the bakufu had almost lost the power to interfere in the Choshu Domain and the Satsuma Domain.</e>
<cmt>the bakufu is→ the bakufu was</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The failure of the second conquest made it public knowledge that the military power of the bakufu was a paper tiger, and as a result, the bakufu had almost lost the power to interfere in the Choshu Domain and the Satsuma Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>そのため、この敗戦が徳川幕府滅亡をほぼ決定付けたとする資料も見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some materials describe that the defeat of this war was the final blow that led to the fall of the Tokugawa Shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some materials argue that the defeat in this war was the final blow that led to the fall of the Tokugawa Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>defeat of this war →defeat in this war</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some materials argue that the defeat in this war was the final blow that led to the fall of the Tokugawa Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>第一次</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first conquest</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first conquest</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first conquest</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>長州藩は尊皇攘夷・公武合体の倒幕思想を掲げて京都の政局に関わっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Choshu clan supported the theory of Sonno Joi (slogan advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners) and Kobu-gattai (integration of the imperial court and the shogunate) to overthrow the Shogunate, and was involved in political activities in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Choshu clan was committed to the political activities in Kyoto, advocating the ideas of Sonno Joi (slogan advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners) and Kobu-Gattai (integration of the imperial court and the shogunate) to overthrow the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>表現、構文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Choshu clan was committed to the political activities in Kyoto, advocating the ideas of Sonno Joi (slogan advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners) and Kobu-Gattai (integration of the imperial court and the shogunate) to overthrow the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし1863年（文久3年）に孝明天皇・公武合体派の公家・薩摩藩・会津藩による八月十八日の政変により京より追放される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, due to the coup by the Emperor Komei, Court nobles from the party advocating Kobu-Gattai, the Satsuma clan and the Aizu clan on August 18, 1863, the Choshu clan was expelled from Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Choshu clan was expelled from Kyoto in a coup called &apos;the political upheaval on August 18&apos; (upheaval occurred on September 30 on the western calendar) launched jointly by the Emperor Komei, the court nobles supporting Kobu-Gattai, the Satsuma clan and the Aizu clan in 1863,.</e>
<cmt>表現、構文を若干変えました。八月十八日の政変：&apos;the political upheaval on August 18&apos; (September 30 on the western calendar)としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Choshu clan was expelled from Kyoto in a coup called &apos;the political upheaval on August 18&apos; (upheaval occurred on September 30 on the western calendar) launched jointly by the Emperor Komei, the court nobles supporting Kobu-Gattai, the Satsuma clan and the Aizu clan in 1863,.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>1864年（元治元年）には藩主父子の赦免などを求めて京へ軍事的に進行する禁門の変が起こると、朝廷は長州藩が京都御所へ向かって発砲を行ったことを理由に長州を朝敵とし、幕府に対して長州征討の勅命を下す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1864, when the Choshu clan staged Kimmon no Hen (Conspiracy of Kimmon) and advanced its army toward Kyoto in order to ask for a pardon of the farther and son of the lord of domain, the Imperial Court declared the Choshu clan as the Emperor&apos;s enemy as they fired toward Kyoto Imperial Palace, then gave an imperial order to the bakufu to conquer the Choshu clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Kinmon no Hen (Conspiracy of Kinmon) occurred in 1864, in which the Choshu clan advanced its army toward Kyoto in order to ask for the Imperial Court&apos;s pardon for its lord and his son, the Imperial Court branded the Choshu clan as the Emperor&apos;s enemy for the reason that its soldiers fired at Kyoto Imperial Palace, and gave an imperial order to the bakufu to conquer the Choshu clan.</e>
<cmt>表現、構文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Kinmon no Hen (Conspiracy of Kinmon) occurred in 1864, in which the Choshu clan advanced its army toward Kyoto in order to ask for the Imperial Court&apos;s pardon for its lord and his son, the Imperial Court branded the Choshu clan as the Emperor&apos;s enemy for the reason that its soldiers fired at Kyoto Imperial Palace, and gave an imperial order to the bakufu to conquer the Choshu clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>幕府は前尾張藩主徳川慶勝を総督、越前藩主松平茂昭を副総督、薩摩藩士西郷隆盛を参謀に任じ、広島へ36藩15万の兵を集結させて長州へ進軍させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bakufu appointed Yoshikatsu TOKUGAWA (the former lord of the Owari domain) to the governor, Mochiaki MATSUDAIRA (the lord of the Echizen domain) to the lieutenant governor, and Takamori SAIGO (the feudal retainer of Satsuma) to the general staff, then gathered 150,000 soldiers from 36 clans to Hiroshima to advance toward Choshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bakufu appointed Yoshikatsu TOKUGAWA (the former lord of the Owari Domain) to the commander, Mochiaki MATSUDAIRA (the lord of the Echizen domain) to the vice commander, and Takamori SAIGO (the feudal retainer of Satsuma) to the general staff, respectively, and marshaled 150,000 soldiers from 36 clans in Hiroshima to made them advance toward the Choshu Domain.</e>
<cmt>表現を若干変えました。総督：commander副総督：vice commander</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bakufu appointed Yoshikatsu TOKUGAWA (the former lord of the Owari Domain) to the commander, Mochiaki MATSUDAIRA (the lord of the Echizen domain) to the vice commander, and Takamori SAIGO (the feudal retainer of Satsuma) to the general staff, respectively, and marshaled 150,000 soldiers from 36 clans in Hiroshima to made them advance toward the Choshu Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>一方、長州藩内部では下関戦争の後に藩論が分裂し、保守派（俗論派）が政権を握る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the opinions of the people in the Choshu Domain were divided after the Shimonoseki War, and the conservatives (conventional party) were controlling the administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the opinions within the Choshu Domain were divided after the Shimonoseki War, and the conservatives (conventional party) were controlling the administration of the domain.</e>
<cmt>表現を若干変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the opinions within the Choshu Domain were divided after the Shimonoseki War, and the conservatives (conventional party) were controlling the administration of the domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>征長総督参謀の西郷隆盛は、禁門の変の責任者である三家老（国司親相・益田兼施・福原元僴）の切腹、三条実美ら五卿の他藩への移転、山口城の破却を撤兵の条件として伝えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takamori SAIGO, the general staff of Sotoku of Seicho (governor conquering of Choshu), made propositions for the withdrawal of troops that included three chief retainers (Chikasuke KUNISHI, Kanenobu MASUDA, Mototake FUKUHARA) who were responsible for Kimmon no Hen to commit Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment), five nobles including Sanetomi SANJO to relocate to other clans, and Yamaguchi-jo Castle to be knocked down, and then the government of domain decided to accept and pay deference to these propositions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takamori SAIGO, the general staff to the commander of the Choshu Conquest, proposed the bakufu army&apos;s withdrawal to Choshu in exchange of three conditions, namely, seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) of three chief retainers (Chikasuke KUNISHI, Kanenobu MASUDA, Mototake FUKUHARA) to show their responsibility for the Incident of Kinmon no Hen, demotion transfer of five nobles including Sanetomi SANJO to other clans, and abandonment of Yamaguchi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takamori SAIGO, the general staff to the commander of the Choshu Conquest, proposed the bakufu army&apos;s withdrawal to Choshu in exchange of three conditions, namely, seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) of three chief retainers (Chikasuke KUNISHI, Kanenobu MASUDA, Mototake FUKUHARA) to show their responsibility for the Incident of Kinmon no Hen, demotion transfer of five nobles including Sanetomi SANJO to other clans, and abandonment of Yamaguchi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>藩庁はこれに従い恭順を決定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Choshu government decided to accept the conditions and express its deference</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Choshu government decided to accept the conditions and express its deference</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>幕府側はこの処置に不満であったが、12月には総督により撤兵令が発せられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the bakufu was not satisfied with this decision, the governor ordered the withdrawal of troops in December.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the bakufu side was not satisfied with this deal, the commander ordered the withdrawal of the troops in January 1864 (表記の変更).</e>
<cmt>表現を若干変えました。12月：December→January 1864 (表記の変更)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the bakufu side was not satisfied with this deal, the commander ordered the withdrawal of the troops in January 1864 (表記の変更).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>第二次</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second conquest</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second conquest</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second conquest</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>1865年（慶応元年）、長州藩では松下村塾出身の高杉晋作らが馬関で挙兵して保守派を打倒するクーデターを起し、倒幕派政権を成立させる（功山寺挙兵）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1865 in the Choshu Domain, Shinsaku TAKASUGI who was a graduate from Shokason Juku raised an army in Bakan to stage a coup to beat the conservatives, and established a government to overthrow the bakufu (raising an army at Kozan-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1865 in the Choshu Domain, Shinsaku TAKASUGI who was a graduate from Shokason Juku (a private school to foster young intellectuals), raised an army in Bakan to stage a coup to beat the conservatives in the domain, and established a domain government to overthrow the bakufu (raising an army at Kozan-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。松下村塾：Shokason Juku →Shokason Juku (a private school to foster young leaders)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1865 in the Choshu Domain, Shinsaku TAKASUGI who was a graduate from Shokason Juku (a private school to foster young intellectuals), raised an army in Bakan to stage a coup to beat the conservatives in the domain, and established a domain government to overthrow the bakufu (raising an army at Kozan-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>高杉らは西洋式軍制を採用した民兵である奇兵隊や長州藩諸隊を整備し、大村益次郎を登用してのゲベール銃やミニエー銃など新式兵器の配備、戦術の転換など軍事改革を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAKASUGI organized Kiheitai Army, which employed the Western style military system, and armies in the Choshu Domain, and then appointed Masujiro OMURA to arrange the latest weapons like Gewehr rifles and reform military affairs including transformation of tactics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takasugi, who organized a militia group adopting a Western-style military system named Kiheitai and consolidated the existing military units in the Choshu Domain, carried out a military reform by appointing Masujiro OMURA, equipping the army with the latest weapons like Gewehr rifles and Minie rifles changing tactics.</e>
<cmt>表現、構文を変えました。ミニエー銃：訳漏れ: Minie rifle</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takasugi, who organized a militia group adopting a Western-style military system named Kiheitai and consolidated the existing military units in the Choshu Domain, carried out a military reform by appointing Masujiro OMURA, equipping the army with the latest weapons like Gewehr rifles and Minie rifles changing tactics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>14代将軍徳川家茂は大坂城へ入り再び長州征討を決定する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iemochi TOKUGAWA, the fourteenth Shogun moved to the Osaka-jo Castle and decided to conquer the Choshu Domain again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iemochi TOKUGAWA, the fourteenth Shogun, moved to the Osaka-jo Castle and decided to restart the operation to conquer the Choshu Domain.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iemochi TOKUGAWA, the fourteenth Shogun, moved to the Osaka-jo Castle and decided to restart the operation to conquer the Choshu Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>四境戦争とも呼ばれている戦争だが、幕府は当初5方面から長州へ攻め入る計画だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it is known as Shikyo War (Four Borders War), the original plan of the bakufu was to attack Choshu from five directions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is known as Shikyo War (Four Borders War), the original plan of the bakufu was to attack Choshu from five directions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is known as Shikyo War (Four Borders War), the original plan of the bakufu was to attack Choshu from five directions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>しかし萩口を命じられた薩摩藩は、土佐藩の坂本龍馬を仲介とした薩長盟約で密かに長州と結びついており出兵を拒否する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, although the Satsuma clan was ordered to attack Choshu from Hagiguchi, it made a secret alliance with Choshu (Saccho meiyaku (pact between Satsuma and Choshu)) with Ryoma SAKAMOTO as their intermediary, and it refused to dispatch troops.</e>
<cmt>萩口の読み方不明。「Hagiguchi」としています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Satsuma clan, which was ordered to attack Choshu from the Hagi-kuchi route, had formed a secret alliance with Choshu (Saccho meiyaku [pact between Satsuma and Choshu]) through the mediation of Ryoma SAKAMOTO of Tosa Domain and refused to dispatch the troops.</e>
<cmt>土佐藩の:訳漏れ: of Tosa Domain</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Satsuma clan, which was ordered to attack Choshu from the Hagi-kuchi route, had formed a secret alliance with Choshu (Saccho meiyaku [pact between Satsuma and Choshu]) through the mediation of Ryoma SAKAMOTO of Tosa Domain and refused to dispatch the troops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>そのため萩口から長州を攻めることができず、4方から攻めることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, the bakufu was not able to attack Choshu from Hagicuchi, but attacked it from four other directions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, the bakufu was not able to attack Choshu from Hagi-kuchi, but attacked it from four other directions.</e>
<cmt>表記を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, the bakufu was not able to attack Choshu from Hagi-kuchi, but attacked it from four other directions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>幕府は大目付永井尚志が長州代表を尋問して処分案を確定させ、老中小笠原長行を全権に内容を伝達して最後通牒を行うが、長州は回答を引き延ばして迎撃の準備を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naoyuki NAGAI, Ometsuke of the bakufu, interrogated the representative of Choshu to determine punishment, and appointed Nagamichi OGASAWARA as the ambassador plenipotentiary to deliver ultimatum, but the Choshu side postponed the reply to prepare for interception.</e>
<cmt>全権大使=&gt;ambassador plenipotentiary</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naoyuki NAGAI, Ometsuke (chief inspector) of the bakufu, interrogated the representative of Choshu to determine the sanctions, and appointed Nagamichi OGASAWARA as the plenipotentiary to deliver the ultimatum to Choshu, but the Choshu side postponed the reply to prepare for engaging the enemy.</e>
<cmt>表現、構文を変えました。大目付：Ometsuke→Ometsuke (chief inspector)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naoyuki NAGAI, Ometsuke (chief inspector) of the bakufu, interrogated the representative of Choshu to determine the sanctions, and appointed Nagamichi OGASAWARA as the plenipotentiary to deliver the ultimatum to Choshu, but the Choshu side postponed the reply to prepare for engaging the enemy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="21">
<j>1866年（慶応2年）6月7日に幕府艦隊の周防大島への砲撃が始まり、13日には芸州口・小瀬川口、16日には石州口、17日には小倉口でそれぞれ戦闘が開始される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 7, 1866, the fleet of the bakufu started firing Suo-oshima Island, and the war was also started in Geishu-guchi on June 13, Sekishuguchi on June 16, and Kokura-guchi on June 17.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 18, 1866 (表記の変更), the fleet of the bakufu opened fire on Suo-oshima Island, and fights started successively in Geishu-guchi on July 24 (表記の変更), Sekishu-guchi on July 27 (表記の変更), and Kokura-guchi on July 28 (表記の変更).</e>
<cmt>1866年（慶応2年）6月7日の日付（6月7日）は西暦でしょうか？ご確認ください。ここでは、慶応2年6月7日と考え July 18, 1866、13日→July 24, 16日→July 27、17日→July 28としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 18, 1866 (表記の変更), the fleet of the bakufu opened fire on Suo-oshima Island, and fights started successively in Geishu-guchi on July 24 (表記の変更), Sekishu-guchi on July 27 (表記の変更), and Kokura-guchi on July 28 (表記の変更).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>長州側は山口の藩政府の合議制により作戦が指揮された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Choshu clan employed collegial system of the administration of the domain to conduct the operations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Choshu clan employed collegial system of the administration of the domain to conduct the operations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Choshu clan employed collegial system of the administration of the domain to conduct the operations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="23">
<j>大島口では、幕府陸軍の洋式歩兵隊と伊予松山藩の兵が、大島に上陸し占領した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Oshima-guchi, the Western style infantry of the bakufu and the soldiers of the Iyo-Matsuyama Domain landed and occupied Oshima.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Western style infantry of the bakufu and the soldiers of the Iyo-Matsuyama Domain landed from Oshima-guchi, and occupied Oshima.</e>
<cmt>表現、構文を若干変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Western style infantry of the bakufu and the soldiers of the Iyo-Matsuyama Domain landed from Oshima-guchi, and occupied Oshima.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>宇和島藩は幕府の出兵命令を拒んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Uwajima clan refused the order of the bakufu to dispatch troops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Uwajima clan refused the order of the bakufu to dispatch the troops.</e>
<cmt>冠詞を入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Uwajima clan refused the order of the bakufu to dispatch the troops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>幕府海軍と高杉率いる艦隊が戦い、奇襲戦法により幕府海軍は敗走した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The navy of the bakufu fought against the fleet of TAKASUGI, and they were put to flight by the surprise attack.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The navy of the bakufu fought against the fleet lead by Takasugi, but it was put to flight by the surprise attack of the Takasugi&apos;s fleet.</e>
<cmt>表現、構文を若干変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The navy of the bakufu fought against the fleet lead by Takasugi, but it was put to flight by the surprise attack of the Takasugi&apos;s fleet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>その後、世良修蔵指揮下の長州軍が大島の奪還を果たすも、島内に逃げ散った幕府軍残党の掃討が終戦まで続く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, although the Choshu army lead by Shuzo SERA managed to recapture Oshima, mopping up of the remnants of the army of bakufu that spread on the island continued until the end of the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, although the Choshu army lead by Shuzo SERA managed to recapture Oshima, the mop-up operation to capture the remnants of the bakufu army spread out around the island continued until the end of the war.</e>
<cmt>表現を若干変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, although the Choshu army lead by Shuzo SERA managed to recapture Oshima, the mop-up operation to capture the remnants of the bakufu army spread out around the island continued until the end of the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="27">
<j>芸州口では、長州藩と岩国藩が幕府歩兵隊や紀州藩兵などとの戦闘が行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Choshu clan and the Iwakuni clan fought against the feudal government&apos;s infantry and the Kishu clan in Geishu-guchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Choshu clan and the Iwakuni clan fought against the bakufu&apos;s infantry and the Kishu clan army in Geishu-guchi.</e>
<cmt>表現を若干変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Choshu clan and the Iwakuni clan fought against the bakufu&apos;s infantry and the Kishu clan army in Geishu-guchi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>彦根藩と高田藩が小瀬川であっさりと壊滅したが幕府歩兵隊と紀州藩兵が両藩に替わって戦闘に入ると幕府・紀州藩側が押し気味ながらも膠着状況に陥る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the Hikone clan and the Takada clan were destroyed instantly in Ozegawa, when the feudal government&apos;s infantry and the army of the Kishu clan took over them, the bakufu and Kishu clan side became predominant and the situation became a stalemate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the Hikone clan and the Takada clan were destroyed instantly in Ozegawa, the bakufu&apos;s infantry and the army of the Kishu clan took over them to fight back, and the situation became a stalemate with a slight predominance of the bakufu and Kishu clan side.</e>
<cmt>表現、構文を若干変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the Hikone clan and the Takada clan were destroyed instantly in Ozegawa, the bakufu&apos;s infantry and the army of the Kishu clan took over them to fight back, and the situation became a stalemate with a slight predominance of the bakufu and Kishu clan side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>また芸州藩は幕府の出兵命令を拒んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Geishu clan refused the order of the bakufu to dispatch troops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Geishu clan refused the order of the bakufu to dispatch the troops.</e>
<cmt>冠詞を入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Geishu clan refused the order of the bakufu to dispatch the troops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="30">
<j>石州口では、大村が指揮し（指揮役は清末藩毛利元純）、中立的立場を取った津和野藩を通過して徳川慶喜の弟が藩主を務める浜田藩へ侵攻し、18日に浜田城を陥落させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Sekishuguchi, OMURA lead the Choshu army (Motozumi MORI of the Kiyosue Domain was the commander), passed through the Tsuwano Domain that took a neutral position, advanced to the Hamada Domain where the younger brother of Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA was the lord of the domain, and took control of the Hamada-jo Castle on 18th.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Sekishu-guchi, OMURA lead the Choshu army (Motozumi MORI of the Kiyosue Domain was the commander), passed through the Tsuwano Domain that took a neutral position, advanced to the Hamada Domain where the younger brother of Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA was the lord of the domain, and took control of the Hamada-jo Castle on July 29 (表記の変更).</e>
<cmt>表現を若干変えました。18日は日付は西暦でしょうか？ご確認ください。ここでは、慶応2年6月１８日→July 29 してあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Sekishu-guchi, OMURA lead the Choshu army (Motozumi MORI of the Kiyosue Domain was the commander), passed through the Tsuwano Domain that took a neutral position, advanced to the Hamada Domain where the younger brother of Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA was the lord of the domain, and took control of the Hamada-jo Castle on July 29 (表記の変更).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>明治まで浜田城と天領だった石見銀山は長州が制圧した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Choshu clan conquered the Hamada-jo Castle and Iwami Ginzan Silver Mine, which were shogunal lands until the Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, the Choshu clan conquered the Hamada-jo Castle and Iwami Ginzan Silver Mine, which were shogunal lands until the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>Thus,を文頭に足しました。the Meiji Period→the Meiji period</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, the Choshu clan conquered the Hamada-jo Castle and Iwami Ginzan Silver Mine, which were shogunal lands until the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="32">
<j>小倉口では、総督・小笠原長行が指揮する九州諸藩と高杉晋作、山縣有朋ら率いる長州藩との戦闘（小倉戦争）が関門海峡をはさんで数度行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kokura-guchi, the alliance of Kyushu domains lead by the governor Nagamichi OGASAWARA fought against the Choshu clan lead by Shinsaku TAKASUGI and Aritomo YAMAGATA a few times across the Kanmon-kaikyo Strait (Ogura War), and at one point the Higo clan fought an even battle (the Battle of Akasaka/Torigoe, near Kitakyushu City Sakuragaoka Primary School).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kokura-guchi, the alliance of Kyushu domains lead by the commander Nagamichi OGASAWARA and the Choshu clan lead by Shinsaku TAKASUGI and Aritomo YAMAGATA had several armed contacts across the Kanmon-kaikyo Strait (Ogura War).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処表現を若干変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kokura-guchi, the alliance of Kyushu domains lead by the commander Nagamichi OGASAWARA and the Choshu clan lead by Shinsaku TAKASUGI and Aritomo YAMAGATA had several armed contacts across the Kanmon-kaikyo Strait (Ogura War).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>一時肥後藩が互角の戦いを見せた（赤坂・鳥越の戦い。現在の北九州市立桜丘小学校付近）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And at one point the Higo clan of the bakufu side fought an even battle (the Battle of Akasaka/Torigoe, near Kitakyushu City Sakuragaoka Primary School).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処表現を若干変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And at one point the Higo clan of the bakufu side fought an even battle (the Battle of Akasaka/Torigoe, near Kitakyushu City Sakuragaoka Primary School).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>しかし佐賀藩は兵を出さず、小笠原の指揮よろしきを得ず、諸藩は随時撤兵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Saga Domain did not dispatch troops, and OGASAWARA&apos;s command was not working, then the domains withdrew their troops whenever they needed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Saga Domain did not dispatch the troops, the commander Ogasawara&apos;s leadership did not work, and the domains of the alliance withdrew their troops one by one.</e>
<cmt>表現を若干変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Saga Domain did not dispatch the troops, the commander Ogasawara&apos;s leadership did not work, and the domains of the alliance withdrew their troops one by one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>将軍家茂薨去の報を受けた小笠原も戦線を離脱した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On receipt of the announcement of the decease of the shogun Iemochi, OGASAWARA left the front line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On receipt of the notice of the shogun Iemochi&apos;s disease, the commander Ogasawara also left the front line.</e>
<cmt>小笠原OGASAWARA</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On receipt of the notice of the shogun Iemochi&apos;s disease, the commander Ogasawara also left the front line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>孤立した小倉藩は8月1日城に火を放ち香春に退却。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The isolated Kokura clan set fire to the castle on August 1, and retreated to Kawara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The isolated Kokura clan set fire to its own castle on September 9 (表記の変更), and retreated to Kawara.</e>
<cmt>表現を若干変えました。8月1日の日付は西暦でしょうか？ご確認ください。ここでは、慶応2年8月１日→September 9としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The isolated Kokura clan set fire to its own castle on September 9 (表記の変更), and retreated to Kawara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>その後も小倉藩と長州藩の戦闘は続くが、これで事実上、幕府軍の全面敗北に終わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the war between the Kokura clan and the Choshu clan continued after that, it practically ended with the total defeat of the army of bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the battle between the Kokura clan and the Choshu clan continued even after that, the Choshu conquest practically ended with the total defeat of the bakufu army.</e>
<cmt>表現を若干変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the battle between the Kokura clan and the Choshu clan continued even after that, the Choshu conquest practically ended with the total defeat of the bakufu army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="38">
<j>更に戦いの長期化に備えて各藩が兵糧米を備蓄した事によって米価が暴騰し、全国各地で一揆や打ちこわしが起こる原因となった（世直し一揆）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since each domain stockpiled provisions of rice for the army, the rice price soared, and as a result uprising and destructive urban riots (reform riot) occurred in various places all over Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, since each domain stockpiled the provisions of rice for their army, the rice price soared, and as a result, uprising and destructive urban riots (Yonaoshi Ikki, a series of uprisings calling for social reforms) occurred in various places all over Japan.</e>
<cmt>表現を若干変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, since each domain stockpiled the provisions of rice for their army, the rice price soared, and as a result, uprising and destructive urban riots (Yonaoshi Ikki, a series of uprisings calling for social reforms) occurred in various places all over Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="39">
<j>徳川慶喜は大討込と称して、みずから出陣して巻き返すことを宣言したが、小倉陥落の報に衝撃を受けて大討込を中止した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA declared that he would lead Ouchikomi (a grand attack) and go to the battle himself to roll back; however, he was so shocked by the news of the fall of Kokura that he called off the attack.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA declared Ouchikomi (a grand attack) in which he himself would lead the troops to the front, however, the fall of the Kokura clan dispirit him and he called off the attack.</e>
<cmt>表現を若干変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA declared Ouchikomi (a grand attack) in which he himself would lead the troops to the front, however, the fall of the Kokura clan dispirit him and he called off the attack.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>家茂の死を公にしたうえで、朝廷に働きかけ、休戦の御沙汰書を発してもらう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also officially announced the death of Iemochi, and approached to the Imperial Court to ask them to publish the imperial words documents of cease-fire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He officially announced the death of Iemochi, and asked the Imperial Court to issue an imperial words document to call cease-fire.</e>
<cmt>表現を若干変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He officially announced the death of Iemochi, and asked the Imperial Court to issue an imperial words document to call cease-fire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>また慶喜の意を受けた勝海舟と長州の広沢真臣・井上馨が宮島で会談し停戦が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaishu KATSU, who represented Yoshinobu, had a meeting with Saneomi HIROSAWA and Kaoru INOUE from Choshu in Miyajima, and they agreed to cease-fire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaishu KATSU, on behalf of Yoshinobu, had a meeting with Saneomi HIROSAWA and Kaoru INOUE of the Choshu Domain in Miyajima, and they agreed on a cease-fire.</e>
<cmt>表現を若干変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaishu KATSU, on behalf of Yoshinobu, had a meeting with Saneomi HIROSAWA and Kaoru INOUE of the Choshu Domain in Miyajima, and they agreed on a cease-fire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 経済準学士(id:22656), Reggaeman(id:6214), Tast(id:29478), Brevam(id:13479), 味っ子(id:17086), マリアヤ(id:245178), Kurz(id:1601), でここ(id:9565), Boa(id:20845), 玄史生(id:43670), Blowback(id:173308), MUSASHI(id:11881), Prism11 VYB05736(id:171949), 曾禰越後守(id:183605), An-chan(id:14590), Qje(id:160294), Kanoe(id:17203), 木戸信長(id:23914), Maakun(id:16735), Snlf1(id:187217), KASAGI(id:24405), V-ＳＳＫ(id:29127), Mnd(id:15140), Taraspa8(id:138350), Izayohi(id:13095), 目白梅(id:141468), 水野白楓(id:22811), 酢溜まり氷(id:65987), Kamitani(id:30757), Kagetudo(id:163875), Chaoswing(id:286537), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), トホホ川(id:50502), Saaki(id:43602), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>