<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>征韓論</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seikanron</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seikanron</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seikanron</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>征韓論（せいかんろん）は、日本の明治初期において、当時留守政府の首脳であった西郷隆盛、板垣退助・江藤新平・後藤象二郎・副島種臣らによってなされた、武力をもって朝鮮を開国しようとする主張である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seikanron is the insistence of the members of the &quot;Rusu-seifu&quot; on making Korea open to the world by military power (Rusu-seifu means the government while heads of government are away: the heads of Rusu-seifu were Takamori SAIGO, Taisuke ITAGAKI, Shinpei ETO, Shojiro GOTO, Taneomi SOEJIMA).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seikanron is the insistence of the members of the &quot;Rusu-seifu&quot; on making Korea open to the world by military power (Rusu-seifu means the government while heads of government are away: the heads of Rusu-seifu were Takamori SAIGO, Taisuke ITAGAKI, Shinpei ETO, Shojiro GOTO, and Taneomi SOEJIMA).</e>
<cmt>Taneomiの前にandが必要です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seikanron is the insistence of the members of the &quot;Rusu-seifu&quot; on making Korea open to the world by military power (Rusu-seifu means the government while heads of government are away: the heads of Rusu-seifu were Takamori SAIGO, Taisuke ITAGAKI, Shinpei ETO, Shojiro GOTO, and Taneomi SOEJIMA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>ただし、征韓論の中心的人物であった西郷自身の主張は出兵ではなく開国を勧める遣韓使節として自らが朝鮮に赴く、むしろ「遣韓論」と言う説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is said that the insistence of SAIGO, who was the central figure of Seikanron, was not on dispatching military but on his himself going there as a Japanese official diplomatic delegation and on asking Korea to open its country to the world (this insistence is called &quot;Kenkanron&quot;(the insistence on sending delegations to Korea)).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is said that the insistence of Saigo, who was the central figure of Seikanron, was not on dispatching military but on his himself going there as a Japanese official diplomatic delegation and on asking Korea to open its country to the world (this insistence is called &quot;Kenkanron&quot; [the insistence on sending delegations to Korea).</e>
<cmt>・SAIGOは名字だけですので、頭文字だけ大文字にしました。・括弧の中の括弧は指示に従って[]にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is said that the insistence of Saigo, who was the central figure of Seikanron, was not on dispatching military but on his himself going there as a Japanese official diplomatic delegation and on asking Korea to open its country to the world (this insistence is called &apos;Kenkanron&apos; [the insistence on sending delegations to Korea).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot; → &apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>江戸時代後期に、国学や水戸学の一部や吉田松陰らの立場から、古代日本が朝鮮半島に支配権を持っていたと『古事記』・『日本書紀』に記述されていると唱えられており、こうしたことを論拠として朝鮮進出を唱えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They insisted on sending military to Korea on ground that some scholars of Kokugaku (the study of Japanese classical literature) and Mito-gaku (the scholarship and academic traditions that arose in the Mito Domain), and Shoin YOSHIDA said that ancient Japan had hegemony over Korean peninsula according to &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Record of Ancient Matters) and &quot;Nihon-shoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They insisted on sending military to Korea on ground that some scholars of Kokugaku (the study of Japanese classical literature) and Mito-gaku (the scholarship and academic traditions that arose in the Mito Domain), and Shoin YOSHIDA said that ancient Japan had hegemony over Korean peninsula according to &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Record of Ancient Matters) and &quot;Nihon-shoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They insisted on sending military to Korea on ground that some scholars of Kokugaku (the study of Japanese classical literature) and Mito-gaku (the scholarship and academic traditions that arose in the Mito Domain), and Shoin YOSHIDA said that ancient Japan had hegemony over Korean peninsula according to &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Record of Ancient Matters) and &quot;Nihon-shoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>なお、尊王攘夷運動の政治的主張にも取り入れられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, this idea was brought into the political insistence of the Sonno-joi movement (the movement advocating reverence for an emperor and the expulsion of foreigners).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, this idea was brought into the political insistence of the Sonno-joi movement (the movement advocating reverence for an emperor and the expulsion of foreigners).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, this idea was brought into the political insistence of the Sonno-joi movement (the movement advocating reverence for an emperor and the expulsion of foreigners).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>明治維新後に対馬府中藩を介して朝鮮に対して新政府発足の通告と国交を望む交渉を行うが、日本の外交文書が江戸時代の形式と異なることを理由に朝鮮側に拒否された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, the Meiji government noticed Korea to establish a new government and negotiated to have diplomatic relations, but Korea rejected them because the format of diplomatic papers was different from the one of Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Restoration, the Meiji government noticed Korea to establish a new government and negotiated to have diplomatic relations, but Korea rejected them because the format of diplomatic papers was different from the one of Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, the Meiji government noticed Korea to establish a new government and negotiated to have diplomatic relations, but Korea rejected them because the format of diplomatic papers was different from the one of Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>朝鮮では国王の父の大院君が政を摂し、鎖国攘夷の策をとり、意気おおいにあがっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Korea, the King&apos;s father Daewongun governed the country instead of the King at that time, adopting the policy of national isolation and expulsion of foreigners, and Korean people was in high spirits.</e>
<cmt>誰の意気があがっているのかがよくわからないので、ここではKorean peopleを主語にしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Korea, the King&apos;s father Daewongun governed the country instead of the King at that time, adopting the policy of national isolation and expulsion of foreigners, and Korean people was in high spirits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Korea, the King&apos;s father Daewongun governed the country instead of the King at that time, adopting the policy of national isolation and expulsion of foreigners, and Korean people was in high spirits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>明治3年2月、明治政府は佐田白茅、森山茂を派遣したが、佐田は朝鮮の状況に憤慨し、帰国後に征韓を建白した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March, 1870, the Meiji government sent Hakubo SATA and Shigeru MORIYAMA sent to Korea, but SATA petitioned the government to conquer Korea by military force because he resented the attitude of Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March 1870, the Meiji government sent Hakubo SATA and Shigeru MORIYAMA to Korea, but SATA petitioned the government to conquer Korea by military force because he resented the attitude of Korea.</e>
<cmt>・Marchの後のコンマは不要です。・sentが重複しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March 1870, the Meiji government sent Hakubo SATA and Shigeru MORIYAMA to Korea, but SATA petitioned the government to conquer Korea by military force because he resented the attitude of Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>9月には、外務権少丞吉岡弘毅を釜山広域市に遣り、明治5年1月には、宗義達を外務大丞に任じ、9月には、外務大丞花房義質を派した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September, the government sent Gaimu-shojo (Junior Secretary of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs) Koki YOSHIOKA to Busan, and in February, 1872, they appointed Yoshiakira SO as Gaimu-taijo (Senior Secretary of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs), and then, they sent Gaimu-taijo Yoshimoto HANABUSA to Korea in September.</e>
<cmt>「外務大丞」の定訳なし</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September, the government sent Gaimu-shojo (Junior Secretary of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs) Koki YOSHIOKA to Busan, and in February 1872, they appointed Yoshiakira SO as Gaimu-taijo (Senior Secretary of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs), and then, they sent Gaimu-taijo Yoshimoto HANABUSA to Korea in September.</e>
<cmt>・Februaryの後のコンマは不要です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September, the government sent Gaimu-shojo (Junior Secretary of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs) Koki YOSHIOKA to Busan, and in February 1872, they appointed Yoshiakira SO as Gaimu-taijo (Senior Secretary of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs), and then, they sent Gaimu-taijo Yoshimoto HANABUSA to Korea in September.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>朝鮮は頑としてこれに応じることなく、明治6年になってからは排日の風がますます強まり、4月、5月には、釜山において官憲の先導によるボイコットなども行なわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The movement of anti-Japanese became more active in 1873 instead of accepting the delegates from Japan, and then Korean officials led a boycott of Japanese goods and people in April and May.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The movement of anti-Japanese became more active in 1873 instead of accepting the delegates from Japan, and then Korean officials led a boycott of Japanese goods and people in April and May.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The movement of anti-Japanese became more active in 1873 instead of accepting the delegates from Japan, and then Korean officials led a boycott of Japanese goods and people in April and May.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>ここに、日本国内において征韓論が沸騰した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the dispute of Seikanron became heated in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the dispute of Seikanron became heated in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the dispute of Seikanron became heated in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>明治6年6月森山帰国後の閣議であらためて対朝鮮外交問題が取り上げられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June, 1873, the problem of diplomacy with Korea was highlighted at the cabinet meeting again after Shigeru MORIYAMA was back to Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June 1873, the problem of diplomacy with Korea was highlighted at the cabinet meeting again after Shigeru MORIYAMA was back to Japan.</e>
<cmt>Juneの後のコンマは不要です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June 1873, the problem of diplomacy with Korea was highlighted at the cabinet meeting again after Shigeru MORIYAMA was back to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>参議である板垣退助は閣議において居留民保護を理由に派兵を主張し、西郷隆盛は派兵に反対し、自身が大使として赴くと主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sangi (the Councilor) Taisuke ITAGAKI insisted that Japan dispatch the military for protecting Japanese residents in Korea, whereas Takamori Saigo opposed to send the military and insisted that he himself go to Korea as an ambassador.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sangi (the Councilor) Taisuke ITAGAKI insisted that Japan dispatch the military for protecting Japanese residents in Korea, whereas Takamori SAIGO opposed to send the military and insisted that he himself go to Korea as an ambassador.</e>
<cmt>Saigoは大文字にする必要があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sangi (the Councilor) Taisuke ITAGAKI insisted that Japan dispatch the military for protecting Japanese residents in Korea, whereas Takamori SAIGO opposed to send the military and insisted that he himself go to Korea as an ambassador.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>後藤象二郎、江藤新平らもこれに賛成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shojiro GOTO, Shinpei ETO agreed with SAIGO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shojiro GOTO, Shinpei ETO agreed with SAIGO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shojiro GOTO, Shinpei ETO agreed with SAIGO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>いったんは、明治6年（1873年）8月に明治政府は西郷隆盛を使節として派遣することを決定するが、同年9月に帰国した岩倉使節団の大久保利通、岩倉具視・木戸孝允らは時期尚早としてこれに反対、同年10月に遣韓中止が決定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Meiji government once decided to send Takamori SAIGO as an ambassador to Korea in August, 1873, but Toshimichi OKUBO, Tomomi IWAKURA, Takayoshi KIDO and other members of the Iwakura Mission who returned Japan in September, 1873, opposed it because it was too early in their opinion, and the government finally decided to suspend to send SAIGO to Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Meiji government once decided to send Takamori SAIGO as an ambassador to Korea in August 1873, but Toshimichi OKUBO, Tomomi IWAKURA, Takayoshi KIDO and other members of the Iwakura Mission who returned Japan in September 1873 opposed it because it was too early in their opinion, and the government finally decided to suspend to send Saigo to Korea.</e>
<cmt>・AugustとSeptemberの後のコンマは不要です。・SAIGOは名字だけの記載ですので、頭文字のみ大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Meiji government once decided to send Takamori SAIGO as an ambassador to Korea in August 1873, but Toshimichi OKUBO, Tomomi IWAKURA, Takayoshi KIDO and other members of the Iwakura Mission who returned Japan in September 1873 opposed it because it was too early in their opinion, and the government finally decided to suspend to send Saigo to Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>収拾に窮した太政大臣三条は病に倒れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Grand Minister SANJO fell ill because the situation became uncontrollable to him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Grand Minister SANJO fell ill because the situation became uncontrollable to him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Grand Minister SANJO fell ill because the situation became uncontrollable to him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>その結果、西郷や板垣らの征韓派は一斉に下野（征韓論政変または明治六年政変）し、1874年の佐賀の乱から1877年の西南戦争に至る士族反乱や自由民権運動の起点となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In consequence, SAIGO, ITAGAKI and others who supported Seikanron went into opposition (this incident is called the &quot;Seikanron Coup&quot; or the &quot;Coup of 1873&quot;), and they became leaders of the revolt by Shizoku (family or person with samurai ancestors) from Saga War in 1874 to Satsuma Rebellion or the Freedom and People&apos;s Right Movement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In consequence, Saigo, Itagaki and others who supported Seikanron went into opposition (this incident is called the &quot;Seikanron Coup&quot; or the &quot;Coup of 1873&quot;), and they became leaders of the revolt by Shizoku (family or person with samurai ancestors) from Saga War in 1874 to Satsuma Rebellion or the Freedom and People&apos;s Right Movement.</e>
<cmt>SAIGOとITAGAKIは名字だけの記載ですので、頭文字だけ大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In consequence, Saigo, Itagaki and others who supported Seikanron went into opposition (this incident is called the &quot;Seikanron Coup&quot; or the &quot;Coup of 1873&quot;), and they became leaders of the revolt by Shizoku (family or person with samurai ancestors) from Saga War in 1874 to Satsuma Rebellion or the Freedom and People&apos;s Right Movement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Noo(id:11041), Straysheep(id:42448), Corruptresearcher(id:9264), 水野白楓(id:22811), Tears for Asia(id:61412), Ttwo(id:82880), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Tuffyrhodes20(id:55171), Johncapistrano(id:969), でここ(id:9565), ニューワーカー(id:16977), Chobot(id:20846), BotMultichill(id:132395), こぶまき(id:38278), Shimoxx(id:9332), Point136(id:211299), Ponsaku(id:31417), NDR(id:5500), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>