<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>愛国公党</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aikokukoto Party</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Aikokukoto Party</e>
<cmt>政党名の前にはtheがつくようです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Aikokukoto Party</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>愛国公党（あいこくこうとう）は、最初の自由民権運動の政治結社。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aikokukoto Party is the first political association in Jiyu Minken Undo (Movement for Liberty and People&apos;s Right).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Aikokukoto Party was the first political organization associated under the Jiyu Minken Undo (Movement for Liberty and People&apos;s Right).</e>
<cmt>is→wasにしました。Political association in→political organization associated under theにしました。政党名の前にはtheがつくようです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Aikokukoto Party was the first political organization associated under the Jiyu Minken Undo (Movement for Liberty and People&apos;s Right).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>明治時代中期の政党。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A political party in the middle Meiji period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Political parties in the middle Meiji period</e>
<cmt>Partyを複数形にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Political parties in the middle Meiji period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>愛国公党 (1874年)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aikokukoto (in 1874)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Aikokukoto (in 1874)</e>
<cmt>政党名の前にはtheがつくようです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Aikokukoto (in 1874)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>征韓論、明治六年の政変で下野した板垣退助らは、幸福安全社を基礎に明治7年（1874年）1月12日、東京の京橋区銀座副島種臣邸に同士を集めて結成。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taisuke ITAGAKI who had lost in the political upheaval in Seikanron in 1873 and retired from the governmental position and his comrades gathered at the residence of Taneomi SOEJIMA in Ginza, Kyobashi Ward, Tokyo and formed a political party on January 12, 1874.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taisuke ITAGAKI, who had lost in the political upheaval in Seikanron in 1873 and retired from the governmental position, and his comrades gathered at the residence of Taneomi SOEJIMA in Ginza, Kyobashi Ward, Tokyo and formed a political party on January 12, 1874.</e>
<cmt>「and his comrades」がどこから続くのか分かりづらかったので、ITAGAKIを修飾する「who･･･position」の前後にコンマを入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taisuke ITAGAKI, who had lost in the political upheaval in Seikanron in 1873 and retired from the governmental position, and his comrades gathered at the residence of Taneomi SOEJIMA in Ginza, Kyobashi Ward, Tokyo and formed a political party on January 12, 1874.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>天賦人権論に基づき、基本的人権を保護し民撰議院設立を政府に要求することが当面の政治課題の第一であると謳っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They asserted that to protect basic human rights based on the theory of Tenpujinken-ron (the theory of the human rights given by the heaven) and to require the government to establish the congress of representatives elected by the commoners were the first goal of their political challenges at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They asserted that the first goal of their political challenges at that time were to protect basic human rights based on the theory of Tenpujinken-ron (the theory of the human rights given by the heaven) and to require the government to establish the congress of representatives elected by the commoners.</e>
<cmt>that節内の主語(to～)が長すぎるので、the first goal～を先にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They asserted that the first goal of their political challenges at that time were to protect basic human rights based on the theory of Tenpujinken-ron (the theory of the human rights given by the heaven) and to require the government to establish the congress of representatives elected by the commoners.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>1月17日、板垣、副島らは政府に対して『民撰議院設立建白書』を提出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 17, Itagaki and Soejima submitted &quot;the political statement for democratic representation&quot; to the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 17, Itagaki and Soejima submitted &quot;the political statement for democratic representation&quot; to the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 17, Itagaki and Soejima submitted &quot;the political statement for democratic representation&quot; to the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>建白書には、この他、後藤象二郎、江藤新平、小室信夫、由利公正、岡本健三郎、古沢滋が署名している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides Itagaki and Soejima, Shojiro GOTO, Shinpei ETO, Shinobu KOMURO, Kosei YURI, Kenzaburo OKAMOTO and Shigeru FURUSAWA sign the statement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides Itagaki and Soejima, Shojiro GOTO, Shinpei ETO, Shinobu KOMURO, Kosei YURI, Kenzaburo OKAMOTO and Shigeru FURUSAWA signed the statement.</e>
<cmt>signを過去形にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides Itagaki and Soejima, Shojiro GOTO, Shinpei ETO, Shinobu KOMURO, Kosei YURI, Kenzaburo OKAMOTO and Shigeru FURUSAWA signed the statement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>愛国公党は、日本でも初期の政治結社に数えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aikokukoto can be considered one of the early political associations in Japan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Aikokukoto can be considered one of the early political associations in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Aikokutotoの前にtheを入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Aikokukoto can be considered one of the early political associations in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>だが、議会の開催前に活動を開始したこともあり、その誕生は時代の流れよりも早すぎた、という感は否めない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But it is undeniable that the birth of the party was too early in the trend of the time, partly because it started its activities before the opening of the Diet.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But it is undeniable that the birth of the party went ahead the trend of the time, partly because it started its activities before the opening of the Diet.</e>
<cmt>「時代の流れよりも早すぎた」は｢時代より先んじてしまった」ことと解釈され、書き直してみたのですが上手に表現できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yet given the fact that this party started its political activities before the National Diet was even formed, it cannot be denied that the party was too much ahead of its time.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>後に板垣退助や片岡健吉が帰郷し、江藤も佐賀の乱に加わったため活動を停止し、自然消滅を迎えることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, as Taisuke ITAGAKI and Kenkichi KATAOKA went home and Eto participated in Saga War, the party stopped its activities and died a natural death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, as Taisuke ITAGAKI and Kenkichi KATAOKA went home and Eto participated in Saga War, the party stopped its activities and died out.</e>
<cmt>｢党」が主語なので「died a natural death｣→「died out」にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, as Taisuke ITAGAKI and Kenkichi KATAOKA went home and Eto participated in Saga War, the party stopped its activities and died out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>愛国公党 (1890年)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aikokukoto Party (in 1890)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Aikokukoto Party (in 1890)</e>
<cmt>政党名の前にはtheがつくようです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Aikokukoto Party (in 1890)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>明治23年（1890年）5月5日に、旧自由党 (日本)土佐派を中心に設立された政党。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A political party whose main members were the Tosa school in the former Liberal Party established on May 5, 1890.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A political party established on May 5, 1890, in which the main members were the Tosa school in the former Liberal Party.</e>
<cmt>established on･･･がLiberal Partyを修飾しているようにも解釈されますので、political partyの直後に移動し、whoseをin whichにしました。この場合は「A political party」でよいでしょうか？</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A political party established on May 5, 1890; it is mainly comprised of the members of Tosa school in the former Liberal Party.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>大同団結運動分裂後の事態に対応して、板垣退助たちが旧自由党員を愛国公党へ結集しようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Responding to the situation after the split of Great Merger Movement, Taisuke ITAGAKI and others tried to pull the members of former Liberal Party into Aikokukoto Party.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Corresponding to the situation after the split of Great Merger Movement, Taisuke ITAGAKI and others tried to invite the members of the former Liberal Party to the Aikokukoto Party.</e>
<cmt>pull into→invite inにし、政党名の前にtheをつけました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response to the situation after the split of Great Merger Movement, Taisuke ITAGAKI and others tried to invite the members of the former Liberal Party to the Aikokukoto Party.</e>
<cmt>Corresponding →In response to</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>これが党創設における契機となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This movement triggered the establishment of Aikokukoto Party.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This movement triggered the establishment of the Aikokukoto Party.</e>
<cmt>Aikokukotoの前にtheをつけました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This movement triggered the establishment of the Aikokukoto Party.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>結党後、直ちに自由党、大同倶楽部と合同に向けて交渉が始まり、5月14日三派が合同し、康寅倶楽部を結成する旨を決議した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the establishment of the party, the negotiations to merge with Liberal Party and Daido Club Party began, and on May 14 the three parties passed a resolution to form Kokin Club Party.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the establishment of the party, negotiations began to merge with the Liberal Party and the Daido Club Party, and on May 14 the three parties passed a resolution to form Kokin Club Party.</e>
<cmt>negotiationsの前のtheを取り、beganをtoの前に移動しました。政党名の前にtheをつけました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the establishment of the party, negotiations began to merge with the Liberal Party and the Daido Club Party, and on May 14 the three parties passed a resolution to form Kokin Club Party.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>8月4日愛国公党は解党した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 4 Aikokukoto Party was dissolved.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 4 the Aikokukoto Party was dissolved.</e>
<cmt>Aikokukotoの前にtheをつけました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 4 the Aikokukoto Party was dissolved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>さらに九州同志会を含めた四派が合同して、9月15日自由党 (日本)立憲自由党 (日本 1890-1891)を結成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And on September 15, Rikken Jiyu-to (Constitutional Liberal Party) was formed by uniting the four parties including Kyushu Doshikai (Kyushu Comrades Party).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And on September 15, the Rikken Jiyu-to (the Constitutional Liberal Party) was formed by uniting the four parties including the Kyushu Doshikai (the Kyushu Comrades Party).</e>
<cmt>政党名の前にtheをつけました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And on September 15, the Rikken Jiyu-to (the Constitutional Liberal Party) was formed by uniting the four parties including the Kyushu Doshikai (the Kyushu Comrades Party).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Ligar(id:12623), Straysheep(id:42448), Kyube(id:9866), SuisuiBot(id:10165), 江戸ラー(id:30154), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Sh(id:2707), BOT-Superzerocool(id:65015), Alex K(id:86829), Johncapistrano(id:969), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>