<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>飛鳥時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Asuka period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Asuka Period</e>
<cmt>Capitalized.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Asuka Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>飛鳥時代（あすかじだい）は、古墳時代の終末期と重なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Asuka period coincides with the last part of Kofun period (the tumulus period).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Asuka Period is a period in Japanese history, stretching from the end of the 6th century to the beginning of the 8th century, during which the capital was located in a place named Asuka.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, word choice.Sentence 2 and 3 interchanged to make the English more natural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Asuka Period is a period in Japanese history, stretching from the end of the 6th century to the beginning of the 8th century, during which the capital was located in a place named Asuka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>それは、6世紀の終わり頃から8世紀初頭にかけて飛鳥に宮・都が置かれていた時代を指す日本の歴史の時代区分の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of divisions in Japanese history, referring to the period from the end of 6th century to the beginning of 8th century during which capital is located in the place named Asuka.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It overlaps with the last part of the Kofun Period (the Tumulus Period).</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It overlaps with the last part of the Kofun Period (the Tumulus Period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>狭義には、崇峻5年（592年）から持統天皇8年（694年）の藤原京への移転までの、約102年間を飛鳥時代と称している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a narrow sense, they call Asuka period of 102 years from 592 to 694, the time in which capital was removed to the place Fujiwara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a narrow sense, the Asuka Period lasted for 102 years, from 592 to 694, the time at which the capital was moved to Fujiwara.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a narrow sense, the Asuka Period lasted for 102 years, from 592 to 694, the time at which the capital was moved to Fujiwara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>以前は、古墳時代と合わせて大和時代とされていた時期があったが、今日では古墳時代と飛鳥時代に分けて捉えるのが一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Formerly, Asuka period was united with Kofun period to be called Yamato period, but today it is common to divide the period into Kofun period and Asuka period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Formerly the Asuka and Kofun Periods were together called the Yamato Period, but today it is common to separate the two.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Formerly the Asuka and Kofun Periods were together called the Yamato Period, but today it is common to separate the two.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>推古朝に飛鳥文化、天武・持統朝に白鳳文化が華開いた時代でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During Asuka period, Asuka culture was prosperous in the age of Empress Suiko and Hakuho culture was glorious in the age of Empress Jito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Asuka Period, Asuka culture prospered in the age of Empress Suiko and Hakuho culture flowered in the age of Empress Jito.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Asuka Period, Asuka culture prospered in the age of Empress Suiko and Hakuho culture flowered in the ages of Emperor Tenmu and Empress Jito.</e>
<cmt>「天武」を補足いたしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>この時代に倭国（倭）から日本へ国号を変えたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the name of the country was changed from Wakoku (Wa) to Japan in this period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the name of the country was changed from Wakoku (Wa) to Japan in this period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the name of the country was changed from Wakoku (Wa) to Japan in this period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>名称</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin of the name of this period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin of the name</e>
<cmt>Simplified.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin of the name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>現在の奈良県高市郡明日香村付近に相当する「飛鳥」の地に宮・都が置かれていたとされることに由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the name of this period stems from the tradition that the palace and the capital were located in the place &quot; Asuka &quot; which corresponds to the place near current Asuka Village, Takaichi County, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the name of this period stems from the fact that the palace and capital were located in Asuka, near present-day Asuka Village, Takaichi County, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the name of this period stems from the fact that the palace and capital were located in Asuka, near present-day Asuka Village, Takaichi County, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>「飛鳥時代」という時代区分は元々美術史や建築史で使われ始めた言葉である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Period division &quot; Asuka&quot; originally began to be used in art and architecture histories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The phrase &quot;the Asuka Period&quot; originally began to be used in relation to the history of art and architecture.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The phrase &apos;the Asuka Period&apos; originally began to be used in relation to the history of art and architecture.</e>
<cmt>「」ですので’’に致しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>1900年前後に美術学者の関野貞と岡倉天心によって提案された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This time period name was proposed by two art scholars. Tadashi SEKINO and Tenshin OKAKURA before or after 1900.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The use of this name for the period of history itself was proposed by two art scholars, Tadashi SEKINO and Tenshin OKAKURA, in around 1900.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The use of this name for the period of history itself was proposed by two art scholars, Tadashi SEKINO and Tenshin OKAKURA, in around 1900.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>関野は大化の改新までを、岡倉は平城京遷都までを飛鳥時代とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time SEKINO proposed to call Asuka period till the time of the Taika Reform and OKAKURA suggested till the time of relocation of the capital to Heijokyo (in the neighborhood of present Nara city).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sekino proposed that the Asuka Period continued until the time of the Taika Reform, yet Okakura suggested it continued to the time of the relocation of the capital to Heijokyo (close to present-day Nara City).</e>
<cmt>Style, punctuation, grammar, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sekino proposed that the Asuka Period continued until the time of the Taika Reform, yet Okakura suggested it continued to the time of the relocation of the capital to Heijokyo (close to present-day Nara City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>日本の歴史では通常岡倉案のものを採用しているが、現在でも美術史や建築史などでは関野案のものを使用し、大化の改新以降を白鳳時代として区別する事がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Japanese history, OKAKURA proposal is usually adopted, but in the art and architecture histories, they use SEKINO proposal and they distinguish the period after Taika Reform from Asuka period, using the name of Hakuho period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okakura&apos;s proposal is usually adopted in relation to Japanese history, but in the art and architectural worlds, they follow the viewpoint of Sekino and distinguish the period after the Taika Reform from the Asuka Period, using the name of the Hakuho Period.</e>
<cmt>Style, punctuation, grammar, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okakura&apos;s proposal is usually adopted in relation to Japanese history, but in the art and architectural worlds, they follow the viewpoint of Sekino and distinguish the period after the Taika Reform from the Asuka Period, using the name of the Hakuho Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>推古朝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Suiko Dynasty</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Suiko Dynasty</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Suiko Dynasty</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>538年（宣化3年）に百済の聖明王が釈迦仏像や経論などを朝廷に贈り仏教が公伝された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 538, King Seimyo in Paekche presented the dynasty with Shaka Buddhist image andBuddhism was officially introduced.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 538, King Seong of Baekje presented the dynasty with a Shaka Buddhist image andBuddhism was officially introduced to Japan.</e>
<cmt>Spelling of king and kingdom - khttp://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seong_of_Baekje</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 538, King Seong of Baekje presented the dynasty with a Shaka Buddhist image and the Buddhist scriptures and commentaries, and Buddhism was officially introduced to Japan.</e>
<cmt>「経論」を補足いたしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>587年（用明2年）天皇の仏教帰依について物部守屋と蘇我馬子が対立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 587, Moriya MONONOBE and Umako SOGA confronted with each ohther regarding the Empress faith in Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 587, Moriya MONONOBE and Umako SOGA confronted each other regarding the Empress&apos; faith in Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>Spelling, punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 587, Moriya MONONOBE and Umako SOGA confronted each other regarding the Empress&apos; faith in Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>後の聖徳太子は蘇我氏側につき、物部氏を滅ぼした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Shotoku sided with the Soga clan and destroyed the Monomobe clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Shotoku sided with the Soga clan and destroyed the Mononobe clan.</e>
<cmt>Spelling.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Shotoku sided with the Soga clan and destroyed the Mononobe clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>物部氏を滅ぼして以降約半世紀の間、蘇我氏が大臣として権力を握った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After having destroyed the Mononobe clan, the Soga clan as the minister wielded power for about half century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following this, members of the Soga clan wielded ministerial power over the next half century.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following this, members of the Soga clan wielded ministerial power over the next half century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>588年（崇峻元年）には蘇我馬子が飛鳥に法興寺（飛鳥寺）の建立を始める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 588, Umako SOGA began to erect Hoko-ji Temple (Asuka-ji Temple) in Asuka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 588, Umako SOGA began to erect Hoko-ji Temple (Asuka-ji Temple) in Asuka.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 588, Umako SOGA began to erect Hoko-ji Temple (Asuka-ji Temple) in Asuka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>592年、蘇我馬子は東漢駒を遣い崇峻天皇を暗殺すると、女帝推古天皇を立てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 592, Umako SOGA assassinated Emperor Sushun by using Koma TOKAN and backed up Empress Suiko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 592, Soga used Koma TOKAN to assassinate Emperor Sushun and established Suiko as empress.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 592, Umako SOGA used Koma TOKAN to assassinate Emperor Sushun and established Suiko as empress.</e>
<cmt>馬子を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>厩戸皇子（聖徳太子）が皇太子に立てられ摂政となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Kurando (Prince Shotoku) was appointed the crown prince and became the regent to the Empress Suiko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Kurando (Prince Shotoku) was appointed crown prince and became regent to Empress Suiko.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Umayado (Prince Shotoku) was appointed crown prince and became regent to Empress Suiko.</e>
<cmt>厩戸皇子を「うまやどのおうじ」に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>604年（推古12年）には、冠位十二階を制定し、聖徳太子が憲法十七条をつくり、仏教の興隆に力を注ぐなど、天皇中心の理想の国家体制づくりの礎を築いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 604, Prince Shotoku established the system of twelve courtly ranks, promulgated the Seventeen-Article Constitution, strived to develop Buddhism and laid the foundation for the ideal national system with the emperor as the nation&apos;s center.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 604, Prince Shotoku established a system of twelve courtly ranks, promulgated the Seventeen-Article Constitution, strived to develop Buddhism and laid the foundation for an ideal national system with the emperor as the nation&apos;s center.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 604, Prince Shotoku established a system of twelve courtly ranks, promulgated the Seventeen-Article Constitution, strived to develop Buddhism and laid the foundation for an ideal national system with the emperor as the nation&apos;s center.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>607年、小野妹子らを隋に遣隋使として遣わして、隋の皇帝に「日出る処の天子、書を日没する処の天子に致す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 607, Prince Shotoku sent Ono no Imoko as an envoy to Sui (China) and sent a diplomatic message to the Sui emperor, with the wording &quot; the Emperor in the Land of the Rising Sun sends a letter to the Emperor in the Land of Setting Sun.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 607, Prince Shotoku sent Ono no Imoko as an envoy to Sui (China) and sent a diplomatic message to the Sui emperor with the wording &quot;The Emperor in the Land of the Rising Sun sends a letter to the Emperor in the Land of Setting Sun.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 607, Prince Shotoku sent Imoko ONO as an envoy to Sui (China) and sent a diplomatic message to the Sui emperor with the wording &apos;The Emperor in the Land of the Rising Sun sends a letter to the Emperor in the Land of Setting Sun.&apos;</e>
<cmt>蘇我馬子もUmako SOGAでしたので、小野妹子もImoko ONOに揃えました。「」ですので&apos;&apos;に致しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>恙無きや。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Are you safe and sound ?&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Are you in good health?&quot;</e>
<cmt>Rewritten. &apos;Safe and sound&apos; gives the impression that the writer is concerned for the welfare of the recipient.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Are you in good health?&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>云々。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>」（「日出處天子致書日沒處天子無恙云云」）の上表文（国書）を送る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He sent the above diplomatic message.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He sent the above diplomatic message.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He sent the above diplomatic message.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>留学生・留学僧を隋に留学させて隋の文化を大いに取り入れて、国家の政治・文化の向上に努めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Shotoku sent students and priests for studying in Sui, adopted Sui culture considerably and strived to improve nation&apos;s politics and culture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Shotoku sent students and priests to study in Sui, adopted Sui culture to a great degree and strived to improve the nation&apos;s politics and culture.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Shotoku sent students and priests to study in Sui, adopted Sui culture to a great degree and strived to improve the nation&apos;s politics and culture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>620年（推古28年）には、聖徳太子は蘇我馬子と「天皇記・国記、臣連伴造国造百八十部併公民等本記」を記した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 620, Prince Shotoku compiled with Umako SOGA a series of massive anthology with the title&apos;天皇記・国記,臣連伴造国造百八十部併公民等本記&apos;</e>
<cmt>「天皇記・国記、臣連伴造国造百八十部併公民等本記」(英訳不可能)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 620, Prince Shotoku compiled a massive anthology with the title&apos;天皇記・国記,臣連伴造国造百八十部併公民等本記&apos;with Umako Soga.</e>
<cmt>Style, word order.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 620, together with Umako SOGA, Prince Shotoku compiled &apos;Tennoki&apos; (The Imperial Record), &apos;The National Record&apos;, and &apos;The Real Record of Omi (a title of the highest rank), Muraji (a title of the highest rank), Tomo no Miyatsuko (the chief of a professional clan), Kuni no Miyatsuko (a local chief), 180 professional groups and Emperor&apos;s People.&apos;</e>
<cmt>天皇記・国記、臣連伴造国造百八十部併公民等本記の部分を補足いたしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="26">
<j>国造制が、遅くとも推古朝頃には、全国的に行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No later than in Suiko Dynasty, Kuninomiyatsuko (local chief) system was introduced through the whole country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kuninomiyatsuko (local chief) system was introduced through the whole country no later than the time of Empress Suiko.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, word order, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kuninomiyatsuko (local chief) system was introduced through the whole country no later than the time of Empress Suiko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>国造とは、王権に服属した各地の有力豪族に与えられた一種の称号で、ヤマト政権の日本古代の地方官制的な性格を持つものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A local chief was a kind of the title which was given to powerful clans in various places who were subjected to the emperor authority. It was a kind of title and had a character of provincial government in ancient times under Yamato political power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Local chief was a kind of title which was given to powerful clans in various places who were subject to the emperor&apos;s authority; it was a form of provincial government in ancient times under the Yamato political system.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation, word choice, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Local chief was a kind of title which was given to powerful clans in various places who were subject to the emperor&apos;s authority; it was a form of provincial government in ancient times under the Yamato political system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="28">
<j>推古29年（621年）に摂政であった厩戸皇子が、同34年（626年）には蘇我馬子が、さらに、推古天皇は36年（628年）に没し、36年間の長期に渡った日本歴史上初めての女帝の時代が終わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 621, Prince Shotoku, in 626, Umako SOGA and in 628, Empress Suiko passed away respectively, and the period of first Empress in Japanese history which lasted for a long time of 36 years finished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Shotoku died in 621, followed by Umako SOGA and Empress Suiko in 626 and 628 respectively, and with this the era of the first empress in Japanese history, lasting for 36 years, finished.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation, word choice, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Shotoku died in 621, followed by Umako SOGA and Empress Suiko in 626 and 628 respectively, and with this the era of the first empress in Japanese history, lasting for 36 years, finished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>舒明・皇極朝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jomei, Kogyoku Dynasty</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Jomei and Kogyoku Dynasties</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Jomei and Kogyoku Dynasties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>聖徳太子と推古天皇が没した後は、蘇我蝦夷と子の蘇我入鹿（いるか）の専横ぶりが目立ったと日本書紀には記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Chronicles of Janan, after the death of Prince Shotoku and Empress Suiko, high-handedness of Emishi SOGA and his son, Iruka SOGA was conspicuous.After the death of Empress Suiko, Emperor Jomei (Prince Tamura) and Yamashirooenoo (son of Prince Shotoku) had become the candidates as the successor to the Imperial Throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the Chronicles of Janan, after the deaths of Prince Shotoku and Empress Suiko, the high-handedness of Emishi SOGA and his son, Iruka SOGA, became apparent.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation, word choice. Second sentence removed as appears below.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the Chronicles of Japan, after the deaths of Prince Shotoku and Empress Suiko, the high-handedness of Emishi SOGA and his son, Iruka SOGA, became apparent.</e>
<cmt>the Chronicles of Japanのスペルを訂正いたしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>推古天皇没後、皇位継承候補となったのは舒明天皇（田村皇子）と山背大兄王（聖徳太子の子）であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Empress Suiko, Emperor Jomei (Prince Tamura) and Yamashirooenoo (son of Prince Shotoku) had become the candidates as the successor to the Imperial Throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Empress Suiko, Emperor Jomei (then Prince Tamura) and Yamashirooenoo (a son of Prince Shotoku) emerged as the leading candidates to succeed to the Imperial Throne.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Empress Suiko, Emperor Jomei (then Prince Tamura) and Yamashirooenoo (a son of Prince Shotoku) emerged as the leading candidates to succeed to the Imperial Throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>蝦夷は推古の遺言を元に舒明を擁立するが、同族境部摩理勢は山背大兄を推したため、蝦夷に滅ぼされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emishi supported Jomei on the basis of the Empress Suiko&apos;s last will, but Marise SAKAIBE, one of his same family supported Ymashirooenoo and Marise was killed by Emishi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emishi supported Jomei on the basis of Empress Suiko&apos;s last will, but as Marise SAKAIBE, a member of his family, supported Yamashirooenoo, Marise was killed by Emishi.</e>
<cmt>Spelling, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emishi supported Jomei on the basis of Empress Suiko&apos;s last will, but as Marise SAKAIBE, a member of his family, supported Yamashirooenoo, Marise was killed by Emishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>舒明の没後は、大后である皇極天皇が皇極天皇として即位した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Emperor Jomei, the queen dowager acceded to the throne as Empress Kogyoku,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Emperor Jomei, the queen dowager acceded to the throne as Empress Kogyoku.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Emperor Jomei, the queen dowager acceded to the throne as Empress Kogyoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>さらに蝦夷・入鹿の専横は激しくなり、蘇我蝦夷が自ら国政を執り、紫の冠を私用したことや643年聖徳太子の子山背大兄王一族（上宮王家）を滅ぼしたことなど、蘇我氏が政治をほしいままにした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, Emishi and Iruka became extremely bossy, the Soga clan usurped politics of the country, used the &quot; purple crown&quot; for their private purposes, and exterminated Yamashirooenoo family. (note; purple crown was used only for a person in highest rank such as an emperor in ancient times).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emishi and Iruka became increasingly authoritarian, and the Soga clan usurped political power, using the &quot;purple crown&quot; for their own purposes (the purple crown was used only for people of the highest rank such as emperors), and exterminating the Yamashirooenoo family in 643.</e>
<cmt>Missing date added, word choice, sentences unified, grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emishi and Iruka became increasingly authoritarian, and the Soga clan usurped political power, using the &apos;purple crown&apos; for their own purposes (the purple crown was used only for people of the highest rank such as emperors), and exterminating the Yamashirooenoo family (Uetsunomiya royal house) in 643.</e>
<cmt>へ変更いたしました。上宮王家を追加いたしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>孝徳朝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kotoku Dynasty</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kotoku Dynasty</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kotoku Dynasty</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>645年（皇極4年）の乙巳の変で、天智天皇・中臣鎌子（藤原鎌足）らが宮中（板蓋宮）で蘇我入鹿を暗殺し、蘇我蝦夷を自殺に追いやり、半世紀も続いた蘇我氏の体制を滅ぼした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 645 (kinotomi coup), Prince Naka no Oe (later, Emperor Tenji) and Nakatomi no Kamatari (later, Fujiwara no Kamatari) assassinated Iruka SOGA at the Imperial Court, drove Emishi SOGA to suicide and annihilated the Soga clan.</e>
<cmt>乙巳：この時代では645年に相当する。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 645, Prince Naka no Oe (later, Emperor Tenji) and Nakatomi no Kamatari (later, Fujiwara no Kamatari) assassinated Iruka SOGA at the Imperial Court, drove Emishi SOGA to suicide and annihilated the Soga clan, in what is known as the The Isshi Incident, or Incident of 645.</e>
<cmt>Word order. I have translated 乙巳の変 as &apos;The Isshi Incident&apos;: please see http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isshi_Incident</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 645, Prince Naka no Oe (later, Emperor Tenji) and Kamako NAKATOMI (later, Kamatari FUJIWARA) assassinated Iruka SOGA at the Imperial Court, drove Emishi SOGA to suicide and annihilated the Soga clan, in what is known as the The Isshi Incident, or Incident of 645.</e>
<cmt>蘇我馬子に合わせて中臣鎌子（なかとみのかまこ）の表記を統一いたしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="35">
<j>新たに即位した孝徳天皇は次々と改革を進めていった（大化の改新）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Kotoku, who newly ascended to the throne, promoted reforms one after another (the Taika Reform).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Kotoku, who had recently ascended to the throne, promoted a succession of reforms which have come to be known as the Taika Reform.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Kotoku, who had recently ascended to the throne, promoted a succession of reforms which have come to be known as the Taika Reform.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>日本書紀の記述によると、翌年（646年）正月には改新の詔を宣して、政治体制の改革を始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Chronicles of Japan, in January, next year (646), Emperor Kotoku declared an imperial proclamation for reform and began reform of political system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the Chronicles of Japan, in January the following year Emperor Kotoku made an imperial proclamation to enact reform and began restructuring the political system.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar, punctuation, &apos;646&apos; removed as tautological.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the Chronicles of Japan, in January the following year Emperor Kotoku made an imperial proclamation to enact reform and began restructuring the political system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>その後も、今までは蘇我氏の大臣1人だけの中央官制を左大臣・右大臣・内臣の3人に改めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The emperor reformed the central government system, increasing the number of minister from one to three, that is, the Minister of the Left, the Minister of the Right, and the Minister of the Inside (Uchitsuomi; senior adviser to an emperor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The emperor reformed the central government system, increasing the number of ministers from one to three, namely the Minister of the Left, the Minister of the Right, and the Minister of the Inside (Uchitsuomi: senior adviser to the emperor).</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The emperor reformed the central government system, increasing the number of ministers from one to three, namely the Minister of the Left, the Minister of the Right, and the Minister of the Inside (Uchitsuomi: senior adviser to the emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>東国等の国司に戸籍調査や田畑の調査を命じたとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The emperor ordered provincial governors in the eastern provinces to investigate family registers and fields.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The emperor ordered provincial governors in the eastern provinces to survey family registers and land.</e>
<cmt>Word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The emperor ordered provincial governors in the eastern provinces to survey family registers and land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>天智朝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenji Dynasty</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tenji Dynasty</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tenji Dynasty</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="39">
<j>孝徳天皇没後は、中大兄皇子が政治の実権を握った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Emperor Kotoku, Prince Naka no Oe grasped the real political power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Emperor Kotoku, Prince Naka no Oe obtained real political power.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Emperor Kotoku, Prince Naka no Oe obtained real political power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>中大兄皇子は何らかの理由により皇位にはつかず、母である皇極天皇を、再度即位（重祚）させた（斉明天皇）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, for some reason, Prince Naka no Oe did not become Emperor and made Empress Kogyoku, his mother accede to the throne again (Empress Saimei).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For reasons unclear Prince Naka no Oe did not become emperor himself, but made his mother Empress Kogyoku take the throne again, as Empress Saimei.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For reasons unclear Prince Naka no Oe did not become emperor himself, but made his mother Empress Kogyoku take the throne again, as Empress Saimei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>斉明天皇没後も数年の間、皇位につかず皇太子の地位で政務に当たった（天皇の位につかず政務を執ることを称制という）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Empress Saimei, for several years, he did not succeed to the Imperial Throne and administered government affairs as a Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For several years after the death of Empress Saimei, while he did not succeed to the Imperial Throne he administered government affairs as Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>Word order, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For several years after the death of Empress Saimei, while he did not succeed to the Imperial Throne he administered government affairs as Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="42">
<j>663年、百済復興に助力するため朝鮮半島へ出兵したが、白村江の戦いで新羅・唐連合軍に大敗した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 663, Prince Naka no Oe dispatched troops to Korean peninsula to help Paekche (Kudara) rebuild the country, but Japanese army was soundly defeated by Silla -Tang allied force in the battle at Hakusukinoe (the mouth of Kum river).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 663, Prince Naka no Oe dispatched troops to the Korean peninsula to help the Kingdom of Baekje (Kudara) rebuild the country, but the Japanese army was soundly defeated by the Silla -Tang allied forces in the battle of Hakusukinoe, at the mouth of Kum River.</e>
<cmt>Spelling, punctuation, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 663, Prince Naka no Oe dispatched troops to the Korean peninsula to help the Kingdom of Baekje (Kudara) rebuild the country, but the Japanese army was soundly defeated by the Silla -Tang allied forces in the battle of Hakusukinoe, at the mouth of Kum River.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>そのことは当時の支配層にとっては大変な脅威であり、日本列島の各地に防衛施設を造り始めるきっかけとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The defeat in the Korean peninsula was a serious threat to the governing class in Japan in those days and led to the beginning to build defense facilities in various places in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The defeat in the Korean peninsula was a serious threat to the governing class in Japan and led to the building of defense facilities in various places in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The defeat in the Korean peninsula was a serious threat to the governing class in Japan and led to the building of defense facilities in various places in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>664年（天智2年）筑紫に大宰府を守る水城を造り、対馬・隠岐・筑紫に防人や烽を置いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 664, they built a castle in the province of Chikushi in Kyushu to defend Dazaifu (the political center in northern Kyushu in those days) and stationed Sakimori (coast guards) in Tsushima, Oki and Chikushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 664, they built a castle in the province of Chikushi in Kyushu to defend Dazaifu (the political center in northern Kyushu at the time) and stationed sakimori (coastguards) in Tsushima, Oki and Chikushi.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 664, they built a castle in the province of Chikushi in Kyushu to defend Dazaifu (the political center in northern Kyushu at the time) and forts in Tsushima, Oki and Chikushi with sakimori (coastguards) stationed there.</e>
<cmt>烽を追加いたしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>666年（天智5年）には、百済人二千余人を東国へ移すなど、防衛施設の整備が進んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 666, they moved more than 2000 of Paekche people from Korea to eastern provinces of Japan and promoted the arrangement of defense facilities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 666, they moved more than 2000 of the people of Baekje from Korea to the eastern provinces of Japan and promoted the construction of defense facilities.</e>
<cmt>Spelling, word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 666, they moved more than 2000 of the people of Baekje from Korea to the eastern provinces of Japan and promoted the construction of defense facilities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>667年（天智6年）都城も防衛しやすい近江宮に移された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 667, the imperial palace in the capital was moved to Omikyu, the place where it is easy to defend the capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 667, the imperial palace in the capital was moved to Omikyu, a place easier to defend.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 667, the imperial palace in the capital was moved to Omikyu, a place easier to defend.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>そのほか、大和に高安城、讃岐に屋島、対馬に金田城が築かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, Takayasu castle in Yamato region, Yashima castle in Sanuki region (in Shikoku) and Kaneda castle in Tsushima island were built respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takayasu Castle in Yamato region, Yashima Castle in Sanuki region (in Shikoku) and Kaneda Castle in Tsushima island were also built.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takayasu Castle in Yamato region, Yashima Castle in Sanuki region (in Shikoku) and Kaneda Castle in Tsushima island were also built.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="48">
<j>668年（天智7年）に皇太子中大兄皇子が即位して、天智天皇となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 668, Prince Naka no Oe ascended to the throne to become Emperor Tenji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 668, Prince Naka no Oe ascended to the throne as Emperor Tenji.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 668, Prince Naka no Oe ascended to the throne as Emperor Tenji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="49">
<j>670年（天智9年）全国的な戸籍（古代の戸籍制度）を作り、人民を把握する国内政策も推進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 670. Emperor Tenji made a nationwide Kanoeuma family register system (family register system in ancient times) and promoted national policy of grasping the people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 670, Emperor Tenji created the nationwide Kanoeuma family register system and promoted a national policy of surveying the condition of the people.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, repetition removed, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 670, Emperor Tenji created the nationwide family register system and promoted a national policy of surveying the condition of the people.</e>
<cmt>庚午とは記されていませんので、削除いたしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>また、東国に柵を造った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also he constructed fences for defense in the eastern provinces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also organized the construction of defensive barriers in the eastern provinces.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also organized the construction of defensive barriers in the eastern provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>天武・持統朝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenmu, Jito Dynasty</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tenmu and Jito Dynasties</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tenmu and Jito Dynasties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="51">
<j>天智天皇が没すると、天智の弟である大海人皇子（後の天武天皇）と、息子である弘文天皇（明治時代に弘文天皇と諡号され、歴代に加えられる）との間で、争いが起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Emperor Tenji, in 672, Jinshin War occurred between Prince Oama (brother of Emperor Tenji) (later Emperor Tenmu), and Emperor Kobun (son of Emperor Tenji) occurred.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Emperor Tenji in 672, a war was fought between Prince Oama, the brother of Emperor Tenji, and Emperor Kobun, the son of Emperor Tenji.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, changed for clarity. Reference to Emperor Tenmu deleted as the same information is contained below.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Emperor Tenji in 672, a war was fought between Prince Oama, the brother of Emperor Tenji, and Emperor Kobun, the son of Emperor Tenji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>672年（弘文元年）壬申の乱である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was the Jinshin war in 672.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the Jinshin War of 672.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the Jinshin War of 672.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>この戦いは、地方豪族の力も得て、最終的には大海人が勝利、即位し、天武天皇となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Oama won in this war with the help of regional clans and acceded to the throne to be Emperor Tenmu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Oama won the war with the help of regional clans and acceded to the throne as Emperor Tenmu.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Oama won the war with the help of powerful regional clans and acceded to the throne as Emperor Tenmu.</e>
<cmt>豪族にpowerfulの修飾語を付記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>天武天皇は、中央集権的な国家体制の整備に努めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Tenmu strived to develop a centralized national system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Tenmu strived to develop a centralized national system of government.</e>
<cmt>Added for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Tenmu strived to develop a centralized national system of government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="55">
<j>672年の末に宮を飛鳥浄御原宮に移した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of 672, Emperor Tenmu moved the palace to Asuka Kiyomihara palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of 672, Emperor Tenmu moved the palace to Asuka Kiyomihara Palace.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of 672, Emperor Tenmu moved the palace to Asuka Kiyomihara Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>官人登用の法、甲子の宣の廃止、貴族・社寺の山・島・浦・林・池などの返還、畿外の豪族と才能のある百姓の任官への道を開き、官人の位階昇進の制度などを新設したりといった諸政を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Tenmu enforced measures such as the law for appointment of government officials, the abolition of Koshi pronouncement, the return to the court of mountains, islands, beaches, woods, ponds and others owned by aristocrats and, shrines and temples; opened the way to government officials for regional clans in remote places and talented farmers; established the new court rank and promotion system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Tenmu enforced a range of measures, such as a law relating to the appointment of government officials, the reversal of the Koshi pronouncement, and the ordering of the return to the court of mountains, islands, beaches, woods, ponds and other natural features owned by aristocrats or belonging to shrines and temples; he also opened the way to government positions for members of regional clans in remote places and talented farmers, and established a new court rank and promotion system.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity and flow, punctuation, grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Tenmu enforced a range of measures, such as a law relating to the appointment of government officials, the reversal of the Koshi pronouncement, and the ordering of the return to the court of mountains, islands, beaches, woods, ponds and other assets owned by aristocrats or shrines and temples; he also opened the way to government positions for members of powerful remote regional clans as well as those near the capital and talented farmers, and established a new court rank and promotion system.</e>
<cmt>畿外の豪族の説明を詳しくしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="57">
<j>681年（天武10年）には、律令の編纂を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 681, Emperor Tenmu began compilation of statutes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 681, Emperor Tenmu began the compilation of statutes.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 681, Emperor Tenmu began the compilation of statutes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>5年後の686年（朱鳥元年）に天武は没する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Five years afterwards, in 686, Emperor Tenmu passed away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Five years later, in 686, Emperor Tenmu died.</e>
<cmt>Word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Five years later, in 686, Emperor Tenmu died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>8年後の689年（持統3年）には諸氏に令1部全22巻で構成される飛鳥浄御原令が制定され、頒布される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eight years afterwards, in 689, administrative law of Asuka Kiyomihara, composed of 22 volumes, was established and promulgated</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 689, the administrative law of the Asuka Kiyomihara, composed of 22 volumes, was established and promulgated.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, removed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 689, the administrative law of the Asuka Kiyomihara, composed of 22 volumes, was established and promulgated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>律は編纂されず、唐律をそのまま用いたのではないかと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Penal law was not compiled. It is considered that penal law of Tang was used as it was.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A new penal law was not compiled, and it is thought that the Tang penal law was used as it was.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar, sentences unified.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A new penal law was not compiled, and it is thought that the Tang penal law was used as it was.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="61">
<j>人民支配のための本格的な古代の戸籍制度作りも開始される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Establishment of a real family register in ancient times was began for controlling people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The beginning of the establishment of a full family register at this time was an attempt to control the population.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, changed for clarity, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The beginning of the establishment of a full family register at this time was an attempt to control the population.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>690年（持統4年）には、庚寅年籍が造られ、「六年一造」の造籍の出発点となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 690, the Kanoetora year family register was established and this was the beginning of investigating family register &quot;once every 6 years.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 690, the Kanoetora year family register was established and this was the beginning of a family register survey &quot;once every 6 years&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Word order, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 690, the Kanoetora year family register was established and this was the beginning of a family register survey &apos;once every 6 years.&apos;</e>
<cmt>に変更いたしました。指示書通り、.を&apos;&apos;の中に含めました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>692年（持統6年）には、畿内に班田大夫を派遣し、公地公民制を基礎とした班田収授法を実施した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 692, the government sent Handentayu (lord steward) for farmland allotment to people in provinces near capital and executed law for tax payment according to the allotted farmland, based on the ownership of farmland.</e>
<cmt>班田収受法：６歳以上の公民・奴婢に田を与え、税を徴収し、本人の死後に朝廷に返還させる法律</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 692, the government sent a handentayu (lord steward for farmland allotment) to people in the provinces near the capital and executed the law for tax payment according to the allotted farmland, based on the ownership of the farmland.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 692, the government sent a handentayu (lord steward for farmland allotment) to people in the provinces near the capital and executed the law for tax payment according to the allotted farmland, based on the ownership of the farmland.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>702年には、大宝令にもとづいた最初の造籍が行われ、国民1人1人が政府に把握されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 702, the first family register preparation was executed on the basis of the Taiho Code and each member of the nation had come to be grasped by the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 702, the first family register was created on the basis of the Taiho Code and each member of the nation had been surveyed by the government.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 702, the first family register was created on the basis of the Taiho Code and each member of the nation had been surveyed by the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>さらに、条里制による耕地の区画整理が進み、班田が与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, adjustment of cultivated land made progress and each member was allotted a farmland to each person.</e>
<cmt>条里制：土地を四角形に区分して管理する方法。古代から中世にかけて行われた。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Through this, the oversight of cultivated land was improved and each member was allotted farmland.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, Jori system (the system of land division) facilitated the readjustment of cultivated land and each member was allotted farmland.</e>
<cmt>条里制を補足説明いたしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="66">
<j>694年（持統8年）には日本初の本格的都城となる藤原京に都を遷した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 694, the Empress Jito transferred the capital to Fujiwarakyo, Japan&apos;s first full-scale castle town (Chinese style town with an orderly grids of streets).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 694, Empress Jito transferred the capital to Fujiwarakyo, Japan&apos;s first full-scale castle town (a Chinese style town with an orderly grid of streets).</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 694, Empress Jito transferred the capital to Fujiwarakyo, Japan&apos;s first full-scale castle town.</e>
<cmt>都の形状は説明されていないので、削除いたしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="67">
<j>持統天皇は子の草壁皇子に位を譲るつもりであったが、早世したため、孫である文武天皇を即位させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Empress Jito intended to hand over the throne to her son, Prince Kusakabe, but he died young, therefore, she made her grandson, Emperor Monmu accede to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Empress Jito intended to hand over the throne to her son, Prince Kusakabe, but as he died young she ensured her grandson, Emperor Monmu, acceded to the throne after her abdication.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar. Added for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Empress Jito intended to hand over the throne to her son, Prince Kusakabe, but as he died young she ensured her grandson, Emperor Monmu, acceded to the throne after her abdication.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>この間、唐の律令制を基本に、律と令にもとづいた政治を実施するために、700年（文武4年）に王臣に令文を読習させ、律条を撰定する作業に取りかかり、翌年の701年（文武5年）に大宝律令が制定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During that time, in 700, Empress Jito let her subjects learn Tang statutes in order to enforce politics based on the Ritsu (penal law) and Ryou (administrative law), after the model of Tang (China) law system, and in 701, the next year, the Taiho Code was completed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 700, Empress Jito made her subjects learn Tang statutes in order to create a political system based on the ritsu (penal law) and ryou (administrative law) codes, following the model of the Tang (China) legal system, and in 701, the following year, the Taiho Code was completed.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar, punctuation, word order.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 700, Empress Jito made administrators learn Tang statutes in order to create a political system based on the ritsu (penal law) and ryou (administrative law) codes, following the model of the Tang (China) legal system, and in 701, the following year, the Taiho Code was completed.</e>
<cmt>王臣は限られた執政者を指すと考えられますので、subjectsからadministratorsに変更いたしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>これにより、天皇を頂点とした、貴族・官僚による中央集権支配体制が完成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the result of the Taiho Code completion, centralization of government system by aristocrats and bureaucrats with Japanese emperor as their top was accomplished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of the completion of the Taiho Code the centralization of the government system by aristocrats and bureaucrats with the Japanese emperor as the top was accomplished.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of the completion of the Taiho Code the centralization of the government system by aristocrats and bureaucrats with the Japanese emperor as the top was accomplished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>これをもって、一応の古代国家成立と見る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With this centralized government system accomplishment, it is considered that the ancient state in Japan was completed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that the accomplishment of this centralized government system marked the completion of the formation of the feudal state in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that the accomplishment of this centralized government system marked the completion of the formation of the ancient state in Japan.</e>
<cmt>feudal stateは日本では鎌倉時代から明治維新までとするのが通常のようですので、ancient stateに戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="71">
<j>日本の官制は太政官と神祇官による二官八省制がとられ、日本古代の地方官制は、国・郡・里制がとられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concerning central government, the system with 2 kinds of officials (the officials in charge of politics and the officials in charge of Shinto religion) and 8 ministries was adopted; and concerning local government, Province, County and Village system was adopted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A system with two kinds of officials (in charge of politics, and in charge of the Shinto religion) and eight ministries was adopted for central government; and a province, county and village system was adopted for local government.</e>
<cmt>Word order, grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A system with two kinds of officials (in charge of politics, and in charge of the Shinto religion) and eight ministries was adopted for central government; and a province, county and village system was adopted for local government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>租・庸・調の税制が整備され、国家財政が支えられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for tax system, taxes in produce or labor were adopted and state finance started to be supported.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the tax system, taxes on production and labor were adopted and state finances started to become more stable.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice/</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the tax system, taxes in kind or service were adopted and state finances started to become more stable.</e>
<cmt>租庸調の定訳はtaxes in kind or serviceのようですので、戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>また律令制度の施行に伴って生じた不備などを調整する目的から、慶雲の改革が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, the Reform of Keiun was conducted in order to adjust problems which had occurred with the enforcement of Ritsu and Ryou code.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, the Keiun Reform was conducted in order to adjust for problems which had occurred with the enforcement of the ritsu and ryou codes.</e>
<cmt>Word order, grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, the Keiun Reform was conducted in order to adjust for problems which had occurred with the enforcement of the ritsu and ryou codes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="74">
<j>文武の死後、母の元明天皇が即位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Emperor Monmu, his mother, Empress Genmyo acceded to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Emperor Monmu, his mother, Empress Genmyo acceded to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Emperor Monmu, his mother, Empress Genmyo acceded to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>710年（和銅3年）に平城京へ遷都した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 710, the court was moved to Heijokyo (now Nara).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 710, the court was moved to Heijokyo (present-day Nara).</e>
<cmt>Word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 710, the court was moved to Heijokyo (present-day Nara).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>飛鳥・白鳳文化</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Asuka, Hakuho culture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Asuka and Hakuho culture</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Asuka and Hakuho culture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>年表</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chronology</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chronology</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chronology</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>531年（継体25年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 531</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">531:</e>
<cmt>Style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">531:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="76">
<j>- 欽明天皇即位する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Jomei acceded to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Jomei accedes to throne</e>
<cmt>Grammar. As the following chronology is a list, each entry does not need a full-stop.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Jomei accedes to throne</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>535年（安閑2年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 535,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">535:</e>
<cmt>Style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">535:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="77">
<j>- 屯倉（みやけ）を多く置く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A lot of lands were put under direct control of the court</e>
<cmt>屯倉：朝廷の直轄地</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many lands put under direct control of the court</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many lands put under direct control of the court</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>538年（宣化3年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 538</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">538:</e>
<cmt>Style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">538:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="78">
<j>- 仏教伝来（公式に史書に記載されている時期として）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Introduction of Buddhism into Japan (538 is the year of introduction officially recorded in a history book).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Introduction of Buddhism into Japan (the year officially recorded in history books)</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Introduction of Buddhism into Japan (the year officially recorded in history books)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>540年（欽明元年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 540,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">540:</e>
<cmt>Style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">540:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="79">
<j>- 秦人・漢人の戸籍を作る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They made family registers for Qin and Han Chinese people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family registers made for Qin and Han Chinese people</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family registers made for Qin and Han Chinese people</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>552年（欽明13年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 552,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">552:</e>
<cmt>Style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">552:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="80">
<j>- 仏像の礼拝を群臣に問う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor asked his subjects on the worship of a Buddha image.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor asks subjects regarding the worship of Buddha images</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor asks subjects for the worship of Buddha images</e>
<cmt>仏教伝来を552年とする説もあるようなので、左記のように変更いたしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>571年（欽明32年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 571,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">571:</e>
<cmt>Style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">571:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="81">
<j>- 欽明天皇没する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Jomei passed away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Death of Emperor Jomei</e>
<cmt>Style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Death of Emperor Jomei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>572年（敏達元年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 572,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">572:</e>
<cmt>Style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">572:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="82">
<j>- 敏達天皇即位する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Bitatsu acceded to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Bitatsu accedes to throne</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Bitatsu accedes to throne</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>587年（用明2年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 587,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">587:</e>
<cmt>Style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">587:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="83">
<j>- 仏教に帰依せんことを群臣にはかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor consulted his subjects on becoming a believer in Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor consults subjects on becoming a believer in Buddhism</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor consults subjects on becoming a believer in Buddhism</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>物部氏と蘇我氏対立し、蘇我氏勝つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mononobe clan and the Soga clan confronted with each other, and the Soga clan won.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soga clan emerges victorious after confrontation with Mononobe clan</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soga clan emerges victorious after confrontation with Mononobe clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>用明天皇没する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Yomei passed away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Death of Emperor Yomei</e>
<cmt>Style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Death of Emperor Yomei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>588年（崇峻元年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 588,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">588:</e>
<cmt>Style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">588:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="86">
<j>- 崇峻天皇即位する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Sushun acceded to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Sushun accedes to throne</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Sushun accedes to throne</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>592年（崇峻5年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 592,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">592:</e>
<cmt>Style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">592:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="87">
<j>- 崇峻天皇暗殺される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Sushun was assassinated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Sushun assassinated</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Sushun assassinated</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>推古天皇即位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Empress Suiko acceded to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Empress Suiko accedes to throne</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Empress Suiko accedes to throne</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="89">
<j>593年（推古元年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 593,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">593:</e>
<cmt>Style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">593:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="90">
<j>- 厩戸皇子（聖徳太子）が皇太子に立てられ摂政となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Shotoku was put in the position of crown prince and became the Prince Regent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Shotoku takes position of crown prince and becomes Prince Regent</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Shotoku takes position of crown prince and becomes Prince Regent</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="20">
<tit>
<j>600年（推古8年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 600,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">600:</e>
<cmt>Style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">600:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="91">
<j>- 『隋書』によれば倭国より遣使。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a Sui book, an envoy came to Sui Dynasty (China) from Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the Book of Sui, an envoy visits Sui Dynasty (China) from Japan</e>
<cmt>The book is a proper noun; see http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Book_of_Sui</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the Book of Sui, an envoy visits Sui Dynasty (China) from Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="21">
<tit>
<j>604年（推古12年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 604,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">604:</e>
<cmt>Style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">604:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="92">
<j>- 十七条憲法・冠位十二階制定。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Seventeen-Article Constitution was promulgated and the system of twelve courtly ranks was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seventeen-Article Constitution promulgated and system of twelve courtly ranks established</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seventeen-Article Constitution promulgated and system of twelve courtly ranks established</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="22">
<tit>
<j>607年（推古15年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 607,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">607:</e>
<cmt>Style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">607:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="93">
<j>-『日本書紀』によれば初の遣唐使（遣隋使？）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Chronicles of Japan, the first envoy to Tang Dynasty China (Sui Dynasty?) was sent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Chronicles of Japan, first envoy to Tang Dynasty China (possibly Sui Dynasty) sent</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Chronicles of Japan, first envoy to Tang Dynasty China (possibly Sui Dynasty) sent</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="23">
<tit>
<j>628年（推古36年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 628,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">628:</e>
<cmt>Style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">628:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="94">
<j>- 推古天皇没する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Empress Suiko passed away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Death of Empress Suiko</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Death of Empress Suiko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>遺詔を巡って群臣争う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subjects engaged in a controversy over the last imperial message left behind by the Empress.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Controversy over last imperial message left behind by Empress Suiko</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar, added for clarity..</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Controversy over last imperial message left behind by Empress Suiko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="24">
<tit>
<j>629年（舒明元年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 629,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">629:</e>
<cmt>Style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">629:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="96">
<j>- 舒明天皇即位する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Jomei acceded to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Jomei accedes to throne</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Jomei accedes to throne</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="25">
<tit>
<j>645年（皇極4年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 645,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">645:</e>
<cmt>Style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">645:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="97">
<j>- 天智天皇・藤原鎌足ら、蘇我入鹿を宮中で暗殺する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Tenji, Kamatari FUJIWARA and others assassinated Iruka SOGA at the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Tenji, Kamatari FUJIWARA and others assassinate Iruka SOGA at Imperial Court</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Tenji, Kamatari FUJIWARA and others assassinate Iruka SOGA at Imperial Court</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>蘇我蝦夷自殺する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emishi SOGA committed suicide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emishi SOGA commits suicide</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emishi SOGA commits suicide</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>（乙巳の変）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The kinotomi (645) coup)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The Isshi Incident, or Incident of 645)</e>
<cmt>Please see http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isshi_Incident</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The Isshi Incident, or Incident of 645)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="26">
<tit>
<j>646年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 646,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">646:</e>
<cmt>Style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">646:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="100">
<j>- 改新の詔を宣する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial Court declared the Reform.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Court announces reform</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Court announces reform</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>（大化の改新）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The Taika Reform)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The Taika Reform)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The Taika Reform)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="27">
<tit>
<j>663年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 663</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">663:</e>
<cmt>Style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">663:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="102">
<j>- 白村江の戦い（はくすきのえのたたかい）で大敗する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese army sustained a crushing defeat in the battle of Hakusukinoe in Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese army sustains crushing defeat at battle of Hakusukinoe, Korea</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese army sustains crushing defeat at battle of Hakusukinoe, Korea</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="28">
<tit>
<j>670年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 670,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">670:</e>
<cmt>Style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">670:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="103">
<j>- 全国的に戸籍を作る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first family register was produced on a nationwide scale.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First family register produced on a national scale</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First family register produced on a national scale</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>（庚午年籍）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Kanoeuma year register)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Kanoeuma year register)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Kanoeuma year register)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="29">
<tit>
<j>672年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 672.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">672:</e>
<cmt>Style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">672:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="105">
<j>- 天智天皇没する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Tenji passed away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Death of Emperor Tenji</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Death of Emperor Tenji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>壬申の乱。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jinshin war occurred.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jinshin War</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jinshin War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>飛鳥浄御原宮（きよみはらのみや）に遷る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The capital was transferred to Asuka Kiyomihara no Miya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Capital transferred to Asuka Kiyomihara no Miya</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Capital transferred to Asuka Kiyomihara no Miya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="30">
<tit>
<j>681年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 681,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">681:</e>
<cmt>Style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">681:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="108">
<j>- 飛鳥浄御原令の編纂を開始する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The compilation of Asuka Kyomihara code began.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Compilation of Asuka Kyomihara code begins</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Compilation of Asuka Kyomihara code begins</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="31">
<tit>
<j>690年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 690,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">690:</e>
<cmt>Style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">690:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="109">
<j>- 戸令により庚寅年籍を作る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The new edition of family register (Kanoetora year register) was produced by the family decree.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanoetora year register produced by decree</e>
<cmt>Simplified.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanoetora year register produced by decree</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="32">
<tit>
<j>694年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 694,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">694:</e>
<cmt>Style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">694:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="110">
<j>- 藤原京に都を移す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The capital was transferred to Fujiwarakyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Capital transferred to Fujiwarakyo</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Capital transferred to Fujiwarakyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="33">
<tit>
<j>697年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 697,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">697:</e>
<cmt>Style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">697:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="111">
<j>- 持統天皇譲位し、文武天皇即位する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Empress Jito abdicated the throne and Emperor Monmu acceded to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Empress Jito abdicates; Emperor Monmu accedes to throne</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Empress Jito abdicates; Emperor Monmu accedes to throne</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="34">
<tit>
<j>701年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 701,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">701:</e>
<cmt>Style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">701:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="112">
<j>- 大宝律令の撰定完成する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Taiho Code was completed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taiho Code completed</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taiho Code completed</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="35">
<tit>
<j>707年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 707,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">707:</e>
<cmt>Style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">707:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="113">
<j>- 文武天皇（25）没し、元明天皇即位する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Monmu passed away (at the age of 25) and Emperor Genmyo acceded to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Death of Emperor Monmu at age of 25; Emperor Genmyo accedes to throne</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Death of Emperor Monmu at age of 25; Empress Genmei accedes to throne</e>
<cmt>元明（げんめい）天皇は女帝です。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="36">
<tit>
<j>708年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 708,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">708:</e>
<cmt>Style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">708:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="114">
<j>- 武蔵国から銅を献上する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Copper was presented by Musashi Province to the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Copper presented by Musashi Province to Imperial Court</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Copper presented by Musashi Province to Imperial Court</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>改元する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The era name was changed to Wado.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Era name changed to Wado</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Era name changed to Wado</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>和同開珎を発行する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Coins &quot;Wado Kaiho&quot; were issued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Wado Kaiho&quot; coins issued</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Wado Kaiho&quot; coins issued</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="37">
<tit>
<j>710年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 710,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">710:</e>
<cmt>Style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">710:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="117">
<j>- 平城京に遷都する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Court was moved to Heijokyo (now Nara).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Court moved to Heijokyo</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar. Reference to Nara removed, as mentioned previously in the text.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Court moved to Heijokyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="38">
<tit>
<j>関連する人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Related persons</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Related people</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Related people</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="118">
<j>聖徳太子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Shotoku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Shotoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Shotoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="119">
<j>蘇我氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Soga clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Soga clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Soga clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="120">
<j>物部氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mononobe clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mononobe clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mononobe clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="121">
<j>中大兄皇子（天智天皇）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Naka no Oe (later the Emperor Tenji)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Naka no Oe (later Emperor Tenji)</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Naka no Oe (later Emperor Tenji)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="122">
<j>大海人皇子（天武天皇）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Oama (later the Emperor Tenmu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Oama (later Emperor Tenmu)</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Oama (later Emperor Tenmu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="123">
<j>大伴氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Otomo clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Otomo clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Otomo clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="124">
<j>中臣氏（藤原氏、藤原鎌足）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nakatomi clan (the Fujiwara clan, FUJIWARA no Kamatari)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nakatomi clan (the Fujiwara clan, FUJIWARA no Kamatari)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nakatomi clan (the Fujiwara clan, Kamatari FUJIWARA)</e>
<cmt>藤原鎌足の語順を揃えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="125">
<j>阿倍比羅夫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ABE no Hirabu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ABE no Hirabu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hirafu ABE</e>
<cmt>阿倍比羅夫（あべのひらふ）の語順を揃えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="39">
<tit>
<j>遺跡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Remains</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historical sites</e>
<cmt>Word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historical sites</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="126">
<j>中ツ道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nakatsumichi (the middle road in the capital city)</e>
<cmt>中ツ道：平城京の中央を北から南に延びる中央道</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nakatsumichi (the central road of the capital city, Heijokyo)</e>
<cmt>Word choice, added for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nakatsumichi (the central road of the capital city, Heijokyo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="127">
<j>藤原宮跡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Remains of Fujiwara palace</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Remains of Fujiwara Palace</e>
<cmt>Capitalized.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Remains of Fujiwara Palace</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="128">
<j>その他、飛鳥村の多数の遺跡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A lot of remains in Asuka village and others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Several remains in Asuka village</e>
<cmt>Word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Several remains in Asuka village</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tommy6-bot(id:171289), Idioma-bot(id:129667), Nnh(id:474), 出羽卒族(id:283926), MIsogi(id:20599), 鹿両性証明(id:71252), Eskimbot(id:29676), Shikire(id:1623), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), 味っ子(id:17086), アスカ(id:9205), Mintleaf(id:2216), Qazzx(id:8772), Tribot(id:186681), BAKU(id:55205), Robert De Smith(id:28533), Mkei(id:96493), Yonidebot(id:247998), Gombe(id:27), Shinobar(id:42025), AlnoktaBOT(id:135808), MUSASHI(id:11881), Rei-bot(id:94097), しょかい(id:73826), Gbr3(id:6539), Silverpenguin(id:291824), Shimoxx(id:9332), 明日香(id:82152), Yas(id:739), Yosemite(id:5808), Tatsujin28(id:9300), Izayohi(id:13095), MystBot(id:224584), Kzy(id:9253), いろはにほへと(id:89648), Cyuuritsu Na Shitenn(id:102276), Forestfarmer(id:59407), Law soma(id:45202), 水野白楓(id:22811), MIO(id:31681), Tiyoringo(id:70026), Godaigo(id:133481), Utsuda(id:605), Hokuto7(id:18100), ごまふあざ(id:36855), Etsuk(id:878), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Nidarin(id:6420), 戸人(id:168148), ＮｉＫｅ(id:7512), Shikai shaw(id:14306), 663highland(id:18755), トホホ川(id:50502), Alexbot(id:157199), 伏儀(id:142093), Suisui(id:69), LeonardoRob0t(id:25875), SieBot(id:126695), Binh Giang(id:79801), Chuta(id:10457), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>