<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>物合</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monoawase</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Monoawase</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Monoawase</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>物合（ものあわせ）は平安時代に隆盛を極めた遊戯。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monoawase (&quot;mono&quot; for things and &quot;awase&quot; for comparison) was a game that became most popular in the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Monoawase (&quot;mono&quot; meaning things and &quot;awase&quot; meaning comparison) was a game that became most popular in the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Monoawase (&quot;mono&quot; meaning things and &quot;awase&quot; meaning comparison) was a game that became most popular in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>半角クォーテーションにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>参加者を左右二組に分けて課題の品物などを持ち寄らせ、審判を立てて何回戦かを競い、左右チーム総合の勝敗を決めるもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was played by splitting participants into teams of right and left, having them bring items of a subject to be compared against each other between the teams in several rounds, and having a judge determine which one won the game at the end.</e>
<cmt>※物合において必須となる「比べる」という作業がないと文章として意味をなさないため、訳文にて補足しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was played by splitting participants into teams of right and left, having them bring items of a subject to be compared against each other between the teams in several rounds, and having a judge determine which team won the game at the end.</e>
<cmt>pronoun</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was played by splitting participants into teams of right and left, having them bring items of a subject to be compared against each other between the teams in several rounds, and having a judge determine which team won the game at the end.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>代表的なものには、歌合・絵合・貝合などがあり、その他にも鳥合（闘鶏）・花合（花いくさ）・小鳥合（こちらは小鳥の品評会）・虫合・前栽合・扇合・琵琶合など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the most well-known games of monoawase were utaawase (poetry), eawase (picture), kaiawase (shell), as well as toriawase (bird), also known as tokei (cockfight), hanaawase (flower), also known as hanaikusa (flower battle), kotoriawase (bird bench show), mushiawase (insect), senzaiawase (plant), ogiawase (fan), and biwaawase (lute).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the most well-known games of monoawase were utaawase (poetry), eawase (picture), and kaiawase (shell), as well as toriawase (bird), also known as tokei (cockfight), hanaawase (flower), also known as hanaikusa (flower battle), kotoriawase (bird bench show), mushiawase (insect), senzaiawase (plant), ogiawase (fan), and biwaawase (lute).</e>
<cmt>inserted &quot;and&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the most well-known games of monoawase were utaawase (poetry match), eawase (picture match), and kaiawase (shell match), as well as toriawase (bird match) (also known as tokei [cockfight]), hanaawase (flower match) (also known as hanaikusa [flower battle]), kotoriawase (bird bench show), mushiawase (insect match), senzaiawase (plant match), ogiawase (fan match), and biwaawase (lute match).</e>
<cmt>用語補足を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>季節の行事として、菖蒲の根合・菊合・紅梅合などもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As seasonal events, shobu-no-neawase (iris root), kikuawase (chrysanthemum), and kobaiawase (red-blossomed plum) were also played.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As seasonal events, shobu-no-neawase (iris root), kikuawase (chrysanthemum), and kobaiawase (red-blossomed plum) were also played.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As seasonal events, shobu-no-neawase (iris root match), kikuawase (chrysanthemum match), and kobaiawase (red-blossomed plum match) were also played.</e>
<cmt>用語補足を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>遊び方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">How to Play</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">How to Play</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">How to Play</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>まず、左方・右方のチームメンバーを決める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fist, members were assigned for right or left teams.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First, members are assigned for right and left teams.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First, members are assigned for right and left teams.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>大体は各チームのスポンサーとなる大貴族が、親類縁者・家臣など関係者の中からその道に優れた人を抜擢する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of the time, major nobles, who were sponsors of each team, selected those skilled in a specific field from their relatives, vassals and related parties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of the time, major nobles, who were sponsors of each team, selected those skilled in a specific field from their relatives, vassals, and related parties.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of the time, major nobles, who were sponsors of each team, selected those skilled in a specific field from their relatives, vassals, and related parties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>歌合などでは、小貴族であっても和歌の腕がよければ選ばれて光栄に浴することも出来たので、身分の低い参加者のうちには文字通り命がけの覚悟で歌を練るものもいたと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since even minor nobles would be able to have the honor of being selected if they were skilled at waka, especially utaawase, it is said that some of the people of low birth were desperate to come up with good poems, literally for their lives.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since even minor nobles would be able to have the honor of being selected if they were skilled at waka, especially utaawase, it is said that some of the people of low birth were desperate to come up with good poems, literally for their lives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since even minor nobles would be able to have the honor of being selected if they were skilled at waka (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables), especially utaawase, it is said that some of the people of low birth were desperate to come up with good poems, literally for their lives.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>左方のチームカラーは暖色系統（当時は紫から橙色まで）で、大きな催しなどではアシスタントの女童たちの衣装や品物を包む料紙なども赤紫から紅の色合いで意匠を統一する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The left team was dressed in warm colors, ranging from purple to orange at the time, and in big events, the designs of costumes of assistant menowarawa (girls) and of writing paper for wrapping items were also unified in colors ranging from reddish purple to red.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The left team was dressed in warm colors, ranging from purple to orange at the time, and in big events, the designs of costumes of assistant menowarawa (girls) and of writing paper for wrapping items were also unified in colors ranging from reddish purple to red.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The left team was dressed in warm colors, ranging from purple to orange at the time, and in big events, the designs of costumes of assistant menowarawa (girls) and of writing paper for wrapping items were also unified in colors ranging from reddish purple to red.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>右方のチームカラーは寒色系統（当時は黄色から青紫まで）で、同じく凝った意匠を競った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The right team was dressed in cold colors, ranging from yellow to bluish purple at the time, and competed in elaborate design as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The right team was dressed in cold colors, ranging from yellow to bluish purple at the time, and competed in elaborate design as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The right team was dressed in cold colors, ranging from yellow to bluish purple at the time, and competed in elaborate design as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>審判（判者）の選定はもっとも神経を使うもので、審美眼はもちろん判定書に必要な書道や文章・和歌の道に優れた老練の人が選ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The selection of judges was a most delicate process, which would select veterans who not only had eye for beauty but also had skills in writing, waka and calligraphy, which was necessary for writing on judging paper.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The selection of judges was a most delicate process, which would select veterans who not only had an eye for beauty but also had skills in writing, waka, and calligraphy, which was necessary for writing on judging paper.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The selection of judges was a most delicate process, which would select veterans who not only had an eye for beauty but also had skills in writing, waka, and calligraphy, which was necessary for writing on judging paper.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>他に、数回戦を競うため各チーム勝ち負けの数を串で記録する記録係「数刺し」がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also selected was a &apos;kazusashi&apos; who used kushi (skewer) to record the number of wins and losses by each team in several rounds.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also selected was a &apos;kazusashi&apos; who used kushi (skewer) to record the number of wins and losses by each team in several rounds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also selected was a &apos;kazusashi&apos; who used kushi (skewer) to record the number of wins and losses by each team in several rounds.</e>
<cmt>半角クォーテーションにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>また、両チームにはチーム代表で解説や進行を担当する「頭」や、応援担当の「念人」が選出されることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, there were cases when &apos;to,&apos; who was in charge of commentary and direction for their team, and &apos;nennin,&apos; whose job was to support their team, were selected.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, there were cases where &apos;to,&apos; who was in charge of commentary and direction for their team, and &apos;nennin,&apos; whose job was to support their team, were selected.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, there were cases where &apos;to,&apos; who was in charge of commentary and direction for their team, and &apos;nennin,&apos; whose job was to support their team, were selected.</e>
<cmt>半角クォーテーションにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), 桜井悠士(id:72420), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>