<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>鹿ケ谷の陰謀</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shishigatani-no-Inbo (Shishigatani Conspiracy)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shishigatani-no-Inbo (Shishigatani Conspiracy)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shishigatani-no-Inbo (Shishigatani Conspiracy)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>鹿ケ谷の陰謀（ししがたにのいんぼう）は、平安時代の安元3年（1177年）6月に京都で起こった、平家打倒の陰謀事件である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shishigatani-no-Inbo (Shishigatani Conspiracy) was a plot to overthrow the Taira clan and occurred in Kyoto in June 1177 during the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shishigatani-no-Inbo (Shishigatani Conspiracy) was a plot to overthrow the Taira clan and occurred in Kyoto in June, 1177, during the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>パンクチュエーションを変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shishigatani Conspiracy was a plot to overthrow the Taira clan and occurred in Kyoto in July, 1177, during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>日本語読みは不要と考え削除。新暦にていせいしました。period小文字にしました・。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>京都、東山鹿ヶ谷（現在の京都市左京区）の静賢法印（藤原通憲の子）の山荘で謀議が行われたとされ、このように呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is called &quot;Shishigatani-no-Inbo&quot; because secret talks were carried out at Jauken-hofuin (child of FUJIWARA no Michinori)&apos;s mountain retreat in Higashiyama Shishigatani, Kyoto (presently, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is called &quot;Shishigatani-no-Inbo&quot; because secret talks were carried out at Joken-hoin (a child of FUJIWARA no Michinori)&apos;s mountain retreat in Higashiyama Shishigatani, Kyoto (presently, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>名前の英訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is called &quot;Shishigatani Conspiracy&quot; because secret talks were carried out at Joken Hoin (a child of FUJIWARA no Michinori)&apos;s mountain retreat in Higashiyama Shishigatani, Kyoto (presently, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>鹿ケ谷の陰謀→Shishigatani Conspiracy としました。Joken-hoin→Joken Hoin としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>経過</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Proceedings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Proceedings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Proceedings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>建春門院の死</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Death of Kenshunmonin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Death of Kenshunmonin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Death of Kenshunmonin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>安元2年（1176年）後白河法皇は50歳となり、正月から祝いの行事が続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The retired Emperor Goshirakawa became 50 in 1176, and various celebratory events continued on from the beginning of the year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The retired Emperor Goshirakawa turned 50 in 1176, and various celebratory events continued from the beginning of the year.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa turned 50 in 1176, and various celebratory events continued from the beginning of the year.</e>
<cmt>法皇→Cloistered Emperor に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>平氏一門も法住寺殿の宴に出席して、法皇との親密ぶりを誇示した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Taira clan members attended parties at Hoiyu-ji Temple, exhibiting there closeness with the retired Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Taira clan members attended parties at Hoiyu-ji Temple, exhibiting their closeness with the retired Emperor.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Taira clan members attended parties at Hoju-ji Temple, exhibiting their closeness with the Cloistered Emperor.</e>
<cmt>法皇→Cloistered Emperor に訂正しました。法住寺殿→Hoju-ji Temple</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>しかし6月に建春門院の病状が悪化して、7月8日に死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Kenshunmonin&apos;s state worsened in June and she died on July 8.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Kenshunmonin&apos;s physical condition worsened in June and she died on July 8.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Kenshunmonin&apos;s physical condition worsened in July and she died on August 21.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>相前後して、高松院（しゅ子内親王）・六条天皇・九条院（藤原呈子）が亡くなり、政界はにわかに動揺する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around the same time, Takamarsuin (Imperial Princess Shushi), Emperor Rokujo and Kujyoin (FUJIWARA no Shimeko) died and the political scene was in turmoil.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the same time, Takamatsuin (Imperial Princess Shushi), Emperor Rokujo and Kujyoin (FUJIWARA no Shimeko) died and the political scene fell into turmoil.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the same time, Takamatsuin (Imperial Princess Shushi), Emperor Rokujo and Kujyoin (FUJIWARA no Shimeko) died and the political scene fell into turmoil.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>まず母の死により、皇子のいない高倉天皇の立場が不安定となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First, the status of Emperor Takakura, who had no sons, became unstable due to the death of his mother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First, the status of Emperor Takakura, who had no sons, became unstable due to the death of his mother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First, the status of Emperor Takakura, who had no sons, became unstable due to the death of his mother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>成人して政務に関与するようになった高倉天皇と、院政継続を望む後白河の間には対立の兆しがあったが、12月5日の除目において後白河近臣の藤原定能・藤原光能が、平知盛らを超えて蔵人頭に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were signs of confrontation between Emperor Takakura, who had started to take part in political matters after reaching adulthood and Goshirakawa, who wanted to continue his cloistered governance, but upon the position assignment day of December 5, FUJIWARA no Nobuyoshi and FUJIWARA no Mitsuyoshi, who were close aides of Goshirakawa, were promoted as Kurodonoto, passing over TAIRA no Tomonori and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were signs of confrontation between Emperor Takakura, who had started to take part in political matters after reaching adulthood, and Goshirakawa, who wanted to continue his cloistered governance, but upon the position assignment on December 5, FUJIWARA no Nobuyoshi and FUJIWARA no Mitsuyoshi, who were close aides of Goshirakawa, were promoted to Kurodonoto, passing over TAIRA no Tomonori and others.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were signs of confrontation between Emperor Takakura, who had started to take part in political matters after reaching adulthood, and Goshirakawa, who wanted to continue his cloistered governance, but upon the position assignment on January 13, 1177, FUJIWARA no Nobuyoshi and FUJIWARA no Mitsuyoshi, who were close aides of Goshirakawa, were promoted to Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain), passing over TAIRA no Tomomori and others.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。平知盛→TAIRA no Tomomori蔵人頭→Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>後白河院政派の躍進に対する巻き返しとして、翌安元3年（1177年）正月の除目では平重盛が近衛府、平宗盛が右大将となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a counter move against the advancement of the Goshirakawa cloistered government group, TAIRA no Shigemori was appointed Konoefu (headquarters of inner palace guards) and TAIRA no Munemori was appointed Udaisho (right palace guards) upon the position assignment day in January 1177.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a counter move against the advancement of the Goshirakawa cloistered government group, TAIRA no Shigemori was appointed Konoefu (head of the inner palace guards) and TAIRA no Munemori was appointed Udaisho (head of the right palace guards) on the position assignment day of January 1177.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a counter move against the advancement of the Goshirakawa cloistered government group, TAIRA no Shigemori was appointed Konoefu (head of the inner palace guards) and TAIRA no Munemori was appointed Udaisho (head of the right palace guards) on the position assignment day of January 1177.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>建春門院という仲介者を失ったことで、人事を巡り高倉を擁する平氏と後白河院を擁する院近臣勢力は相争うことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Losing a mediator in Kenshunmonin, the Taira clan who supported Takakura and the group of aides who supported Goshirakawa began to fight over position appointments.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Losing a mediator in Kenshunmonin, the Taira clan, who supported Takakura, and the group of aides who supported Goshirakawa began to fight over position appointments.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Losing a mediator in Kenshunmonin, the Taira clan, who supported Takakura, and the group of aides who supported Goshirakawa began to fight over position appointments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>それでも3月14日に、後白河院が千僧供養のため福原京を訪れて平氏に好意的態度を示し、亀裂は修復されたかに見えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, on March 14, Goshirakawa visited Fukuhara-kyo for a thousand-monk Buddhist ceremony, acted favorably towards the Taira clan and it seemed as if the rift had been mended.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, on March 14, Goshirakawa visited Fukuhara-kyo for a ceremony involving a thousand Bhuddist monks, where he acted favorably towards the Taira clan and it seemed as if the rift had been mended.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, on April 21, Goshirakawa visited Fukuhara-kyo for a ceremony involving a thousand Bhuddist monks, where he acted favorably towards the Taira clan and it seemed as if the rift had been mended.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>白山事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hakusan Incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hakusan Incident</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hakusan Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>ところが、後白河が帰京した3月22日、山門（比叡山延暦寺）の大衆 (仏教)が加賀国守・藤原師高の配流を求めて強訴を起こした（白山事件）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when Goshirakawa returned to Kyoto on March 22, the daishu (Buddhist monks) at the Sanmon (Enryaku-ji Temple, Hieizan Mountain) demanded the removal of the Kaga (presently Ishikawa Pref.) governor, FUJIWARA no Morotaka (Hakusan Incident).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when Goshirakawa returned to Kyoto on March 22, the daishu (Buddhist monks) at the Sanmon (Enryaku-ji Temple, Hieizan Mountain) demanded the removal of the Kaga (presently Ishikawa Pref.) governor, FUJIWARA no Morotaka (Hakusan Incident).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when Goshirakawa returned to Kyoto on April 29, the daishu (Buddhist monks) at the Sanmon (Enryaku-ji Temple, Hieizan Mountain) demanded the removal of the Kaga (presently Ishikawa Pref.) governor, FUJIWARA no Morotaka (Hakusan Incident).</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>発端は西光の子・師高が加賀守となり、目代・師経が白山の末寺・宇河寺を焼いたことに激怒した白山の僧侶が山門に訴えたことだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The cause was that monks at Hakusan appealed to the Sanmon because Morotaka, Saiko&apos;s child, became governor of Kaga and the Mokudai (substitute for the governor who lives in the province and does the actual duties) Morotsune burned Ukawa-ji Temple, a branch temple of Hakusan,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The cause was that monks at Hakusan appealed to the Sanmon because Morotaka, Saiko&apos;s child, became governor of Kaga and the Mokudai (substitute for the governor who lives in the province and performs actual duties) Morotsune burned down Ukawa-ji Temple, a branch temple of Hakusan,</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The cause was that monks at Hakusan appealed to the Sanmon because Morotaka, Saiko&apos;s child, became governor of Kaga Province and the Mokudai (substitute for the governor who lives in the province and performs actual duties) Morotsune burned down Ukawa-ji Temple, a branch temple of Hakusan,</e>
<cmt>Province補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>国衙の目代と現地の寺社が、寺領荘園の所務を巡り紛争を起こすことは各地で頻発していたが、この事件では白山が山門の末寺で、国司が院近臣・西光の子であることから、中央に波及して山門と院勢力の全面衝突に発展した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was common for the Mokudai of the governor&apos;s office and temples/shrines at the province to fight over various aspects regarding shoen (private estates) owned by temples, but this incident sent ripples into the central government and caused a full confrontation between the Sanmon and cloistered government group because Hakusan was a branch temple of the Sanmon and the governor was the child of Saiko, a close aide of the cloistered government,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was common for the Mokudai of the governor&apos;s office and temples/shrines at the province to fight over various aspects regarding shoen (private estates) owned by temples, but this incident sent ripples into the central government and caused a full confrontation between the Sanmon and the cloistered government group because Hakusan was a branch temple of the Sanmon and the governor was a child of Saiko, a close aide of the cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was common for the Mokudai of the governor&apos;s office and temples/shrines at the province to fight over various aspects regarding shoen (private estates) owned by temples, but this incident sent ripples into the central government and caused a full confrontation between the Sanmon and the cloistered government group because Hakusan was a branch temple of the Sanmon and the governor was a child of Saiko, a close aide of the cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>後白河は目代・師経を備後国に流罪にすることで事態を収拾しようとしたが、大衆は納得せず4月12日に神輿を持ち出して内裏に向かう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goshirakawa tried to settle the situation by exiling the Mokudai, Morotsune, to Bingo no kuni (present eastern half of Hiroshima prefecture), but the monks were not satisfied and brought out a mikoshi (portable shrine) and headed towards the inner Imperial Court on April 12.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goshirakawa tried to settle the situation by exiling the Mokudai, Morotsune, to Bingo no kuni (present eastern half of Hiroshima prefecture), but the monks were not satisfied and brought out a mikoshi (portable shrine) and headed towards the inner Imperial Court on April 12.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goshirakawa tried to settle the situation by exiling the Mokudai, Morotsune, to Bingo Province (present eastern half of Hiroshima prefecture), but the monks were not satisfied and brought out a mikoshi (portable shrine) and headed towards the inner Imperial Court on May 18.</e>
<cmt>no kuni削除、Provinceに訂正しました。新暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>後白河は強硬策をとり官兵を派遣するが、警備にあたった重盛の兵と大衆の間で衝突が起こり、矢が神輿に当たったことから事態はさらに悪化する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goshirakawa took strong measures and sent court troops, but there was a confrontation between the guards in Shigemori&apos;s troops and the monks, and the situation worsens because an arrow hit the mikoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goshirakawa took strong measures and sent court troops, but there was a confrontation between Shigemori&apos;s troops, who were sent to maintain security, and the monks, and the situation worsened after an arrow hit the mikoshi.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goshirakawa took strong measures and sent court troops, but there was a confrontation between Shigemori&apos;s troops, who were sent to maintain security, and the monks, and the situation worsened after an arrow hit the mikoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>4月20日、師高の尾張国への配流、神輿に矢を射た重盛の家人の拘禁が決定、大衆の要求を全面的に受諾することで事件は決着する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 20, the incident came to a closure by agreeing to all of the demands of the monks with Morotaka exiled to Owari no Kuni (present western Aichi Prefecture) and the householder of Shigemori who fired an arrow into the mikoshi detained.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 20, the incident came to a finishdue to agreement to all of the demands of the monks, with Morotaka exiled to Owari no Kuni (present western Aichi Prefecture) and Shigemori&apos;s soldier who fired the arrow into the mikoshi detained.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 26, the incident came to a finish due to agreement to all of the demands of the monks, with Morotaka exiled to Owari Province (present western Aichi Prefecture) and Shigemori&apos;s soldier who fired the arrow into the mikoshi detained.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。スペース補足。no kuni削除、Provinceに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>山門攻撃準備</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Preparations to attack the Sanmon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Preparations to attack the Sanmon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Preparations to attack the Sanmon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>直後の4月28日、「太郎焼亡」と称される大火が発生、大極殿および関白松殿基房以下13人の公卿の邸宅が焼失して、人々に衝撃を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Immediately after this on April 28, an extensive fire called &quot;Taro Shobo&quot; broke out and shocked the people when it burned the Daigoku-den and housing complexes of 13 aristocrats including Motofusa MATSUDONO(also FUJIWARA) (chief adviser to the Emperor) burned down.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon after, on April 28, an extensive fire referred to as &quot;Taro Shobo&quot; broke out and shocked the people as it burned down the Daigoku-den and housing complexes of 13 aristocrats including Motofusa MATSUDONO (chief adviser to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon after, on June 3, an extensive fire referred to as &apos;Taro Shobo&apos; broke out and shocked the people as it burned down the Daigoku-den Palace and housing complexes of 13 aristocrats including Motofusa MATSUDONO (chief adviser to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。Palace 補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>このような中で、後白河は突如として先の事件を蒸し返し、天台座主・明雲を解任、所領を没官すると5月22日に伊豆国へ配流した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this situation, Goshirakawa suddenly brought up the former incident and dismissed the Tendai-zasu (chief Tendai abbot) Myoun and took away his property, exiling him to Izu no kuni on May 22.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this situation, Goshirakawa suddenly brought up the former incident and dismissed the Tendai-zasu (chief Tendai abbot) Myoun, took away his property, and exiled him to Izu no kuni on May 22.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this situation, Goshirakawa suddenly brought up the former incident and dismissed Myoun of Tendai-zasu (head priest of the Tendai sect), took away his property, and exiled him to Izu Province on June 27.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。no kuni削除、Provinceに訂正しました。天台座主・明雲→Myoun of Tendai-zasu (head priest of the Tendai sect)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>西光が師高の流罪を嘆き、強訴の張本人が明雲であるとして処罰を訴えたことが原因であったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that this was caused by Saiko, saddened by the exile of Morotaka, blaming Myoun as the leader of the demonstrations and demanding punishment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that this was caused by Saiko, who saddened by the exile of Morotaka, blamed Myoun as the leader of the demonstrations and demanded punishment.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that this was caused by Saiko, who saddened by the exile of Morotaka, blamed Myoun as the leader of the demonstrations and demanded punishment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>座主配流に反発する大衆が明雲の身柄を奪回したため、後白河は平清盛を呼び出し山門攻撃を命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the monks rebelled against the exile of their chief and rescued him, Goshirakawa ordered TAIRA no Kiyomori to attack the Sanmon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the monks rebelled against the exile of their chief and rescued him, Goshirakawa ordered TAIRA no Kiyomori to attack the Sanmon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the monks rebelled against the exile of their chief and rescued him, Goshirakawa ordered TAIRA no Kiyomori to attack the Sanmon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>清盛は攻撃に消極的だったが後白河に押し切られる形となり、近江国・美濃国・越前国の武士も動員されて攻撃開始は目前に迫った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomori was not in favor of attacking, but was pressured by Goshirakawa and samurai from Omi-no-kuni (present Shiga Prefecture), Mino-no-kuni (present southern Gifu Prefecture) and Echizen-no-kuni (present northern part of Fukui Prefecture) were readied in preparation for the start of the attack.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomori was not in favor of attacking, but was pressured by Goshirakawa, and so samurai from Omi-no-kuni (present Shiga Prefecture), Mino-no-kuni (present southern Gifu Prefecture) and Echizen-no-kuni (present northern part of Fukui Prefecture) were readied in preparation for an attack.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomori was not in favor of attacking, but was pressured by Goshirakawa, and so samurai from Omi Province (present Shiga Prefecture), Mino Province (present southern Gifu Prefecture) and Echizen Province (present northern part of Fukui Prefecture) were readied in preparation for an attack.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除。no kuni削除、Provinceに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>陰謀発覚</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Discovery of the plot</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Discovery of the plot</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Discovery of the plot</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>出撃直前の6月1日、清盛の西八条邸を多田行綱が訪れて平氏打倒の謀議を密告した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Just before the attack, Yukitsuna TADA visited Kiyomori&apos;s house at Nishi-Hachijo and informed him about the plan to destroy the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Just before the attack, Yukitsuna TADA visited Kiyomori&apos;s house at Nishi-Hachijo and informed him about the plan to destroy the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Just before the attack, Yukitsuna TADA visited Kiyomori&apos;s house at Nishi-Hachijo and informed him about the plan to destroy the Taira clan on July 5.</e>
<cmt>新暦を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>『愚管抄』によれば、後白河が静賢の鹿ケ谷山荘に御幸した際、藤原成親・西光・俊寛が集まり平氏打倒の計画が話し合われ、行綱が呼ばれて旗揚げの白旗用として宇治布30反が与えられたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the &quot;Gukansho&quot;, when Goshirakawa made an Imperial visit to Jauken&apos;s Shishigatani mountain retreat, FUJIWARA no Narichika, Saiko and Shunkan met together to talk about plans to destroy the Taira clan and Yukitsuna was called for and given 30 rolls of Uji fabric to make white flags for the launch.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Gukansho&quot;, when Goshirakawa made a visit to Joken&apos;s Shishigatani mountain retreat, FUJIWARA no Narichika, Saiko and Shunkan met together to talk about plans to destroy the Taira clan and Yukitsuna was called and given 30 rolls of Uji fabric to make white flags for the launch.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Gukansho,&quot; when Goshirakawa made a visit to Joken&apos;s Shishigatani mountain retreat, FUJIWARA no Narichika, Saiko and Shunkan met together to talk about plans to destroy the Taira clan and Yukitsuna was called and given 30 rolls of Uji fabric to make white flags for the launch.</e>
<cmt>,の位置訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>また『平家物語』によれば、成親が立ち上がって瓶子（へいじ）が倒れ、後白河が「あれはいかに」と問うと成親が「平氏（瓶子）たはれ候ぬ」と答え、俊寛がそれをどうするか尋ねると西光が「頸をとるにしかず」と瓶子の首を折り割ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the &quot;Heike Monogatari (Historic Romance of Taira Family)&quot;, sake bottle (&quot;heiji&quot;) fell over when Narichika stood up and when Goshirakawa asked, &quot;what was that?&quot;, Narichika answered, &quot;The Heishi (heiji) toopleed&quot;, and when Shunkan asked what to do with it, Saiko said &quot;Must take its neck (kill)&quot; and broke the neck of the bottle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Heike Monogatari (The Historic Romance of Taira Family)&quot;, a sake bottle (a &quot;heiji&quot;) fell over when Narichika stood up and when Goshirakawa asked, &quot;what was that?&quot;, Narichika answered, &quot;The sake bottle (heiji) fell over&quot;, and when Shunkan asked what to do with it, Saiko said &quot;we must take its neck (kill)&quot; and broke the neck of the bottle.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The Historic Romance of Taira Family), a sake bottle (called &quot;heiji&quot;, the same pronunciation as &quot;the Taira clan&quot; in Japanese) fell over when Narichika stood up and when Goshirakawa asked, &apos;what was that?&apos; Narichika answered, &apos;the sake bottle (heiji) fell over,&apos; and when Shunkan asked what to do with it, Saiko said &apos;we must take its neck (kill)&apos; and broke the neck of the bottle.</e>
<cmt>括弧書きを&quot;の外へ訂正しました。(called &quot;heiji&quot;, the same pronunciation as &quot;the Taira clan&quot; in Japanese)と訂正しました。スペース削除。,削除。the小文字にしました。原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="27">
<j>清盛は直ちに西光を呼び出して拷問にかけ、全てを自供させると首を刎ねた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomori immediately sent for Saiko and when he admitted to all of the charges under torture, he was beheaded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomori immediately sent for Saiko and when he admitted to all of the charges under torture, he was beheaded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomori immediately sent for Saiko and when he admitted to all of the charges under torture, he was beheaded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>同じく呼び出された成親も拘束された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Narichika was also sent for and detained.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Narichika was also sent for and detained.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Narichika was also sent for and detained.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>成親の妹を妻にしていた重盛は、命だけは助かるようにすると成親を励ましたという（『愚管抄』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Shigemori, who had Narichika&apos;s younger sister as a wife, encouraged Narichika by promising to save his life (&quot;Gukansho&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Shigemori, whose wife was Narichika&apos;s younger sister, encouraged Narichika by promising to save his life (&quot;Gukansho&quot;).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Shigemori, whose wife was Narichika&apos;s younger sister, encouraged Narichika by promising to save his life (&quot;Gukansho&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>西坂本まで下っていた山門の大衆はこの動きを知ると、清盛に使者を送り敵を討ったことへの感謝を述べて山へ戻っていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the monks of the Sanmon, who had descended down to Nishi-Sakamoto, became aware of this, they set a messenger to Kiyomori to thank him for killing the enemy and returned to their mountain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the monks of the Sanmon, who had descended to Nishi-Sakamoto, became aware of this, they sent a messenger to Kiyomori to thank him for killing their enemy and returned to their mountain.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the monks of the Sanmon, who had descended to Nishi-Sakamoto, became aware of this, they sent a messenger to Kiyomori to thank him for killing their enemy and returned to their mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>4日、俊寛・基仲・中原基兼・惟宗信房・平資行・平康頼など参加者が一網打尽にされ、5日、明雲が配流を解かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the 4th,participants such as Shunkan, Motonaka, NAKAHARA no Motokane, Nobufusa KOREMUNE, TAIRA no Sukeuki and TAIRA no Yasuyori were all captured and on the 5th, Myoun was released from exile.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the 4th, participants such as Shunkan, Motonaka, NAKAHARA no Motokane, Nobufusa KOREMUNE, TAIRA no Sukeuki and TAIRA no Yasuyori were all captured, and on the 5th, Myoun was released from exile.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 8, participants such as Shunkan, Motonaka, NAKAHARA no Motokane, Nobufusa KOREMUNE, TAIRA no Sukeyuki and TAIRA no Yasuyori were all captured, and on July 9, Myoun was released from exile.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。平資行→TAIRA no Sukeyuki</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>9日、尾張に流されていた師高が、清盛の家人の襲撃を受けて惨殺、成親は一旦は助命されて備前国に配流されるが、食物を与えられず殺害されてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the 9th, Morotaka, who was exiled to Owari, was attacked by householders of Kiyomori and brutally killed, and although Narichika was saved and exiled to Bizen no kuni, he was killed by not being given any food.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the 9th, Morotaka, who has been exiled to Owari, was attacked by followers of Kiyomori and brutally killed, and although Narichika was saved and exiled to Bizen no kuni, he was starved to death.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 13, Morotaka, who has been exiled to Owari, was attacked by followers of Kiyomori and brutally killed, and although Narichika was saved and exiled to Bizen Province, he was starved to death.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。 no kuni削除、Province補足。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Effects</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Effects</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Effects</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="33">
<j>謀議が事実であったかどうかは当時でも疑問視する向きが多く、西光と成親が清盛の呼び出しに簡単に応じていることから、平氏側（清盛）が院近臣勢力を潰すため、もしくは山門との衝突を回避するためにでっち上げた疑獄事件の可能性もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whether there actually were any secret plans was questioned even at that plan and since Saiko and Narichika readily attended to Kiyomori&apos;s call, there is a possibility that it was a made-up plot for the Taira clan (Kiyomori) to destroy close aides of the cloistered government or evade confrontation with the Sanmon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whether there actually were any secret plans was questioned even at that point and since Saiko and Narichika readily attended to Kiyomori&apos;s call, there is a possibility that it was a plot by the Taira clan (Kiyomori) to destroy close aides of the cloistered government or evade confrontation with the Sanmon.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whether there in fact were any secret plans was questioned even at that point and since Saiko and Narichika readily attended to Kiyomori&apos;s call, there is a possibility that it was a plot by the Taira clan (Kiyomori) to destroy close aides of the cloistered government or evade confrontation with the Sanmon.</e>
<cmt>actually -&gt; &quot;in fact&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>清盛が狙いをつけたのは院近臣の中核である西光・成親で、後白河には手を下さず福原に引き上げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomori targeted the core aides of the cloistered government, Saiko and Narichika, and did not penalize Goshirakawa but sent him to Fukuhara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomori targeted the core aides of the cloistered government, Saiko and Narichika, and did not penalize Goshirakawa, instead sending him to Fukuhara.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomori targeted the core aides of the cloistered government, Saiko and Narichika, and did not penalize Goshirakawa, instead sending him to Fukuhara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>後白河は「こはされば何事ぞや、御とかあるべしとも思し召さず」と白を切ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goshirakawa was said to completely feign ignorance and said &quot;What it all this? I don&apos;t think I have anything to be accused of&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goshirakawa was said to feign complete ignorance and said &quot;What it all this? I don&apos;t think I have anything to be accused of&quot;.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goshirakawa was said to feign complete ignorance and said &apos;what it all this? I don&apos;t think I have anything to be accused of.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="36">
<j>重盛は、白山事件で家人が矢を神輿に当てる失態を犯したのに加え、妻の兄が配流されて助命を求めたにも関わらず殺害されたことで面目を失い、6月5日に左大将を辞任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigemori quit the position of Sadaisho (left palace guards) on June 5 because he had lost face when his householder hit the mikoshi with an arrow during the Hakusan Incident and his wife&apos;s elder brother was killed during exile even after Shigemori asked for his life to be spared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigemori quit the position of Sadaisho (head of the left palace guards) on June 5 because he had lost face when his soldier hit the mikoshi with an arrow during the Hakusan Incident and his wife&apos;s elder brother was killed during exile even after Shigemori asked for his life to be spared.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigemori quit the position of Sadaisho (head of the left palace guards) on July 9 because he had lost face when his soldier hit the mikoshi with an arrow during the Hakusan Incident and his wife&apos;s elder brother was killed during exile even after Shigemori asked for his life to be spared.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>この結果、宗盛が清盛の後継者の地位を確立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, the position of Munemori as Kiyomori&apos;s successor became established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Munemori established his position as Kiyomori&apos;s successor.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Munemori established his position as Kiyomori&apos;s successor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>清盛は山門との衝突を回避し、反平氏の動きを見せていた院近臣の排除に成功したが、清盛と後白河の関係は取り返しのつかないものとなり治承三年の政変（1179年）へとつながっていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomori was able to prevent a confrontation with the Sanmon and eliminate close aide of the cloistered government that were against the Taira clan, but the relationship between Kiyomori and Goshirakawa was irreversibly damaged and this led to the Jisho-sannen-no-seihen (political change of 1179).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomori was able to prevent a confrontation with the Sanmon and eliminate close aides of the cloistered government who were against the Taira clan, but the relationship between Kiyomori and Goshirakawa was irreversibly damaged and this led to the Jisho-sannen-no-seihen (political change of 1179).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomori was able to prevent a confrontation with the Sanmon and eliminate close aides of the cloistered government who were against the Taira clan, but the relationship between Kiyomori and Goshirakawa was irreversibly damaged and this led to the &quot;Jisho sannen no seihen&quot; (Coup of the Third Year of Jisho, 1179).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;補足。ハイフン削除、スペース補足。治承三年の政変→Coup of the Third Year of Jisho　補足。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>史料</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Historical references</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historical references</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historical references</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="39">
<j>『愚管抄』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Gukansho&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Gukansho&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Gukansho&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), でここ(id:9565), Non-stop24(id:10471), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), 怪蘇(id:45514), 味っ子(id:17086), トホホ川(id:50502), Andee(id:20421), Yas(id:739), Greenishpurplr(id:39890), 小者(id:172526), Kamitani(id:30757), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>