<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>エルトゥールル号遭難事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The distress of Ertuğrul Fırkateyni</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The distress of Frigate Ertuğrul Fırkateyni</e>
<cmt>Frigateを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The distress of Frigate Ertuğrul Fırkateyni</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>エルトゥールル号遭難事件（エルトゥールルごうそうなんじけん）とは、1890年（明治23年）9月16日夜半、オスマン帝国（現在のトルコ）の軍艦エルトゥールル号（Ertuğrul Fırkateyni）が、和歌山県串本町沖、紀伊大島の樫野埼灯台東方海上で遭難した事件。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The distress of Ertuğrul was a disaster that Ertuğrul, a sailing frigate of the Ottoman Navy met, off the east coast of Kashinozaki Lighthouse in Kii-Oshima Island, Kushimoto-cho Town, Wakayama prefecture, in the midnight of September 16, 1890.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The distress of Frigate Ertuğrul was a shipwreck that Ertuğrul, a sailing frigate of the Ottoman Navy, suffered off the east of Kashinozaki Lighthouse in Kii-Oshima Island, Kushimoto-cho Town, Wakayama prefecture, on the middle of the night of September 16, 1890.</e>
<cmt>commaの位置を直し、若干語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The distress of Frigate Ertuğrul was a shipwreck that Ertuğrul, a sailing frigate of the Ottoman Navy, suffered off the east of Kashinozaki Lighthouse in Kii-Oshima Island, Kushimoto-cho Town, Wakayama prefecture, on the middle of the night of September 16, 1890.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>この事件は、日本とトルコの友好関係の起点として記憶されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This disaster is being remembered as a starting point of the friendship between Japan and Turkey.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This disaster is remembered as a starting point of the friendship between Japan and Turkey.</e>
<cmt>時制を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This disaster is remembered as a starting point of the friendship between Japan and Turkey.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>現在、和歌山県串本町の樫野崎灯台そばには、エルトゥールル号遭難慰霊碑およびトルコ記念館が立つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, near the Kashiwazaki Lighthouse in the town of Kushimoto, Wakayama Prefectuere, they have Frigate Ertuğrul Memorial and the Turkish Museum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, near the Kashiwazaki Lighthouse in the town of Kushimoto-cho, Wakayama Prefectuere, the Frigate Ertuğrul Memorial and the Turkish Museum stand.</e>
<cmt>Kushimoto-choとし、語を若干変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, near the Kashiwazaki Lighthouse in the town of Kushimoto-cho, Wakayama Prefectuere, the Frigate Ertuğrul Memorial and the Turkish Museum stand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また、町と在日本トルコ大使館の共催による慰霊祭も5年ごとに行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And, every five year, the town residents and the Embassy of Turkey in Japan jointly hold a memorial ceremony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And, every five year residents of the town and the Embassy of Turkey in Japan jointly hold a memorial ceremony.</e>
<cmt>若干語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And, every five year residents of the town and the Embassy of Turkey in Japan jointly hold a memorial ceremony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>事件の経過</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The process of the disaster</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Progress of the disaster</e>
<cmt>語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Progress of the disaster</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>木造フリゲート艦エルトゥールル号（1864年建造、全長76m）は、1887年に行われた日本の皇族、小松宮彰仁親王夫妻のイスタンブル訪問に応えることを目的に、訓練不足のオスマン帝国海軍の練習航海を兼ねて日本へ派遣されることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To respond to Istanbul visit of 1887 by Imperial Prince and Princess Komatsunomiya Akihito, the Imperial family of Japan, Ertuğrul, the wooden frigate (built in 1864, total length, 76m) was dispatched to Japan, also with a aim of training voyage of the the Ottoman Empire Navy, which had not been well-trained.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to respond to the visit of the Imperial Prince Komatsunomiya Akihito and Princess from the Imperial family of Japan in 1887, the dispatch of the Ertuğrul, a wooden frigate (built in 1864 with its total length of 76m), to Japan was decided, also aiming to make a training voyage of the the Ottoman Empire Navy which lacked enough training.</e>
<cmt>語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response to the visit to Istanbul by Imperial Prince Komatsunomiya Akihito and his wife from the Imperial family of Japan in 1887, it was decided that the Ertuğrul, a wooden frigate (built in 1864 with a total length of 76 m) would be dispatched, to Japan; this would also serve as a training voyage for the Ottoman Empire Navy, which lacked sufficient training at that time.</e>
<cmt>the が重複していたので一つ削除しました。イスタンブル訪問の「イスタンブル」の訳抜けに対応しました。visit of→visit to Istanbul by</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>1889年7月、イスタンブルを出港。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July, 1889, she set sail from Istanbul.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 1889, she set sail from Istanbul.</e>
<cmt>Commaを減らしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July 1889, she set sail from Istanbul.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>数々の困難に遭いながらも、航海の途上に立ち寄ったイスラム教国で熱烈な歓迎を受けつつ、11ヶ月をかけて翌1890年6月ようやく日本に到着した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While encountering many difficulties, receiving enthusiastic welcome in Islamic countries where they stopped by on their way, finally they arrived Japan the next year, in June 1890, taking 11 months.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having received enthusiastic welcome in Islamic countries where she stopped by on her way while encountering many difficulties, finally she arrived in Japan the next year, in June 1890; the voyage took 11 months.</e>
<cmt>一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Despite encountering many difficulties on her journey, she received an enthusiastic welcome in the Islamic countries she stopped off at on her way home; she finally arrived back in Japan the next year in June 1890, with the voyage having taken 11 months.</e>
<cmt>一部書き換えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>横浜港に入港したエルトゥールル号の司令官オスマン・パシャを特使とする一行は、6月13日に皇帝親書を明治天皇に奉呈し、オスマン帝国最初の親善訪日使節団として歓迎を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After arriving at Yokohama Port, the party, including Ambassodar Osman Pasha, who was also a commander of Ertuğrul, presented a letter from the Sultan to the Emperor Meiji.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After arriving at Yokohama Port, the party led by a special envoy Osman Pasha, who was also a commander of Ertuğrul, presented a letter from the Sultan to the Emperor Meiji on June 13 and was welcomed as the first goodwill mission to Japan from the Ottoman Empire.</e>
<cmt>日付が抜けていたので補いました。若干語を変えました。本文と次の文を原文通りまとめ一文としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After arriving at Yokohama Port, the party led by a special envoy Osman Pasha, who was also a commander of Ertuğrul, presented a letter from the Sultan to the Emperor Meiji on June 13 and was welcomed as the first goodwill mission to Japan from the Ottoman Empire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>しかし、エルトゥールル号は出港以来蓄積した艦の老朽や物資・資金不足は限界に達していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since her departure, Ertuğrul almost had reached limit due to piled-up deterioration of the ship, commodity shortage and financial problems.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the damage to the hull and commodity and financial shortage of the Ertuğrul had piled up so much since her departure that it was now nearly impossible for her to sail back.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the damage to the hull and commodity and financial shortage of the Ertuğrul had piled up so much since her departure that it was now nearly impossible for her to sail back.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>多くの乗員がコレラに見舞われたため、9月になってようやく横浜出港の目処をつけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since many crews members had been hit by cholera, in September, they finally met a chance to sail out of Yokohama.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since many crews had caught cholera, it was in September that they finally found a chance to sail out of Yokohama Port.</e>
<cmt>語と表現を若干変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since many crews had caught cholera, it was in September that they finally found a chance to sail out of Yokohama Port.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>遠洋航海に耐えない老朽ぶりをみた日本側は台風の時期をやり過ごすようにと勧めるた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan thought the ship was too old to endure long voyage and recommended to delay departure during typhoon season.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese thought the ship was too old to endure a long voyage and recommended delaying departure until the typhoon season ended.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese thought the ship was too old to endure a long voyage and recommended delaying departure until the typhoon season ended.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>だが制止を振り切って帰路についた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, they forcibly departed homeward.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, they forcibly departed homeward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, they forcibly departed homeward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>このように無理を押してエルトゥールル号が派遣された裏には、インド・東南アジアのムスリム（イスラム教徒）にイスラム教の盟主オスマン帝国の国力を誇示したい皇帝アブデュルハミト2世の意志が働いていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Behind this forced dispatch, Emperor Abdülhamid II had an intention to show off power of the Ottoman Empire, the leader of Isram, to Muslims in India and Southeast Asian countries.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Behind this irrational dispatch, there was an intention of the Sultan Abdülhamid II to show off the power of the Ottoman Empire, the leader of Muslim countries, to Muslims in India and Southeast Asian countries.</e>
<cmt>スペルミスを直し、表現と語を若干変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Behind this irrational dispatch, there was an intention of the Sultan Abdülhamid II to show off the power of the Ottoman Empire, the leader of Muslim countries, to Muslims in India and Southeast Asian countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>出港を強行したのも日本に留まりつづけることでオスマン帝国海軍の弱体化ぶりが喧伝されてしまうことを恐れたのだと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He forced to sail out becuuse he seemed to have been afraid of reputation for the weakness of the Ottoman Empire Navy.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the return sail was carried out because he was afraid that the reputation of the weakened Ottoman Empire Navy would spread.</e>
<cmt>スペルミスを修正、不要な半角スペースを削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the return sail was carried out because he was afraid that the reputation of the weakened Ottoman Empire Navy would spread.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>遭難事件はその帰途に起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The disaster occurred on their way home.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The disaster occurred on their way home.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The disaster occurred on their way home.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>1890年（明治23年）9月16日夜半、エルトゥールル号は折からの台風による強風にあおられ、紀伊大島の樫野崎に連なる岩礁に激突した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 16, 1890, at midnight, Ertuğrul was pushed by the strong wind by typhoon and hit the rocks at Kashinozaki, Kii-Oshima Island.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the middle of the night on September 16, 1890, the Ertuğrul was pushed by a strong wind in a typhoon and hit the rocks at Kashinozaki, Kii-Oshima Island.</e>
<cmt>夜半は真夜中とするべきではないと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the middle of the night on September 16, 1890, the Ertuğrul was pushed by a strong wind in a typhoon and hit the rocks at Kashinozaki, Kii-Oshima Island.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>座礁したエルトゥールル号は機関部に浸水して水蒸気爆発を起こし、沈没した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ertuğrul was stranded, with flooded engine department, she was exploded and sunk due to a vapor explosion.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ertuğrul was stranded and water broke through into the engine room, which caused a vapor explosion and finally she sank.</e>
<cmt>語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ertuğrul was stranded and water broke through into the engine room, which caused a vapor explosion and finally she sank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これにより、司令官オスマン・パシャをはじめとする587名が死亡または行方不明になる大惨事となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This led a catastrophic incident that 587 people including the commander Osman Pasha missed, or lost their lives.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This led to a catastrophic incident that 587 people including the commander Osman Pasha missed or lost.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This led to a catastrophic incident that 587 people including the commander Osman Pasha missed or lost.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>このとき、樫野埼灯台下に流れ着いた生存者は、数十メートルの断崖を這い登って灯台に遭難を知らせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, the survivors, who were washed ashore near the Kashinozaki Lighthouse, scrambled up several dozen meters cliff and let the lighthouse know the disaster.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, the survivors, who were washed ashore near the Kashinozaki Lighthouse, scrambled up the cliff several dozen meters high and let the lighthouse know the disaster.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, the survivors, who were washed ashore near the Kashinozaki Lighthouse, scrambled up the cliff several dozen meters high and let the lighthouse know the disaster.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>灯台守の通報を受けた紀伊大島（現在の串本町）樫野の住民たちは、総出で救助と生存者の介抱に当たった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Receiving information from the lighthouse keeper, all the people in Kii-Oshima-mura village(now Kushimoto-cho Town)rescued and cared for the survivors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Receiving information from the lighthouse keeper, all the people in Kii-Oshima-mura village(now Kushimoto-cho Town)rescued and cared for the survivors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Receiving information from the lighthouse keeper, all the people in Kii-Oshima-mura village(now Kushimoto-cho Town)rescued and cared for the survivors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>この時、台風により出漁できず食料の蓄えもわずかだったにもかかわらず、住民は、浴衣などの衣類、卵やサツマイモ、それに非常用のニワトリすら供出するなど、献身的に生存者たちの回復に努めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Despite few food reserves since typhoon had stopped people from fishing, they delivered clothes such as yukata, and foods such as eggs, potatoes and even chickens for emergency food, and dedicated themselves to care for the survivors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Despite few food reserves since the typhoon had stopped people from fishing, they provided clothes such as yukata, and eggs, potatoes and even chickens they had kept for an emergency, and dedicated themselves to care for the survivors.</e>
<cmt>語を少し補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Despite few food reserves since the typhoon had stopped people from fishing, they provided clothes such as yukata, and eggs, potatoes and even chickens they had kept for an emergency, and dedicated themselves to care for the survivors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>この結果、樫野の寺、学校、灯台に収容された69名が救出され生還することができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, 69 people taken to the Kasino Temple, school, and the lighthouse were rescued alive.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, 69 people taken to a temple, a school and the lighthouse in Kashino were rescued alive.</e>
<cmt>「樫野の寺」は固有名詞ではないと解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, 69 people taken to a temple, a school and the lighthouse in Kashino were rescued alive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="23">
<j>遭難の翌朝、事件は樫野の区長から大島村長の沖周（おきしゅう）に伝えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The next day of the disaster, the incident was informed to Shu OKI, a Oshima village mayor via a Kashino ward head.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The next day of the disaster, Shu OKI, the Oshima village mayor, was informed of the incident via the head of the Kashino ward.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The next day of the disaster, Shu OKI, the Oshima village mayor, was informed of the incident via the head of the Kashino ward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>沖は神戸港の外国領事館に援助を求めて生存者を神戸市の病院に搬送させるよう手配するとともに、県を通じて日本政府に通報した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oki asked help to the foreign consulate in Kobe port and arranged the survivors transport to hospitals in Kobe City while reporting to the government of Japan via prefecture.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処　外国領事館の意味不明です。（オスマントルコ領事館のことでしょうか？）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oki asked help of foreign consulates in Kobe Port and arranged to transport the survivors to the hospital in Kobe City while reporting to the Japanese government via a prefectural agency.</e>
<cmt>外国領事館はオスマントルコ領事館の可能性がありますが確認できないため、そのまま外国領事館と訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oki asked help of foreign consulates in Kobe Port and arranged to transport the survivors to the hospital in Kobe City while reporting to the Japanese government via a prefectural agency.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>知らせを聞いた明治天皇はこの遭難に大いに心を痛め、政府として可能な限りの援助を行うよう指示したと伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having received the news, the Emperor Meiji was deeply troubled and directed the government to help as much as possible, as they say.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having received the news, the Emperor Meiji was deeply troubled and directed the government to help as much as possible, as they say.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having received the news, the Emperor Meiji was deeply troubled and directed the government to help as much as possible, as they say.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>こうして遭難者に対する支援が政府をあげて行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, together with the government, the support to the victims was operated.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, support was offered to the victims under the leadership of the government.</e>
<cmt>表現を少し変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, support was offered to the victims under the leadership of the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>10月5日に東京の品川湾から出航した大日本帝国海軍の「比叡 (コルベット)」「金剛 (コルベット)」2隻により、生存者たちは翌1891年（明治24年）1月2日にオスマン帝国の首都イスタンブルに送り届けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two corvettes, &apos;Hiei&apos; and &apos;Konogo&apos; of the Imperial Japanese Navy, departed from Tokyo Shinagawa bay on October 5, sent the survivors back to Istanbul, the capital city of the Ottoman Empire next year, on January 2, 1891.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The survivors were sent back by two corvettes of the Imperial Japanese Navy, &apos;Hiei&apos; and &apos;Konogo,&apos; which had departed from Shinagawa Bay in Tokyo on October 5, arriving in Istanbul, the capital of the Ottoman Empire, on January 2 of the next year, 1891.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正し、分かりやすくするため表現を変え、語を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The survivors were sent back by two corvettes of the Imperial Japanese Navy, &apos;Hiei&apos; and &apos;Konogo,&apos; which had departed from Shinagawa Bay in Tokyo on October 5, arriving in Istanbul, the capital of the Ottoman Empire, on January 2 of the next year, 1891.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="28">
<j>エルトゥールル号の遭難はオスマン帝国の国内に大きな衝撃を呼んだが、専制君主アブデュルハミト2世のもとでは人災としての側面は覆い隠され、天災による殉難と位置付けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The distress of the Ertuğrul impacted people in the Ottoman Empire, however, under Abdul Hamid II, the absolute monarch, the incident was regarded as martyrdom due to natural disaster instead of man-made calamity.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The distress of the Ertuğrul made a great impact on people in the Ottoman Empire; however, under the rule of the absolute monarch Abdülhamid II, the incident was regarded as martyrdom due to a natural disaster and the aspect as a man-made calamity was concealed.</e>
<cmt>文法の誤りを修正し、表現を変え、訳漏れ部を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The distress of the Ertuğrul made a great impact on people in the Ottoman Empire; however, under the rule of the absolute monarch Abdülhamid II, the incident was regarded as martyrdom due to a natural disaster and the aspect as a man-made calamity was concealed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>新聞で大きく報道されるとともに、遺族への弔慰金が集められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the newspaper&apos;s coverage, condolence money for the families of the victims were collected.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The news was widely reported in newspapers, and condolence money for the families of the victims was collected.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正し、原文に近い意味にするため修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The news was widely reported in newspapers, and condolence money for the families of the victims was collected.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>またこのとき、新聞を通じて大島村民による救助活動や日本政府の尽力が伝えられ、当時のトルコの人々は遠い異国である日本と日本人に対して好印象を抱いたといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the newspaper also reported the rescue operation by Oshima village people and dedications by the government of Japan, Turkish people had good impression on a far foreign country Japan, and Japanese people, as they say.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the newspapers also reported the rescue operation by the people of Oshima Village and the dedication of the Japanese government, Turkish people had a good impression on a far foreign country Japan and Japanese people, as they say.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the newspapers also reported the rescue operation by the people of Oshima Village and the dedication of the Japanese government, Turkish people had a good impression on a far foreign country Japan and Japanese people, as they say.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="31">
<j>エルトゥールル号の残骸は、現在も大島沖の海底に眠っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The remains of the Ertuğrul still lie on the bottom of the sea, off the coast of Oshima.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The remains of the Ertuğrul still lie on the bottom of the sea off Oshima Island.</e>
<cmt>省ける部分を省略しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The remains of the Ertuğrul still lie on the bottom of the sea off Oshima Island.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>2007年から、トルコを中心とする数カ国からなる水中考古学の調査団は海中のエルトゥールル号の調査を進めており、海底からの遺品引き揚げを進めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since 2007, the underwater archaeology research group consists of Turkey and several countries has been investigating the Ertuğrul under the water, and they have salvaged remains from seabed. &quot;Kii Minpo news&quot; January 27, 2007.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since 2007, the multinational underwater archaeological research group, consisting of Turkey as a leading country and several countries, has been investigating the Ertuğrul in the water and working on the salvage of her remains from the seabed (&quot;Kii Minpo news,&quot; January 27, 2007).</e>
<cmt>文法の誤り等直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since 2007, the multinational underwater archaeological research group, consisting of Turkey as a leading country and several countries, has been investigating the Ertuğrul in the water and working on the salvage of her remains from the seabed.</e>
<cmt>原文から「」『紀伊民報』、2007年1月27日の部分を削除しました。（後列に全く同じものがあるため）それに対応する訳文も削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="33">
<j>「」『紀伊民報』、2007年1月27日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kii Minpo news&quot; January 27, 2007</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kii Minpo news,&quot; January 27, 2007</e>
<cmt>Commaを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kii Minpo news,&quot; January 27, 2007</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>「」Milliyet、2007年1月5日（東京外国語大学による日本語訳）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Milliyet, January 5, 2007(translated in Japanese by Tokyo University of Foreign Studies)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Milliyet, January 5, 2007 (a Japanese translation by Tokyo University of Foreign Studies)</e>
<cmt>この部分は脚注のようですが、前後の文脈とかみ合わず意味不明な内容になっています。とりあえず原文通りにしておきます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Milliyet, January 5, 2007 (a Japanese translation by Tokyo University of Foreign Studies)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="35">
<j>2008年（平成20年）6月7日に行われた追悼式典には、来日中のアブドゥラー・ギュルトルコの大統領も出席した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 7, 2008, Turkish president Abdullah Gül, who was visiting in Japan, also attended the memorial ceremony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 7, 2008, the President of the Republic of Turkey, Abdullah Gül, attended the memorial ceremony during his visit to Japan.</e>
<cmt>トルコ国名としてthe Republic of Turkeyを用いました。他表現を若干変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 7, 2008, the President of the Republic of Turkey, Abdullah Gül, attended the memorial ceremony during his visit to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>遭難事件後の日土関係</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Relations between Japan and Turkey after the disaster.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Relations between Japan and Turkey after the disaster</e>
<cmt>Periodを除きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Relations between Japan and Turkey after the disaster</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="36">
<j>日本でもエルトゥールル号遭難事件は衝撃的なニュースとして伝わり、政府を通じて多くの義捐金・弔慰金が寄せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, the distress of the Ertuğrul was also known as shocking news that collected a lot of clarities and condolence money via the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, the distress of the Ertuğrul was also reported as shocking news, and a great amount of contributions and condolence money was collected via the government.</e>
<cmt>文法の誤りを直し、表現と語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, the distress of the Ertuğrul was also reported as shocking news, and a great amount of contributions and condolence money was collected via the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="37">
<j>茶道宗偏流の跡取り、山田宗有もこの事件に衝撃を受けた日本人のひとりであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soyu YAMADA, a successor of the Sohen-ryu Style of the tea ceremony, was also the Japanese who was shocked by the incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soyu YAMADA, the successor of the Sohen school of tea ceremony, was one of Japanese who was shocked by the accident.</e>
<cmt>流にはschoolを用いました。他、若干表現と語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soyu YAMADA, the successor of the Sohen school of tea ceremony, was one of Japanese who was shocked by the accident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>彼は日本の民間からエルトゥールル号事件の犠牲者の遺族に対する義捐金を集めるキャンペーンを行い、事件の翌々年に集まった義捐金を自ら携えてオスマン帝国の首都イスタンブルに渡った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He started fund-raising campaign among the Japanese people to collect money for charity to the families of the Ertuğrul victims, then after two years, he went to Istanbul, the capital city of the Ottoman Empire with charities he collected.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He started a fund-raising campaign among Japanese citizens to collect contributions for the families of the victims of the Ertuğrul incident; after two years, he travelled to Istanbul, the capital of the Ottoman Empire, carrying the collected donations.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He started a fund-raising campaign among Japanese citizens to collect contributions for the families of the victims of the Ertuğrul incident; after two years, he travelled to Istanbul, the capital of the Ottoman Empire, carrying the collected donations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="39">
<j>山田が民間人ながら義捐金をもってやってきたことが知られるや彼は熱烈な歓迎を受け、皇帝アブデュルハミト2世に拝謁する機会にすら恵まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When people knew Yamada, a private citizen brought charities with him, he received enthusiastic welcome and even got a chance to have an audience with the Sultan Abdul Hamid II.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As soon as Turkish people noticed that a private citizen Yamada had brought contributions, he received enthusiastic welcome and further was granted an audience with the Sultan Abdülhamid II.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正し、語を若干変えました。Abdülhamid Iiは初出時のスペルに統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As soon as Turkish people noticed that a private citizen Yamada had brought contributions, he received enthusiastic welcome and further was granted an audience with the Sultan Abdülhamid II.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>このとき、皇帝の要請でトルコに留まることを決意した山田はイスタンブルに貿易商店を開いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamada, in response to the Sultan&apos;s request, decided to stay in Turkey to start a trading shop in Istanbul.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then Yamada, in response to the Sultan&apos;s request, decided to stay in Turkey and started a trading shop in Istanbul.</e>
<cmt>文意が混同されないよう、表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then Yamada, in response to the Sultan&apos;s request, decided to stay in Turkey and started a trading shop in Istanbul.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>士官学校で少壮の士官に日本語や日本のことを教え、日本政府の高官のイスタンブル訪問を手引きするなど、日土国交が樹立されない中で官民の交流に尽力した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While teaching about Japan and Japanese language to young officers at the military academy, prior to establishment of diplomatic relations between Japan and Turkey, he dedicated himself to establish civilian relationships by arranging Istanbul visit for top Japanese government officials and so on.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He taught the Japanese language and told of Japan to young officers at the military academy, and helped to arrange visits to Istanbul for high officials in the Japanese government; thus, he dedicated himself to cultivate international civilian and governmental exchanges when there were no established diplomatic relations between Japan and Turkey.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正し、分かりやすくするため文の構造を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He taught the Japanese language and told of Japan to young officers at the military academy, and helped to arrange visits to Istanbul for high officials in the Japanese government; thus, he dedicated himself to cultivate international civilian and governmental exchanges when there were no established diplomatic relations between Japan and Turkey.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>彼が士官学校で教鞭をとった際、その教えを受けた生徒の中には、後にトルコ共和国の初代大統領となったケマル・アタテュルクもいたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he was teaching at the military academy, Kemal Ataturk, later became the first president of the Republic of Turkey, was considered to have been his student.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kemal Ataturk, who later became the first president of the Republic of Turkey, is said to have been one of his students when he was teaching at the military academy.</e>
<cmt>文法の誤りを直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kemal Ataturk, who later became the first president of the Republic of Turkey, is said to have been one of his students when he was teaching at the military academy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="43">
<j>山田がイスタンブルに滞在中に起こった日露戦争が日本の勝利に帰すと、長らくロシアから圧力を受け続けて、同じくロシアの南下圧力にさらされる日本に対する親近感を高めていたオスマン帝国の人々は、東の小国日本の快挙としてこれに熱狂した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Japan won the Russo-Japanese War, which had broken out during Yamada&apos;s Istanbul stay, people in the Ottoman Empire, who had been constantly pressured by Russia, sympathized with Japan, which also had been exposed to the pressure from Russia, were enthusiastic about the brilliant achievement by Japan, a small eastern country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Japan won the Russo-Japanese War, which had broken out while Yamada stayed in Istanbul, the people in the Ottoman Empire went wild with joy at the news, regarding it as a brilliant achievement by a small eastern country Japan, since they had long suffered the pressure from Russia and therefore grown affinity with Japan, the country which also had been troubled by the pressure from Russia.</e>
<cmt>文法を直し、分かりやすくするため表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Japan won the Russo-Japanese War, which had broken out while Yamada stayed in Istanbul, the people in the Ottoman Empire went wild with joy at the news, regarding it as a brilliant achievement by a small eastern country Japan, since they had long suffered the pressure from Russia and therefore grown affinity with Japan, the country which also had been troubled by the pressure from Russia.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>このとき日本海軍の英雄東郷平八郎提督にちなんでトーゴーという名を子供につけることが流行したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That time, Togo, named after the Commodore Heihachiro TOGO, a hero of the Japanese Imperial Navy became popular as children&apos;s names.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that naming a child Togo after the Admiral Heihachiro TOGO, a hero of the Japanese Imperial Navy, became popular at the time.</e>
<cmt>分かりやすくするため表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that naming a child Togo after the Admiral Heihachiro TOGO, a hero of the Japanese Imperial Navy, became popular at the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="45">
<j>しかし、山田宗有らの尽力による民間交流とはうらはらに、とうとうオスマン帝国が滅びるまで正式の国交が結ばれることはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, despite such civil exchanges supported by Soyu YAMADA and others, formal diplomatic relation was not realized until the fall of the Ottoman Empire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, despite such civilian exchanges supported by Soyu YAMADA and others, formal diplomatic relations were not realized until the fall of the Ottoman Empire.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, despite such civilian exchanges supported by Soyu YAMADA and others, formal diplomatic relations were not realized until the fall of the Ottoman Empire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>日本とオスマン帝国の外交当局による国交交渉は何度も行われたのであるが、日本側が欧米列強と同等の待遇の条約を望み、治外法権を認めるよう要求したのに対し、オスマン帝国は不平等条約の拡大を嫌い、両者の交渉が暗礁に乗り上げたためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan and the Ottoman Empire, both authorities negotiated the diplomatic relations many times</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was because the negotiations over the diplomatic relations between Japan and the Ottoman Empire deadlocked despite frequent negotiations by both authorities; the Ottoman Empire did not want another unequal treat while Japan demanded the same level of treaty as allowed the great powers of Europe and America, insisting on Japan&apos;s extraterritoriality.</e>
<cmt>「ためである」の部分を訳すために、これを含む文が前文のすぐ後に来る必要があるので、原文通り一文として訳しました。また、欧米がオスマン帝国と既に結んだ条約が、オスマン帝国にとって不平等だったという前提で訳出をしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason for this was that negotiations over the establishment of diplomatic relations between Japan and the Ottoman Empire remained deadlocked despite both sides engaging in frequent rounds of negotiations; the Ottoman Empire did not wish to enter into another unequal treaty, but Japan was demanding the same level of treaty as the Ottoman Empire had agreed to with the great powers of Europe and America, insisting on Japan&apos;s extraterritorial rights.</e>
<cmt>一部書き換えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="47">
<j>1914年、第一次世界大戦が勃発するとドイツら同盟国側に引き入れられつつあったオスマン帝国の対外情勢は緊迫し、山田はイスタンブルの店を閉鎖して退去し、日本へと帰国した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1914, when the World War I broke out, the Ottoman Empire that had being involved in the Central Powers such as German, had diplomatic tension, so Yamada closed his ship in Istanbul and returned to Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1914, when the First World War broke out, the foreign situation of the Ottoman Empire, which had being dragged into the Central Powers consisting of Germany and others, grew tense, so Yamada closed his shop in Istanbul and returned to Japan.</e>
<cmt>文法の誤りを修正し、原文の意味がはっきり訳されるようにするため表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1914, when the First World War broke out, the foreign situation of the Ottoman Empire, which had being dragged into the Central Powers consisting of Germany and others, grew tense, so Yamada closed his shop in Istanbul and returned to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>この戦争でイギリスら連合国の側についた日本はオスマン帝国と敵同士となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan, having sided with the Allies such as Britain in this war, became the Ottoman Empire&apos;s enemy.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan, having sided with the Allies consisting of Britain and others in this war, became the Ottoman Empire&apos;s enemy.</e>
<cmt>表現を少し変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan, having sided with the Allies consisting of Britain and others in this war, became the Ottoman Empire&apos;s enemy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>戦後のオスマン帝国の解体とトルコ共和国の成立という目まぐるしい情勢の変化を経て、1924年発効のローザンヌ条約締結、1925年の大使館開設により、ようやく日本とトルコは正式の国交を結ぶことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Through drastic changes of the circumstance such as fall of the Ottoman Empire and establishment of Republic of Turkey after the war, Japan and Turkey finally entered into diplomatic relations following conclusion of the Treaty of Lausann issued in 1924, and setting up the Embassy in 1925.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Through drastic changes of circumstances such as the fall of the Ottoman Empire and the establishment of the Republic of Turkey after the war, Japan and Turkey finally entered into diplomatic relations following the conclusion of the Treaty of Lausann in 1924 and the establishment of the Embassy in 1925.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Through drastic changes of circumstances such as the fall of the Ottoman Empire and the establishment of the Republic of Turkey after the war, Japan and Turkey finally entered into diplomatic relations following the conclusion of the Treaty of Lausann in 1924 and the establishment of the Embassy in 1925.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>「日土友好の起点」の記憶</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The memory of &apos;the staring point of friendly relations between Japan and Turkey&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Memory of &apos;the staring point of friendly relations between Japan and Turkey&apos;</e>
<cmt>タイトル風に直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Memory of &apos;the staring point of friendly relations between Japan and Turkey&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="50">
<j>エルトゥールル号遭難事件は、オスマン帝国末期の外交政策と海軍の弱体化がもたらした悲劇であったが、この事件で被害者に対して示された日本人の友誼は、その後も長く日土友好関係の起点として両国の関係者に記憶されることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The distress of the Ertuğrul was a tragedy provided by the foreign policy of the late Ottoman Empire and weakened Navy, however, Japanese amity to victims of the disaster has been remembered by people in both countries long as the starting point of friendly relations between Japan and Turkey.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The distress of the Ertuğrul was a tragedy caused by a foreign policy of the late Ottoman Empire and the weakened Navy; however, Japan&apos;s amity to the victims of the disaster has been long remembered by persons concerned in both countries as a starting point of friendly relations between Japan and Turkey.</e>
<cmt>若干文法と語を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The distress of the Ertuğrul was a tragedy caused by a foreign policy of the late Ottoman Empire and the weakened Navy; however, Japan&apos;s amity to the victims of the disaster has been long remembered by persons concerned in both countries as a starting point of friendly relations between Japan and Turkey.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>トルコ人が公的な場で日本人に対して日土友好の歴史について語るとき、必ずといっていいほど第一に持ち出されるのがエルトゥールル号遭難事件の顛末である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Turkish people talk to Japanese people about the friendly relations history between Turkey and Japan in public, above all things, they never miss a chance to mention the whole story of the Ertuğrul and her disaster.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Turks talk to Japanese people about the history of friendly relations between Turkey and Japan in public, they almost always mention the story of the Ertuğrul and her disaster above all things.</e>
<cmt>文法と表現を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Turks talk to Japanese people about the history of friendly relations between Turkey and Japan in public, they almost always mention the story of the Ertuğrul and her disaster above all things.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="52">
<j>こうしたトルコ人の言説に対して、エルトゥールル号遭難事件の顛末は日本ではあまり記憶されておらず、長らく公的な場で語られることすらもまれであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Contrary to Turkish people&apos;s discourse, the whole story of the Ertuğrul distress were not well remembered in Japan, even rarely mentioned in public for a long time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Contrary to Turks&apos; discourse, the story of the Ertuğrul&apos;s distress was not well remembered in Japan and had been rarely mentioned in public for a long time.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Contrary to Turks&apos; discourse, the story of the Ertuğrul&apos;s distress was not well remembered in Japan and had been rarely mentioned in public for a long time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>しかし21世紀に入ってからは、エルトゥールル号事件の顛末が、以下の事件と絡めて、インターネット上の電子掲示板やメールマガジンで紹介される機会が増えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the 21st century, the whole story of Ertuğru disaster came to be introduced through electronic bulletin board and mail magazines on internet including the following incident.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処　ここから下の部分のパラグラフがＷｉｋｉｐｅｄｉａのオリジナルとだいぶ違って（多分オリジナルの方は後で直したのだと思います）「エルトゥールル事件の顛末が」の後、別の事件が挿入され、それが数パラグラフにまたがって続いているためこのパラグラフを分割しても、また、次のパラグラフを入れ替えても「顛末が」を完結できないため訳出できませんでした。（技術的ではなく、文法的に不可能です）訳出のため、Ｗｉｋｉｐｅｄｉａのオリジナルを元にパラグラフ内の文章の順番を多少変更してあります。個々の単語や、内容に変更はありません。変更したのは「しかし２１世紀に入って」から「人々の間に徐々に広まっている」です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the 21st century, the whole story of the Ertuğru disaster came to be introduced through electronic bulletin boards or mail magazines on the Internet along with the following incident.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。私も原文はこのように分割されなくてはいけないと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the 21st century, the whole story of the Ertuğru disaster came to be introduced through electronic bulletin boards or mail magazines on the Internet along with the following incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>1985年のイラン・イラク戦争において、イラクのイラン上空の航空機に対する無差別攻撃宣言に対し、イラン国内に取り残された日本人が、自衛隊の海外派遣不可の原則のために自衛隊機による救援を受けられなかったうえ、日本航空の組合問題により日本航空インターナショナル機による救援もできないために危機的状況にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1985, in the Iran-Iraq War, when Iran proclaimed indiscriminate attacks to any airplanes flew over Iran, Japanese people left behind in Iran were in crisis because they couldn&apos;t expect the rescue by Self-Defense Force according to the principle that disapproved the dispatch overseas of Self-Defense Force troops, and Japan Airlines also couldn&apos;t help them using JAL international airplanes because of their union issue.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処　「ビルレル」のスペルが不明でした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1985 during the Iran-Iraq War, when Iraq proclaimed indiscriminate attacks to any aircraft flew over Iran, the Japanese people in Iran were stuck in a crisis because the rescue by Self-Defense Force was not made according to the principle that the overseas dispatch of Self-Defense Force troops is prohibited, and Japan Airlines did not fly JAL international airplanes because of a union issue.</e>
<cmt>スペルミスを修正し、若干語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1985 during the Iran-Iraq War, when Iraq proclaimed indiscriminate attacks to any aircraft flew over Iran, the Japanese people in Iran were stuck in a crisis because the rescue by Self-Defense Force was not made according to the principle that the overseas dispatch of Self-Defense Force troops is prohibited, and Japan Airlines did not fly JAL international airplanes because of a union issue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>イランの日本大使館の野村豊大使は、トルコ大使館のビルレル大使に窮状を訴えると大使は次のように答えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yutaka NOMURA, the Ambassador of Japanese Embassy in Iran, recounted their difficulties to ビルレル, the Ambassador of Turkish Embassy said, &apos; Ok, I will ask my country to send a rescue airplane&apos;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処　一文にするため、次のパラグラフをここに結合しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yutaka NOMURA, the Ambassador of the Japanese Embassy in Iran, appealed for help for this plight to ビルレル, the Ambassador of the Turkish Embassy, he said in response, &apos;Okay, I will ask my country to send a rescue airplane.</e>
<cmt>ビルレルのスペル不明</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yutaka NOMURA, the then Japanese ambassador to Iran, appealed for help in resolving this issue to Ismet Birsel, the then Turkish ambassador to Iran, he responded as follows:</e>
<cmt>「」内を後列に分けました。以下のサイトから「ビルレル」 は&quot;Ismet Birsel&quot;のようです。http://www.jeanpaulleblanc.com/Japan.htm</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>「わかりました。ただちに本国に求め、救援機を派遣させましょう。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okay, I will ask my country to send a rescue airplane.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文にかぎかっこ、訳文に引用符をつけました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>「トルコ人ならだれもが、エルトゥールル号の遭難の際に受けた恩義を知っています。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Every Turkish know your kindness we received at the time of the disaster of Ertuğrul,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Every Turk knows Japan&apos;s kindness we received at the time of the disaster of Ertuğrul.</e>
<cmt>スペルミスを直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Every Turk knows Japan&apos;s kindness we received at the time of the disaster of Ertuğrul.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文にかぎかっこ、訳文に引用符をつけました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>「ご恩返しをさせていただきましょうとも」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Now we will repay the kindness&apos;</e>
<cmt>後列のカギ括弧部分をこちらに分けました。原文にかぎかっこ、訳文に引用符をつけました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>大使の要請を受けて派遣されたトルコ航空機によって215名の日本人全員が救出され、無事にトルコ経由で帰国できた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">We will repay you,&apos; then all 215 Japanese people were picked up by Turkish airplanes, which was dispatched in response to the Ambassador&apos;s request, and they returned to Japan via Turkey.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Now we will repay the kindness&apos;; thus all 215 Japanese people were picked up by the Turkish Airlines airplane dispatched in response to the Ambassador&apos;s request and managed to return to Japan via Turkey safely.</e>
<cmt>若干表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus all 215 Japanese people were picked up by the Turkish Airlines airplane dispatched in response to the Ambassador&apos;s request and managed to return to Japan via Turkey safely.</e>
<cmt>カギ括弧の部分を分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>特に2002年のサッカーFIFAワールドカップ日韓大会でのトルコチームの活躍を機に盛んにテレビ番組や雑誌でも取り上げられるようになるなど、日本の一般の人々の間に徐々に広まっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This Ertuğrul incident has gradually became popular among the people in Japan, especially in 2002, at the FIFA World Cup Korea/Japan, Turkish team&apos;s good success was an opportunity for TV programs or magazines to pick up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The story of the Ertuğrul disaster has gradually spread out among the people in Japan; it has been frequently talked about in many TV programs or magazines, especially after the Turkish team achieved remarkable results in the 2002 FIFA World Cup Korea/Japan.</e>
<cmt>分かりやすくするため表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The story of the Ertuğrul disaster has gradually spread out among the people in Japan; it has been frequently talked about in many TV programs or magazines, especially after the Turkish team achieved remarkable results in the 2002 FIFA World Cup Korea/Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>2004年には、これらのことを紹介した児童書が小学生高学年向けの読書感想文コンクール課題図書ともなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 2004, a children book that introduced the incident was designated as a book for fifth and sixth grade elementary school pupils for the book reports competition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 2004, a children book that introduced the incident was designated as a book on which fifth and sixth grade elementary school pupils were assigned to write book reports for a writing competition.</e>
<cmt>分かりやすくするため表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 2004, a children book that introduced the incident was designated as a book on which fifth and sixth grade elementary school pupils were assigned to write book reports for a writing competition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>こうして今では、日本でもエルトゥールル号遭難事件は「親日親日的とされる国と地域の一覧トルコ」のイメージを語るエピソードとしてなくてはならないものになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, also in Japan, the distress of Ertuğrul became essential epsode when people talk about &quot;Turkey, a friendly country toward Japan&quot;.</e>
<cmt>「親日親日的とされる国と地域の一覧トルコ」の意味が不明瞭でした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, also in Japan today, the distress of the Ertuğrul is regarded as an essential episode to talk about &quot;a pro-Japanese country, Turkey.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「親日親日的とされる国と地域の一覧トルコ」は意味不明のため、wikipediaの記事を参考に「親日国トルコ」として訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, also in Japan today, the distress of the Ertuğrul is regarded as an essential episode to talk about &quot;a pro-Japanese country, Turkey.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="63">
<j>上記、イラン・イラク戦争時のトルコ政府・トルコ航空による日本人救助活動について、実際は伊藤忠商事イスタンブール支店関係者、在テヘラン日本大使館からのトルコ政府への救援要請に対し、トルコ側が「快諾」し、トルコ航空機の派遣を決定したとも言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Actually about such rescure operation for Japanese people by the Turkish government and Turkish Airlines in the Iran-Iraq War, they also say that in response to request from people of the Istanbul branch office of ITOCHU corporation and the Japanese Embassy in Teheran, the Turkish government was pleased to accept to dipatch Turkish Airlines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Actually, with regard to the above-mentioned rescue operation by the Turkish government and Turkish Airlines to save Japanese people during the Iran-Iraq War, there is another explanation which says that it was conducted in response to the request from people of the Istanbul branch office of the ITOCHU corporation and the Japanese Embassy in Teheran, to which the Turkish government gave &apos;a willing consent&apos; to dispatch a Turkish Airlines airplane.</e>
<cmt>スペルミスを直し、なるべく分かりやすくするため表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another explanation that has been proposed for the above-mentioned rescue operation by the Turkish government and Turkish Airlines to save Japanese people during the Iran-Iraq War is that a request was made by the Istanbul branch office of ITOCHU Corporation and the Japanese Embassy in Teheran, to which the Turkish government gave &apos;their willing consent&apos; to dispatch a Turkish Airlines airplane.</e>
<cmt>引用符を半角に変更しました。一部書き換えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>なお、この事件に関するシンポジウムが2007年10月28日、東京都三鷹市の中近東文化センターで、同時期に開催されたエルトゥールル号回顧展に併せて、当該トルコ航空機の元機長、元客室乗務員、野村元駐イラン日本国特命全権大使、森永元伊藤忠商事イスタンブール支店長、毛利悟元東京銀行テヘラン駐在員ら当時の関係者出席の上、行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 28, 2007, at the Middle Eastern Culture Center in Mitaka City, Tokyo, along with a retrospective exhibition of Ertuğrul, a symposium on the above incident was held with attendants of a former pilot and flight attendants of the Turkish Airlines, Nomura, a former Japanese ambassador extraordinary and plenipotentiary to Iran, Morinaga, a former Istanbul branch office manager of ITOCHU Corporation, Satoru MORI, a former representative of The Bank of Tokyo in Tehran, who had been involved with the incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 28, 2007, at the Middle Eastern Culture Center in Mitaka City, Tokyo, along with a retrospective exhibition of the Ertuğrul, a symposium on this incident was held with attendants of persons concerned in the incident, including the former pilot and flight attendants of the Turkish Airlines airplane that actually flew, Nomura, a former Japanese ambassador extraordinary and plenipotentiary to Iran, Morinaga, a former Istanbul branch office manager of the ITOCHU Corporation, Satoru MORI, a former representative of the Bank of Tokyo in Tehran.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正し、分かりやすくするため若干表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 28, 2007, at the Middle Eastern Culture Center in Mitaka City, Tokyo, along with a retrospective exhibition of the Ertuğrul, a symposium on this incident was held with attendants of persons concerned in the incident, including the former pilot and flight attendants of the Turkish Airlines airplane that actually flew, Nomura, a former Japanese ambassador extraordinary and plenipotentiary to Iran, Morinaga, a former Istanbul branch office manager of the ITOCHU Corporation, Satoru MORI, a former representative of the Bank of Tokyo in Tehran.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="65">
<j>NHKは、イラン・イラク戦争時のトルコ政府・トルコ航空による日本人救助活動について、プロジェクトXにて取り上げた際に、エルトゥールル号遭難事件との関連については、全く触れなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When NHK picked up the rescue operation for Japanese people by the Government of Turkey and Turkish Airlines in the Iran-Iraq War on &apos;The Project X&apos;, (a Japanese TV show), they never touched the Ertuğrul incident in relation to its topic.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When NHK featured the rescue mission of Japanese by the Turkish government and Turkish Airlines during the Iran-Iraq War in the program &apos;The Project X,&apos; they never mentioned the Ertuğrul incident in relation to the topic.</e>
<cmt>語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When NHK featured the rescue mission of Japanese by the Turkish government and Turkish Airlines during the Iran-Iraq War in the program &apos;The Project X,&apos; they never mentioned the Ertuğrul incident in relation to the topic.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>この点についてのNHKへの問い合わせに対して、NHK側は、「1985年の救出に直接関わったトルコ大使やトルコ航空機長など当事者の方々に確認したところ、エルトゥールル号事件のことは全くご存知ありませんでした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In response to inquiries to NHK about this issue, &apos;We asked people who had been concerned with the rescue operation in 1985 such as a Turkish ambassador and a Turkish Airlines captain, however nobody knew about the Ertuğrul incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In response to inquiries to NHK about this issue, they said, &apos;We asked the people who had been directly involved in the rescue operation in 1985, such as the Turkish ambassador and the Turkish Airlines captain; however nobody knew about the Ertuğrul incident.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正し表現を若干変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response to inquiries to NHK about this issue, they said, &apos;We asked the people who had been directly involved in the rescue operation in 1985, such as the Turkish ambassador and the Turkish Airlines captain; however nobody knew about the Ertuğrul incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>114年前のことであり、ほとんどのトルコの人々は事件を知らないのが実状でした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The disaster occurred 114 year ago, most of the Turkish people actually didn&apos;t know the incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The disaster occurred 114 year ago, and in truth most Turks did not know the incident.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正し表現を若干変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The disaster occurred 114 year ago, and in truth most Turks did not know the incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>またエルトゥールル号事件がトルコの学校で広く教えられているという事実も無く、教科書も見つかっていません。」と回答している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, there is no evidence that Turkish schools generally teach the Ertuğrul incident, such textbooks have not been found,&apos; they said.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, there is no evidence that Turkish schools generally teach the Ertuğrul incident, and neither have such textbooks been found.&apos;</e>
<cmt>文法を修正し表現を若干変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, there is no evidence that Turkish schools generally teach the Ertuğrul incident, and neither have such textbooks been found.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="69">
<j>2008年1～2月、米国・海洋考古学研究所のトルコ人スタッフらが発掘調査を行い、遺骨や弾丸など1000点以上の遺品を引き揚げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January and February, 2008, Turkish staff members of the Institute of Nautical Archaeology of the United States, carried out underwater excavation and salvaged over 1000 remains, bullets and other articles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January and February, 2008, Turkish staff members of the Institute of Nautical Archaeology of the United States carried out an underwater excavation and salvaged over 1000 articles of her remains, such as bullets and remains of the body.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正し、訳漏れの語を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January and February, 2008, Turkish staff members of the Institute of Nautical Archaeology of the United States carried out an underwater excavation and salvaged over 1000 articles of her remains, such as bullets and remains of the body.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="70">
<j>2008年6月7日、来日していたトルコのアブドゥラー・ギュル大統領は、同国の大統領として初めてこの地を訪れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In official visit toJapan, Turkish president Abdullah Gul went to the disaster area as the first president of this country.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During an official visit to Japan, Turkish president Abdullah Gül visited the site of the disaster for the first time as the president of his country.</e>
<cmt>分かりやすくするため表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During an official visit to Japan, Turkish president Abdullah Gül visited the site of the disaster for the first time as the president of his country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>そして遭難慰霊碑前で行われた追悼式典に出席し献花を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He attended the memorial ceremony held in front of the distress memorial and offered flowers.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He attended the memorial ceremony held in front of the distress memorial and offered flowers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He attended the memorial ceremony held in front of the distress memorial and offered flowers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), RadioActive(id:18024), Los688(id:12316), 九鬼備助(id:45564), Kawai(id:5634), 経済準学士(id:22656), Nonomura(id:72557), Kogane(id:28186), Yhr(id:10977), Kotoito(id:21045), 大友ディミトリ(id:160856), Nakaoka7675(id:39645), Reedo(id:155043), Gombe(id:27), ぎゅうひ(id:9206), MioUzaki(id:89034), 継之助(id:39352), 代言人(id:33675), 大根(id:82963), 七篠権兵衛(id:129041), Etoa(id:20987), さーとる(id:96104), Maldoror(id:14782), Cpa2007(id:178266), 浩(id:70121), いろはにほへと(id:89648), Carbuncle(id:346), Sweeper tamonten(id:183520), Doppo1127(id:169097), Centaurus(id:33865), Tassi-(id:81774), Blooms(id:30658), Ajtnk(id:18368), MDR-SK(id:192066), VolkovBot(id:105371), Kouchiumi(id:19253), Fromm(id:71291), ＮｉＫｅ(id:7512), Kanjy(id:36859), 663highland(id:18755), 梅桃桜(id:35850), 豊平大権現(id:249503), Safkan(id:423), Nsq(id:54991), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>