<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>徳政令</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Order for the Acts of Virtuous Government</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Order for the Acts of Virtuous Government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokuseirei</e>
<cmt>徳政令→Tokuseirei (ordering return of land sold and dissolution of debts)　と訂正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>徳政令(とくせいれい)とは、日本の中世、鎌倉時代から室町時代にかけて朝廷、幕府などが債権や債務の放棄を命じた法令である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Order for the Acts of Virtuous Government were acts by the Imperial court and bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) during the Middle Ages in Japan, the Kamakura Period to the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Orders for the Acts of Virtuous Government were acts by the Imperial court and the bakufu (Japanese feudal governments headed by a shogun) during the Middle Ages in Japan, from the Kamakura Period to the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Tokuseirei&quot; (ordering return of land sold and dissolution of debts) was acts by the Imperial Court and the bakufu (Japanese feudal governments headed by a shogun) during the Middle Ages in Japan, from the Kamakura period to the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>徳政令→Tokuseirei (ordering return of land sold and dissolution of debts)　と訂正しました。Court大文字にしました。period小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>徳政</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acts of Virtuous Government</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acts of Virtuous Government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokusei</e>
<cmt>Tokuseiとしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>「徳政（とくせい）」とは天人相関思想に基づき、代替わり或いは災害などに伴い改元が行われた際に天皇が行う貧民救済活動や神領興行（儀式遂行とその財源たる所領等の保障）、訴訟処理などの社会政策のことであり、「新制」とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Acts of Virtuous Government&quot;, also called &quot;Shinsei&quot;(new system), are social policies that the Emperor initiated upon ascending the throne or when the name of the era was changed because of natural disasters, etc. and is based on the theory of correlation between heaven and man and entailed activities to save the poor, &quot;Shinryo-kogyo&quot; (conducting ceremonies and securing property for revenue) and court case processing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Acts of Virtuous Government&quot;, also called &quot;Shinsei&quot; (new system), are social policies that the Emperor initiated upon ascending to the throne or when the name of the era was changed because of natural disasters, etc. and were based on the theory of correlation between heaven and man and entailed activities to save the poor, &quot;Shinryo-kogyo&quot; (conducting ceremonies and securing property for revenue) and court case processing.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokusei&apos; (acts of Virtuous Government), also called &apos;Shinsei&apos; (new system), are social policies that the Emperor initiated upon ascending to the throne or when the name of the era was changed because of natural disasters, etc. and were based on the theory of correlation between heaven and man and entailed activities to save the poor, &quot;Shinryo-kogyo&quot; (conducting ceremonies and securing property for revenue) and court case processing.</e>
<cmt>Tokuseiを補足しました。原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>既売却地・質流れ地の無償返付，所領や債権債務についての訴訟（雑訴）の円滑処理などを行うことを通じて、旧体制へ復帰を図る目的があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The aim was to return to the old system by voluntary restoration of sold or foreclosed property and smooth processing of court cases (zasso) regarding property and debts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The aim was to return to the old system by voluntary restoration of sold or foreclosed property and smooth processing of court cases (zasso) regarding property and debts.</e>
<cmt>不要な空白を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The aim was to return to the old system by voluntary restoration of sold or foreclosed property and smooth processing of court cases (zasso) regarding property and debts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>鎌倉時代に入ると災害や戦乱などの社会的混乱が貴族社会にも及び始め、遂に承久の乱では朝廷軍が敗北して太上天皇の流罪が行われるなど、貴族社会が存続の危機に差し掛かっていることが明白となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the beginning of the Kamakura Period, social turmoil such as natural disasters and war began to affect the society of the aristocracy, and it was clearly apparent that the existence of the aristocracy itself was threatened when the Imperial court forces lost and the Daijyo Emperor was exiled in Jyokyu no Ran.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the beginning of the Kamakura Period, social turmoil such as natural disasters and war began to affect the aristocracy, and it was clearly apparent that the existence of the aristocracy itself was threatened when the Imperial court forces were defeated and the Daijyo Emperor was exiled in Jyokyu no Ran.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the beginning of the Kamakura period, social turmoil such as natural disasters and war began to affect the aristocracy, and it was clearly apparent that the existence of the aristocracy itself was threatened when the Imperial Court forces were defeated and the retired emperor was exiled in Jokyu Disturbance.</e>
<cmt>period小文字にしました。Court大文字にしました。太上天皇→the retired emperor に訂正しました。Jyokyu no Ran→Jokyu Disturbanceに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>こうした中で、朝廷内では現実的な政治に目を向ける事で求心力を回復させて昔の権威を取り戻そうとする動きが盛んになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In such situation, there was a movement within the Imperial court to recover authority and regain centripetal force by politics based in reality.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this situation, there was a movement within the Imperial court to recover authority and regain centrified power by realistic politics.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this situation, there was a movement within the Imperial Court to recover authority and regain unifying power by realistic politics.</e>
<cmt>centrified→unifyingに訂正しました。Court大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>「徳政」はその路線の上に推進された政策であり、徳政令はそうした政策の一つである（徳政≠徳政令）という事を留意する必要がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Acts of Virtuous Government&quot; was one of the policies that was promoted as part of this movement and it is necessary to be aware that &quot;Acts of Virtuous Government&quot; is not equivalent to &quot;Order for the Acts of Virtuous Government&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Acts of Virtuous Government&quot; was one of the policies that was promoted as part of this movement and it is necessary to understand that &quot;Acts of Virtuous Government&quot; are not equivalent to the &quot;Order for the Acts of Virtuous Government&quot;.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;Tokusei&apos; (acts of Virtuous Government) was one of the policies that was promoted as part of this movement and it is necessary to understand that &apos;Tokusei&apos; is not equivalent to the &apos;Tokuseirei&apos; (ordering return of land sold and dissolution of debts).</e>
<cmt>The &apos;Tokusei&apos; (acts of Virtuous Government)としました。原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。&quot;位置訂正。徳政令→Tokuseirei (ordering return of land sold and dissolution of debts)　と訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>鎌倉幕府も朝廷政治の現状を状況を批判的に見る立場から朝廷に対して「徳政」推進を求めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the stance of being critical towards the Imperial court&apos;s situation, the Kamakura bakufu requested the promotion of &quot;Acts of Virtuous Government&quot;.</e>
<cmt>原文「現状を状況を批判的」がすこしおかしいので、「現状の状況を批判的」と訳</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the stance of being critical of the Imperial court&apos;s situation, the Kamakura bakufu requested the promotion of the &quot;Acts of Virtuous Government&quot;.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the stance of being critical of the Imperial Court&apos;s situation, the Kamakura bakufu requested the promotion of the &apos;Tokusei.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。Court大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>後嵯峨上皇の下で記録所が再建され、続く亀山上皇院政下の1286年（弘安9年）には、院評定を徳政沙汰（人事・寺社などの行政問題）と雑訴沙汰（所領・金銭などの一般的な訴訟）に分割するなどの改革を行い（「弘安徳政」）、1293年(正応6年・永仁元年)には伏見天皇（のち上皇）が記録所を徳政推進の機関として充実を図った（「永仁徳政」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The retired Emperor Gosaga re-established Kirokusho and in 1286, the subsequent retired Emperor Kameyama cloistered government promoted reforms (&quot;Koan-Tokusei&quot;, political reforms in the Koan era) such as dividing In-hyojo into Tokusei-sata (governmental issues related to personnel and temple/shrines) and Zasso-sata (ordinary court cases related to property, money, etc.) and in 1293, Emperor Fushimi (later Jyoko) enhanced Kirokusho as the organization for promoting tokusei (&quot;Enin-Tokusei&quot;, political reforms in the Enin era).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The retired Emperor Gosaga re-established Kirokusho and in 1286, the retired Emperor Kameyama cloistered government promoted reforms (&quot;Koan-Tokusei&quot;, political reforms in the Koan era) such as dividing In-hyojo into Tokusei-sata (governmental issues related to personnel and temples/shrines) and Zasso-sata (ordinary court cases related to property, money, etc.) and in 1293, Emperor Fushimi (later Jyoko) enhanced Kirokusho as the organization for promoting tokusei (&quot;Enin-Tokusei&quot;, political reforms in the Enin era).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Retired Emperor Gosaga re-established Kirokusho and in 1286, the Retired Emperor Kameyama cloistered government promoted reforms (&apos;Koan-Tokusei,&apos; political reforms in the Koan era) such as dividing In-hyojo into Tokusei-sata (governmental issues related to personnel and temples/shrines) and Zasso-sata (ordinary court cases related to property, money, etc.) and in 1293, Emperor Fushimi (later the Retired Emperor) enhanced Kirokusho as the organization for promoting tokusei (&apos;Enin-Tokusei,&apos; political reforms in the Enin era).</e>
<cmt>Retired大文字にしました。原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。Jyoko→the Retired Emperor</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>当初、こうした政策は元寇などによって混乱する社会秩序の回復を図りたい鎌倉幕府の政策と軌を一にするもの（安達泰盛による幕政改革も「弘安徳政」と呼ばれている）であったが、やがて徳政の本格化とともに朝廷の威信回復の考えが旧体制（鎌倉幕府以前への）復帰を模索する動きに結び付けられるようになると、鎌倉幕府は皇位継承における両統迭立政策を名目とした政治介入を行い、亀山・伏見両上皇の院政停止を行った事から朝幕間に緊張状態を生み、やがて後醍醐天皇の親政に至ってついに鎌倉幕府に対する討幕運動へと転化することになったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Initially, these reforms were in agreement with the Kamakura bakufu&apos;s policies to recover public order after confusion due to the Mongolian invasion attempts against Japan, etc.(the bakufu reforms by Taimori ADACHI are also called &quot;Koan-Tokusei&quot;), but when the scale of tokusei was enlarged and exploratory movements to go back to the old system (before the Kamakura bakufu) became linked with the thought of recovering the authority of the Imperial court, the Kamakura bakufu used Ryotoutetsuritsu policies for the Imperial succession as a reason to intervene politically and terminated the cloistered governments of retired Emperors Kameyama and Fushimi, causing tension between the bakufu and Imperial court, leading to Emperor Godaigo&apos;s direct governance, which eventually transitioned into the movement to overthrow the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially, these reforms were in agreement with the Kamakura bakufu&apos;s policies to recover public order after confusion due to Mongolian attempts to invade Japan, etc.(the bakufu reforms by Taimori ADACHI are also called &quot;Koan-Tokusei&quot;), but when the scale of tokusei was enlarged and consideration of reversion to the old system (before the Kamakura bakufu) became linked with the idea of recovering the authority of the Imperial court, the Kamakura bakufu used Ryotoutetsuritsu policies for the Imperial succession as a reason to intervene politically and terminated the cloistered governments of retired Emperors Kameyama and Fushimi, causing tension between the bakufu and the Imperial court, leading to Emperor Godaigo&apos;s direct governance, which eventually transformed into the movement to overthrow the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially, these reforms were in agreement with the Kamakura bakufu&apos;s policies to recover public order after confusion due to Mongolian attempts to invade Japan, etc. (the bakufu reforms by Yasumori ADACHI are also called &apos;Koan-Tokusei&apos;), but when the scale of tokusei was enlarged and consideration of reversion to the old system (before the Kamakura bakufu) became linked with the idea of recovering the authority of the Imperial Court, the Kamakura bakufu used Ryoto tetsuritsu policies for the Imperial succession as a reason to intervene politically and terminated the cloistered governments of Retired Emperors Kameyama and Fushimi, causing tension between the bakufu and the Imperial Court, leading to Emperor Godaigo&apos;s direct governance, which eventually transformed into the movement to overthrow the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。スペース補足。安達泰盛→Yasumori ADACHI に訂正しました。Court大文字にしました。Ryotoに訂正しました。Retired大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>徳政令の実施</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Administration of the Order for the Acts of Virtuous Government</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Administration of the Order for the Acts of Virtuous Government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Administration of Tokuseirei (ordering return of land sold and dissolution of debts)</e>
<cmt>徳政令→Tokuseirei (ordering return of land sold and dissolution of debts)　と訂正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>鎌倉時代の徳政令には、貧窮に苦しむ御家人保護の名目が強く、1297年(永仁5)の永仁の徳政令が知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Orders for the Acts of Virtuous Government during the Kamakura Period were mainly for protecting poor and suffering vassals, and the most commonly known order is the Order for the Acts of Virtuous Government in Einin Era in 1297.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Orders for the Acts of Virtuous Government during the Kamakura Period were mainly for protecting poor and suffering vassals, and the most commonly known order is the Order for the Acts of Virtuous Government in the Einin Era in 1297.</e>
<cmt>冠詞を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Orders for Tokuseirei during the Kamakura period were mainly for protecting poor and suffering vassals, and the most commonly known order is Tokuseirei in the Einin era in 1297.</e>
<cmt>Tokuseireiに訂正しました。period、era小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>建武の新政期である1334年(建武元)には後醍醐天皇が徳政令を行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1334, during the Kenmu Restoration, Emperor Godaigo issued an Order for the Acts of Virtuous Government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1334, during the Kenmu Restoration, Emperor Godaigo issued an Order for the Acts of Virtuous Government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1334, during the Kenmu Restoration, Emperor Godaigo issued an Tokuseirei.</e>
<cmt>Tokuseireiに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>室町時代になると惣の発達により、徳政令を求める土一揆、徳政一揆などが頻発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the spread of &quot;So (village)&quot; in the Muromachi Period, peasant uprisings and Tokusei uprisings demanding an Order for the Acts of Virtuous Government increased.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the spread of &quot;So (village)&quot; in the Muromachi Period, peasant uprisings and Tokusei uprisings demanding an Order for the Acts of Virtuous Government increased.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the spread of So (so village) in the Muromachi period, peasant uprisings and Tokusei uprisings demanding an Tokuseirei increased.</e>
<cmt>惣→so (so village)原文に『』がないので&quot;削除。period小文字にしました。Tokuseireiに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また、一揆勢力や在地勢力が独自に行う私徳政なども行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, private acts of virtuous government were issued by uprising forces and local powers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, private acts of virtuous government were issued by uprising forces and local powers.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, private Tokuseirei was issued by uprising forces and local powers.</e>
<cmt>Tokuseireiに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これらの一揆は将軍の代替わり期に多く発生し、「代初めの徳政」を要求している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These uprisings commonly happened at the change of shoguns and demanded an &quot;Order for the Acts of Virtuous Government upon Change of the Shogun&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These uprisings commonly happened upon the change of shoguns, and involved demands for &quot;Order for the Acts of Virtuous Government upon Change of the Shogun&quot;.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These uprisings commonly happened upon the change of shoguns, and involved demands for &apos;Tokuseirei upon Change of the Shogun.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。Tokuseireiに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>正長の土一揆では室町幕府から正式な徳政令は出なかったものの、嘉吉の徳政一揆に際しては幕府から正式にな徳政令（嘉吉の徳政令）の発布が行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Peasant Uprising in the Shocho Era did not lead to an official Order for the Acts of Virtuous Government from the Muromachi bakufu, but the Tokusei Uprising in the Kakitsu Era led to an official Order for the Acts of Virtuous Government from the bakufu (Order for the Acts of Virtuous Government in Kakitsu Era).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Peasant Uprising in the Shocho Era did not lead to an official Order for the Acts of Virtuous Government from the Muromachi bakufu, however the Tokusei Uprising in the Kakitsu Era led to an official Order for the Acts of Virtuous Government from the bakufu (the Order for the Acts of Virtuous Government in Kakitsu Era).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The peasant uprising in the Shocho era did not lead to an official Order for the Acts of Virtuous Government from the Muromachi bakufu, however the Tokusei Uprising in the Kakitsu era led to an official Order for the Acts of Virtuous Government from the bakufu (the Order for the Acts of Virtuous Government in Kakitsu era).</e>
<cmt>peasant uprising、era小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>当初は徳政令に慎重だった室町幕府は、1454年の土一揆を機に分一銭（ぶいちせん・分一徳政令（ぶいちとくせいれい）・徳政分一銭（とくせいぶいちせん）とも）を発布して、債権債務額の1割を一種の手数料として幕府に納めた紛争当事者に当該債権債務の権利を許す命令を出したが、これは債務の1割が幕府の収入となったため、後に幕府財政再建のために濫用されることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Initially, the Muromachi bakufu was careful about issuing Orders for the Acts of Virtuous Government, but in 1454, the bakufu issued &quot;Buichi-sen&quot;,&quot;Buichi Order for the Acts of Virtuous Government&quot;.&quot;Tokusei-buichi-sen&quot;, which ordered 10% of debt repayments to be paid to the government as a sort of handling fee, and since this 10% of debt became income for the bakufu, it was later on frequently unlawfully used to re-establish the bakufu finances.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially, the Muromachi bakufu was cautious about issuing Orders for the Acts of Virtuous Government, but in 1454, the bakufu issued &quot;Buichi-sen&quot;, &quot;Buichi Order for the Acts of Virtuous Government&quot;. &quot;Tokusei-buichi-sen&quot;, which ordered 10% of debt repayments to be paid to the government as a type of handling fee, and since this 10% of debt became income for the bakufu, it was later frequently used to unlawfully renew the bakufu finances.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially, the Muromachi bakufu was cautious about issuing Tokuseirei, but in 1454, the bakufu issued &quot;Buichi-sen,&quot; &quot;Buichi Tokuseirei,&quot; &quot;Tokusei-buichi-sen,&quot; which ordered 10% of debt repayments to be paid to the government as a type of handling fee, and since this 10% of debt became income for the bakufu, it was later frequently used to unlawfully renew the bakufu finances.</e>
<cmt>Tokuseireiに訂正しました。&quot;の位置訂正。,補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)においては、相模国の戦国大名である北条氏康が大飢饉の発生に際して北条氏政への家督相続を行い、「代初めの徳政」を行った事例があるなど、「代初めの徳政」が定着していたことをうかがい知ることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Warring States period (Japan), there is an example of the warring lord of Sagami-no-kuni (western Kanagawa), Ujiyasu HOJO, passed the position of family head to Ujimasa HOJO and started &quot;Tokusei upon head change&quot; when there was a great famine, suggesting that &quot;Tokusei upon head change&quot; was an established practice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Warring States period (Japan), there was a case where the lord of Sagami-no-kuni (western Kanagawa), Ujiyasu HOJO, passed the position of family head to Ujimasa HOJO and started &quot;Tokusei upon family head change&quot; when there was a great famine, suggesting that &quot;Tokusei upon family head change&quot; was an established practice.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Sengoku period (period of warring states), there was a case where the lord of Sagami Province (western Kanagawa), Ujiyasu HOJO, passed the position of family head to Ujimasa HOJO and started &apos;Tokusei upon family head change&apos; when there was a great famine, suggesting that &apos;Tokusei upon family head change&apos; was an established practice.</e>
<cmt>戦国時代→the Sengoku period (period of warring states)-no-kuni→Province に訂正しました。原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Law soma(id:45202), 水野白楓(id:22811), 表現等規制委員会(id:61918), Extrahitz(id:26245), Areare(id:119960), Nalc(id:139567), 伏儀(id:142093), 彩華1226(id:64711), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>