<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>御牧藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mimaki Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mimaki Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mimaki Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>御牧藩（みまきはん）は、山城国久世郡御牧（現在の京都府久世郡久御山町）に存在した藩。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mimaki Domain is a domain which was in Mimaki, Kuse-gun, Yamashiro Province (present-day Kumiyama-cho, Kuse-gun, Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mimaki Domain is a domain which was in Mimaki, Kuse-gun, Yamashiro Province (present-day Kumiyama-cho, Kuse-gun, Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mimaki Domain is a domain which was in Mimaki, Kuse County, Yamashiro Province (present-day Kumiyama-cho, Kuse-gun, Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>旧地名修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>藩主家は津田氏である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The head family of the domain was the Tsuda family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The head family of the domain was the Tsuda family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The head family of the domain was the Tsuda family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>津田信成は織田信長の一族で、信長没後は豊臣秀吉に仕えて山城御牧に1万3000石を領していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunari Tsuda was related to Nobunaga ODA&apos;s family, and after the death of Nobunaga, he served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and possessed a territory worth 13,000 koku (crop yields).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunari Tsuda was related to Nobunaga ODA&apos;s family, and after the death of Nobunaga, he served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and possessed a territory worth 13,000 koku (crop yields).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunari Tsuda was related to Nobunaga ODA&apos;s family, and after the death of Nobunaga, he served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and possessed a territory worth 13,000 koku (crop yields).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>秀吉没後は豊臣秀頼に仕えていたが、関ヶ原の戦い直前に徳川家康に急接近して東軍に与した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although after Hideyoshi died, he had been serving Hideyori, he made advances to Ieyasu TOKUGAWA just before the Battle of Sekigahara and joined the Eastern Army.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処をしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although after Hideyoshi died, he had been serving Hideyori, he made advances to Ieyasu TOKUGAWA just before the Battle of Sekigahara and joined the Eastern Army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although after Hideyoshi died, he had been serving Hideyori TOYOTOMI, he made advances to Ieyasu TOKUGAWA just before the Battle of Sekigahara and joined the Eastern Army.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>戦功を挙げたために所領を安堵され、存続を許された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As he successfully fought in the battle, he was approved of his territory and was permitted to continue his family line.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処をしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As he successfully fought in the battle, his territory was approved and he was permitted to continue his family line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As he successfully fought in the battle, his territory was approved and he was permitted to continue his family line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>しかし慶長12年（1607年）、美濃国清水藩の稲葉通重と共に京都の祇園に赴いたとき、茶屋の女房をはじめとする美女七十八名に乱暴狼藉を働いた経緯を家康に咎められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ieyasu, however, accused Nobunari Tsuda of the incident which, in 1607, he and Michishige INABA from Shimizu Domain of Mino Province, visited Gion in Kyogo and committed an outrage of sexually abusing 78 beautiful women including the female proprietor of the tea house.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処をしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ieyasu, however, accused Nobunari Tsuda of the incident which, in 1607, he and Michishige INABA from the Shimizu Domain of Mino Province, visited Gion in Kyogo and committed an outrage, sexually abusing seventy-eight beautiful women including the female proprietor of the tea house.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ieyasu, however, accused Nobunari TSUDA of the incident which, in 1607, he and Michishige INABA from the Shimizu Domain of Mino Province, visited Gion in Kyoto and committed an outrage, sexually abusing seventy-eight beautiful women including the female proprietor of the tea house.</e>
<cmt>人名修正スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そして御牧藩は改易されてしまったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, he was punished by being deprived of his fief, and Mimaki Domain became extinct.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処をしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, he was punished by being deprived of his fief, and the Mimaki Domain became extinct.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, he was punished by being deprived of his fief, and the Mimaki Domain became extinct.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), Reggaeman(id:6214), シェーラ(id:17988), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>