<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>京大天皇事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyodai-Tenno incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyodai-Tenno incident</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyodai-Tenno incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>京大天皇事件（きょうだいてんのうじけん）は、1951年11月12日の昭和天皇の京都大学来学に際し、キャンパスに押しかけた多数の学生との間で混乱が生じ、京大の学生自治会である同学会に解散処分などが下された事件である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyodai-Tenno incident was an incident in which disorder arose between the Emperor Showa who visited Kyoto University on November 12, 1951 and many students who gathered at the campus on the day, and Dogakukai, the student self-governing association of Kyoto University, was ordered to dissolve later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kyodai-Tenno incident was an incident in which disorder arose between the Emperor Showa who visited Kyoto University on November 12, 1951 and many students who gathered at the campus on that day, and Dogakukai, the student self-governing association of Kyoto University, was ordered to dissolve later.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kyodai-Tenno incident was an incident in which disorder arose between the Emperor Showa who visited Kyoto University on November 12, 1951 and many students who gathered at the campus on that day, and Dogakukai, the student self-governing association of Kyoto University, was ordered to dissolve later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「京大事件」とも称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called &quot;Kyodai incident&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called the &quot;Kyodai incident.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called the &quot;Kyodai incident.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Backgrounds</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>昭和天皇が関西地方巡幸の過程で京都市を訪れた1951年は、講和問題や賃上げ問題などをめぐって全般的に労働運動・学生運動が復活の動きを見せた年であり、京都でも労働運動が高揚していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1951, a year when the Emperor Showa visited Kyoto City during his tour in Kasai region, labor movement as well as student movement started to revive nationwide on the problems of peace treaty and wage increase, and labor movement was also vigorous in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1951, the year when the Emperor Showa visited Kyoto City during his tour in the Kasai region, the labor movement as well as the student movement started to revive nationwide on the problems of the peace treaty and wage increases, and the labor movement was also vigorous in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1951, the year when the Emperor Showa visited Kyoto City during his tour in the Kansai region, the labor movement as well as the student movement started to revive nationwide on the problems of the peace treaty and wage increases, and the labor movement was also vigorous in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Kasai→Kansai</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>京都入りした天皇の訪問先となっていた島津製作所三条工場では、訪問直前まで賃上げストが行われ（労資の紛争を天皇の目に触れさせたくない）関係者の気を揉ませた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Sanjo Works, Shimazu Corporation, one of the destination of the Emperor&apos;s visit, a strike demanding wage increase was conducted until just before the Emperor&apos;s vist and it had relevant people (who didn&apos;t want the scene of labor-management conflicts catch the eye of the Emperor) worried.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At Sanjo Works, Shimazu Corporation, one of the destinations of the Emperor&apos;s visit, a strike demanding wage increases was conducted until just before the Emperor&apos;s visit and it had relevant people (who didn&apos;t want a scene of labor-management conflicts to catch the eye of the Emperor) worried.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo, Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At Sanjo Works, Shimazu Corporation, one of the destinations of the Emperor&apos;s visit, a strike demanding wage increases was conducted until just before the Emperor&apos;s visit and it had relevant people (who didn&apos;t want a scene of labor-management conflicts to catch the eye of the Emperor) worried.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>天皇の訪問が同様に予定されていた京都市役所前の「組合掲示板」ではそうした事態を皮肉り、（天皇の巡幸が社会問題の存在を掃き出し隠蔽するという意味で）「天皇はほうきである」という大書がなされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the &quot;union signboard&quot; placed in front of Kyoto Municipal Office, which was also the destination of the Emperor&apos;s visit, a phrase saying &quot;the Emperor is a broom&quot; was written in large letters with sarcasm (in the sense that the Emperor&apos;s tour was intended to sweep out and conceal social problems).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the &quot;union signboard&quot; placed in front of the Kyoto Municipal Office, which was also the destination of the Emperor&apos;s visit, a phrase saying &quot;the Emperor is a broom&quot; was written in large letters with sarcasm (in the sense that the Emperor&apos;s tour was intended to sweep out and conceal social problems).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the &quot;union signboard&quot; placed in front of the Kyoto Municipal Office, which was also the destination of the Emperor&apos;s visit, a phrase saying &quot;the Emperor is a broom&quot; was written in large letters with sarcasm (in the sense that the Emperor&apos;s tour was intended to sweep out and conceal social problems).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>市当局は掲示板の撤去を要求、組合との間で徹夜交渉がもたれ、11月12日の天皇の来訪1時間前に目につかない場所に移すことで妥協が成立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The city authority requested to remove it, and after a night-long negotiation with the union, a compromise was reached, only one hour before the Emperor&apos;s visit scheduled on November 12, that it should be moved to an out-of-sight place.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The city authority requested it removed, and after a night-long negotiation with the union, a compromise was reached, only one hour before the Emperor&apos;s visit scheduled on November 12, that it would be moved to an out-of-sight place.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The city authority requested it removed, and after a night-long negotiation with the union, a compromise was reached, only one hour before the Emperor&apos;s visit scheduled on November 12, that it would be moved to an out-of-sight place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>市役所訪問後、天皇が進講を受けるため来学することが予定されていた京都大学でも、前年1950年以降、学生運動が高揚に向かっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the previous year 1950, student movement was on the rise at Kyoto University which the Emperor was scheduled to visit after the City office in order to have a briefing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Beginning the previous year in 1950, the student movement was on the rise at Kyoto University which the Emperor was scheduled to visit after the City office in order to have a briefing.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Beginning the previous year in 1950, the student movement was on the rise at Kyoto University which the Emperor was scheduled to visit after the City office in order to have a briefing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>全日本学生自治会総連合では少数派（非主流派）であった所感派の思想的・政治的影響下にあった当時の同学会（京都大学の全学学生自治会）は、1950年度のレッド・パージ粉砕闘争を主導した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dogakukai (students&apos; self-governing association of Kyoto University) which was under the philosophical/political influence of Shokan sect, a minority group (a non-mainstream faction) of All-Japan Federation of Students&apos; Self-governing Associations, played a leading role in the anti Red Purge struggle in 1950.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dogakukai (students&apos; self-governing association of Kyoto University) which was under the philosophical/political influence of the Shokan sect, a minority group (a non-mainstream faction) of the All-Japan Federation of Students&apos; Self-governing Associations, played a leading role in the anti Red Purge struggle in 1950.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dogakukai (students&apos; self-governing association of Kyoto University) which was under the philosophical/political influence of the Shokan sect, a minority group (a non-mainstream faction) of the All-Japan Federation of Students&apos; Self-governing Associations, played a leading role in the anti Red Purge struggle in 1950.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>これに対し大学当局（服部峻治郎学長）はすべての学生ストライキ禁止の措置で臨んだため、多くの処分学生を出すことになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In response, the authority of the university (president of the university Shunjiro HATTORI) banned students&apos; strike thoroughly and punished many students.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In response, the authority of the university (president of the university Shunjiro HATTORI) banned the students&apos; strike thoroughly and punished many students.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response, the authority of the university (president of the university Shunjiro HATTORI) banned the students&apos; strike thoroughly and punished many students.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>このため、1951年に入っても騒然とした学内状況が続いていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, the situation at the university was still tumultuous in 1951.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, the situation at the university was still tumultuous in 1951.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, the situation at the university was still tumultuous in 1951.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>同学会は天皇来学に際し、（当時の左翼勢力の主流がしていたように）天皇制反対を声高に訴えるのでなく「歓迎もしなければ拒否もしない」「（天皇を）一個人として迎える」という態度を取り、学生と天皇との会見を要求していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the Emperor&apos;s visit, Dogakukai took a position &quot;We will neither welcome nor reject his visit&quot; and &quot;We will receive (the Emperor) as an individual&quot;, rather than vociferously appealing the abolition of Imperial system (unlike other left-wing organizations which did so), and requested to meet the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the Emperor&apos;s visit, Dogakukai took a position of &quot;We will neither welcome nor reject his visit&quot; and &quot;We will receive (the Emperor) as an individual,&quot; rather than vociferously appealing the abolition of the Imperial system (unlike other left-wing organizations which did so), and requested to meet the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the Emperor&apos;s visit, Dogakukai took a position of &quot;We will neither welcome nor reject his visit&quot; and &quot;We will receive (the Emperor) as an individual,&quot; rather than vociferously appealing the abolition of the Imperial system (unlike other left-wing organizations which did so), and requested to meet the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>天皇の京大来学</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor&apos;s visit to Kyoto University</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor&apos;s visit to Kyoto University</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor&apos;s visit to Kyoto University</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>天皇の来学に先立ち、京大吉田（本部）キャンパスでは、2,000人にのぼる学生・教職員などが正門近くの本部（時計台）前広場（画像参照）に見物（あるいは歓迎）に押しかけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Kyoto University Yoshida (headquarter) campus, two thousands of students/school personnel gathered, before the arrival of the Emperor, at the open space in front of the university headquarter building (clock tower) (refer to a picture) in order to see (or welcome) the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At Kyoto University Yoshida (headquarter) campus, two thousand students/school personnel gathered, before the arrival of the Emperor, at an open space in front of the university headquarter building (clock tower) (refer to the picture) in order to see (or welcome) the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At Kyoto University Yoshida (headquarter) campus, two thousand students/school personnel gathered, before the arrival of the Emperor, at an open space in front of the university headquarter building (clock tower) (refer to the picture) in order to see (or welcome) the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>吉田分校（現在の総合人間学部キャンパス）の門前には縦3m・横2mに及ぶ「天皇へのお願い」と題された看板が立てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In front of the gate of Yoshida branch school (campus of the Faculty of Integrated Human Studies), a signboard, whose size was three meters long and two meters wide, stating &quot;Our pleas to the Emperor&quot; was put up.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In front of a gate at the Yoshida branch school (campus of the Faculty of Integrated Human Studies), a signboard, whose size was three meters long and two meters wide, stating &quot;Our pleas to the Emperor&quot; was put up.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In front of a gate at the Yoshida branch school (campus of the Faculty of Integrated Human Studies), a signboard, whose size was three meters long and two meters wide, stating &quot;Our pleas to the Emperor&quot; was put up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>この時、正門外で突然毎日新聞社の車が「君が代」を流したため、これに反発した学生の中から反戦歌「平和を守れ」の歌声が流れ、次第に大合唱となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, as a person on board a vehicle of The Mainichi Newspapers played &quot;Kimigayo&quot; (Japan&apos;s national anthem), some students who were offended by it started to sing an antiwar song &quot;Heiwa wo mamore&quot; (maintain peace) and many students joined force with them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, someone on board a vehicle for the Mainichi Newspapers played &quot;Kimigayo&quot; (Japan&apos;s national anthem), and some students who were offended by it started to sing an antiwar song &quot;Heiwa wo mamore&quot; (maintain peace) and many students joined forces with them.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, someone on board a vehicle for the Mainichi Newspapers played &quot;Kimigayo&quot; (Japan&apos;s national anthem), and some students who were offended by it started to sing an antiwar song &quot;Heiwa wo mamore&quot; (maintain peace) and many students joined forces with them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>騒然とした雰囲気のなか、正午過ぎの午後1時20分天皇は自動車に乗って到着し、進講のため本部の会議室に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor arrived by car at 1:20 pm in an atmosphere of disquiet and entered a conference room of headquarter building in order to have a briefing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor arrived by car at 1:20 pm in an atmosphere of disquiet and entered a conference room in the headquarters in order to have a briefing.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor arrived by car at 1:20 pm in an atmosphere of disquiet and entered a conference room in the headquarters in order to have a briefing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>進講者の一人である瀧川幸辰（のち京大学長）によれば、この時天皇制廃止を記したプラカードを掲げた学生たちが正面玄関に殺到する行動があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Yukitoki TAKIGAWA (he later became the president of Kyoto University), who was one of lecturers, students who were carrying a placard asserting the abolition of Imperial system rushed to the front entrance at this time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Yukitoki TAKIGAWA (he later became the president of Kyoto University), who was one of lecturers, students who were carrying a placard asserting the abolition of Imperial system rushed to the front entrance at this time.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Yukitoki TAKIGAWA (he later became the president of Kyoto University), who was one of lecturers, students who were carrying a placard asserting the abolition of Imperial system rushed to the front entrance at this time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>反戦歌の合唱は天皇が建物の中にいる最中ずっと続けられ、さらに学生が増えたため時計台前の群集は車の進路を塞ぐ形になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As students continued to sing the antiwar song while the Emperor was in the building and the number of students increased further, a large group of people gathered in front of the clock tower eventually blocked the root of Emperor&apos;s car.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As students continued to sing the antiwar song while the Emperor was in the building and the number of students increased further, a large group of people gathered in front of the clock tower and eventually blocked the Emperor&apos;s car.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As students continued to sing the antiwar song while the Emperor was in the building and the number of students increased further, a large group of people gathered in front of the clock tower and eventually blocked the Emperor&apos;s car.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>大学当局は大学から出ていく天皇のために進路を確保するべく警官隊を学内に導入した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The authority of the university asked for the dispatch of polce force to the campus in order to secure the root for the Emperor&apos;s departure.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The authority of the university asked for the dispatch of police force to the campus in order to secure the path for the Emperor&apos;s departure.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The authority of the university asked for the dispatch of police force to the campus in order to secure the path for the Emperor&apos;s departure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>これに抗議する学生の声と合唱の中で天皇は警官隊の人垣を通って午後2時過ぎに京大を去った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being surrounded by the students&apos; voice and song of protest, the Emperor left Kyoto University after 2 pm through the throng of policemen.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Being surrounded by the students&apos; voices and songs of protest, the Emperor left Kyoto University after 2 pm through a throng of policemen.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Being surrounded by the students&apos; voices and songs of protest, the Emperor left Kyoto University after 2 pm through a throng of policemen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>この間、（前記のプラカード学生の突出した行動を唯一の例外として）学生たちは天皇一行の出入りを遠巻きに合唱していただけで、特にこれを妨害する行動はとっていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the meantime, students (except for those who took a radical action while carrying the above-mentioned placard) were singing together while looking across at the Emperor&apos;s party and didn&apos;t take any actions to hinder them.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the meantime, students (except for those who took radical action while carrying the above-mentioned placards) were singing together while looking across at the Emperor&apos;s party and didn&apos;t take any actions to hinder them.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the meantime, students (except for those who took radical action while carrying the above-mentioned placards) were singing together while looking across at the Emperor&apos;s party and didn&apos;t take any actions to hinder them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>若干のもみ合いを除けば学生と警官隊との衝突（乱闘）というような事態はなかったため、一人の逮捕者も発生しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, as there were no clashes (brawls) between students and the police force with the exception of some jostles, no one was arrested.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, as there were no clashes (brawls) between students and the police force with the exception of some jostles, no one was arrested.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, as there were no clashes (brawls) between students and the police force with the exception of some jostles, no one was arrested.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>学生の「公開質問状」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Open letter&quot; of students</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Open letter&quot; from students</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Open letter&quot; from students</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>京都大学同学会は5ヵ条からなる「公開質問状」を作成し、天皇に渡すことを計画していたが拒否された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto University Dogakukai prepared the &quot;open letter&quot; of five points and planned to submit it to the Emperor, but its acceptance was rejected.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kyoto University Dogakukai prepared an &quot;open letter&quot; concerning five points and planned to submit it to the Emperor, but its acceptance was rejected.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kyoto University Dogakukai prepared an &quot;open letter&quot; concerning five points and planned to submit it to the Emperor, but its acceptance was rejected.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>「私達は一個の人間として貴方を見る時、同情に耐えません」で始まるこの質問状は、当時学生であった中岡哲郎（のち大阪市立大学教授）の執筆によるものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This open letter, which started with a phrase &quot;When we look at you as an individual human being, we cannot help but feel compassion&quot;, was written by a student Tetsuro Nakaoka (he later became a professor of Osaka City University).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This open letter, which started with the phrase &quot;When we look at you as an individual human being, we cannot help but feel compassion,&quot; was written by a student, Tetsuro Nakaoka (he later became a professor of Osaka City University).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This open letter, which started with the phrase &quot;When we look at you as an individual human being, we cannot help but feel compassion,&quot; was written by a student, Tetsuro Nakaoka (he later became a professor of Osaka City University).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>先述のように現実の社会矛盾が取り繕われ隠蔽されたなかで天皇が多額の公費により巡幸を行っていることを悲しむとともに、米軍占領下での再軍備や朝鮮戦争が進行していた当時の情勢を踏まえ、日本が戦争に巻き込まれそうになった時の対応などを問うものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this letter, students expressed sadness for the Emperor&apos;s tour on the ground that it was done using a big amount of tax while social problems were being glossed over and concealed, and based on the situation at the time where Japan&apos;s remilitarization was in progress under U.S. occupation and Korean War was becoming serious, they asked about Japan&apos;s attitude if it was on the verge of being dragged into the war.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this letter, students expressed sadness for the Emperor&apos;s tour on the ground that it was done using a big amount of tax money while social problems were being glossed over and concealed, and based on the situation at the time where Japan&apos;s re-militarization was in progress under U.S. occupation and the Korean War was becoming serious, they asked about Japan&apos;s attitude if it was on the verge of being dragged into the war.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this letter, students expressed sadness for the Emperor&apos;s tour on the ground that it was done using a big amount of tax money while social problems were being glossed over and concealed, and based on the situation at the time where Japan&apos;s re-militarization was in progress under U.S. occupation and the Korean War was becoming serious, they asked about Japan&apos;s attitude if it was on the verge of being dragged into the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>また「貴方が今又、単独講和と再軍備の日本でかつてと同じような戦争イデオロギーの一つの支柱としての役割を果たそうとしている」と、天皇の戦争責任や政治利用というタブーにも言及していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, they also mentioned about the Emperor&apos;s wartime responsibility as well as the political exploitation of the Emperor, which were under taboo, by saying &quot;You are now playing a role of propping up war ideology as you did in the past under the situation where Japan is planning to conclude seperate peace treaties and rearm itself&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, they also mentioned the Emperor&apos;s wartime responsibility as well as the political exploitation of the Emperor, which were taboo, by saying &quot;You are now playing a role of propping up war ideology as you did in the past under the situation where Japan is planning to conclude separate peace treaties and rearm itself.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, they also mentioned the Emperor&apos;s wartime responsibility as well as the political exploitation of the Emperor, which were taboo, by saying &quot;You are now playing a role of propping up war ideology as you did in the past under the situation where Japan is planning to conclude separate peace treaties and rearm itself.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>関係者の処分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Disciplinary action against persons involved</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Disciplinary action against persons involved</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Disciplinary action against persons involved</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>何ら暴力的な事件が起こっていなかったにもかかわらず、翌11月13日、衆議院文部委員会では、大学管理法案審議の過程で天野貞祐歴代の文部大臣がこの「事件」に言及した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there wasn&apos;t any act of violence, Minister for Education Teiyu AMANO mentioned about this &quot;incident&quot; on the next day, November 13, at the Lower House Education Committee in the process of the deliberation of the draft law of university administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there wasn&apos;t any acts of violence, the Minister for Education, Teiyu AMANO, mentioned this &quot;incident&quot; the next day, November 13, at the Lower House Education Committee in the process of the deliberation of the draft law of the university administration.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there wasn&apos;t any acts of violence, the Minister for Education, Teiyu AMANO, mentioned this &quot;incident&quot; the next day, November 13, at the Lower House Education Committee in the process of the deliberation of the draft law of the university administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>大学当局は11月15日に同学会の解散命令を下し、11月18日には同学会幹部8名の無期限停学処分を発表した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The authority of university ordered the dissolution of Dogakukai on November 15, and indefinitely suspended eight executives of Dogakukai from the university on November 18.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The authority of the university ordered the dissolution of the Dogakukai on November 15, and indefinitely suspended eight executives of the Dogakukai from the university on November 18.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The authority of the university ordered the dissolution of the Dogakukai on November 15, and indefinitely suspended eight executives of the Dogakukai from the university on November 18.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>来学当日、群集整理に協力しむしろ混乱を鎮める側に回っていた同学会に厳しい処分が下されたのは、先述した公開質問状の内容と、それに対する世論の反発（後述）を考慮したことによるものと考えられている（解散された同学会は1953年に再建された）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that Dogakukai, which cooperated to regulate crowd and restore quiet on the day of Emperor&apos;s visit, was punished severely because of the content of open letter mentioned above and the backlash in public opinion (Dogakukai was reconstructed in 1953).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that the Dogakukai, which cooperated to regulate the crowd and restore quiet on the day of Emperor&apos;s visit, was punished severely because of the content of the open letter mentioned above and the backlash in public opinion (Dogakukai was reconstructed in 1953).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that the Dogakukai, which cooperated to regulate the crowd and restore quiet on the day of Emperor&apos;s visit, was punished severely because of the content of the open letter mentioned above and the backlash in public opinion (Dogakukai was reconstructed in 1953).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>11月26日には衆議院法務委員会に服部学長と同学会委員長が喚問される事態となり、政府（第3次吉田内閣）および与党自由党はこの事件をきっかけに大学への警官の自由な立ち入りを認めさせようと画策した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The president of the university Hattori and the chairman of Dogakukai were summoned to Lower House Judicial Affairs Committee on November 26, and the Government (the third Yoshida cabinet) and ruling Liberal Party planned, taking advantage of this incident, to make it possible for the police to enter a university campus freely.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The president of the university Hattori and the chairman of the Dogakukai were summoned to the Lower House Judicial Affairs Committee on November 26, and the Government (the third Yoshida cabinet) and the ruling Liberal Party planned, taking advantage of this incident, to make it possible for the police to enter the university campus freely.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The president of the university Hattori and the chairman of the Dogakukai were summoned to the Lower House Judicial Affairs Committee on November 26, and the Government (the third Yoshida cabinet) and the ruling Liberal Party planned, taking advantage of this incident, to make it possible for the police to enter the university campus freely.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>また京都地方検察庁は公安条例違反による関係者の起訴を考えていたが、関係者を取り調べた結果、条例に違反するような事件は発生していないとみなし立件を断念した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kyoto District Public Prosecutors Office studied the possibility of prosecuting them for the violation of Public Safety Regulations, but after investigating relevant personnel, it found no violation and gave up prosecution.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kyoto District Public Prosecutors Office studied the possibility of prosecuting them for the violation of Public Safety Regulations, but after investigating relevant personnel, it found no violation and gave up prosecution.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kyoto District Public Prosecutors Office studied the possibility of prosecuting them for the violation of Public Safety Regulations, but after investigating relevant personnel, it found no violation and gave up prosecution.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>当時の反応</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Public opinion at the time</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Public opinion at the time</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Public opinion at the time</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="31">
<j>この事件と同じ1951年、同学会を中心に京大生が企画・開催した「綜合原爆展 (京大)」は盛況を呼び、京都市民から好意的に迎えられていた（「質問状」でも天皇の原爆展参観を要望している）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1951, the same year with this incident, students of Kyoto university with Dogakukai in the center held &quot;The synthetic exhibition of A-bomb (Kyoto University)&quot;, and it attracted many people and was favorably received by the citizens of Kyoto (in the open letter, they asked the Emperor to visit A-bomb exhibition).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1951, the same year as this incident, students of Kyoto university with the Dogakukai in the center held &quot;The synthetic exhibition of the A-bomb (Kyoto University),&quot; and it attracted many people and was favorably received by the citizens of Kyoto (in the open letter, they asked the Emperor to visit the A-bomb exhibition).</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1951, the same year as this incident, students of Kyoto university with the Dogakukai in the center held &quot;The synthetic exhibition of the A-bomb (Kyoto University),&quot; and it attracted many people and was favorably received by the citizens of Kyoto (in the open letter, they asked the Emperor to visit the A-bomb exhibition).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>そして事件後、作家野間宏は同学会宛にメッセージを寄せ、学生たちの「行動の正しさ」を讃えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the incident, novelist Hiroshi NOMA sent a message to Dogakukai and acclaimed &quot;right action&quot; of students.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the incident, novelist Hiroshi NOMA sent a message to the Dogakukai and acclaimed the &quot;right actions&quot; of the students.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the incident, novelist Hiroshi NOMA sent a message to the Dogakukai and acclaimed the &quot;right actions&quot; of the students.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>しかしこの事件に関して京大生や同学会に対する好意的反応は少数派であり、「京大を廃校にせよ」「貴方たちは狂人ですか」といった非難が集中した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the number of people who were in favor of the students of Kyoto University and Dogakukai concerning this incident was relatively small, and many people condemned them by saying &quot;Abolish Kyoto University&quot; or &quot;Are you madmen ?&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the number of people who were in favor of the students of Kyoto University and the Dogakukai concerning this incident were relatively small, and many people condemned them by saying &quot;Abolish Kyoto University&quot; or &quot;Are you madmen?&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the number of people who were in favor of the students of Kyoto University and the Dogakukai concerning this incident were relatively small, and many people condemned them by saying &quot;Abolish Kyoto University&quot; or &quot;Are you madmen?&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>特に11月13日付で「天皇への無礼と京大の責任」なる論説を掲載した京都新聞を初めとして新聞は学生側を強く非難し、常軌を逸した「不敬罪」であるかのように書き立てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially, newspapers strongly condemned students as if they committed &quot;lese majesty&quot;, including Kyoto Shimbun which posted the article &quot; Disrespect for the Emperor and Kyoto University&apos;s responsibility &quot; on November 13.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially, newspapers strongly condemned students as if they committed &quot;lese majesty,&quot; including Kyoto Shimbun which posted the article &quot;Disrespect for the Emperor and Kyoto University&apos;s responsibility&quot; on November 13.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially, newspapers strongly condemned students as if they committed &quot;lese majesty,&quot; including Kyoto Shimbun which posted the article &quot;Disrespect for the Emperor and Kyoto University&apos;s responsibility&quot; on November 13.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>このため、京都市民の反応はおおむね厳しいものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, reaction of Kyoto citizens was unfavorable to students largely.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, the reaction of Kyoto citizens was unfavorable to students largely.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, the reaction of Kyoto citizens was unfavorable to students largely.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>事件を扱った作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A literary work which dealt with the incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A literary work which dealt with the incident</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A literary work which dealt with the incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="36">
<j>城山三郎『大義の末』1959年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saburo SHIROYAMA &quot;Taiginosue&quot; 1959</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saburo SHIROYAMA &quot;Taiginosue&quot; 1959</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saburo SHIROYAMA &quot;Taiginosue&quot; 1959</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>「公開質問状」執筆者の中岡哲郎とほぼ同世代の作家である城山の自伝的小説。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is an autographical novel written by Shiroyama, a novelist of the same generation with Tetsuro NAKAOAKA, a writer of the &quot;open letter&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is an autobiographical novel written by Shiroyama, a novelist of the same generation as Tetsuro NAKAOAKA, an author of the &quot;open letter.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is an autobiographical novel written by Shiroyama, a novelist of the same generation as Tetsuro NAKAOAKA, an author of the &quot;open letter.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>質問状の内容について言及がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Remarks concerning the open letter are seen in this novel.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Remarks concerning the open letter are seen in this novel.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Remarks concerning the open letter are seen in this novel.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Straysheep(id:42448), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>