<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>在家役</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Zaike-Yaku&quot; (The Tax And The Labor Imposed In Medieval Japan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Zaike-Yaku&quot; (The Tax And The Labor Imposed In Medieval Japan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Zaike-Yaku&quot; (The Tax And The Labor Imposed In Medieval Japan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>在家役（ざいけやく）とは、中世において在家を収取単位として賦課された租税のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Zaike-yaku&quot; refers to the tax and the labor that were imposed per &quot;zaike&quot; in medieval Japan.</e>
<cmt>・他のセルの内容を見ると（例えばセル12）、「租税」のみならず「労役」も賦課されたので（注・・・「労役」は概念として「租税」とは区別される）、原文2行目の「租税」のあとに「及び労役」と補って訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Zaike-yaku&quot; refers to the tax and the labor that were imposed per &quot;zaike&quot; in medieval Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Zaike-yaku&quot; refers to the tax and the labor that were imposed per &quot;zaike&quot; in medieval Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>在家とは荘園・公領における住屋と付属する宅地・田畠・住人を1つの収取単位として扱ったものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And &quot;zaike&quot; refers to an unit of taxation and labor-enforcement, which was made up of a house and its premises, the nearby paddy and field, and the inhabitants, all of which existed in both &quot;shoen&quot; (a manor, or a private estate) and &quot;koryo&quot; (public land).</e>
<cmt>・当時、「荘園」は大寺社・有力貴族が租税徴収権を有するに至っており、要は「私有地」だったと言えます。・他方、「公領」はあくまで国司の支配下に置かれていたのであり、要は「公有地」だったと言えます。・「住屋と付属する宅地・田畠・住人」については、「家屋とその敷地、及びこれに隣接する田畠、住人」の意味に解しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And &quot;zaike&quot; refers to an unit of taxation and labor-enforcement, which was made up of a house and its premises, the nearby paddy and field, and the inhabitants, all of which existed in both &quot;shoen&quot; (a manor, or a private estate) and &quot;koryo&quot; (public land).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And &quot;zaike&quot; refers to an unit of taxation and labor-enforcement, which was made up of a house and its premises, the nearby paddy and field, and the inhabitants, all of which existed in both &quot;shoen&quot; (a manor, or a private estate) and &quot;koryo&quot; (public land).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>平安時代後期に成立した年貢・公事・夫役を徴収するために、名田単位でそれらの賦課が行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the later Heian period, the system of &quot;nengu&quot; (land tax), &quot;kuji&quot; (public duties/temporary taxes), and &quot;bueki&quot; (compulsory service) was established, and their imposition was done per &quot;myoden&quot; (the farming land that served as the unit of taxation and labor-enforcement in those days).</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処　・「公事」については、「労役」を内容とするものと、「臨時に課される税（畑作物等）」の2種類があったようです。・「名田」については「当時（平安後期）、租税・労役の賦課単位とされた農地」と解説しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the later Heian period, the system of &quot;nengu&quot; (land tax), &quot;kuji&quot; (public duties/temporary taxes), and &quot;bueki&quot; (compulsory service) was established, and their imposition was done per &quot;myoden&quot; (the farming land that served as the unit of taxation and labor-enforcement in those days).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the later Heian period, the system of &quot;nengu&quot; (land tax), &quot;kuji&quot; (public duties/temporary taxes), and &quot;bueki&quot; (compulsory service) was established, and their imposition was done per &quot;myoden&quot; (the farming land that served as the unit of taxation and labor-enforcement in those days).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>しかし名田が確立できなかった地域や、供御人・神人など名田体系では把握できなかった人々が存在したので、これらに対しても年貢などを賦課するために、在家を単位として収取したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the myoden system could not catch hold of some areas, nor could it of some people, such as &quot;kugonin&quot; (privileged people who contributed provisions to the emperor) and &quot;jinin&quot; (associates of Shinto shrines), so instead, zaike was newly introduced as the unit of taxation and labor enforcement in order to seize those areas and people.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the myoden system could not catch hold of some areas, nor could it catch hold of some people, such as &quot;kugonin&quot; (privileged people who contributed provisions to the emperor) and &quot;jinin&quot; (associates of Shinto shrines), so instead, zaike was newly introduced as the unit of taxation and labor enforcement in order to seize those areas and people.</e>
<cmt>repeated words for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the myoden system could not catch hold of some areas, nor could it catch hold of some people, such as &quot;kugonin&quot; (privileged people who contributed provisions to the emperor) and &quot;jinin&quot; (associates of Shinto shrines), so instead, zaike was newly introduced as the unit of taxation and labor enforcement in order to seize those areas and people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>更に12世紀の公領においては実際は公領に居住しながら、表面上は荘民身分を得て国衙からの税負担を逃れようとする農民がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, in the 12th century, there existed some farmers who tried to evade the tax from &quot;kokuga&quot; (provincial government offices) by disguising themselves as &quot;shokan&quot; (people living in a manor, who were exemt from the tax), though they lived in koryo in reality.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, in the 12th century, there existed some farmers who tried to evade the tax from &quot;kokuga&quot; (provincial government offices) by disguising themselves as &quot;shokan&quot; (people living in a manor, who were exempt from the tax), although in reality they lived in koryo.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, in the 12th century, there existed some farmers who tried to evade the tax from &quot;kokuga&quot; (provincial government offices) by disguising themselves as &quot;shokan&quot; (people living in a manor, who were exempt from the tax), although in reality they lived in koryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>彼らから確実に収取するためにも、在家制度が導入されたのである（反対に荘園側でも同様の賦課を行った）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the purposes of introducing zaike system was to make sure of those farmers&apos; tax payment, and similar tax imposition was begun in the shoen.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the purposes of introducing the zaike system was to make sure of those farmers&apos; tax payment, and similar tax imposition was begun in the shoen.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the purposes of introducing the zaike system was to make sure of those farmers&apos; tax payment, and similar tax imposition was begun in the shoen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>在家役は桑・苧・絹・漆などの畠作物や夫役形式で課されることが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In most cases, zaike-yaku was imposed in the form of bueki, or in the form of the tax on crops grown in fields, such as mulberry, Boehmeria nipononivea (a fiber material for clothing), silk, and lacquer.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In most cases, zaike-yaku was imposed in the form of bueki, or in the form of the tax on crops grown in fields, such as mulberry, Boehmeria nipononivea (a fiber material for clothing), silk, and lacquer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In most cases, zaike-yaku was imposed in the form of bueki, or in the form of the tax on crops grown in fields, such as mulberry, Boehmeria nipononivea (a fiber material for clothing), silk, and lacquer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>一方、田畠の少ない山地河海周辺や都市部では、住屋や宅地に対する地子（賃借料）を名目とした在家地子（ざいけじし）が賦課されて鮎・薪・炭などの非農業生産物が課された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, in areas that were scarce in paddies and fields - such as a mountainous district, a riverside area, a coastal area, and a merchant district - &quot;jishi&quot; (a kind of a rent, called &quot;zaike-jishi&quot;) was imposed on a house and its premises, and people were also obliged to provide non-agricultural products, such as sweetfish, firewood and charcoal.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, in areas that were scarce in paddies and fields - such as mountainous districts, riverside areas, coastal areas, and merchant districts - &quot;jishi&quot; (a kind of rent, called &quot;zaike-jishi&quot;) was imposed on a house and its premises, and people were also obliged to provide non-agricultural products, such as sweetfish, firewood, and charcoal.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, in areas that were scarce in paddies and fields - such as mountainous districts, riverside areas, coastal areas, and merchant districts - &quot;jishi&quot; (a kind of rent, called &quot;zaike-jishi&quot;) was imposed on a house and its premises, and people were also obliged to provide non-agricultural products, such as sweetfish, firewood, and charcoal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>更に、荘園領主の居住地から遠い地方では金銭や軽貨など運搬が簡易な物が望まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the owner of shoen who lived far away from it wanted the shoen residents to bring money or other light freight that was easy to transport.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The owner of a shoen who lived far away from it wanted the shoen residents to bring money or other light freight that was easy to transport.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;and&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The owner of a shoen who lived far away from it wanted the shoen residents to bring money or other light freight that was easy to transport.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>反対に近い地方では夫役や大量のかさばる品物などが収取され易かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrast, the owner of shoen who lived near to it tended to want the shoen residents to offer bueki or a huge amount of bulky goods and the like.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast, the owner of a shoen who lived nearby it tended to want the shoen residents to offer bueki or a huge amount of bulky goods and the like.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast, the owner of a shoen who lived nearby it tended to want the shoen residents to offer bueki or a huge amount of bulky goods and the like.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>南北朝時代 (日本)以後になると、在家役・在家地子とも屋敷年貢化して銭納が一般的な収取形態となっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the period of the Northern and Southern Courts, zaike-yaku became a kind of a rent just like zaike-jishi, so it became common for zaike-yaku to be paid in cash.</e>
<cmt>・「屋敷年貢化して」ですが、「賃料化して」の意味に解しています。・またセル13にあるように在家地子の方はもともと「賃料」に近かったわけですから、ここのセルの言わんとするところも「在家役も在家地子のように屋敷年貢化して」であると解されます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the period of the Northern and Southern Courts, zaike-yaku became a kind of a rent just like zaike-jishi, so it became common for zaike-yaku to be paid in cash.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the period of the Northern and Southern Courts, zaike-yaku became a kind of a rent just like zaike-jishi, so it became common for zaike-yaku to be paid in cash.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>