<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>日本外史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nihon Gaishi (historical book on Japan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nihon Gaishi (historical book on Japan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nihon Gaishi (historical book on Japan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>日本外史（にほんがいし）とは、江戸時代、頼山陽が著作した日本の歴史書。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nihon Gaishi is a historical book on Japan written by Sanyo RAI in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nihon Gaishi is a historical book on Japan, written by Sanyo RAI in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>カンマを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nihon Gaishi is a historical book on Japan, written by Sanyo RAI in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>文政10年（1827年）に山陽と親しかった松平定信（元老中）に進呈、2年後に発行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The book was presented to Sadanobu MATSUDAIRA (former roju [senior councilor]) who was close to Sanyo in 1827 and published two years later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The book was presented to Sadanobu MATSUDAIRA (former roju [senior councilor]) who was close to Sanyo in 1827, and published two years later.</e>
<cmt>カンマを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The book was presented to Sadanobu MATSUDAIRA (former roju [senior councilor]) who was close to Sanyo in 1827, and published two years later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>全二十二巻、漢文体で書かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The book is made up of 22 volumes and written in classical Chinese.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The book is made up of 22 volumes and written in classical Chinese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The book is made up of 22 volumes and written in classical Chinese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>現在では書き下し体（文語体）に直された岩波文庫上中下巻が刊行している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, three-volume Iwanami paperback edition which is transcription of Chinese classics into Japanese (bungotai [Japanese literary style]) has been published.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present, three-volume Iwanami paperback edition which changed the Chinese classics into Japanese (bungotai [Japanese literary style]) has been published.</e>
<cmt>is transcription of→changed the と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present, three-volume Iwanami paperback edition which changed the Chinese classics into Japanese (bungotai [Japanese literary style]) has been published.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また「巻十四の織田氏」までの数篇が現代語訳で、「頼山陽　日本の名著20」中央公論新社で出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, several books up to &quot;Volume 14, ODA clan&quot; are published in modern Japanese by Chuokoron-shinsha, Inc. under the title of &quot;Sanyo RAI Nihon no Meicho [Japanese classic] volume 20.&quot;</e>
<cmt>中央公論新社のHPでは「頼山陽　日本の名著28巻」となっていますが、原文の通り訳出しています。「名著」は定訳不明でしたので&quot;classic&quot;としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, several books up to &quot;Volume 14, the Oda clan&quot; are published in modern Japanese by Chuokoron-shinsha, Inc. under the title of &quot;Sanyo RAI Nihon no Meicho [Japanese classic] volume 20.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ODA→the Oda と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, several books up to &quot;Volume 14, the Oda clan&quot; are published in modern Japanese by Chuokoron-shinsha, Inc. under the title of &quot;Sanyo RAI Nihon no Meicho [Japanese classic] volume 20.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>平安時代末期の清和源氏・桓武平氏の争いから始まり、北条氏・楠木氏・新田氏・足利氏・毛利氏・後北条氏・武田氏・上杉氏・織田氏・豊臣氏・徳川氏までの諸氏の歴史を、武家の興亡を中心に家系ごとに分割されて（列伝体）書かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The book is started from the battle between Seiwa-Genji (MINAMOTO clan) and Kanmu-Heishi (TAIRA clan) in the end of Heian period, and the history of various clans, from HOJO clan, KUSUNOKI clan, NITTA clan, ASHIKAGA clan, MORI clan, GOHOJO clan, TAKEDA clan, UESUGI clan, ODA clan, TOYOTOMI clan, to TOKUGAWA clan is described focusing on the rise and fall of buke (warriors) by dividing the story into each family line (biographical style.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The book is started from the battle between Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan) and Kanmu-Heishi (Taira clan) in the end of Heian period, and the history of various clans, from the Hojo clan, the Kusunoki clan, the Nitta clan, the Ashikaga clan, the Mori clan, the Gohojo clan, the Takeda clan, the Uesugi clan, the Oda clan, the Toyotomi clan, to the Tokugawa clan is described focusing on the rise and fall of the samurai families by dividing the story into each family line (Biographical style.)</e>
<cmt>名字は最初の文字だけ大文字にし、それぞれthe を補いました。「武家」の部分を修正しました。最後のカッコ内を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The book is started from the battle between Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan) and Kanmu-Heishi (Taira clan) in the end of Heian period, and the history of various clans, from the Hojo clan, the Kusunoki clan, the Nitta clan, the Ashikaga clan, the Mori clan, the Gohojo clan, the Takeda clan, the Uesugi clan, the Oda clan, the Toyotomi clan, to the Tokugawa clan is described focusing on the rise and fall of the samurai families by dividing the story into each family line (Biographical style.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>簡明な叙述であり、情熱的な文章であった為に広く愛読されたが、参考史料として軍記物語なども用いているため、歴史的事実に忠実であるとは言いがたい記事も散見する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concise descriptions and enthusiastic sentences were very popular, however, it used tales of war as reference historical materials and there are some articles found, which are hard to say to be true to the historic facts.</e>
<cmt>「参考史料」となっているのは「参考資料」の間違いのようでもありますが、&quot;reference historical materials&quot;としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concise descriptions and enthusiastic sentences were very popular, however, it used those war chronicles and so on as reference historical materials and there are some articles found, which are hard to say to be true to the historical facts.</e>
<cmt>「軍記物語など」の部分を修正しました。historic→historical と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concise descriptions and enthusiastic sentences were very popular, however, it used those war chronicles and so on as reference historical materials and there are some articles found, which are hard to say to be true to the historical facts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>言い換えれば、史伝小説の源流の一つと言い得る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, the book can be said one of the sources of a story based on historical materials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, the book can be said one of the origins of those novels that are based on historical materials.</e>
<cmt>「史伝小説の源流」という部分を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, the book can be said one of the origins of those novels that are based on historical materials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>幕末の尊皇攘夷運動や勤王に大きな影響を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The book greatly affected &quot;Revere the Emperor and expel the barbarians&quot; movement and loyalty to the Emperor in the end of Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The book greatly influenced the &quot;Revere the Emperor and expel the barbarians&quot; movement and loyalty to the Emperor in the end of Edo period.</e>
<cmt>affected→influenced,the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The book greatly influenced the &quot;Revere the Emperor and expel the barbarians&quot; movement and loyalty to the Emperor in the end of Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Higashi(id:8842), Rai koku(id:1661), NIKE(id:16342), きゅうり(id:2182), Johncapistrano(id:969), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>