<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>寧波の乱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Neiha War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ningbo War</e>
<cmt>&quot;Neiha&quot; &gt; &quot;Ningbo&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ningbo War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>寧波の乱（にんぽーのらん・ねいはのらん）とは、1523年（日本では室町時代の大永3年、明では嘉靖2年）に、明の寧波において日本人が起した事件である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Neiha War is an incident carried out by Japanese nationals in Neiha, China in the Ming period in 1523.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ningbo War was an incident caused by Japanese nationals in Ningha in Ming Dynasty China in 1523.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Neiha&quot; &gt; &quot;Ningbo&quot;&quot;carried out&quot; &gt; &quot;caused&quot;&quot;, China in the Ming period&quot; &gt; &quot;in Ming Dynasty China&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ningbo War (also referred as Neiha War) was an incident caused by Japanese nationals in Ningbo in Ming Dynasty China in 1523.</e>
<cmt>別読みを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>寧波争貢事件、明州の乱、宗設の乱。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also called the Neiha incident, the Meishu War, and the Sosetsu War.</e>
<cmt>「寧波争貢事件」の読み方を確認することができませんでしたので、the Neiha incidentと仮訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also known as the Ningbo Incident, the Mingzhou War and the Sosetsu War.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Neiha&quot; &gt; &quot;Ningbo&quot;&quot;Meishu&quot; &gt; &quot;Mingzhou&quot;Deleted comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also known as the Ningbo Incident, the Mingzhou War and the Sosetsu War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>日明貿易</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The trade between Japan and the Ming Dynasty in China</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Trade between Japan and Ming Dynasty China</e>
<cmt>Title caseDeleted &quot;The&quot;&quot;the Ming Dynasty in China&quot; &gt; &quot;Ming Dynasty China&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Trade between Japan and Ming Dynasty China</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>日本の室町幕府と中国の明朝との間で行われた日明貿易（勘合貿易）は、室町初期の幕府3代将軍足利義満、明の建文帝の頃に開始された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The trade between the Muromachi bakufu in Japan and the Ming Dynasty in China (the tally trade (between Japan and the Ming dynasty)) started at the time when the 3rd Shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA of the early Muromachi bakufu governed Japan, and Kenbun-tei (Jianwen Emperor) governed China.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japan-Ming trade (tally trade) between the Muromachi bakufu (feudal government headed by a shogun) in Japan and the Ming Dynasty in China began around the time when the 3rd Shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA of the early Muromachi bakufu governed Japan and Emperor Jianwen ruled China.</e>
<cmt>&quot;trade&quot; &gt; &quot;Japan-Ming trade (tally trade)&quot;Added &quot;(feudal government headed by a shogun)&quot;Deleted &quot;(the tally trade (between Japan and the Ming dynasty))&quot;&quot;started&quot; &gt; &quot;began&quot;&quot;at the time&quot; &gt; &quot;around the time&quot;&quot;Kenbun-tei (Jianwen Emperor)&quot; &gt; &quot;Emperor Jianwen&quot;&quot;governed&quot; &gt; &quot;ruled&quot;Deleted commaDeleted spaces after full-stop</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japan-Ming trade (tally trade) between the Muromachi bakufu (feudal government headed by a shogun) in Japan and the Ming Dynasty in China began around the time when the third Shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA of the early Muromachi bakufu governed Japan and Emperor Jianwen ruled China.</e>
<cmt>スペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>明が海禁政策を行っている事情から足利将軍家の幕府将軍が「日本国王」として冊封した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because the Ming dynasty adopted Kaikin Policy (the policy to forbid private people to trade with foreign countries), the Shogun of the Ashikaga Shogun Family was given sakuho (homage by the Chinese emperor).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the Ming Dynasty adopted the haijin policy (a ban on maritime activities), the shogun of the Ashikaga Shogun Family was granted the title of &apos;King of Japan&apos; by the emperor of China.</e>
<cmt>&quot;dynasty&quot; &gt; &quot;Dynasty&quot;&quot;Kaikin Policy (the policy to forbid private people to trade with foreign countries)&quot; &gt; &quot;haijin policy (a ban on maritime activities)&quot;&quot;Shogun&quot; &gt; &quot;shogun&quot;&quot;given sakuho (homage by the Chinese emperor)&quot; &gt; &quot;granted the title of &apos;King of Japan&apos; by the emperor of China&quot;Deleted spaces after full-stop</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the Ming Dynasty adopted the haijin policy (a ban on maritime activities), the shogun of the Ashikaga Shogun Family was granted the title of &apos;King of Japan&apos; by the emperor of China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>倭寇と区別するため勘合符を発行して相手を承認する朝貢形態で行われ、十年一朝など制限がされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to distinguish from wako (Japanese pirates), approval was given with the issue of kangofu (a certificate to show that the ship was lawfully registered by Ming) in return for tribute, and restrictions were imposed like Junen Iccho (ten years for the reign of one dynasty).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「十年一朝」のJunen Iccho (ten years for the reign of one dynasty)は、仮訳です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to distinguish legitimate traders from wako (Japanese pirates), a kangofu (certificate to show that the ship is lawfully registered by Ming) was issued in return for a tribute, and restrictions such as a limit of ten years per dynasty were imposed.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to distinguish legitimate traders from wako (Japanese pirates), a kangofu (certificate to show that the ship is lawfully registered by Ming) was issued in return for a tribute, and restrictions such as a limit of ten years per dynasty were imposed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>幕府が派遣する使節には博多や堺市などの有力日本商人が随行し、その間で私的な貿易が行われていた</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Missions dispatched by the bakufu were accompanied by Japanese influential merchants of Hakata and Sakai City, and private trade was conducted among them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Missions dispatched by the bakufu were accompanied by influential Japanese merchants from Hakata and Sakai City, and private trade was conducted among them.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Japanese influential&quot; &gt; &quot;influential Japanese&quot;&quot;of&quot; &gt; &quot;from&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Missions dispatched by the bakufu were accompanied by influential Japanese merchants from Hakata and Sakai City, and private trade was conducted among them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>乱の背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Background of the war</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background of the War</e>
<cmt>Title case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>足利将軍家の家督争いなどから1467年に応仁の乱が起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Onin War occurred in 1467 because of the succession dispute of the Ashikaga Shogun Family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Onin War broke out in 1467 due to a succession dispute within the Ashikaga Shogun Family.</e>
<cmt>&quot;occurred&quot; &gt; &quot;broke out&quot;&quot;because of the&quot; &gt; &quot;due to a&quot;&quot;of&quot; &gt; &quot;within&quot;Deleted spaces after full-stop</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Onin War broke out in 1467 due to a succession dispute within the Ashikaga Shogun Family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>そして幕府の管領家で堺を貿易の拠点にしていた細川氏や、山口市を本拠に博多、応仁の乱で得た兵庫などに権益を持っていた大内氏がそれぞれ独自に使節団を派遣した貿易を経営をはじめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, the Hosokawa clan that was the Kanryo Family (the family in control) of the bakufu and conducted trade from Sakai, and the Ouchi clan that had interests in Yamaguchi City, Hakata and Hyogo, which came under the control of the Ouchi clan after the Onin War, started trading separately and dispatched each delegation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hosokawa clan, which was a kanryo family (family in the position of the shogunal deputy) and conducted trade from Sakai, and the Ouchi clan, which had interests in the areas of Yamaguchi City, Hakata and Hyogo that they obtained during the Onin War, each conducted trading separately and dispatched their own delegations.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read more naturally and use correct terminology.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hosokawa clan, who was a kanrei family (family in the position of the shogunal deputy) and conducted trade from Sakai, and the Ouchi clan based in Yamaguchi City, who had interests in Hakata, and Hyogo that they obtained during the Onin War, each conducted trading separately and dispatched their own delegations.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>大内と細川は勘合符を巡って対立していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ouchi clan and the Hosokawa clan started to oppose with each other around kangofu (a certificate to show that the ship was lawfully registered by Ming).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ouchi clan and Hosokawa clan were opposed to one another over kangofu.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ouchi clan and the Hosokawa clan were opposed to one another over kangofu.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>明で正徳帝（武宗）が即位し、大内氏が遣明船（勘合船）を主催して発行された正徳勘合符を独占する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Seitoku Emperor (Buso) ascended the throne in the Ming Dynasty, and the Ouchi clan sponsored the Envoy Ship Dispatched to Ming China (kangosen), and monopolized Seitoku-kangofu which was issued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Emperor Zhengde (Wuzong) ascended the Ming Dynasty throne, the Ouchi clan sponsored the kenminsen (envoy ship dispatched to Ming Dynasty China) and monopolize all Zhengde kangofu which were issued.</e>
<cmt>Retranslated to better reflect source text.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Emperor Zhengde (Wuzong) ascended the Ming Dynasty throne, the Ouchi clan sponsored the kenminsen (namely, Kangosen, the envoy ship dispatched to Ming Dynasty China) and monopolize all Zhengde kangofu which were issued.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>1523年、大内義興は謙道宗設（けんどうそうせつ）を正使に遣明船を派遣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1523, Yoshioki OUCHI dispatched an envoy ship called Kenminsen to Ming China with Sosetsu KENDO as seishi (a senior envoy).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1523, Yoshioki OUCHI dispatched a kenminsen to Ming Dynasty China with Sosetsu KENDO as seishi (senior envoy).</e>
<cmt>&quot;an envoy ship called Kenminsen&quot; &gt; &quot;a kenminsen&quot;Added &quot;Dynasty&quot;Deleted &quot;a&quot;Deleted spaces after full-stop</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1523, Yoshioki OUCHI dispatched a kenminsen to Ming Dynasty China with Sosetsu KENDO as seishi (senior envoy).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>そうすると細川高国が対抗して鸞岡端佐（らんこうずいさ）を正使、宋素卿（朱縞）を副使として、既に無効となった弘治勘合符を持たせて南海経由で遣明船を派遣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Takakuni HOSOKAWA, being in rivalry with OUCHI, dispatched Kenminsen via Nankai with Zuisa RANKO, as a senior envoy, and Sosokei (Shuko), as a vice-envoy, having expired Kochi-kangofu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In opposition to this, Takakuni HOSOKAWA dispatched a kenminsen with an expired Emperor Hongzhi kangofu via the South China Sea on which Zuisa RANKO served as seishi and Sosokei (Shuko) as fukushi (vice-envoy).</e>
<cmt>Retranslated to read more naturally and use correct terminology.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In opposition to this, Takakuni HOSOKAWA dispatched a kenminsen with an expired Emperor Hongzhi kangofu via the South China Sea on which Zuisa RANKO served as seishi and Sokei (Shuko) SO as fukushi (vice-envoy).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>乱の展開</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Development of the war</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Development of the War</e>
<cmt>Title case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Development of the War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>寧波には先に大内方の遣明船が入港しており、細川方には不利であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ouchi side&apos;s envoy ship entered port in Neiha before the Hosokawa side&apos;s envoy ship did, so the Hosokawa side was disadvantaged.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ouchi ship had already docked in Ningbo, which was unfavorable for the Hosokawa faction.</e>
<cmt>Retranslated to read more naturally and use correct terminology.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ouchi&apos;s kenmeisen ship had already docked in Ningbo, which was unfavorable for the Hosokawa faction.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかし細川方の副使宋素卿（そうそけい）は明の入港管理所である市舶司大監の頼恩に賄賂を贈り、細川方を先に入港検査させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But the Hosokawa side&apos;s vice-envoy Sosokei offered a bribe to Raion who was Shihakushi-daiken in a port authority in Ming China, and Raion let Sosoke go through port entry inspection before the Ouchi side underwent port entry inspection.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処頼恩は、読み方が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But the Hosokawa side&apos;s vice-envoy Sosokei offered a bribe to Laien who was superintendent of shipping at the port authority of Ming China, and Laien allowed the Hosokawa ship to go through port inspection before the Ouchi ship.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Raion&quot; &gt; &quot;Laien&quot;&quot;Shihakushi-daiken&quot; &gt; &quot;superintendent of shipping&quot;&quot;in a port authority in&quot; &gt; &quot;at the port authority of&quot;Rewritten second half to read more naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But the Hosokawa side&apos;s vice-envoy Sokei SO offered a bribe to Laien who was Shihakushi-daikan (inspector of the Office of Merchant Ships) at the port authority of Ming China, and Laien allowed the Hosokawa ship to go through port inspection before the Ouchi ship.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>大内方は細川方を襲撃し遣明船を焼き払い、明の官憲は細川方を支援した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ouchi side attacked the Hosokawa side, and burned down their envoy ship, and officials of Ming supported the Hosokawa side.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ouchi faction attacked the Hosokawa faction, burning their ship, and Ming officials supported the Hosokawa faction.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read more naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ouchi faction attacked the Hosokawa faction, burning their ship, and Ming officials supported the Hosokawa faction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>しかし謙道宗設により鸞岡端佐は殺され、紹興城へ逃れた宋素卿らを追い明の役人を殺害する事件が起こる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, war occurred when Sosetsu KENDO killed Zuisa RANKO, ran after Sosokei, who escaped to the Shoko-jo castle, and killed the officials of Ming.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, an incident occurred in which Sosetsu KENDO killed Zuisa RANKO, pursued Sosokei who had escaped to Shaoxing City and killed Ming government officials.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation. Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, an incident occurred in which Sosetsu KENDO killed Zuisa RANKO, pursued Sokei SO who had escaped to Shaoxing City and killed Ming government officials.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="20">
<j>乱の顛末</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Detailed account of the war</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Detailed Account of the War</e>
<cmt>Title case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Detailed Account of the War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>事件は外交問題となり、宋素卿は投獄されて獄死。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The incident became a diplomatic issue, and Sosokei was imprisoned and died in prison.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The incident became a diplomatic issue, and Sosokei was imprisoned and died in prison.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The incident became a diplomatic issue, and Sokei SO was imprisoned and died in prison.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>対日感情の悪化から1529年には市舶司大監は廃止される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shihakushi-daiken was abolished in 1529 because of an aggravated feeling (sentiment) toward Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The post of superintendent of shipping was abolished in 1529 due to a deterioration in sentiment toward Japan.</e>
<cmt>Reworded to read more naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The post of Shihakushi-daikan was abolished in 1529 due to a deterioration in sentiment toward Japan.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>遣明船は1536年（天文 (元号)5）には大内義隆が貿易を再開し、貿易は1551年（天文20）に義隆が家臣の陶晴賢の謀反で滅亡するまで続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The envoy ship to Ming China restarted to be dispatched in 1536 when Yoshitaka OUCHI resumed trade, and the trade continued until 1551 when Yoshitaka went to rack due to rebellion by his vassal, Harukata SUE.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenminsen ships once again became dispatched in 1536 when Yoshitaka OUCHI resumed trade which continued until 1551 when Yoshitaka was overthrown in a rebellion by his vassal Harukata SUE.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation. Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenminsen ships once again became dispatched in 1536 when Yoshitaka OUCHI resumed trade which continued until 1551 when Yoshitaka was overthrown in a rebellion by his vassal Harukata SUE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>この事件をきっかけに寧波に近い双嶼や、船山諸島など沿岸部で日本人商人との私貿易、密貿易が活発化し、倭寇（後期倭寇）の活動となって行く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This incident activated private and illegal trade with Japanese merchants in Ryanbo and Funayama islands along the coast near Neiha, and stimulated the latter part of the activities of wako (Japanese pirates).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処船山諸島は、読み方が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This incident led to increased private trade and smuggling with Japanese merchants at coastal areas such as Shuangyu near Ningbo and the Chuanshan Archipelago, as well as activities of wako (later wako).</e>
<cmt>Poor translation. Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This incident led to increased private trade and smuggling with Japanese merchants at coastal areas such as Shuangyu near Ningbo and the Zhoushan Islands, as well as activities of wako (koki wako [the 16th-century wako pirate-traders]).</e>
<cmt>「船山諸島」は「舟山」として地名修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Taka 470(id:239005), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), でここ(id:9565), Rusk(id:9895), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Straysheep(id:42448), Alexbot(id:157199), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>