<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>日朝修好条規</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese-Korean Treaty of Amity</e>
<cmt>Japanese-Korea&apos; is inconsistent.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese-Korean Treaty of Amity</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>日朝修好条規（にっちょうしゅうこうじょうき）は、1876年（明治9年、朝鮮暦高宗 (朝鮮王)13年）に日本と李氏朝鮮との間で締結された条約とそれに付随した諸協定を含めて指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Treaty of Ganghwa is a treaty and all agreements subsidiary to it which concluded between Japan and Joseon Dynasty Korea in 1876.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese-Korean Treaty of Amity refers to the treaty between Japan and the Joseon Dynasty concluded in 1876 and all agreements subsidiary to it.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese-Korean Treaty of Amity refers to the treaty between Japan and the Joseon Dynasty concluded in 1876 and all agreements subsidiary to it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>江華島事件後に調印されたため江華（島）条約（）とも、丙子の年に結ばれたために丙子修交条約ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also it was called Treaty of Ganghwa or Bingzi Treaty of Amity, because it was signed after Ganghwa Island incident on the year of Bingzi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called the Treaty of Ganghwa or the Bingzi Treaty of Amity, because it was signed after the Ganghwa Island incident on the year of Bingzi.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called the Treaty of Ganghwa or the Bingzi Treaty of Amity, because it was signed after the Ganghwa Island incident on the year of Bingzi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>当時東アジアで結ばれた多くの条約と同様、不平等条約であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the unequal treaty as many other treaties concluded in East Asia at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was an unequal treaty, as were many other treaties concluded in East Asia at that time.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was an unequal treaty, as were many other treaties concluded in East Asia at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>1875年に起きた江華島事件の後、日朝間で結ばれた条約であるが、条約そのものは全12款から成り、それとは別に具体的なことを定めた付属文書が全11款、貿易規則11則、及び公文がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a treaty concluded between Japan and Korea after Ganghwa Island incident in 1875, which was consisted of 12 provisions of the treaty itself and 11 affiliated documents providing concrete contents, 11 trade rules, and official documents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The treaty was concluded between Japan and Korea after the Ganghwa Island incident in 1875, and consisted of 12 provisions of the treaty itself, 11 affiliated documents providing concrete contents, 11 trade rules, and official documents.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The treaty was concluded between Japan and Korea after the Ganghwa Island incident in 1875, and consisted of 12 provisions of the treaty itself, 11 affiliated documents providing concrete contents, 11 trade rules, and official documents.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>これら全てを含んで一体のものとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All of them were included as one treaty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All of these were included as one treaty.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All of these were included as one treaty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>朝鮮が清朝の冊封から独立した国家主権を持つ独立国であることを明記したが、片務的領事裁判権の設定や関税自主権の喪失といった不平等条約的条項を内容とすることなどが、その特徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was described in the treaty that Korea was a nation independent from sakuho (a nominal homage concluded by the emperor of Chinese Dynasty) of the Qing dynasty, holding state sovereign power, however its characteristic was unequal treaty with the provisions describing the establishment of one-sided consular jurisdiction and the loss of tariff autonomy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was described in the treaty that Korea was a nation independent from Sakuho (a nominal homage concluded by the emperor of the Chinese Dynasty) of the Qing dynasty, holding state sovereign power, however it was characteristic of an unequal treaty with the provisions describing the establishment of one-sided consular jurisdiction and the loss of tariff autonomy.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was described in the treaty that Korea was a nation independent from the tributary system of the Qing dynasty, holding state sovereign power, however it was characteristic of an unequal treaty with the provisions describing the establishment of one-sided consular jurisdiction and the loss of tariff autonomy.</e>
<cmt>冊封の説明を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>それまで世界とは限定的な国交しか持たなかった朝鮮が、開国する契機となった条約であるが、近代国際法に詳しい人材がいなかったため、朝鮮側に不利なものとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Korea, which had limited diplomatic relations so far, was triggered to open the country due to the treaty, however it was unequal to the Korean side as they did not had specialists in the modern international law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Korea, which had engaged in only limited diplomatic relations up to this point, was able to open the country due to the treaty, however it was unequal to the Korean side as they did not have specialists in modern international law.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Korea, which had engaged in only limited diplomatic relations up to this point, was able to open the country due to the treaty, however it was unequal to the Korean side as they did not have specialists in modern international law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その後朝鮮は似たような内容の条約を他の西洋諸国（アメリカ合衆国、イギリス、ドイツ、ロシア帝国、フランス）とも同様の条約を締結することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Korea concluded the treaties with similar contents between other Western countries (the United States of America, England, Germany, the Russian Empire, and France).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Korea concluded treaties with similar contents between other Western countries (the United States of America, England, Germany, the Russian Empire, and France).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Korea concluded treaties with similar contents between other Western countries (the United States of America, England, Germany, the Russian Empire, and France).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>そのため好む好まざるとに関わらず近代の資本主義が席巻する世界に巻き込まれていくことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So that Korea was going to be involved in the world where the modern capitalism was sweeping, whether it was preferable or not.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this Korea would be dragged into the world of sweeping modern capitalism whether it liked it or not.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this Korea would be dragged into the world of sweeping modern capitalism whether it liked it or not.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A background</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>朝鮮における攘夷高揚</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Exaltation of expulsion of foreigners in Korea</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Exaltation of expulsion of foreigners in Korea</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Exaltation of expulsion of foreigners in Korea</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>この条約が締結される頃の東アジア世界は、近代的国際法を掲げながら、実際には弱肉強食を旨とする西欧列強が浸透してくる時期にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When this treaty was concluded the world in East Asia was in the period that it was worked into by the Western Europe powerful countries which appealed the modern international law in one hand, but believed the theory of the stronger prey upon the weaker in other hand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When this treaty was concluded the powerful countries of Western Europe, which on one hand appealed to modern international law but on the other believed in survival of the fittest, were spreading into East Asia.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When this treaty was concluded, the powerful countries of Western Europe were spreading into East Asia, holding up the modern international law on one hand but practicing the principle of survival of the fittest on the other hand.</e>
<cmt>語順等を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>当時朝鮮は清の冊封国であったが、鎖国政策を国是としていたため、国際交流は非常に限られていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time Korea was sakuho-koku (a country of a sovereign who became a nominal subject of the Chinese Emperor by sakuho.), however as its national policy was seclusionism, it had diplomatic relations with very limited countries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time Korea was a Sakuho-koku (a country of a sovereign who became a nominal subject of the Chinese Emperor by sakuho), however as its national policy was seclusionism, it had diplomatic relations with very limited countries.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time Korea was a tributary state of the Qing dynasty, but as its national policy was seclusionism, it had diplomatic relations with very limited countries.</e>
<cmt>Sakuho-koku (a country of a sovereign who became a nominal subject of the Chinese Emperor by sakuho), however→tributary state of the Qing dynasty, but</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかしそのような朝鮮にも1860年代以降国際化の波（外圧）が押し寄せ、海上から西欧諸国が訪れるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, after 1860&apos;s the wave of internationalization (foreign pressure) flooded into Korea under the national isolation, Western Europe countries began to come over the sea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after the 1860s the wave of internationalization (foreign pressure) flooded into Korea, and the countries of Western Europe began to come over the sea.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after the 1860s the wave of internationalization (foreign pressure) flooded into Korea, and the countries of Western Europe began to come over the sea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>朝鮮と西欧列強との出会いは、概ね芳しいものではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The encounter of Korea and Western Europe countries was not satisfactory in general.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The encounters between Korea and Western European countries were generally not satisfactory.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The encounters between Korea and Western European countries were generally not satisfactory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>たとえば1866年にはフランス軍がキリスト教徒虐殺事件（丙寅迫害）の報復として朝鮮の江華島を攻撃する丙寅洋擾が発生し、1871年にはアメリカ合衆国もジェネラル・シャーマン号事件（1866年発生）の報復として朝鮮の江華島に攻撃を行っている（辛未洋擾）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For instance, in 1866 Byeong-in yangyo that the French army attacked the Ganghwa Island in Korea in retaliation for slaughter of the Christian, which was called Byeong-in persecution, occurred, while in 1871, the United States of America attacked Ganghwa Island in retaliation for General Sherman incident in 1866, which was called Shinmiyangyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For instance, in 1866 the French army attacked Ganghwa Island in Korea in retaliation for the slaughter of Christians (known as the Byeong-in persecution), while in 1871, the United States of America attacked Ganghwa Island (an incident known as Shinmiyangyo) in retaliation for the General Sherman incident of 1866.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For instance, in 1866 the French army attacked Ganghwa Island in Korea in retaliation for the slaughter of Christians (known as the Byeong-in persecution), while in 1871, the United States of America attacked Ganghwa Island (an incident known as Shinmiyangyo) in retaliation for the General Sherman incident of 1866.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>当時朝鮮の政権を担っていたのは高宗 (朝鮮王)の実父興宣大院君である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The person who was in office at that time was HEUNGSEON Daewongun, a real father of GOJONG (the king of Korea).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The person in office at that time was HEUNGSEON Daewongun, the real father of GOJONG (the king of Korea).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The person in office at that time was HEUNGSEON Daewongun, the real father of GOJONG (the king of Korea).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>清朝から西欧列強の情報を得ていた大院君は、断固として鎖国を維持する姿勢を貫いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daewongun already had received the information of the Western Europe powerful countries from the Qing dynasty, so he firmly persisted to maintain the policy of national isolation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daewongun had already received information on the powerful countries of Western Europe from the Qing dynasty, so he firmly maintained the policy of national isolation.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daewongun had already received information on the powerful countries of Western Europe from the Qing dynasty, so he firmly maintained the policy of national isolation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これは中国における西欧側の非道を知ったこともあるが、朱子学以外を認めない衛正斥邪という思想政策を積極的に推し進めたことから分かるように、大院君は中華思想的発想の持ち主であり、その点から西欧諸国を夷狄視していたことも理由の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One reason for that attitude was that Daewongun knew villainy of the West European side in China, and for another reason, as he promoted actively the policy of the idea called Eiseisekija which was not to admit other ideas but the doctrines of Zhu Xi, he had the idea of Sinocentrism, and he presumed the Western Europe countries to be barbarous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daewongun knew the atrocoties of West Europeans in China, and he actively promoted the policy Eiseisekija, which was not to admit ideas other than the doctrines of Zhu Xi, and also he believed in Sinocentrism, and because of this he presumed the Western Europe countries to be barbarous.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daewongun knew the atrocities of West Europeans in China, and he actively promoted the wijŏng ch&apos;ŏksa policy (defense of Confucian orthodoxy and rejection of Christian heterodoxy), which was not to admit ideas other than the doctrines of Zhu Xi, and also he believed in Sinocentrism, and because of this he presumed the Western Europe countries to be barbarous.</e>
<cmt>atrocityのスペルを直しました。衛正斥邪の訳を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>その強い姿勢は「西洋蛮人の侵犯に戦わない事は和議をする事であり、和議を主張することは売国行為である」と書かれた斥和碑を朝鮮各地に建てたことに窺うことができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His firm attitude was shown to the monuments written &apos;Not to fight against encroachment of the Western barbarians means peace negotiations, while insisting peace negotiations means to sell our nation.&apos;, which were erected through Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His firm attitude can be seen written on monuments which were erected throughout Korea, with the words &apos;to not fight against encroachment of the Western barbarians means peace negotiations; to negotiate is to sell our nation&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His firm attitude can be seen written on monuments which were erected throughout Korea, reading &apos;No fighting against encroachment of the Western barbarians means doing peace negotiations, and doing negotiations is selling our nation.&apos;</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>このように当時の朝鮮では攘夷熱が高まっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The emotion of expulsion of foreigners rose in Korea at that time like this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time in Korea there was increasingly strong enthusiasm towards the expulsion of foreigners.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time in Korea there was increasingly strong enthusiasm towards the expulsion of foreigners.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>日朝間の懸案：書契問題</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The pending problem between Japan and Korea: a problem of diplomatic correspondence</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The pending problem between Japan and Korea: a problem of diplomatic correspondence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The pending problem between Japan and Korea: a problem of diplomatic correspondence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>他方、西欧列強が迫っていた東アジア諸国の中で、いちはやく開国し明治維新により近代国家となった日本は、西欧諸国のみならず、自国周辺のアジア諸国とも近代的な国際関係を樹立しようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While, among the East Asian countries where the Western Europe powerful countries were approaching, Japan was the first country that opened it to the world and became a modern state by the Meiji Restoration, and it began to establish modern international relations not only between the West European countries, but also between Asian countries around Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among East Asian countries where the powerful countries of Western Europe powerful countries, Japan was the first country that opened itself to the world and became a modern state through the Meiji Restoration, and it began to establish modern international relations not only with the West European countries, but also with Asian countries around Japan.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among East Asian countries where the powerful countries of Western Europe were watching for a chance to invade, Japan was the first country that opened itself to the world and became a modern state through the Meiji Restoration, and it began to establish modern international relations not only with the West European countries but also with Asian countries around Japan.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>朝鮮にも1868年12月に明治政府が樹立するとすぐに書契、すなわち国書を対馬藩の宗氏を介し送った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Right after the establishment of the Meiji government in December 1866, Japan sent a diplomatic correspondence, that is to say sovereign&apos;s message to Korea through the So clan in Tsushima.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Right after the establishment of the Meiji government in December 1866, Japan sent Korea a diplomatic correspondence, that is to say a sovereign&apos;s message, through the So clan in Tsushima.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Right after the establishment of the Meiji government in December 1866, Japan sent Korea a diplomatic correspondence, that is to say a sovereign&apos;s message, through the So clan in Tsushima.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>江戸時代を通じて、朝鮮との関係は宗氏を通じ行われてきたためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That was because the relation between Korea had been maintained through the So clan since the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That was because relations with Korea had been maintained through the So clan since the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That was because relations with Korea had been maintained through the So clan since the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>しかし国書の中に「皇」や「奉勅」といったことばが使用されていたために、朝鮮側は受け取りを拒否した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Korea side refused to receive the sovereign&apos;s message because it used the words &apos;imperial&apos; and &apos;obeying imperial order&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Korean side refused to receive the sovereign&apos;s message because it used the words &apos;imperial&apos; and &apos;imperial order&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Korean side refused to receive the sovereign&apos;s message because it used the words &apos;imperial&apos; and &apos;imperial order.&apos;</e>
<cmt>を半角とし、位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>近代的な国際関係樹立は、はなから躓いたといえよう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The establishment of the modern international relations might have met with a setback from the beginning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be said that the establishment of modern international relations was in difficulty from the beginning.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be said that the establishment of modern international relations was in difficulty from the beginning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>この問題は、日朝双方の国交に対する思惑がすれ違ったことが原因である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason of this matter was the expectations of both Japan and Korea for diplomatic relations were cross-purposes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The root of this problem lied in Japan and Korea&apos;s differing expectations regarding diplomatic relations.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The root of this problem lied in Japan and Korea&apos;s differing expectations regarding diplomatic relations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>日本側は従来の冊封体制的な交隣関係から、条約に基礎づけられた関係へと、日朝関係を変化させることを企図したのであるが、一方朝鮮側はこれまでどおり冊封関係にとどまり、その中で日本との関係を位置づけようとしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan side attempted to change the style of the relationship between Korea from that of peace and amity based on the conventional Sakuho system to which based on the treaty, on the other hand, Korea side intended to maintain the conventional Sakuho system, and establish the relationship between Japan in that circumstance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan attempted to change the style of the relationship with Korea from that of peace and amity based on the conventional Sakuho system to one based on the treaty, whereas Korea intended to maintain the conventional Sakuho system, and establish a relationship with Japan under those circumstances.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan attempted to change the style of the relationship with Korea from that of peace and amity based on the conventional tributary system to that based on a treaty, whereas Korea intended to maintain the conventional tributary system and establish a relationship with Japan under its framework.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>前近代における冊封体制下において、「皇上」や「奉勅」ということばは中国の王朝にのみ許されたことばであって、日本がそれを使用するということは、冊封体制の頂点に立ち朝鮮よりも日本の国際地位を上とすることを画策したと朝鮮は捉えたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Korea understood that Japan attempted to reach the higher position than Korea in the world by standing at the top of Sakuho system, because Japan used the words of &apos;imperial&apos; and &apos;imperial order&apos; which were allowed to use just for the Chinese dynasty under the Sakuho system in the premodern era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Japan used the words &apos;imperial&apos; and &apos;imperial order&apos;, which were only allowed to be used by the Chinese dynasty under the Sakuho system of the premodern era, Korea understood that Japan was attempting to stand at the top of the Sakuho system and reach a higher position in the world than Korea.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Japan used the words &apos;imperial&apos; and &apos;imperial order,&apos; which were only allowed to be used by the Chinese dynasty under the tributary system of the premodern era, Korea understood that Japan was attempting to stand at the top of the tributary system and get a higher position in the world than Korea.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="28">
<j>なお近代以前の日朝関係については朝鮮通信使に詳しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Refer to the Messenger of Korea as for the detail of Japan-Korea relation before modern era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Refer to &apos;the Messenger of Korea&apos; for details of the Japan-Korea relation before the modern era.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Refer to &apos;the Messenger of Korea&apos; for details of the Japan-Korea relation before the modern era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="29">
<j>1868年以来、何度か日本からの国書がもたらされたが、日朝双方の思惑の違いから両国の関係は円滑なものとは言えなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the sovereign&apos;s messages had been sent to Korea from Japan several times since 1868, the relations among them was not smooth due to the different expectations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Japan sent sovereign&apos;s messages to Korea several times after 1868, relations between them were not smooth due to their different expectations.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Japan sent sovereign&apos;s messages to Korea several times after 1868, their relation were not smooth due to misunderstanding.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>書契問題を背景として生じた日本国内における「征韓論」の高まりに、大院君が非常な警戒心を抱いたことも一因である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another reason was that Daewongun felt a great cautiousness against the rise of &apos;Seikanron&apos; (the opinion to dispatch a mission to Korea) in Japan which occurred from the problem of diplomatic correspondence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another reason was that Daewongun felt a great cautiousness against the rise of &apos;Seikanron&apos; (the policy of conquering Korea by military force) in Japan which occurred from the problem of diplomatic correspondence.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another reason was that Daewongun felt a great cautiousness against the debate over sending a military expedition to Korea in Japan which had occurred from the problem of diplomatic correspondence.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>また釜山広域市においては日朝両国の官僚同士が険悪となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also the relation of the bureaucrats of both Japan and Korea became vicious in Busan Metropolitan City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, relations between bureaucrats of Japan and Korea became vicious in Busan Metropolitan City.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, relations between bureaucrats of Japan and Korea became tense in Busan Metropolitan City.</e>
<cmt>viciousをtenseに変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>長崎の出島のごとき釜山の倭館に限定した国交を望む朝鮮側と、対馬宗氏から外交権を取り上げて外交を一元化し、開国を迫る日本との間に齟齬が生じたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a contradiction between Korea which required to maintain the diplomatic relations just in Wakan (consular office) in Busan as Dejima in Nagasaki and Japan which attempted to unify the diplomatic route by depriving the diplomatic right from the So clan in Tsushima and urged to open the country to the world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a contradiction between Korea which maintained diplomatic relations just in Wakan (consular office) in Busan like in Dejima in Nagasaki, and Japan, which attempted to unify the diplomatic route by depriving the So clan in Tsushima their diplomatic rights and urged them to open the country to the world.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a contradiction between Korea, which wanted to maintain diplomatic relations just in the Japanese consular office in Busan like Dejima in Nagasaki, and Japan, which attempted to unify the diplomatic route by depriving the So clan in Tsushima of their diplomatic rights and urged Korea to open the country to the world.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>釜山の倭館は朝鮮側が日本、特に対馬藩の使節や商人を饗応するために設けた施設であったが、明治政府は対馬藩から外交権を取り上げ、朝鮮との交渉に乗り出そうとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wakan in Busan was established by Korea to wine and dine Japan, especially the envoy and merchants from the Tsushima clan, but the Meiji government tried to deprive the diplomatic right from the Tsushima clan and launch a negotiation with Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wakan in Busan was established by Korea to entertain Japan, especially the envoy and merchants from the Tsushima clan, but the Meiji government tried to deprive the Tsushima clan diplomatic rights and entered into negotiations with Korea.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese consular office in Busan was established by Korea to entertain Japanese envoys and merchants especially from the Tsushima domain, but the Meiji government tried to deprive the Tsushima domain of the diplomatic rights and start direct negotiations with Korea.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>その際、倭館をも朝鮮側の承諾無しに接収し日本公館としたことから事態が悪化したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The situation went worse, because at that time Japan took over Wakan without the admission of Korea and changed it to the diplomatic establishment of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time Japan took over Wakan without the consent of Korea and changed it to the diplomatic establishment of Japan, causing the situation to worsen.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time Japan took over the Japanese consular office in Busan without the consent of Korea and changed it to the diplomatic establishment of Japan, to cause the situation to worsen.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>結果、必要物資の供給及び密貿易の停止が朝鮮側から宣言される事態となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result Korea declared to suspend the supply of necessary goods and illegal trades.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result Korea declared a suspension of the supply of necessary goods and illegal trades.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result Korea declared a suspension of the supply of necessary goods and illegal trades.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="36">
<j>日本側も単に国書を送りつけるだけだったわけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What Japan did against Korea was not just sending a sovereign&apos;s message.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan did not just continue sending sovereign&apos;s messages to Korea.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan did not just continue sending sovereign&apos;s messages to Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>版籍奉還という日本国内の難問を無事に乗り越えた1870年、朝鮮との国交交渉を有利にするため、冊封体制の頂点にたつ清朝と対等の条約、日清修好条規を締結した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The year of 1870 when Japan completed a domestic difficult matter, Hansekihokan (returning of lands and people to the emperor) without incident, Japan concluded the equal treaty (Japanese-Ching Treaty of Amity) with the Qing dynasty which was at the top of sakuho system, in order to be advantageous to diplomatic negotiations with Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1870 when Japan overcame the problematic domestic matter &apos;Hansekihokan&apos; (returning of lands and people to the emperor) without incident, Japan concluded the equal treaty (Japanese-Qing Treaty of Amity) with the Qing dynasty, which was at the top of the sakuho system, because it would to advantageous to diplomatic negotiations with Korea.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1870 when Japan finished the &apos;Hansekihokan&apos; (returning of lands and people to the emperor), a challenge in the domestic policy, successfully, Japan concluded the equal treaty (Japanese-Qing Treaty of Amity) with the Qing dynasty, which was at the top of the tributary system, because it would be advantageous to diplomatic negotiations with Korea.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>これにより冊封体制の維持を理由に国交交渉を忌避する朝鮮を、交渉のテーブルに着くように促したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of that, Japan urged Korea, which avoided the diplomatic negotiations due to the reason for the maintenance of sakuho system, to go to the negotiating table.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of that, Japan urged Korea, which had avoided the diplomatic negotiations in order to maintain the sakuho system, to go to the negotiating table.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of that, Japan urged Korea to enter into negotiations, while Korea had been avoiding the diplomatic negotiations in order to maintain the tributary system.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="39">
<j>1873年に対外強硬派の大院君が失脚し、王妃閔妃一派が権力を握っても、日朝関係は容易に好転しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jingoistic Daewongun was disgraced in 1873, the Empress Myeongseong group assumed the authority, but the relation between Japan and Korea did not turn better.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hard-liner Daewongun was disgraced in 1873, and the Empress Myeongseong group assumed authority, but relations between Japan and Korea did not turn better.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hard-liner Daewongun was disgraced in 1873, and the Empress Myeongseong group assumed authority, but relations between Japan and Korea did not turn better.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>転機が訪れたのは、翌年日清間の抗争に発展した台湾出兵である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The turning point was the Taiwan expedition that was developed to the conflict between Japan and Qing the next year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The turning point was when Japan dispatched troops to Taiwan during the conflict between Japan and Qing that developed the following year.</e>
<cmt>Taiwan expedition&apos; makes it unclear whether Taiwan troops were dispatched, or troops were dispatched to Taiwan.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The turning point was when Japan dispatched troops to Taiwan during the conflict between Japan and Qing that developed the following year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>この時、日本が朝鮮に出兵する可能性を清朝より知らされた朝鮮側では、李裕元や朴珪寿を中心に日本からの国書を受理すべしという声が高まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time Korea was informed by the Qing dynasty of the possibility of expedition from Japan, so that Yuan YU, Gyu-su PARK and others insisted that Korea should have received the sovereign&apos;s message.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time Korea was informed by the Qing dynasty of the possibility that Japan would dispatch troops, so Yuan YU, Gyu-su PARK and others insisted that Korea should receive the sovereign&apos;s message.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time Korea was informed by the Qing dynasty of the possibility that Japan would dispatch troops, so Yuan YU, Gyu-su PARK and others insisted that Korea should receive the sovereign&apos;s message of Japan.</e>
<cmt>を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>李・朴は対馬藩のもたらす国書に「皇」や「勅」とあるのは単に自尊を意味するに過ぎず、朝鮮に対して唱えているのではない、受理しないというのは「交隣講好の道」に反していると主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">YU and PARK insisted that the words &apos;imperial&apos; and &apos;imperial order&apos; written in the sovereign&apos;s message delivered by the Tsushima clan did not persist to Korea, but simply meant their pride, so that to reject the acceptance of the message would oppose to &apos;the way to the peace and amity&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">YU and PARK insisted that the words &apos;imperial&apos; and &apos;imperial order&apos; written in the sovereign&apos;s message delivered by the Tsushima clan did not pertain to Korea, but simply showed Japan&apos;s pride, and that to reject the acceptance of the message would be to oppose &apos;the way to peace and amity&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">YU and PARK insisted that the words &apos;imperial&apos; and &apos;imperial order&apos; written in the sovereign&apos;s message delivered by the Tsushima clan was not a statement to Korea but simply showed Japan&apos;s pride, and that to reject the acceptance of the message would be to oppose &apos;the way to peace and amity.&apos;</e>
<cmt>を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>これにより朝鮮側の対日姿勢がやや軟化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to their insistence, the attitude of Korea against Japan slightly softened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In line with their insistence, the attitude of Korea against Japan softened slightly.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In line with their insistence, the attitude of Korea against Japan softened slightly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>条約締結までの経過</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The progress until the conclusion of the treaty</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Progress until the conclusion of the treaty</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Progress until the conclusion of the treaty</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>国交交渉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The negotiation for diplomatic relations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Diplomatic negotiations</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Diplomatic negotiations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="44">
<j>国交交渉再開の気運が高まり、1875年に交渉が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tendency to resume the negotiation for diplomatic relations was growing, the negotiation started in 1875.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a growing tendency to resume negotiations for diplomatic relations, and the negotiations started in 1875.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a growing tendency to resume negotiations for diplomatic relations, and the negotiations started in 1875.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>日本側は外務省理事官森山茂と広津弘信、朝鮮側は東莱府の官僚が交渉のテーブルに着いたが、やはり書契に使用される文字について両者の認識に食い違いが生じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A resident of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Shigeru MORIYAMA and Hironobu HIROTSU from Japan and the bureaucrats of Toraifu from Korea sat down the table of the negotiation, but the same as before, they had the different recognition of the words used in the sovereign&apos;s message.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A resident of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Shigeru MORIYAMA, and Hironobu HIROTSU from Japan and bureaucrats from Toraifu in Korea sat down at the negotiating table, but the same as before, they recognized the words used in the sovereign&apos;s message differently.</e>
<cmt>Are Moriyama and Hirotsu are both from the Ministry of Foreign Affairs?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigeru MORIYAMA and Hironobu HIROTSU, a councilor of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, from Japan and bureaucrats from Dongrae-Bu (the administrative districts in Korea) sat down at the negotiating table, but the same as before, there were differences between them about the words used in the sovereign&apos;s messages.</e>
<cmt>を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>この他森山の洋服着用など欧米スタイルを貫こうとする姿勢に朝鮮側が嫌悪感を示したことで交渉ははかばかしくなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, as MORIYAMA wore the Western clothes, Japan persisted in the European and American style, so that Korea showed a sense of aversion and the negotiation did not go smoothly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, as MORIYAMA wore Western clothes and the Japanese persisted in the European and American style, the Koreans showed a sense of aversion and the negotiation did not go smoothly.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, as the Japanese persisted in the European and American style, such as Moriyama wearing Western clothes, to which the Koreans showed aversion, the negotiation did not go smoothly.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>そして8月には森山が日本に帰国してしまう事態となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Finally it resulted that MORIYAMA returned in August.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result MORIYAMA returned to Japan in August.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result Moriyama returned to Japan in August.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>交渉の停滞に業を煮やした日本側は砲艦外交を行うことを日本政府に上申した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan-side got angry about the stagnation of the negotiation, so that it gave an opinion to the government of Japan to start gunboat diplomacy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese got angry about the stagnation of negotiations, and they submitted a recommendation to the government of Japan to start gunboat diplomacy.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese got angry about the stagnation of negotiations, and they asked the Japanese government to resort to the gunboat diplomacy.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>これが江華島事件の発端となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was the outset of Ganghwa Island incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the beginning of the Ganghwa Island incident.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the beginning of the Ganghwa Island incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>砲艦外交の展開：江華島事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Development of gunboat diplomacy: Ganghwa Island incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Development of gunboat diplomacy: the Ganghwa Island incident</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Development of gunboat diplomacy: the Ganghwa Island incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="50">
<j>1875年4月以降、日本側は朝鮮近海に軍艦を派遣し、軍事的示威行動を取った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After April of 1875, Japan-side dispatched warships to the seas near Korea, exercised demonstrational actions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From April of 1875, the Japanese dispatched warships to the seas near Korea, and exercised demonstrational actions.</e>
<cmt>Wording. &apos;Japan-side&apos; is very unnatural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From April of 1875, the Japanese dispatched warships to the seas near Korea, and exercised demonstrational actions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>その後、9月20日に江華島事件が発生して永宗島の要塞を占領。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Ganghwa Island incident occurred on September 20, the fortress of the Eishu Island was occupied.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, the Ganghwa Island incident occurred on September 20, and the Japanese occupied the fortress of Eishu Island.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, the Ganghwa Island incident occurred on September 20, and the Japanese occupied the fortress of Yeongjong Island.</e>
<cmt>Eishu Island→Yeongjong Island</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>この事件における被害は、朝鮮側の死者35名、日本側の死傷者は2名であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The victims of this incident were 35 dead in Korea and 2 dead and injured in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The victims of this incident included 35 dead on the Korean side and 2 dead or injured on the Japanese side.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The victims of this incident included 35 dead on the Korean side and 2 dead or injured on the Japanese side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>戦後砲台の武装解除を行い、取り外した武器等を戦利品として鹵獲している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aftermath, Japan disarmed the gun battery, and plundered the taken arms as spoils of war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the aftermath, Japan disarmed the gun battery, and plundered arms as spoils of war.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the aftermath, Japan disarmed the gun battery, and confiscated these arms as spoils of war.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>この事件は、日本の挑発行動から発生した明らかな侵略行為であったが、日本側は逆に江華島事件をきっかけに条約を締結することを目論んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This incident was apparently the aggression caused by the provocative behavior of Japan, but Japan aimed to conclude the treaty using Ganghwa Island incident as a trigger.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This aggressive incident was clearly caused by the provocative behavior of Japan, but the Japanese aimed to use the Ganghwa Island incident as an opportunity to conclude the treaty.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This aggressive incident was clearly caused by the provocative behavior of Japan, but the Japanese aimed to use the Ganghwa Island incident as an opportunity to conclude the treaty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>条約交渉における日本側の基本姿勢</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basic attitude of Japan at the treaty negotiation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The basic attitude of Japan at the treaty negotiations</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The basic attitude of Japan at the treaty negotiations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="55">
<j>明治政府のお雇い外国人ギュスターヴ・エミール・ボアソナードは、事件を処理するために派遣される使節への訓令について、以下を決して朝鮮に譲歩すべきではないと具申した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A foreign resident in Japan employed by the Meiji government, Gustave Emile BOISSONADE gave an instruction to the envoy that would be dispatched to dispose the incident, stating that they must not concede Korea the following points.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A foreign resident in Japan employed by the Meiji government, Gustave Emile BOISSONADE gave an instruction to the envoy that would be dispatched to dispose the incident, stating that they must not concede Korea the following points.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gustave Emile BOISSONADE, a foreign specialist in the Meiji government, gave an instruction to the envoy who would be dispatched to dispose the incident that they should not concede Korea the following points.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="56">
<j>釜山・江華港を貿易港として開港する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To open Port of Busan and Ganghwa Port as trading ports.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To open Busan Port and Ganghwa Port as trading ports.</e>
<cmt>Unsure regarding strictness of fragments in par section.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To open Busan Port and Ganghwa Port as trading ports.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="57">
<j>朝鮮海航行の自由。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Free navigation of Sea of Korea</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To allow free navigation of the Sea of Korea.</e>
<cmt>As above.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To allow free navigation of the Sea of Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="58">
<j>江華島事件についての謝罪要求。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Requirement of apology for Ganghwa Island incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Requirement of an apology for the Ganghwa Island incident.</e>
<cmt>As above.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Requirement of an apology for the Ganghwa Island incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="59">
<j>またこれらが満たされない場合、軍事行動も含む強硬な外交姿勢を取ることをも合わせて意見している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also he stated that if these requirements were not accepted, Japan should exercise hard diplomatic attitude including military action.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also he stated that if these requirements were not accepted, Japan should demonstrate a hard diplomatic position which includes the use of military action.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also he advised that if these requirements were not accepted, Japan should demonstrate a hard diplomatic position which includes the use of military action.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>これらの意見はほとんど変更されることなく、太政大臣三条実美を通じて訓示に付属する内諭として使節に伝えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This opinion was told to the envoy by the Grand Minister Sanetomi SANJO as unofficial message affiliated to the instruction without any specific change.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This opinion was conveyed to the envoy without change by the Grand Minister Sanetomi SANJO as an unofficial message attached to the instruction.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This opinion was conveyed to the envoy without change by the Grand Minister Sanetomi SANJO as an unofficial message attached to the instruction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>さらに朝鮮に対する基本姿勢として、三条はこの江華島事件に対して「相応なる賠償を求む」べきとしながら、使節団の目的を「我主意の注ぐ所は、交を続くに在るを以て、・・・和約を結ぶことを主とし、彼能我が和交を修め、貿易を広むるの求に従ひときは、即此を以て雲揚 (軍艦)の賠償と看做し、承諾すること」だと述べていた（強調、加筆者）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, as a basic attitude towards Korea, SANJO considered &apos;Japan should require a suitable compensation&apos;, while stated about the purpose of the envoy as &apos;the main objective was to continue the negotiation, then conclude a treaty of peace, when they conclude the peace treaty and obeyed to expand trading, we should regard the attitude as the compensation of the battle ship and accept it&apos;. (emphasis, a writer touched in)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, as a basic attitude towards Korea, SANJO considered &apos;Japan should require suitable compensation&apos;, while stating about the purpose of the envoy &apos;the main objective is to continue the negotiation, then conclude a treaty of peace, when they conclude the peace treaty and obey the demand to expand trading, we should regard this attitude as compensation for the battle ship and accept it&apos; (emphasis, amended by writer).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, as a basic attitude towards Korea, Sanjo considered &apos;Japan should require suitable compensation,&apos; while stating about the purpose of the envoy &apos;the main objective is to continue the negotiation, then conclude a treaty of peace, when they conclude the peace treaty and obey the demand to expand trading, we should regard this attitude as compensation for the battle ship and accept it&apos; (emphasized and amended by the writer).</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>これは欧米列強の干渉を招かないよう配慮すべし、という森有礼の言が容れられたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In these words the comment of Arimasa MORI that the message should consider not bringing the intervention of the allied western powers, was included.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These words included the comment of Arimasa MORI that they should consider not inviting the intervention of the allied western powers.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These words included the comment of Arimasa MORI that they should consider not inviting the intervention of the allied western powers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="63">
<j>さらにボアソナードのいう軍事行動も含む強硬な外交姿勢も、日本は忠実に実行に移している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, Japan practiced faithfully the hard diplomatic attitude including military action as BOISSONADE said.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, Japan faithfully practiced the hard diplomatic attitude including military action as recommended by BOISSONADE.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides, Japan faithfully practiced the hard diplomatic attitude including military action as recommended by Boissonade.</e>
<cmt>BOISSONADEをワードキャップにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>使節団一行には軍艦や兵士の護衛がつき、威圧効果を朝鮮側に与えようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The guard of battle ship and soldiers accompanied the envoy, so that Japan tried to give coercive effect to Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan tried to coerce Korea by sending a guard of battleships and soldiers to accompany the envoy.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan tried to coerce Korea by sending a guard of battleships and soldiers to accompany the envoy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>また交渉が決裂した場合に備え、山縣有朋が山口県下関市に入り、広島市・熊本市両鎮台の兵力をいつでも投入できるよう準備していたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in case of the breakdown of the negotiation, Aritomo YAMAGATA went into Shimonoseki City in Yamaguchi Prefecture, prepared to throw the force of both Hiroshima City and Kumamoto City in the case of emergency.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, in case of a breakdown in negotiations, Aritomo YAMAGATA went to Shimonoseki City in Yamaguchi Prefecture, and prepared the forces of both Hiroshima City and Kumamoto City for action.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, in case of a breakdown in negotiations, Aritomo YAMAGATA went to Shimonoseki City in Yamaguchi Prefecture, and prepared the forces of both Hiroshima City and Kumamoto City for action.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>さらにいえば、日本の砲艦外交的姿勢は無論朝鮮の屈服を促すものであったが、同時に日本国内の「征韓論」を唱える不平士族の溜飲を下げることも狙ったものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, the gunboat diplomatic attitude of Japan was naturally to urge Korea to submit, but at the same time it aimed to release the complaint of fuhei shizoku (former samurai with gripes) who advocated &apos;Seikanron&apos; (opinion to dispatch a mission to Korea).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, the gunboat diplomatic attitude of Japan was of course an attempt at urging Korea to submit, but at the same time it aimed to appease the complaints of fuhei shizoku (former samurai with gripes) who advocated &apos;Seikanron&apos; (the policy of conquering Korea by military force).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the gunboat diplomatic attitude of Japan was of course an attempt at urging Korea to submit, but at the same time it aimed to appease the complaints of the former samurai class who advocated the policy of conquering Korea by military force.</e>
<cmt>音訳を略しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="67">
<j>ただこのように軍事的高圧な姿勢を表面上見せながら、当時の日本は軍費の負担という点からいって、戦争が好ましいとは考えていなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, while Japan showed military oppressive attitude on the surface, Japan at that time thought that the war would not be preferable from the point of paying war expenditure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, while Japan showed an oppressive military attitude on the surface, Japan at that time thought that the war would not be preferable from the point of paying war expenditure.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, while Japan showed an oppressive military attitude on the surface, Japan at that time thought that the war would not be preferable from the point of military expenditure.</e>
<cmt>war expenditure→military expenditure</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>また戦争の発生がロシアや清朝の介入を許すきっかけになるかもしれず、その点からも極力戦争は避ける考えであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also the outbreak of war might trigger allowing the intervention of Russia and the Qing dynasty, so that from that point, Japan thought to avoid war as much as possible.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also the outbreak of war could have triggered the intervention of Russia and the Qing Dynasty, and because of this, Japan thought it best to avoid war as much as possible.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also the outbreak of war could have triggered the intervention of Russia and the Qing Dynasty, and because of this, Japan thought it best to avoid war as much as possible.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="69">
<j>以上をまとめると日本側の交渉の基本姿勢は、以下の二点に集約される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Putting together them, the basic attitude of Japan for the negotiation could be integrated to the following 2 points.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan&apos;s basic attitude towards negotiations was based on a combination of these two points.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan&apos;s basic attitude towards negotiations was based on a combination of these two points.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="70">
<j>砲艦外交を最大限推し進めながら、実際には戦争をできるだけ回避すること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While promoting gunboat diplomacy to the maximum, actually avoiding war as much as possible.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They pushed forward with gunboat diplomacy as much as possible, while actually avoiding war as much as possible.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They pushed forward with gunboat diplomacy as much as possible, while actually avoiding war as much as possible.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="71">
<j>江華島事件の問罪を前面に押し出しながら、実質的には条約を締結し、両国の懸案で長年解決しなかった近代的な国際関係を樹立すること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While prioritizing the investigation of the crimes of Ganghwa Island incident, practically concluding a treaty and establishing modern international relation that was a pending problem of the two countries and being left for many years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While prioritizing the investigation of crimes of the Ganghwa Island incident, practically concluding a treaty and establishing modern international relation was a pending problem of the two countries that was left unresovled for many years.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While emphasizing the reproof of the Ganghwa Island incident, they practically tried to conclude a treaty and establish modern international relationship with Korea, which had been left unsettled for many years.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="72">
<j>また清朝の干渉をなくすべく、事前に清朝の大官たちと折衝を重ねることも日本は行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in order to avoid the intervention by the Qing dynasty, Japan negotiated with the government officials of that state many times in advance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, in order to avoid intervention by the Qing dynasty, Japan negotiated with the government officials of that state many times in advance.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, in order to avoid intervention by the Qing dynasty, Japan negotiated with the government officials of that state many times in advance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>19世紀、欧米列強のアジア侵略に対抗するため、清朝は、朝鮮やベトナム、琉球などの冊封国を保護国あるいは併合することによって中国皇帝を中心としたアジアの伝統的な国際関係をそのまま近代的国際関係へと移行させて清の地位と影響力を保持しようとし、冊封国に対して保護国化を強めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the 19 century, in order to resist the intervention of the allied western powers into Asia, the Qing dynasty changed sakuho countries such as Korea, Vietnam, Ryukyu to the protected states, or merged them, and intended to switch the traditional international relationship in Asia to the modern international relationship with Ching emperor at its center in order to maintain the position and influential power, so that it strengthened to switch to the protected county from sakuho country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the 19 century, in order to resist the intervention of the allied western powers in Asia, the Qing dynasty changed Sakuho countries such as Korea, Vietnam and Ryukyu to protected states, or merged them, and endeavoured to change the traditional international relationships in Asia to modern international relationships with the Qing emperor at its center in order to maintain a position of influential power, thus strengthening the protected countries of sakuho.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the 19 century, in order to resist the invasion of the western powers in Asia, the Qing dynasty tried to shift the traditional international relationships in Asia to the modern ones with the Qing emperor in the center intactly to maintain the influential status by means of changing the subordinate countries under the tributary system, such as Korea, Vietnam and Ryukyu, to protected states, or merging them, thus promoted to make its subordinate countries protectorates.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="74">
<j>この時期の東アジアは、日中朝そして西欧列強の間における複雑な絡み合いが相互作用する場が形成されつつあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan, China, Korea and Western Europe powerful countries related complicatedly, and a circumstance where these countries interacted was being formed during this period in East Asia.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that period, the relationships between Japan, China, Korea and the powerful countires of Western Europe were complicated, and the formation of circumstances where these countries could interact was taking place.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that period, the stage of complicated interaction began to appear in East Asia, where Japan, China, Korea and the powerful countries of Western Europe got involved together.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>日朝間の国交交渉再開もその結果としてもたらされたものであると同時に、また別の歴史事象の原因でもあったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The resumption of the negotiation between Japan and Korea was realized as a result of that, and at the same time it triggered another historical phenomenon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The resumption of negotiations between Japan and Korea was realized as a result of that, and at the same time it triggered another historical phenomenon.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of that, the resumption of negotiations between Japan and Korea was realized, but at the same time it was triggered by another historical phenomenon.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>条約交渉－1－</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Negotiation of treaty -1-</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Negotiation of the treaty -1-</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Negotiation of the treaty -1-</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>日朝修好条規の締結</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Conclusion of Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Conclusion of the Japanese-Korean Treaty of Amity</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Conclusion of the Japanese-Korean Treaty of Amity</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="76">
<j>条約交渉は大きく分けて二段階ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The negotiation of the treaty was divided into two stages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The negotiation of the treaty was divided into two stages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The negotiation of the treaty was divided into two stages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>まずは日朝修好条規そのものの交渉。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first stage was to negotiate the Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity itself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first stage was to negotiate the Japanese-Korean Treaty of Amity itself.</e>
<cmt>Japanese-Korea inconsistent</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first stage was to negotiate the Japanese-Korean Treaty of Amity itself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>次に条規附録及び貿易規則に関する交渉。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second stage was to negotiate the affiliated provisions and trade rules.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second stage was to negotiate the affiliated provisions and trade rules.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second stage was to negotiate the affiliated provisions and trade rules.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="79">
<j>前者の条約交渉には、日本からは全権大使黒田清隆と副使井上馨が、朝鮮からは簡判中枢府事申櫶と副総管尹滋承が出席した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The persons who attended to the negotiation at the first stage were Ambassador plenipotentiary Kiyotaka KURODA and the Vice –envoy Kaoru INOUE from Japan and General of the Royal Brigade Heon SHIN and Minister of Rites Ja-seung YUN from Korea.</e>
<cmt>「簡判中枢府事」と「副総管」は定訳不明です。「The land of scholars:Two thousand years of Korean Confucianism (Kang Jaae-eun著)」に記載の役職表記を参考にしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first stage of negotiations were attended to by Ambassador plenipotentiary Kiyotaka KURODA and the Vice-envoy Kaoru INOUE from Japan and General of the Royal Brigade Heon SHIN and Minister of Rites Ja-seung YUN from Korea.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the first stage of negotiations Ambassador plenipotentiary Kiyotaka KURODA and the Vice-envoy Kaoru INOUE from Japan and General of the Royal Brigade Heon SHIN and Minister of Rites Ja-seung YUN from Korea attended.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>交渉場所は事件のあった江華島とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The venue of the negotiation was Ganghwa Island where the incident was occurred.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The venue of the negotiation was Ganghwa Island, where the incident had occurred.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The venue of the negotiation was Ganghwa Island, where the incident had occurred.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="81">
<j>交渉は最初から日本ペースで進められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The negotiation proceeded in advantageous way to Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The negotiations initially proceeded to Japan&apos;s advantage.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The negotiations initially proceeded to Japan&apos;s advantage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>まず随行兵士の人数や武器携帯をめぐって、本交渉の前に協議されたが、日本側は朝鮮側の抗議を一蹴している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First of all, the topic about the number of soldiers and carrying arms were talked before starting the negotiation, and Japan-side refused the protest of Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First of all, before starting negotiations, the number of soldiers and carrying arms were talked about, but the Japanese refused the protests of Korea.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First of all, before starting negotiations, the number of soldiers and carrying arms were talked about, but the Japanese refused the protests of Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>そして1876年2月11日に本交渉が開始された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February 11, 1876, the main negotiation started.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February 11, 1876, the main negotiations started.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 11, 1876, the main negotiations started.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>しかし日朝両国の思惑は最初から最後まですれ違っていたといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it can be said that the expectations of Japan and Korea were cross-purposes from the beginning to the end.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it can be said that the expectations of Japan and Korea were at cross-purposes from beginning to end.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it can be said that the expectations of Japan and Korea were at cross-purposes from beginning to end.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>そもそも朝鮮側は、江華島事件に関する謝罪と賠償が交渉のテーマだと考えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Korea thought from the beginning that the theme of the negotiation would be apology and compensation on Ganghwa Island incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Korea thought from the beginning that the theme of negotiations would be an apology and compensation for the Ganghwa Island incident.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Korea thought from the beginning that the theme of negotiations would be an apology and compensation for the Ganghwa Island incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>日清間で数年前に起きた台湾出兵の時の日本側の交渉姿勢が念頭にあったためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That was because the attitude of Japan on the negotiation of the Taiwan expedition which had occurred between Japan and Ching several years before was kept in mind of Korea-side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That was because the Koreans were mindful of the attitude of Japan during the negotiation of the Taiwan expedition which had occurred between Japan and Ching several years before.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That was because the Koreans were mindful of the attitude of Japan during the negotiation of the Taiwan expedition which had occurred between Japan and Ching several years before.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>しかし日本はさきに書いたように、江華島事件はあくまで条約締結のための呼び水に過ぎず、「和約を結ぶこと」こそが主たる目的であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as described before, Japan regarded Ganghwa Island incident just to stimulate the conclusion of the treaty, so that &apos;to conclude a peace treaty&apos; was the main purpose.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as described before, Japan regarded the Ganghwa Island incident as just a stimulus towards conclusion of the treaty, and for them &apos;to conclude a peace treaty&apos; was the main purpose.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as described before, Japan regarded the Ganghwa Island incident as just a stimulus towards conclusion of the treaty, and for them &apos;to conclude a peace treaty&apos; was the main purpose.</e>
<cmt>を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="88">
<j>日本側が突然条約締結を持ち出したのは、以下の理由による。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason why suddenly Japan brought up the conclusion of the treaty was as below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason why Japan suddenly brought up the conclusion of the treaty was as follows.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason why Japan suddenly brought up the conclusion of the treaty was as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>釜山における国交交渉が数年間継続しても挫折しつづけてきたことに焦れた日本はマシュー・カルブレース・ペリーの江戸湾来航の前例に倣い、ソウル特別市に近い江華島で威迫交渉することで一挙に積年の懸案を解決しようと図ったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Japan exhausted that the negotiation of diplomatic relations at Busan repeated failure during several years, it tried to solve the long-standing pending problem at a burst by exercising a menace negotiation at Ganghwa Island near Seoul special city, following the precedent of the arrival of Matthew Calbraith PERRY.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Japan grew anxious that the negotiation of diplomatic relations at Busan repeatedly failed over the course of several years, it tried to solve the long-standing problem at a stroke by exercising a menacing negotiation at Ganghwa Island near Seoul special city, following the precedent of Matthew Calbraith PERRY&apos;s arrival at Edo Bay.</e>
<cmt>Wording. Trans 1 failed to include Edo Bay.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Japan grew anxious that the negotiation of diplomatic relations at Busan repeatedly failed over the course of several years, it tried to solve the long-standing problem at a stroke by exercising a menacing negotiation at Ganghwa Island near Seoul special city, following the precedent of Matthew Calbraith PERRY&apos;s arrival at Edo Bay.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>そのために朝鮮との交渉に際し、事前に日本側はペリーの『日本遠征記』を研究し、交渉姿勢から後に締結する条約に至るまで模倣したと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order that, Japan-side studied &quot;Narrative of the Expedition of an American Squadron to the China Seas and Japan&quot; written by PERRY when they were going to start negotiation with Korea, so that they were supposed to imitate from the attitude for negotiation to conclusion of a treaty which would have been completed later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to do this, before starting negotiations with Korea the Japanese side studied &quot;Narrative of the Expedition of an American Squadron to the China Seas and Japan&quot; written by PERRY, so that they could imitate the attitude toward negotiations and later achieve conclusion of the treaty.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to do this, before starting negotiations with Korea the Japanese side studied &quot;Narrative of the Expedition of an American Squadron to the China Seas and Japan&quot; written by Perry, so that they could imitate the attitude toward negotiations and later achieve conclusion of the treaty.</e>
<cmt>&quot;を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="91">
<j>朝鮮側はこの突然の条約締結の申し入れに驚き、最初は拒否したが、日本側の提示した条約に対する修正案を出すこととなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Surprised by the sudden offer of conclusion of a treaty, at first Korea refused it, however, they decided to present an amendment to the treaty presented by Japan-side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Surprised by the sudden offer of conclusion of the treaty, Korea at first refused it, however, they decided to propose an amendment to the treaty presented by the Japanese.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Surprised by the sudden offer of conclusion of the treaty, Korea at first refused it, but they decided to propose an amendment to the treaty presented by the Japanese.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>朝鮮側が受け入れたのは、以下の理由による。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason why Korea accepted the treaty was as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason why Korea accepted the treaty was as follows.</e>
<cmt>Tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason why Korea accepted the treaty was as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="93">
<j>日本側の砲艦外交に対し、戦端を開く覚悟までは至らなかったこと</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Korea could not prepare for the outbreak of war against the gunboat diplomacy of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Korea could not prepare for the outbreak of war against the gunboat diplomacy of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Korea could not prepare for the outbreak of war against the gunboat diplomacy of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>清朝の実力者李鴻章が条約締結を助言したこと</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A powerful person in the Qing dynasty Hung Chang LI advised to conclude the treaty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A powerful person in the Qing dynasty Hung Chang LI advised them to conclude the treaty.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A powerful person in the Qing dynasty Hung Chang LI advised them to conclude the treaty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>朴珪寿らの開国論者たちの努力によって反対派を説得したこと</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Person who advocated the Theory of opening of a country to the world like Gyu-su PARK strived to persuade the opponents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gyu-su PARK and others, who advocated the theory of opening a country to the world, strived to persuade opponents.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gyu-su PARK and others, who advocated the theory of opening a country to the world, strived to persuade opponents.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="96">
<j>日朝間の交渉で挙がった修正項目は、両国の国名をどう記載するか、相手国に赴く使臣の交渉相手とその資格・往復回数、開港場所とその数、最恵国待遇などであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The amendments proposed at the negotiation between Japan and Korea were the description of the names of both countries, a negotiation partner to the envoi who was going to visit the opponent country, his qualification, the place of the opening port and its number, and most-favored nation treatment, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The amendments proposed at the negotiation between Japan and Korea were: the description of the names of both countries; a negotiation partner to the envoy who was going to visit the other country, and his qualifications and number of visits; the place of the opening port and its number; status as a most-favored nation treatment, and others.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The amendments proposed at the negotiation between Japan and Korea were: the description of the names of both countries; a negotiation partner to the envoy who was going to visit the other country, and his qualifications and number of visits; the place of the opening port and its number; status as a most-favored nation treatment, and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>具体的には後述するが、注目すべきなのは、朝鮮側の修正要求は冊封国としての体面的なものが多く、後々問題となる領事裁判権は一切問題とならなかった点である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The detail will be described later, but notable point was that Korea required amendments to maintain their respectability as Sakuho country, and did not mind at all about consular jurisdiction which would become a problem later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The details will be described later, but an important point was that while Korea required amendments to maintain their honor as a Sakuho country, they did not mind at all about consular jurisdiction, which would later become a problem.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The details will be described later, but an important point was that while Korea required amendments to maintain their honor as a tributary country, they did not mind at all about consular jurisdiction, which would later become a problem.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>数ヶ月後に結ばれた条規附録や貿易規則で定められた関税自主権などもスムーズに承認された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tariff autonomy, which was prescribed in the affiliated provision and trading rules concluded several months later, was also approved smoothly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tariff autonomy, which was prescribed in the affiliated provision and trading rules concluded several months later, was also approved smoothly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tariff autonomy, which was prescribed in the affiliated provision and trading rules concluded several months later, was also approved smoothly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>この点は朝鮮側の国際情勢に関する疎さに由来するものであって、日本側が本来意図していた条約項目はそのまま締結される運びとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Korea was ignorant about the international affairs, the provisions which were prepared by Japan were concluded without any amendments.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Korea was ignorant about international affairs, the provisions which were prepared by Japan were concluded without any amendments.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Korea was ignorant about international affairs, the provisions prepared by Japan were concluded without any amendments.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="100">
<j>条約批准の段階に至っても、朝鮮側の関心事は体面的なものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even at the stage of treaty ratification, Korea was interested just in their respectability.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even at the stage of treaty ratification, Korea was only interested in their honor.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even at the stage of treaty ratification, Korea was only interested in their honor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>すなわち批准の際、朝鮮国王の署名を要しないことを日本側に求めたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is to say, Korea required Japan not to demand signification of the King of Korea at ratification.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Namely, Korea required Japan not to demand the signature of the King of Korea at ratification.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Namely, Korea required Japan not to demand the signature of the King of Korea at ratification.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>結局、この問題は「朝鮮国主上之宝」という玉璽を新鋳して押下批准することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So that Korea newly made the Imperial Seal of &apos;朝鮮国主上之宝&apos; (treasure of King of Korea), put it on the document at ratification.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end, Korea made a new Imperial Seal called &apos;朝鮮国主上之宝&apos;, and used this on the document at ratification.</e>
<cmt>I think romaji would be preferable to kanji here but was unsure of the reading so left it unchanged.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end, Korea made a new Imperial Seal called &apos;朝鮮国主上之宝&apos;, and used this on the document at ratification.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>そしてついに2月27日（朝鮮旧暦2月3日）に、江華府練武堂で条約を締結及び批准したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Finally on February 27, the treaty was concluded and ratified at Ganghwabu Renbudo.</e>
<cmt>「練武堂」が定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Finally on February 27, the treaty was concluded and ratified at Ganghwabu Renbudo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Finally on February 27, the treaty was concluded and ratified at Ganghwabu Renbudo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>条約の主な内容</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main contents of the treaty</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Main contents of the treaty</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Main contents of the treaty</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="104">
<j>修好条規は12款で構成され、条文は漢文と日本語で書かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The treaty of Peace and Amity was consisted of 12 provisions, written in both Kanbun (Chinese classics) and Japanese.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The treaty of Peace and Amity consisted of 12 provisions, written in both Kanbun (Chinese classics) and Japanese.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The treaty of Peace and Amity consisted of 12 provisions, written in both Chinese and Japanese.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>また両国の外交文書は日本語と朝鮮真文（漢文）で書くこととし、日本側の文書には、先10年間は日本語に漢文を併記する事とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also they decided that the diplomatic documents of both countries should be written in Japanese and Kanbun (Chinese classics), and the documents of Japan should be written both Japanese and Kanbun for the next 10 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also they decided that the diplomatic documents of both countries should be written in Japanese and Kanbun (Chinese classics), and the documents of Japan should be written in both Japanese and Kanbun for the next 10 years.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also they decided that the diplomatic documents of both countries should be written in Japanese and the legitimate language of Korea (namely Chinese), and the documents of Japan should be written in both Japanese and Chinese for the next 10 years.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>両国の国名はそれぞれ「大日本国」、「大朝鮮国」と表記することとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The both countries should be described as &apos;Great Japanese Nation&apos; and &apos;Great Korean Nation&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The two countries should be described as &apos;Great Japanese Nation&apos; and &apos;Great Korean Nation&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The two countries should be described as &apos;Great Japanese Nation&apos; and &apos;Great Korean Nation.&apos;</e>
<cmt>を半角とし、位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="107">
<j>第一款　朝鮮は自主の国であり、日本と平等の権利を有する国家と認める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The provision 1 Korea is an independent country, so it is admitted that Korea is a nation to have an equal right as Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Provision 1 - Korea is an independent country, so it is admitted that Korea is a nation that has equal rights with Japan.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Provision 1 - Korea is an independent country, so it is admitted that Korea is a nation that has equal rights with Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="108">
<j>この条文は、朝鮮が清朝の藩属国であること考慮して特に日本が挿入した一文である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This provision was inserted by Japan especially considering the situation of Korea as a client state of the Qing dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This provision was specially inserted by Japan considering the situation of Korea as a client state of the Qing dynasty.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This provision was specially inserted by Japan considering the situation of Korea as a client state of the Qing dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>冊封体制の下での「属国」・「属邦」とは、近代あるいは現代の国際法におけるそれとは表記を同じくしながら、性格を異にする存在とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The meaning of &apos;subject state&apos; or &apos;client state&apos; was different from that used in the international law in modern times and the present day, despite they have the same expression.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the terms &apos;subject state&apos; or &apos;client state&apos; used under the tributary system have a different meaning in the international law of recent history and the present day, the same expressions are still used.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the terms &apos;subject state&apos; or &apos;client state&apos; used under the tributary system have a different meaning in the international law of recent history and the present day, the same expressions are still used.</e>
<cmt>を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>近代国際法の立場から見て、当時の朝鮮をどのように位置づけるかは種々の意見があったが、日本はこの一文を入れることで、解釈の一元化を試み朝鮮を近代国際法に於ける独立国に措定しようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were several opinions about the situation of Korea at that time from the point of the modern international law, but by inserting that sentence, Japan tried to unify and determine the interpretation of Korea in the modern international law as the independent country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were several opinions about the situation of Korea at that time from the point of modern international law, but by inserting that sentence, Japan tried to unify the interpretation of Korea as an independent country under modern international law.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were several opinions about the situation of Korea at that time from the point of modern international law, but by inserting that sentence, Japan tried to unify the interpretation of Korea as an independent country under modern international law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>「自主の国」独立国という解釈であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The interpretation was &apos;country of freedom&apos;, independent country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The interpretation was &apos;country of freedom&apos;, independent country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The interpretation was an &apos;autonomous country,&apos; or independent country.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>つまりそう措定することで清朝が朝鮮に介入する余地を無くそうとしたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan tried to prevent the Qing dynasty from intervening Korea by determining the interpretation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan tried to prevent the Qing dynasty from intervening in Korea by determining the interpretation.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan tried to prevent the Qing dynasty from intervening in Korea by determining the interpretation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>しかし朝鮮側はそのようには解釈していなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Korea did not understand as Japan intended.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Korea did not understand as Japan intended.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Korea did not understand as Japan intended.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>冊封体制下では「属国」でありながら、「自主」であることは矛盾しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the Sakuho system, &apos;being independent&apos; as well as &apos;being client state&apos; did not contradict.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the Sakuho system, being &apos;independent&apos; as well as being a&apos;client state&apos; did not contradict each other.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the tributary system, being an &apos;independent&apos; state as well as an &apos;autonomous state&apos; did not contradict each other.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>というより属国か独立国か、という二項対立的な枠組みそのものが近代の所産である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Or it can be said that dividing into the two conflicting terms of client or independent is offspring of modern times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Or it can be said that the framework where the two terms &apos;client&apos; and &apos;independent&apos; conlict is an offspring of modern times.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Or it can be said that the framework where the two terms &apos;client&apos; and &apos;independent&apos; conflict is an offspring of modern times.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>国王が臣下の礼をとっても、朝鮮の国政全般に清朝の影響が及ぶわけではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even if the king of Korea showed the vassal fealty, the Qing dynasty would not influence the affairs of state in Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even if the king of Korea showed loyalty to the Qing dynasty, Qing would not influence affairs of the state in Korea.</e>
<cmt>The term &apos;vassal fealty&apos; is hard to understand.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even if the king of Korea showed loyalty to the Qing dynasty, Qing would not influence affairs of the state in Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>たとえば清は日朝間の外交関係すらよく把握していなかったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, the Qing of dynasty did not grasp even diplomatic relations between Japan and Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, the Qing of dynasty did not understand even diplomatic relations between Japan and Korea.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, the Qing dynasty did not understand even diplomatic relations between Japan and Korea.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>清・朝関係は、近代的国際法から見ると極めてファジーな属人主義的関係であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The relation between Japan and Korea was quite fuzzily dependent from the point of modern international law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The independence of the relationship between Qing and Korea was extremely blurred from the point of modern international law.</e>
<cmt>Mistranslation - Qing and Korea, not Japan and Korea.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the viewpoint of modern international law, the relationship between the Qing dynasty and Korea was extremely ambiguous on the personal principle.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>この条項に対する両国の思惑の違いは、この後も継続し、最終的な決着を見たのは下関条約の時である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The expectations of the two countries for this provision did not meet for years, so that it was after the conclusion of the Treaty of Shimonoseki that they reached a final settlement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The expectations of the two countries for this provision did not meet for years, so that it was only after the conclusion of the Treaty of Shimonoseki that they reached a final settlement.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The misunderstanding between the two countries for this provision had not been solved for years until the Shimonoseki Treaty, and at that time they reached a final settlement.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>その条約の第一条がほぼ同様の一文となっているのは、そのためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the reason why the sentence of the Provision 1 was almost the same as that of the Treaty of Shimonoseki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the reason why the sentence of provision 1 was almost the same as that of the Treaty of Shimonoseki.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the reason why the sentence of the provision 1 was almost the same as that of the Shimonoseki Treaty.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="121">
<j>第二款　日朝両国が相互にその首都に公使を駐在させること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Provision 2 Ministers should be resided in the capitals in both Japan and Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Provision 2 - ministers of Japan and Korea should reside in the capitals of each other&apos;s country.</e>
<cmt>Wording/ fragment</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Provision 2 - ministers of Japan and Korea should reside in the capitals of each other&apos;s country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="122">
<j>日本側原案では、公使は常駐であったが、朝鮮側の要求で「随時」とし、必要がある場合に限り派遣することとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan required in the original plan that ministers should be permanently stationed, but it was amended to &apos;at any time&apos; to dispatch them only when they were necessary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the original plan Japan required that ministers should be permanently stationed, but it was amended to &apos;at any time&apos; so they could be dispatched only when they were necessary.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the original plan Japan required that ministers should be permanently stationed, but it was amended to &apos;at any time&apos; so they could be dispatched only when they were necessary.</e>
<cmt>を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="123">
<j>第四款・第五款　すでに日本公館が存在する釜山広域市以外に2港を選び開港すること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Provision 4, The Provision 5 Except for Busan Metropolitan City where already the diplomatic establishment of Japan is, other two ports should be chosen and opened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Provisions 4 and 5 - in addition to Busan Metropolitan City, where the diplomatic establishment of Japan was located, two more ports should be chosen and opened.</e>
<cmt>Wording/ fragment</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Provisions 4 and 5 - in addition to Busan Metropolitan City, where the diplomatic establishment of Japan was located, two more ports should be chosen and opened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>開港においては土地を貸借し家屋を造営しあるいは所在する朝鮮人の家屋を賃借することも各人の自由に任せること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When ports were opened, people can decide by themselves whether they borrow the land and construct their houses, or borrow there houses from Koreans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When ports are opened, people can decide by themselves whether to borrow land and construct their houses, or borrow their houses from Koreans.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When ports are opened, people can decide by themselves whether to borrow land and construct their houses, or borrow their houses from Koreans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="125">
<j>具体的な開港地の選定などは、改めて後で協議することになっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was scheduled to negotiate later about the decision of several matters such as the exact places for opening the port.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Negotiations about the decision of several matters such as the exact places for opening the port were to be scheduled for a later date.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Negotiations about matters, such as the decision of ports to be opened, were scheduled for a later date.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>そして1880年に元山市、1883年に仁川広域市が開港した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two ports were opened, in Wonsan City in 1880 and in Incheon Metropolitan City in 1883.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two ports were opened, in Wonsan City in 1880 and in Incheon Metropolitan City in 1883.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two ports were opened, in Wonsan City in 1880 and in Incheon Metropolitan City in 1883.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="127">
<j>第七款　朝鮮の沿岸は島嶼岩礁が険しいため、きわめて危険であるので、日本の航海者が自由に沿岸を測量してその位置や深度を明らかにして地図を編纂して両国客船の安全な航海を可能とするべし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Provision 7 Because the coast of Korea is extremely dangerous as it is rugged and precipitous, the navigators from Japan can measure the coast freely and make up a map to show the position and the depth in order to realize the safe navigation of the passenger boats from both countries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Provision 7 - because the rugged and precipitous coast of Korea is extremely dangerous, the navigators from Japan can measure the coast freely and make up a map to show the position and the depth in order to allow safe navigation of passenger boats from both countries.</e>
<cmt>Wording/ fragment</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Provision 7 - because the rugged and precipitous coast of Korea is extremely dangerous, the Japanese navigators should be able to measure the coast freely and make up a map to show the position and the depth in order to ensure safety of the navigation of passenger boats of both countries.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="128">
<j>第九款　通商については、各々の人民に任せ、自由貿易を行うこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Provision 9 As for the trade, the people of both countries can decide by themselves to practice free trade.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Provision 9 - free trade should be allowed, and left to the people of both countries.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Provision 9 - free trade should be allowed, and left to the people of both countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>両国の官吏は少しもこれに関係してはならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The government officials of both countries should not participate in it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Government officials of both countries should not participate in it.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Government officials of both countries should not participate in it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>貿易の制限を行ったり、禁止してはならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They cannot restrict nor prohibit the trade.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They cannot restrict nor prohibit trade.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They cannot restrict nor prohibit trade.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>しかし詐欺や貸借の不払いがあれば両国の官吏はこれを取り締まり追徴すべし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However in the case of fraud or nonpayment of borrowing and lending, the government officials of both countries should control and exact it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However in the case of fraud or nonpayment of borrowing and lending, the government officials of both countries should regulate this and impose additional charges.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However in the case of fraud or nonpayment of borrowing and lending, the government officials of both countries should regulate this and impose additional charges.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="132">
<j>自由貿易について定めた条項。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The provision provided on free trade.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The provision provided on free trade.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The provision regulated on free trade.</e>
<cmt>provideの重複を避けました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="133">
<j>第十款　日本人が開港にて罪を犯した場合は日本の官吏が裁判を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Provision 10 If a Japanese committed a crime in the city where the port is opened, the Japanese government official will try it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Provision 10 - if a Japanese commits a crime in a city where the port is opened, the Japanese government official will conduct a trial.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Provision 10 - if a Japanese commits a crime in a city where the port is opened, the Japanese government official will conduct a trial.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>また朝鮮人が罪を犯した場合は朝鮮官吏が裁判を行うこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also if a Korean committed a crime, the Korean government official will try it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also if a Korean commits a crime, the Korean government official will conduct a trial.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also if a Korean commits a crime, the Korean government official will conduct a trial.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>しかし双方は、その国法をもって裁判を行い、すこしも加減をすることなく努めて公平に裁判することを示すべし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the both sides should try under the state law and judge as equally as possible without any modification.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, both sides should conduct trials under the state law and pass judgment as equally as possible without any modification.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, both sides should conduct trials under the state law and pass judgment as equally as possible without any modification.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="136">
<j>領事裁判権に関する条項。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The provision on consular jurisdiction</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The provision on consular jurisdiction</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The provision on consular jurisdiction</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>この項目については三条実美からは何ら指示がなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanetomi SANJO did not give any instruction about this provision.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanetomi SANJO did not give any instruction about this provision.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanetomi SANJO did not give any instruction about this provision.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>黒田ら全権大使たちの個人的判断で挿入されたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was considered that the provision was inserted by the individual decision of the ambassador plenipotentiary, KURODA and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was thought that this provision was inserted at the individual decision of the ambassador plenipotentiary, KURODA, and his team.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was thought that this provision was inserted at the personal decision of the ambassador plenipotentiary, Kuroda, and his team.</e>
<cmt>Kurodaとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>この条約における不平等的性格を決定づけた条項といえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be said that this provision decided the character of the unequal treaty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be said that the unequal nature of the treaty was determined by this provision.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be said that the unequal nature of the treaty was determined by this provision.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>朝鮮国内においては、国籍によって裁判の管轄を分けるが、日本国内においては一切朝鮮側の領事裁判権を認めないという点で片務的なものとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a one-sided treaty, because while the jurisdiction of trial was divided depending on the nationality in Korea, the consular jurisdiction of Korea was never admitted in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a one-sided treaty, because while the jurisdiction of trial was divided depending on nationality in Korea, the consular jurisdiction of Korea was never admitted in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a one-sided treaty, because while the jurisdiction of trial was divided depending on nationality in Korea, the consular jurisdiction of Korea was never admitted in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="141">
<j>朝鮮側がこの条項になんら抵抗を示していないのは、先に述べたように国際法についての無関心からくるのであるが、それ以外に江戸時代の対馬藩との往来の頃には民事案件であろうと刑事のものであろうと、日本人犯罪者は倭館の日本人責任者に引き渡していた慣例があったためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One reason why Korea did not resist to this provision was that they were indifferent to the international law, as described before, and another reason was that during the Edo period when they traded with Tsushima clan, traditionally the criminals were given over the Japanese in charge in Wakan (consular office) no matter whether it was the case of civil or criminal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One reason why Korea did not resist this provision was that they were indifferent to international law, as described before, and another reason was that during the Edo period when they traded with the Tsushima clan, traditionally the criminals were given over to the Japanese in charge in Wakan (consular office) no matter whether it was a civil or criminal case.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One reason why Korea did not resist this provision was that they were indifferent to international law, as described before, but there was another reason that during the Edo period when they traded with the Tsushima clan, traditionally the criminals were given over to the Japanese in charge in the Japanese consular office, no matter whether it was a civil or criminal case.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>すなわち朝鮮側は、この時の慣例を条文化したものだと認識していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That was to say, Korea perceived that the custom at that time was provided in the treaty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That was to say, Korea perceived that the custom at that time was provided in the treaty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That was to say, Korea perceived that the custom at that time was provided in the treaty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>開港後、日本人が次第に多く流入するようになると、これが失策だったことに気づくことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After opening the ports, increasingly the Japanese were coming in Korea, they noticed that admitting that provision was mistake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After opening the ports, there was an influx of Japanese into Korea, and they realized that admitting that provision was mistake.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After opening the ports, there was an influx of Japanese into Korea, and they realized that admitting that provision was a mistake.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="144">
<j>この他特記しておかねばならないのが、最恵国待遇の条項である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The provision of most-favored nation status should be mentioned particularly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The other provision that should be mention is that regarding most-favored nation status.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The other provision that should be mention is that regarding most-favored nation status.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>日本側の原案にはこの条項が当然入っていたが、朝鮮側の強い要望により削除された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The provision was provided as a matter of course in the original plan given by Japan, but it was deleted, because Korea strongly required it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The provision was provided as a matter of course in the original plan given by Japan, but due to Korea&apos;s strong demands it was deleted.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The provision was provided as a matter of course in the original plan given by Japan, but due to Korea&apos;s strong demands it was deleted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>朝鮮は今後も西欧列強に対し開国する意志がないので無用だというのが、その理由であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason for that was that Korea would not open the country to the Western Europe powerful countries in the future, so that provision would not be necessary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason for that was that Korea did not intend to open the country to the powerful countries of Western Europe in the future, so that provision would not be necessary.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason for that was that Korea did not intend to open the country to the powerful countries of Western Europe in the future, so that provision would not be necessary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>条約交渉－2－</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The negotiation of the treaty -2-</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The negotiation of the treaty -2-</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The negotiation of the treaty -2-</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>日朝修好条規付録及び貿易規則の交渉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The negotiation of the subsidiary agreements of Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity and trade regulations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The negotiation of the subsidiary agreements of Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity and trade regulations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The negotiation of the subsidiary agreements of Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity and trade regulations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="147">
<j>通商関係については、条規そのものでは詳しい取り決めをしなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They did not decide about trade relations in detail in the provision itself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They did not decide about trade relations in detail in the provision itself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They did not decide about trade relations in detail in the provision itself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>第11条で6ヶ月以内に再度協議することを定めたのみであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They just decided in the Provision 11 to talk again within 6 months.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They just decided in the Provision 11 to talk again within 6 months.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They just decided in the Provision 11 to talk again within 6 months.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>そこで8月5日よりソウルで交渉が開始された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So that they resumed the negotiation in Seoul from August 5.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They resumed negotiations in Seoul from August 5.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They resumed negotiations in Seoul from August 5.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>日本側代表は理事官外務大丞である宮本小一、朝鮮側代表は講修官議政府堂上の肩書きを持つ趙寅熙であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The representatives were Resident Foreign Ministry, Okazu MIYAMOTO from Japan and CHO from Korea, who had a title of Koshukan Giseifu Dojo.</e>
<cmt>「趙寅熙」の正確な読み方が不明です。姓のCHOのみといたしました（チョ　インヒとも思われます）。また、肩書きもローマ字表記としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The representatives were Resident Foreign Ministry, Okazu MIYAMOTO from Japan and CHO from Korea, who had the title of Koshukan Giseifu Dojo.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The representatives were the Resident Foreign Minister Okazu MIYAMOTO from Japan and In Hee CHO from Korea, a negotiator on behalf of the Korean government with a title of 講修官議政府堂上.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="151">
<j>交渉中特に問題となったのは、公使がソウルに官舎を構えるか否か（公使派出問題）、日本の役人が朝鮮内地を移動できるか否か、開港地における一般日本人の移動範囲、米や雑穀の輸出入といったテーマであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The matters risen during the negotiation were, whether the ministers would establish the official residence (a problem of dispatch of ministers), whether Japanese government officials could move inland of Korea, the range of traveling for general Japanese in the place of opining the port, and import and export of rice and millet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The matters brought up during the negotiation were, whether the ministers would establish the official residence (a problem of dispatch of ministers), whether Japanese government officials could move inland in Korea, the range of traveling for general Japanese in the places where ports were opened, and import and export of rice and grain.</e>
<cmt>Wording. I think grain is a more commonly used word than millet.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They had long arguments about those topics in particular, such as whether the ministers would establish the official residence (a problem of dispatch of ministers), whether Japanese government officials could move inland in Korea, the range of traveling for general Japanese in the places where ports were opened, and import and export of rice and grain.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>交渉の結果、官舎の設置や朝鮮内地の旅行は、朝鮮側の強い反対で日本側が撤回した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of the negotiation, Japan withdrew about the matter of establishment of the official residence and traveling inland of Korea, because of severe objection by Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of the negotiation, Japan withdrew the matters regarding establishment of the official residence and traveling inland in Korea, because of severe objection by Korea.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of the negotiation, Japan withdrew the matters regarding establishment of the official residence and traveling inland in Korea, because of severe objection by Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>また開港地での移動範囲は10里（朝鮮里程）以内となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The range of movement in the place the port was opened was within 10 Ri (Korean mileage).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The range of movement allowed from the open ports was within 10 Ri (Korean mileage).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The range of movement in the city with open ports was set within 10 Ri (Korean mileage).</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="154">
<j>穀類の輸出入は条規に盛り込まれることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The export and import of millet was decided to be described in the regulations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The export and import of grain was to be described in the regulations.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The export and import of grain was to be described in the regulations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>12回にわたる交渉の結果、8月24日（旧暦7月6日）、細目に当たる修好条規付録（11款）と章程にあたる貿易規則（11則）が定められる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of the negotiations over 12 times, subsidiary agreements of Treaty of Amity (11 provisions) as the details and trade regulations as the rules were established on August 24.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of negotiations over 12 times, details for subsidiary agreements of the Treaty of Amity (11 provisions) and ordinance for trade regulations were established on August 24.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of negotiations over 12 times, details for subsidiary agreements of the Treaty of Amity (11 provisions) and the precise rules of trade regulations (11 rules) were established on August 24.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>関税自主権に関わる重要な取り決めが含まれていたが、大きな衝突もなく、短期間で妥結した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It included the important agreement which was related to tariff autonomy, the negotiation was settled in a short period without serious conflict.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It included an important agreement related to tariff autonomy, but the negotiation was settled in a short period without serious conflict.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It included an important agreement related to tariff autonomy, but the negotiation was settled in a short period without serious conflict.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>主な内容</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main contents</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Main contents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Main contents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>付録</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Appendix</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Appendix</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Appendix</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="157">
<j>付録第五款　開港地において日本人は朝鮮人に賃金を支払うことにより雇用することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Appendix the Provision 5 Japanese people can employ Korean people by paying wages at the place where the port was opened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The appendix of provision 5 - Japanese people can employ Korean people by paying wages at the place where the port was opened.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The appendix of provision 5 - Japanese people can employ Korean people by paying wages at the place where the port was opened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>朝鮮政府の許可あれば、来日することも問題なしとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese people can come to Japan if they had permission by the Korean government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese people can come to Japan if they have permission from the Korean government.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese people can come to Japan if they have permission from the Korean government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="159">
<j>この条文前半は、三条太政大臣が譲歩すべきではないとした訓示の一つであったが、朝鮮側の反対はなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first half of this provision was one of the instructions given by the Grand Minister SANJO who insisted not to compromise, but Korea did not opposed to it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first half of this provision was one of the instructions given by the Grand Minister SANJO who insisted not to compromise, but Korea did not oppose it.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first half of this provision was one of the instructions given by the Grand Minister Sanjo who insisted not to compromise, but Korea did not oppose it.</e>
<cmt>Sanjoとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>来日については交渉の妨げになるようであれば、削除もやむなしという姿勢であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan prepared to delete the part of coming to Japan, if it interfered the negotiation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If the part concerning coming to Japan interfered with negotiations, Japan were prepared to delete it.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If the part concerning coming to Japan interfered with negotiations, Japan were prepared to delete it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="161">
<j>付属第七款　開港場において日本人は自国の貨幣を使用することができ、朝鮮人は売買によって入手した貨幣を日本製品購入のために使用することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Appendix the Provision 7 Japanese people can use the Japanese currency at the city where the port was opened, and Korean people can use them that they got through buying and selling when they purchase the Japanese products.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The appendix of provision 7 - Japanese people can use the Japanese currency at cities where the port is open, and Korean people can use currency that they got through trade when they purchase Japanese products.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The appendix of provision 7 - Japanese people can use the Japanese currency at cities where the port is open, and Korean people can use currency that they got through trade when they purchase Japanese products.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>また日本人は朝鮮銅貨を運輸することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also Japanese people can carry Korean copper coins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also Japanese people can carry Korean copper coins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also Japanese people can carry Korean copper coins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="163">
<j>貨幣偽造があれば、その国の法に照らし罰する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of forge of currency, it should be punished based on the law of the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Forgery of currency should be punished based on the law of the country.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Forgery of currency should be punished based on the law of the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="164">
<j>日本人が日朝双方の貨幣を使用することができるようにする条項も、三条から譲歩してはいけないと訓示されていたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The provision about the currency providing that Japanese people could use those of the both countries was also instructed by SANJO not to compromise.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SANJO also instructed that the provision about the currency stating that Japanese people could use those of both countries was not to be compromised.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanjo also instructed that the provision stating that Japanese people could use currencies of Japan and Korea was not to be compromised.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>朝鮮側は朝鮮銅貨である常平銭を日本人が使用することを禁じようとしたが、日本側に押し切られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Korea tried to prohibit Japanese people to use the Korean copper coin called Joheisen, but it failed because of the pressure by Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Korea tried to prohibit use of the Korean copper coin called Joheisen by Japanese people, but it failed because of pressure by Japan.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Korea tried to prohibit use of the Korean copper coin called Sangpyeong Tongbo by Japanese people, but it failed because of opposition from Japan.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="166">
<j>材料の銅を輸入に頼らざるを得なかった朝鮮としては、日本によって国外に銅が流出する危惧を抱いていたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Korea had to rely on the import of the material of copper, they worried that coppers would flow out of Korea by Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Korea had to rely on the import of the material copper, they worried that coppers would flow out of Korea to Japan.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Korea relied on the import of copper, the material of currency, they worried that copper would flow out of Korea to Japan.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="167">
<j>付録第十款　朝鮮は海外諸国との国交がないが、今後朝鮮に国交のない諸国の船が遭難し、漂着する人がいれば、日本の管理官がいる開港地まで送り届け、そこから遭難者の本国に送還することとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Appendix the Provision 10 Although Korea did not have diplomatic relations with foreign countries, if the ships of those countries were shipwrecked and somebody was drifted ashore, they would be sent to the city of opening port where the Japanese officer was, then the victims would be sent back to their own countries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Appedix of provision 10 - Although Korea did not have diplomatic relations with foreign countries, if the ships of those countries were shipwrecked and somebody drifted ashore, they would be sent to the city of an open port where a Japanese officer was, then the victims would be sent back to their own countries.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Appendix of provision 10 - Although Korea did not have diplomatic relations with other foreign countries, if the ships of those countries were shipwrecked and somebody drifted ashore, they would be sent to the city of an open port where a Japanese officer was stationed, and then the victims would be sent back to their own countries from there.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="168">
<j>この条項は日朝間にだけ関わるものではなく、その他の国も念頭に置いたものとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This provision was considered to be related not only between Japan and Korea, but also between Korea and other countries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This provision was related not only to events between Japan and Korea, but also between Korea and other countries.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This provision was related not only to events between Japan and Korea, but also between Korea and other countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="169">
<j>人道的措置の履行を義務づけるこの条項は、西欧列強の朝鮮に対する要望を日本が替わりに挿入したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This provision that provided the obligation of humanitarian measures was inserted by Japan for the requirement of the Western Europe powerful countries against Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This provision, which provided the obligation of humanitarian measures, was inserted by Japan as a requirement of the powerful countries of Western Europe against Korea.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This provision, which provided the obligation of humanitarian measures, was inserted by Japan as a requirement of the powerful countries of Western Europe toward Korea.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>パークスや駐日アメリカ公使ビンガムなどはこの一条の挿入に対し非常な肯定的評価をしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">PARKS and the American minister to Japan, BINGHAM gave extremely positive estimates to the insertion of this provision.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">PARKS and the American minister to Japan, BINGHAM gave extremely positive estimates to the insertion of this provision.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Parks and Bingham, the American minister to Japan, gave extremely positive estimates to the insertion of this provision.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>規則</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regulations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regulations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regulations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="171">
<j>第6則　開港地での米や雑穀の輸出入を認める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Regulation 6 Admit the export and import of rice and millets at the city of opening port.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regulation 6 - Admit the export and import of rice and grain at the city of an open port.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regulation 6 - Admitting the export and import of rice and grain at the city of an open port.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="172">
<j>条約締結以前、大量の米が対馬に流出したことがあったため、朝鮮側は穀類の輸出入禁止を提案したが、日本側が押し切った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a large amount of rice had flown out to Tsushima before the conclusion of the treaty, Korea proposed the prohibition of the export and import of rice and millets, but Japan opposed and decided it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As there had been a large outflow of rice to Tsushima before the conclusion of the treaty, Korea proposed the prohibition of the export and import of rice and grain, but Japan successfully opposed this.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As there had been a large outflow of rice to Tsushima before the conclusion of the treaty, Korea proposed the prohibition of the export and import of rice and grain, but Japan overcame the opposition from Korea successfully.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="173">
<j>貿易が開始されると、朝鮮側の米輸出過多となり米価が高騰した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After starting the trade, the rice of Korea was exported excessively, rice price was soared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After starting trade, Korean rice was exported excessively, and price of rice soared.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After starting trade, Korean rice was exported excessively, and price of rice soared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="174">
<j>第9則　指定された開港場以外において密貿易を行い、その地の官僚に摘発された時は、日本の管理官に引き渡し、日本側は没収した金品を全て朝鮮側に交付すべし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The regulation 9 If an illegal trade at a site except for the appointed ports was exposed by the government officials of the area, the criminal would be given over to the officer of the administration of Japan, and Japan should return all of the confiscated money and goods to Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regulation 9 - If illegal trade at a site outside the appointed ports was exposed by the government officials of the area, the criminal would be given over to the officer of the Japanese administration, and Japan should return all of the confiscated money and goods to Korea.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regulation 9 - If illegal trade at a site outside the appointed ports was exposed by the government officials of the area, the criminal would be given over to the officer of the Japanese administration, and Japan should return all of the confiscated money and goods to Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="175">
<j>貿易規則そのものには穀物の輸出入及び港税が不当に低く抑えられていることを除けば、さして問題となる箇所はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Except for the unfairly low tariff on the export and import of grains and that on port, there were no points that caused a problem in the trade regulation itself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Except for the unfairly low tariff on the export and import of grains and on the ports, there were no points that caused a problem in the trade regulation itself.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Except for the unfairly low tariff on the export and import of grains and on the ports, there were no points that caused a problem in the trade regulation itself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="176">
<j>不平等条約的性格が看取されるのは、この時貿易規則とは別に、宮本小一から趙寅熙に渡された公文（「修好条規付録に付属する往復文書」）の中においてである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The character as an equal treaty can be seen in the official document (&apos;correspondence attached to the appendix of treaty of amity&apos;) which was handed over from Okazu MIYAMOTO to CHO apart from the trade regulations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The character as an unequal treaty can be seen in the official document (&apos;correspondence attached to the appendix of the treaty of amity&apos;) which was handed over from Okazu MIYAMOTO to CHO, apart from the trade regulations.</e>
<cmt>Mistranslation - unequal treaty, not equal treaty.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The character as an unequal treaty can be seen in the official document (&apos;the correspondence attached to the appendix of the treaty of amity&apos;) which was handed over from Okazu MIYAMOTO to In Hee CHO, apart from the trade regulations.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="177">
<j>この公文は「人民に公布して不可なるもの」と位置づけられたものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This official document was treated as &apos;document which should not be proclaimed to the people&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This official document was treated as &apos;a document which should not be proclaimed to the people&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This official document was treated as &apos;a document which should not be proclaimed to the people.&apos;</e>
<cmt>を半角にし、位置をずらしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="178">
<j>公文の一部　日本から朝鮮に輸出するものについては日本の税関では輸出税をかけず、一方朝鮮から日本への輸出するものにも輸入税をかけない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A part of the official document The exported products from Japan to Korea would not be imposed export duties in the Customs in Japan, while the products exported from Korea to Japan would not be imposed import duties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A part of the official document - The products exported from Japan to Korea will not be imposed export duties in customs in Japan, while the products exported from Korea to Japan will not be imposed import duties.</e>
<cmt>Tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A part of the official document - The products exported from Japan to Korea will not be imposed export duties in customs in Japan, while the products exported from Korea to Japan will not be imposed import duties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="179">
<j>日朝間の貿易は無関税にするという通告。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a notification that the trade between Japan and Korea would not be imposed taxes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a notification that taxes would not be imposed on trade between Japan and Korea.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a notification that taxes would not be imposed on trade between Japan and Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="180">
<j>いわゆる関税自主権の喪失を決定づけた一文である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This sentence determined the loss of tariff autonomy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This sentence determined the loss of tariff autonomy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This sentence determined the loss of tariff autonomy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="181">
<j>一見双方平等のようであるが、貿易に関する力量がすでに異なっていたため、朝鮮側にとって著しく不利なものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seemed an equal treaty, but the ability of trade was already different, so that it was remarkably disadvantageous to Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seemed an equal treaty, but the ability to trade was already different, so it was remarkably disadvantageous to Korea.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seemed an equal treaty at a glance, but the ability to trade was already different, so it was remarkably disadvantageous to Korea.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="182">
<j>この時の使節団訪朝前に、日本では寺島宗則外務卿が、「朝鮮輸出税は今より無論に是を徴せす。彼国より輸入し来る物品と雖少数、且多くは実用品にて国害となるへき物品無之候」と三条太政大臣に意見具申している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the envoy visited Korea from Japan, Chief of Foreign Ministry Munenori TERASHIMA gave his opinion to the Grand Minister SANJO &apos;The export duty to Korea would not be imposed from now on. Although the import products from Korea would be not so many, most of them were utilities which would not be harmful for our country.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the envoy visited Korea from Japan, Chief of the Foreign Ministry Munenori TERASHIMA gave his opinion to the Grand Minister SANJO &apos;Export duty to Korea will not be imposed from now on. Although the imported products from Korea would be not so many, most of them were utilities which would not be harmful to our country.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the envoy visited Korea from Japan, Munenori TERASHIMA, the chief of the Foreign Ministry, gave his opinion to the Grand Minister Sanjo, &apos;Export duties to Korea will not be imposed from now on. As the imported products from Korea would be not so many and most of them were utilities, those would not be harmful to our country.&apos;</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="183">
<j>つまり日本側に与える経済的ダメージが少ないからこそ無関税を唱えたことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This meant that as it had a little economic damage, he proposed not to impose the tax.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He meant that because there would be little economic damage to Japan he proposed not to impose the tax.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He meant that because there would be little economic damage to Japan he proposed not to impose the tax.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="184">
<j>これを受け三条は「貿易の催進を要する為、彼我共に輸出入税を徴するなし。是通商章程中の要旨なり」（句読及び強調、加筆者）と使節団に訓示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In response to this, SANJO instructed to the envoy &apos;In order to promote trade, the export and import duty would not be imposed in both sides. This is the point of the provision of the trade.&apos; (punctuation and emphasis were improved by a writer)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In response to this, SANJO instructed the envoy &apos;In order to promote trade, export and import duty will not be imposed on both sides. This is the point of the provision of trade.&apos; (punctuation and emphasis were improved by a writer)</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response to this, Sanjo instructed the envoy &apos;In order to promote trade, export and import duties will not be imposed on both sides. This is the point of the provision of trade (punctuation and emphasis were improved by a writer).&apos;</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="185">
<j>宮本小一はそれを忠実に提案し、朝鮮側は国際法の常識に欠けていたため反論せず、そのまま無関税体制が敷かれることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okazu MIYAMOTO proposed it faithfully, as Korea did not oppose to it because of the ignorance to the commonsense of the international law, the customs-fee system was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okazu MIYAMOTO proposed it faithfully, and Korea did not oppose it because of their ignorance of the international law, so the customs-fee system was established.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okazu MIYAMOTO proposed it faithfully, and Korea did not oppose it because of their ignorance of the international law, so the customs-fee system was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>比較の視点－日本の安政五ヶ国条約との相違点－</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A view point of comparison – Different points compared to the treaty among five countries in Ansei era in Japan –</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A comparison of view points – Different points comparing the treaties of five countries in Ansei era in Japan -</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A comparison of view points – Different points comparing the treaties of five countries in Ansei era in Japan -</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="186">
<j>日朝修好条規の締結は、それ以外の諸国の人々の関心も引いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The conclusion of Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity drew attentions of other countries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The conclusion of the Japanese-Korean Treaty of Amity drew the attention of other countries.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The conclusion of the Japanese-Korean Treaty of Amity drew the attention of other countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="187">
<j>たとえば駐日イギリス公使ハリー・パークスは日朝修好条規が日英通商条約と類似しているとの感想を漏らしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, English Minister to Japan, Harry PARKES talked his impression that the Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity was similar to the Anglo-Japanese Treaty of Amity and Commerce.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, English Minister to Japan, Harry PARKES talked of his impression that the Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity was similar to the Anglo-Japanese Treaty of Amity and Commerce.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, English Minister to Japan, Harry PARKES talked of his impression that the Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity was similar to the Anglo-Japanese Treaty of Amity and Commerce.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="188">
<j>日本が最初に締結した日米和親条約や日米修好通商条約はその後に結ばれた西欧列強と締結した諸条約のモデルとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Treaty between the United States of America and the Empire of Japan which was the first treaty that Japan concluded, and the Treaty of Amity and Commerce between the United States and Japan were the models of the treaties that Japan concluded with the Western Europe powerful countries later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Treaty between the United States of America and the Empire of Japan which was the first treaty that Japan concluded, and the Treaty of Amity and Commerce between the United States and Japan was a model for the treaties that Japan later concluded with the powerful countries of Western Europe.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Treaty between the United States of America and the Empire of Japan which was the first treaty that Japan concluded, and the Treaty of Amity and Commerce between the United States and Japan were models for the treaties that Japan later concluded with the powerful countries of Western Europe.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="189">
<j>日朝修好条規は日米間の条約を研究して結ばれたものであるから、パークスが感じるように日朝修好条規と日英間の条約の性格が似ているのは当然といえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity was concluded based on the study of the treaties between Japan and the United States, it would be natural that PARKES felt the character of Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity was similar to that of the treaty between Japan and England.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Japanese-Korean Treaty of Amity was concluded based on the study of the treaties between Japan and the United States, it would be natural that PARKES felt the character of the Japanese-Korean Treaty of Amity was similar to that of the treaty between Japan and England.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Japanese-Korean Treaty of Amity was concluded based on the study of the treaties between Japan and the United States, it would be natural that Parkes felt the character of the Japanese-Korean Treaty of Amity was similar to that of the treaty between Japan and England.</e>
<cmt>Parkesにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="190">
<j>強いて類別すれば、条規そのものは日米和親条約にあたり、付録及び貿易規則・公文は日米修好通商条約に該当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It dare to be classified that the treaty itself was applicable to the Treaty between the United States of America and the Empire of Japan, while the Appendix, and trade regulations and official documents were applicable to the Treaty of Amity and Commerce between the United States and Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If it must be classified, the stipulation itself corresponded to the Treaty between the United States of America and the Empire of Japan, while the Appendix, and trade regulations and official documents corresponded to the Treaty of Amity and Commerce between the United States and Japan.</e>
<cmt>Use of the word &apos;treaty&apos; for both 条規 and 条約 makes no sense in this instance.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If it must be classified, the stipulation itself corresponded to the Treaty between the United States of America and the Empire of Japan, while the Appendix, and trade regulations and official documents corresponded to the Treaty of Amity and Commerce between the United States and Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="191">
<j>しかし同様の性格を有しながら、いくつか相違点もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although they had similar characters, there were several different points.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although they had similar characters, there were several different points.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although they had similar characters, there were several different points.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="192">
<j>朝鮮を「自主の国」とわざわざ言明している点は、この条約の特殊な点である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Describing Korea as &apos;an independent country&apos; was a special point of this treaty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Describing Korea as &apos;an independent country&apos; was a special point of this treaty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Describing Korea as &apos;an independent country&apos; was a unique point of this treaty.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="193">
<j>西欧列強の対日条約のいずれにも、これに類似する項目は無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">None of the treaties between Japan and the Western Europe powerful countries included the provisions similar to this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">None of the treaties between Japan and the powerful countries of Western Europe included similar provisions to this.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">None of the treaties between Japan and the powerful countries of Western Europe included similar provisions to this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="194">
<j>また最恵国待遇がないことも特徴の一つであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was no description of the most-favored nation treatment would be another character of this treaty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another characteristic of this treaty was that it did not include a description of most-favored nation status.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another characteristic of this treaty was that it did not include a description of most-favored nation status.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="195">
<j>その他挙げなければならないのは、総じて西欧の対日条約の中に見出すことができるものの、その不平等性が増している条項の存在である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What should be noted was that the provisions in the treaties between Japan and the Western Europe countries strengthened the unequal character.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What should be noted was that the provisions in the treaties between Japan and the countries of Western Europe served to strengthened the unequal character of this treaty.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What should be noted was that the provisions in the treaties between Japan and the countries of Western Europe served to strengthened the unequal character of this treaty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="196">
<j>駐日イギリス公使パークスも、日本の朝鮮への要求が日本に対する欧米側の要求よりも上まわっていることについて、非常に注目していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The English Minister to Japan PARKES also noted especially to the point that the demand from Japan to Korea was stronger than that from Europe and the United States to Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">PARKES, The English Minister to Japan, also especially noted the point that the demand from Japan to Korea was stronger than that from Europe and the United States to Japan.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Parkes, the English minister to Japan, paid great attention to the point that the Japanese demand to Korea was heavier than that from Europe and the United States to Japan.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="197">
<j>以下に主要な違いを列挙する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The major differences are as below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The major differences are as below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The major differences are as below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="198">
<j>朝鮮側の雇用が前提とはいえ、日本の商船が開港地以外での沿岸貿易が許される余地があること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the employment of the Korean people was the prerequisite condition, it was possible for the Japanese merchant ships to exercise the coastal trade at the places besides the cities where the ports were opened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the employment of Korean people was a prerequisite condition, it was possible for the Japanese merchant ships to exercise coastal trade at places other than the cities where ports were opened.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the employment of Korean people was a prerequisite condition, it was possible for the Japanese merchant ships to exercise coastal trade at places other than the cities where ports were opened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="199">
<j>これは当時日本自身が欧米列強から強く要求されていたものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was strongly required by the allied western powers to Japan itself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The allied western powers strongly required this of Japan itself.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was exactly the same as the strong request from the western powers imposed on Japan in those days.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="200">
<j>開港地に外国人の遊歩区域を設けている点は同様であるが、日朝修好条規では外国人の商業行為をも認めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The both treaties allowed establishing the area of free-movement for foreigners in the cities where the ports were opened, but the Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity admitted the foreigners to do business.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both treaties allowed establishment of an area of free-movement for foreigners in the cities where ports were opened, but the Japanese-Korean Treaty of Amity permitted foreigners to do business.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The similarity is the establishment of the free-movement area for foreign residents in the cities with open ports, while the Japanese-Korean Treaty of Amity permitted foreigners to do business.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="201">
<j>安政五カ国条約では、治外法権を犠牲にしても外国人の商業行為を阻止した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Treaty between five countries in the Ansei era was concluded, Japan inhibited foreigners from doing business, even though they sacrificed the extraterritoriality.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the treaties between five countries in the Ansei era were concluded, even though Japan sacrificed extraterritoriality, they prevented foreigners from doing business,.</e>
<cmt>Wording - plural of treaties</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the treaties between five countries in the Ansei era were concluded, even though Japan sacrificed extraterritoriality, they prevented foreigners from doing business.</e>
<cmt>文末の,を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="202">
<j>それにより日本が国内の産業育成の時間的猶予を得られたといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of that, Japan might have obtained additional time for the domestic industrial development.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of that, Japan may have obtained additional time for domestic industrial development.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that as a result of that, Japan could have obtained additional time for domestic industrial development.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="203">
<j>しかし日朝修好条規では、そうした暇を朝鮮に与えることは無かったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as for Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity, Japan did not give such time to Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Japan did not give such time to Korea for the Japanese-Korean Treaty of Amity.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Japan did not give such time to Korea in the Japanese-Korean Treaty of Amity.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="204">
<j>同じく開港場にて日本の貨幣使用が認められている点も西欧の対日条約と同じであるが、それらでは銅貨の輸出は認められていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The use of Japanese currency at the cities where the ports were opened was admitted as it described in the treaties between Japan and the Western Europe, but Japan was not allowed to export copper coin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The use of Japanese currency at the cities where the ports were opened was permitted as described in the treaties between Japan and the Western Europe, but Japan was not allowed to export copper coins to these countries.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The use of Japanese currency at the cities with open ports was permitted in the treaties between Japan and the countries in Western Europe, where the export of copper coins was not allowed, however.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="205">
<j>しかしこの日朝修好条規では認められ、その海外流出を促した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the export of copper coin was allowed in Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity to promote the outflow of it to the foreign countries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the export of copper coins was allowed in the Japanese-Korean Treaty of Amity to promote the outflow of it to foreign countries.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the export of copper coins was allowed in the Japanese-Korean Treaty of Amity, which caused the outflow of them.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="206">
<j>港税の価格が異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The price of the port dues was different.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The price of the port dues was different.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The price of the port dues was different.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="207">
<j>日本と欧米間の取り決めでは港税は22ドル（入港料15ドル+出港料7ドル）であったのに対し、日朝間では蒸気船など大きな船舶については5円、それ以下の規模の船は積載量により2円と1円50銭とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the treaty between Japan and Europe and the United States, the port due was 22 dollars (15 dollars for entrance + 7 dollars for clearance), while in the treaty between Japan and Korea, it was 5 yen for large ships like steamships, and 2 yen or 1.50 yen for the smaller ships, which was decided depending on the burden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the treaty between Japan and Europe and the United States, the port due was 22 dollars (15 dollars for entrance + 7 dollars for clearance), while in the treaty between Japan and Korea, it was 5 yen for large ships like steamships, and 2 yen or 1.50 yen for the smaller ships, which was decided depending on the burden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the treaty between Japan and Europe and the United States, the port due was 22 dollars (15 dollars for entrance + 7 dollars for clearance), while in the treaty between Japan and Korea, it was 5 yen for large ships like steamships, and 2 yen or 1.50 yen for the smaller ships, which was decided depending on the burden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="208">
<j>明治のこの時期の為替レートは1円1ドルほどであったので、港税は1/4程度の廉価に抑えられているといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The exchange rate of that period in Meiji era was 1 yen to the dollar, so that the port dues were kept lower prices to about one quarter in this treaty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The exchange rate of that period in Meiji era was 1 yen to the dollar, so port dues were kept at about a quarter of the price in this treaty.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The exchange rate of that period in the Meiji period was 1 yen to the dollar, so port dues were kept low at about a quarter of the price in this treaty.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="209">
<j>貿易・海外進出に関し先行する日本にとって有利なものとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was advantageous to Japan, because it was preceded as for the trade and the advance to abroad.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was advantageous to Japan, which was leading trade and advancing into overseas markets.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was advantageous to Japan, which was leading trade and advancing into overseas markets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="210">
<j>米など穀類の輸出の自由。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The freedom of export of rice and grain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was freedom of export of rice and grain.</e>
<cmt>Fragment in par section.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was freedom of export of rice and grain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="211">
<j>朝鮮人の地主と直接交渉して土地貸借ができること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese people could borrow the land by negotiating directly to the Korean landlord.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese people could borrow land by negotiating directly with the Korean landowner.</e>
<cmt>Landlord sounds like a house owner rather than land.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese people could borrow land by negotiating directly with the Korean landowner.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="212">
<j>以上から日朝修好条規は、日本が欧米と結んだ諸条約と比較してより過酷な内容を持ったものになっている、といえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From these points, the Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity was understood that it had more severe provisions compared to those between Japan and Europe and the United States.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From these points, it can be said that the Japanese-Korean Treaty of Amity had more severe provisions than those between Japan and Europe and the United States.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From these points, it can be said that the Japanese-Korean Treaty of Amity had more severe provisions than those between Japan and Europe and the United States.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>条約締結後の問題</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The problems after concluding the treaty</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Problems after concluding the treaty</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Problems after concluding the treaty</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>開港地の選定</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The selection of the cities to open the port</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Selection of cities to open the port</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Selection of cities to open the port</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="213">
<j>日朝修好条規において、釜山以外に二港を開港するとしながら、どこにするかという具体論になると交渉は難航した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity provided that two ports would be opened besides Busan, however the negotiation to decide the exact place was made slow progress.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese-Korean Treaty of Amity provided that two ports would be opened besides Busan, however negotiations to decide the exact places made slow progress.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese-Korean Treaty of Amity provided that two ports would be opened besides Busan, but negotiations to decide the exact places were proceeding with difficulty.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="214">
<j>日本は候補の一つとして文川市郡松田里を強く推したが、その地は王陵（王家の墓地）があるために朝鮮側が難色を示した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan insisted Munchon-si, gun, as one of the possible sites, however Korea disapproved, because there was a tomb of a king (a grave of royal family) at the site.</e>
<cmt>「松田里」の読み方および定訳が不明のため、文川市のみとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan insisted that Munchon-si, Gun, should be one of the possible sites, however Korea were reluctant because there was a tomb of a king (a grave of the royal family) at the site.</e>
<cmt>Wording. I understand &apos;gun&apos; is the town/province name; if so it needs a capital letter.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan insisted that Songjon Village in Munchon City should be one of the possible sites, but Korea were reluctant because there was a royal tomb.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="215">
<j>代替として候補に挙がったのが徳源府元山市津であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The another proposal as the substitute site was Wonsan.</e>
<cmt>「徳源府元山市津」は&quot;Wonsan&quot;としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wonsan was proposed as an alternative site.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wonsan was proposed as an alternative site.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="216">
<j>日本はこれを受け入れ、1880年5月開港となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan accepted it, and it was opened in May, 1880.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan accepted it, and it was opened in May, 1880.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan accepted it, and it was opened in May, 1880.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="217">
<j>日本は十万坪強の居留地を設定し、領事館を置いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan established the settlement in the land of 330,000 sq.m., and constructed the consular office.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan established a settlement on land of 330,000m², and constructed a consular office.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan established a settlement covering 330,000m², and constructed a consular office there.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="218">
<j>元山は単に貿易の要所としてだけでなく、対ロシアの拠点としての機能も重視された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wonsan was considered as an important site not only for a trade, but also for a foothold against Russia.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wonsan was considered as an important site not only for trade, but also as a foothold against Russia.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wonsan was considered as an important site not only for trade, but also as a foothold against Russia.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="219">
<j>そのため明治政府は積極的な移住政策を推し進めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So that the Meiji government promoted actively the policy of emigration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this the Meiji government actively promoted the policy of emigration.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this the Meiji government actively promoted the policy of emigration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="220">
<j>もう一つの開港地として日本側が求めたのは仁川広域市府済物浦である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another city to open the port where Japan required was Jemulpo, Incheon Metropolitan City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another city that Japan requested open port was Jemulpo, Incheon Metropolitan City.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another city that Japan requested to open a port was Jemulpo, presently Incheon Metropolitan City.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="221">
<j>仁川は朝鮮の首都漢城の外港にあたる地であるため交渉は非常に難航したが、朝鮮側が妥協して1881年2月受諾を通告してきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The negotiation was made slow progress as Incheon was the outer harbor of Hanseong, the capital of Korea, but Korea compromised and notified their acceptance in February 1881.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The negotiation made slow progress as Incheon was the outer harbor of Hanseong, the capital of Korea, but Korea compromised and notified Japan of their acceptance in February 1881.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The negotiation ran into trouble extremely as Incheon was the outer harbor of Hanseong, the capital of Korea, but Korea compromised and notified Japan of their acceptance in February 1881.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="222">
<j>ただ実際の開港は壬午事変が発生したため、延期となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However the opening the port was postponed because of the outbreak of Jingo incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, opening of the port was postponed because of the outbreak of the Jingo incident.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, opening of the port was postponed because of the outbreak of the Imo Incident.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="223">
<j>1882年に領事館が置かれたものの、開港はさらに遅れ、最終的には1883年1月になって漸く開港された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the consular office was established in 1882, the opening the port was postponed much later, and finally it was opened in January 1883.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the consular office was established in 1882, opening of the port was postponed until much later, and it was finally opened in January 1883.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the consular office was established in 1882, opening of the port was postponed until much later, and it was finally opened in January 1883.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="224">
<j>同年9月には七千坪ほどの居留地が設けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September 1883, a settlement was established having the area of about 23,100 sq.m..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September 1883, a settlement was established with an area of about 23,100m².</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September 1883, a settlement was established with an area of about 23,100m².</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="20">
<tit>
<j>公使常駐問題</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The problem of the permanent residence of minister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The problem of the permanent residence of ministers</e>
<cmt>No period required in sec section.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The problem of the permanent residence of ministers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="225">
<j>朝鮮側の認識では、日朝修好条規の締結は江戸時代における冊封体制下における交隣関係復活であると捉えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Korea understood the conclusion of the Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity was a revival of the relationship of peace and amity under the Sakuho system (tributary system) during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Korea understood the conclusion of the Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity was a revival of the relationship of peace and amity under the Sakuho system (tributary system) during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Korea understood the conclusion of the Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity was a revival of the relationship of peace and amity under the tributary system during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>音訳を略しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="226">
<j>決して近代的な国際関係の中に自国が置かれたとは考えていなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Korea never thought that they were settled in the modern international relations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Korea certainly did not think they were involved in modern international relations.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Korea certainly did not think they were involved in modern international relations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="227">
<j>したがって両国が公使を相互に常駐させる必要性を認めることはなかったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So that Korea did no admit the necessity of the mutual permanent residence of ministers of both countries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason Korea did not admit the necessity of mutual permanent residence of ministers of both countries.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason Korea did not admit the necessity of mutual permanent residence of ministers of both countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="228">
<j>むしろ朝鮮通信使のように、慶弔といった事柄に対し随時使節を送れば良いと主張し、そして首都に常駐することに非常な懸念を表明した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Korea insisted that ministers should be dispatched at any time such as congratulation or condolence as the messenger of Korea did, so that they strongly concerned about the permanent residence of a minister in the capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Korea insisted that ministers should be dispatched at any time such as occasions of congratulation or condolence as the messenger of Korea did, so they were very concerned about the permanent residence of a minister in the capital.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Korea insisted that ministers should be dispatched at any time such as occasions of congratulation or condolence as the messenger of Korea did, so they were very concerned about the permanent residence of a minister in the capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="229">
<j>日朝で激しいやりとりがあったが、弁理公使花房義質が日朝間を頻繁に往来して、ついには1880年12月漢城に公使館を設置し長期滞在して既成事実化するようになると、朝鮮側も黙認せざるを得なくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the severe discussion of both sides, minister resident Yoshimoto HANABUSA traveled often between Japan and Korea, and finally Japan established a consular office in Hanseong in December 1880, HANABUSA stayed there for a long term to create a fait accompli, so that Korea had no choice but connivance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the severe discussion between the two sides, minister resident Yoshimoto HANABUSA traveled often between Japan and Korea, and finally Japan established a consular office in Hanseong in December 1880, HANABUSA stayed there for a long term to create a fait accompli, and Korea had no choice but to concede.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the severe discussion between the two sides, minister resident Yoshimoto HANABUSA traveled often between Japan and Korea, and finally Japan established a consular office in Hanseong in December 1880, Hanabusa stayed there for a long term to create a fait accompli, and Korea had no choice but to concede.</e>
<cmt>Hanabusaとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="230">
<j>同年朝鮮側も東京に公使館を設置している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Korea also established a consular office in Tokyo the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Korea also established a consular office in Tokyo in the same year.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Korea also established a consular office in Tokyo in the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="231">
<j>一方朝鮮側は1876年5月、答礼使節として両班を成員とする修信使を日本に派遣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While in May 1876, Korea dispatched to Japan the training delegates whose members were yangban (traditional ruling class or nobles of dynastic Korea during the Joseon Dynasty) as a return salute envoy.</e>
<cmt>「修信使」が定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May 1876, Korea dispatched to Japan the training delegates whose members were yangban (traditional ruling class or nobles of dynastic Korea during the Joseon Dynasty) as a return salute envoy.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 1876, Korea dispatched to Japan the training delegates whose members were yangban (traditional ruling class or nobles of dynastic Korea during the Joseon Dynasty) as a return salute envoy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="232">
<j>これは日本側の勧めによるもので、開化途上にある日本の現状を視察するのが本当の目的であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan advised to do so, and the real purpose of the dispatch was to inspect the present state of Japan on the way of civilization.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan advised to do so, and the real purpose of the dispatch was to inspect the present state of Japan on the way to civilization.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan advised to do so, and the real purpose of the dispatch was to inspect the present state of Japan on the way to civilization.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="233">
<j>しかし派遣された両班たちには保守的な者が多く、あまり成果は無かったといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, many of the dispatched yangban were conservatives, so that it was said that they almost got nowhere.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, many of the dispatched yangban were conservatives, so that it was said that little was achieved.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, many of the dispatched yangban were conservatives, so that it was said that little was achieved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="234">
<j>しかし金弘集 (1842年)に率いられた二度目の修信使は、駐日清朝公使何如璋及び黄遵憲と面会し、黄の『朝鮮策略』を持ち帰っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the second group of the training delegates led by Koshu KIM (Born in 1842) met with the Qing dynasty minister to Japan Ruzhang HE and Zunxian HUANG, and brought back &quot;A tactic of Korea&quot; written by HUANG.</e>
<cmt>「金弘集」（キムホンジプ）が定訳不明です。日本語表記（きんこうしゅう）をローマ字表記にしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the second group of the training delegates led by Koshu KIM (Born in 1842) met with the Qing dynasty minister to Japan Ruzhang HE and Zunxian HUANG, and brought back &quot;A strategem for Korea&quot; written by HUANG.</e>
<cmt>I think strategem is a better term than tactic in this instance.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the second group of the training delegates led by Hong-jip KIM (born in 1842) met with the Qing dynasty minister to Japan Ruzhang HE and Zunxian HUANG, and brought back &quot;A stratagem for Korea&quot; written by Huang.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="235">
<j>第二回修信使の見聞、日本政府との交渉、そして『朝鮮策略』の持参によって、朝鮮の対外政策は欧米に対する開国政策へと舵をきり始めるのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Through the second experience of the training delegates, the negotiation with the Japanese government, and bringing back &quot;A tactic of Korea&quot;, the diplomatic policy of Korea changed to the policy of opening of the country to the Europe and the United States.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Through the experience of the second training delegates, negotiations with the Japanese government, and bringing back &quot;A strategem for Korea&quot;, the diplomatic policy of Korea changed to the policy of opening of the country to Europe and the United States.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Through the experiences of the second training delegates, negotiations with the Japanese government, and bringing back &quot;A stratagem for Korea,&quot; the diplomatic policy of Korea changed to the policy of opening of the country to Europe and the United States.</e>
<cmt>&quot;を小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="21">
<tit>
<j>経済問題</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Matter of economics</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Economic problems</e>
<cmt>Matters&apos; does not reflect the following content as well as &apos;problem&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Economic problems</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="236">
<j>日朝修好条規締結後、多くの日本人が朝鮮開港地を訪れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A lot of Japanese people visited the cities of opening port in Korea after the conclusion of the Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A lot of Japanese people visited the Korean cities with open ports after the conclusion of the Japanese-Korean Treaty of Amity.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A lot of Japanese people visited the Korean cities with open ports after the conclusion of the Japanese-Korean Treaty of Amity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="237">
<j>たとえば釜山では開港当初数百人しかいなかったにもかかわらず、1882年には2000名弱の日本人が在留していたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, although there were only several hundred Japanese residents in Busan when the port was opened they increased to a little less than 2,000 in 1882.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, although there were only several hundred Japanese residents in Busan when the port was opened, this figure increased to a little less than 2,000 in 1882.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, although there were only several hundred Japanese residents in Busan when the port was opened, this figure increased to a little less than 2,000 in 1882.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="238">
<j>大阪や九州、対馬の商人が多かったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of them were merchants from Osaka, Kyushu, and Tsushima.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of them were merchants from Osaka, Kyushu, and Tsushima.</e>
<cmt>Just removed unnecessary space from start of sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of them were merchants from Osaka, Kyushu, and Tsushima.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="239">
<j>貿易も比例して大きくなり、やがて中朝貿易よりも日朝貿易は大きくなるのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In proportion to the increase of Japanese people, the scale of trade between Japan and Korea became larger than that of China and Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In proportion with the increase of Japanese people, the scale of trade between Japan and Korea became larger than that between China and Korea.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In proportion with the increase of Japanese people, the scale of trade between Japan and Korea became larger than that between China and Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="240">
<j>しかしそれに伴い、多くの問題が発生するようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in accordance with that, many problems occurred.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in accordance with that, many problems occurred.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in accordance with that, many problems occurred.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="241">
<j>まず穀物が朝鮮から大量輸出されるようになり、国内において深刻な米不足米価騰貴をもたらした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First of all, as a large amount of grain was exported from Korea, it brought serious rice shortage and soar of rice price domestically.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First of all, as a large amount of grain was exported from Korea, it brought about a serious rice shortage and the price of rice soared domestically.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First of all, as a large amount of grain was exported from Korea, it brought about a serious rice shortage and the price of rice soared domestically in Korea.</e>
<cmt>in Koreaを付け加えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="242">
<j>次に無関税貿易により、著しい貿易不均衡が起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Next, tariff-free trade caused remarkable trade imbalance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Next, tariff-free trade caused remarkable trade imbalance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Next, tariff-free trade caused remarkable trade imbalance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="243">
<j>遅まきながら、関税自主権回復の必要性を悟った朝鮮側は、まず自国の在釜山商人に税を課しはじめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though it was rather too late, Korea realized the necessity of recovery of tariff autonomy, and started to impose tax to the merchants living in Busan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though it was rather too late, Korea realized the necessity of recovery of tariff autonomy, and started to impose tax to the merchants living in Busan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though it was rather too late, Korea realized the necessity of recovery of tariff autonomy, and started to impose tax to the merchants living in Busan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="244">
<j>しかし日本側の砲艦外交によって頓挫した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However it was frustrated by a gunboat diplomacy by Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However it was frustrated by gunboat diplomacy by Japan.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However it was frustrated by gunboat diplomacy by Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="245">
<j>その後幾度か関税についての取り決めを改める使節を日本に派遣したが、いずれも成功しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Korea dispatched envoy several times to Japan in order to revise the agreement on the taxation, but it did not succeed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Korea dispatched envoys to Japan several times in order to revise the agreement on taxation, but it did not succeed.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Korea dispatched envoys to Japan several times in order to revise the agreement on taxation, but it did not succeed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="246">
<j>関税に関する条項が改訂されるのは、朝米通商条約において関税が定められ、自国のみ突出するわけにはいかないと日本が判断した後である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The provision on the taxation was amended after the Treaty of commerce between Korea and the United States was concluded, because it provided the taxation and Japan decided that they should not maintain the provision anymore.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The provision on taxation was amended after the Treaty of Commerce between Korea and the United States was concluded, because it provided taxation, and Japan decided that they should not maintain the provision anymore.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The provision on taxation was amended after the Treaty of Commerce between Korea and the United States was concluded, where taxation was provided, and Japan decided that they should not maintain the preferential provision anymore.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="247">
<j>上記のような経済問題は、領事裁判権問題とも密接な関わりがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The economic matter as mentioned above was related closely to the matter of consular jurisdiction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The economic matter as mentioned above was related closely to the matter of consular jurisdiction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These economic problems mentioned above was related closely to the matter of consular jurisdiction.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="248">
<j>大倉喜八郎や福田増兵衛といった政商、第一銀行といった大資本が朝鮮貿易に参入するようになると、対馬商人たちは経済的に脇に追いやられるようになり、本来貿易が許されないはずの開港地の外縁へと暴力的に進出していくようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The businessman with political ties, Kihachiro OKURA and Zohei FUKUDA, the great capital such as Bank of Daiichi started to compete in the trade with Korea, so that the merchants in Tsushima were expelled economically and advanced to out of the opened ports violently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The businessmen with political ties, Kihachiro OKURA and Zohei FUKUDA, and the holders of great capital such as the Bank of Daiichi started to compete in the trade with Korea, so the merchants in Tsushima were expelled economically and they advanced violently to the outskirts of the opened ports.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the businessmen with political ties, Kihachiro OKURA and Zohei FUKUDA, and the holders of great capital such as the Bank of Daiichi started to enter the trade with Korea, the merchants in Tsushima were expelled economically and furthermore advanced violently to the outskirts of the open ports.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="249">
<j>そのため朝鮮人ともめ事を起こすことになっていくが、当然、対馬商人たちは日本側が引き取り裁判を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So that the merchants in Tsushima caused trouble with Korean people, and naturally they were taken in and tried by Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The merchants in Tsushima caused trouble with Korean people, and naturally they were taken in and tried by Japan.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The merchants in Tsushima began to cause troubles with Korean people, but naturally they were taken in and tried by the Japanese court.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="250">
<j>このような日本側の姿勢は「てんびん棒帝国主義」と評された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This attitude of Japan was described as &apos;Balance Imperialism&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This attitude of Japan was described as &apos;Balanced Imperialism&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This attitude of Japan was described as &apos;Balanced Imperialism.&apos;</e>
<cmt>を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="22">
<tit>
<j>条約締結の影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Influence of the conclusion of the treaty</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Influence of the conclusion of the treaty</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Influence of the conclusion of the treaty</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="251">
<j>条約の締結によって、李氏朝鮮は開国し、海禁政策（鎖国）は事実上終了した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of the conclusion of the treaty, Joseon Dynasty opened the port which led to the end of Kaikin Policy (national isolation) practically.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of the conclusion of the treaty, the Joseon Dynasty opened a port which in practice led to the end of Kaikin Policy (national isolation).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of the conclusion of the treaty, the Joseon Dynasty opened the country, which in practice led to the end of the national isolation policy.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="252">
<j>砲艦外交や米価騰貴、領事裁判権などいくつもの要因が重複して、朝鮮側の日本への悪感情を蓄積させていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gunboat diplomacy, soaring price of rice, consular jurisdiction, and other factors were overlapped, then the bad feeling against Japan were accumulated in Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gunboat diplomacy, the soaring price of rice, consular jurisdiction, and other factors overlapped, and the bad feeling against Japan accumulated in Korea.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the gunboat diplomacy, the soaring price of rice, consular jurisdiction, and other factors overlapping, the bad feelings against Japan had been accumulated in Korea.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="253">
<j>それはやがて壬午事変の暴発を招いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This caused Jingo incident later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This later caused the Jingo incident.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This later caused the Imo incident.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="254">
<j>条約締結以後、清朝が最後の冊封国朝鮮を維持しようと、朝鮮に積極的に関与するようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the conclusion of the treaty, the Qing dynasty positively involved with Korea in order to maintain the last sakuho country (a country of a sovereign who became a nominal subject of the Chinese Emperor by sakuho.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After conclusion of the treaty, the Qing dynasty became positively involved with Korea in order to maintain the last Sakuho country (a country of a sovereign who became a nominal subject of the Chinese Emperor by Sakuho).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After conclusion of the treaty, the Qing dynasty became positively involved with Korea in order to maintain the last subject state under the tributary system.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="255">
<j>朝鮮を冊封体制から近代国際法的な属国へと位置づけし直そうとしはじめる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Qing dynasty started to change the position of Korea from a subject state in sakuho system (tributary system) to that based on the modern international law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Qing dynasty started to change the position of Korea from a subject state under the Sakuho system (tributary system) to that based on modern international law.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Qing dynasty started to change the position of Korea from a subject state under the tributary system to that based on modern international law.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="256">
<j>同じく日本も朝鮮を影響下に置こうと画策しはじめていたため、日本と清朝の対立が深まり、日清戦争の遠因となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan, as well, started to scheme to put Korea under the control, the conflict between Japan and the Qing dynasty became more seriously, which became the indirect cause of Sino-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan, as well, started to scheme to put Korea under their control, the conflict between Japan and the Qing dynasty became more serious, and this became an indirect cause of the Sino-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Japan also started to scheme to put Korea under their control, the conflict between Japan and the Qing dynasty became more serious, and this became an indirect cause of the Sino-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Straysheep(id:42448), Novo(id:87875), ちとせ(id:81263), Jjok(id:55405), 22010515528(id:43149), おはぐろ蜻蛉(id:8405), 阿修羅(id:29454), Uraios(id:72687), 冒涜的な利用者名(id:14641), でここ(id:9565), Takeler(id:51437), Prism11 VYB05736(id:171949), 家栽の人(id:135484), Chobot(id:20846), Point136(id:211299), 田牧(id:172560), Bankokuya(id:91191), Tatsujin28(id:9300), LERK(id:4460), Lonicera(id:20638), Haeha(id:9372), いろはにほへと(id:89648), Tears for Asia(id:61412), Nallimbot(id:230812), Yanahan(id:2437), 雲居雁乃(id:15842), Yhiroyuki(id:84500), 夏の雪雲(id:188722), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), Fryed-peach(id:63402), Saintjust(id:21864), Nidarin(id:6420), NDR(id:5500), Trek011(id:7105), Suisui(id:69), Ciro(id:4058), 黒毛金眼九尾猫(id:112621), K.Ikeda(id:19248), ToePeu.bot(id:157833), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>