<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>武家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buke (Samurai Families)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buke (Samurai Families)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buke (Samurai Families)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>武家（ぶけ）とは、幕府権力の総称、将軍家、または武士一般を指す語。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Buke&quot; is the word which refers collectively to all powers of bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun,) or shogun-ke (families of shogun), or bushi ippan (warriors in general.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Buke&quot; is the word which refers collectively to all powers of bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun,) or shogun-ke (families of shogun), or bushi ippan (warriors in general.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word &quot;buke&quot; refers to the collection of various powers which support the authority of a bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and this word sometimes also refers to a Shogun family or general samurai.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>解説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Explanations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Explanations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Explanations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>平安時代中期の貴族社会において、官職や職能が特定の家系に固定化していく「家業の継承」が急速に進展していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the middle of Heian Period, the society of nobilities had accelerated its tendency of &quot;kagyo no keisho&quot; (literally, &quot;the succession of family business&quot;) by stabilizing succession of particular posts and functions by certain limited familiy lines in the government.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the middle of Heian Period, the society of nobilities had accelerated their tendency for &quot;kagyo no keisho&quot; (literally, &quot;the succession of family business&quot;) by stabilizing succession of particular posts and functions by certain limited familiy lines in the government.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the society of the nobility of the middle Heian period, the trend of the &quot;succession of family business&quot; rapidly became popular, and only specific families began to occupy certain government official posts or occupations.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>武芸を職能とする下級貴族もまた、「兵（つわもの）の家」として武芸に特化した家柄を形成し、その中から軍事貴族という成立期武士の中核的な存在が登場していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, lower ranking nobles whose function was to hone their military arts had also developed their particular pedigrees specialized in military arts, which were called &quot;tsuwamono no ie&quot; (literally, &quot;soldiers&apos; houses,&quot;) and produced some military aristocracy who played a central role among the fledgling samurai (warrior) class.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, lower ranking nobles whose function was to hone their military arts had also developed their particular pedigrees specialized in military arts, which were called &quot;tsuwamono no ie&quot; (literally, &quot;soldiers&apos; houses,&quot;) and produced some military aristocracy who played a central role among the fledgling samurai (warrior) class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, lower-ranked nobles whose function was to be skilled in the military arts had also developed their own family characteristics specialized in the military arts, and such families were called &quot;tsuwamono no ie&quot; (literally, &quot;soldier family&quot;). Subsequently, some of such families began to play a key role as the military elite at the dawn of samurai.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>これらの家系・家柄を指して「武家」もしくは「武勇の家」「武門」の呼称が生じたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These lineages or pedigrees are believed to have created their appellatives like &quot;buke,&quot; (&quot;a samurai family,&quot;) &quot;buyuu no ie&quot; (&quot;a house of heroes&quot;) or &quot;bumon&quot; (&quot;a samurai clan.&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These lineages or pedigrees are believed to have created their appellatives like &quot;buke,&quot; (&quot;a samurai family,&quot;) &quot;buyuu no ie&quot; (&quot;a house of heroes&quot;) or &quot;bumon&quot; (&quot;a samurai clan.&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that people began to use the terms &apos;buke,&apos; &apos;buyu no ie&apos; (a house of heroes), and &apos;bumon&apos; (a samurai clan) in order to refer to those lineages or families.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>この呼称は、武力・武勇をもって朝家（天皇）に奉仕する家系という意味合いを含んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These appellatives also implied such lineages as were engaged in serving Imperial families with buryoku (military powers) and buyuu (heroic acts.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These appellatives also implied such lineages as were engaged in serving Imperial families with buryoku (military powers) and buyuu (heroic acts.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These terms also implied lineages who served the Imperial Family (or an emperor) with their military power and bravery.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その後、東国に鎌倉幕府が成立すると、幕府および鎌倉殿を武家と称するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And then, when Kamakura bakufu was established in Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region,) the term &quot;buke&quot; became to mean bakufu and Kamakura-dono (the lord of Kamakura.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Kamakura bakufu was established in Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region,) the term &quot;buke&quot; came to mean bakufu and Kamakura-dono (the lord of Kamakura.)</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Kamakura bakufu was established in the eastern part of Japan, the term &quot;buke&quot; came to mean the bakufu and Kamakura-dono (the lord of Kamakura).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>幕府および鎌倉殿（源頼朝）が、朝廷に対し武力面で奉仕すると約束し、その見返りとして朝廷が、幕府および鎌倉殿の軍事警察権などを公認したことの反映である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This reflects the fact that the bakufu and Kamakura-dono (i.e. MINAMOTO no Yoritomo) promised to serve the Imperial court with their military power, and in return, the Imperial court approved officially the military and police authorities of bakufu and Kamakura-dono.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This reflects the fact that the bakufu and Kamakura-dono (i.e. MINAMOTO no Yoritomo) promised to serve the Imperial court with their military power, and in return, the Imperial court officially approved the military and police authorities of the bakufu and Kamakura-dono.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This reflected the fact that the bakufu and Kamakura-dono (MINAMOTO no Yoritomo) promised to serve the Imperial Court with their military power and the Imperial Court officially approved the military-police authority of the bakufu and Kamakura-dono in return.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>鎌倉幕府武家という呼称が定着すると、朝廷に仕える文官の総称としての「公家」が登場するようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the compellation of &quot;Kamakura bakufu buke&quot; (&quot;samurai families of Kamakura bakufu&quot;) obtained popularity, a new term &quot;kuge&quot; (&quot;court nobles&quot;) emerged to indicate collectively all civil servants attending on the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the compellation of &quot;Kamakura bakufu buke&quot; (&quot;samurai families of Kamakura bakufu&quot;) obtained popularity, a new term, &quot;kuge,&quot; (&quot;court nobles&quot;) emerged to collectively indicate all civil servants attending the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once people became accustomed to referring to the Kamakura bakufu as buke, another new word &apos;kuge,&apos; which was a general term representing civil officials at the Imperial Court, appeared.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>朝家に政務一般で奉仕する公家と軍事面で奉仕する武家という対比に基づいていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Use of these two terms were based on the comparison of their services to the Imperial families, namely &quot;kuge&quot; in charge of government affairs in general and &quot;buke&quot; in charge of military affairs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Use of these two terms were based on the comparison of their services to the Imperial families, namely &quot;kuge&quot; in charge of government affairs in general and &quot;buke&quot; in charge of military affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The use of these two terms was based on the comparison of their services to the Imperial Family, namely &quot;kuge&quot; in charge of general government affairs and &quot;buke&quot; in charge of military affairs.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>鎌倉時代初期の朝廷は、幕府を武家もしくは関東と呼称していたが、承久の乱を経て、幕府が朝廷を監視するため京都に六波羅探題を設置すると、武家の語は六波羅探題のみを指し、幕府は関東とのみ呼ばれるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the beginning of Kamakura Period, the Imperial court had called bakufu either buke or Kanto, but since bakufu installed Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto) after the Jokyu War, the term &quot;buke&quot; became to indicate Rokuhara Tandai only, and bakufu was called just Kanto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the beginning of the Kamakura Period, the Imperial court had called bakufu either buke or Kanto, but since the bakufu installed Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto) after the Jokyu War, the term &quot;buke&quot; came to indicate Rokuhara Tandai only, while the bakufu was simply called Kanto.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the beginning of the Kamakura period, the Imperial Court had called the bakufu buke or Kanto (derived from the &quot;Kanto region&quot;), but once the bakufu installed Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto) in order to monitor the Imperial Court after the Jokyu War, the term &quot;buke&quot; came to indicate Rokuhara Tandai only, while the bakufu was simply called Kanto.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし、一般の間では幕府および幕府諸機関・幕府権力を武家と呼ぶことが定着していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, among ordinary people, the term &quot;buke&quot; became commonly used to address bakufu and its various agencies or authorities.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, among ordinary people, the term &quot;buke&quot; came to be commonly used to address bakufu and its various agencies or authorities.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among ordinary people, however, the term &quot;buke&quot; came to be commonly used to address the bakufu, their various agencies, and their authority.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>幕府権力の発露の末端である御家人も武家と呼ばれ始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, it began to cover gokenin (immediate vasals of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods) who were regarded as the marges of bakufu government to bring out its influence.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, it also came to encompass gokenin (immediate vasals of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods) who were regarded as the marges of the bakufu government that enforced its influence.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the term also came to encompass gokenin (immediate vassals of the shogun in the Kamakura and Muromachi periods) who were regarded as the rank and file of the bakufu that enforced the influence of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>室町時代には室町幕府および将軍家を指すようになったが、江戸時代には幕府・将軍家のみならず諸大名や上層武士も武家と呼ばれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Muromachi Period, the term &quot;buke&quot; indicated the Muromachi bakufu and Shogun families, and in Edo Period, it became to cover not only bakufu and Shogun families but also various daimyo (Japanese feudal lords) and high-ranked bushi (warriors.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Muromachi Period, the term &quot;buke&quot; indicated the Muromachi bakufu and Shogun families, while in the Edo Period, it came to cover not only the bakufu and Shogun families but also various daimyo (Japanese feudal lords) and high-ranked bushi (warriors.)</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Muromachi period, the term &quot;buke&quot; indicated the Muromachi bakufu and the Shogun family, while in the Edo period, the term came to cover not only the bakufu and the Shogun family but also various daimyo (Japanese feudal lords) and high-ranked samurai.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>武士以外の百姓・町人らは武士身分一般をも武家と呼んでいたらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems likely that peasants and townsmen, other than bushi (warriors,) used to call the bushi class people in general as buke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems likely that peasants and townsmen, other than bushi (warriors,) used to call the bushi class people buke in general.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that people except for samurai, namely peasants and townsmen, referred to all samurai as buke.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>江戸時代の大名以下の武家の官職は員外の官とされ、同じ官職名でも従来の公家の官職、定員数とは関係の無い別のものとして扱われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Edo Period, official posts assigned to various buke (samurai families) under daimyo (feudal lords) were considerred as supernumerary having nothing to do with traditional posts and authorized number of posts allowed to kuge (court nobles.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo Period, official posts assigned to various buke (samurai families) under daimyo (feudal lords) had nothing to do with traditional posts and the authorized number of posts allowed to kuge (court nobles.)</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period, Imperial posts assigned to buke such as daimyo were regarded as ingai-kan (supernumerary positions), and these positions had nothing to do with traditional posts given to kuge even if they had the same post names; additionally, samurai at these positions were excluded from the prescribed number of personnel of such traditional posts.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>格付けをするための形式的な呼称の意味合いが強い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the term &quot;buke&quot; implies rather a formal appellation for ranking purpose.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the term &quot;buke&quot; implies rather a formal meaning for the purpose of rank.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, such &quot;Imperial posts&quot; were rather very nominal ones used for the purpose of ranking.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>朝廷の許可無く勝手に名乗っていたケースも多かったようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that the term was often used without approval of the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that the term was often used without approval of the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that such posts were often used without approval of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>（詳しくは武家官位を参照。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(For more details, please refer to Buke-Kani (Official Court Titles for Samurai.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(For more details, please refer to Buke-Kani (Official Court Titles for Samurai.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(For more details, please refer to Buke-Kani (Official Court Titles for Samurai.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="20">
<j>武家の官職の格付けは大名のランクに応じて明確に決められていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Posts to be allotted to buke (samurai families) were clearly ranked according to the rank of each daimyo (a feudal lord.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Posts to be allotted to buke (samurai families) were clearly ranked according to the rank of each daimyo (a feudal lord.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A post which could be allotted to a certain buke was strictly specified according to the rank of that daimyo.</e>
<cmt>「buke (samurai families)」→「buke」「daimyo (feudal lords)」→「daimyo」としました（既出のため）。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>江戸幕府の幕藩体制の秩序を守るために利用されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This ranking system was made use of by Edo bakufu to maintain its bakuhan taisei (feudal system characteristic of the shogunate.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This ranking system was used by the Edo bakufu to maintain its bakuhan taisei (feudal system characteristic of the shogunate.)</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This ranking system was used by the Edo bakufu to maintain its bakuhan taisei (feudal system characteristic of the shogunate).</e>
<cmt>「.)」→「).」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 田無稲子(id:63575), Ceridwen(id:36889), Nnh(id:474), 水野白楓(id:22811), 海衛士(id:19229), くっちゃめ(id:86793), Loveless(id:129239), Shimoxx(id:9332), Alexbot(id:157199), Yakouhai(id:25799), ウィキ豊(id:82961), Morita42(id:11003), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>