<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>国司苛政上訴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokushi kasei joso (appeals or armed struggles against kokushi (provincial governor taken by farmers)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokushi kasei joso (appeals or armed struggles against kokushi (provincial governor taken by farmers)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokushi Kasei Joso</e>
<cmt>(appeals or armed struggles against kokushi (provincial governor taken by farmers)以下説明があるので、削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>国司苛政上訴（こくしかせいじょうそ）は、日本の平安時代に郡司・田堵・負名・百姓階層が地方官である国司（受領）の苛政・非法を中央政府（太政官）へ訴えた行為、現象または闘争形態。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokushi kasei joso refers to acts and phenomena of appeals and a form of armed struggles taken by Gunji (local magistrates), Tato (cultivators), Fumyo (tiller of the public rice field) and the farmer class in order to complain to the central government Daijokan (Grand Council of State) about tyrannies and illegal behaviors of Kokushi (or Zuryo) (provincial governors), Chihokan (local officials) during the Heian period in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokushi kasei joso refers to acts and phenomena of appeals and armed struggles by Gunji (local magistrates), Tato (cultivators), Fumyo (tiller of the public rice field), and the farmer class in order to complain to the central government Daijokan (Grand Council of State) about tyrannies and illegal behaviors of Kokushi (or Zuryo) (provincial governors), Chihokan (local officials) during the Heian period in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokushi kasei joso refers to acts and phenomena of appeals and armed struggles by Gunji (local magistrates), Tato (cultivators), Fumyo (tiller of the public rice field), and the farmer class in order to complain to the central government Daijokan (Grand Council of State) about tyrannies and illegal behaviors of Kokushi (or Zuryo) (provincial governors), Chihokan (local officials) during the Heian period in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>国司苛政愁訴（-しゅうそ）とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called kokushi kasei shuso.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called kokushi kasei shuso.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called kokushi kasei shuso.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>地方の郡司・百姓らが上京し、大内裏の陽明門（内裏の公門とされていた）前で国司の苛政・非法を太政官へ訴えるという形態が通例であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gunji or farmers of provinces commonly visited the capital to complain to the Daijokan about tyrannies and illegal behaviors of Kokushi in front of Yomei-mon gate (the public gate of the Imperial Palace) of Daidairi (the Greater Imperial Palace)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gunji or farmers of provinces commonly visited the capital to complain to the Daijokan about tyrannies and illegal behaviors of Kokushi in front of Yomei-mon gate (the public gate of the Imperial Palace) of Daidairi (the Greater Imperial Palace).</e>
<cmt>Spacing, Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gunji or farmers of provinces commonly visited the capital to complain to the Daijokan about tyrannies and illegal behaviors of Kokushi in front of Yomei-mon gate (the public gate of the Imperial Palace) of Daidairi (the Greater Imperial Palace).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>10世紀後期から現れ始め、藤原道長執政期を中心に頻発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It started to appear in the second half of the 10th century and often occurred particularly when FUJIWARA no Michinaga was an administrator.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It started to appear in the second half of the 10th century and often occurred particularly when FUJIWARA no Michinaga was an administrator.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It started to appear in the second half of the 10th century and often occurred particularly when FUJIWARA no Michinaga was an administrator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>しかし次第に沈静化していき、11世紀40年代には終息した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However it became increasingly nominal, ending in the 1040&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However it became increasingly nominal, ending in the 1040&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However it became increasingly nominal, ending in the 1040&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outline</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outline</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>史料上の国司苛政上訴の初見は、974年（天延2）に尾張国の百姓らが国守藤原連貞の非法を太政官へ訴えた事例である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first historical record of Kokushi kasei joso was a case in which farmers in Owari Province complaint to Daijokan about illegal behaviors of their kokushi, FUJIWARA no Tsurasada in 974.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first historical record of Kokushi kasei joso was a case in which farmers in Owari Province complained to Daijokan about illegal behaviors of their kokushi, FUJIWARA no Tsurasada in 974.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first historical record of Kokushi kasei joso was a case in which farmers in Owari Province complained to Daijokan about illegal behaviors of their kokushu, FUJIWARA no Tsurasada in 974.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>本来、律令の規定によれば、百姓は訴訟権が認められていたが、規定外の機関への訴訟提起（越訴）は禁じられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally under the Ritsuryo codes, farmers had a right of action but were prohibited from bringing a case without going through formalities (.a direct appeal to a senior official)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally under the Ritsuryo codes, farmers had a right of action but were prohibited from bringing a case without going through formalities (a direct appeal to a senior official).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally under the Ritsuryo codes, farmers had a right of action but were prohibited from bringing a case without going through formalities (a direct appeal to a senior official).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>国司苛政上訴は明らかに越訴の形態をとっており、このような越訴が承認されるようになった理由は明らかでない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is not unknown why Kokushi kasei joso, apparently a form of direct appeals, began to be accepted.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not unknown why Kokushi kasei joso, apparently a form of direct appeals, began to be accepted.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not unknown why Kokushi kasei joso, apparently a form of direct appeals, began to be accepted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>しかし受領による国内支配の強化への妥協と見る説と、郡司層が旧来の権利を失った代替として越訴権が与えられたとする見解が提出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, some have suggested it was accepted as a compromise measure against Zuryo&apos;s growing control over entire Japan, while other have suggested that the Gunji class (local magistrates) was given the right to direct appeals in exchange of their lost conventional rights.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, some have suggested it was accepted as a compromise measure against Zuryo&apos;s growing control over entire Japan, while others have suggested that the Gunji class (local magistrates) was given the right to direct appeals in exchange for their lost conventional rights.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, some have suggested it was accepted as a compromise measure against Zuryo&apos;s growing control over entire Japan, while others have suggested that the Gunji class (local magistrates) was given the right to direct appeals in exchange for their lost conventional rights.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>その後、1140年代までの約60年間に渡り、史料に残るだけでも約20数件の事例が検出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the first case, the number of appeals only found in historical documents rose to more than twenty over about sixty years until the 1140&apos;s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the first case, the number of appeals only found in historical documents rose to more than twenty over about sixty years until the 1140&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>Spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the first case, the number of appeals only found in historical documents rose to more than twenty over about sixty years until the 1140&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>中でも著名なのが988年（永延2）11月8日付けの「尾張国郡司百姓等解」であり、尾張の郡司・百姓層が国守藤原元命による非法・濫行横法31条を訴えた事例である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the most famous appeals was &quot;Owari no kuni (Owari Province) Gunji (a local government official) Hyakusho (farmers) ra no Gebumi(letter),&quot; in which the Gunji and farmers in Owari complained their Kokushu, FUJIWARA no Motonaga&apos;s illegal behaviors as a breach of thirty-one articles of misconduct and violence.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the most famous appeals was &quot;Owari no kuni (Owari Province) Gunji (a local government official) Hyakusho (farmers) ra no Gebumi(letter),&quot; in which the Gunji and farmers in Owari complained their Kokushu, FUJIWARA no Motonaga&apos;s illegal behaviors as a breach of thirty-one articles of misconduct and violence.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the most famous appeals was &apos;Owari no kuni (Owari Province) Gunji (a local government official) Hyakusho (farmers) ra no Gebumi (letter)&apos; of November 8, 988, in which the Gunji and farmers in Owari complained their Kokushu, FUJIWARA no Motonaga&apos;s illegal behaviors as a breach of thirty-one articles of misconduct and violence.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入日付補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>この結果、元命は国司を罷免されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the result, Motonaga was dismissed of Kokushu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the result, Motonaga was dismissed of Kokushu.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the result, Motonaga was dismissed of Kokushi.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>このように当初は太政官が郡司・百姓らの主張を認め、国司を解任することが基調となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Initially as described above, it was common that Daijokan approved claims of gunji and farmers and dismissed the kokushu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially as described above, it was common that Daijokan approved claims of gunji and farmers and dismissed the kokushu.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially as described above, it was common that Daijokan approved claims of gunji and farmers and dismissed the kokushi.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>しかし、郡司・百姓層の要求が多分に自利的であることに藤原道長を首班とする太政官も次第に気付き始め、1110年代後期～1120年代にかけて国司解任に至る事例は約5割から約2割へと激減していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However Daijokan headed by FUJIWARA no Michinaga became aware that some claims of Gunji and farmers are rather selfish and thus claims that won dismissal of the Kokushu dramatically dropped from about 50% to 20% during the period between the latter half of the 1110&apos;s and the 1120&apos;s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However Daijokan headed by FUJIWARA no Michinaga became aware that some claims of Gunji and farmers are rather selfish and thus claims that won dismissal of the Kokushu dramatically dropped from about 50% to 20% during the period between the latter half of the 1110&apos;s and the 1120&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However Daijokan headed by FUJIWARA no Michinaga became aware that some claims of Gunji and farmers are rather selfish and thus claims that won dismissal of the Kokushu dramatically dropped from about 50% to 20% during the period between the latter half of the 1110&apos;s and the 1120&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>そして、1140年代の事例を最後に国司苛政上訴はほとんど見られなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eventually Kokushi kasei joso became rare after claims in the 1140&apos;s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eventually Kokushi kasei joso became rare after claims in the 1140&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eventually Kokushi kasei joso became rare after claims in the 1140&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>評価</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Evaluation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Evaluation</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Evaluation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>戦前（1940年代以前）は平安時代を王朝政治の形骸化・地方政治の荒廃が進んだ時期と解釈した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the war (before the 1940&apos;s) the Heian period was interpreted as a period when dynasty government was becoming a mere shell or dead letter and local government is devastating</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the war (before the 1940&apos;s) the Heian period was interpreted as a period when dynasty government was becoming a mere shell or dead letter and local government was devastating.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the war (before the 1940&apos;s) the Heian period was interpreted as a period when dynasty government was becoming a mere shell or dead letter and local government was devastating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>国司苛政上訴についても、受領層が私利私欲に溺れ、地方政治が混乱していたことの現れとする評価が一般的だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokushi kasei joso was also commonly regarded as an evidence of disrupting local governments with Juryoso (career provincial official class) seeking only for their own interests.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokushi kasei joso was also commonly regarded as evidence of disrupting local governments with Juryoso (career provincial official class) seeking only for their own interests.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokushi kasei joso was also commonly regarded as evidence of disrupting local governments with Juryoso (career provincial official class) seeking only for their own interests.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>戦後になると、王朝国家体制論のもとで国司苛政上訴に対して根本的に異なる評価が与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the war fundamentally different evolutions were given to Kokushi kasei joso based on the dynastic polity theory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the war fundamentally different evolutions were given to Kokushi kasei joso based on the dynastic polity theory.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the war fundamentally different evolutions were given to Kokushi kasei joso based on the dynastic polity theory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>10世紀前期ごろから、人民百姓を戸籍・計帳により把握する律令制的な人別支配が崩壊した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around the former half of the 10th century, the rule over people under the Ritsuryo system was destructed in which people and farmers were controlled with family register and keicho (the yearly tax registers).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the former half of the 10th century, the rule over people under the Ritsuryo system was destructed in which people and farmers were controlled with family register and keicho (the yearly tax registers).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the former half of the 10th century, the rule over people under the Ritsuryo system was destructed in which people and farmers were controlled with family register and keicho (the yearly tax registers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>朝廷は租税収入を確保するために、諸国の国衙領を名田という単位へ分割し、在地の富豪層（田堵）へ名田経営と租税納入を請け負わせる支配体制へと移行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To ensure yields of tax, the Imperial Court introduced a new ruling system where Kokugaryo (territories governed by provincial government office) in provinces were divided into units of myoden (rice field lots in charge of nominal holders) so that land lords of the wealthy class (Tato (cultivators)) undertook the management of mhyoden and land tax payment.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To ensure yields of tax, the Imperial Court introduced a new ruling system where Kokugaryo (territories governed by provincial government office) in provinces were divided into units of myoden (rice field lots in charge of nominal holders) so that land lords of the wealthy class (Tato (cultivators)) undertook the management of mhyoden and land tax payment.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To ensure yields of tax, the Imperial Court introduced a new ruling system where Kokugaryo (territories governed by provincial government office) in provinces were divided into units of myoden (rice field lots in charge of nominal holders) so that land lords of the wealthy class (Tato (cultivators)) undertook the management of myoden and land tax payment.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>これを負名体制といい、負名体制を基盤とする国家体制が王朝国家体制である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This system is called the local tax manager system, which constitutes a foundation of the system of the dynasty state as a regime.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This system is called the local tax manager system, which constitutes a foundation of the system of the dynasty state as a regime.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This system is called the local tax manager system, which constitutes a foundation of the system of the dynasty state as a regime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>こうした流れの中で国司行政も、所定の租税（官物・雑役など）の納入のみが求められ、その他は現地赴任の筆頭国司の裁量に任されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In response to this shift of the system, the administration of Kokushi (provincial governors) was required only to pay a certain taxes (such as kanmotsu (tribute goods paid as taxes or tithes) and zatsueki (odd-job tasks)) with other tasks leaving to a discretion of the appointed head of the provincial governors.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In response to this shift of the system, the administration of Kokushi (provincial governors) was required only to pay certain taxes (such as kanmotsu (tribute goods paid as taxes or tithes) and zatsueki (odd-job tasks)) with other tasks left to the discretion of the appointed head of the provincial governors.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response to this shift of the system, the administration of Kokushi (provincial governors) was required only to pay certain taxes (such as kanmotsu (tribute goods paid as taxes or tithes) and zatsueki (odd-job tasks)) with other tasks left to the discretion of the appointed head of the provincial governors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>このような国司を受領という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such Kokushi is Zuryo (the head of the provincial governors).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such Kokushi is Zuryo (the head of the provincial governors).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such Kokushi is Zuryo (the head of the provincial governors).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>受領は、自らの判断で国内支配することが許されたため、郡司・田堵・負名・百姓層から苛烈な収奪をすることが可能となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Zuryo was entitled to control over his own province at their own discretion, allowing them to collect taxes strictly from Gunji (local magistrates), Tato, Fumyo (tiller of the public rice field) and farmers.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Zuryo was entitled to control over his own province at their own discretion, allowing them to collect taxes strictly from Gunji (local magistrates), Tato, Fumyo (tiller of the public rice field), and farmers.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Zuryo was entitled to control over his own province at their own discretion, allowing them to collect taxes strictly from Gunji (local magistrates), Tato, Fumyo (tiller of the public rice field), and farmers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>それに反発した郡司・百姓層が階級闘争として国司苛政上訴を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gunji and farmers who opposed to Zuryo appealed Kokushi kasei joso as a class struggle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gunji and farmers who were opposed to Zuryo appealed Kokushi kasei joso as a class struggle.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gunji and farmers who were opposed to Zuryo appealed Kokushi kasei joso as a class struggle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>そして、国司苛政上訴が功を奏し、太政官の政策に影響を与え、国内の税率を固定化する「公田官物率法」が1040年代に制定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokushi kasei joso was effective in having an effect on Daijokan&apos;s policies, resulting in the enactment of &quot;Koden kanmotsu rippo (fixing a limit of 3 to of rice per tan of land)&quot; in 1040 for fixing the tax rates in Japan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokushi kasei joso was effective in having an effect on Daijokan&apos;s policies, resulting in the enactment of &quot;Koden kanmotsu rippo (fixing a limit of 3 to of rice per tan of land)&quot; in 1040 for fixing the tax rates in Japan.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokushi kasei joso was effective in having an effect on Daijokan&apos;s policies, resulting in the enactment of &quot;Koden kanmotsu rippo&quot; (fixing a limit of 3 to of rice per tan of land) in 1040 for fixing the tax rates in Japan.</e>
<cmt>&quot;位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>受領の恣意的支配が抑制されたため、国司苛政上訴も沈静化した、とする評価である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore the post-war evaluation is that the disappear of Kokushi kasei joso was because Zuryo&apos;s arbitrary administration had been controlled.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore the post-war evaluation is that the disappearance of Kokushi kasei joso was because Zuryo&apos;s arbitrary administration had been controlled.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore the post-war evaluation is that the disappearance of Kokushi kasei joso was because Zuryo&apos;s arbitrary administration had been controlled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="28">
<j>以上の考え方に対して、当時の受領層は必ずしも私欲的に郡司・百姓層を抑圧していたのではないとする考えもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some have opinions different from above; Juryoso (career provincial official class) in those days did not necessarily suppress Gunji and farmers to pursue their own self-interest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some have opinions different from above; Juryoso (career provincial official class) in those days did not necessarily suppress Gunji and farmers to pursue their own self-interest.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some have opinions different from above; Juryoso (career provincial official class) in those days did not necessarily suppress Gunji and farmers to pursue their own self-interest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>個別の国司苛政上訴事案を観察すると、訴えられた国司らは、慣例で免除されていた税目を法令どおりに課税したり、当時よく発令された天皇代替わり新制に伴う地方税制に則った課税を行ったりと、彼らの遵法的な行政姿勢が見て取れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Examining individual cases of Kokushi kasei joso, we can find law-abiding admistrative stances of sued Kokushi; some legally levied tax items not collected by custom or others levied local taxes, often collected in those days under a new system by the change of the emperors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Examining individual cases of Kokushi kasei joso, we can find law-abiding administrative stances of the sued Kokushi; some legally levied tax items not collected by customs or others levied local taxes, often collected in those days under a new system by the change of the emperors.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Examining individual cases of Kokushi kasei joso, we can find law-abiding administrative stances of the sued Kokushi; some legally levied tax items not collected by customs or others levied local taxes, often collected in those days under a new system by the change of the emperors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>貪欲な受領とされることの多い藤原元命だが、当時、花山天皇が即位直後に地方税制の改革など積極的な政策展開を行っており、元命はこの花山新制の方針を遵守したに過ぎないとする見方もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although FUJIWARA no Motonaga have been often regarded as a greedy Zuryo, some suggest that Motonaga only observed strictly the policy of Kazan shinsei (new laws issued by Emperor Kazan) under the new local tax system Emperor Kazan actively introduced immediately after his enthronement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although FUJIWARA no Motonaga had been often regarded as a greedy Zuryo, some suggest that Motonaga only observed strictly the policy of Kazan shinsei (new laws issued by Emperor Kazan) under the new local tax system Emperor Kazan actively introduced immediately after his enthronement.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although FUJIWARA no Motonaga had been often regarded as a greedy Zuryo, some suggest that Motonaga only observed strictly the policy of Kazan shinsei (new laws issued by Emperor Kazan) under the new local tax system Emperor Kazan actively introduced immediately after his enthronement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>これらから、負名体制が本来的に有していた矛盾が国司苛政上訴という形態で現れたと評価する見解が提出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These views have brought about a opinion that a contradiction intrinsic to the local tax manager system appeared in the form of Kokushi kasei joso.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These views have brought about an opinion that a contradiction intrinsic to the local tax manager system appeared in the form of Kokushi kasei joso.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These views have brought about an opinion that a contradiction intrinsic to the local tax manager system appeared in the form of Kokushi kasei joso.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>実際、長門国守と紛争を起こした在庁官人が意趣返し的に苛政上訴を行う事例や、丹波国守を苛政上訴していた百姓らがその直後に当該国守を称揚する書状を提出した事例、上訴百姓が京にある国守宅に焼き打ちした事例など、むしろ郡司・百姓層に私欲的な姿勢を見いだすこともできる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, rather selfish desires of Gunji and farmers can be seen in some cases: for example, Kokushi kasei joso was a revenge by zaichokanjin (the local officials in Heian and Kamakura periods) who had an argument with Nagato no kuni no kami (governor of Nagato Province); farmers submitted a letter to praise their Tanba no kuni no kami immediately after Kokushi kasei joso; and appealing farmers set fire to the kokushi&apos;s residence in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, rather selfish desires of Gunji and farmers can be seen in some cases: for example, Kokushi kasei joso was a revenge by zaichokanjin (the local officials in Heian and Kamakura periods) who had an argument with Nagato no kuni no kami (governor of Nagato Province); farmers submitted a letter to praise their Tanba no kuni no kami immediately after Kokushi kasei joso; and appealing farmers set fire to the kokushi&apos;s residence in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, rather selfish desires of Gunji and farmers can be seen in some cases: for example, Kokushi kasei joso was a revenge by zaichokanjin (the local officials in Heian and Kamakura periods) who had an argument with Nagato no kuni no kami (governor of Nagato Province); farmers submitted a letter to praise their Tanba no kuni no kami immediately after Kokushi kasei joso; and appealing farmers set fire to the kokushi&apos;s residence in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>この見解では、郡司・百姓層が在庁官人として国衙行政に取り込まれていったことにより、国司苛政上訴が消滅したとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this opinion, Kokushi kasei joso disappeared because Gunji and farmers became involved in Kokuga government as Zaichokanjin (the local officials in Heian and Kamakura periods).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this opinion, Kokushi kasei joso disappeared because Gunji and farmers became involved in Kokuga government as Zaichokanjin (the local officials in Heian and Kamakura periods).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this opinion, Kokushi kasei joso disappeared because Gunji and farmers became involved in Kokuga government as Zaichokanjin (the local officials in Heian and Kamakura periods).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="34">
<j>また、10世紀後期には国衙職員と郡司が雑色人（ぞうしきにん）と一体的に呼ばれるようになっいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, officials in kokuga (provincial government offices) and Gunji began to be collectively called Zoshikinin (lower-level functionaries in the provincial government) in the latter half the 10th century.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, officials in kokuga (provincial government offices) and Gunji began to be collectively called Zoshikinin (lower-level functionaries in the provincial government) in the latter half the 10th century.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, officials in kokuga (provincial government offices) and Gunji began to be collectively called Zoshikinin (lower-level functionaries in the provincial government) in the latter half the 10th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>この雑色人が在地支配層と連携し、国司・受領層と対抗したことが国司苛政上訴として現れたとする見解も出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other opinions, Kokushi kasei joso appeared as the evidence that these Zoshikinin worked with local influential persons to counter the Kokushi and Zuryo class</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other opinions, Kokushi kasei joso appeared as the evidence that these Zoshikinin worked with local influential persons to counter the Kokushi and Zuryo class.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other opinions, Kokushi kasei joso appeared as the evidence that these Zoshikinin worked with local influential persons to counter the Kokushi and Zuryo class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="36">
<j>そもそも、これらの歴史的事件を評価するときに念頭に置いておかなければならないのは、受領層に対して闘争を行った百姓層とは決して受領の収奪にあえぐ零細な農民などではなく、隷属民や私兵を多数擁して地域支配や産業において莫大な利権を持ち、国衙と負名契約を結んでいた、農業など諸産業の大規模経営者であったということである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In evaluating these historical events, we should keep it in mind in the first place that the farmer class refers not to poor farmers suffering from heavy taxes Zuryo collected but to large-scale managers of agriculture and other industries who had vested rights in the local community and industries with many subordinate people and private solders and had a contract with kokuga over fumyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In evaluating these historical events, we should keep in mind that the farmer class refers not to poor farmers suffering from heavy taxes Zuryo collected but to large-scale managers of agriculture and other industries who had vested rights in the local community and industries with many subordinate people and private solders and had a contract with kokuga over fumyo.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In evaluating these historical events, we should keep in mind that the farmer class refers not to poor farmers suffering from heavy taxes Zuryo collected but to large-scale managers of agriculture and other industries who had vested rights in the local community and industries with many subordinate people and private solders and had a contract with kokuga over fumyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>こうした闘争をどう評価するにせよ、地域統治と収税の効率化のためにこうした富豪百姓層の成長を助け、彼らが莫大な利権を獲得する契機を与えたのはまぎれもなく受領を筆頭とする国衙機構であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No matter what evaluations are given to these conflicts, it is clear that the mechanism of Kokuga (provincial government offices) headed by Zuryo helped such a wealthy farmer class grow to control the region and collect taxes more efficiently and gave them opportunities of acquiring a huge vested interests.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No matter what evaluations are given to these conflicts, it is clear that the mechanism of Kokuga (provincial government offices) headed by Zuryo helped such a wealthy farmer class grow to control the region and collect taxes more efficiently and gave them opportunities of acquiring huge vested interests.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No matter what evaluations are given to these conflicts, it is clear that the mechanism of Kokuga (provincial government offices) headed by Zuryo helped such a wealthy farmer class grow to control the region and collect taxes more efficiently and gave them opportunities of acquiring huge vested interests.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>この闘争は正にそうして発生した富をめぐって朝廷から地方統治と租税徴収を任された受領と、富を集積していた富豪百姓層が、激しく衝突したものだったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These conflicts were brought about by severe competition for wealth between Zuryo who took responsibility in the local governance and tax collection and the wealthy farmer class who were gathering wealth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These conflicts were brought about by severe competition for wealth between Zuryo who took responsibility in the local governance and tax collection and the wealthy farmer class who were gathering wealth.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These conflicts were brought about by severe competition for wealth between Zuryo who took responsibility in the local governance and tax collection and the wealthy farmer class who were gathering wealth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>こうした事情は田堵、負名、受領、百姓、武士といった関連諸項目をも参照のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For more details, see sections of Tato and Fumyo, Zuryo and warriors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For more details, see sections of Tato and Fumyo, Zuryo and warriors.</e>
<cmt>Spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For more details, see sections of Tato and Fumyo, Zuryo, farmers and warriors.</e>
<cmt>farmers補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Shimoxx(id:9332), Novo(id:87875), ウミユスリカ(id:9504), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>