<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>草薙剣盗難事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Case of Theft of Kusanagi no Tsurugi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Case of Theft of Kusanagi no Tsurugi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Case of Theft of Kusanagi no Tsurugi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>草薙剣盗難事件（くさなぎのつるぎとうなんじけん）は、668年(天智天皇7年)に発生した盗難事件。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The case of theft of Kusanagi no tsurugi occurred in 668 (the seventh year of Emperor Tenchi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The case of theft of Kusanagi no tsurugi (alternate name for Ama-no-Murakumo no Tsurugi, the sword of the Imperial regalia) occurred in 668.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The case of theft of Kusanagi no tsurugi (alternate name for Ama-no-Murakumo no Tsurugi, the sword of the Imperial regalia) occurred in 668.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>熱田神宮の神体である草薙剣が盗まれた事件である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kusanagi no tsurugi, an object of worship in Atsuta-jingu Shrine, was stolen in the case.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kusanagi no tsurugi, an object of worship in Atsuta-jingu Shrine, was stolen in the case.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kusanagi no tsurugi, an object of worship in Atsuta-jingu Shrine, was stolen in the case.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経緯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Circumstances Behind the Incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Circumstances Behind the Case</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Circumstances Behind the Case</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>『日本書紀』天智天皇紀には668年（天智天皇7年）のこととして、「是歳。沙門道行盗草薙剣、逃向新羅。而中路風雨。荒迷而帰」（この年、僧道行が草薙剣を盗んだ。新羅に向かって逃げたが、その路の途中で風雨が荒れ、迷って帰ってきた。）と記載されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a description as follows in the history of Emperor Tenchi of &quot;Chronicles of Japan&quot; regarding the incident in 668 (the seventh year of Emperor Tenchi): This year the priest Dogyo stole Kusanagi no tsurugi. He fled to Shiragi (ancient Korean kingdom), but he had stormy weather on his way, got lost and turned back.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a description as follows in the history of Emperor Tenchi of &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) regarding the case in 668: This year the priest Dogyo stole Kusanagi no tsurugi; he fled to Silla (ancient Korean kingdom), but he had stormy weather on his way, got lost and turned back.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a description as follows in the history of Emperor Tenchi of &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) regarding the case in 668: This year the priest Dogyo stole Kusanagi no tsurugi; he fled to Silla (ancient Korean kingdom), but he had stormy weather on his way, got lost and turned back.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>沙門道行盗草薙剣、逃向新羅。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The priest Dogyo stole Kusanagi no tsurugi; he fled to Silla.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。前出文と重複しています。ウェブでは重複はありませんが、訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The priest Dogyo stole Kusanagi no tsurugi; he fled to Silla.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>而中路風雨。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But he had stormy weather on his way.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。前出文と重複しています。ウェブでは重複はありませんが、訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But he had stormy weather on his way.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>「荒迷而帰」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He got lost and turned back.&apos;</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。前出文と重複しています。ウェブでは重複はありませんが、訳出しました。またかっこを補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He got lost and turned back.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>（この年、僧道行が草薙剣を盗んだ。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(This year the priest Dogyo stole Kusanagi no tsurugi.)</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。前出文と重複しています。ウェブでは重複はありませんが、訳出し、かっこを補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(This year the priest Dogyo stole Kusanagi no tsurugi.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>（新羅に向かって逃げたが、その路の途中で風雨が荒れ、迷って帰ってきた。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(He fled to Silla, but had stormy weather on his way, got lost and turned back.)</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。前出文と重複しています。ウェブでは重複はありませんが、訳出し、かっこを補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(He fled to Silla, but had stormy weather on his way, got lost and turned back.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>このように記載されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It described as this.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。前出文と重複しています。ウェブでは重複はありませんが、訳出しました。原文を文章になるように修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It described as this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>熱田神宮の社伝では、新羅の僧・道行が、熱田神宮を参詣した折、清雪門より内部に侵入し、草薙剣を盗み出したとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shrine&apos;s biography of Atsuta-jingu Shrine showed that when Shiragi&apos;s priest Dogyo visited Atsuta-jingu Shrine, he trespassed on the shrine through Seisetsu Gate and stole Kusanagi no tsurugi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shrine&apos;s biography of Atsuta-jingu Shrine showed that when Silla&apos;s priest Dogyo visited the Atsuta-jingu Shrine, he trespassed on the shrine through Seisetsu Gate and stole the Kusanagi no tsurugi.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shrine&apos;s biography of Atsuta-jingu Shrine showed that when Silla&apos;s priest Dogyo visited the Atsuta-jingu Shrine, he trespassed on the shrine through Seisetsu Gate and stole the Kusanagi no tsurugi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>（この事件以来、清雪門は「不開門（あかずのもん）」と呼ばれ、閉ざされたままとなっている。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Seisetsu Gate has been closed since this incident, and called a never-opened gate.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The Seisetsu Gate has been closed since this case, and called &apos;Akazu no Mon&apos; [a never-opened gate].)</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The Seisetsu Gate has been closed since this case, and called &apos;Akazu no Mon&apos; [a never-opened gate].)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>道行は草薙剣を持って祖国の新羅に渡ろうとしたが、嵐により果たせず失敗に終わったとする点は『日本書紀』と同じである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shrine&apos;s biography corresponded with &quot;Chronicles of Japan&quot; in that although Dogyo tried to come back to his homeland Shiragi carrying Kusanagi no tsurugi with him, the storm prevented him from doing so.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the same as the description in &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; that although Dogyo tried to come back to his homeland Silla carrying the Kusanagi no tsurugi with him, the storm prevented him from doing so.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the same as the description in &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; that although Dogyo tried to come back to his homeland Silla carrying the Kusanagi no tsurugi with him, the storm prevented him from doing so.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>社伝によると道行はその後捕らわれの身となり、草薙剣は宮中で預かることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the shrine&apos;s biography, Dogyo was held in captivity, and Kusanagi no tsurugi was kept in the Imperial Court after that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the shrine&apos;s biography, Dogyo was held in captivity, and the Kusanagi no tsurugi was kept in the Imperial Court after that.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the shrine&apos;s biography, Dogyo was held in captivity, and the Kusanagi no tsurugi was kept in the Imperial Court after that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>686年（朱鳥元年）になって、草薙剣は熱田神宮に返還された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 686 Kusanagi no tsurugi was returned to Atsuta-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 686 the Kusanagi no tsurugi was returned to the Atsuta-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 686 the Kusanagi no tsurugi was returned to the Atsuta-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>ただしこれは、天武天皇が草薙剣の祟り（合理的に解釈するならば熱田側からの圧力や反乱）によって病を得て崩御したことがきっかけであったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this seemed to be prompted by the fact that Emperor Tenmu got sick by the curse of Kusanagi no tsurugi (realistically because of the pressure and rebellion from Atsuta-jingu Shrine), and that Emperor Tenmu passed away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this seemed to be prompted by the fact that Emperor Tenmu got sick by the curse of the Kusanagi no tsurugi (realistically because of the pressure and rebellion from the Atsuta-jingu Shrine), and that Emperor Tenmu passed away.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this seemed to be prompted by the fact that Emperor Tenmu got sick by the curse of the Kusanagi no tsurugi (realistically because of the pressure and rebellion from the Atsuta-jingu Shrine), and that Emperor Tenmu passed away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>なお、大阪市の放出（はなてん）という地名は、道行が神罰（嵐）を怖れ、草薙剣を放り出したことが由来（はなつて→はなて→はなてん）とする説があり、同地にはその伝承を伝える阿遅速雄神社がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a rumor, the name of a place in Osaka City Hanaten derived from the episode that Dogyo scared of divine punishment (storm) threw out Kusanagi no tsurugi there (the Japanese word Hanatsu means to throw out something), and there is Ajihayao-jinja Shrine in the place that handed down the tradition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a rumor, Hanaten, the name of a place in Osaka City, derived from the episode that Dogyo scared of divine punishment (storm) threw out the Kusanagi no tsurugi there (the Japanese word Hanatsu means to throw out something and the word Hanatsu turned into Hanate then Hanaten), and there is Ajihayao-jinja Shrine there which handed down the tradition.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a rumor, Hanaten, the name of a place in Osaka City, derived from the episode that Dogyo scared of divine punishment (storm) threw out the Kusanagi no tsurugi there (the Japanese word Hanatsu means to throw out something and the word Hanatsu turned into Hanate then Hanaten), and there is Ajihayao-jinja Shrine there which handed down the tradition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>道行の経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career of Dogyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career of Dogyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career of Dogyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>道行は新羅王族の末裔といわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dogyo was said to be a descendant of a royal family in Shiragi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dogyo is said to be a descendant of a royal family in Silla.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dogyo is said to be a descendant of a royal family in Silla.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>霊験あらたかな草薙剣を盗んで新羅の物にすれば、その神通力で新羅が強国になることができるというのが動機であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dogyo stole Kusanagi no tsurugi because he thought that if the wonder-working Kusanagi no tsurugi became Shiragi&apos;s possessions, its divine power would help Shiragi to be a great power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dogyo stole the Kusanagi no tsurugi because he thought that if the wonder-working of the sword became Silla&apos;s possessions, its divine power would help Silla to be a great power.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dogyo stole the Kusanagi no tsurugi because he thought that if the wonder-working of the sword became Silla&apos;s possessions, its divine power would help Silla to be a great power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="20">
<j>逮捕後、道行は博多で斬首されたとも、赦免されて愛知県知多市の法海寺を開いたともいわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that after the arrest, Dogyo was beheaded in Hakata, or that he was absolved and founded Hokai-ji Temple in Chita City, Aichi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that after the arrest, Dogyo was beheaded in Hakata, or that he was absolved and founded Hokai-ji Temple in Chita City, Aichi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that after the arrest, Dogyo was beheaded in Hakata, or that he was absolved and founded Hokai-ji Temple in Chita City, Aichi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="21">
<j>解釈</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Interpretation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Interpretation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Interpretation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>上述のように道行が赦免されたのだとすると、この事件はそもそも天智天皇の自作自演だった可能性がある、という説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a theory, if it was true that Dogyo was discharged as described above, there was a possibility that Emperor Tenmu performed his own work in this incident,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a theory, if it was true that Dogyo was discharged as previously described, there was a possibility that Emperor Tenmu performed his own work in this case.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a theory, if it was true that Dogyo was discharged as previously described, there was a possibility that Emperor Tenmu performed his own work in this case.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>つまり、日本武尊が独断で宮簀媛に預け、結果的に手放すことになってしまった草薙剣を取り返すべく、道行を買収したわけである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, the side of Emperor Tenmu bribed Dogyo into stealing for the purpose of recovering Kusanagi no tsurugi which YAMATO Takeru no Mikoto left in the care of Miyazu Hime at his own discretion, resulting in letting go of.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, the side of Emperor Tenmu bribed Dogyo into stealing for the purpose of recovering the Kusanagi no tsurugi which YAMATO Takeru no Mikoto left in the care of Miyazu Hime at his own discretion, resulting in letting go of.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, the side of Emperor Tenmu bribed Dogyo into stealing for the purpose of recovering the Kusanagi no tsurugi which YAMATO Takeru no Mikoto left in the care of Miyazu Hime at his own discretion, resulting in letting go of.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>この場合、天智天皇が法海寺建立を許可したのはその褒美ということになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this case, Emperor Tenmu gave Dogyo his approval to erect Hokai-ji Temple as rewards for his work.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this case, Emperor Tenmu gave Dogyo his approval to erect Hokai-ji Temple as rewards for his work.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this case, Emperor Tenmu gave Dogyo his approval to erect Hokai-ji Temple as rewards for his work.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>確かにこの説に従えば、668年から686年までの18年間も剣を返還せずに占有していた不自然さは解消できるだろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Indeed this theory may help dissipate the unnaturalness that Emperor Tenmu possessed Kusanagi no tsurugi for 18 years from 668 to 686 without returning it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Indeed this theory may help dissipate the unnaturalness that Emperor Tenmu possessed the Kusanagi no tsurugi for 18 years from 668 to 686 without returning it.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Indeed this theory may help dissipate the unnaturalness that Emperor Tenmu possessed the Kusanagi no tsurugi for 18 years from 668 to 686 without returning it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>そもそも、事件後に草薙剣を宮中で預かったのが正当な処置であるのなら、天武天皇が草薙剣の祟りに見舞われるはずなどないとも言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It may be said that in the first place Emperor Tenmu should not be met with the curse of Kusanagi no tsurugi if it was proper treatment that the Imperial Court took Kusanagi no tsurugi in charge after the incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It may be said that in the first place Emperor Tenmu should not be met with the curse of the Kusanagi no tsurugi if it was proper treatment that the Imperial Court took the Kusanagi no tsurugi in charge after the case.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It may be said that in the first place Emperor Tenmu should not be met with the curse of the Kusanagi no tsurugi if it was proper treatment that the Imperial Court took the Kusanagi no tsurugi in charge after the case.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Jihi(id:261170), 幕張防波堤(id:58869), Hopedoffer(id:160959), Japan Maik(id:254359), Law soma(id:45202), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>