<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>東山御文庫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Higashiyama Go-bunko(collection)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Higashiyama Gobunko (the imperial library)</e>
<cmt>Go-bunko→Gobunko と修正しました。カッコ部分を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Higashiyama Gobunko (the imperial library)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>東山御文庫（ひがしやまごぶんこ）とは、京都御所内の東北隅に位置する皇室の文庫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Higashiyama Go-bunko refers to the Imperial family library located in northeast corner of Kyoto Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Higashiyama Go-bunko refers to the imperial family library located in northeast corner of Kyoto Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>Imperial→imperial と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Higashiyama Go-bunko refers to the imperial family library located in northeast corner of Kyoto Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>禁裏御文庫（きんりごぶんこ）・東山文庫（ひがしやまぶんこ）とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Kinri Go-bunko and Higashiyama bunko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called Kinri Gobunko and Higashiyama bunko.</e>
<cmt>Go-bunko→Gobunko と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called Kinri Gobunko and Higashiyama bunko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>歴代天皇の宸翰及び収集・手沢の書画・道具など約6万点が収蔵されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The past Emperor&apos;s shinkan (Imperial letter) or the collections, the favorite calligraphic works and paintings and instruments, which are about sixty thousand items, are stored.</e>
<cmt>「収集」とありますが、「何の収集」なのか読み取り不可で、the collectionsとしておきました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The past emperors&apos; shinkan (imperial letter) or the collections, the favorite calligraphic works and paintings and tools, which are about 60,000 items, are stored.</e>
<cmt>Emperor&apos;s→emperors&apos;,Imperial→imperial,instruments→tools,sixty thousand→60,000 と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The past emperors&apos; shinkan (imperial letter) or the collections, the favorite calligraphic works and paintings and tools, which are about 60,000 items, are stored.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>現在、東大寺正倉院などと同様に勅封扱いとなっており、宮内庁侍従職が管理している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present it is treated as chokufu (imperial seal) like Todai-ji Temple Shosoin and so on, and jiju (a chamberlain) of the Imperial Household Agency manages it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present it is treated as chokufu (imperial seal) same as Todai-ji Temple Shosoin and so on, and jiju (a chamberlain) of the Imperial Household Agency manages it.</e>
<cmt>like→same as と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present it is treated as chokufu (imperial seal) same as Todai-ji Temple Shosoin and so on, and jiju (a chamberlain) of the Imperial Household Agency manages it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>秋の曝涼（所蔵物の「虫干し」のことで定期的に行われる）の際に専門家を対象とした特別な調査が許される以外に公開されることはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Except for the special check by experts in the time of bakuryo (airing) in autumn (the airing for stored items is regularly done), it is not opened to the public.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Except for the special examination by experts in the occasion of bakuryo (airing) in autumn (the &apos;airing&apos; for stored items is regularly done), it is not opened to the public.</e>
<cmt>check→examination,time→occasion,クォーツを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Except for the special examination by experts in the occasion of bakuryo (airing) in autumn (the &apos;airing&apos; for stored items is regularly done), it is not opened to the public.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>ただし、書陵部によってマイクロフィルム化が、東京大学史料編纂所によって写本（「京都御所東山御文庫記録」）化が進められており、内容の一部が公開されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the items are being microfilmed by Imperial Household Archives and are being copied by Historiographical Institute The University of Tokyo (&apos;Kyoto Imperial Palace Higashiyama Go-bunko Record&apos;) and a part of the contents comes to be opened to the public.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the items are being microfilmed by the Imperial Household Archives and are being copied by Historiographical Institute of The University of Tokyo (&apos;Kyoto Imperial Palace Higashiyama Gobunko Record&apos;), and a part of the contents comes to be opened to the public.</e>
<cmt>the, of, カンマを補いました。 Go-bunko→Gobunko と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the items are being microfilmed by the Imperial Household Archives and are being copied by Historiographical Institute of The University of Tokyo (&apos;Kyoto Imperial Palace Higashiyama Gobunko Record&apos;), and a part of the contents comes to be opened to the public.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>なお、「東山」の名称は近衛家邸内にあった「東山の御庫」と称する土蔵が、1881年に近衛忠煕より献上・移設されて文庫の施設として利用されたことに由来している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name &apos;Higashiyama&apos; originates from the fact that dozo (warehouse made of soil) in the Konoe family, called &apos;Higashiyama no goko,&apos; was dedicated and transferred by Tadahiro KONOE in 1881 and was used for a facility of the library.</e>
<cmt>「御庫」、読み方不明でした。Gokoとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name &apos;Higashiyama&apos; originates from the fact that dozo (warehouse made of soil) in the Konoe family, called &apos;Higashiyama no goko,&apos; was presented and transferred by Tadahiro KONOE in 1881 and was used for a facility of the library.</e>
<cmt>dedicated→presented と修正しました。「御庫」については、”みくら”ではないかと思いますが確認は取れていません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name &apos;Higashiyama&apos; originates from the fact that dozo (warehouse made of soil) in the Konoe family, called &apos;Higashiyama no goko,&apos; was presented and transferred by Tadahiro KONOE in 1881 and was used for a facility of the library.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>従って、足利義政の東山殿や東山天皇（113代天皇）などとは直接の関連性はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, it is not directly related with Higashimaya-dono of Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA or Emperor Higashiyama (the one hundred thirteenth Emperor) and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, it is not directly related with Higashimaya-dono of Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA or the Emperor Higashiyama (the one hundred thirteenth Emperor) and so on.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, it is not directly related with Higashimaya-dono of Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA or the Emperor Higashiyama (the one hundred thirteenth Emperor) and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>皇室には古代から様々な書籍などが伝えられてきたが、応仁の乱や戦国時代 (日本)の経済的衰微によって多くを手放した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Imperial family, various books and so on had been inherited from ancient times, but through economic decline in Onin war or the Sengoku period (period of warring states) (Japan), many of them were lost.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Imperial family, various books and so on had been inherited from ancient times, but through the economic decline in the Onin War or the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) (Japan), many of them were lost.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。war→War,「戦国時代」を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Imperial family, various books and so on had been inherited from ancient times, but through the economic decline in the Onin War or the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) (Japan), many of them were lost.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その後、後陽成天皇・後水尾天皇が社会の安定化を受けて収集に尽力したが、承応2年6月23日 (旧暦)（1653年7月17日）の火災で内裏はほぼ全焼し、文庫も1宇を残して全て灰燼に帰した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Emperor Goyozei and Emperor Gomizunoo did their best to collect the books with the stabilization of society, but the fire on July 17, 1653 burned down almost all the dairi (Imperial Palace) and all the libraries were burnt down except for one house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, the Emperor Goyozei and the Emperor Gomizunoo did their best to collect the books with the stabilization of the society, but the fire on July 17, 1653 burned almost all the dairi (Imperial Palace) and all the libraries were burnt down except for one.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。 down, house を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, the Emperor Goyozei and the Emperor Gomizunoo did their best to collect the books with the stabilization of the society, but the fire on July 17, 1653 burned almost all the dairi (Imperial Palace) and all the libraries were burnt down except for one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>これを憂慮した後西天皇・霊元天皇は、京都の公家や寺社に要請して和歌・物語・日記・記録・有職故実・公事関連書・社寺文書類などの精度の高い写本を作成し、更に貴重な典籍を謄写して副本を作成を作成して別の場所に置くことによって亡失を防ごうとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Disturbed by this, Emperor Gosai and Emperor Reigen asked court nobles or temples and shrines in Kyoto to accurately copy waka (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables), stories, diaries, records, Yusoku kojitsu (court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquette), documents on kuji (public duties) and shrines and temples and so on, and furthermore, made the precious books and documents copied to be the duplicates and stored them in the other places in order to prevent the lost.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Disturbed by this, the Emperor Gosai and the Emperor Reigen asked court nobles or temples and shrines in Kyoto to accurately copy waka (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables), stories, diaries, records, Yusoku kojitsu (court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquette), documents on kuji (public duties) and shrines and temples and so on, and furthermore, made the precious books and documents copied to be the duplicates and stored them in the other places in order to prevent the loss.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。 lost→loss と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Disturbed by this, the Emperor Gosai and the Emperor Reigen asked court nobles or temples and shrines in Kyoto to accurately copy waka (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables), stories, diaries, records, Yusoku kojitsu (court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquette), documents on kuji (public duties) and shrines and temples and so on, and furthermore, made the precious books and documents copied to be the duplicates and stored them in the other places in order to prevent the loss.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>万治4年1月15日 (旧暦)（1661年2月14日）、再度の内裏火災で残された蔵書の多くが焼失したが、別に安置した副本は被害を免れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 14, 1661, the fire in dairi burned down the remained books and documents again, but the duplicates in the other places remained safe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 14, 1661, again the fire in dairi burned the remained books and documents, but the duplicates in the other places remained safe.</e>
<cmt>down を削除しました。オーダーを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 14, 1661, again the fire in dairi burned the remained books and documents, but the duplicates in the other places remained safe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>これを機に歴代天皇は貴重書の収集とその副本作成に尽くし、副本を納める倉庫を充実させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Successive Emperors took this occasion to do their best to collect precious books and make the duplicate books and enhance the storehouses for the duplicate books.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Successive emperors took this chance to do their best to collect precious books and make the duplicate books and maintain the storehouses for the duplicate books.</e>
<cmt>Emperors→emperors,occasion→chance,enhance→maintain と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Successive emperors took this chance to do their best to collect precious books and make the duplicate books and maintain the storehouses for the duplicate books.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これが後の東山文庫の始まりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was the beginning of Hiagashiyama bunko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the beginning of Hiagashiyama bunko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the beginning of Hiagashiyama bunko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>貴重書収集・副本作成の作業には天皇自身も深く関与し、その宸筆によって本文・外題が記されたものが多く、蔵書印も後西天皇（「明暦」）・東山天皇（「元禄」）・桜町天皇（「延享」）・後桜町天皇（「明和」）など在位中の元号を用いたものや「皇統文庫」という統一印を用いる例（後西・桜町・孝明天皇）などが使用され、孝明天皇のように「統仁」・「此華」・「天淵」などの独自の蔵書印を作成する天皇もいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperors themselves were deeply involved with the collection and production of precious books and many of the contents and titles were written by the Shinpitsu (Emperor&apos;s own handwriting), as for book collection seals, the era names on the throne such as Emperor Gosai (&apos;Meireki era&apos;), Emperor Higashiyama (&apos;Genroku era&apos;), Emperor Gosakuramachi (&apos;Meiwa Era&apos;) and so on were used, or unified seal called &apos;imperial line bunko&apos; was used (for example, Gosai Emperor, Sakuramachi Emperor and Emperor Komei), and some Emperors made unique book collection seals such as &apos;Osahito,&apos; &apos;Konohana,&apos; &apos;Tenen&apos; and so on, like Emperor Komei.</e>
<cmt>「蔵書印」を、book collection sealとしました。また、「用いる例（後西・桜町・孝明天皇）などが使用され」は、「例などが使用され」とは日本語として不適切(意味不明）なので、シンプルに「用いられることもあり」と取りました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperors themselves were deeply involved with the collection of the precious books and production of copies, and many of the contents and titles were written by the Shinpitsu (emperor&apos;s own handwriting), as for book collection seals, the era names on the throne such as the Emperor Gosai (&apos;Meireki era&apos;), the Emperor Higashiyama (&apos;Genroku era&apos;), the Emperor Gosakuramachi (&apos;Meiwa Era&apos;) and so on were used, or unified seal called &apos;imperial line bunko&apos; was used (for example, the Gosai Emperor, the Sakuramachi Emperor and the Emperor Komei), and some emperors made unique book collection seals such as &apos;Osahito,&apos; &apos;Konohana,&apos; &apos;Tenen&apos; and so on, like the Emperor Komei.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。 Emperor, Emperors →emperor, emperors と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperors themselves were deeply involved with the collection of the precious books and production of copies, and many of the contents and titles were written by the Shinpitsu (emperor&apos;s own handwriting), as for book collection seals, the era names on the throne such as the Emperor Gosai (&apos;Meireki era&apos;), the Emperor Higashiyama (&apos;Genroku era&apos;), the Emperor Gosakuramachi (&apos;Meiwa Era&apos;) and so on were used, or unified seal called &apos;imperial line bunko&apos; was used (for example, the Gosai Emperor, the Sakuramachi Emperor and the Emperor Komei), and some emperors made unique book collection seals such as &apos;Osahito,&apos; &apos;Konohana,&apos; &apos;Tenen&apos; and so on, like the Emperor Komei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>東京奠都後、内裏の蔵書の一部は新御所の設置された皇居に移され、更に宮家創設時に分与された例もある（ただし、分与を受けた宮家は後に全て断絶してしまうこととなり、蔵書は宮内庁書陵部や国立歴史民俗博物館に移された）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the transfer of the capital to Tokyo, a part of the stored books in dairi was transferred to new Imperial Palace and furthermore, in the foundation of Imperial families, some of them were shared to them (however, all the Imperial families which received the share discontinued later and the stored books were transferred to Imperial Household Archives or National Museum of Japanese History).</e>
<cmt>「御所」も「皇居」も、英語ではImperial Palaceとなるため、和文の冗長性を簡略化しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the transfer of the capital to Tokyo, a part of the stored books in dairi was transferred to new Imperial Palace and furthermore, in the establishment of miyake (families allowed to have the status of Imperial family), some of them were allocated to them (However, all the miyake which received the allocation were discontinued later and the stored books were transferred to Imperial Household Archives or National Museum of Japanese History.)</e>
<cmt>foundation→establishment,「宮家」を修正しました。shared→allocated, share→allocation were と修正しました。カッコ内、ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the transfer of the capital to Tokyo, a part of the stored books in dairi was transferred to new Imperial Palace and furthermore, in the establishment of miyake (families allowed to have the status of Imperial family), some of them were allocated to them (However, all the miyake which received the allocation were discontinued later and the stored books were transferred to Imperial Household Archives or National Museum of Japanese History.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>その後、近衛家の東京移住に伴って取り壊されることになった近衛邸のうち、東山の御蔵が献上されて残された文庫の保管に用いられたために、その名前がそのまま文庫名となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, when the Konoe family moved to Tokyo the houses were demolished, but the okura (a rice storehouse of the Edo shogunate) of Higashiyama was dedicated and used for storing the remained books and thus the name became a name of the library.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, the original houses were decided to be demolished when the Konoe family moved to Tokyo, but the okura (a rice storehouse of the Edo bakufu) of Higashiyama was presented and used for storing the remained books and thus the name became a name of the library.</e>
<cmt>shogunate→bakufu,dedicated→presented と修正しました。文脈より修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, the original houses were decided to be demolished when the Konoe family moved to Tokyo, but the okura (a rice storehouse of the Edo bakufu) of Higashiyama was presented and used for storing the remained books and thus the name became a name of the library.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>