<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>柳本藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yanagimoto Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yanagimoto Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yanagimoto Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>柳本藩（やなぎもとはん）は、大和国式上郡・山辺郡・宇陀郡を領有した藩。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yanagimoto domain covered Shikijo, Yamabe and Uda counties of Yamato-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yanagimoto Domain covered Shikijo, Yamabe and Uda counties of Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>Domain を大文字にしました。Yamato Province としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yanagimoto Domain covered Shikijo, Yamabe and Uda counties of Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藩庁は柳本陣屋（現在の奈良県天理市柳本町黒塚古墳）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The seat of government was the Yanagimoto Jinya (present-day Kurozuka Tumulus, Yanagimoto-cho, Tenri City, Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The seat of government was the Yanagimoto Jinya (present-day Kurozuka Tumulus, Yanagimoto-cho, Tenri City, Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The seat of government was the Yanagimoto Jinya (present-day Kurozuka Tumulus, Yanagimoto-cho, Tenri City, Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>なお、藩庁は陣屋であるが、家格は城主大名であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the domain government was a jinya, the family status was equivalent to a castle-owning feudal lord.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the domain government was a jinya, the family status was equivalent to a castle-owning feudal lord.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the domain government was a jinya, the family status was equivalent to a castle-owning feudal lord.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>藩史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History of the domain</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History of the domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>織田信長の弟で、茶道として有名な織田長益（織田長益）は、慶長5年（1600年）の関ヶ原の戦いで東軍に与して戦功を挙げたことから、大和国と河内国の内に3万石の所領を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagamasu ODA, the younger brother of Nobunaga ODA and a famous master of tea ceremony, received domain worth 30,000 koku (rice yield) in Yamato-no-kuni and Kawachi-no-kuni provinces, after military success contributing to the victory of the East camp in the Battle of Sekigahara of 1600.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagamasu ODA, the younger brother of Nobunaga ODA and a famous master of tea ceremony, received domain worth 30,000 koku (an unit of assessed crop yields of the land [1 koku: about 180 liter], which was also used to express the size of the land) in Yamato Province and Kawachi Province, after military success contributing to the victory of the East camp in the Battle of Sekigahara of 1600.</e>
<cmt>Yamato Province としました。石（koku)　補足を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagamasu ODA, the younger brother of Nobunaga ODA and a famous master of tea ceremony, received domain worth 30,000 koku (an unit of assessed crop yields of the land [1 koku: about 180 liter], which was also used to express the size of the land) in Yamato Province and Kawachi Province, after military success contributing to the victory of the East camp in the Battle of Sekigahara of 1600.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>その後は徳川家康に仕えず、豊臣秀頼の大叔父ということで秀頼の家臣となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he did not serve Ieyasu TOKUGAWA but, being a grand-uncle to Hideyori TOYOTOMI, chose to become his vassal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he did not serve Ieyasu TOKUGAWA but, being a grand-uncle to Hideyori TOYOTOMI, chose to become his vassal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he did not serve Ieyasu TOKUGAWA but, being a grand-uncle to Hideyori TOYOTOMI, chose to become his vassal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>大坂冬の陣では豊臣方として戦ったが、その裏では徳川方に内通したり、冬の陣における和睦交渉で裏工作を行なっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he allied with the Toyotomi camp in the Winter Siege of Osaka, he engaged in covert activities, providing information to the Tokugawa side and engaging in reconciliatory talks during the siege.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he allied with the Toyotomi camp in the Winter Siege of Osaka, he engaged in covert activities, providing information to the Tokugawa side and engaging in reconciliatory talks during the siege.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he allied with the Toyotomi camp in the Winter Siege of Osaka, he engaged in covert activities, providing information to the Tokugawa side and engaging in reconciliatory talks during the siege.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そして夏の陣直前に豊臣方から離れたため、戦後に罪には問われなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He did not suffer punitive action from the Tokugawa later in history because of his departure from the Toyotomi camp prior to the Summer Siege.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He did not suffer punitive action from the Tokugawa side later after the war because of his departure from the Toyotomi camp prior to the Summer Siege.</e>
<cmt>Tokugawa side としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He did not suffer punitive action from the Tokugawa side later after the war because of his departure from the Toyotomi camp prior to the Summer Siege.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし有楽斎は藩領3万石のうち、1万石を自分の隠居料とし、残りの2万石うち、1万石を四男の織田長政 (大名)に、同じく1万石を五男の織田尚長にそれぞれ分与した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On retirement, however, Yurakusai divided the domain, keeping 10,000 koku as retirement stipend and giving 10,000 koku to his 4th son Nagamasa ODA (a feudal lord) and 10,000 koku to his 5th son Naonaga ODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On retirement, however, Yurakusai (pseudonym of Nagamasu ODA) divided the domain, keeping 10,000 koku as retirement stipend and giving 10,000 koku to his fourth son Nagamasa ODA (a feudal lord) and 10,000 koku to his fifth son Naonaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>有楽斎は織田長益の号であるようですので、ここに補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On retirement, however, Yurakusai (pseudonym of Nagamasu ODA) divided the domain, keeping 10,000 koku as retirement stipend and giving 10,000 koku to his fourth son Nagamasa ODA (a feudal lord) and 10,000 koku to his fifth son Naonaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>このため、長政の系統は大和国芝村藩として、尚長の系統は柳本藩として存続することとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hence, Nagamasa and his descendants held Shibamura Domain of Yamato-no-kuni and Naonaga&apos;s family held to Yanagimoto domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hence, Nagamasa and his descendants held Shibamura Domain of Yamato Province and Naonaga&apos;s family held to Yanagimoto Domain of Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>domain を大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hence, Nagamasa and his descendants held Shibamura Domain of Yamato Province and Naonaga&apos;s family held to Yanagimoto Domain of Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>柳本藩は尚長の後、織田長種、織田秀一と続いたが、第4代藩主・織田秀親の代である宝永6年（1709年）2月、前将軍・徳川綱吉の法会が寛永寺で行なわれているときに、発狂した前田利昌 (大聖寺新田藩主)によって秀親が殺されてしまったのであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yanagimoto Domain continued after Naonaga, with his successors Nagatane and Hidekazu ODA, but faced a crisis with the 4th lord Hidechika ODA, when he was killed by the crazed lord of Daishoiji Nitta Domain Toshimasa MAEDA, during a Buddhist mass held in memorial of the late shogun Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA at Kanei-ji Temple in February 1709.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yanagimoto Domain continued after Naonaga, with his successors Nagatane and Hidekazu ODA, but faced a crisis with the fourth lord Hidechika ODA, when he was killed by the crazed lord of Daishoiji Nitta Domain Toshimasa MAEDA, during a Buddhist mass held in memorial of the late shogun Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA at Kanei-ji Temple in March 1709.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yanagimoto Domain continued after Naonaga, with his successors Nagatane and Hidekazu ODA, but faced a crisis with the fourth lord Hidechika ODA, when he was killed by the crazed lord of Daishoiji Nitta Domain Toshimasa MAEDA, during a Buddhist mass held in memorial of the late shogun Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA at Kanei-ji Temple in March 1709.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>このため、柳本藩は改易の危機を迎えたが、藩の家老たちが機転をきかせて秀親は病死ということにして弟の織田成純を養嗣子として後を継がせ、改易の危機を脱したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The threat of collapse was averted by the Yanagimoto retainers who acted quickly to claim the passing of Hidechika due to illness and appointment of his brother Naritoshi ODA as adoptive heir.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The threat of collapse was averted by the Karo (chief retainers) of Yanagimoto Domain who acted quickly to claim the passing of Hidechika due to illness and by the appointment of his brother Naritoshi ODA as adoptive heir.</e>
<cmt>家老　を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The threat of collapse was averted by the Karo (chief retainers) of Yanagimoto Domain who acted quickly to claim the passing of Hidechika due to illness and by the appointment of his brother Naritoshi ODA as adoptive heir.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>江戸時代中期頃になると、小藩の悲しさから藩財政の窮乏化が表面化する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the mid-Edo Period, the domain faced serious financial crisis due to its small size.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the mid-Edo period, the domain faced serious financial crisis due to its small size.</e>
<cmt>period を小文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the mid-Edo period, the domain faced serious financial crisis due to its small size.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>このため領民に重税を敷いたが、第10代藩主・織田秀綿の代である明和6年（1769年）1月には百姓が重税に反対して強訴を起こすに至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, the farmers of the domain were levied heavily, leading the farmers petitioning the shogunate in January 1769 against the 10th lord Hidetsura ODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, the farmers of the domain were levied heavily, leading the farmers petitioning the shogunate in February 1769 against the tenth lord Hidetsura ODA.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, the farmers of the domain were levied heavily, leading the farmers petitioning the shogunate in February 1769 against the tenth lord Hidetsura ODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>享和2年（1802年）12月にも百姓による年貢軽減を求める一揆が発生し、織田軍と百姓との間で乱闘による死傷者が多数出ている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A riot broke out also in December 1802, demanding reduction in rice levy, and ended with heavy casualties both among the Oda force and the farmers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A riot broke out also in December 1802, demanding reduction in rice levy, and ended with heavy casualties both among the Oda force and the farmers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A riot broke out also in December 1802, demanding reduction in rice levy, and ended with heavy casualties both among the Oda force and the farmers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>さらに江戸時代後期に入ると、ただでさえ藩財政が厳しい中で文政13年（1830年）には火事により柳本屋敷が全焼する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the latter half of the Edo Period, the Yanagimoto estate was burned down by fire in 1830, complicating the harsh financial situation further.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the latter half of the Edo period, the Yanagimoto estate was burned down by fire in 1830, complicating the harsh financial situation further.</e>
<cmt>period を小文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the latter half of the Edo period, the Yanagimoto estate was burned down by fire in 1830, complicating the harsh financial situation further.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>このため第11代藩主・織田信陽は天保4年（1833年）10月に藩士27人のリストラを行なっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This led to the 11th lord Nobuakira ODA to dismiss 27 retainers in October 1833.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This led to the 11th lord Nobuakira ODA to dismiss 27 retainers in November 1833.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This led to the 11th lord Nobuakira ODA to dismiss 27 retainers in November 1833.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>そして嘉永5年（1852年）12月27日には信長以来の名族ということもあって、城主大名に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 27, 1852, the Oda family was designated a feudal lord, due to its historic renown since Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 5, 1853, the Oda family was designated Joshu daimyo (daimyo who is allowed to live in a castle), due to its historic renown since Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>城主大名　補足を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 5, 1853, the Oda family was designated Joshu daimyo (daimyo who is allowed to live in a castle), due to its historic renown since Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>幕末期では天誅組の反乱鎮圧や天皇陵の修築工事を行なうなど、早くから官軍に近づいていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the last years of the Edo Period, the family was early in approaching the Imperialist forces, helping in the suppression of the Tenchu-gumi (royalist forces) and in the repair of the Imperial mausoleum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the last years of the Edo period, the family approached the Imperial forces from the early stage, helping in the suppression of the Tenchu-gumi (royalist forces) War and in the repair of the Imperial mausoleum.</e>
<cmt>表現を一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the last years of the Edo period, the family approached the Imperial forces from the early stage, helping in the suppression of the Tenchu-gumi (royalist forces) War and in the repair of the Imperial mausoleum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>明治維新後は版籍奉還により藩知事となり、明治4年（1871年）の廃藩置県により柳本藩は廃藩となり、柳本県を経て奈良県に編入されたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Meiji Restoration, Oda was designated governor of the domain with abolition of feudal domains and restoration of Imperial rule, and Yanagimoto domain was dissolved with establishment of the prefectural government system in 1871, established initially as Yanagimoto Prefecture and later amalgamated into Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Meiji Restoration, Oda was designated governor of the domain upon Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures), and Yanagimoto Domain was dissolved with establishment of the prefectural government system in 1871, established initially as Yanagimoto Prefecture and later amalgamated into Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>廃藩置県　読みを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Meiji Restoration, Oda was designated governor of the domain upon Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures), and Yanagimoto Domain was dissolved with establishment of the prefectural government system in 1871, established initially as Yanagimoto Prefecture and later amalgamated into Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>なお、織田氏の諸藩では、織田信雄の系統で天童藩、丹波柏原藩が、有楽斎の系統では柳本藩の他に芝村藩（戒重藩）が、明治維新まで存続した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of the feudal domains of the Oda clan, the descendants of Nobukatsu ODA held the Tendo and Kashiwara (Tanba Province) domains and those descending from Yurakusai held Shibamura (Kaiju) domain, in addition to Yanagimoto domain, until Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of the feudal domains of the Oda clan, the descendants of Nobukatsu ODA held the Tendo and Kashiwara (Tanba Province) domains and those descending from Yurakusai held Shibamura (Kaiju) Domain, in addition to Yanagimoto Domain, until Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>domain を大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of the feudal domains of the Oda clan, the descendants of Nobukatsu ODA held the Tendo and Kashiwara (Tanba Province) domains and those descending from Yurakusai held Shibamura (Kaiju) Domain, in addition to Yanagimoto Domain, until Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>有楽斎の系統は他に味舌藩、野村藩が存在したが、これらは江戸時代初期に除封、無嗣断絶している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mashita and Nomura domains were also related to Yurakusai but were closed or dissolved completed in the early Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mashita and Nomura domains were also related to Yurakusai but were closed or dissolved in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>period を小文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mashita and Nomura domains were also related to Yurakusai but were closed or dissolved in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Carkuni(id:79281), Monado(id:53906), Reggaeman(id:6214), Whiz(id:15769), 水野白楓(id:22811), Point136(id:211299), Muhammad jp(id:89111), Yas(id:739), Akimoto(id:6951), Roga246(id:53246), シェーラ(id:17988), 地理さん(id:106627), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>