<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>慶長通宝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keicho Tsuho coin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keicho Tsuho coin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keicho Tsuho coin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>慶長通宝（けいちょうつうほう）は、慶長11年（1606年）に江戸幕府によって発行された銅銭（異説もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Keicho Tsuho was a copper coin issued by the Edo Shognate in 1606. (different theories exist.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Keicho Tsuho was a copper coin issued by the Edo Shognate in 1606. (different theories exist.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Keicho Tsuho was a copper coin issued by the Edo Shognate in 1606. (different theories exist.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日本では平安時代の皇朝十二銭以来久しく途絶えていた中央政府による鋳造貨幣であるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, it was considered as the first mintage issued by the central movement after many years, since the &apos;Kocho -Jyunisen&apos; coin (the twelve types of coins minted by the imperial court) had been discontinued in the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>用語集の訳語で「皇朝十二銭」がKocho-Junisen (twelve coins casted in Japan)　となっていますが、&apos;cast&apos; の過去分詞はcasted ではありません。あきらかに誤りなのでこの部分のみ手を入れました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, it was considered as the first mintage issued by the central government after many years, since the &apos;Kocho -Jyunisen&apos; coin (the twelve types of coins minted by the imperial court) was discontinued in the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>・movement→governmentの誤記と思われます。・sinceの後は過去形が適切と思われます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, it was considered as the first mintage issued by the central government after many years, since the &apos;Kocho -Jyunisen&apos; coin (the twelve types of coins minted by the imperial court) was discontinued in the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>銭文は「慶長通寳」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The letters of &apos;慶長通寳&apos; was raised on it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The letters of &apos;慶長通寳&apos; was raised on it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The letters of &apos;慶長通寳&apos; was raised on it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>銭容は大きく分けて2系統がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The coin had roughly two types of shapes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The coin had roughly two types of shapes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The coin had roughly two types of shapes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>一つは大形で文字も整った比較的良質なものであり、もう一つは小型で質も劣悪であり永楽通宝から「永樂」を削除し「慶長」を嵌め込み変造した鋳型を用いたと思われる私鋳銭である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One was comparably big and good quality with well-raised letters, the other was small and bad quality, a private mint coin made in altered mold for the &apos;Eiraku Tsuho coin&apos; that the letters of &apos;Eiraku&apos; had been changed to the letters of &apos;Keicho&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One was comparably big and good quality with well-raised letters, and the other was small and bad quality, a private mint coin made in the molds which had originally been used for the &apos;Eiraku Tsuho coin&apos; but were modified for the &apos;Keicho Tsuho coin&apos; by changing the letters of &apos;Eiraku&apos; to &apos;Keicho.&apos;</e>
<cmt>・altered moldはEiraku Tsuho coilのために変更されたと誤読される可能性があります。さらに、that the lettersのthatは不自然なため、合わせて表現を修正しました。・2文がコンマでつながっているため、andでつなぎました。・指示書に従って、ピリオドをクォーテーションマークの中に入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One was comparably big and good quality with well-raised letters, and the other was small and bad quality, a private mint coin made in the molds which had originally been used for the &apos;Eiraku Tsuho coin&apos; but were modified for the &apos;Keicho Tsuho coin&apos; by changing the letters of &apos;Eiraku&apos; to &apos;Keicho.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>前者は主に江戸や京都周辺で用いられ、後者は主として九州方面にて用いられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first coin was mostly used in Edo or Kyoto area around, the second one was mainly used in Kyushu area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former was mostly used in around the Edo and Kyoto areas, and the latter was mainly used in the Kyushu area.</e>
<cmt>・前者後者はformer・latterが適切と思われます。・aroundの位置が不適切なため修正しました。・areaは可算名詞のため定冠詞をつけました。・2文がコンマでつながっていたため、andでつなぎました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former was mostly used in around the Edo and Kyoto areas, and the latter was mainly used in the Kyushu area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>一方で、堺市の環壕遺跡からは宋銭、明銭、および琉球貨幣などに混じって66枚の慶長通寳が出土している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, along with Sung coins, Ming coins, and Ryukyu currency, the 66 Keicho Tsuho coins were excavated in the Kango remains in Sakai City.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処　</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, along with Sung coins, Ming coins, and Ryukyu currency, 66 Keicho Tsuho coins were excavated in the Kango remains in Sakai City.</e>
<cmt>・「一方で」はmeanwhileでは時間的な意味合いになります。ここでは、「この通貨は江戸や京都で用いられていたはずだが、堺市でも見つかった」という流れですので、howeverが適切と思われます。・初出なので、66の前の冠詞は不要と思われます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, along with Sung coins, Ming coins, and Ryukyu currency, 66 Keicho Tsuho coins were excavated in the Kango remains in Sakai City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>慶長元年（1596年）から2年（1597年）頃に掛けて大坂あるいは鐚銭の鋳造が盛んであった、堺で鋳造されたとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some theories suggest that from 1596 to 1957 around, cheap coins were minted much in Osaka or Sakai City.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処　「大坂あるいは鐚銭の鋳造が」は文章の誤りかと思います。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some theories suggest that from around 1596 to 1597, the coins had been minted in Osaka, and in Sakai City, where cheap coins had been actively minted.</e>
<cmt>・「鐚銭の鋳造が」以降は、大坂にはかけずに堺だけにかけるためにこの位置に挿入されていると思われます。したがって、「鋳造が盛んだった」という説明は堺市だけに限定してかけるのが適切と思われます。・1957→1597の誤記です。・aroundの位置が不自然なため修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some theories suggest that from around 1596 to 1597, the coins had been minted in Osaka, and in Sakai City, where cheap coins had been actively minted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また東京都奥多摩町の日原鍾乳洞からも30枚出土している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, 30 coins were excavated from the Nippara Limestone cave in Okutama-cho town in Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thirty Keicho Tsuho coins were excavated from the Nippara Limestone cave in Okutama-cho town in Tokyo as well.</e>
<cmt>・alsoの意味が不明瞭なので、文末にas wellを置き、場所に係るようにしました。・上記変更に従って、文頭の数値はスペルアウトしました（文頭の数値は不適切なため）。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thirty Keicho Tsuho coins were excavated from the Nippara Limestone cave in Okutama-cho town in Tokyo as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>当時の鋳造記録が殆ど無く、江戸幕府による鋳造を否定する説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since mint documents of the time were not found, some people refute its minting by the Edo Shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because nearly no documents about mintage at that time have been found, some theories deny the minting of the coin by the Edo Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>・Sinceは共通認識がある程度ある場合に使われるので、ここではbecauseが適切と思われます。・itsの指すものがここからは少し遠いので具体的に書きました。・「殆ど」ないということですが、現状の訳では「無い」となっているので、「ほとんど」のニュアンスも訳出しました。・「people」ではなく、原文どおり「説」（theories）としました。・mint documentでは意味が通じないため、修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because nearly no documents about mintage at that time have been found, some theories deny the minting of the coin by the Edo Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>だが、慶長13年（1608年）に永楽通宝の使用を禁ずる法令が幕府から出されている事から、永楽通宝に代わる然るべき銅銭が存在したと考えるのが妥当である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, considering the act enacted by the government in 1608 that banned the use of the Eiraku Tsuho coins, it is reasonable to think that other appropriate copper coins would have existed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, considering the act enacted by the government in 1608 that banned the use of the Eiraku Tsuho coins, it is reasonable to think that other appropriate copper coins would have existed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, considering the act enacted by the government in 1608 that banned the use of the Eiraku Tsuho coins, it is reasonable to think that other appropriate copper coins would have existed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>翌年に御定相場として金1両＝銀50匁＝永楽通宝1貫文＝「京銭（きんせん）」4貫文の交換比率が定められている.</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In next year, as Osadame soba (a system of officially fixed prices), the exchange rate of one ryo of gold = 50 monme of silver = one kanmon of the Eiraku Tsuho coin = four kanmon of the &apos;Kinsen&apos; coin were determined.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the next year, as Osadame soba (a system of officially fixed prices), the exchange rate was decided as one ryo of gold to 50 monme of silver to one kanmon of the Eiraku Tsuho coin to four kanmon of the &apos;Kinsen&apos; coin.</e>
<cmt>・ここではnextには定冠詞が必要と思われます。・ここでは記号が入ると意味が取りづらいため、表現を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the next year, as Osadame soba (a system of officially fixed prices), the exchange rate was decided as one ryo of gold to 50 monme of silver to one kanmon of the Eiraku Tsuho coin to four kanmon of the &apos;Kinsen&apos; coin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>この「京銭」が慶長通宝に当たるのではと考えられている（これについても、鐚銭の事とする説もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This &apos;Kinsen&apos; was considered as the Keicho Tsuho coin. (some people say it was &apos;Bitasen&apos;, low quality coins whose surfaces were worn away).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This &apos;Kinsen&apos; is considered as the Keicho Tsuho coin (some people say it was &apos;Bitasen,&apos; low quality coins whose surfaces were worn away.)</e>
<cmt>・現在考えられていることなのでisとしました。・指示に従ってコンマはクォーテーションマークの中に入れました。・ピリオドが2つあったので括弧の直前のピリオドは削除しました。・統一事項に従って、ピリオドは括弧の中に入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This &apos;Kinsen&apos; is considered as the Keicho Tsuho coin (some people say it was &apos;Bitasen,&apos; low quality coins whose surfaces were worn away.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また永楽通宝の使用を禁ずる法令を出したものの、慶長通寳の鋳造量が絶対的に不足し永楽通宝に代えるには不十分であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the use of the Eiraku Tsuho coin was banned, the amount of mintage of the Keicho Tsuho were definitely not sufficient to substitute the Eiraku Tsuho.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the use of the Eiraku Tsuho coin was banned, the amount of mintage of the Keicho Tsuho was definitely not sufficient to substitute for the Eiraku Tsuho.</e>
<cmt>・the amountが主語なのでwasとしました。・substituteの目的語が間違っていましたので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the use of the Eiraku Tsuho coin was banned, the amount of mintage of the Keicho Tsuho was definitely not sufficient to substitute for the Eiraku Tsuho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>ことから、この禁令は事実上、永楽通宝の永勘定（金1両＝永1貫文）としての優位的使用を禁止したものであったとの説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, some theories say that this prohibition was practically to prevent advantage of using the Eiraku Tsuho, that had been exchanged as the rate of one ryo of Gold = one kanmon of Ei.</e>
<cmt>「永勘定としての優位的使用」の意味が不明でした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, some theories say that this act was practically to prohibit the preferential use of the Eiraku Tsuho, which had been exchanged at the rate of one ryo of Gold to one kanmon of Ei.</e>
<cmt>・「永勘定としての優位的使用」の意味が不明でした。・原文と意味が少しずれていたため、表現を一部修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, some theories say that this act was practically to prohibit the preferential use of the Eiraku Tsuho, which had been exchanged at the rate of one ryo of Gold to one kanmon of Ei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>だが、当時の江戸幕府は成立したばかりであり、国内最大の経済都市である堺市・大坂を幕府と敵対する豊臣氏が支配していた事や全国経済の把握が進んでいなかった事、更に悪質な私鋳銭も出回ったこともあって、全国的な流通には至らなかったものと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Actually the Edo Shognate was just established at the time, it seems that the Keicho Tsuho coins were not distributed nationwide because Osaka and Sakai, the most economically developed cities were ruled by the Toyotomi Clan, who had felt hostility against the Edo Shogunate, then, the comprehension of the national economics was behind, and moreover, private low quality coins had been distributed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Edo Shognate had in fact just been established at the time, and it seems that the Keicho Tsuho coins were not distributed nationwide because Osaka and Sakai, the most economically developed cities, had been ruled by the Toyotomi Clan, who had felt hostility against the Edo Shogunate; the national economy had not been fully understood; and private low quality coins had been distributed.</e>
<cmt>・actuallyはNG用語なのでin factに変えました。・時制が一部不適切だったため修正しました。・把握はここではcomrehendよりもunderstandが適切と思われます。・経済学や仕組みを表すeconomicsよりも経済自体を表すeconomyが適切と思われます。・2文がコンマでつながっていたため、andでつなげました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Edo Shognate had in fact just been established at the time, and it seems that the Keicho Tsuho coins were not distributed nationwide because Osaka and Sakai, the most economically developed cities, had been ruled by the Toyotomi Clan, who had felt hostility against the Edo Shogunate; the national economy had not been fully understood; and private low quality coins had been distributed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>江戸幕府が全国的な貨幣統一を確立するのは豊臣氏が滅亡してその全国支配が確立した後に発行された寛永通宝の発行まで待つ事になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The nationwide currency by the Edo Shogunate had not been established until the Kanei Tsuho coin issued after the Edo Shogunate governed throughout the nation when the Toyotomi clan had ruined.</e>
<cmt>「江戸幕府が支配を確立」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nationwide currency by the Edo Shogunate was not established until the Kanei Tsuho coin, which was issued after the Edo Shogunate established the government of the entire nation when the Toyotomi clan was ruined.</e>
<cmt>・ruinは他動詞なので修正しました。・throughoutは副詞句を作るため、目的語が必要な個所では不適切です。entire nationとしました。・afterの後の意味は「支配した後」になってしまうので、「確立した後」としました。・主文の時制が不適切だったため修正しました。・文頭の定冠詞は不要と思われます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nationwide currency by the Edo Shogunate was not established until the Kanei Tsuho coin, which was issued after the Edo Shogunate established the government of the entire nation when the Toyotomi clan was ruined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 As6022014(id:214263), Blue sapphire(id:130304), ZassouTori(id:136771), 松茸(id:27535), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), 水野白楓(id:22811), 怪蘇(id:45514), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>