<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>自治党</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jichi To</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jichi to (Autonomy Party)</e>
<cmt>訳抜け</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jichi to (Autonomy Party)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>自治党（じちとう）とは、1888年から翌年にかけて井上馨が進めてきた町村長ら地方の名望家を集めて結成を構想した新党構想であるが、失敗に終わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jichi To was the idea of a new political party framed by Kaoru INOUE from 1888 to 1889 that was planned to be formed by organizing men with high public standing such as mayors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jichi To was the idea of new political party formed by local renown men such as mayors of towns and villages promoted by Kaoru INOUE from 1888 to 1889 but failed in the end.</e>
<cmt>訳抜け（「失敗に終わった」）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jichi To was the idea of new political party formed by local renown men such as mayors of towns and villages promoted by Kaoru INOUE from 1888 to 1889 but failed in the end.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>第1次伊藤内閣の末期、条約改正の失敗の責任をとって外務大臣 (日本)を辞任した井上は、町村長ら地方自治運営の主体となる名望家層を結集させて、民党に対抗する保守政党を結成する構想を抱いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">INOUE, who resigned from his post as Minister of Forreign Affairs (Japan) to take responsibility for the failure of a treaty revision at the late stage of the first Ito cabinet, conceived a plan to form a conservative party opposing minto (general term of the political parties such as Liberal Party and Progressive Party that conflicted with the han-dominated government when the Imperial Diet was inaugurated) by organizing men with high local public standing such as mayors, who were the main constituent to manage local autonomies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inoue, who resigned from his post as Japanese Minister of Foreign Affairs took responsibility for the failure of a treaty revision at the late stage of the first Ito cabinet by conceiving a plan to form a conservative party opposing minto (general term of the political parties such as Liberal Party and Progressive Party that conflicted with the domain government when the Imperial Diet was inaugurated) by organizing men with high reputation such as mayors, who were the main constituent to manage local autonomies.</e>
<cmt>Foreign→Foreignのスペルミス、文章をもう少し滑らかに編集しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inoue, who resigned from his post as Japanese Minister of Foreign Affairs took responsibility for the failure of a treaty revision at the late stage of the first Ito cabinet by conceiving a plan to form a conservative party opposing minto (general term of the political parties such as Liberal Party and Progressive Party that conflicted with the domain government when the Imperial Diet was inaugurated) by organizing men with high reputation such as mayors, who were the main constituent to manage local autonomies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>1888年7月下旬、井上は農商務大臣としての入閣を要請してきた黒田清隆に対して手紙を送り、薩長藩閥による政治の支配を永続させることは不可能であり、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of July in 1888, INOUE sent a letter to Kiyotaka KURODA, who had asked him to join the cabinet as the Minister of Agriculture and Commerce, and proposed therein that it would be impossible to perpetuate the political rule by the Satsuma-Choshu domain clique and emergences of radical parties of the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement and radical nationalists should be avoided by way of forming a new political party organized by middle-class wealthy persons in order to take the lead in local autonomies and let them advance to the national political arena with seasoned political experiences so as to form a moderate conservative power, as a means of cultivating politicians for the next generation to inherit the policy of Fukoku Kyohei (fortifying the country, strengthening the military), which the Meiji Government put forward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">INOUE sent a letter at the end of July in 1888, to Kiyotaka KURODA, who asked him to join the cabinet as the Minister of Agriculture and Commerce, and proposed therein that it would be impossible to perpetuate the political rule by the Satsuma-Choshu domain clique.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">INOUE sent a letter at the end of July in 1888, to Kiyotaka KURODA, who asked him to join the cabinet as the Minister of Agriculture and Commerce, and proposed therein that it would be impossible to perpetuate the political rule by the Satsuma-Choshu domain clique.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>明治政府が進める富国強兵路線を継承する次世代の政治家を育てる手段として中等以上の財産家を集めて新党を結成して地方自治において主導権を握るとともに、彼らに政治的経験を積ませて中央に進出させ、穏健な保守勢力を形成させることで、過激な自由民権派や国粋主義者の台頭を食い止める構想を打ち明けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also introduced the concept of collecting the wealthy men above the middle class to establish a new political party having the central power in local districts, make them have seasoned political experience before dispatching to central political district to develop moderate conservative power to prevent the increase of school of the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement and nationalist as means of providing the politicians of the next generation who will continue the policy of enhancing the wealth and military strength of a country sought by the Meiji government</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also introduced the concept of collecting the wealthy men above the middle class to establish a new political party having the central power in local districts, make them have seasoned political experience before dispatching to central political district to develop moderate conservative power to prevent the increase of school of the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement and nationalist as means of providing the politicians of the next generation who will continue the policy of enhancing the wealth and military strength of a country sought by the Meiji government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>同様の趣旨の手紙を伊藤博文にも送って理解を求めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">INOUE also sent the same letter to Hirobumi ITO to ask for understanding of it.</e>
<cmt>主語を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inoue also sent the same letter to Hirobumi ITO to seek agreement.</e>
<cmt>文章を短縮しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inoue also sent the same letter to Hirobumi ITO to seek agreement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>井上の入閣後の同年10月5日、陸奥宗光・青木周蔵らとともに事実上の新党準備会にあたる「自治制研究会」を発足させて機関誌『自治新報』を発行するなど準備を進めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 15, 1888, after INOUE had joined the cabinet, he proceeded with preparations such as inaugurating &quot;Jichisei Kenkyu Kai&quot; (a study group for autonomy), which was virtually a committee for a new political party, with Munemitsu MUTSU and Shuzo AOKI, and issuing a party newspaper called &quot;Jichi Shinpo&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inoue started preparing &quot;Jichisei Kenkyu Kai&quot; (a study group for autonomy) with Munemitsu MUTSU and Shuzo AOKI on October 15, 1888 after Inoue joined the cabinet, and it was virtually a committee for a new political party with a party newspaper called &quot;Jichi Shinpo&quot; (New Autonomy News).</e>
<cmt>Run-on sentenceでしたので編集しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inoue started preparing &quot;Jichisei Kenkyu Kai&quot; (a study group for autonomy) with Munemitsu MUTSU and Shuzo AOKI on October 15, 1888 after Inoue joined the cabinet, and it was virtually a committee for a new political party with a party newspaper called &quot;Jichi Shinpo&quot; (New Autonomy News).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>だが、翌年黒田が行った「超然主義演説」や山縣有朋らの反対、条約改正を巡る井上自身と黒田との対立もあって運動は低調となり、1889年夏には事実上計画は中止され、『自治新報』も1890年に廃刊された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, due to &quot;the doctrine of superiority&quot; of KURODA, the opposition of Aritomo YAMAGATA, as well as the conflict between INOUE and KURODA regarding the treaty revision, the movement cooled down, and thus the plan was stopped in effect in the summer of 1889, and &quot;Jichisei Shinpo&quot; was no longer being published in 1890.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the movement cooled down due to &quot;the doctrine of superiority&quot; of Kuroda, the opposition of Aritomo YAMAGATA, as well as the conflict between Inoue and Kuroda regarding the treaty revision, and the plan was abolished in the summer of 1889 while &quot;Jichisei Shinpo&quot; discontinued publication in 1890.</e>
<cmt>滑らかになる様に編集しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the movement cooled down due to &quot;the doctrine of superiority&quot; of Kuroda, the opposition of Aritomo YAMAGATA, as well as the conflict between Inoue and Kuroda regarding the treaty revision, and the plan was abolished in the summer of 1889 while &quot;Jichisei Shinpo&quot; discontinued publication in 1890.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tomo suzuki(id:11928), Prism11 VYB05736(id:171949), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>