<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>秋月の乱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akizuki-no-ran War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akizuki-no-ran War (turmoil of Akizuki)</e>
<cmt>指示に従って、補足説明を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akizuki-no-ran War (turmoil of Akizuki)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>秋月の乱（あきづきのらん）は、1876年（明治9年）に福岡県秋月（現・福岡県朝倉市秋月）で起こった明治政府に対する士族反乱の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Akizuki-no-ran War is a revolt by the warrior class against the Meiji Government which took place in Akizuki, Fukuoka Prefecture (currently Akizuki, Asakura City, Fukuoka Prefecture) in 1876.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Akizuki-no-ran War is a revolt by the warrior class against the Meiji Government which took place in Akizuki, Fukuoka Prefecture (currently Akizuki, Asakura City, Fukuoka Prefecture) in 1876.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Akizuki-no-ran War is a revolt by the warrior class against the Meiji Government which took place in Akizuki, Fukuoka Prefecture (currently Akizuki, Asakura City, Fukuoka Prefecture) in 1876.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経緯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Details</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Details</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Details</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>1876年10月24日に熊本県で起こった神風連の乱に呼応して、旧秋月藩の士族宮崎車之助、磯淳、戸原安浦、磯平八、戸波半九郎、宮崎哲之助、土岐清、益田静方、今村百八郎ら約400名によって起こされた反乱である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A rebellion started by about 400 people including Kurumanosuke MIYAZAKI, Atsushi ISO, Yasura TOBARA, Heihachi ISO, Hankuro TONAMI, Tetsunosuke MIYAZAKI, Kiyoshi TOKI, Shizukata MASUDA and Hyakuhachiro IMAMURA from the warrior class in the former Akizuki Domain in response to the Shimpuren-no-ran War, which took place on October 24, 1876 in Kumamoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A rebellion was started by about 400 people including Kurumanosuke MIYAZAKI, Atsushi ISO, Yasura TOBARA, Heihachi ISO, Hankuro TONAMI, Tetsunosuke MIYAZAKI, Kiyoshi TOKI, Shizukata MASUDA and Hyakuhachiro IMAMURA from the warrior class in the former Akizuki Domain in response to the Shimpuren-no-ran War, which took place on October 24, 1876 in Kumamoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>byとのつながりが不自然なため、A rebellion started by→A rebellion was started byに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A rebellion was started by about 400 people including Kurumanosuke MIYAZAKI, Atsushi ISO, Yasura TOBARA, Heihachi ISO, Hankuro TONAMI, Tetsunosuke MIYAZAKI, Kiyoshi TOKI, Shizukata MASUDA and Hyakuhachiro IMAMURA from the warrior class in the former Akizuki Domain in response to the Shimpuren-no-ran War, which took place on October 24, 1876 in Kumamoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>神風連の乱から3日後の10月27日、今村を隊長とする「秋月党」が挙兵、まず明元寺で警察官を殺害（日本初の警察官の殉職）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 27, three days after the Shimpuren-no-ran War, the &quot;Akizuki-to&quot; party led by IMAMURA raised the army and started by killing a police officer in Myogen-ji temple (the first death of a police officer on duty in Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 27, three days after the Shimpuren-no-ran War, the &apos;Akizuki-to&apos; party led by Imamura raised the army and started by killing a police officer in Myogen-ji temple (the first death of police officers on duty in Japan).</e>
<cmt>・クォーテーションマークを原文に合わせてシングルにしました。・IMAMURAは名字だけの記載なので、指示に従って頭文字だけ大文字にしました。・the first death of a police officerとすると、一人の警官が二度以上死ぬような印象を与えるためpolice officersとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 27, three days after the Shimpuren-no-ran War, the &apos;Akizuki-to&apos; party led by Imamura raised the army and started by killing a police officer in Myogen-ji temple (the first death of police officers on duty in Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>旧秋月藩の士族はあらかじめ旧豊津藩の士族、杉生十郎らと同時決起を約束していたため、このあとみやこ町へと向かい、10月29日に到着する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Members of the warrior class in the former Akizuki Domain later headed for Miyako Town and arrived there on October 29 because they had promised in advance to rally simultaneously with Juro SUGIO and others from the warrior class in the former Toyotsu Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Members of the warrior class in the former Akizuki Domain later headed for Miyako Town and arrived there on October 29 because they had promised in advance to rally simultaneously with Juro SUGIO and others from the warrior class in the former Toyotsu Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Members of the warrior class in the former Akizuki Domain later headed for Miyako Town and arrived there on October 29 because they had promised in advance to rally simultaneously with Juro SUGIO and others from the warrior class in the former Toyotsu Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>しかしこのとき旧豊津藩士族は決起しない方針を固め、杉生らは監禁されており、談判中、豊津側の連絡を受けて到着した乃木希典率いる北九州市鎮台が秋月党を攻撃。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as the warrior class of the former Toyotsu Domain decided not to rally at that time and SUGIO and others were incarcerated, the Kitakyushu City Chindai Army led by Maresuke NOGI, who had arrived on receiving the correspondence from the Toyotsu side, attacked the Akizuki-to party during the negotiation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as the warrior class of the former Toyotsu Domain decided not to rally at that time and Sugio and others were incarcerated, the Kitakyushu City Chindai Army, led by Maresuke NOGI, who had arrived on receiving the correspondence from the Toyotsu side, attacked the Akizuki-to party during the negotiation.</e>
<cmt>・SUGIOは名字だけの記載なので、頭文字だけ大文字にしました。・led byの前にはコンマが必要ですので追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as the warrior class of the former Toyotsu Domain decided not to rally at that time and Sugio and others were incarcerated, the Kitakyushu City Chindai Army, led by Maresuke NOGI, who had arrived on receiving the correspondence from the Toyotsu side, attacked the Akizuki-to party during the negotiation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>秋月側は死者17名を出し（政府軍の死者2名）江川村栗河内（現・朝倉市大字江川字栗河内）へ退却、10月31日に秋月党は解散し、磯、宮崎、土岐ら七士は自刃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With a death toll of 17 on the Akizuki side (two deaths in the government forces), the Akizuki-to party retreated to Kurikochi, Egawa Village (currently, Aza Kurikochi, Oaza Egawa, Asakura City) and was disbanded on October 31 and seven men including ISO, MIYAZAKI and TOKI committed suicide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With a death toll of 17 on the Akizuki side (two deaths in the government forces), the Akizuki-to party retreated to Kurikochi, Egawa Village (currently, Aza Kurikochi, Oaza Egawa, Asakura City) and was disbanded on October 31 and seven men including Iso, Miyazaki and Toki committed suicide.</e>
<cmt>ISO、MIYAZAKIおよびTOKIは名字だけの記載なので、頭文字だけ大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With a death toll of 17 on the Akizuki side (two deaths in the government forces), the Akizuki-to party retreated to Kurikochi, Egawa Village (currently, Aza Kurikochi, Oaza Egawa, Asakura City) and was disbanded on October 31 and seven men including Iso, Miyazaki and Toki committed suicide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>抗戦派の今村は他26名とともに秋月へ戻り、秋月小学校に置かれていた秋月党討伐本部を襲撃し県高官2名を殺害、反乱に加わった士族を拘留していた酒屋倉庫を焼き払ったのち、分かれて逃亡したが、11月24日に逮捕された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">IMAMURA of the resistance force returned to Akizuki together with 26 others, attacked the Akizuki-to suppression headquarters situated in Akizuki Elementary School, killed two prefectural high officials, burned down the liquor store warehouse where warrior class members joining the rebellion were kept in detention, and then separately escaped, but they were arrested on November 24.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imamura of the resistance force returned to Akizuki together with 26 others, attacked the Akizuki-to suppression headquarters situated in Akizuki Elementary School, killed two prefectural high officials, burned down the liquor store warehouse where warrior class members joining the rebellion were kept in detention, and then separately escaped, but they were arrested on November 24.</e>
<cmt>IMAMURAは名字だけの記載なので、頭文字だけ大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imamura of the resistance force returned to Akizuki together with 26 others, attacked the Akizuki-to suppression headquarters situated in Akizuki Elementary School, killed two prefectural high officials, burned down the liquor store warehouse where warrior class members joining the rebellion were kept in detention, and then separately escaped, but they were arrested on November 24.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>なお益田は挙兵前の10月26日に旧佐賀藩士族の同時決起を求めるため佐賀市へ向かったが、その帰りに逮捕されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MASUDA left for Saga City on October 26 before raising the army in order to ask the former Saga Domain warrior class for a simultaneous rally, but he was arrested on his way back.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masuda left for Saga City on October 26 before raising the army in order to ask the former Saga Domain warrior class for a simultaneous rally, but he was arrested on his way back.</e>
<cmt>MASUDAは名字だけの記載なので、頭文字だけ大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masuda left for Saga City on October 26 before raising the army in order to ask the former Saga Domain warrior class for a simultaneous rally, but he was arrested on his way back.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>12月3日に福岡臨時裁判所で関係者の判決が言い渡され、首謀者とされた今村と益田は即日斬首され、約150名に懲役、除族などの懲罰が下された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As sentences were passed on the people involved at the Fukuoka provisional court on December 3, IMAMURA and MASUDA, who were considered ringleaders, were beheaded on the same day and penalties including imprisonment with work and deprivation of the family status were imposed on about 150 people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As sentences were passed on the people involved at the Fukuoka provisional court on December 3, Imamura and Masuda, who were considered ringleaders, were beheaded on the same day and penalties including imprisonment with work and deprivation of the family status were imposed on about 150 people.</e>
<cmt>IMAMURAとMASUDAは名字だけの記載なので、頭文字だけ大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As sentences were passed on the people involved at the Fukuoka provisional court on December 3, Imamura and Masuda, who were considered ringleaders, were beheaded on the same day and penalties including imprisonment with work and deprivation of the family status were imposed on about 150 people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>現在、秋月にある秋月郷土資料館（戸波半九郎屋敷跡）に、幹部直筆の辞世の句などが展示されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, the death poems in the leaders&apos; own handwriting are on display at the Akizuki Folk Museum (formerly the residence of Hankuro TONAMI) in Akizuki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present, the death poems in the leaders&apos; own handwriting are on display at the Akizuki Folk Museum (formerly the residence of Hankuro TONAMI) in Akizuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present, the death poems in the leaders&apos; own handwriting are on display at the Akizuki Folk Museum (formerly the residence of Hankuro TONAMI) in Akizuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Northface(id:70750), Reggaeman(id:6214), Claytonian(id:125258), SO1983(id:60024), 219.106の者(id:151047), Muyo(id:14948), Yanahan(id:2437), Udon-ya(id:48431), 味っ子(id:17086), Yas(id:739), Mishika(id:276), Kamitani(id:30757), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>