<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>文安の麹騒動</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bunan no Koji Sodo (Riot caused by koji malt sellers in the Bunan era)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bunan no Koji Sodo (Riot caused by koji malt sellers in the Bunan era)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bunan no Koji Sodo (Bunan-era Koji Dispute)</e>
<cmt>次に説明があるし、麹座が引き起こしたRiotではないので括弧書きを削除しました。ご確認願います。I&apos;ve added &quot;era&quot; as otherwise the reader would have no idea what &quot;Bunan&quot; is supposed to mean. I&apos;ve also added an explanation of &quot;koji&quot; in the first sentence of the text below as this is a term that the reader is unlikely to recognize.</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>文安の麹騒動（ぶんあんのこうじそうどう）とは、室町時代、京都において酒造工程の一つである麹造りを支配していた座（北野麹座）が室町幕府の攻撃を受けて没落した事件。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bunan no Koji Sodo was an incident in which Kitano koji za (A koji malt guild in Kitano) that controlled production of koji malt in Kyoto, a process of sake brewing, was attacked by Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and declined in Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bunan no Koji Sodo was an incident in which Kitano koji za (A koji malt guild in Kitano) that controlled production of koji malt in Kyoto, a process of sake brewing, was attacked by Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) causing its decline during the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bunan no Koji Sodo was an incident in which Kitano koji za (a guild in Kitano for producers of koji malt, a kind of mold grown on produce such as boiled rice), who controlled production of koji malt (which is part of the sake brewing process) in Kyoto, was attacked by the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) causing its decline during the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>Muromachi bakufu→the Muromachi bakufu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>この結果、麹の専門業界は没落して酒屋業へ組み入れられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of this, the industry specialized in the koji malt was brought to ruin and incorporated into sakaya (liquor store) industry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, this lead to the downfall of the koji malt industry which was subsequently incorporated into the sakaya (liquor store) industry.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, this lead to the downfall of the koji malt industry which was subsequently incorporated into the sakaya (liquor store) industry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>鎌倉時代から京都には酒屋が隆盛をきわめていったが、当時はまだ麹造りは酒屋の職業範囲ではなく、麹の製造から販売までをつかさどる麹屋が別個に存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the sakaya industry had been blooming in Kyoto since Kamakura Period, production of the koji malt was not categorized in the sakaya industry at the time, and kojiya that produced and sold the koji malt existed independently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the sakaya industry had existed in Kyoto since the Kamakura Period, production of koji malt did not fall under the sakaya industry at the time, with the production and sale of kojiya malt being independent.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the sakaya industry had existed in Kyoto since the Kamakura Period, production of koji malt did not fall under the sakaya industry at the time, with the production and sale of kojiya malt being independent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>麹屋は北野社（現在の北野天満宮）の神人（じにん）身分を得て「麹座」と呼ばれる同業者組合（座）を結成して北野社（本所）の権威を背景に京都西部の麹の製造・販売の独占権を有していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Obtaining the position of jinin (associates of Shinto shrines) at Kitano-sha Shrine (present Kitano Tenmangu Shrine), the kojiya formed a guild called &quot;koji-za&quot; and had an exclusive rights to produce and sell the koji malt in the western part of Kyoto supported by the authority of Kitano-sha Shrine (honjo (proprietor or guarantor of manor)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Obtaining the position of jinin (associates of Shinto shrines) at Kitano-sha Shrine (present Kitano Tenmangu Shrine), the kojiya formed a guild called &quot;koji-za&quot; and had exclusive rights to produce and sell koji malt in the western part of Kyoto backed by the authority of Kitano-sha Shrine (honjo (proprietor or guarantor of manor)).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Obtaining the position of jinin (associates of Shinto shrines) at Kitano-sha Shrine (present Kitano Tenman-gu Shrine), the kojiya formed a guild called &apos;koji-za&apos; and had exclusive rights to produce and sell koji malt in the western part of Kyoto backed by the authority of Kitano-sha Shrine (honjo (proprietor or guarantor of manor)).</e>
<cmt>Tenmangu→Tenman-gu&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>資本力をもった酒屋が業界の垣根をこえて麹造りにも進出し、北野麹座は強く反発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sakaya with the financial power penetrated into the production of the koji malt beyond the industrial border, and Kitano koji za strongly reacted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kitano koji za reacted strongly to the penetration of the koji malt production industry by Sakaya with financial power.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kitano koji za reacted strongly to the penetration of the koji malt production industry by Sakaya with financial power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>だが、この頃、室町幕府が足利義満のもとで全盛期を迎えており、至徳 (日本)3年（1386年）には延暦寺以下京都の有力寺社が京都の地域内において私的権力を行使する事が制限された（警察権の幕府への集中）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Muromachi Bakufu, in its prime under Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, regulated Enryaku-ji Temple and other powerful temples and shrines in Kyoto exercising their private power in Kyoto area in 1386 (concentration of police authority to the bakufu).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Muromachi Bakufu, in its prime under Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, regulated Enryaku-ji Temple and other powerful temples and shrines in Kyoto which exercised their private power within the Kyoto area in 1386 (Concentrating police authority in the bakufu).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Muromachi bakufu, in its prime under Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, regulated Enryaku-ji Temple and other powerful temples and shrines in Kyoto which exercised their private power within the Kyoto area in 1386 (Concentrating police authority in the bakufu).</e>
<cmt>Muromachi Bakufu→the Muromachi bakufu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>更に、明徳4年（1393年）には「洛中辺土散在土倉并酒屋役条々」が出され、幕府が京都の土倉・酒屋に対して座への加入を問わず一律に課税する事となり、本所の座への支配権は幕府の制限下においてのみ許されるという状況にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, with &apos;Five rules regarding doso and sake shops scattered around Rakuchu&apos; enacted in 1393, the bakufu taxed doso (money broker) and sakaya in Kyoto without exception regardless of membership of a guild, and, as a result, the honjo&apos;s sovereignty over the guild was allowed only under the regulation by the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, with &apos;Five rules regarding doso and sake shops scattered around Rakuchu&apos; enacted in 1393, the bakufu taxed doso (money brokers) and sakaya in Kyoto without exception regardless of guild membership, and, as a result, the honjo&apos;s sovereignty over the guild was allowed only under regulation by the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, with &apos;Five rules regarding doso and sake shops scattered around Rakuchu&apos; enacted in 1393, the bakufu taxed doso (pawnbrokers and moneylenders) and sakaya in Kyoto without exception regardless of guild membership, and, as a result, the honjo&apos;s sovereignty over the guild was allowed only under regulation by the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>土倉の定訳不明</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>これには当時最大の本所勢力であった延暦寺などは強く反発したが、当時の義満の勢いの前にはなすすべもなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Enryaku-ji Temple that was the largest honjo power at the time and others strongly opposed it, but they were helpless before the momentum of Yoshimitsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Enryaku-ji Temple was the largest honjo power at the time and was strongly opposed by others, they were helpless before the momentum of Yoshimitsu.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Enryaku-ji Temple, the largest honjo power at the time, strongly opposed to these rules, they were helpless before the momentum of Yoshimitsu.</e>
<cmt>andの後の文は意味が逆になっていたので訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>この情勢に目をつけた北野麹座は幕府への運上金と引き換えに幕府に接近する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taking advantage of this situation, Kitano koji za approached the bakufu in exchange for tax paid to the bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taking advantage of this situation, Kitano koji za approached the bakufu in exchange for tax paid to the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taking advantage of this situation, Kitano koji za approached the bakufu in exchange for tax paid to the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>応永26年（1419年）幕府は北野麹座に京都全域における麹の製造販売の権利一切を与え、京都の全ての酒屋は北野麹座から麹を購入する事が決定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1419, the bakufu gave all rights of producing and selling the koji malt all over Kyoto to Kitano koji za, and it was determined that all the sakaya in Kyoto should purchase the koji malt from Kitano koji za.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1419, the bakufu gave all rights to produce and sell koji malt in Kyoto to Kitano koji za, and it was determined that all sakaya in Kyoto should purchase koji malt from Kitano koji za.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1419, the bakufu gave all rights to produce and sell koji malt in Kyoto to Kitano koji za, and it was determined that all sakaya in Kyoto should purchase koji malt from Kitano koji za.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>これに酒屋側が反発すると、幕府は兵を動員して「麹室」と呼ばれる酒屋付属の麹工房を悉く打ち壊した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the sakaya side opposed this, the bakufu mobilized an army to destroy every koji factory called koji muro attached to the sakaya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the sakayas opposed this, the bakufu mobilized an army to destroy every koji factory called koji muro attached to the sakaya.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the sakayas opposed this, the bakufu mobilized an army to destroy every koji factory called &apos;koji muro&apos; attached to the sakaya.</e>
<cmt>koji muro→&apos;koji muro&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>ところが酒屋の座の中には延暦寺を本所とするものがおり、彼らは延暦寺に麹座と幕府の行為を訴えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, some of the sakaya belonged to Enryaku-ji Temple as their honjo, and they complained about the conduct of the bakufu and the koji za to Enryaku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, some of the sakaya belonged to Enryaku-ji Temple as their honjo, and they complained about the conduct of the bakufu and the koji za to Enryaku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, some of the sakaya belonged to Enryaku-ji Temple as their honjo, and they complained about the conduct of the bakufu and the koji za to Enryaku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>当時北野社は延暦寺の傘下にあり、自己支配下の酒屋の衰退が運上金の減少を招くと考えた延暦寺は北野社に独占を止めるように求めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kitano-sha Shrine was under the control of Enryaku-ji Temple at the time, and, worried that the decline of the sakaya under its control would result in decrease of tax income, Enryaku-ji Temple asked Kitano-sha Shrine to stop the monopoly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kitano-sha Shrine was under the control of Enryaku-ji Temple at the time, and, worried that the decline of the sakaya under its control would result in decreased tax income, Enryaku-ji Temple asked Kitano-sha Shrine to stop the monopoly.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kitano-sha Shrine was under the control of Enryaku-ji Temple at the time, and, worried that the decline of the sakaya under its control would result in decreased tax income, Enryaku-ji Temple asked Kitano-sha Shrine to stop the monopoly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>だが、北野社側も自己の運上金収入に関わる問題でありこれを拒絶した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Kitano-sha Shrine rejected the request because it was an issue of its own tax income.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Kitano-sha Shrine rejected the request because the issue had to due with their own tax income.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Kitano-sha Shrine rejected the request because the issue had to due with their own tax income.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>麹座と酒屋、そして背後の北野社と延暦寺の対立はエスカレートし、文安元年（1444年）延暦寺は西塔釈迦堂に立てこもり、次いで京都に向けて強訴を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An escalation of the conflict between the koji za and the sakaya and that between Kitano-sha Shrine and Enryaku-ji Temple behind them resulted in that Enryaku-ji Temple barricaded themselves in Saito-Shakado and then made a direct petition to Kyoto in 1444.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The conflict between the koji za and the sakaya and between Kitano-sha Shrine and Enryaku-ji Temple escalated resulting in Enryaku-ji Temple barricading themselves in Saito-Shakado, and petitioning Kyoto in 1444.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The conflict between the koji za and the sakaya and between Kitano-sha Shrine and Enryaku-ji Temple escalated resulting in Enryaku-ji Temple barricading themselves in Saito-Shakado, and petitioning Kyoto in 1444.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>3年前の嘉吉の変以後その政治的影響力が減退していた幕府はこれに屈して北野麹座の独占権の廃止を認めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bakufu, whose political influence weakened after the Kakitsu Incident three years before, gave in to Enryaku-ji Temple, and allowed an abolition of the monopoly by Kitano koji za.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bakufu, whose political influence had weakened after the Kakitsu Incident three years before, gave in to Enryaku-ji Temple, and allowed the abolition of the monopoly on Kitano koji za.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bakufu, whose political influence had weakened after the Kakitsu Incident three years before, gave in to Enryaku-ji Temple, and allowed the abolition of the monopoly on Kitano koji za.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これに対して北野麹座に属する神人らが北野社に立てこもった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Against the decision, a group of jinin belonging to Kitano koji za barricaded themselves in Kitano-sha Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A group of jinin belonging to Kitano koji za barricaded themselves in Kitano-sha Shrine in protest against the decision.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A group of jinin belonging to Kitano koji za barricaded themselves in Kitano-sha Shrine in protest against the decision.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これに対して管領畠山持国は4月13日に鎮圧の兵を北野社に差し向けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Against this, Mochikuni HATAKEYAMA, the kanrei (shogunal deputy), dispatched an army for suppression to Kitano-sha Shrine on April 13.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In response, Mochikuni HATAKEYAMA, the kanrei (shogunal deputy), dispatched an army to Kitano-sha Shrine on April 13 to suppress the protest.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response, Mochikuni HATAKEYAMA, the kanrei (shogunal deputy), dispatched an army to Kitano-sha Shrine on April 13 to suppress the protest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>これによって武力衝突に発展して死者も出した上、北野社一帯が炎上したが幕府側が付近の制圧に成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This lead to an armed conflict in which some people died and the area around Kitano-sha Shrine was burnt, but the bakufu successfully conquered the surrounding area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This lead to an armed conflict leaving some dead, and the area around Kitano-sha Shrine burnt, but the bakufu successfully conquered the surrounding area.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This lead to an armed conflict leaving some dead, and the area around Kitano-sha Shrine burnt, but the bakufu successfully conquered the surrounding area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>その結果、麹屋側は酒屋側に屈服して京都における麹座は衰退した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, the kojiya gave in to the sakaya, and the koji za in Kyoto declined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, the kojiya gave in to the sakaya, and the koji za in Kyoto fell into decline.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, the kojiya gave in to the sakaya, and the koji za in Kyoto fell into decline.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>また、政治的には京都における幕府の支配力の低下が明らかとなり、京都における有力寺社の影響力も復活した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a political sense, the derogation of the bakufu&apos;s power to control Kyoto became apparent, and the influence by the powerful temples in Kyoto revived.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a political sense, the derogation of the bakufu&apos;s power to control Kyoto became apparent, and revived the influence held by powerful temples.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a political sense, the derogation of the bakufu&apos;s power to control Kyoto became apparent, and revived the influence held by powerful temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>その後、麹屋側の巻き返しにより天文_(元号)14年（1545年）には再度北野麹座による麹の独占が許されるものの、室町幕府の権威が完全に失墜した状況下では時は既に遅く、やがて麹造りは酒屋業の一工程となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, though the monopoly of the koji malt by Kitano koji za was permitted again in 1545 due to the catch up by Kitano koji za, it was too late under the situation where the Muromachi bakufu had entirely fallen from the power, and the production of the koji malt became one of processes in the sakaya industry in time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, though the monopoly of the koji malt by Kitano koji za was permitted again in 1545 due to the catch up by Kitano koji za, it was too late, as the Muromachi bakufu had fallen from power, and the production of koji malt had become integrated into the sakaya industry.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, though the monopoly of the koji malt by Kitano koji za was permitted again in 1545 due to the catch up by Kitano koji za, it was too late, as the Muromachi bakufu had fallen from power, and the production of koji malt had become integrated into the sakaya industry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="23">
<j>またこの事件は、奈良の『菩提泉（ぼだいせん）』『山樽（やまだる）』『大和多武峯（たふのみね）酒』、越前の『豊原（ほうげん）酒』、近江の『百済寺酒』、河内の『観心寺酒』などの僧坊酒が台頭する一因ともなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This incident also contributed to the rise of sobo shu (sake produced by monks) such as &quot;Bodaisen,&quot; &quot;Yamadaru,&quot; and &quot;Yamato Tafunomine zake&quot; in Nara, &quot;Hogen zake&quot; in Echizen, &quot;Hyakusaidera shu&quot; in Omi, and &quot;Kanshinji shu&quot; in Kawachi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This incident also contributed to the rise of sobo shu (sake produced by monks) such as &quot;Bodaisen,&quot; &quot;Yamadaru,&quot; and &quot;Yamato Tafunomine zake&quot; in Nara, &quot;Hogen zake&quot; in Echizen, &quot;Hyakusaidera shu&quot; in Omi, and &quot;Kanshinji shu&quot; in Kawachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This incident also contributed to the rise of sobo shu (sake produced by monks) such as &quot;Bodaisen,&quot; &quot;Yamadaru,&quot; and &quot;Yamato Tafunomine zake&quot; in Nara, &quot;Hogen zake&quot; in Echizen, &quot;Hyakusaidera shu&quot; in Omi, and &quot;Kanshinji shu&quot; in Kawachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 พริกขี้หนู(id:131976), Nnh(id:474), ５１６(id:45205), ポピュラーポプラ(id:157724), Kzhr(id:131), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>