<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>江戸開城</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Surrender of Edo Castle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Surrender of Edo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Surrender of Edo-jp Castle</e>
<cmt>Edo-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>江戸開城（えどかいじょう）とは、江戸時代末期（幕末）の慶応4年（1868年）3月から4月（旧暦）にかけて、明治新政府軍の代表西郷隆盛と旧江戸幕府軍（徳川家）の代表勝海舟らの交渉により、江戸城の無血開城がもたらされたことをいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Surrender of Edo Castle was executed during the ending of the Edo Period (the final phase of Tokugawa Shogunate), occurring over the months of April to May in &apos;1868&apos;; Takamori SAIGO, a representative of the new Meiji government, and Kaishu KATSU, a representative of the former Tokugawa troop (Tokugawa Family Shogunate); together strategically negotiated a peaceful resolution to the surrender of Edo castle; this peacefully negotiated transfer was to become historically known as, The Bloodless Surrender of Edo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Surrender of Edo Castle was executed during the ending of the Edo Period (the final phase of the Tokugawa Shogunate), occurring over the months of April to May in &apos;1868;&apos; Takamori SAIGO, a representative of the new Meiji government, and Kaishu KATSU, a representative of the former Tokugawa troops (Tokugawa Family Shogunate); together strategically negotiated a peaceful resolution to the surrender of Edo castle; this peacefully negotiated transfer was to become historically known as, The Bloodless Surrender of Edo Castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Surrender of Edo-jo Castle was executed during the ending of the Edo period (the final phase of the Tokugawa shogunate), occurring over the months of March to April in 1868; Takamori SAIGO, a representative of the new Meiji government, and Kaishu KATSU, a representative of the former Tokugawa shogunate troops; together strategically negotiated a peaceful resolution to the surrender of Edo-jo Castle; this peacefully negotiated transfer was to become historically known as, The Bloodless Surrender of Edo-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>Edo-jo Castle、Edo period、Tokugawa troops (Tokugawa Family Shogunate)→Tokugawa shogunate troopsとし、クォーテーション削除、April to May→March to Aprilに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>同年から翌年にかけて行われた一連の戊辰戦争の中で、新政府側が大きく優勢となる画期となった象徴的な事件である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Over this time, then through to the next year (1868-1867), the Surrender of Edo Castle turned out to be the essential ground-breaking point in a series of following actions taken during the Boshin Civil War; therefore providing greater advantage to the new government&apos;s forces, and effectively establishing the castles fall as a highly significant event in Japanese history.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Over this time, then through to the next year (1868-1867), the Surrender of Edo Castle turned out to be the essential ground-breaking point in a series of following actions taken during the Boshin Civil War; therefore providing greater advantage to the new government&apos;s forces, and effectively establishing the castles fall as a highly significant event in Japanese history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Over this time, then through to the next year (1868-1869), the Surrender of Edo-jo Castle turned out to be the essential ground-breaking point in a series of following actions taken during the Boshin Civil War; therefore providing greater advantage to the new government&apos;s forces, and effectively establishing the castles fall as a highly significant event in Japanese history.</e>
<cmt>1868-1867→1868-1869に修正、Edo-jo Castleとし、全角アポストロフィーを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>それととともに、交渉前後の劇的な展開から、小説・演劇・テレビドラマ・映画などの恰好の素材となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, due to the historical significance of these dramatically developing events, before and after the negotiations in the Surrender of Edo Castle, this effectively attracted novelist, playwrights, and producers of movies and TV dramas, to this historically critical content.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, due to the historical significance of these dramatically developing events, before and after the negotiations in the Surrender of Edo Castle, this effectively attracted novelist, playwrights, and producers of movies and TV dramas, to this historically critical content.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, due to the historical significance of these dramatically developing events, before and after the negotiations in the Surrender of Edo-jo Castle, this effectively attracted novelist, playwrights, and producers of movies and TV dramas, to this historically critical content.</e>
<cmt>Edo-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>※以下、日付はすべて旧暦（天保暦）によるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">*From now on, the dates will be written in the Japan&apos;s last lunar calendar (Tenporeki; in use from 1844 to 1872).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">*From now on, the dates will be written according to Japan&apos;s last lunar calendar (Tenporeki; in use from 1844 to 1872).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">*From now on, the dates will be written according to Japan&apos;s last lunar calendar (Tenporeki; in use from 1844 to 1872).</e>
<cmt>全角アポストロフィーを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The background</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>戊辰戦争勃発と慶喜追討令</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The outbreak of the Boshin Civil War and the decree to search and kill Yoshinobu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The outbreak of the Boshin Civil War and the decree to search and kill Yoshinobu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The outbreak of the Boshin Civil War and the decree to search and kill Yoshinobu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>慶応3年（1867年）10月大政奉還により政権を朝廷へ返上した15代征夷大将軍徳川慶喜は、新設されるであろう諸侯会議の議長として影響力を行使することを想定していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October of 1867 (November, 1867), Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA, the fifteenth Seiitaishogun (commonly know as Shogun; the commander-in-chief of the expeditionary force against the barbarians; the great and unifying leader), gave up political power to the Imperial Court by the Taiseihokan (restoration of imperial rule) and he expected to have great influence over the potential newly established Lords Conference, through his potential role as the president of the conference.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October 1867 (November, 1867), Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA, the fifteenth Seiitaishogun (commonly know as Shogun; the commander-in-chief of the expeditionary force against the barbarians; the great and unifying leader), gave up political power to the Imperial Court by the Taiseihokan (restoration of imperial rule) and he expected to have great influence over the potential newly established Lords Conference through his potential role as the president of the conference.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October 1867, Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA, the fifteenth Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;), gave up political power to the Imperial Court by the Taiseihokan (restoration of imperial rule) and he expected to have great influence over the potential newly established Lords Conference through his potential role as the president of the conference.</e>
<cmt>前文に旧暦表記に関する注釈があるため、統一事項より(November, 1867)を削除、「征夷大将軍」→統一リストの表記に修正、スペース追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし、討幕派の公家岩倉具視や薩摩藩の大久保利通・西郷隆盛らが主導した12月初旬の王政復古 (日本)とそれに続く小御所会議が開かれ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, despite Yoshinobu&apos;s wish, Tomomi IWAKURA, who belonged to an anti-Shogunate group, Toshimichi OKUBO and Takamori SAIGO, who were from Satsuma Domain, formed the &quot;Restoration of Imperial Rule&quot; then the &quot;Kogoshokaigi&quot; (an Imperial Council held in the Kyoto Imperial Palace) met in the early December (actually January 3rd, 1867).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, despite Yoshinobu&apos;s wish, Tomomi IWAKURA, who belonged to an anti-Shogunate group, Toshimichi OKUBO and Takamori SAIGO, who were from the Satsuma Domain, formed the &quot;Restoration of Imperial Rule&quot; then the &quot;Kogoshokaigi&quot; (an Imperial Council held in the Kyoto Imperial Palace) met in early December (actually January 3, 1867).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, despite Yoshinobu&apos;s wish, Tomomi IWAKURA, who belonged to an anti-shogunate group, Toshimichi OKUBO and Takamori SAIGO, who were from the Satsuma Domain, formed the &quot;Restoration of Imperial Rule&quot; then the &quot;Kogosho Conference&quot; (an Imperial Council held in the Kyoto Imperial Palace) met in early December.</e>
<cmt>全角アポストロフィー・クォーテーションを半角に修正、anti-shogunate groupとし、表記統一のためKogoshokaigi→Kogosho Conferenceに修正、統一事項より、新暦表記を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>それらによって自身の辞官納地（官職・領土の返上）が決定されてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In conclusion, the decision of these meetings resulted in; Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA being subjected to the Jikan Nochi (an order for surrendering the Shogunate post, including other official court rankings, governmental postings, and all of his domains, including territories ruled, to the Imperial court).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In conclusion, the decision of these meetings resulted in; Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA being subjected to the Jikan Nochi (an order to surrender the Shogunate post, including other official court rankings, governmental postings, and all of his domains, including territories ruled, to the Imperial court).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In conclusion, the decision of these meetings resulted in; Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA being subjected to the Jikan Nochi (an order to surrender the shogunate post, including other official court rankings, governmental postings, and all of his domains, including territories ruled, to the Imperial Court).</e>
<cmt>Shogunateの頭文字を小文字に変更し、the Imperial Courtとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>慶喜はいったん大坂城に退くが、公議政体派の山内容堂（前土佐藩主）・松平春嶽（前越前藩主）・徳川慶勝（前尾張藩主）らの工作により、小御所会議の決定は骨抜きにされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Yoshinobu once retreated to the Osaka Castle, the members of the parliamentary regime, Yodo YAMAUCHI (the former lord of Tosa domain), Shungaku MATSUDAIRA (the former lord of the Echizen domain), and Yoshikatsu TOKUGAWA (the former lord of the Owari domain) and those who were members of the parliamentary regime maneuvered and water downed the decision of the &quot;Kogosho Conference.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Yoshinobu once retreated to Osaka Castle, the members of the parliamentary regime, Yodo YAMAUCHI (the former lord of the Tosa domain), Shungaku MATSUDAIRA (the former lord of the Echizen domain), and Yoshikatsu TOKUGAWA (the former lord of the Owari domain) and those who were members of the parliamentary regime maneuvered and water downed the decision of the &quot;Kogosho Conference.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Yoshinobu once retreated to Osaka-jo Castle, the members of the parliamentary regime, Yodo YAMAUCHI (the former lord of the Tosa Domain), Shungaku MATSUDAIRA (the former lord of the Echizen Domain), and Yoshikatsu TOKUGAWA (the former lord of the Owari Domain) and those who were members of the parliamentary regime maneuvered and water downed the decision of the &quot;Kogosho Conference.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Osaka-jo Castleとし、domainの頭文字を大文字に変更、全角クォーテーションを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また慶喜も諸外国の公使に対して外交権の継続を宣言するなど、次第に列侯会議派の巻き返しが顕著となってきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, Yoshinobu himself declared his continuation of diplomatic right to the ministers of foreign countries, so gradually and then noticeably, the party of council by feudal lords recovered from this set back.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, Yoshinobu himself declared his continuation of diplomatic rights to the ministers of foreign countries, so gradually and then noticeably, the party of council by feudal lords recovered from this set back.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, Yoshinobu himself declared his continuation of diplomatic rights to the ministers of foreign countries, so gradually and then noticeably, the party of council by feudal lords recovered from this set back.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>そこで西郷は、幕府側を挑発するという非常手段（作略）に出る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Saigo took extreme measures (tactics) to provoke the Tokugawa Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Saigo took extreme measures (tactics) to provoke the Tokugawa Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Saigo took extreme measures (tactics) to provoke the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) side.</e>
<cmt>Tokugawa Bakufu→Edo bakufuに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>江戸薩摩藩邸の益満休之助・伊牟田尚平に命じ、相楽総三ら浪士を集めて江戸市中に放火・掠奪・暴行などを行わせる攪乱工作を開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, Saigo ordered Kyunosuke MASUMITSU and Sozo SAGARA who resided in the residence of the Satsuma Domain, to gather the roshi (master less or unemployed samurai) samurais, asking them (roshi samurais) to begin the disturbance maneuvers such as, arson, looting, and committing outrageous or violence activities in the city of Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, Saigo ordered Kyunosuke MASUMITSU and Sozo SAGARA who resided in the residence of the Satsuma Domain, to gather the roshi (master less or unemployed samurai) samurai, asking them (roshi samurai) to begin disturbance maneuvers such as, arson, looting, and committing outrageous or violence activities in the city of Edo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, Saigo ordered Kyunosuke MASUMITSU and Shohei IMUTA who resided in the residence of the Satsuma clan in Edo to gather the roshi (master less or unemployed samurai) samurai including Sozo SAGARA, asking them (roshi samurai) to begin disturbance maneuvers such as, arson, looting, and committing outrageous or violence activities in the city of Edo.</e>
<cmt>「伊牟田尚平」→訳漏れのため訳出、the residence of the Satsuma Domain→the residence of the Satsuma clan in Edoに修正、原文に沿わない部分を一部訳し直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>江戸市中警備の任にあった庄内藩がこれに怒り、12月25日、薩摩藩および佐土原藩（薩摩支藩）邸を焼き討ちするという事件が発生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The retainers of the Shonai domains reaction to these disturbance maneuvers by Saigo in the Shonai domain, since it was their assignment to guard the city of Edo, was one of anger, resulting in their setting fire to residency of the Satsuma Domain and the residency of the Sadowara domain (branch domain of the Satsuma domain) on December 25th (actually January 19th, 1868).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The retainers of the Shonai domains reaction to these disturbances by Saigo in the Shonai domain, since it was their assignment to guard the city of Edo, was one of anger, resulting in their setting fire to the residency of the Satsuma Domain and the residency of the Sadowara domain (branch domain of the Satsuma domain) on December 25th (actually January 19th, 1868).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The retainers of the Shonai Domain reaction to these disturbances by Saigo, since it was their assignment to guard the city of Edo, was one of anger, resulting in their setting fire to the residency of the Satsuma Domain and the residency of the Sadowara Domain (branch domain of the Satsuma Domain) on December 25th.</e>
<cmt>Shonai domains→Shonai Domainに修正、in the Shonai domain削除、Sadowara Domain、Satsuma Domainとし、統一事項より新暦表記削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>この報が12月28日大坂城にもたらされると、城内の強硬派が激昂。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the news of the event came into Osaka Castle in December 28th (actually January 22nd, 1868), had-liners on the Tokugawa Bakufu side became indignant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the news of the event arrived at Osaka Castle on December 28th (actually January 22, 1868), had-liners on the Tokugawa Bakufu side became indignant.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the news of the event arrived at Osaka-jo Castle on December 28th, hard-liners on the Tokugawa shogunate side became indignant.</e>
<cmt>Osaka-jo Castleとし、統一事項より新暦表記削除、had-liner→hard-liner、Tokugawa Bakufu→Tokugawa shogunateに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>薩摩を討つべしとの主戦論が沸騰し、「討薩表」を携えた幕府軍が上京を試みることなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tokugawa Bakufu side had heated debates on the advocacy of war and attacking Satsuma; then the army of Tokugawa Bakufu acting on &quot;the statement to the Emperor to avenge Satsuma&quot; tried to come up to the capital, Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tokugawa Bakufu side had heated debates on advocacating war and attacking Satsuma; then the army of the Tokugawa Bakufu acting on &quot;the statement to the Emperor to avenge Satsuma&quot; tried to go to the capital, Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tokugawa shogunate side had heated debates on advocacating war and attacking Satsuma; then the army of the Tokugawa shogunate acting on &quot;the statement to the Emperor to avenge Satsuma&quot; tried to go to the capital, Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Tokugawa Bakufu→Tokugawa shogunateに修正、全角クォーテーションを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>慶応4年正月3日鳥羽 (洛外)（京都市）で薩摩藩兵と衝突し、戦闘となった（詳細は鳥羽・伏見の戦いを参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 3rd, 1868 (actually January 27th, 1868), the army of Tokugawa Bakufu confronted the army of the Satsuma Domain at the Toba (&quot;Rakugai&quot;; on the outskirts of Kyoto in Kyoto city); this incident would lead to a battle. (Please refer to The Battle of Toba-Fushimi).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 3, 1868 (actually January 27, 1868), the army of the Tokugawa Bakufu confronted the army of the Satsuma Domain at the Toba (&quot;Rakugai;&quot; on the outskirts of Kyoto in Kyoto city); this incident would lead to a battle. (Please refer to The Battle of Toba-Fushimi).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 3, 1868, the army of the Tokugawa shogunate confronted the army of the Satsuma Domain at Toba (&quot;Rakugai;&quot; on the outskirts of Kyoto in Kyoto City); this incident would lead to a battle (Please refer to The Battle of Toba-Fushimi).</e>
<cmt>Tokugawa Bakufu→Tokugawa shogunate、at the Toba→at Tobaとし、全角クォーテーションを半角に修正、Kyoto Cityとし、統一事項より新暦表記削除、余分なピリオド削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>しかし戦局が劣勢となった上、淀藩・津藩などが寝返ってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the war situation worsens on the Tokugawa Bakufu side, furthermore, the Yodo Domain and the Tsu Domain betrayed Bakufu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the war situation worsened on the Tokugawa Bakufu side, furthermore, the Yodo and the Tsu Domains betrayed the Bakufu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the war situation worsened on the Tokugawa shogunate side, furthermore, the Yodo and the Tsu Domains betrayed the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>Tokugawa Bakufu→Tokugawa shogunate、the Bakufu→the bakufuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>また薩摩・長州藩兵側に錦旗が翻る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The army of the Satsuma and the Choshu Domains displayed the Kinki (a gold-brocade flag which was used as a symbol of the governments army in support of conquering the Emperor&apos;s enemy) flag.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The army of the Satsuma and Choshu Domains displayed the Kinki (a gold-brocade flag which was used as a symbol of the governments army in support of conquering the Emperor&apos;s enemy) flag.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The army of the Satsuma and Choshu Domains displayed the Kinki (a gold-brocade flag which was used as a symbol of the governments army in support of conquering the Emperor&apos;s enemy) flag.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>それにより幕府軍は朝敵となってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequentially, the army on Tokugawa Bakufu&apos;s side became the Emperor&apos;s enemy.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequentially, the army on Tokugawa Bakufu&apos;s side became the Emperor&apos;s enemy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequentially, the army on the Tokugawa shogunate&apos;s side became the Emperor&apos;s enemy.</e>
<cmt>Tokugawa Bakufu’s side→the Tokugawa shogunate&apos;s sideに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>慶喜は6日、軍を捨てて大坂城を脱出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 6th 1868 (actually January 30th, 1868), Yoshinobu abandoned his army of the Tokugawa Bakufu and escaped from Osaka Castle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 6th 1868 (actually January 30th, 1868), Yoshinobu abandoned his army of the Tokugawa Bakufu and escaped from Osaka Castle.</e>
<cmt>wrapped text</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 6th 1868, Yoshinobu abandoned his army of the Tokugawa shogunate and escaped from Osaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>(actually January 30th, 1868)削除、Tokugawa shogunate、Osaka-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>そして、軍艦開陽丸で海路江戸へ逃走した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then he boarded the Kaiyo Maru Warship and fled to Edo Castle by sea route.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then he boarded the Kaiyo Maru Warship and fled to Edo Castle by the sea route.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then he boarded the Kaiyo Maru Warship and fled to Edo-jo Castle by the sea route.</e>
<cmt>Edo-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>ここに鳥羽・伏見の戦いは幕府の完敗で終幕した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, The Battle of Toba-Fushimi had ended, the Tokugawa Bakufu side utterly defeated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, The Battle of Toba-Fushimi had ended, the Tokugawa Bakufu side was utterly defeated.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, The Battle of Toba-Fushimi had ended, the Tokugawa shogunate side was utterly defeated.</e>
<cmt>Tokugawa shogunateとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="24">
<j>新政府は7日徳川慶喜追討令を発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January, 7th (January 31st, 1868), the new government issued this statement, &quot;decree to search and kill Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January, 7 (January 31, 1868), the new government issued this statement, &quot;a decree to search and kill Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January, 7, the new government issued this statement, &quot;a decree to search and kill Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA.&quot;</e>
<cmt>(January 31, 1868)削除、全角クォーテーションを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>10日には慶喜・松平容保（会津藩主、元京都守護職）・松平定敬（桑名藩主、元京都所司代）を初め幕閣など27人の「朝敵」の官職を剥奪し、京都藩邸を没収するなどの処分を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January, 10th (actually February 3rd, 1868) the new government ordered as punishment to the offending supporters, &quot;enemy of the Emperor.&quot;: Taking of governmental posts, commandeering the hantei (residence maintained by a daimyo in Kyoto) residences in Kyoto of their twenty-seven highest cabinet members and those of other top ranking officials in the Tokugawa Bakufu administration, including Nobuyoshi, Katamori MATSUDAIRA [the lord of the Aizu domain and the former Kyoto shugoshoku (Military governor of Kyoto)] and Sadaaki MATSUDAIRA [the lord of the Kuwana Domain and the former Kyoto shoshidai (The Kyoto deputy)].</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January, 10 (actually February 3, 1868) the new government ordered as punishment to the offending supporters, &quot;enemy of the Emperor:&quot; Taking of governmental posts, commandeering the hantei (residence maintained by a daimyo in Kyoto) residences in Kyoto of their twenty-seven highest cabinet members and those of other top ranking officials in the Tokugawa Bakufu administration, including Nobuyoshi, Katamori MATSUDAIRA [the lord of the Aizu domain and the former Kyoto shugoshoku (Military governor of Kyoto)] and Sadaaki MATSUDAIRA [the lord of the Kuwana Domain and the former Kyoto shoshidai (The Kyoto deputy)].</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January, 10 the new government ordered as punishment to the offending supporters, &quot;enemy of the Emperor&quot;; taking of governmental posts, commandeering the hantei (residence maintained by a daimyo in Kyoto) residences in Kyoto of their twenty-seven highest cabinet members and those of other top ranking officials in the Tokugawa shogunate administration, including Yoshinobu, Katamori MATSUDAIRA (the lord of the Aizu Domain and the former Kyoto shugoshoku [Military governor of Kyoto]) and Sadaaki MATSUDAIRA (the lord of the Kuwana Domain and the former Kyoto shoshidai [The Kyoto deputy]).</e>
<cmt>(actually February 3, 1868)、全角クォーテーションを半角に修正、文中のピリオド→セミコロンに変更、Tokugawa shogunateとし、Nobuyoshi→Yoshinobuに修正、カッコ表記修正、domainの頭文字を大文字に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>翌日には諸藩に対して兵を上京させるよう命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the next day, the new government ordered the lords of other domains to mobilize their armies, and then come to the Kyoto Capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the next day, the new government ordered the lords of other domains to mobilize their armies, and then come to the Kyoto Capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the next day, the new government ordered the lords of other domains to mobilize their armies, and then come to the Kyoto Capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>また21日には外国事務総督東久世通禧から諸外国の代表に対して、徳川方に武器・軍艦の供与や兵の移送、軍事顧問の派遣などの援助を行わないよう要請した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the 21st (actually February, 14th, 1868), Michitomi HIGASHIKUZE, the ministerial governor of foreign affairs, and a representative of the new government, requested of the representatives of foreign countries, to refrain from any performance in support of the Tokugawa Bakufu side; this included the providing of weapons, warships, the transferring of supporting troops and the sending of military advisers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the 21st (actually February, 14, 1868), Michitomi HIGASHIKUZE, the ministerial governor of foreign affairs, and a representative of the new government, requested the representatives of foreign countries, to refrain from any show of support of the Tokugawa Bakufu side; this included providing weapons, warships, the transferring of supporting troops and the sending of military advisers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the 21st, Michitomi HIGASHIKUZE, the ministerial governor of foreign affairs, and a representative of the new government, requested the representatives of foreign countries, to refrain from any show of support of the Tokugawa shogunate side; this included providing weapons, warships, the transferring of supporting troops and the sending of military advisers.</e>
<cmt>(actually February, 14, 1868)削除、Tokugawa shogunateとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>これを受け25日諸外国は、それぞれ局外中立を宣言。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On 25th (actually February, 18th, 1868), all of foreign countries contacted declared their neutrality position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On 25th (actually February, 18, 1868), all of foreign countries contacted declared their position of neutrality.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the 25th, all of foreign countries contacted declared their position of neutrality.</e>
<cmt>On the 25thとし、(actually February, 18, 1868)削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>事実上新政府軍は、かつて諸外国と条約を締結した政府としての徳川家と、対等の交戦団体として認識されたことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was an official recognition by the foreign governments of the new governmental army as an equal party, to then engage in battle against the Tokugawa Family, which up to this time, was the official governmental entity for concluding their treaties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was an official recognition by the foreign governments of the new governmental army as an equal party, to then engage in battle against the Tokugawa Family, which up to this time, was the official governmental entity for concluding treaties.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was an official recognition by the foreign governments of the new governmental army as an equal party, to then engage in battle against the Tokugawa family, which up to this time, was the official governmental entity for concluding treaties.</e>
<cmt>the Tokugawa familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="30">
<j>旧幕府側の主戦論と恭順論</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The war advocacy policy and allegiance policy toward the new government (Imperial government) within the former Tokugawa Bakufu side</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The war advocacy policy and allegiance policy toward the new government (Imperial government) within the former Tokugawa Bakufu side</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The war advocacy policy and allegiance policy toward the new government (Imperial government) within the former Tokugawa shogunate side</e>
<cmt>Tokugawa shogunateとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="31">
<j>正月11日、品川に到着した慶喜。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 11th (actually February, 2nd, 1868), Yoshinobu reached Shinagawa.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 11th (actually February, 2, 1868), Yoshinobu reached Shinagawa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 11th, Yoshinobu reached Shinagawa.</e>
<cmt>(actually February, 2, 1868)削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>慶喜は、翌12日江戸城西の丸に入り今後の対策を練った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the next day Yoshinobu entered into the Nishi no Maru (a castle compound to the west of the main compound) inside the Edo Castle and contemplated his future plans.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the next day Yoshinobu entered Nishi no Maru (a castle compound to the west of the main compound) inside the Edo Castle and contemplated his future plans.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the next day Yoshinobu entered Nishi no Maru (a castle compound to the west of the main compound) inside the Edo-jo Castle and contemplated his future plans.</e>
<cmt>Edo-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>慶喜はひとまず13日歩兵頭に駿府（現静岡市）警備、14日には土井利与（古河藩主）に神奈川（現横浜市）警備を命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First, on January 13th (February 4th, 1868) Yoshinobu ordered the head of his infantry to guard Sunpu (current, Shizuoka City); on January 14th ((actually February 5th, 1868), Yoshinobu ordered Toshitomo DOI (the lord of Koga Domain) to guard Kangawa (currently, Yokohama City).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First, on January 13th (February 4, 1868) Yoshinobu ordered the head of his infantry to guard Sunpu (current, Shizuoka City); on January 14th (actually February 5, 1868), Yoshinobu ordered Toshitomo DOI (the lord of Koga Domain) to guard Kangawa (currently, Yokohama City).</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First, on January 13th Yoshinobu ordered the head of his infantry to guard Sunpu (current, Shizuoka City); on January 14th, Yoshinobu ordered Toshitomo DOI (the lord of the Koga Domain) to guard Kanagawa (currently, Yokohama City).</e>
<cmt>(February 4, 1868) (actually February 5, 1868)削除、the Koga Domainとし、Kangawa→Kanagawaに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>17日には目付を箱根関・碓氷峠の関所に配した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 17th (actually February 8th, 1868), Yoshinobu positioned the Metsuke (the inspectors of foot soldiers) officials at the checking stations of Hakone and Usui-toge Passes.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 17th (actually February 8, 1868), Yoshinobu positioned the Metsuke (the inspectors of foot soldiers) officials at the checking stations of Hakone and Usui-toge Passes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 17th, Yoshinobu positioned the Metsuke (the inspectors of foot soldiers) officials at the checking stations of Hakone and Usui-toge Passes.</e>
<cmt>(actually February 8, 1868)削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>20日には松本藩・高崎藩に碓氷関警備を命令。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 20th (actually February 11th, 1868), Yoshinobu ordered the Matsumoto Domain and the akasaki Domain to guard the checking station for the Usui-toge Pass.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 20th (actually February 11, 1868), Yoshinobu ordered the Matsumoto Domain and the akasaki Domain to guard the checking station for the Usui-toge Pass.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 20th, Yoshinobu ordered the Matsumoto Domain and the Takasaki Domain to guard the checking station for the Usui-toge Pass.</e>
<cmt>(actually February 11, 1868)削除、akasaki→Takasakiに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>さらに親幕府派の松平春嶽・山内容堂らに書翰を送って周旋を依頼するなど、さしあたっての応急処置を施している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Yoshinobu sent correspondence to Shungaku MATSUDAIRA and Yodo YAMAUCHI, who were the sympathizers of the (Tokugawa) Bakufu side, and requested mediation; this was the sequence of emergency directions executed by Yoshinobu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Yoshinobu sent correspondence to Shungaku MATSUDAIRA and Yodo YAMAUCHI, who were the sympathizers of the (Tokugawa) Bakufu side, and requested mediation; this was the sequence of emergency directions executed by Yoshinobu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Yoshinobu sent correspondence to Shungaku MATSUDAIRA and Yodo YAMAUCHI, who were the sympathizers of the bakufu side, and requested mediation; this was the sequence of emergency directions executed by Yoshinobu.</e>
<cmt>the (Tokugawa) Bakufu side→the bakufu sideとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>鳥羽・伏見敗戦にともなって新政府による徳川征伐軍の襲来が予想されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Tokugawa Bakufu side lost at the battle of Toba-Fushimi, the Bakufu side expected the army for conquest of Tokugawa, formed by the new government, was prepared to attack the Bakufu side immediately.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Tokugawa Bakufu side lost at the battle of Toba-Fushimi, the Bakufu side expected the army conquest of Tokugawa, formed by the new government, was prepared to attack the Bakufu side immediately.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the bakufu side lost at the battle of Toba-Fushimi, the bakufu side expected the army conquest of Tokugawa, formed by the new government, was prepared to attack the bakufu side immediately.</e>
<cmt>the Tokugawa Bakufu side→the bakufu side、Bakufu→bakufuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>この時点で、徳川家の取り得る方策は徹底恭順か、抗戦しつつ佐幕派諸藩と提携して形勢を逆転するかの2つの選択肢があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this moment, Tokugawa family could have two plans to choose from; on one hand was allegiance to the new government; on the other hand is the continuation of their current Bakufu defense; then at the same time, the Bakufu group could form an alliance with the Sabaku-ha (supporters of the Shogun) domains, eventually gaining the power to reverse the present situation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this moment, the Tokugawa family had two plans to choose from, on one hand was allegiance to the new government and on the other hand the continuation of their current Bakufu defense and at the same time the Bakufu group could form an alliance with the Sabaku-ha (supporters of the Shogun) domains and eventually gain the power to reverse the present situation.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this moment, the Tokugawa family had two plans to choose from, on one hand was allegiance to the new government and on the other hand the continuation of their current bakufu defense and at the same time the bakufu group could form an alliance with the Sabaku-ha (supporters of the Shogun) domains and eventually gain the power to reverse the present situation.</e>
<cmt>Bakufu→bakufuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="39">
<j>勘定奉行兼陸軍奉行並の小栗忠順や、軍艦頭並の榎本武揚らは主戦論を主張。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadamasa OGURI, who was a Kanjo Bugyo (commissioner of finance) and also was assigned as a Rikugun Bugyo (commissioner of the Bakufu Army) ranking position, and Takeaki ENOMOTO, who was the chief ranking official of the Bakufu Navy, insisted upon a war advocacy policy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadamasa OGURI, a Kanjo Bugyo (commissioner of finance) also was assigned as a Rikugun Bugyo (commissioner of the Bakufu Army) ranking position, and Takeaki ENOMOTO, the chief ranking official of the Bakufu Navy, insisted upon a war advocacy policy.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadamasa OGURI, a Kanjo Bugyo (commissioner of finance) also was assigned as a Rikugun Bugyo (commissioner of the bakufu army) ranking position, and Takeaki ENOMOTO, the chief ranking official of the bakufu navy, insisted upon a war advocacy policy.</e>
<cmt>the bakufu army、the bakufu navyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>小栗の作戦は、敵軍を箱根以東に誘い込んだところで、兵力的に勝る幕府海軍が駿河湾に出動して敵の退路を断った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The strategic plan of Oguri was one in which the Bakufu would entice the enemy army out, east of Hakone; then the Bakufu Navy would approach from Suruga Bay, shutting down the enemy&apos;s retreat.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The strategic plan of Oguri was the Bakufu would entice the enemy army out to the east of Hakone and the Bakufu Navy would approach from Suruga Bay shutting down the enemy&apos;s retreat.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The strategic plan of Oguri was the bakufu would entice the enemy army out to the east of Hakone and the bakufu navy would approach from Suruga Bay shutting down the enemy&apos;s retreat.</e>
<cmt>Bakufu→bakufu、the bakufu navyとし、全角アポストロフィーを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>フランス式軍事演習で鍛えられた幕府陸軍で一挙に敵を粉砕。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Now, the Bakufu Army having trained in the French tactical military strategy would enter the battle, attacking and destroying the enemy.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Now, the Bakufu Army having been trained in French tactical military strategy would enter the battle, to attack and destroy the enemy.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Now, the bakufu army having been trained in French tactical military strategy would enter the battle, to attack and destroy the enemy.</e>
<cmt>the bakufu armyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>海軍をさらに兵庫・大阪方面に派遣して近畿を奪還するというものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, the Bakufu Navy would send additional warships, advancing to the Hyogo and the Osaka prefectures in order to successfully reclaim the Kinki region.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Bakufu Navy would send additional warships, and advance to Hyogo and Osaka prefectures to successfully reclaim the Kinki region.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bakufu navy would send additional warships, and advance to Hyogo and Osaka prefectures to successfully reclaim the Kinki region.</e>
<cmt>The bakufu nabyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>が、慶喜の容れるところとならず、小栗は正月15日に罷免されてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Nobuyoshi did not accept Oguri&apos;s plan and abruptly discharged Oguri on January 15th (actually February, 8th, 1868).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Nobuyoshi did not accept Oguri&apos;s plan and abruptly discharged Oguri on January 15th (actually February, 8th, 1868).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Yoshinobu did not accept Oguri&apos;s plan and abruptly discharged Oguri on January 15th.</e>
<cmt>Nobuyoshi→Yoshinobuに修正、全角アポストロフィーを半角に修正、(actually February, 8th, 1868)を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>19日には在江戸諸藩主を召し、恭順の意を伝えて協力を要請をしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 19th (actually February, 12th, 1868), Yoshinobu summoned the lords residing in the other domains of Edo, declaring his intent; it was his decision to form an allegiance to the new government and request their corporation in the same.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 19th (actually February, 12th, 1868), Yoshinobu summoned the lords residing in the other domains of Edo, declaring his intent that it was his decision to form an allegiance to the new government and requested their corporation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 19th, Yoshinobu summoned the lords residing in the other domains of Edo, declaring his intent that it was his decision to form an allegiance to the new government and requested their corporation.</e>
<cmt>(actually February, 12th, 1868)削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>翌日には静寛院宮にも同様の要請をしている（後述）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the next day, Yoshinobu submitted the same proposal to the Princess Kazu (Seikan in no Miya) (This matter will be described later.).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The next day Yoshinobu submitted the same proposal to Princess Kazu (Seikan in no Miya) (This matter will be described later).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The next day Yoshinobu submitted the same proposal to Seikanin no miya (This matter will be described later).</e>
<cmt>「静寛院宮」の表記を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>続く23日、恭順派を中心として配置した徳川家人事の変更が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Continuously, on January 23rd (actually February, 16th, 1868), Yoshinobu ordered the personnel for the governmental administration of the Tokugawa family replaced; he then formed the cabinet body, and positioned personnel, primarily chosen from the party favoring allegiance, into the new government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Continuously on January 23rd (actually February, 16th, 1868) Yoshinobu ordered the personnel for the governmental administration of the Tokugawa family to be replaced, he then formed the cabinet body and positioned personnel, primarily chosen from the party favoring allegiance, into the new government.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Continuously on January 23rd Yoshinobu ordered the personnel for the governmental administration of the Tokugawa family to be replaced, he then formed the cabinet body and positioned personnel, primarily chosen from the party favoring allegiance, into the new government.</e>
<cmt>(actually February, 16th, 1868)削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="47">
<j>若年寄 平山敬忠、川勝広運</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Listed here are some samples of the personnel assigned in the Bakufu: Wakadoshiyori (junior councilor): Yoshitada HIRAYAMA and Hirokazu KAWAKATSU</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Listed here are some examples of personnel assigned in the Bakufu; Wakadoshiyori (junior councilor), Yoshitada HIRAYAMA, and Hirokazu KAWAKATSU</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Listed here are some examples of personnel assigned in the bakufu; Wakadoshiyori (junior councilor), Yoshitada HIRAYAMA, and Hirokazu KAWAKATSU</e>
<cmt>Bakufu→bakufuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>陸軍総裁 勝海舟、副総裁 藤沢次謙</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rikugun Sosai (the president of the Bakufu Army): Kaishu KATSU, and the Fuku Sosai (the vice president of the Bakufu Army): Tsuguyoshi FUJISAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rikugun Sosai (president of the Bakufu Army), Kaishu KATSU, and the Fuku Sosai (vice president of the Bakufu Army), Tsuguyoshi FUJISAWA</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rikugun Sosai (president of the bakufu army), Kaishu KATSU, and the Fuku Sosai (vice president of the bakufu army), Tsuguyoshi FUJISAWA</e>
<cmt>the bakufu armyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>海軍総裁 矢田堀鴻、副総裁 榎本武揚</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaigun Sosai (the president of the Bakufu Navy) Kou YATABORI and the Fuku Sosai (the vice president of the Bakufu Navy): Takeaki ENOMOTO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaigun Sosai (president of the Bakufu Navy), Kou YATABORI and the Fuku Sosai (vice president of the Bakufu Navy), Takeaki ENOMOTO</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaigun Sosai (president of the bakufu navy), Kou YATABORI and the Fuku Sosai (vice president of the bakufu navy), Takeaki ENOMOTO</e>
<cmt>the bakufu navyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>会計総裁 大久保一翁、副総裁 成島柳北</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaikei Sosai (the president of the Treasury department in the Bakufu): Ichio OKUBO and the Fuku Sosai (the vice president of the Treasury department in the Bakufu) Ryuhoku NARUSHIMA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaikei Sosai (president of the Treasury department in the Bakufu): Ichio OKUBO and the Fuku Sosai (vice president of the Treasury department in the Bakufu) Ryuhoku NARUSHIMA</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaikei Sosai (president of the Treasury department in the bakufu): Ichio OKUBO and the Fuku Sosai (vice president of the Treasury department in the bakufu) Ryuhoku NARUSHIMA</e>
<cmt>Bakufu→bakufuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>外国事務総裁 山口直毅、副総裁 河津祐邦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gaikoku Jimu Sosai (the president of the ministry of foreign affairs): Naoki YAMAGUCHI and the fuku Sosai (the vice president of the ministry of foreign affairs: Sukekuni KAWAZU</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gaikoku Jimu Sosai (president of the ministry of foreign affairs), Naoki YAMAGUCHI and the fuku Sosai (vice president of the ministry of foreign affairs, Sukekuni KAWAZU</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gaikoku Jimu Sosai (president of the ministry of foreign affairs), Naoki YAMAGUCHI and the fuku Sosai (vice president of the ministry of foreign affairs), Sukekuni KAWAZU</e>
<cmt>カッコ不足分追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="52">
<j>このうち、庶政を取り仕切る会計総裁大久保一翁と、軍事を司る陸軍総裁勝海舟の2人が、瓦解しつつある徳川家の事実上の最高指揮官となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the newly assigned officials was, Ichio OKUBO, the Kaikei Sosai who would manage all phases of government affairs; Kaishu KATSU, the Rikugun Sosai who would control military affairs, these two officials, were to become out of practically, the highest commanders in what remained of the collapsing Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the newly assigned officials was, Ichio OKUBO, the Kaikei Sosai who would manage all phases of government affairs, Kaishu KATSU, the Rikugun Sosai who would control military affairs, these two officials, were to become, the highest commanders in what remained of the collapsing Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the newly assigned officials, Ichio OKUBO, the Kaikei Sosai who would manage all phases of government affairs, Kaishu KATSU, the Rikugun Sosai who would control military affairs, these two officials, bacame the actual highest commanders in what remained of the collapsing Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>was削除、were to become→became、the highest commanders→the actual highest commandersとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>そして、恭順策を実行に移していくことになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, these two officials implemented the execution of the policy for allegiance in the new government.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These two officials implemented the execution of the policy for allegiance in the new government.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These two officials implemented the execution of the policy for allegiance in the new government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>この時期、フランス第二帝政公使レオン・ロッシュがたびたび登城して慶喜に抗戦を提案しているが、慶喜はそれも退けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, Léon Roches the Minister of the French Second Empire, in one of his frequent visits to Edo Castle, suggested to the Yoshinobu his support in defense of battle; but Yoshinobu refused his suggestion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, Léon Roches the Minister of the French Second Empire, in one of his frequent visits to Edo Castle, suggested to Yoshinobu his support in defense of battle, but Yoshinobu refused his suggestion.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, Léon ROCHES the Minister of the French Second Empire, in one of his frequent visits to Edo-jo Castle, suggested to Yoshinobu his support in defense of battle, but Yoshinobu refused his suggestion.</e>
<cmt>Léon Roches→Léon ROCHESに修正、Edo-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>27日、慶喜は徳川茂承（紀州藩主）らに隠居・恭順を朝廷に奏上することを告げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 27th (actually February, 20th, 1868), Yoshinobu declared to Mochitsugu TOKUGAWA (the lord of the Kishu domain) and others that he would report to the Emperor on his retirement, there he would acknowledge his allegiance to the new government and Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 27th (actually February, 20th, 1868), Yoshinobu declared to Mochitsugu TOKUGAWA (the lord of the Kishu domain) and others that he would report to the Emperor on his retirement, and then he would acknowledge his allegiance to the new government and Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 27th, Yoshinobu declared to Mochitsugu TOKUGAWA (the lord of the Kishu Domain) and others that he would report to the Emperor on his retirement, and then he would acknowledge his allegiance to the new government and Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>(actually February, 20th, 1868)削除、domainの頭文字を大文字に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>ここに至って徳川家の公式方針は恭順に確定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was at this point in time the Tokugawa family defined their official policy, a universal declaration of their allegiance to the new government.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was at this point in time the Tokugawa family defined their official policy, a universal declaration of their allegiance to the new government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was at this point in time the Tokugawa family defined their official policy, a universal declaration of their allegiance to the new government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>しかし、それに不満を持つ幕臣たちは独自行動をとることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there were vassals under the control of Tokugawa Bakufu dissatisfied with this decision; they in turn, would seize the initiative to act on their own.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there were vassals under the control of the Tokugawa Bakufu who were dissatisfied with this decision, they in turn, would seize the initiative to act on their own.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there were vassals under the control of the Tokugawa shogunate who were dissatisfied with this decision, they in turn, would seize the initiative to act on their own.</e>
<cmt>Tokugawa shogunateとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>さらに2月9日には鳥羽・伏見の戦いの責任者を一斉に処分。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, on February 9th (actually March 2nd, 1868), Yoshinobu punished all of the officials and personnel responsible for The Battle of Toba-Fushimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, on February 9th (actually March 2, 1868), Yoshinobu punished all of the officials and personnel responsible for The Battle of Toba-Fushimi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, on February 9th, Yoshinobu punished all of the officials and personnel responsible for The Battle of Toba-Fushimi.</e>
<cmt>(actually March 2, 1868)削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>12日、慶喜は江戸城を徳川慶頼（田安徳川家当主、元将軍後見職）・松平斉民（前津山藩主）に委任して退出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 12th (actually March 5th, 1868), Yoshinobu entrusted Yoshiyori TOKUGAWA [the head of the Tayasu-Tokugawa Family and former Shogun-kokenshoku (one of three important governmental administrative officials, the guardian for the Shogun)] and Naritami MATSUDAIRA (the former lord of Tsuyama Domain) with the Edo Castle, then subsequently retired.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 12th (actually March 5th, 1868), Yoshinobu entrusted Yoshiyori TOKUGAWA [the head of the Tayasu-Tokugawa Family and former Shogun-kokenshoku (one of three important governmental administrative officials, the guardian for the Shogun)] and Naritami MATSUDAIRA (the former lord of Tsuyama Domain) with the Edo Castle, then subsequently retired.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 12th, Yoshinobu entrusted Yoshiyori TOKUGAWA (the head of the Tayasu-Tokugawa family and former Shogun-kokenshoku [one of three important governmental administrative officials, the guardian for the Shogun]) and Naritami MATSUDAIRA (the former lord of the Tsuyama Domain) with the Edo-jo Castle, then subsequently retired.</e>
<cmt>(actually March 5th, 1868)削除、the Tayasu-Tokugawa familyとし、カッコ表記修正、the Tsuyama Domain、Edo-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>上野寛永寺大慈院に移って、その後謹慎生活を送った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time Yoshinobu relocated into the Ueno Kanei-ji Temple Daiji-in; he was to spend his life confined inside this temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time Yoshinobu relocated to the Ueno Kanei-ji Temple Daiji-in and he was to spend his life confined inside this temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time Yoshinobu relocated to the Ueno Kanei-ji Temple Daiji-in and he was to spend his life confined inside this temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="61">
<j>新政府側の強硬論と寛典論</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hard-liner policy and lenient treatment policy administered by the new government</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hard-line and lenient treatment policies administered by the new government</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hard-line and lenient treatment policies administered by the new government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>新政府側でも徳川家（特に前将軍慶喜）に対して厳しい処分を断行すべきとする強硬論と、長引く内紛や過酷な処分は国益に反するとして穏当な処分で済ませようとする寛典論の両論が存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Within the new government there were two opposing policies regarding treatment of the Tokugawa Bakufu; one was the Hard-liner policy, which insisted upon the administration of severely harsh punishment to Tokugawa family (particularly the former Shogun, Yoshinobu); the more liberal group persisted in the application of a more lenient treatment policy, which considered a more appropriate (reasonable) and tempered punishment toward the Tokugawa family; this stance was an effort to address the potential for prolonged turmoil resulting from a harsher punishment, and the resulting effects upon the national interests.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Within the new government there were two opposing policies regarding treatment of the Tokugawa Bakufu; one was the Hard-liner policy, which insisted upon the administration of severely harsh punishment to Tokugawa family (particularly the former Shogun, Yoshinobu); the more liberal group persisted in the application of a more lenient treatment policy, which considered a more appropriate (reasonable) and tempered punishment toward the Tokugawa family; this stance was an effort to address the potential for prolonged turmoil resulting from a harsher punishment, and the resulting effects upon the national interests.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Within the new government there were two opposing policies regarding treatment of the Tokugawa shogunate; one was the Hard-liner policy, which insisted upon the administration of severely harsh punishment to the Tokugawa family (particularly the former Shogun, Yoshinobu); the more liberal group persisted in the application of a more lenient treatment policy, which considered a more appropriate (reasonable) and tempered punishment toward the Tokugawa family; this stance was an effort to address the potential for prolonged turmoil resulting from a harsher punishment, and the resulting effects upon the national interests.</e>
<cmt>the Tokugawa shogunate、the Tokugawa familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>薩摩藩の西郷隆盛などは強硬論であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takamori SAIGO, from Satsuma Domain was the one example of those who favored the Hard-liner policy.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takamori SAIGO, from Satsuma Domain was the one example of those who favored the Hard-liner policy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takamori SAIGO, from the Satsuma Domain was the one example of those who favored the Hard-liner policy.</e>
<cmt>the Satsuma Domainとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>大久保利通宛ての書状などで慶喜の切腹を断固求める旨を訴えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a letter he sent to Toshimichi OKUBO, Takamori SAIGO definitely lobbied for his belief in the need for Yoshinobu&apos;s Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a letter he sent to Toshimichi OKUBO, Takamori SAIGO definitely lobbied for his belief in the need for Yoshinobu&apos;s Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a letter he sent to Toshimichi OKUBO, Takamori SAIGO definitely lobbied for his belief in the need for Yoshinobu&apos;s Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment).</e>
<cmt>全角アポストロフィーを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>大久保も同様に慶喜が謹慎したくらいで赦すのはもってのほかであると考えていた節が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Similar in manner to Saigo, some evidence supports the idea of Okubo lobbying for consideration of a more severe punishment, than the confinement of Yoshinobu to his own residence (or house arrest); that was not sufficient.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similarly to Saigo, some evidence supports the idea of Okubo lobbying for consideration of a more severe punishment than confinement of Yoshinobu to his own residence (or house arrest) and that it was not sufficient.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similarly to Saigo, some evidence supports the idea of Okubo lobbying for consideration of a more severe punishment than confinement of Yoshinobu to his own residence (or house arrest) and that it was not sufficient.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>このように、東征軍の目的は単に江戸城の奪取のみに留まらず、徳川慶喜（およびそれに加担した松平容保・松平定敬）への処罰であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taken from these examples on the opinions of Saigo and Okubo, the object of &apos;the expeditionary force to the east&apos; was not only in seizing the Edo Castle; there was also the element for punishment of Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA (and his supporters, Katamori MATSUDAIRA and Sadaaki MATSUDAIRA).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taken from these examples of opinions of Saigo and Okubo, the object of &apos;the expeditionary force to the east&apos; was not only to seize Edo Castle, but also in punishing Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA (and his supporters, Katamori MATSUDAIRA, and Sadaaki MATSUDAIRA).</e>
<cmt>grammar,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taken from these examples of opinions of Saigo and Okubo, the object of &apos;the expeditionary force to the east&apos; was not only to seize Edo-jo Castle, but also in punishing Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA (and his supporters, Katamori MATSUDAIRA, and Sadaaki MATSUDAIRA).</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーションを半角に修正、Edo-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>および徳川家の存廃と常にセットとして語られるべき問題であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, there was the additional issue up for consideration, how to proceed with the elimination of the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, there was the additional issue up for consideration, how to proceed with the elimination of the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, there was the additional issue up for consideration, how to proceed with the elimination of the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="68">
<j>一方、長州藩の木戸孝允・広沢真臣らは徳川慶喜個人に対しては寛典論を想定していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Takayoshi KIDO and Saneomi HIROSAWA from Choshu Domain individually supported a more lenient treatment policy for Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Takayoshi KIDO and Saneomi HIROSAWA from Choshu Domain individually supported a more lenient treatment policy for Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Takayoshi KIDO and Saneomi HIROSAWA from the Choshu Domain individually supported a more lenient treatment policy for Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>the Choshu Domainとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>また公議政体派の山内容堂・松平春嶽・伊達宗城（前宇和島藩主）ら諸侯も、心情的にまだ慶喜への親近感もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, Yodo YAMAUCHI, Shungaku MATSUDAIRA, and Munenari DATE (the former lord of Uwajima Domain), these were lords who continued to favor a parliamentary regime, each, still felt a strong affinity in their hearts for Yashinobu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, Yodo YAMAUCHI, Shungaku MATSUDAIRA, and Munenari DATE (the former lord of Uwajima Domain), lords who continued to favor a parliamentary regime, each still felt a strong affinity in their hearts for Yashinobu.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, Yodo YAMAUCHI, Shungaku MATSUDAIRA, and Munenari DATE (the former lord of the Uwajima Domain), lords who continued to favor a parliamentary regime, each still felt a strong affinity in their hearts for Yoshinobu.</e>
<cmt>the Uwajima Domainとし、Yashinobu→Yoshinobuに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>そのため、慶喜の死罪および徳川家改易などの厳罰には反対していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, they stood against the severe penalties of Capital crime lobbied upon Yoshinobu, and changing the ranking of the Tokugawa family</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, they stood against the severe penalties of Capital crime lobbied upon Yoshinobu, and the changing in the ranking of the Tokugawa family</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, they stood against the severe penalties of Capital crime lobbied upon Yoshinobu, and the changing in the ranking of the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="71">
<j>新政府はすでに東海道・東山道・北陸道の三道から江戸を攻撃すべく出撃させていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The new government&apos;s side had already prepared for the attack upon Edo region from the three main Roads, Tokaido Road, Tosando Road and the Hokurikudo Road.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The new government&apos;s side had already prepared for the attack upon Edo region from the three main Roads, Tokaido Road, Tosando Road and the Hokurikudo Road.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The new government&apos;s side had already prepared for the attack upon Edo region from the three main roads, Tokaido Road, Tosando Road and the Hokurikudo Road.</e>
<cmt>three main roadsとし、全角アポストロフィーを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>正月5日には橋本実梁を東海道鎮撫総督に任命して出撃させていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 5th (actually January 29th, 1868), the new government assigned Saneyana HASHIMOTO as the pacification governor-general of the Tokaido Road.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 5th (actually January 29th, 1868), the new government assigned Saneyana HASHIMOTO as the pacification governor-general of the Tokaido Road.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 5th, the new government assigned Saneyana HASHIMOTO as the pacification governor-general of the Tokaido Road.</e>
<cmt>(actually January 29th, 1868)を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>同9日には岩倉具定を東山道鎮撫総督に、高倉永さちを北陸道鎮撫総督に任命して出撃させていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, on January 9th (actually February 2nd, 1868), the new government assigned Tomosada IWAKURA as the pacification governor-general of the Tousando Road, then came the assignment of Nagasachi TAKAKURA, as the pacification governor-general of the Hokurikudo Road giving the order for them to sortie.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, on January 9th (actually February 2nd, 1868), the new government assigned Tomosada IWAKURA as the pacification governor-general of the Tousando Road, then came the assignment of Nagasachi TAKAKURA, as the pacification governor-general of the Hokurikudo Road giving the order for them to sortie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, on January 9th, the new government assigned Tomosada IWAKURA as the pacification governor-general of the Tosando Road, then came the assignment of Nagasachi TAKAKURA, as the pacification governor-general of the Hokurikudo Road giving the order for them to sortie.</e>
<cmt>(actually February 2nd, 1868)を削除、Tousando→Tosandoに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>が、2月6日天皇親征の方針が決まると、それまでの東海道・東山道・北陸道鎮撫総督は先鋒総督兼鎮撫使に改称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, on February 6th (February 28th, 1868), the Emperor implemented a change in policy, he decider to lead the army and to conquer Tokugawa Family; these former pacification governor-generals of Tokaido, Tousando, and Hokurikudo had their positions adjusted to Spearhead governor and Chinbushi (temporary government post).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, on February 6th (February 28th, 1868), the Emperor implemented a change in policy, he decider to lead the army and to conquer Tokugawa Family; these former pacification governor-generals of Tokaido, Tousando, and Hokurikudo had their positions adjusted to Spearhead governor and Chinbushi (temporary government post).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, on February 6th, the Emperor implemented a change in policy, he decider to lead the army and to conquer Tokugawa family; these former pacification governor-generals of Tokaido, Tosando, and Hokurikudo had their positions adjusted to Spearhead governor and Chinbushi (temporary government post).</e>
<cmt>(February 28th, 1868)削除、the Tokuga familyとし、Tousando→Tosandoに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>2月9日には有栖川宮熾仁親王が東征大総督に任命される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 9th (March 2nd, 1868), &apos;Imperial Prince Arisugawa no Miya Taruhito&apos; was assigned as the Tousei Dai Soutoku (the commander of the temporary army to suppress any remaining power of Tokugawa Edo Bakufu Army).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 9th (March 2nd, 1868), &apos;Imperial Prince Arisugawa no Miya Taruhito&apos; was assigned as the Tousei Dai Soutoku (the commander of the temporary army to suppress any remaining power of Tokugawa Edo Bakufu Army).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 9th (March 2nd, 1868), Imperial Prince Arisugawanomiya Taruhito was assigned as the Tosei Dai Sotoku (the commander of the temporary army to suppress any remaining power of the Tokugawa Edo bakufu army).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション削除、Arisugawa no Miya→Arisugawanomiya、Tousei Dai Soutoku→Tosei Dai Sotokuに修正、the Tokugawa Edo bakufu armyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>先の鎮撫使はすべて大総督府の下に組み入れられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All of those Chinbushi mentioned earlier were positioned under the grand government general.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All of those Chinbushi mentioned earlier were positioned under the grand government general.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All of those Chinbushi mentioned earlier were positioned under the grand government general.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>その上、東征大総督には江戸城・徳川家の件のみならず東日本に関わる裁量のほぼ全権が与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, the Tousei Dai Soutoku had been given controlling power over Edo Castle and the Tokugawa Family; furthermore, the Tousei Dai Soutoku had full power in the management in the affairs for the East region of Japan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, the Tousei Dai Soutoku had been given the controlling power over Edo Castle and the Tokugawa Family; furthermore, the Tousei Dai Soutoku had full power in the management in the affairs for the Eastern region of Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the Tosei Dai Sotoku had been given the controlling power over Edo-jo Castle and the Tokugawa family; furthermore, the Tosei Dai Sotoku had full power in the management in the affairs for the Eastern region of Japan.</e>
<cmt>Tousei Dai Soutoku→Tosei Dai Sotokuに修正、Edo-jo Castle、the Tokugawa familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>東征大総督府参謀には、正親町公董・西四辻公業（公家）・広沢真臣（長州）が任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The new government assigned Kintada OGIMACHI, Kiminari NISHIYOTSUTSUJI (a Court noble), and Saneomi HIROSAWA (Choshu) as staff officers to the Tousei Dai Soutoku Fu (the Headquarter for the temporary army; this military force was established by the new government to suppress the power of the Tokugawa Edo Bakufu Army).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The new government assigned Kintada OGIMACHI, Kiminari NISHIYOTSUTSUJI (a Court noble), and Saneomi HIROSAWA (Choshu) as staff officers to the Tousei Dai Soutoku Fu (the Headquarter for the temporary army; this military force was established by the new government to suppress the power of the Tokugawa Edo Bakufu Army).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The new government assigned Kintada OGIMACHI, Kiminari NISHIYOTSUTSUJI (a Court noble), and Saneomi HIROSAWA (Choshu) as staff officers to the Tosei Dai Sotoku Fu (the Headquarter for the temporary army; this military force was established by the new government to suppress the power of the Tokugawa Edo bakufu army).</e>
<cmt>Tousei Dai Soutoku Fu→Tosei Dai Sotoku Fuに修正、the Tokugawa Edo bakufu armyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>しかし、寛典論の広沢は12日に辞退し、代わって14日強硬派の西郷隆盛（薩摩）と林通顕（宇和島）が補任された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hirosawa, who had favored a more lenient treatment policy, resigned his position on February 12th (actually March 5th, 1868); the replacements were Hirosawa, Takamori SAIGO (Satsuma) and Michiaki HAYASHI (Uwajima) and they were appointed to this office on February 15th (actually March 8th, 1868).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hirosawa, who had favored a more lenient treatment policy, resigned his position on February 12th (actually March 5th, 1868); the replacements were Hirosawa, Takamori SAIGO (Satsuma), and Michiaki HAYASHI (Uwajima), and they were appointed to this office on February 15th (actually March 8, 1868).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hirosawa, who had favored a more lenient treatment policy, resigned his position on February 12th; the replacements for Hirosawa were Takamori SAIGO (Satsuma), and Michiaki HAYASHI (Uwajima), and they were appointed to this office on February 15th.</e>
<cmt>(actually March 5th, 1868) (actually March 8, 1868)削除、the replacements were Hirosawa→the replacements for Hirosawa wereに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>2月15日、東征大総督は京都を進発して東下を開始し、3月5日には駿府に到着。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 15th (actually March 8th, 1868), &apos;Tousei Dai Soutoku&apos; began to relocate the Army from Kyoto; his purpose was to reposition the army to the west, and he would reach Sunpu on March 5th (actually March 28th, 1868).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 15th (actually March 8, 1868), &apos;Tousei Dai Soutoku&apos; began to relocate the Army from Kyoto; his purpose was to reposition the army to the west, and he would reach Sunpu on March 5th (actually March 28, 1868).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 15th, Tosei Dai Sotoku began to relocate the army from Kyoto; his purpose was to reposition the army to the west, and he would reach Sunpu on March 5th.</e>
<cmt>(actually March 8, 1868) (actually March 28, 1868)削除、クォーテーション削除、Tosei Dai Sotokuに修正、the Army→the armyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>翌日には江戸城総攻撃の日付が3月15日と決定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following day, the new government decided upon the date for the general attack on Edo Castle, this was &quot;March 15th (actually April 5th, 1868).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following day, the new government decided upon the date for the general attack on Edo Castle, this was &quot;March 15th (actually April 5, 1868).&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following day, the new government decided upon the date for the general attack on Edo-jo Castle, this was &quot;March 15th.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Edo-jo Castleとし、(actually April 5, 1868)削除、全角クォーテーションを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="82">
<j>徳川家側の動き</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The movements on Tokugawa Family side</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Movements on the Tokugawa Family side</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Movements on the Tokugawa family side</e>
<cmt>the Tokugawa familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>諸隊の脱走と抗戦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The desertion of troops and battle defense</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The desertion of troops and battle defense</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The desertion of troops and battle defense</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>2月5日には伝習隊の歩兵400名が八王子方面に脱走（後に大鳥圭介軍に合流する）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 5th (actually February 27th, 1868), four hundred infantry soldiers from the Denshutai (Army of Tokugawa Bakufu) strategically deserted to the Hachioji region (Later, these troops were to join up with the Armey of Keisuke OTORI.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 5th (actually February 27, 1868), four hundred infantry soldiers from the Denshutai (Army of Tokugawa Bakufu) strategically deserted to the Hachioji region (Later, these troops were to join up with the Army of Keisuke OTORI.).</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 5th, four hundred infantry soldiers from the Denshutai (army of the Tokugawa shogunate) strategically deserted to the Hachioji region (Later, these troops were to join up with the army of Keisuke OTORI.).</e>
<cmt>(actually February 27, 1868)削除、Army of Tokugawa Bakufu→army of the Tokugawa shogunate、the Army→the armyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>また2月7日夜、旧幕府兵の一部（歩兵第11・12連隊）が脱走。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, on the night of February 7th (actually February 29th, 1868), parts of the former Bakufu Army (infantry soldiers from the eleventh and twelfth regiments) deserted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, on the night of February 7th (actually February 29, 1868), parts of the former Bakufu Army (infantry soldiers from the eleventh and twelfth regiments) deserted.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, on the night of February 7th, parts of the former bakufu army (infantry soldiers from the eleventh and twelfth regiments) deserted.</e>
<cmt>(actually February 29, 1868)削除、the former bakufu armyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>これらは歩兵頭古屋作左衛門に統率されて同月末、羽生陣屋（埼玉県羽生市）に1800人が結集した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakusaemon FURUYA as commander of the infantry gathered together the deserting troops, up to a total of eighteen hundred soldiers to Habu jinya (a regional government office; this place is currently located in Hanyu City, Saitama Prefecture) by the end of the month (March 21st, 1868).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakusaemon FURUYA as commander of the infantry gathered together the deserting troops, up to a total of eighteen hundred soldiers to Habu jinya (a regional government office; this place is currently located in Hanyu City, Saitama Prefecture) by the end of the month (March 21, 1868).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakusaemon FURUYA as commander of the infantry gathered together the deserting troops, up to a total of eighteen hundred soldiers to Habu jinya (a regional government office; this place is currently located in Hanyu City, Saitama Prefecture) by the end of the month.</e>
<cmt>(March 21, 1868)削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>3月8日には下野国簗田（栃木県足利市梁田町）で東征軍と戦って敗れた（古屋はのちに今井信郎らと衝鋒隊を結成し、東北戦争・箱館戦争に従軍する）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 8th (actually March 31st, 1868), these deserting troops fighting with &apos;the expeditionary force to the east&apos; at the Yanada in Shimotsuke Province (The current location is in Yanada-cho, Ashikaga City, Tochigi Prefecture) were defeated (Later, Furuya formed the &quot;Shohotai&quot; unit with Nobuo IMAI, serving in the Tohoku and Hakodate Wars.).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 8th (actually March 31, 1868), these deserting troops fighting with &apos;the expeditionary force to the east&apos; at the Yanada in Shimotsuke Province (The current location is in Yanada-cho, Ashikaga City, Tochigi Prefecture) were defeated (Later, Furuya formed the &quot;Shohotai&quot; unit with Nobuo IMAI, serving in the Tohoku and Hakodate Wars.).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 8th, these deserting troops fighting with &apos;the expeditionary force to the east&apos; at the Yanada in Shimotsuke Province (The current location is in Yanada-cho, Ashikaga City, Tochigi Prefecture) were defeated (Later, Furuya formed the &quot;Shohotai&quot; unit with Nobuo IMAI, serving in the Tohoku and Hakodate Wars.).</e>
<cmt>(actually March 31, 1868)削除。全角クォーテーションを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="88">
<j>また、新選組の近藤勇・土方歳三らも甲陽鎮撫隊と称して、甲州街道を進撃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, Isami KONDO and Toshizo HIJIKATA of the Shinsengumi (a group who guarded Kyoto during the end of Tokugawa Shogunate) formed an army unit under the name of &quot;Koyo Chinbutai&quot; and advanced this army on to Koshu-kaido Road.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, Isami KONDO and Toshizo HIJIKATA of the Shinsengumi (a group who guarded Kyoto during the end of Tokugawa Shogunate) formed an army unit under the name of &quot;Koyo Chinbutai&quot; and advanced this army on to Koshu-kaido Road.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, Isami KONDO and Toshizo HIJIKATA of the Shinsengumi (a group who guarded Kyoto during the end of the Tokugawa shogunate) formed an army unit under the name of &quot;Koyo Chinbutai&quot; and advanced this army on to Koshu-kaido Road.</e>
<cmt>the Tokugawa shogunateとし、全角クォーテーションを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>甲府城を占拠して東征軍を迎撃しようと試みる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &apos;Koyo Chinbutai&apos; army unit planned to take over (occupy) Kofu Castle then would able to lie in wait to attack the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; from the Castles&apos; advantage; but the &apos;Koyo Chinbutai&apos; engaged the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; earlier at Katsunuma, losing the battle on March 6th (actually March 29th, 1868).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &apos;Koyo Chinbutai&apos; army unit planned to take over (occupy) Kofu Castle then would able to lie in wait to attack the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; from the Castles&apos; advantage; but the &apos;Koyo Chinbutai&apos; engaged the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; earlier at Katsunuma, losing the battle on March 6th (actually March 29, 1868).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;Koyo Chinbutai&apos; army unit planned to take over (occupy) Kofu-jo Castle then would able to lie in wait to attack the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; from the Castles&apos; advantage.</e>
<cmt>Kofu-jo Castleとし、全角クォーテーション・アポストロフィーを半角に修正、原文に合わせ訳文の一部を次行に移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>が、3月6日勝沼で東征軍と戦闘して敗れ、下総国流山（千葉県流山市）へ転戦した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, &apos;Koyo Chinbutai&apos; continued to skirmish in one place after another onward toward the Nagareyama District, Shimousa Province (Currently this location is in Nagareyama City, Chiba Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, &apos;Koyo Chinbutai&apos; continued to skirmish in one place after another onward toward the Nagareyama District, Shimousa Province (Currently this location is Nagareyama City, Chiba Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the &apos;Koyo Chinbutai&apos; engaged the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; earlier at Katsunuma, losing the battle on March 6th; then, &apos;Koyo Chinbutai&apos; continued to skirmish in one place after another onward toward the Nagareyama District, Shimosa Province (Currently this location is Nagareyama City, Chiba Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>but→Howeverに変更、全角クォーテーションを半角に修正、(actually March 29, 1868)削除、Shimousa→Shimosaに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="91">
<j>これらの暴発は、陸軍総裁勝海舟の暗黙の承認や支援を得て行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaishu KATSU, the Rikugun Sosai (the president of the Bakufu Army), was cognizant of the spontaneous battles fought by the individually formed army units, and from this tacit understanding he came to support the battles of the individual units.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaishu KATSU, the Rikugun Sosai (the president of the Bakufu Army), was cognizant of the spontaneous battles fought by the individually formed army units, and from this tacit understanding he came to support the battles of the individual units.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaishu KATSU, the Rikugun Sosai was cognizant of the spontaneous battles fought by the individually formed army units, and from this tacit understanding he came to support the battles of the individual units.</e>
<cmt>Rikugun Sosai→既出のため補足削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>いずれも兵数・装備の質から東征軍には全く歯が立たないことを見越したうえで出撃していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due in greater part to the smaller numbers of their troops and inferior quality of their equipment, each individual unit fully comprehended these apparent disadvantages, but rallied their forces, nevertheless.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due in greater part to the smaller numbers of their troops and inferior quality of their equipment, each individual unit fully comprehended these apparent disadvantages, but rallied their forces, nevertheless.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due in greater part to the smaller numbers of their troops and inferior quality of their equipment, each individual unit fully comprehended these apparent disadvantages, but rallied their forces, nevertheless.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>恭順への不満派の江戸からの排除という目的もあったと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Historians and experts assume that the Tokugawa Edo Family side may have allowed for these individual battles to purposely expose the party who was dissatisfied with &apos;the coming allegiance of the new government&apos; subsequently excluding them from the Edo region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historians and experts assume that the Tokugawa Edo Family side may have allowed for these individual battles to purposely expose the parties dissatisfied with &apos;the coming allegiance of the new government&apos; subsequently excluding them from the Edo region.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historians and experts assume that the Tokugawa family side may have allowed for these individual battles to purposely expose the parties dissatisfied with &apos;the coming allegiance of the new government&apos; subsequently excluding them from the Edo region.</e>
<cmt>the Tokugawa Edo Family side→the Tokugawa family sideとし、全角クォーテーションを半角に修正、余分なスペース消去しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="94">
<j>天璋院・静寛院・輪王寺宮の歎願</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The plea from Tenshoin, Seikanin (Princess Kazu), and &apos;Rinoji no Miiya&apos; (Prince Kitashirakawa Yoshihisa)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The plea from Tenshoin, Seikanin (Princess Kazu), and &apos;Rinoji no Miiya&apos; (Prince Kitashirakawa Yoshihisa)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The plea from Tenshoin, Seikanin, and Rinojinomiya</e>
<cmt>(Princess Kazu) (Prince Kitashirakawa Yoshihisa) →原文にないため削除、Rinojinomiyaとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="95">
<j>13代将軍徳川家定正室として江戸城大奥の総責任者であった天璋院（近衛敬子）は、薩摩国の出身で島津斉彬の養女であった縁がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the seishitsu (legal wife) of the thirteenth Shogun, Iesada TOKUGAWA, Tenshoin (Sumiko KONOE) was the person chiefly responsible for management of affairs inside Edo Castle Ooku (the inner palace of Edo Castle); in addition, she was from Satsuma Province and was the adopted daughter of Nariakira SHIMAZU, so she had connections with Satsuma (the new government side).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the seishitsu (legal wife) of the thirteenth Shogun, Iesada TOKUGAWA, Tenshoin (Sumiko KONOE) was the person chiefly responsible for management of affairs inside Edo Castle Ooku (the inner palace of Edo Castle); in addition, she was from Satsuma Province and was the adopted daughter of Nariakira SHIMAZU, so she had connections with Satsuma (the new government side).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the seishitsu (legal wife) of the thirteenth Shogun, Iesada TOKUGAWA, Tenshoin (Sumiko KONOE) was the person chiefly responsible for management of affairs inside Edo-jo Castle Ooku (the inner palace of Edo-jo Castle); in addition, she was from Satsuma Province and was the adopted daughter of Nariakira SHIMAZU, so she had connections with Satsuma (the new government side).</e>
<cmt>Edo-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>また明治天皇の叔母にあたる14代将軍徳川家茂正室の和宮親子内親王も東征大総督有栖川宮とかつて婚約者であった縁がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, Imperial Princess Kazunomiya Chikako (Princess Kazu) was the seishitsu (legal wife) of the fourteenth Shogun, Iemochi TOKUGAWA, and was the aunt of the Emperor Meiji; because she was also once the fiancée of &apos;Imperial Prince Arisugawa,&apos; the Tousei Dai Soutoku (the commander of temporary army assigned to suppress the power of Tokugawa Edo Bakufu Army), she had connections to the Imperial court (the new government side).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, Imperial Princess Kazunomiya Chikako (Princess Kazu) was the seishitsu (legal wife) of the fourteenth Shogun, Iemochi TOKUGAWA, and was the aunt of the Emperor Meiji; because she was also once the fiancée of &apos;Imperial Prince Arisugawa,&apos; the Tousei Dai Soutoku (the commander of temporary army assigned to suppress the power of Tokugawa Edo Bakufu Army), she had connections to the Imperial court (the new government side).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, Imperial Princess Kazunomiya Chikako (Seikanin) was the seishitsu (legal wife) of the fourteenth Shogun, Iemochi TOKUGAWA, and was the aunt of the Emperor Meiji; because she was also once the fiancée of Prince Arisugawanomiya, the Tosei Dai Sotoku, she had connections to the Imperial Court (the new government side).</e>
<cmt>(Princess Kazu)→(Seikanin)とし、‘Imperial Prince Arisugawa’→Prince Arisugawanomiya、Tosei Dai Soutoku→Tosei Dai Sotokuとし既出のため補足削除、the Imperial Courtとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>そのため、それぞれ東征軍との縁故がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, each of these women was connected to the &apos;expeditionary force to the east.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, each of these women was connected to the &apos;expeditionary force to the east.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, each of these women was connected to the &apos;expeditionary force to the east.&apos;</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーションを半角に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>また上野寛永寺には前年に京都から入山した輪王寺宮公現法親王（後の北白川宮能久親王）がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, the &apos;Cloistered Imperial Prince Rinoji no Miya Kogen&apos; (later, he became Imperial Prince Kitashirakawa no Miya Yoshihisa) had entered into the Ueno Kanei-ji Temple, as a monk priest from Kyoto the previous year.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, the &apos;Cloistered Imperial Prince Rinoji no Miya Kogen&apos; (later, he became Imperial Prince Kitashirakawa no Miya Yoshihisa) had entered Ueno Kanei-ji Temple, as a monk priest from Kyoto, the previous year.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the Cloistered Imperial Prince Rinojinomiya Kogen (later, he became Imperial Prince Kitashirakawanomiya Yoshihisa) had entered Ueno Kanei-ji Temple, as a monk priest from Kyoto, the previous year.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション削除、Rinojinomiya、Kitashirakawanomiya としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>藁にもすがる思いの慶喜はこれらの人物を通じて、東征軍に対し助命ならびに徳川家存続の歎願を立て続けに出している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshinobu was becoming more desperate, took to clutching at straws, so he requested petitions for the sparing of his life, and the possible continuance of the Tokugawa Family&apos;s existence; this was sent to the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; continuously through these significant figures and nobles connections.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshinobu was becoming more desperate, took to clutching at straws, so he requested petitions for the sparing of his life, and the possible continuance of the Tokugawa Family&apos;s existence; this was sent to the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; continuously through these significant figures and nobles connections.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshinobu was becoming more desperate, took to clutching at straws, so he requested petitions for the sparing of his life, and the possible continuance of the Tokugawa family&apos;s existence; this was sent to the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; continuously through these significant figures and nobles connections.</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーション・アポストロフィーを半角に修正、the Tokugawa familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="100">
<j>正月21日、静寛院は慶喜の歎願書に橋本実麗・橋本実梁父子宛の自筆歎願書を添えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 21st (actually February 14th, 1868), &apos;Seikan in no Miya&apos; (Princess Kazu) added Yoshinobu&apos;s petition to her own written petition addressed to Saneakira HASHIMOTO and Saneyana HASHIMOTO, father and son.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 21st (actually February 14, 1868), &apos;Seikan in no Miya&apos; (Princess Kazu) added Yoshinobu&apos;s petition to her own written petition addressed to Saneakira HASHIMOTO and Saneyana HASHIMOTO, father and son.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 21st, Seikanin no miya added Yoshinobu&apos;s petition to her own written petition addressed to Saneakira HASHIMOTO and Saneyana HASHIMOTO, father and son.</e>
<cmt>(actually February 14, 1868)削除、Seikanin no miyaとし(Princess Kazu)削除、クォーテーション削除、全角アポストロフィーを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>それを、侍女の土御門藤子を使者として遣わした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, she sent Fujiko TSUCHIMIKADO, a lady&apos;s maid, as her envoy to the &apos;expeditionary force to the east.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, she sent Fujiko TSUCHIMIKADO, a lady in waiting, as her envoy to the &apos;expeditionary force to the east.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, she sent Fujiko TSUCHIMIKADO, a lady in waiting, as her envoy to the &apos;expeditionary force to the east.&apos;</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーションを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>東海道先鋒総督の橋本実梁は、2月1日に在陣中の桑名（三重県桑名市）でこの書状を受け取る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 1st, (actually February 21st, 1868), Saneyana HASHIMOTO, the Spearhead governor of the Tokai-do Road, received these petitions while he was at the front in Kuwana (currently, the location is in Kuwana City, Mie Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 1st, (actually February 21, 1868), Saneyana HASHIMOTO, the Spearhead governor of the Tokai-do Road, received these petitions while he was at the front in Kuwana (currently, the location is in Kuwana City, Mie Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 1st, Saneyana HASHIMOTO, the Spearhead governor of the Tokaido Road, received these petitions while he was at the front in Kuwana (currently, the location is in Kuwana City, Mie Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>(actually February 21, 1868)削除、カンマ削除、表記統一のため、Tokaido Roadとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>しかし、参謀西郷隆盛はいかに和宮からの歎願であったとしても所詮は賊徒からの申し分であるとして歯牙にもかけなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, staff officer, Takamori SAIGO, dismissed the petition instantly without any hesitation; although the petition was from Princess Kazunomiya, Saigo thought after all the petition came from the rebel Yoshinobu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, staff officer Takamori SAIGO dismissed the petition instantly without any hesitation, although the petition was from Princess Kazunomiya, Saigo thought after all the petition came from the rebel Yoshinobu.</e>
<cmt>spacing, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, staff officer Takamori SAIGO dismissed the petition instantly without any hesitation, although the petition was from Princess Kazunomiya, Saigo thought after all the petition came from the rebel Yoshinobu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>知らせを受けた京都の大久保もまた同意見であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Okubo&apos;s opinion from Kyoto was the same as Saigo, once he received the news.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Okubo&apos;s opinion from Kyoto was the same as Saigo, once he received the news.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Okubo&apos;s opinion from Kyoto was the same as Saigo, once he received the news.</e>
<cmt>全角アポストロフィーを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>土御門藤子はやむなく上京し、6日に入京している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fujiko TSUCHIMIKADO was compelled to go to Kyoto, entering the Capital on February 6th (actually February, 28th, 1868).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fujiko TSUCHIMIKADO was compelled to go to Kyoto, entering the Capital on February 6th (actually February, 28, 1868).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fujiko TSUCHIMIKADO was compelled to go to Kyoto, entering the Capital on February 6th.</e>
<cmt>(actually February, 28, 1868)削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>議定長谷信篤・参与中院通富らに静寛院の歎願を訴えた結果、万里小路博房から岩倉具視へも伝わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After her appeal for the petition to the following people; &apos;Seikan in no Miya&apos; (Princess Kazu) to the Gijo (official post) Nobuatsu NAGATANI and the Sanyo (councilor) Michitomi NAKANOIN, notification of the petition came to Tomomi IWAKURA via Hirofusa MADENOKOJI.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After her appeal for the petition to the following people; &apos;Seikan in no Miya&apos; (Princess Kazu) to the Gijo (official post) Nobuatsu NAGATANI and the Sanyo (councilor) Michitomi NAKANOIN, notification of the petition came to Tomomi IWAKURA via Hirofusa MADENOKOJI.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After her appeal for the petition of Seikanin to the Gijo (official post) Nobuatsu NAGATANI and the Sanyo (councilor) Michitomi NAKANOIN, notification of the petition came to Tomomi IWAKURA via Hirofusa MADENOKOJI.</e>
<cmt>‘Seikan in no Miya’ (Princess Kazu)→Seikaninとし、原文に沿わない部分を訳し直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>16日橋本実麗に対して口頭書ながら徳川家存続の内諾を得る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 16th (actually March 9th, 1868), although this would be an oral agreement, Fujiko TSUCHIMIKADO gained informal consent about for the continuance of the Tokugawa Family from Saneakira HASHIMOTO.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 16th (actually March 9, 1868), although this would be an oral agreement, Fujiko TSUCHIMIKADO gained informal consent for the continuance of the Tokugawa Family from Saneakira HASHIMOTO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 16th, although this would be an oral agreement, Fujiko TSUCHIMIKADO gained informal consent for the continuance of the Tokugawa family from Saneakira HASHIMOTO.</e>
<cmt>(actually March 9, 1868)削除、the Tokugawa familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>8日に京都を発った藤子は2月30日に江戸へ戻り、静寛院に復命している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She left Kyoto on February 18th (actually March 11th, 1868), retuned Edo by February 30th (March 23rd, 1868), and reported on her mission to &apos;Seikan in no Miya&apos; (Princess Kazu).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She left Kyoto on February 18th (actually March 11, 1868), retuned to Edo by February 30th (March 23, 1868), and reported on her mission to &apos;Seikan in no Miya&apos; (Princess Kazu).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She left Kyoto on February 8th, retuned to Edo by February 30th, and reported on her mission to Seikanin.</e>
<cmt>February 18th→February 8thに修正、(actually March 11, 1868) (March 23, 1868)削除、‘Seikan in no Miya’ (Princess Kazu)→Seikaninとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="109">
<j>いっぽう輪王寺宮公現法親王は2月21日、江戸を発って東海道を西に上った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, &apos;Cloistered Imperial Prince Rinojinomiya Kogen&apos; left Edo on February 21st (actually March 14th, 1868) taking the trip westward along the Tokai-do Road.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the &apos;Cloistered Imperial Prince Rinojinomiya Kogen&apos; left Edo on February 21st (actually March 14, 1868) westward along the Tokai-do Road.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the Cloistered Imperial Prince Rinojinomiya Kogen left Edo on February 21st westward along the Tokaido Road.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション削除、(actually March 14, 1868) 削除、表記統一のためTokaido Roadとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>3月7日には駿府で大総督有栖川宮熾仁親王と対面し、慶喜の謝罪状と自身の歎願書を差し出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, on March 7th (actually March 30th, 1868), the prince had a meeting with the Dai Soutoku (the commander of temporary army) and &apos;Imperial Prince Arisugawa no Miya Taruhito,&apos; at the Sunpu, there he presented two letters to &apos;Imperial Prince Arisugawa no Miya Taruhito&apos;: One, was an apology letter from Yoshinobu, the other one was his own petition for Yoshinobu and the Tokugawa Family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, on March 7th (actually March 30, 1868), the prince had a meeting with the Dai Soutoku (the commander of the temporary army) and &apos;Imperial Prince Arisugawa no Miya Taruhito,&apos; at the Sunpu, there he presented two letters to &apos;Imperial Prince Arisugawa no Miya Taruhito;&apos; One, was an apology letter from Yoshinobu, the other one was his own petition for Yoshinobu and the Tokugawa Family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, on March 7th, the prince had a meeting with the Dai Sotoku (the commander of the temporary army) Imperial Prince Arisugawanomiya Taruhito, at Sunpu, there he presented two letters to Imperial Prince Arisugawanomiya Taruhito; One, was an apology letter from Yoshinobu, the other one was his own petition for Yoshinobu and the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>(actually March 30, 1868)削除、Dai Soutoku→Dai Sotokuに修正、and削除、クォーテーション削除、Arisugawanomiya Taruhito、the Tokugawa family、at the Sunpu→at Sunpuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>が、参謀西郷隆盛・林通顕らがかえって甲陽鎮撫隊による抗戦を厳しく咎めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, staff officers Takamori SAIGO and Michiaki HAYASHI severely rebuked the petition, because of the battle with the &quot;Koyo Chinbutai&quot; army unit.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, staff officers Takamori SAIGO and Michiaki HAYASHI severely rebuked the petition, because of the battle with the &quot;Koyo Chinbutai&quot; army unit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, staff officers Takamori SAIGO and Michiaki HAYASHI severely rebuked the petition, because of the battle with the &quot;Koyo Chinbutai&quot; army unit.</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーションを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>12日には大総督宮から歎願不採用が申し下された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, on February 12th (actually March 5th, 1868), the Daisotoku no Miya (the commander of the temporary army) announced the rejection of the petition.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, on February 12th (actually March 5, 1868), the Daisotoku no Miya (the commander of the temporary army) announced the rejection of the petition.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, on February 12th, the Daisotoku no Miya (the commander of the temporary army) announced the rejection of the petition.</e>
<cmt>(actually March 5, 1868)削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="113">
<j>また天璋院は慶喜個人に対してはあまり好感情を持っていなかったが、徳川家存続には熱心であり、「薩州隊長人々」に宛てて歎願書を記した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Tenshoin personally held limited empathy for Yoshinobu, due to her lack of a favorable impression of him, she was enthusiastic for the continuance of the Tokugawa Family; she wrote a petition addressed to the &quot;the commanding officers of Sasshu (Satsuma Domain).&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Tenshoin personally held little empathy for Yoshinobu, due to her lack of a favorable impression of him, she was enthusiastic for the continuance of the Tokugawa Family and she wrote a petition addressed to the &quot;the commanding officers of Sasshu (Satsuma Domain).&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Tenshoin personally held little empathy for Yoshinobu, due to her lack of a favorable impression of him, she was enthusiastic for the continuance of the Tokugawa family and she wrote a petition addressed to &quot;the commanding officers of Sasshu (Satsuma Domain).&quot;</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーションを半角に修正、the Tokugawa familyとし、theの重複分を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>また3月11日に東征軍へ使者として老女を遣わしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, on March 11th (actually April 3rd, 1868), Tenshoin sent her &apos;senior lady-in-waiting&apos; as her envoy to the &apos;expeditionary force in the east.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, on March 11th (actually April 3, 1868), Tenshoin sent her &apos;senior lady-in-waiting&apos; as her envoy to the &apos;expeditionary force in the east.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, on March 11th, Tenshoin sent her senior lady-in-waiting as her envoy to the &apos;expeditionary force in the east.&apos;</e>
<cmt>(actually April 3, 1868)削除、一部クォーテーション削除、全角クォーテーションを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>この使者は13日に帰城しているが、ほとんど影響を与えなかったようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This envoy returned to Edo Castle on March 13th (actually April 5th, 1868), apparently the petition letter would not effect the situation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This envoy returned to Edo Castle on March 13th (actually April 5, 1868), apparently the petition letter had no effect on the situation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This envoy returned to Edo-jo Castle on March 13th, apparently the petition letter had no effect on the situation.</e>
<cmt>Edo-jo Castleとし、(actually April 5, 1868)削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="116">
<j>これらの歎願の多くは結果的には却下されることが多かったが、大総督有栖川宮や参謀西郷隆盛などに何らかの心理的影響を与えた可能性もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The end result, although many of the petitions were rejected, was the possibility of directing some psychological impact upon the Dai Soutoku, &apos;Prince Arisugawa no Miya,&apos; and the staff officer, Takamori SAIGO.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The end result, although many of the petitions were rejected, was the possibility of directing some psychological impact upon the Dai Soutoku, &apos;Prince Arisugawa no Miya,&apos; and the staff officer, Takamori SAIGO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The end result, although many of the petitions were rejected, was the possibility of directing some psychological impact upon the Dai Sotoku, Prince Arisugawanomiya, and the staff officer, Takamori SAIGO.</e>
<cmt>Soutoku→Sotokuに修正、クォーテーション削除、Prince Arisugawanomiyaとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>小説やドラマなどでは積極的にエピソードとして採用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, many writers, novelist and dramatist inserted the contextual elements of the petitions into their dramatic works.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, many writers, novelist and dramatist inserted the contextual elements of the petitions into their dramatic works.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, many writers, novelist and dramatist inserted the contextual elements of the petitions into their dramatic works.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="118">
<j>山岡鉄太郎の準備交渉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The negotiation preparation of Tetsutaro YAMAOKA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The negotiation prepared by Tetsutaro YAMAOKA</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The negotiation prepared by Tetsutaro YAMAOKA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="119">
<j>差し迫る東征軍に対し、寛永寺で謹慎中の徳川慶喜を護衛していた高橋泥舟の義弟で精鋭隊頭の山岡鉄舟。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to deal with an imminent threat from the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; as it approached Edo, Yoshinobu selected Tesshu YAMAOKA (Tesshu), the chief of Seieitai (an elite army force on the Bakufu side) and a brother in law to Deishu TAKAHASHI; he was guarding Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA as his envoy, while Yoshinobu confined himself in the Kanei-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to deal with an imminent threat from the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; as it approached Edo, Yoshinobu selected Tesshu YAMAOKA (Tesshu), the chief of Seieitai (an elite army force on the Bakufu side) and a brother in law to Deishu TAKAHASHI; he was guarding Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA as his envoy, while Yoshinobu confined himself in Kanei-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to deal with an imminent threat from the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; as it approached Edo, Yoshinobu selected Tesshu YAMAOKA, the chief of Seieitai (an elite army force on the bakufu side) and a brother in law to Deishu TAKAHASHI; he was guarding Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA as his envoy, while Yoshinobu confined himself in Kanei-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Tesshu YAMAOKA (Tesshu)→Tesshu YAMAOKAに修正、the bakufu sideとし、全角クォーテーションを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>その山岡鉄舟が、3月9日慶喜の意を体して、駿府まで進撃していた東征大総督府に赴くこととなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, on March 9th (actually April 1st, 1868), Tesshu YAMAOKA was on his way to the Tousei Dai Soutoku Fu (the temporary army to suppress the power of the Tokugawa Edo Bakufu Army) which was currently encamped in the Sunpu region.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, on March 9th (actually April 1, 1868), Tesshu YAMAOKA was on his way to the Tousei Dai Soutoku Fu (the temporary army to suppress the power of the Tokugawa Edo Bakufu Army) which was currently encamped in the Sunpu region.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, on March 9th, Tesshu YAMAOKA was on his way to the Tosei Dai Sotoku Fu which was currently encamped in the Sunpu region.</e>
<cmt>(actually April 1, 1868)削除、Tosei Dai Sotoku Fuに修正、既出のため補足削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>山岡は西郷を知らなかったこともあり、まず陸軍総裁勝海舟の邸を訪問する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Yamaoka would not have a chance to meet with Saigo, Yamaoka first visited the residence of Kaishu KATSU, Rikugun Sosai (the president of the Bakufu Army).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Yamaoka would not have a chance to meet with Saigo, Yamaoka first visited the residence of Kaishu KATSU, Rikugun Sosai (the president of the Bakufu Army).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Yamaoka would not have a chance to meet with Saigo, Yamaoka first visited the residence of Kaishu KATSU, Rikugun Sosai.</e>
<cmt>Rikugun Sosai→既出のため補足削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="122">
<j>勝は山岡とは初対面であったが、一見してその人物を大いに評価し、進んで西郷への書状を認める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it was the first time that Katsu met Yamaoka, he was greatly impressed with the personality of Yamaoka during their brief encounter, so he was eager to write the letter for Yamaoka addressed to Saigo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it was the first time that Katsu met Yamaoka, he was greatly impressed with the personality of Yamaoka during their brief encounter, so he was eager to write the letter for Yamaoka addressed to Saigo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it was the first time that Katsu met Yamaoka, he was greatly impressed with the personality of Yamaoka during their brief encounter, so he was eager to write the letter for Yamaoka addressed to Saigo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>それとともに、前年の薩摩藩焼き討ち事件の際に捕らわれた後、勝家に保護されていた薩摩藩士益満休之助を護衛につけて送り出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, Katsu sent Yamaoka out from his residence with an escort guard, Kyunosuke MASUMITSU; he was the feudal retainer of Satsuma but was in protective custody under Katsu&apos;s supervision, this was the result of his capture in the incident of the fire attack on the residence of the Satsuma Domain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, Katsu sent Yamaoka out from his residence with an escort guard, Kyunosuke MASUMITSU; he was the feudal retainer of Satsuma but was in protective custody under Katsu&apos;s supervision, this was the result of his capture in the incident of the fire attack on the residence of the Satsuma Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, Katsu sent Yamaoka out from his residence with an escort guard, Kyunosuke MASUMITSU; he was the feudal retainer of Satsuma but was in protective custody under Katsu&apos;s supervision, this was the result of his capture in the incident of the fire attack on the residence of the Satsuma Domain.</e>
<cmt>全角アポストロフィーを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>（山岡と益満は、かつて尊王攘夷派の浪士清河八郎が結成した虎尾の会のメンバーであり、旧知であった。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Yamaoka and Masumitsu knew each other for long time, they also used to be members of the &quot;Torao no Kai&quot; which was formed by Hachiro KIYOKAWA, a roshi saurai and also members in the &quot;Sonnojoi Ha&quot; [a political party that was a supporter to the doctrine of restoring the emperor and expelling the barbarians].)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Yamaoka and Masumitsu knew each other for long time, they also used to be members of the &quot;Torao no Kai&quot; which was formed by Hachiro KIYOKAWA, a roshi saurai and also members in the &quot;Sonnojoi Ha&quot; [a political party that was a supporter of the doctrine of restoring the emperor and expelling the barbarians].)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Yamaoka and Masumitsu knew each other for long time, they also used to be members of the &quot;Kobi no Kai&quot; which was formed by Hachiro KIYOKAWA, a roshi samurai and also members in the &quot;Sonnojoi Ha&quot; [a political party that was a supporter of the doctrine of restoring the emperor and expelling the barbarians].)</e>
<cmt>Torao no Kai→Kobi no Kai、saurai→samuraiに修正、全角クォーテーションを半角に修正しました。(参照: http://jpco.sakura.ne.jp/shishitati1/kakuhan-page1/10/10-7.htm)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="125">
<j>山岡と益満は駿府の大総督府へ急行し、参謀西郷隆盛の宿泊する旅館に乗り込み、西郷との面談を求めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamaoka and Masumitsu rushed to visit the Tousei Dai Soutoku Fu who was staying with the army at Sunp. There, Yamaoka and Masumitsu entered the Japanese hotel where Takamori SAIGO, the staff officer, was staying and requested that he meet with them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamaoka and Masumitsu rushed to visit the Tousei Dai Soutoku Fu who was staying with the army at Sunp. There, Yamaoka and Masumitsu entered the Japanese hotel where Takamori SAIGO, the staff officer, was staying and requested that he meet with them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamaoka and Masumitsu rushed to visit the Tosei Dai Sotoku Fu at Sunpu, and they entered the Japanese hotel where Takamori SAIGO, the staff officer, was staying and requested that he meet with them.</e>
<cmt>Tousei Dai Soutoku Fu→Tosei Dai Sotoku Fu、Sunp.→Sunpuに修正、原文に沿わない部分を訳し直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>すでに江戸城総攻撃の予定は3月15日と決定していたが、西郷は勝からの使者と聞いて山岡と会談を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although they were already prepared, the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; decided to set the date of the general attack on Edo Castle to &quot;March 15th (actually April 7th, 1868),&quot; Saigo was now aware of Yamaoka&apos;s status as the envoy from Katsu, so Saigo agreed to meet with Yamaoka.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although they were already prepared, the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; decided to set the date of the general attack on Edo Castle to &quot;March 15th (actually April 7, 1868),&quot; Saigo was now aware of Yamaoka&apos;s status as the envoy from Katsu, so Saigo agreed to meet with Yamaoka.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; already decided to set the date of the general attack on Edo-jo Castle to &quot;March 15th,&quot; Saigo was now aware of Yamaoka&apos;s status as the envoy from Katsu, so Saigo agreed to meet with Yamaoka.</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーション・アポストロフィーを半角に修正、(actually April 7, 1868)削除、Edo-jo Castleとし、一部訳文を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>山岡の真摯な態度に感じ入り、交渉に応じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saigo was deeply impressed by the earnest attitude of Yamaoka and was agreeable to negotiations with him.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saigo was deeply impressed by the earnest attitude of Yamaoka and was agreeable to negotiations with him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saigo was deeply impressed by the earnest attitude of Yamaoka and was agreeable to negotiations with him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>ここで初めて東征軍から徳川家へ開戦回避に向けた条件提示がなされたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was the first time the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; presented the conditions to avoiding an open war against the Tokugawa Family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the first time the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; presented the conditions to avoide an open war against the Tokugawa Family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the first time the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; presented the conditions to avoide an open war against the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーションを半角に修正、the Tokugawa familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>このとき江戸城総攻撃の回避条件として西郷から山岡へ提示されたのは以下の7箇条である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time Saigo presented the seven conditions, should they be met, to suspend and avoid the general attack about to commence on Edo Castle, Yamaoka was to consider the following:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time Saigo presented the seven conditions, should they be met, to suspend and avoid the general attack about to commence on Edo Castle, Yamaoka was to consider the following:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time Saigo presented the seven conditions, should they be met, to suspend and avoid the general attack about to commence on Edo-jo Castle, Yamaoka was to consider the following:</e>
<cmt>Edo-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="130">
<j>徳川慶喜の身柄を備前藩に預けること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Condition Article Number One: Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA would be in custody of Bizen Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Condition Article Number One: Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA would be in custody of the Bizen Domain.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Condition Article Number One: Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA would be in custody of the Bizen Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="131">
<j>江戸城を明け渡すこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Condition Article Number Two: The Tokugawa Family would evacuate the Edo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Condition Article Number Two: The Tokugawa Family would evacuate Edo Castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Condition Article Number Two: The Tokugawa family would evacuate Edo-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>The Tokugawa family、Edo-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="132">
<j>軍艦をすべて引き渡すこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Condition Article Number Three: The Tokugawa Bakufu Army would hand over all warships to the new government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Condition Article Number Three: The Tokugawa Bakufu Army would hand over all warships to the new government.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Condition Article Number Three: The Tokugawa shogunate army would hand over all warships to the new government.</e>
<cmt>The Tokugaw shogunate armyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="133">
<j>武器をすべて引き渡すこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Condition Article Number Four: The Tokugawa Bakufu Army would hand over all weapons to the new government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Condition Article Number Four: The Tokugawa Bakufu Army would hand over all weapons to the new government.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Condition Article Number Four: The Tokugawa shogunate army would hand over all weapons to the new government.</e>
<cmt>The Tokugaw shogunate armyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="134">
<j>城内の家臣は向島 (墨田区)（東京都墨田区）に移って謹慎すること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Condition Article Number Five: The retainers of the Edo Castles would move into Mukojima (Sumida Ward, Tokyo Prefecture) and would confine themselves in the respective locations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Condition Article Number Five: The retainers of the Edo Castle would move into Mukojima (Sumida Ward, Tokyo Prefecture) and would confine themselves in the respective locations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Condition Article Number Five: The retainers of the Edo-jo Castle would move into Mukojima (Sumida Ward, Tokyo Prefecture) and would confine themselves in the respective locations.</e>
<cmt>Edo-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="32">
<sen id="135">
<j>徳川慶喜の暴挙を補佐した人物を厳しく調査し、処罰すること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Condition Article Number Six: Any personnel who supported the reckless actions of Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA would be subject to severe investigation and then would be subject to severe punishment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Condition Article Number Six: Any personnel who supported the reckless actions of Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA would be subject to severe investigation and then would be subject to severe punishment.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Condition Article Number Six: Any personnel who supported the reckless actions of Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA would be subject to severe investigation and then would be subject to severe punishment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="33">
<sen id="136">
<j>暴発の徒が手に余る場合、官軍が鎮圧すること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Condition Article Number Seven: The Imperial army would suppress any accidental violence initiated by the retainers or soldiers of the Tokugawa Family or the Tokugawa Bakufu Army, should the Tokugawa Family not control the violence through use of its own power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Condition Article Number Seven: The Imperial army would suppress any accidental violence initiated by the retainers or soldiers of the Tokugawa Family or the Tokugawa Bakufu Army, should the Tokugawa Family not control the violence through use of its own power.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Condition Article Number Seven: The Imperial army would suppress any accidental violence initiated by the retainers or soldiers of the Tokugawa shogunate army, should the Tokugawa family not control the violence through use of its own power.</e>
<cmt>the Tokugawa Family or the Tokugawa Bakufu Army→the Tokugawa shogunate armyとし、the Tokugawa familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="34">
<sen id="137">
<j>山岡は上記7箇条のうち第一条を除く6箇条の受け入れは示した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamaoka accepted the six articles out of the seven condition articles, excluding article number one.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamaoka accepted the six articles out of the seven condition articles, excluding article number one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamaoka accepted the six articles out of the seven condition articles, excluding article number one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>しかし、第一条のみは絶対に受けられないとして断固拒否し、西郷と問答が続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamaoka insisted that he would never accept Article Number One, rejecting the condition of the Article Number One and continued an exchange of dialogue with Saigo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamaoka insisted that he would never accept Article Number One, rejected the condition of the Article Number One and continued an exchange of dialogue with Saigo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamaoka insisted that he would never accept article number one, rejected the condition of the article number one and continued an exchange of dialogue with Saigo.</e>
<cmt>article number oneとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>ついには山岡が、もし立場を入れ替えて西郷が島津忠義を他藩に預けろと言われたら承知するかと詰問する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Finally, Yamaoka questioned Saigo, &quot;As if we could switch our points of view, then please consider that you would be ordered to place Tadayoshi SHIMAZU (the lord of the Satsuma Domain) into the custody of another Domain. Would you accept that?&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Finally, Yamaoka questioned Saigo, &quot;As if we could switch our points of view, then please consider that you would be ordered to place Tadayoshi SHIMAZU (the lord of the Satsuma Domain) into the custody of another Domain. Would you accept that?&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Finally, Yamaoka questioned Saigo, &quot;As if we could switch our points of view, then please consider that you would be ordered to place Tadayoshi SHIMAZU (the lord of the Satsuma Domain) into the custody of another domain. Would you accept that?&quot;</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーションを半角に修正、another domainとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>西郷も山岡の立場を理解して折れ、第一条は西郷が預かる形で保留となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saigo then understood Yamaoka&apos;s point of view and compromised on the conditions, keeping Article Number One in his hand; so, a compromise was made and Article Number One was withheld.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saigo then understood Yamaoka&apos;s point of view and compromised on the conditions, keeping Article Number One in his hand; so, a compromise was made and Article Number One was withheld.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saigo then understood Yamaoka&apos;s point of view and compromised on the conditions, keeping article number one in his hand; so, a compromise was made and article number one was withheld.</e>
<cmt>全角アポストロフィーを半角に修正、article number oneとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="35">
<sen id="141">
<j>ここに来ての西郷の軟化は、和宮などの度重なる歎願のためであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Up to this point Takamori SAIGO was known as a hard-liner, but changed and softened his attitude abruptly; so he of reconsidered his policy because of the continuous petitions by Princess Kazu and others. Saigo also may have changed his mind because he ascertained that the personnel representing the Tokugawa side were trustworthy persons, such as Ichio OKUBO and Kaishu KATSU.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Up to this point Takamori SAIGO was known as a hard-liner, but changed and softened his attitude abruptly; so he of reconsidered his policy because of the continuous petitions by Princess Kazu and others. Saigo also may have changed his mind because he ascertained that the personnel representing the Tokugawa side were trustworthy persons, such as Ichio OKUBO and Kaishu KATSU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saigo changed and softened his attitude abruptly because of the continuous petitions by Princess Kazunomiya and others.</e>
<cmt>表記統一のためPrincess Kazu→Princess Kazunomiyaに修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>また徳川家側の責任者が信頼に足る大久保一翁・勝らであったためであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saigo also may have changed his mind because he ascertained that the personnel representing the Tokugawa side were trustworthy persons, such as Ichio OKUBO and Kaishu KATSU.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>そのことなどにより、この頃すでに西郷や大久保利通らの間にも、慶喜の恭順が完全であれば厳罰には及ばないとの合意ができつつあったためと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, it appeared that between Saigo and Toshimichi OKUBO were already in agreement; they would not pursue a more severe punishment for Yoshinobu, if they could confirm Yoshinobu&apos;s allegiance to the new government, and his action would be complete and definite.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, it appeared that between Saigo and Toshimichi OKUBO were already in agreement; they would not pursue a more severe punishment for Yoshinobu, if they could confirm Yoshinobu&apos;s allegiance to the new government, and his action would be complete and definite.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, it appeared that between Saigo and Toshimichi OKUBO were already in agreement; they would not pursue a more severe punishment for Yoshinobu, if they could confirm Yoshinobu&apos;s allegiance to the new government, and his action would be complete and definite.</e>
<cmt>全角アポストロフィーを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>実際、この日西郷が山岡に提示した7条件も、前月に大久保利通が新政府に提出した意見書にほぼ添うものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, the Seven Conditions which Saigo presented to the Yamaoka on that day were comparable to the opinion documents, which Toshimichi OKUBO submitted to the new government the previous month.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, the Seven Conditions which Saigo presented to the Yamaoka on that day were comparable to the opinion documents, which Toshimichi OKUBO submitted to the new government the previous month.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, the Seven Conditions which Saigo presented to the Yamaoka on that day were comparable to the opinion documents, which Toshimichi OKUBO submitted to the new government the previous month.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="36">
<sen id="145">
<j>山岡はこの結果を持って翌10日、江戸へ帰り勝に報告。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamaoka took forth the result and retuned to Edo, there he reported to Katsu on March 10th (actually April 2nd, 1868).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamaoka took forth the results and retuned to Edo, there he reported to Katsu on March 10th (actually April 2, 1868).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamaoka took forth the results and retuned to Edo, there he reported to Katsu on March 10th.</e>
<cmt>(actually April 2, 1868)を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>西郷も山岡を追うように11日に駿府を発って13日には江戸薩摩藩邸に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saigo left Sunp on March 11th (actually April 3rd, 1868) as if he were pursuing Yamaoka and entered the Edo Satsuma Hantei (the residence of Satsuma Domain which was maintained by a daimyo in Edo) on March 13th (actually April 5th, 1868). SAIGO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saigo left Sunp on March 11th (actually April 3rd, 1868) as if he were pursuing Yamaoka and entered the Edo Satsuma Hantei (the residence of the Satsuma Domain which was maintained by a daimyo in Edo) on March 13th (actually April 5, 1868). SAIGO</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saigo left Sunp on March 11th as if he were pursuing Yamaoka and entered the residence of the Satsuma clan in Edo on March 13th.</e>
<cmt>(actually April 3rd, 1868) (actually April 5, 1868)を削除、「江戸薩摩藩邸」の表記を修正、文末のSAIGOを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="147">
<j>江戸城への総攻撃を予定されていた15日のわずか2日前であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The day Saigo entered the Edo region was just two days before the set date of March 15th (actually April 7th, 1868), the day of the planned general attack upon Edo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The day Saigo entered the Edo region was just two days before the set date of March 15th (actually April 7, 1868), the day of the planned general attack upon Edo Castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The day Saigo entered Edo was just two days before the set date of March 15th, the day of the planned general attack upon Edo-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>the Edo region→Edoとし、(actually April 7, 1868)を削除、Edo-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="37">
<sen id="148">
<j>焦土作戦の準備</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The preparation of the scorched-earth strategy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The preparation for the scorched-earth strategy</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The preparation for the scorched-earth strategy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>勝は東征軍との交渉を前に、いざという時の備えのために焦土作戦を準備していたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the negotiation with the &apos;expeditionary force to the east,&apos; Katsu prepared for the scorched-earth strategy; this was the preparation in case of emergency and for the worst case scenario.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the negotiations with the &apos;expeditionary force to the east,&apos; Katsu prepared for a scorched-earth strategy; this was preparation in case of an emergency and for a worst case scenario.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the negotiations with the &apos;expeditionary force to the east,&apos; Katsu prepared for a scorched-earth strategy; this was preparation in case of an emergency and for a worst case scenario.</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーションを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>もし東征軍側が徳川家の歎願を聞き入れずに攻撃に移った場合や、徳川家臣の我慢の限度を越えた屈辱的な内容の条件しか受け入れない場合の作である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The scorched-earth strategy was in preparation for the worst case scenarios such as; the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; declining to accept a petition by the Tokugawa Family, then proceeding with an attack; or, in the event of the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; only accepting those conditions which would have extended humiliation and other intolerable actions upon the retainers to the Tokugawa Family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The scorched-earth strategy was in preparation for a worst case scenario such as; the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; declining to accept a petition by the Tokugawa Family, then proceeding with an attack; or, in the event of the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; only accepting those conditions which would have extended humiliation and other intolerable actions upon the retainers to the Tokugawa Family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The scorched-earth strategy was in preparation for a worst case scenario such as; the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; declining to accept a petition by the Tokugawa family, then proceeding with an attack; or, in the event of the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; only accepting those conditions which would have extended humiliation and other intolerable actions upon the retainers to the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーションを半角に修正、the Tokugawa familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="151">
<j>敵の攻撃を受ける前に、江戸城および江戸の町に放火して敵の進軍を防いで焦土と化す作戦である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If these scenarios were present, then the scorched-earth strategy would have been enacted as follows: the Tokugawa Family side would set fire to the Edo Castle and all of Edo city; this strategy was to be implemented to impede the enemy&apos;s military advancement, the method; setting a devastating firestorm upon the Edo community prior to an attack from the &apos;expeditionary force to the east.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If these scenarios were present, then the scorched-earth strategy would have been enacted as follows: the Tokugawa Family side would set fire to Edo Castle and all of Edo city; this strategy was to be implemented to impede the enemy&apos;s military advance, the method; setting a devastating firestorm upon the Edo community prior to an attack from the &apos;expeditionary force to the east.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If these scenarios were present, then the scorched-earth strategy would have been enacted as follows: the Tokugawa family side would set fire to Edo-jo Castle and all of Edo town; this strategy was to be implemented to impede the enemy&apos;s military advance, the method; setting a devastating firestorm upon the Edo community prior to an attack from the &apos;expeditionary force to the east.&apos;</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーション・アポストロフィーを半角に修正、Edo city→Edo town、Edo-jo Castle、the Tokugawa familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>1812年にナポレオン・ボナパルトの攻撃を受けたロシア帝国がモスクワで行った作戦（1812年ロシア戦役を参照）を参考にしたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tokugawa Family side seemed have adapted this scorched-earth strategy from one taken by the Russian Empire to city of Moscow, during the military campaign by Napoleon BONAPARTE in &apos;1812&apos; (Please refer to the &quot;the Russian military campaign in 1812.&quot;).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tokugawa Family side seemed have adapted this scorched-earth strategy from one taken by the Russian Empire to city of Moscow, during the military campaign by Napoleon BONAPARTE in &apos;1812&apos; (Please refer to the &quot;the Russian military campaign of 1812.&quot;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tokugawa family side seemed to have adapted this scorched-earth strategy from one taken by the Russian Empire to city of Moscow, during the military campaign by Napoleon BONAPARTE in &apos;1812&apos; (Please refer to &quot;the Russian military campaign of 1812.&quot;).</e>
<cmt>seemed have adapted→seemed to have adaptedに修正、全角クォーテーションを半角に修正、The Tokugawa familyとし、余分なスペース消去、theの重複分を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>しかし、それとは異なりいったん火災が発生した後はあらかじめ江戸湾に集めておいた雇い船で避難民をできるだけ救出する計画だったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the scorched-earth strategy differed from that of the Russian military campaign of &apos;1812&apos;; the Tokugawa Family planned to evacuate, by contract ships moored in Edo Bay, most of Edo&apos;s residents once the firestorm was set.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the scorched-earth strategy differed from that of the Russian military campaign of &apos;1812,&apos; the Tokugawa Family planned to evacuate, on contracted ships moored in Edo Bay with most of Edo&apos;s residents once the firestorm was set.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the scorched-earth strategy differed from that of the Russian military campaign of &apos;1812,&apos; the Tokugawa family planned to evacuate, on contracted ships moored in Edo Bay with most of Edo&apos;s residents once the firestorm was set.</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーション・アポストロフィーを半角に修正、the Tokugawa familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="154">
<j>勝は焦土作戦を準備するにあたって、新門辰五郎ら市井の友人の伝手を頼った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Katsu prepared the scorched-earth strategy, he relied on the connections of his friends with in the towns&apos; people of Edo, such as Tatsugoro SHINMON. Katsu made personal visits, calling upon those with influence among the commoners in Edo town.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Katsu prepared the scorched-earth strategy, he relied on the connections of his friends with in the towns&apos; people of Edo, such as Tatsugoro SHINMON. Katsu made personal visits, calling upon those with influence among the commoners in Edo town.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Katsu prepared the scorched-earth strategy, he relied on the connections of his friends with in the towns&apos; people of Edo, such as Tatsugoro SHINMON.</e>
<cmt>全角アポストロフィーを半角に修正、Katsu made personal visits, calling upon those with influence among the commoners in Edo town→分割後の訳文が残っているため削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>町火消組、鳶職の親分、博徒の親方、非人頭の家を自ら回って協力を求めたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsu made personal visits, calling upon those with influence among the commoners in Edo town; this was to acquire the cooperation of the following groups: The township fire fighter organization, the head Tobishoku (a scaffolding man), the Oyakata (stable master) masters of Bakuto (the race of gamblers), and the heads of the Hinin (one group comprising the lowest rank of Japan&apos;s Edo-period caste system (often ex-convicts or vagrants) residences.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsu made personal visits, calling upon those with influence among the commoners in Edo town; this was to acquire the cooperation of the following groups: The township fire fighter organization, the head Tobishoku (a scaffolding man), the Oyakata (stable master) masters of Bakuto (the race of gamblers), and the heads of the Hinin (one group comprising the lowest rank of Japan&apos;s Edo-period caste system (often ex-convicts or vagrants) residences.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsu made personal visits, calling upon those with influence among the commoners in Edo town; this was to acquire the cooperation of the following groups: The township fire fighter organization, the head Tobishoku (a scaffolding man), the Oyakata (stable master) masters of Bakuto (the race of gamblers), and the heads of the Hinin (one group comprising the lowest rank of Japan&apos;s Edo-period caste system [often ex-convicts or vagrants]) residences.</e>
<cmt>カッコ表記を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>これらは後年の勝が語るところであるが、勝は特有の大言癖があるため、どこまでが真実なのかは不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, although Katsu retold these stories in his later years, Katsu was known to be of the habit of using the unique story telling style of embellishment, so the validity of the story contained an element of uncertainty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, although Katsu retold these stories in his later years, Katsu was known to be of the habit of using the unique story telling style of embellishment, so the validity of the story contained an element of uncertainty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, although Katsu retold these stories in his later years, Katsu was known to be of the habit of using the unique story telling style of embellishment, so the validity of the story contained an element of uncertainty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>しかし、西郷との談判に臨むにあたってこれだけの準備があったからこそ相手を呑む胆力が生じたと回顧している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nevertheless, Katsu spoke of his recollection, &quot;When he was going to negotiate with Saigo, he would gain the courage to overpower the enemy, partly because he was very well prepared.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nevertheless, Katsu spoke of his recollection, &quot;When he was going to negotiate with Saigo, he would gain the courage to overpower the enemy, partly because he was very well prepared.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nevertheless, Katsu spoke of his recollection, &quot;When he was going to negotiate with Saigo, he would gain the courage to overpower the enemy, partly because he was very well prepared.&quot;</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーションを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="38">
<sen id="158">
<j>勝・西郷会談</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The meeting between Katsu and Saigo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The meeting between Katsu and Saigo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The meeting between Katsu and Saigo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="39">
<sen id="159">
<j>山岡の下交渉を受けて、徳川家側の最高責任者である会計総裁・大久保一翁、陸軍総裁・勝海舟と、東征軍参謀・西郷隆盛との江戸開城交渉は、田町（東京都港区 (東京都)）の薩摩藩江戸藩邸において行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After preparing for negotiations with Yamaoka, the representatives were gathered at the Edo Satsuma Hantei residence of the Satsuma Domain in Tamachi [Minato Ward, Tokyo (Tokyo Metropolis)] to perform the negotiation for the Surrender of Edo Castle: The highest personnel responsible representing the Tokugawa Family side, Ichio OKUBO who was the Kaikei Sosai, Kaishu KATSU who was the Rikugun Sosai, and Takamori SAIGO who was staff officer of the &apos;expeditionary force to the east.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After preparing for negotiations with Yamaoka, the representatives were gathered at the Edo Satsuma Hantei residence of the Satsuma Domain in Tamachi [Minato Ward, Tokyo (Tokyo Metropolis)] to conduct the negotiation for the Surrender of Edo Castle: The highest personnel responsible representing the Tokugawa Family side, Ichio OKUBO who was the Kaikei Sosai, Kaishu KATSU who was the Rikugun Sosai, and Takamori SAIGO who was staff officer of the &apos;expeditionary force to the east.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After preparing for negotiations with Yamaoka, the representatives were gathered at the residence of the Satsuma clan in Edo, located at Tamachi (Minato Ward, Tokyo) to conduct the negotiation for the Surrender of Edo-jo Castle: The highest personnel responsible representing the Tokugawa family side, Ichio OKUBO who was the Kaikei Sosai, Kaishu KATSU who was the Rikugun Sosai, and Takamori SAIGO who was staff officer of the &apos;expeditionary force to the east.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「薩摩藩江戸藩邸」の表記を修正、in Tamachi [Minato Ward, Tokyo (Tokyo Metropolis)]→located at Tamachi (Minato Ward, Tokyo)とし、全角クォーテーションを半角に修正、Edo-jo Castle、the Tokugawa familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>3月13日・14日の2回行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were two meetings for the negotiation on the Surrender of Edo Castle; March 13th (actually April 5th, 1868) and March 14th (actually April 6th, 1868).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were two meetings for the negotiation on the Surrender of Edo Castle; March 13th (actually April 5, 1868) and March 14th (actually April 6, 1868).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were two meetings for the negotiation on the Surrender of Edo-jo Castle; March 13th and 14th.</e>
<cmt>Edo-jo Castle、March 13th and 14thとし、(actually April 5, 1868) (actually April 6, 1868)を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="161">
<j>小説やドラマなどの創作では演出上、勝と西郷の2人のみが面会したように描かれることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the creative works by novelist and dramatist, the authors and producers often described the scene in this edited manner; placing only Katsu and Saigo in attendance at the meeting, for dramatic necessity.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the creative works by novelist and dramatist, the authors and producers often described the scene in this edited manner; placing only Katsu and Saigo in attendance at the meeting, for dramatic necessity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the creative works by novelist and dramatist, the authors and producers often described the scene in this edited manner; placing only Katsu and Saigo in attendance at the meeting, for dramatic necessity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>しかし、実際には徳川家側から大久保や山岡、東征軍側から村田新八・桐野利秋らも同席していたと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In reality, additional personnel definitely attended the meetings, this would have included: Okubo and Yamaoka from the Tokugawa Family side, and Shimpachi MURATA and Toshiaki KIRINO from the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; side.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In reality, additional personnel definitely attended the meetings, this would have included: Okubo and Yamaoka from the Tokugawa Family side, and Shimpachi MURATA and Toshiaki KIRINO from the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In reality, additional personnel definitely attended the meetings, this would have included: Okubo and Yamaoka from the Tokugawa family side, and Shinpachi MURATA and Toshiaki KIRINO from the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; side.</e>
<cmt>Shimpachi→Shinpachiに修正、the Tokugawa familyとし、全角クォーテーションを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="40">
<sen id="163">
<j>勝と西郷は元治元年（1864年）9月に大坂で面会して以来の旧知の仲であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsu and Saigo knew each other since they met in Osaka on September of 1864 (actually October of 1864).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsu and Saigo knew each other since they met in Osaka on September of 1864 (actually October of 1864).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsu and Saigo knew each other since they met in Osaka in September 1864.</e>
<cmt>on September of 1864→in September 1864に修正、新暦表記削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="164">
<j>西郷にとって勝は、幕府の存在を前提としない新政権の構想を教示された恩人でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, to Saigo, Katsu was also his benefactor through the instruction of Saigo on the planning and establishment of a new government, this done without considering the premise for the continued existence of the Bakufu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, to Saigo, Katsu was also his benefactor through the instruction of Saigo on the planning and establishment of a new government, this done without considering the premise for the continued existence of the Bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, to Saigo, Katsu was also his benefactor through the instruction of Saigo on the planning and establishment of a new government, this done without considering the premise for the continued existence of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>the bakufuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>西郷は徳川家の総責任者が勝と大久保であることを知った後は、交渉によって妥結できるであろうと情勢を楽観視していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Saigo became familiar with the general representative personnel for the Tokugawa Family lead by Katsu and Okubo, Saigo believed the negotiations could result in a compromise on the agreement; so, he was optimistic about the situation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Saigo became familiar with the general representative personnel for the Tokugawa Family lead by Katsu and Okubo, Saigo believed the negotiations could result in a compromise on the agreement; so, he was optimistic about the situation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Saigo became familiar with the general representative personnel for the Tokugawa family lead by Katsu and Okubo, Saigo believed the negotiations could result in a compromise on the agreement; so, he was optimistic about the situation.</e>
<cmt>the Tokugawa familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="41">
<sen id="166">
<j>この間、11日には東山道先鋒総督参謀の板垣退助（土佐藩）が八王子駅に到着。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, on March 11th (actually April 3rd, 1868), Tomosada IWAKURA (Tosa Domain) who was staff officer for the Spearhead governor of the Tousando, reached the Hachioji station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, on March 11th (actually April 3, 1868), Tomosada IWAKURA (Tosa Domain), who was staff officer for the Spearhead governor of the Tousando, reached Hachioji station.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, on March 11th, Taisuke ITAGAKI (Tosa Domain), who was staff officer for the Spearhead governor of the Tosando, reached Hachioji Station.</e>
<cmt>(actually April 3, 1868)削除、Tomosada IWAKURA→Taisuke ITAGAKI、Tousando→Tosandoに修正、stationの頭文字を大文字に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>12日には同じく伊地知正治（薩摩藩）が板橋 (板橋区)に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, on March 13th (actually April 5th, 1868), Tomosada IWAKURA, the staff officer for the Spearhead governor of the Tousando, entered Itabashi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, on March 13th (actually April 5, 1868), Tomosada IWAKURA, the staff officer for the Spearhead governor of the Tousando, entered Itabashi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, on March 12th, Masaharu IJICHI (Satsuma Domain), the staff officer for the Spearhead governor of the Tosando, entered Itabashi.</e>
<cmt>March 13th→March 12thに修正、新暦表記削除、Tomosada IWAKURA→Masaharu IJICHI、Tousando→Tosandoに修正、（薩摩藩）→訳漏れのため訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="168">
<j>13日には東山道先鋒総督岩倉具定も板橋駅に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, on March 13th (actually April 5th, 1868), Tomosada IWAKURA, the staff officer for the Spearhead governor of the Tousando, entered Itabashi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, on March 13th (actually April 5, 1868), Tomosada IWAKURA, the staff officer for the Spearhead governor of the Tousando, entered Itabashi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, on March 13th, Tomosada IWAKURA, the Spearhead governor of the Tosando, entered Itabashi Station.</e>
<cmt>新暦表記削除、the staff officer forを削除、Tousando→Tosando、Itabashi→Itabashi Stationに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="169">
<j>江戸城の包囲網は完成しつつあり、緊迫した状況下における会談となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; had nearly completed the encircling net around Edo Castle; the negotiation meetings were conducted within this tense situation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; had nearly completed the encircling net around Edo Castle; the negotiation meetings were conducted within this tense situation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; had nearly completed the encircling net around Edo-jo Castle; the negotiation meetings were conducted within this tense situation.</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーションを半角に修正、Edo-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>しかし西郷は血気にはやる板垣らを抑えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Saigo restrained those officers driven by youthful ardor, such as Itagaki.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Saigo restrained those officers driven by youthful ardor, such as Itagaki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Saigo restrained those officers driven by youthful ardor, such as Itagaki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="171">
<j>勝らとの交渉が終了するまでは厳に攻撃開始を戒めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Saigo strictly ordered no attack was to begin until he could finish the negotiations with Katsu and the other representatives.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Saigo strictly ordered no attack was to begin until he could finish the negotiations with Katsu and the other representatives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Saigo strictly ordered no attack was to begin until he could finish the negotiations with Katsu and the other representatives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="42">
<sen id="172">
<j>第一回交渉（3月13日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first negotiation meeting (March 13th in the Lunar calendar; April 5th 1868 in the Western calendar)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first negotiation meeting (March 13 on the Lunar calendar; April 5, 1868 on the Western calendar)</e>
<cmt>the</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first negotiation meeting (March 13)</e>
<cmt>旧暦表記のみとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="173">
<j>江戸に到着したばかりの西郷と、西郷の到着を待望していた勝との間で、3月13日に行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 13th (April 5th 1868), Saigo, who had just arrived to Edo, and Katsu, who had arrived much earlier than Saigo, they were two of the representatives from each party present at the initial negotiation meeting.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 13th (April 5 1868), Saigo, who had just arrived to Edo, and Katsu, who had arrived much earlier than Saigo, they were two of the representatives from each party present at the initial negotiation meeting.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 13th, Saigo, who had just arrived to Edo, and Katsu, who had arrived much earlier than Saigo, they were two of the representatives from each party present at the initial negotiation meeting.</e>
<cmt>旧暦表記のみとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="174">
<j>第一回交渉では和宮の処遇問題と、以前山岡に提示された慶喜の降伏条件の確認のみとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the first negotiation meeting, the content for discussion focused on two main points; the issue regarding the treatment of the Princess Kazunomiya, and the conditions for the surrender of Yoshinobu; these concerns of Saigo were presented to Yamaoka prior to the meeting.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the first negotiation meeting, the content for discussion focused on two main points; the issue regarding the treatment of Princess Kazunomiya, and the conditions for the surrender of Yoshinobu; these concerns of Saigo were presented to Yamaoka prior to the meeting.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the first negotiation meeting, the content for discussion focused on two main points; the issue regarding the treatment of Princess Kazunomiya, and the conditions for the surrender of Yoshinobu; these concerns of Saigo were presented to Yamaoka prior to the meeting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="175">
<j>突っ込んだ話は行われず、若干の質問・応答のみで終了となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, during the meeting they did not pursue in depth discussion, but instead, concluded this meeting with several sessions of questions and answers.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, during the meeting they did not pursue in depth discussion, but instead, concluded this meeting with several sessions of questions and answers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, during the meeting they did not pursue in depth discussion, but instead, concluded this meeting with several sessions of questions and answers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="43">
<sen id="176">
<j>第二回交渉（3月14日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second negotiation meeting (March 14th in lunar calendar; April 6th 1868 in the Western calendar)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second negotiation meeting (March 14 on the lunar calendar; April 6 1868 on the Western calendar)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second negotiation meeting (March 14)</e>
<cmt>旧暦表記のみとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="177">
<j>3月14日の第二回交渉では、勝から先般の降伏条件に対する回答が提示された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the second negotiation meeting, Katsu presented his response for the conditions of surrender, which Katsu and Saigo had considered in their meeting the previous day:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the second negotiation meeting, Katsu presented his response for the conditions of surrender, which Katsu and Saigo had considered in their meeting the previous day:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the second negotiation meeting on March 14, Katsu presented his response for the conditions of surrender, which Katsu and Saigo had considered in their meeting the previous day:</e>
<cmt>「3月14日の」→訳漏れのため訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="44">
<sen id="178">
<j>徳川慶喜は故郷の水戸市で謹慎する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Condition Number One: Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA should confine himself within his hometown of Mito City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Condition Number One: Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA should confine himself within his hometown of Mito City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Condition Number One: Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA should confine himself within his hometown of Mito City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="45">
<sen id="179">
<j>慶喜を助けた諸侯は寛典に処して、命に関わる処分者は出さない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Condition Number Two: Those lords aligned in support to Yoshinobu should be punished, but with lenient treatment, therefore, the lords should not have the charge of capital punishment administered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Condition Number Two: Those lords aligned in support to Yoshinobu should be punished, but with lenient treatment, therefore, the lords should not have the charge of capital punishment administered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Condition Number Two: Those lords aligned in support to Yoshinobu should be punished, but with lenient treatment, therefore, the lords should not have the charge of capital punishment administered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="46">
<sen id="180">
<j>武器・軍艦はまとめておく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Condition Number Three: The Tokugawa Bakufu Army should gather all weapons and warships. Then, the Tokugawa Family should hand over those weapons to the new government; this was to take place following the new government&apos;s administration of lenient treatment toward the Tokugawa Family and all other involved parties.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Condition Number Three: The Tokugawa Bakufu Army should gather all weapons and warships. Then, the Tokugawa Family should hand over those weapons to the new government; this was to take place following the new government&apos;s administration of lenient treatment toward the Tokugawa Family and all other involved parties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Condition Number Three: The Tokugawa shogunate army should gather all weapons and warships.</e>
<cmt>The Tokugawa Bakufu Army→The Toaugawa shogunate armyとし、分割前の訳文が残っていたため削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="181">
<j>そして、寛典の処分が下された後に差し渡す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, the Tokugawa Family should hand over those weapons to the new government; this was to take place following the new government&apos;s administration of lenient treatment toward the Tokugawa Family and all other involved parties.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, the Tokugawa Family should hand over those weapons to the new government; this was to take place following the new government&apos;s administration of lenient treatment toward the Tokugawa Family and all other involved parties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, the Tokugawa family should hand over those weapons to the new government; this was to take place following the new government&apos;s administration of lenient treatment toward the Tokugawa family and all other involved parties.</e>
<cmt>the Tokugawa familyとし、全角アポストロフィーを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="47">
<sen id="182">
<j>城内居住の者は、城外に移って謹慎する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Condition Number Four: Those personnel residing in Edo Castle should move out and subsequently to confine themselves in the agreed designated locations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Condition Number Four: Those personnel residing in Edo Castle should move out and subsequently to confine themselves in the agreed designated locations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Condition Number Four: Those personnel residing in Edo-jo Castle should move out and subsequently to confine themselves in the agreed designated locations.</e>
<cmt>Edo-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="48">
<sen id="183">
<j>江戸城を明け渡しの手続きを終えた後は即刻田安家へ返却を願う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Condition Number Five: Once the process in the surrender of Edo Castle is complete, the Tokugawa Family should immediately implement procedures for returning Edo Castle to the Tayasu Family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Condition Number Five: Once the process in the surrender of Edo Castle is complete, the Tokugawa Family should immediately implement procedures for returning Edo Castle to the Tayasu Family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Condition Number Five: Once the process in the surrender of Edo Castle is complete, the Tokugawa family should immediately implement procedures for returning Edo-jo Castle to the Tayasu family.</e>
<cmt>the Tokugaa family、Edo-jo Caslte、the Tayasu familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="49">
<sen id="184">
<j>暴発の士民鎮定の件は可能な限り努力する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Condition Number Six: The Tokugawa Family should exert maximum effort in the suppression of any potential accidental discharge of samurais and retainers by the Tokugawa Family or the former Tokugawa Baku Army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Condition Number Six: The Tokugawa Family should exert maximum effort in the suppression of any potential accidental discharge of samurais and retainers by the Tokugawa Family or the former Tokugawa Baku Army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Condition Number Six: The Tokugawa family should exert maximum effort in the suppression of any potential accidental discharge of samurais and retainers by the Tokugawa family or the former Tokugawa shogunate army.</e>
<cmt>the Tokugawa familyとし、Tokugawa Baku Army→Tokugawa shogunate armyに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="50">
<sen id="185">
<j>これは、以前に山岡に提示された条件に対する全くの骨抜き回答であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsu had given Saigo these responses to effectively water-down the original conditions Saigo previously presented to Yamaoka.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsu had given Saigo these responses to effectively water-down the original conditions Saigo previously presented to Yamaoka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsu had given Saigo these responses to effectively water down the original conditions Saigo previously presented to Yamaoka.</e>
<cmt>water-down→water downとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="186">
<j>事実上拒否したに等しかったが、西郷は勝・大久保を信頼して、翌日の江戸城総攻撃を中止した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, Katsu answered as if he were in fact rejecting these conditions; Saigo trusted Katsu and Okubo, so Saigo terminated the following day&apos;s general attack upon Edo Castle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, Katsu answered as if he were in fact rejecting these conditions; Saigo trusted Katsu and Okubo, so Saigo terminated the following day&apos;s general attack upon Edo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, Katsu answered as if he were rejecting these conditions; Saigo trusted Katsu and Okubo, so Saigo terminated the following day&apos;s general attack upon Edo-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>表記重複のためin fact削除、全角アポストロフィーを半角に修正、Edo-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="187">
<j>自らの責任で回答を京都へ持ち帰って検討することを約した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Saigo promised Katsu and Okubo that he would assume responsibility for delivery of their response to Kyoto for its due consideration.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Saigo promised Katsu and Okubo that he would assume responsibility for delivery of their response to Kyoto for its due consideration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Saigo promised Katsu and Okubo that he would assume responsibility for delivery of their response to Kyoto for its due consideration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="188">
<j>ここに、江戸城無血明け渡しが決定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequent to this, Saigo made the decision for a bloodless surrender of Edo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequent to this, Saigo made the decision for a bloodless surrender of Edo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequent to this, Saigo made the decision for a bloodless surrender of Edo-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>Edo-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="189">
<j>この日、京都では天皇が諸臣を従えて自ら天神地祇の前で誓う形式で五箇条の御誓文が発布される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the same day in the Imperial Court of Kyoto, the Emperor accompanied by his shoshin (retainers) proclaimed in this &apos;sworn by God&apos; declaration ceremony there before the &apos;gods of heaven and earth&apos;, presenting &apos;the Imperial Covenant Consisting of Five Articles.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the same day in the Imperial Court of Kyoto, the Emperor accompanied by his shoshin (retainers) proclaimed in this &apos;sworn by God&apos; declaration ceremony there before the &apos;gods of heaven and earth,&apos; presenting &apos;the Imperial Covenant Consisting of Five Articles.&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the same day in the Imperial Court of Kyoto, the Emperor accompanied by his retainers proclaimed in this &apos;sworn by God&apos; declaration ceremony there before the &apos;gods of heaven and earth,&apos; presenting &apos;the Imperial Covenant Consisting of Five Articles.&apos;</e>
<cmt>shoshin (retainers)→retainersとし、全角クォーテーションを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="190">
<j>そこに、明治国家の基本方針が示されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was in this declaration; the Mejia state (the new government) outlined the new governance policy.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was in this declaration; the Mejia state (the new government) outlined the new governance policy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was in this declaration; the Meiji state (the new government) outlined the new governance policy.</e>
<cmt>Meijiのスペルミス修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="51">
<sen id="191">
<j>「パークスの圧力」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The pressure of Parkes&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;The pressure of Parkes&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;The pressure of Parkes&quot;</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーションを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="192">
<j>西郷が徳川方の事実上の骨抜き回答という不利な条件を飲み、総攻撃を中止した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saigo agreed to the disadvantage of those counter conditions, presented in the water-downed response by the Tokugawa side, there for terminating the general attack.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saigo agreed to the disadvantage of those counter conditions, presented in the water-downed response by the Tokugawa side, there for terminating the general attack.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saigo agreed to the disadvantage of those counter conditions, presented in the watered-down response by the Tokugawa side, there for terminating the general attack.</e>
<cmt>water-downed→watered-downに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="193">
<j>その背景には、イギリス公使ハリー・パークスからの徳川家温存の圧力があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A background story, posed the theory that the official British minister, Harry PARKES, applied pressure for the continuance of Tokugawa Family line upon Saigo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A background story, posed the theory that the official British minister, Harry PARKES, applied pressure for the continuance of Tokugawa Family line upon Saigo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A background story, posed the theory that the official British minister, Harry PARKES, applied pressure for the continuance of the Tokugawa family line upon Saigo.</e>
<cmt>the Tokugawa familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="194">
<j>その為に、西郷が受け入れざるを得なかったとする説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Saigo was convinced to accept the water-downed conditions.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Saigo was convinced to accept the water-downed conditions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Saigo was convinced to accept the watered-down conditions.</e>
<cmt>water-downed→watered-downに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="52">
<sen id="195">
<j>正月25日の局外中立宣言後、パークスは横浜に戻った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the declaration of their neutrality position on January 25th (actually February 18th, 1868), Parkes retuned to Yokohama.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the declaration of their neutrality position on January 25th (actually February 18, 1868), Parkes retuned to Yokohama.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the declaration of their neutrality position on January 25th, Parkes retuned to Yokohama.</e>
<cmt>旧暦表記のみとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="196">
<j>治安維持のため、横浜在留諸外国の軍隊で防備する体制を固めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Parkes established a unified security force, assembled from the foreign nations military detachments residing in Yokohama; this would be to maintain security within the foreign compound.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Parkes established a unified security force, assembled from the foreign nations military detachments residing in Yokohama; this would be to maintain security within the foreign compound.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Parkes established a unified security force, assembled from the foreign nations military detachments residing in Yokohama; this would be to maintain security within the foreign compound.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="197">
<j>そののち、東征軍および徳川家の情勢が全く不明であったことから、公使館通訳アーネスト・サトウを江戸へ派遣して情勢を探らせる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Parkes dispatched the interpreter for the British delegation, Ernest SATOW, to Edo to ascertain the current situation, since Parkes did not have sufficient knowledge on the status of the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; and of the Tokugawa Family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Parkes dispatched the interpreter for the British delegation, Ernest SATOW, to Edo to ascertain the current situation, since Parkes did not have sufficient knowledge on the status of the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; and of the Tokugawa Family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Parkes dispatched the interpreter for the British delegation, Ernest SATOW, to Edo to ascertain the current situation, since Parkes did not have sufficient knowledge on the status of the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; and of the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーションを半角に修正、余分なスペース消去、the Tokugawa familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="198">
<j>いっぽう、3月13日（1868年4月5日）午後には新政府の代表を横浜へ赴任させるよう要請すべくラットラー号を大阪へ派遣している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, on March 13th (actually April 5th, 1868), Parkes demanded of the new government the assignment of a governmental representative to Yokohama, then Parkes dispatched the HMS Rattler ship to Osaka.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, on March 13th (actually April 5, 1868), Parkes demanded of the new government the assignment of a governmental representative to Yokohama, then Parkes dispatched the ship HMS Rattler to Osaka.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, on March 13th (April 5, 1868 in new calendar), Parkes demanded of the new government the assignment of a governmental representative to Yokohama, then Parkes dispatched the ship HMS Rattler to Osaka.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに基づき、3月13日（1868年4月5日）→March 13th (April 5, 1868 in new calendar)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="53">
<sen id="199">
<j>東征軍が関東へ入ると、東征軍先鋒参謀木梨精一郎（長州藩士）および渡辺清（大村藩士）は、横浜の英国公使館へ向かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following the arrival of the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; into Kanto, Seiichirou KINASHI (a feudal retainer of Choshu Domain), a Spearhead staff officer of the &apos;expeditionary force to the east,&apos; and Kiyoshi WATANABE (the Omura Domain) proceeded to the British delegation quarters in Yokohama.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following the arrival of the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; into Kanto, Seiichirou KINASHI (a feudal retainer of Choshu Domain), a Spearhead staff officer of the &apos;expeditionary force to the east,&apos; and Kiyoshi WATANABE (the Omura Domain) proceeded to the British delegation quarters in Yokohama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following the arrival of the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; into Kanto, Seiichirou KINASHI (a feudal retainer of the Choshu clan), a Spearhead staff officer of the &apos;expeditionary force to the east,&apos; and Kiyoshi WATANABE (a feudal retainer of the Omura clan) proceeded to the British delegation quarters in Yokohama.</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーションを半角に修正、a feudal retainer of Choshu Domain→a feudal retainer of the Choshu clan、the Omura Domain→a feudal retainer of the Omura clanに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="200">
<j>そこで、来るべき戦争で生じる傷病者の手当や、病院の手配などを申し込んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once there, the request was made of Parkes for assistance in the treatment of any potential wounded, injured or ill members of the population, and hospitalization arrangements, in the event of a future war.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once there, the request was made of Parkes for assistance in the treatment of any potential wounded, injured or ill members of the population, and hospitalization arrangements, in the event of a future war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once there, the request was made of Parkes for assistance in the treatment of any potential wounded, injured or ill members of the population, and hospitalization arrangements, in the event of a future war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="201">
<j>しかし、パークスはナポレオンさえも処刑されずにセントヘレナ島への流刑に留まった例を持ち出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Parkes brought up the example of Napoléon; in fact, Napoléon was not executed, but exiled to the island of Saint Helena.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Parkes brought up the example of Napoléon; in fact, Napoléon was not executed, but exiled to the island of Saint Helena.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Parkes brought up the example of Napoléon; in fact, Napoléon was not executed, but exiled to the island of Saint Helena.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="202">
<j>そして、恭順・謹慎を示している無抵抗の徳川慶喜に対して攻撃することは万国公法に反するとして激昂した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Parkes became indignant, declaring it a violation of International law to proceed with an attack against someone such as Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA, who had chosen not to resist, but had instead demonstrated an allegiance to the new government, and an agreement to be confined in his residence.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Parkes became indignant, declaring it a violation of International law to proceed with an attack against someone such as Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA, who had chosen not to resist, but had instead demonstrated an allegiance to the new government, and an agreement to be confined in his residence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Parkes became indignant, declaring it a violation of International law to proceed with an attack against someone such as Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA, who had chosen not to resist, but had instead demonstrated an allegiance to the new government, and an agreement to be confined in his residence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="203">
<j>その為、面談を中止したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, Parkes ended the meeting.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, Parkes ended the meeting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, Parkes ended the meeting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="204">
<j>またパークスは、徳川慶喜が外国に亡命することも万国公法上は問題ないと話したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, Parkes informed the officers of International Law allowing for Yoshinobu&apos;s asylum in a foreign nation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, Parkes informed the officers of International Law allowing for Yoshinobu&apos;s asylum in a foreign nation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, Parkes informed the officers of International Law allowing for Yoshinobu&apos;s asylum in a foreign nation.</e>
<cmt>全角アポストロフィーを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="205">
<j>このパークスの怒りを伝え聞いた西郷が大きく衝撃を受け、江戸城攻撃中止への外圧となったというものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Saigo was told of Parkes angry reaction, he was greatly shocked, terminating his attack on Edo Castle; therefore the external pressure of Parkes had an obvious effect upon him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Saigo was told of Parkes angry reaction, he was greatly shocked, terminating his attack on Edo Castle; therefore the external pressure of Parkes had an obvious effect upon him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Saigo was told of Parkes angry reaction, he was greatly shocked, terminating his attack on Edo-jo Castle; therefore the external pressure of Parkes had an obvious effect upon him.</e>
<cmt>Edo-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="54">
<sen id="206">
<j>ただしパークスの発言が実際に、勝と交渉中の西郷に影響を与えたかどうかについては不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, irrefutable support is lacking on the subject of the influence of Parkes&apos;s statements upon Saigo during the negotiations with Katsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, irrefutable support is lacking on the subject of the influence of Parkes&apos;s statements upon Saigo during the negotiations with Katsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, irrefutable support is lacking on the subject of the influence of Parkes&apos;s statements upon Saigo during the negotiations with Katsu.</e>
<cmt>全角アポストロフィーを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="207">
<j>そもそも上記のパークス・木梨の会談が行われたのがいつのことであるかが鮮明ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There isn&apos;t any clearly written documentation placing the time for the meeting, of Parkes and Kinashi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There isn&apos;t any clearly written documentation placing the time for the meeting, of Parkes and Kinashi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is not any clearly written documentation placing the time for the meeting, of Parkes and Kinashi.</e>
<cmt>isn’t→is notに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="208">
<j>主に3月13日説をとる史料が多いが、14日説をとるもの、日付を明示していないものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A majority of historian and authors of historical materials have adopted this theory, placing the day of the on March 13th (actually April 5th, 1868), others adopting the theory of the meeting on March 14th (actually April 6th, 1868), and some with out a date certain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A majority of historians and authors of historical materials have adopted this theory, placing the day of the on March 13th (actually April 5, 1868), others adopting the theory of the meeting on March 14th (actually April 6, 1868), and some with out a date certain.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A majority of historians and authors of historical materials have adopted this theory, placing the day of the meeting on March 13th, others adopting the theory of the meeting on March 14th, and some without a date certain.</e>
<cmt>the day of the on→the day of the meeting on、with out→withoutとし、旧暦表記のみとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="209">
<j>しかし、いずれもパークスが先日上方へ軍艦を派遣した後に面会したと記載されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nevertheless, one thing was common to each case; all of the historical material writers described Parkes meeting Kinashi after Parkes had dispatched a warship to Kamigata (Kyoto and vicinity) region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nevertheless, one thing was common to each case; all of the historical material writers described Parkes meeting Kinashi after Parkes had dispatched a warship to Kamigata (Kyoto and vicinity) region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nevertheless, one thing was common to each case; all of the historical material writers described Parkes meeting Kinashi after Parkes had dispatched a warship to Kamigata (Kyoto and vicinity) region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="210">
<j>パークスによる軍艦派遣は西洋暦4月5日すなわち和暦3月13日であることが確実である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because Parkes dispatched the warship on April 5th, 1868, in the western calendar, it would certainly be March 13th in the old Japanese lunar calendar.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Parkes dispatched the warship on April 5, 1868, according to the western calendar, it would certainly be March 13 on the old Japanese lunar calendar.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Parkes dispatched the warship on April 5, 1868, according to the western calendar, it would certainly be March 13 on the old Japanese lunar calendar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="211">
<j>そのため、会談自体は3月14日以降に行われたと考えざるをえない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, we must conclude that the meeting itself, was held after March 14th (actually April 6th, 1868).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, we must conclude that the meeting itself, was held after March 14th (actually April 6, 1868).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, we must conclude that the meeting itself, was held after March 14th.</e>
<cmt>旧暦表記のみとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="212">
<j>そうなると、前述の3月14日夕刻まで行われた第2回勝・西郷会談と同日になってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If this is true, Parkes&apos;s meeting date was on the same day as the second negotiation of Katsu and Saigo, which continued into the evening.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If this is true, Parkes&apos;s meeting date was on the same day as the second negotiation of Katsu and Saigo, which continued into the evening.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If this is true, Parkes&apos;s meeting date was on the same day as the second negotiation of Katsu and Saigo, which continued into the evening.</e>
<cmt>全角アポストロフィーを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="213">
<j>そのため、事前にパークスの発言が西郷の耳に届いていたとは考えがたい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So, it&apos;s hard to believe Saigo had heard Parkes&apos;s statement prior to the negotiations.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So, it&apos;s hard to believe Saigo had heard Parkes&apos;s statement prior to the negotiations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So, it is hard to believe Saigo had heard Parkes&apos;s statement prior to the negotiations.</e>
<cmt>it’s→it isに修正、全角アポストロフィーを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="214">
<j>そのため萩原延壽は、下記のように述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Nobutoshi HAGIWARA thought that &quot;The pressure of Parkes&quot; would not have affected Saigo before his meeting with Katsu and Saigo; rather the statements of Parkes were presented to Saigo after the meeting.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Nobutoshi HAGIWARA thought that &quot;The pressure of Parkes&quot; would not have affected Saigo before his meeting with Katsu and Saigo; rather the statements of Parkes were presented to Saigo after the meeting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Nobutoshi HAGIWARA thought as below:</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」split sampleに基づき分割し直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="215">
<j>「パークスの圧力」は勝・西郷会談の前に西郷へ影響を与えたというよりは、会談後に西郷の下にもたらされたのではないか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;The pressure of Parkes&quot; would not have affected Saigo before his meeting with Katsu and Saigo; rather the statements of Parkes were presented to Saigo after the meeting.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」全角クォーテーションを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="216">
<j>そして、強硬論から寛典論に180度転じた西郷が、同じく強硬派だった板垣や京都の面々にその政策転換を説明する口実として利用したのではないか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Nobutoshi HAGIWARA described Saigo using &quot;The pressure of Parkes&quot; as the justification to substantiate the strategic policy change after Saigo&apos;s conversion to belief in a more lenient treatment policy, than that of the hardliners; a one-hundred and eighty degree change.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Nobutoshi HAGIWARA described Saigo using &quot;The pressure of Parkes&quot; as the justification to substantiate the strategic policy change after Saigo&apos;s conversion to belief in a more lenient treatment policy, than that of the hardliners; a one-hundred and eighty degree change.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Nobutoshi HAGIWARA described Saigo using &quot;The pressure of Parkes&quot; as the justification to substantiate the strategic policy change after Saigo&apos;s conversion to belief in a more lenient treatment policy, than that of the hardliners; a one-hundred and eighty degree change.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」全角クォーテーション・アポストロフィーを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="217">
<j>事実、板垣は総攻撃中止の決定に対して猛反対したが、パークスとのやりとりを聞くとあっさり引き下がっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, Itagaki furiously opposed the termination of the general attack upon Edo Castle, but he simply accepted this result, after he was made aware of the incidence of the exchange with Parkes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, Itagaki furiously opposed the termination of the general attack upon Edo Castle, but he simply accepted this result, after he was made aware of the incidence of the exchange with Parkes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, Itagaki furiously opposed the termination of the general attack upon Edo-jo Castle, but he simply accepted this result, after he was made aware of the incidence of the exchange with Parkes.</e>
<cmt>Edo-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="218">
<j>パークスの話を西郷に伝えた渡辺清も、後に同様の意見を述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Kiyoshi WATANABE, was told of the story of Parkes statement to Saigo; he was of a similar opinion to that of Nobutoshi HAGIWARA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Kiyoshi WATANABE, was told of the story of Parkes statement to Saigo; he was of a similar opinion to that of Nobutoshi HAGIWARA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Kiyoshi WATANABE, was told of the story of Parkes statement to Saigo; he was of a similar opinion to that of Nobutoshi HAGIWARA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="55">
<sen id="219">
<j>江戸城明け渡し</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The surrender of the Edo Castle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The surrender of Edo Castle</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The surrender of Edo-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>Edo-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="220">
<j>西郷の帰京と方針確定</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The retuning to the Kyoto Capital and the confirmation of policy of Saigo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The retuning to the Kyoto Capital and the confirmation of the policy of Saigo</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The retuning to the Kyoto Capital and the confirmation of the policy of Saigo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="221">
<j>勝との会談を受けて江戸を発った西郷は急ぎ上京した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After completed the meeting with Katsu, Saigo left Edo and rushed to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After completing the meeting with Katsu, Saigo left Edo and rushed to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After completing the meeting with Katsu, Saigo left Edo and rushed to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="222">
<j>3月20日にはさっそく朝議が催された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, on March 20th (actually April 12th, 1868), the Court Council met took an immediate meeting.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, on March 20th (actually April 12, 1868), the Court Council met took an immediate meeting.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, on March 20th, the Court Council met took an immediate meeting.</e>
<cmt>旧暦表記のみとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="223">
<j>強硬論者だった西郷が慶喜助命に転じたことは、木戸孝允・山内容堂・松平春嶽ら寛典論派にも驚きをもって迎えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The lenient treatment policy advocates, Takayoshi KIDO, Yodo YAMAUCHI, and Shungaku MATSUDAIRA, were surprised to hear to the modified policy of Saigo, conversion from hardliner, and advocating on sparing the life of Nobuyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lenient treatment policy advocates, Takayoshi KIDO, Yodo YAMAUCHI, and Shungaku MATSUDAIRA, were surprised to hear to the modified policy of Saigo, conversion from hardliner, and advocating sparing the life of Nobuyoshi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lenient treatment policy advocates, Takayoshi KIDO, Yodo YAMAUCHI, and Shungaku MATSUDAIRA, were surprised to hear to the modified policy of Saigo, conversion from hardliner, and advocating sparing the life of Yoshinobu.</e>
<cmt>Nobuyoshi→Yoshinobuに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="56">
<sen id="224">
<j>西郷の提議で勝の出した徳川方の新条件が検討された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saigo proposed to discuss the new conditions for the Tokugawa side which were presented by Katsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saigo proposed to discuss the new conditions for the Tokugawa side which were presented by Katsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saigo proposed to discuss the new conditions for the Tokugawa side which were presented by Katsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="225">
<j>第一条、慶喜の水戸謹慎に対しては政府副総裁の岩倉具視が反対した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The conditions of Article Number One; the Vice President in charge of the new government (Seifu Fuku Sosai), Tomomi IWAKURA, was opposed to the confinement of Yoshinobu in Mito</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The conditions of Article Number One; the Vice President in charge of the new government (Seifu Fuku Sosai), Tomomi IWAKURA, was opposed to the confinement of Yoshinobu in Mito</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The conditions of Article Number One; the Vice President in charge of the new government (Seifu Fuku Sosai), Tomomi IWAKURA, was opposed to the confinement of Yoshinobu in Mito.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="226">
<j>慶喜自ら総督府に出頭して謝罪すること、徳川家は徳川家達（徳川慶頼の子）に相続させるが、北国もしくは西国に移して石高は70万石ないし50万石とすることなどを要求した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iwakura demanded the following items: that Yoshinobu should present himself before the grand government&apos;s general to offer his personal apology; that the Tokugawa Family line would be allowed to continue, once Iesato TOKUGAWA (the child of Yoshinori TOKUGAWA) became successor; but the Tokugawa Family should be relocated to either the northern or southern provinces; within a territory having a area of between 700,000 koku (with approximately 126 million liters of crop yield) to 500,000 koku (with approximately 90 million liters of crop yield).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iwakura demanded the following items: that Yoshinobu should present himself before the grand government&apos;s general to offer his personal apology; that the Tokugawa Family line would be allowed to continue, once Iesato TOKUGAWA (the child of Yoshinori TOKUGAWA) became successor; but the Tokugawa Family should be relocated to either the northern or southern provinces; within a territory having a area of between 700,000 koku (with approximately 126 million liters of crop yield) to 500,000 koku (with approximately 90,000,000 liters of crop yield).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iwakura demanded the following items: that Yoshinobu should present himself before the grand government&apos;s general to offer his personal apology; that the Tokugawa family line would be allowed to continue, once Iesato TOKUGAWA (the child of Yoshinori TOKUGAWA) became successor; but the Tokugawa family should be relocated to either the northern or southern provinces; within a territory having a area of between 700,000 koku (with approximately 126 million liters of crop yield) to 500,000 koku (with approximately 90,000,000 liters of crop yield).</e>
<cmt>全角アポストロフィーを半角に修正、the Tokugawa familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="227">
<j>しかし結局は勝案に譲歩して水戸謹慎で確定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ultimately, Iwakura compromised, accepting the suggestions of Katsu for the confinement of Yoshinobu in Mito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ultimately, Iwakura compromised, accepting the suggestions of Katsu for the confinement of Yoshinobu in Mito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ultimately, Iwakura compromised, accepting the suggestions of Katsu for the confinement of Yoshinobu in Mito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="228">
<j>第二条に関しても、田安家に江戸城を即刻返すという勝案は却下されたものの、大総督に一任されることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The condition of Article Number Two; Katsu&apos;s suggestion of the immediate return of Edo Castle to the Tayasu Family was rejected; this decision was left to the Dai Soutoku (the commander of temporally army).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The condition of Article Number Two; Katsu&apos;s suggestion of the immediate return of Edo Castle to the Tayasu Family was rejected; this decision was left to the Dai Soutoku (the commander of the temporary army).</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The condition of Article Number Two; Katsu&apos;s suggestion of the immediate return of Edo-jo Castle to the Tayasu family was rejected; this decision was left to the Dai Sotoku (the commander of the temporary army).</e>
<cmt>全角アポストロフィーを半角に修正、Edo-jpo Castle、the Tayasu family、Dai Sotokuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="229">
<j>第三・四条の武器・軍艦引き渡しに関しては岩倉の要求が通った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The conditions of Articles Three and Four; Iwakura had gained the necessary support for his opinion on transfer of weapons and warships.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The conditions of Articles Three and Four; Iwakura had gained the necessary support for his opinion on the transfer of weapons and warships.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The conditions of Articles Three and Four; Iwakura had gained the necessary support for his opinion on the transfer of weapons and warships.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="230">
<j>いったん新政府軍が接収した後に改めて徳川家に入用の分を下げ渡すことになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The new government was to receive everything from the Tokugawa Family, then should it become necessary, reissue the weapons and ships to the Tokugawa Family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The new government was to receive everything from the Tokugawa Family, then should it become necessary, reissue the weapons and ships to the Tokugawa Family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The new government was to receive everything from the Tokugawa family, then should it become necessary, reissue the weapons and ships to the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>the Tokugawa familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="231">
<j>第五・七条は原案通り。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The conditions of Articles Number Five and Seven were not changed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The conditions of Articles Number Five and Seven were not changed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The conditions of Articles Number Five and Seven were not changed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="232">
<j>第六条の慶喜を支えた面々の処分については副総裁三条実美が反対した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The conditions of Article number Six: Vice President, Sanetomi SANJO, was opposed to Katsu&apos;s suggestion for the supporters of Yoshinobu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The conditions of Article number Six: Vice President, Sanetomi SANJO, was opposed to Katsu&apos;s suggestion for the supporters of Yoshinobu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The conditions of Article number Six: Vice President, Sanetomi SANJO, was opposed to Katsu&apos;s suggestion for the supporters of Yoshinobu.</e>
<cmt>全角アポストロフィーを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="233">
<j>特に松平容保・松平定敬の両人に対しては、はっきり死罪を求める厳しい要求を主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanjo adamantly persisted in his demand for specific punishment; this was the execution of Katamori MATSUDAIRA and Sadaaki MATSUDAIRA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanjo adamantly persisted in his demand for specific punishment; this was the execution of Katamori MATSUDAIRA and Sadaaki MATSUDAIRA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanjo adamantly persisted in his demand for specific punishment; this was the execution of Katamori MATSUDAIRA and Sadaaki MATSUDAIRA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="234">
<j>結局は会津・桑名に対して問罪の軍兵を派遣し、降伏すればよし、抗戦した場合は速やかに討伐すると修正された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After all, the new government had revised its punishment for the Tokugawa supporters in the Aizu and Kuwana domains; the new government would dispatch a military force for &apos;the accusation&apos;, once there, a battle would be avoided if the two domains would surrender; then the new government would engage and conquer the domains, should the domains engage in a counter attack upon the new government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After all, the new government had revised its punishment for the Tokugawa supporters in the Aizu and Kuwana domains; the new government would dispatch a military force for &apos;the accusation,&apos; once there, a battle would be avoided if the two domains would surrender; then the new government would engage and conquer the domains, should the domains engage in a counter attack upon the new government.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After all, the new government had revised its punishment for the Tokugawa supporters in the Aizu and Kuwana domains; the new government would dispatch a military force for &apos;the accusation,&apos; once there, a battle would be avoided if the two domains would surrender; then the new government would engage and conquer the domains, should the domains engage in a counter attack upon the new government.</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーションを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="235">
<j>この決定が後の会津戦争に繋がることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This decision eventually leads to the Battle of Aizu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This decision eventually led to the Battle of Aizu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This decision eventually led to the Battle of Aizu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="236">
<j>修正・確定された7箇条を携えて、西郷は再び江戸へ下ることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saigo again left Kyoto for Edo, carrying on him the revisions and confirmation to the conditions of Article Seven.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saigo again left Kyoto for Edo, carrying on him the revisions and confirmation to the conditions of Article Seven.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saigo again left Kyoto for Edo, carrying on him the revisions and confirmation to the conditions of Seven Articles.</e>
<cmt>Article Seven→Seven Articlesに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="57">
<sen id="237">
<j>この間の3月23日、東征軍海軍先鋒大原重実が横浜に来航した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the interim, on March 23rd (actually April 15th, 1868), Shigezane OHARA, who was the Spearhead of the Navy&apos;s &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; arrived in Yokohama by ship.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the interim, on March 23rd (actually April 15, 1868), Shigezane OHARA, who was the Spearhead of the Navy&apos;s &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; arrived in Yokohama by ship.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the interim, on March 23rd, Shigezane OHARA, who was the Spearhead of the Navy&apos;s &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; arrived in Yokohama by ship.</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーション・アポストロフィーを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="238">
<j>附属参謀島義勇（佐賀藩士）を派遣して徳川家軍艦の引き渡しを要求した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ohara dispatched, the Navy associated staff officer, Yoshitake SHIMA (feudal retainer of the Saga Domain), to demand the handing over all warships.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ohara dispatched, the Navy associated staff officer, Yoshitake SHIMA (feudal retainer of the Saga Domain), to demand the handing over of all warships.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ohara dispatched, the Navy associated staff officer, Yoshitake SHIMA (a feudal retainer of the Saga clan), to demand the handing over of all warships.</e>
<cmt>feudal retainer of the Saga Domain→a feudal retainer of the Saga clanに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="239">
<j>しかし、勝は未だ徳川処分が決定していないことを理由にこれを拒否している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Katsu refused this demand, reasoning that the Tokugawa Family had not yet been officially charged.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Katsu refused this demand, reasoning that the Tokugawa Family had not yet been officially charged.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Katsu refused this demand, reasoning that the Tokugawa family had not yet been officially charged.</e>
<cmt>the Tokugawa familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="240">
<j>勝としては交渉相手を西郷のみに絞っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsu narrowed down the negotiation window and only dealt with Saigo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsu narrowed down the negotiation window and only dealt with Saigo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsu narrowed down the negotiation window and only dealt with Saigo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="241">
<j>切り札である慶喜の身柄や徳川家の軍装に関して、西郷の再東下より前に妥協するつもりはなかったためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, he had no intention in compromising with any of his opponent&apos;s staff on conditions in the treatment or custody of Yoshinobu and the armed forces of the Tokugawa Family, until the arrival of Saigo from Kyoto to the Kanto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, he had no intention in compromising with any of his opponent&apos;s staff on conditions in the treatment or custody of Yoshinobu and the armed forces of the Tokugawa Family, until the arrival of Saigo from Kyoto to the Kanto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, he had no intention in compromising with any of his opponent&apos;s staff on conditions in the treatment or custody of Yoshinobu and the armed forces of the Tokugawa family, until the arrival of Saigo from Kyoto to the Kanto.</e>
<cmt>全角アポストロフィーを半角に修正、the Tokugawa familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="58">
<sen id="242">
<j>3月28日、西郷は横浜にパークスを訪問し、事の経緯と新政権の方針を説明している（なおその前日には勝もパークスを訪問している）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 28th (actually April 20th, 1868), Saigo visited Parkes in Yokohama and explained the detail of events and the policy of the new government (additionally, on the day before, Katsu visited Parkes.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 28th (actually April 20, 1868), Saigo visited Parkes in Yokohama and explained the details of events and the policy of the new government (additionally, on the day before, Katsu visited Parkes.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 28th, Saigo visited Parkes in Yokohama and explained the details of events and the policy of the new government (additionally, on the day before, Katsu visited Parkes).</e>
<cmt>旧暦表記のみとし、ピリオドの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="243">
<j>パークスは西郷の説明に満足し、ここに「パークスの圧力」は消滅した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Parkes was satisfied with Saigo&apos;s explanation, so &quot;The pressure from Parkes&quot; ceased at this time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Parkes was satisfied with Saigo&apos;s explanation, so &quot;The pressure from Parkes&quot; ceased at this time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Parkes was satisfied with Saigo&apos;s explanation, so &quot;The pressure from Parkes&quot; ceased at this time.</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーション・アポストロフィーを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="59">
<sen id="244">
<j>城明け渡しと慶喜の水戸退去</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The surrender of the Castle and Yoshinobu&apos;s expulsion to Mito</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The surrender of the Castle and Yoshinobu&apos;s expulsion to Mito</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The surrender of the Castle and Yoshinobu&apos;s expulsion to Mito</e>
<cmt>全角アポストロフィーを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="245">
<j>江戸へ再来した西郷は勝・大久保らとの間で最終的な条件を詰めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saigo re-visited Edo and continued to discuss the final conditions with Katsu and Okubo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saigo re-visited Edo and continued to discuss the final conditions with Katsu and Okubo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saigo re-visited Edo and continued to discuss the final conditions with Katsu and Okubo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="246">
<j>4月4日には大総督府と徳川家との間で最終合意に達した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 4th (actually April 26th, 1868), the grand government general and the Tokugawa Family reached a final agreement.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 4th (actually April 26, 1868), the grand government general and the Tokugawa Family reached a final agreement.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 4th, the grand government general and the Tokugawa family reached a final agreement.</e>
<cmt>旧暦表記のみとし、the Tokugawa familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="247">
<j>東海道先鋒総督橋本実梁、副総督柳原前光、参謀西郷らが兵を率いて江戸城へ入城した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, the pacification governor-general of Tokaido, Saneyana HASHIMOTO, and the lieutenant governor Sakimitsu YANAGIWARA, and the staff officer, Saigo, entered the Edo Castle, leading their troops.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, the pacification governor-general of Tokaido, Saneyana HASHIMOTO, and the lieutenant governor Sakimitsu YANAGIWARA, and the staff officer, Saigo, entered the Edo Castle, leading their troops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, the pacification governor-general of Tokaido, Saneyana HASHIMOTO, and the lieutenant governor Sakimitsu YANAGIWARA, and the staff officer, Saigo, entered the Edo-jo Castle, leading their troops.</e>
<cmt>Edo-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="248">
<j>同時に徳川慶喜の死一等を減じ、水戸での謹慎を許可する勅旨が下された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, the Imperial court ordered that the first degree execution punishment of Yoshinobu be stricken from sentence; he was allowed confinement in Mito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, the Imperial court ordered that the first degree execution punishment of Yoshinobu be stricken from sentence; he was allowed confinement in Mito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, the Imperial court ordered that the first degree execution punishment of Yoshinobu be stricken from sentence; he was allowed confinement in Mito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="249">
<j>この勅旨を受け、11日には慶喜は謹慎所の寛永寺から水戸へ出発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshinobu received the Imperial order and on April 11th (actually May 3rd, 1868), departed from the Kanei-ji Temple, where he had been confined, to Mito.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshinobu received the Imperial order and on April 11th (actually May 3, 1868), departed from the Kanei-ji Temple, where he had been confined, to Mito.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshinobu received the Imperial order and on April 11th, departed from the Kanei-ji Temple, where he had been confined, to Mito.</e>
<cmt>旧暦表記のみとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="250">
<j>同日をもって江戸城は無血開城、東征軍が接収した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was on this day, the Tokugawa Family bloodlessly surrendered Edo Castle, and the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; seized the Castle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was on this day, the Tokugawa Family bloodlessly surrendered Edo Castle, and the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; seized the Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was on this day, the Tokugawa family bloodlessly surrendered Edo-jo Castle, and the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; seized the Castle.</e>
<cmt>the Tokugawa family、Edo-jo Castleとし、全角クォーテーションを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="60">
<sen id="251">
<j>それより前、4月8日に東征大総督有栖川宮は駿府を発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prior to this date, on April 8th (actually April 30th, 1868), &apos;Tousei Dai Soutoku&apos; (the commander of temporary army to suppress the might of the Tokugawa Edo Bakufu Army), Imperial Prince Arisugawa,&apos; departed from Sunpu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prior to this date, on April 8th (actually April 30, 1868), &apos;Tousei Dai Soutoku&apos; (the commander of the temporary army to suppress the might of the Tokugawa Edo Bakufu Army), Imperial Prince Arisugawa,&apos; departed from Sunpu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prior to this date, on April 8th, &apos;Tosei Dai Sotoku,&apos; Imperial Prince Arisugawanomiya, departed from Sunpu.</e>
<cmt>Tosei Dai Sotokuとし、全角クォーテーションを半角に修正、既出のため補足削除、Arisugawa→Arisugawanomiya、旧暦表記のみとし、不要なクォーテーション削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="252">
<j>同21日江戸城へ入城。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He entered into Edo Castle on April 21st (actually May 13th, 1868).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He entered into Edo Castle on April 21st (actually May 13, 1868).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He entered into Edo-jo Castle on April 21st.</e>
<cmt>旧暦表記のみとし、Edo-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="253">
<j>ここに江戸城は正式に大総督府の管下に入り、江戸城明け渡しが完了した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That was exact moment of Edo Castle&apos;s official jurisdiction transfer to the grand government general, and the grand government general&apos;s completion in the surrender of Edo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That was the exact moment of Edo Castle&apos;s official jurisdiction transfer to the grand government general, and the grand government general&apos;s completion in the surrender of Edo Castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That was the exact moment of Edo-jo Castle&apos;s official jurisdiction transfer to the grand government general, and the grand government general&apos;s completion in the surrender of Edo-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>全角アポストロフィーを半角に修正、Edo-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="254">
<j>また京都では4月9日、明治天皇が紫宸殿において軍神を祀った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, in Kyoto, on April 9th (actually May 1st, 1868), the Emperor Meiji worshiped the god of war at the Shishin-den Hall (hall for state ceremonies) inside the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, in Kyoto, on April 9th (actually May 1, 1868), the Emperor Meiji worshiped the god of war at the Shishin-den Hall (hall for state ceremonies) inside the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, in Kyoto, on April 9th, the Emperor Meiji worshiped the god of war at the Shishin-den Hall (hall for state ceremonies) inside the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>the Imperial Courtとし、旧暦表記のみとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="255">
<j>徳川慶喜が謝罪し、江戸を平定したことを報告している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor Meiji reported that Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA had apologized and that the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; conquered Edo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor Meiji reported that Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA had apologized and that the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; conquered Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor Meiji reported that Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA had apologized and that the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; conquered Edo.</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーションを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="61">
<sen id="256">
<j>榎本艦隊脱走</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The desertion of fleet ENOMOTO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The desertion of the fleet by ENOMOTO</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The desertion of the fleet by ENOMOTO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="257">
<j>海軍副総裁の榎本武揚は徳川家に対する処置を不満とし、約束の軍艦引き渡しを断固拒否していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The vice president of the Navy, Takeaki ENOMOTO firmly rejected the promise of handing over the warships based on his dissatisfaction in the treatment of the Tokugawa Family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The vice president of the Navy, Takeaki ENOMOTO firmly rejected the promise of handing over the warships based on his dissatisfaction in the treatment of the Tokugawa Family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The vice president of the Navy, Takeaki ENOMOTO firmly rejected the promise of handing over the warships based on his dissatisfaction in the treatment of the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>the Tokugawa familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="258">
<j>が、徳川慶喜が寛永寺から水戸へ移った4月11日、抗戦派の旧幕臣らとともに旧幕府艦隊7隻を率いて品川沖から出港し、館山市沖に逃れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 11th (actually May 3rd, 1868), while Yoshinobu was departing from the Kanei-ji Temple to Mito, Enomoto with other former retainers of the Tokugawa Bakufu, who were advocates of the resistance force party, left off port from the coast of Shinagawa; he was deserting to a point off the coast of Tateyama City, leading seven fleets of the former Bakufu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 11th (actually May 3, 1868), while Yoshinobu was departing from the Kanei-ji Temple to Mito, Enomoto with other former retainers of the Tokugawa Bakufu, who were advocates of the resistance force party, left the port from the coast of Shinagawa; he was deserting to a point off the coast of Tateyama City, leading seven ships of the former Bakufu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 11th, while Yoshinobu was departing from the Kanei-ji Temple to Mito, Enomoto with other former retainers of the Tokugawa shogunate, who were advocates of the resistance force party, left the port from the coast of Shinagawa; he was deserting to a point off the coast of Tateyama City, leading seven ships of the former bakufu.</e>
<cmt>the Tokugawa Bakufu→the Tokugawa shogunate、the former Bakufu→the former bakufuとし、旧暦表記のみとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="259">
<j>結局、勝の説得により艦隊はいったん品川に戻った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After all, Katsu successfully persuaded Enomoto and all other former retainers of the Bakufu, so the seven fleets returned to Shinagawa.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After all, Katsu successfully persuaded Enomoto and all other former retainers of the Bakufu so, the seven ships returned to Shinagawa.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After all, Katsu successfully persuaded Enomoto and all other former retainers of the bakufu so, the seven ships returned to Shinagawa.</e>
<cmt>the bakufuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="260">
<j>新政府軍に4隻（富士・朝陽・翔鶴・観光）を渡すことで妥協した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Enomoto and all the other former retainers compromised on the hand over of these four fleets (Fuji, Choyo, Shokaku, and Kanko) to the new government.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Enomoto and all the other former retainers compromised on the hand over of these four ships (Fuji, Choyo, Shokaku, and Kanko) to the new government.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Enomoto and all the other former retainers compromised on the hand over of these four ships (Fuji, Choyo, Shokaku, and Kanko) to the new government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="261">
<j>しかし、これにより降伏条件は完全には満たされなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this internal defiance, the Tokugawa Family couldn&apos;t completely fulfill the surrender conditions.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this internal defiance, the Tokugawa Family couldn&apos;t completely fulfill the surrender conditions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this internal defiance, the Tokugawa family could not completely fulfill the surrender conditions.</e>
<cmt>the Tokugawa familyとし、couldn’t→could notに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="262">
<j>その後も再三にわたり勝は榎本に自重を求めたが、徳川家に対する処分に不服の榎本はこれを聞かなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this incident, although Katsu repeatedly requested Enomoto to be prudent, Enomoto did not listen to Katsu since he was still dissatisfied with the punishment of the Tokugawa Family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this incident, although Katsu repeatedly requested Enomoto to be prudent, Enomoto did not listen to Katsu since he was still dissatisfied with the punishment of the Tokugawa Family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this incident, although Katsu repeatedly requested Enomoto to be prudent, Enomoto did not listen to Katsu since he was still dissatisfied with the punishment of the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>the Tokugawa familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="263">
<j>結局8月19日に8隻（開陽丸・回天丸・蟠竜丸・千代田形丸・神速丸・長鯨・美賀保・咸臨丸）を率いて東征軍に抵抗する東北諸藩の支援に向かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Finally, on August 19th (actually October 4th, 1868), Enomoto sailed away to support the Tohoku (Northern-east region) domains that were resisting the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; leading eight fleets (Kaiyo Maru, Kaiten Maru, Bonryu Maru, Chiyodagat, Shinsoku Maru, Cyogei, Mikaho Maru, and Kanrin Maru).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Finally, on August 19th (actually October 4, 1868), Enomoto sailed away to support the Tohoku (Northern-east region) domains that were resisting the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; leading eight ships (Kaiyo Maru, Kaiten Maru, Bonryu Maru, Chiyodagat, Shinsoku Maru, Cyogei, Mikaho Maru, and Kanrin Maru).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Finally, on August 19th, Enomoto sailed away to support the Tohoku (Northern-east region) domains that were resisting the &apos;expeditionary force to the east&apos; leading eight ships (Kaiyo Maru, Kaiten Maru, Banryu Maru, Chiyodagata Maru, Shinsoku Maru, Cyogei, Mikaho Maru, and Kanrin Maru).</e>
<cmt>Bonryu Maru→Banryu Maru、Chiyodagat→Chiyodagata Maruに修正、旧暦表記のみとし、全角クォーテーションを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="264">
<j>後に榎本らは函館市の五稜郭を占拠し、最後まで新政府軍に抵抗した（→箱館戦争）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Enomoto and other defiant former retainers occupied the Goryokaku (five-sided fortification) in Hakodate City and resisted the new government&apos;s Army until the end (please refer to the Battle of Hakodate.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Enomoto and other defiant former retainers occupied the Goryokaku (five-sided fortification) in Hakodate City and resisted the new government&apos;s Army until the end (please refer to the Battle of Hakodate.).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Enomoto and other defiant former retainers occupied the Goryokaku (five-sided fortification) in Hakodate City and resisted the new government&apos;s army until the end (please refer to the Battle of Hakodate.).</e>
<cmt>the new government&apos;s armyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="62">
<sen id="265">
<j>抗戦派と上野戦争</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The resistance force party and the Battle of Ueno</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The resistance force party and the Battle of Ueno</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The resistance force party and the Battle of Ueno</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="63">
<sen id="266">
<j>徳川家処分に不満を持つ抗戦派は、江戸近辺で挙兵する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The resistance force party maintaining its dissatisfaction with the punishment of the Tokugawa Family raised an army against the new government Army, from an area around the Edo region.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The resistance force party maintaining its dissatisfaction with the punishment of the Tokugawa Family raised an army against the new government Army, from an area around the Edo region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The resistance force party maintaining its dissatisfaction with the punishment of the Tokugawa family raised an army against the new government&apos;s army, from an area around the Edo region.</e>
<cmt>the Tokugawa family、the new government&apos;s armyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="267">
<j>しかし、新政府軍に各個撃破されていくことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the new government&apos;s Army destroyed them individually, one by one.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the new government&apos;s Army destroyed them individually, one by one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the new government&apos;s army destroyed them individually, one by one.</e>
<cmt>the new government&apos;s armyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="268">
<j>福田道直率いる撒兵隊は1500人程度で木更津市から船橋市へ出た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michinao FUKUDA was leading the Satsupeitai (the western style foot solders who were trained by a French military stratigist; this was established during the late Tokugawa Edo Bakufu period.) troops that numbered nearly 1,500.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michinao FUKUDA was leading the Satsupeitai (the western style foot solders who were trained by a French military stratigist; this was established during the late Tokugawa Edo Bakufu period.) troops that numbered nearly 1,500.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michinao FUKUDA was leading the Sappeitai (the western style foot solders who were trained by a French military stratigist; this was established during the late Tokugawa Edo bakufu period) troops that numbered nearly 1,500 and the troops went out from Kisarazu to Funahashi.</e>
<cmt>「木更津市から船橋市へ出た」→訳漏れのため訳出、Satsupeitai→Sappeitai、Edo Bakufu→Edo bakufuに修正、余分なピリオド削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="269">
<j>そこで海道軍と衝突、撃破された（市川・船橋戦争）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There the Tokaido-gun Army destroyed them. (The Battle of Ichikawa and Funabashi)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There the Tokaido-gun Army destroyed them. (The Battle of Ichikawa and Funabashi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There the Tokaido-gun Army destroyed them (The Battle of Ichikawa and Funabashi).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="270">
<j>大鳥圭介と歩兵隊は下総国府台 (市川市)（千葉県市川市）に集結した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keisuke OTORI and infantry soldiers Army gathered at Kunodai in Shimousa Province (Currently this place is located in Ichikawa City, Chiba prefecture.).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keisuke OTORI and an Army of infantry soldiers gathered at Kunodai in Shimousa Province (Currently this place is located in Ichikawa City, Chiba prefecture.).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keisuke OTORI and an Army of infantry soldiers gathered at Konodai in Shimosa Province (Currently this place is located in Ichikawa City, Chiba Prefecture.).</e>
<cmt>Kunodai→Konodai、Shimousa→Shimosaに修正、Chiba Pefectureとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="271">
<j>新選組の土方歳三らを加えて宇都宮城を陥落させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Otori and the infantry soldiers Army added Toshizo HIJIKATA and other soldiers of the Shinsengumi (a group who guarded Kyoto during the end of Tokugawa Shogunate) successfully seized Utsunomiya Castle and it fell to them.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Otori and the infantry soldiers added Toshizo HIJIKATA and other soldiers of the Shinsengumi (a group that guarded Kyoto during the end of Tokugawa Shogunate) successfully seized Utsunomiya Castle and it fell to them.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Otori and the infantry soldiers added Toshizo HIJIKATA and other soldiers of the Shinsengumi successfully seized Utsunomiya-jo Castle and it fell to them.</e>
<cmt>Shinsengumi→既出のため補足削除、Utsunomiya-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="272">
<j>しかし、東山道軍によって奪還された（宇都宮城の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Tokaido-gun Army recovered the Utsunomiya Castle (The battle of Utsunomiya Castle).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Tokaido-gun Army recovered the Utsunomiya Castle (The battle of Utsunomiya Castle).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Tosando-gun Army recovered the Utsunomiya-jo Castle (The Battle of Utsunomiya-jo Castle).</e>
<cmt>Tokaido-gun Army→Tosando-gun Armyに修正、Utsunomiya-jo Castle、The Battle of Utsunomiya-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="273">
<j>日光街道を北へ逃走し、その後東北から箱館へ転戦した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward, Otori and Hijikata fled with the infantry north along the Nikko-kaido Road, fighting throughout the Tohoku into the Hakodate regions, in one place after another.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterward, Otori and Hijikata fled with the infantry north along the Nikko-kaido Road, fighting throughout the Tohoku into the Hakodate regions, one place after another.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterward, Otori and Hijikata fled with the infantry north along the Nikko-kaido Road, fighting throughout the Tohoku into the Hakodate regions, one place after another.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="64">
<sen id="274">
<j>いっぽう一橋徳川家家臣の渋沢成一郎・天野八郎らは上野寛永寺に謹慎していた慶喜の冤罪を晴らし、薩賊を討つと称して幕臣などを集めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the vassals of the Hitotsubashi Tokugawa family, Seiichiro SHIBUSAWA and Hachiro AMANO, gathered shogunate retainers in progress of their purpose; they were intent on clearing the false charge of Yoshinobu, who had been confining himself in the Kanei-ji Temple; they intended to defeat the Satsuzoku (the Satsuma Domain).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the vassals of the Hitotsubashi Tokugawa family, Seiichiro SHIBUSAWA and Hachiro AMANO, gathered shogunate retainers in progress of their purpose; they were intent on clearing the false charge of Yoshinobu, who had been confining himself in the Kanei-ji Temple; they intended to defeat the Satsuzoku (the Satsuma Domain).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the vassals of the Hitotsubashi Tokugawa family, Seiichiro SHIBUSAWA and Hachiro AMANO, gathered shogunate retainers in progress of their purpose; they were intent on clearing the false charge of Yoshinobu, who had been confining himself in the Ueno Kanei-ji Temple; they intended to defeat the Satsuzoku (the Satsuma clan).</e>
<cmt>「上野」→訳漏れのため訳出、the Satsuma Domain→the Satsuma clanとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="275">
<j>それから、彰義隊を結成。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Shibusawa, Amano, and the shogunate retainers formed the Shogitai (a group of former Tokugawa retainers opposed to the Meiji government who fought in the Battle of Ueno).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Shibusawa, Amano, and the shogunate retainers formed the Shogitai (a group of former Tokugawa retainers opposed to the Meiji government who fought in the Battle of Ueno).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Shibusawa, Amano, and the shogunate retainers formed the Shogitai (a group of former Tokugawa retainers opposed to the Meiji government who fought in the Battle of Ueno).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="276">
<j>上野の山に集結していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The members of the Shogitai gathered in the Ueno Mountain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The members of the Shogitai gathered on Ueno Mountain.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The members of the Shogitai gathered on Ueno Mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="277">
<j>江戸城留守居の松平斉民は、彰義隊を利用して江戸の治安維持を図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naritami MATSUDAIRA, was the Rusui (a caretaker or keeper; an official post in the Edo period) of Edo Castle; he attempted to use the Shogitai troops in the enforcement of maintenance of security at Edo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naritami MATSUDAIRA, was the Rusui (a caretaker or keeper; an official post in the Edo period) of Edo Castle; he attempted to use the Shogitai troops in the enforcement of maintenance of security at Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naritami MATSUDAIRA, was the Rusui (a caretaker or keeper; an official post in the Edo period) of Edo-jo Castle; he attempted to use the Shogitai troops in the enforcement of maintenance of security at Edo.</e>
<cmt>Edo-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="278">
<j>しかし、かえって彰義隊の力が増大し、新政府軍の懐疑を招く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Shogitai troop force increased in power, inviting remarks of skepticism from the new government.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Shogitai troop force increased in power, inviting remarks of skepticism from the new government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Shogitai troop force increased in power, inviting remarks of skepticism from the new government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="279">
<j>4月11日に慶喜が上野を退去した後も、彰義隊は寛永寺に住する輪王寺宮公現法親王を擁して上野に居座り続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Yoshinobu left Edo on April 11th (actually May 3rd, 1868), the Shogitai troops changed their master to the &apos;Cloistered Imperial Prince Rinojinomiya Kogen&apos; who was residing in the Kanei-ji Temple, then continued to stay in Ueno.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Yoshinobu left Edo on April 11th (actually May 3, 1868), the Shogitai troops changed their master to the &apos;Cloistered Imperial Prince Rinojinomiya Kogen&apos; who was residing in the Kanei-ji Temple, then continued to stay in Ueno.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Yoshinobu left Ueno on April 11th, the Shogitai troops changed their master to the Cloistered Imperial Prince Rinojinomiya Kogen who was residing in the Kanei-ji Temple, then continued to stay in Ueno.</e>
<cmt>Edo→Uenoに修正、クォーテーション削除、旧暦表記のみとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="280">
<j>閏4月29日関東監察使として江戸に下った総裁三条実美は、鎮将府を設置した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was on April 29th (actually June 19th, 1868), that the inspector of Kanto region Sanetomi SANJO, in his role as President of the new government, went to Edo and established the Chinshyo Fu (the new government organization).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was on April 29th (actually June 19, 1868), that the inspector of the Kanto region Sanetomi SANJO, in his role as President of the new government, went to Edo and established the Chinshyo Fu (the new government organization).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was on April 29th of the leap year, that the inspector of the Kanto region Sanetomi SANJO, in his role as President of the new government, went to Edo and established the Chinsho Fu (the new government organization).</e>
<cmt>Chinshyo Fu→Chinsho Fuに修正、「閏」→訳漏れのため訳出、旧暦表記のみとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="281">
<j>民政・治安権限を徳川家から奪取し、彰義隊の江戸市中取締の任を解くことを通告した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Sanetomi SANJO removed the all authority over civil administration and public security from the Tokugawa Family; in addition, he reportedly removed the Shogitai form the post of control in the City of Edo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Sanetomi SANJO removed the all authority over civil administration and public security from the Tokugawa Family; in addition, he reportedly removed the Shogitai form the post of control in the City of Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Sanetomi SANJO removed the all authority over civil administration and public security from the Tokugawa family; in addition, he reportedly removed the Shogitai form the post of control in the City of Edo.</e>
<cmt>the Tokugawa familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="282">
<j>その後、新政府自身が彰義隊の武装解除に当たる旨を布告した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, the new government declared by statement to order for the disarmament of the Shogitai troops.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, the new government declared by statement to order the disarmaming of the Shogitai troops.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, the new government declared by statement to order the disarmaming of the Shogitai troops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="283">
<j>5月15日に大村益次郎率いる新政府軍が1日で鎮圧した（→上野戦争）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 15th (actually July 4th, 1868), Masujiro OMURA leading the new government&apos;s Army, suppressed the Shogitai troops in one day (Please refer to the Battle of Ueno.).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 15th (actually July 4, 1868), Masujiro OMURA leading the new government&apos;s Army, suppressed the Shogitai troops in one day (Please refer to the Battle of Ueno.).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 15th, Masujiro OMURA leading the new government&apos;s army, suppressed the Shogitai troops in one day (Please refer to the Battle of Ueno.).</e>
<cmt>the new government&apos;s armyとし、旧暦表記のみとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="284">
<j>これらの戦いにより、抗戦派はほぼ江戸近辺から一掃された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After these battles, the resistance force policy party was nearly eliminated in Edo, and area surrounded the region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After these battles, the resistance force policy party was nearly eliminated in Edo, and area surrounding the region.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After these battles, the resistance force policy party was nearly eliminated in Edo, and area surrounding the region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="65">
<sen id="285">
<j>静岡藩の成立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The establishment of the Shizuoka Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The establishment of the Shizuoka Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The establishment of the Shizuoka Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="286">
<j>関東監察使三条実美は閏4月29日、田安亀之助（後の徳川家達。6歳）による徳川家相続を差し許す勅旨を伝達した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 29th (Actually June 19th, 1868), the inspector of the Kanto region, Sanetomi SANJO, notified by imperial order, that the Imperial Court would allow Kamenosuke TAYASU (Later, he became Iesato TOKUGAWA. He was six years old.) to become the successor to Tokugawa Family line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 29th (Actually June 19, 1868), the inspector of the Kanto region, Sanetomi SANJO, notified by imperial order, that the Imperial Court would allow Kamenosuke TAYASU (Later, he became Iesato TOKUGAWA. He was six years old.) to become the successor to Tokugawa Family line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 29th of the leap year, the inspector of the Kanto region, Sanetomi SANJO, notified by imperial order, that the Imperial Court would allow Kamenosuke TAYASU (He was 6 year old then. Later he was known as Iesato TOKUGAWA) to become the successor to Tokugawa family line.</e>
<cmt>「閏」→訳漏れのため訳出、旧暦表記のみとし、余分なスペース消去、the Tokugawa familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="287">
<j>ついで5月24日には駿府70万石に移封されることが発表となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, on May 24th (Actually July 13th, 1868), The Imperial Court announced movement of the Tokugawa Family for relocation to the Sunpu region with its 700,000 koku (approximately 126 million liters of crop yield).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, on May 24th (Actually July 13, 1868), The Imperial Court announced movement of the Tokugawa Family for relocation to the Sunpu region with its 700,000 koku (approximately 126 million liters of crop yield).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, on May 24th, the Imperial Court announced movement of the Tokugawa family for relocation to the Sunpu region with its 700,000 koku (approximately 126 million liters of crop yield).</e>
<cmt>The→theに修正、the Tokugawa familyとし、旧暦表記のみとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="288">
<j>これにより新たに駿府藩徳川家が成立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial Court established the new Tokugawa Family of Sunpu Domain in this announcement.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Court established the new Tokugawa Family of Sunpu Domain in this announcement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Court established the new Tokugawa family of the Sunpu Domain in this announcement.</e>
<cmt>Tokugawa family、the Sunpu Domainとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="289">
<j>しかし、800万石から70万石への減封によって膨大な家臣団を養うことはできなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the new Tokugawa Family in Sunpu Domain could not support a large body of former vassals since their territory had been dramatically reduced; this was from 8million koku (approximately 1,440 million liters of crop yield) to 700,000 koku (approximately 126 million liters of crop yield).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the new Tokugawa Family in Sunpu Domain could not support a large body of former vassals since their territory had been dramatically reduced; this was from 8,000,000 koku (approximately 1,440,000,000 liters of crop yield) to 700,000 koku (approximately 126,000,000 liters of crop yield).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the new Tokugawa family in the Sunpu Domain could not support a large body of former vassals since their territory had been dramatically reduced; this was from 8,000,000 koku (approximately 1,440,000,000 liters of crop yield) to 700,000 koku (approximately 126,000,000 liters of crop yield).</e>
<cmt>Tokugawa family、the Sunpu Domainとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="290">
<j>駿府へ赴いた者は15000人程度だったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the number of the people serving in the Sunpu Domain was approximately 15,000.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the number of the people serving in the Sunpu Domain was approximately 15,000.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the number of the people serving in the Sunpu Domain was approximately 15,000.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="66">
<sen id="291">
<j>江戸城から皇居へ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Converting the Edo Castle to the Imperial Palace</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Converting the Edo Castle to the Imperial Palace</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Converting the Edo-jo Castle to the Imperial Palace</e>
<cmt>Edo-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="67">
<sen id="292">
<j>すでに大久保利通は正月下旬の時点で、京都には旧弊が多いとして大阪遷都論を政府へ提出している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshimichi OKUBO, by the end of January (Actually the middle of February, 1868) had submitted the doctrine for transferring the capital from Kyoto to Osaka; this was because there were too many conservative minded people in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshimichi OKUBO, by the end of January (Actually the middle of February, 1868) had submitted the doctrine for transferring the capital from Kyoto to Osaka; this was because there were too many conservative minded people in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshimichi OKUBO, by the end of January, had submitted the doctrine for transferring the capital from Kyoto to Osaka; this was because there were too many conservative minded people in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>旧暦表記のみとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="293">
<j>木戸もこれに強く賛同している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kido was in strongly agreement with this doctrine.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kido was in strong agreement with this doctrine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kido was in strong agreement with this doctrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="294">
<j>これには公家などから反対が多く、結局大阪行幸の実行に留まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mainly of the court&apos;s nobles opposed this doctrine, so the new government only performed Imperial visitation in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mainly of the court&apos;s nobles opposed this doctrine, so the new government only performed Imperial visitation in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mainly of the court&apos;s nobles opposed this doctrine, so the new government only performed Imperial visitation in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>全角アポストロフィーを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="295">
<j>しかし、大久保・木戸らの間で遷都論は燻り続けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Okubo and Kido continued to bring up the doctrine for transferring the capital.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Okubo and Kido continued to bring up the doctrine for transferring the capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Okubo and Kido continued to bring up the doctrine for transferring the capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="296">
<j>そんな中、江戸城が無血で新政府の管轄に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the middle of debate on the transference of the capital, the new government acquired Edo Castle bloodlessly.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the middle of debate on the transference of the capital, the new government acquired Edo Castle bloodlessly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the middle of debate on the transference of the capital, the new government acquired Edo-jo Castle bloodlessly.</e>
<cmt>Edo-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="297">
<j>このことは、遷都先として江戸が急浮上することに繋がった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the new government abruptly nominated Edo as a potential place for relocation of the Capital.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the new government abruptly nominated Edo as a potential place for relocation of the Capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the new government abruptly nominated Edo as a potential place for relocation of the Capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="68">
<sen id="298">
<j>9月8日、元号が明治と改元される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 8th (Actually October 23rd, 1868), the Imperial Court proclaimed the new era name, &quot;Meiji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 8th (Actually October 23, 1868), the Imperial Court proclaimed the new era name, &quot;Meiji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 8th, the Imperial Court proclaimed the new era name, &quot;Meiji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーションを半角に修正、旧暦のみとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="299">
<j>すると、同月20日明治天皇が東京（7月に江戸ヲ称シテ東京ト為スノ詔書）行幸に出発し、10月13日に江戸城に到着。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, on September 20th (Actually November 11th, 1868), the Emperor Meiji departed from Kyoto to perform the Imperial visit to Tokyo [In July (Actually September of 1868); there the Imperial court issued the imperial edict for Edo to be renamed as Tokyo.]; and then, the Emperor arrived at Edo Castle on October 13th (Actually November 26th, 1868).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, on September 20th (Actually November 11th, 1868), Emperor Meiji departed from Kyoto to perform the Imperial visit to Tokyo [In July (Actually September of 1868); there the Imperial court issued the imperial edict for Edo to be renamed as Tokyo.]; and then, the Emperor arrived at Edo Castle on October 13th (Actually November 26, 1868).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, on September 20th, Emperor Meiji departed from Kyoto to perform the Imperial visit to Tokyo (In July there the Imperial court issued the imperial edict for Edo to be renamed as Tokyo.); and then, the Emperor arrived at Edo-jo Castle on October 13th.</e>
<cmt>カッコ表記修正、旧暦のみとし、Edo-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="300">
<j>同時に名を「東京城」と改められ、東幸の際の皇居と定められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time of the Emperor&apos;s arrival, the Imperial Court renamed Edo Castle as &quot;the Tokyo Castle&quot; elevating it to the level of an Imperial Palace when the Emperor would perform his &quot;going to the east&quot; trip.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time of the Emperor&apos;s arrival, the Imperial Court renamed Edo Castle as &quot;Tokyo Castle&quot; elevating it to the level of an Imperial Palace when the Emperor would perform his &quot;going to the east&quot; trip.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time of the Emperor&apos;s arrival, the Imperial Court renamed Edo-jo Castle as &quot;Tokyo-jo Castle&quot; elevating it to the level of an Imperial Palace when the Emperor would perform his &quot;going to the east&quot; trip.</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーション・アポストロフィーを半角に修正、Edo-jo Castle、Tokyo-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="301">
<j>幕府のシンボルであった江戸城に天皇が入ることで、天皇が皇国一体・東西同視のもと自ら政を決することを宣言するデモンストレーションともなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor entered into the Edo Castle which was the symbol of the Bakufu, and this was a symbolic event for the Emperor was demonstrating that the entire imperial country was to be unified; the east and west to be identified as one, then the Emperor declared that he would control all administration by his decision.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor entered the Edo Castle which was the symbol of the Bakufu, and this was a symbolic event for the Emperor was demonstrating that the entire imperial country was to be unified; the east and west to be identified as one, then the Emperor declared that he would control all administration by his decision.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor entered the Edo-jo Castle which was the symbol of the bakufu, and this was a symbolic event for the Emperor was demonstrating that the entire imperial country was to be unified; the east and west to be identified as one, then the Emperor declared that he would control all administration by his decision.</e>
<cmt>Edo-jo Castle、the bakufuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="302">
<j>この後、再度の東幸が行われるとともに、首都機能が京都から東京へ次々と移転。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this historical turn of events, the Emperor repeatedly performed his &apos;going to the east&apos; trip; thru these trips, the new government was relocating the administration of the capitals functions, one after another, from Kyoto to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this historical turn of events, the Emperor repeatedly performed his &apos;going to the east&apos; trip; thru these trips, the new government was relocating the administration of the capital functions, one after another, from Kyoto to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this historical turn of events, the Emperor repeatedly performed his &apos;going to the east&apos; trip; through these trips, the new government was relocating the administration of the capital functions, one after another, from Kyoto to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>thru→through、全角クォーテーションを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="303">
<j>事実上東京が首都と見なされるようになり、東京城はやがて「宮城」「皇居」と呼ばれるようになったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eventually, the citizens of Japan recognized the fact, that Tokyo was the defacto capital; then gradually &quot;Tokyo Castle&quot; became to be referred to as the &quot;Kyujo (place where the Emperor lives),&quot; and finally as the &quot;Kokyo (Imperial Palace).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eventually, the citizens of Japan recognized the fact, that Tokyo was the defacto capital; then gradually &quot;Tokyo Castle&quot; became to be referred to as the &quot;Kyujo (place where the Emperor lives),&quot; and finally as the &quot;Kokyo (Imperial Palace).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eventually, the citizens of Japan recognized the fact, that Tokyo was the de facto capital; then gradually &quot;Tokyo-jo Castle&quot; became to be referred to as the &quot;Kyujo&quot; (place where the Emperor lives), and finally as the &quot;Kokyo&quot; (Imperial Palace).</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーションを半角に修正、位置を移動、defacto→de factoに修正、Tokyo-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="69">
<sen id="304">
<j>江戸開城の意義</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The meaning of the surrender of the Edo Castel</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The meaning of the surrender of the Edo Castle</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The meaning of the surrender of the Edo-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>Edo-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="305">
<j>当時、人口100万人を超える世界最大規模の都市であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, the population of Edo was more than one million, so Edo City was the largest city in the world.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, the population of Edo was more than one million, so Edo City was the largest city in the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, the population of Edo was more than one million, so Edo City was the largest city in the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="306">
<j>江戸とその住民を戦火に巻き込まずにすんだことは、江戸開城の最大の成果であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, two significant elements accomplished in the surrender of the Edo Castle were the avoidance war and fire upon Edo City and its massive population.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, two significant elements were accomplished in the surrender of the Edo Castle; the avoidance war and fire upon Edo City and its massive population.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, two significant elements were accomplished in the surrender of the Edo-jo Castle; the avoidance war and fire upon Edo City and its massive population.</e>
<cmt>Edo-jo Castleとし、余分なスペース消去しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="307">
<j>勝は後に西郷を「江戸の大恩人」と讃えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsu would later praise Saigo as &quot;the great benefactor of the Edo.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsu would later praise Saigo as &quot;the great benefactor of the Edo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsu would later praise Saigo as &quot;the great benefactor of the Edo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーションを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="308">
<j>また、江戸開城は一連の戊辰戦争の流れの中で、それまで日本の支配者であった徳川家が、新時代の支配者たるべき明治新政府に対して完全降伏するという象徴的な事件であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, the surrender of the Edo Castle was a historically symbolic incident during the continuous lines of the Boshin Civil War; the Tokugawa Family completely surrendered to the New Meiji government which would assert the political control into the new age.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, the surrender of Edo Castle was a historically symbolic incident during the continuous lines of the Boshin Civil War; the Tokugawa Family completely surrendered to the New Meiji government which would assert the political control into the new age.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, the surrender of Edo-jo Castle was a historically symbolic incident during the continuous lines of the Boshin Civil War; the Tokugawa family completely surrendered to the New Meiji government which would assert the political control into the new age.</e>
<cmt>Edo-jo Castle、the Tokugawa familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="309">
<j>日本統治の正統性が徳川幕府から天皇を中心とする朝廷に移ったことも意味した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This event is illustrative to the meaning for transferring legitimate rights to govern Japan; it was transferred from the Tokugawa Bakufu to the Imperial Court of which the Emperors were the central figure.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This event is illustrative to the meaning for transferring legitimate rights to govern Japan; it was transferred from the Tokugawa Bakufu to the Imperial Court of which the Emperors were the central figure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This event is illustrative to the meaning for transferring legitimate rights to govern Japan; it was transferred from the Tokugawa shogunate to the Imperial Court of which the Emperors were the central figure.</e>
<cmt>the Tokugawa shogunateとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="310">
<j>諸外国の立場もこれ以降、局外中立を保ちながらも、新政府側へ徐々にシフトしていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this incident, all foreign countries maintained their neutrality positions; then they would gradually realign into positions in support of the new government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this incident, all foreign countries maintained their neutrality positions; then they would gradually realign into positions in support of the new government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this incident, all foreign countries maintained their neutrality positions; then they would gradually realign into positions in support of the new government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="311">
<j>以後の戦いは、新政府軍の鎮撫とそれに抵抗する奥羽越列藩同盟という構図で語られることが多くなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the surrender of Edo Castle, historians and other experts often considered the wars which followed to be directly connected with suppression by the new government Army and the reaction of the resisting forces of the Ouetsu-reppan alliance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the surrender of Edo Castle, historians and other experts often considered the wars which followed to be directly connected with suppression by the new government Army and the reaction of the resisting forces of the Ouetsu-reppan alliance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the surrender of Edo-jo Castle, historians and other experts often considered the wars which followed to be directly connected with suppression by the new government army and the reaction of the resisting forces of the Ouetsu-reppan alliance.</e>
<cmt>Edo-jo Castle、the new government armyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="312">
<j>また江戸時代に事実上日本の首都機能を担った江戸という財産が、ほぼ無傷で新政府の傘下に接収された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The new government seized property, taking Edo city, the main Japanese capital for functions during the Edo period, this was done with almost no damage; so, Edo came under organizational control of the new government.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The new government seized property, taking Edo city, the main Japanese capital for functions during the Edo period, this was done with almost no destruction so, Edo came under the organizational control of the new government.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The new government seized property, taking Edo, the main Japanese capital for functions during the Edo period, this was done with almost no destruction so, Edo came under the organizational control of the new government.</e>
<cmt>Edo city→Edoとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="313">
<j>このことは、新国家の建設に向けて邁進しつつあった新政府にとっては、大きなメリットになったと言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, the new government seemed to have the great merit from seizing Edo because the new government was striving to establish the new country.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, the new government seemed to enjoy great merit from seizing Edo because the new government was striving to establish the new country.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, the new government seemed to enjoy great merit from seizing Edo because the new government was striving to establish the new country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="70">
<sen id="314">
<j>その一方で、無血開城という事実が一人歩きした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, &quot;the bloodless surrender of the Castle&quot; led to unintended consequences.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, &quot;the bloodless surrender of the Castle&quot; led to unintended consequences.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, &quot;the bloodless surrender of the Castle&quot; led to unintended consequences.</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーションを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="315">
<j>内外に戊辰戦争全体が最低限の流血で乗り越えられたといういわば虚像をも産むことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The domestic and foreign perspective opinions reached the general misconception of the Boshin Civil War being a less bloody conflict.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The domestic and foreign perspective opinions reached the general misconception of the Boshin Civil War being a less bloody conflict.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The domestic and foreign perspective opinions reached the general misconception of the Boshin Civil War being a less bloody conflict.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="316">
<j>しかし江戸開城自体は、戊辰戦争史全体の中では序盤に位置する事件であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in reality, the surrender of the Edo Castle was the opening chapter phase into the entire history of the Boshin Civil War.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in reality, the surrender of the Edo Castle was the opening chapter phase into the entire history of the Boshin Civil War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in reality, the surrender of the Edo-jo Castle was the opening chapter phase into the entire history of the Boshin Civil War.</e>
<cmt>Edo-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="317">
<j>それ以後の北越戦争・会津戦争・箱館まで続く一連の内戦は、むしろこれ以降いっそう激化していったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this incident, the Boshin Civil War continued; the civil war became rather violent as in: the Hokuetsu War, Aizu War, and Hakodate War; so the Civil War was never a war of minimal bloodshed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this incident, the Boshin Civil War continued; the civil war became rather violent as in: the Hokuetsu War, Aizu War, and Hakodate War; so the Civil War was never a war of minimal bloodshed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this incident, the Boshin Civil War continued; the civil war became rather violent as in: the Hokuetsu War, Aizu War, and Hakodate War; so the Civil War was never a war of minimal bloodshed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="318">
<j>決して内戦の流血自体が少なく済んだわけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This, the Civil War was never a war of minimal bloodshed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This, the Civil War was never a war of minimal bloodshed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This, the Civil War was never a war of minimal bloodshed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="319">
<j>江戸城という精神的支柱を失った幕臣たちの中にも、榎本の艦隊とともに北上し、戊辰戦争を戦い続ける者たちも少なくなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the Shogunate vassals who lost their psychological &quot;backbone&quot;, at Edo Castle, many joined the fleet of Enomoto and went north; this allowed them to participate in the future battles of the Boshin Civil War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the Shogunate vassals who lost their psychological &quot;backbone,&quot; at Edo Castle, many joined the fleet of Enomoto and went north; this allowed them to participate in the future battles of the Boshin Civil War.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the shogunate vassals who lost their psychological &quot;backbone,&quot; at Edo-jo Castle, many joined the fleet of Enomoto and went north; this allowed them to participate in the future battles of the Boshin Civil War.</e>
<cmt>the shogunate vassals、Edo-jo Castleとし、全角クォーテーションを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="71">
<sen id="320">
<j>江戸城が無傷で開城したことは半ば予想されたこととはいえ、新政府の主要士族メンバーにとっては拍子抜けでもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although, many of the shizoku (family or person with samurai ancestors) being main members of the new government, had some sense of Edo Castle being surrendered undamaged, they never the less, felt deflated as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although, many of the shizoku families or persons with samurai ancestors, being main members of the new government, had some sense of Edo Castle being surrendered undamaged, they never the less, felt deflated as well.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although, many of the shizoku families or persons with samurai ancestors, being main members of the new government, had some sense of Edo-jo Castle being surrendered undamaged, they nevertheless, felt deflated as well.</e>
<cmt>never the less→nevertheless、Edo-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="321">
<j>なぜなら、以前より軍事的衝突を回避しようとしていた松平春嶽ら列侯会議派が常に政府の主導権の巻き返しを図ろうとしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were other factors behind this feeling of deflation within the new governments side; one factor, Shungaku MATSUDAIRA and some other members in the council of the feudal lords&apos; party, made previous efforts for avoidance of militaristic conflicts between the two opponents; however, they always attempted to recover from any setbacks, proceeding to regain their initiative.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were other factors behind this feeling of deflation within the new governments side; one factor, Shungaku MATSUDAIRA and some other members in the council of the feudal lords&apos; party, made previous efforts for avoiding militaristic conflicts between the two opponents; however, they always attempted to recover from any setbacks, proceeding to regain their initiative.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were other factors behind this feeling of deflation within the new governments side; one factor, Shungaku MATSUDAIRA and some other members in the council of the feudal lords&apos; party, made previous efforts for avoiding militaristic conflicts between the two opponents; however, they always attempted to recover from any setbacks, proceeding to regain their initiative.</e>
<cmt>全角アポストロフィーを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="322">
<j>そのうえ、にわか仕立ての新政府軍はその実、統一日本国の軍隊ではあり得ず、事実上諸藩の緩やかな連合体に過ぎなかったため、諸藩の結束を高めるためには強力な敵を打倒するという目的を必要としていたからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, another factor was the newly established &apos;new government Army&apos; inability to as the unified Japanese Army in a practical sense; in reality, this was the only the alliance which loosely combined all of the domains.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, another factor was the newly established &apos;new government Army&apos; inability as a unified Japanese Army in a practical sense; in reality, this was the only an alliance which loosely combined all of the domains.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, another factor was the newly established &apos;new government army&apos; inability as a unified Japanese Army in a practical sense; in reality, this was the only an alliance which loosely combined all of the domains.</e>
<cmt>new government armyとし、全角クォーテーションを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="323">
<j>そのため、諸藩の結束を高めるためには強力な敵を打倒するという目的を必要としていたからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the new government required the direct purpose of defeating a powerful enemy in order to achieve a firm consensus to unify the domains.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the new government required the direct purpose of defeating a powerful enemy in order to achieve a firm consensus to unify the domains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the new government required the direct purpose of defeating a powerful enemy in order to achieve a firm consensus to unify the domains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="324">
<j>そこで諸藩の団結強化のため、江戸城に代わる新たな犠牲を想定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, the new government created scapegoats in order to strengthen its position for unification of the domains.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, the new government created scapegoats in order to strengthen its position for unification of the domains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, the new government created scapegoats in order to strengthen its position for unification of the domains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="325">
<j>それは、先の降伏条件でも問罪の対象として名指しされた松平容保の会津藩（および弟の松平定敬）であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the scapegoats the new government directed its focus on was the lord of Aize Domain Katamori MATSUDAIRA (and the younger of brother, Sadaaki MATSUDAIRA); he was an accusation target of the new government, because of his connection to the original Edo edict.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the scapegoats the new government directed its focus on was the lord of Aize Domain Katamori MATSUDAIRA (and the younger of brother, Sadaaki MATSUDAIRA); he was an accusation target of the new government, because of his connection to the original Edo edict.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the scapegoats the new government directed its focus on was the lord of the Aize Domain Katamori MATSUDAIRA (and the younger brother, Sadaaki MATSUDAIRA); he was an accusation target of the new government, because of his connection to the original Edo edict.</e>
<cmt>the Aizu Domainとし、the younger of brother→the younger brotherに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="326">
<j>また去就を明らかにしていなかった東北諸藩であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, some of the other scapegoats the new government focused upon were in the domains of the Tohoku region, which had yet to clear their behavior.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, some of the other scapegoats the new government focused upon were in the domains of the Tohoku region, which had yet to clear their behavior.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, some of the other scapegoats the new government focused upon were in the domains of the Tohoku region, which had yet to clear their behavior.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="327">
<j>実際、徳川慶喜に対する処分にはそれほど強硬ではなかった木戸孝允も、大久保利通に対して会津藩を討伐しなくては新政府は成り立たないと述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, TAKAyoshi KIDO, who had not demonstrated a strong opinion regarding the severe punishment of Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA, told Toshimichi OKUBO that the new government could not be established without defeating the Aizu Domain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, TAKAyoshi KIDO, who had not demonstrated a strong opinion regarding the severe punishment of Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA, told Toshimichi OKUBO that the new government could not be established without defeating the Aizu Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, Takayoshi KIDO, who had not demonstrated a strong opinion regarding the severe punishment of Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA, told Toshimichi OKUBO that the new government could not be established without defeating the Aizu Domain.</e>
<cmt>TAKAyoshi→Takayoshiに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="328">
<j>大久保も賛同している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Okubo agreed with Kido.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Okubo agreed with Kido.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Okubo agreed with Kido.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="72">
<sen id="329">
<j>また、江戸城とともに従来の幕府の統治機構である幕藩体制がほぼ明治政府に継承された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, along with the Edo Castle, the new Meiji government took over almost all of the feudal system, which was the characteristic of the Shogunate and was the governing structure of the former Tokugawa Bakufu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, along with the Edo Castle, the new Meiji government took over almost all of the feudal system, which was the characteristic of the Shogunate and was the governing structure of the former Tokugawa Bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, along with the Edo-jo Castle, the new Meiji government took over almost all of the feudal system, which was the characteristic of the bakufu and was the governing structure of the former Tokugawa shogunate.</e>
<cmt>Edo-jo Caslte、the Shogunate→the bakufu、Tokugawa Bakufu→Tokugawa shogunateとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="330">
<j>強力な政府の下に富国強兵を図り、欧米列強に対抗しうる中央集権的な国家を形成しようとしていた新政府であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The new government attempted to implement the fukoku kyohei (fortifying the country and strengthening the military) policy under the strong governmental power and then to build strong state; this would have the effect of centralization in administrative powers in order to stand up against any of the worlds major powers of the west.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The new government attempted to implement the fukoku kyohei (fortifying the country and strengthening the military) policy under the strong governmental power and then to build strong state; this would have the effect of centralization in administrative powers in order to stand up against any of the worlds major powers of the west.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The new government attempted to implement the fukoku kyohei (fortifying the country and strengthening the military) policy under the strong governmental power and then to build strong state; this would have the effect of centralization in administrative powers in order to stand up against any of the worlds major powers of the west.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="331">
<j>だから、この事は新政府にとっては、旧弊を温存することにもなりうる諸刃の剣であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it would have been the assumption of a double-edged sword to the new government, as the new government inherited the feudal system from the former Bakufu, since the new government would also incorporate all of the conservative people.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it would have been the assumption of a double-edged sword to the new government, as the new government inherited the feudal system from the former Bakufu, since the new government would also incorporate all of the conservative people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it would have been the assumption of a double-edged sword to the new government, as the new government inherited the feudal system from the former bakufu, since the new government would also incorporate all of the conservative people.</e>
<cmt>Bakufu→bakufuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="332">
<j>結局のところ近代国家を建設するためには、各地を支配する藩（大名）の解体が不可避であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After all, the new government could not avoid dismantling the domains [a daimyo (Japanese feudal lord)] which ruled the local areas in order to build the modern state.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After all, the new government could not avoid dismantling the domains [a daimyo (Japanese feudal lord)] which ruled the local areas in order to build the modern state.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After all, the new government could not avoid dismantling the domains (a daimyo [Japanese feudal lord]) which ruled the local areas in order to build the modern state.</e>
<cmt>カッコ表記修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="333">
<j>いったん藩地と人民を朝廷に返還する手続きを取った（版籍奉還）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once the new government would implement the process; the lords would return their territorial domains and residences to the Imperial Court (&quot;Hansekihokna&quot;; the return of the lands and people from the feudal lords to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once the new government would implement the process; the lords would return their territorial domains and residences to the Imperial Court (&quot;Hansekihokna;&quot; the return of the lands and people from the feudal lords to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once the new government would implement the process; the lords would return their territorial domains and residences to the Imperial Court (&quot;Hanseki hokan;&quot; the return of the lands and people from the feudal lords to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>Hansekihokna→Hanseki hokanに修正、全角クォーテーションを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="334">
<j>さらに最終的には幕藩体制自体を完全解体する廃藩置県というもう一つの革命（こちらの革命は正真正銘無血で行われた）を必要としたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Finally, the new government needed this evolution the Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures), which was required the complete dismantling of the current feudal system of the Shogunate (The new government achieved this evolution bloodlessly.).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Finally, the new government needed this evolution the Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures), which was required the complete dismantling of the current feudal system of the Shogunate (The new government achieved this evolution bloodlessly).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Finally, the new government needed this evolution the Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures), which was required the complete dismantling of the current feudal system of the bakufu (The new government achieved this evolution bloodlessly).</e>
<cmt>the Shogunate→the bakufuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="73">
<sen id="335">
<j>略年表</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The summary of the Timeline</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The summary of the Timeline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The summary of the Timeline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="336">
<j>以下は上記の江戸開城に関連する事項を時系列で並べた略年表である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Listed below is the summary for the timeline which are events noted by their dates, relating to &quot;the surrender of the Edo Castle.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Listed below is the summary for the timeline which are events noted by their dates, relating to &quot;the surrender of the Edo Castle.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Listed below is the summary for the timeline which are events noted by their dates, relating to &quot;the surrender of the Edo-jo Castle.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Edo-jo Castleとし、全角クォーテーションを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="337">
<j>右に参考としてグレゴリオ暦の日付（すべて1868年）を附した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the right column are dates added which reference the Gregorian calendar (all in year the&apos;1868&apos;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the right column are dates added which reference the Gregorian calendar (all in year the&apos;1868&apos;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the right column are dates added which reference the Gregorian calendar (all in year the &apos;1868&apos;).</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーションを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="74">
<sen id="338">
<j>フィクション作品への影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The influence of fictional works</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The influence of fictional works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The influence of fictional works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="339">
<j>江戸開城は戊辰戦争中の一大画期として象徴的な事件であるとともに、勝・西郷その他多くの人物が関わる劇的な要素に富む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The surrender of Edo Castle was a significant development to the commencement of the Boshin civil War; there was also an abundance of dramatic contributions from several individuals involved in these incidents, such as, Katsu and Saigo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The surrender of Edo Castle was a significant development to the commencement of the Boshin civil War; there was also an abundance of dramatic contributions from several individuals involved in these incidents, such as, Katsu and Saigo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The surrender of Edo-jo Castle was a significant development to the commencement of the Boshin Civil War; there was also an abundance of dramatic contributions from several individuals involved in these incidents, such as, Katsu and Saigo.</e>
<cmt>the Boshin Civil Warとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="340">
<j>このことが好まれ、明治以来数多くの創作作品の題材となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, writers and other dramatist valued these historical incidents, choosing this subject material for the production of many creative works going forward from the Meiji era.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, writers and other dramatist valued these historical incidents, choosing this subject material for the production of many creative works going forward from the Meiji era.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, writers and other dramatist valued these historical incidents, choosing this subject material for the production of many creative works going forward from the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>the Meiji era→the Meiji periodとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Lupinoid(id:68), トホホ川(id:50502), 曾禰越後守(id:183605), 彩華1226(id:64711), Kizer(id:251325), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>