<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>開発領主</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaihatsu-Ryoshu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaihatsu-Ryoshu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaihatsu-Ryoshu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>開発領主（かいほつりょうしゅ/かいはつりょうしゅ）は、日本の荘園公領制において、田地を開発して領地を確保した者をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaihatsu-ryoshu (also pronounced as &quot;kaihotsu-ryoshu&quot;) were those who owned the lands they developed as their territories in shoen koryo sei (The System of Public Lands and Private Estates) in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaihatsu-ryoshu (also pronounced as &quot;kaihotsu-ryoshu&quot;) were those who owned the lands they developed as their territories in shoen koryo sei (The System of Public Lands and Private Estates) in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaihatsu-ryoshu (also pronounced as Kaihotsu-ryoshu) were those who owned the lands they developed as their territories in Shoen koryo sei (The System of Public Lands and Private Estates) in Japan.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>根本領主ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were also called &quot;konpon ryoshu&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were also called &quot;konpon ryoshu&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were also called konpon-ryoshu.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>天平15年（743年）の墾田永年私財法の施行以後、墾田に基づく土地私有者は広く発生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Konden einen shizai Law (a law allowing farmers who cleared new lands to own them permanently) took effect in 743, a number of land owners based on konden (newly developed rice field) emerged over an extensive area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Konden einen shizai Law (a law allowing farmers who cleared new lands to own them permanently) took effect in 743, a number of land owners based on konden (newly developed rice field) emerged over an extensive area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Konden einen shizai Law (a law allowing farmers who cleared new lands to own them permanently) took effect in 743, a number of land owners based on konden (newly developed rice field) emerged over an extensive area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>もともと開発は田地を「ひらきおこす」という意味で、未開の原野の開墾だけでなく荒廃田の再開も含んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, &quot;development&quot; meant to &apos;carve out and revive&apos; the land, suggesting not only cultivation of undeveloped wilderness, but also resumption of ruined fields.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, &quot;development&quot; meant to &apos;carve out and revive&apos; the land, suggesting not only cultivation of undeveloped wilderness, but also resumption of ruined fields.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, Kaihatsu meant to &apos;carve out and revive&apos; the land, suggesting not only cultivation of undeveloped wilderness, but also resumption of ruined fields.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>当初は、荒廃田を再開させた開発者には、期限つきで耕作権が認められるに過ぎなかったが、平安時代初期には終身の権利に発展したため、富豪農民（田堵）・郡司級土豪は積極的に開発を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An award given to developers who resumed ruined fields was at first nothing but the right to cultivate the land on a temporary basis, but eventually evolved into the permanent rights in the early Heian period, which greatly motivated Tato (wealthy cultivators) and powerful local clans at Gunji (magistrates) level to cultivate fields.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An award given to developers who resumed ruined fields was at first nothing but the right to cultivate the land on a temporary basis, but eventually evolved into permanent rights in the early Heian period, which greatly motivated Tato (wealthy cultivators) and powerful local clans at Gunji (magistrates) level to cultivate fields.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An award given to developers who resumed ruined fields was at first nothing but the right to cultivate the land on a temporary basis, but eventually evolved into permanent rights in the early Heian period, which greatly motivated Tato (wealthy cultivators) and powerful local clans at Gunji (magistrates) level to cultivate fields.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>国衙も官物の免除などの特典を与えて常に内外の開発者を募った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokuga (provincial government offices), in turn, used incentives such as exemption from kanmotsu (tribute goods paid as taxes or tithes) to constantly recruit land developers inside and outside of their provinces.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokuga (provincial government offices), in turn, used incentives such as exemption from kanmotsu (tribute goods paid as taxes or tithes) to constantly recruit land developers inside and outside of their provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokuga (provincial government offices), in turn, used incentives such as exemption from kanmotsu (tribute goods paid as taxes or tithes) to constantly recruit land developers inside and outside of their provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし荒廃田を再開しても国衙に収公されてしまう場合が多く、平安時代中期には条里外の未開原野を広く占めて開田する領主的開発が主流となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since in many cases resumed ruined lands would end up being confiscated by kokuga, in the mid-Heian period, a load-style development method of widely taking up and carving out undeveloped wilderness outside of cultivation area became a mainstream.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since in many cases resumed ruined lands would end up being confiscated by kokuga, in the mid-Heian period, a load-style development method of widely taking up and carving out undeveloped wilderness outside of cultivated areas became the mainstream.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since in many cases resumed ruined lands would end up being confiscated by kokuga, in the mid-Heian period, a load-style development method of widely taking up and carving out undeveloped wilderness outside of cultivated areas became the mainstream.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>開発者は国衙に申請して開発を始める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Developers would start their development by applying for it to kokuga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Developers would start their development by applying for it to kokuga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Developers would start their development by applying for it to kokuga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>まず開発拠点を設置して、開発費用を支出して労働力である内外の浪人や百姓を誘致した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First, setting up the development base, they paid development expenses to recruit ronin (masterless samurai) and peasants as workforce inside and outside of their provinces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First, setting up the development base, they paid development expenses to recruit ronin (masterless samurai) and peasants as workforce inside and outside of their provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First, setting up the development base, they paid development expenses to recruit ronin (masterless samurai) and peasants as workforce inside and outside of their provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>開発者の家人・下人・従者は労働の監督にあたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenin (retainers), low ranked people, and followers of the developers acted as managers of the workforce.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenin (retainers), low ranked people, and followers of the developers acted as managers of the workforce.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenin (retainers), low ranked people, and followers of the developers acted as managers of the workforce.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>開発労働力の確保と並んで、池溝堰堤の建設・整備も行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In parallel with acquisition of labor for the development, construction and improvement of ponds, ditches and dikes were also carried out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In parallel with acquisition of labor for the development, construction and improvement of ponds, ditches and dikes were also carried out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In parallel with acquisition of labor for the development, construction and improvement of ponds, ditches and dikes were also carried out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>開発された田地では、所領田畠とその農民に対する強力な進止権が国衙より公的に与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At developed farmlands, strong ruling rights were officially given to horyo (territory) fields and their farmers by kokuga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At developed farmlands, strong ruling rights were officially given to horyo (territory) fields and their farmers by kokuga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At developed farmlands, strong ruling rights were officially given to shoryo (territory) fields and their farmers by kokuga.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>国衙領（公領）において開発田は郡・郷・保・別名に編成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Within Kokugaryo (territories governed by provincial government office), developed fields were categorized as Gun, Go, Ho, and Bechimyo.</e>
<cmt>根本領主権 - 定訳不明一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Within Kokugaryo (territories governed by provincial government office), developed fields were categorized as Gun, Go, Ho, and Bechimyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Within Kokugaryo (territories governed by provincial government office), developed fields were categorized as Gun, Go, Ho, and Bechimyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>郡司・郷司・保司・別名名主などの職の体系に補任された開発領主は、開発田の勧農を中心とする所務、私的な雑役・夫役の徴収、検断権といった根本領主権を保証された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaihatsu-ryoshu were appointed in a profession system consisting of Gunji (local magistrates), Goji (a local government official under the ritsuryo system), Hoji (an officer governing koryo, or public land), and Bechimyo myoshu (an owner of developed farmland), and guaranteed the local load rights, which included the rights for shomu (land management) centered on Kanno (encouragement of agriculture) of developed fields, private tax collection of zoyaku (odd-jobs tasks) and buyaku (labor service), and judgment of criminal cases.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaihatsu-ryoshu were appointed in a profession system consisting of Gunji (local magistrates), Goji (a local government official under the ritsuryo system), Hoji (an officer governing koryo, or public land), and Bechimyo myoshu (an owner of developed farmland), and guaranteed the local load rights, which included the rights for shomu (land management) centered on Kanno (encouragement of agriculture) of developed fields, private tax collection of zoyaku (odd-jobs tasks) and buyaku (labor service), and judgment of criminal cases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaihatsu-ryoshu were assumed the position of the officers&apos; organization, such as Gunji (a local government for Gun territory), Goji (a local government official for Go territory), Hoji (a local government official for Ho territory), and Bechimyo myoshu (a local government official for Bechimyo territory), and guaranteed the local load rights, which included the rights for shomu (land management) centered on Kanno (encouragement of agriculture) of developed fields, private tax collection of zoyaku (odd-jobs tasks) and buyaku (labor service), and judgment of criminal cases.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>荘園内の開発でも事情は同じであり、開発領主は下司・公文などに任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The situation for development inside shoen was the same, where kaihatsu-ryoshu were appointed as lower ranked officer or kumon (a local shoen (manor) official below the gesu in rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The situation for development inside shoen was the same, where kaihatsu-ryoshu were appointed as lower ranked officers or kumon (a local shoen (manor) official below the gesu in rank).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The situation for development inside shoen was the same, where kaihatsu-ryoshu were appointed as lower ranked officers or kumon (a local shoen official below the gesu in rank), and so on.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>開発領主は、権利の所在を明記した文書（公験）を大事に保管し、子孫代々伝世していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaihatsu-ryoshu carefully stored the documents that clearly stipulated the basis of their rights (or &quot;kugen&quot;, a type of certification authorizing a certain privilege to a person), handing them down for generations.</e>
<cmt>公験の説明は次のサイトを基にしました。http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E5%85%AC%E9%A8%93</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaihatsu-ryoshu carefully stored the documents that clearly stipulated the basis of their rights (or &quot;kugen&quot;, a type of certification authorizing a certain privilege to a person), handing them down for generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaihatsu-ryoshu carefully stored the documents that clearly stipulated the basis of their rights (kugen [a type of certification authorizing a certain privilege to a person]), handing them down for generations.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかし、国司が交代すると認可を取り消される可能性も高く、境界などを巡って他の開発領主などと紛争が起こることもたびたびあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it was highly possible that authorization to them were revoked upon the change of kokushi (provincial governors), and also, disputes with other kaihatsu-ryoshu often erupted over such elements as the border.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it was highly possible that authorization to them were revoked upon the change of kokushi (provincial governors), and also, disputes with other kaihatsu-ryoshu often erupted over such elements as the border.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it was highly possible that authorization to them were revoked upon the change of kokushi (provincial governors), and also, disputes with other kaihatsu-ryoshu often erupted over such elements as the border.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>開発領主は国衙よりも権威のある中央の有力貴族や有力寺社へ開発田地を寄進して（寄進型荘園）、国衙の圧力を断ち切ることで支配権・管理権を確保していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, kaihatsu-ryoshu tried to secure their dominion and management right by donating their developed fields to central nobility, temples, and shrines, that were more powerful than kokuga, to eliminate the pressure from kokuga (those shoen were specifically categorized as &quot;donated shoen&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, kaihatsu-ryoshu tried to secure their dominion and management rights by donating their developed fields to central nobility, temples, and shrines, that were more powerful than kokuga, to eliminate the pressure from kokuga (those shoen were specifically categorized as &quot;donated shoen&quot;).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, kaihatsu-ryoshu tried to secure their dominion and management rights by donating their developed fields to major central nobility, temples, and shrines, that were more powerful than kokuga, to eliminate the pressure from kokuga (those shoen were specifically categorized as donated shoen).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>荘園寄進時に、開発領主は寄進先の荘園領主から荘官に任じられることが多く見られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In many cases, when donating shoen, kaihatsu-ryoshu were appointed as shokan (an officer governing shoen) by the lord of the manor they donated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In many cases, when donating shoen, kaihatsu-ryoshu were appointed as shokan (an officer governing shoen) by the lord of the manor to whom they donated it.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In many cases, when donating shoen, kaihatsu-ryoshu were appointed as shokan (an officer governing shoen) by the lord of the manor to whom they donated it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>一方で、開発領主は在庁官人でもあり、国衙と結びつくのが有利な場合はそのまま国衙領にとどまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, also being Zaichokanjin (the local officials in Heian and Kamakura periods), kaihatsu-ryoshu would remain inside the kokugaryo if they determined it would be advantageous for them to keep close ties with kokuga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, also being Zaichokanjin (local officials in the Heian and Kamakura periods), kaihatsu-ryoshu would remain inside the kokugaryo if they determined it would be advantageous for them to keep close ties with kokuga.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, also being Zaichokanjin (local officials in the Heian and Kamakura periods), kaihatsu-ryoshu would remain inside the kokugaryo if they determined it would be advantageous for them to keep close ties with kokuga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="21">
<j>平安中期頃、中央政界からあぶれた武士身分の下級貴族が多数、地方へ下向してきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In around the mid-Heian period, a number of lower-ranking noblemen with samurai status, who were left out of the central political world, went down to provinces.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In around the mid-Heian period, a number of lower-ranking noblemen with samurai status, who were left out of the central political world, went down to the provinces.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In around the mid-Heian period, a number of lower-ranking noblemen with samurai status, who were left out of the central political world, went down to the provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>開発領主はそれらの武士貴族と主従関係を結ぶことにより、荘園を巡る紛争解決に役立てようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaihatsu-ryoshu tried to establish the lord-and-vassal relationship with those samurai to facilitate dispute resolution over their shoen.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaihatsu-ryoshu tried to establish the lord-and-vassal relationship with those samurai to facilitate dispute resolution over their shoen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaihatsu-ryoshu tried to establish the lord-and-vassal relationship with those samurai to facilitate dispute resolution over their shoen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>そのため、武士となる開発領主も少なくなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, quite a lot of kaihatsu-ryoshu became samurai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, many kaihatsu-ryoshu became samurai.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, many kaihatsu-ryoshu became samurai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>鎌倉時代には、地頭や御家人に任じられる開発領主も現れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kamakura period, some kaihatsu-ryoshu were even appointed as jito (manager and lord of manor) or gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kamakura period, some kaihatsu-ryoshu were even appointed as jito (manager and lord of manor) or gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kamakura period, some kaihatsu-ryoshu were even appointed as jito (manager and lord of manor) or gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Ktmchi(id:113301), Shimoxx(id:9332), BAKU(id:55205), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>