<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>越訴方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ossokata</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ossokata</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ossokata</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>越訴方（おっそかた）とは、鎌倉幕府・室町幕府における訴訟機関。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ossokata refers a lawsuit body of Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ossokata refers a lawsuit body of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ossokata refers a lawsuit body of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>裁判の再審・越訴に関する審理を担当した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It took charge of the retrials and direct appeals (to a senior official without going through the normal formalities).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It took charge of the retrials and direct appeals (to a senior official without going through the normal formalities).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It took charge of the retrials and direct appeals (to a senior official without going through the normal formalities).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>文永元年（1264年）、これまで、1次の審理を行っていた引付衆が担当していた越訴などを専門として扱う部署として誕生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was established in 1264, as a special section that handled direct appeal, etc., which were previously handled by Hikitsukeshu (Co-adjustor of the High Court) where the first trials were examined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was established in 1264, as a special section that handled direct appeal, etc., previously handled by Hikitsukeshu (Co-adjustor of the High Court) where the first trials were examined.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was established in 1264, as a special section that handled direct appeal, and so on, previously handled by Hikitsukeshu (Co-adjustor of the High Court) where the first trials were examined.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>長である越訴頭人と引付衆の中から2・3名の越訴奉行（おっそぶぎょう）から構成（越訴頭人も広義の越訴奉行に含む説もある（『関東評定伝』など））されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ossotonin (the head of legal institutions) and two or three Ossobugyo (temporary positions in charge of retrials and accepting appeals) from Hikitsukeshu were in commission (according to &quot;Kanto hyojo den&quot; etc., Ossotonin might be a part of Ossobugyo in a broad sense).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ossotonin (the head of legal institutions) and two or three Ossobugyo (temporary positions in charge of retrials and accepting appeals) from Hikitsukeshu were in commission (according to &quot;Kanto hyojo den&quot; etc., Ossotonin might be a part of Ossobugyo in a broad sense).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ossotonin (the head of legal institutions) and two or three Ossobugyo (temporary positions in charge of retrials and accepting appeals) from Hikitsukeshu were in commission (according to &quot;Kanto hyojo den&quot; (an annual listing of personnel for the years 1226 and 1232 to 1284) and so on, Ossotonin might be a part of Ossobugyo in a broad sense).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>しかし、越訴頭人は初代の頭人が金沢実時・安達泰盛であったように引付衆の中でも執権・連署を除く上首（最上位）もしくはそれに次ぐ御家人が任じられる慣例があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, among the hikitsukeshu, particularly joshu (the head) or second-tier vassal, except regency and rensho (assistant to regents), were customarily appointed as ossotonin; for example, the first ossotonin were Sanetoki KANEZAWA and Yasumori ADACHI.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, among the hikitsukeshu, particularly joshu (the head) or second-tier vassal, except regency and rensho (assistant to regents), were customarily appointed as ossotonin; for example, the first ossotonin were Sanetoki KANEZAWA and Yasumori ADACHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, among Hikitsukeshu, particularly joshu (the head) or second-tier vassal, except regency and rensho (assistant to regents), were customarily appointed as ossotonin; for example, the first ossotonin were Sanetoki KANEZAWA and Yasumori ADACHI.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>一方越訴奉行は実際の審理発生ごとに執権・連署・頭人以外の引付衆より選定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, ossobugyo were chosen from Hikitsukeshu, except for regency, rensho and ossotonin, for each trial.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, ossobugyo were chosen from Hikitsukeshu, except for regency, rensho and ossotonin, for each trial.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, ossobugyo were chosen from Hikitsukeshu, except for regency, rensho and ossotonin, for each trial.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>彼らは頭人の指揮下で審理実務を担当した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They took charge of practical business for a trial, under the supervision of the ossotonin.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They took charge of practical business for a trial, under the supervision of the ossotonin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They took charge of practical business for a trial, under the supervision of the ossotonin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>その後、北条氏得宗による訴訟権限の掌握によって、判決に対する異議申立機関である越訴方の存在は疎外される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, the ossokata, an institution for adverse claim to a judicial decision, was excluded when Hojo clan Tokuso seized the lawsuit authority.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, the ossokata, an institution to handle adverse claims to a judicial decision, was excluded when Hojo clan Tokuso seized the lawsuit authority.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, the ossokata, an institution to handle adverse claims to a judicial decision, was excluded when the Hojo clan Tokuso (the patrimonial head of the main branch of the Hojo clan) seized the lawsuit authority.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>永仁の徳政令を機に廃止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was abolished at the enforcement of Einin no Tokuseirei (a debt cancellation order).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was abolished at the enforcement of Einin no Tokuseirei (a debt cancellation order).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was abolished at the enforcement of Einin no Tokuseirei (a debt cancellation order).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>翌年の徳政令廃止とともに二階堂行藤・摂津道厳を頭人に任命して復置された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the next year, it was reestablished with Yukifuji NIKAIDO and SETTSU no Dogen as ossotonin upon the repeal of the Tokuseirei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the next year, it was reestablished with Yukifuji NIKAIDO and SETTSU no Dogen as ossotonin upon the repeal of the Tokuseirei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the next year, it was reestablished with Yukifuji NIKAIDO and SETTSU no Dogen as ossotonin upon the repeal of the Tokuseirei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>だが、正安2年（1300年）には得宗北条貞時の御内人5名が越訴を担当するように命じられるなど、越訴を含めた得宗の訴訟権限支配が模索された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Tokuso tried to control lawsuit including direct appeals; for example, five Miuchibito (private vassals) of Tokuso Sadatoki HOJO were ordered to take charge to a direct appeal in 1300.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Tokuso tried to control lawsuits including direct appeals; for example, five Miuchibito (private vassals) of Tokuso Sadatoki HOJO were ordered to take charge to a direct appeal in 1300.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Tokuso tried to control lawsuits including direct appeals; for example, five Miuchibito (private vassals) of Tokuso Sadatoki HOJO were ordered to take charge to a direct appeal in 1300.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>朝廷でも伏見天皇親政期に越訴奉行が設置され、室町幕府でも初期には越訴方・越訴奉行が設置された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ossobugyo was organized in Imperial Court during Emperor Fushimi Shinsei period (the period in which the Emperor had the control of the government), and the ossokata and ossobugyo were organized in Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ossobugyo was organized in the Imperial Court during Emperor Fushimi Shinsei period (the period in which the Emperor had the control of the government), and the ossokata and ossobugyo were organized in the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ossobugyo was organized in the Imperial Court during the period in which Emperor Fushimi had the control of the government from 1287 to 1298), and the ossokata and ossobugyo were organized in the early Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>しかし、その詳細は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, their detail has been unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, their details are unknown.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, their details are unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>南北朝時代 (日本)末期には組織・役職としては消滅したと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were thought to be disappeared as organization and post in the end of the Northern and Southern Court Period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were thought to have disappeared as an organization and post during the end of the Northern and Southern Court Period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were thought to have disappeared as an organization and post during the end of the period of the Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>