<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>駄賃馬稼</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dachin-uma kasegi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dachin-uma kasegi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dachin-Uma Kasegi</e>
<cmt>タイトルのため、頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>駄賃馬稼（だちんうまかせぎ）とは、近代以前の日本においてウマの背中に貨物や人を乗せて輸送に従事する職業のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dachin-uma kasegi refers to an occupation engaging in transportation by carrying freight and people on the back of horses in Japan before modern times.</e>
<cmt>登録ではdachin umakasegiとなっていますが、駄馬を駄賃馬ともいうため、dachin-uma kasegiと切るのが妥当かと。http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/search?stype=0&amp;ei=UTF-8&amp;dtype=2&amp;p=駄賃</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dachin-uma kasegi refers to an occupation in Japan before modern times that engaged in the transportation of freight and people by carrying them on horseback.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;on the back of horses&quot; to &quot;on horseback&quot;; rearranged sentence and fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dachin-uma kasegi refers to an occupation in Japan before modern times that engaged in the transportation of freight and people by carrying them on horseback.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>この職業に従事する人を馬借（ばしゃく）あるいは馬子（まご）、使用された馬を駄馬（だば）あるいは稼馬（かせぎうま）・荷馬（にうま）、輸送料金を駄賃（だちん）と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The person who was engaged in this occupation was called bashaku (shipping agent using horses) or mago (packhorse driver), the horse to use was called daba (packhorse), kasegiuma (horse for earning) or niuma (draft horse), and the transportation fee was called dachin (carriage charge).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those engaged in this occupation were called a bashaku (shipping agent using horses) or mago (packhorse driver), while the horse was called a daba (packhorse), kasegiuma (horse for earning) or niuma (draft horse), and the transportation fee was called dachin (carriage charge).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;The person who was&quot; to &quot;Those&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those engaged in this occupation were called a bashaku (shipping agent using horses) or mago (packhorse driver), while the horse was called a daba (packhorse), kasegiuma (horse for earning) or niuma (draft horse), and the transportation fee was called dachin (carriage charge).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>日本では古くから馬は重要な輸送手段であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, a horse was an important means of transportation since ancient times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From ancient times in Japan, horses have been an important mode of transportation.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From ancient times in Japan, horses have been an important mode of transportation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>壬申の乱で挙兵した天武天皇が菟田評家において、伊勢国から大津京に向けて米を運ぶ馬50頭を連れた行列に出会った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Oama, who raised an army at the Jinshin War, encountered a procession with 50 horses carrying rice from Ise Province to Otsukyo at Udahyoka.</e>
<cmt>「出会った皇子は。」となっているのは、「出会った。皇子は」としか思えないため、下のセルといったん結合の上、分割し直しました。菟田評家は、今の奈良県宇陀郡榛原町の旧地名のようです。天武天皇はリンク先の単語で、原文では大海人皇子となっており、この後「皇子」として話が進むため、Prince Oamaとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Prince Oama, who raised an army for the Jinshin War, encountered a procession of fifty horses carrying rice from Ise Province to Otsukyo at Udahyoka, he had the horses discharged and requisitioned as war-horses.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;50&quot; to &quot;fifty&quot;; this sentence appears to be connected to nothing until the following sentence is read, so I combined them; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Oama, who raised an army for the Jinshin War, encountered a procession of fifty horses carrying rice from Ise Province to Otsukyo at Udahyoka.</e>
<cmt>仕様書に基づき、原文一文に対し訳文一文となるよう修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>皇子はその荷を下ろさせて馬を軍馬として徴発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Prince had the horse discharged and requisitioned them as war-horses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Prince had the horse discharged and requisitioned them as war-horses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had the horses discharged and requisitioned as war-horses.</e>
<cmt>仕様書に基づき、原文一文に対し訳文一文となるよう修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>これは当時の政権が大規模な輸送を行う能力を持っていたことを裏付けている（この徴発によって反乱軍を率いる皇子側は軍馬を確保するとともに、結果的には敵の本拠である大津京への兵糧搬入を妨害したことにもなった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This proves the government of the time was capable of large-scale transportation (this impressment made the Prince side leading the rebel troops secure war-horses, and at the same time, interrupted the delivery of provisions to Otsukyo, the enemy&apos;s base, as a result).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Operations of this size give evidence to support the capability of the government of the time to have large-scale transportation (As a result of this requisition, the rebel troops on the Prince&apos;s side gained war-horses while simultaneously interrupting the delivery of provisions to the enemy&apos;s base in Otsukyo).</e>
<cmt>I don&apos;t really see the logic in the sentence outside of parenthesis, so I changed &quot;This&quot; to &quot;Operations of this size&quot; to help give it more reason...; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Operations of this size give evidence to support the capability of the government of the time to have large-scale transportation (As a result of this requisition, the rebel troops on the Prince&apos;s side gained war-horses while simultaneously interrupting the delivery of provisions to the enemy&apos;s base in Otsukyo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>律令制においては、国司が郡司・富豪などの地方の有力者の馬を駄賃と引換に徴発して年貢を日本の首都に運ばせるのが主であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code), a Kokushi (provincial governor) usually had nengu (land tax) delivered to the Japanese capital by requisitioning horses of local leaders such as Gunji (local magistrates) or rich men in exchange for dachin.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code), a Kokushi (provincial governor) usually had nengu (land tax) delivered to the Japanese capital by requisitioning horses of local leaders, such as a Gunji (local magistrate) or wealthy families in exchange for dachin.</e>
<cmt>added comma after &quot;leaders&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code), a Kokushi (provincial governor) usually had nengu (land tax) delivered to the Japanese capital by requisitioning horses of local leaders, such as a Gunji (local magistrate) or wealthy families in exchange for dachin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>が、やがて東国においては、これらの荷の運搬と安全を請け負う僦馬（しゅうめ）と呼ばれる職業的に輸送に従事する集団が現れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, later in Togoku (Kanto region), there emerged a group called Shume who engaged in transportation as business to undertake the transfer and safety of such loads.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before long, however, a group called Shume emerged in Togoku (Kanto region) that engaged in transportation as a business, engaging in the safe transfer of such loads.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before long, however, a group called Shume emerged in Togoku (Kanto region) that engaged in transportation as a business, engaging in the safe transfer of such loads.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>後に他の地域でも農閑期の農耕馬の活用のために輸送に従事した農民などが輸送を専業としていく例が増加することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then later in other areas as well, farmers engaging in transportation to utilize dobbins during the slack season on the farm, increasingly concentrated on transportation.</e>
<cmt>「農閑期」は英辞郎を参照して変更</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later on in other areas as well, farmers who engaged in transportation by utilizing their farm horses during the slack season increasingly concentrated on transportation.</e>
<cmt>I see that 英治郎 gives &quot;dobbins&quot; as the first translation for &quot;農耕馬&quot; but I have never seen this word before, so I changed it to &quot;farm horses&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later on in other areas as well, farmers who engaged in transportation by utilizing their farm horses during the slack season increasingly concentrated on transportation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>鎌倉時代に入ると、畿内においても商業の活発化により馬借と呼ばれる輸送集団が現れるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kamakura Period, commercial vitalization made transportation groups called bashaku emerge also in Kinai (Kinki region).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As it became the Kamakura Period, increased commercial activity caused the emergence of transportation groups called bashaku in Kinai (Kinki region) as well.</e>
<cmt>&quot;revitalization&quot; is a word I have seen many time, but &quot;vitalization&quot; sounds strange to me, so I changed &quot;commercial vitalization&quot; to &quot;increased commercial activity&quot;; changed &quot;also&quot; to &quot;as well&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As it became the Kamakura period, increased commercial activity caused the emergence of transportation groups called bashaku in Kinai (Kinki region) as well.</e>
<cmt>Periodの頭文字を小文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>室町時代には大和国八木（現在の奈良県橿原市）に馬借の座が形成されたほか、各地に同様の職業が広まっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Muromachi Period, the guild of bashaku was organized in Yagi, Yamato Province (present Kashihara City, Nara Prefecture), and similar occupations prevailed in various areas.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Muromachi Period, a bashaku guild was organized in Yagi, Yamato Province (present Kashihara City, Nara Prefecture), and similar occupations prevailed in various areas.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;In&quot; to &quot;During&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Muromachi period, a bashaku guild was organized in Yagi, Yamato Province (present Kashihara City, Nara Prefecture), and similar occupations prevailed in various areas.</e>
<cmt>Periodの頭文字を小文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>戦国時代_(日本)には戦国大名が自らの輸送・通信手段を確保するために、輸送業者に対して伝馬や小荷駄などの義務を課して、それと引換に駄賃馬稼の許可を与えるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States), in order to secure their own means of transportation and communication, warring lords imposed duties such as posts and provisions on carriers, and gave a permission of Dachin-uma kasegi in exchange.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States), in order to secure their own means of transportation and communication, Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period) imposed duties such as posts and provisions on carriers in exchange for permission to use Dachin-uma kasegi.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;warring lords&quot; to &quot;Sengoku daimyo&quot; and added description to follow the word list; rearranged sentence to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Sengoku period (period of Warring States), in order to secure their own means of transportation and communication, Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period) imposed duties such as posts and provisions on carriers in exchange for permission to use Dachin-uma kasegi.</e>
<cmt>Periodの頭文字を小文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>江戸時代に入ると、江戸幕府（幕府においては慶長7年（1602年）と正徳_(日本)元年（1711年））や諸藩が公定駄賃を定めて悪質な業者の排除に乗り出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo Period, the Edo shogunate (in 1602 and 1711 by the feudal government) and domains launched elimination of malicious business by setting official carriage charge.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As it became the Edo Period, the Edo bakufu (in 1602 and 1711 by the feudal government), along with various domains set out to eliminate malicious businesses by setting an official carriage charge.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;shogunate&quot; to &quot;bakufu&quot; to match the word list; changed &quot;and domains&quot; to &quot;along with various domains&quot; for &quot;諸藩&quot;; changed &quot;launched&quot; to &quot;set out to&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As it became the Edo period, the Edo bakufu (in 1602 and 1711 by the feudal government), along with various domains set out to eliminate malicious businesses by setting an official carriage charge.</e>
<cmt>Periodの頭文字を小文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>その他、近隣の業者が連携して輸送の効率化を図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And also, neighboring carriers cooperated to improve the efficiency of transportation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Neighboring carriers cooperated to improve the efficiency of transportation as well.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;And also&quot; to &quot;as well&quot; and put at the end of the sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Neighboring carriers cooperated to improve the efficiency of transportation as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>明治時代に入っても、依然として馬による輸送が重視されて「陸運会社」の結成が新政府によって奨励された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even in the Meiji Period, transportation by horses was still valued, and establishment of &apos;a land transportation company&apos; was encouraged by the new government.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even as it became the Meiji Period, transportation by horses was still valued, and an establishment of a &quot;land transportation company&quot; was encouraged by the new government.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even as it became the Meiji period, transportation by horses was still valued, and an establishment of a &apos;land transportation company&apos; was encouraged by the new government.</e>
<cmt>Periodの頭文字を小文字に変更、シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし、やがて鉄道の整備に伴って衰微の道をたどってゆくことになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, however, it would decline with construction of railways.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before long, however, the use of Dachin uma-kasegi declined with the construction of railways.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;Later&quot; to &quot;Before long&quot; for &quot;やがて&quot;; changed &quot;it&quot; to &quot;Dachin uma-kasegi&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before long, however, the use of Dachin uma-kasegi declined with the construction of railways.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>軍隊での兵站輸送の手段としては第二次世界大戦まで世界各国で残っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It remained as a means of logistic transportation for army until World War II, and it was only US forces which did not have logistic transportation by horses during World War II.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Horses remained as a means of logistic transportation for armies in various nations across the world until World War II. During the war, only US forces did not conduct coummuncations using horses as a form of transportation.</e>
<cmt>This sentence almost uses the same exact words twice in a row, so I changed it into two sentences and reworded it to read more naturally; added &quot;across the world&quot; for &quot;世界各国&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Horses remained as a means of logistic transportation for armies in various nations across the world until World War II.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>第二次世界大戦で馬による兵站輸送を行わなかったのはアメリカ軍ぐらいしかない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the war, only US forces did not conduct coummuncations using horses as a form of transportation.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>備考</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Remarks</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Remarks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Remarks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>近代以前において馬は最も重要な輸送手段であったから、優れた馬（駿馬）は軍事や行政用として用いられるのが常であり、輸送に用いられた駄馬は人を乗せて早く走らせることの出来ない質の良くない馬であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since a horse was the most important means of transportation before modern times, swift horses (shunme) were usually used for military or government use, and the daba used for transportation were poor quality horses which were not able to run fast with carrying a person.</e>
<cmt>ここでの「行政用」はfor government という形で訳出</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since a horse was the most important means of transportation before modern times, swift horses (shunme) were usually reserved for military or government use, and the daba used for transportation were poor quality horses that were unable to run fast while carrying a person.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;with&quot; to &quot;while&quot; before &quot;carrying a person&quot;; changed &quot;use&quot; to &quot;reserved&quot; to avoid word repetition with the following &quot;used&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since a horse was the most important means of transportation before modern times, swift horses (shunme) were usually reserved for military or government use, and the daba used for transportation were poor quality horses that were unable to run fast while carrying a person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>このため、転じて質の悪い下等の馬の事を一般に「駄馬」と呼ぶようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, an inferior horse with poor quality started to be generally called &apos;daba&apos; by extension.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is how inferior horses of poor quality came to be generally referred to as &quot;daba.&quot;</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is how inferior horses of poor quality came to be generally referred to as &apos;daba.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="21">
<j>その昔、馬子が離れた町の問屋などの依頼によって輸送をする荷物を依頼主のもとまで取りに行く際に、途中において他者の荷物の輸送を引き受けて駄賃を受けることによって小銭を稼ぐことがしばしば行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Long time ago, when mago went to pick up packages to transport at request of a warehouse merchant in a distant town, he often accepted transportation of another package from someone else on his way and gained dachin to earn small money.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the past, when a mago (packhorse driver) went to pick up packages to transport at the request of a warehouse merchant in a distant town, they would often accept another package from someone else to transport on the way, gaining dachin and earning small money.</e>
<cmt>added (packhorse driver) after &quot;mago&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the past, when a mago (packhorse driver) went to pick up packages to transport at the request of a warehouse merchant in a distant town, they would often accept another package from someone else to transport on the way, gaining dachin and earning small money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>このため、転じて子供の買い物など簡単な雑用と引換に貰う小銭のことを「（お）駄賃」と呼ぶようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore the small money to get in exchange for a simple chore including shopping by a child started to be called &apos;(o)dachin&apos; by extension.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This resulted in small money that was given in exchange for a simple chore, such as a child going shopping, being called &quot;(o)dachin.&quot;</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This resulted in small money that was given in exchange for a simple chore, such as a child going shopping, being called &apos;(o)dachin.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MIO(id:31681), Kurihaya(id:132524), K. Takeda(id:119013), Afaz(id:64776), Wikiner(id:225795), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>