<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>青苧座</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Aoso-Za&quot; (The Guild Of &apos;Aoso&apos; [Boehmeria Nipononivea, A Fiber Material For Clothing])</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Aoso-Za&quot; (The Guild Of &apos;Aoso&apos; [Boehmeria Nipononivea, A Fiber Material For Clothing])</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Aoso-Za&quot; (The Guild Of &apos;Aoso&apos; [Boehmeria Nipononivea, A Fiber Material For Clothing])</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>青苧座（あおそざ）とは中世後期に繊維素材である青苧を扱う商人たちで結成された座のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Aoso-za&quot; refers to &quot;za&quot; (the guild) of &quot;aoso&quot; (Boehmeria nipononivea, a fiber material for clothing), which was established in the later middle ages of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Aoso-za&quot; refers to &quot;za&quot; (the guild) of &quot;aoso&quot; (Boehmeria nipononivea, a fiber material for clothing), which was established in the later middle ages of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Aoso-za&quot; refers to &quot;za&quot; (the guild) of &quot;aoso&quot; (Boehmeria nipononivea, a fiber material for clothing), which was established in the later middle ages of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>主要なものとして越後府中（生産地）・近江坂本（中継地）・京都・天王寺区（ともに消費地）が知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Well-known major aoso-za existed in Echigofuchu (the then aoso producing area, now part of Joetsu City, Niigata Prefecture), in Omi Sakamoto (the then midpoint of aoso distribution network, now part of Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture), and in Kyoto and in the area now called Tennoji Ward, Osaka (both the then consuming cities of aoso).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Well-known major aoso-za existed in Echigofuchu (the then aoso-producing area, now part of Joetsu City, Niigata Prefecture), in Omi Sakamoto (the then midpoint of the aoso distribution network, now part of Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture), and in Kyoto and in the area now called Tennoji Ward, Osaka (then both aoso-consuming cities).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Well-known major aoso-za existed in Echigofuchu (the then aoso-producing area, now part of Joetsu City, Niigata Prefecture), in Omi Sakamoto (the then midpoint of the aoso distribution network, now part of Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture), and in Kyoto and in the area now called Tennoji Ward, Osaka (then both aoso-consuming cities).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>成立時期は明らかではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is unclear exactly when aoso-za was established.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is unclear exactly when aoso-za was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is unclear exactly when aoso-za was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>しかし少なくとも、南北朝時代 (日本)末期の永徳3年（1383年）頃に本所が正親町三条家から同族の三条西家に譲渡される以前と考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But at least, it must have been established before the position of &quot;honjo&quot; (proprietor or guarantor of manor) was transferred around 1383 from the Ogimachisanjo family to the Sanjonishi family (the relatives of Ogimachisanjo family).</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But at least, it must have been established before the position of &quot;honjo&quot; (proprietor or guarantor of manor) was transferred around 1383 from the Ogimachisanjo family to the Sanjonishi family (relatives of the Ogimachisanjo family).</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But at least, it must have been established before the position of &quot;honjo&quot; (proprietor or guarantor of manor) was transferred around 1383 from the Ogimachisanjo family to the Sanjonishi family (relatives of the Ogimachisanjo family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>正親町三条家との関連が強い官司と青苧商人のつながりより生じたものであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems to have been born of the aoso merchants linked with government officials who had strong connections with the Ogimachisanjo family</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems to have been born of aoso merchants linked with government officials who had strong connections with the Ogimachisanjo family</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems to have been born of aoso merchants linked with government officials who had strong connections with the Ogimachisanjo family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>本所である三条西家は京都周辺の諸口や丹波国・美濃国・近江坂本などに関所を設置したり、代官を派遣したりした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Utilizing the position of honjo, the Sanjonishi family set up some checkpoints around Kyoto, for example, in Moroguchi, in Tanba Province (the area that includes today&apos;s northern part of Kyoto Prefecture), in Mino Province (part of today&apos;s Gifu Prefecture), and in Omi Sakamoto, and dispatched local governors there.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Utilizing the position of honjo, the Sanjonishi family set up some checkpoints around Kyoto; for example, in Moroguchi, in Tanba Province (the area that includes today&apos;s northern part of Kyoto Prefecture), in Mino Province (part of today&apos;s Gifu Prefecture), and in Omi Sakamoto, and dispatched local governors there.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Utilizing the position of honjo, the Sanjonishi family set up some checkpoints around Kyoto; for example, in Moroguchi, in Tanba Province (the area that includes today&apos;s northern part of Kyoto Prefecture), in Mino Province (part of today&apos;s Gifu Prefecture), and in Omi Sakamoto, and dispatched local governors there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>これにより、同地を通過する青苧に対して公事を徴収したのである（苧公事）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With these measures, the Sanjonishi family collected &quot;kuji&quot; (the temporary tax) from aoso merchants who went through those checkpoints, and the kuji imposed on aoso merchants was called &quot;so-kuji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処 ・「公事」はここでは「臨時の租税」と解説しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With these measures, the Sanjonishi family collected &quot;kuji&quot; (temporary tax) from aoso merchants who passed through those checkpoints, and the kuji imposed on aoso merchants was called &quot;so-kuji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With these measures, the Sanjonishi family collected &quot;kuji&quot; (temporary tax) from aoso merchants who passed through those checkpoints, and the kuji imposed on aoso merchants was called &quot;so-kuji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>一方、青苧座は苧公事納入と引換に青苧の独占販売の権限を得ていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, aoso-za gained the exclusive right of selling aoso in exchange for the payment of so-kuji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, aoso-za gained the exclusive right of selling aoso in exchange for the payment of so-kuji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, aoso-za gained the exclusive right of selling aoso in exchange for the payment of so-kuji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>特に天王寺苧座の発言力は大きかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among others, &quot;Tennoji so-za&quot; (the guild of aoso in Tennoji) had a particularly powerful voice within the aoso community.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among others, &quot;Tennoji so-za&quot; (the guild of aoso in Tennoji) had a particularly powerful voice within the aoso community.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among others, &quot;Tennoji so-za&quot; (the guild of aoso in Tennoji) had a particularly powerful voice within the aoso community.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>というのも、天王寺苧座はまず、原料が集まる越後府中に赴いて越後苧座から独占的に買上げていたからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is firstly because Tennoji so-za had an almost exclusive right of purchasing asoso from &quot;Echigo so-za&quot; (the guild of aoso in Echigofuchu [the aoso producing area]).</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is firstly because Tennoji so-za had an almost exclusive right of purchasing aoso from &quot;Echigo so-za&quot; (the guild of aoso in Echigofuchu [the aoso-producing area]).</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is firstly because Tennoji so-za had an almost exclusive right of purchasing aoso from &quot;Echigo so-za&quot; (the guild of aoso in Echigofuchu [the aoso-producing area]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>更に天王寺苧座は坂本苧座・京中苧座に対してこれを独占的に販売していたからでもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And secondly, Tennoji so-za also had an almost exclusive right of selling aoso to &quot;Sakamoto so-za&quot; (the guild of aoso in Sakamoto) and to &quot;Kyochu so-za&quot; (the guild of aoso in Kyoto)</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And secondly, Tennoji so-za also had an almost exclusive right of selling aoso to &quot;Sakamoto so-za&quot; (the guild of aoso in Sakamoto) and to &quot;Kyochu so-za&quot; (the guild of aoso in Kyoto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And secondly, Tennoji so-za also had an almost exclusive right of selling aoso to &quot;Sakamoto so-za&quot; (the guild of aoso in Sakamoto) and to &quot;Kyochu so-za&quot; (the guild of aoso in Kyoto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>要するに天王寺苧座は越後－畿内間の青苧流通を完全に支配していたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In short, Tennoji so-za monopolized the distribution network of aoso from Echigo Province to &quot;Kinai region&quot; (the five provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara).</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In short, Tennoji so-za monopolized the distribution network of aoso from Echigo Province to the &quot;Kinai region&quot; (the five provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara).</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In short, Tennoji so-za monopolized the distribution network of aoso from Echigo Province to the &quot;Kinai region&quot; (the five provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その維持のため天王寺苧座は、本所である三条西家に対して通過時の苧公事の納入を免除して貰う替わりに年間150貫に及ぶ苧課役を三条西家に納入していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To keep its monopoly, Tennoji so-za paid the tax in kind as much as 562.5 kg annually to its honjo Sanjonishi family in exchange for the exemption from so-kuji that it paid when going through the checkpoints.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処 ・1貫は3.75kgなので150貫は562.5ｋｇです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To keep its monopoly, Tennoji so-za paid the tax in kind in an amount of as much as 562.5 kg annually to its honjo Sanjonishi family in exchange for the exemption from so-kuji that it paid when passing through the checkpoints.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To keep its monopoly, Tennoji so-za paid the tax in kind in an amount of as much as 562.5 kg annually to its honjo Sanjonishi family in exchange for the exemption from so-kuji that it paid when passing through the checkpoints.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>天文 (日本)年間には甲斐国・信濃国など新興の青苧産地からの青苧にも苧公事を賦課している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Tenmon era (A.D. 1532 - 1555), so-kuji was imposed also on the growing aoso producing areas, such as Kai Province (the present Yamanashi Prefecture) and Shinano Province (almost the same area as the present Nagano Prefecture covers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Tenmon era (A.D. 1532 - 1555), so-kuji was imposed also on the growing aoso-producing areas, such as Kai Province (the present Yamanashi Prefecture) and Shinano Province (almost the same area as that covered by the present Nagano Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Tenmon era (A.D. 1532 - 1555), so-kuji was imposed also on the growing aoso-producing areas, such as Kai Province (the present Yamanashi Prefecture) and Shinano Province (almost the same area as that covered by the present Nagano Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>ところが、明応6年（1497年）頃に守護代長尾氏が越後の国政を掌握すると、天王寺苧座の購入独占権が否定されるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when the Nagao clan, which assumed &quot;Shugodai&quot; (deputy of &apos;Shugo&apos; [provincial constable]) of Echigo Province, got control of the province administration around 1497, the clan did not permit Tennoji so-za the exclusive aoso-purchasing right.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when the Nagao clan, which assumed &quot;Shugodai&quot; (deputy of &apos;Shugo&apos; [provincial constable]) of Echigo Province, gained control of the province administration around 1497, the clan did not permit Tennoji so-za the exclusive aoso-purchasing right.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when the Nagao clan, which assumed &quot;Shugodai&quot; (deputy of &apos;Shugo&apos; [provincial constable]) of Echigo Province, gained control of the province administration around 1497, the clan did not permit Tennoji so-za the exclusive aoso-purchasing right.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>更に永正の乱によって長尾氏が守護上杉氏を完全に傀儡化すると、青苧座に対しても支配を及ぼすようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And after the Eisho War, the Nagao clan made the Uesugi clan (the Shugo of Echigo Province) its puppet, and it also began to exert its control over aoso-za.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And after the Eisho War, the Nagao clan made the Uesugi clan (the Shugo of Echigo Province) its puppet, and it also began to exert its control over aoso-za.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And after the Eisho War, the Nagao clan made the Uesugi clan (the Shugo of Echigo Province) its puppet, and it also began to exert its control over aoso-za.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>大永年間には長尾氏は越後苧座の頭人であった蔵田氏に青苧の公事徴収・流通統制権を認めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Daiei era (A.D. 1521- 1528), the Nagao clan gave both the kuji collection right and the distribution control right of aoso to the Kurata clan, which was &quot;tonin&quot; (the director) of Echigo so-za.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Daiei era (A.D. 1521- 1528), the Nagao clan gave both the kuji collection right and the distribution control right of aoso to the Kurata clan, which was &quot;tonin&quot; (the director) of Echigo so-za.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Daiei era (A.D. 1521- 1528), the Nagao clan gave both the kuji collection right and the distribution control right of aoso to the Kurata clan, which was &quot;tonin&quot; (the director) of Echigo so-za.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>また長尾氏は三条西家に対してもこれまで天王寺苧座などが納めていた苧課役を50貫に減額させた上で越後苧座による京都への青苧搬入を認めさせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the Nagao clan forced the Sanjonishi family not only to reduce the tax in kind, which was paid by Tennoji so-za, to 187.5 kg a year, but also to allow Echigo so-za to transport aoso into Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And the Nagao clan forced the Sanjonishi family not only to reduce the tax in kind, which was paid by Tennoji so-za, to 187.5 kg a year, but also to allow Echigo so-za to transport aoso into Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And the Nagao clan forced the Sanjonishi family not only to reduce the tax in kind, which was paid by Tennoji so-za, to 187.5 kg a year, but also to allow Echigo so-za to transport aoso into Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>この傾向は長尾景虎（上杉謙信）が上杉氏宗家を継承した後も強化された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This tendency was accelerated after Kagetora NAGAO (more commonly called &quot;Kenshin UESUGI&quot;) succeeded to &quot;Soke&quot; (the head family or house) of the Uesugi clan.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This tendency was accelerated after Kagetora NAGAO (more commonly called &quot;Kenshin UESUGI&quot;) succeeded to &quot;Soke&quot; (the head family or house) of the Uesugi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This tendency was accelerated after Kagetora NAGAO (more commonly called &quot;Kenshin UESUGI&quot;) succeeded to &quot;Soke&quot; (the head family or house) of the Uesugi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>この時代には各地から青苧購入のために訪れる諸国の船に対しても課税を行って越後－畿内間の青苧流通の支配権を獲得していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During his reign, he imposed the tax on the merchants who came by sea to Echigo Province from other provinces for aoso, thereby getting the control over the distribution network of aoso from Echigo Province to Kinai region.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During his reign, he imposed the tax on the merchants who came by sea to Echigo Province from other provinces for aoso, thereby gaining control over the distribution network of aoso from Echigo Province to the Kinai region.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During his reign, he imposed the tax on the merchants who came by sea to Echigo Province from other provinces for aoso, thereby gaining control over the distribution network of aoso from Echigo Province to the Kinai region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>この際に活躍したのが前述の蔵田氏である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And it was the above-mentioned Kurata clan that was actively involved in this aoso trade.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And it was the above-mentioned Kurata clan that was actively involved in this aoso trade.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And it was the above-mentioned Kurata clan that was actively involved in this aoso trade.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>蔵田氏は越後の苧商人を統括するとともに長尾氏（上杉氏）御用商人として長尾景虎（上杉謙信）の軍事活動を経済的な面から支えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kurata clan unified the aoso merchants in Echigo Province, and backed up the military activities of Kagetora NAGAO (Kenshin UESUGI) in economy as its purveyor.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kurata clan unified the aoso merchants in Echigo Province, and backed up the military activities of Kagetora NAGAO (Kenshin UESUGI) in economy as its purveyor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kurata clan unified the aoso merchants in Echigo Province, and backed up the military activities of Kagetora NAGAO (Kenshin UESUGI) in economy as its purveyor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="23">
<j>青苧座は織豊政権による座の撤廃と上杉氏の移封によって力を失うことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward, za was abolished by &quot;the Shokuho regime&quot; (the regime of Nobunaga ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI. &quot;Shoku&quot; and &quot;ho&quot; are the initial letters of Oda and Toyotomi), and the territory of the Uesugi clan was changed, so that aoso-za in Echigo Province lost its influence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterward, za was abolished by &quot;the Shokuho regime&quot; (the regime of Nobunaga ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI; &quot;Shoku&quot; and &quot;ho&quot; are the initial letters of Oda and Toyotomi), and the territory of the Uesugi clan was changed, so that aoso-za in Echigo Province lost its influence.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterward, za was abolished by &quot;the Shokuho regime&quot; (the regime of Nobunaga ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI; &quot;Shoku&quot; and &quot;ho&quot; are the initial letters of Oda and Toyotomi), and the territory of the Uesugi clan was changed, so that aoso-za in Echigo Province lost its influence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>そして皮肉なことに越後の青苧が江戸時代元禄年間に没落した最大の理由は上杉氏の移封とともに青苧栽培技術が伝来された会津藩・米沢藩両藩産の青苧との競争に敗北した影響が大きかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And ironically, the aoso in Echigo Province is said to have got the finishing stroke during the Genroku era (A.D. 1688 - 1704) of the Edo period in the loss of the competition over aoso with the Aizu domain and the Yonezawa domain, into which the cultivation techniques of aoso were introduced when the Uesugi clan had its territory changed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And ironically, the aoso in Echigo Province is said to have gotten the finishing stroke during the Genroku era (A.D. 1688 - 1704) of the Edo period in the loss of the competition over aoso with the Aizu domain and the Yonezawa domain, into which the cultivation techniques of aoso were introduced when the Uesugi clan had its territory changed.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And ironically, the aoso in Echigo Province is said to have gotten the finishing stroke during the Genroku era (A.D. 1688 - 1704) of the Edo period in the loss of the competition over aoso with the Aizu domain and the Yonezawa domain, into which the cultivation techniques of aoso were introduced when the Uesugi clan had its territory changed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>