<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>脱藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dappan (Leaving the Domain)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dappan (Leaving the Domain)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dappan (Leaving the Domain)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>脱藩（だっぱん）は、江戸時代に武士が藩を脱出して浪人になること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dappan means when a samurai left his domain and became a Ronin (masterless samurai).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Dappan&quot; was the act of a samurai leaving his master&apos;s domain to become a Ronin (masterless samurai).</e>
<cmt>文書の流れをスムーズにするために変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Dappan&quot; was the act of a samurai leaving his master&apos;s domain to become a Ronin (masterless samurai).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)では、主君を違える行為は一般的に発生していたが、江戸時代に入ると「脱藩は臣下の身で主を見限るものとして」許されない風潮が高まり、討手が放たれることもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Sengoku period in Japan, incidents of a samurai rebelling against his lord were frequent but in the Edo period, it was usually unacceptable as &apos;Dappan means to abandon his lord when he was only a vassal&apos; and pursuers were sometimes sent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Sengoku Period of Japan it was a frequent occurrence for samurai&apos;s to part from their masters, but from the Edo Period it became an unforgiveable crime for a vassal to abandon his lord and many times pursuers were sent after them.</e>
<cmt>文書の流れをスムーズにするために変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Sengoku Period of Japan it was a frequent occurrence for samurai&apos;s to part from their masters, but from the Edo Period it became an unforgiveable crime for a vassal to abandon his lord and many times pursuers were sent after them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>これは、脱藩者を通じて軍事機密や御家騒動などが表沙汰になり、藩（藩主）にとっては致命的な改易が頻繁に生じたことも一因である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was because, through the Dappan samurai, the Domain&apos;s military secrecy and family troubles could be revealed in public and frequently caused fatal &apos;Kaieki&apos; sanctions (sudden dismissal and deprivation of position, privileges and properties) for the domain (and/or the lord of the domain).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was because, through the Dappan samurai, the Domain&apos;s military secrecy and family troubles could be revealed in public and frequently caused fatal &apos;Kaieki&apos; sanctions (sudden dismissal and deprivation of position, privileges and properties) for the domain (and/or the lord of the domain).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was because, through the Dappan samurai, the Domain&apos;s military secrecy and family troubles could be revealed in public and frequently caused fatal &apos;Kaieki&apos; sanctions (sudden dismissal and deprivation of position, privileges and properties) for the domain (and/or the lord of the domain).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>しかし、江戸時代中期以降、太平の時代に入ると、軍事機密の意味は無くなり、慢性的な財政難のため、家臣が禄を離れることは、枢要な人物で無い限り事実上自由になっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the middle of the Edo period - in the Taihei era - military secrecy had no meaning and because chronic financial difficulties caused vassals to leave their Roku (salaries); they were basically free unless they were in important positions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the mid-Edo Period to the Taihei Period, military secrecy was no longer needed and ongoing financial difficulty made it possible for vassals to leave, unless they served in key positions.</e>
<cmt>文書の流れをスムーズにするために変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the mid-Edo Period to the Taihei Period, military secrecy was no longer needed and ongoing financial difficulty made it possible for vassals to leave, unless they served in key positions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>もっともその場合にも法的な手続をとる事が要件となっており、これに反して無断で脱藩した場合には欠落の罪として扱われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were required to take legal steps in order to leave and if they left without approval, it was dealt as a sin of running away.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By then it was also a requirement to go through legal procedures in order to leave, and those who left without it were charged with desertion.</e>
<cmt>文書の流れをスムーズにするために変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By then it was also a requirement to go through legal procedures in order to leave, and those who left without it were charged with desertion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>家名は断絶・闕所、本人が捕らえられれば場合によっては死刑にされたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their Kamei (family name) was to be extinct and Kessho (confiscation of one&apos;s estate for punishment) was conducted; if the samurai was caught, they were in some cases executed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Offenders had their family name declared extinct, their estates confiscated, and if they were caught, they faced the possibility of execution.</e>
<cmt>文書の流れをスムーズにするために変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Offenders had their family name declared extinct, their estates confiscated, and if they were caught, they faced the possibility of execution.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>幕末には、藩にいると自由に行動できないので、脱藩し尊王攘夷の志を立てようとする武士が増えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of the Edo period, because they could not act freely if they were in a domain, many samurai chose to leave their Domains and decide to work towards Sonno Joi (advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Towards the end of the Edo period, many samurai were dissatisfied with their lack of freedom within their domains and opted to leave their domain and back the Sonno Joi ideal (Imperialism and the expulsion of foreigners).</e>
<cmt>文書の流れをスムーズにするために変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Towards the end of the Edo period, many samurai were dissatisfied with their lack of freedom within their domains and opted to leave their domain and back the Sonno Joi ideal (Imperialism and the expulsion of foreigners).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>藩の側も脱藩を黙認することが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Quite often, Domains overlooked Dappan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In many cases, the domains overlooked those who left.</e>
<cmt>文書の流れをスムーズにするために変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In many cases, the domains overlooked those who left.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>主な脱藩者には、吉田松陰や坂本龍馬、中岡慎太郎などが挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dappan samurai include Shoin YOSHIDA, Ryoma SAKAMOTO, Shintaro NAKAOKA, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Well-known &quot;Dappan&quot; samurai include Shoin YOSHIDA, Ryoma SAKAMOTO, Shintaro NAKAOKA, etc, are.</e>
<cmt>文書の流れをスムーズにするために変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Well-known &quot;Dappan&quot; samurai include Shoin YOSHIDA, Ryoma SAKAMOTO, Shintaro NAKAOKA and so on.</e>
<cmt>etc→and so onare を削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Chaoswing(id:286537), らりた(id:1327), 橄欖岩(id:24996), 水野白楓(id:22811), Lupinoid(id:68), Extrahitz(id:26245), 難民(id:4644), 土方　誠(id:3651), Ultratomio(id:1090), BAKU(id:55205), Anexus6(id:190046), Johncapistrano(id:969), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>