<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>太閤検地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taiko-kenchi (the land survey by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taiko-kenchi (the land survey by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taiko-kenchi (the land survey by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>太閤検地 （たいこうけんち）は、豊臣秀吉が全国的に行った検地（田畑（つまり山林は除く）の測量及び収穫量調査）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taiko-kenchi is the land surveys conducted by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI throughout Japan (surveys of the agricultural lands (i.e., except mountains and forests) and productions).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taiko-kenchi is the land survey conducted by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI throughout Japan (survey of agricultural lands (i.e., except mountains and forests - and produce).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Taiko-kenchi is a series of land surveys (surveys of agricultural lands [i.e. except mountains and forests] and production) conducted by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI throughout Japan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>天正の石直し・文禄の検地ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Tensho no Kokunaoshi (Taiko-kenchi in Tensho era) or the land survey in Bunroku era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called Tensho no Kokunaoshi (Taiko-kenchi in the Tensho era) or and survey in the Bunroku era.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called &quot;Tensho no Kokunaoshi&quot; (literally, &quot;the review of lands of the Tensho era&quot;) or &quot;Bunroku no Kenchi&quot; (literally, &quot;land surveys of the Bunroku era&quot;).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>豊臣秀吉は、1582年から検地を行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI began the land survey in 1582.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI began the land survey in 1582.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI began the land survey in 1582.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>1591年に関白を豊臣秀次に譲るまでは太閤（たいこう）ではなかったが、1591年以降は秀吉自身が「太閤」の称号を好んで使用したこともあり、1591年以前の検地も含めて「太閤検地」と言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Hideyoshi did not assume the title Taiko (father of the Imperial adviser) until he handed over the title Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) to Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI in 1591, the land surveys including those conducted before 1591 have been called &quot;Taiko-kenchi&quot;, because Hideyoshi was pleased to be titled &quot;Taiko&quot; after 1591.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Hideyoshi did not assume the title Taiko (father of the Imperial adviser) until he handed over the title Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) to Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI in 1591, the land surveys including those conducted before 1591 had been called &quot;Taiko-kenchi&quot;, because Hideyoshi was pleased with the title &quot;Taiko&quot; after 1591.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Hideyoshi had not had the title of Taiko (the father of the Imperial adviser) until he handed over the title of Kanpaku (the chief adviser for an emperor) to Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI in 1591, all his land surveys including the surveys conducted before 1591 were included in the &apos;Taiko-kenchi,&apos; because Hideyoshi had been pleased with the use of the title of &apos;Taiko&apos; since 1591.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>これを企画発案したのは石田三成で、検地奉行として事実上の施行者となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was Mitsunari ISHIDA who drew up and carried out Taiko-kenchi and also served as Kenchi survey magistrate, actually conducting the surveys.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was Mitsunari ISHIDA who drew up and conducted Taiko-kenchi and also served as the Kenchi survey magistrate, actually conducting the surveys.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was Mitsunari ISHIDA who drew up and suggested the Taiko-kenchi, and he actually conducted the surveys as a land survey magistrate.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>秀吉は、各地を征服するごとに検地を行い、征服地を確実に把握して全国統一の基礎とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi carried out the land surveys on each area he had just conquered so that he can surely comprehend his land to form the foundation of building a united country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi carried out the land surveys in each area he conquered to understand the extent of the land as a foundation to build a united country.</e>
<cmt>wordiness, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi carried out the land surveys in each area he conquered to understand the extent of the land as a foundation to build a united country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、太閤検地では全国的な規模で統一された方法で行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taiko-kenchi was carried out nation wide in a uniform method.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taiko-kenchi was carried out nation wide by a uniform method.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A uniform method was used throughout the country for the Taiko-kenchi.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>太閤検地は、それまでの複雑な土地所有関係を整理し、土地制度を一新した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of Taiko-kenchi, complicated relationships of landownership that had developed until then were consolidated and the land system was renewed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of Taiko-kenchi, complicated relationships concerning land ownership that had developed until then were resolved and consolidated and the land system was renewed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Taiko-kenchi enabled them to investigate and reorganize the long-established complicated land ownership matters, so that they could establish a new land system.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>これにより、荘園制度は完全に崩壊することとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That obliterated the manorial system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That obliterated the manorial system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, the manorial system was finally obliterated entirely.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>さらに、物差し、升を統一して行われたため、度量衡の統一がなされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, Taiko-kenchi was carried out with standardized measures and bushels, thereby weights and measures were also standardized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, Taiko-kenchi was carried out with standardized measures and bushels, thereby weights and measures were also standardized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides, since the Taiko-kenchi was carried out with standardized measures and bushels, weights and measures were also standardized.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>この太閤検地の実施により兵糧を絶やすことなく小田原城を約20万の兵で囲み、北条氏を滅亡させた（小田原の役）のは有名な話である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a famous story that, thanks to Taiko-kenchi, Hideyoshi sieged Odawara-jo Castle by two hundred thousand soldiers to defeat the Hojo clan (the Siege of Odawara) without running out the army provisions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a famous story, thanks to Taiko-kenchi, Hideyoshi sieged Odawara-jo Castle with two hundred thousand samurai to defeat the Hojo clan (the Siege of Odawara) without running out of provisions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a famous story that Hideyoshi attacked Odawara-jo Castle surrounding it with two hundred thousand samurai and succeeded in defeating the Hojo clan (this battle is called &quot;the Siege of Odawara&quot;), without running out of provisions owing to the Taiko-kenchi.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>太閤検地によって、各地の石高が確定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Taiko-kenchi, Kokudaka (crop yield) of each province was defined.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In accordance with Taiko-kenchi, Kokudaka (crop yield) for each province was defined.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In accordance with Taiko-kenchi, Kokudaka (crop yield) for each province was defined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>それは、その後江戸時代の幕藩体制の基礎となる石高制のもととなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That originated the system of Kokudaka (assessed yield; tax system based on rice, measured by reference to the rated annual yield of the domain) which formed the foundation of the shogunate system in the subsequent Edo period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This originated the system of Kokudaka (assessed yield; tax system based on rice, determined according to the annual rated yield of the domain) which formed the foundation of the shogunate system in the subsequent Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This originated the system of Kokudaka (assessed yield; tax system based on rice, determined according to the annual rated yield of the domain) which formed the foundation of the shogunate system in the subsequent Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>江戸時代においてもこれに倣って検地が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period, the land surveys were conducted after the example of Taiko-kenchi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period, land surveys were conducted after the example of Taiko-kenchi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period, land surveys were also conducted following the example of the Taiko-kenchi.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>これ以前にも、織田信長によって大規模な検地(指出検地とも呼ばれる)が行われた（一部の者はこれを「信長検地（しんちょうけんち）」と呼ぶ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even before Taiko-kenchi, comprehensive land surveys (also called Sashidashi Kenchi) were conducted by Nobunaga ODA (some people call this &quot;Shincho Kenchi&quot;).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even before Taiko-kenchi, comprehensive land surveys (also called Sashidashi Kenchi) were conducted by Nobunaga ODA (some people call it &quot;Shincho Kenchi&quot;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even before Taiko-kenchi, comprehensive land surveys (also called Sashidashi Kenchi) were conducted by Nobunaga ODA (some people call it &apos;Shincho Kenchi&apos;).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」にあわせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これは、太閤検地の原型になったといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sashidashi Kenchi, or Shincho Kenchi, is said to have originated Taiko-kenchi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sashidashi Kenchi, or Shincho Kenchi, is said to have originated Taiko-kenchi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sashidashi-kenchi (or the Shincho-kenchi) is said to be the model for the Taiko-kenchi.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>学説史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History of Studies</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History of Studies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History of studies</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>太閤検地論争</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taiko-Kenchi Controversy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taiko-Kenchi Controversy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taiko-Kenchi Controversy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>安良城・勝俣論争</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Controversy between Araki and Katsumata</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Controversy between Araki and Katsumata</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Controversy between Araki and Katsumata</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 もね～るmoner(id:28477), ゆず湯(id:190382), Race(id:131322), こおりやんま(id:108912), Lilium auratum(id:13615), Mintleaf(id:2216), 青山コロハ(id:118527), 日陰猫Joga(id:9749), Nerimaman(id:61206), Shimoxx(id:9332), こぶまき(id:38278), 伏儀(id:142093), 越中掾(id:149423), 神奈川大学2年経済学部経済学科(id:1107), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), Satotakuya(id:182505), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>