<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>宇佐山城</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Usayama-jo Castle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Usayama-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Usayama-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>宇佐山城（うさやまじょう）は滋賀県大津市錦織に残る、中世の山城である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Usayama-jo Castle was a yamajiro (a castle built on a mountain to take advantage of the mountain&apos;s topography) constructed in the Medieval Period, whose remains still exist near Nishikoori, Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Usayama-jo Castle was a yamajiro (a castle built atop a mountain to take advantage of the mountain&apos;s topography) constructed in the Medieval Period, and its ruins can be found near Nishikoori, Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Usayama-jo Castle was a yamajiro (a castle built atop a mountain to take advantage of the mountain&apos;s topography) constructed in the Medieval Period, and its ruins can be found near Nishikoori, Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>湖西周りで京に向かうには避けては通れない位置にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was located at a place unavoidable when one heads toward Kyoto along the western coast of Lake Biwa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was located in a conspicuous location along the route to Kyoto on the western coast of Lake Biwa.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was located in a conspicuous location along the route to Kyoto on the western coast of Lake Biwa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>標高336ｍの高さがある、宇佐山にあり、琵琶湖を一望できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Usayama-jo Castle was located at the top of 336-meter-high Mt. Usayama, commanding a full view of Lake Biwa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Usayama-jo Castle was located at the top of the 336 meter high Mt. Usayama, commanding a full view of Lake Biwa.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Usayama-jo Castle was located at the top of the 336 meter high Mt. Usayama, commanding a full view of Lake Biwa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>元亀元年（1570年）、朝倉氏の南進に備えるべく、琵琶湖と北国街道の押さえを意図する織田信長に命じられた森可成によって、近江国滋賀郡に築かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Usayama-jo Castle was built by Yoshinari MORI in Shiga County, Omi Province in 1570 by order of Nobunaga ODA, who intended to take control of Lake Biwa and Hokkoku-kaido Road, bracing for the advance of the Asakura clan to the south.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Usayama-jo Castle was built by Yoshinari MORI in Shiga County, Omi Province in 1570 by order of Nobunaga ODA, who intended to take control of Lake Biwa and Hokkoku-kaido Road, bracing for the advance of the Asakura clan to the south.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Usayama-jo Castle was built by Yoshinari MORI in Shiga County, Omi Province in 1570 by order of Nobunaga ODA, who intended to take control of Lake Biwa and Hokkoku-kaido Road, bracing for the advance of the Asakura clan to the south.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>同年、摂津国で勃発した野田城・福島城の戦いで織田軍主力が投入されている中、浅井氏・朝倉連合軍は信長の背後を突くべく進軍を開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Oda&apos;s main force was assigned to the Battle of Noda-jo Castle and Fukushima-jo Castle erupted in Settsu Province in the same year, the Asai and Asakura allied forces started to advance aiming to attack Nobunaga from behind.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Oda&apos;s main force was assigned to the Battle of Noda-jo Castle and Fukushima-jo Castle which erupted in the Settsu Province in the same year, the Asai and Asakura allied forces started to advance towards Oda, aiming to attack his forces from behind.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Oda&apos;s main force was assigned to the Battle of Noda-jo Castle and Fukushima-jo Castle which erupted in the Settsu Province in the same year, the Asai and Asakura allied forces started to advance towards Oda, aiming to attack his forces from behind.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>城主・森可成は近江に居た野府城主・織田信治、青地茂綱らと共に交通の要所である坂本 (大津市)を先に占領して街道を封鎖して連合軍の進軍妨害を試みる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshinari MORI, the lord of Usayama-jo Castle, attempted to intercept the advance of the allied forces by preemptively conquering Sakamoto (Otsu City), a strategic point of transportation, to blockade roads together with Nobuharu ODA, the lord of Nobu-jo Castle, and Shigetsuna AOCHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshinari MORI, the lord of Usayama-jo Castle, attempted to intercept the advance of the allied forces by preemptively conquering Sakamoto (Otsu City), a strategic point of transportation, to help blockade roads along with Nobuharu ODA, the lord of Nobu-jo Castle, and Shigetsuna AOCHI.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshinari MORI, the lord of Usayama-jo Castle, attempted to intercept the advance of the allied forces by preemptively conquering Sakamoto (Otsu City), a strategic point of transportation, to help blockade roads along with Nobuharu ODA, the lord of Nobu-jo Castle, and Shigetsuna AOCHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そして9月16日に緒戦においては連合軍を撃退する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 16, they fought off the allied forces at the beginning of the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 16, they fended off the allied forces towards the beginning of the war.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 25, they fended off the allied forces towards the beginning of the war.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし本願寺顕如の要請を受けた延暦寺の僧兵も連合軍に加わり、9月20日にさらに数の膨らんだ連合軍の侵攻を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the allied forces were joined by armed priests of Enryaku-ji Temple at the request of Kennyo HONGANJI, and On September 20, further expanded allied forces invaded the territory of Yoshinari&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the allied forces were joined by armed priests of Enryaku-ji Temple at the request of Kennyo HONGANJI, and on September 20, the enlarged allied forces invaded the Yoshinari&apos;s territory.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the allied forces were joined by armed priests of Enryaku-ji Temple at the request of Kennyo HONGANJI, and on October 29, the enlarged allied forces invaded the Yoshinari&apos;s territory.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>先鋒の朝倉景鏡を押し返すなど健闘を見せるが、浅井対馬･玄蕃の2千に側面から攻撃を仕掛けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Yoshinari&apos;s force fought bravely, such as pushing back Kageakira ASAKURA who lead the allied forces, they were attacked on the flank by 2,000 soldiers of ASAI Tsushima and Genba army.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Yoshinari&apos;s forces fought bravely by pushing back Kageakira ASAKURA who led the allied forces, they were attacked on the flank by 2,000 soldiers from the Genba and Tsushima ASAI armies.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Yoshinari&apos;s forces fought bravely by pushing back Kageakira ASAKURA who led the allied forces, they were attacked on the flank by 2,000 soldiers from the Genba and Tsushima ASAI armies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>さらに朝倉中務、山崎吉家、阿波賀三郎の隊に加え浅井長政本隊もこれに加わったためついに崩れ森可成、織田信治、青地茂綱の3人は討ち死にする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the main army of Nagamasa ASAI joined the attack together with the armies of ASAKURA Nakatsukasa, Yoshiie YAMAZAKI, and Saburo AHAKA, Yoshinari&apos;s force finally broke down, leading to the deaths of Yoshinari MORI, Nobuharu ODA, and Shigetsuna AOCHI in the battle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the main army of Nagamasa ASAI joined the armies of ASAKURA Nakatsukasa, Yoshiie YAMAZAKI, and Saburo AHAKA, Yoshinari&apos;s forces finally broke down, leading to the deaths of Yoshinari MORI, Nobuharu ODA, and Shigetsuna AOCHI.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the main army of Nagamasa ASAI joined the armies of ASAKURA Nakatsukasa, Yoshiie YAMAZAKI, and Saburo AHAKA, Yoshinari&apos;s forces finally broke down, leading to the deaths of Yoshinari MORI, Nobuharu ODA, and Shigetsuna AOCHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>22日には摂津の信長にも知らせが届き、近江の情勢を知った信長はこの浅井・朝倉連合軍との対決を優先。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga in Settsu, who had heard the news on the 22nd and realized the situation in Omi, decided to prioritize the battle with the Asai and Asakura allied forces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga in Settsu, who had heard the news on the 22nd and became aware of the situation in Omi, decided to prioritize the battle against the Asai and Asakura allied forces.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga in Settsu, who had heard the news on the 31st and became aware of the situation in Omi, decided to prioritize the battle against the Asai and Asakura allied forces.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>23日に「野田城・福島城の戦い」から織田軍主力を撤退させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the 23rd, he withdrew his main force from the Battle of Noda-jo Castle and Fukushima-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the 23rd, he withdrew his main force from the Battle of Noda-jo Castle and Fukushima-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the November 1, he withdrew his main force from &apos;the Battle of Noda-jo Castle and Fukushima-jo Castle.&apos;</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。原文｢｣の部分に&apos; &apos;を付加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>その間、宇佐山城は坂本で森らを破った連合軍の猛攻を受けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, Usayama-jo Castle had been fiercely attacked by the allied forces that had previously defeated Yoshinari MORI&apos;s army in Sakamoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Usayama-jo Castle had been fiercely attacked by the allied forces that had previously defeated Yoshinari MORI&apos;s army in Sakamoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Usayama-jo Castle had been fiercely attacked by the allied forces that had previously defeated Yoshinari MORI&apos;s army in Sakamoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>しかし、可成の部下である各務元正らが城兵と共に強硬に抵抗し、24日に信長が大津市が救援に現れるまでついに落城しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Motomasa KAGAMI, Yoshinari&apos;s subordinate, and others strongly fought back along with the castle garrison, and tenaciously held out until Nobunaga arrived in Otsu City to help them on the 24th.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Motomasa KAGAMI, Yoshinari&apos;s subordinate, and others strongly fought back along with the castle garrison, and tenaciously held out until Nobunaga arrived in Otsu City to help them on the 24th.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Motomasa KAGAMI, Yoshinari&apos;s subordinate, and others strongly fought back along with the castle garrison, and tenaciously held out until Nobunaga arrived in Otsu City to help them on the November 2.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>その後、この地を賜った明智光秀が入城するも、翌年坂本城を築いて移ったため廃城となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Mitsuhide AKECHI had been later given this territory and entered the castle, the castle was demolished after Mitsuhide moved to Sakamoto-jo Castle that he built next year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Mitsuhide AKECHI was later given this territory and the castle, the castle was demolished after Mitsuhide moved to Sakamoto-jo Castle which he built the following year.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Mitsuhide AKECHI was later given this territory and the castle, the castle was demolished after Mitsuhide moved to Sakamoto-jo Castle which he built the following year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tiyoringo(id:70026), Fryed-peach(id:63402), Bakira(id:184047), のーさん(id:258153), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>