<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>水替人足</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mizukae nisoku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mizukae nisoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mizukae nisoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>水替人足（みずかえにんそく）は、鉱山に溜まった排水を外部に排出する仕事（水替）に従事した人足（労働者）のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;mizukae nisoku (drainage laborers)&quot; refers to those mining laborers engaged in removing the water that collects in mines and pumping it outside the mine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;mizukae nisoku (drainage laborers)&quot; refers to those mining laborers engaged in removing the water that collects in mines and pumping it outside the mine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;mizukae nisoku (drainage laborers)&quot; refers to those mining laborers engaged in removing the water that collects in mines and pumping it outside the mine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>ここでは主に江戸幕府が管理した佐渡金山にて、坑道の排水を排出する仕事に従事した人足について述べる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The remainder of this article will focus mainly on the laborers engaged in tunnel-based drainage efforts at the Sado gold mine, which was run directly by the Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The remainder of this article will focus mainly on the laborers engaged in tunnel-based drainage efforts at the Sado gold mine, which was run directly by the Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The remainder of this article will focus mainly on the laborers engaged in tunnel-based drainage efforts at the Sado gold mine, which was run directly by the Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>佐渡金山へ水替人足が送られるようになったのは安永6年(1777年)のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first time drainage laborers were sent to Sado gold mine was in 1777.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first time drainage laborers were sent to Sado gold mine was in 1777.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first time drainage laborers were sent to Sado gold mine was in 1777.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>天明の大飢饉など、折からの政情不安により発生した無宿が大量に江戸周辺に流入し、様々な凶悪犯罪を犯すようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a huge influx of homeless people into Edo and its environs due to the Great Tenmei Famine and the resulting political instability, a situation which led to a wide variety of serious crimes being committed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a huge influx of homeless people into Edo and its environs due to the Great Tenmei Famine and the resulting political instability, and many of the homeless committed a wide variety of serious crimes.</e>
<cmt>文末を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a huge influx of homeless people into Edo and its environs due to the Great Tenmei Famine and the resulting political instability, and many of the homeless committed a wide variety of serious crimes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>その予防対策として、懲罰としての意味合いや将軍のお膝元である江戸浄化のため、犯罪者の予備軍になりえる無宿者を捕らえて佐渡島の佐渡金山に送り、彼らを人足として使役しようとするものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In what was at once a preventative and punitive measure as well as an effort by the Shogun to clean up Edo--the seat of his power--homeless people living in Edo, now deemed potential criminals, were rounded up and sent to the Sado gold mine on Sadoshima Island and put to work as laborers there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In what was at once a preventative and punitive measure as well as an effort by the Shogun to clean up Edo, the seat of his power, the homeless who were deemed potential criminals were rounded up and sent to the Sado gold mine on Sadoga-shima Island and put to work as laborers there.</e>
<cmt>佐渡島の表記を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In what was at once a preventative and punitive measure as well as an effort by the Shogun to clean up Edo, the seat of his power, the homeless who were deemed potential criminals were rounded up and sent to the Sado gold mine on Sadoga-shima Island and put to work as laborers there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>発案者は勘定奉行の石谷清昌（元佐渡奉行）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first to propose this plan was the kanjo bugyo (commissioner of finance) Kiyomasa ISHITANI (the former Sado bugyo (commissioner of Sado)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first to propose this plan was the kanjo bugyo (commissioner of finance) Kiyomasa ISHITANI (the former Sado bugyo [commissioner of Sado]).</e>
<cmt>括弧内カッコを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first to propose this plan was the kanjo bugyo (commissioner of finance) Kiyomasa ISHITANI (the former Sado bugyo [commissioner of Sado]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>佐渡奉行は治安が悪化するといって反対したが、半ば強引に押し切る形で無宿者が佐渡島に送られることになり、毎年数十人が送られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The then-current commissioner of Sado opposed the plan, citing fears that public order would deteriorate, but proponents, succeeded (not without forceful coercion) in ramming through their plan, and homeless people began to be sent to Sadoshima Island; thereafter, every year several dozen would be sent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The then-current commissioner of Sado opposed the plan, citing fears that public order would deteriorate, but proponents succeeded (not without forceful coercion) in ramming through their plan, and homeless people began to be sent to Sadoga-shima Island; thereafter, every year several dozen would be sent.</e>
<cmt>カンマをひとつ削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The then-current commissioner of Sado opposed the plan, citing fears that public order would deteriorate, but proponents succeeded (not without forceful coercion) in ramming through their plan, and homeless people began to be sent to Sadoga-shima Island; thereafter, every year several dozen would be sent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>当地の佐渡では遠島の刑を受けた流人（「島流し」）と区別するため（佐渡への遠島は元禄13年(1700年)に廃止されている）、水替人足は「島送り」と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To distinguish drainage laborers from those who had suffered the penalty of &quot;ento&quot; or exile to a remote island (note however that in 1700 Sadoshima was abandoned as a potential remote island for this penalty), who were called &quot;shimanagashi&quot; (&quot;exiled to the island&quot;), such laborers were referred to as &quot;shimaokuri&quot; (&quot;sent to the island&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To distinguish from those who had suffered the penalty of &quot;ento&quot; or exile to a remote island who were called &quot;shimanagashi&quot; (&quot;exiled to the island&quot;), drainage laborers were referred to as &quot;shimaokuri&quot; (&quot;sent to the island&quot;) (because the banishment to Sadoga-shima had already been abolished in 1700).</e>
<cmt>文章の流れを分かりやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To distinguish from those who had suffered the penalty of &quot;ento&quot; or exile to a remote island who were called &quot;shimanagashi&quot; (&quot;exiled to the island&quot;), drainage laborers were referred to as &quot;shimaokuri&quot; (&quot;sent to the island&quot;) (because the banishment to Sadoga-shima had already been abolished in 1700).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>当初は無宿である者のみを送ったが、天明8年(1788年)には敲や入墨の刑に処されたが身元保証人がいない者、文化(元号)2年(1805年)には人足寄場での行いが悪い者、追放刑を受けても改悛する姿勢が見えない者まで送られるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though at first only homeless people were sent, the scope of who could be sent gradually widened, beginning in 1788 with those who had been punished with flogging or tattooing and had no personal guarantor, continuing in 1805 with those who had acted poorly at their work-houses, and finally extending to those who had shown no contrition for their crimes even after enduring exile.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though at first only homeless people were sent, the scope of who could be sent gradually widened, beginning in 1788 with those who had been punished with flogging or tattooing and had no personal guarantor, continuing in 1805 with those who had acted poorly at their work-houses, and finally extending to those who had shown no contrition for their crimes even after enduring exile.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though at first only homeless people were sent, the scope of who could be sent gradually widened, beginning in 1788 with those who had been punished with flogging or tattooing and had no personal guarantor, continuing in 1805 with those who had acted poorly at their work-houses, and finally extending to those who had shown no contrition for their crimes even after enduring exile.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="10">
<j>犯罪者の更生という目的もあった（作業に応じて小遣銭が支給され、改悛した者は釈放された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One goal of the policy was to rehabilitate criminals (they earned small salaries from their labor, and those who repented of their crimes would be released.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One goal of the policy was to rehabilitate criminals (they earned small salaries from their labor, and those who repented of their crimes would be released. Convicts on Sadoga-shima Island, much like those at the work-houses of Tsukudajima Island, were given one type of labor to perform, and so if they showed contrition they would receive a tiny sum as savings and, after many years, would be allowed to return to their hometowns), but drainage work was extremely heavy labor, and drainage laborers were so cruelly exploited that it was said they could not survive for more than three years.</e>
<cmt>括弧の途中で分割されていたので1文にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One goal of the policy was to rehabilitate criminals (they earned small salaries from their labor, and those who repented of their crimes would be released. Convicts on Sadoga-shima Island, much like those at the work-houses of Tsukudajima Island, were given one type of labor to perform, and so if they showed contrition they would receive a tiny sum as savings and, after many years, would be allowed to return to their hometowns), but drainage work was extremely heavy labor, and drainage laborers were so cruelly exploited that it was said they could not survive for more than three years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>佃島の人足寄場とおなじく、囚徒に一種の職をあたえたから、改悟すれば些少の貯蓄を得て年を経て郷里にかえることをゆるされた）が、水替は過酷な重労働であり、3年以上は生存できないといわれるほど酷使された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Convicts on Sadoshima Island, much like those at the work-houses of Tsukudajima Island, were given one type of labor to perform, and so if they showed contrition they would receive a tiny sum as savings and, after many years, would be allowed to return to their hometowns), but drainage work was extremely heavy labor, and drainage laborers were so cruelly exploited that it was said they could not survive for more than three years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Convicts on Sadoshima Island, much like those at the work-houses of Tsukudajima Island, were given one type of labor to perform, and so if they showed contrition they would receive a tiny sum as savings and, after many years, would be allowed to return to their hometowns), but drainage work was extremely heavy labor, and drainage laborers were so cruelly exploited that it was said they could not survive for more than three years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Convicts on Sadoshima Island, much like those at the work-houses of Tsukudajima Island, were given one type of labor to perform, and so if they showed contrition they would receive a tiny sum as savings and, after many years, would be allowed to return to their hometowns), but drainage work was extremely heavy labor, and drainage laborers were so cruelly exploited that it was said they could not survive for more than three years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>そのため逃亡する者が後を絶たず、犯罪者の隔離施設としても、矯正施設としても十分な役割を果たすことが出来なかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently, there was a never-ending string of convicts who tried to escape, and neither the facilities built to isolate the convict population nor the correctional facilities were able to do much towards accomplishing their objectives.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, there was a never-ending string of convicts who tried to escape, so the system failed to play its full part to isolate nor to correct these criminals.</e>
<cmt>簡潔にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, there was a never-ending string of convicts who tried to escape, so the system failed to play its full part to isolate nor to correct these criminals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="13">
<j>島においてさらに犯罪のあったときは鉱穴に禁錮されたが、これは敷内追込といい、また島から逃亡した者は死罪であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those who committed additional crimes while on the island were confined in mineshafts, a punishment known as &quot;shikinai oikomi,&quot; while those who attempted to escape from the island were given a death sentence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those who committed additional crimes while on the island were confined in mineshafts, a punishment known as &quot;shikinai oikomi,&quot; while those who attempted to escape from the island were given a death sentence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those who committed additional crimes while on the island were confined in mineshafts, a punishment known as &quot;shikinai oikomi,&quot; while those who attempted to escape from the island were given a death sentence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 竃馬(id:102733), Onething(id:65263), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>