<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>匁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Monme&quot; (A Weight Unit in The Japanese Traditional System of Weights And Measures)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Monme (A Weight Unit in The Japanese Traditional System of Weights And Measures)</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Monme (A Weight Unit in The Japanese Traditional System of Weights And Measures)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>匁（もんめ）とは、尺貫法における質量の単位である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Monme&quot; is a weight unit in the Japanese traditional system of weights and measures.</e>
<cmt>（注①）・・・「尺貫法」は、広義では東アジア一帯で用いられる度量衡の単位系、狭義では日本で独自に用いられる度量衡の単位系です。ここは「匁」が日本独特の単位であることもあり狭義のものと捉えています。（注②）・・・「匁」は真珠の質量単位としていまだに使われているところから現在形にしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Monme is a weight unit in the Japanese traditional system of weights and measures.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Monme is a weight unit in the Japanese traditional system of weights and measures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>1匁は明治24年（1891年）公布の度量衡法により3.75グラムと規定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Weights and Measures Act, promulgated in 1891, set the weight of 1 monme at 3.75 grams.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Weights and Measures Act, promulgated in 1891, set the weight of 1 monme at 3.75 grams.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Weights and Measures Act, promulgated in 1891, set the weight of 1 monme at 3.75 grams.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>この単位の公式の名称が「匁」になったのは明治時代のことで、それまでは銭と呼んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was only in the Meiji period that the name monme officially began to be used as the weight unit, and until then, &quot;sen&quot; had been used instead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was only in the Meiji period that the name monme officially began to be used as the weight unit, and until then, &quot;sen&quot; had been used instead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was only in the Meiji period that the name monme officially began to be used as the weight unit, and until then, &quot;sen&quot; had been used instead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>その名の通り、1文銭の重さに由来するものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the name itself suggests, sen came from the weight of 1 &quot;monsen&quot; (&apos;mon&apos; was a former Japanese currency unit, and &apos;sen&apos; means &apos;coin&apos;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the name itself suggests, sen came from the weight of 1 mon-sen (&apos;mon&apos; was a former Japanese currency unit, and &apos;sen&apos; means &apos;coin&apos;).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the name itself suggests, sen came from the weight of 1 mon-sen (&apos;mon&apos; was a former Japanese currency unit, and &apos;sen&apos; means &apos;coin&apos;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>北宋代以降の中国では、開元通宝（開通元寳との説もあり）と呼ばれる唐代の銭貨10枚の質量が24銖すなわち1両という基準でつくられ、1枚あたりの質量を「銭」と呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In China, a copper coin called &quot;Kai Yuan Tong Bao&quot; (or &apos;Kai Tong Yuan Bao&apos;) was minted for the first time in the age of the Tang dynasty, and from the age of Northern Sung dynasty, it began to be remade (at the weight of 24 &quot;shu&quot; [in pinyin, &apos;zhu&apos;], or 1 tael, for 10 coins), and the weight of one coin was 1 &quot;sen&quot; (in pinyin, &apos;qian&apos;).</e>
<cmt>（注）・・・「開元通宝」は元々中国の貨幣であり、しかもここでは中国国内でのその使用が話題にされているので、日本語読みを記述することにはあまり意味がないと思われます。それゆえピンイン（中国語読みのローマ字表記）を示しておきました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In China in and after Northern Sung Dynasty, a coin was minted in a manner that the weight of 10 coins of Tang dynasty called Kai Yuan Tong Bao (or Kai Tong Yuan Bao) equaled 24 zhu, that is to say, 1 ryo (tael), and a weight of the one coin was called &apos;sen&apos; (銭).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In China in and after Northern Sung Dynasty, a coin was minted in a manner that the weight of 10 coins of Tang dynasty called Kai Yuan Tong Bao (or Kai Tong Yuan Bao) equaled 24 zhu, that is to say, 1 ryo (tael), and a weight of the one coin was called &apos;sen&apos; (銭).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>従って1/10両＝1銭となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, a tenth tael was 1 sen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, a tenth ryo was 1 sen.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, a tenth ryo was 1 sen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>ただし大量生産される鋳造貨幣というものは質量を一定に製作することは困難で（最大2倍程度のばらつきはある）、質量の基準が開元通寳というわけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, mass-produced metallic currency was difficult to be equalized in weight - at worst, the disparity was as large as almost twice - so Kai Yuan Tong Bao could not be said the standard of the weight of currencies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, mass-produced metallic currency was difficult to be equalized in weight (at worst, the disparity was as large as almost twice) so Kai Yuan Tong Bao could not be said the standard of the weight of currencies.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, mass-produced metallic currency was difficult to be equalized in weight (at worst, the disparity was as large as almost twice) so Kai Yuan Tong Bao could not be said the standard of the weight of currencies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>この単位が日本に伝わり、日本では、一文 (通貨単位)銭の目方であることから「文目」（もんめ）とも呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When this unit sen was introduced into Japan, it was called &quot;monme,&quot; which was an abbreviation for &quot;&apos;mekata&apos; (weight) of 1 monsen.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When this unit sen was introduced into Japan, it was called &apos;monme,&apos; which was an abbreviation for mekata (weight) of 1 mon-sen.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When this unit sen was introduced into Japan, it was called &apos;monme,&apos; which was an abbreviation for mekata (weight) of 1 mon-sen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>「匁」という文字は銭と同音の「泉」の草書体、あるいは「文メ」を続けて書いたものに由来するとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Chinese character 匁 (reads as &quot;monme&quot;) is said to have originated from the cursive style writing of 泉 (reads as &quot;sen&quot; like 銭 used for the unit of a tenth tael), or from the Chinese character 文 (reads as &quot;mon&quot;) attached メ, which belongs to &quot;katakana&quot; (the square form of &apos;kana&apos; [Japanese syllabaries]) and reads as &quot;me.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Chinese character &apos;匁&apos; (monme) is said to have originated from the cursive style writing as &apos;泉,&apos; a homonymy of 銭, or from the Chinese character &apos;文&apos; (mon) attached &apos;メ&apos; (me), a character of katakana (the square form of kana [Japanese syllabaries]).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Chinese character &apos;匁&apos; (monme) is said to have originated from the cursive style writing as &apos;泉,&apos; a homonymy of 銭, or from the Chinese character &apos;文&apos; (mon) attached &apos;メ&apos; (me), a character of katakana (the square form of kana [Japanese syllabaries]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>江戸時代には秤量銀貨の実測値が通貨単位として使用され、元禄13年（1700年）に丁銀60匁は小判1両に相当すると公定されたが、実態は市場経済による変動相場であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period, the currency value of &quot;hyoryo ginka&quot; (the silver coin used as the currency by weight) depended on its weight, and in A.D. 1700, 60 monme of silver was officially equalized in value with 1 tael of &quot;koban&quot; (former Japanese gold coin of oval shape), but nevertheless, the currency conversion mechanism was basically the floating exchange rate system, left in the hands of market economy.</e>
<cmt>（注①）・・・「秤量（ひょうりょう）銀貨」の定訳は見つかりませんでしたが、「秤量貨幣」の研究社・大和英の訳（currency by weight)を参考に&quot;silver coin used as currency by weight&quot;としました。（注②）・・・「秤量銀貨の実測値が通貨単位として使用され」の意味ですが「秤量銀貨はその実測値によって貨幣価値が決まり」と解しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period, the currency value of Hyoryo ginka (the silver coin used as the currency by weight) depended on its weight, and in 1700, 60 monme of chogin (silver coin) was officially equalized in value with 1 ryo of koban (former Japanese gold coin of oval shape), however, it was actually floating rate by the market economy.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period, the currency value of Hyoryo ginka (the silver coin used as the currency by weight) depended on its weight, and in 1700, 60 monme of chogin (silver coin) was officially equalized in value with 1 ryo of koban (former Japanese gold coin of oval shape), however, it was actually floating rate by the market economy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>寛文5年（1665年）に度量衡の「衡」が統一され、両替商で用いられる分銅は後藤四郎兵衛家のみ製作が許され、これ以外のものの製作および使用は不正を防止するため厳禁とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1665, the Japanese weight units were standardized, and thereafter, Shirobei GOTO and his descendants monopolized the production right of &quot;fundo&quot; (counterweight) used at an exchange house, and the production and use of other kinds of fundo was prohibited strictly for the prevention of illegal exchange.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1665, the Japanese weight units were standardized, and thereafter, Shirobei GOTO and his descendants monopolized the right to produce counterweights used at an exchange house, and the production and use of other kinds of counterweights were prohibited strictly for the prevention of illegal exchange.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1665, the Japanese weight units were standardized, and thereafter, Shirobei GOTO and his descendants monopolized the right to produce counterweights used at an exchange house, and the production and use of other kinds of counterweights were prohibited strictly for the prevention of illegal exchange.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>この分銅は「両」を基本単位としており、「匁」は補助単位であるが、秤量銀貨の通貨単位は、小判の通貨単位の「両」との混同を避ける意味から「匁」および「貫」が用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The basic weight unit of the fundo was tael, and monme was just a secondly unit, but it was &quot;monme&quot; and &quot;kan&quot; that were adopted as the currency unit for hyoryo ginka, lest the term &quot;tael&quot; should be confused with the tael used as the currency unit of koban.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For these counterweights, &apos;ryo&apos; was used as a base unit and &apos;monme&apos; a secondly, while &apos;monme&apos; and &apos;kan&apos; were used for the currency unit for Hyoryo ginka, to avoid being mixed up with &apos;ryo,&apos; the currency unit for koban.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For these counterweights, &apos;ryo&apos; was used as a base unit and &apos;monme&apos; a secondly, while &apos;monme&apos; and &apos;kan&apos; were used for the currency unit for Hyoryo ginka, to avoid being mixed up with &apos;ryo,&apos; the currency unit for koban.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>すなわち、伍両（ごりょう）の分銅と釣合う丁銀は銀50匁と表した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And so, when &quot;chogin&quot; (the silver coin used as the currency by weight) was balanced with 5 tael of fundo, the chogin&apos;s currency value was depicted as 50 monme of silver.</e>
<cmt>（注①）・・・「伍両」は「五両」の当て字です。（注②）・・・「丁銀」とは「枰量銀貨として用いられた銀貨」のことです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is, chogin balanced with 5 ryo of the counterweights was said as 50 monme of silver.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That is, chogin balanced with 5 ryo of the counterweights was said as 50 monme of silver.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>このため質量の単位としては「匁」が普及した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That was why monme diffused as the weight unit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This made &apos;monme&apos; spread as a weight unit.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This made &apos;monme&apos; spread as a weight unit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>この当時の1匁は3.75グラムよりやや小さく3.74から3.75グラムの間である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, 1 monme was set around 3.74 - 3.75 grams.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, 1 monme was set between 3.74 to 3.75 grams, slightly lighter than 3.75.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。「3.75グラムよりやや小さく」を補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, 1 monme was set between 3.74 to 3.75 grams, slightly lighter than 3.75.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="16">
<j>明治に入り、銭 (曖昧さ回避)は円 (通貨) の1/100の日本の補助貨幣の単位として使用することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Meiji period, &apos;sen&apos; was ranked the secondary currency unit of a hundredth value of 1 yen in Japan.</e>
<cmt>（注）一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Meiji period, sen was ranked the secondary currency unit of a hundredth value of 1 yen in Japan.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Meiji period, sen was ranked the secondary currency unit of a hundredth value of 1 yen in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これに伴い、明治4年（1871年）の新貨条例では質量の単位には匁が公式に採用され（ただし、第二次大戦前までは銭も併用されていた）、匁は貫の1000分の1と規定され、1匁＝3.756521グラムと定められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Instead of sen, monme was officially adopted as the weight unit by the New Currency Act in A.D. 1871 - though sen was used in parallel until World War Ⅱ- and 1 monme was equalized with a thousandth kan, and the weight of 1 monme was set at 3.756521 grams.</e>
<cmt>（注）一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Instead, monme was officially adopted as the weight unit by the New Currency Act in 1871 (though sen was used in parallel before World War II) and 1 monme was equalized with a thousandth kan, and the weight of 1 monme was set at 3.756521 grams.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせ、表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Instead, monme was officially adopted as the weight unit by the New Currency Act in 1871 (though sen was used in parallel before World War II) and 1 monme was equalized with a thousandth kan, and the weight of 1 monme was set at 3.756521 grams.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>その後、単位換算の便宜を図るため明治24年の度量衡法により、1貫＝3.75キログラムと定められたので、1匁＝3.75グラムとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, for convenience in conversion among units, the Weights and Measures Act set 1 kan at 3.75 kilograms, so 1 monme became equal to 3.75 grams.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, for convenience in conversion among units, the Weights and Measures Act set 1 kan at 3.75 kilograms, so 1 monme became equal to 3.75 grams.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, for convenience in conversion among units, the Weights and Measures Act set 1 kan at 3.75 kilograms, so 1 monme became equal to 3.75 grams.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="19">
<j>また古くから交易のあった中国の単位と、日本国内のものとは密接な関係があったわけであるが、呉承洛の『中国度量衡史』による隋代の1銭は4.1762グラム、唐代の1銭は3.7301グラムである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And in China, whose weight units influenced Japanese counterparts through commerce from ancient times, 1 sen was set at 4.1762 grams in Sui dynasty China, and at 3.7301 grams in the Tang dynasty, says History of Chinese Weights and Measures, written by Wu Chengluo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And in China, whose weight units influenced Japanese counterparts through commerce from ancient times, 1 sen was set at 4.1762 grams in Sui dynasty, and at 3.7301 grams in the Tang dynasty, says &quot;History of Chinese Weights and Measures&quot; written by Wu Chengluo.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And in China, whose weight units influenced Japanese counterparts through commerce from ancient times, 1 sen was set at 4.1762 grams in Sui dynasty, and at 3.7301 grams in the Tang dynasty, says &quot;History of Chinese Weights and Measures&quot; written by Wu Chengluo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="20">
<j>1匁の1000倍が貫（かん）、10倍が両（りょう）、10分の1を分 (数)（ふん）、100分の1を厘（りん）、1000分の1を毛 (数)（もう）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1000 times 1 monme is 1 &quot;kan,&quot; and 10 times 1 monme is 1 tael, and a tenth of 1 monme is 1 &quot;fun,&quot; and a hundredth of 1 monme is 1 &quot;rin,&quot; and a thousandth of 1 monme is 1 &quot;mo.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1000 times 1 monme is 1 kan, and 10 times 1 monme is 1 ryo, and a tenth of 1 monme is 1 fun, and a hundredth of 1 monme is 1 rin, and a thousandth of 1 monme is 1 mo.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1000 times 1 monme is 1 kan, and 10 times 1 monme is 1 ryo, and a tenth of 1 monme is 1 fun, and a hundredth of 1 monme is 1 rin, and a thousandth of 1 monme is 1 mo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>ただし、分、厘、毛は正確に言えば割合（小数）を示すものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accurately, however, fun, rin, and mo are the units to show the proportion of decimal fractions to 1.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accurately, however, fun, rin, and mo are the units to show the proportion of decimal fractions to 1.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accurately, however, fun, rin, and mo are the units to show the proportion of decimal fractions to 1.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また「分」を「ぶ」と発音せず「ふん」と呼んだのは金貨の通貨単位である一分金（ぶ）との混同を避けるためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And here, a tenth of 1 monme is called 1 &quot;fun,&quot; not 1 &quot;bu,&quot; lest the term &quot;bu&quot; should be confused with the &quot;bu&quot; which was used as the currency unit of gold coins, such as &quot;ichibu-kin&quot; (a former Japanese gold coin of 1 bu).</e>
<cmt>（注）「金貨の通貨単位である一分金」の部分は「一分金のような金貨の通貨単位である分」の意味に解しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And here, it is called &apos;fun&apos; rather than &apos;bu&apos; to avoid mixing up with bu which was used as the currency unit of a gold coin, ichibu-kin (a former Japanese gold coin of 1 bu).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And here, it is called &apos;fun&apos; rather than &apos;bu&apos; to avoid mixing up with bu which was used as the currency unit of a gold coin, ichibu-kin (a former Japanese gold coin of 1 bu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="23">
<j>本来小数を表す漢数字は10分の1を分（ぶ）、100分の1を厘、1000分の1を毛（もう）で表すが、日本では1/10を表す歩合は「割」であり、これを基準にそれぞれ10分の1、100分の1とするため割合としての単位は100分の1が分、1000分の1が厘となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally in China, 1 &quot;bu&quot; (in piyin, &apos;fen&apos;) means a tenth of 1, and 1 &quot;rin&quot; (in pinyin, &apos;li&apos;) means a hundredth of 1, and 1 &quot;mo&quot; (in pinyin, &apos;mao&apos;) means a thousandth of 1, but in Japan, 1 &quot;wari&quot; means a tenth of 1, and 1 bu and 1 rin are set at a tenth and a hundredth of 1 wari, so 1 bu means a hundredth of 1, and 1 rin means a thousandth of 1, respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, for decimals in Chinese numeral, a tenth is represented as bu, a hundredth as ri, and a thousandth as mo, while a rate to represent a tenth is &apos;wari&apos; in Japan which is the base of the rate unit, and a hundredth becomes bu and a thousandth ri.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, for decimals in Chinese numeral, a tenth is represented as bu, a hundredth as ri, and a thousandth as mo, while a rate to represent a tenth is &apos;wari&apos; in Japan which is the base of the rate unit, and a hundredth becomes bu and a thousandth ri.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>これは「両」が本来の質量の基本単位であったためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was because the basic weight unit in Japan was tael.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was because the basic weight unit in Japan was &apos;ryo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was because the basic weight unit in Japan was &apos;ryo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="25">
<j>匁は貫とともに真珠の質量の単位として国際的に使われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monme, along with kan, is still used as an international weight unit for a pearl.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Monme, along with kan, is still used as an international weight unit for a pearl.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Monme, along with kan, is still used as an international weight unit for a pearl.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>これは真珠が日本の特産品であったことによるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is because a pearl was a Japanese specialty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because a pearl was a Japanese specialty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because a pearl was a Japanese specialty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>この場合はmommeと綴られ、momという記号が使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For a pearl, monme is written as &quot;momme&quot; (in abbreviation, mom).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For a pearl, monme is written as momme and symbolized as mom.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For a pearl, monme is written as momme and symbolized as mom.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>日本の計量法では、尺貫法の単位はほぼ全廃されているが、匁だけは真珠の質量の計量に限定して使用して良い単位となっている（ただし表記は平仮名の「もんめ」である）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese Measurement Act prohibits almost all units used under the traditional system of weights and measures, but it allows monme (written in &quot;hiragana&quot; [the cursive form of kana]) to be used - merely for weighing a pearl, though.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese Measurement Act has abolished almost all units used under the traditional system of weights and measures, but it allows monme (written in &apos;もんめ&apos; in hiragana [the cursive form of kana, the Japanese syllabary]) to be used merely for weighing a pearl.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese Measurement Act has abolished almost all units used under the traditional system of weights and measures, but it allows monme (written in &apos;もんめ&apos; in hiragana [the cursive form of kana, the Japanese syllabary]) to be used merely for weighing a pearl.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="29">
<j>また、日本の五円硬貨の質量は3.75gで、ちょうど1匁である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese 5 yen coin has the weight of 3.75 grams, or 1 monme.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese 5 yen coin has the weight of 3.75 grams, or 1 monme.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese 5 yen coin has the weight of 3.75 grams, or 1 monme.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="30">
<j>なお、匁で表した値の1の位が0である場合には、匁の代わりに「目」（め）と書くことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, when the units digit is zero, &quot;monme&quot; is occasionally replaced with &quot;me.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, when the unit&apos;s digit is zero, monme (匁) is occasionally replaced with &apos;me&apos; (目).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, when the unit&apos;s digit is zero, monme (匁) is occasionally replaced with &apos;me&apos; (目).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>例えば30匁は三十目、300匁は三百目とも書く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, 30 monme can be replaced with 30 me, and 300 monme can be replaced with 300 me.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, 30 monme can be replaced with 30 me, and 300 monme with 300 me.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, 30 monme can be replaced with 30 me, and 300 monme with 300 me.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>ただし、この「十目」「百目」は単位というわけではないので、例えば232匁を二百目三十二匁などとは書かない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, me is not a weight unit, so, for example, 232 monme cannot be depicted as 200 me plus 32 monme.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the me used as &apos;10 me,&apos; &apos;100 me&apos; and others is not a weight unit, so, for example, 232 monme cannot be written as 200 me plus 32 monme.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the me used as &apos;10 me,&apos; &apos;100 me&apos; and others is not a weight unit, so, for example, 232 monme cannot be written as 200 me plus 32 monme.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>0以外の場合は必ず匁と書く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the units digit is not zero, weight should always be depicted with monme.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the unit&apos;s digit is not zero, weight should always be written with monme.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the unit&apos;s digit is not zero, weight should always be written with monme.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>すなわち、17匁を17目のようにはしない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, 17 monme canot be depicted as 17 me.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, 17 monme cannot be written as 17 me.</e>
<cmt>スペル、表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, 17 monme cannot be written as 17 me.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="35">
<j>中国では現在でも「銭」が質量の単位となっており、メートル法採用後、1銭＝5グラムと規定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In China, sen serves as the weight unit even today, and after the metric system was adopted, 1 sen was set at 5 grams.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In China, &apos;sen&apos; serves as the weight unit even today, and after the metric system was adopted, 1 sen was set at 5 grams.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In China, &apos;sen&apos; serves as the weight unit even today, and after the metric system was adopted, 1 sen was set at 5 grams.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>10倍が両、10分の1が分であるのは日本と同じである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ten times 1 sen is 1 tael, and a tenth of 1 sen is 1 bu, which are both the same as Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">10 times 1 sen is 1 ryo, and a tenth of 1 sen is 1 bu, which are both the same as Japan.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">10 times 1 sen is 1 ryo, and a tenth of 1 sen is 1 bu, which are both the same as Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>（市制 (単位系)も参照）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">cf. the section of Chinese Traditional System of Measurement</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Also refer to the article of Chinese Traditional System of Measurement)</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Also refer to the article of Chinese Traditional System of Measurement)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 DumZiBoT(id:230315), As6022014(id:214263), Rusk(id:9895), Raad(id:4918), Peehyoro Acala(id:170), Nnh(id:474), Michey.M(id:906), Πrate(id:11329), Shimoxx(id:9332), 伏儀(id:142093), LaaknorBot(id:220851), Lucas0123(id:130266), 小太刀(id:18154), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>