<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>為房卿記</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tamefusa-kyo Ki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tamefusa-kyo Ki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tamefusa-kyo Ki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>為房卿記（ためふさきょうき）は、後三条・白河・堀河・鳥羽天皇に蔵人・蔵人頭として仕え、大蔵卿・参議として活躍した藤原為房の日記で、「大記」「大御記」「大府記」とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tamefusa-kyo Ki is a diary which is also called &apos;Daiki&apos; &apos;Daigyoki&apos; &apos;Daifuki&apos; written by FUJIWARA no Tamefusa who served the Emperors Gosanjo, Shirakawa, Horikawa and Toba as Kurodo and Kurodonoto (an government official of the imperial household institution) and played an active part as the Secretary of the Ministry of Finance and the government adviser.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tamefusa-kyo Ki, also called &apos;Daiki&apos;, &apos;Daigyoki&apos; and &apos;Daifuki&apos;, is a diary written by FUJIWARA no Tamefusa. Tamefusa served as Kurodo and Kurodo no to (a government official in the imperial household) and was active as the Secretary of the Ministry of Finance and a government advisor for Emperors Gosanjo, Shirakawa, Horikawa and Toba.</e>
<cmt>split into two sentences for easier reading; moved Emperors to the the end of the second sentence; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tamefusa-kyo Ki, also called &apos;Daiki,&apos; &apos;Daigyoki&apos; and &apos;Daifuki,&apos; is a diary written by FUJIWARA no Tamefusa, who served as Kurodo (chamberlain) and Kurodo no to (head chamberlain) and was active as Okura-kyo (Minister of the Treasury) and Sangi (councilor) for Emperors Gosanjo, Shirakawa, Horikawa and Toba.</e>
<cmt>役職名を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>延久2年（1070年）から永久 (元号)2年（1114年）までの記録があるが、治暦年間（1065年-1068年）頃から記していたとも言われるが、京都大学文学部所蔵の自筆1巻を残し、ほとんどが散逸する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The records from 1070 to 1114 have remained, but it was likely to be started to write in a period between 1065and 1068 and most of them were scattered and lost except the autograph book, volume one at Faculty of Letters of Kyoto University.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there are records from the diary from the year 1070 to 1114, it is likely that Tamefusa began writing it between 1065 and 1068. Most of it has been scattered and lost except for volume one of the autograph book which is kept at the Faculty of Letters in Kyoto University.</e>
<cmt>split into two sentences for easier reading; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there are records from the diary from the year 1070 to 1114, it is likely that Tamefusa began writing it between 1065 and 1068; most of it has been scattered and lost except for volume one of his own writing, which is kept at the Faculty of Letters in Kyoto University.</e>
<cmt>自筆→own writing としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>ただ、鎌倉期の古写本が京都大学や陽明文庫・宮内庁書陵部などに残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However the old manuscript copies in the Kamakura period were still in Kyoto University, Yomei Library, Archives and Mausolea Department of Imperial Household Agency etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only the old manuscript copies from the Kamakura period are still kept at Kyoto University, the Yomei Library and Archives and Mausolea Department of the Imperial Household Agency.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;However&quot; to &quot;Only&quot; for &quot;ただ&quot;; eliminated &quot;etc&quot; since it did not feel natural to have it here</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only the old manuscript copies from the Kamakura period are still kept at Kyoto University, the Yomei Library and Archives and Mausolea Department of the Imperial Household Agency.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>院政政治についての内容が現存しているが、一年分を完備した年はなく断続的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are existing descriptions about the governments ruled by retired emperors, but any year&apos;s description remained intermittently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Still existing are descriptions of the governments ruled by retired emperors, but descriptions on the years are intermittent.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;remained&quot; to &quot;are&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Still existing are descriptions of the governments ruled by retired emperors, but descriptions that cover events of a whole year do not exist, and are intermittent.</e>
<cmt>一年分　の表現を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また、永保元年（1081年）秋の熊野詣の記事は特に「為房卿熊野参詣日記」として取り上げられることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The description about the visit of Kumano-jinja Shrine in fall, 1081 is sometimes featured as &apos;Tamefusa-kyo Kumano Sankei Nikki (Kumano Visit Diary of Lord Tamefusa&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A description about a visit Tamefusa made to the Kumano-jinja Shrine in the fall of 1081 is sometimes featured as &apos;Tamefusa-kyo Kumano Sankei Nikki&apos; (Kumano Temple Visit Diary of Lord Tamefusa).</e>
<cmt>added &quot;Temple&quot; in &quot;Kumano Temple Visit Diary of Lord Tamefusa&quot; for better clarity on the meaning of &quot;参詣&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A description about a visit Tamefusa made to the Kumano-jinja Shrine in the fall of 1081 is sometimes featured as &apos;Tamefusa-kyo Kumano Sankei Nikki&apos; (Kumano Temple Visit Diary of Lord Tamefusa).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>当時の政治や社会状況を知る上では重要な歴史資料。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is very important historical material to know the politics and social circumstances at the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The diary is important historical material in understanding the politics and social circumstances of the time it was written.</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;very&quot;; changed &quot;to know&quot; to &quot;understanding&quot;; changed &quot;at the time&quot; to &quot;of the time it was written&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The diary is important historical material in understanding the politics and social circumstances of the time it was written.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>刊本としては、部分的ではあるが、『大日本史料』第3編や『歴代残闕日記』第7冊、『翻刻為房卿記』（『史聚』第10号）に掲載。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is partially included in printed and published books such as the 3rd volume of &quot;Dai Nihon Shiryo (Large Historical Records)&quot; and the 7the volume of &quot;Rekidai Zanketsu Nikki (Successive Partial Diary) and &quot;Honkoku (Reprint) Tamefusa-kyo Ki&quot; (the 10th volume of &quot;Shishu (Historical Stories)&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Parts of the diary are included in printed and published books, such as the third volume of the &quot;Dai Nihon Shiryo&quot; (Important Historical Records), the seventh volume of the &quot;Rekidai Zanketsu Nikki&quot; (Successive Partial Diary) and the reprint &quot;Honkoku Tamefusa-kyo Ki&quot; (the tenth volume of &quot;Shishu&quot; (Historical Stories)).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;3rd&quot; to &quot;third&quot;; changed &quot;7the&quot; to &quot;seventh&quot;; changed &quot;10th&quot; to &quot;tenth&quot;; changed &quot;Large Historical Records&quot; to &quot;Important Historical Records&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Parts of the diary are included in printed and published books, such as the third volume of the &quot;Dai Nihon Shiryo&quot; (Important Historical Records), the seventh volume of the &quot;Rekidai Zanketsu Nikki&quot; (Successive Partial Diary) and the reprint &quot;Honkoku Tamefusa-kyo Ki&quot; (the tenth volume of &quot;Shishu&quot; [Historical Stories]).</e>
<cmt>括弧内の括弧を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Ktmchi(id:113301), Volfgang(id:98768), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>