<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>政事要略</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seiji yoryaku (examples of the politics in the Heian period)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seiji yoryaku (examples of political events in the Heian period)</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seiji yoryaku</e>
<cmt>タイトルなので補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>政事要略（せいじようりゃく）は、平安時代の政務運営に関する事例を掲げた書。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seiji yoryaku is a written document which carries examples of the governmental management in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seiji yoryaku is a written document which gives examples of the governmental management in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seiji yoryaku is a written document which gives examples of the governmental management in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>編者は明法博士惟宗允亮。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was edited by KOREMUNE no Tadasuke, a Myobo hakase (Professor of Law)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was edited by KOREMUNE no Tadasuke, a Myobo hakase (Professor of Law)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was edited by KOREMUNE no Tadasuke, a Myobo hakase (Professor of Law).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>惟宗氏は代々明法家の名門で、彼の曽祖父は、『律集解』『令集解』を編んだ惟宗直本、祖父は『本朝月令』を編纂した惟宗公方。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Koremune clan was successively a good family of scholars of law; his grand-grandfather was KOREMUNE no Naomoto who edited &quot;Ritsu-no-shuge&quot; (a written document on the criminal code) and &quot;Ryo-no-shuge&quot; (a written document on the civil code) and his grandfather was KOREMUNE no Kinkata who compiled &quot;Honcho Gatsuryo&quot;</e>
<cmt>http://www.rinsen.com/linkbooks/ISBN4-653-03801-5.htm, http://d.hatena.ne.jp/keyword/%CE%A7%CE%E1</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Koremune clan was a family that produced good scholars of law; his grand-grandfather was KOREMUNE no Naomoto, who edited &quot;Ritsu-no-shuge&quot; (a written document on the criminal code) and &quot;Ryo-no-shuge&quot; (a written document on the civil code), and his grandfather was KOREMUNE no Kinkata, who compiled &quot;Honcho Gatsuryo&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Koremune clan was a family that produced good scholars of law; his grand-grandfather was KOREMUNE no Naomoto, who edited &quot;Ritsu-no-shuge&quot; (a written document on the criminal code) and &quot;Ryo-no-shuge&quot; (a written document on the civil code), and his grandfather was KOREMUNE no Kinkata, who compiled &quot;Honcho Gatsuryo&quot; (also known as Honcho Gatsuryo, a book about the knowledge of court rules, ceremony, documents in the mid Heian period).</e>
<cmt>半角カッコにし、用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>本書は、惟宗氏の明法家としての活動の集大成といえる書で、平安時代の政治を理解するうえでの重要な史料である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The document can be said to be a great collection of Koremune family&apos;s activities as scholars of law and is an important historical material for understanding politics in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The document can be said to be a great collection of the Koremune family&apos;s activities as scholars of law and is an important historical material for understanding politics in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The document can be said to be a great collection of the Koremune clan&apos;s activities as scholars of law and is an important historical material for understanding politics in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>用語を変え、半角クォーテーションにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>なお、「令宗」（よしむね）の姓は、惟宗氏全員の改姓ではなく、長保元年（999年）頃、允亮と彼の弟と思われる惟宗允正のみに与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way, the surname &apos;Yoshimune&apos; was not another name for all members of the Koremune clan, but was granted around 999 only to Tadasuke and KOREMUNE no Tadamasa who is considered to be Tadasuke&apos;s younger brother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the way, the surname &apos;Yoshimune&apos; was not another name for all members of the Koremune clan, but was granted around 999 only to Tadasuke and KOREMUNE no Tadamasa, who is thought to be Tadasuke&apos;s younger brother.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the way, the surname &apos;Yoshimune&apos; was not another name for all members of the Koremune clan, but was granted around 999 only to Tadasuke and KOREMUNE no Tadamasa, who is thought to be Tadasuke&apos;s younger brother.</e>
<cmt>半角クォーテーションにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>「令宗」は「律令の宗師」という意味である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimune&apos; means &apos;the origin of the Ritsuryo codes&apos;.</e>
<cmt>「大宗師」については「根源」という説明がありましたので、「宗師」をoriginと訳しました。http://www.cam.hi-ho.ne.jp/h_sakamoto/thought/soshi.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimune&apos; means &apos;the origin of the Ritsuryo codes.&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimune&apos; means &apos;the respective authority of the Ritsuryo codes.&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語を変え、半角クォーテーションにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>本書の成立年代は詳らかではないが、本書のなかに一条天皇を「今上」と記していることから一条天皇の朝に行われたと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is not well known when this book was compiled, but judging from the fact that the Emperor Ichijo was referred to as &quot;the present emperor&quot; in the text, it is considered to be edited during the Emperor Ichijo&apos;s reign.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処 「朝に行われ、」となっていますが、文の続き方がわかりにくいので、「行われたと考えられる。」とし、２文にしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not well known when this book was compiled, but judging from the fact that the Emperor Ichijo was referred to as &quot;the present emperor&quot; in the text, it is considered to have been edited during the Emperor Ichijo&apos;s reign.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not well known when this book was compiled, but judging from the fact that the Emperor Ichijo was referred to as &quot;the present emperor&quot; in the text, it is considered to be edited during the Emperor Ichijo&apos;s reign.</e>
<cmt>半角クォーテーションにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>長保4年（1002年）11月に編纂が完了したが、允亮の歿年と考えられる寛弘5年（1008年）頃まで追記がなされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The compilation was finished in November, 1002, and followed by occasional addition until nearly 1008, which is thought to be the year of Tadasuke&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The compilation was finished in November, 1002, and was followed by occasional addition until nearly 1008, which is thought to be the year of Tadasuke&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;was&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The compilation was finished in December, 1002, and was followed by occasional addition until nearly 1008, which is thought to be the year of Tadasuke&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦にし、半角クォーテーションにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また、本書の編纂は、小野宮右大臣藤原実資の依嘱によってなされたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also it is said that the compilation of the book was conducted by a request from FUJIWARA no Sanesuke, Ononomiya Minister of the Right.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, it is said that the compilation of the book was conducted in response to a request from FUJIWARA no Sanesuke, Ononomiya Minister of the Right.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, it is said that the compilation of the book was conducted in response to a request from FUJIWARA no Sanesuke of Ononomiya lineage, Minister of the Right.</e>
<cmt>一部補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その根拠は、『小記目録』（『小右記』の目録）に「長保四年十一月五日、世事要略部類畢んぬ事」と記されていることや、本書が代々小野宮家に相伝されていたこと等である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ground lies in the fact that there is a description in the contents of &quot;Shoyuki&quot; (the diary of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke) that &apos;November 5, 1002, I have finished a category of seji yoryaku (examples of social affairs)&apos; and that the book was handed down to the Ononomiya family from generation to generation, and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ground lies in a description in the contents of &quot;Shoyuki&quot; (the diary of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke) that reads: &apos;November 5, 1002, I have finished a category of seji yoryaku (examples of social affairs),&apos; in the book having been handed down to the Ononomiya family from generation to generation, and so on.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ground lies in a description in &quot;Shoyu mokuroku&quot; (the contents of &quot;Shoyuki&quot; [The Diary of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke]) that reads: &apos;December 17, 1002, I have finished a category of seji yoryaku (examples of social affairs),&apos; in the book having been handed down to the Ononomiya family from generation to generation, and so on.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦にし、半角クォーテーションにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>巻数について、『中右記』『本朝書籍目録』等で、全130巻あったことが分かるが、現存するのはそのうちの26巻である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the number of volumes, it is evident from &quot;Chuyuki&quot; (the diary written by FUJIWARA no Munetada), &quot;Honchoshojaku mokuroku&quot; (the oldest list of Japanese books in existence written in the Kamakura period) and others that there were 130 volumes in total, of which 26 still exist now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the number of volumes, it is evident from &quot;Chuyuki&quot; (the diary written by FUJIWARA no Munetada), &quot;Honchoshojaku mokuroku&quot; (the oldest list of Japanese books in existence written in the Kamakura period) and others that there were 130 volumes in total, of which 26 still exist now.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the number of volumes, it is evident from &quot;Chuyuki&quot; (The Diary of FUJIWARA no Munetada), &quot;Honchoshojaku mokuroku&quot; (the oldest list of Japanese books in existence written in the Kamakura period) and others that there were 130 volumes in total, of which 26 still exist now.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせ、半角クォーテーションにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>全130巻の部立てはおそらく、次の通りであったと推定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Categorization of all the 130 volumes are assumed to have been possibly as follows:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Categorization of all 130 volumes is assumed to possibly have been as follows:</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Categorization of all 130 volumes is assumed to possibly have been as follows:</e>
<cmt>原文をまとめ、表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>年中行事（全30巻）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Annual events (30 volumes in total)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Annual events (30 volumes in total)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Annual events (30 volumes in total)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>公務要事（5巻程度）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Public service duties (approximately 5 volumes)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Public service duties (approximately 5 volumes)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Public service duties (approximately 5 volumes)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>交替雑事（20巻）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kotai zatsuji (miscellaneous matters about administrative transitions) (20 volumes)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kotai zatsuji (miscellaneous matters about administrative transitions) (20 volumes)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kotai zatsuji (miscellaneous matters about administrative transitions) (20 volumes)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>糺弾雑事（30巻程度）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyudan zatsuji (miscellaneous matters about impeachment) (approximately 30 volumes)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyudan zatsuji (miscellaneous matters about impeachment) (approximately 30 volumes)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyudan zatsuji (miscellaneous matters about impeachment) (approximately 30 volumes)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>至要雑事（5～10巻）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shiyo zatsuji (miscellaneous matters about essentials) (5-10 volumes)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shiyo zatsuji (miscellaneous matters about essentials) (5-10 volumes)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shiyo zatsuji (miscellaneous matters about essentials) (5 to 10 volumes)</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>国郡雑事（巻数不明）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokugun zatsuji (miscellaneous matters about administrative divisions) (the number is unknown)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokugun zatsuji (miscellaneous matters about administrative divisions) (the number is unknown)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokugun zatsuji (miscellaneous matters about administrative divisions) (the number is unknown)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>臨時雑事（巻数不明）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rinji zatsuji (miscellaneous matters about extra events) (the number is unknown)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rinji zatsuji (miscellaneous matters about extra events) (the number is unknown)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rinji zatsuji (miscellaneous matters about extra events) (the number is unknown)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="20">
<j>このように、本書は政務に関するあらゆる事例を掲げたもので、それぞれに関係する律令格式の条文や国史・日記の記事、その他和漢の典籍を正確に引用し、彼自身や父祖先輩の勘文・勘答も収録している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus it carries every example of governmental affairs, accurately quotes related articles on laws of codes and ethics (conduct), and related reports from the national history and diaries, in addition to Chinese and Japanese classical books, and also includes not only his own kanmon (written reports for what the imperial court requested) and kanto (written response) but also those of his ancestors and older lawyers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, it carries every example of governmental affairs, accurately quotes related articles on laws of codes and ethics (conduct), and related reports from the national history and diaries, in addition to Chinese and Japanese classical books, and also includes not only his own kanmon (written reports for what the imperial court requested) and kanto (written response), but also those of his ancestors and older lawyers.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, it carries every example of governmental affairs, accurately quotes related articles on laws of codes and ethics (conduct), and related reports from the national history and diaries, in addition to Chinese and Japanese classical books, and also includes not only his own kanmon (written reports for what the imperial court requested) and kanto (written response), but also those of his ancestors and older lawyers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>よって、本書によって知られる官符や典籍もあり、それの逸文も多く含まれているので、その史料的価値は高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, since it has made known some kanpu (official documents from Dajokan, or Great Council of State) and books, and also includes many surviving fragments of these documents, the value of the historical material of the book is high.</e>
<cmt>「よって」は文脈から「その上」として訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, since it has made known some kanpu (official documents from Dajokan, or Great Council of State) and books, and also includes many surviving fragments of these documents, the historical material of the book has high historical value.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, since it has made known some kanpu (official documents from Dajokan [Great Council of State]) and books, and also includes many surviving fragments of these documents, the historical material of the book has high historical value.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また、国史の記事の引用について、祖父公方が編纂した『本朝月令』が、直接『日本書紀』以下の六国史から引用しているのに対し、本書は、六国史からの引用と、菅原道真が編纂した『類聚国史』からの引用も見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And as for quotation of articles of the national history, while &quot;Honcho Gatsuryo&quot; compiled by Kinkata, Tadasuke&apos;s grandfather, uses direct quotations from &quot;Rikkokushi&quot; (Japan&apos;s six national histories chronicling the seventh and eighth centuries) such as &quot;The Nihon Shoki (the Chronicle of Japan), the Seiji yoryaku includes some quotations not only from &quot;Rikkokushi&quot; but also from &quot;Ruiju-kokushi&quot; (History book) compiled by SUGAWARA no Michizane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for quotation of articles of the national history, while &quot;Honcho Gatsuryo&quot; compiled by Kinkata, Tadasuke&apos;s grandfather, uses direct quotations from &quot;Rikkokushi&quot; (Japan&apos;s six national histories chronicling the seventh and eighth centuries) such as &quot;The Nihon Shoki (the Chronicle of Japan), the Seiji yoryaku includes not only some quotations from &quot;Rikkokushi&quot; but also some from &quot;Ruiju-kokushi&quot; (History book) compiled by SUGAWARA no Michizane.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for quotation of articles of the national history, while &quot;Honcho Gatsuryo&quot; compiled by Kinkata, Tadasuke&apos;s grandfather, uses direct quotations from &quot;Rikkokushi&quot; (Japan&apos;s six national histories chronicling the seventh and eighth centuries) such as &quot;The Nihon Shoki&quot; (the Chronicle of Japan), the Seiji yoryaku includes not only some quotations from Rikkokushi (the Six National Histories) but also some from &quot;Ruiju-kokushi&quot; (Classified National History) compiled by SUGAWARA no Michizane.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="23">
<j>本書は小野宮(藤原実資)家相伝の書であったため広く流布しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The book was not widely spread because it was a document handed down to the Ononomiya (FUJIWARA no Sanesuke) family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The book was not widely spread, as it was a document handed down to the Ononomiya (FUJIWARA no Sanesuke) family.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The book was not widely spread, as it was a document handed down to the Ononomiya (FUJIWARA no Sanesuke) family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>が、皇學館大學教授の清水潔によれば藤原通俊や大江匡房という知識人はその存在を知り才を磨く参考にしていたという、また一条兼良も有職故実の研究に活用したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, according to Kiyoshi SHIMIZU, a professor of Kogakkan University, some intellectuals such as FUJIWARA no Michitoshi and OE no Masafusa referred to it to develop their talent, finding its existence, and Kaneyoshi ICHIJO also utilized it for research of Yusoku kojitsu (court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquette).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, according to Kiyoshi SHIMIZU, a professor of Kogakkan University, some intellectuals such as FUJIWARA no Michitoshi and OE no Masafusa referred to it in order to develop their talents, finding its existence, and Kaneyoshi ICHIJO also utilized it for research of Yusoku kojitsu (court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquette).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, according to Kiyoshi SHIMIZU, a professor of Kogakkan University, some intellectuals such as FUJIWARA no Michitoshi and OE no Masafusa referred to it in order to develop their talents, finding its existence, and Kaneyoshi ICHIJO also utilized it for research of Yusoku kojitsu (court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquette).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>しかし応仁の乱によりその過半が失われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unfortunately the greater part of it was lost due to the Onin War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unfortunately the greater part of it was lost due to the Onin War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unfortunately the greater part of it was lost due to the Onin War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>近世に入り、中原章純が、天明6年（1786年）に本書の残闕本を各所より収集して、ほぼ現在の形まで編輯した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the early-modern times, Shojun NAKAHARA collected incomplete parts of the book from various places in 1786 and reedited it into the nearly present format.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the early-modern times, Shojun NAKAHARA collected incomplete parts of the book from various places in 1786 and reedited it into the nearly present format.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the early-modern times, Shojun NAKAHARA collected incomplete parts of the book from various places in 1786 and reedited it into the nearly present format.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>以来約200年を経過した今日でもそれ以上の残闕本資料が出ていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even today when two hundred years have passed since then, no more incomplete parts have newly found.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even today, with two hundred years having passed since then, no more incomplete parts have newly found.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even today, with 200 years having passed since then, no more incomplete parts have newly found.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>現在、本書のテクストとして広く新訂増補国史大系本が用いられるが、これは、中原章純本の系統を踏む福田文庫本を底本として用いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Now a newly revised and enlarged edition of the Anthology of Japanese History has been widely used as a text of the book but it uses as the original text a book of Fukuda library which traces back to the system of Shojun NAKAHARA&apos;s book.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Now a newly revised and enlarged edition of the Anthology of Japanese History has been widely used as a text of the book, but it uses as the original text a book of Fukuda library, which traces back to the system of Shojun NAKAHARA&apos;s book.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Now a newly revised and enlarged edition of the Anthology of Japanese History has been widely used as a text of the book, but it uses as the original text a book of Fukuda library, which traces back to the system of Shojun NAKAHARA&apos;s book.</e>
<cmt>半角クォーテーションにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Straysheep(id:42448), Papamaruchan22(id:71152), 蘇民(id:87832), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>