<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>川浚冥加金</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kawazarae Myogakin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kawazarae Myogakin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kawazarae Myogakin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>川浚冥加金（かわざらえみょうがきん）は、江戸時代、大坂で川浚えのために課された冥加金である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kawazarae Myogakin is votive offering tax imposed by the government of the Ed period for dredging in Osaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kawazarae Myogakin is votive offering tax imposed by the government for dredging rivers in Osaka in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>語順の変更を行いました。江戸がEdになっていたのでEdoに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kawazarae Myogakin is votive offering tax imposed by the government for dredging rivers in Osaka in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>大坂ではその市内を縦横に走る川が交通手段その他の点で重要であったから、その維持管理である川浚え（浚渫）もまた重要であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Osaka rivers that flow in all directions in the city were important as the means of transportation and other uses; accordingly dredging, which was a way of controlling and maintaining rivers, was also important.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Osaka, crisscrossing rivers in the city were important as the means of transportation and other uses; accordingly, dredging, which was a way of controlling and maintaining rivers, was also important.</e>
<cmt>カンマの追加、「市内を縦横に走る川」の訳の変更を行いました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Osaka, crisscrossing rivers in the city were important as the means of transportation and other uses; accordingly, dredging, which was a way of controlling and maintaining rivers, was also important.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>川浚えは、大川浚（淀川）、内川浚（淀川の諸分流）および両川口浚（安治川河口、木津川 (大阪府)河口）の3つに分かれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dredging was divided into three; these three were dredging of the Yodo-gawa River, various branch rivers of the Yodo-gawa River, and the two estuaries of the Yodo-gawa River consisting of the Aji-gawa River and the Kizu-gawa River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dredging was classified into three: Okawazarae (dredging of the Yodo-gawa River), uchikawazarae (dredging of branches of the Yodo-gawa River), and ryokawaguchizarae (dredging of the Aji-gawa River and the Kizu-gawa River).</e>
<cmt>divideをclassifyに修正、セミコロンをコロンに修正、3種類のそれぞれの川浚の名称が書かれていなかったので追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dredging was classified into three: Okawazarae (dredging of the Yodo-gawa River), uchikawazarae (dredging of branches of the Yodo-gawa River), and ryokawaguchizarae (dredging of the Aji-gawa River and the Kizu-gawa River).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>川浚え費用は、1772年（安永 (元号)元年）には、(1)家質差配所の冥加金910両（銀換算で54貫600目）、(2)十川築地代銀貸付利銀80貫596匁8分、(3)堀江上荷船船床銀64貫200匁、その内2貫目は船床銀の徴収料になるから62貫200目。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1772, the expense of dredging came for the following three sources: (1) The license tax received from Kajichi Sahaisho: 910-ryo (in gin 54-kan 600 monme), (2) Togawa Tsuijidai-gin Kashitsuke Rigin (interest from the sales of the reclaimed land of Togawa) 80-kan 596-monme 8-bu, (3) Horie Uenibune (freighters) Funadoko-gin 64-kan 200 monme; out of 64-kan 200 monme, 2-kan is collection fee of Funadoko-gin; therefore, the net is 62 kan 200 monme.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1772, the expense of dredging came from the following three sources: (1) The license tax received from Kajichi Sahaisho: 910-ryo (in silver 54 kan [unit of volume, approx. 3.75 kg] and 600 monme [unit of volume, approx. 3.75 g]), (2) Togawa Tsuijidai-gin Kashitsuke Rigin (interest from the sales of the reclaimed land of Togawa) 80-kan 596-monme and 8-bu (unit of volume, approx. 0.375 g) in silver, (3) Horie Uenibune (freighters) Funadoko-gin 64-kan and 200 monme in silver, but 2 kan out of 64 kan and 200 monme, was Funadoko-gin (boat registration fee), so the net was 62 kan and 200 monme.</e>
<cmt>単位の説明や用語の説明の追加、前置詞の修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1772, the expense of dredging came from the following three sources: (1) The license tax received from Kajichi Sahaisho: 910-ryo (in silver 54 kan [unit of volume, approx. 3.75 kg] and 600 monme [unit of volume, approx. 3.75 g]), (2) Togawa Tsuijidai-gin Kashitsuke Rigin (interest from the sales of the reclaimed land of Togawa) 80-kan 596-monme and 8-bu (unit of volume, approx. 0.375 g) in silver, (3) Horie Uenibune (freighters) Funadoko-gin 64-kan and 200 monme in silver, but 2 kan out of 64 kan and 200 monme, was Funadoko-gin (boat registration fee), so the net was 62 kan and 200 monme.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>以上の合計197貫396匁8分が1年間の費用であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The total of the three sources 197-kan 396 monme was the annual expense for dredging.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The total of the three sources, 197 kan and 396 monme, was the annual expense for dredging.</e>
<cmt>andの追加、カンマの追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The total of the three sources, 197 kan and 396 monme, was the annual expense for dredging.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>船床銀とは1698年（元禄11年）堀江新地発展のために上荷船500艘を許したことに対する冥加金であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Funadoko-gin is the tax imposed for permission of 500 uwanibune (freighters) to develop Horie Shinchi in 1698; Togawa Tsuijidai-gin is interest to be paid annually; in 1767, land reclamation was executed to the following rivers: Sonezaki-gawa River, Kyomachi Hori-kawa River, Tateurihori-kawa River, Awahori-kawa River, Toyokohori-kawa River, Kaifuhori-kawa River, Satsumahori-kawa River, Nakanoshima Uenohana in Osaka, Edo Hori-kawa Shitanohana, Enokojima Shitanohana; reclaimed land from these rivers were sold respectively and the payment received was loaned; interest is from this loan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Funadoko-gin was a tax imposed for 500 uwanibune (freighters) which were newly permitted in order to develop the area called Horie Shinchi in 1698.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処としました。全体的に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Funadoko-gin was a tax imposed for 500 uwanibune (freighters) which were newly permitted in order to develop the area called Horie Shinchi in 1698.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>十川築地代銀とは1767年（明和4年）曽根崎川、京町堀川、立売堀川、阿波堀川、東横堀川、海部堀川、薩摩堀川、中之島 (大阪府)上ノ鼻、江戸堀川下ノ鼻、江ノ子島下ノ鼻その他それぞれあらたに築地をおこなった築地の売り払い代銀を貸し付け、年ごとに納める利銀である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Togawa Tsuijidai-gin was interest which should be paid annually, and that interest was from a loan of money which was made by selling reclaimed lands along the Sonezaki-gawa River, the Kyomachi Hori-kawa River, the Tateurihori-kawa River, the Awahori-kawa River, the Toyokohori-kawa River, the Kaifuhori-kawa River, the Satsumahori-kawa River, the Nakanoshima Uenohana, the Edo Hori-kawa Shitanohana, and the Enokojima Shitanohana in 1767.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処としました。全体的に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Togawa Tsuijidai-gin was interest which should be paid annually, and that interest was from a loan of money which was made by selling reclaimed lands along the Sonezaki-gawa River, the Kyomachi Hori-kawa River, the Tateurihori-kawa River, the Awahori-kawa River, the Toyokohori-kawa River, the Kaifuhori-kawa River, the Satsumahori-kawa River, the Nakanoshima Uenohana, the Edo Hori-kawa Shitanohana, and the Enokojima Shitanohana in 1767.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>家質差配所とは明和4年12月江戸の町人清右衛門、大坂周防町津国屋長右衛門および住吉屋町紙屋利兵衛の3人が1年に冥加金9950両を差し出し、許可を得たもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kajichi Sahaisho came into existence in 1767 when three men consisting of Kiyoemon who is a merchant of Edo, Tsu no Kuniya Choemon who is from Suomach, Osaka and Kamiya Ribee from Sumiyoshiyamachi paid license tax of 9950-ryo annually for their business as agent for managing Kajichi Sahaisho; they did paper work for lender and the borrowers; borrowers needed to mortgage their house when they borrowed money; from Sango to farmers in the nearby villages, borrowers had to write down their possessions such as houses, storehouses, various shares, barber shop in possesion and so forth; when borrowers borrowed gold and silver, they had to submit a deed to Sahaisho the document from Sahaisho must contain a seal of approval at the end of the document; if borrower used to borrow money from other lenders, Sahaisho led the borrowers to change the place of borrowing from other lenders to Sahaisho when the bill at debt had to be renewed; if a lending process requires seal of approval at the end of the document, Sahaisho collected service charge from both of lender and borrower; lenders had to pay 4 monme per gin 1-kanme; borrowers had to pay 6 per gin 1-kanme; the document of mortgage of house had to be rewritten every 6-month; indenture on the quality of various shares had to be renewed annually.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kajichi Sahaisho came into existence in 1767 when three men (Kiyoemon who was a merchant of Edo, Tsu no Kuniya Choemon who was from Suomach, Osaka, and Kamiya Ribee from Sumiyoshiyamachi) paid annual license tax of 9950-ryo for their business as an agent for managing Kajichi Sahaisho.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処としました。全体的な書き直しが必要でした。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kajichi Sahaisho came into existence in 1767 when three men (Kiyoemon who was a merchant of Edo, Tsu no Kuniya Choemon who was from Suomach, Osaka, and Kamiya Ribee from Sumiyoshiyamachi) paid annual license tax of 9950-ryo for their business as an agent for managing Kajichi Sahaisho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>三郷および近在の農民に至るまで、その所有する家屋敷、土蔵、諸株、髪結床その他を質物に書き入れ、金銀貸借する時はかならず証文を差配所に提出し、奥印を請けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Farmers in Sango and nearby villages, borrowers had to write down their possessions such as houses, storehouses, various shares, barber shop in possesion and so on, and when they borrowed gold and silver, they had to submit a deed with a seal of approval to the Sahaisho.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処としました。全体的な書き直しが必要でした。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Farmers in Sango and nearby villages, borrowers had to write down their possessions such as houses, storehouses, various shares, barber shop in possesion and so on, and when they borrowed gold and silver, they had to submit a deed with a seal of approval to the Sahaisho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>差配所から金銀を貸し付けて従来よそから借り入れた分は期日に証文を改める際にしだいしだいに差配所の貸し付け銀に借り換えさせ、奥印を経る時には差配所は世話料として銀1貫目あたり貸し主から4匁、借り主から6匁の奥印料を徴収した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If borrowers had borrowed money from other lenders, the Sahaisho told them to refunding money from the Sahaisho on due date, and when a new seal of approval was given to them, the Sahaisho collected service charge from both of the former lender and the borrower; for example, the lender had to pay 4 monme per 1-kanme of silver, and the borrower had to pay 6 monme per 1-kanme of silver.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処としました。全体的な書き直しが必要でした。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If borrowers had borrowed money from other lenders, the Sahaisho told them to refunding money from the Sahaisho on due date, and when a new seal of approval was given to them, the Sahaisho collected service charge from both of the former lender and the borrower; for example, the lender had to pay 4 monme per 1-kanme of silver, and the borrower had to pay 6 monme per 1-kanme of silver.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>家質は6ヶ月毎に、諸株の質は1年毎に、証書を書き換えなければならないとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such a document of house mortgage had to be rewritten every 6 months, and indentures of various shares had to be renewed annually.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処としました。全体的な書き直しが必要でした。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such a document of house mortgage had to be rewritten every 6 months, and indentures of various shares had to be renewed annually.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>このことに驚いた市民からは大変な悪評を蒙り、翌5年1月6日以後町々から抗議が相次いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The citizens were surprised and this arrangement had really bad reputation; after 1768 many towns protested one after another.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People were surprised and this arrangement had a really bad reputation, and after February 23, 1768, towns made protest against this successively.</e>
<cmt>the citizensをpeopleに、日付が訳されていなかったので追加、余分なセミコロンの削除、後半書き直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People were surprised and this arrangement had a really bad reputation, and after February 23, 1768, towns made protest against this successively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="13">
<j>奉行所はこれを取り上げなかったために、正月22日から24日にかけて大坂市中に暴動が発生し、紙屋、津国屋をはじめとし、家質差配所に関係する者の家々に乱入し、打ち壊した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The magistrate&apos;s office did nothing with these protests; thereupon from January 22 to 24 in New Year&apos;s holidays riots occurred in the town of Osaka; people broke into houses whose owners were related to Kajichi Sahaisho including Kamiya and Tsunokuniya and made havoc of them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the magistrate&apos;s office did nothing with these protests, riots occurred in the town of Osaka from March 10 through March 12, and people broke into and destroyed houses whose owners were related to Kajichi Sahaisho including Kamiya and Tsunokuniya.</e>
<cmt>余分なセミコロンの削除、接続詞の追加、日付の変更、「打ち壊した」をdestroyに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the magistrate&apos;s office did nothing with these protests, riots occurred in the town of Osaka from March 10 through March 12, and people broke into and destroyed houses whose owners were related to Kajichi Sahaisho including Kamiya and Tsunokuniya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="14">
<j>奉行所は市民の不平を慰撫するべく差配所冥加金の一部を川浚えに使用することとし、1773年（安永2年）に川浚費は4900両に引き上げられ、これで一切の川浚え費を支弁した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The magistrate&apos;s office decided to use a part of the license tax the office received from Sahaisho for dredging to pacify the complaints voiced by the citizens; accordingly, the expense of dredging was raised to 4900-ryo in 1773 and all the expenses needed for dredging was paid with this money.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The magistrate&apos;s office decided to use a part of the license tax the office received from Sahaisho for dredging to pacify the complaints voiced by the citizens; accordingly, the expense of dredging was raised to 4900 ryo in 1773 and all the expenses needed for dredging was paid with this money.</e>
<cmt>余分なハイフンの削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The magistrate&apos;s office decided to use a part of the license tax the office received from Sahaisho for dredging to pacify the complaints voiced by the citizens; accordingly, the expense of dredging was raised to 4900 ryo in 1773 and all the expenses needed for dredging was paid with this money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="15">
<j>その費用は家質差配所冥加金だけから支出されることとし、十川築地代銀貸付利銀および堀江上荷船船床銀は城内金蔵に納めることにした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is decided that the dredging expense is paid out only from the license tax received from Kajichi Sahaisho; Togawa Tsuijidai-gin Kashitsuke Rigin (interest from the sales of the reclaimed land of Togawa) and Horie Uenibune (freighters) Funadoko-gin were to be stored in the treasury of the castle; however, objection about the Okuin (seal of approval on the end of a deed) from the citizens never ceased to stop that the magistrate office finally discontinued this method; The magistrate office decided to collect money as &apos;tax for dredging&apos; which was up to that time came from Sahaisho for The amount of 9950-ryo annually; after 1775 the citizens were to pay three times per year in February, May, and October in installment. For dredging, 4900-ryo was paid out of these installed payments.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was decided that the dredging expense should be paid out only from the license tax received from Kajichi Sahaisho, and Togawa Tsuijidai-gin Kashitsuke Rigin (interest from the sales of the reclaimed land of Togawa) and Horie Uenibune (freighters) Funadoko-gin were to be stored in the treasury of the castle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処としました。時制の修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was decided that the dredging expense should be paid out only from the license tax received from Kajichi Sahaisho, and Togawa Tsuijidai-gin Kashitsuke Rigin (interest from the sales of the reclaimed land of Togawa) and Horie Uenibune (freighters) Funadoko-gin were to be stored in the treasury of the castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>が、差配所の奥印については市民の反対が絶えないためについにこれを廃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as objection about Okuin (seal of approval on the end of a deed) from the citizens never ceased to stop, the magistrate office finally discontinued this.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処としました。余分な語（that）の削除、接続詞asの追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as objection about Okuin (seal of approval on the end of a deed) from the citizens never ceased to stop, the magistrate office finally discontinued this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>差配所から納めていた冥加金1年9950両を「川浚冥加金」という名目で市民から徴収することとし、安永4年（1775年）以後は1年3回2月、5月、10月に分納させ、この金額のなかからなお4900両を川浚費に支弁した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The magistrate&apos;s office decided to collect the annual amount of 9950 ryo, which originally came from the Sahaisho, by &apos;tax for dredging,&apos; and after 1775, the citizens had to pay three times per year (in February, May, and October), and eventually, 4900 ryo out of these installed payments were used for the dredging.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処としました。全体的な書き換え</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The magistrate&apos;s office decided to collect the annual amount of 9950 ryo, which originally came from the Sahaisho, by &apos;tax for dredging,&apos; and after 1775, the citizens had to pay three times per year (in February, May, and October), and eventually, 4900 ryo out of these installed payments were used for the dredging.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="18">
<j>冥加金の割り方は三郷売券高30万5287貫500匁で、冥加金総額を除くと1貫目につき1匁9分5厘6毛となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The method of allocating Myogakin (tax) is as follows: the total of deeds in the central part of Osaka was 305,287-kan 500 monme; when the total amount of Myogakin was taken out, the amount that comes out is 1-monme 9-bu 5-ri 6-mo per 1-kanme.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The allocating method of the Myogakin (tax) was as follows: the total of deeds in the central part of Osaka was 305,287 kan and 500 monme, and when the total amount of the Myogakin was taken out, the amount that came out was 1 monme 9 bu 5 ri and 6 mo per kanme.</e>
<cmt>時制の修正、余分なハイフンの削除、余分なセミコロンの削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The allocating method of the Myogakin (tax) was as follows: the total of deeds in the central part of Osaka was 305,287 kan and 500 monme, and when the total amount of the Myogakin was taken out, the amount that came out was 1 monme 9 bu 5 ri and 6 mo per kanme.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="19">
<j>これを町ごとの売券高に応じて、その町の負担額を定め、間口割にして、町人から取り立てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the amount of the deeds collected, the obligation fees are decided for each town based on this amount and the dredging tax was collected from the townspeople by frontage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each town&apos;s expense was decided based on the amount of deeds collected, and the dredging tax per person was decided according to the size of each house&apos;s frontage before actual collection.</e>
<cmt>全体的に書き換えました。特に間口割の解釈（訳）が誤っています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each town&apos;s expense was decided based on the amount of deeds collected, and the dredging tax per person was decided according to the size of each house&apos;s frontage before actual collection.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="20">
<j>無役屋敷は町々によってさまざまであったが、1796年（寛政8年）から無役屋敷はすべてこれを除いて町々の冥加金額を定めることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Every town had houses exempt from the dredging tax although the percentage was differed; however after 1796 the dredging tax was to be decided excluding houses with exemption of this tax.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although policies about muyaku-yashiki (houses which were exempt from taxes) varied depending on towns, it was decided that all muyaku-yashiki were excluded from the calculation of the amount of the Myogakin in 1796.</e>
<cmt>全体的に書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although policies about muyaku-yashiki (houses which were exempt from taxes) varied depending on towns, it was decided that all muyaku-yashiki were excluded from the calculation of the amount of the Myogakin in 1796.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 遡雨祈胡(id:180528), Rusk(id:9895), Volfgang(id:98768), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>