<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>音道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ondo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ondo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ondo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>音道（おんどう）とは、日本律令制の大学寮において、儒教経典をそのまま音読するために必要な漢音（中国語）の発音について習う学科。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ondo is a subject of Daigakuryo, an educational institution under the system of centralized administration established under the ritsuryo legal codes in Japan, to learn the Han pronunciations of Chinese characters to read aloud the scriptures of Confucianism with the original pronunciations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ondo is one of the subjects of Daigakuryo, an educational institution under the system of centralized administration established under the Ritsuryo Legal Codes in Japan, to learn the Han pronunciations of Chinese characters in order to allow the reading aloud of the scriptures of Confucianism with the original pronunciations.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ondo is one of the subjects of Daigaku-ryo, an educational institution under the system of centralized administration established under the Ritsuryo Legal Codes in Japan, to learn the Han pronunciations of Chinese characters in order to allow the reading aloud of the scriptures of Confucianism with the original pronunciations.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>『日本書紀』によれば、691年に持統天皇が唐より招いた続守言・薩弘格を音博士に任じたのが最古とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Nihon Shoki (Chronicles of Japan)&quot;, it originated that the Emperor Jito invited Shugen ZOKU and Kokaku SATSU and appointed them as the doctors of Ondo in 691.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Nihon Shoki (The Chronicles of Japan)&quot;, its history goes back to a time when Emperor Jito invited and appointed Shugen ZOKU and Kokaku SATSU to become Professors of Ondo in 691.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; (The Chronicles of Japan), its history goes back to a time when Emperor Jito invited and appointed Shugen ZOKU and Kokaku SATSU to become Professors of Ondo in 691.</e>
<cmt>”を半角にして、括弧の位置を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>律令制確立後に大学寮の下に音博士が位置づけられたが、本科（後の明経道）の学生が儒教の教育を受けるために行う最初の課程であった経典の音読を指導するのが役割であった事から、算道・書道_(大学寮)のような独自の学生を保持することは学令などにも記載されていないなど、最初から補助的地位に止められていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the ritsuryo legal codes was established, the doctors of Ondo were positioned under Daigakuryo, but because their role was to teach reading aloud of the scriptures which was the first course of Confucianism for the students of the regular course (future Myogyodo, the Confucian department of Daigakuryo), their position was only supplementary and it was not stated on the regulations that they had own students like Sando (mathmatics) and Shodo (calligraphy).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Ritsuryo Legal Codes were established, the Professors of Ondo were positioned within the Daigakuryo system, but because their role was to teach the reading aloud of the scriptures during the first course of Confucianism to the students of the main course (later known as Myogyodo, the Confucian department of Daigakuryo), their position was only deemed to be supplementary and it was not mentioned within the regulations that they may have their own students like Sando (Mathmatics) and Shodo (Calligraphy) Departments.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Ritsuryo Legal Codes were established, the Professors of Ondo were positioned within the Daigaku-ryo system, but because their role was to teach the reading aloud of the scriptures during the first course of Confucianism to the students of the main course (later known as Myogyodo, the Confucian department of Daigaku-ryo), their position was only deemed to be supplementary and it was not mentioned within the regulations that they may have their own students like Sando (Mathematics) and Shodo (Calligraphy) Departments.</e>
<cmt>Mathematicsスペル訂正しました。ハイフン補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>それでも唐の文化の影響が強まった平安時代初期の延暦11年11月20日 (旧暦)（793年1月7日）、桓武天皇が漢音奨励の勅を出して学生には漢音の学習が義務づけられ（『日本紀略』）、続いて延暦17年2月14日 (旧暦)（798年3月6日）には学生に従来から日本に存在する南朝 (中国)系の呉音を禁じて漢音での発音が義務付けられた（『弘仁格抄』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Still, on January 7, 793 in the early Heian period of increasing influences from Tang (a dynasty of China) culture, according to the edict of the Emperor Kammu to encourage the Han pronunciations of Chinese characters, students were obliged to learn it (&quot;Nihongiryaku (Abstract of Japanse History)&quot;) and on March 6, 798, students were obliged the Han pronunciations of Chinese characters and prohibited Goon, existing pronunciations from the Southern Dynasty in China (&quot;Koninkyakusho (Regulations in Konin period)&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the increasing influence from the Chinese Tang culture of the early Heian period, Emperor Kammu issued a decree to encourage the Han pronunciations of the Chinese characters on January 7, 793, which in effect forced the students learn it (&quot;Nihongiryaku (Abstract of Japanse History)&quot;), and on March 6, 798, students were prohibited from learning Goon, the existing pronunciations from the Southern Dynasty in China were prohibited and were instructed to learn the Han pronunciations of the Chinese characters (&quot;Koninkyakusho (Regulations in Konin period)&quot;).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the increasing influence from the Chinese Tang culture of the early Heian period, Emperor Kammu issued a decree to encourage the Han pronunciations of the Chinese characters on January 11, 793, which in effect forced the students learn it (&quot;Nihongiryaku&quot; (Abstract of Japanese History)), and on March 10, 798, students were prohibited from learning Goon, the existing pronunciations from the Southern Dynasty in China were prohibited and were instructed to learn the Han pronunciations of the Chinese characters (&quot;Koninkyakusho&quot; (Regulations in Konin period)).</e>
<cmt>Japaneseスペル訂正しました。”を半角にして、括弧の位置を訂正しました。調査したところ、原文の西暦はユリウス暦で「延暦11年閏11月20日」となります。原文に「閏」はありませんが、このユリウス暦をグレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>なお、同様の措置は僧侶に対しても取られており、音博士も僧侶の試験のために派遣されている（延暦12年4月28日 (旧暦)（793年6月11日）に年分度者に対して漢音に通じなければ得度を認めないとし（『日本紀略』・『類聚国史』）、延暦20年4月15日 (旧暦)（801年5月30日）には、僧侶の得度の際に漢音の試験を課している（『日本紀略』））。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The same measures were taken to the monks and some doctors of Ondo were sent for examinations to the monks and on June 11, 793 it was stated that monks must master the Han pronunciation to be the monks entering the Buddhist priesthood of each year (&quot;Nihongiryaku&quot;, Ruijukokushi (classified history of Japan)&quot;and on May 30, 801 the examination of the Han pronunciations of Chinese characters was imposed to the monks (&quot;Nihongiryaku&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similar laws were passed which applied to monks and Professors of Ondo were sent in to perform examinations of the monks, and further, on June 11, 793, the law stated that monks must master the Han pronunciation in order to enter the Buddhist priesthood (&quot;Nihongiryaku&quot;, &quot; Ruijukokushi (Classified History of Japan)&quot;), and then on May 30, 801, the Examination of Han Pronunciations of Chinese Characters was imposed on the monks entering the Buddhist priesthood (&quot;Nihongiryaku&quot;).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similar laws were passed which applied to monks and Professors of Ondo were sent in to perform examinations of the monks, and further, on June 15, 793, the law stated that monks must master the Han pronunciation in order to enter the Buddhist priesthood (&quot;Nihongiryaku,&quot; &quot;Ruijukokushi&quot; (Classified History of Japan)), and then on June 3, 801, the Examination of Han Pronunciations of Chinese Characters was imposed on the monks entering the Buddhist priesthood (&quot;Nihongiryaku&quot;).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。”を半角にして、括弧の位置を訂正しました。コンマの位置を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>そして、嵯峨天皇の弘仁8年4月17日 (旧暦)（817年5月6日）付で4名の「音生」及び白丁からなる6名の「漢語生」設置の格式が出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And an ordinance was established to take &apos;Kangosei (students of Chinese)&apos;, composed of 6students incduding 4 &apos;Onsei&apos;s and Hakuchos, dated on May 6, 817 of the Emperor Saga&apos;s period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During Emperor Saga&apos;s reign, an ordinance was issued on May 6, 817 to establish the &apos;Kangosei (students of Chinese)&apos;, which composed of six students including four Onsei and Hakucho.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During Emperor Saga&apos;s reign, an ordinance was issued on May 10, 817 to establish the &apos;Kangosei&apos; (students of Chinese), which composed of six students including four Onsei and Hakucho.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。括弧の位置を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>だが、承和 (日本)5年（839年）を最後に遣唐使が中絶（寛平6年（894年）廃止）されると、漢音を日本国内で用いる必要性がほとんど失われ、音道は急激に衰退する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But after the Japanese envoy to Tang Dynasty in China was stopped in 839, there was seldom need for the Han pronunciations of Chinese characters in Japan and Ondo declined rapidly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But after the Japanese envoy to the Chinese Tang Dynasty ceased in 839, there were hardly any need for the Han pronunciations of Chinese characters in Japan, and as such, Ondo&apos;s popularity declined rapidly.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But after the Japanese envoy to the Chinese Tang Dynasty ceased in 839, there were hardly any need for the Han pronunciations of Chinese characters in Japan, and as such, Ondo&apos;s popularity declined rapidly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>恐らくは書道よりも早い段階で明経道に事実上吸収されていき、明経道を独占した中原氏・清原氏が明経道の職に就くまでの暫定的な地位となっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Probably it was absorbed by Myogyodo in effect at the earlier stage than calligraphy and stayed in a temporally position until the Nakahara clan and the Kiyohara clan who dominated Myogyodo got appointments with Myogyodo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was most likely absorbed by Myogyodo even before Calligraphy and maintained a temporary place there until the Nakahara clan and the Kiyohara clan got appointments to Myogyodo and were later able to dominate Myogyodo.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was most likely absorbed by Myogyodo even before Calligraphy and maintained a temporary place there until the Nakahara clan and the Kiyohara clan got appointments to Myogyodo and were later able to dominate Myogyodo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Straysheep(id:42448), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>