<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>日甫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nichiho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nichiho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nichiho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>日甫（にちほ、慶長12年（1607年） - 元禄11年（1698年））は、江戸時代前期の日蓮宗の僧で立花の名手。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nihciho (born in 1607 and passed away in 1698) was a Nichiren sect priest in the former Edo period and master of tatebana (standing flowers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nihciho (born in 1607 and passed away in 1698) was a Nichiren sect priest in the early Edo period and master of tatebana (standing flowers).</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nichiho (1607 - 1698) was a Nichiren sect priest in the early Edo period and master of tatebana (standing flowers).</e>
<cmt>日付表記スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>京都本能寺塔頭高俊院第4世院主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the fourth Inju, (the chief) of Honno-ji Temple Tacchu Koshun-in in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the fourth Inju (chief) of Honno-ji Temple Tacchu Koshun-in in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the fourth Inju (chief) of Honno-ji Temple Tacchu Koshun-in in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>号は大住院以信。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His pseydonym (pen name) was Daiju-in Ishin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His pseydonym (pen name) was Daiju-in Ishin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His pseudonym (pen name) was Daiju-in Ishin.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>2世池坊専好に師事して華道を修め、1648年（慶安元年）から1653年（承応2年）にかけて江戸に下向し、紀州徳川家をはじめとする大名屋敷で活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He learned Kado, flower arrangement, under the second Senko IKENOBO, went down to Edo from 1648 to 1653 and worked actively at a daimyo yashiki (mansion of a feudal lord), such as Kishu Tokugawa Family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He learned Kado, flower arrangement, under the second Senko IKENOBO, went down to Edo from 1648 to 1653, and worked actively at a daimyo yashiki (mansion of a feudal lord), the Kishu Tokugawa Family.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He learned Kado, flower arrangement, under the second Senko IKENOBO, went down to Edo from 1648 to 1653, and worked actively at a daimyo yashiki (mansion of a feudal lord), including the Kishu Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>including補足スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>その後京へ戻り、宮中や公卿の社会を中心に活躍し、1678年（延宝6年）自選の作品集である「大住院立花砂之物図」を刊行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he returned to Kyoto, worked actively mainly in the Imperial Court and in the society of court nobles and in 1678, he published &apos;Daijuin Rikka Sunamonozu, Daijuin Tatehana Sabutsuzu,&apos; a collection of his works selected by himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he returned to Kyoto, worked actively mainly in the Imperial Court and in the society of court nobles, and in 1678 he published &apos;Daijuin Rikka Sunamonozu, Daijuin Tatehana Sabutsuzu,&apos; a collection of his works selected by himself.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he returned to Kyoto, worked actively mainly in the Imperial Court and in the society of court nobles, and in 1678 he published &apos;Daijuin Rikka Sunamonozu, Daijuin Tatehana Sabutsuzu,&apos; a collection of his works selected by himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>池坊宣養を擁立した安立坊周玉らと対立し、晩年は尾張・江戸に下向したが、池坊の立花に押され活躍できなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Antagonizing Shugyoku ANRYUBO and others, who supported Senyo IKENOBO, Nichiho went down to Owari and Edo and couldn&apos;t be active because of IKENOBO&apos;s tatebana.</e>
<cmt>池坊宣養の発音が不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Antagonizing Shugyoku ANRYUBO and others, who supported Senyo IKENOBO, Nichiho went down to Owari and Edo and couldn&apos;t be active because of IKENOBO&apos;s tatebana.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Antagonizing Shugyoku ANRYUBO and others, who supported Senyo IKENOBO, Nichiho went down to Owari and Edo and couldn&apos;t be active because of Ikenobo&apos;s tatebana.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 目白梅(id:141468), R28Bot(id:177951), 松茸(id:27535), Dream100(id:41924), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>