<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>本禅寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honzen-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honzen-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honzen-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>本禅寺（ほんぜんじ）は、法華宗陣門流の京別院。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honzen-ji Temple is a branch temple in Kyoto Jinmon lineage of Hokke sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honzen-ji Temple is a branch temple in the Kyoto Jinmon lineage of the Hokke sect.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honzen-ji Temple is a branch temple in the Kyoto Jinmon lineage of the Hokke sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>山号を光了山（こうりょうさん）と号する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sango (name of a group of Buddhist temples) is Koryosan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its sango (name of a group of Buddhist temples) is Koryosan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its sango (literally, &quot;mountain name&quot;), which is the title prefixed to the name of a Buddhist temple, is Koryosan.</e>
<cmt>山号用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>応永13年（1406年）、門祖日陣創建。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The temple was built by 門祖Nichijin in 1406.</e>
<cmt>門祖→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The temple was built in 1406 by 門祖Nichijin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The temple was built in 1406 by monso (founder) Nichijin.</e>
<cmt>門祖→monso (founder)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>塔頭が四院ある（心城院、詮量院、玄妙院、円龍院）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are four in of tatchu. (sub-temples in the site of main temple) (Shinjo-in Temple, Senryo-in Temple, Genmyo-in Temple, Enryo-in Temple)</e>
<cmt>円龍院→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are four in of tatchu (sub-temples on the site of the main temple): Shinjo-in Temple, Senryo-in Temple, Genmyo-in Temple and Enryo-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are four in of tatchu (sub-temples on the site of the main temple): Shinjo-in Temple, Senryo-in Temple, Genmyo-in Temple and Enryo-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>本禅寺の特色</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The feature of Honzen-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Features of Honzen-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Features of Honzen-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>法華宗陣門流（総本山は越後国三条長久山本成寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Jinmon lineage of Hokke sect (Sohonzan (the head temple of a Buddhist sect) is Chokyuzan Honjo-ji Temple in Sanjo, Echigo Province.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kyoto Jinmon lineage of the Hokke sect (Sohonzan (the head temple of a Buddhist sect) is Chokyuzan Honjo-ji Temple in Sanjo, Echigo Province).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kyoto Jinmon lineage of the Hokke sect (Sohonzan (the head temple of a Buddhist sect) is Chokyuzan Honjo-ji Temple in Sanjo, Echigo Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>&lt;現、新潟県三条市&gt;）の近畿地方での別院（京別院、上別院）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a branch temple in Kinki district ((current Sanjo City, Nigata Prefecture) branch temple in Kyoto, 上別院)</e>
<cmt>上別院→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s a branch temple in the Kinki district ((the present-day Sanjo City, Nigata Prefecture) branch temple in Kyoto, 上別院).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s a branch temple in the Kinki district (the present-day Sanjo City, Niigata Prefecture) branch temple in Kyoto, 上別院).</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>宗祖日蓮の随身仏と言われる金銅立像釈尊が立像堂（りゅうぞうどう）に有る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is 金銅立像釈尊 in 立像堂, which said to be 随身仏 of the founder of the religious sect, Nichiren.</e>
<cmt>金銅立像釈尊 立像堂、随身仏→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is 金銅立像釈尊 in 立像堂, which is said to be 随身仏 of the founder of the religious sect, Nichiren.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a gilt bronze standing statue of Shakyamuni in Ryuzo-do Hall, which is said to be 随身仏 of the founder of the religious sect, Nichiren.</e>
<cmt>金銅立像釈尊→a gilt bronze standing statue of Shakyamuni立像堂→Ryuzo-do Hall</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>室町時代の天文法難後、後奈良天皇より綸旨（りんじ）を賜り、勅願寺となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Tenbun-honan (Tenbun Hokke War) in the Muromachi period, Honjec-ji Temple received rinji (the Emperor&apos;s command) from Emperor Gonara to became chokugan-ji. (temple built at the order of the emperor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following Tenbun-honan (Tenbun Hokke War) in the Muromachi period, Honjec-ji Temple received rinji (the Emperor&apos;s command) from Emperor Gonara to became chokugan-ji (a temple built at the order of the emperor).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following Tenbun-honan (Tenbun Hokke War) in the Muromachi period, Honzen-ji Temple received rinji (the Emperor&apos;s command) from Emperor Gonara to became chokugan-ji (a temple built at the order of the emperor).</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>天保10年（1839年）には有栖川宮家の祈願所となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1839 the temple became Arisugawanomiya family&apos;s place for prayer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1839, the temple became the Arisugawanomiya family&apos;s place of prayer.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1839, the temple became the Arisugawanomiya family&apos;s place of prayer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>洛中法華21ヶ寺のひとつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of the temple out of twenty-one temples of Rakuchu-Hokke sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is one of 21 temples of the Rakuchu-Hokke sect.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is one of 21 temples of the Rakuchu-Hokke sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="11">
<j>豊臣秀頼が鋳造し、徳川家康が大坂の役で陣鐘として用い、大久保彦左衛門が奉納したとされる梵鐘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a bronze bell (temple bell) which said to be casted by Hideyori TOYOTOMI, and was used by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA as a gong in Osaka no Eki (The Siege of Osaka), and was dedicated to the temple by Hikozaemon OKUBO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bronze bell (temple bell) is said to have been cast by Hideyori TOYOTOMI and used by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA as a gong in Osaka no Eki (The Siege of Osaka); it was dedicated to the temple by Hikozaemon OKUBO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bronze bell (temple bell) is said to have been cast by Hideyori TOYOTOMI and used by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA as a gong in Osaka no Eki (The Siege of Osaka); it was dedicated to the temple by Hikozaemon OKUBO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="12">
<j>大久保彦左衛門、画家岸駒（がんく）、拝匠梅室（ばいしつ）の墓が有る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is cemetery of Hikozaemon OKUBO, an artist, Ganku, 拝匠, Baisitsu.</e>
<cmt>拝匠→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the cemetery of Hikozaemon OKUBO, an artist, Ganku, 拝匠 and Baisitsu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the cemetery of Hikozaemon OKUBO, an artist, Ganku, 拝匠 and Baishitsu.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="13">
<j>歴代には日覺大僧正などの名僧が多数。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were many successive, famous monks such as 日覺 who was well known, successive daisojo (a Buddhist priest of the highest order).</e>
<cmt>日覺 →読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were many successive, famous monks such as 日覺, who was well known, along with successive aisojo (Buddhist priests of the highest order).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were many successive, famous monks such as Nikkaku, who was well known, along with successive daisojo (Buddhist priests of the highest order).</e>
<cmt>日覺→Nikkaku 一般的な読みとしましたスペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>法脈</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dharma lineage</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dharma lineage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dharma lineage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>宗祖日蓮から、日朗（六老僧）、日印（鎌倉殿中問答の勝者）、日静（上杉氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dharma lineage started from the founder of a religious sect, Nichiren, followed by Nichiro (Rokuroso), Nichiin (the winner of Kamakura denchu mondo Dialogue), Nichijo (originated from the Uesugi clan)</e>
<cmt>六老僧、 鎌倉殿中問答→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dharma lineage started with the founder of a religious sect, Nichiren, followed by Nichiro (Rokuroso), Nichiin (the winner of Kamakura denchu mondo dialogue), and Nichijo (who originated from the Uesugi clan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dharma lineage started with the founder of a religious sect, Nichiren, followed by Nichiro (Rokuroso), Nichiin (the winner of Kamakura denchu mondo dialogue), and Nichijo (who originated from the Uesugi clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>&lt;藤原北家系&gt;出身、後に除歴）、日陣（門祖）と流れる法脈である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan line), later being removed from the successive chief priest), Nichijin. (Monso)</e>
<cmt>門祖→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The Northern House of the Fujiwara clan line), later removed from the succession of chief priests), Nichijin (Monso).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">((The Northern House of the Fujiwara clan line), later removed from the succession of chief priests), Nichijin (Monso)).</e>
<cmt>()補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>御開帳</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gokaicho (exhibition of Buddhist image)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gokaicho (exhibition of Buddhist images)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gokaicho (exhibition of Buddhist images)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>立像堂（りゅうぞうどう）の宗祖日蓮の念持仏｢立像釈迦牟尼仏｣は､年二回､万人講（4月上旬）と御会式（おえしき）（10月13日）の時において、御開帳される｡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Gokaicho of the founder of the religious sect, Nichiren&apos;s nenjibutsu (a small statue of Buddha kept beside the person), &apos;standing statue of Shakamuni Butsu&apos; in Ryudoxo is exhibit to the public twice a year, once in 万人講(early April) and other time in Oeshiki (a Buddhist (memorial) service in Nichiren sect) (October 13).</e>
<cmt>万人講→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Gokaicho of the founder of the religious sect, Nichiren&apos;s nenjibutsu (a small statue of Buddha kept beside the person), &apos;standing statue of Shakamuni Butsu&apos; in Ryudoxo is exhibited to the public twice each year, once in 万人講 (early April) and again in Oeshiki (a Buddhist (memorial) service in the Nichiren sect, held on October 13).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Gokaicho of the founder of the religious sect, Nichiren&apos;s nenjibutsu (a small statue of Buddha kept beside the person), &apos;standing statue of Shakyamuni Butsu&apos; in Ryuzo-do Hall is exhibited to the public twice each year, once in Manninko (early April) and again in Oeshiki (a Buddhist (memorial) service in the Nichiren sect, held on October 13).</e>
<cmt>用語統一万人講→Manninko</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>所在地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Location</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Location</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Location</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>京都府京都市上京区寺町通広小路通 (京都市)上ル北之辺町394番地（京都御所の北東）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">394 Kitanobe machi, Hirokoji-dori (Kyoto City) noboru, Teramachi dori, Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture (north east of Kyoto Imperial Palace)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is located at 394 Kitanobe machi, Hirokoji-dori (Kyoto City) noboru, Teramachi dori, Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture (northeast of Kyoto Imperial Palace)</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is located at 394 Kitanobe machi, Hirokoji-dori (Kyoto City) noboru, Teramachi dori, Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture (northeast of Kyoto Imperial Palace).</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>京都御所の清和院御門を出て、寺町通を少し北に進むと、道の東側に南から境内に｢紫式部邸宅遺跡｣がある廬山寺､｢身代り不動｣が有名な清浄華院､本禅寺の三寺が並ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After exiting from Seiwa-in Gomon Gate of Kyoto Imperial Palce and go up to the north for a while from Teramachi dori, there are three famous temples, Rozan-ji Temple where the remains of Murasakishikibu&apos;s villa on the east side of the street, and the south side to the precincts of the temple, Shojoke-in Temple, which is famous for Migawarifudo and Honzen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>身代り不動→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After exiting from Seiwa-in Gomon Gate of Kyoto Imperial Palace and heading north for a while from Teramachi-dori, there are three famous temples: Rozan-ji Temple, where the remains of Murasakishikibu&apos;s villa are found on the east side of the street, and the south side to the precincts of the temple, Shojoke-in Temple, which is famous for Migawarifudo and Honzen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After exiting from Seiwa-in Gomon Gate of Kyoto Imperial Palace and heading north for a while from Teramachi-dori, there are three famous temples: Rozan-ji Temple, where the remains of Murasakishikibu&apos;s villa are found on the east side of the street, and the south side to the precincts of the temple, Shojoke-in Temple, which is famous for Migawarifudo and Honzen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>かつて、日陣創建時は四条通堀川通に有り、天文法難以後、日覚大僧正の時に西陣の方四町の地に移る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It used to be located on Shijo dori horikawa dori, and it was moved to 方四町in Nichijin after Tenbun-honan (Tenbun Hokke War) during Nichikaku daisojo was in power.</e>
<cmt>方四町→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was once located on Shijo-dori horikawa-dori, but it was moved to 方四町in Nichijin after Tenbun-honan (Tenbun Hokke War) during the time in which Nichikaku daisojo was in power.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was once located on Shijo-dori horikawa-dori, but it was moved to 方四町 in Nishijin after Tenbun-honan (Tenbun Hokke War) during the time in which Nichikaku daisojo was in power.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>天正19年（1591年）、現在地に移る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1591 it moved to the current place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1591 it moved in 1591 to the site it now occupies.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1591 it moved to the site it now occupies.</e>
<cmt>in 1591 削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="21">
<j>総本山・別院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sohonzan (the head temple of a Buddhist sect), branch temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sohonzan (the head temple of a Buddhist sect), branch temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sohonzan (the head temple of a Buddhist sect), branch temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>総本山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sohonzan</e>
<cmt>補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>長久山本成寺（新潟県三条市）（越後国）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sohonzan (Chokyuzan Honjo-ji Temple) (Sanjo City, Nigata Prefecture) (Echigo Province)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sohonzan (Chokyuzan Honjo-ji Temple) (Sanjo City, Nigata Prefecture) (Echigo Province)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chokyuzan Honjo-ji Temple (Sanjo City, Niigata Prefecture) (Echigo Province)</e>
<cmt>Sohonzan削除スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>当寺以外の別院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other branch temples other than Honzen-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Branch temples other than Honzen-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Branch temples other than Honzen-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>東海別院　常霊山本興寺 (湖西市)（静岡県湖西市）（遠江国）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">a branch temple in Tokai Joreizan Honko-ji Temple (Kosai City) (Kosai City, Shizuoka Prefecture) (Totomi Province)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A branch temple in Tokai Joreizan Honko-ji Temple (Kosai City) (Kosai City, Shizuoka Prefecture) (Totomi Province)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A branch temple in Tokai Joreizan Honko-ji Temple (Kosai City, Shizuoka Prefecture) (Totomi Province)</e>
<cmt>(Kosai City) 重複削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>東京別院　徳栄山本妙寺 (東京都豊島区)（東京都豊島区）（武蔵国）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">a branch temple in Tokyo Tokueisan Honmyo-ji Temple (Toshima Ward, Tokyo) (Toshima Ward, Tokyo) (Musashi Province)</e>
<cmt>徳栄山本妙寺→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A branch temple in Tokyo Tokueisan Honmyo-ji Temple (Toshima Ward, Tokyo) (Toshima Ward, Tokyo) (Musashi Province)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A branch temple in Tokyo Tokueisan Honmyo-ji Temple (Toshima Ward, Tokyo) (Musashi Province)</e>
<cmt>(Toshima Ward, Tokyo) 重複削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>北陸別院　長松山本法寺 (富山市)（富山県富山市八尾町）（越中国）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">a branch temple in Hokuriku Choshozan Honpo-ji Temple (Toyama City) (Yatsuo-machi, Toyama City, Toyama Prefecture) (Etchu Province)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A branch temple in Hokuriku Choshozan Honpo-ji Temple (Toyama City) (Yatsuo-machi, Toyama City, Toyama Prefecture) (Etchu Province)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A branch temple in Hokuriku Choshozan Honpo-ji Temple (Yatsuo-machi, Toyama City, Toyama Prefecture) (Ecchu Province)</e>
<cmt>(Toyama City) 重複削除スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>霊跡別院　俎岩山蓮着寺（静岡県伊東市）（伊豆国）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">a branch temple in 霊跡 Soganzan Renchaku-ji Temple (Ito City, Shizuoka Prefecture) (Izu Province)</e>
<cmt>霊跡別院→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A branch temple in 霊跡 Soganzan Renchaku-ji Temple (Ito City, Shizuoka Prefecture) (Izu Province)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A branch temple in 霊跡 Soganzan Renchaku-ji Temple (Ito City, Shizuoka Prefecture) (Izu Province)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kiyok(id:76023), Miyuki h(id:84952), Yas(id:739), 赤井彗星(id:18381), ASAMA501(id:91947), Blowback(id:173308), Kstigarbha(id:13376), ウィキ豊(id:82961), Jade0416(id:104181), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>