<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大柴燈護摩供</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daisaitogoma ceremony</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daisaitogoma ceremony</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daisaitogoma ceremony</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大柴燈護摩供（だいさいとう ごまく）とは、野外で行う大規模な護摩法要のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daisaitogoma ceremony refers to large-scale Goma (Holy Fire) Mass held in the field.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daisaitogoma ceremony refers to large-scale Goma (Holy Fire) Mass held in the field.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daisaitogoma ceremony refers to large-scale Goma (Holy Fire) Mass held in the field.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>伝統的な柴燈護摩は真言宗を開いた空海の孫弟子に当たる聖宝理源大師が初めて行ったといわれており、醍醐寺をはじめとする真言宗の当山派修験道の法流を継承する寺院で行われる事が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The traditional Saitogoma is said to have been held for the first time by Shobo Rigen Daishi, a disciple of a disciple of Kukai, who established the Shingon sect, and it is mostly held by the temples inheriting the lineage of Tozan school of Shugendo (Japanese mountain asceticism-shamanism incorporating Shinto and Buddhist concepts) including Daigo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The traditional Saitogoma is said to have been held for the first time by Shobo Rigen Daishi, a disciple of a disciple of Kukai, who established the Shingon sect, and it is mostly held by the temples inheriting the lineage of the Tozan school of Shugendo (Japanese mountain asceticism-shamanism incorporating Shinto and Buddhist concepts) including Daigo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The traditional Saitogoma is said to have been held for the first time by Shobo Rigen Daishi, a disciple of a disciple of Kukai, who established the Shingonshu sect, and it is mostly held by the temples inheriting the lineage of the Tozan school of Shugendo (Japanese mountain asceticism-shamanism incorporating Shinto and Buddhist concepts) including Daigo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Shingon→Shingonshu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>すなわち、日本特有の仏教行事である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is, in other words, a Buddhist ceremony unique to Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is, in other words, a Buddhist ceremony unique to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is, in other words, a Buddhist ceremony unique to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>伝統真言宗系当山派の寺院が行う「柴燈護摩」は、本来山中修行にて行者だけで修するものであるため規模や護摩木の数の多寡を問うことはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saitogoma&apos; held by the temples of the traditional Shingon sect Tozan school is originally an ascetic practice in the mountain performed only by practitioners, which does not regard the scale or the number of Gomagi (wood for ritual burning).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saitogoma&apos; held by the temples of the traditional Shingon sect Tozan school is originally an ascetic practice in the mountain performed only by practitioners, which does not regard the scale or the number of Gomagi (pieces of wood for ritual burning).</e>
<cmt>added &quot;pieces of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saitogoma&apos; held by the temples of the traditional Shingonshu sect Tozan school is originally an ascetic practice in the mountain performed only by practitioners, which does not regard the scale or the number of Gomagi (pieces of wood for ritual burning).</e>
<cmt>Shingon→Shingonshu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>が、新宗教の一つである阿含宗の大柴燈護摩供の場合は護摩木も数千万本と国内外でもほとんど類をみないほど大規模でイベント色が強い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Daisaitogoma ceremony of the Agon sect, one of the new religion, has tens of millions of Gomagi and is uniquely large-scale domestically and internationally and more of an event.</e>
<cmt>同上</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Daisaitogoma ceremony of the Agon sect, one of the new religions, has tens of millions of Gomagi and is uniquely large-scale domestically and internationally and more of an event.</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Daisaitogoma ceremony of the Agonshu sect, one of the new religions, has tens of millions of Gomagi and is uniquely large-scale domestically and internationally and more of an event.</e>
<cmt>Agon→Agonshu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また、阿含宗の大柴燈護摩と、伝統的な真言宗系当山派修験道の柴燈護摩の違いについてはそれぞれ主催者側の主張が異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each organizer has a different point on the difference between Daisaitogoma of the Agon sect and Saitogoma of the traditional Shingon sect Tozan school Shugendo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each organizer has a different point on the difference between Daisaitogoma of the Agon sect and Saitogoma of the traditional Shingon sect Tozan school Shugendo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each organizer has a different point on the difference between Daisaitogoma of the Agonshu sect and Saitogoma of the traditional Shingonshu sect Tozan school Shugendo.</e>
<cmt>Shingon→Shingonshu、Agon→Agonshu</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>伝統的な真言宗系当山派の柴燈護摩に柴の字が当てられているのは、山中修行で正式な密具の荘厳もままならず、柴や薪で檀を築いたことによる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason why the character 柴 (brushwood) is used for saitogoma (柴燈護摩) of the traditional Shingon sect Tozan school is that they made a ceremonial mound with brushwood and firewood because they could not decorate even esoteric tools due to the ascetic practice in the mountain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason why the character 柴 (brushwood) is used for saitogoma (柴燈護摩) of the traditional Shingon sect Tozan school is that they made a ceremonial mound with brushwood and firewood because they could not decorate even esoteric tools due to the ascetic practice in the mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason why the character 柴 (brushwood) is used for saitogoma (柴燈護摩) of the traditional Shingonshu sect Tozan school is that they made a ceremonial mound with brushwood and firewood because they could not decorate even esoteric tools due to the ascetic practice in the mountain.</e>
<cmt>Shingon→Shingonshu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>なお、天台宗系本山派が行う野外の護摩供養は、「採燈護摩」というが、真言宗系当山派の柴燈護摩から「採取」した火により行われたので、その字が当てられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Goma Ritual in the field held by the Tendai sect Honzan school is called &apos;採燈護摩&apos; (saitogoma), because it was held with the fire picked (&apos;採取&apos;) from the saitogoma of the Shingon sect Tozan school, and the character is used in it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Goma Ritual in the field held by the Tendai sect Honzan school is called &apos;採燈護摩&apos; (saitogoma), because it was held with the fire picked (&apos;採取&apos;) from the saitogoma of the Shingon sect Tozan school, and the character is used in it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Goma Ritual in the field held by the Tendaishu sect Honzan school is called &apos;採燈護摩&apos; (saitogoma), because it was held with the fire picked (&apos;採取&apos;) from the saitogoma of the Shingonshu sect Tozan school, and the character is used in it.</e>
<cmt>Tendai→Tendaishu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また、醍醐寺の密教の法流を汲んだと主張する新宗教の真如苑では、斉の字を当てて「斉燈護摩」と呼称している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And Shinjoen, new religion alleging that they belong to the lineage of the Esoteric Buddhism of Daigo-ji Temple, calls it &apos;斉燈護摩&apos; (saitogoma) using the character 斉.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinjoen, a new religion alleging that they belong to the lineage of the Esoteric Buddhism of Daigo-ji Temple, calls it &apos;斉燈護摩&apos; (saitogoma) using the character 斉.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinnyoen, a new religion alleging that they belong to the lineage of the Esoteric Buddhism of Daigo-ji Temple, calls it &apos;斉燈護摩&apos; (saitogoma) using the character 斉.</e>
<cmt>Shinjoen→Shinnyoen</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>国内の大柴（採・斉）燈護摩供</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daisaitogoma ceremonies in Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daisaitogoma ceremonies in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daisaitogoma ceremonies in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>国内で最大のものは、炊きあげる護摩木の本数3,000万本以上、参拝者数十万人で他を圧倒する規模の大柴燈護摩供は毎年2月11日、京都市山科区北花山大峰で開催される「炎の祭典・阿含の星まつり　神仏両界大柴燈護摩供」であろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The biggest Daisaitogoma ceremony in Japan would be &apos;The fire rite festival Agon&apos;s Hoshi Matsuri: Shinto-Buddhist Daisaitogoma ceremony,&apos; which is overwhelmingly large-scale with more than 30 million Gomagi to fire and hundreds of thousands of visitors, held in Omine, Kitakazan, Yamashina Ward, Kyoto City on February 11 each year.</e>
<cmt>祭り名は下記参照http://www.agon.org/us/events/a_03.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The biggest Daisaitogoma ceremony in Japan would be &apos;The fire rite festival Agon&apos;s Hoshi Matsuri: Shinto-Buddhist Daisaitogoma ceremony,&apos; which is overwhelmingly large-scale with more than 30 million Gomagi to fire and hundreds of thousands of visitors, held in Omine, Kitakazan, Yamashina Ward, Kyoto City on February 11 each year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The biggest Daisaitogoma ceremony in Japan would be &apos;The fire rite festival Agon&apos;s Hoshi Matsuri: Shinto-Buddhist Daisaitogoma ceremony,&apos; which is overwhelmingly large-scale with more than 30 million Gomagi to fire and hundreds of thousands of visitors, held in Omine, Kitakazan, Yamashina Ward, Kyoto City on February 11 each year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>阿含の星まつり大柴燈護摩供：http//www.agon.org/schedule/hoshimaturi/hoshimaturi_04.html</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Agon&apos;s Hoshimatsuri Daisaitogoma ceremony:http//www.agon.org/schedule/hoshimaturi/hoshimaturi_04.html</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Agon&apos;s Hoshimatsuri Daisaitogoma ceremony:http//www.agon.org/schedule/hoshimaturi/hoshimaturi_04.html</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Agon&apos;s Hoshimatsuri Daisaitogoma ceremony:http//www.agon.org/schedule/hoshimaturi/hoshimaturi_04.html</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>高野山の大柴燈護摩供：http//www.pref.wakayama.lg.jp/prefg/000200/ren/web/ren11/pro_2.html</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daisaitogoma ceremony in Mt. Koya:http//www.pref.wakayama.lg.jp/prefg/000200/ren/web/ren11/pro_2.html</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daisaitogoma ceremony in Mt. Koya:http//www.pref.wakayama.lg.jp/prefg/000200/ren/web/ren11/pro_2.html</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daisaitogoma ceremony in Mt. Koya:http//www.pref.wakayama.lg.jp/prefg/000200/ren/web/ren11/pro_2.html</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>真言系新宗教の行う海外での柴（斉）燈護摩供</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saitogoma ceremonies held overseas by the Shingon-related new religion</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saitogoma ceremonies held overseas by the Shingon-related new religion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saitogoma ceremonies held overseas by the Shingonshu-related new religion</e>
<cmt>Shingon→Shingonshu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>2007年7月8日（ロシア・ハバロフスク市）阿含宗・シベリア大柴燈護摩供：http//www.agon.org/siberia/index.html</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 8, 2007 (Khabarovsk, Russia) Agon sect Siberia Daisaitogoma ceremony:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 8, 2007 (Khabarovsk, Russia) Agon sect Siberia Daisaitogoma ceremony:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 8, 2007 (Khabarovsk, Russia) Agonshu sect Siberia Daisaitogoma ceremony:</e>
<cmt>Agon→Agonshu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>2007年4月20日、21日（アメリカ・ロサンゼルス）真如苑LA斉燈護摩法要　日本の伝統仏教法要と、その願いに賛同した地元のダンサー、オーケストラとの共演。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 20 and 21, 2007, (Los Angels, USA) Shinjoen LA Saitogoma Mass: Joint performance of Japanese traditional Buddhist mass, and the local dancers and orchestra sympathizing the prayers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 20 and 21, 2007, (Los Angeles, USA) Shinjoen LA Saitogoma Mass: Joint performance of Japanese traditional Buddhist mass, and the local dancers and orchestra sympathizing with the prayers.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 20 and 21, 2007, (Los Angeles, USA) Shinnyoen LA Saitogoma Mass: Joint performance of Japanese traditional Buddhist mass, and the local dancers and orchestra sympathizing with the prayers.</e>
<cmt>Shinjoen→Shinnyoen</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>2006年06月13日（ポーランド市アウシュヴィッツ強制収容所近郊）阿含宗・世界平和祈念・アウシュヴィッツ大柴燈護摩供奉修</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 13, 2006 (near Auschwitz concentration camp, Poland) Agon sect World Peace Dedication Auschwitz Daisaitogoma ceremony</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 13, 2006 (near Auschwitz concentration camp, Poland) Agon sect World Peace Dedication Auschwitz Daisaitogoma ceremony</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 13, 2006 (near Auschwitz concentration camp, Poland) Agonshu sect World Peace Dedication Auschwitz Daisaitogoma ceremony</e>
<cmt>Agon→Agonshu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>2003年6月（パリ・シャンドマルス広場）阿含宗・世界平和祈念パリ大柴燈護摩供奉修　フランスのルーヴル美術館に視覚障害者用展示室寄贈とフランスのルーヴル美術館オーディトリアムで瞑想講演会開催</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June, 2003 (Champ de Mars, Paris) Agon sect World Peace Dedication Paris Daisaitogoma ceremony: Donation of an exhibition room for the visually-impaired to the Louvre Museum in France, and holding of a meditation presentation at the auditorium of the Louvre Museum in France.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June, 2003 (Champ de Mars, Paris) Agon sect World Peace Dedication Paris Daisaitogoma ceremony: Donation of an exhibition room for the visually-impaired to the Louvre Museum in France, and holding of a meditation presentation at the auditorium of the Louvre Museum in France.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June, 2003 (Champ de Mars, Paris) Agonshu sect World Peace Dedication Paris Daisaitogoma ceremony: Donation of an exhibition room for the visually-impaired to the Louvre Museum in France, and holding of a meditation presentation at the auditorium of the Louvre Museum in France.</e>
<cmt>Agon→Agonshu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>1998年5月15日 （イギリス・ロンドン）真如苑開基60年真如苑ヨーロッパUK斉燈護摩法要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May 15, 1998 (London, UK) Shinjoen 60th Anniversary Shinjoen Europe UK Saitogoma Mass</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">May 15, 1998 (London, UK) Shinjoen 60th Anniversary Shinjoen Europe UK Saitogoma Mass</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 15, 1998 (London, UK) Shinnyoen 60th Anniversary Shinjoen Europe UK Saitogoma Mass</e>
<cmt>Shinjoen→Shinnyoen</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>1977年4月（パラオ）阿含宗・南太平洋･平和の祈り大柴燈護摩供　海外初の柴燈護摩法要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April, 1977 (Palau) Agon sect South Pacific Peace Prayer Daisaitogoma ceremony: The first Saitogoma mass overseas</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April, 1977 (Palau) Agon sect South Pacific Peace Prayer Daisaitogoma ceremony: The first Saitogoma mass overseas</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April, 1977 (Palau) Agonshu sect South Pacific Peace Prayer Daisaitogoma ceremony: The first Saitogoma mass overseas</e>
<cmt>Agon→Agonshu</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 アーガマ(id:86874), 南無観自在(id:180807), Boca samba(id:137526), Adonis(id:24011), Vvawavv(id:82129), Wtool(id:42723), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>