<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>日重</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nichiju</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nichiju</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nichiju</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>日重（にちじゅう、天文 (元号)18年（1549年） － 元和 (日本)9年（1623年））は、安土桃山時代から江戸時代前期にかけての日蓮宗の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nichiju (1549 to 1623) was a Nichiren sect priest from the Azuchi-momoyama to the early the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nichiju (1549 to 1623) was a Nichiren sect priest from the Azuchi-momoyama to the early the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nichiju (1549 to 1623) was a Nichiren sect priest from the Azuchi-momoyama to the early the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>若狭国の出身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was from Wakasa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was from Wakasa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was from Wakasa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>字は頼順。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Azana (popular name) was Yoriyuki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Azana (popular name) was Yoriyuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Azana (popular name) was Yoriyuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>号は一如院。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His pseudonym (pen name) was Ichinyoin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His pseudonym (pen name) was Ichinyoin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His pseudonym (pen name) was Ichinyoin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>幼い頃に仏心院日こうに師事して、日蓮教学を学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his childhood, he learned Nichiren Kyogaku under Nichiko at Busshinin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his childhood, he learned Nichiren Kyogaku under Nichiko at Busshinin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his childhood, he learned Nichiren Kyogaku under Nichiko at Busshinin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>奈良の教学をはじめ漢詩文や儒学も修め、本満寺12世となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He learned teaching of the Nara period as well as Chinese poetry and Confucianism and became the 12th top priest of Honman-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>「奈良の教学」が何を指すのか不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He learned the teachings of the Nara period as well as Chinese poetry and Confucianism and became the 12th top priest of Honman-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He learned the teachings of the Nara period as well as Chinese poetry and Confucianism and became the 12th top priest of Honman-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>教学的には師日珖の折伏主義を排して摂受主義の教義を発展的に継承した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the doctrine, Nichiju denied his master, Nichiko&apos;s Shakubuku shugi (the doctrine of Shakubuku, the method of propagating Buddhism by correct another&apos;s mistaken views) but accepted the doctrine of Shoju shugi (the doctrine of Shoju, the method of propagating Buddhism by teaching without pointing out mistaken beliefs) and developed it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the doctrine, Nichiju denied his master, Nichiko&apos;s Shakubuku shugi (the doctrine of Shakubuku, the method of propagating Buddhism by correcting another&apos;s mistaken views) but accepted the doctrine of Shoju shugi (the doctrine of Shoju, the method of propagating Buddhism by teaching without pointing out mistaken beliefs) and developed it.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the doctrine, Nichiju denied his master, Nichiko&apos;s Shakubuku shugi (the doctrine of Shakubuku, the method of propagating Buddhism by correcting another&apos;s mistaken views) but accepted the doctrine of Shoju shugi (the doctrine of Shoju, the method of propagating Buddhism by teaching without pointing out mistaken beliefs) and developed it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>1595年（文禄4年）豊臣秀吉が主催した京都方広寺大仏殿の千僧供養会に日蓮宗として出仕するかどうかの問題では、宗門護持の立場から受不施を推進し、不受不施の立場を取った日奥と鋭く対立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1595, it was discussed whether they should attend Senso kuyoe (ceremony of thousand priest mass) as representatives of the Nichiren sect. Nichiju promoted Jufuse from the standpoint of protecting the doctrine and strongly opposed to Nichio, who took the position of Fuju-fuse-gi (nothing could be received or given).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1595, it was discussed whether they should attend Senso kuyoe (ceremony of a thousand priests) as representatives of the Nichiren sect. Nichiju promoted Jufuse from the standpoint of protecting the doctrine and strongly opposed to Nichio, who took the position of Fuju-fuse-gi (nothing could be received or given).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1595, it was discussed whether they should attend Senso kuyoe (ceremony of a thousand priests) which was hosted by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI as representatives of the Nichiren sect, Nichiju promoted Jufuse from the standpoint of protecting the doctrine and strongly opposed to Nichio, who took the position of Fuju-fuse-gi (nothing could be received or given).</e>
<cmt>which was hosted by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Yonoemon(id:55450), 地図帳(id:122587), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), Charenji(id:7908), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>