<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>長信</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Choshin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Choshin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Choshin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>長信（ちょうしん、長和3年（1014年） - 延久4年9月30日 (旧暦)（1072年11月12日））は、平安時代中期の真言宗の僧侶。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Choshin (1014-November 12, 1072) was a Buddhist monk of Shingon sect, in the mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Choshin (1014 - November 12, 1072) was a Buddhist monk of the Shingon sect, in the mid-Heian period.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Choshin (1014 - November 12, 1072) was a Buddhist monk of the Shingon sect, in the mid-Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は摂政藤原道長。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was a Sessho (regent), FUJUWARA no Michinaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was FUJIWARA no Michinaga, a Sessho (regent).</e>
<cmt>grammar + FujIwara</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was FUJIWARA no Michinaga, a Sessho (regent).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は大納言源重光（代明親王の子）の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of a Dainagon (chief councilor of state), MINAMOTO no Shigemitsu who was a child of the Imperial Prince Yoshiakira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was a daughter of a Dainagon (chief councilor of state), MINAMOTO no Shigemitsu, who was a child of Imperial Prince Yoshiakira.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of a Dainagon (chief councilor of state), MINAMOTO no Shigemitsu, who was a child of Imperial Prince Yoshiakira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>通称は「池辺僧正」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He has been gone by the name of Ikebe Sojo.</e>
<cmt>池辺僧正→読みが不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also went by the name Ikebe Sojo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also went by the name Ikebe Sojo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>仁和寺観音院の延尋（源扶義の子）の元に入門して出家、永承3年（1047年）に同院で性信入道親王から灌頂を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became a disciple of Enjin who was a child of MINAMOTO no Sukenori in Kannon-in of Ninna-ji Temple, and became a priest there, then received kanjo (a ceremony to be the successor) by priest-Imperial Prince Shoshin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became a disciple of Enjin, who was a child of MINAMOTO no Sukenori in Kannon-in of Ninna-ji Temple, and became a priest there, whereupon he received kanjo (a ceremony to be the successor) by priest-Imperial Prince Shoshin.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became a disciple of Enjin, who was a child of MINAMOTO no Sukenori in Kannon-in of Ninna-ji Temple, and became a priest there, whereupon he received kanjo (a ceremony to be the successor) by priest-Imperial Prince Shoshin in 1047.</e>
<cmt>年号補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>永承5年（1049年）に東寺に移って権少僧都・一身阿闍梨となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1049, he moved to To-ji Temple and became gon shosozu (Junior lesser prelate), isshin-ajari (a special class of the teaching priests, who are noble and permitted to play role of ajari).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1049, he moved to To-ji Temple and became gon shosozu (junior lesser prelate), isshin-ajari (a special class of teaching priests who were noble and permitted to play the role of ajari).</e>
<cmt>c</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1049, he moved to To-ji Temple and became gon shosozu (junior lesser prelate), isshin-ajari (a special class of teaching priests who were noble and permitted to play the role of ajari).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>天喜2年（1054年）には東寺と真言宗全体の長である第29代東寺長者に任じられて法印に昇進する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1054, He was appointed as the 29th choja of the To-ji Temple who was the chief abbot of the To-ji temple and the entire Shingon sect, and promoted to hoin (the highest rank among Buddhist priests).</e>
<cmt>原文を「東寺長者によって（長信が）（法印に）任じられ」と｢(長信が）東寺長者として任じられ」の2通りに解釈することができますが、後者として訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1054, he was appointed as the twenty-ninth choja of To-ji Temple, who was the chief abbot of the temple and the entire Shingon sect, and was promoted to hoin (the highest rank among Buddhist priests).</e>
<cmt>c</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1054, he was appointed as the twenty-ninth choja of To-ji Temple, who was the chief abbot of the temple and the entire Shingon sect, and was promoted to hoin (the highest rank among Buddhist priests).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>治暦2年（1066年）権僧正となり、この年の旱魃に際して僧侶20人を率いて雨乞いの修法を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1066, he became gon no sojo (a highest ranking priest, next to a sojo) and made a ritual for rain along with 20 priests on the drought that year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1066, he became gon no sojo (the highest-ranking priest next to a sojo) and performed a ritual for rain along with 20 priests on behalf of relief from that year&apos;s drought.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1066, he became gon no sojo (the highest-ranking priest next to a sojo) and performed a ritual for rain along with 20 priests on behalf of relief from that year&apos;s drought.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>延久2年（1070年）には僧正に任じられて、翌年には東寺内に「池坊」を建立してそこに居住する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1070, he was appointed as Sojo, and in the following year he erected &quot;Ikenobo&quot; in the territory of To-ji Temple and lived there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1070, he was appointed as Sojo, and in the following year he erected &quot;Ikenobo&quot; in the territory of To-ji Temple and lived there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1070, he was appointed as Sojo, and in the following year he erected &apos;Ikenobo&apos; in the territory of To-ji Temple and lived there.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>後三条天皇の信任が厚く、この年には百官を連れて長信の元を訪れ、封戸25戸を下賜された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had been in great confidence of the Emperor Gosanjo, who visited Chosin with his all the officials that year and granted fuko (a vassal household allotted to courtier, shrines and temples) 25-households.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had been in the close confidence of Emperor Gosanjo, who visited Chosin with all his officials that year and granted fuko (a vassal household allotted to courtiers, shrines and temples) 25 households.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had been in the close confidence of Emperor Gosanjo, who visited Chosin with all his officials that year and granted fuko (a vassal household allotted to courtiers, shrines and temples) 25 households.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>晩年は仁和寺などの別当を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served as betto (intendant) in such temples as Ninna-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served as betto (intendant) in such temples as Ninna-ji.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served as betto (intendant) in such temples as Ninna-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Mobnoboka(id:35218), R28Bot(id:177951), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>