<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>清瀧権現</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seiryu Gongen, Seiryo Gongen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seiryu Gongen (Seiryo Gongen)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seiryu Gongen (Seiryo Gongen)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>清瀧権現（せいりゅうごんげん または せいりょうごんげん）は、京都市伏見区所在の真言宗醍醐派総本山、醍醐寺の守護女神。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seiryu Gongen or Seiryo Gongen is a guardian goddess of Daigo-ji Temple, Grand Head Temple of Shingon sect Daigo-ha in Fushimi Ward Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seiryu Gongen, or Seiryo Gongen, is a guardian goddess of Daigo-ji Temple, the grand head temple of the Shingon sect Daigo-ha in the Fushimi ward of Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seiryu Gongen (清瀧権現), or Seiryo Gongen, is a guardian goddess of Daigo-ji Temple, the grand head temple of the Shingon sect Daigo-ha branch in the Fushimi Ward of Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>醍醐派の補足として、　branch　を追加しました。 次の文に出てくる漢字表記の違いを出すために、 (清瀧権現)　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>清瀧大権現とも呼称され、清滝権現とも書く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Seiryu Daigongen (Seiryo Daigongen) and also written in Seiryu Gongen (Seiryo Gongen).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called Seiryu Daigongen (Seiryo Daigongen) and is written about in Seiryu Gongen (Seiryo Gongen).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, it is called Seiryu Daigongen (Seiryo Daigongen) and is also written as 清滝権現 (Seiryu Gongen, Seiryo Gongen).</e>
<cmt>「清滝権現」を追加して表記の違いを訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>本地仏は准胝観音と如意輪観音である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honjibutsu, the original Buddhist identity of a Shinto deity, is Jundei Kannon and Nyoirin Kannon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honjibutsu, the original Buddhist identity of a Shinto deity, is Jundei Kannon and Nyoirin Kannon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honjibutsu, the original Buddhist identity of a Shinto deity, is Jundei Kannon and Nyoirin Kannon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>清瀧権現は経軌には説かれておらず、空海の御遺告によると、インド神話に登場する八大竜王の一、沙掲羅（しゃから、シャガーラ）の第三王女（一説には第四王女とも伝えられる）である善女（善如）龍王で、無熱地に住していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seiryu Gongen is not described in Kyoki, and according to Kukai&apos;s Goyuigo it was Zennyo Ryuo, Dragon King Zennyo, the third daughter of Shakara (Sakara, Shagara), one of the Hachidai Ryuo, Eight Dragon Kings in the Indian myth, and lived in Munetsuchi (無熱地).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seiryu Gongen is not described in Kyoki, but according to Kukai&apos;s Goyuigo it was Zennyo Ryuo, (Dragon King Zennyo) the third daughter of Shakara (Sakara, Shagara), one of the Hachidai Ryuo (the eight dragon kings of Indian myth) and lived in Munetsuchi (無熱地).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seiryu Gongen isn&apos;t described in Kyoki (sutra), but according to Kukai&apos;s Goyuigo (written will) it was Zennyo Ryuo, (Dragon King Zennyo) the third (also said to be fourth) daughter of Shakara (Sakara, Shagara), one of the Hachidai Ryuo (the eight dragon kings of Indian myth), and lived in Munetsuchi (無熱池) (a legendary pond that is said to be located in the Himalayas).</e>
<cmt>経軌に(sutra)、 御遺告に　(written will)　と補足をしました。　「無熱地」　ですが、　「無熱池」　ではないかと解釈し、(a legendary pond that is said to be located in the Himalayas)　と訳しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>龍に善悪あるが、善女龍王は害を加えない善龍であり、真言の奥義を敬って出現した8寸（2.5cm）の金色蛇で9尺（3m弱）の蛇の頂上に位置するという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are two kinds of dragons, good and evil, and Zennyo Ryuo was a good dragon who did not do harm, a golden snake of 2.5cm long who appeared with the respect of the dharma of mantra, Shingon, and stands on the top of the snake of about 3m long.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are two kinds of dragons--good and evil--and Zennyo Ryuo was a good dragon who did not do harm; it a golden snake of 2.5cm long who appeared with the respect of the dharma of mantra, Shingon, and stands atop a snake of about 3m long.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are two kinds of dragons--good and evil--and Zennyo Ryuo was a good dragon who did not do harm; it is a golden snake of 2.5 cm long who appeared with the respect of the dharma of mantra, Shingon, and stands atop a snake of about 3 meters long.</e>
<cmt>is 追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>空海が神泉苑で請雨修法の際に出現したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that it appeared at the time of religious ceremony to pray for rainfall by Kukai at Shinsen-en.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that it appeared at the time of a religious ceremony to pray for rainfall held by Kukai at Shinsen-en.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that it appeared at the time of a religious ceremony to pray for rainfall held by Kukai at Shinsen-en.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>善女龍王は密教を守護していた中国・青龍寺に飛来して同寺の鎮守（守護神）「清龍」となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zennyo Ryuo came to Shoryu-ji Temple (Qinglongsi Temple) in China by air which guarded Mikkyo and became a guardian goddess of the temple, &apos;Seiryu.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zennyo Ryuo came to Shoryu-ji Temple (Qinglongsi Temple) in China by air, guarded Mikkyo and became a guardian goddess of the temple, &apos;Seiryu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zennyo Ryuo came flying to Shoryu-ji Temple (Qinglongsi Temple) in China, where Mikkyo was guarded, and became a guardian goddess of the temple, &apos;Seiryu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>came to by air ではなく、came flying としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>後年、弘法大師空海が青龍寺を訪れ仏法を学んだ際、三昧耶戒を授けてほしいと懇請したが許されなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In later years when Kobo-daishi Kukai visited Seiryu-ji Temple and learned Buddhism, he begged to be given Samaya-vrata but it was not permitted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In later years, when Kobo-daishi Kukai visited Seiryu-ji Temple and learned Buddhism, he begged to be given Samaya-vrata but it was not permitted.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In later years, when Kobo-daishi Kukai visited Seiryu-ji Temple and learned Buddhism, he begged to be given Samaya-vrata but it was not permitted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>空海が帰国する際に船中に現れて密教を守護することを誓ったため、京都洛西の高雄山麓に勧請された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Kukai went back to Japan it appeared in a ship and Kukai swore to guard Mikkyo, so that it was transferred by praying at the foot of Takao-san Mountain in Rakusai Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Kukai went back to Japan, it appeared in a ship and Kukai swore to guard Mikkyo, so that it was transferred by praying at the foot of Mt. Takao-san in Rakusai, Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Kukai came back to Japan, it appeared in a ship and Kukai swore to guard Mikkyo, so that it was transferred by praying at the foot of Mt. Takao-san in Rakusai, Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>went back →　came back</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>その際、海を渡ったので龍の字に「さんずい」を加えて日本では「清瀧権現」と敬称するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time it crossed the sea so that it became to be called &apos;Seiryu Gongen (清瀧権現)&apos; with respect in Japan, adding a left-hand radical of &apos;Sanzui (sense of water)&apos; to the Chinese character, 龍 (dragon).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time it crossed the sea so that it came to be called &apos;Seiryu Gongen (清瀧権現)&apos; with respect in Japan, adding the left-hand radical of &apos;Sanzui (sense of water)&apos; to the Chinese character, 龍 (dragon).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time it crossed the sea so that it came to be called &apos;Seiryu Gongen (清瀧権現)&apos; with respect in Japan, adding the left-hand radical of &apos;Sanzui (sense of water)&apos; to the Chinese character, 龍 (dragon).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>高雄山麓の川も清滝（きよたき）と改称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The river at the foot of Takao-san Mountain also changed the name to Kiyotaki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, the name of the river at the foot of Mt. Takao-san was changed to Kiyotaki.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, the name of the river at the foot of Mt. Takao-san was changed to Kiyotaki (清滝）.</e>
<cmt>漢字を追加して、関係が分かるようにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また恵運も迎えて安祥寺に勧請した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Eun also prayed for the coming to Ansho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Eun prayed for the coming to Ansho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, Eun was invited to pray when transferring it to Ansho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>迎えて、とありますので、invitedを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>清瀧権現は日本に飛来し複数の寺を巡った後、900年ころに聖宝により現在の安置所である醍醐寺山頂に降臨し留まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Seiryu Gongen came to Japan by air and visited various temples, it descended to the peak of Daigo-ji Temple of the present place around 900 by Shobo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Seiryu Gongen came to Japan by air and visited various temples, it descended to the peak of Daigo-ji Temple, in the present place, in around 900 by the invocations of Shobo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Seiryu Gongen came flying to Japan and visited various temples, it descended to the peak of Daigo-ji Temple, in the present place, in around 900 by the invocations of Shobo.</e>
<cmt>came flying としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>以後同寺に伝えられる真言密教を守護する女神となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, it became the goddess who guarded Shingo Mikkyo which has been transmitted in that temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, it became the goddess that guarded Shingo Mikkyo, which has been transmitted in that temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently it became the goddess that guarded Shingon Mikkyo, which has been transmitted in that temple.</e>
<cmt>subsequently, Shingon　としました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>承徳元年（1097年）、勝覚が醍醐寺の山上と下に分祀し、現在は清瀧権現が降臨したと伝えられる「上醍醐」醍醐水泉の正面に、室町時代に建立された国宝「清瀧宮拝殿」、醍醐山麓に広がる「下醍醐」境内には国の重要文化財「清瀧宮本殿」が建っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1097 Shokaku separated Daigo-ji Temple into the upper part and the lower part of the mountain so that in &apos;Kami-Daigo (the upper part of Daigo)&apos; at the front of Daigo-sui spring stands &apos;Seiryu-gu Haiden,&apos; a national treasure, which was built in Muromachi Period, and in &apos;Shimo-Daigo (the lower part of Daigo)&apos; which is at the foot of Daigo-san Mountain stands &apos;Seiryu-gu Honden/Haiden,&apos; an important cultural property of government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1097 Shokaku separated Daigo-ji Temple into the upper and lower parts of the mountain, so that in &apos;Kami-Daigo (the upper part of Daigo)&apos; at the front of Daigo-sui spring stands &apos;Seiryu-gu Haiden,&apos; a national treasure, which was built during the Muromachi period, and in &apos;Shimo-Daigo (the lower part of Daigo),&apos; which is at the foot of Mt. Daigo-san, stands &apos;Seiryu-gu Honden/Haiden,&apos; an important cultural property of the government.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1097, Shokaku separated Daigo-ji Temple into the upper and lower parts of the mountain, so that in &apos;Kami-Daigo (the upper part of Daigo),&apos; where Seiryu Gongen is said to have descended; at the front of the Daigo-sui spring stands &apos;Seiryu-gu Haiden,&apos; a national treasure, which was built during the Muromachi period, and in &apos;Shimo-Daigo (the lower part of Daigo),&apos; which is at the foot of Mt. Daigo-san, stands &apos;Seiryu-gu Honden,&apos; a national important cultural property.</e>
<cmt>一部訳を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 白怖じ屋(id:10780), Inaiinaibah(id:4540), Boca samba(id:137526), Kstigarbha(id:13376), R28Bot(id:177951), Urania(id:7213), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>