<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>血脈相承</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kechimyaku-sojo (kechimyaku-sosho)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kechimyaku-sojo (kechimyaku-sosho)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kechimyaku-sojo</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>血脈相承（けちみゃく・そうじょう、そうしょう）は、仏教において、法 (仏教)が師から、弟子へと相続されることを、人体における血液の流れに譬えた語。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kechimyaku-sojo (kechimyaku-sosho) or blood inheritance is a metaphor that is used to describe the inheritance of teachings (Buddhism) from a memtor to a pupil, taking the blood flow as an analogy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kechimyaku-sojo (kechimyaku-sosho) or blood inheritance is a metaphor that is used to describe the inheritance of teachings (Buddhism) from a memtor to a pupil, taking the blood flow as an analogy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kechimyaku-sojo (also referred as kechimyaku-sosho) or blood inheritance is a metaphor that is used to describe the inheritance of teachings (Buddhism) from a mentor to a pupil, taking the blood flow as an analogy.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>師から授けられるものは、本尊や教義・戒律、切紙などの奥義・秘伝の類、あるいは宝物など、要するに血脈相承における「法」とは、”次代の師となるべき者が相続するもの”である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The teachings in kechimyaku-sojo consist of the principal object of worship, doctorine, religious precepts, documents describing the esoteric techniques and secrets, and treasures, which are all given from a memtor and, therefore, are the things that need to be inherited by a person who will become a mentor in the next generation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The teachings in kechimyaku-sojo consist of the principal object of worship, doctorine, religious precepts, documents describing the esoteric techniques and secrets, and treasures, which are all given from a mentor and, therefore, are the things that need to be inherited by a person who will become a mentor in the next generation.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The teachings in kechimyaku-sojo consist of the principal object of worship, doctrine, religious precepts, documents describing the esoteric techniques and secrets, and treasures, which are all given from a mentor and, therefore, are &apos;the things that need to be inherited by a person who will become a mentor in the next generation.&apos;</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>基本的に非公開の場で伝達される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally, everything is transmitted behind closed doors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, everything is transmitted behind closed doors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, everything is transmitted behind closed doors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>単なる相続と見るか、一子相伝の秘儀の相続と見るかで、意味の重みが異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its meaning can vary from when it is looked at a mere inheritance to when it is looked at secrets being handed down from father to son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its meaning can vary from when it is looked at as a mere inheritance, to when it is looked at as secrets being handed down from father to son.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its meaning can vary from when it is looked at as a mere inheritance, to when it is looked at as secrets being handed down from father to son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>各宗派における血脈相承</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kechimyaku-sojo in each sect</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kechimyaku-sojo in each sect</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kechimyaku-sojo in Each Sect</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>浄土真宗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shin Sect</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shin Sect</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism)</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>浄土真宗においては伝灯相承（でんとうそうしょう）と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is called Dento-sosho (the light inheritance) in the Shin Sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is called Dento-sosho (the light inheritance) in the Shin Sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is called Dento-sosho (the light inheritance) in the Jodo Shinshu.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>特に浄土真宗本願寺派や真宗大谷派などでは、門主（門首、法主）の座が親鸞の子孫に受け継がれることを指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Hongan-ji school and Otani school of the Shin Sect, the word particularly refers to the hand-over of the position of the chief of the school to a descendant of Shinran.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Hongan-ji school and Otani school of the Shin Sect, the word particularly refers to the hand-over of the position of the chief of the school to a descendant of Shinran.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Hongan-ji School and Otani School of the Jodo Shinshu, the word particularly refers to the hand-over of the position of the chief of the school to a descendant of Shinran.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>真言宗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shingon Sect</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shingon Sect</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shingon Sect</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>真言宗では、恵果から受けた伝法灌頂によって、密教の正統は全て空海に相伝されたとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Shingon Sect, all orthodoxies of esoteric Buddhism were handed down to Kukai when he received the teachings of Buddhism as well as the enthronement initialtion known as kanjo from Keika.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Shingon Sect, all orthodoxies of esoteric Buddhism were handed down to Kukai when he received the teachings of Buddhism as well as the enthronement initiation known as kanjo from Keika.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Shingon Sect, all orthodoxies of Esoteric Buddhism were handed down to Kukai when he received denpo-kanjo (the consecration for the Transmission of the Dharma) from Keika.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>禅宗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Zen Sect</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Zen Sect</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zen Sect</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>禅宗では法嗣といい、釈迦 - 摩訶迦葉へと伝えられた教外別伝の法を、代々受け継いだ付法蔵の第28祖が達磨であったと主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is called Hoshi in the Zen Sect, in which they claim that it was Daruma who was the twenty-eighth founder of Fuhozo that succeeded the teachings of Buddhist revelation through intuitive discernment from generation to generation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is called Hoshi in the Zen Sect, in which they claim that it was Daruma who was the twenty-eighth founder of Fuhozo that succeeded the teachings of Buddhist revelations through intuitive discernment from generation to generation.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is called Hoshi in the Zen Sect, in which they claim that it was Daruma who was the twenty-eighth founder of fuhozo (those who, after Shakyamuni Buddha&apos;s death, successively inherited the lineage of his teachings and propagated them in India) that succeeded the Kyogai betsuden teaching (transmission of spiritual awakening without words or characters, but in a heart-to-heart way) from Shakamuni to Makakasho, through intuitive discernment from generation to generation.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>禅宗六祖の慧能までの衣鉢の授受を以てその証拠とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be proven by the receipt of robes and bowls of the predecessors up to Eno, the sixth founder of the Zen Sect.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be proven by the receipt of the robes and bowls of the predecessors up to Eno, the sixth founder of the Zen Sect.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be proven by the receipt of the robes and bowls of the predecessors up to Eno, the sixth founder of the Zen Sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>日蓮正宗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nichiren Shoshu Sect</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nichiren Shoshu Sect</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nichiren Sho Sect</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>日蓮正宗における血脈相承については、血脈相承 (日蓮正宗)を参照とされたい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Please refer to Kechimyaku-sojo (Nichiren Shoshu Sect) for Kechimyaku-sojo in the Nichiren Shoshu Sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Please refer to Kechimyaku-sojo (Nichiren Shoshu Sect) for Kechimyaku-sojo in the Nichiren Shoshu Sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Please refer to the article of Kechimyaku-sojo (Nichiren Sho Sect) for Kechimyaku-sojo in the Nichiren Sho Sect.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>※なお、血脈相承という語を用いない宗派、血脈相承的な概念自体が存在しない宗派もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">*There are sects that do not use the term Kechimyaku-sojo or do not have a concept similar to Kechimyaku-sojo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">*There are sects that do not use the term Kechimyaku-sojo or do not have a concept similar to Kechimyaku-sojo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are sects that do not use the term Kechimyaku-sojo or do not have a concept similar to Kechimyaku-sojo.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>善光寺における血脈</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kechimyaku at Zenko-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kechimyaku at Zenko-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kechimyaku at Zenko-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>長野県にある善光寺では、血脈を浄土往生の認定証のように取り扱っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zenko-ji Temple in Nagano Prefecture regards the kechimyaku as a certification to be reborn in heaven.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zenko-ji Temple in Nagano Prefecture regards the kechimyaku as a certification to be reborn in heaven.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zenko-ji Temple in Nagano Prefecture regards the kechimyaku as a certification to be reborn in heaven.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>御血脈授与所において、志納をすれば誰でも額に「極楽往生を保障する血脈の印」を頂くことが出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anyone who pays a fee at the place to provide the kechimyaku can be given &apos;the kechimyaku stamp ensuring the road to heaven&apos; on its forehaead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anyone who pays a fee at the place to provide the kechimyaku can be given &apos;the kechimyaku stamp ensuring the road to heaven&apos; on its forehaead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anyone who pays a fee at the place to provide the kechimyaku can be given &apos;the kechimyaku stamp ensuring the road to heaven&apos; on its forehead.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>江戸時代において既にポピュラーな儀式であったようで、落語の『お血脈』の題材に使用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that this ritual already became popular in the Edo Era, and was used as a material for rakugo or a traditional comic monologue titled &quot;Okechimyaku.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that this ritual had already became popular in the Edo Era, and was used as material for rakugo, or a traditional comic monologue, titled &quot;Okechimyaku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that this ritual had already became popular in the Edo period, and was used as material for rakugo (a traditional comic monologue), titled &quot;Okechimyaku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Boca samba(id:137526), Mait(id:73947), Ajcxx(id:103602), Kstigarbha(id:13376), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>