<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>勧学会</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kangakue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kangakue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kangakue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>勧学会（かんがくえ）とは、平安時代中期・後期に大学寮紀伝道の学生（文章生）と比叡山延暦寺の僧侶が、3月15日 (旧暦)あるいは9月15日 (旧暦)に比叡山西麓あるいは平安京内外の寺院に集まって『法華経』をテーマとして講義・念仏・漢詩を行った法会。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kangakue was a Buddhist meeting held to conduct teaching, nenbutsu (Buddhist invocation), and making of Chinese-style poems with &quot;Hokekyo&quot; (Lotus Sutra) as the theme, held by the scholars of Kidendo (the study of the histories) in Daigakuryo (Bureau of Education) and the priests of Enryaku-ji Temple in Hiei-zan Mountain, on March 15 (in old lunar calendar) or September 15 (in old lunar calendar) at the western foot of Hiei-zan Mountain or at the temples in and around Heian-kyo (ancient Kyoto), in the mid through latter period of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kangakue was a Buddhist meeting held to conduct teaching, nenbutsu (Buddhist invocation), and create Chinese-style poems themed after &quot;Hokekyo&quot; (Lotus Sutra), and was held by the scholars of Kidendo (the study of the histories) in Daigakuryo (Bureau of Education) and the priests of Enryaku-ji Temple in Hiei-zan Mountain, on March 15 (in old lunar calendar) or September 15 (in old lunar calendar) at the western foot of Hiei-zan Mountain or at the temples in and around Heian-kyo (ancient Kyoto), in the mid through latter period of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kangakue was a Buddhist meeting held to conduct teaching, nenbutsu (Buddhist invocation), and create Chinese-style poems themed after &quot;Hokekyo&quot; (Lotus Sutra), and was held by the scholars of Kidendo (the study of the histories) in Daigakuryo (Bureau of Education) and the priests of Enryaku-ji Temple on Mt. Hiei, on March 15 (in old lunar calendar) or September 15 (in old lunar calendar) at the western foot of Mt. Hiei or at the temples in and around Heian-kyo (ancient Kyoto), in the mid through latter period of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>旧暦の説明のため、旧暦表記のまま訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>元来、日本の大学寮は唐の国子監をモデルとした制度であったが、国子監の運営の中心にあたっていた儒学者は『孝経』などを引用して僧侶は親から貰った頭髪を剃り、親を捨てて寺院に籠るのは「孝」に反するとして、強い排仏意識を有していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, Daigakuryo in Japan was a system which had Kokushikan (an educational system in China) of the Tang Dynasty as the model, but the Confucian scholars, who were the main managers of Kokushikan, had a strong anti-Buddhist thought because shaving the hair which were given from the parents and secluding in a temple by leaving their parents were against the principle of &apos;ko&apos; (serving well to one&apos;s parents), quoted in &quot;Kokyo&quot; (The book of filial piety).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, Daigakuryo in Japan was a system that was modeled after the Kokushikan (an educational system in China) of the Tang Dynasty, but the Confucian scholars, who were the main managers of Kokushikan, were strongly anti-Buddhist because shaving the hair which were given from the parents and secluding oneself in a temple, and leaving ones parents was against the principle of &apos;ko&apos; (serving well to one&apos;s parents), quoted in &quot;Kokyo&quot; (The book of filial piety).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, Daigakuryo in Japan was a system that was modeled after the Kokushikan (an educational system in China) of the Tang Dynasty, but the Confucian scholars, who were the main managers of Kokushikan, were strongly anti-Buddhist because shaving the hair which were given from the parents and secluding oneself in a temple, and leaving ones parents was against the principle of &apos;ko&apos; (serving well to one&apos;s parents), quoted in &quot;Kokyo&quot; (The book of filial piety).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>従って、その仕組をそのまま導入して日本の大学寮も儒教を教える明経道を軸に据えており、仏教色を排除していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of that, Daigakuryo in Japan, having that system directly introduced, had Myogyodo, a thought which taught Confucianism, as the main idea, and eliminated the color of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to Daigakuryo in Japan, having been introduced directly through this system, emplaced Myogyodo, which placed Confucianism as the main idea and eliminated all traces of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to Daigakuryo in Japan, having been introduced directly through this system, emplaced Myogyodo, which placed Confucianism as the main idea and eliminated all traces of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>だが、日本においては、一部に摩擦を抱えながらも仏教と伝統宗教である神道の共存が確立しており、儒教を受容しながらもこれを仏教と相反するとする意識は高くなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But in Japan, even though there were some conflicts, Buddhism and Shinto, which was the traditional religion, coexisted together, lowering the awareness of the people that Buddhism was against Confucianism, even though they had taken in the teaching of Confucianism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But in Japan, even though there were conflicts, Buddhism and Shinto, which were traditional religions, coexisted together, lowering people&apos;s views of Buddhism being against Confucianism, even though they had taken in the teaching of Confucianism.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But in Japan, even though there were conflicts, Buddhism and Shinto, which were traditional religions, coexisted together, lowering people&apos;s views of Buddhism being against Confucianism, even though they had taken in the teaching of Confucianism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>従って、国家の統治理念として儒教的な思想と仏教的な思想（鎮護国家）が共存していたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of that, as a philosophy to rule the nation, the ideas of Confucianism and the ideas of Buddhism (nation protection) coexisted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to this, as a philosophy to rule the nation, the ideas of Confucianism and the ideas of Buddhism (nation protection) coexisted.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to this, as a philosophy to rule the nation, the ideas of Confucianism and the ideas of Buddhism (nation protection) coexisted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>しかも、9世紀に入ると、明経道の地位が低下して正史や漢詩などの漢文学を扱う（儒教も学ぶものの、そのウェイトは高くはなかった）紀伝道が台頭してきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, when it entered the 9th century, the position of Myogyodo was lowered and Kidendo, handling the official history and the Chinese-style poetry (they learned Confucianism, too, but its ratio was not very high), became popular.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処置です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, when it entered the 9th century, the position of Myogyodo was lowered and Kidendo, which handled the official history and Chinese-style poetry (they learned Confucianism, too, but its ratio was not very high), became popular.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, when it entered the ninth century, the position of Myogyodo was lowered and Kidendo, which handled the official history and Chinese-style poetry (they learned Confucianism, too, but its ratio was not very high), became popular.</e>
<cmt>スペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>それに加えて、遣唐使の廃止によって国風文化が台頭するようになると、貴族社会を中心に仏教崇敬の風潮が強まって大学寮の教官や学生の間でも授業を離れれば、密教や新興の浄土教などに深い関心を寄せるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to that, when the Kokufu Bunka (Japan&apos;s original national culture) became popular by the abolition of the Kento-shi (Japanese envoy to the Tang Dynasty), a trend to worship Buddhism began to spread mainly in the aristocratic society, pulling the strong interests of the teachers and the students of Daigakuryo to Esoteric Buddhism and the Jodo (Pure Land) sect, a sect which was emerging at the time, when they were away from their classes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to this, when Kokufu Bunka (Japan&apos;s original national culture) became popular with the abolition of Kento-shi (Japanese envoy to the Tang Dynasty), a trend to worship Buddhism began to spread mainly in the aristocratic society, strongly interesting the teachers and the students of Daigakuryo to Esoteric Buddhism and the Jodo (Pure Land) sect, a sect which was emerging at the time, once they were away from their classes.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to this, when Kokufu Bunka (Japan&apos;s original national culture) became popular with the abolition of Kento-shi (Japanese envoy to the Tang Dynasty), a trend to worship Buddhism began to spread mainly in the aristocratic society, strongly interesting the teachers and the students of Daigakuryo to Esoteric Buddhism and the Jodo (Pure Land) sect, a sect which was emerging at the time, once they were away from their classes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>これに対して、8世紀には大学寮において一部ながら見られ、『経国集』などによって今日でも見ることが出来る儒教的見地からの仏教批判はすっかり影を潜めるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In opposition, the criticism against Buddhism from the Confucianism side of view, which could have partly be seen in Daigakuryo in the 8th century, and can still be seen today in historical sources such as &quot;Keikokushu,&quot; had eclipsed totally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In opposition to this, criticism against Buddhism from the Confucianism side of view, which could partly be seen in Daigakuryo in the 8th century, and can still be seen today in historical sources such as &quot;Keikokushu,&quot; became completely eclipsed.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In opposition to this, criticism against Buddhism from the Confucianism side of view, which could partly be seen in Daigakuryo in the eighth century, and can still be seen today in historical sources such as &quot;Keikokushu&quot; (A collection of managing the country) became completely eclipsed.</e>
<cmt>スペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>第1期勧学会</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 1st period of Kangakue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 1st period of Kangakue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first period of Kangakue</e>
<cmt>スペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>最初の勧学会とされているのは、応和4年（康保元年）3月15日に比叡山西麓の月林寺（廃寺、現在の曼殊院付近）あるいはその近くにあった親林寺（廃寺）で開かれたものとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The meeting which is regarded as the first Kangakue was held at Getsurin-ji Temple (abolished temple, around present-day Manshu-in Temple) at the western foot of Hiei-zan Mountain, or at Shinrin-ji Temple (abolished temple) which stood nearby.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The meeting which is regarded as the first Kangakue was held at Getsurin-ji Temple (an abolished temple, around present-day Manshu-in Temple) at the western foot of Hiei-zan Mountain, or at Shinrin-ji Temple (abolished temple) which stood nearby.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The meeting which is regarded as the first Kangakue was held at Getsurin-ji Temple (an abolished temple, around present-day Manshu-in Temple) at the western foot of Mt. Hiei, or at Shinrin-ji Temple (abolished temple) which stood nearby.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>主な参加者は慶滋保胤・藤原在国（後の藤原有国）・橘倚平・高階積善ら紀伝学生らで延暦寺側の参加者については不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main participants from the students of Kidendo were YOSHISHIGE no Yasutane, FUJIWARA no Arikuni (later FUJIWARA no Arikuni), TACHIBANA no Yorihira, and TAKASHINA no Moriyoshi, and the participants from Enryaku-ji Temple are not known.</e>
<cmt>藤原在国は読みが変わってないので訳文では名前が重複しています</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main participants from the students of Kidendo were YOSHISHIGE no Yasutane, FUJIWARA no Arikuni (later FUJIWARA no Arikuni), TACHIBANA no Yorihira, and TAKASHINA no Moriyoshi, but the participants from Enryaku-ji Temple are unknown.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main participants from the students of Kidendo were YOSHISHIGE no Yasutane, FUJIWARA no Arikuni (藤原在国, later FUJIWARA no Arikuni (藤原有国)), TACHIBANA no Yorihira, and TAKASHINA no Moriyoshi, but the participants from Enryaku-ji Temple are unknown.</e>
<cmt>同じ読みの漢字を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>後に大江以言らも参加して20年ほど続けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, OE no Mochitoki and others had joined, and the Kangakue continued for about 20 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, OE no Mochitoki and others joined, and the Kangakue continued for about 20 years.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, OE no Mochitoki and others joined, and the Kangakue continued for about 20 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>『本朝文粋』に所収された参加者の漢詩などによって勧学会の様子が垣間見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People can catch a glimpse of how the Kangakue took place through the Chinese-style poems made by the participants, recorded in &quot;Honcho monzui.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People can catch a glimpse of how the Kangakue took place through the Chinese-style poems composed by the participants, recorded in &quot;Honcho monzui.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People can catch a glimpse of how the Kangakue took place through the Chinese-style poems composed by the participants, recorded in &quot;Honcho monzui&quot; (Anthology of waka poems and prose written in classical Chinese).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また、『三宝絵詞』には会の詳細な様子が描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in &quot;Sanboekotoba,&quot; thorough details of the meeting are written.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">tthorough details of the meeting were written. in &quot;Sanboekotoba.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thorough details of the meeting were written in &quot;Sanpo-ekotoba&quot; (a Japanese literary collection of Buddhist narratives).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>同書によれば、開催日前日の14日夕方に延暦寺の僧侶が下山して会場となる寺院を訪問し、学生ら俗世側の参加者は予め会場に集って詩句や経文を誦しながら僧侶の来訪を待つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the same book, the priests of Enryaku-ji Temple came down from the mountain in the evening of the 14th day of the month, a day before the opening day of the Kangakue, to visit the temple in which the Kangakue will take place, and the participants of the common people&apos;s side, such as students, gathered at the site in advance, waiting for the visit of the priests by making poems and reading sutras.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the same book, the priests of Enryaku-ji Temple came down from the mountain in the evening of the 14th day of the month, a day before the opening day of the Kangakue, to visit the temple in which the Kangakue would take place, and the participants of the common people&apos;s side, such as students, gathered at the site in advance, and passed the time by composing poems and reading sutras while waiting for the priests to visit</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the same book, the priests of Enryaku-ji Temple came down from the mountain in the evening of the 14th day of the month, a day before the opening day of the Kangakue, to visit the temple in which the Kangakue would take place, and the participants of the common people&apos;s side, such as students, gathered at the site in advance, and passed the time by composing poems and reading sutras while waiting for the priests to visit</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>勧学会初日の15日は朝から『法華経』の購読を行い、夕方に弥陀を念じ（阿弥陀の名前を唱える）、夜は仏教の功徳を称える漢詩を作成する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the first day of the Kangakue, or the 15th day of the month, they read &quot;Hokekyo&quot; in the morning, made invocation of Mida (reciting of the name of Amida Buddha) in the evening, and made Chinese-style poems, admiring the merit of Buddhism, at night.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the first day of the Kangakue, or the 15th day of the month, they read &quot;Hokekyo&quot; in the morning, made invocation of Mida (reciting of the name of Amida Buddha) in the evening, and made Chinese-style poems, admiring the merit of Buddhism, at night.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the first day of the Kangakue, or the 15th day of the month, they read &quot;Hokekyo&quot; in the morning, made invocation of Mida (reciting of the name of Amida Buddha) in the evening, and made Chinese-style poems, admiring the merit of Buddhism, at night.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>その後、俗側は白楽天（儒教的教養の持ち主ながら仏教を擁護した）の詩を、僧側は『法華経』を朗読して夜を明かし、翌16日朝に解散したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, they spent the night with the common people reading poems by Hakurakuten (or Bai Letian, he defended Buddhism, even though he was cultivated with Confucianism) and the priests reading &quot;Hokekyo,&quot; and they were dispersed at the morning of the next day, the 16th day of the month.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, they spent the night with common people reading poems by Hakurakuten (or Bai Letian, he defended Buddhism, even though he was cultivated with Confucianism) and priests who read &quot;Hokekyo,&quot; after which they were dispersed in the morning of the next day, the 16th day of the month.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, they spent the night with common people reading poems by Hakurakuten (or Bai Letian, he defended Buddhism, even though he was cultivated with Confucianism) and priests who read &quot;Hokekyo,&quot; after which they were dispersed in the morning of the next day, the 16th day of the month.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>また、『本朝文粋』には天延2年（979年）から翌年にかけて参加者が勧学会を開くための会場となる念仏堂建立を計画していたことが記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in &quot;Honcho monzui,&quot; it is recorded that in 979 through the next year, the participants of Kangakue had planned to construct a Nenbutsu-do Hall (hall to make nenbutsu) as a site to conduct Kangakue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also in &quot;Honcho monzui,&quot; it is recorded that in 979 through the next year, the participants of Kangakue had planned to construct a Nenbutsu-do Hall (hall to make nenbutsu) as a site to conduct Kangakue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also in &quot;Honcho monzui,&quot; it is recorded that in 979 through the next year, the participants of Kangakue had planned to construct a Nenbutsu-do Hall (hall to make nenbutsu) as a site to conduct Kangakue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>だが、資力不足から計画は挫折し、更に主導的な立場にあった慶滋保胤が寛和2年（986年）に出家して、俗界の行事であった勧学会から離脱した事から自然消滅したと見られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the plan was frustrated from the lack of funds, and since YOSHISHIGE no Yasutane, who was at the position as the leader of the plan, became as a priest in 986 and left from Kangakue since it was an event for the common people, the plan itself seems to have been disappeared as a natural result.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the plan was in limbo due to a lack of funds, and since YOSHISHIGE no Yasutane, who was in the position of being leader of the plan, became a priest in 986 and left Kangakue due to its being an event for the common people, the plan itself seemed to have naturally disappeared as a result.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the plan was in limbo due to a lack of funds, and since YOSHISHIGE no Yasutane, who was in the position of being leader of the plan, became a priest in 986 and left Kangakue due to its being an event for the common people, the plan itself seemed to have naturally disappeared as a result.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>なお、再開された最初の勧学会に参加した第1期参加者の藤原有国の漢詩（「世尊大恩」）と高階積善の詩序に中断期間が19年間であったことが明記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it is recorded clearly in the Chinese-style poem by FUJIWARA no Arikuni (&apos;Seson Daion&apos;) and in the preface of the poem by TAKASHINA no Moriyoshi, who were both the participants of the first Kangakue which was resumed and also were the participants of the very first Kangakue, that the length of the period of a blank of Kangakue was 19 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, it is recorded clearly in the Chinese-style poem by FUJIWARA no Arikuni (&apos;Seson Daion&apos;) and in the preface of the poem by TAKASHINA no Moriyoshi, who were both participants at the first Kangakue which was resumed and also were participants at the very first Kangakue, that the Kangakue was put on hold for 19 years.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, it is recorded clearly in the Chinese-style poem (&apos;Seson Daion&apos;) by FUJIWARA no Arikuni and in the preface of the poem by TAKASHINA no Moriyoshi, who were both participants at the first Kangakue which was resumed and also were participants at the very first Kangakue, that the Kangakue was put on hold for 19 years.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>この期間については永観2年（984年、『三宝絵詞』の作成年）から正暦3年（992年）、終期を長保5年（1003年）から寛弘8年（1011年、勧学会再興に尽力した藤原有国の没年）までの間のうちの19年間と考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for that period of a blank, it is believed that it was the 19 years starting in 984 (year in which &quot;Sanboekotoba&quot; was written) through 992, and ending in 1003 though 1011 (year of the death of FUJIWARA no Arikuni, who have put effort in the revival of Kangakue).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that the 19 years started in 984 (year in which &quot;Sanboekotoba&quot; was written) through 992, and ending in 1003 though 1011 (year of the death of FUJIWARA no Arikuni, who have put effort in the revival of Kangakue).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that the 19 years started in 984 (year in which &quot;Sanpo-ekotoba&quot; was written) through 992, and ending in 1003 though 1011 (year of the death of FUJIWARA no Arikuni, who have put effort in the revival of Kangakue).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>第2期勧学会</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 2nd period of Kangakue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 2nd period of Kangakue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second period of Kangakue</e>
<cmt>スペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>第2期の開始年代は不明であるが、寛弘年間（1004年以後）に再興されたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The year in which the second period of Kangakue had started is not known for sure, but it is believed that it had restarted in the Kanko era (after 1004).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year in which the second period of Kangakue had started is not known for sure, but it is believed that it was restarted in the Kanko era (after 1004).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year in which the second period of Kangakue had started is not known for sure, but it is believed that it was restarted in the Kanko era (after 1004).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>『本朝文粋』には月林寺が既に荒廃してしまい、代わりの会場探しに手間取る参加者のために左大臣藤原道長が父の藤原兼家が建てた法興院を会場として提供したことが記録されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Honcho monzui,&quot; it is recorded that since Getsurin-ji Temple had already been abolished, Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) FUJIWARA no Michinaga offered Hoko-in Temple, a temple established by his father, FUJIWARA no Kaneie, as a site for Kangakue, for the participants having trouble with finding a site to open Kangakue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Honcho monzui,&quot; it is recorded that since Getsurin-ji Temple had already been abolished, Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) FUJIWARA no Michinaga offered Hoko-in Temple, a temple established by his father, FUJIWARA no Kaneie, as a site for Kangakue, for participants that were having trouble finding a site to hold Kangakue.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Honcho monzui,&quot; it is recorded that since Getsurin-ji Temple had already been abolished, Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) FUJIWARA no Michinaga offered Hoko-in Temple, a temple established by his father, FUJIWARA no Kaneie, as a site for Kangakue, for participants that were having trouble finding a site to hold Kangakue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>主導的な役割を果たしたのは第1期のメンバーの生存者である藤原有国・高階積善とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that the members in position as the leaders were FUJIWARA no Arikuni and TAKASHINA no Moriyoshi, who were also the members of the first period of Kangakue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that the members in position as the leaders were FUJIWARA no Arikuni and TAKASHINA no Moriyoshi, who were also the members of the first period of Kangakue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that the members in position as the leaders were FUJIWARA no Arikuni and TAKASHINA no Moriyoshi, who were also the members of the first period of Kangakue.</e>
<cmt>スペースをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>ただし、参加者は前回の参加者が主であり記録もほとんどない事から短期間のうちに再度中断されたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since the main members of the participants were the members of the first period of Kangakue and there are almost no record left concerning to this period of Kangakue, it is believed that it had been suspended again in a short period of time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since the main members of the participants were the members of the first period of Kangakue and there are almost no records left concerning this period of Kangakue, it is believed that it was suspended again in a short period of time.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since the main members of the participants were the members of the first period of Kangakue and there are almost no records left concerning this period of Kangakue, it is believed that it was suspended again in a short period of time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>第3期勧学会</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 3rd period of Kangakue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 3rd period of Kangakue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The third period of Kangakue</e>
<cmt>スペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>ところが、長元年間に入ると突如として従来学生らに招かれる立場であった比叡山側からの呼びかけによって再興される事となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when it enters the Chogen era, Kangakue was suddenly restarted by the call from Hiei-zan Mountain side, even though until then, priests in Hiei-zan were being invited by the students.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, during the Chogen era, Kangakue was suddenly restarted by the Hiei-zan Mountain, even though until then, priests in Hiei-zan were invited by the students.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, during 1028 and 1036, Kangakue was suddenly restarted by Mt. Hiei, even though until then, priests in Mt. Hiei were invited by the students.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>この時随願寺にて再興された勧学会に参加した菅原定義（『更級日記』に登場する「兄」として著名）の詩序（『本朝続文粋』）によれば、天台座主慶命の呼びかけであったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the preface of the poem (&quot;Honcho Zoku Monzui &quot;) by SUGAWARA no Sadanori (he is famous for being the &apos;older brother&apos; in &quot;Sarashina Nikki&quot;), who had participated in the Kangakue restarted at Zuigan-ji Temple, the Kangakue was being held by the call of Keimyo, the Tendai-zasu (head priest of the Tendai sect) at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the preface of the poem (&quot;Honcho Zoku Monzui &quot;) by SUGAWARA no Sadanori (he is famous for being the &apos;older brother&apos; in &quot;Sarashina Nikki&quot;), who had participated in the Kangakue restarted at Zuigan-ji Temple, the Kangakue was being held by the call of Keimyo, the Tendai-zasu (head priest of the Tendai sect) at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the preface of the poem (&quot;Honcho Zoku Monzui&quot; (Literary Essence of Our Court, Continued)) by SUGAWARA no Sadanori (he was famous for being the &apos;older brother&apos; in &quot;Sarashina Nikki&quot; (The Sarashina Diary)), who had participated in the Kangakue restarted at Zuigan-ji Temple, the Kangakue was being held by the call of Keimyo, the Tendai-zasu (head priest of the Tendai sect) at that time.</e>
<cmt>用語集より補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>慶命は第2期勧学会再興の中心であった藤原有国の甥（兄の子）で、長元元年（1028年）に天台座主に補されて同年間中は一貫してその地位にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keimyo was a nephew (old brother&apos;s son) of FUJIWARA no Arikuni, who was the main person in restarting of the second period of Kangakue, and in 1028, he was appointed as the Tendai-zasu and held that post throughout that year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keimyo was a nephew (old brother&apos;s son) of FUJIWARA no Arikuni, who was the main person responsible for restarting the second period of Kangakue, and in 1028, he was appointed as the Tendai-zasu and held that post throughout that year.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keimyo was a nephew (old brother&apos;s son) of FUJIWARA no Arikuni, who was the main person responsible for restarting the second period of Kangakue, and in 1028, he was appointed as the Tendai-zasu and held that post throughout that year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>従ってかつての勧学会に関わりがあったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, it is believed that he was related to Kangakue in the past.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, it is believed that he was related to Kangakue in the past.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, it is believed that he was related to Kangakue in the past.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>この時の勧学会は末法思想の高まりなどもあって比較的長期にわたって続けられ、断続的であるが勧学会関係の出来事も確認できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because the Mappo-shiso (the &quot;end of the world&quot; belief) became popular in this period of time, Kangakue was held for comparatively long period, and some events relating to Kangakue can be confirmed, intermittently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the Mappo-shiso (the &quot;end of the world&quot; belief) became popular in this period of time, Kangakue was held for a comparatively long period, and some events relating to Kangakue can be confirmed, intermittently.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the Mappo-shiso (the &quot;end of the world&quot; belief) became popular in this period of time, Kangakue was held for a comparatively long period, and some events relating to Kangakue can be confirmed, intermittently.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>永承元年（1046年）に大宰権帥となった藤原経通は、安楽寺の僧である基円（菅原定義の弟）と図って安楽寺で二季勧学会を始めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tsunemichi, who became as a Dazai gon no sochi (Provisional Governor-General of the Dazai-fu offices) in 1046, along with Kien (younger brother of SUGAWARA no Sadanori), who was a priest of Anraku-ji Temple, planned and started Niki Kangakue at Anraku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>二季勧学会→定訳不明です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Tsunemichi, who became a Dazai gon no sochi (Provisional Governor-General of the Dazai-fu offices) in 1046, along with Kien (younger brother of SUGAWARA no Sadanori), who was a priest of Anraku-ji Temple, planned and started Niki Kangakue at Anraku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tsunemichi, who became a Dazai gon no sochi (Provisional Governor-General of the Dazai-fu offices) in 1046, along with Kien (younger brother of SUGAWARA no Sadanori), who was a priest of Anraku-ji Temple, planned and started Niki (second) Kangakue at Anraku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>経通は文芸的には知られていないものの、勧学会の参加者であった可能性はある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In records, Tsunemichi can&apos;t be recognized as a participant of the Kangakue, but there is a possibility that he was a participant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In records, Tsunemichi can&apos;t be recognized as a participant of the Kangakue, but there is a possibility that he was a participant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In records, Tsunemichi can&apos;t be recognized as a participant of the Kangakue, but there is a possibility that he was a participant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>さらに延久3年3月15日（1071年4月17日）に雲林院で開催された勧学会は、『勧学会之記』として記録が編纂された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further in a Kangakue held on April 17, 1071 at Urin-in Temple, a record was compiled as &quot;Kangakue no ki.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further in a Kangakue held on April 17, 1071 at Urin-in Temple, a record was compiled as &quot;Kangakue no ki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further in a Kangakue held on April 23, 1071 at Urin-in Temple, a record was compiled as &quot;Kangakue no ki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>なお、この時藤原成季の提案により勧学会用の『法華経』を予め整備したという（『朝野群戴』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, in that Kangakue, it is said that a &quot;Hokekyo&quot; for the Kangakue was prepared by a proposal by FUJIWARA no Narisue (&quot;Choyagunsai&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, during this Kangakue, it is said that a &quot;Hokekyo&quot; for the Kangakue was prepared through a proposal by FUJIWARA no Narisue (&quot;Choyagunsai&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, during this Kangakue, it is said that a &quot;Hokekyo&quot; for the Kangakue was prepared through a proposal by FUJIWARA no Narisue (&quot;Choya Gunsai&quot; (Classified Records of Court and Country)).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>承暦4年（1080年）3月29日 (旧暦)には六波羅蜜寺で勧学会が開かれているが、以後同寺が勧学会会場として確定する一方で、毎年3月もしくは9月の15日と定められていた開催日が記録上初めて破られており、以後開催日の遅延が続く事になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 27, 1080, a Kangakue was held in Rokuharamitsu-ji Temple, making the temple as the site of Kangakue that would follow in the future, too, but the rule for the opening day of Kangakue, which was decided as the 15th day of March or September, was broken for the first time in records, and the delays of the opening day of Kangakue were continued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 27, 1080, a Kangakue was held in Rokuharamitsu-ji Temple, making the temple the site of Kangakue in the future, but the rule for the opening day of Kangakue, which was decided to be the 15th day of March or September, was broken for the first time, and the opening day of Kangakue continued to be delayed.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 27, 1080, a Kangakue was held in Rokuharamitsu-ji Temple, making the temple the site of Kangakue in the future, but the rule for the opening day of Kangakue, which was decided to be the 15th day of March or September, was broken for the first time, and the opening day of Kangakue continued to be delayed.</e>
<cmt>スペースをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>以後、寛治2年（1088年）、天永2年（1111年）及び3年（1112年）、永久 (日本)4年（1116年）及び5年（1117年）に六波羅蜜寺で開催された記録が残されている（記録が残されていない年も中絶したとする記録がないため、続行されていたと考えられている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, there are records remaining which state that Kangakue were held at Rokuharamitsu-ji Temple in 1088, 1111, 1112, 1116, and 1117 (since there are no records telling that there were any suspension in the years which are not recorded as the years of Kangakue, it is believed that Kangakue was continued in those years, too).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, there are records remaining which state that Kangakue were held at Rokuharamitsu-ji Temple in 1088, 1111, 1112, 1116, and 1117 (since there are no records of any suspension occuring during the years which were not recorded as having held Kangakue, it is believed that Kangakue continued to be held during those years as well.)</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, there are records remaining which state that Kangakue were held at Rokuharamitsu-ji Temple in 1088, 1111, 1112, 1116, and 1117 (since there are no records of any suspension occurring during the years which were not recorded as having held Kangakue, it is believed that Kangakue continued to be held during those years as well).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>だが、次第に内容が形式化していった事は否めず、旧儀が再興されたと言われている延久3年の勧学会でも3月15日の未の刻より亥の刻までと、本来の3日（実質2日）がかりの行事がわずか半日で終了している（形式化が進んだ以後の勧学会は更に時間も内容も削られていったと考えられている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it can&apos;t be denied that the content of Kangakue was gradually formalized, and even in the Kangakue held in 1071, which is said to be a Kangakue in which old customs were revived, an event was only held for half a day, from 2p.m. through 10p.m., even though originally, it should be held for 3 days (actually, 2 days) (it is believed that as the formalization advanced, the period and content of Kangakue was reduced, too).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it can&apos;t be denied that the content of Kangakue was gradually formalized, and even in the Kangakue held in 1071, which is said to be a Kangakue in which old customs were revived, an event was only held for half a day, from 2p.m. through 10p.m., even though originally, it should be held for 3 days (actually, 2 days) (it is believed that as the formalization advanced, the period and content of Kangakue was reduced, too).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it can&apos;t be denied that the content of Kangakue was gradually formalized, and even in the Kangakue held in 1071, which is said to be a Kangakue in which old customs were revived, an event was only held for half a day, from 2 p.m. through 10 p.m., even though originally, it should be held for three days (actually, two days) (it is believed that as the formalization advanced, the period and content of Kangakue was reduced, too).</e>
<cmt>スペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>また、参加者も先達と呼ばれる経験者、しかもかつては学生でも今では式部大輔や大学頭、文章博士といった学生たちから見れば「雲の上」的存在の人々が多くを占めるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, the ratio of the participants who have experienced Kangakue in the past, who are called Sendatsu, became greater, and those people now held positions such as Shikibu no taifu (Senior Assistant Minister of the Ministry of Ceremonial), Daigaku no kami (Director of the Bureau of Education), and Monjo hakase (professor of literature), which are positions which are &apos;high above the sky&apos; if seen from students, even though those Sendatsu were students back then.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処置です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, the ratio of participants who experienced Kangakue in the past, who were called Sendatsu, increased, and those people came to hold positions such as Shikibu no taifu (Senior Assistant Minister of the Ministry of Ceremonial), Daigaku no kami (Director of the Bureau of Education), and Monjo hakase (professor of literature), which were positions that were &apos;high above the sky&apos; if seen from students, even though those Sendatsu were students back then.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, the ratio of participants who experienced Kangakue in the past, who were called Sendatsu, increased, and those people came to hold positions such as Shikibu no taifu (Senior Assistant Minister of the Ministry of Ceremonial), Daigaku no kami (Director of the Bureau of Education), and Monjo hakase (professor of literature), which were positions that were &apos;high above the sky&apos; if seen from students, even though those Sendatsu were students back then.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>さらに、結学生と呼ばれた学生参加者が少なくなったために円滑な世代交代が行われにくくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, since the student participants, who were called 結学生, became less, it became difficult to transit power between generations.</e>
<cmt>結学生→読み不明です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, since the student participants, who were called 結学生, decreased, it became difficult to pass power between generations.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, since the student participants, who were called Ketsugakusei (結学生), decreased, it became difficult to pass power between generations.</e>
<cmt>想定される読みを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>やがて保安 (日本)3年（1122年）3月某日に六波羅蜜寺で行われた勧学会を最後に以後記録上から姿を消すことになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before long, on a day in March 1122, the last Kangakue on records was held in Rokuharamitsu-ji Temple, and no records of Kangakue can be seen from then.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before long, one day in March 1122, the last Kangakue on record was held in Rokuharamitsu-ji Temple, and no records of Kangakue have been found since then.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before long, one day in April 1122, the last Kangakue on record was held in Rokuharamitsu-ji Temple, and no records of Kangakue have been found since then.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Influence</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Influence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Influence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="40">
<j>勧学会は主に紀伝道と天台宗（延暦寺）の人々を中心とする行事であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kangakue was an event held mainly by people of Kidendo and Tendai sect (Enryaku-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処置です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kangakue was an event held mainly by people of the Kidendo and Tendai sect (Enryaku-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kangakue was an event held mainly by people of the Kidendo and Tendai sect (Enryaku-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>これに対して平安時代後期には儒教教育の中心であったはずの明経道の学生の間にも同様の動きが発生して、勧学会と同日に清水寺において長講会と呼ばれる法会が開かれるようになったことが藤原為房の『撰集秘記』に書かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Against that, in the latter period of the Heian period, it is written in &quot;Senju-hiki&quot; by FUJIWARA no Tamefusa that a similar movement arose among the students of Myogyodo, which once was the center of Confucian education, and a Buddhist meeting called Chokoe was held at Kiyomizu-dera Temple on the same day with Kangakue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the latter period of the Heian period, it was written in &quot;Senju-hiki&quot; by FUJIWARA no Tamefusa that a similar movement rose among the students of Myogyodo, which once was the center of Confucian education, and a Buddhist meeting called Chokoe was held at Kiyomizu-dera Temple on the same day with Kangakue.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the latter period of the Heian period, it was written in &quot;Senju-hiki&quot; (literally, collection of secret records) by FUJIWARA no Tamefusa that a similar movement rose among the students of Myogyodo, which once was the center of Confucian education, and a Buddhist meeting called Chogo-e (an Expanding Lecture) was held at Kiyomizu-dera Temple on the same day with Kangakue.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>だが、その詳細については不明な点が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, details of that meeting are not known for sure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, details of that meeting are not known for sure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, details of that meeting are not known for sure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="43">
<j>なお、鎌倉時代以後、寺院内部において僧侶大衆 (仏教)が経典の講義を行う勧学会あるいは勧学講と呼ばれる儀式が有力寺院を中心に行われるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, in and after the Kamakura period, ceremonies called Kangakue and Kangakuko, in which teaching of sutras was being held by a group of priests, were began to be held mainly in powerful temples (as a representative example, a ceremony held by Jien, the Tendai-zasu at that time, of Enryaku-ji Temple in 1195 is famous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, in and after the Kamakura period, ceremonies called Kangakue and Kangakuko, in which teaching of sutras were held by a group of priests, began to be held in powerful temples (as an example, a ceremony held by Jien, the Tendai-zasu at that time, of Enryaku-ji Temple in 1195 is particularly famous.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, in and after the Kamakura period, ceremonies called Kangakue and Kangakuko, in which teaching of sutras were held by a group of priests, began to be held in powerful temples.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="44">
<j>（代表的なものに延暦寺の天台座主慈円が建久6年（1195年）に始めたものが著名。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, in and after the Kamakura period, ceremonies called Kangakue and Kangakuko, in which teaching of sutras was being held by a group of priests, were began to be held mainly in powerful temples (as a representative example, a ceremony held by Jien, the Tendai-zasu at that time, of Enryaku-ji Temple in 1195 is famous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, in and after the Kamakura period, ceremonies called Kangakue and Kangakuko, in which teaching of sutras were held by a group of priests, began to be held in powerful temples (as an example, a ceremony held by Jien, the Tendai-zasu at that time, of Enryaku-ji Temple in 1195 is particularly famous.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(As an example, a ceremony held by Jien, the Tendai-zasu at that time, of Enryaku-ji Temple in 1195 is particularly famous.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。分割し、かっこを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>（他にも金剛峯寺・仁和寺・東寺・醍醐寺・法隆寺などにも同様の行事が見られた）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than that, similar events were held in Kongobu-ji Temple, Ninna-ji Temple, To-ji Temple, Daigo-ji Temple, Horyu-ji Temple, and so on.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than that, similar events were held in Kongobu-ji Temple, Ninna-ji Temple, To-ji Temple, Daigo-ji Temple, Horyu-ji Temple, and so on.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Other than that, similar events were held in Kongobu-ji Temple, Ninna-ji Temple, To-ji Temple, Daigo-ji Temple, Horyu-ji Temple, and so on.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。分割し、かっこを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>だが、これらの行事に世俗からの参加者は見られず、平安時代の勧学会とは無関係あるいは極めて希薄なものであったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However in these events, participants from the common people can&apos;t be seen, which can be thought that it had little or no relationship with the Kangakue in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However in these events, participants from the common people can&apos;t be seen, which is thought to show that it had little or no relationship with the Kangakue in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However in these events, participants from the common people can&apos;t be seen, which is thought to show that it had little or no relationship with the Kangakue in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Straysheep(id:42448), КОЛЯ(id:59429), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>