<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>文観</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monkan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Monkan</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Monkan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>文観（もんかん、弘安元年（1278年） - 正平 (日本)12年/延文2年10月9日 (旧暦)（1357年11月21日））は、鎌倉時代から南北朝時代の僧である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monkan (1278-October 9th in 1357 (old lunar calendar) (November 21st in 1357)) was a priest who lived from Kamakura Period to Nambokucho Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Monkan (1278-October 9th, 1357 (old lunar calendar) (November 21st, 1357)) was a priest who lived from the Kamakura Period to the Nambokucho Period.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Monkan (1278 - November 29, 1357) was a priest who lived from the Kamakura period to the period of the Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し、用語を統一しました。。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>小野僧正。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ono Sojo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ono Sojo</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ono Sojo.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>殊音、弘真。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shuon, Koshin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shuon, Koshin.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shuon, Koshin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>醍醐寺座主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the head priest of Daigo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the head priest of Daigo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the head priest of Daigo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>1302年（正安2）には般若寺の律宗の僧で、西大寺 (奈良市)に属する播磨国北条常楽寺（兵庫県加古川市）、大和国笠山竹山寺（奈良県桜井市笠）などで真言律を学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1302 he was a priest of Risshu sect at Hannya-ji Temple and learned Shingonritsu at the related temples of Saidai-ji Temple such as Hojo Joraku-ji Temple in Harima Province (Kakogawa City Hyogo Prefecture) and Kasayama Chikuzan-ji Temple in Yamato Province (Kasa Sakurai City Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1302 he was a priest of the Risshu sect at Hannya-ji Temple and learned Shingonritsu at temples related to Saidai-ji Temple such as Hojo Joraku-ji Temple in Harima Province (Kakogawa City, Hyogo Prefecture) and Kasayama Chikuzan-ji Temple in Yamato Province (Kasa Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1302, he was a priest of the Risshu sect at Hannya-ji Temple and learned Shingonritsu at temples related to Saidai-ji Temple (Nara City) such as Hojo Joraku-ji Temple in Harima Province (Kakogawa City, Hyogo Prefecture) and Kasayama Chikuzan-ji Temple in Yamato Province (Kasa, Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>（奈良市）などを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>1316年に醍醐寺報恩院の道順から灌頂を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1316 he was given Kanjo (conferred the basic precepts and mystic teachings of esoteric Buddhism) by Dojun of Daigo-ji Temple Hoon-in.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1316 he was given Kanjo (conferred the basic precepts and mystic teachings of esoteric Buddhism) by Dojun of Daigo-ji Temple Hoon-in.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1316, he was given Kanjo (conferred the basic precepts and mystic teachings of esoteric Buddhism) by Dojun of Hoonin, Daigo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>順序を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>邪教とされていた真言宗立川流 (密教)の僧としても知られ、円観（恵鎮）とともに遁世僧で貧民救済なども行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is also known as a priest of Shingon sect Tachikawa-ryu (Mikkyo, Esoteric Buddhism) which was considered as a bad religion, and he was a priest who renounced the world d and relieved the poor with Enkan (Echin).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is also known as a priest of the Shingon sect Tachikawa-ryu (Mikkyo, Esoteric Buddhism) which was considered as a bad religion, and he was a priest who renounced the world and relieved the poor with Enkan (Echin).</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also known as a priest of Tachikawa school (Mikkyo, Esoteric Buddhism), the Shingon sect, which was considered as a heretical religion, and he was a priest who renounced the world and relieved the poor with Enkan (Echin).</e>
<cmt>過去形にし、用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>後醍醐天皇に重用されて醍醐寺座主・天王寺別当となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was taken into confidence by Emperor Godaigo and assumed the head priest of Daigo-ji Temple and Betto of Tenno-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was taken into confidence by Emperor Godaigo and assumed the role of head priest of Daigo-ji Temple and Betto of Tenno-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was taken into confidence by Emperor Godaigo and assumed the role of the head priest of Daigo-ji Temple and Betto (the superior of a temple) of Tenno-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>1324年（元亨4）には般若寺に文殊菩薩像を造り、1326年から後醍醐中宮藤原禧子の御産祈願と称して鎌倉幕府の調伏などを行っていた事が発覚し、1331年（元徳2）には逮捕され硫黄島 (鹿児島県)へ流罪となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1324 he made the statue of Monju Bosatsu at Hannya-ji Temple and it was brought to light that he had implemented rituals to destroy Kamakura Shogunate in nominal terms of wish for an easy delivery by FUJIWARA no Kishi, the Empress of Godaigo, since 1326, so that he was arrested in 1331 and was sentenced to deportation to Io-jima Island (Kagoshima Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1324 he made the statue of Monju Bosatsu at Hannya-ji Temple and it was brought to light that he had implemented rituals to attempt to destroy the Kamakura Shogunate, by FUJIWARA no Kishi, the Empress of Godaigo from 1326, so he was arrested in 1331 and was sentenced to deportation to Io-jima Island (Kagoshima Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1324, he made the statue of Monju Bosatsu (Manjusri Bodhisattva associated with wisdom, doctrine and awareness) at Hannya-ji Temple and it was brought to light that he had implemented rituals to attempt to destroy the Kamakura Shogunate, by FUJIWARA no Kishi, chugu (the second consort of an emperor) of Godaigo from 1326, so he was arrested in 1331 and was sentenced to deportation to Io-jima Island (Kagoshima Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>用語補足などをしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>1333年（正慶2/元弘3）に元弘の変の後に鎌倉幕府が滅亡すると京都へ戻り、建武の新政から南北朝時代となっても後醍醐方に属して吉野へ随行し、東寺長者、大僧正となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Kamakura Shogunate was subverted after Genko no hen (the Genko Incident) in 1333, he went back to Kyoto, and he also moved to Yoshino in attendance on Godaigo and became Chief abbot of To-ji Temple and Daisojo, high priest, during Nambokucho Period after Kenmu Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Kamakura Shogunate was subverted after Genko no hen (the Genko Incident) in 1333, he went back to Kyoto, and he also moved to Yoshino in attendance of Godaigo and became Chief Abbot of To-ji Temple and Daisojo, high priest, during the Nambokucho Period after the Kenmu Restoration.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Kamakura Shogunate was subverted after the Genko Incident in 1333, he went back to Kyoto, and he also moved to Yoshino in attendance of Godaigo and became Chief Abbot of To-ji Temple and daisojo (a Buddhist priest of the highest order).</e>
<cmt>用語表現などを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>河内国天野山金剛寺 (河内長野市)（大阪府河内長野市）で没、享年80。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at Amano-san Kongo-ji Temple in Kawachi Province (Kawachinagano City Osaka Prefecture) at the age of 80.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at Amano-san Kongo-ji Temple in Kawachi Province (Kawachinagano City, Osaka Prefecture) at the age of 80.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at Kongo-ji Temple on Mt. Amano in Kawachi Province (Kawachinagano City, Osaka Prefecture) at the age of 80.</e>
<cmt>用語を他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>日野俊基の抜擢や河内の悪党として知られる楠木正成と後醍醐天皇を仲介した人物とも考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also considered to promote Toshimoto HINO and to intermediate between Masashige KUSUNOKI, who was known as Akuto (a villain in the medieval times) in Kawachi, and Emperor Godaigo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also considered as having promoted Toshimoto HINO and to mediate between Masashige KUSUNOKI, who was known as Akuto (a villain in medieval times) in Kawachi, and Emperor Godaigo.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also considered as having promoted Toshimoto HINO and to mediate between Masashige KUSUNOKI, who was known as Akuto (a villain in medieval times) in Kawachi, and Emperor Godaigo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), Oxhop(id:2551), Rusk(id:9895), Natunohi(id:6550), Yonoemon(id:55450), Lombroso(id:20212), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), Law soma(id:45202), Wei Yuan(id:13342), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), 無空(id:17049), Toki-ho(id:10691), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>