<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>阿野全成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zenjo/Zensei ANO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zenjo/Zensei ANO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zenjo (or Zensei) ANO</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>阿野 全成（あの ぜんじょう／ぜんせい、仁平3年（1153年） - 建仁3年6月23日 (旧暦)（1203年8月1日））は平安時代末期、鎌倉時代初期の僧で、源義朝の七男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zenjo/Zensei ANO was a person who lived from 1153 (late Heian Period) until August 1, 1203 (early Kamakura Period); he was born the seventh boy of MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo and became a priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zenjo/Zensei ANO was a person who lived from 1153 (late Heian Period) until August 1, 1203 (early Kamakura Period); he was born the seventh boy of MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo and became a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zenjo ANO (1153 - August 8, 1203) was a priest from late Heian period to early Kamakura period and the seventh son of MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo.</e>
<cmt>全成の訳が冗長なので、以降Zenjoとし、表記を他ファイルと合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>阿野法橋全成とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is also known as hokkyo Zenjo/Zensei ANO (the term &quot;hokkyo&quot; refers to the third highest of the three higher court ranks of the priesthood which came to be used in 864, corresponding to the older term &quot;risshi&quot;(superintendent: the third highest grade in the Buddhist hierarchy)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is also known as Hokkyo Zenjo/Zensei ANO (the term &quot;hokkyo&quot; refers to the third highest of the three higher court ranks of the priesthood which came to be used in 864, corresponding to the older term &quot;risshi&quot;(superintendent: the third highest grade in the Buddhist hierarchy)).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also known as Hokkyo (the third highest rank for Buddhist priests) Zenjo (or Zensei) ANO.</e>
<cmt>過去形にし、マイページに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>母は常盤御前。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was Tokiwa Gozen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was Tokiwa Gozen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was Tokiwa Gozen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>幼名・今若丸。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was Imawakamaru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Imawakamaru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Imawakamaru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>義円・源義経の同母兄、源頼朝の異母弟。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gien and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune were his younger brother by the same mother, and MINAMOTO no Yoritomo was his elder brother by a different mother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gien and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune were his younger brothers by the same mother, and MINAMOTO no Yoritomo was his elder brother by a different mother.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gien and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune were his younger brothers by the same mother, and MINAMOTO no Yoritomo was his elder brother by a different mother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>妻は北条時政の娘阿波局 (北条時政の娘)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His wife was Awa no Tsubone (Tokimasa HOJO&apos;s daughter) (the term &quot;tsubone&quot; refers to a court lady).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His wife was Awa no Tsubone (Tokimasa HOJO&apos;s daughter) (the term &quot;tsubone&quot; refers to a court lady).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His wife was Awa no Tsubone (Tokimasa HOJO&apos;s daughter).</e>
<cmt>補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>子は播磨公頼全（はりまのきみよりまさ）、阿野時元、藤原公佐室、他。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His children include: Yorimasa, who served as Harima-no-Kimi (the lord of Harima Province); Tokimoto ANO; the daughter who married FUJIWARA no Kinnari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children include: Yorimasa, who served as Harima-no-Kimi (the lord of Harima Province) and Tokimoto ANO; the daughter who married FUJIWARA no Kinnari.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children included: Harimanokimi (the lord of Harima Province) Yorimasa, and Tokimoto ANO, a wife of FUJIWARA no Kimisuke (藤原公佐室).</e>
<cmt>藤原公佐の読み方が不明なため、漢字を残しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>今若が7歳の平治元年（1159年）、平治の乱で父義朝が敗死したため幼くして醍醐寺にて出家させられ、隆超（または隆起）と名乗り、ほどなく全成と改名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the age of 7 (in 1159), Imawaka&apos;s father Yoshitomo was defeated and died in the Heiji Civil War; consequently, Imawaka was caused to enter the priesthood at Daigo-ji Temple and took the Buddhist name of Ryucho (隆超) (or Ryuki (隆起)), which was changed to Zenjo/Zensei in a little while.</e>
<cmt>隆超→Ryucho (隆超)[読み不明]隆起→Ryuki (隆起)[読み不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the age of 7 (in 1159), Imawaka&apos;s father Yoshitomo was defeated and died in the Heiji Civil War; consequently, Imawaka was forced to enter the priesthood at Daigo-ji Temple and took the Buddhist name of Ryucho (隆超) (or Ryuki (隆起)), which was changed to Zenjo/Zensei after a short while.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Imawaka&apos;s father Yoshitomo was defeated and died in the Heiji War when he was at an early age of 7 in 1159, he was forced to enter the priesthood at Daigo-ji Temple and named himself Ryucho (隆超) (or Ryuki (隆起)), then Zenjo after a short while.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>通称醍醐禅師、もしくはその荒くれ者ぶりから悪禅師とも呼ばれた（『平治物語』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was commonly known as the Reverend Daigo, but was also called an evil reverend because he was a rowdy person (&quot;Heiji Monogatari&quot; (war tale)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was commonly known as the Reverend Daigo, but was also called an evil reverend because he was a rowdy person (&quot;Heiji Monogatari&quot; (war tale)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was commonly known as Daigo Zenji (Master of Zen Buddhism), or Aku (evil) Zenji from his crudeness (&quot;Heiji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Heiji).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>治承4年（1180年）8月17日、異母兄の源頼朝が伊豆国で挙兵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 1, 1180, MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, his elder brother by a different mother, raised an army in Izu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 1, 1180, MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, his elder brother by a different mother, raised an army in Izu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 15, 1180, MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, his elder brother by a different mother, raised an army in Izu Province.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>それを知った全成は寺を抜け出し、同年8月26日石橋山の戦いで頼朝が敗北した直後に佐々木定綱ら兄弟と行き会い、相模国渋谷荘に匿われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon knowing the fact, Zenjo slipped out of the temple, then happened to meet Sadatsuna SASAKI and Sadatsuna&apos;s brothers immediately after Yoritomo was defeated in the Battle of Ishibashiyama on August 20, and was given refuge with those brothers in Shibuya-so (渋谷荘) (a manor)..</e>
<cmt>渋谷荘→→Shibuya-so (渋谷荘) (a manor)[読み方不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon knowing this fact, Zenjo slipped out of the temple and happened to meet Sadatsuna SASAKI and Sadatsuna&apos;s brothers immediately after Yoritomo was defeated in the Battle of Ishibashiyama on August 20, and was given refuge by these brothers in Shibuya-so (渋谷荘) (a manor)..</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon knowing this fact, Zenjo slipped out of the temple and happened to meet Sadatsuna SASAKI and Sadatsuna&apos;s brothers shortly after Yoritomo was defeated in the Battle of Ishibashiyama on September 24, and was given refuge by them in Shibuya no sho Manor in Sagami Province.</e>
<cmt>Sagami Provinceを補足、グレゴリオ暦に変え、用語修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>10月1日には下総国鷺沼の宿所で頼朝と対面を果たす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 1, he managed to meet Yoritomo at a lodging in Saginuma, Shimofusa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 1, he managed to meet Yoritomo at a lodging in Saginuma, Shimofusa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 28, he managed to meet Yoritomo at a lodging in Saginuma, Shimousa Province.</e>
<cmt>治承4年10月1日として、グレゴリオ暦に変え、Shimousaとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>源氏一門で最初の合流であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was the first reunion of members of the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the first reunion of members of the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the first reunion of members of the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>全成は京都で令旨が出された事を知り、密かに寺を抜け出して修行僧に扮して下ってきた事を語り、頼朝は泣いてその志を喜んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zenjo told Yoritomo that he had secretly slipped out of the temple in Kyoto upon having known the issuance of His Highness&apos; address and then come down to Shimofusa Province while having disguised himself as a trainee priest, and Yoritomo appreciated Zenjo&apos;s resolution weeping with joy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zenjo told Yoritomo that he had secretly slipped out of the temple in Kyoto upon knowing about the issuance of His Highness&apos; address and then went down to Shimofusa Province having disguised himself as a trainee priest, and Yoritomo appreciated Zenjo&apos;s resolution by weeping with joy.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zenjo told Yoritomo that he had secretly slipped out of the temple in Kyoto upon knowing about ryoji (orders issued by princes, empresses, and so on) and then went down to the place having disguised himself as a trainee priest, and Yoritomo appreciated Zenjo&apos;s resolution by weeping with joy.</e>
<cmt>マイページに合わせ、他表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>頼朝の信任を得た全成は武蔵国長尾寺（現川崎市多摩区の妙楽寺）を与えられ、頼朝の妻・北条政子の妹である阿波局 (北条時政の娘)と結婚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Getting Yoritomo&apos;s trust, Zenjo was rewarded with Nagao-ji Temple (the present Myoraku-ji Temple, which is located in Tama Ward, Kawasaki City) and Married Awa no Tsubone (a sister of Masako HOJO (Yoritomo&apos;s wife) and a daughter of Tokimasa HOJO).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Getting Yoritomo&apos;s trust, Zenjo was rewarded with Nagao-ji Temple (the present Myoraku-ji Temple, which is located in Tama Ward, Kawasaki City) and married Awa no Tsubone (a sister of Masako HOJO (Yoritomo&apos;s wife) and a daughter of Tokimasa HOJO).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Winning Yoritomo&apos;s confidence, Zenjo was rewarded with Nagao-ji Temple in Musashi Province (the present Myoraku-ji Temple in Tama-ku Ward, Kawasaki City) and married Awa no Tsubone (a daughter of Tokimasa HOJO) who was a younger sister of Masako HOJO, Yoritomo&apos;s wife.</e>
<cmt>Musashi Provinceを補足し、表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>阿波局は頼朝の次男千幡丸（後の源実朝）の乳母となり、以降頼朝政権において地味ながら着実な地位を築いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Awa no Tsubone became a wet nurse for Senbanmaru (千幡丸), who was later to become MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, and thereafter established an unspectacular but solid position in the Yoritomo&apos;s administration.</e>
<cmt>千幡丸→Senbanmaru[読み不明]頼朝政権において地味ながら着実な地位を築いた：原文を見る限り、主語は阿波局ですが、この時代に女性が政権において地位を築くのは不自然だと思いました。地位を築いたのは、全成ではないでしょうか。一応原文の語句に従って、主語を阿波局として訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Awa no Tsubone became a wet nurse for Senbanmaru (千幡丸), who was later to become MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, and thereafter established an unspectacular but solid position in the Yoritomo administration.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Awa no Tsubone became a wet nurse for the second son of Yoritomo, Senmanmaru (later MINAMOTO no Sanetomo), and thereafter established an unspectacular but solid position in the Yoritomo administration.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>しかし正治元年（1199年）に頼朝が死去し、甥の源頼家が将軍職を継ぐと、全成は源実朝を擁する舅の北条時政と義兄弟の北条義時と結び、頼家一派と対立するようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Yoritomo&apos;s death and the succession to the office of a shogun by MINAMOTO no Yoriie (Zenjo&apos;s nephew) in 1199 resulted in Zenjo being allied with Tokimasa HOJO (Zenjo&apos;s father-in-law) and Yoshitoki HOJO (Zenjo&apos;s brother-in-law) who supported MINAMOTO no Sanetomo and coming to be opposed to Yoriie&apos;s followers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Yoritomo&apos;s death and the succession to the office of a shogun by MINAMOTO no Yoriie (Zenjo&apos;s nephew) in 1199 resulted in Zenjo being allied with Tokimasa HOJO (Zenjo&apos;s father-in-law) and Yoshitoki HOJO (Zenjo&apos;s brother-in-law) who supported MINAMOTO no Sanetomo and came to be opposed to Yoriie&apos;s followers.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Yoritomo&apos;s death and the succession to the office of a shogun by MINAMOTO no Yoriie (Zenjo&apos;s nephew) in 1199 resulted in Zenjo being allied with Tokimasa HOJO (Zenjo&apos;s father-in-law) and Yoshitoki HOJO (Zenjo&apos;s brother-in-law) who supported MINAMOTO no Sanetomo and came to be opposed to Yoriie&apos;s followers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>建仁3年（1203年）5月19日の深夜0時頃、先手を打った頼家は武田信光を派遣し、全成を謀反人として捕縛し鎌倉御所に押し込めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoriie moved one step ahead of Zenjo and dispatched Nobumitsu TAKEDA around midnight on May 19, 1203 to have him arrest Zenjo as a rebel and shut Zenjo up in Kamakura Gosho (the residence of a shogun of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)).</e>
<cmt>建仁3年（1203年）5月19日の深夜0時頃：この句が武田信光を派遣した時刻に言及するものなのか、全成を鎌倉御所に押し込めた時刻に言及するものなのかを判断できませんでした。暫定的に前者に言及するものとして訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriie moved one step ahead of Zenjo and dispatched Nobumitsu TAKEDA around midnight on May 19, 1203 to have him arrest Zenjo as a rebel and shut Zenjo up in Kamakura Gosho (the residence of a shogun of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriie moved one step ahead of Zenjo and dispatched Nobumitsu TAKEDA around midnight on July 6, 1203, to have him arrest Zenjo as a rebel and shut Zenjo up in Kamakura Gosho (the residence of a shogun of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>全成は5月25日に常陸国に配流され、6月23日、頼家の命を受けた八田知家によって誅殺された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zenjo was exiled to Hitachi Province on May 25 and put to death on June 23 by Tomoie HATTA being under the order from Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zenjo was exiled to Hitachi Province on May 25 and put to death on June 23 by Tomoie HATTA under orders from Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zenjo was exiled to Hitachi Province on July 12 and killed on August 8 by Tomoie HATTA under orders of Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>享年51。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was fifty-one years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was fifty-one years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was fifty-one years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>7月16日には京都の東山延年寺で、子の播磨公頼全が在京御家人によって殺害された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 16, Yorimasa, Zenjo&apos;s son who served as Harima-no-Kimi was killed at Higashiyama Ennen-ji Temple in Kyoto by an immediate vassal of the shogun residing in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 16, Yorimasa, Zenjo&apos;s son who served as Harima-no-Kimi was killed at Higashiyama Ennen-ji Temple in Kyoto by an immediate vassal of the shogun residing in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 31, Harimanokimi Yorimasa, Zenjo&apos;s son, was killed at Higashiyama Ennen-ji Temple in Kyoto by an immediate vassal of the shogun residing in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="22">
<j>全成の墓は、静岡県沼津市の大泉寺に嫡男阿野時元のものと並んで現存し、市の史跡に指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tomb of Zenjo exists in Daisen-ji Temple in Numazu City, Shizuoka Prefecture, adjoining the tomb of Tokimoto ANO, Zenjo&apos;s eldest son, and is designated as a historic relic of the said city.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tomb of Zenjo exists in Daisen-ji Temple in Numazu City, Shizuoka Prefecture, adjoining the tomb of Tokimoto ANO, Zenjo&apos;s eldest son, and is designated as a historic relic of that city.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tomb of Zenjo exists in Daisen-ji Temple in Numazu City, Shizuoka Prefecture, adjoining the tomb of Tokimoto ANO, Zenjo&apos;s legitimate son, and is designated as a historic relic of the city.</e>
<cmt>用語表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>子孫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Descendants</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Descendants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Descendants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>武家としての阿野氏は時元の系統に受け継がれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ano clan as a samurai family was taken over by the lineage of Tokimoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ano clan as a samurai family was taken over by the lineage of Tokimoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ano clan as a samurai family was taken over by the lineage of Tokimoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>その子孫は、南北朝時代 (日本)期までは確実に存在したことが記録に残っているが、同じ河内源氏の系統に繋がる源氏庶流の足利氏などと比べても、非常に小さな勢力でしかなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a record, the lineage surely existed until the Southern and Northern Dynasties period (of Japanese history); however, the linage was much less influential, compared with the Ashikaga clan, a clan that was descended from the linage of Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan) as the Ano clan was.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to records, the lineage surely existed until the Southern and Northern Dynasties period (of Japanese history); however, the lineage was much less influential, compared with the Ashikaga clan, a clan that was descended from the lineage of Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan) as the Ano clan was.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to records, the lineage surely existed until the period of the Northern and Southern Courts, however, the lineage was much less influential, compared with the Ashikaga clan, a branch family of the Minamoto clan, which lineage was the same Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan) as that of the Ano clan.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>これは、全成や時元が謀反人として誅殺されたという事実が大きく作用しているが、また別の要因として、阿野氏が源義朝の子孫であり、義朝の数代前の分家である足利氏などと比べても源頼朝に近い血統であったため、北条氏から非常に警戒されていたためということが考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is considerably attributable to the fact that Zenjo and Tokimoto were put to death as rebels, and also seems to be be attributable to the fact that the Hojo clan was extraordinarily wary of the Ano clan because the Ano clan, which was the lineage originating from MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo, was closer to MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, compared with the Ashikaga clan, which was a branch family originating from Yoshitomo&apos;s ancestor several generations back.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is considerably attributable to the fact that Zenjo and Tokimoto were put to death as rebels, and also seems to be be attributable to the fact that the Hojo clan was extraordinarily wary of the Ano clan because the Ano clan, which was the lineage originating from MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo, was closer to MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, compared with the Ashikaga clan, which was a branch family originating from Yoshitomo&apos;s ancestor several generations previously.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was considerably attributable to the fact that Zenjo and Tokimoto were killed as rebels, and another fact that the Hojo clan was extraordinarily wary of the Ano clan because the Ano clan was the lineage of MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo which was closer to MINAMOTO no Yoritomo than that of the Ashikaga clan, which branched from several generations before Yoshitomo.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="26">
<j>また全成の娘は藤原北家藤原魚名流の藤原公佐と結婚しており、その子阿野実直は母方の名字を称し公家としての阿野家の祖となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Zenjo&apos;s daughter married FUJIWARA no Kinnari, a member of the family descended from FUJIWARA no Uona, which stemmed from the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan, and her son Sanenao founded the Ano family as a court noble by assuming the surname of his mother&apos;s family, Ano.</e>
<cmt>「その子阿野実直」：翻訳指示に従えば、&quot;her son Sanenao ANO&quot;と訳出すべきですが、この個所で&quot;ANO&quot;を訳出すると、訳文が不自然になりますので、訳出しておりません（後続の&quot;assumed the surname of his mother&apos;s family, Ano&quot;で訳出できていると判断しました）。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Zenjo&apos;s daughter married FUJIWARA no Kinnari, a member of the family descended from FUJIWARA no Uona, which stemmed from the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan, and her son Sanenao founded the Ano family as a court noble by assuming the surname of his mother&apos;s family, Ano.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Zenjo&apos;s daughter married FUJIWARA no Kimisuke, a lineage of FUJIWARA no Uona of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan, and her son Sanenao ANO founded the Ano family as a court noble from his maternal surname.</e>
<cmt>前出通りFUJIWARA no Kimisukeとし、表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>後醍醐天皇の寵愛を受け後村上天皇の母となった阿野廉子はその末裔である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Renshi ANO (阿野廉子), who stood high in Emperor Godaigo&apos;s favor and gave birth to Emperor Gomurakami, was a descendant of this Ano clan.</e>
<cmt>阿野廉子→Renshi ANO (阿野廉子)[読み方不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Renshi ANO (阿野廉子), who stood high in Emperor Godaigo&apos;s favor and gave birth to Emperor Gomurakami, was a descendant of this Ano clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Renshi ANO (阿野廉子), who was in Emperor Godaigo&apos;s favor and gave birth to Emperor Gomurakami, was a descendant of the Ano clan.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>また、幕末期に活躍した玉松操もこの阿野家の末流に連なる人物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Misao TAMAMATSU, who played an active part in the closing days of the Tokugawa shogunate.</e>
<cmt>「幕末期に活躍した」：どのような方面で活躍したのかを明記しないと訳文に不自然さが残ります。この人物は、王政復古において活躍した人物なので、&quot;who played an active part in the restoration of imperial rule in the closing days of the Tokugawa shogunate&quot;のようにした方が良いと思います。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Misao TAMAMATSU, who played an active part in the closing days of the Tokugawa shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Misao TAMAMATSU, who played an active role in the end of Edo period, was also a descendant of the Ano family.</e>
<cmt>「もこの阿野家の末流に連なる人物である」を補足、表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Izayohi(id:13095), 諏訪太郎頼光(id:98476), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), ちちぶ(id:184715), Tiyoringo(id:70026), 味っ子(id:17086), Seibuabina(id:37532), D.328(id:29724), Andee(id:20421), 小者(id:172526), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>