<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>除夜の鐘</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Joyano kane</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Joyano kane</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Joyano kane</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>除夜の鐘（じょやのかね）とは12月31日の除夜（大晦日の夜）の深夜0時を挟んで寺院で撞かれる梵鐘のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Joyano kane means bronze bell (temple bell) stroked before and after 12:00 am 0n the New Year&apos;s Eve of 31st December.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Joyano kane means bronze bell (temple bell) stroked before and after 12:00 am on New Year&apos;s Eve(31st December).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Joyano kane means striking a bronze bell (temple bell) around 12:00 am on New Year&apos;s Eve (December 31).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>除夜の鐘は108回撞かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Joyas no kane is stroked one hundred and eight times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Joyas no kane is stroked one hundred and eight times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Joyano kane is struck one hundred and eight times.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しましたスペル修正、表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>この由来には諸説ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are various theories oh the reason why the bell is stroked one hundred and eight times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various theories on the reason why the bell is stroked one hundred and eight times.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various theories on the reason why the bell is struck one hundred and eight times.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>眼（げん）・耳（に）・鼻（び）・舌（ぜつ）・身（しん）・意（い）の六根のそれぞれに好（こう：気持ちが好い）・悪（あく：気持ちが悪い）・平（へい：どうでもよい）があって18類、この18類それぞれに浄（じょう）・染（せん：きたない）の2類があって36類、この36類を前世・今世・来世の三世に配当して108となり、人間の煩悩の数を表す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number, one hundred and eight represents human&apos;s Bonno (earthly desires), which each rokkon (the six senses) of eyes, ears, nose, tong, body, mind have eighteen types of feeling, Ko (sense to feel good), Aku (sense to feel not good), Hei (sense to feel either way), then each of eighteen feelings have two types of feeling, Jo and Sen (dirty), which make thirty six types, this is multiplied by three to make one hundred and eight, to represent previous life, current life, future life.</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number, one hundred and eight represents human Bonno (earthly desires), whereby each rokkon (the six senses) of the eyes, ears, nose, tong, body, mind have eighteen types of feeling, Ko (sense to feel good), Aku (sense to feel not good), Hei (sense to feel either way), then each of the eighteen feelings have two types of feeling, Jo and Sen (dirty), which make thirty six types, this is multiplied by three to make one hundred and eight, to represent previous life, current life, future life.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number, one hundred and eight, represents human Bonno (earthly desires); each of rokkon (the six senses), which are eyes, ears, nose, tongue, body, mind, has three types of senses, Ko (sense to feel good), Aku (sense to feel bad), Hei (sense to feel indifferent), thus producing eighteen kinds of senses in total; then each of the eighteen senses has two types of feeling, Jo (pure) and Sen (dirty), making thirty six types; these thirty six types are multiplied by three, representing the previous life, the current life and future life, to make one hundred and eight.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました英訳を補足しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="5">
<j>月 (暦)の数の12、二十四節気の数の24、七十二候の数の72を足した数が108となり、1年間を表す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of the Month (calendar), twelve, added by 24 divisions of the old calendar, and added by 七十二候 become one hundred and eight, which represent one year.</e>
<cmt>候→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of the Month (calendar), twelve, added by 24 divisions of the old calendar, and added to 七十二候 become one hundred and eight, which represent one year.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Twelve, which is the number of months (calendar), added by twenty-four, which comes from Nijushi sekki (days that divide a year in the old lunar calendar into twenty-four equal sections), and by seventy-two, which comes from Shichijuni-ko (72 divisions of the solar year), makes one hundred and eight and represents one year.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="6">
<j>四苦八苦を取り払うということで、4×9+8×9108をかけたとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is another theory that number 4 and 9, 8 and 9 were each multiplied and added to the number to get rid of Shikuhakku. (hardship)</e>
<cmt>四苦八苦→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is another theory that number 4 and 9, 8 and 9 were each multiplied and added to the number to get rid of Shikuhakku. (hardship)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another theory says that 108 means to get rid of Shikuhakku (hardship): in Japanese, four, nine, eight is pronounced &apos;shi&apos;, &apos;ku&apos;, &apos;ha(tchi)&apos;, respectively, and 4X9+8X9 could be pronounced Shikuhakku and 4X9+8X9 is equal to 108.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="7">
<j>鐘を撞く前には鐘に向かって合掌する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is custom to put the palms of hands together before striking the bell.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is custom to put the palms of hands together before striking the bell.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is customary to join your hands in prayer before striking a bell.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>108回のうち107回は旧年（12月31日）のうちに撞き、残りの1回を新年（1月1日）に撞く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One hundred and eight bells should be stroked in the old year (on 31st, December) and other one bell should be stroked in the New Year on 1st January.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One hundred and eight bells should be struck in the old year (on 31st, December) and other bell should be struck in the New Year on 1st January.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One hundred and seven should be struck in the old year (on December 31) and the last strike should be made in the New Year (on January 1).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>但し、大石寺では例外的に年明けと同時に1発目が撞かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However as an exception, the first bell is stroked, as soon as the New Year start in Taiseki-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as an exception, the first bell is struck as soon as the New Year starts in Taiseki-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, they start striking the bell as soon as the New Year starts on an exceptional basis in Taiseki-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="10">
<j>本来は108回の鐘は除夜だけでなく毎日、朝夕に撞かれるべきものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally one hundred and eight bells should be stroked everyday, in the morning and in the evening.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally one hundred and eight bells should be stroked everyday, in the morning and in the evening.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Normally a bell in a temple should be struck 108 times not only on the New Year&apos;s Eve but also every day, in the morning and in the evening.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし、普段は略して18回に留められる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However it is shortened to strike eighteen times in everyday life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is shortened and struck eighteen times in everyday life.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the number of striking a bell is shortened in everyday llife and the bell is struck only eighteen times a day.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Ligar(id:12623), Opponent(id:720), やすとし(id:63220), Teknoboz(id:5308), Nnh(id:474), Robert De Smith(id:28533), まるゆ(id:4371), MASA(id:2399), Kstigarbha(id:13376), ウィキ豊(id:82961), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>