<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>化仏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kebutsu (the Artificial Buddha)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kebutsu (the Artificial Buddha)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kebutsu</e>
<cmt>タイトルなので補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>化仏（けぶつ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kebutsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kebutsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kebutsu (the Artificial Buddha)</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>変化仏、または応化仏の略。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is an abbreviation of Hengebutsu or Okebutsu (transformations of Buddha).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An abbreviation of Hengebutsu or Okebutsu (transformations of Buddha).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An abbreviation of Hengebutsu or Okebutsu (transformations of Buddha).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>仏や菩薩が、衆生を救うため、その機根に応じて現れる仏や菩薩、また明王となった姿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is an appearance of Buddha or Bosatsu (Bodhisattva) as Buddha, Bosatsu or Myoo (Atavaka, general of the heavenly cohorts, who was accused of eating human flesh), in order to relieve living things depending on the capability of people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It refers to an appearance of Buddha or Bosatsu (Bodhisattva) as Buddha, Bosatsu or Myoo (Atavaka, general of the heavenly cohorts, who was accused of eating human flesh), in order to relieve living things depending on the capability of people.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It refers to an appearance of Buddha or Bosatsu (Bodhisattva) as Buddha, Bosatsu or Myoo (Atavaka, general of the heavenly cohorts, who was accused of eating human flesh), in order to relieve living things depending on the capability of people.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>仮の仏形。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a temporary figure of Buddha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A temporary figure of Buddha.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A temporary figure of Buddha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>化身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is an incarnation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An incarnation.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An incarnation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また三身論の報身や応身を化仏ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Hosin (sambhoga-kaya) and Ojin (nirmana-kaya) in the theory of trikaya (three bodies of the Buddha) are also called kebutsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, According to the theory of trikaya (three bodies of the Buddha) Hosin (sambhoga-kaya) and Ojin (nirmana-kaya) are also called kebutsu.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, according to hojin (Bliss Body; Reward Body) and ojin (Manifested Body) in the theory of trikaya (three bodies of the Buddha) are also called kebutsu.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>娑婆世界に出世した釈迦仏は応身の仏とされ、浄土教の阿弥陀仏は、西方極楽浄土の法身から変えてこの娑婆世界に報身として衆生を迎えにきたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shakyamuni buddha who appeared in this corrupt world is regarded as Ojin Buddha and the Amida Buddha of the Jodo (Pure Land) sect is regarded to come to this corrupt world to welcome living things as Hosin Buddha, changed itself from Hosshin (dharma-kaya) Buddha in the Saiho Gokuraku Jodo (The West Pure Land (of Amida Buddha)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shakyamuni buddha who appeared in this corrupt world is regarded as Ojin Buddha and the Amida Buddha of the Jodo (Pure Land) sect is regarded as having come to this corrupt world to welcome living things as Hosin Buddha, and changed himself from Hosshin (dharma-kaya) Buddha in the Saiho Gokuraku Jodo (The West Pure Land (of Amida Buddha)).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shakyamuni Buddha who appeared in this corrupt world is regarded as Ojin Buddha and the Amida Buddha of the Jodo (Pure Land) Sect is regarded as having changed himself from hojin in the Saiho Gokuraku Jodo (The West Pure Land (of Amida Buddha)) to hosshin (Dharma Body) to come to this corrupt world to welcome living things.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>仏像や菩薩像などの頭上、または光背に配置されている小さな仏の形像、また天蓋に表された小さな仏形や図柄も化仏という場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A small statue of Buddha which is placed on the head of Buddha statue or Bosatsu statue or on its halo, and a small Buddha image or picture on the ceiling are also called kebutsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A small statue of Buddha which is placed on the head of Buddha statue or Bosatsu statue or on its halo, and a small image of Buddha or picture on the ceiling are also called kebutsu.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A small statue of Buddha which is placed on the head of Buddha statue or Bosatsu statue or on its halo, and a small image of Buddha or picture on the ceiling are also called kebutsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>菩薩の場合は、その本地仏を表すため、頭上に頂く仏形をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of Bosatsu, the Buddha statue on the head is called kebutsu in order to show honji-butsu (original Buddhist divinity).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of Bosatsu, the Buddha statue on the head is called kebutsu in order to show honji-butsu (original Buddhist divinity).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of Bosatsu, the Buddha statue on the head is called kebutsu in order to show honji-butsu (original Buddhist divinity).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>観音の頭上の阿弥陀像がその例である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Amida statue on the head of Kannon (Deity of Mercy) is its example.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Amida statue on the head of Kannon (Deity of Mercy) is an example.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Amida statue on the head of Kannon (Deity of Mercy) is an example.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また東大寺盧舎那仏像の光背にある16体の仏像も化仏であり、京都の六波羅蜜寺の空也上人像の口から飛び出す6体の阿弥陀如来も化仏の一種といわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the sixteen Buddha statues on the halo of the statue of Rushana-butsu (Rushana Buddha) in the Todai-ji Temple are also kebutsu, and the six Amida Nyorai (Amitabha Tathagata) statues which are thrown out of the mouth of the Kuya Shonin statue in the Rokuharamitsu-ji Temple in Kyoto are also said to be a kind of kebutsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the sixteen Buddha statues on the halo of the statue of Rushana-butsu (Rushana Buddha) in the Todai-ji Temple are also kebutsu, and the six Amida Nyorai (Amitabha Tathagata) statues which are thrown out of the mouth of the Kuya Shonin statue in the Rokuharamitsu-ji Temple in Kyoto are also said to be a kind of kebutsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the 16 Buddha statues on the halo of the statue of Rushana-butsu (Rushana Buddha) in the Todai-ji Temple are also kebutsu, and the 6 Amida Nyorai (Amitabha Tathagata) statues which are thrown out of the mouth of the Kuya Shonin statue in the Rokuharamitsu-ji Temple in Kyoto are also said to be a kind of kebutsu.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また仏ではないが、馬頭観音の頭上の馬も化仏と呼ぶ場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, a horse statue on the head of Bato Kannon (horse-headed Kannon), although it is not a Buddha statue, is also called kebutsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, the horse statue on the head of Bato Kannon (horse-headed Kannon), although it is not a Buddha statue, is also called kebutsu.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the horse statue on the head of Bato Kannon (horse-headed Kannon), although it is not a Buddha statue, is also called kebutsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>釈尊が説法を説いた際に、白毫から一千の光明と一千の化仏が現れたとされ、仏画の題材にもされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that when Shakyamuni preached, a thousand of light and a thousand of kebutsu appeared, which has been often adopted as a subject of Buddhist painting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that when Shakyamuni preached, a thousand lights and a thousand kebutsu appeared, which has been often adopted as a subject of Buddhist paintings.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that when Shakyamuni preached, a thousand lights and a thousand kebutsu appeared from Shakyamuni&apos;s byakugo (whorl of hair in the centre of the forehead of Buddha), which has been often adopted as a subject of Buddhist paintings.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Vigilante(id:175380), 文姫(id:66661), Monaneko(id:28864), Boca samba(id:137526), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>