<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>真言宗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shingon sect</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shingon Sect</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shingon Sect</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>真言宗（しんごんしゅう）は、空海（弘法大師）によって9世紀初頭に開かれた、日本の仏教の宗派。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shingon sect is a Buddhism sect of Japan which was founded Kukai (Kobo-daishi) in the early 9th century.</e>
<cmt>真言宗→英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shingon sect is a Buddhist sect of Japan that was founded Kukai (Kobo-daishi) in the early ninth century.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shingon sect is a Buddhist sect of Japan that was founded by Kukai (Kobo Daishi) in the early ninth century.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;by&quot;　Kobo Daishi としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>真言陀羅尼宗（しんごんだらにしゅう）、曼荼羅宗（まんだらしゅう）、秘密宗（ひみつしゅう）とも称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Shingon Darani sect, Mandara sect or Himitsu sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called the Shingon Darani sect, Mandara sect or Himitsu sect.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called the Shingon Darani sect, Mandala sect or Himitsu sect.</e>
<cmt>Mandara→Mandala に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>空海が中国（唐時代）の長安に渡り、青龍寺 (西安市)で恵果から学んだ密教を基盤としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is based on Mikkyo, Esoteric Buddhism, which Kukai learned from Eka, Keika, at Shoryuji Temple, Qinglongsi Temple, of Choan, Changgan, of China at the age of Tang Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>長安→英辞郎 on the WEB、青龍寺→http://www.chinaviki.com/china-travel/attrations/Shannxi/Xian/Qinglongsi-Temple/、西安市→英辞郎on the WEB,　密教→http://www.koyasan.or.jp/english/shingonshu/mikkyo.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is based on Mikkyo, or esoteric Buddhism, which Kukai learned from Eka, Keika, at Shoryuji Temple, Qinglongsi Temple in Choan, Changgan (China) during the Tang dynasty.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is based on Mikkyo, or esoteric Buddhism, which Kukai learned from Eka (Keika), at Shoryu-ji Temple (Qinglongsi Temple) in Choan, (Changan) (Xian City) during the Tang dynasty.</e>
<cmt>china →Xian City</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>同時期に最澄によって開かれた日本の天台宗が法華経学、密教、戒律、禅を兼修するのに対し、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Tendai sect in Japan founded by Saicho around same time learns Hoke-kyo Sutra, Mikkyo, commandment and Zen at the same time,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, the Tendai sect in Japan, which was founded by Saicho at about the same time, learned the Hoke-kyo Sutra, Mikkyo, commandment and Zen simultaneously.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, the Tendai sect in Japan, which was founded by Saicho at about the same time, learned the Hoke-kyo Sutra, Mikkyo, commandment and Zen simultaneously.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>空海は著作「秘密曼荼羅十住心論」（ひみつまんだらじゅうじゅうしんろん）、「秘蔵宝鑰」（ひぞうほうやく）で、空海が執筆していた当時に伝来していた仏教各派の教学に一応の評価を与えつつ、真言宗を最上位に置くことによって十段階の思想体系の中に組み込んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his works &apos;Himitsu Mandara Jujushinron&apos; and &apos;Hizohoyaku&apos;, Kukai appreciated other Buddhism sects Dharma which had been introduced at that time to some extent, and　built them into a rating of 1 to 10 thinking system by putting Shingon sect on the top of them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his works &quot;Himitsu Mandara Jujushinron&quot; and &quot;Hizohoyaku,&quot; Kukai appreciated another Buddhism sect, Dharma, which had been introduced at that time to some extent, and built that thinking into a rating system of 1 to 10 by placing the Shingon sect above the Dharma.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his works &apos;Himitsu Mandala Jujushinron&apos; and &apos;Hizohoyaku,&apos; Kukai expressed appreciation for another Buddhist sect, Dharma, which was at that time established to some extent, and built that thinking into a rating system of 1 to 10 by placing the Shingon sect above the Dharma.</e>
<cmt>Mandara→Mandala に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>最終的には顕教と比べて、密教（真言密教）の優位性、顕教の思想・経典も真言密教に摂包されることを説いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Finally, he preached that Mikkyo (Shingon Mikkyo) was superior to exoteric Buddhism and that the thought and sutras of exoteric Buddhism were included to Shingon Mikkyo.</e>
<cmt>顕教→英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Finally, he preached that Mikkyo (Shingon Mikkyo) was superior to esoteric Buddhism and that the thinking and sutras of esoteric Buddhism were included to Shingon Mikkyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Finally, he preached that Mikkyo (Shingon Mikkyo) was superior to esoteric Buddhism and that the thinking and sutras of esoteric Buddhism were included to Shingon Mikkyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>天台密教を「台密」と称するのに対し、真言密教を「東密」と称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Tendai Mikkyo is called &apos;Daimitsu&apos;, Shingon Mikkyo is called &apos;Toumitsu&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Tendai Mikkyo is called &quot;Daimitsu,&quot; Shingon Mikkyo is called &quot;Toumitsu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Tendai Mikkyo is called &apos;Daimitsu,&apos; Shingon Mikkyo is called &apos;Tomitsu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Tomitsu としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>真言宗の密教は東寺を基盤としたので「東密」と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mikkyo of Shingon sect was called &apos;Toumitsu&apos; because it was based on To-ji Temple (Kyoogokoku-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>東寺→http://kaiwai.city.kyoto.jp/search/view_sight.php?ManageCode=1000042&amp;InforKindCode=1</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mikkyo, of the Shingon sectm was called &quot;Toumitsu&quot; because it was based on the To-ji Temple (Kyoogokoku-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mikkyo, of the Shingon sect, was called &apos;Tomitsu&apos; because it was centered on the To-ji Temple (Kyoogokoku-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>sectm→ sect</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>開宗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Foundation of sect</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The founding of the sect</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The founding of the sect</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>空海は、816年（弘仁7年）に高野山金剛峯寺を修禅の道場として開創し、弘仁14年（823年）に勅賜された教王護国寺（東寺）を真言宗の根本道場として宗団を確立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kukai founded Koyasan Kongobu-ji Temple as Dojo for training Zen in 816 and established a sect with having Kyoogokoku-ji Temple (To-ji Temple) which was given by the Imperial Court in 823 a fundamental Dojo of Shingon sect.</e>
<cmt>高野山金剛峯寺→http://www.koyasan.or.jp/english/index.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kukai founded Koyasan Kongobu-ji Temple in 816 as a dojo for Zen training, and established a sect having the Kyoogokoku-ji Temple (To-ji Temple), which was given by the Imperial Court in 823, as a fundamental dojo of the Shingon sect.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kukai founded Koyasan Kongobu-ji Temple in 816 as a dojo for Zen training, and established a sect having the Kyoogokoku-ji Temple (To-ji Temple), which was given by the Imperial Court in 823, as a fundamental dojo of the Shingon sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>空海入定後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After falling into deep meditation of Kukai</e>
<cmt>入定→英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After falling into deep meditation of Kukai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After falling into deep meditation of Kukai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>空海は入定に際して、住持していた寺院を弟子に付嘱した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before Kukai fell into deep mediation, he asked his disciples to put in charge of the temples which he had worked as chief priests.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before Kukai fell into deep meditation, he asked his disciples to take charge of the temples in which he had worked as a chief priest.</e>
<cmt>singular</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before Kukai fell into deep meditation, he asked his disciples to take charge of the temples in which he had worked as a chief priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>東寺は実慧、金剛峯寺は真然、神護寺は真済、安祥寺 (京都市)を恵運、寛平法皇（宇多天皇）が開基した仁和寺、醍醐寺は聖宝、円成寺は益信などがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To-ji Temple was put in charge of Jitsue, Kongobu-ji Temple was Shinzen, Jingo-ji Temple was Shinzei, Ansho-ji Temple (Kyoto City) was Eun, Ninna-ji Temple founded by Kanpyo Hoo (an abdicated emperor who has joined a Buddhist order)　(寛平法皇) (Emperor Uda) was Shobo, Enjo-ji Temple was Yakushin and so on; these temples were permitted to be Nenbundosya (state-sanctioned school of monks) (年分度者), and tended to be independent.</e>
<cmt>実慧→http://homepage3.nifty.com/y-maki/gosyo/sinnpenn/0258.pdf、金剛峯寺→http://www.koyasan.or.jp/english/index.html、真然→http://homepage3.nifty.com/y-maki/gosyo/sinnpenn/0258.pdf、神護寺→http://www7b.biglobe.ne.jp/~kosho/、真済→http://homepage3.nifty.com/y-maki/gosyo/sinnpenn/0258.pdf、恵運→Yahoo辞書、寛平法皇→定訳不明、Yahoo辞書、仁和寺→http://web.kyoto-inet.or.jp/org/ninnaji/、醍醐寺→http://www.daigoji.or.jp/、聖宝→http://homepage3.nifty.com/y-maki/gosyo/sinnpenn/0258.pdf、円成寺→http://www.naranet.co.jp/enjyouji/index.html、益信→http://homepage3.nifty.com/y-maki/gosyo/sinnpenn/0258.pdf、年分度者→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To-ji Temple was put in charge of Jitsue, Kongobu-ji Temple was Shinzen, Jingo-ji Temple was Shinzei, Ansho-ji Temple (Kyoto City) was Eun, Ninna-ji Temple founded by Kanpyo Hoo (an abdicated emperor who had joined a Buddhist order); (寛平法皇) (Emperor Uda) was Shobo, Enjo-ji Temple was Yakushin and so on; these temples were permitted to be Nenbundosya (state-sanctioned schools of monks) (年分度者), and therefore tended to be independent.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To-ji Temple was put in charge by Jitsue, Kongobu-ji Temple by Shinzen, Jingo-ji Temple by Shinzei, Ansho-ji Temple (Kyoto City) by Eun, Ninna-ji Temple was founded by Kanpyo Hoo (an abdicated emperor who had joined a Buddhist order); (寛平法皇) (Emperor Uda) by Shobo, Enjo-ji Temple by Yakushin and so on.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>これらの寺院に年分度者（ねんぶんどしゃ）（国家公認の僧侶の養成）を許可され、それぞれの寺院が独立した傾向を持っていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These temples were permitted to be state-sanctioned schools of monks (Nenbundosha) (年分度者), and therefore tended to be independent.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>本末争い（東寺と高野山）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Conflict of Honmatsu, between head temple and sub temple (between To-ji Temple and Mt.Koya, Koyasan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Conflict of Honmatsu, between the head temple and the sub-temple (between To-ji Temple and Mt. Koya, Koyasan)</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Conflict of Honmatsu, between the head temple and the sub-temple (between To-ji Temple and Mt. Koya, Koyasan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>観賢が東寺長者・金剛峯寺座主を兼ね、東寺を本寺とし、金剛峯寺を末寺とする本末制度を確立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kangen became Toji-Choja, the chief abbot of To-ji Temple, and Kongobu-ji Temple&apos;s head priest at the same time and established Honmatsu system in which To-ji Temple was head temple and Kongobu-ji Temple was sub temple.</e>
<cmt>東寺長者→http://inbuds.hanazono.ac.jp/show_tr.php?mdid1=0-00133&amp;mdid2=000021&amp;trid=003、金剛峯寺座主→http://www.koyasan.or.jp/http://www.websters-online-dictionary.org/definition/temple%2527s+head+priest</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kangen became Toji-Choja, the chief abbot of To-ji Temple, and at the same time Kongobu-ji Temple&apos;s head priest established the Honmatsu system in which To-ji Temple was the head temple and Kongobu-ji Temple was the sub-temple.</e>
<cmt>g</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kangen became Toji-Choja (the chief abbot of To-ji Temple) and at the same time Kongobu-ji Temple&apos;s head priest, and established the Honmatsu system in which To-ji Temple was the head temple and Kongobu-ji Temple was the sub-temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>東寺長者が真言宗を統括することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toji-Choja became to control Shingon sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toji-Choja came to control the Shingon sect.</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toji-Choja came to control the Shingon sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>金剛峯寺は、この本末争いに負けた後、落雷により伽藍・諸堂を焼失した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After a defeat of this conflict of Honmatsu, Kongobu-ji Temple was burned down by lightning and lost halls..</e>
<cmt>伽藍→temple</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After a defeat in the conflict of Honmatsu, Kongobu-ji Temple was damaged in a fire due to lightning and lost its halls.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After a defeat in the conflict of Honmatsu, Kongobu-ji Temple was damaged in a fire due to lightning and lost its halls.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>また国司による押妨などにより、高野山は衰微し、無人の状態になるまでに至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koyasan was declined and fell into unmanned situation by tyranny of provincial officer and other reasons.</e>
<cmt>押妨は横暴の意で訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koyasan fell into decline and abandonment due to the tyranny of provincial officers and other reasons.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koyasan fell into decline and abandonment due to the tyranny of provincial officers and other reasons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>この状態が平安時代中期まで続くが、藤原道長が高野山に登山（山上の寺社に参詣すること）したことにより復興が進み、皇族・摂関家・公家が高野山への登山が続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This situation continued until the mid-Heian Period, but climbing Koyasan (making a pilgrimage to a shrine on the mountain) by FUJIWARA no Michinaga promoted rehabilitation, and climbing by imperial family, Sekkann-ke Regent Family (摂関家) and court nobles followed.</e>
<cmt>摂関家→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This situation continued until the mid-Heian period, but climbing Koyasan (making a pilgrimage to a shrine on the mountain) by Fujiwara no Michinaga promoted rehabilitation, and climbing by the Imperial Family, Sekkann-ke Regent Family (摂関家) and court nobles followed.</e>
<cmt>capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This situation continued until the mid-Heian period, but Koyasan began to make a recovery after FUJIWARA no Michinaga climbed it (making a pilgrimage to a shrine on the mountain), and he was later followed by the Imperial Family, the Sekkan-ke (the families which produced regents), and court nobles.</e>
<cmt>I don&apos;t think kanji is necessary here so I have deleted it. I have also had to rewrite this quite a bit to make it a bit more understandable to a native speaker of English.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>その後、皇族・摂関家・公家などによる経済的な支援もあり、財政においても安定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, it got financial stability partly because of economic assistance by imperial family, Sekkann-ke Regent Family, court nobles and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, it gained financial stability partly due to economic assistance by the Imperial Family, Sekkann-ke regent family, court nobles and so on.</e>
<cmt>capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, it gained financial stability partly due to economic assistance by the Imperial Family, Sekkann-ke regent family, court nobles and so on.</e>
<cmt>subsequently</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>覚鑁（かくばん）と高野山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kakuban and Koyasan</e>
<cmt>覚鑁→http://www.ne.jp/asahi/chisan/jigenji/kougyoudaishi.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kakuban and Koyasan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kakuban and Koyasan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="21">
<j>師資相承を重視するために分派していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It split into sects because it valued shishisosho, a succession from a teacher to a disciple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It split into sects because it valued shishisosho, a succession from a teacher to a disciple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It split into sects because it valued shishisosho, a succession from a teacher to a disciple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>事相（真言密教を実践するための作法。修法の作法など）の違いによる分派であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This split was caused by the difference of Jiso (事相), a way to implement Shingon Mikkyo (e.g., a manner of ascetic training).</e>
<cmt>事相→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This split was caused by the difference of Jiso (事相), a way to implement Shingon Mikkyo (e.g., a manner of ascetic training).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This split was caused by the difference of Jiso (事相), a way to implement Shingon Mikkyo (e.g., a manner of ascetic training).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>教学（教義）そのものは、空海により大成されていたため、平安時代半ばまで、宗内での論争はあまりなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dharma itself had been completed by Kukai so that there was no dispute inside of the sect until the mid-Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dharma itself had been completed by Kukai so that there was no dispute within the sect until the mid-Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dharma itself had been completed by Kukai so that there was no dispute within the sect until the mid-Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="24">
<j>しかし、11世紀末、覚鑁（興教大師）が高野山で秘密念仏思想を提唱した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But in the end of 11th century Kakuban (Kogyo Daishi) began to preach the thought of Himitsu Nenbutsu at Koyasan.</e>
<cmt>興教大師→http://www.tanjoin.net/tera/kakuban/index.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, at the end of the eleventh century Kakuban (Kogyo Daishi) began to preach the thought of Himitsu Nenbutsu at Koyasan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, at the end of the eleventh century Kakuban (Kogyo Daishi) began to preach the thought of Himitsu Nenbutsu at Koyasan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="25">
<j>また、覚鑁は、大伝法院を創建、教学の振興のために大伝法会の復興を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Kakuban built Daidenpo-in and revitalized Daidenpo-e in order to promote Shingon Dharma.</e>
<cmt>大伝法院→http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110006548120/、大伝法会→Yahoo辞書</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, Kakuban built Daidenpo-in and revitalized Daidenpo-e in order to promote Shingon Dharma.</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, Kakuban built Daidenpo-in and revitalized Daidenpo-e in order to promote Shingon Dharma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>東寺の支配から高野山の独立を図り、東寺長者が金剛峯寺の座主を兼職する慣例を廃止し、金剛峯寺座主に任ぜられたが、金剛峯寺方（本寺方）の反発を受け失敗した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He tried to attain independency of Koyasan from To-ji Temple&apos;s control so that he abolished a custom that Toji-Chojya became Kongobu-ji Temple&apos;s head priest at the same time and was ordained to be Kongobu-ji Temple&apos;s head priest, but his trial fell into a failure by an objection of Kongobuji side (Hon-ji side).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He tried to attain the independence of Koyasan from To-ji Temple&apos;s control, whereby he abolished the custom that Toji-Chojya became the head priest of Kongobu-ji Temple at the same time and was ordained to be Kongobu-ji Temple&apos;s head priest; however, his trial failed due to the objection of the Kongobuji side (Hon-ji side).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He tried to achieve the independence of Koyasan from To-ji Temple&apos;s control, whereby he abolished the custom whereby Toji-Choja became the head priest of Kongobu-ji Temple at the same time and was ordained to be Kongobu-ji Temple&apos;s head priest; however, his effort failed due to the objection of the Kongobu-ji side (Hon-ji side).</e>
<cmt>choja としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>その後、座主を辞して根来山（和歌山県）に隠棲した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he resigned head priest and retired at Mt.Negoro (Wakayama Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, he resigned as head priest and retired at Mt. Negoro (Wakayama Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, he resigned as head priest and retired at Mt. Negoro (Wakayama Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="28">
<j>これより、金剛峯寺方（本寺方）と大伝法院（院方）の長く確執が続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this incident, Kongobuji side (Hon-ji side, 本寺方) continued to fight against Daidenpo-in (In side, 院方) for a long time.</e>
<cmt>「大伝法院」は「大伝法院方」の誤りだと思われますが、そのまま訳しました。院方→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this incident, the Kongobuji side (Hon-ji side, 本寺方) continued to fight against Daidenpo-in (inside, 院方), and this continued for a long time.</e>
<cmt>words missing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this incident, the Kongobu-ji side (Hon-ji side, 本寺方) continued to fight against Daidenpo-in (inside, 院方), and this continued for a long time.</e>
<cmt>上記と統一してKongobu-ji　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>両派は、古義（古義真言宗）・新義（新義真言宗）に分かれていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both sides split into Kogi (Kogi Shingon sect) and Shingi (Shingi Shingon sect).</e>
<cmt>古義真言宗→定訳不明、新義真言宗→http://homepage3.nifty.com/shingi/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The two sides split into the Kogi (Kogi Shingon sect) and Shingi (Shingi Shingon sect).</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The two sides split into the Kogi (Kogi Shingon sect) and Shingi (Shingi Shingon sect).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>豊山派・智山派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buzan-ha and Chisan-ha</e>
<cmt>http://www.buzan.or.jp/、http://www.chisan.or.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buzan-ha and Chisan-ha</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buzan-ha and Chisan-ha</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="30">
<j>1290年（正応3年）に頼瑜が大伝法院を根来山に移し、大日如来の加持法身説（新義）を唱えて、新義真言宗の教義の基礎を確立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1290 Raiyu relocated Daidenpo-in to Mt.Negoro and established the base of Shingi Shingon sect&apos;s Dharma by Kajihosshinsetsu (加持法身説) (Shingi) of Dainichinyorai.</e>
<cmt>頼瑜→Yahoo辞書、根来寺→http://www.negoroji.org/、加持法身説→定訳不明,http://www8.plala.or.jp/konjouin/oshie.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1290 Raiyu relocated Daidenpo-in to Mt. Negoro and established the base of the Shingi Shingon sect&apos;s Dharma by Kajihosshinsetsu (加持法身説) (Shingi) of Dainichinyorai.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1290 Raiyu relocated Daidenpo-in to Mt. Negoro and established the base of the Shingi Shingon sect&apos;s Dharma by Kajihosshinsetsu (加持法身説) (Shingi) of Dainichinyorai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>根来山は大伝法院を含めて根来寺となり隆盛を極めたが、1585年（天正13年）豊臣秀吉により、焼き討ちにされ灰燼に帰した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Negoro-ji Temple, founded at Mt.Negoro including Daidenpo-in, was in the ascendant, but was burned down by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI in 1585.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Negoro-ji Temple, founded at Mt. Negoro (including Daidenpo-in) was in the ascendant but was burned down by Hideyoshi Toyotomi in 1585.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Negoro-ji Temple, founded at Mt. Negoro (including Daidenpo-in) was in its ascendancy but was burned down by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI in 1585.</e>
<cmt>TOYOTOMIとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>そのため、1588年（天正16年）に専誉が長谷寺に入り、後に真言宗豊山派の総本山となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, Senyo went into Hasedera Temple in 1588, which became to be Grand Head Temple of Shingon sect Buzan-ha.</e>
<cmt>長谷寺→http://www.hasedera.or.jp/、真言宗豊山派→http://www.buzan.or.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, Senyo went into Hasedera Temple in 1588, which came to be the Grand Head Temple of the Shingon sect Buzan-ha.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, Senyo went into Hase-dera Temple in 1588, which came to be the grand head temple of the Shingon sect Buzan-ha.</e>
<cmt>hase-deraとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>1601年（慶長6年）に徳川家康の保護を受けて、玄宥（げんゆう）が根来寺にあった智積院を京都・七条に再建し、後に真言宗智山派の総本山となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1601 Genyu rebuilt Chishakuin Temple, which had located in the precincts of Neogro-ji Temple, at Shichijo in Kyoto by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA&apos;s support, and it became to be Grand Head Temple of Shingon sect Chisan-ha later.</e>
<cmt>玄宥→http://www10.ocn.ne.jp/~mk123456/kyoto/tisyaku.htm、智積院→http://kaiwai.city.kyoto.jp/search/view_sight.php?InforKindCode=1&amp;ManageCode=1000168、真言宗智山派→http://www.chisan.or.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1601 Genyu rebuilt Chishakuin Temple (which had located to the precincts of Neogro-ji Temple) at Shichijo, in Kyoto, doing so with Ieyasu Tokugawa&apos;s support, and later it became the Grand Head Temple of Shingon sect Chisan-ha.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1601 Genyu rebuilt Chishakuin Temple (which had relocated to the precincts of Neogro-ji Temple) at Shichijo, in Kyoto, doing so with Ieyasu TOKUGAWA&apos;s support, and later it became the grand head temple of the Shingon sect Chisan-ha.</e>
<cmt>TOKUGAWAとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>古義派教学の振興</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Promotion of Kogi sect&apos;s Dharma</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Promotion of the Kogi sect&apos;s Dharma</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Promotion of the Kogi sect&apos;s Dharma</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>南北朝時代 (日本)に東寺の僧、杲宝（ごうほう）・賢宝（げんぼう）らにより東寺不二門教学を大成させて、大日如来の本地加持説（古義）を説いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Nanbokucho Period (Japan) To-ji Temple&apos;s priests such as Goho and Kenpo completed Tojifujimonkyogaku (東寺不二門教学) and taught Honchikajisetsu (本地加持説) (Kogi) of Dainichinyorai.</e>
<cmt>杲宝→Yahoo辞書、賢宝→http://21dzk.l.u-tokyo.ac.jp/INBUDS/search.php?m=trdd&amp;usid=52288&amp;a=、東寺不二門教学、本地加持説→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Nanbokucho period (Japan) To-ji Temple&apos;s priests such as Goho and Kenpo completed Tojifujimonkyogaku (東寺不二門教学) and taught Honchikajisetsu (本地加持説) (Kogi) of Dainichinyorai.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan) To-ji Temple&apos;s priests such as Goho and Kenpo completed Tojifujimonkyogaku (東寺不二門教学) and taught Honchikajisetsu (本地加持説) (Kogi) of Dainichinyorai.</e>
<cmt>南北朝時代の訳を修正(Northern and Southern Dynasties) periodが重複または不要のため、削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>江戸幕府による統制</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Control by Government of Edo</e>
<cmt>江戸幕府→英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Control by the government of Edo</e>
<cmt>article, lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Control by the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)</e>
<cmt>the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) を追加しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="35">
<j>江戸時代に入ると、江戸幕府は仏教界に対して新たな宗教統制を講じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo Period Government of Edo carried out a new control measure of religions against Buddhism sects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo period, the government of Edo carried out a new control measure over religions, against Buddhist sects.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period, the Edo bakufu carried out a new control measure over religions, against Buddhist sects.</e>
<cmt>the Edo bakufu としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>真言宗には1604年（慶長14年）に東寺・醍醐寺・高野山学侶方・関東真言宗古義法度などの法度が出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Against Shingon sect, Hatto Acts such as Toji Daigoji Koyasan Gakuryogata Kanto Shingon sect Kogi Hatto Act (東寺・醍醐寺・高野山学侶方・関東真言宗古義法度) were put into effect in 1604.</e>
<cmt>東寺・醍醐寺・高野山学侶方・関東真言宗古義法度→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Against the Shingon sect, Hatto acts such as Toji Daigoji Koyasan Gakuryogata and the Kogi Hatto Act against the Kanto Shingon sect (東寺・醍醐寺・高野山学侶方・関東真言宗古義法度) were put into effect in 1604.</e>
<cmt>structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Counter to the Shingon sect, Hatto acts against To-ji Temple, Daigo-ji Temple and Koyasan Gakuryogata, as well as Hatto act against Kanto Shingon sect Kogi (関東真言宗古義法度) were put into effect in 1604.</e>
<cmt>東寺・醍醐寺・高野山学侶方のような寺院に対する法度、および　関東真言宗古義法度　が出されたと解釈し、左記の英文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>これにより、幕府の監視下に置かれることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By these acts, Shingon sect was placed under observation of government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of these acts, the Shingon sect was placed under agovernment observation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of these acts, the Shingon sect was placed under bakufu&apos;s (government) observation.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>廃仏棄釈の打撃・明治政府による統制</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Damage by the Exclusion of Buddhism and control by Meiji Government</e>
<cmt>廃仏棄釈→http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110000965537/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Damage by the Exclusion of Buddhism and control by Meiji Government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Damage by the exclusion of Buddhism and control by the Meiji government</e>
<cmt>一部大文字を小文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="38">
<j>明治維新以降、明治政府は神仏分離を推進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration Meiji Government promoted separation of Buddhism and Shintoism.</e>
<cmt>明治維新→英辞郎 on the WEB、神仏分離→http://bab.la/dictionary/english-japanese/separation+of+Buddhism+and+Shintoism.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Restoration, the Meiji government promoted the separation of Buddhism and Shintoism.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, the Meiji government promoted the separation of Buddhism and Shintoism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>それに伴い、廃仏棄釈が起った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It resulted in the Exclusion of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This resulted in the exclusion of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This resulted in the exclusion of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>真言宗の寺院は本山・末寺にかかわらず大きな打撃を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shingon sect temples suffered a big damage without regard to Head temple or sub temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The temples of the Shingon sect suffered great damage without regard to their status as head temples or sub-temples.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The temples of the Shingon sect suffered great damage without regard to their status as head temples or sub-temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>経済的には、政府の命令で、寺領の返納を要求して、強制的に返納させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the point of financial matters, Meiji Government forced them to return their property.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding financial matters, the Meiji government forced them to return their wealth.</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding financial matters, the Meiji government forced them to return their wealth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>没収もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a case of confiscation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a case of confiscation involved.</e>
<cmt>completed</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a case of confiscation involved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>特権も廃され、勅願所・門跡の称号の禁止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Privileges were abolished and the title of Chokugansyo, the temple Emperors prayed, and Monｚeki, the temple Imperial prince lived, were prohibited.</e>
<cmt>勅願所→定訳不明、門跡→定訳不明、http://dictionary.goo.ne.jp/leaf/jn/193500/m0u/%E9%96%80%E8%B7%A1/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Privileges were abolished and the title of Chokugansyo, the temple in which Emperors prayed, and Monzeki, the temple where the Imperial Prince lived, were prohibited.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Privileges were abolished, and the title of Chokugansho, the temple in which emperors prayed, and Monzeki--the temple where the Imperial Prince lived--were prohibited.</e>
<cmt>chokuganshoとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>これにより、多くの寺院の経営が立ち行かなくなり、廃寺に追い込まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By these, many temples became to have a difficulty in their management, so that they were forced to be abolished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, many temples began to experience difficulties in their management, so that they were forced to become defunct.</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, many temples began to experience difficulties in their management, so that they were forced to become defunct.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>僧籍を離れて、還俗する僧侶も現れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some monks left the priesthood and returned to secular life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some monks left the priesthood and returned to secular life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some monks left the priesthood and returned to secular life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>大師信仰</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Faith in Daishi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Faith in Daishi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Faith in Daishi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="46">
<j>宗祖・空海（弘法大師）への敬慕が厚い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a strong admiration for Kukai, the founder of sect (Kobo-daishi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a strong admiration for Kukai, the founder of sect (Kobo-daishi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a strong admiration for Kukai, the founder of the sect (Kobo Daishi).</e>
<cmt>Kobo Daishiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>10世紀には高野山で空海の入定信仰が起った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the 10th century, Nyujoshinko, a faith that Kukai had fallen into deep meditation, was created at Koyasan.</e>
<cmt>入定信仰→http://www.koyasan.or.jp/shingonshu/about/taishishinko.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the tenth century Nyujoshinko, the faith in which Kukai had fallen into deep meditation, was created at Koyasan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the tenth century Nyujoshinko, the faith in which Kukai had fallen into deep meditation, was created at Koyasan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>弘法大師信仰（大師信仰）を説いているのが真言宗の各派にいえる特徴の一つでもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the characteristic of Shingon sects is the preaching of faith in Kobo-daishi (faith in Daishi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the characteristics of the Shingon sects is the preaching of faith in Kobo-daishi (faith in Daishi).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the characteristics of the Shingon sects is the preaching of faith in Kobo-daishi (faith in Daishi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="49">
<j>宗祖・空海（774 - 835年）は、讃岐国屏風浦（現・香川県善通寺市）の出身で、仏教者であるとともに思想家、著述家、また「三筆」の1人に数えられる能書家として、後の日本文化に多大な影響を与えた人物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The founder of sect, Kukai (774-835) was born at Byobu-ga-ura Sanuki-no-kuni (讃岐国屏風浦), and a thinker, a writer and a good calligrapher consisting one of Sanpitsu, the three good calligraphers in history, as well as a Buddhist, and gave a strong influence on Japanese culture in later years.</e>
<cmt>讃岐国屏風浦→定訳不明、三筆→定訳不明、</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The founder of the sect, Kukai (774-835) was born at Byobu-ga-ura Sanuki-no-kuni (讃岐国屏風浦) (current Zentsu-ji City, Kagawa Prefecture); and as a thinker, writer and talented calligrapher from among the Sanpitsu (the three great calligraphers of history), as well as a Buddhist, he had a strong influence on Japanese culture in later years.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The founder of the sect, Kukai (774-835) was born at Byobu-ga-ura Sanuki-no-kuni (讃岐国屏風浦) (current Zentsu-ji City, Kagawa Prefecture); and as a thinker, writer and talented calligrapher from among the Sanpitsu (the three great calligraphers of history), as well as a Buddhist, he had a strong influence on Japanese culture in later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>彼は延暦23年（804年）、遣唐使船に同乗して唐に渡り、長安・青龍寺の恵果から密教の奥義を授かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went to Tang by Kentoshi Ship in 804 and was given an essential Dharma of Mikkyo from Eka of Shoryu-ji Temple in Choan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He went to Tang on the ship &quot;Kentoshi&quot; in 804, and was given an essential Dharma of Mikkyo from Eka, of Shoryu-ji Temple, in Choan.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He went to Tang on the ship &quot;Kentoshi&quot; in 804, and was given an essential Dharma of Mikkyo from Eka, of Shoryu-ji Temple, in Choan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>また、唐で多くの仏典、仏具、仏画などを得、日本へ請来した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He got many Buddhist scriptures, Buddhist altar equipment, Buddhist picture in Tang and brought them to Japan.</e>
<cmt>仏典、仏具、仏画→Webster Online Dictionary</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He obtained many Buddhist scriptures, Buddhist altar pieces and a Buddhist picture in Tang, and brought them to Japan.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He obtained many Buddhist scriptures, Buddhist altar pieces and a Buddhist picture in Tang, and brought them to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="52">
<j>弘仁7年（816年）には高野山（和歌山県伊都郡高野町）の地を得て、ここに金剛峯寺を開創、弘仁14年（823年）には、平安京の官寺であった東寺を嵯峨天皇より下賜され、これら両寺を真言密教の根本道場とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 816 he got a land of Koyasan (Koya-cho Itogun Wakayama Prefecture) and founded Kongobu-ji Temple there, and in 823 he was given To-ji Temple, which was a National Temple of Heiankyo, by Emperor Saga, and made them the fundamental Dojo of Shingon Mikkyo.</e>
<cmt>和歌山県伊都郡高野町→http://www.post.japanpost.jp/cgi-zip/zipcode.php?pref=30&amp;city=1303440、官寺→http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110000540572/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 816 he obtained the land of Koyasan (Koya-cho Itogun Wakayama Prefecture) and founded Kongobu-ji Temple there; later (in 823) he was given To-ji Temple, which was a national temple of Heiankyo, by Emperor Saga, and made them the fundamental dojo of Shingon Mikkyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 816 Kukai obtained the land of Koyasan (Koya-cho, Itogun, Wakayama Prefecture) and founded Kongobu-ji Temple there; later (in 823), the Emperor Saga gave him To-ji Temple, which was a national temple of Heian-kyo, and he made these temples the fundamental dojo of Shingon Mikkyo.</e>
<cmt>カンマの使い方を修正。theを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="53">
<j>835年（承和 (日本)2年）3月21日に、62才で高野山で入定（にゅうじょう）した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 21, 835, he fell into deep meditation at the age of 62 at Koyasan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 21, 835, he fell into deep meditation at the age of 62 at Koyasan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 21, 835, he fell into deep meditation at the age of 62 at Koyasan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>空海が入定してから86年後の延喜21年（921年）に、弘法大師の諡号が醍醐天皇より贈られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 921, 86 years later from Kukai&apos;s demise, Emperor Daigo gave a posthumous title of Kobo-daishi.</e>
<cmt>諡号→http://dictionary.goo.ne.jp/leaf/je/4520/m0u/%E3%81%8A%E3%81%8F%E3%82%8A%E3%81%AA/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 921, 86 years after Kukai&apos;s demise, Emperor Daigo awarded him the posthumous title of Kobo Daishi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 921, 86 years after Kukai&apos;s demise, the Emperor Daigo awarded him the posthumous title of Kobo Daishi.</e>
<cmt>theを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>真言八祖（しんごんはっそ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shingon Hasso (eight forefathers)</e>
<cmt>真言八祖→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shingon Hasso (Eight Forefathers)</e>
<cmt>capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shingon Hasso (Eight Forefathers)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="55">
<j>密教がインドで起こり、中国を経て、空海（弘法大師）に伝えられ、日本で独立した宗派として真言宗を開くまでに、八祖を経て伝えられたとする伝承がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a legend that there were eight forefathers during the time Mikkyo occurred in India, conveyed to Kukai (Kobo Daishi) through China, and Kukai established Shingon sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A legend holds that there were eight forefathers during the time in which Mikkyo occurred in India; this was conveyed to Kukai (Kobo Daishi) through China, and subsequently Kukai established the Shingon sect.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A legend holds that there were eight forefathers during the time in which Mikkyo occurred in India; this was conveyed to Kukai (Kobo Daishi) through China, and subsequently Kukai established the Shingon sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>これを真言八祖（しんごんはっそ）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is called Shingon Hasso.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is called Shingon Hasso.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is called Shingon Hasso.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="57">
<j>付法（ふほう）の八祖と伝持（でんじ）の八祖の二つがあり、空海は著作「秘密曼荼羅教付法伝」・「真言付法伝」で、真言密教の起源と付法の七祖・伝持の七祖（付法・伝持の八祖の内、弘法大師を除く七祖）の伝記や付法の系譜を記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are two kinds of Hasso, Fuho(付法) Hasso and Denji　(伝持) Hasso, and Kukai described the origin of Shingon Mikkyo, biography of ｓeven forefathers of Fuho and seven forefathers of Denji (seven forefathers of Fuso and Denji Hasso except Kobo-daishi) and lineage of Fuho in his works &apos;Himitsu Mandara Kyo Fuho Den (秘密曼荼羅教付法伝)&apos; and &apos;Shingon Fuho Den (真言付法伝)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>付法、伝持、秘密曼荼羅教付法伝、真言付法伝→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are two kinds of Hasso--Fuho(付法) Hasso and Denji (伝持) Hasso--and Kukai described the origin of Shingon Mikkyo, the biographies of the seven forefathers of Fuho and seven forefathers of Denji (seven forefathers of Fuso and Denji Hasso, excluding Kobo-daishi) and lineage of Fuho in his works entitled &quot;Himitsu Mandara Kyo Fuho Den (秘密曼荼羅教付法伝)&quot; and &quot;Shingon Fuho Den (真言付法伝).&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are two kinds of Hasso--Fuho Hasso (eight forefathers from Dainichinyorai to Kukai) and Denji Hasso (eight forefathers who appeared during the period of history in which the teachings of the Shingon sect had been introduced to Japan)--and Kukai described the origin of Shingon Mikkyo, the biographies of the seven forefathers of Fuho and seven forefathers of Denji (seven forefathers of Fuso and Denji Hasso except Kobo-daishi) and lineage of Fuho in his works &apos;Himitsu Mandala Kyo Fuho Den (秘密曼荼羅教付法伝)&apos; and &apos;Shingon Fuho Den (真言付法伝).&apos;</e>
<cmt>付法（ふほう）の八祖を　(eight forefathers from Dainichinyorai to Kukai)　、　伝持（でんじ）の八祖を (eight forefathers who appeared during the period of history in which the teachings of the Shingon sect had been introduced to Japan)←132より抜粋　として補足しました。Mandara→Mandala に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="58">
<j>本堂などに真言八祖（（伝持の八祖）・絵像で制作されることが多い）を祀られているのが、真言宗の寺院の特徴の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the characteristics of Shingon sect temples is that Shingon Hasso (Denji Hasso) are enshrined at main hall or other places (they are often drawn on pictures).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the characteristics of temples of the Shingon sect is that Shingon Hasso (Denji Hasso) are enshrined in the main hall or other places (they are often drawn as pictures).</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the characteristics of temples of the Shingon sect is that Shingon Hasso (Denji Hasso) are enshrined in the main hall or other places (they are often drawn as pictures).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>（祀られていない寺院もある。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Some temples do not enshrine them.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Some temples do not enshrine them.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Some temples do not enshrine them.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>付法の八祖</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fuho Hasso</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fuho Hasso</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fuho Hasso</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="60">
<j>真言宗の法流の正系を示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It shows the orthodox line of Shingon sect Dharma.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This shows the orthodox lineage of the Shingon sect Dharma.</e>
<cmt>Improved</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This shows the orthodox lineage of the Shingon sect Dharma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>教主大日如来の説法を金剛薩埵が聞いて教法が起こり、真言宗の教えが伝わった系譜である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a lineage of transmitting of Shingon Dharma since Kongosatta heard Dainichinyorai&apos;s sermon and Shingon Dharma began.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a lineage transmitting the Shingon Dharma since the time that Kongosatta heard Dainichinyorai&apos;s sermon and Shingon Dharma began.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was when Kongosatta heard Dainichinyorai&apos;s sermon that the Shingon Dharma&apos;s lineage began.</e>
<cmt>全体的に訳し直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="62">
<j>大日如来（だいにちにょらい）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dainichinyorai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dainichinyorai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dainichinyorai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="63">
<j>金剛薩埵（こんごうさった）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kongosatta</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kongosatta</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kongosatta</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="64">
<j>龍猛菩薩（りゅうみょうぼさつ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryumyo Bosatsu</e>
<cmt>http://www.tokuzouin.com/tokuzouin/shingonhasso.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryumyo Bosatsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryumyo Bosatsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="65">
<j>龍智菩薩（りゅうちぼさつ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryuchi Bosatu</e>
<cmt>http://www.tokuzouin.com/tokuzouin/shingonhasso.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryuchi Bosatu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryuchi Bosatu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="66">
<j>金剛智三蔵（こんごうちさんぞう）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kongochisanzo</e>
<cmt>http://www.tokuzouin.com/tokuzouin/shingonhasso.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kongochisanzo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kongochisanzo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="67">
<j>不空三蔵（ふくうさんぞう）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukusanzo</e>
<cmt>http://www.tokuzouin.com/tokuzouin/shingonhasso.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukusanzo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukusanzo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="68">
<j>恵果阿闍梨（けいかあじゃり）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keika Ajari</e>
<cmt>http://www.tokuzouin.com/tokuzouin/shingonhasso.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keika Ajari</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keika Ajari</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="69">
<j>弘法大師</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kobo-daishi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kobo-daishi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kobo-daishi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>伝持の八祖</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Denji Hasso</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Denji Hasso</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Denji Hasso</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="70">
<j>真言宗の教えが日本に伝わるまでの歴史に関わった8人の祖師。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It means eight forefathers who appeared in the history while teaching of Shingon sect had been introduced to Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It means that eight forefathers who appeared during the period of history in which the teachings of the Shingon sect had been introduced to Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It means that eight forefathers who appeared during the period of history in which the teachings of the Shingon sect had been introduced to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>付法の八祖の内、大日如来、金剛薩埵は歴史上の人物ではないために除いて、2人の祖師を加えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dainichinyorai and Kongosatta were removed from Fuho Hasso because they were not historical figures and the other two forefathers were added.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dainichinyorai and Kongosatta were removed from Fuho Hasso because they were not historical figures, and consequently the other two forefathers were added.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dainichinyorai and Kongosatta were removed from Fuho Hasso because they were not historical figures, and consequently the other two forefathers were added.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>八祖大師（はっそだいし）とも称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are also called Hasso Daishi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are also called Hasso Daishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are also called Hasso Daishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="73">
<j>一人一人持ち物を持っているが、その持ち物は悟りの本質をあらわしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each forefather has a belonging, which shows the essence of enlightenment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each forefather has a belonging that illustrates the essence of enlightenment.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each forefather has a belonging that illustrates the essence of enlightenment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="74">
<j>龍樹菩薩　：　大日如来の直弟子金剛薩埵（こんごうさった）から密教経典を授かって、世に伝えたといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryuju Bosatsu : it is said that he was given Mikkyo sutras from Kongosatta, an immediate pupil of Dainichinyorai, and conveyed them in this world.</e>
<cmt>龍樹菩薩→http://sips03.narahaku.go.jp/meihin/cyokoku/017.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was said that Ryuju Bosatsu had been given Mikkyo sutras from Kongosatta, an immediate pupil of Dainichinyorai, and thus conveyed them in this world.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was said that Ryuju Bosatsu had been given Mikkyo sutras from Kongosatta, an immediate pupil of Dainichinyorai, and thus conveyed them in this world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>（三鈷杵（さんこしょ）を右手に持っている）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(He holds Sankosho in the right hand.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(He holds Sankosho in the right hand.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(He holds Sankosho in the right hand.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="76">
<j>龍智菩薩　：　龍猛から密教を授かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryuchi Bosatsu : he was be initiated into Mikkyo from Ryumyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryuchi Bosatsu was initiated into Mikkyo from Ryumyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryuchi Bosatsu: he was initiated into Mikkyo from Ryumyo.</e>
<cmt>日本文と英訳文のスタイルを合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>（経文を右手に持っている）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(He has sutras in the right hand.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(He has sutras in the right hand.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(He has sutras in the right hand.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="78">
<j>金剛智三蔵　：　インドで龍智から密教を学んだのち唐へ渡り、「金剛頂経」を伝える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kongochi Sanzo : he went to Tang and conveyed &apos;Kongocho-kyo&apos; after he learned Mikkyo from Ryuchi in India.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kongochisanzo went to Tang and conveyed &quot;Kongocho-kyo&quot; after he learned Mikkyo from Ryuchi in India.</e>
<cmt>comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kongochisanzo went to Tang and conveyed &quot;Kongocho-kyo&quot; after he learned Mikkyo from Ryuchi in India.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>（数珠を右手に持っている）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(He has beadroll in the right hand.)</e>
<cmt>英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(He has a beadroll in his right hand.)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(He has a beadroll in his right hand.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="80">
<j>不空三蔵　：　西域生まれ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fuku Sanzo : he was born at the west area of China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukusanzo was born in western China.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukusanzo was born in western China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>貿易商の叔父に連れられて唐へ行き、長安で金剛智に入門。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went to Tang with his uncle, a merchant, and became a disciple of Kongochi at Choan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He went to Tang with his uncle, a merchant, and became a disciple of Kongochi at Choan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He went to Tang with his uncle, a merchant, and became a disciple of Kongochi at Choan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>「金剛頂経」を漢語に翻訳し、灌頂道場を開いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He translated &apos;Kongocho-kyo&apos; into Chinese and opened Kanjo Dojo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He translated &apos;Kongocho-kyo&apos; into Chinese, and opened Kanjo Dojo.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He translated &apos;Kongocho-kyo&apos; into Chinese, and opened Kanjo Dojo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>（外縛印（げばくいん）を結んでいる）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(He makes Gebaku-in, a Buddhism symbolic gesture with fingers.)</e>
<cmt>印を結ぶ→http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E7%9C%9F%E8%A8%80%E5%AE%97</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(He makes Gebaku-in, a symbolic Buddhist gesture, with his fingers.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(He makes Gebaku-in, a symbolic Buddhist gesture, with his fingers.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="84">
<j>善無畏三蔵（ぜんむいさんぞう　：　インド生まれ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zenmuisanzo : he was born in India.</e>
<cmt>http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E7%9C%9F%E8%A8%80%E5%AE%97</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zenmuisanzo was born in India.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zenmuisanzo was born in India.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>大乗仏教を学び、さらに密教を受け継ぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He learned Mahayana Buddhism and took over Mikkyo.</e>
<cmt>大乗仏教→Webster Online Dictionary</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He learned Mahayana Buddhism and took over Mikkyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He learned Mahayana Buddhism and took over Mikkyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>80歳になって唐に渡り、「大日経」を伝える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went to Tang at the age of 80, and conveyed Dainichi-kyo Sutra.</e>
<cmt>大日経→Yahoo辞書</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He went to Tang at the age of 80, and conveyed the Dainichi-kyo sutra.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He went to Tang at the age of 80, and conveyed the Dainichi-kyo sutra.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>（右手の人さし指をたてている）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(He holds up an index finger of right hand.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(He holds up the index finger of his right hand.)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(He holds up the index finger of his right hand.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="88">
<j>一行禅師（いちぎょうぜんじ）：　中国生まれ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ichigyozenji : he was born in China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ichigyozenji was born in China.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zen master Ichigyo was born in China.</e>
<cmt>zen masterとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>禅や天台教学、天文学、数学を学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He learned Zen, Tendai Dharma, astronomy and math.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He studied Zen, Tendai Dharma, astronomy and mathematics.</e>
<cmt>completed</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He studied Zen, Tendai Dharma, astronomy and mathematics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>長安で善無畏に入門し、善無畏の口述をもとに「大日経疏（だいにちきょうしょ）」を完成させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He learned from Zenmui at Choan and completed &apos;Dainichikyo-sho&apos; based on the dictations of Zenmui.</e>
<cmt>善無畏→http://www.tokuzouin.com/tokuzouin/shingonhasso.html、大日経疏→Yahoo辞書</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He learned from Zenmui at Choan, and completed &quot;Dainichikyo-sho&quot; based on the dictations of Zenmui.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He learned from Zenmui at Choan, and completed &apos;Dainichikyo-sho&apos; based on the dictations of Zenmui.</e>
<cmt>括弧を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>（法衣のなかで印を結んでいる）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(He makes a symbolic gesture with fingers in his clerical garment.)</e>
<cmt>法衣→Webster Online Dictionary</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Clothed in his clerical garb, he makes a symbolic gesture with his fingers.)</e>
<cmt>clearer</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Clothed in his clerical garb, he makes a symbolic gesture with his fingers.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="92">
<j>恵果阿闍梨　：　中国生まれ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keika Ajari : he was born in China.</e>
<cmt>http://www.tokuzouin.com/tokuzouin/shingonhasso.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keika Ajari was born in China.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keika Ajari was born in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>金剛界・胎蔵界両部の密教を受け継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He took over Mikkyo of both Vajradhatu and Garbhadhatu.</e>
<cmt>金剛界・胎蔵界→http://en.bab.la/dictionary/english-japanese/Vajradhatu+Mandala.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He took over the Mikkyo of Vajradhatu and Garbhadhatu.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He took over the Mikkyo of Vajradhatu and Garbhadhatu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>（椅子に座り、横に童を待らせている）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(He is seated on a chair and has a child serve beside him.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(He is seated on a chair and has a child serve beside him.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(He is seated on a chair and has a child serve beside him.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="95">
<j>弘法大師　：　恵果阿闍梨から金剛・胎蔵界両部を授けられ、日本に伝えて真言密教を開いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kobo-daishi : he was given both Vajradhatu and Garbhadhatu from Keika Ajari and founded Shingon Mikkyo by conveying them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kobo-daishi was given both Vajradhatu and Garbhadhatu from Keika Ajari, and he founded Shingon Mikkyo by conveying them.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kobo-daishi was given both Vajradhatu and Garbhadhatu from Keika Ajari, and he founded Shingon Mikkyo by conveying them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>空海。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kukai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kukai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kukai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>（五鈷杵（ごこしょ）を右手にもち、左手には念珠をもっている）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(He has 5 - Pronged Pestles on the right hand and rosary in the left hand.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(He has five-prong pestles on his right hand and a rosary in his left hand.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(He has five-prong pestles on his right hand and a rosary in his left hand.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>教義</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dharma</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dharma</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dharma</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="98">
<j>真言宗は即身成仏と密厳国土をその教義とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Dharma of Shingon sect is Sokushin Jobutsu and Mitsugonkokudo.</e>
<cmt>即身成仏→http://www.shingon.org/teachings/ShingonMikkyo/sokushin.html、　密厳国土→http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=%E3%81%BF%E3%81%A4%E3%81%94&amp;dtype=0&amp;stype=0&amp;dname=0ss&amp;pagenum=1&amp;index=118809200000</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dharmas of the Shingon sect are Sokushin Jobutsu and Mitsugonkokudo.</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dharmas of the Shingon sect are Sokushin Jobutsu (becoming Buddha in this life) and Mitsugonkokudo (esoterically adorned Buddha&apos;s Land).</e>
<cmt>即身成仏　と　密厳国土　の補足を左記としました。　→[http://www.shingon.org/teachings/ShingonMikkyo/mitsugon.html]</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>本尊は宇宙の本体であり絶対の真理である大日如来。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main image is Dainichinyorai, who is an entity of the universe and the absolute truth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main image is Dainichinyorai, which is an entity of the universe and the absolute truth.</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main image is Dainichinyorai, which is an entity of the universe and the absolute truth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="100">
<j>所依の経典（基本の重要経典）は大日経（正式には大毘盧遮那成仏神変加持経／だいびるしゃなじょうぶつじんぺんかじきょう）と金剛頂経（正式には「金剛頂一切如来真実摂大乗現証大教王教」、または「金剛頂瑜伽真実大教王経」、「蘇悉地経」（そじつぢきょう）・「瑜祗経」（ゆぎきょう）・「要略念誦経」（ようりゃくねんじゅきょう）・理趣経（りしゅきょう）などである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fundamental Sutra is Dainichi-kyo Sutra (formally, &apos;Daibirushanabutsu-Jimpenkaji-kyo Sutra&apos;) and Kongocho-kyo (formally, Kongocho Issainyorai Shinjitsusetsudaijogensho Daikyoo-kyo) or &apos;Kongocho-Yuga-Shinjitsu-Daio-kyo Sutra&apos;, &apos;Soshitsuji-kyo Sutra&apos;, &apos;Yugi-kyo Sutra&apos;, &apos;Yoryakunenju-kyo Sutra&apos;&apos;, &apos;Rishu-kyo Sutra&apos;, and so on.</e>
<cmt>大毘盧遮那成仏神変加持経→http://www.emuseum.jp/cgi/bunsyutu.cgi?SyoID=5&amp;ID=w027&amp;SubID=s182&amp;Link=w027x006、金剛頂一切如来真実摂大乗現証大教王教→http://edb.kulib.kyoto-u.ac.jp/exhibit/kichosearch/src/ippan301.html,金剛頂瑜伽真実大教王経→http://www.bdk.or.jp/activity/list.html#list040、蘇悉地経→http://www.j-reimei.com/soshitsujikyo.htm、瑜祗経、要略念誦経、理趣経→http://www.bukkyo.net/shuuha/singonshu.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fundamental sutra is Dainichi-kyo Sutra (formally, Daibirushanabutsu-Jimpenkaji-kyo Sutra) and Kongocho-kyo (formally, Kongocho Issainyorai Shinjitsusetsudaijogensho Daikyoo-kyo) or Kongocho-Yuga-Shinjitsu-Daio-kyo Sutra, Soshitsuji-kyo Sutra, Yugi-kyo Sutra, Yoryakunenju-kyo Sutra, Rishu-kyo Sutra, and so on.</e>
<cmt>excessive punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fundamental sutra is Dainichi-kyo Sutra (formally, &apos;Daibirushanajobutsu-Jinpenkaji-kyo Sutra&apos;) and Kongocho-kyo (formally, &apos;Kongocho Issainyorai Shinjitsusetsudaijogensho Daikyoo-kyo&apos; or &apos;Kongocho-Yuga-Shinjitsu-Daio-kyo Sutra,&apos; &apos;Soshitsuji-kyo Sutra,&apos; &apos;Yugi-kyo Sutra,&apos; &apos;Yoryakunenju-kyo Sutra,&apos; &apos;Rishu-kyo Sutra,&apos;) and so on.</e>
<cmt>Daibirushanajobutsuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="101">
<j>論疏（論文の類）は「菩提心論」（ぼだいしんろん）・「釈摩訶衍論」（しゃくまかえんろん）・「大日経疏」（だいにちきょうしょ）などである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ronso (a kind of academic papers) are &apos;Bodaishinron&apos;, &apos;Shakumakaenron&apos;, &apos;Dainichi-kyoso&apos;, and so on.</e>
<cmt>論疏→定訳不明、菩提心論→http://www.sakai.zaq.ne.jp/piicats/sokushin.htm、釈摩訶衍論→http://www.hannya.net/advaita.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ronso (academic papers) are &apos;Bodaishinron,&apos; &apos;Shakumakaenron,&apos; &apos;Dainichi-kyoso&apos; and so on.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ronso (academic papers) are &apos;Bodaishinron,&apos; &apos;Shakumakaenron,&apos; &apos;Dainichi-kyoso&apos; and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="102">
<j>空海の著作、秘密曼荼羅十住心論（ひみつまんだらじゅうじゅうしんろん）（「十住心論・じゅうじゅうしんろん）・「秘蔵宝鑰」（ひぞうほうやく）・「辦顕密二教論」（べんけんみつにきょうろん）・「即身成仏義」（そくしんじょうぶつぎ）・「声字実相義」（しょうじじっそうぎ）・「吽字義」（うんじぎ）なども論疏としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following Kukai&apos;s works are considered as Ronso: &apos;Himitsu-Mandara-Jujushinron&apos; (&apos;Jujushinron&apos;), &apos;Hizo-Hoyaku&apos;, &apos;Benkenmitsu-Nikyoron&apos;, &apos;Sokushinjobutsu-gi&apos;, &apos;Shojijisso-gi&apos;, &apos;Un-jigi&apos; and so on.</e>
<cmt>十住心論→http://www.sakai.zaq.ne.jp/piicats/jyujyushinnron.html、辦顕密(べんけんみつ)二教論→http://www.sakai.zaq.ne.jp/piicats/sokushin.htm、即身成仏義→http://www.sakai.zaq.ne.jp/piicats/sokushinnjyoubutsugi.htm、声字実相(しょうじじっそう)義→http://www.sakai.zaq.ne.jp/piicats/sokushin.html、吽(うん)字義→http://www.sakai.zaq.ne.jp/piicats/sokushin.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following works of Kukai are considered to be ronso: &apos;Himitsu-Mandara-Jujushinron (Jujushinron),&apos; &apos;Hizo-Hoyaku,&apos; &apos;Benkenmitsu-Nikyoron,&apos; &apos;Sokushinjobutsu-gi,&apos; &apos;Shojijisso-gi,&apos; &apos;Un-jigi&apos; and so on.</e>
<cmt>Structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following works of Kukai are considered to be ronso: &apos;Himitsu-Mandala-Jujushinron (Jujushinron),&apos; &apos;Hizo-Hoyaku,&apos; &apos;Benkenmitsu-Nikyoron,&apos; &apos;Sokushinjobutsu-gi,&apos; &apos;Shojijisso-gi,&apos; &apos;Un-jigi&apos; and so on.</e>
<cmt>Mandara→Mandala に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="103">
<j>三密（（身密・手に諸尊の印契（印相）を結ぶ）、（口密（語密）・口に真言を読誦する）、（心密・心に曼荼羅の諸尊を観想する））の修行により、本尊と一体となり、即身成仏が実現するとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the Dharma, ascetic training of the Three Mysteries (the Secret of the Body, i.e., making symbolic gestures with the fingers, the Secret of Speech, i.e., reciting Shingon, and the Secret of Mind, i.e., visualization of the Buddha on Mandara picture) leads to integration with the main image and Sokushin Jobutsu, which means that one becomes Buddha with one&apos;s present physical body..</e>
<cmt>三密、身密、口密、語密→http://www.shingon.org/teachings/ShingonMikkyo/sanmitsu.html、曼荼羅→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the Dharma, ascetic training of the Three Mysteries (the Secret of the Body, i.e., making symbolic gestures with the fingers; the Secret of Speech, i.e., reciting Shingon; and the Secret of Mind, i.e., visualization of the Buddha in the Mandara picture) leads to integration with the main image and Sokushin Jobutsu, which means that one becomes Buddha with one&apos;s present physical body.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the Dharma, ascetic training of the Three Mysteries (the Secret of the Body, i.e., making symbolic gestures with the fingers; the Secret of Speech, i.e., reciting Shingon; and the Secret of Mind, i.e., visualization of the Buddha in the Mandala picture) leads to integration with the main image and Sokushin Jobutsu, which means that one becomes Buddha with one&apos;s present physical body.</e>
<cmt>Mandara→Mandala に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>事相と教相</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jiso and Kyoso (教相)</e>
<cmt>教相→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jiso and Kyoso (教相)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jiso and Kyoso (教相)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="104">
<j>真言密教を学んでいくうえで、「事相」（じそう）と「教相」（きょうそう）が重要視される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For learning of Shingon Mikkyo, &apos;Jiso&apos; and &apos;Kyoso&apos; are considered to be important.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jiso&apos; and &apos;Kyoso&apos; are considered important in the learning of Shingon Mikkyo.</e>
<cmt>excess</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jiso&apos; and &apos;Kyoso&apos; are considered important in the learning of Shingon Mikkyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>事相は、教相の対語で、真言密教を実践する方法。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jiso is a word as opposed to Kyoso and a way to implement Shingon Mikkyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Jiso&quot; is a word (as opposed to &quot;Kyoso&quot;) and a way to implement Shingon Mikkyo.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jiso is a word (as opposed to Kyoso) and a way to implement Shingon Mikkyo.</e>
<cmt>括弧削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>修法の作法（灌頂・護摩・観法・印契・真言などの行法）を指し、教相は、真言密教の理論である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It means a manner of ascetic training (修法) (training manners (行法) such as Kanjo, rite, Kanpo (mediation, 観法), Ingei (sign of fingers, 印契), Shingon) and Kyoso is a theory of Shingon Mikkyo.</e>
<cmt>修法→定訳不明、http://dictionary.goo.ne.jp/leaf/jn/91738/m0u/%E4%BF%AE%E6%B3%95/、観法、行法→定訳不明、護摩→Webster Online Dictionary、印契→定訳不明,http://www10.ocn.ne.jp/~seihou/art/kouza/m005.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It means a manner of ascetic training (修法) (training manners (行法) such as Kanjo, rite, Kanpo (meditation, 観法) and Ingei (sign made with the fingers, 印契), Shingon), while Kyoso is a theory of Shingon Mikkyo.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It means a manner of ascetic training (修法) (training manners (行法) such as Kanjo, rite, Kanpo (meditation, 観法) and Ingei (sign made with the fingers, 印契), Shingon), while Kyoso is a theory of Shingon Mikkyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>真言宗の主要経典「大日経」は教相の経典、金剛頂経は事相の経典である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dainichi-kyo Sutra, the main sutra of Shingon sect is a sutra of Kyoso, and Kongocho-kyo is a sutra of Jiso.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dainichi-kyo Sutra, the main sutra of the Shingon sect, is a sutra of Kyoso, and Kongocho-kyo is a sutra of Jiso.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dainichi-kyo Sutra, the main sutra of the Shingon sect, is a sutra of Kyoso, and Kongocho-kyo is a sutra of Jiso.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="108">
<j>教相を学んでいくことで、真言密教の理論を理解し、理論を実践する方法を行うために事相を学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Learning Kyoso leads to understanding of Shingon Mikkyo theory and learning Jiso leads to implementing a theory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Learning Kyoso leads to an understanding of Shingon Mikkyo theory, and learning Jiso leads to the implementation of a theory.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Learning Kyoso leads to an understanding of Shingon Mikkyo theory, and learning Jiso leads to the implementation of a theory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>教相の裏付けのない、事相は無意味な動作になってしまうという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jiso without any support of Kyoso falls into meaningless activity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jiso, without any support of Kyoso, simply becomes a meaningless activity.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jiso, without any support of Kyoso, simply becomes a meaningless activity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="110">
<j>事相・教相の両方を学ばなければ、真言密教の理想への到達は出来ないとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Without learning both of Jiso and Kyoso, no one can reach the ideal of Shingon Mikkyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Without learning both Jiso and Kyoso, one cannot reach the ideal of Shingon Mikkyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Without learning both Jiso and Kyoso, one cannot reach the ideal of Shingon Mikkyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>事相・教相の両方を習得する重要性を説くたとえとして、事相・教相を車の両輪に置き換えて説く場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For an example to show the importance to learn both of Jiso and Kyoso, there is an explanation to compare Jiso and Kyoso to two wheels of one cart.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As an example of the importance of learning both Jiso and Kyoso, there is an explanation that compares Jiso and Kyoso to two wheels on a single cart.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To explain the importance of learning both Jiso and Kyoso, some have compared Jiso and Kyoso to two wheels on a single cart.</e>
<cmt>「～する場合がある」　を訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>また、慈雲は「事相を離れて教相なく、教相を離れて事相なし、事教一致して、密義をつくすべき」と述べた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Jiun said &apos;Kyoso does not exist without Jiso and Jiso does not exist without Kyoso, so that we should learn them together and try to get Mitsugi (the Dharma of Mikkyo)(密義)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>慈雲→http://www.horakuji.hello-net.info/jiun/about.htm、密義→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, Jiun said, &apos;Kyoso does not exist without Jiso and Jiso does not exist without Kyoso, so that we should learn them together and try to attain Mitsugi (the Dharma of Mikkyo)(密義).&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, Jiun said, &apos;Kyoso does not exist without Jiso and Jiso does not exist without Kyoso, so that we should learn them together and try to attain Mitsugi (the Dharma of Mikkyo)(密義).&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="113">
<j>9世紀半ば（平安時代中期）から、事相の研究が盛んとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the mid-ninth century (in the mid-Heian Period), research of Jiso had become popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The research of Jiso has been popular since the mid-ninth century (during the mid-Heian period).</e>
<cmt>structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The research of Jiso has been popular since the mid-ninth century (during the mid-Heian period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>益信（やくしん）に始まる広沢流（ひろさわりゅう）、聖宝（しょうほう）を祖とする小野流（おのりゅう）が起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yakushin began Hirosawa-ryu and Shoho began Ono-ryu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yakushin began Hirosawa-ryu, and Shoho began Ono-ryu.</e>
<cmt>comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yakushin began Hirosawa-ryu school, and Shoho began Ono-ryu school.</e>
<cmt>「流」　の説明として　school　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>両派は、それぞれ六流に分かれて、野沢（やたく）十二流（根本十二流）になり、やがて三十六流になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both schools separated into each six schools, i.e.,Yataku Juni-ryu (Konpon Juni-ryu, (根本十二流)) and became 36 schools later.</e>
<cmt>根本十二流→定訳不明,http://72.14.235.132/search?q=cache:hqwXlmj-0-AJ:www.kongouji.com/kouza87.rtf+%E6%A0%B9%E6%9C%AC%E5%8D%81%E4%BA%8C%E6%B5%81&amp;cd=5&amp;hl=ja&amp;ct=clnk&amp;gl=jp</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both schools separated into six schools each, e.g. Yataku Juni-ryu (Konpon Juni-ryu, (根本十二流)), and ultimately they became 36 schools.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both schools separated into six schools each, e.g. Yataku Juni-ryu (12 schools of Yataku, also called Konpon Juni-ryu (12 schools of basics)), and ultimately they became 36 schools.</e>
<cmt>野沢（やたく）十二流（根本十二流）を、Yataku Juni-ryu (12 schools of Yataku, also called Konpon Juni-ryu (12 schools of basics))と補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>その後、法流は、あわせて100余りを数えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, the number of schools was over 100.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, the number of schools exceeded 100.</e>
<cmt>better</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, the number of schools exceeded 100.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>真言密教の事相の流派は、すべて、広沢流・小野流の二流から分かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The school of Shingon Mikkyo&apos;s Jiso were all divided from two schools, Hirosawa-ryu and Ono-ryu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The schools of Shingon Mikkyo&apos;s Jiso were all derived from two schools: Hirosawa-ryu and Ono-ryu.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The schools of Shingon Mikkyo&apos;s Jiso were all derived from two schools: Hirosawa-ryu and Ono-ryu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="118">
<j>広沢流・小野流（野沢十二流）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hirosawa-ryu and Ono-ryu (Yataku Juni-ryu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hirosawa-ryu and Ono-ryu (Yataku Juni-ryu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hirosawa-ryu and Ono-ryu (Yataku Juni-ryu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="119">
<j>平安中期に益信に始まる広沢流、聖宝を始祖とする小野流が起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the mid-Heian Period, Yakushin began Hirosawa-ryu and Shoho began Ono-ryu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the mid-Heian period, Yakushin began Hirosawa-ryu and Shoho began Ono-ryu.</e>
<cmt>better</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the mid-Heian period, Yakushin began Hirosawa-ryu school and Shoho began Ono-ryu school.</e>
<cmt>「流」の後にschoolを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>両派は、それぞれ六流に分かれて、野沢十二流（やたくじゅうにりゅう）、または、根本十二流と称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both schools split over each six schools and called Yataku Juni-ryu or Konpon Juni-ryu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both schools split into six schools and called themselves Yataku Juni-ryu or Konpon Juni-ryu.</e>
<cmt>grammar, clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both schools split into six schools and called themselves Yataku Juni-ryu or Konpon Juni-ryu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="121">
<j>野沢十二流の定義では、持明院流を広沢流に入れない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the definition of Yataku Juni-ryu, Jimyoiin-ryu is not included into Hirosawa-ryu.</e>
<cmt>持明院流→Yahoo辞書</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the definition of Yataku Juni-ryu, Jimyoiin-ryu is not included in Hirosawa-ryu.</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the definition of Yataku Juni-ryu, Jimyoiin-ryu is not included in Hirosawa-ryu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>また、中院流を小野流に入れない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Nakanoin-ryu is not included into Ono-ryu.</e>
<cmt>中院流→Yahoo辞書</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, Nakanoin-ryu is not included in Ono-ryu.</e>
<cmt>better</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, Nakanoin-ryu is not included in Ono-ryu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>いずれの法流も、高野山に移ったためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is because both schools moved to Koyasan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because both schools had moved to Koyasan.</e>
<cmt>better</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because both schools had moved to Koyasan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>これは、御七日御修法など公請の修法に関与しないために区別されただけで、野沢十二流は、東密事相の法流をすべてを示したものではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These are distinguished just because they play no role in Kujo no Shuho (Official Mikkyo rites, 公請の修法) such as Goshichinichimishiho, so that Yataku Juni-ryu does not include all schools of Tomitsu Jiso (東密事相).</e>
<cmt>「御七日御修法」→「後七日御修法」の誤りと思われます。http://www5b.biglobe.ne.jp/~jurinji/mishiho.htm、公請→定訳不明、http://dictionary.goo.ne.jp/leaf/jn/53174/m0u/%E5%85%AC%E8%AB%8B/、東密事相→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These are distinguished simply because they play no role in Kujo no Shuho (official Mikkyo rites, 公請の修法) such as Goshichinichimishiho, so that Yataku Juni-ryu does not include all the schools of Tomitsu Jiso (東密事相).</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These are distinguished simply because they play no role in Kujo no Shuho (official Mikkyo rites, 公請の修法) such as Goshichinichimishiho (annual Shingon prayer ritual), so that Yataku Juni-ryu does not include all the schools of Tomitsu Jiso (東密事相).</e>
<cmt>説明として　annual Shingon prayer ritual　を追加しました。→[http://jishobot.com/terms/show/274348]</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>広沢流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hirosawa-ryu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hirosawa-ryu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hirosawa-ryu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="125">
<j>特徴は、儀軌を重んじる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is characterized by putting a high value on Giki (rules of rites,儀軌).</e>
<cmt>儀軌→定訳不明、http://dictionary.goo.ne.jp/leaf/jn/43383/m0u/%E5%84%80%E8%BB%8C/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is characterized by the high value that is placed on Giki (rules of rites,儀軌).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is characterized by the high value that is placed on Giki (rules of rites,儀軌).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>寛朝が建立した京都市右京区嵯峨広沢にある広沢池の南にある遍照寺 (京都市)の所在地名が語源となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was named after a place name of Hensho-ji Temple (Kyoto City) built by Kancho, which lies in the south of Hirosawa-no-ike Pond (Saga Hirosawa Ukyo Ward Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was named after the place name of Hensho-ji Temple (Kyoto City) built by Kancho, which lies in the south of Hirosawa-no-ike Pond (in the Saga Hirosawa Ukyo ward of Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was named after the place name of Hensho-ji Temple (Kyoto City) built by Kancho, which lies in the south of Hirosawa-no-ike Pond (in the Saga Hirosawa, Ukyo ward of Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>カンマ追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="127">
<j>広義では、東密事相を2分した場合、小野流の対をなす法流。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a broad sense, when Tomitsujiso is divided into two, it is the school as opposed to Ono-ryu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a broad sense, when Tomitsujiso is divided in two, it is the school as opposed to Ono-ryu.</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a broad sense, when Tomitsujiso is divided in two, it is the school as opposed to Ono-ryu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>狭義では、広沢流内の法流、仁和三流、広沢三流をあわせて広沢六流と称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a narrow sense, Ninna-san-ryu, inside school of Hirosawa-ryu, and Hirosawa-san-ryu are called Hirosawa-roku-ryu altogether.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a narrow sense, Ninna-san-ryu (within the school of Hirosawa-ryu) and Hirosawa-san-ryu are together called Hirosawa-roku-ryu.</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a narrow sense, Ninna-san-ryu (within the school of Hirosawa-ryu) and Hirosawa-san-ryu are together called Hirosawa-roku-ryu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>しかし、六流に属する法流は一定しておらず、観音院流・仁和御流系の北院流・慈尊院流などを入れる説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But which schools should be included in Roku-ryu is not established and there is a theory including Hokuin-ryu and Jisonin-ryu, linage of Hokuin-ryu and Ninna-goryu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While it is not clear which of the schools should be included in Roku-ryu is not established, there is a theory that includes Hokuin-ryu and Jisonin-ryu in the lineage of Hokuin-ryu and Ninna-goryu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, which of the schools should be included in Roku-ryu is not established, and there is a theory that includes Hokuin-ryu and Jisonin-ryu in the lineage of Kannonin-ryu and Ninna-goryu.</e>
<cmt>Hokuin-ryu→Kannonin-ryu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>保寿院流・仁和御流・西院流（にしのいんりゅう）を仁和三流と称し、華蔵院流・忍辱山流（にんにくせんりゅう）・伝法院流を広沢三流と称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hojuin-ryu, Ninna-goryu and Nishinoin-ryu are called Ninna-san-ryu, and Kezoin-ryu, Ninnikuse-ryu and Denpoin-ryu are called Hirosawa-san-ryu.</e>
<cmt>西院流→http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110000349542/、華蔵院流→http://www.kanto88.net/kanto88_62.html、伝法院流→用語リストではDenpoun-ryuとなっていましたが、「大伝法院」はDaidenpo-in(用語リスト61) なので、Denpoin-ryuと判断しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hojuin-ryu, Ninna-goryu and Nishinoin-ryu are called Ninna-san-ryu, and Kezoin-ryu, Ninnikuse-ryu and Denpoin-ryu are called Hirosawa-san-ryu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hojuin-ryu, Ninna-goryu and Nishinoin-ryu are called Ninna-san-ryu, and Kezoin-ryu, Ninnikusen-ryu and Denpoin-ryu are called Hirosawa-san-ryu.</e>
<cmt>Ninnikusen-ryuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="131">
<j>広沢流系流派略系譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The simplified linage of Hirosawa-ryu schools</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The simplified lineage of Hirosawa-ryu schools</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The simplified lineage of Hirosawa-ryu schools</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>仁和御流略系譜（派祖・覚法）　空海-真雅-源仁-益信-寛平法皇（宇多天皇）-寛朝-済信-性信-寛助-覚法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ninna-goryu simplified linage (founder: Kakuho) Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Yakushin - Kanpyo Hoo (Emperor Uda) - Kancho - Saishin - Shoshin - Kanjo - Kakuho</e>
<cmt>覚法→http://www.horakuji.hello-net.info/jiun/biography/10.htm、真雅→http://homepage3.nifty.com/y-maki/gosyo/sinnpenn/0258.pdf、源仁→http://www.ubasoku.jp/introduction/shobo.htm、済信→http://homepage3.nifty.com/y-maki/gosyo/sinnpenn/0258.pdf、性信→http://www.sol.dti.ne.jp/~shiraka/24hai.html、寛助→Yahoo辞書</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ninna-goryu simplified lineage (founder, Kakuho): Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Yakushin - Kanpyo Hoo (Emperor Uda) - Kancho - Saishin - Shoshin - Kanjo - Kakuho</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ninna-goryu simplified lineage (founder, Kakuho): Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Yakushin - Kanpyo Hoo (Emperor Uda) - Kancho - Saishin - Shoshin - Kanjo - Kakuho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>西院流略系譜（派祖・信証）　空海-真雅-源仁-益信-寛平法皇（宇多天皇）-寛朝-済信-性信-寛助-信証</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nishinoin-ryu simplified linage (founder: Shinsho(信証)) Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Yakushin - Kanpyo Hoo (Emperor Uda) - Kancho - Saishin - Shoshin - Kanjo - Shinsho</e>
<cmt>信証→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nishinoin-ryu simplified lineage (founder, Shinsho (信証)): Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Yakushin - Kanpyo Hoo (Emperor Uda) - Kancho - Saishin - Shoshin - Kanjo - Shinsho</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nishinoin-ryu simplified lineage (founder, Shinsho (信証)): Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Yakushin - Kanpyo Hoo (Emperor Uda) - Kancho - Saishin - Shoshin - Kanjo - Shinsho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>保寿院流略系譜（派祖・永厳）　空海-真雅-源仁-益信-寛平法皇（宇多天皇）-寛朝-済信-性信-寛助-永厳</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hojuiin-ryu simplified linage (founder: Eigon) Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Yakushin - Kanpyo Hoo (Emperor Uda) - Kancho - Saishin - Shoshin - Kanjo - Eigon</e>
<cmt>永厳→http://www.city.kasugai.lg.jp/bunka/bunkazai/kyodoshikasugai/kyodoshi35.htmlhttp://www.ab.auone-net.jp/~badra20/nariainoki.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hojuiin-ryu simplified lineage (founder, Eigon): Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Yakushin - Kanpyo Hoo (Emperor Uda) - Kancho - Saishin - Shoshin - Kanjo - Eigon</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hojuiin-ryu simplified lineage (founder, Eigen): Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Yakushin - Kanpyo Hoo (Emperor Uda) - Kancho - Saishin - Shoshin - Kanjo - Eigon</e>
<cmt>Eigenとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>華蔵院流略系譜（派祖・聖恵）　空海-真雅-源仁-益信-寛平法皇（宇多天皇）-寛朝-済信-性信-寛助-聖恵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kezoin-ryu simplified linage (founder: Shoe) Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Yakushin - Kanpyo Hoo (Emperor Uda) - Kancho - Saishin - Shoshin - Kanjo - Shoe</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kezoin-ryu simplified lineage (founder, Shoe): Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Yakushin - Kanpyo Hoo (Emperor Uda) - Kancho - Saishin - Shoshin - Kanjo - Shoe</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kezoin-ryu simplified lineage (founder, Shoe): Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Yakushin - Kanpyo Hoo (Emperor Uda) - Kancho - Saishin - Shoshin - Kanjo - Shoe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>忍辱山流略系譜（派祖・寛遍）　空海-真雅-源仁-益信-寛平法皇（宇多天皇）-寛朝-済信-性信-寛助-寛遍</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ninnikusen-ryu simplified linage (founder: Kanpen) Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Yakushin - Kanpyo Hoo (Emperor Uda) - Kancho - Saishin - Shoshin - Kanjo - Kanpen</e>
<cmt>寛遍→http://www4.ocn.ne.jp/~taxi/enjyoji.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ninnikusen-ryu simplified lineage (founder, Kanpen): Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Yakushin - Kanpyo Hoo (Emperor Uda) - Kancho - Saishin - Shoshin - Kanjo - Kanpen</e>
<cmt>spelling, space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ninnikusen-ryu simplified lineage (founder, Kanpen): Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Yakushin - Kanpyo Hoo (Emperor Uda) - Kancho - Saishin - Shoshin - Kanjo - Kanpen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>伝法院流略系譜（派祖・覚鑁）　空海-真雅-源仁-益信-寛平法皇（宇多天皇）-寛朝-済信-性信-寛助-覚鑁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Denpoin-ryu simplified linage (founder: Kakuban) Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Yakushin - Kanpyo Hoo (Emperor Uda) - Kancho - Saishin - Shoshin - Kanjo - Kakuban</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Denpoin-ryu simplified lineage (founder, Kakuban): Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Yakushin - Kanpyo Hoo (Emperor Uda) - Kancho - Saishin - Shoshin - Kanjo - Kakuban</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Denpoin-ryu simplified lineage (founder, Kakuban): Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Yakushin - Kanpyo Hoo (Emperor Uda) - Kancho - Saishin - Shoshin - Kanjo - Kakuban</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>小野流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ono-ryu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ono-ryu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ono-ryu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="138">
<j>特徴は、口伝口訣を重じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is characterized by placing a high value in instruction of the secrets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is characterized by placing a high value on the instruction of the secrets.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is characterized by the high value that is placed on the instruction of the secrets.</e>
<cmt>表現を広沢流と統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>真言宗善通寺派大本山大本山随心院（旧称・曼荼羅寺）がある京都市東山区山科小野が語源となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was named after a place name of Yamashina Ono Higashiyama Ward Kyoto City, where Zuishinin Grand Head Temple of Shingon sect Zentsuji-ha (真言宗善通寺派大本山随心院) (the former name: Mandara Temple).</e>
<cmt>真言宗善通寺派大本山随心院→定訳不明http://www.zuishinin.or.jp/、曼荼羅寺→http://www.k3.dion.ne.jp/~kanzoin/e_index.html京都市東山区山科小野は現在、京都市山科区小野ですが、あえてそのまま訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was named after the place name of the Yamashina Ono, Higashiyama ward of Kyoto City, the site of Zuishinin grand head temple of the Shingon sect Zentsuji-ha (真言宗善通寺派大本山随心院) (formerly called Mandara Temple).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was named after the place name of the Yamashina Ono, Higashiyama ward of Kyoto City, the site of Zuishinin grand head temple of the Shingon sect Zentsuji-ha (真言宗善通寺派大本山随心院) (formerly called Mandala Temple).</e>
<cmt>Mandara→Mandala に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>聖宝を小野流元祖、随心院を開創した仁海を小野流流祖とする場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some cases Shobo is regarded as an originator (元祖) of Ono-ryu and Ningai who founded Zuisinin is regarded as a founder (流祖) of Ono-ryu.</e>
<cmt>仁海→Yahoo辞書</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some cases Shobo is regarded as an originator (元祖) of Ono-ryu, while Ningai, who founded Zuisinin, is regarded as a founder (流祖) of Ono-ryu.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some cases Shobo is regarded as an originator (元祖) of Ono-ryu while Ningai, who founded Zuishinin, is regarded as a founder (流祖) of Ono-ryu.</e>
<cmt>Zuishininとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="141">
<j>広義では、東密事相を2分した場合、広沢流の対をなす法流。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a broad sense, it is the school as opposed to Hirosawa-ryu when Tomitsijiso is divided into two.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a broad sense it is the school as opposed to Hirosawa-ryu when Tomitsijiso is divided in two.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a broad sense, it was the school that was opposed to Hirosawa-ryu when Tomitsujiso was divided in two.</e>
<cmt>Tomitsujiso としました。全体的に訳し直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>狭義では、小野流内の流派、醍醐三流（理性院流・三宝院流・金剛王院流）と勧修寺三流（随心院流・安祥寺流・勧修寺流）を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a narrow sense it indicates Daigo-san-ryu (Rishoin-ryu, Sanpoin-ryu and Kongooin-ryu) and Kajuji-san-ryu (Zuishinin-ryu, Anshoji-ryu, Kajuji-ryu).</e>
<cmt>三宝院流→Yahoo辞書、金剛王院流→http://www.kyototsuu.jp/Temple/IchigonJi.html、安祥寺流→http://www.anshoji.ne.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a narrow sense it indicates Daigo-san-ryu (Rishoin-ryu, Sanpoin-ryu and Kongooin-ryu) and Kajuji-san-ryu (Zuishinin-ryu, Anshoji-ryu, Kajuji-ryu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a narrow sense it indicates Daigo-san-ryu (Rishoin-ryu, Sanpoin-ryu and Kongooin-ryu) and Kajuji-san-ryu (Zuishinin-ryu, Anshoji-ryu, Kajuji-ryu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>単に随心院流のみを指す場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other cases it indicates only Zuishinin-ryu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other cases it indicates only Zuishinin-ryu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other cases it indicates only Zuishinin-ryu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="144">
<j>小野流系流派略系譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The simplified linage of Ono-ryu schools</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The simplified lineage of Ono-ryu schools</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The simplified lineage of Ono-ryu schools</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>安祥寺流略系譜（派祖・宗意）　空海-真雅-源仁-聖宝-観賢-仁海-成尊-範俊-厳覚-宗意</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anshoji-ryu simplified linage (founder: Soi) Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Shobo - Kangen - Ningai - Seison - Hanshun - Genkaku - Soi</e>
<cmt>宗意→http://www.ab.auone-net.jp/~badra20/nariainoki.html、成尊→http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110000252326/範俊→http://homepage3.nifty.com/y-maki/gosyo/sinnpenn/1613.pdf、厳覚→http://www.wul.waseda.ac.jp/PUBS/fumi/14/14-08.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anshoji-ryu simplified lineage (founder, Soi): Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Shobo - Kangen - Ningai - Seison - Hanshun - Genkaku - Soi</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anshoji-ryu simplified lineage (founder, Soi): Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Shobo - Kangen - Ningai - Seison - Hanshun - Genkaku - Soi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>勧修寺流略系譜（派祖・寛信）　空海-真雅-源仁-聖宝-観賢-仁海-成尊-範俊-厳覚-寛信</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanjuji-ryu simplified linage (founder: Kanshin) Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Shobo - Kangen - Ningai - Seison - Hanshun - Genkaku - Kanshin</e>
<cmt>寛信→http://sips03.narahaku.go.jp/magazine/backnumber-32.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanjuji-ryu simplified lineage (founder, Kanshin): Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Shobo - Kangen - Ningai - Seison - Hanshun - Genkaku - Kanshin</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanjuji-ryu simplified lineage (founder, Kanshin): Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Shobo - Kangen - Ningai - Seison - Hanshun - Genkaku - Kanshin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="147">
<j>随心寺流略系譜（派祖・増俊）　空海-真雅-源仁-聖宝-観賢-仁海-成尊-範俊-厳覚-増俊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zuisinji-ryu simplified linage (founder: Shoshun) Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Shobo - Kangen - Ningai - Seison - Hanshun - Genkaku - Shoshun</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zuisinji-ryu simplified lineage (founder, Shoshun): Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Shobo - Kangen - Ningai - Seison - Hanshun - Genkaku - Shoshun</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zuishinji-ryu simplified lineage (founder, Shoshun): Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Shobo - Kangen - Ningai - Seison - Hanshun - Genkaku - Shoshun</e>
<cmt>Zuishinji-ryuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>三宝院流略系譜（派祖・定海）　空海-真雅-源仁-聖宝-観賢-仁海-成尊-義範-勝覚-定海</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanpoin-ryu simplified linage (founder: Jokai) Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Shobo - Kangen - Ningai - Seison - Gihan - Shokaku - Jokai</e>
<cmt>義範→http://homepage3.nifty.com/y-maki/gosyo/sinnpenn/1613.pdf、勝覚→http://www.koyasan.or.jp/tazuneru/sights/toutou.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanpoin-ryu simplified lineage (founder, Jokai): Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Shobo - Kangen - Ningai - Seison - Gihan - Shokaku - Jokai</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanpoin-ryu simplified lineage (founder, Jokai): Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Shobo - Kangen - Ningai - Seison - Gihan - Shokaku - Jokai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>理性院流略系譜（派祖・賢覚）　空海-真雅-源仁-聖宝-観賢-仁海-成尊-義範-勝覚-賢覚</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rishoin-ryu simplified linage (Founder: Genkaku) Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Shobo - Kangen - Ningai - Seison - Gihan - Shokaku - Genkaku</e>
<cmt>勝覚→http://www.koyasan.or.jp/tazuneru/sights/toutou.html、賢覚→Yahoo辞書</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rishoin-ryu simplified lineage (founder, Genkaku): Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Shobo - Kangen - Ningai - Seison - Gihan - Shokaku - Genkaku</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rishoin-ryu simplified lineage (founder, Genkaku): Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Shobo - Kangen - Ningai - Seison - Gihan - Shokaku - Genkaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>金剛王院流略系譜（派祖・聖賢）　空海-真雅-源仁-聖宝-観賢-仁海-成尊-義範-勝覚-聖賢</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kongooin-ryu simplified linage (founder: Shoken) Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Shobo - Kangen - Ningai - Seison - Gihan - Shokaku - Shoken</e>
<cmt>聖賢→http://www.kyototsuu.jp/Temple/IchigonJi.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kongooin-ryu simplified lineage (founder, Shoken): Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Shobo - Kangen - Ningai - Seison - Gihan - Shokaku - Shoken</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kongooin-ryu simplified lineage (founder, Shoken): Kukai - Shinga - Gennin - Shobo - Kangen - Ningai - Seison - Gihan - Shokaku - Shoken</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>古義派・新義派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kogi-ha and Shingi-ha</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kogi-ha and Shingi-ha</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kogi-ha and Shingi-ha</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="151">
<j>真言宗は日本の仏教宗派の中では分派の多いものの1つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shingon sect is one of the sects which have many schools among Buddhism sects in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shingon sect is one of the sects that have many schools among Buddhist sects in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shingon sect is one of the sects that have many schools among Buddhist sects in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>13世紀末に古義真言宗と新義真言宗に別れ、さらにそこから多種多様な教義が展開して現在に至っているのが特徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Characteristically, it has developed a wide variety of Dharma after it split into Kogi Shingon sect and Shingi Shingon sect at the end of the 13th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, it has developed a wide variety of dharma since it split into the Kogi Shingon sect and Shingi Shingon sect at the end of the thirteenth century.</e>
<cmt>syntax</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, it has developed a wide variety of dharma since it split into the Kogi Shingon sect and Shingi Shingon sect at the end of the thirteenth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>古義派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kogi-ha</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kogi-ha</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kogi-ha</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="153">
<j>大日如来の本地法身説の教学（古義）による。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It relies on Dharma-Kaya of Hon-ji, of Dainichinyorai (Kogi).</e>
<cmt>本地法身説→http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110000548446/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It relies on Dharma-Kaya of Hon-ji, of Dainichinyorai (Kogi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It relies on Dharma-Kaya of Hon-ji, of Dainichinyorai (Kogi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="154">
<j>現実世界の一事一物が法身（真理そのものを仏の身体とみなす）の大日如来の説法であると説いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It preaches that each event and each thing in this world is a sermon of Dainichinyorai, Buddhism&apos;s highest form of existence (the truth itself is regarded as Buddha&apos;s body).</e>
<cmt>法身→Webster Online Dictionary</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It preaches that each event and each thing in this world is a sermon of Dainichinyorai, Buddhism&apos;s highest form of existence (the truth itself is regarded as Buddha&apos;s body).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It preaches that each event and each thing in this world is a sermon of Dainichinyorai, Buddhism&apos;s highest form of existence (the truth itself is regarded as Buddha&apos;s body).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>新義派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shingi-ha</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shingi-ha</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shingi-ha</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="155">
<j>覚鑁（かくばん）（興教大師）を派祖とし、大日如来の加持身説の教学（新義）による。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was begun by Kakuban (Kogyo Daishi) and relies on the Dharma of Adhisthana-kaya of Dainichinyorai (Shingi).</e>
<cmt>加持身→http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110000253248/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was begun by Kakuban (Kogyo Daishi) and relies on the Dharma of Adhisthana-kaya of Dainichinyorai (Shingi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was begun by Kakuban (Kogyo Daishi) and relies on the Dharma of Adhisthana-kaya of Dainichinyorai (Shingi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>現実世界の一事一物は、加持身の大日如来の説法であると説いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It preaches that each event and each thing in this world is a sermon of Dainichinyorai, Adhisthana-kaya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It preaches that each event and each thing in this world is a sermon of Dainichinyorai, Adhisthana-kaya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It preaches that each event and each thing in this world is a sermon of Dainichinyorai, Adhisthana-kaya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>真言宗各派総大本山会（各山会）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Grand Head Temple&apos;s association of Shingon sect&apos;s schools (Kakuzankai)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The grand head temple&apos;s association of Shingon sect&apos;s schools (Kakuzankai)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The grand head temple&apos;s association of Shingon sect&apos;s schools (Kakuzankai)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="157">
<j>昭和14年（1939年）の宗教団体法成立により、真言律宗以外の宗派は真言宗として統合された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the enactment of Religious Organizations Act in 1939, Shingon sects except Shingon Risshu sect were integrated as Shingon sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequent upon the enactment of Religious Organizations Act in 1939, Shingon sects (except for the Shingon Risshu) were integrated as the Shingon sect.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequent upon the enactment of Religious Organizations Act in 1939, Shingon sects (except for the Shingon Risshu) were integrated as the Shingon sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>しかし、戦後は分派独立が相継ぎ、現在は約50の宗派がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, after the World WarⅡ, many sect split and became independent one after another, so that there are more than 50 schools at present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after World WarⅡmany sects split and became independent one after another, so that today there are more than 50 schools.</e>
<cmt>structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after World WarⅡmany sects split and became independent one after another, so that today there are more than 50 schools.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>そのうち主要な16派の18の総大本山が、昭和33年（1958年）6月15日に、真言宗各派総大本山会（各山会）を各山の連絡親睦・共通事業の主宰を目的に結成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 18 Grand Head Temples of main 16 schools set up the Grand Head Temple&apos;s association of Shingon sect&apos;s schools (Kakuzankai) on June 15, 1958, in order to communicate each other, cultivate mutual friendship and hold common events together.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 18 grand head temples of the main 16 schools were set up as the Grand Head Temple&apos;s association of Shingon sect schools (Kakuzankai) on June 15, 1958, in order to communicate with each other, cultivate mutual friendships and hold events in cooperation with one another.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 18 grand head temples of the main 16 schools were set up as the Grand Head Temple&apos;s association of Shingon sect schools (Kakuzankai) on June 15, 1958, in order to communicate with each other, cultivate mutual friendships and hold events in cooperation with one another.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>これらの寺院を真言宗十八本山という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These temples are called 18 Head Temple of Shingon sect (真言宗十八本山).</e>
<cmt>真言宗十八本山→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These temples are called the 18 head temples of the Shingon sect (真言宗十八本山).</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These temples are called the 18 head temples of the Shingon sect (真言宗十八本山).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="161">
<j>各山会の事務局 - 総本山智積院内</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Office of Kakuzankai - at Chishakuin Grand Head Temple</e>
<cmt>「総本山智積院」→用語リストではChisekiinとなっていますが、Chishakuinと判断しました。http://www.chisan.or.jp/sohonzan/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Office of Kakuzankai - at Chishakuin Grand Head Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Office of Kakuzankai - at Chishakuin Grand Head Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="20">
<tit>
<j>各山会に参画する真言宗十八本山（順不同）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">18 Head Temples of Shingon sect which join in Kakuzankai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 18 head temples of the Shingon sect, which join in Kakuzankai</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 18 head temples of the Shingon sect, which join in Kakuzankai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="162">
<j>古義真言宗系</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kogi Shingon sect linage</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lineage of the Kogi Shingon</e>
<cmt>structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kogi Shingon lineage</e>
<cmt>shingiと統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="163">
<j>金剛峯寺 - 高野山真言宗総本山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kongobu-ji Temple - Grand Head Temple of Koyasan Shingon sect (高野山真言宗総本山)</e>
<cmt>高野山真言宗総本山→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kongobu-ji Temple - Grand head temple of the Koyasan Shingon sect (高野山真言宗総本山)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kongobu-ji Temple - Grand head temple of the Koyasan Shingon sect (高野山真言宗総本山)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="164">
<j>東寺 - 東寺真言宗総本山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To-ji Temple - Grand Head Temple of Toji Shingon sect (東寺真言宗総本山)</e>
<cmt>東寺真言宗総本山→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To-ji Temple - Grand head temple of the Toji Shingon sect (東寺真言宗総本山)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To-ji Temple - Grand head temple of the Toji Shingon sect (東寺真言宗総本山)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="165">
<j>善通寺 - 真言宗善通寺派総本山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zentsu-ji Temple - Grand Head Temple of Shingon sect Zentsuji-ha (真言宗善通寺派総本山)</e>
<cmt>善通寺→http://www.zentsuji.com/、真言宗善通寺派大本山→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zentsu-ji Temple - Grand head temple of the Shingon sect Zentsuji-ha (真言宗善通寺派総本山)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zentsu-ji Temple - Grand head temple of the Shingon sect Zentsuji-ha (真言宗善通寺派総本山)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="166">
<j>随心院 - 真言宗善通寺派大本山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zuishinin - Grand Head Temple of Shingon sect Zentsuji-ha (真言宗善通寺派大本山)</e>
<cmt>同上</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zuishinin - Grand head temple of the Shingon sect Zentsuji-ha (真言宗善通寺派大本山)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zuishinin - Grand head temple of the Shingon sect Zentsuji-ha (真言宗善通寺派大本山)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="167">
<j>醍醐寺 - 真言宗醍醐派総本山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daigo-ji Temple - Grand Head Temple of Shingon sect Daigo-ha (真言宗醍醐派総本山)</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daigo-ji Temple - Grand head temple of the Shingon sect Daigo-ha (真言宗醍醐派総本山)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daigo-ji Temple - Grand head temple of the Shingon sect Daigo-ha (真言宗醍醐派総本山)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="168">
<j>仁和寺 - 真言宗御室派総本山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ninna-ji Temple - Grand Head Temple of Shingon sect Omuro-ha (真言宗御室派総本山)</e>
<cmt>仁和寺→http://web.kyoto-inet.or.jp/org/ninnaji/、真言宗御室派総本山→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ninna-ji Temple - Grand head temple of the Shingon sect Omuro-ha (真言宗御室派総本山)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ninna-ji Temple - Grand head temple of the Shingon sect Omuro-ha (真言宗御室派総本山)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="169">
<j>大覚寺 - 真言宗大覚寺派大本山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daikaku-ji Temple - Grand Head Temple of Shingon sect Daikakuji-ha (真言宗大覚寺派大本山)</e>
<cmt>真言宗大覚寺派大本山→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daikaku-ji Temple - Grand head temple of the Shingon sect Daikakuji-ha (真言宗大覚寺派大本山)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daikaku-ji Temple - Grand head temple of the Shingon sect Daikakuji-ha (真言宗大覚寺派大本山)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="170">
<j>泉涌寺 - 真言宗泉涌寺派総本山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senyuji Temple</e>
<cmt>泉涌寺→http://www.mitera.org/、真言宗泉涌寺派総本山→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senyuji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senyu-ji Temple - Grand head temple of Shingon sect Senyuji-ha (真言宗泉涌寺派総本山)</e>
<cmt>訳抜け</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="171">
<j>勧修寺 - 真言宗山階派大本山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kajuji Temple　-　Grand Head Temple of Shingon sect Yamashina-ha (真言宗山階派大本山)</e>
<cmt>勧修寺→http://kaiwai.city.kyoto.jp/search/view_sight.php?InforKindCode=1&amp;ManageCode=1000031、真言宗山階派大本山→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kajuji Temple　-　Grand head temple of the Shingon sect Yamashina-ha (真言宗山階派大本山)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaju-ji Temple　-　Grand head temple of the Shingon sect Yamashina-ha (真言宗山階派大本山)</e>
<cmt>上記と統一してKaju-jiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="172">
<j>朝護孫子寺 - 信貴山真言宗総本山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chogosonshiji Temple - Grand Head Temple Shigisan Shingon sect (信貴山真言宗総本山)</e>
<cmt>朝護孫子寺→http://yamamototake.blog74.fc2.com/blog-category-24.html、信貴山真言宗総本山→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chogosonshiji Temple - Grand Head Temple Shigisan Shingon sect (信貴山真言宗総本山)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chogosonshi-ji Temple - Grand head temple Shigisan Shingon sect (信貴山真言宗総本山)</e>
<cmt>同上</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="173">
<j>中山寺 (宝塚市) - 真言宗中山寺派大本山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nakayamadera Temple (Takarazuka City) - Grand Head Temple of Shingon sect Nakayamadera-ha (真言宗中山寺派大本山)</e>
<cmt>中山寺→http://www.nakayamadera.or.jp/top.html、真言宗中山寺派大本山→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nakayamadera Temple (Takarazuka City) - Grand head temple of the Shingon sect Nakayamadera-ha (真言宗中山寺派大本山)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nakayama-dera Temple (Takarazuka City) - Grand head temple of the Shingon sect Nakayamadera-ha (真言宗中山寺派大本山)</e>
<cmt>Nakayama-deraとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="174">
<j>清荒神清澄寺 - 真言三宝宗大本山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyoshikojin Seichoji Temple - Grand Head Temple of Shingon-Sanpo sect (真言三宝宗大本山)</e>
<cmt>清荒神清澄寺→http://www.kiyoshikojin.or.jp/、真言三宝宗大本山→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyoshikojin Seichoji Temple - Grand head temple of the Shingon-Sanpo sect (真言三宝宗大本山)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyoshikojin Seichoji Temple - Grand head temple of the Shingon-Sanpo sect (真言三宝宗大本山)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="175">
<j>須磨寺 - 真言宗須磨寺派大本山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumadera Temple - Grand Head Temple of Shingon sect Sumadera-ha (真言宗須磨寺派大本山)</e>
<cmt>須磨寺→http://www.sumadera.or.jp/、真言宗須磨寺派大本山→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sumadera Temple - Grand head temple of the Shingon sect Sumadera-ha (真言宗須磨寺派大本山)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suma-dera Temple - Grand head temple of the Shingon sect Sumadera-ha (真言宗須磨寺派大本山)</e>
<cmt>Suma-deraとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="176">
<j>新義真言宗系</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shingi Shingon linage</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shingi Shingon lineage</e>
<cmt>article, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shingi Shingon lineage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="177">
<j>智積院 - 真言宗智山派総本山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chishakuin Temple - Grand Head Temple of Shingon sect Chisan-ha (真言宗智山派総本山)</e>
<cmt>真言宗智山派総本山→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chishakuin Temple - Grand head temple of the Shingon sect Chisan-ha (真言宗智山派総本山)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chishakuin Temple - Grand head temple of the Shingon sect Chisan-ha (真言宗智山派総本山)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="178">
<j>長谷寺 - 真言宗豊山派総本山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hasedera Temple - Grand Head Temple of Shingon sect Buzan-ha (真言宗豊山派総本山)</e>
<cmt>長谷寺→http://www.hasedera.or.jp/、真言宗豊山派総本山→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hasedera Temple - Grand head temple of the Shingon sect Buzan-ha (真言宗豊山派総本山)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hase-dera Temple - Grand head temple of the Shingon sect Buzan-ha (真言宗豊山派総本山)</e>
<cmt>Hase-deraとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="179">
<j>根来寺 - 新義真言宗総本山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Negoro-ji Temple - Grand Head Temple of Shingi Shingon sect (新義真言宗総本山)</e>
<cmt>新義真言宗総本山→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Negoro-ji Temple - Grand head temple of the Shingi Shingon sect (新義真言宗総本山)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Negoro-ji Temple - Grand head temple of the Shingi Shingon sect (新義真言宗総本山)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="180">
<j>真言律宗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shingon Risshu sect</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shingon Risshu sect</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shingon Risshu sect</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="181">
<j>西大寺 (奈良市) - 真言律宗総本山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saidai-ji Temple (Nara City) - Grand Head Temple of Shingon Risshu sect (真言律宗大本山)</e>
<cmt>真言律宗総本山→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saidai-ji Temple (Nara City) - Grand head temple of the Shingon Risshu sect (真言律宗大本山)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saidai-ji Temple (Nara City) - Grand head temple of the Shingon Risshu sect (真言律宗大本山)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="182">
<j>宝山寺 - 真言律宗大本山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hozan-ji Temple - Grand Head Temple of Shingon Risshu sect (真言律宗大本山)</e>
<cmt>宝山寺→http://www.bukkyo.net/hozanji/、</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hozan-ji Temple - Grand head temple of the Shingon Risshu sect (真言律宗大本山)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hozan-ji Temple - Grand head temple of the Shingon Risshu sect (真言律宗大本山)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="21">
<tit>
<j>後七日御修法（ごしちにちのみしほ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goshichinichinomishiho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goshichinichinomishiho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goshichinichinomishiho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="183">
<j>真言宗各派総大本山会所属の各宗派管長・山主と真言宗各派総大本山会所属の各宗派から選んだ定額僧（じょうがくそう）により、毎年1月8日から1月14日までの一週間（21座）、東寺・灌頂院にて後七日御修法を行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For a week (21times, 21座) from January 8 to 14 (21座), Goshichinichinomichiho has been held at Kanjo-in of To-ji Temple by chief abbots (管長・山主) and Jogakuso (priests, 定額僧) of each sect belonging to Grand Head Temple&apos;s association of Shingon sect&apos;s schools.</e>
<cmt>管長→Webster Online Dictionary、山主、定額僧→定訳不明、21座→定訳不明、http://www.niji.or.jp/home/hasikura/cgi-bin/sb/sb.cgi?eid=63</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For a week (21 times, 21座) from January 8 to 14 (21座), Goshichinichinomichiho has been held at Kanjo-in of To-ji Temple by the chief abbots (管長・山主) and Jogakuso (priests, 定額僧) of each sect belonging to the grand head temple&apos;s association of Shingon sect schools.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For a week from January 8 to 14 (21 times, 21座) every year, Goshichinichinomishiho has been held at Kanjo-in of To-ji Temple by the chief abbots (管長・山主) and Jogakuso (priests, 定額僧) of each sect belonging to grand head temple&apos;s association of Shingon sect schools.</e>
<cmt>(21座) を削除 Goshichinichinomishihoスペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="184">
<j>構成（真言宗各派総大本山会所属の各宗派より選出された者）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Formation (priests who are elected by each school of Grand Head Temple&apos;s association of Shingon sect&apos;s schools)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Formations (priests who are elected by each school of the Grand Head Temple&apos;s association of Shingon sect schools)</e>
<cmt>article, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Formations (priests who are elected by each school of the Grand Head Temple&apos;s association of Shingon sect schools)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="185">
<j>大阿闍梨（真言宗各派総大本山会所属の各宗派管長・山主）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dai Ajari (chief abbots of Grand Head Temple&apos;s association of Shingon sect&apos;s schools)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dai Ajari (chief abbots of the grand head temple&apos;s association of Shingon sect schools)</e>
<cmt>article, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dai Ajari (chief abbots of the grand head temple&apos;s association of Shingon sect schools)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="186">
<j>御手替（真言宗各派総大本山会所属の各宗派管長・山主）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">御手替 (chief abbots of Grand Head Temple&apos;s association of Shingon sect&apos;s schools)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">御手替 (chief abbots of the grand head temple&apos;s association of Shingon sect schools)</e>
<cmt>article, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">御手替 (chief abbots of the grand head temple&apos;s association of Shingon sect schools)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="187">
<j>二間観音供（1名）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ninoma Kannon-ku Mass (二間観音供) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ninoma Kannon-ku Mass (二間観音供) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ninoma Kannon-ku Mass (二間観音供) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="188">
<j>神供（1名）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jinku (神供) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>定訳不明, kotobank</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jinku (神供) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jinku (神供) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="189">
<j>伴僧（4名）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Banso (伴僧) (4 persons)</e>
<cmt>定訳不明, kotobank</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Banso (伴僧) (4 persons)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Banso (伴僧) (4 persons)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="190">
<j>十二天供（1名）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Juniten-gu (十二天供) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>定訳不明, kotobank</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Juniten-gu (十二天供) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juniten-gu (十二天供) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="191">
<j>増益護摩供（1名）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soyaku Goma-ku, Soyaku Goma-gu, Soyaku Goma-kyo (増益護摩供) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>定訳不明http://www.ctb.ne.jp/~souen-in/houinoma5.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soyaku Goma-ku, Soyaku Goma-gu, Soyaku Goma-kyo (増益護摩供) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soyaku Goma-ku, Soyaku Goma-gu, Soyaku Goma-kyo (増益護摩供) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="192">
<j>咒頭（1名）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shu no kami (咒頭) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shu no kami (咒頭) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shu no kami (咒頭) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="193">
<j>舎利守（1名）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shari no mori(舎利守) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shari no mori(舎利守) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shari no mori(舎利守) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="194">
<j>息災護摩供（1名）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sokusai Goma-ku, Sokusai Goma-gu, Sokusai Goma-kyo (息災護摩供) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>定訳不明http://www.ctb.ne.jp/~souen-in/houinoma5.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sokusai Goma-ku, Sokusai Goma-gu, Sokusai Goma-kyo (息災護摩供) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sokusai Goma-ku, Sokusai Goma-gu, Sokusai Goma-kyo (息災護摩供) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="195">
<j>聖天（1名）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoten, Shoden (聖天) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>定訳不明, kotobank</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoten, Shoden (聖天) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoten, Shoden (聖天) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="196">
<j>五大尊供（1名）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Godaison-ku, Godaison-gu, Godaison-kyo (五大尊供) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>定訳不明, kotobank</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Godaison-ku, Godaison-gu, Godaison-kyo (五大尊供) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Godaison-ku, Godaison-gu, Godaison-kyo (五大尊供) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="197">
<j>定額僧</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jogakuso</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jogakuso</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jogakuso</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="198">
<j>随行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zuiko (随行)</e>
<cmt>定訳不明, kotobank</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zuiko (随行)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zuiko (随行)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="199">
<j>承仕</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoji, Joji (承仕)</e>
<cmt>定訳不明, kotobank</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoji, Joji (承仕)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoji, Joji (承仕)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="200">
<j>徒弟子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Disciple</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Disciple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Disciple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="201">
<j>事務局</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Office</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Office</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Office</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="202">
<j>別当（1名）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Betto (別当) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>定訳不明, kotobank</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Betto (別当) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Betto (別当) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="203">
<j>大行事（1名）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dai-gyoji (大行事) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>定訳不明, kotobank</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dai-gyoji (大行事) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dai-gyoji (大行事) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="204">
<j>小行事（1名）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sho-Gyoji (小行事) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>定訳不明, kotobank</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sho-Gyoji (小行事) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sho-Gyoji (小行事) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="205">
<j>用度（1名）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yodo (用度) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>定訳不明, kotobank</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yodo (用度) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yodo (用度) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="206">
<j>局長（1名）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyokucho (局長) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>定訳不明, kotobank</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyokucho (局長) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyokucho (局長) (1 person)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="207">
<j>後七日御修法は真言院御修法（しんごんいんみしほ）などと呼ばれ、通称は御修法（みしほ）と呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goshichinichinomishiho is also called Shingoninmishiho and others, and is commonly known as Mishiho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goshichinichinomishiho is also called Shingoninmishiho and others, and is commonly known as Mishiho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goshichinichinomishiho is also called Shingoninmishiho and others, and is commonly known as Mishiho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="208">
<j>834年（承和 (日本)元年）空海（弘法大師）が宮中にて、国家安泰・玉体安穏（ぎょくたいあんのん）・万民豊楽（ばんみんぶらく）を祈って行われてから、毎年、宮中の恒例行事として正月に行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Kukai (Kobo-daishi) prayed for peace of Japan, safety of Emperor and prosperity of people at the Imperial Palace in 834, it had been hold as New Year annual event of Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Kukai (Kobo-daishi) had prayed for the peace of Japan, the safety of the Emperor and the prosperity of the people at the Imperial Palace in 834, it was held annually as a New Year event of the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Kukai (Kobo-daishi) had prayed for the peace of Japan, the safety of the Emperor and the prosperity of the people at the Imperial Palace in 834, it was held annually as a New Year event of the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="209">
<j>南北朝時代 (日本)の戦乱期などを含めて、数度、中断する時期があったが、後水尾天皇と醍醐寺座主義演の尽力により、1623年（元和 (日本)9年）に170年ぶりに復活された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there were several interruption including civil war time of Nanbokucho Period (Japan), it was revived by efforts of Emperor Gomizuono and Gien, Daigo-ji Temple&apos;s head priest in 1623 after a 170-year absence.</e>
<cmt>後水尾天皇→http://www.kunaicho.go.jp/ryobo/guide/108/index.html、座主→http://www.websters-online-dictionary.org/definition/temple%2527s+head+priest、義演→http://www.tenzo.net/keizan/keizan-1.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there were several interruptions, including civil war during the Nanbokucho period (Japan), it was revived through the efforts of Emperor Go-Mizuono and Gien, Daigo-ji Temple&apos;s head priest in 1623, after an absence of 170 years.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there were several interruptions, including civil war during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), it was revived through the efforts of the Emperor Go-Mizuono and Gien, Daigo-ji Temple&apos;s head priest in 1623, after an absence of 170 years.</e>
<cmt>南北朝時代の訳を修正theを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="210">
<j>1871年（明治4年）に廃仏棄釈の影響により廃止されるまで行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It had been held until 1871, when it was abolished by an influence of The Exclusion of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was held until 1871, when it was abolished under the influence of the official decree on the exclusion of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>clearer</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was held until 1871, when it was abolished under the influence of the official decree on the exclusion of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="211">
<j>釈雲照らの嘆願により、1883年（明治16年）に復活した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was revived by a petition of Unsho SHAKU and others in 1883.</e>
<cmt>釈雲照→http://www.horakuji.hello-net.info/jiun/about.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was revived through a petition by Unsho SHAKU and others in 1883.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was revived through a petition by Unsho SHAKU and others in 1883.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="212">
<j>そのときから、修法を行う場所を宮中から東寺・灌頂院に移した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The place of the ascetic training was moved from Palace to Kanjo-in of To-ji Temple since then.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, the place of ascetic training was moved from the Palace to Kanjo-in of To-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, the place of ascetic training was moved from the Palace to Kanjo-in of To-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="213">
<j>修法は、合計21ヶ座行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ascetic training is held 21times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ascetic training is held 21times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ascetic training is held 21times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="214">
<j>金剛界法と胎蔵界法を1年置きに交互に修し、息災・増益の護摩と五大明王、十二天、聖天法などを併せて修する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Participants use Kongokai-ho and Taizokai-ho alternately, one year each, and implement the rites of peace and increase of benefit, and Godai-myoo (五大明王), Juni-ten (十二天), Shoten-ho (聖天法) and so on.</e>
<cmt>金剛界法→定訳不明、http://dictionary.goo.ne.jp/leaf/jn/72492/m0u/%E9%87%91%E5%89%9B%E7%95%8C%E6%B3%95/、胎蔵界法→定訳不明、http://dictionary.goo.ne.jp/leaf/jn/116934/m0u/%E8%83%8E%E8%94%B5%E7%95%8C/、五大明王→定訳不明、http://dictionary.goo.ne.jp/leaf/jn/69200/m0u/%E4%BA%94%E5%A4%A7%E6%98%8E%E7%8E%8B/、十二天→定訳不明、http://dictionary.goo.ne.jp/leaf/jn/90033/m0u/%E5%8D%81%E4%BA%8C%E5%A4%A9/、聖天法→定訳不明、http://dictionary.goo.ne.jp/leaf/jn/94680/m0u/%E8%81%96%E5%A4%A9/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Participants use Kongokai-ho and Taizokai-ho alternately, one year each, and implement the rites of peace and increase of benefit, and Godai-myoo (五大明王), Juni-ten (十二天), Shoten-ho (聖天法) and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Participants use Kongokai-ho and Taizokai-ho alternately, one year each, and implement the rites of peace and increase of benefit, and Godai-myoo (五大明王), Juni-ten (十二天), Shoten-ho (聖天法) and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="215">
<j>初日（開白）の1月8日には、宮内庁より、天皇の御衣を納めた唐櫃（からびつ）を捧持した勅使を東寺・灌頂院に遣わして、御衣を東寺灌頂院道場の内堂に安置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the first day (開白) of January 8, the imperial messenger, who has the Karabitsu (Chinese-style chest) in which the Emperor&apos;s cloth is placed, is sent from the Imperial Household Agency to Kanjo-in of To-ji Temple, and he places it within the inner hall of To-ji Kanjo-in Dojo.</e>
<cmt>宮内庁→英辞郎on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the first day (開白) of January 8, the imperial messenger, who has the Karabitsu (Chinese-style chest) in which the Emperor&apos;s cloth is placed, is sent from the Imperial Household Agency to Kanjo-in of To-ji Temple, and he places it within the inner hall of To-ji Kanjo-in Dojo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the first day (開白) of January 8, the imperial messenger, who has the Karabitsu (Chinese-style chest) in which the Emperor&apos;s cloth is placed, is sent from the Imperial Household Agency to Kanjo-in of To-ji Temple, and he places it within the inner hall of To-ji Kanjo-in Dojo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="216">
<j>11日（中日）・14日（結願）は勅使が、東寺・灌頂院の道場に焼香して参拝をされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the 11th (the middle day, 中日) and the 14th (expiration of term of a vow), the imperial messenger burns incense and worships at To-ji Kanjo-in Dojo.</e>
<cmt>結願→Webster Online Dictionary</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the 11th (the middle day, 中日) and the 14th (expiration of term of a vow), the imperial messenger burns incense and worships at To-ji Kanjo-in Dojo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the 11th (the middle day, 中日) and the 14th (expiration of term of a vow), the imperial messenger burns incense and worships at To-ji Kanjo-in Dojo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="217">
<j>同日14日、勅使に御衣奉還の儀式を東寺灌頂院の前堂にて行い、後七日御修法は成満する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the 14th, a ceremony to return the Emperor&apos;s cloth to the imperial messenger is held at the front hall of To-ji Kanjo-in Dojo, and Goshichinichinomishiho ends successfully (成満).</e>
<cmt>成満→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the 14th, a ceremony to return the Emperor&apos;s cloth to the imperial messenger is held at the front hall of To-ji Kanjo-in Dojo, and Goshichinichinomishiho ends successfully (成満).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the 14th, a ceremony to return the Emperor&apos;s cloth to the imperial messenger is held at the front hall of To-ji Kanjo-in Dojo, and Goshichinichinomishiho ends successfully (成満).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="218">
<j>真言宗最高の秘儀とされ、修法で使用する念珠・五鈷杵（ごこしょ）・袈裟などは、空海（弘法大師）が唐（中国）より持ち帰った法具である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is regarded as the supreme secret ceremony of the Shingon sect, and religious articles (法具) such as a rosary, five-pronged pestles, a stole and others, which are used in ascetic training, were brought by Kukai (Kobo-daishi) from Tang (China).</e>
<cmt>法具→定訳不明、袈裟→stole</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is regarded as the supreme secret ceremony of the Shingon sect, and religious articles (法具) such as a rosary, five-pronged pestles, a stole and others, which are used in ascetic training, were brought by Kukai (Kobo-daishi) from Tang (China).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is regarded as the supreme secret ceremony of the Shingon sect, and religious articles (法具) such as a rosary, five-pronged pestles, a stole and others, which are used in ascetic training, were brought by Kukai (Kobo-daishi) from Tang (China).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="219">
<j>以前は、東寺長者（とうじちょうじゃ）が大阿闍梨を務めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Previously, Toji-chojya played the role of Dai Ajari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Previously, Toji-chojya played the role of Dai Ajari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Previously, Toji-Choja played a role of Dai Ajari.</e>
<cmt>choja としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="220">
<j>現在、修法を行う大阿闍梨（詳名・法務法印大阿闍梨、通称・大阿）は真言宗各派総大本山会所属の各宗派の管長・山主が毎年交代して務めているが、その年の大阿闍梨を務めた後に、真言宗長者に就任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Currently, the role of Dai Ajari, who holds ascetic training (the more specific name is Homuhoin Dai Ajari (法務法印大阿闍梨), commonly known as Daia (大阿)) is alternated by the chief abbots of each sect belonging to the grand head temple&apos;s association of Shingon sect schools every year, and after serving as Dai Ajari he is installed as the chief abbot of the Shingon sect.</e>
<cmt>法務法印大阿闍梨、大阿→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently, the role of Dai Ajari, who holds ascetic training (the more specific name is Homuhoin Dai Ajari (法務法印大阿闍梨), commonly known as Daia (大阿)) is alternated by the chief abbots of each sect belonging to the grand head temple&apos;s association of Shingon sect schools every year, and after serving as Dai Ajari he is installed as the chief abbot of the Shingon sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Currently, the role of Dai Ajari, who holds ascetic training (the more specific name is Homuhoin Dai Ajari (法務法印大阿闍梨), commonly known as Daia (大阿)) is alternated by the chief abbots of each sect belonging to the grand head temple&apos;s association of Shingon sect schools every year, and after serving as Dai Ajari he is installed as the chief abbot of the Shingon sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="221">
<j>任期は1年間。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term of service is one year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term of service is one year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term of service is one year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="222">
<j>就任時には、長者杖が贈られる慣習となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Customarily, he is given the staff of the chief abbot at the time of inauguration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Customarily, he is given the staff of the chief abbot at the time of inauguration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Customarily, he is given the staff of the chief abbot at the time of inauguration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="223">
<j>結願後に限り、東寺灌頂院道場への一般参拝が許されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the time after the expiration of the term of a vow, To-ji Kanjo-in Dojo is open to the public and anyone can worship there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the time after the expiration of the term of a vow, To-ji Kanjo-in Dojo is open to the public and anyone can worship there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the time after the expiration of the term of a vow, To-ji Kanjo-in Dojo is open to the public and anyone can worship there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 JAnDbot(id:66507), ノトス(id:42992), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Eskimbot(id:29676), Urania(id:7213), 妙翅鳥(id:55475), Lupinoid(id:68), Kumatora(id:16941), 代言人(id:33675), Ko-ken(id:49348), くっちゃめ(id:86793), Knua(id:66861), Loveless(id:129239), Yas(id:739), 無空(id:17049), Yamabig(id:21134), Kouko0515(id:100370), ロリ(id:613), Washisama(id:9333), Chi-Ham(id:143515), 水野白楓(id:22811), Authority(id:10737), Setu(id:88), Hrs885(id:104160), Makotozushi(id:4545), BOT-Superzerocool(id:65015), Escarbot(id:59151), 樒(id:35770), Kamitani(id:30757), Carkuni(id:79281), Rusk(id:9895), Etsuk(id:878), Yonoemon(id:55450), 唯(id:15499), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Boca samba(id:137526), SuisuiBot(id:10165), Miya(id:1881), DuskTdawn(id:83309), R28Bot(id:177951), 岡部碩道(id:182846), Falcosapiens(id:221), Ha～Ha(id:36403), Louperibot(id:128971), Suisui(id:69), Riden(id:27573), KTX(id:15123), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>