<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>隠し念仏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kakushi Nenbutsu&quot; (The General Term That Means Heretical Sects [And Their Belief] Within Buddhism)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kakushi Nenbutsu&quot; (A General Term for Heretical Sects [and Their Beliefs] Within Buddhism)</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kakushi Nenbutsu&quot; (A General Term for Heretical Sects [and Their Beliefs] Within Buddhism)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>隠し念仏（かくしねんぶつ）は、種々の秘密主義をもつ仏教異端宗派を意味する呼称である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kakushi nenbutsu&quot; refers to the general term that means heretical sects (and their belief) within Buddhism, which have various secretive aspects.</e>
<cmt>・以下のセルの内容を見ると、「隠し念仏」には「異端宗派」のみならずその宗派の「信仰」そのものを意味する場合があるので、括弧書きでそれを加えています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kakushi nenbutsu&quot; is a general term that refers to heretical sects (and their beliefs) within Buddhism, which have various secretive aspects.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kakushi nenbutsu&quot; is a general term that refers to heretical sects (and their beliefs) within Buddhism, which have various secretive aspects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>そのなかでも、浄土真宗系で呪術的な隠し念仏がよく知られており、浄土真宗では異端であることを意味する異安心とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among others, the occult kakushi nenbutsu that is derived from &quot;Jodo Shinshu&quot; (True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) is well known, and the kakushi nenbutsu is said to be &quot;ianjin,&quot; which means the heretical sect, by the mainstream of Jodo Shinshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among others, the cult kakushi nenbutsu, whose name is derived from &quot;Jodo Shinshu&quot; (True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) is well known, and is said to be &quot;ianjin,&quot; which means the heretical sect, by the mainstream of Jodo Shinshu.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among others, the cult kakushi nenbutsu, whose name is derived from &quot;Jodo Shinshu&quot; (True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) is well known, and is said to be &quot;ianjin,&quot; which means the heretical sect, by the mainstream of Jodo Shinshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>信者は、御内法、御内証などと呼び、浄土真宗からは秘事法門、邪義などと呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kakushi nenbutsu is called &quot;Gonaiho&quot; (the inward law) or &quot;Gonaisho&quot;(the secret law) by the believers, and it is called &quot;Hijihomon&quot; (the secret belief) or &quot;Jagi&quot; (heresy) by Jodo Shinshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kakushi nenbutsu is called &quot;Gonaiho&quot; (the inward law) or &quot;Gonaisho&quot;(the secret law) by its believers, and it is called &quot;Hijihomon&quot; (the secret belief) or &quot;Jagi&quot; (heresy) by Jodo Shinshu.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kakushi nenbutsu is called &quot;Gonaiho&quot; (the inward law) or &quot;Gonaisho&quot;(the secret law) by its believers, and it is called &quot;Hijihomon&quot; (the secret belief) or &quot;Jagi&quot; (heresy) by Jodo Shinshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>信者同士では在家仏教、内信心とも呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Within the believers, it is also called &quot;Zaike Bukkyo&quot; (the lay devotees&apos; Buddhism) or &quot;Naishinjin&quot; (the inward belief).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Within believers, it is also called &quot;Zaike Bukkyo&quot; (the lay devotees&apos; Buddhism) or &quot;Naishinjin&quot; (the inward belief).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Within believers, it is also called &quot;Zaike Bukkyo&quot; (the lay devotees&apos; Buddhism) or &quot;Naishinjin&quot; (the inward belief).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>隠し念仏は、藩からの宗教宗派弾圧のために隠れざるを得なかった薩摩藩や人吉藩の浄土真宗弾圧における隠れ念仏とは全く別物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kakushi nenbutsu is completely different from &quot;kakure nenbutsu,&quot; which was the group of Jodo-shinshu believers in the Satsuma clan and the Hitoyoshi clan who could not help concealing their belief because of the suppression on Jodo Shinshu by the clan.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kakushi nenbutsu is completely different from &quot;kakure nenbutsu,&quot; which was a group of Jodo-shinshu believers in the Satsuma clan and the Hitoyoshi clan who could not help concealing their beliefs because of the suppression on Jodo Shinshu by the clans.</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kakushi nenbutsu is completely different from &quot;kakure nenbutsu,&quot; which was a group of Jodo-shinshu believers in the Satsuma clan and the Hitoyoshi clan who could not help concealing their beliefs because of the suppression on Jodo Shinshu by the clans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>日本の江戸期における隠れキリシタンともまったく異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, kakushi nenbutsu is quite different from &quot;kakure kirishitan&quot; (crypto-Christian), who secretly believed in Christianity in Japan during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, kakushi nenbutsu is quite different from &quot;kakure kirishitan&quot; (crypto-Christian), a group who secretly believed in Christianity in Japan during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, kakushi nenbutsu is quite different from &quot;kakure kirishitan&quot; (crypto-Christian), a group who secretly believed in Christianity in Japan during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>隠れ念仏の多くは、浄土真宗本願寺教団自体が認可しており、教団に属していたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of the kakure nenbutsu belonged to - and were authorized by - the very organization of the Hongan-ji school of Jodo Shinshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of the kakure nenbutsu belonged to - and were authorized by - the very organization of the Hongan-ji school of Jodo Shinshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of the kakure nenbutsu belonged to - and were authorized by - the very organization of the Hongan-ji school of Jodo Shinshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>一方、浄土真宗系の隠し念仏の例を挙げると、浄土真宗本願寺教団そのものから異端視されて邪教とされたため、教団に対しても隠さざるを得なかった宗派内異教である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, the kakushi nenbutsu derived from Jodo Shinshu could not help concealing their belief even from the organization of the Hongan-ji school of Jodo Shinshu, because it was deemed heresy from the organization itself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, the kakushi nenbutsu derived from Jodo Shinshu could not help concealing their beliefs even from the organization of the Hongan-ji school of Jodo Shinshu, because it was deemed heresy from the organization itself.</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, the kakushi nenbutsu derived from Jodo Shinshu could not help concealing their beliefs even from the organization of the Hongan-ji school of Jodo Shinshu, because it was deemed heresy from the organization itself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>蓮如（1415年-1499年）が書き記した浄土真宗の『御文章』では、信じれば無間地獄に沈むと警告されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Gobunsho&quot; (a collection of letters written by Jodo Shinshu high priest Rennyo [1415-1499] to his pupils) says the believers of kakushi nenbutsu would go to &quot;mugen jigoku&quot; (the Avici hell, which is believed to be the most painful of the eight hells).</e>
<cmt>・「御文章」は、蓮如が門弟に出した浄土真宗の教えを説く手紙をまとめたものです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Gobunsho&quot; (a collection of letters written by Jodo Shinshu high priest Rennyo [1415-1499] to his pupils) says the believers of kakushi nenbutsu would go to &quot;mugen jigoku&quot; (the Avici hell, which is believed to be the most painful of the eight hells).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Gobunsho&quot; (a collection of letters written by Jodo Shinshu high priest Rennyo [1415-1499] to his pupils) says the believers of kakushi nenbutsu would go to &quot;mugen jigoku&quot; (the Avici hell, which is believed to be the most painful of the eight hells).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>隠し念仏は総称であり、地域や流儀などによって呪術的儀式は異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kakushi nenbutsu is the general term of heretical sects, and their occult rituals differ from region to region, from school to school.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kakushi nenbutsu is the general term for heretical sects, and their occult rituals differ from region to region, and from school to school.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kakushi nenbutsu is the general term for heretical sects, and their occult rituals differ from region to region, and from school to school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>平安時代の真言密教の呪術がそもそもの起源のものも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of the sects originated from the occultism of Shingon Sect of Esoteric Buddhism in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of the sects originated from the occultism of the Shingon Sect of Esoteric Buddhism in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of the sects originated from the occultism of the Shingon Sect of Esoteric Buddhism in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>さらに排他的秘密主義のために、その儀式は土俗化しており全貌はいまだに明らかではないが、五木寛之によると、最近では少しずつその秘密儀式の一部などを公開する動きも出ているという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the sects are exclusive and secretive, so that the whole picture of the localized rituals is still covered in a veil, but Hiroyuki ITSUKI says that the secretive rituals and others have partially begun to be made public little by little these days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the sects are exclusive and secretive, so the whole picture of the localized rituals is still covered in a veil, but Hiroyuki ITSUKI says that some of the secretive rituals and others have begun to be made public little by little in recent days.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the sects are exclusive and secretive, so the whole picture of the localized rituals is still covered in a veil, but Hiroyuki ITSUKI says that some of the secretive rituals and others have begun to be made public little by little in recent days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>浄土真宗隠し念仏は、浄土真宗の開祖である親鸞（1173年-1263年）の長男である善鸞（1217年-1286年）が浄土真宗の東国布教に遣わされた際に現地で信じたと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The kakushi nenbutsu derived from Jodo Shinshu is said to have been believed by Zenran (1217 - 1286), the eldest son of Jodo Shinshu founder Shinran (1173 - 1263), when he was sent to the eastern part of Japan for the missions of Jodo Shinshu.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kakushi nenbutsu derived from Jodo Shinshu is said to have been believed by Zenran (1217 - 1286), the eldest son of Jodo Shinshu founder Shinran (1173 - 1263), when he was sent to the eastern part of Japan for the missions of Jodo Shinshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kakushi nenbutsu derived from Jodo Shinshu is said to have been believed by Zenran (1217 - 1286), the eldest son of Jodo Shinshu founder Shinran (1173 - 1263), when he was sent to the eastern part of Japan for the missions of Jodo Shinshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>邪教に傾き布教したことを理由として、善鸞は父の親鸞から絶縁・追放されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father broke off relations with Zenran and expelled him for his inclination to - and his propagation of - the heresy.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father broke off relations with Zenran and expelled him for his inclination to - and his propagation of - the heresy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father broke off relations with Zenran and expelled him for his inclination to - and his propagation of - the heresy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>善鸞などの隠し念仏の善知識と呼ばれる指導者は、『御書』をよむことができ、儀式を執り行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The leaders of kakushi nenbutsu, including Zenran, are called &quot;zen chishiki&quot; (kalyaana-mitra, the Sanskrit word which means the person who offers spiritual friendship and guidance), and they can read &quot;Gosho&quot; (secret books) and hold the rituals of kakushi nenbutsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The leaders of kakushi nenbutsu, including Zenran, are called &quot;zen chishiki&quot; (kalyaana-mitra, a Sanskrit word which means a person who offers spiritual friendship and guidance), and they can read &quot;Gosho&quot; (secret books) and hold the rituals of kakushi nenbutsu.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The leaders of kakushi nenbutsu, including Zenran, are called &quot;zen chishiki&quot; (kalyaana-mitra, a Sanskrit word which means a person who offers spiritual friendship and guidance), and they can read &quot;Gosho&quot; (secret books) and hold the rituals of kakushi nenbutsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>善知識は、死ぬ前に次の善知識を3人以内選び、『御書』を伝える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zen chishiki select the next zen chishiki (in three or less) and hand down Gosho before they die.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before they die, zen chishiki select the next zen chishiki (three or fewer) and hand down Gosho.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before they die, zen chishiki select the next zen chishiki (three or fewer) and hand down Gosho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>その教義を形作っている書物には、『法要章』（ほうようしょう）や、秘事を行うものに相伝される『御袖下の御書』がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The key books of their doctrines are &quot;Hoyosho&quot; (the book that tried to justify kakushi nenbutsu) and &quot;Osodeshita no Gosho&quot; (the book on secret religious ceremonies that is handed down from the ceremony performer to the next).</e>
<cmt>・『法要章』の括弧の中の解説は「隠し念仏を正当化することを試みた書物」としています。・『御袖下の御書』の括弧の中の解説は「秘事について書かれ、これを行う者に相伝される書物」としています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The key books of their doctrines are &quot;Hoyosho&quot; (the book that tried to justify kakushi nenbutsu) and &quot;Osodeshita no Gosho&quot; (the book on secret religious ceremonies that is handed down from one ceremony performer to the next).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The key books of their doctrines are &quot;Hoyosho&quot; (the book that tried to justify kakushi nenbutsu) and &quot;Osodeshita no Gosho&quot; (the book on secret religious ceremonies that is handed down from one ceremony performer to the next).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>いくつかの書物があるが、なかでも『法要章』が隠し念仏の聖典である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There exist some books in kakushi nenbutsu, and Hoyosho is its scriputure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There exist some books in kakushi nenbutsu, and Hoyosho is its scriputure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There exist some books in kakushi nenbutsu, and Hoyosho is its scripture.</e>
<cmt>scriputureをscriptureに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="20">
<j>『法要章』は、隠し念仏が親鸞から蓮如の流れを継ぐ正統な教えであると説く書物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoyosho says kakushi nenbutsu inherits orthodox teachings from Shinran via Rennyo.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoyosho says kakushi nenbutsu inherits orthodox teachings from Shinran via Rennyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Hoyosho&quot; says kakushi nenbutsu inherits orthodox teachings from Shinran via Rennyo.</e>
<cmt>&quot;をつけました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>相伝を得た善知識に会い、たすけたまえと一念に頼む儀式を行って、何年何月何日何時に弥陀に頼んで救われたとわかるような信心決定（しんじんけつじょう）を得ることがその教えの眼目である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The point of the teachings is for the believers to get &quot;Shinjin Ketsujo&quot; (Amitabha Tathagata&apos;s salvation) at a specific time and date through meeting with zen chishiki and through implementing the ritual of a singlehearted appeal for salvation to zen chishiki.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処 ・「信心決定」については括弧書きで「阿弥陀如来による救済」と解説しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The point of the teachings is for the believers to gain &quot;Shinjin Ketsujo&quot; (Amitabha Tathagata&apos;s salvation) at a specific time and date through meeting with zen chishiki and through implementing the ritual of a singlehearted appeal for salvation to zen chishiki.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The point of the teachings is for the believers to gain &quot;Shinjin Ketsujo&quot; (Amitabha Tathagata&apos;s salvation) at a specific time and date through meeting with zen chishiki and through implementing the ritual of a single-hearted appeal for salvation to zen chishiki.</e>
<cmt>singleheartedをsingle-heartedに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>しかし、この善知識に頼るということは、弥陀ではなくて善知識というこの世の救済者に頼ることであり、これこそが浄土真宗本願寺教団が異端として激しく排除する理由である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This means that the believers of kakushi nenbutsu depend on zen chishiki (an earthly savior), not on Amitabha Tathagata, which is the very reason that the organization of Hongan-ji school of Jodo Shinshu severely excludes kakushi nenbutsu as a heresy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This means that the believers of kakushi nenbutsu depend on zen chishiki (an earthly savior), not on Amitabha Tathagata, which is the very reason that the organization of the Hongan-ji school of Jodo Shinshu severely excludes kakushi nenbutsu as a heresy.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This means that the believers of kakushi nenbutsu depend on zen chishiki (an earthly savior), not on Amitabha Tathagata, which is the very reason that the organization of the Hongan-ji school of Jodo Shinshu severely excludes kakushi nenbutsu as a heresy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>蓮如は、救われるためには善知識に会わなければならないという教義を厳しく否定してきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rennyo severely rejected the teachings of kakushi nenbutsu that the believers have to meet with zen chishiki in order to get salvation.</e>
<cmt>・「教義」の内容は現在も変わらないものと考えられるので、that節の時制は現在形にしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rennyo severely rejected the teachings of kakushi nenbutsu that the believers have to meet with zen chishiki in order to gain salvation.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rennyo severely rejected the teachings of kakushi nenbutsu that the believers have to meet with zen chishiki in order to gain salvation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="24">
<j>隠し念仏では、本尊は弘法大師（空海）、興教大師（覚鑁）、親鸞とされ、真言密教の影響が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In kakushi nenbutsu, &quot;honzon&quot; (principal image of Buddha) is &quot;Kobo Daishi&quot; (a posthumous title of the priest Kukai), &quot;Kogyo Daishi&quot; (a posthumous title of the priest Kakuban), or Shinran, and the influence of Shingon Sect of Esoteric Buddhism is seen in its rituals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In kakushi nenbutsu, &quot;honzon&quot; (principal image of Buddha) is &quot;Kobo Daishi&quot; (a posthumous title of the priest Kukai), &quot;Kogyo Daishi&quot; (a posthumous title of the priest Kakuban), or Shinran, and the influence of the Shingon Sect of Esoteric Buddhism is seen in its rituals.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In kakushi nenbutsu, &quot;honzon&quot; (principal image of Buddha) is &quot;Kobo Daishi&quot; (a posthumous title of the priest Kukai), &quot;Kogyo Daishi&quot; (a posthumous title of the priest Kakuban), or Shinran, and the influence of the Shingon Sect of Esoteric Buddhism is seen in its rituals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>表向きは曹洞宗など他の教団に属しており、葬式などは寺で行うが、その後に信者どうしが集まって内々でその教義の秘密のとむらいを行うという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outwardly, kakushi nenbutsu belongs to the other sect, such as Soto Zen Sect, and holds a funeral and other rituals at a temple, but after these rituals, there is a secret funeral for the believers only, they say.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outwardly, kakushi nenbutsu belongs to another sect, such as Soto Zen Sect, and holds a funeral and other rituals at a temple, but after these rituals, there is a secret funeral for the believers only, they say.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Outwardly, kakushi nenbutsu belongs to another sect, such as Soto Zen Sect, and holds a funeral and other rituals at a temple, but after these rituals, there is a secret funeral for the believers only, they say.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>信者は、既存の寺の教えを表法と呼び、隠し念仏の教えを内法（内信心）と呼んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The believers call the existing teachings of a temple the outward law, and call the teachings of kakushi nenbutsu the inward law (or the inward belief).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The believers call the existing teachings of a temple the outward law, and call the teachings of kakushi nenbutsu the inward law (or the inward belief).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The believers call the existing teachings of a temple the outward law, and call the teachings of kakushi nenbutsu the inward law (or the inward belief).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="27">
<j>オトリアゲ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Otoriage&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Otoriage&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otoriage</e>
<cmt>&quot;をとりました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>信心決定の儀式はオトリアゲと呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ritual of Shinjin Ketsujo is called &quot;Otoriage.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ritual of Shinjin Ketsujo is called &quot;Otoriage.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ritual of Shinjin Ketsujo is called Otoriage.</e>
<cmt>&quot;をとりました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="29">
<j>善知識に会い、「助けたまえ」と頼む儀式が行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Otoriage, a believer of kakushi nenbutsu meets with zen chishiki and implements the ritual of an appeal for salvation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Otoriage, a believer of kakushi nenbutsu meets with zen chishiki and implements the ritual of an appeal for salvation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Otoriage, a believer of kakushi nenbutsu meets with zen chishiki and implements the ritual of an appeal for salvation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>ある文献では同時に、頭を打ち付ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A document says the believer has to knock its forehead against the floor at this occasion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A document says that on this occasion the believer has to knock his or her forehead against the floor.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A document says that on this occasion the believer has to knock his or her forehead against the floor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>これを善知識が「よし」というまで行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And he (or she) has to continue knocking until zen chishiki says, &quot;Enough.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And he (or she) has to continue knocking until zen chishiki says, &quot;Enough.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And he (or she) has to continue knocking until zen chishiki says, Enough.</e>
<cmt>&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>鏡で儀式の終わった後、鏡でピカピカさせて光明として拝ませることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Occasionally, zen chishiki reflects the shine of the believer&apos;s forehead with a mirror and makes him (or her) worship the shine after the ritual.</e>
<cmt>・冒頭の「鏡で」は意味不明であり不要なので省略しています。 ・「鏡でピカピカさせて」は「鏡で額のてかりを反射させて」の意味に解しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Occasionally, zen chishiki reflects the shine of the believer&apos;s forehead with a mirror and makes him (or her) worship the shine after the ritual.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Occasionally, zen chishiki reflects the shine of the believer&apos;s forehead with a mirror and makes him (or her) worship the shine after the ritual.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>信者は内容を部外者には語ってはならない、言えば血を吐いて死ぬと脅すことも行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The believer is forbidden to let out the ritual under the threat that he (or she) will vomid blood and die if he (or she) does so.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The believer is forbidden to reveal the ritual under the threat that he (or she) will vomit blood and die if he (or she) does so.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The believer is forbidden to reveal the ritual under the threat that he (or she) will vomit blood and die if he (or she) does so.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="34">
<j>潜伏する理由として、金儲けを企む者に知られて教えが退廃することを防ぐためとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The believers say they conceal themselves for fear that the teachings will deteriorate when money chasers come to know and utilize these teachings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The believers say they conceal themselves for fear that the teachings will deteriorate when money chasers come to know and utilize these teachings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The believers say they conceal themselves for fear that the teachings will deteriorate when money chasers come to know and utilize these teachings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>『法要章』には、隠し念仏ではお金を出さなければという気持ちになるので、お金を持っている人からは信心が得にくいとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, Hoyosho says it is difficult for kakushi nenbutsu to attract the rich, because the teachings often stir up the believers&apos; sense of duty to offer money.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Hoyosho says it is difficult for kakushi nenbutsu to attract the rich, because the teachings often stir up the believers&apos; sense of duty to offer money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, &quot;Hoyosho&quot; says it is difficult for kakushi nenbutsu to attract the rich, because the teachings often stir up the believers&apos; sense of duty to offer money.</e>
<cmt>&quot;&quot;をつけました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="36">
<j>オトモヅケ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Otomoduke&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Otomoduke&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otomozuke</e>
<cmt>dをzに変更しました。&quot;をとりました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>生まれてまもなくの赤子に信心を与えることはオトモヅケと呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ritual of having a newborn baby get involved in kakushi nenbutsu is called &quot;Otomoduke.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ritual of having a newborn baby get involved in kakushi nenbutsu is called &quot;Otomoduke.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ritual of having a newborn baby get involved in kakushi nenbutsu is called Otomozuke.</e>
<cmt>dをzに変更しました。&quot;をとりました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>その後、6～7歳になったときオトリアゲを行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward, at the age of six or seven, he (or she) undergoes Otoriage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterward, at the age of six or seven, he (or she) undergoes Otoriage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterward, at the age of six or seven, he (or she) undergoes Otoriage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="39">
<j>摘発と影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Exposure of kakushi nenbutsu and its influence</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Exposure of kakushi nenbutsu and its influence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Exposure of kakushi nenbutsu and its influence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>1722年には西本願寺の別院から、隠し念仏の信者をみつけたら、正しい教えに改めさせるようにとの掟が各寺に出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1722, the branch temple of Nishi Hongan-ji Temple issued the order that every temple under its cotrol should make kakushi nenbutsu believers convert their belief any time they were found.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1722, the branch temple of Nishi Hongan-ji Temple issued an order that every temple under its cotrol should make kakushi nenbutsu believers convert their beliefs any time they are found.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1722, the branch temple of Nishi Hongan-ji Temple issued an order that every temple under its control should make kakushi nenbutsu believers convert their beliefs any time they are found.</e>
<cmt>cotrolを controlに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>1754年には、仙台藩が摘発し代表者が死罪となり、その後も幾度か摘発された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1754, the Sendai clan exposed kakushi nenbutsu within its domain and executed the leader, and even after that, there were similar exposures several times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1754, the Sendai clan exposed kakushi nenbutsu within its domain and executed the leader, and even after that, there were several similar exposures.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1754, the Sendai clan exposed kakushi nenbutsu within its domain and executed the leader, and even after that, there were several similar exposures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="42">
<j>1900年前後の明治時代後期にも、名古屋や岐阜、浅草や横浜に秘密結社的に存在して問題視され、根絶を目的として教義体系の暴露本が出版されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the later Meiji period around 1900, kakushi nenbutsu existed as a secret society in some places, such as Nagoya, Gifu, Asakusa and Yokohama, and since its existence was regarded as problematic, a muckraking book on the system of its doctorines was published in order to wipe it out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the later Meiji period around 1900, kakushi nenbutsu existed as a secret society in some places, such as Nagoya, Gifu, Asakusa, and Yokohama, and since its existence was regarded problematic, a muckraking book on the system of its doctorines was published in order to wipe it out.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the later Meiji period around 1900, kakushi nenbutsu existed as a secret society in some places, such as Nagoya, Gifu, Asakusa, and Yokohama, and since its existence was regarded problematic, a muckraking book on the system of its doctrines was published in order to wipe it out.</e>
<cmt>doctorinesを doctrinesに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>1931年（昭和6年）ごろにも、秘密結社的な悪習であるとして警察に摘発されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also around 1931, the police exposed kakushi nenbutsu, regarding it as a secret society having a bad custom.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also around 1931, the police exposed kakushi nenbutsu, regarding it as a secret society having a bad custom.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also around 1931, the police exposed kakushi nenbutsu, regarding it as a secret society having a bad custom.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>このときには、養老院建設の寄付を募るため地位のある寄付者名簿を見せて勧誘した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this case, kakushi nenbutsu asked some people to donate money to the construction of an asylum for the aged, using a list of donators who occupied high social positions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this case, kakushi nenbutsu asked some people to donate money toward the construction of an asylum for the aged, using a list of donators who occupied high social positions.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this case, kakushi nenbutsu asked some people to donate money toward the construction of an asylum for the aged, using a list of donators who occupied high social positions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="45">
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>佐賀県に生まれ、後に高野山で得度して中山身語正宗などを開いた木原覚恵という人物がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once there was a man named Kakue KIHARA, who was born in Saga Prefecture, and later entered the Buddhist priesthood on Mt. Koya, and then founded some Buddhist sects, including &quot;Nakayama Shingo Shoshu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once there was a man named Kakue KIHARA, who was born in Saga Prefecture, later entered the Buddhist priesthood on Mt. Koya, and then founded some Buddhist sects, including &quot;Nakayama Shingo Shoshu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>omitted &apos;&quot;and&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once there was a man named Kakue KIHARA, who was born in Saga Prefecture, later entered the Buddhist priesthood on Mt. Koya, and then founded some Buddhist sects, including Nakayama Shingo Shoshu.</e>
<cmt>&quot;をとりました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>彼の実家は浄土真宗の檀徒だったものの、「身語正」という一種の内信心（＝隠し念仏）を家伝とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outwardly, his parents&apos; home was a supporter of a Jodo Shinshu temple, but it had a kind of an inward belief (= kakushi nenbutsu) called &quot;Shingosho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outwardly, his parents&apos; home was a supporter of a Jodo Shinshu temple, but it had a kind of inward belief (= kakushi nenbutsu) called &quot;Shingosho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Outwardly, his parents&apos; home was a supporter of a Jodo Shinshu temple, but it had a kind of inward belief (= kakushi nenbutsu) called &apos;Shingosho.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>その教えの一部が中山身語正宗などの諸教派でも伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, part of the teachings is handed down to some Buddhist sects, incluing Nakayama Shingo Shoshu.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, some of the teachings are handed down to some Buddhist sects, incluing Nakayama Shingo Shoshu.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, some of the teachings are handed down to some Buddhist sects, including Nakayama Shingo Shoshu.</e>
<cmt>incluingを includingに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 杉山真大(id:2297), Gobodousamani(id:218358), Tmtm(id:14181), R28Bot(id:177951), Metatron(id:64025), お気楽蜻蛉(id:199007), 寂華(id:83725), 郁(id:143484), BAKU(id:55205), 机龍之介(id:61257), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>