<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>題目講</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daimokuko (lecture of Buddhist scriptures, composed by congregation of Hokkeshu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daimokuko (lecture of Buddhist scriptures, composed by congregation of Hokkeshu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daimokuko</e>
<cmt>タイトルであり次セルに説明があるため、補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>題目講（だいもくこう）とは、法華宗系の信徒によって構成された講。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daimokuko is a ko (meeting to lecture Buddhist scriptures) composed by followers of Hokkeshu sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daimokuko is a ko (meeting to lecture Buddhist scriptures) composed by followers of Hokkeshu sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daimokuko is a ko (meeting to lecture Buddhist scriptures) composed by followers of Hokke sects.</e>
<cmt>訳語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>同宗の祖である日蓮が没した日にちなんで毎月13日あるいはその前夜に開かれたことから十三日講とも称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also reffered as Jusannichiko (lecture of Buddhist scriptures, composed by congregation of Hokkeshu) because it was held before and/or after 13th day every month, having to do with the day when Nichiren, founder of the sect, died,.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also reffered as Jusannichiko (lecture of Buddhist scriptures, composed by congregation of Hokkeshu) because it was held before and/or after 13th day every month, having to do with the day when Nichiren, founder of the sect, died,.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also referred as Jusannichiko (lecture of Buddhist scriptures, composed by congregation of Hokke sect) because it was held before and after 13th day every month, having to do with the day when Nichiren, founder of the sect, died.</e>
<cmt>表記などを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>法華経の題目である「南無妙法蓮華経」を唱えることで、日蓮の唱えた教義と信徒間のつながりを確認する意図があるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that it has an aim to confirm the creed Nichiren advocated and relationship among followers by chanting together Nam Myoho Renge-kyo Sutra (Devotion to the Law of Hokekyo), daimoku (Nichiren chant) of Hokekyo (the Lotus Sutra).</e>
<cmt>「信徒間のつながりを確認する」とありますので、「唱えることで」のところに(chanting) togetherを付け加えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that it was aimed to confirm the creed Nichiren advocated and relationship among followers by chanting together Nam Myoho Renge-kyo Sutra (Devotion to the Law of Hokekyo), daimoku (Nichiren chant) of Hokekyo (the Lotus Sutra).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that it was aimed to confirm the creed Nichiren advocated and relationship among followers by chanting together &apos;Namu Myoho Renge-kyo Sutra&apos; (Devotion to the Law of Hokekyo (the Lotus Sutra), daimoku (Nichiren chant) of Hokekyo.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>鎌倉時代末期から知られており、当初は血縁関係に基づく参加が重んじられて一家一族連帯の儀式としても尊重された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been known since the late Kamakura period, and it was also valued as a ritual for ikka-ichizoku rentai (solidarity of one family and one clan), because at an early stage participation in the ritual based on blood relationship was highly important.</e>
<cmt>ハイフォンは原則として省き、名詞にかかる形容詞の場合のみ、使用しました。そのために「一家一族連帯」などの一語が二語に分割されています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been known since the late Kamakura period, and it was also valued as a ritual for ikka-ichizoku rentai (solidarity of one family and one clan), because at an early stage participation in the ritual based on blood relationship was highly important.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been known since the late Kamakura period, and it was also valued as a ritual for ikka-ichizoku rentai (solidarity of one family and one clan), because at an early stage participation in the ritual based on blood relationship was highly important.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>だが、中世後期には地縁の紐帯を強める儀式に変質するとともに周辺地域の題目講との連携や所属する寺院が属する本寺及び門流の行事・事業を支援するなど、宗派全体の信仰・経済両面から支える組織となっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the late medieval period it was transformed into a ceremony to tighten important connection of a regional community, and at the same time it was changed into a systematic organization to support the whole sect both in religion and economy such as facilitating to connect with daimokuko of peripheral regions and assisting rites and festivals and other activities not only of the main temple but also monryu (school of a sect) of the temples to which followers belong.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the late medieval period it was transformed into a ceremony to tighten important connection of a regional community, and at the same time it was changed into a systematic organization to support the whole sect both in religion and economy such as facilitating to connect with daimokuko of peripheral regions and assisting rites and festivals and other activities not only of the main temple but also monryu (school of a sect) of the temples to which followers belong.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the late medieval period it was transformed into a ceremony to tighten important connection of a regional community, and at the same time it was changed into a systematic organization to support the whole sect both in religion and economy such as facilitating to connect with daimokuko of peripheral regions and assisting rites and festivals and other activities not only of the main temple but also monryu (school of a sect) of the temples to which followers belong.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kstigarbha(id:13376), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>