<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>宗門改</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shumon aratame (the inquisition for suppressing Christianity)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shumon aratame (the inquisition for suppressing Christianity)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shumon aratame (the inquisition for suppressing Christianity)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>宗門改（しゅうもんあらため）は、江戸幕府が行った宗教政策および民衆統制政策。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shumon aratame was religion policy and the control of the public promoted by the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shumon aratame was religion policy and the control of the public promoted by the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shumon aratame was religion policy and the control of the public promoted by the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>当初は、キリスト教の禁止に伴うキリシタンの摘発および改宗を目的としていたが、寺請制度による宗門人別改帳が整備されてくると、住民調査的な制度となっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, due to a ban on Christianity, it aimed at detecting and converting Christians, but its purpose gradually shifted to the policing of the public as the system of Shumon-Ninbetsu-Aratame-Cho (The Village People Register of Religious Faith and Relationship) developed based on the Terauke seido (the system of organizing whole temples in Japan with registration of follower families).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, due to a ban on Christianity, it aimed at detecting and converting Christians, but its purpose gradually shifted to the policing of the public as the system of Shumon-Ninbetsu-Aratame-Cho (The Village People Register of Religious Faith and Relationship) developed based on the Terauke seido (the system of organizing whole temples in Japan with registration of follower families).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, due to a ban on Christianity, it aimed at detecting and converting Christians, but its purpose gradually shifted to the policing of the public as the system of Shumon-Ninbetsu-Aratame-Cho (The Village People Register of Religious Faith and Relationship) developed based on the Terauke seido (the system of organizing whole temples in Japan with registration of follower families).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>キリスト教は1549年（天文 (元号)18年）にフランシスコ・ザビエルによってカトリックが日本に伝えられて以来、貿易などを通して信者（キリシタン）が増加した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since 1549 when Catholicism was firstly introduced to Japan by Francis Xavier, the number of Christians increased, stimulated by trades and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since 1549, when Catholicism was firstly introduced to Japan by Francis Xavier, the number of Christians increased, stimulated by trade and other factors.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since 1549, when Catholicism was firstly introduced to Japan by Francis Xavier, the number of Christians increased, stimulated by trade and other factors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>しかし、他国による侵略などを憂慮した豊臣秀吉は1587年（天正15年）宣教師追放令を出してキリスト教の排除に乗り出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1587, however, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, who was worried about invasion by foreign countries, issued a decree of purging missionaries and embarked on the oppression of Christians.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1587, however, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, who was worried about invasion by foreign countries, issued a decree of purging missionaries and embarked on the oppression of Christians.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1587, however, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, who was worried about invasion by foreign countries, issued a decree of purging missionaries and embarked on the oppression of Christians.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>江戸幕府もこれを引き継ぎ1612年（慶長17年）まず幕府領内にキリスト教禁止令を出し、翌年には全国的にキリスト教が禁制となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Edo bakufu followed suit and issued a ban on Christianity in 1612 that took effect within shognal demesnes, followed by a nationwide prohibition on Christianity in the following year.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Edo bakufu followed suit and issued a ban on Christianity in 1612 that took effect within shognal demesnes, followed by a nationwide prohibition on Christianity in the following year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Edo bakufu followed this policy and issued a ban on Christianity in 1612 that took effect within shogunal demesnes, followed by a nationwide prohibition on Christianity in the following year.</e>
<cmt>suitをthis policyに変更しました。shognalをshogunalに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>当初、幕府はキリスト像が刻まれた板を踏ませる踏絵や密告の奨励などを行うことによりキリシタンの取締りを実施し、キリシタンではないことを仏教寺院に請け負わせてその証明とした（寺請制度）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, the bakufu persecuted Christians by forcing them to step on the wood sheet with a likeness of Jesus (this practice is called &apos;fumie&apos;) or by encouraging whistle-blowing to reveal Christians, and Buddhist temples were commissioned by the bakufu to prove their parishioners were not Christians (this system is called &apos;terauke seido&apos;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, the bakufu persecuted Christians by forcing them to step on a wood sheet containing a likeness of Jesus (this practice is called &apos;fumie&apos;) or by encouraging whistle-blowing to reveal Christians, and Buddhist temples were commissioned by the bakufu to prove that their parishioners were not Christians (this system is called &apos;terauke seido&apos;).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, the bakufu persecuted Christians by forcing them to step on a wood sheet containing a likeness of Jesus (this practice is called &apos;fumie&apos;) or by encouraging whistle-blowing to reveal Christians, and Buddhist temples were commissioned by the bakufu to prove that their parishioners were not Christians (this system is called &apos;terauke seido&apos;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>1637年（寛永17年）からその翌年にかけて九州でおきた島原の乱の後、1640年（寛永17年）幕府は宗門改役を設置し、1664年（寛文4年）には諸藩に宗門改役を設置するよう命じている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Shimabara Rebellion, an uprising in Kyushu that continued from 1637 to 1638, the bakufu introduced shumon aratame-yaku (an officer in charge of the persecution of Christians) in1640 and issued the order in 1664 that required all the domains to introduce shumon aratame-yaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Shimabara Rebellion, an uprising in Kyushu that continued from 1637 to 1638, the bakufu introduced shumon aratame-yaku (an officer in charge of the persecution of Christians) in 1640 and issued an order in 1664 that required all the domains to introduce shumon aratame-yaku.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Shimabara Rebellion, an uprising in Kyushu that continued from 1637 to 1638, the bakufu introduced shumon aratame-yaku (an officer in charge of the persecution of Christians) in 1640 and issued an order in 1664 that required all the domains to introduce shumon aratame-yaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>1665年（寛文5年）には日蓮宗のうち強硬派である不受不施派が禁制となったことにより、他宗派に改宗させる宗門改の対象となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the Fujufuse (Not Receive and Not Give (from and to people other than those belonging to the Nichiren Sect)) School, a fundamentalist faction of the Nichiren Sect, was banned in 1665, people affiliated with the faction became targets of shumon aratame, which aimed at converting heretics to other Buddhist sects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Fujufuse (Not Receive and Not Give (from and to people other than those belonging to the Nichiren Sect)) School, a fundamentalist faction of the Nichiren Sect, was banned in 1665, people affiliated with the faction became targets of shumon aratame, which aimed at converting heretics to other Buddhist sects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Fujufuse (Not Receive and Not Give (from and to people other than those belonging to the Nichiren Sect)) School, a fundamentalist faction of the Nichiren Sect, was banned in 1665, people affiliated with the faction became targets of shumon aratame, which aimed at converting heretics to other Buddhist sects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>1671年（寛文11年）幕府は宗門人別改帳の作成を義務付け、原則として特定の仏教寺院（不受不施派を除く檀那寺、藩によっては神社もあった）に属する寺請制度とともに宗門改が確立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the 1671 bakufu decree that made it mandatory to create Shumon-Ninbetsu-Aratame-Cho, the system of shumon aratame was completed together with the terauke seido, where Shognal subjects were required to belong, in principle, to specific temples (family temples excluding the Fujufuse School, and sometimes shrines depending on domains).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the 1671 bakufu decree that made it mandatory to create Shumon-Ninbetsu-Aratame-Cho, the system of shumon aratame was completed together with the terauke seido, where Shognal subjects were required to belong, in principle, to specific temples (family temples excluding the Fujufuse School, and sometimes shrines, depending on the domain).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the 1671 bakufu decree that made it mandatory to create Shumon-Ninbetsu-Aratame-Cho, the system of shumon aratame was completed together with the terauke seido, where Shogunal subjects were required to belong, in principle, to specific temples (family temples excluding the Fujufuse School, and sometimes shrines, depending on the domain).</e>
<cmt>shognalをshogunalに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>宗門改の制度は、1873年（明治6年）キリスト教の禁制が解除されるまで続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shumon aratame system existed until 1873 when a ban on Christianity was abolished (by the Meiji Government).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shumon aratame system existed until 1873, when a ban on Christianity was abolished (by the Meiji Government).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shumon aratame system existed until 1873, when a ban on Christianity was abolished (by the Meiji Government).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>明治政府によるキリスト教徒へのスパイ活動は当初は弾正台が「諜者規則」（1870年6月）に基づいて行い、翌年7月には新しい太政官制により正院内の監部課が引き継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, Meiji Government&apos;s spy operations against Christians were led by the Danjodai (Inspection Bureau) based on &quot;Rules for Espionages&quot; (June, 1870), succeeded in July 1871 by the Inspection Division at the Seiin (the central state council in the early Meiji period), which was set up with the new birth of the Daijokan (Department of State) system.</e>
<cmt>「諜者規則」定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, the Meiji Government&apos;s spy operations against Christians were led by the Danjodai (Inspection Bureau) based on &quot;Rules for Espionages&quot; (June, 1870), succeeded in July 1871 by the Inspection Division at the Seiin (the central state council in the early Meiji period), which was set up with the new birth of the Daijokan (Department of State) system.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, the Meiji Government&apos;s spy operations against Christians were led by the Danjodai (Inspection Bureau) based on &apos;Rules for Espionages&apos; (June, 1870), succeeded in July 1871 by the Inspection Division at the Seiin (the central state council in the early Meiji period), which was set up with the new birth of the Daijokan (Department of State) system.</e>
<cmt>&quot;を &apos; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>監部課の異宗諜者の廃止はキリスト教解禁の翌年（1874年6月）であったが、異宗諜者の報告書は1876年（明治9年）3月まで存在している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although heresy inspectors at the Inspection Division were abolished in June 1874, one year after the lifting of the ban on Christianity, it is confirmed that reports by heretic inspectors continued until March 1876.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although heresy inspectors at the Inspection Division were abolished in June 1874, one year after the lifting of the ban on Christianity, it is confirmed that reports by heretic inspectors continued until March 1876.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although heresy inspectors at the Inspection Division were abolished in June 1874, one year after the lifting of the ban on Christianity, it is confirmed that reports by heretic inspectors continued until March 1876.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), 赤井彗星(id:18381), Mooko(id:36162), Nonpee(id:135653), くっちゃめ(id:86793), Sapphire123(id:147732), The Side(id:69360), Memosa(id:131221), YODAFON(id:161109), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>