<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>悟り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Satori: Enlightenment</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Satori: Enlightenment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Satori: Enlightenment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>悟り（さとり）は知らなかったことを知ること、気がつくこと、感づくことを言い覚りとも書く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Satori (悟り: enlightment) means that you learn, become aware of, or notice what you haven&apos;t known. Another Kanji (覚り), whose meaning is similar to awakening, is sometimes used.</e>
<cmt>「悟り」と「覚り」という漢字表記の違いを明示するため、英文にも漢字を入れております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Satori (悟り: enlightenment) means that one learns, becomes aware of or notices what one hasn&apos;t known; another Kanji (覚り), whose meaning is similar to awakening, is sometimes used.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Satori (悟り: enlightenment) means that one learns, becomes aware of or notices what one hasn&apos;t known; another Kanji (覚り), whose meaning is similar to awakening, is sometimes used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>宗教上の悟りは迷妄を去った真理やその取得を言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Religious enlightment means Shinri, which was left from illustion or the acquisition of the truth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Religious enlightenment means Shinri, which is the obtainment of truth or the opposite of illusion.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Religious enlightenment means Shinri, which is the obtainment of truth or the opposite of illusion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>サンスクリットでは「bodhi ボーディ」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In sanskrit, it is called &apos;bodhi.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Sanskrit, it is called &apos;bodhi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Sanskrit, it is called &apos;bodhi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>日本語では「菩提」「開悟」「成道」（じょうどう成仏得道の略）ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japanese, it is also called &apos;Bodai&apos;, &apos;Kaigo&apos;, or&apos;Jodo&apos;, the abbriviation of &apos;Jobutsuedo.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japanese, it is also called &apos;Bodai,&apos; &apos;Kaigo&apos; or &apos;Jodo,&apos; the abbreviation of &apos;Jobutsuedo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japanese, it is also called &apos;Bodai,&apos; &apos;Kaigo&apos; or &apos;Jodo,&apos; the abbreviation of &apos;Jobutsuedo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>悟りを開いた者を「buddha ブッダ」といい、漢字で音写し「仏陀」「仏」としたり、「覚者」と意訳したりする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The person who attained enlightment is called &apos;buddha&apos;. It was transliterated into Kanji. It is pronounced &apos;Buddha&apos; or &apos;Butsu, and also paraphrased as &apos;the enlightened one, Kakusha.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The person who attained enlightenment is called &apos;Buddha,&apos; a name that was transliterated into Kanji; it is pronounced &apos;Buddha&apos; or &apos;Butsu&apos; and is also paraphrased as &apos;the enlightened one, Kakusha.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The person who attained enlightenment is called &apos;Buddha,&apos; a name that was transliterated into Kanji; it is pronounced &apos;Buddha&apos; or &apos;Butsu&apos; and is also paraphrased as &apos;the enlightened one, Kakusha.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>各宗教における悟り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enlightment in various religions</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enlightment in various religions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enlightment in various religions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>仏教</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buddhism</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buddhism</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddhism</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>仏教の悟り （さとり、覚り）は、原語のサンスクリットでは、bodhiボーディ、である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Satori in Buddism is called Bodhi in Sanskrit, the original language of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Satori in Buddism is called Bodhi in Sanskrit, the original language of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Satori in Buddhism is called Bodhi in Sanskrit, the original language of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>Buddism→Buddhism</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>日本語・漢語では「菩提（ぼだい）」「覚悟」「証（しょう）」「修証（しゅしょう）」「証得（しょうとく）」「証悟（しょうご）」「道（どう）」などの別称もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has other names such as &apos;Bodai&apos;, &apos;Kakugo&apos;, &apos;Show&apos;, Shushou&apos;, &apos;Shoutoku&apos;, &apos;Shougo&apos; or &apos;Dou.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has other names such as &apos;Bodai,&apos; &apos;Kakugo,&apos; &apos;Show,&apos; Shushou,&apos; &apos;Shoutoku,&apos; &apos;Shougo&apos; and &apos;Dou.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has other names such as &apos;Bodai,&apos; &apos;Kakugo,&apos; &apos;Sho,&apos; Shusho,&apos; &apos;Shotoku,&apos; &apos;Shogo&apos; and &apos;Do.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ローマ字表記（しょうshou→shoなど）</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>真理（法）に目覚めること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Awakening of shinri (law)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Awakening of shinri (law)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Awakening of shinri (law)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>迷いの反対。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The opposite word of illusion</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The opposite of illusion</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The opposite of illusion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>さとりは初期仏教から部派仏教あたりまでは究極目的であり、悟るためにさまざまな修行が説かれ実践される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enlightment was the ultimate purpose from the primary stage to Hinayana. In order to attain enlightment, various practices were explained and conducted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enlightenment was the ultimate purpose, from the primary stage to Hinayana.; in order to attain enlightenment, various practices were conducted and explained.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the earliest period of Buddhism through to the emergence of sects, the ultimate aim of the Satori (enlightenment) concept entailed putting into practice the pursuit of various forms of knowledge and disciplines.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>仏教の悟りは般若を体としており、凡夫（ぼんぶ）が煩悩（ぼんのう）に左右されて迷いの生存を繰り返し、輪廻（りんね）を続けているのは、それは何事にも分別（ふんべつ）の心をもってし、分析的に納得しようとする結果であるとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enlightment in Buddhism takes the form of Hannya, and Bompu, an ordinary man, is subject to Bonno, repeats the lives of illusion and continues the wheel of life because he tries to face every thing with sensibility and to understand it fully and analytically. An ordinary man must be liberated from earthly desires and the woes of man with the help of wisdom, and he can realize it by means of observing things well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enlightenment in Buddhism takes the form of Hannya, but Bompu, an ordinary man, is subject to Bonno, repeats the lives of illusion and continues the wheel of life because he tries to face everything with sensibility so as to understand it fully and analytically; thus an ordinary man must be liberated from earthly desires and the woes of man with the help of wisdom, and he can realize it by observing things well.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Satori concept in Buddhism encapsulates the unenlightened (Sanskrit: prthag-jana) being captive to a bewildering cycle of worldly desires and eventually developing a sense of the meaningless in relation to this endless treadmill of birth and rebirth.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処。前出補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>輪廻の迷いから智慧の力によって解脱（げだつ）しなければならない、その方法は事物を如実（にょじつ）に観察（かんざつ）することで実現する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To gain release from this morass-like vortex, nirvana is reached only through the power of wisdom (Sanskrit: prajna) by means of practicing the observation of reality.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これが真理を悟ることであり、そこには思考がなく、言葉もない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is how to attain enlightment, which includes no thoughts or words.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is how to attain enlightenment, which does not include thoughts or words.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is how to attain enlightenment, which does not include thoughts or words.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>大乗経典では、それ以前の教義と峻別するために「覚り」を超えるものとして「阿耨多羅三藐三菩提（あのくたらさんみゃくさんぼだい、原語Anuttara samyaksaMbodhi）」「無上正等正覚（むじょうしょうとうしょうがく）」を措定している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mahayana Sutra made too sharp a distinction between its doctorine and the former ones. It predicates &quot;Anokutara sanmyaku sanbodai (supreme perfect enlightenment (in the original language &quot;Anuttara samyaksaMbodhi&quot;) &quot; and &quot;Mujo shoto shogaku (supreme perfect wisdom) &quot; as being above enlightment.</e>
<cmt>Mahayana Sutra madeとするかMahayana Sutra makesとするか判断に迷いました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mahayana Sutra made too sharp a distinction between its doctrine and the former ones; it predicates &quot;Anokutara sanmyaku sanbodai (supreme perfect enlightenment (in the original language, &apos;Anuttara samyaksaMbodhi&apos;) &quot; and &quot;Mujo shoto shogaku (supreme perfect wisdom)&quot; as being above enlightenment.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For doctrinal and distinct difference reasons, the Satoriconcept that appears in the Mahayana Sutra supposedly goes further than the &apos;mujoshotoshogaku&apos; (greater enlightened being) concept of Anuttara samyaksaMbodhi (supreme perfect enlightenment).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しました。前出補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>悟りの意味の違いが宗教・宗派の違いであるということもできるが、般若経などでは、「覚り」と「悟り」は別のものとして使い分けられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be said that the difference of the meaning of enlightment means the difference of religion or sect. Although in Hannya-kyo Sutra, awakening and enlightment were differently used, in the present Japanese Buddhism world (including this article), these two terms are often confused.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be said that the difference in the meaning of enlightenment means the difference of religion or sect; while in Hannya-kyo Sutra, awakening and enlightenment were differently used, in the present world of Japanese Buddhism (including this article), the two terms are often confused.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be said that there are differences in the meaning of Satori between Buddhist sects however, in Prajnaparamita (wisdom) scriptures and elsewhere, the Satori concept can be written using different characters (&apos;覚り&apos; and &apos;悟り&apos;).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処。クォーテーションを半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかし、現代日本の仏教界（この記事を含む）では混乱して使われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be said that the difference of the meaning of enlightment means the difference of religion or sect. Although in Hannya-kyo Sutra, awakening and enlightment were differently used, in the present Japanese Buddhism world (including this article), these two terms are often confused.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be said that the difference of the meaning of enlightment means the difference of religion or sect. Although in Hannya-kyo Sutra, awakening and enlightment were differently used, in the present Japanese Buddhism world (including this article), these two terms are often confused.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in current day Japanese Buddhism (this text included), there is discord about which character should be used.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>釈迦（しゃか）は多くの哲学者や宗教家の教えを受け、苦行にも専念したが悟りを得られなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shaka studied under many philosophers or people of religion and practiced asceticism. However, he could not attain enlightment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shaka studied under many philosophers or people of religion and practiced asceticism, but he was unable to attain enlightenment.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shaka studied under many philosophers or people of religion and practiced asceticism, but he was unable to attain enlightenment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>そこで今までの修行法をすてて、尼連禅河（にれんぜんが）で沐浴し身を清め、村娘スジャータから乳粥（ちちがゆ）の供養（くよう）を受けて河を渡り、対岸のピッパラ樹の下で坐禅をして禅定に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So, he gave up the ascetic practices he had practiced, bathed and purified himself in Nirenzenga. After being given milk porridge by a village girl named Sujahta, he crossed the river and entered Dhyana - Meditation under a Pippala Tree.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So, he gave up the ascetic practices he had practiced, bathed and purified himself in Nirenzenga. After being given milk porridge by a village girl named Sujahta, he crossed the river and entered Dhyana - Meditation under a Pippala Tree.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So, he gave up the ascetic practices he had practiced, bathed and purified himself in Nirenzenga. After being given milk porridge by a village girl named Sujahta, he crossed the river and entered Dhyana - Meditation under a Pippala Tree.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>その禅定がしだいに深化し、三昧の中で「三明」が顕れ、真理を悟ることができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Dhyana-Meditation gradually deepened, &quot;sanmyo (three insights)&quot; appeared in zammai, and he was able to attain Shinri.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Dhyana Meditation gradually deepened, &quot;sanmyo (three insights)&quot; appeared in zammai, and he was ultimately able to attain Shinri.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Dhyana Meditation gradually deepened, &quot;sanmyo (three insights)&quot; appeared in zammai, and he was ultimately able to attain Shinri.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>これによって釈迦は悟った者（覚者）、すなわち「ブッダ（仏陀）」になったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Through this, Shaka became the awakened one (Kakusha), or Buddha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Through this, Shaka became the awakened one (Kakusha), or Buddha.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Through this, Shaka became the awakened one (Kakusha), or Buddha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="22">
<j>この悟りの境地を「涅槃（ねはん）」といい、それは「寂静（じゃくじょう）」であるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The state of attaining enlightment is called &apos;nehan (nirvana)&apos;, which is described as &apos;jakujyou (quiet and peaceful).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The state of attaining enlightment is called &apos;nehan (nirvana)&apos;, which is described as &apos;jakujyou (quiet and peaceful).&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The state of attaining enlightment is called &apos;nehan (nirvana)&apos;, which is described as &apos;jakujo (quiet and peaceful).&apos;</e>
<cmt>jakujyou→jakujo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>煩悩が制御されているので、とらわれのない心の静けさがあるということである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It means that there is peace in the unoccupied mind since Bonno is controlled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It means there is peace in the unoccupied mind, since Bonno is controlled.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It means there is peace in the unoccupied mind, since Bonno is controlled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="24">
<j>また、悟りを求める心を菩提心という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The mind that seeks enlightment is called aspiration for Buddhahood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The mind that seeks enlightenment is said to aspire toward Buddhahood.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The mind that seeks enlightenment is said to aspire toward Buddhahood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>悟りを求める点では部派仏教も大乗仏教も共通であるが、自分のさとりを追求する部派仏教の場合、声聞（しょうもん）は四諦（したい）の教えを聞いて修行し、縁覚（えんがく）は十二因縁を覚ってそれぞれ解脱するとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both Hinayana and Mahayana Buddhism seek enlightment. However, in Hinayana where an individual seeks his enlightment, an individual can be liberated from earthly desires through the practice of listening to the teaching of the Four Axioms according to Shomon and through realizing the twelve nidanas according to Engaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both Hinayana and Mahayana Buddhism seek enlightenment, but in Hinayana, where an individual seeks his enlightenment, an individual can be liberated from earthly desires through the practice of listening to the teaching of the Four Axioms according to Shomon and by realizing the twelve nidanas according to Engaku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both Hinayana and Mahayana Buddhism seek enlightenment, but in Hinayana, where an individual seeks his enlightenment, an individual can be liberated from earthly desires through the practice of listening to the teaching of the Four Axioms according to Shomon and by realizing the twelve nidanas according to Engaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="26">
<j>また「覚り」とも言い、部派仏教の旧訳（くやく）ではサンスクリット語「vitarka」の訳である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called &apos;awakening&apos;. In the old translated version of Hinayama, it is the translated from the word, &quot;vitarka.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called &apos;awakening&apos;; in the old translated version of Hinayama, it is the translated from the word &quot;vitarka.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called &apos;awakening&apos;; in the old translated version of Hinayama, it is the translated from the word &quot;vitarka&quot; in Sanskrit.</e>
<cmt>in Sanskritを追加。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>vitarkaは「尋」とも訳し、対象を推しはかって分別する麁（あら）い心の働きをいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Vitarka is also translated as &quot;Jin&quot;,meaning the rough action of the mind that presumes and judges objects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Vitarka is also translated as &quot;Jin,&quot; meaning the rough action of the mind that presumes and judges objects.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Vitarka is also translated as &quot;Jin,&quot; meaning the rough action of the mind that presumes and judges objects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>一方、細かい心の働きを「vicaara」（旧訳では観（かん）、新訳では伺（し））といい、両者は対になって用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the delicate action of mind is called &quot;vicaara&quot; (Kan in the old and Shi in the new version). Vitarka and vicaara are used as a pair.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the delicate action of mind is called &quot;vicaara&quot; (Kan in the old version and Shi in the new); Vitarka and vicaara are used as a pair.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the delicate action of mind is called &quot;vicaara&quot; (Kan in the old version and Shi in the new); Vitarka and vicaara are used as a pair.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>この両者はともに定心（じようしん）を妨げるが、禅定の深まりによって消滅する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both of them hinder Concentration, but disappear as Dhyana - Meditation deepens.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both of them hinder concentration but disappear as Dhyana Meditation deepens.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both of them hinder concentration but disappear as Dhyana Meditation deepens.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="30">
<j>大乗経典では「覚り」は「bodhi」の訳である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Mahayana Sutra, &apos;awakening&apos; is transliterated from &apos;bodhi&apos;. It means awakening or the wisdom of awakening.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Mahayana Sutra, &apos;awakening&apos; is transliterated from &apos;bodhi&apos;; it means awakening or the wisdom of awakening.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Mahayana Sutra, &apos;awakening&apos; is a translation of &apos;bodhi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>「菩提」と音写され、覚り、もしくは覚りの智慧を表す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is transliterated as the word &apos;bodai&apos;; it means awakening or the wisdom of awakening.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>古くは「道（どう）」「意」「覚意」などと訳された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the ancient times, it was translated as &quot;Dou&quot;, &quot;I&quot; or &quot;Kakui.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the ancient times, it was translated as &quot;Dou,&quot; &quot;I&quot; or &quot;Kakui.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the ancient times, it was translated as &quot;Do,&quot; &quot;I&quot; or &quot;Kakui.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Dou→Do</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>大乗仏教では自分の悟りは他人のさとりを前提に成立するという立場である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Mahayana Sutra presumes that each person&apos;s enlightment is based on others&apos;, it puts an emphasis on Rokuharamitsu, a Bosatsu practice, which pursues Ritako (Altruistic Practice).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the Mahayana Sutra presumes that each person&apos;s enlightenment is based on others,&apos; it places an emphasis on Rokuharamitsu, a Bosatsu practice that pursues Ritako (Altruistic Practice).</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mahayana Buddhism maintains a, stance based on an assumption that the Satori of others is proceeded by ones own enlightenment.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処。前出補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>六波羅蜜（ろくはらみつ）という利他行を実践する菩薩（ぼさつぎょう）を強調する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As such, emphasis is placed on bodhisattva (compassion) amongst the so called Rokuharamitsu (six virtues of Buddha) where altruism is put into practice.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処。クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>悟りは固定した状態ではなく、悟りの行は、自利と利他の両面を願って行動し続けることであり、自らの悟りに安住することなく、悟りを求める人々に実践を指導するために活動し続けた釈迦の姿が想定されており、活動していくことに悟りの意味を求めているのが、大乗仏教の菩薩の特徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mahayana Sutra Bosatsu has the following characteristics: Enlightment is not a fixed state and enlightment practice means continuation of action, wishing both self-interst and altuism.Mahayana Sutra thinks of Shaka, who was not satisfied with staying in his enlightment but continues leading practices for those who sought enlightment. Mahayana Sutra is the meaning of enlightment in action.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mahayana Sutra Bosatsu has the following characteristics: enlightenment is not a fixed state and enlightenment practice means the continuation of action, wishing both self-interest and altruism; Mahayana Sutra thinks of Shaka, who was not satisfied with staying in his enlightenment but continued to lead practices for those who sought enlightenment; Mahayana Sutra is the meaning of enlightenment in action.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mahayana Sutra Bosatsu has the following characteristics: enlightenment is not a fixed state and enlightenment practice means the continuation of action, wishing both self-interest and altruism; Mahayana Sutra thinks of Shaka, who was not satisfied with staying in his enlightenment but continued to lead practices for those who sought enlightenment; Mahayana Sutra is the meaning of enlightenment in action.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>そして菩薩の悟りは声聞や縁覚と違い、究極最高のものであるとして「阿耨多羅三藐三菩提」「無上正等正覚」、あるいは単に正覚と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The enlightment of Bosatsu is defined as supreme and ultimate, different from Shoman or Enkaku. It is called &quot;Anokutara sanmyaku sanbodai &quot;, &quot;Mujo shoto shogaku&quot; or simply Shogaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The enlightenment of Bosatsu is defined as supreme and ultimate, being different from Shoman or Enkaku; it is called &quot;Anokutara sanmyaku sanbodai,&quot; &quot;Mujo shoto shogaku&quot; or simply &quot;Shogaku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The enlightenment of Bosatsu is defined as supreme and ultimate, being different from Shoman or Enkaku; it is called &quot;Anokutara sanmyaku sanbodai,&quot; &quot;Mujo shoto shogaku&quot; or simply &quot;Shogaku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="37">
<j>中国仏教</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chinese Buddhism</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chinese Buddhism</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chinese Buddhism</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>仏教の中国における大きな支流である禅には段階的な手順を得て起きる悟り（漸悟）を説く北方禅と、瞬時に起きる突然の悟り（頓悟）を説く南方禅に分かれた時期があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a time that Zen, a major stream of Buddhism in China was divided into Hoppozen (Northern Zen) and Nanpozen (Southern Zen). Hoppozen preaches gradual enlightment (zengo) while Nanpozen preaches sudden enlightment(tongo). Since Hoppozen died out earlier, a stream of Nanpozen came to Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a time when Zen, a major stream of Buddhism in China, was divided into Hoppozen (Northern Zen) and Nanpozen (Southern Zen), in which Hoppozen preached gradual enlightenment (zengo) while Nanpozen preached sudden enlightenment (tongo); however, since Hoppozen died out earlier, a stream of Nanpozen came to Japan.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In China where there is a big Zen Buddhism movement, Northern Chinese Zen advocates the obtaining of Satori through a process of graded steps and, this differs from Southern Chinese Zen&apos;s preaching of sudden and momentary enlightenment.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処。前出補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>だが、北方禅は先に廃れたため、日本に伝わったのは、突然の悟りを説く南方禅の流れを汲む宗派である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, because Northern Chinese Zen was abandoned earlier, the version handed-down to Japan comes from the sect that aligns itself with the practice of Southern Chinese Zen that advocated sudden enlightenment.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>しかし、日本に伝わったのは宋代で、禅が形骸化してきた時代でもあり、全盛期の唐代のものとは大きく違う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it came to Japan in the Sou period, when Zen had become a mere façade, it was largely different from that in the Tou period, when it was in full bloom.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it came to Japan during the Sou period, when Zen had become a mere façade; it was largely different from that of the Tou period, when it was in full bloom.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as the version that was handed down to Japan emanated from the Song Dynasty, for a time Zen lost much of its substance and differs greatly from its heyday during the Tang Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>例えば現代日本の臨済宗、曹洞宗は、それぞれ臨済、洞山の悟りに対する宗風をほとんど受け継いでいない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, either Rinzai sect or Soto sect hardly inheited its respective way toward enlightment of Rinzai or Soto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, neither the Rinzai sect or the Soto sect inherited very much of the respective paths toward enlightenment as espoused by Rinzai and Soto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, neither the Rinzai sect or the Soto sect inherited very much of the respective paths toward enlightenment as espoused by Rinzai and Soto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="42">
<j>もうひとつの中国仏教の大きな支流は浄土経であるが、この宗派は時代背景を反映している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another major stream of Chinese Buddhism is Jodo sect, which reflected the background of its era. It seeks death in the Pure Land of Amida Buddha and does not make enlightment an important goal..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another major stream of Chinese Buddhism is the Jodo sect, which has reflected the background of its era; it seeks death in the Pure Land of Amida Buddha but does not make enlightenment an important goal.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another major stream of Chinese Buddhism is the Jodo (Pure Land) sect however, this sect is a reflection of the influences of the times.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>阿弥陀仏の浄土に往生することを欣求し、悟りは大きな目標とはしない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dying a happy death is a keen aspiration of Amitabha Jodo Buddhism whereas, Satori is not a major aim.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処。前出補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>これは平安時代の日本に伝わり、貴族の間に極楽往生を求める信仰が広まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was transmitted into Japan in the Heian period, and the religion seeking for gokuraku ojo (peaceful death) spread among the aristocracy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was transmitted into Japan during the Heian period, and the religion seeking gokuraku ojo (peaceful death) spread among the aristocracy.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was transmitted into Japan during the Heian period, and the religion seeking gokuraku ojo (peaceful death) spread among the aristocracy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="45">
<j>一方、中国撰述とされる論書、『大乗起信論』では、阿頼耶識（あらやしき）に不覚と覚の二義があるとし、覚をさらに始覚（しかく）と本覚（ほんがく）とに分けて説明する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Daijokishinron (the Awakening of Faith in Mahayana),&quot; which is considered to have been made in China, describes that there are two kinds of rightousness, Fukakua(blunder) and Kaku(awakening). It is explained as follows: dividing Kaku into Shikaku(acquired awakening) and Hongaku(original awakening).</e>
<cmt>不覚、覚、始覚、本覚に「」が付く方が分かり易いと思います。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Daijokishinron (the Awakening of Faith in Mahayana),&quot; which is considered to have originated in China, states that there are two kinds of righteousness--Fukakua (blunder) and Kaku (awakening)--is explained by dividing Kaku into Shikaku (acquired awakening) and Hongaku (original awakening).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Daijokishinron (the Awakening of Faith in Mahayana),&quot; which is considered to have originated in China, states that there are two kinds of righteousness--Fukaku (blunder) and Kaku (awakening)--is explained by dividing Kaku into Shikaku (acquired awakening) and Hongaku (original awakening).</e>
<cmt>不覚（fukakua→fukaku）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>我々の心性（しんしょう）は、現実には無明（むみょう）に覆われ、妄念にとらわれているから不覚であるが、この無明が止滅して妄念を離れた状態が「覚」であるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In reality, our real nature is blunder(fukaku) because it is covered with avidya(,umyo) and trapped by illusions. When such blunder and illusion disappear, the state is &apos;Kaku(awakening).&apos;</e>
<cmt>無明、不覚、覚の対比と判断し、Fukaku, Mumyoも訳文に入れました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In reality, human nature is blunder (fukaku) because it is covered with avidya (umyo) and trapped by illusions; when blunder and illusion disappear, the state of &apos;Kaku (awakening)&apos; remains.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In reality, human nature is blunder (fukaku) because it is covered with avidya (mumyo) and trapped by illusions; when blunder and illusion disappear, the state of &apos;Kaku (awakening)&apos; remains.</e>
<cmt>umyo→mumyo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>ところで、無明は無始以来のものであるから、それに依拠する不覚に対しては「始覚」といわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also explained as follows:avidya started with no beginning and blunder completely relies on it. &apos;Shikaku(acquired enlightenment)&apos; is called so in contrast with fukaku. The source of our real nature is essentially clean awakening itself (&apos;hongaku&apos;) but it happens to be covered with avidya. Shikaku is not different from Hongaku but it helps us to be united with Hongaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also explained as follows: avidya started with no beginning, and blunder completely relies on it; &apos;Shikaku (acquired enlightenment)&apos; is called so in contrast with fukaku; the source of our real nature is essentially a clean awakening (&apos;hongaku&apos;), but it happens to be covered with avidya; Shikaku is not different from Hongaku, but it helps to unite us with Hongaku.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As an aside, the esoteric Buddhist concept of avidya (ignorance) comes after the beginning-less (Mushi) concept and as such, lack of dependence is called &apos;Shikaku&apos; (acquired enlightenment).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>しかし、われわれの心性の根源は本来清浄な覚りそのもの（「本覚」）であって、それがたまたま無明に覆われてい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, if one&apos;s nature is in principle primarily pure then &apos;Hongaku&apos; (fundamental enlightenment) may occur which in turn can by chance be concealed by avidya.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>そのため、始覚といってもそれは本覚と別のものではなく、始覚によって本覚に帰一するに過ぎない、と説明する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, it is explained that it is not going to far to say that Shikaku is no different to Hongaku and, depending on the manifestation of Shikaku may meld into Hongaku.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処。前出補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>つまり、誰にでも覚りに至る道は開けており、それに向かっての修行が必要なことを説いているのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Namely, it preaches that the way to awakening is open to anyone and that the practice to achieve it is necessary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Namely, it preaches that the way toward awakening is open to anyone but that the practice to achieve it is necessary.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Namely, it preaches that the way toward awakening is open to anyone but that the practice to achieve it is necessary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>さらに、覚りは清浄なものであることも説明されており、この論書の特長である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also explains that awakening is clean and pure, which is the characteristic of this book.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also explains that awakening is clean and pure, which is the characteristic of this book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also explains that awakening is clean and pure, which is the characteristic of this book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="52">
<j>ジャイナ教</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jainism</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jainism</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jainism</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>ヒンドゥー教（バラモン教）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hindooism (Brahmanism)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hinduism (Brahmanism)</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hinduism (Brahmanism)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="53">
<j>ヒンドゥー教は非常に雑多な宗教であるが、そこにはヴェーダの時代から続く悟りの探求の長い歴史がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hinddoism is a religion of variety of complex. It has a long history seeking for enlightment from the age of Veda.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hinduism is a varied and complex religion with a long history seeking enlightenment since the age of Veda.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hinduism is a varied and complex religion with a long history seeking enlightenment since the age of Veda.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="54">
<j>仏教に対峙するヴェーダの宗教系で使われる悟りは意識の状態で、人が到達することの出来る最高の状態のいくつかを言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrast to Buddhism, Veda-related religions refers to enlightment as the state of consciousness; some of the supreme state human-beings can attain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast to Buddhism, Veda-related religion refers to enlightenment as the state of consciousness, one of the supreme states that human beings can attain.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast to Buddhism, Veda-related religion refers to enlightenment as the state of consciousness, one of the supreme states that human beings can attain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>サンスクリットの涅槃（涅槃）に相当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It corresponds to Nehan in Sanskrit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It corresponds to Nehan in Sanskrit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It corresponds to Nehan in Sanskrit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>光明または大悟と呼ばれることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Komyo or Daigo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called Komyo or Daigo.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called Komyo or Daigo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>悟りを得る時に強烈な光に包まれる場合があることから、光明と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is called Komyo because a person may be wrapped in dazzling light when he/she attains enlightment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is called Komyo because a person may be wrapped in dazzling light when he or she attains enlightenment.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is called Komyo because a person may be wrapped in dazzling light when he or she attains enlightenment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="58">
<j>インドではヴェーダの時代から、「悟りを得るための科学」というものが求められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In India, since the age of Veda, &apos;the sciences to attain enlightment&apos; have been sought.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In India, since the age of Veda, &apos;the sciences by which to attain enlightenment&apos; have been sought.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In India, since the age of Veda, &apos;the sciences by which to attain enlightenment&apos; have been sought.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>それらは特に哲学的な表現でウパニシャッドなどに記述されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are described in Upanishad and so on in philosophical expressions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are described in Upanishad, etc., using philosophical expressions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are described in Upanishad, etc., using philosophical expressions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>古代の時代の悟りを得た存在は特にリシと呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The existence that attains enlightment of the ancient times is called Rishi.</e>
<cmt>リシの英訳語は見つけられませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The existence that attains the enlightenment of ancient times is called Rishi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The existence that attains the enlightenment of ancient times is called Rishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="61">
<j>ニルヴァーナには3つの段階が存在するといわれ、マハパリ・ニルヴァーナが最高のものとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that there are three stages in Nirvana, among which Mahapari-Nirvana is considered the highest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that there are three stages in Nirvana, among which Mahapari-Nirvana is considered the highest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that there are three stages in Nirvana, among which Mahapari-Nirvana is considered the highest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>悟りと呼ぶ場合はこのどれも指すようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enlightment seems to refer to every stage of them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enlightenment seems to refer to each respective stage.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enlightenment seems to refer to each respective stage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>どの段階のニルヴァーナに到達しても、その意識状態は失われることはないとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the state of mind is not lost no matter which stage one reaches.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the state of mind is not lost, no matter which stage one reaches.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the state of mind is not lost, no matter which stage one reaches.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>また、マハパリ・ニルヴァーナは肉体を持ったまま得るのは難しいとされ、悟りを得た存在が肉体を離れる場合にマハパリ・ニルヴァーナに入ると言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that Mahapari-Nirvana is hard to attain with one&apos;s body and that one can enter Mahapari-Nirvana when one attains enlightenment and leaves his/her body.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that Mahapari-Nirvana is hard to attain with one&apos;s body and that one can enter Mahapari-Nirvana when one attains enlightenment and leaves his or her body.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that Mahapari-Nirvana is hard to attain with one&apos;s body and that one can enter Mahapari-Nirvana when one attains enlightenment and leaves his or her body.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="65">
<j>悟りを得た存在が肉体を離れるときには、「死んだ」とは言われず、「肉体を離れる」、「入滅する」、「涅槃に入る」なとど言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the existence that has attained enlightment leaves its body, it is not referred as &quot;dead.&quot; Instead, the words such as &quot;leaving its body,&quot;&quot;entering nirvana,&quot; or &quot;entering Nehan&quot; are used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the existence that has attained enlightenment leaves its body, it is not considered dead; instead, phrases such as &quot;leaving its body,&quot;&quot;entering nirvana&quot; or &quot;entering Nehan&quot; are used.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the spirit of a person that has attained enlightenment leaves the body, it is not described as being dead; instead, it is described as having, for example, &quot;left the body,&quot; &quot;entered nirvana&quot; or &quot;entered Nehan&quot;.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しました。クォーテーションの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="66">
<j>悟りという場合、ニルヴァーナの世界をかいま見る神秘体験を指す場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sometimes enlightment refers to a mysterious experience of having a glimpse of the world of Nirvana.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sometimes enlightment refers to a mysterious experience of having a glimpse of the world of Nirvana.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sometimes enlightment refers to a mysterious experience of having a glimpse of the world of Nirvana.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>この場合はニルヴァーナには含まれないとされ、偽のニルヴァーナと呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This case is not included in Nirvana but called the pseudo Nirvana.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This case is not included in Nirvana but is called pseudo Nirvana.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This case is not included in Nirvana but is called pseudo Nirvana.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>偽のニルヴァーナであっても、人生が変わる体験となるので、偽のニルヴァーナを含めて、ニルヴァーナには4つあるとする場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some say there are four kinds of Nirvana, including the pseudo Nirvana because even if it is the pseudo Nirvana, it also gives an experience to change one&apos;s life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some say there are four kinds of Nirvana (including pseudo Nirvana), because even if it is a pseudo Nirvana it also provides the experience of changing one&apos;s life.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some say there are four kinds of Nirvana (including pseudo Nirvana), because even if it is a pseudo Nirvana it also provides the experience of changing one&apos;s life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="69">
<j>現在でも、ゴータマ・ブッダの時代と同じように山野で修行を行う行者が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even nowadays, many practitioners conduct ascetic training over hill and dale just like the age of Buddha Gautama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even today, many practitioners conduct ascetic training over hill and dale, just as occurred in the age of Buddha Gautama.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even today, many practitioners conduct ascetic training over hill and dale, just as occurred in the age of Buddha Gautama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>どんな時代にでも多くの場所に沢山の数の悟りを得た（と自称している）存在に事欠かない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anywhere and at any time, there are some people who think that they have attained a lot of enlightment and call themselves enlightened..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anywhere and at any time, there will be people who believe they have attained considerable enlightenment and will therefore call refer to themselves as enlightened.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anywhere and at any time, there will be people who believe they have attained considerable enlightenment and will therefore call refer to themselves as enlightened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="71">
<j>通常、悟りを得たとする存在もヒンドゥー教、またはその全段階のバラモン教の伝統の内にとどまっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those who thought to have attained enlightment usually stayed in the tradition of Hinduism, or Brahmanism, its previous stage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those believed to have attained enlightenment usually stayed in the tradition of Hinduism, or Brahmanism, its previous stage.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those believed to have attained enlightenment usually stayed in the tradition of Hinduism, or Brahmanism, its previous stage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>しかし、特にゴータマ・ブッダの時代はバラモン教が司祭の血統であるブラフミン（バラモン）を特別な存在と主張した時で、それに反対してバラモン教の範囲から飛び出している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, especially in the age of Buddha Gautamma, Brahmanism proclaimed that Brahman(Brahman), a bloodline of their priest was the special existence. Those who thought to have attained enlightment were against the idea and went out of Brahmanism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, particularly in the age of Buddha Gautamma, Brahmanism proclaimed that Brahman (Brahman), a bloodline of their priest, was the special existence; those who were thought to have attained enlightenment were against the idea and left Brahmanism.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, particularly in the age of Buddha Gautama, Brahmanism proclaimed that Brahmin (Brahman), a bloodline of their priest, was the special existence; those who were thought to have attained enlightenment were against the idea and left Brahmanism.</e>
<cmt>Gautamma→Gautama「ブラフミン」は「Brahmin」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>同時代にはジャイナ教のマハヴィーラも悟りを得た存在としており、やはり階級制であるカーストに反対してこれを認めず、バラモン教から独立している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, Mahavira of Jainism thought to have attained enlightment and became independent of Brahmanism. He was opposed to the caste system, a hierarchy, and did not accept it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, Mahavira of Jainism was thought to have attained enlightenment and became independent of Brahmanism he was opposed to the caste system, a hierarchy, and shunned it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, Mahavira of Jainism was thought to have attained enlightenment and became independent of Brahmanism he was opposed to the caste system, a hierarchy, and shunned it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="74">
<j>キリスト教</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Christianity</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Christianity</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Christianity</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>キリスト教用語には“悟り”はないが、神を知る体験があるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Christianity does not include &quot;enlightment&quot; but an experience to know the existence of the God.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Christianity does not include &quot;enlightenment&quot; but the experience of knowing the existence of God.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Christianity does not include &quot;enlightenment&quot; but the experience of knowing the existence of God.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>これは初めの人アダムとイブの時代に神から離れた人類にもう一度神との交わりに入るときの霊的体験と説明される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is explained as a spritual experience to reenter the interaction with the God although human beings left Him at the age of Adam and Eve.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is explained as a spiritual experience to re-enter interaction with God, although humanity left Him when Adam and Eve, their forebears, ate the forbidden fruit.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is explained as a spiritual experience to re-enter interaction with God, although humanity left Him when Adam and Eve, their forebears, ate the forbidden fruit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>ここで言う霊とは死後の霊といった意味ではなく、三位一体の神の位格の一つ聖霊との交流を意味する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The spirit mentioned here does not mean spirits of the dead but it means the interaction with the Spirit, one of the Trinity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The spirit mentioned here does not mean spirits of the dead but instead means the interaction with the Spirit, one of the Holy Trinity.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The spirit mentioned here does not mean spirits of the dead but instead means the interaction with the Spirit, one of the Holy Trinity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>ナザレのイエスが天から地に現れた神の子、キリストであると信じるに至る際の体験である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the experience which is attained when one believes that Jesus of Nazareth is Christ, the Son of the God, who came to the Earth from the Heaven.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the experience that is attained when one believes that Jesus of Nazareth is Christ, the Son of the God, who came to earth from Heaven.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the experience that is attained when one believes that Jesus of Nazareth is Christ, the Son of the God, who came to earth from Heaven.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>聖書に記録される、イエスや初期クリスチャンらに倣って、神を体験することである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It means to experience the God following Jesus who is recorded in the Bible or by Christians at the early period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It means to experience God by following Jesus, whose life is recorded in the Bible and by early Christians.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It means to experience God by following Jesus, whose life is recorded in the Bible and early Christians.</e>
<cmt>2度目のｂｙを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>これにより神とイエスを真理と認識する為、ある意味では「悟り」と呼べるかもしれないが、仏教の悟りとは無関係である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The experience means to recognize the God and Jesus as truth and might be interpreted as &quot;enlightment&quot; in a sense. However, it has nothing to do with &quot;enlightment&quot; in Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The experience means to recognize God and Jesus as truth, and consequently it might be interpreted as &quot;enlightenment&quot; in a sense; however, it has nothing to do with the &quot;enlightenment&quot; of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It may be said that become aware of or know the truth of God or Jesus means in some sense to have reached Satori however, this bears no relation to the Buddhist concept of Satori.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しました。前出補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="81">
<j>カトリック教会の聖人と呼ばれる人々の中には悟りに近い領域にいると思われる人がおり、僧侶がする修行の中には瞑想も含まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those who are called Saints in Catholic are considered to be very close to &quot;enlightment.&quot; Ascetic trainings practiced by priets include meditation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those who are called saints in Catholicism are considered to be very close to &quot;enlightenment&quot;; the ascetic training practiced by priests includes meditation.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those who are called saints in Catholicism are considered to be very close to &quot;enlightenment&quot;; the ascetic training practiced by priests includes meditation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>また、伝統的なプロテスタント派では覚りは説かれないが、プロテスタント系統の体験派とも言われるペンテコステ・カリスマ派とその類で、上記の体験があるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Traditional Protestant denominations do not preach enlightment. However, Pentecostal and Charismatic Christians and others like it, which is a stream of Protestant and called the Experientist, have had such experiences as mentioned above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Traditional Protestant denominations do not preach enlightenment; however, Pentecostal Christians, Charismatic Christians and other forms of Protestantism, such as one called Experientism, have had such experiences as mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Traditional Protestant denominations do not preach enlightenment; however, Pentecostal Christians, Charismatic Christians and other forms of Protestantism, such as one called Experientism, have had such experiences as mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>ギリシャ哲学等と融合し、異端とされたグノーシス派では、真に神を知ることを覚り（グノーシス）と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gnosticism, which was blended with Greek philosophy and so on and was labelled as heretical, refers to the true recognition of the god as attaining direct acquaintance of the God (Gnosis).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gnosticism, which was blended with Greek philosophy and so on and was once labeled as heretical, refers to the true recognition of God as attaining the direct acquaintance of God (Gnosis).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gnosticism, which was blended with Greek philosophy and so on and was once labeled as heretical, refers to the true recognition of God as attaining the direct acquaintance of God (Gnosis).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="84">
<j>また、近年「自己喪失の体験」を書いたバーナデット・ロバーツはごく普通の主婦でありキリスト教を信じるものとしての体験をまとめている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bernadette Roberts, who wrote &quot;The Experience of No-Self, A Contemplative Journey&quot;recently, is an ordinary housewife. She wrote about her experience, describing Christianity as an object to believe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bernadette Roberts, author of the recent work &quot;The Experience of No-Self, A Contemplative Journey,&quot; is an ordinary housewife who has written about her experience, describing Christianity as an object of belief.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bernadette Roberts, author of the recent work &quot;The Experience of No-Self, A Contemplative Journey,&quot; is an ordinary housewife who has written about her experience, describing Christianity as an object of belief.</e>
<cmt>スペース</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>これは悟りのプロセスとして知られているものに非常に近いか同一である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is very close to or the same as what is known as the process of enlightment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is very close to or the same as what is known as the process of enlightment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is very close to or the same as what is known as the process of enlightment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>一般的な言葉で非常に客観的に自分に起きたプロセスをまとめている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She writes about the process which happened to her very objectively in general speech.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She writes very objectively, in general terms, about the process that occurred to her.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She writes very objectively, in general terms, about the process that occurred to her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>ヴェーダの単語を使っていないのでなじみのない者に理解がしやすい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Veda terms are not used, so it is easy to comprehend to lay people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Terms from Veda are not used, so it&apos;s easy for lay people to comprehend.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Terms from Veda are not used, so it&apos;s easy for lay people to comprehend.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="88">
<j>ヴェーダの宗教の系統では、ナザレのイエスを悟りを得た存在として尊重する場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some streams of Veda, Jesus of Nazareth is respected as the existence who has attained enlightment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some streams of Veda, Jesus of Nazareth is respected as the existence who has attained enlightment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some streams of Veda, Jesus of Nazareth is respected as the existence who has attained enlightment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>キリスト教会ではイエス・キリストを神と人をつなぐ仲介者、また三位一体の神の位格の一つ、神の子（子なる神）であり中心的な存在として崇拝している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Christian churches worship Jesus Christ as the mediator between the God and human beings. They also look up to him as one of the Trinity, the Son of God (God the Son) or the central existence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Christian churches worship Jesus Christ as the mediator between humanity and God, but they also look up to him as one of the Trinity as the Son of God (God the Son) or the central existence.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Christian churches worship Jesus Christ as the mediator between humanity and God, but they also look up to him as one of the Trinity as the Son of God (God the Son) or the central existence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="90">
<j>ニューエイジ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">New Age</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">New Age</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">New Age</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>近年の欧米で、キリスト教徒として留まったままでキリスト教の枠組みから外れて宗教的探求をする運動があり、ニューエイジと呼ばれているが、それらの人々によって悟りの概念が取り入れられ、イエス・キリストをある種の悟りを得た存在としてとらえる場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently in the West, there is a movement in which participants remain Christians and at the same time seek Universal Truth out of the framework of Christianity. The movement is called New Age, and the participants accept the concept of enlightment and sometimes regard Jesus Christ as the existence who attained a sort of enlightment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The West has a contemporary movement in which participants remain Christians but at the same time seek Universal Truth outside the framework of Christianity; the movement is called New Age, and the participants accept the concept of enlightenment and sometimes regard Jesus Christ as the existence who attained a sort of enlightenment.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The West has a contemporary movement in which participants remain Christians but at the same time seek Universal Truth outside the framework of Christianity; the movement is called New Age, and the participants accept the concept of enlightenment and sometimes regard Jesus Christ as the existence who attained a sort of enlightenment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="92">
<j>イスラム教</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Islam</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Islam</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Islam</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>一般のイスラム教には悟りの伝統は含まれていないが、特にイスラム教神秘主義とも呼ばれるスーフィーは、内なる神との合一を目的としており、そのプロセスは悟りのプロセスのいずれかに近い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In general, Islam does not include the tradition of enlightment. Sufi, which is also called Sufism, aims to become one with God and the process is close to either process of enlightment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, Islam does not include the tradition of enlightenment; however, Sufi, which is also called Sufism, aims to become one with God, and the process is close to either process of enlightenment.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, Islam does not include the tradition of enlightenment; however, Sufi, which is also called Sufism, aims to become one with God, and the process is close to either process of enlightenment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>しかし、神との合一を成し遂げたスーフィの中には「我は神なり」と宣言して一般のイスラム教徒に処刑される場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, some Sufis who have accomplished their aim declare &apos;I am God&apos; and were executed by general Islamists.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, some Sufis who accomplished their aim declared, &apos;I am God&apos; and were executed by general Islamists.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, some Sufis who accomplished their aim declared, &apos;I am God&apos; and were executed by general Islamists.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="95">
<j>悟りと似た意味の言葉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Words with similar meaning to enlightment</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Words with meanings similar enlightenment</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Words with meanings similar enlightenment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>モクシャ （解脱）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moksha (Emanicipation)</e>
<cmt>Emanicipationは&quot;The Three Pure Land Sutras&quot;から引用しました。（Hongwanji International Center)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moksha (Emancipation)</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moksha (Emancipation)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>- モクシャには自由の意味があり、最終的な自由を得ることをさす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moksha means liberty and to achieve ultimate liberty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moksha means liberty and to achieve ultimate liberty.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moksha means liberty and to achieve ultimate liberty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>また、天国と地獄を超越した場所として、モクシャを指す場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It sometimes means a place beyond paradise and hell.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It sometimes means a place beyond Paradise and Hell.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It sometimes means a place beyond Paradise and Hell.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>モクシャは、天国に入るという事ではなく、天国と地獄を超越した場所にはいることを示す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moksha does not mean to enter paradise but to enter the place beyond paradise and hell.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moksha does not mean to enter Paradise but to enter the place beyond Paradise and Hell.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moksha does not mean to enter Paradise but to enter the place beyond Paradise and Hell.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="100">
<j>光明を得たとされる人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those who are considered to have attained light</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those who are considered to have attained light</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those who are considered to have attained light</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>古代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ancient times</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ancient times</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ancient times</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>マハヴィーラ （ジャイナ教開祖）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mahavira (the originator of Jainism)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mahavira (the originator of Jainism)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mahavira (the originator of Jainism)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>近代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recent period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recent period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recent period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>ラーマクリシュナ （神秘思想家）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ramakrishna(person of supernatural idea)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ramakrishna (person of a supernatural idea)</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ramakrishna (person of a supernatural idea)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>現代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nowadays</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>ジッドゥ・クリシュナムルティ （瞑想的思想家）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jiddu Krishnamurti(person of meditation)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jiddu Krishnamurti (person of meditation)</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jiddu Krishnamurti (person of meditation)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 JAnDbot(id:66507), Star of Sea(id:63593), Nnh(id:474), Mait(id:73947), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Cprobot(id:97843), Gauss(id:8879), Toto-tarou(id:16648), 麓(id:77268), るがこむ(id:181), Tetralemma(id:11903), マイコン坊主(id:338), Oddmake(id:29591), Yas(id:739), Choya-nyc(id:51851), FlaBot(id:30804), Stay cool(id:1253), Koyama tetsuo(id:103005), Mizusumashi(id:360), Izayohi(id:13095), Armjoe(id:104999), ArthurBot(id:265089), 与左衛門(id:159462), MizusumashiBot(id:180225), Authority(id:10737), Setu(id:88), Inukawa(id:842), Yrogetac(id:87379), Kiyok(id:76023), Boca samba(id:137526), Sionnach(id:21673), Saaki(id:43602), サトルくん(id:113933), Broad-Sky(id:68334), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>