<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>塑像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Earthen image</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Earthen image</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Earthen image</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>塑像（そぞう）は、粘土を素材とした像。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term of earthen image means images of which material is clay.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term earthen image means images of which the material is clay.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term earthen image means images of which the material is clay.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>テラコッタと異なり、焼成を行わない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike terra cotta, a firing process is not involved in producing them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike terra cotta, a firing process is not involved in producing them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike terra cotta, a firing process is not involved in producing them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>日本には奈良時代前期に唐から伝来し、奈良時代後期に盛行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Earthen image was introduced from Tang into Japan in the early Nara period and many images were produced in the late Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Earthen images were introduced from Tang into Japan in the early Nara period and many images were produced in the late Nara period.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Earthen images were introduced from Tang into Japan in the early Nara period and many images were produced in the late Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>心木に藁縄などを巻きつけ、粒子の荒い荒土から、細かい仕上げ土へと順次盛り上げ、箆（へら）や指で造型する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their producing process is winding straw ropes around wooden mandrel, heaping up coarse-grained barren soil followed by fine-particle finishing soil and molding by a pallet or fingers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The producing process employed winding straw ropes around wooden mandrel, heaping up coarse-grained barren soil followed by fine-particle finishing soil and molding by a pallet or the fingers.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The producing process employed winding straw ropes around wooden mandrel, heaping up coarse-grained barren soil followed by fine-particle finishing soil and molding by a pallet or the fingers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>日本に現存する主な塑像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Existent principal earthen images in Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Existent principal earthen images in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Existent Principal Earthen Images in Japan</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>奈良県当麻寺金堂本尊の弥勒仏坐像は7世紀後半にさかのぼる作で、日本最古の塑像と言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sedentary statue of Miroku Buddha, which is the principal image of Buddha of Nara Taima-dera Temple Kondo (main hall), was produced in the late 7th century and is believed to be the oldest earthen image in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sedentary statue of Miroku Buddha, which is the principal image of Buddha at Nara Taima-dera Temple Kondo (main hall), was produced in the late 7th century and is believed to be the oldest earthen image in Japan.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The seated statue of Miroku Buddha, which is the principal image of Buddha at Kondo (main hall) of Taima-dera Temple in Nara, was produced in the late 7th century and is believed to be the oldest earthen image in Japan.</e>
<cmt>seated statueとし表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>日本では、塑像の作例は奈良時代に集中しており、木彫が彫刻界の主流となった平安時代以降（おおむね9世紀以降）の塑像の作例はまれである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of earthen images were produced in Nara period and few were produced in Heian period or later when wood carving became the mainstream in sculpture society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of the earthen images were produced in the Nara period and few were produced in Heian period or later when wood carvings became the mainstream in sculpture society.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of the earthen images were produced in the Nara period and few were produced in Heian period or later (mainly after 9th century) when wood carvings became the mainstream in sculpture society.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>以下に国宝指定物件を中心に著名な作例を挙げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Well-known products, especially those designated as national treasures, are as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Well-known products, especially those designated as national treasures, are as follows.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Well-known products, especially those designated as national treasures, are as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>奈良時代前期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Early Nara period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Early Nara period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Early Nara Period</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>当麻寺金堂（奈良県）弥勒仏坐像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sedentary statue of Miroku Buddha at Taima-dera Temple Kondo (Nara Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sedentary statue of Miroku Buddha at Taima-dera Temple Kondo (Nara Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The seated statue of Miroku Buddha (Maitreya) at Kondo of Taima-dera Temple (Nara Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>seatedを使用し、順序を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>奈良時代後期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Late Nara period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Late Nara period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Late Nara Period</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>龍蓋寺（奈良県）如意輪観音坐像 - 像高4.6ｍの日本最大の塑像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sedentary statue of of Nyoirin Kannon enshrined at Ryugai-ji Temple (Nara Prefecture) - its hight is 4.6m and it is the tallest earthen image in Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sedentary statue of of Nyoirin Kannon enshrined at Ryugai-ji Temple (Nara Prefecture) - its height is 4.6m and it is the tallest earthen image in Japan</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The seated statue of Nyoirin Kannon (the Bodhisattva of Compassion) enshrined at Ryugai-ji Temple (Nara Prefecture) - its height is 4.6 m and it is the tallest earthen image in Japan</e>
<cmt>seatedを使用し、補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>法隆寺（奈良県）五重塔初層安置塑像群</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A group of earthen images enshrined at the first store of Gojuno-to (five-storied pagoda) of Horyu-ji Temple (Nara Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A group of earthen images enshrined in the first store of Gojuno-to (five-storied pagoda) of Horyu-ji Temple (Nara Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A group of earthen images enshrined in the first layer of Gojuno-to (five-storey pagoda) of Horyu-ji Temple (Nara Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>法隆寺中門　金剛力士立像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The standing statue of Kongo Rikishi enshrined at Nakamon (inner gate) of Horyu-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The standing statue of Kongo Rikishi enshrined at Nakamon (inner gate) of Horyu-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The standing statue of Kongo Rikishi (the guardian gods at a temple gate) enshrined at Chumon (inner gate) of Horyu-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>法隆寺食堂（じきどう）旧安置　四天王立像、梵天・帝釈天立像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The standing statue of Shitenno and the standing statue of Bonten・Taishakuten that were once enshrined at Jikido (dinning hall) of Horyu-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The standing statue of Shitenno and the standing statue of Bonten・Taishakuten that were once enshrined at Jikido (dining hall) of Horyu-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The standing statue of Shitenno (the Four Devas) and the standing statue of Bonten (Brahma-Deva) and Taishakuten (Sakra devanam Indra) that were once enshrined at Jikido (dining hall) of Horyu-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>新薬師寺（奈良市）十二神将立像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The standing statue of Junishinsho enshrined at Shinyakushi-ji Temple (Nara Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The standing statue of Junishinsho enshrined at Shinyakushi-ji Temple (Nara Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The standing statue of Junishinsho (the twelve protective deities) enshrined at Shinyakushi-ji Temple (Nara Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="14">
<j>東大寺法華堂（三月堂）（奈良市）執金剛神立像、日光菩薩像・月光菩薩立像、弁才天・吉祥天立像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The standing statue of Shukongoshin, the standing statue of Nikko Bosatsu・Gakko Bosatsu and the standing statue of Benzaiten・Kisshoten that are enshrined at Hokkedo (Sangatsudo) of Todaiji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The standing statue of Shukongoshin, the standing statue of Nikko Bosatsu・Gakko Bosatsu and the standing statue of Benzaiten・Kisshoten that are enshrined at Hokkedo (Sangatsudo) of Todaiji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The standing statue of Shukongoshin (vajra-wielding gods), the standing statue of Nikko Bosatsu (Nikko Bosatsu (Bodhisattva of Sunlight)) and Gakko Bosatsu (Gakko Bosatsu (Bodhisattva of Moonlight)) and the standing statue of Benzaiten (Sarasvati, Buddhist goddess of music, learning, eloquence, wealth, longevity, and protection from natural disasters) and Kisshoten (Laksmi) that are enshrined at Hokkedo (Sangatsudo) of Todai-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="15">
<j>東大寺戒壇院 四天王立像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The standing statue of Shitenno enshrined at kaidanin of Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The standing statue of Shitenno enshrined at kaidanin of Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The standing statue of Shitenno enshrined at Kaidanin of Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="16">
<j>天福寺 (宇佐市)（宇佐市）三尊像残欠</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The statue of Three Buddah (imperfect) enshrined at Tenpuku-ji Temple (Usa City) (Usa City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The statue of Three Budda (imperfect) enshrined at Tenpuku-ji Temple (Usa City) (Usa City)</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The incomplete remains of the statue of Three Buddha enshrined at Tenpuku-ji Temple (Usa City)</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>平安時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heian Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heian Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heian Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>法隆寺夢殿　道詮律師坐像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sedentary statue of Dosen-Risshi enshrined at Yumedono of Horyu-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sedentary statue of Dosen-Risshi enshrined at Yumedono of Horyu-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The seated statue of Dosen-Risshi (Buddhist priest) enshrined at Yumedono of Horyu-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>seatedを使用し補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>広隆寺（京都市）弥勒仏坐像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sedentary statue of Miroku Buddha enshrined at Koryu-ji Temple (Kyoto City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sedentary statue of Miroku Buddha enshrined at Koryu-ji Temple (Kyoto City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The seated statue of Miroku Buddha enshrined at Koryu-ji Temple (Kyoto City)</e>
<cmt>seatedを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>出土した主な塑像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Principal earthen statues that were excavated</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Principal earthen statues that were excavated</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Principal Earthen Statues that were Excavated</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>斎尾廃寺跡（琴浦町）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The site of abolished Saino-ji Temple (Kotoura City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The site of the abolished Saino-ji Temple (Kotoura City)</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The site of the abolished Saino-ji Temple (Kotoura-cho Town)</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>上淀廃寺跡（米子市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The site of abolished Kamiyodo-ji Temple (Yonago City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The site of the abolished Kamiyodo-ji Temple (Yonago City)</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The site of the abolished Kamiyodo-ji Temple (Yonago City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="21">
<j>山王廃寺跡（前橋市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The site of abolished Sanno-ji Temple (Maebashi City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The site of the abolished Sanno-ji Temple (Maebashi City)</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The site of the abolished Sanno-ji Temple (Maebashi City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 663highland(id:18755), BoB774(id:148281), Ha～Ha(id:36403), 与左衛門(id:159462), Kstigarbha(id:13376), R28Bot(id:177951), Urania(id:7213), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>