<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>禅文化研究所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Institute for Zen Studies</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Institute for Zen Studies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Institute for Zen Studies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>禅文化研究所（ぜんぶんかけんきゅうじょ、英字The Institute for Zen Studies）は、臨済宗と黄檗宗が共同で設立した禅とその文化に関する研究所（財団法人）であり、花園大学内にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Institute for Zen Studies is the research institute (a corporation) about Zen and Zen-related culture established jointly by the Rinzai sect and the Obaku Sect, and is located in the premises of Hanazono University.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Institute for Zen Studies is a research institute (a corporation) about Zen and Zen-related culture established jointly by the Rinzai and Obaku Sects, and is located on the premises of Hanazono University.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Institute for Zen Studies is a research institute (a corporation) about Zen and Zen-related culture established jointly by the Rinzaishu and Obakushu sects, and is located on the premises of Hanazono University.</e>
<cmt>宗名表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>研究所では季刊『禅文化』や『禅文化研究所紀要』発行しているほか、『祖堂集』などの油印本の刊行、『白隠禅師法語全集』『祖堂集索引』等各種研究書を刊行し、禅文化の普及に努める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to the quarterly issuance of &quot;Zen Bunka&quot; (Zen culture) and that of &quot;Zen Bunka Kenkyujo Kiyo&quot; (Journal of The Institute for Zen Studies), the research institute has made efforts to promote Zen culture through the publication of mimeograph-based books, such as &quot;Sodoshu,&quot; and through that of various books for research, such as &quot;Hakuin Zenji Hogo Zenshu&quot; (Complete Collection of Buddhist Sermons by Hakuin Zenji) and &quot;Sodoshu Sakuin&quot; (Index to Sodoshu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to the quarterly issuing of &quot;Zen Bunka&quot; (Zen culture) and that of &quot;Zen Bunka Kenkyujo Kiyo&quot; (Journal of The Institute for Zen Studies), the research institute has made efforts to promote Zen culture through the publication of mimeograph-based books, such as &quot;Sodoshu,&quot; and also through various books concerning research such as &quot;Hakuin Zenji Hogo Zenshu&quot; (Complete Collection of Buddhist Sermons by Hakuin Zenji) and &quot;Sodoshu Sakuin&quot; (Index to Sodoshu).</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to the quarterly issuing of &quot;Zen Bunka&quot; (Zen culture) and that of &quot;Zen Bunka Kenkyujo Kiyo&quot; (Journal of The Institute for Zen Studies), the research institute has made efforts to promote Zen culture through the publication of mimeograph-based books, such as &quot;Sodoshu,&quot; and also through various books concerning research such as &quot;Hakuin Zenji Hogo Zenshu&quot; (Complete Collection of Buddhist Sermons by Hakuin Zenji) and &quot;Sodoshu Sakuin&quot; (Index to Sodoshu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>また、書籍のほかに寺務管理ソフトや研修講師派遣など、寺院の発展にも関わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, in addition to publishing books, the institute is also engaged in promoting the prosperity of temples through the development of temple job management software and the sending of lecturers for training courses concerned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, in addition to publishing books, the institute is also engaged in promoting the prosperity of temples through the development of temple job management software and the sending of lecturers on training courses.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, in addition to publishing books, the institute is also engaged in promoting the prosperity of temples through the development of temple job management software and the sending of lecturers on training courses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>かつて入矢義高が所属していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitaka IRIYA once belonged to the institute.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitaka IRIYA once belonged to the institute.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitaka IRIYA once belonged to the institute.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>歴代の所長も山田無文師や平田精耕師など著名な禅者が務めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Famous Zen priests, such as priest Mumon YAMADA and priest Seiko HIRATA, assumed successive heads of the institute.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Famous Zen priests, such as the priests Mumon YAMADA and Seiko HIRATA, became heads of the institute.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation..</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Famous Zen priests, such as the priests Mumon YAMADA and Seiko HIRATA, became heads of the institute.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Pseudoscience(id:223756), Mooko(id:36162), Fromm(id:71291), Kstigarbha(id:13376), 果心居士(id:248111), R28Bot(id:177951), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>