<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>鉄眼道光</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Doko TETSUGEN</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Doko TETSUGEN</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Doko TETSUGEN</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>鉄眼道光（てつげん どうこう、寛永7年1月1日 (旧暦)（1630年2月12日） - 天和 (日本)2年3月20日 (旧暦)（1682年4月27日））は、江戸時代前期の黄檗宗の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Doko TETSUGEN (February 12, 1630 - April 27, 1682) was a Zen priest of Obaku school who was active in the Early Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Doko TETSUGEN (February 12, 1630 - April 27, 1682) was a Zen priest of the Obaku school who was active in the early Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Doko TETSUGEN (February 12, 1630 - April 27, 1682) was a Zen priest of the Obaku School in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>諡号は宝蔵国師。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Shigo (posthumous name) was Hozo Kokushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Shigo (posthumous name) was Hozo Kokushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His shigo (a posthumous name) was Hozo Kokushi.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>肥後国益城郡守山村の生まれ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Higo-no-Kuni Masuki-gun Moriyama-mura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Higo-no-Kuni Masuki-gun Moriyama-mura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Moriyama-mura, Masuki-gun, Higo Province.</e>
<cmt>順序を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>最初、徹玄と号していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Initially, he named himself Tetsugen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially, he named himself Tetsugen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially, he called himself Tetsugen.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>佐伯浄信という守山八幡宮の社僧を父として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as a son of Joshin SAEKI, who was a Buddhist priest attached to Moriyama Hachiman-gu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born as a son of Joshin SAEKI, who was a Buddhist priest attached to Moriyama Hachiman-gu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born as a son of Joshin SAEKI, who was a Buddhist priest attached to Moriyama Hachiman-gu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>当初は、父の影響で浄土真宗を学んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Initially, he studied Jodo-Shinshu Buddhism with the influence of his father.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially, he studied Jodo-Shinshu Buddhism due to the influence of his father.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially, he studied Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) due to the influence of his father.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>出家（13歳時）の師は、浄土真宗の海雲である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he entered the priesthood (at the age of 13 year old), his then mentor was Kaiun, a priest of Jodo-Shinshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he entered the priesthood (at the age of 13 years old), his then-mentor was Kaiun, a priest of Jodo-Shinshu.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he entered the priesthood (at the age of 13 years old), his then-mentor was Kaiun, a priest of Jodo Shinshu.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>が、本願寺宗徒では才徳がなくとも寺格の高下によって上座にあることを潔しとせず、1655年（明暦元年）隠元隆きに参禅して禅に帰依し、隠元の弟子木庵性トウの法を嗣いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as he was ashamed of becoming a high-ranking priest among Hongan-ji Temple priests thanks to the high status of his temple irrespective of his talent and virtue, he converted to Zen Sect in 1655 with practicing Zen meditation under Ryuki INGEN and succeeded the teachings of Shoto MOKUAN, a disciple of INGEN.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as he was ashamed of becoming a high-ranking priest among Hongan-ji Temple priests, thanks to the high status of his temple, irrespective of his talent and virtue, he converted to Zen Sect in 1655 while practicing Zen meditation under Ryuki INGEN and succeeded the teachings of Shoto MOKUAN, a disciple of INGEN.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as he was ashamed of becoming a high-ranking priest among Hongan-ji Temple priests, thanks to the high status of his temple, irrespective of his talent and virtue, he converted to Zen Sect in 1655 while practicing Zen meditation under Ryuki INGEN and succeeded the teachings of Shoto MOKUAN, a disciple of INGEN.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>後、摂津国難波村に瑞龍寺 (大阪市)を開建した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, he founded Zuiryu-ji Temple (Osaka City) in Settsu-no-Kuni Nanba-mura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, he founded Zuiryu-ji Temple (Osaka City) in Settsu-no-Kuni Nanba-mura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, he founded Zuiryu-ji Temple (Osaka City) in Nanba-mura, Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt>順序を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>畿内の飢えに苦しむ住民の救済にも尽力し、1度は集まった蔵経開版のための施財を、惜しげもなく飢民に給付し尽くした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He endeavored to help residents of Kinai (the region in the vicinity of the capital) who were tormented by starvation and doled out, without stinting, the alms that were donated for the publication of Daizokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He endeavored to help residents of Kinai (the region in the vicinity of the capital) who were tormented by starvation and dstributed, without stinting, the alms that were donated for the publication of Daizokyo.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He endeavored to help residents of Kinai (the region in the vicinity of the capital) who were tormented by starvation and distributed, without stinting, the alms that were donated for the publication of Daizokyo (the Tripitaka).</e>
<cmt>スペル修正、補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかも、そのようなことが、2度に及んだという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that he did such action twice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that he took such action twice.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that he took such action twice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>『鉄眼禅師仮名法話』は女性に向けて法を説いたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tetsugen Zenshi Kana Howa&quot; is a book written for the purpose of preaching the teachings to female.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Tetsugen Zenshi Kana Howa&quot; is a book written for the purpose of preaching the teachings to females.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Tetsugen Zenshi Kana Howa&quot; (Buddhist sermon by Tetsugan Zenshi) is a book written for the purpose of preaching the teachings to females.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>終生、法嗣をたてず、弟弟子に当たる宝洲に寺を付嘱した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He didn&apos;t decide the successor of his teaching till the end of his life and asked Hoshu, his junior disciple, to take care of the temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He didn&apos;t decide the successor to his teachings until the end of his life and asked Hoshu, his junior disciple, to take care of the temple.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He didn&apos;t decide the successor to his teachings until the end of his life and asked Hoshu, his junior disciple, to take care of the temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>その奇特な行ないによって、『近世畸人傳』巻2に立伝されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thanks to his praiseworthy activities, he was listed in the volume 2 of &quot;Kinsei kijinden&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thanks to his praiseworthy activities, he was listed in volume 2 of &quot;Kinsei kijinden&quot;.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thanks to his praiseworthy activities, he was listed in volume 2 of &quot;Kinsei kijin den&quot; (Biographies of Eccentrics of Recent Times).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>黄檗版大蔵経（鉄眼版）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Obaku edition of Daizokyo (Tetsugen edition)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Obaku edition of Daizokyo (Tetsugen edition)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Obaku Edition of Daizokyo (Tetsugen Edition)</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>1664年（寛文4年）に『大蔵経』を刊行することを発願し、1667年（寛文7年）には全国行脚を行って施材を集めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He swore by Buddha to publish &quot;Daizokyo&quot; in 1664 and collected alms in 1667 by making a pilgrimage throughout the nation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He swore by Buddha to publish &quot;Daizokyo&quot; in 1664 and collected alms in 1667 by making a pilgrimage throughout the nation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He swore by Buddha to publish &quot;Daizokyo&quot; in 1664 and collected alms in 1667 by making a pilgrimage throughout the nation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>上述の事情によって、2度まで断念したが、3度目にしてようやく施財を集めることを得、京都の木屋町二条の地に印経房（のちの貝葉書院）を開設し、1668年（寛文8年）に中国明の万暦版を基に覆刻開版し、1678年（延宝6年）に完成させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he had given up twice due to the above-mentioned circumstances, he finally succeeded in collecting alms in his third trial and established Inkyobo (Baiyo shoin) at Kyoto Kiya-machi Nijo, started to carve a woodblock in 1668 based on the Banreki edition of Ming, China, and finally completed it in 1678.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he had given up twice due to the above-mentioned circumstances, he finally succeeded in collecting alms at his third attempt and established Inkyobo (Baiyo shoin) at Kyoto Kiya-machi Nijo, started to carve a woodblock in 1668 based on the Banreki edition of Ming, China, and finally completed it in 1678.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he had given up twice due to the above-mentioned circumstances, he finally succeeded in collecting alms at his third attempt and established Inkyobo (later Baiyo shoin) at Nijo, Kiya-machi, Kyoto, started to carve a woodblock in 1668 based on the Banreki edition of Ming, China, and finally completed it in 1678.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>1,618部7,334巻。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1,618 copies, 7334 volumes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1,618 copies, 7334 volumes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1,618 copies, 7334 volumes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>後水尾天皇に上進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He reported to the Emperor Gomizunoo.</e>
<cmt>「上進する」は「上申する」と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He reported to the Emperor Gomizunoo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He reported to the Emperor Gomizunoo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>この大蔵経は黄檗版大蔵経または鉄眼版と呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This Daizokyo is called Obaku edition Daizokyo or Tetsugen edition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Daizokyo is called Obaku edition Daizokyo or Tetsugen edition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Daizokyo is called Obaku edition Daizokyo or Tetsugen edition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>万暦版の覆刻ではあるが、行間に界線は彫られていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although its woodblock was carved based on Banreki edition, no border lines were carved between the lines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although its woodblock was carved based on the Banreki edition, no border lines were carved between the lines.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although its woodblock was carved based on the Banreki edition, no border lines were carved between the lines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>その版木は、後世まで黄檗山の宝蔵院に収蔵され、貝葉書院を通じて、求めに応じて摺印が行なわれ続けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its woodblock has been kept in Hozoin Temple of Obakusan through the ages and Baiyo shoin has been printing as and when requested.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The woodblock has been kept in Hozoin Temple of Obakusan through the ages and Baiyo shoin has been printed as and when requested.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The woodblock has been kept in Hozoin Temple on Mt. Obaku through the ages and Baiyo shoin has been printed as and when requested.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 M-sho-gun(id:88956), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Carkuni(id:79281), 浩(id:70121), Lobbyonce(id:195963), Mait(id:73947), Chi-Ham(id:143515), 瑞雲(id:27410), Ko-ken(id:49348), R28Bot(id:177951), 水野白楓(id:22811), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), Loveless(id:129239), 酢溜まり氷(id:65987), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>