<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>勧進</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanjin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanjin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanjin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>勧進（かんじん）とは、仏教の僧侶が衆庶の救済のための布教活動の一環として行われる行為の1つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanjin was a work done by Buddhist monks in connection with missionary activities to relieve people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanjin was work done by Buddhist monks in connection with missionary activities intended to bring relief to people.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanjin was work done by Buddhist monks in connection with missionary activities intended to bring relief to people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>その内容としては直接民衆に説いて念仏・誦経などの行為を勧める者や寺院・仏像などの新造あるいは修復・再建のために浄財の寄付を求める者がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In details, some monks directly encouraged people to pray nenbutsu (Buddhist prayer) or jukyo (chanting or reading the sutras) and others called for people to offer money for building, repairing, and remodeling a new temple or statue.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Specifically, some monks directly encouraged people to recite nenbutsu (Buddhist prayers) or jukyo (chanting or reading the sutras), and others called for people to offer money for building, repairing and remodeling a new temple or statue.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Specifically, some monks directly encouraged people to recite nenbutsu (Buddhist prayers) or jukyo (chanting or reading the sutras), and others called for people to offer money for building, repairing and remodeling a new temple or statue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>中世以後には後者の行為を指すことが一般的となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In and after the middle ages, Kanjin has generally means the latter.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the middle ages, Kanjin has generally meant the latter.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the middle ages, Kanjin has generally meant the latter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>勧進とは</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What is Kanjin?</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What is Kanjin?</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What is Kanjin?</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>勧進とは、寺院の建立や修繕などのために、信者や有志者を説きすすめてその費用を奉納させることをいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanjin refers to a work of monks in which they encouraged or persuaded followers and supporters to offer money for building and repairing temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanjin refers to the work of monks in which they encouraged or persuaded followers and supporters to offer money for building and repairing temples.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanjin refers to the work of monks in which they encouraged or persuaded followers and supporters to offer money for building and repairing temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>そのことにより人びとを仏道に導き入れ、作善をなさしめるのが元来の意であったが、のちには寄付を集める方法として興行を催し、観覧料の収入をもってこれに当てるという意味としても広く用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It originally meant to lead people to butsudo (Buddhist teachings) to do good deeds through donations, but in later years it widely meant to hold entertaining performances as a means to collect donations.and devote collected admission fees to kanjin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally it meant to lead people to butsudo (Buddhist teachings) in order to do good deeds through donations, but in later years it generally meant to hold entertaining performances as a means of collecting donations and devoting the collected admission fees to kanjin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally it meant to lead people to butsudo (Buddhist teachings) in order to do good deeds through donations, but in later years it generally meant to hold entertaining performances as a means of collecting donations and devoting the collected admission fees to kanjin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>中世においては、橋や道路の修理・整備から官寺（鐘や仏像、写経をふくむ）の建設や修造など、本来は朝廷（国家）や国衙（地方行政機関）がおこなうべき公共事業も、勧進によってなされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the middle ages, kanjin was a source of fund for public works ranging from the construction and maintenance of bridges and roads to the building and repairs of kanji (state-sponsored temples) (including temple bells, Buddhist statues, and handwritten sutra), although the Chotei (Imperial Court) or kokuga (provincial government) should have done so.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the middle ages, kanjin was a source of funds for public works ranging from the construction and maintenance of bridges and roads to the building and repair of kanji (state-sponsored temples) (including temple bells, Buddhist statues and handwritten sutra), although the Chotei (Imperial Court) or kokuga (provincial government) should have done so.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the middle ages, kanjin was a source of funds for public works ranging from the construction and maintenance of bridges and roads to the building and repair of kanji (state-sponsored temples) (including temple bells, Buddhist statues and handwritten sutra), although the Chotei (Imperial Court) or kokuga (provincial government) should have done so.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>勧進をおこなう者は、勧進帳（後述）をたずさえて諸国を遍歴したり、橋のたもとや寺社の門前、関所などで「一紙半銭」の寄付を募った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monks engaged in kanjin made a tour of the country carrying a book called Kanjin cho (described below) with them and collect contributions by offering Isshi Hansen (a piece of paper for a half mon (currency) meaning very little) at the foot of bridges or in front of the gate of a temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Monks engaged in kanjin would tour the countryside, carrying with them a book called Kanjin cho (described below) and collecting contributions by offering Isshi Hansen (a piece of paper for a half-mon (currency) meaning very little) at the feet of bridges or in front of temple gates.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Monks engaged in kanjin would tour the countryside, carrying with them a book called Kanjin cho (described below) and collecting contributions by offering Isshi Hansen (a piece of paper for a half-mon (currency) meaning very little) at the feet of bridges or in front of temple gates.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>勧進聖らの活動</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Activities of kanjin-hijiri</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Activities of kanjin-hijiri</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Activities of kanjin-hijiri</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>初期の勧進は主として勧進聖（かんじんひじり）・勧進僧（かんじんそう）・勧進上人（かんじんしょうにん）と呼ばれる僧侶によって担われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the beginning, monks called kanjin-hijiri, kanjin-so, or kanjin-shonin are mainly engaged in kanjin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially, monks called kanjin-hijiri, kanjin-so or kanjin-shonin were mainly engaged in kanjin.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially, monks called kanjin-hijiri, kanjin-so or kanjin-shonin were mainly engaged in kanjin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>彼らは各地を遍歴しながら説法を行い、人々から銭や米の寄付を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They made a tour of the county to preach sermons and collect contributions of money and rice from people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They would tour the countryside, preach sermons and collect contributions of money and rice from people.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They would tour the countryside, preach sermons and collect contributions of money and rice from people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>彼らは必要経費のみをそこから受け取り、残りを事業達成のための寄付に充てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They took only necessary expenses from the collected contributions and devoted the rest to works for the public.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They took only necessary expenses from the collected contributions and devoted the rest to works for the public.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They took only necessary expenses from the collected contributions and devoted the rest to works for the public.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>こうした勧進聖としては、奈良時代の行基や平安時代の空也・行円などが著名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Famous kanjin monks included Gyoki in the Nara Period, and Kuya and Gyoen in the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Famous kanjin monks included Gyoki in the Nara period, and Kuya and Gyoen in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Famous kanjin monks included Gyoki in the Nara period, and Kuya and Gyoen in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また、尼の中にも勧進活動に加わるものもおり、これを勧進比丘尼（かんじんびくに）と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some nuns who participated in kanjin activities, were called kanjin bikuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some nuns who participated in kanjin activities were called kanjin bikuni.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some nuns who participated in kanjin activities were called kanjin bikuni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>ただし、勧進比丘尼の中には神仏習合の影響を受けて尼の形態をした巫女なども含まれており、また近世に入ると遊女的な行いをする者も存在したため、純粋な尼とは言えない者が多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However there were many nuns who did not fit the original definition of kanjin bikini; some of the kanjin bikini were miko (shrine maiden) who looked like a nun under the influence of shinbutsu shugo (syncretism of Shinto and Buddhism) and others in the early-modern times were engaged in sexual activities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were, however, many nuns who didn&apos;t fit the original definition of kanjin bikuni; some of the kanjin bikuni were miko (shrine maidens) who looked like nuns due to the influence of shinbutsu shugo (syncretism of Shinto and Buddhism), and others in the early modern times were engaged in sexual activities.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were, however, many nuns who didn&apos;t fit the original definition of kanjin bikuni; some of the kanjin bikuni were miko (shrine maidens) who looked like nuns due to the influence of shinbutsu shugo (syncretism of Shinto and Buddhism), and others in the early modern times were engaged in sexual activities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>それでも戦国時代 (日本)の清順のように勧進活動によって寺院を再興した勧進比丘尼も少なからずおり、その活動も評価されるものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nevertheless there were not a few kanjin bikuni whose services are highly recognized; for example, Seijun in the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) were engageed in kanjin to rebuilt temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nevertheless, more than a few kanjin bikuni whose services are highly recognized; for example, Seijun in the Sengoku (Warring States) period were engaged in kanjin as the means to rebuild temples.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nevertheless, more than a few kanjin bikuni whose services are highly recognized; for example, Seijun in the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) were engaged in kanjin as the means to rebuild temples.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>勧進の普及</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Spread of Kanjin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Spread of Kanjin</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Spread of Kanjin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>こうした勧進があまねく庶民に受容され、広く社会に浸透していくのは、およそ12世紀以降のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was in and after the 12th century that these kanjin activities were generally accepted by people and widely spread to the society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was in and after the twelfth century that these kanjin activities were generally accepted by people and spread throughout society.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was in and after the twelfth century that these kanjin activities were generally accepted by people and spread throughout society.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>鐘については、保延7年（1141年）に大和国（奈良県）の金峯山寺の鐘が勧進僧道寂の勧進によって作られており、国家管理の橋であった山城国（京都府）の宇治橋や近江国（滋賀県）瀬田の唐橋も、12世紀に入ると勧進によって管理・維持がなされるようになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinpusen-ji Temple&apos;s bell in Yamato Province (Nara Prefecture) was made in 1141 through kanjin of a kanjin-so named Dojaku, and Uji-bashi Bridge in Yamashiro Province (Kyoto Prefecture) and Seta no karahashi Bridge in Omi Province (Shiga Prefecture) were repaired and maintained through kanjin in the 12th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinpusen-ji Temple&apos;s bell in Yamato Province (Nara Prefecture) was made in 1141 through the kanjin of a kanjin-so called Dojaku, and Uji-bashi Bridge in Yamashiro Province (Kyoto Prefecture) and Seta no karahashi Bridge in Omi Province (Shiga Prefecture) were repaired and maintained through kanjin in the twelfth century.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinpusen-ji Temple&apos;s bell in Yamato Province (Nara Prefecture) was made in 1141 through the kanjin of a kanjin-so called Dojaku, and Uji-bashi Bridge in Yamashiro Province (Kyoto Prefecture) and Seta no karahashi Bridge in Omi Province (Shiga Prefecture) which were under Chotei (Imperial Court) control were repaired and maintained through kanjin in the twelfth century.</e>
<cmt>which were under Chotei (Imperial Court) control補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また、近江関寺の再興は治承3年（1179年）の南無阿聖人の勧進によるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seki-dera Temple in Omi was also reconstructed in 1179 through kanjin of monks of Jodoshinnshu sect of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>南無阿聖人は南無阿弥陀仏を唱える僧、つまり浄土真宗の僧と解釈し訳してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seki-dera Temple, in Omi, was also reconstructed in 1179 through the kanjin of monks from the Jodoshinnshu sect of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seki-dera Temple, in Omi, was also reconstructed in 1179 through the kanjin of monks from the Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism).</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>東大寺大勧進職</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Todaiji Dai Kanjin shoku Position</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The position of Todaiji Dai Kanjin shoku</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The position of Todaiji Dai Kanjin shoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>治承4年（1180年）の平氏政権による南都焼き討ちによって東大寺は灰燼に帰した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1180 Todai-ji Temple was burnt to ground in the fire of the southern capital set by the Taira clan government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1180, Todai-ji Temple burned to the ground in the fire of the southern capital set by the Taira clan government.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1180, Todai-ji Temple burned to the ground in the fire of the southern capital set by the Taira clan government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>これを憂慮した後白河法皇は、勧進聖らに東大寺再建のための勧進活動への協力を求め、養和元年（1181年）、その責任者として重源を大勧進職（だいかんじんしょく）に任命した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, who felt concern about this destruction, asked monks to cooperate in reconstruction of Todai-ji Temple through kanjin and appointed Chogen as Dai Kanjin shoku Position to lead such activities of monks in 1181.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, who felt concern about this destruction, asked monks to cooperate in the reconstruction of Todai-ji Temple through kanjin, and in 1181 he appointed Chogen to the position of Dai Kanjin shoku in order to lead the monks in their activities.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, who felt concern about this destruction, asked monks to cooperate in the reconstruction of Todai-ji Temple through kanjin, and in 1181 he appointed Chogen to the position of Dai Kanjin shoku in order to lead the monks in their activities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>当時、61歳だった重源は勧進聖や勧進僧、土木建築や美術装飾に関わる技術者・職人を集めて組織して、勧進活動によって再興に必要な資金を集め、それを元手に技術者・職人が実際の再建事業に従事した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chogen at the age of 61at that time organized monks (kanjin-hijiri and kanjin-so) as well as engineers and craftsmen to be engaged in engineering and decoration works so that monks could collect fund needed for rebuilding the temple and engineers and craftmen could start rebuilding the temple with the fund.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chogen, who was then 61 years old, organized monks (kanjin-hijiri and kanjin-so) as well as engineers and craftsmen to handle the engineering and decoration works so that the monks could collect the funds needed for rebuilding the temple and the engineers and craftsmen could start rebuilding the temple with the funds they&apos;d collected.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chogen, who was then 61 years old, organized monks (kanjin-hijiri and kanjin-so) as well as engineers and craftsmen to handle the engineering and decoration works so that the monks could collect the funds needed for rebuilding the temple and the engineers and craftsmen could start rebuilding the temple with the funds they&apos;d collected.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>また、重源自身も、京都の後白河法皇や九条兼実、鎌倉の源頼朝などに浄財寄付を依頼している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chogen himself requested Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa and Kanezane KUJO in Kyoto and MINAMOTO no Yoritomo in Kamakura to make jozai (donations).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chogen himself asked Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa and Kanezane KUJO, in Kyoto, and MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, in Kamakura, to make jozai (donations).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chogen himself asked Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa and Kanezane KUJO, in Kyoto, and MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, in Kamakura, to make jozai (donations).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>途中、いくつもの課題もあったものの、重源と彼が組織した人々の働きによって東大寺は再建された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Todaiji temples was rebuilt through efforts of Chogen and people organzied by him, although they had faced many problems during the construction works.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Todaiji Temple was rebuilt through the efforts of Chogen and people organized by him, although they had faced many problems during the construction process.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Todai-ji Temple was rebuilt through the efforts of Chogen and people organized by him, although they had faced many problems during the construction process.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>なお、重源は東大寺再建に際し、西行に奥羽への砂金勧進を依頼している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chogen also requested Saigyo to travel to Ou (Mutsu province and Dewa Province) to collect donations of sakin (gold dust) for rebuilding the Todaiji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chogen also asked Saigyo to travel to Ou (Mutsu and Dewa provinces) to collect donations of sakin (gold dust) for the rebuilding of Todaiji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chogen also asked Saigyo to travel to Ou (Mutsu and Dewa provinces) to collect donations of sakin (gold dust) for the rebuilding of Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="24">
<j>以後も東大寺の施設の再建や管理維持のための役職として大勧進職は継続され、栄西（2代目）・行勇（3代目）・円爾（10代目）・忍性（14代目）・円観（24代目）らが任命された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Dai Kanjin shoku Position,, a post responsible for rebuilding and managing facilities of Todaiji Temple were taken over; appointed were Eisai (the second), Gyoyu (the third), Enni (the tenth), Ninsho (the fourteenth) and Enkan (the twenty-fourth).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The position of Dai Kanjin shoku, a post responsible for rebuilding and managing the facilities of Todaiji Temple, was taken over; appointed were Eisai (the second), Gyoyu (the third), Enni (the tenth), Ninsho (the fourteenth) and Enkan (the twenty-fourth).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The position of Dai Kanjin shoku, a post responsible for rebuilding and managing the facilities of Todai-ji Temple, was taken over; appointed were Eisai (the second), Gyoyu (the third), Enni (the tenth), Ninsho (the fourteenth) and Enkan (the twenty-fourth).</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>戦国時代に財政難によって一度は廃絶されるも江戸時代の再建時には公慶が大勧進職を復興して東大寺の再建を果たしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the restruction of Todaiji Temple was suspended due to financial difficulties during the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States), it was completed after Kokei had revived Todaiji Dai Kanjin shoku Position.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the reconstruction of Todaiji Temple was suspended during the Sengoku (Warring States) period due to financial difficulties, it was completed after Kokei revived the position of Todaiji Dai Kanjin shoku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the reconstruction of Todai-ji Temple was suspended during the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) due to financial difficulties, it was completed after Kokei revived the position of Todaiji Dai Kanjin shoku.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>勧進職の普及とその変質</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Spread and change of Kanjin shoku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Spread and Change of Kanjin Shoku</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Spread and Change of Kanjin Shoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>東大寺を再建させたこの制度は他の寺院にも用いられて、有力寺院の再建には勧進職（かんじんしょく）が任命されるのが恒例とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This system that enabled reconstruction of Todaiji Temple became popular among other temples, and major temples often installed the Kanjin shoku position for restricting them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This system, which had made possible the reconstruction of Todaiji Temple, became popular among other temples, and major temples often installed the Kanjin shoku position in order to restrict them.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This system, which had made possible the reconstruction of Todai-ji Temple, became popular among other temples, and major temples often installed the Kanjin shoku position in order to restrict them.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>特に鎌倉時代に律宗（真言律宗含む）が再興されると、律宗が僧侶が私利私欲を抱くことを戒めて、利益を得た場合にはその公平な配分を義務付けたこと、更に新しい律宗が従来の教学研究専念を脱却して、布教による職人階層との関係を強めたことで評価を得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the revival of Risshu Sect (including Shingon Risshu Sect) during the Kamakura Period, the Risshu Sect gained a high reputation because the sect forbidden its monks from having self-interest, obliged them to divide profits, if gained, equally among them, and shifted its priority from the study of teaching to a close tie with the workman class through its missionary works.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the revival of the Risshu sect (including the Shingon Risshu sect) during the Kamakura period, the Risshu sect gained a high reputation because it prohibited its monks from having self-interest, obliged them to divide profits (if any) equally among themselves, and shifted its priority from the study of teaching to a close tie with the working class through its missionary works.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the revival of the Risshu sect (including the Shingon Risshu sect) during the Kamakura period, the Risshu sect gained a high reputation because it prohibited its monks from having self-interest, obliged them to divide profits (if any) equally among themselves, and shifted its priority from the study of teaching to a close tie with the working class through its missionary works.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>勧進職に律宗僧を任じる傾向が増加していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its monks were increasingly appointed as kanjin shoku:</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its monks were increasingly appointed as kanjin shoku:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its monks were increasingly appointed as kanjin shoku:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>だが、時代が進むにつれて朝廷や幕府などが勧進職に対して直接的な寄付を行うだけではなく、所領などを与えて（東大寺の周防国一国など）その収益から再建費用を捻出させるように取り計らったたために、勧進職は一種の利権の絡む役職となり、更に律宗の衰微も加わって、勧進職を巡る寺内の抗争や、その収益を私する勧進職が出現するなど問題も生じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the time progressed, however, problems arose such as conflicts among temples over the post of kanjinshoku and emergence of kanjin shoku that monopolied profits, with the decline of the Risshu Sect; kanjin shoku became a kind of post that involve vested interest because the chotei (Imperial Court) and the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) not only made direct contributions to the Kanjin shoku monks but offered a shoryo (territory) (for example, the entire province of Sue Province) for making money for the destruction of temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as time progressed problems arose, including conflicts among temples over the post of kanjinshoku and the emergence of kanjin shoku, which monopolized profits, concurrently with the decline of the Risshu sect; kanjin shoku became a kind of post that involved vested interest, because the chotei (Imperial Court) and the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) not only made direct contributions to the Kanjin shoku monks but also offered a shoryo (territory) (for example, all of Sue Province) for making money for the destruction of temples.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as time progressed problems arose, including conflicts among temples over the post of kanjinshoku and the emergence of kanjin shoku, which monopolized profits, concurrently with the decline of the Risshu sect; kanjin shoku became a kind of post that involved vested interest, because the chotei (Imperial Court) and the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) not only made direct contributions to the Kanjin shoku monks but also offered a shoryo (territory) (for example, all of Sue Province) for making money for the destruction of temples.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>また、熱心に再建に尽くした僧侶の中にも再建のための財源を勧進活動には依存せずに、朝廷や幕府、その他の有力者との政治交渉による再建費用獲得などに力を入れる僧侶もいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore some monks, who earnestly devoted themselves to such constructions, focused more on political negotiations with magnates such as the chotei and bakufu to obtain fund for the restructions than on collect moeny through kanjin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore some monks, who earnestly devoted themselves to such construction works, focused more on political negotiations with magnates such as the chotei and bakufu in order to obtain funds for reconstruction instead of collecting money through kanjin.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore some monks, who earnestly devoted themselves to such construction works, focused more on political negotiations with magnates such as the chotei and bakufu in order to obtain funds for reconstruction instead of collecting money through kanjin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>このため、勧進職と勧進聖らとの関係は希薄になることもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this, some kanjin shoku had less close relation with kanjin-so monks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, some kanjin shoku didn&apos;t have such close relationships with kanjin-so monks.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, some kanjin shoku didn&apos;t have such close relationships with kanjin-so monks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>勿論、そのような時代になっても全国各地を回って勧進に尽力する勧進聖らも少なくなかったが、反面勧進聖を名乗って実態は物乞いなどの行為を行う者も現れる（前述の勧進比丘尼の遊女化もその1つである）ようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is true that, even with the change of situations, not a few monks worked hard travelling across the county to be engaged in kanjin activities, but there were those who disguised themselves as monks but in effect begged for money (or some kanjin bikuni who prostitutes themselves as mentioned above).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is true that, even with the change in circumstances, many monks worked hard traveling the countryside for the sake of their kanjin activities, but there were those who disguised themselves as monks but in effect begged for money (or some kanjin bikuni who prostituted themselves, as mentioned above).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is true that, even with the change in circumstances, many monks worked hard traveling the countryside for the sake of their kanjin activities, but there were those who disguised themselves as monks but in effect begged for money (or some kanjin bikuni who prostituted themselves, as mentioned above).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>結果的に寺院内部（勧進職を含めて）や世間一般から蔑視されるような状況も生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently the reputation of kanjin monks were declining within the circle of temples (including kanjin shoku monks) as well as among the general public.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, the reputation of kanjin monks declined within the circle of temples (including the kanjin shoku monks) as well as among the general public.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, the reputation of kanjin monks declined within the circle of temples (including the kanjin shoku monks) as well as among the general public.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="34">
<j>後にこの「勧進」のスタイルを基にした様々な「勧進○○」と称されるものが出現することとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later on words beginning with &quot;kanjin&quot; emerged which came from the activities of &quot;kanjin.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eventually, words beginning with &quot;kanjin&quot; emerged, stemming from the activities of &quot;kanjin.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eventually, words beginning with &apos;kanjin&apos; emerged, stemming from the activities of &apos;kanjin.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>勧進帳</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">kangin cho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">kangin cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanjin cho</e>
<cmt>文頭大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="35">
<j>勧進帳（かんじんちょう）とは、勧化帳（かんげちょう）とも呼ばれており、勧進の目的について書かれた巻物形式の趣意書を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanjin cho, also called kange cho, refers to a rolled book that describes the objectives of kanjin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanjin cho, or kange cho, refers to a rolled book that describes the objectives of kanjin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanjin cho, or kange cho, refers to a rolled book that describes the objectives of kanjin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="36">
<j>勧進の発願趣旨に始まり、念仏・誦経の功徳、寄付・作善に関わることによる功徳（現世利益・極楽往生）などを説いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It begins with hotsugan (vow to attain enlightenment and save people) and explains a kudoku (merits) of praying to Amitadha and reciting a sutra and another kudoku (benefits in this world and for entering into the bliss of Heaven) resulting from monetary donations and good deeds.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It begins with hotsugan (a vow to attain enlightenment and save people) and explains the kudoku (merits) of praying to Amitadha and reciting a sutra and another kudoku (benefits in this world and for entering into the bliss of Heaven) resulting from monetary donations and good deeds.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It begins with hotsugan (a vow to attain enlightenment and save people) and explains the kudoku (merits) of praying to Amitabha and reciting a sutra and another kudoku (benefits in this world and for entering into the bliss of Heaven) resulting from monetary donations and good deeds.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>勧進聖は説教を聞くために集まった人々に対してこれを読み上げ、あるいは閲覧させて、寄付・作善を通じた結縁を呼びかけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanjin-hijiri monks read and showed this book to people who gathered to hear preaches and encouraged them to have a realtion with Buddah through donations and good deeds.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanjin-hijiri monks read and showed this book to people who gathered to hear preaching, and encouraged them to have a relationship with Buddha through donations and good deeds.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanjin-hijiri monks read and showed this book to people who gathered to hear preaching, and encouraged them to have a relationship with Buddha through donations and good deeds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>なお、勧進帳とは対として寄付の実績などを記した奉加帳がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Paired with kanjin cho was Hoga cho, which recorded the amounts of collected donations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Paired with kanjin cho was Hoga cho, which recorded the amounts of collected donations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Paired with kanjin cho was Hoga cho, which recorded the amounts of collected donations.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="39">
<j>これは、重源の東大寺再建時の勧進帳である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is Chogen&apos;s kanjin cho for the restruction of Todaji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is Chogen&apos;s kanjin cho for the reconstruction of Todaiji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is Chogen&apos;s kanjin cho for the reconstruction of Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="40">
<j>東大寺勧進上人重源敬って白す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dear fellow believers:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dear fellow believers:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dear fellow believers:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="41">
<j>特に十方檀那の助成を蒙り、絲綸の旨に任せ、土木の功を終へ、仏像を修補し、堂宇を営作せんと請う状</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I hereby request that all believers in Buddhism provide support for our civil engineering project aimed at repairing the Buddhist statue and rebuilding Todai-ji Temple in accordance with the emperor&apos;s order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I hereby request that all believers in Buddhism provide support for our civil engineering project aimed at repairing the Buddhist statue and rebuilding Todai-ji Temple, in accordance with the Emperor&apos;s order.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I hereby request that all believers in Buddhism provide support for our civil engineering project aimed at repairing the Buddhist statue and rebuilding Todai-ji Temple, in accordance with the Emperor&apos;s order.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="42">
<j>右当伽藍は風雨を天半に軼べ、棟甍の竦櫂を有ち、仏法恢弘の精舎、神明保護の霊地なり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a sacred Buddhist center that serves to spread Buddhism in Japan, Todai-ji Temple has provided us Buddhist believers with protection from wind and rain by its tiled roofs rising high into the sky.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a sacred Buddhist center that serves to spread Buddhism in Japan, Todai-ji Temple has provided us Buddhist believers with protection from wind and rain by its tiled roofs rising high into the sky.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a sacred Buddhist center that serves to spread Buddhism in Japan, Todai-ji Temple has provided us Buddhist believers with protection from wind and rain by its tiled roofs rising high into the sky.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>原夫れ聖武天皇作治の叡願を発し、行基菩薩知識の懇誠を表す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The temple was originally built by the honorable priest, Gyoki, at the behest of Emperor Shomu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The temple was originally built by the honorable priest Gyoki, at the behest of Emperor Shomu.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The temple was originally built by the honorable priest Gyoki, at the behest of Emperor Shomu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>加之、天照大神両国の黄金を出し、之を採りて尊像に塗り奉る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its great statue of Buddha was painted with gold collected from all over Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its great statue of Buddha was painted with gold collected from all over Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its great statue of Buddha was painted with gold collected from all over Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>菩提僧正万里の滄海を渡り、これを崛して仏眼を開かしむ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was then consecrated by a venerable Buddhist priest who was invited from across the ocean.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was then consecrated by a venerable Buddhist priest who was invited from across the sea.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was then consecrated by a venerable Buddhist priest who was invited from across the sea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>彼の北天竺八十尺弥勒菩薩は光明を毎月の斎日に現じ、此の東大寺の十六丈盧舎那仏は利益を数代の聖朝に施す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The famous 80-feet statue of Miroku Buddha in Northern India sheds the light of wisdom on a Buddhist celebration day every month, while the 50-meter great statue of Buddha at Todai-ji Temple has brought benefits to the Japanese people over many decades.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The famous 80-foot statue of Miroku Buddha, in northern India, sheds the light of wisdom on a Buddhist celebration day every month, while the 50-meter great statue of Buddha at Todai-ji Temple has brought benefits to the Japanese people over many decades.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The famous 80-foot statue of Miroku Buddha, in northern India, sheds the light of wisdom on a Buddhist celebration day every month, while the 50-meter great statue of Buddha at Todai-ji Temple has brought benefits to the Japanese people over many decades.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>彼を以って此に比するに、此猶卓然たり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The statue of Buddha at Todai-ji Temple thus rivals or even exceeds the statue in India.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The statue of Buddha at Todai-ji Temple thus rivals or even exceeds the statue in India.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The statue of Buddha at Todai-ji Temple thus rivals or even exceeds the statue in India.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>是を以って代々の国王尊崇他無し。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is no wonder, then, that our temple has been worshipped by generations of emperors in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is no wonder, then, that our temple has been worshiped by generations of emperors in Japan.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is no wonder, then, that our temple has been worshiped by generations of emperors in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>蠢々たる土俗帰敬懈るに匪ず。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has also faithfully fulfilled its duty to convert unenlightened common people to Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has also faithfully fulfilled its duty of converting unenlightened common people to Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has also faithfully fulfilled its duty of converting unenlightened common people to Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>然る間、去年窮冬下旬八日、図らざるに火あり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, a fire broke out in the city of Nara on the eighth of December (traditional Japanese calendar month) last year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, a fire broke out in the city of Nara on the eighth of December [on the traditional Japanese calendar] last year.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, a fire broke out in the city of Nara on the eighth of December (old lunar calendar) last year.</e>
<cmt>カッコ修正用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>延て此寺に及び、堂宇灰と成り、仏像煙と化す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fire spread to our temple, burning down its buildings and reducing the statue of Buddha to ashes.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fire spread to our temple, burning down its buildings and reducing the statue of Buddha to ashes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fire spread to our temple, burning down its buildings and reducing the statue of Buddha to ashes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>跋提河の春の浪哀声再び聞え、沙羅林の朝の雲憂色重て聳え、眼を戴いて天を迎げば、則ち白霧胸に塞りて散せず。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Walking on riverbanks in this spring, we hear people wailing among camellia trees that stand in heavy morning mist, and when we raise our eyes to heaven, we feel a mist of sadness clouding our hearts.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Walking on the riverbanks this spring, we hear people wailing among the camellia trees that stand in the heavy morning mist, and when we raise our eyes to the heavens we feel a mist of sadness clouding our hearts.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Walking on the riverbanks this spring, we hear people wailing among the camellia trees that stand in the heavy morning mist, and when we raise our eyes to the heavens we feel a mist of sadness clouding our hearts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>首を傾けて地に俯すれば、亦紅塵面に満ちて忽ち昏く、天下誰か之を歔欷せざらん。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When we look down at the ground, we feel our sorrow deepen by the dust of ash glowing red in the sun, causing everyone to cry over what we have lost.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When we look down at the ground, we feel our sorrow deepen by the dust of ash glowing red in the sun, causing everyone to cry over what we have lost.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When we look down at the ground, we feel our sorrow deepen by the dust of ash glowing red in the sun, causing everyone to cry over what we have lost.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>海内誰か之を悲歎せざらん。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Who would not lament the destruction of our temple?</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Who would not lament the destruction of our temple?</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Who would not lament the destruction of our temple?</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>底露を摧かんより、成風を企つるに若かず。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Despite the unbearable sorrow, however, we need to summon up the courage to reconstruct what has been destroyed instead of grieving over the loss.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Despite the unbearable sorrow, however, we must summon the courage to reconstruct what has been destroyed instead of grieving over the loss.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Despite the unbearable sorrow, however, we must summon the courage to reconstruct what has been destroyed instead of grieving over the loss.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>玆に因って、遠く貞観延喜の奮規を訪び、近く今上宣下の勅命に任せ、須らく都鄙をして、以って営作を遂げしむ可し。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Let us then follow the example of our ancestors, who took the initiative to build Todai-ji Temple during the Jogan and Engi eras, in order to achieve the reconstruction of the temple under the orders of the current emperor in collaboration with people from across the country.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Let us then follow the example of our ancestors, who took the initiative to build Todai-ji Temple during the Jogan and Engi eras, in order to achieve the reconstruction of the temple under the orders of the current Emperor in collaboration with people from across the country.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Let us then follow the example of our ancestors, who took the initiative to build Todai-ji Temple during the Jogan and Engi eras, in order to achieve the reconstruction of the temple under the orders of the current Emperor in collaboration with people from across the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>伏して乞う、十方一切同心合力、家々の清虚を謂ふこと莫れ、只力の能ふ所に任す可し。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I therefore urgently request that all Buddhist believers, the rich and the poor alike, work together to the best of their abilities to achieve our purpose.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I therefore urgently request that all Buddhist believers, the rich and the poor alike, work together to the best of their abilities to achieve our purpose.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I therefore urgently request that all Buddhist believers, the rich and the poor alike, work together to the best of their abilities to achieve our purpose.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>尺布寸鉄と雖も一木半銭と雖も、必ず勧進の詞に答え、各奉加の志を抽んでよ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Please respond to our request and give us whatever donation you are able to offer - a piece of cloth, iron scrap, a piece of wood or even half a penny.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Please respond to our request and give us whatever donation you are able to offer - a piece of cloth, iron scrap, a piece of wood or even half a penny.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Please respond to our request and give us whatever donation you are able to offer - a piece of cloth, iron scrap, a piece of wood or even half a penny.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>然らば、即ち与善の輩結縁の人、現世には松柏の樹を指して比算し、当来に芙蕖の華に坐して結跏せん。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, you will be awarded the highest honor among Buddhist believers in this world and will be allowed to sit in a lotus flower in the next world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, you will be awarded the highest honor among Buddhist believers in this world and will be allowed to sit in a lotus flower in the next world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, you will be awarded the highest honor among Buddhist believers in this world and will be allowed to sit in a lotus flower in the next world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>其福無量得て記す加からざるもの乎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You will be blessed with everlasting happiness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You will be blessed with everlasting happiness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You will be blessed with everlasting happiness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>敬うて白す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sincerely yours,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sincerely yours,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sincerely yours,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="62">
<j>養和元年八月 日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August (traditional Japanese calendar month) 1181</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August [traditional Japanese calendar] 1181</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August (old lunar calendar) 1181</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>勧進上人重源 敬白</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chogen, a Buddhist priest serving to collect donations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chogen, a Buddhist priest serving to collect donations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chogen, a Buddhist priest serving to collect donations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="64">
<j>別当法務大僧正大和尚（在判）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chief Steward and Grand Priest of Todai-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chief Steward and Grand Priest of Todai-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chief Steward and Grand Priest of Todai-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="65">
<j>なお、歌舞伎の演目として知られる『勧進帳』も武蔵坊弁慶が富樫左衛門の前で勧進帳を読み上げる場面に由来している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A famous program of Kabuki Play titled &quot;Kanjicho&quot; came from a scene where Musashibo Benkei reads out Kanjicho in front of Yasuie TOGASHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A famous program of the Kabuki play entitled &quot;Kanjicho&quot; came from a scene in which Musashibo Benkei recites Kanjicho in front of Yasuie TOGASHI.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A famous program of the Kabuki play entitled &quot;Kanjincho&quot; came from a scene in which Musashibo Benkei recites Kanjincho in front of Yasuie TOGASHI.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>勧進船</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanjin bune</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanjin bune</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanjin bune</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="66">
<j>勧進船（かんじんぶね）は、中世に勧進を進めるために勧進聖らに乗船をさせた船。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanjin bune was a boat in the middle ages where kanjin-hijiri monks were sent to promote kanjin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanjin bune was a boat in the middle ages on which kanjin-hijiri monks were sent to promote kanjin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanjin bune was a boat in the middle ages on which kanjin-hijiri monks were sent to promote kanjin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>主に水上交通の要所を経由する船内で乗客のために説法などを行わせて寄付を募らせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monks preached mainly on the boats that visited key water transportion points to collect donations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Monks preached mainly on the boats that visited key water-transportation points in order to collect donations.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Monks preached mainly on the boats that visited key water-transportation points in order to collect donations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>後に勧進を目的とした芸能の徒なども乗船させるようになったり、水上演芸船の様相を呈したものもあったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In later years enteriners were sent to such boats to carry out kanjin activities, and some are said to have been just like an entertainment boat on the water..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In later years, entertainers were sent to such boats to carry out kanjin activities, and it has been said that some were like floating entertainment halls.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In later years, entertainers were sent to such boats to carry out kanjin activities, and it has been said that some were like floating entertainment halls.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>勧進興行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Knajin Entertainment</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Knajin Entertainment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanjin entertainment</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字スペル</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>勧進平家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanjin Heike</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanjin Heike</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanjin Heike</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="69">
<j>勧進平家（かんじんへいけ）は、寺社の改修費用などを集めるために琵琶法師が『平家物語』の全200句を語ったもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanjin Heike refers to a total of 200 phrases of &quot;Tale of the Heike&quot; narrated by Biwa Hoshi to collect money for repairing temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanjin Heike refers to a total of 200 phrases of &quot;Tale of the Heike,&quot; as narrated by Biwa Hoshi to collect money for temple repairs.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanjin Heike refers to a total of 200 phrases of &quot;Tale of the Heike,&quot; as narrated by Biwa Hoshi to collect money for temple repairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>平家詞曲相伝の立場からは、全句を語るのに要した時間はおよそ90時間から120時間程度とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To inherit words and music of the entire Heike tale to the next generation, all the phrases needs narrating but it is said to have taken about 90 to 120 hours.</e>
<cmt>「平家詞曲相伝の立場から」　は平家物語の詩と曲を次の世代に伝えること、と訳してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To pass on the words and music of the entire Heike tale to the next generation, all the phrases must be recited, but it is said to have taken approximately 90 to 120 hours.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To pass on the words and music of the entire Heike tale to the next generation, all the phrases must be recited, but it is said to have taken approximately 90 to 120 hours.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="71">
<j>貞治2年（1362年）に、琵琶法師の検校明石覚一が勧進平家を演じた記録が、『師守記』の同年正月3日の条に見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moromori-ki Diary described that Kakuichi AKASHI, Biwa Hoshi and kengyo (temple or shrine administrators) performed Kanjin Heike in 1362.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moromori-ki Diary described that Kakuichi AKASHI, Biwa Hoshi and kengyo (temple or shrine administrators) performed the Kanjin Heike in 1362.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the article of January 3, 1362 (old lunar calendar) of &quot;Moromori-ki Diary&quot; described that Kakuichi AKASHI, Biwa Hoshi and kengyo (temple or shrine administrators) performed the Kanjin Heike in 1362.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足In the article of January 3, 1362 (old lunar calendar) of 補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="72">
<j>今日家君密々聴聞五条高倉薬師堂覚一検校平給</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today Lord Moromori enjoyed &quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot; performed privately by Kengyo Kakuichi AKASHI at Gojo Takakura Yakushido Temple.</e>
<cmt>現代訳がないため訳し出しできませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, Lord Moromori enjoyed &quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot; in a private performance by Kengyo Kakuichi AKASHI at Gojo Takakura Yakushido Temple.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, Lord Moromori enjoyed &quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot; in a private performance by Kengyo Kakuichi AKASHI at Gojo Takakura Yakushido Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="73">
<j>なお、「五条高倉薬師堂」とは、狂言「因幡堂」で知られる京都市下京区の平等寺 (京都市下京区)のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Gojo Takakura Yakushido&quot; means Byodo-ji Temple (Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto City), which is well known for &quot;Inabado&quot; of Kyogen Play.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Gojo Takakura Yakushido&quot; means Byodo-ji Temple (Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto City), which is well known for &quot;Inabado&quot; of the Kyogen play.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gojo Takakura Yakushido&apos; means Byodo-ji Temple (Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto City), which is well known for &apos;Inabado&apos; of the Kyogen play.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="74">
<j>勧進平家は、江戸時代にもさかんに行われ、複数の検校が約1ヶ月かけて交代で全句を語ることが多かったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanjin Heike were often performed during the Edo Period, too; kengyo (temple or shrine administrators) are said to have commonly spent about a month in narrating all the phrases on rotation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanjin Heike were often performed during the Edo period, too; kengyo (temple or shrine administrators) are said to have commonly spent about a month narrating all the phrases on rotation.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanjin Heike were often performed during the Edo period, too; kengyo (temple or shrine administrators) are said to have commonly spent about a month narrating all the phrases on rotation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>江戸時代の記録より、琵琶平家琵琶などで好んで語られるのは50句程度であったものと推定されることから、愛好家にとっては、滅多に聴けない句を聴くことのできる、またとない機会となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A record of the Edo period says that such performances provide a golden opportunity for lovers of the tale because the number of favored phrases most Biwa Hoshi narrated in Heike Biwa was estimated at about 50.</e>
<cmt>「琵琶平家琵琶」は「平家琵琶」と訳しました。http://homepage3.nifty.com/heikebiwa-arao/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A record from the Edo period states that such performances provided a golden opportunity for lovers of the tale, because the number of favored phrases most Biwa Hoshi narrated in Heike Biwa was estimated at about 50.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A record from the Edo period states that such performances provided a golden opportunity for lovers of the tale, because the number of favored phrases most Biwa Hoshi narrated in Heike Biwa was estimated at about 50.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>勧進相撲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanjin Zumo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanjin Zumo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanjin Zumo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="76">
<j>宮廷行事としての相撲節会は承安 (日本)4年（1174年）に廃止されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumo Sechie (sumo performed at ancient Japanese imperial court) as a court event was abolished in 1174.</e>
<cmt>「承安 (日本)4年（1174年）」は単に年号だけ訳してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sumo Sechie (sumo performed at the Imperial Court of ancient Japan) as a court event was abolished in 1174.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sumo Sechie (sumo performed at the Imperial Court of ancient Japan) as a court event was abolished in 1174.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>その後、相撲は武家社会に根づき、武士たちの屋敷で行われるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At a later time, sumo took hold in the buke shakai (samurai society) and was held in the residential sites of bushi (samurai)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, sumo took hold in the buke shakai (samurai society) and was held in the residential sites of bushi (samurai).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, sumo took hold in the buke shakai (samurai society) and was held in the residential sites of bushi (samurai).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="78">
<j>いっぽう、現在の大相撲は神社仏閣の再興や造営の費用を捻出するための江戸時代初期の勧進相撲（かんじんずもう）に端を発している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Ozumo we see today originates from Kanjin Zumo held to make money for destruction and building shrines and temples in the early Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the Ozumo we see today originates from Kanjin Zumo, which was held during the Edo period to make money for the demolition and construction of shrines and temples.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the Ozumo we see today originates from Kanjin Zumo, which was held during the Edo period to make money for the demolition and construction of shrines and temples.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>勧進相撲は、京都、大阪、江戸の三都を中心に開かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanjin Zumo was held mainly in the 3 major cities: Kyoto, Osaka, and Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanjin Zumo was held mainly in the three major cities of Kyoto, Osaka and Edo.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanjin Zumo was held mainly in the three major cities of Kyoto, Osaka and Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>当時、各地に職業的な力士集団が生まれつつあり、勧進相撲に招かれては出場した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those day, professional rikishi (sumo wrestlers) was coming into being in regions and were invited to compete in Kanjin Zumo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those days, professional rikishi (sumo wrestlers) were emerging regionally and were invited to compete in Kanjin Zumo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those days, professional rikishi (sumo wrestlers) were emerging regionally and were invited to compete in Kanjin Zumo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>しかし、戦国時代の気風が抜けきれず、様々な問題を引き起こしたため、江戸幕府は慶安元年（1648年）に「風紀を乱す」という理由で勧進相撲禁止令を出している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, violence in the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) remained, which caused various problems, and Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) issued an order banning kanjin sumo in 1648 for the reason of &quot;disorderly conducts.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, violence continued in the Sengoku (Warring States) period, causing various problems, and Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) issued an order banning kanjin sumo in 1648 on the basis of &quot;disorderly conduct.&quot;</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, violence continued in the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States), causing various problems, and Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) issued an order banning kanjin sumo in 1648 on the basis of &apos;disorderly conduct.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="82">
<j>貞享から元禄にかけて、勧進相撲の禁令は随時解かれていき、江戸でも1680年代に興行制限が大幅に緩和された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ban on kanjin sumo was gradually lifted from the period of Jokyo to Genroku; in Tokyo, restrictions on spectacular sumo matches were significantly relaxed in the 1680&apos;s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ban on kanjin sumo was gradually lifted from the period of Jokyo to Genroku; in Tokyo, restrictions on spectacular sumo matches were significantly relaxed in the 1680s.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ban on kanjin sumo was gradually lifted from the period of Jokyo to Genroku; in Tokyo, restrictions on spectacular sumo matches were significantly relaxed in the 1680s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>京都では元禄12年（1699年）に岡崎神社で再開されたという記録がのこり、大坂では、元禄15年（1702年）に現在の南堀江公園（大阪市西区 (大阪市)南堀江）で再開されたとの記録がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a record, sumo matches resumed at Okazaki-jinja Shrine in Kyoto in 1699, at present-day Minami Horie-koen Park (Minami Horie, Nishi Ward, Osaka Prefecture) in 1702.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the record, sumo matches resumed at Okazaki-jinja Shrine in Kyoto in 1699 and at the present-day Minami Horie-koen Park (Minami Horie, Nishi Ward, Osaka Prefecture) in 1702.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the record, sumo matches resumed at Okazaki-jinja Shrine in Kyoto in 1699 and at the present-day Minami Horie-koen Park (Minami Horie, Nishi Ward, Osaka City) in 1702.</e>
<cmt>地名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>なお、おもな力士集団は、久保田藩、南部藩、津軽藩、仙台藩、大坂、京、尾張国、紀伊国、讃岐国、播磨国、因幡国、長崎市、肥後国、薩摩藩にあったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Groups of wrestlers are said to have belonged to Kubota Domain, Nanbu Domain, Tsugaru Domain, Sendai Domain, Owari Province, Ki Provinc, Sanuki Province, Harima Province, Inaba Province, Nagasaki City, Higo Province, and Satsuma Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Groups of wrestlers are said to have belonged to the Satsuma, Kubota, Nanbu, Tsugaru and Sendai domains, as well as Nagasaki City and the provinces of Owari, Ki, Sanuki, Harima, Inaba and Higo.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Groups of wrestlers are said to have belonged to the Satsuma, Kubota, Nanbu, Tsugaru and Sendai domains, as well as Nagasaki City, Osaka and Kyoto, and the provinces of Owari, Kii, Sanuki, Harima, Inaba and Higo.</e>
<cmt>Osaka and Kyoto,補足スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>勧進相撲は、江戸相撲、京都相撲、大坂相撲の各々が独立した力士集団をもつのではなく、各国の力士集団が勧進元との契約によって招かれて相撲興行に参加するという形式をとった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kanjin sumo, each of Edo zumo, Kyoto zumo, and Osaka zumo has not its own wrestler groups: groups of wrestlers were invited from regions to participate in spectacular sumo matches by contract with the organizer of kanjin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kanjin sumo, each of the Edo zumo, Kyoto zumo and Osaka zumo didn&apos;t have its own group of wrestlers; instead, groups of wrestlers were invited from regions to participate in spectacular sumo matches by contract with the organizer of the kanjin.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kanjin sumo, each of the Edo zumo, Kyoto zumo and Osaka zumo didn&apos;t have its own group of wrestlers; instead, groups of wrestlers were invited from regions to participate in spectacular sumo matches by contract with the organizer of the kanjin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="86">
<j>やがて、寛保2年（1742年）に江戸で勧進興行のすべてにわたって解禁され、春は江戸、夏は京、秋は大坂、冬は江戸で「四季勧進相撲」を実施するという体制が確立していく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the ban on kanjin sumo matches were completely lifted in 1742, the system of Shiki Kanjin zumo (seasonal kanjin zumo) was established in which spring matches were held in Tokyo, summer matches in Kyo, and autumn matches in Osaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the ban on kanjin sumo matches was completely lifted in 1742, the system of Shiki Kanjin zumo (seasonal kanjin zumo) was established in which spring matches were held in Tokyo, summer matches in Kyoto and autumn matches in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the ban on kanjin sumo matches was completely lifted in Tokyo in 1742, the system of Shiki Kanjin zumo (seasonal kanjin zumo) was established in which spring matches were held in Tokyo, summer matches in Kyoto, autumn matches in Osaka and winter matches in Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>in Tokyo補足winter matches in Tokyo.補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>神社仏閣の再興などに資することがなくなっても「勧進相撲」の名称はのこった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of &quot;kanjin sumo&quot; continued to be used after its purpose shifted from contributing to the destruction of shrines and temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name &quot;kanjin sumo&quot; continued to be used after its purpose shifted from contributing to the construction of shrines and temples.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name &apos;kanjin sumo&apos; continued to be used after its purpose shifted from contributing to the construction of shrines and temples.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>それは幕藩体制において寺社奉行の許可が必要だったためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is because permission of the government&apos;s commissioner of temples and shrines was required to hold the sumo matches.</e>
<cmt>http://ejje.weblio.jp/content/%E5%AF%BA%E7%A4%BE%E5%A5%89%E8%A1%8C</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because permission from the government&apos;s commissioner of temples and shrines was required in order to hold the sumo matches.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because permission from the government&apos;s commissioner of temples and shrines was required in order to hold the sumo matches.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>そして、1925年（大正14年）には東京、大阪の相撲集団が合流し大日本相撲協会（いまの日本相撲協会）へと発展する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sumo groups in Tokyo and Osaka joined in 1925 to develop into Dai Nihon Sumo Kyokai (present-day Nihon Sumo Kyokai (Japan Sumo Association).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sumo groups in Tokyo and Osaka joined together in 1925 and developed into Dai Nihon Sumo Kyokai (the present-day Nihon Sumo Kyokai (Japan Sumo Association).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sumo groups in Tokyo and Osaka joined together in 1925 and developed into Dai Nihon Sumo Kyokai (the present-day Nihon Sumo Kyokai (Japan Sumo Association).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>形式的にではあるが、「勧進元」という呼称は1944年（昭和19年）まで残り、その名残として地方巡業の主催者のことを勧進元とよぶことが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of the title, Kanjinmoto (backer, promoter), remained until 1944, though only nominally; and it is commonly used as its vistage to refer to the organizer of sumo tournaments in local regions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of the title, Kanjinmoto (backer, promoter), remained until 1944, though only nominally; and it is commonly used in reference to an organizer of sumo tournaments in local regions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of the title, Kanjinmoto (backer, promoter), remained until 1944, though only nominally; and it is commonly used in reference to an organizer of sumo tournaments in local regions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>おどま勧進</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Odoma kanjin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Odoma kanjin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Odoma kanjin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="91">
<j>熊本県球磨郡で歌われた五木の子守歌に</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a traditional lullaby called Itsuki no komoriuta Song sung in Kuma Gun, Kumamoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a traditional lullaby called the &quot;Itsuki no komoriuta&quot; song, which sung in Kuma Gun, Kumamoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a traditional lullaby called the &quot;Itsuki no komoriuta&quot; song, which sung in Kuma Gun, Kumamoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>おどま かんじん かんじん あん人たちゃ よかしゅ よかしゃ よかおび よかきもん</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Odoma kanjin kanjin anhitota sha yokashu yokasha yoka obi yoka kimon&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Odoma kanjin kanjin anhitota sha yokashu yokasha yoka obi yoka kimon&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Odoma kanjin kanjin anhitota cha yokashu yokasha yoka obi yoka kimon&quot;</e>
<cmt>スペース削除スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="93">
<j>という歌詞が出てくる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The song bigins with these words.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The song begins with these words:</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The song begins with these words:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>ここに出てくる「かんじん」とは勧進のことであり、ここでは「物乞い」「乞食」という意味で用いられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kanjin&quot; in this lyrics is kanjin described in this section and refers to a beggar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kanjin&quot; in this lyric is kanjin, as described in this section, and refers to a beggar.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanjin&apos; in this lyric is kanjin, as described in this section, and refers to a beggar.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>歌の意味は「私は乞食のようなものだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These words means that I am just like a beggar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These words means that I am just like a beggar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These words means that I am just like a beggar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>（それにくらべて）あの人たちは良か衆（お金持ち、旦那衆）で、良い帯を締めて立派な着物を着ている」となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(In contrast) those guys (rish masters) wear better kimono and obi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(In contrast) those guys (rich masters) wear better kimono and obi.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(In contrast) those guys (rich masters) wear better kimono and obi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="97">
<j>伝承によれば、治承寿永の戦いに敗れた平氏一族が五家荘（八代市）に定着したので、鎌倉幕府は梶原氏や土肥氏など東国の武士を送って隣の五木村に住まわせ、平氏の動向を監視させたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a folklore, the Taira clan, which were defeated in isho-Juei no ran (Jisho-Juei War) settled in Gokanosho (Yatsushiro-City), and the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) sent their samurai warriors to its next village Itsuki Mura Village to live there for keeping tabs on activities of the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to folklore, the Taira clan, which was defeated in Isho-Juei no ran (Jisho-Juei War), settled in Gokanosho (Yatsushiro-City), and the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) sent samurai warriors to the next village, Itsuki Mura, to live there as a means of keeping tabs on the activities of the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to folklore, the Taira clan, which was defeated in Jisho-Juei no ran (Jisho-Juei War), settled in Gokanosho (Yatsushiro-City), and the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) sent samurai warriors such as Kajiwara clan and Dohi clan to the next village, Itsuki Mura, to live there as a means of keeping tabs on the activities of the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>スペルsuch as Kajiwara clan and Dohi clan 補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>その後、これら武士の子孫を中心として「三十三人衆」と呼ばれる地主層が形成され、「かんじん」と呼ばれた小作人（名子小作）たちは田畑はもちろん、家屋敷から農具に至るまで旦那衆から借り受けて生計を立てなくてはならなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In later years, the landowner class called Sanju-san-nin shu was formed mainly by the offspring of these samurai warriors, and kosakuninn (nago kosaku (tenant farmers in a lower class)) called kanjin have to borrow not only rice fields and vegetable fields but also houses and farm tools from masters to make their living.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In later years, the landowner class called Sanju-san-nin shu was formed mainly by the offspring of these samurai warriors, and kosakuninn (nago kosaku (tenant farmers of a lower class)) called kanjin had to borrow not only rice fields and vegetable fields but also houses and farm tools from masters in order to earn a living.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In later years, the landowner class called Sanju-san-nin shu was formed mainly by the offspring of these samurai warriors, and kosakunin (nago kosaku (tenant farmers of a lower class)) called kanjin had to borrow not only rice fields and vegetable fields but also houses and farm tools from masters in order to earn a living.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>娘たちも10歳になると、地主の家や他村へ子守奉公に出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Girls at the age of 10 were sent out to their landlord&apos;s houses or other villages as a live-in baby-sitter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Girls at the age of 10 were sent out to their landlord&apos;s houses or other villages as live-in babysitters.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Girls at the age of 10 were sent out to their landlord&apos;s houses or other villages as live-in babysitters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>この悲哀を歌ったのが「五木の子守歌」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Itsuki no komoriuta Song,&quot; sings this sorrow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Itsuki no komoriuta&quot; song laments this sorrow.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;Itsuki no komoriuta&apos; song laments this sorrow.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), 竃馬(id:102733), Greenland4(id:114494), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>