<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>薬師三尊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yakushi sanzon, Yakushi triad</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yakushi sanzon, Yakushi triad</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yakushi sanzon, Yakushi triad</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>薬師三尊（やくしさんぞん） は、仏教における仏像安置形式の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yakushi sanzon, Yakushi triad, is one style to place styles of Buddhist image in Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yakushi sanzon, or Yakushi triad, is one of the styles to place Buddhist images in Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yakushi sanzon, or Yakushi triad, is one of the styles to place Buddhist images in Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>スペースを半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>薬師如来を中尊とし、日光菩薩を左脇侍、月光菩薩（がっこうぼさつ）を右脇侍とする三尊形式である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a triad style and consists of Yakushi-Nyorai at the center (Chuson) and two attendant figures (Kyoji), Nikko Bosatsu on the left and Gakko Bosatsu on the right.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a triad style and consists of Yakushi-Nyorai at the center (Chuson) and two attendant figures (Kyoji), Nikko Bosatsu on the left and Gakko Bosatsu on the right.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a triad style and consists of Yakushi-Nyorai (Bhaisajyaguru) at the center (Chuson) and two Kyoji (attendant figures), Nikko Bosatsu (Sunlight Bodhisattva) on the left and Gakko Bosatsu (Moonlight Bodhisattva) on the right.</e>
<cmt>英訳を補足するなどしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>（この場合の「左」「右」は中尊から見た「左」「右」を指す。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The &apos;left&apos; or &apos;right&apos; in this case is the direction seen from Yakushi-Nyorai.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The &apos;left&apos; or &apos;right&apos; in this case is the direction as seen from Yakushi-Nyorai.)</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The &apos;left&apos; or &apos;right&apos; in this case is the direction as seen from Yakushi-Nyorai).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>月光菩薩は月の様な清涼をもって衆生の生死煩悩の焦熱から離れるという意味がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of Gakko Bosatsu means to leave from burning earthly desires for life and death of living things with coolness like the moon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of Gakko Bosatsu means to be free from the burning earthly desires of life and death of living things with the coolness of the moon.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of Gakko Bosatsu means to be free from the burning earthly desires of life and death of living things with the coolness of the moon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="5">
<j>奈良市・薬師寺の金堂本尊像は、日本における薬師三尊像の古例であるとともに、最高傑作の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The statue of principal image of Buddha at Kondo (golden hall) in Yakushi-ji Temple in Nara City is an old example of Yakushi sanzon statue and one of the masterpieces in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The statue of the principal image of Buddha at Kondo (Golden Hall) in Yakushi-ji Temple in Nara City is an old example of Yakushi sanzon statues and is one of the masterpieces in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The statue of the principal image of Buddha at Kondo (Golden Hall) in Yakushi-ji Temple in Nara City is an old example of Yakushi sanzon statues and is one of the masterpieces in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="6">
<j>薬師寺像のように、中尊を坐像、脇侍を立像とするのが一般的だが、法隆寺大講堂像のように、中尊、脇侍ともに坐像とする場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally Chuson was made as seated statue and Kyoji were made as standing statues like the statue of Yakushi-ji Temple, but in some cases both Chuson and Kyoji were made as seated statues such as Horyu-ji Temple Daikodo Lecture Hall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, Chuson was made as a seated statue and Kyoji were made as standing statues like the statue of Yakushi-ji Temple, but in some cases both Chuson and Kyoji were made as seated statues such as in the Horyu-ji Temple Daikodo Lecture Hall.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, Chuson was made as a sedentary statue and Kyoji were made as standing statues like the statues of Yakushi-ji Temple, but in some cases both Chuson and Kyoji were made as sedentary statues such as in the Daikodo Lecture Hall of Horyu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>表記などを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="7">
<j>日光菩薩・月光菩薩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nikko Bosatsu and Gakko Bosatsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nikko Bosatsu and Gakko Bosatsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nikko Bosatsu and Gakko Bosatsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>日光菩薩・月光菩薩は『薬師本願経』に、薬師如来の浄土である東方瑠璃光世界の主要な菩薩であるとして言及されるが、薬師如来の脇侍として造像される以外に、日光菩薩・月光菩薩単独での信仰や造像はないと言ってよい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nikko Bosatsu and Gakko Bosatsu are described as the main Buddha in the Buddhist paradise of Yakushi-Nyorai, the realm known as Joruri or Pure Lapis Lazuli in the eastern quarter, Vaiduryanirbhasa in Sanskrit in &quot;Yakushi Hongan-kyo Sutra&quot;, and it could be said that there is neither faith nor statue of Nikko Bosatsu and Gakko Bosatsu individually other than the statues of Kyoji of Yakushi-Nyorai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nikko Bosatsu and Gakko Bosatsu are described as the main Buddha in the Buddhist paradise of Yakushi-Nyorai, the realm known as Joruri or Pure Lapis Lazuli in the eastern quarter, Vaiduryanirbhasa in Sanskrit in &quot;Yakushi Hongan-kyo Sutra&quot;, and it can be said that there is neither faith nor statues of Nikko Bosatsu and Gakko Bosatsu individually, other than the statues of the Kyoji of Yakushi-Nyorai.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nikko Bosatsu and Gakko Bosatsu are described as the main Buddha in the Buddhist paradise of Yakushi-Nyorai, the realm known as Joruri or Pure Lapis Lazuli in the eastern quarter, Vaiduryanirbhasa in Sanskrit in &quot;Yakushi Hongan-kyo Sutra,&quot; and it can be said that there is neither faith nor statues of Nikko Bosatsu and Gakko Bosatsu individually, other than the statues of the Kyoji of Yakushi-Nyorai.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="9">
<j>図像的には、日光・月光菩薩がそれぞれ日輪・月輪を持つ例が多いが、奈良・薬師寺金堂像のように、古い作例では持物のない場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the point of iconography, each Nikko and Gakko Bosatsu often has the sun and the moon but there is an old case that they have no belongings like the statue at Kondo in Yakushi-ji Temple in Nara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the viewpoint of iconography, each Nikko and Gakko Bosatsu often has the sun and the moon, but there are old cases where they have no belongings, like the statue at the Kondo in Yakushi-ji Temple in Nara.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the viewpoint of iconography, each Nikko and Gakko Bosatsu often has the sun disc and the moon disc, but there are old cases where they have no belongings, like the statue at the Kondo hall in Yakushi-ji Temple in Nara.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="10">
<j>なお、日光・月光菩薩が薬師如来以外の像の脇侍になっている場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, in some cases Nikko and Gakko Bosatsu are places as Kyoji of other statue except Yakushi-Nyorai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, in some cases Nikko and Gakko Bosatsu are Kyoji in place of other statues except at Yakushi-Nyorai.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, in some cases Nikko and Gakko Bosatsu are Kyoji in place of other statues except at Yakushi-Nyorai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>和歌山県・道成寺の本尊千手観音像の脇侍が日光・月光菩薩と呼ばれているのはその例である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, the Kyoji of Senju Kannon (Sahasrabhuja-arya-avalokites &apos;vara, &quot;Thousand-armed Kannon&quot; or Kannon with a thousand arms) Statue, the principal image of Buddha in Dojo-ji Temple in Wakayama Prefecture, are Nikko and Gakko Bosatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, the Kyoji of Senju Kannon (Sahasrabhuja-arya-avalokites &apos;vara, &quot;Thousand-armed Kannon&quot; or Kannon with a thousand arms) Statue, the principal image of Buddha at Dojo-ji Temple in Wakayama Prefecture, are Nikko and Gakko Bosatsu.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, the Kyoji of Senju Kannon (Sahasrabhuja-arya-avalokites &apos;vara, &quot;Thousand-armed Kannon&quot; or Kannon with a thousand arms) Statue, the principal image of Buddha at Dojo-ji Temple in Wakayama Prefecture, are Nikko and Gakko Bosatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="12">
<j>奈良・東大寺法華堂（三月堂）本尊不空羂索観音像の両脇に立つ、塑造日光菩薩・月光菩薩像は天平彫刻の名作として著名であるが、本来の像名は不明で、当初から日光・月光菩薩として造立されたものではないようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nikko Bosatsu and Gakko Bosatsu statues which are placed on the both sides of Fukukensaku Kannon, (Fukukenjaku Kannon), the principal image at Todai-ji Temple Hokke-do (Sangatsudo) in Nara are famous as masterpieces of Tempyo sculpture but the original name of statues are not known and they seems not to have been shaped as Nikko and Gakko Bosatsu since the beginning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nikko Bosatsu and Gakko Bosatsu statues which are placed on both sides of Fukukensaku Kannon, (Fukukenjaku Kannon), the principal image at Todai-ji Temple Hokke-do (Sangatsudo) in Nara are famous as masterpieces of Tempyo sculpture but the original names of the statues are not known and they seem to have not been shaped as Nikko and Gakko Bosatsu from the beginning.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nikko Bosatsu and Gakko Bosatsu statues which are placed on both sides of Fukukensaku Kannon, (or Fukukenjaku Kannon, Never Empty Lasso Kannon (deity of Mercy)), the principal image at Hokke-do (Sangatsudo) of Todai-ji Temple in Nara are famous as masterpieces of Tenpyo sculpture (style of sculpture created in Tenpyo period) but the original names of the statues are not known and they seem to have not been shaped as Nikko and Gakko Bosatsu from the beginning.</e>
<cmt>英訳を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Yanahan(id:2437), Youtetsu(id:7844), Chi-Ham(id:143515), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Urania(id:7213), くっちゃめ(id:86793), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>