<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>卍山道白</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dohaku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dohaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dohaku MANZAN</e>
<cmt>original列をシート名の文字列にし変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>卍山道白（まんざんどうはく。寛永11年（1635年）-正徳 (日本)5年（1715年））は江戸初期の曹洞宗僧侶。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dohaku MANZAN (1635 - 1715) was a priest of Soto Sect who was active in the early Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dohaku MANZAN (1635 - 1715) was a priest of Soto Sect who was active in the early Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dohaku MANZAN (1635 - 1715) was a priest of Soto Sect in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>備後国（現在の広島県）出身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He hailed from Bingo-no-Kuni (Hiroshima Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He hailed from Bingo-no-Kuni (Hiroshima Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was originally from Bingo Province (present Hiroshima Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>俗姓は藤井氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His secular surname was Fujii clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His secular surname was Fujii.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His secular surname was Fujii.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>復古道人と号する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Go (pen name) was Dojin FUKKO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Go (pen name) was Dojin FUKKO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Go (pen name) was Dojin FUKKO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>10歳で龍興寺の一線道播について得度。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the age of 10, he entered the Buddhist priesthood under the guidance of Dohan ISSEN of Ryuko-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the age of 10, he entered the Buddhist priesthood under the guidance of Dohan ISSEN of Ryuko-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the age of 10, he entered the Buddhist priesthood under the guidance of Dohan ISSEN of Ryuko-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>龍興寺を退任した道播にしたがって東下する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Dohan resigned from the post of Ryuko-ji Temple, Dohaku accompanied him and went to the east region of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Dohan resigned from the post at Ryuko-ji Temple, Dohaku accompanied him and went to the east region of Japan.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Dohan resigned from the post at Ryuko-ji Temple, Dohaku accompanied him and went to the east region of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>高秀文春、月舟宗胡らの下に参禅。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He practiced Zen meditation under Bunshun KOSHU and Soko GESSHU.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He practiced Zen meditation under Bunshun KOSHU and Soko GESSHU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He practiced Zen meditation under Bunshun KOSHU and Soko GESSHU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>月舟宗胡の法を嗣ぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He succeeded the teachings of Soko GESSHU.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He succeeded the teachings of Soko GESSHU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He succeeded the teachings of Soko GESSHU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>宗胡の後席として加賀国（現在の石川県）大乗寺の住職となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the successor of Soko, he became the chief priest of Daijo-ji Temple in Kaga-no-Kuni (Ishikawa Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the successor of Soko, he became the chief priest of Daijo-ji Temple in Kaga-no-Kuni (Ishikawa Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the successor of Soko, he assumed the position of the chief priest of Daijo-ji Temple in Kaga Province (present Ishikawa Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>師僧宗胡、面山瑞方らと共に宗統復興を唱え宗門の嗣法・規矩の更正に尽力した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Along with his mentor priest Soko and Zuiho MENZAN, he advocated the restoration of sect&apos;s tradition and strived for the rehabilitation of shiho (succession of the lineage of sect) and kiku (regulations) in the sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Along with his mentor priest Soko and Zuiho MENZAN, he advocated the restoration of the sect&apos;s tradition and strived for the rehabilitation of shiho (succession of the lineage of sect) and kiku (regulations) in the sect.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Along with his mentor priest Soko and Zuiho MENZAN, he advocated the restoration of the sect&apos;s tradition and strived for the rehabilitation of shiho (succession of the lineage of sect) and kiku (regulations) in the sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>当時の曹洞宗では師僧から弟子に面授される法統（人法）の他に、寺院の住職を継ぐことによって伝えられる法統（伽藍法）があるとされ、両者の混乱から様々な弊害を生じていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the then Soto Sect, other than Hoto (the lineage of sect) that is inherited from a mentor priest to a disciple by means of menju (face to face transmission) (nin-po), there also was the another Hoto that is inherited by means of succeeding the position of chief priest of a temple (garan-ho), and under such circumstances, there were a variety of abuses resulting from such confusions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the then Soto Sect, other than Hoto (the lineage of sect) that is inherited from a mentor priest to a disciple by means of menju (face to face transmission) (nin-po), there was also another Hoto that is inherited by means of succeeding the position of chief priest of a temple (garan-ho), and under such circumstances, there were a variety of abuses resulting from such confusion.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Soto Sect at that time, other than Hoto (the lineage of sect) that was inherited from a mentor priest to a disciple by means of menju (face to face transmission) (nin-po), there was also another Hoto that was inherited by means of succeeding the position of chief priest of a temple (garan-ho), and under such circumstances, there were a variety of abuses resulting from such confusion.</e>
<cmt>過去形にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>これに対し、道白らは宗祖道元が尊重した一師印証の面授嗣法（人法）のみを正統とするべきであると訴えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under such circumstances, Dohaku etc. asserted that only menju shiho of isshi-insho (a rule that a priest who received menju from his mentor priest shall not change his mentor priest all his life) (nin-po), which the founder Dogen valued, should be regarded as legitimate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under such circumstances, Dohaku etc. asserted that only menju shiho of isshi-insho (a rule whereby a priest who received menju from his mentor priest shall not change his mentor priest during his whole life) (nin-po), which the founder Dogen valued, should be regarded as legitimate.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under such circumstances, Dohaku and others asserted that only menju shiho of isshi-insho (a rule whereby a priest who received menju from his mentor priest shall not change his mentor priest during his whole life) (nin-po), which the founder Dogen valued, should be regarded as legitimate.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>道白らの運動は寺社奉行を動かし、永平寺法度・總持寺法度の制定によって達成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The campaign by Dohaku etc. affected Jisha-bugyo (a commissioner of temples and shrines) and their objectives were accomplished when Eihei-ji Temple law and Soji-ji Temple law were enacted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The campaign by Dohaku etc. affected Jisha-bugyo (a commissioner of temples and shrines) and their objectives were accomplished when Eihei-ji Temple law and Soji-ji Temple law were enacted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The campaign by Dohaku and others affected Jisha-bugyo (a commissioner of temples and shrines) and their objectives were accomplished when Eihei-ji Temple law and Soji-ji Temple law were enacted.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>また、隠元隆きの「黄檗清規」を手本として、乱れを生じていた宗派の規矩を整理、刷新を図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also rearranged and revamped sect&apos;s kiku, which had been corrupted, following Ryuki INGEN&apos;s &quot;Obaku-shingi&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also rearranged and revamped the sect&apos;s kiku, which had been corrupted, following Ryuki INGEN&apos;s &quot;Obaku-shingi&quot;.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also rearranged and revamped the sect&apos;s kiku, which had been corrupted, following Ryuki INGEN&apos;s &apos;Obaku Shingi&apos; (Chinese Characters as Symbols in the Huanboquingui).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>道白の大乗寺は厳正な規矩で知られるようになり「規矩大乗」と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daijo-ji Temple, of which chief priest was Dohaku, became known as the temple of rigid kiku and was called &quot;Kikudaijo&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daijo-ji Temple, of which the chief priest was Dohaku, became known as the temple of rigid kiku and was called &quot;Kikudaijo&quot;.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daijo-ji Temple, of which the chief priest was Dohaku, became known as the temple of rigid kiku and was called &apos;Kikudaijo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>元禄2年（1689年）には永平寺住職晃全が叢規復興にあたって道白らに顧問を要請するなど刷新は宗派内に着実に定着していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1689, Kozen, the chief priest of Eihei-ji Temple, asked Dohaku etc. to become advisors for restoring soki (the rules of the temple) and the reform initiated by Dohuku gradually took root in the sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1689, Kozen, the chief priest of Eihei-ji Temple, asked Dohaku and others to become advisors for restoring soki (the rules of the temple) and the reform initiated by Dohuku gradually took root in the sect.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1689, Kozen, the chief priest of Eihei-ji Temple, asked Dohaku and others to become advisors for restoring soki (the rules of the temple) and the reform initiated by Dohaku gradually took root in the sect.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかし一方で天桂伝尊などが、道元以来の宗規に拠らず他流（黄檗宗）の清規を当てはめようとした道白を「形式主義」と批判し、論争をよんだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Tenkei Denson etc. criticized Dohaku, who tried to apply seiki (regulations) of the other sect (Obaku Sect) instead of traditional regulations established by Dogen, as &quot;formalism&quot; and there were debates among them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Tenkei Denson etc. criticized Dohaku, who tried to apply seiki (regulations) of the other sect (Obaku Sect) instead of traditional regulations established by Dogen, as &quot;formalism&quot; and there were debates amongbetween them.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Tenkei Denson and others criticized Dohaku, who tried to apply seiki (regulations) of the other sect (Obaku Sect) instead of traditional regulations established by Dogen, as &apos;formalism&apos; and there were debates among them.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>これらの論争は曹洞宗における宗学研究、宗典の校訂・出版を活性化させ多くの業績を生む原動力となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These debates, however, activated the study of sect teachings or the revision and publication of sect code and produced a lot of achievements.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These debates, however, activated the study of sect teachings and the revision and publication of sect code, and produced many achievements.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These debates, however, activated the study of sect teachings and the revision and publication of sect code, and produced many achievements in Soto Sect.</e>
<cmt>曹洞宗における、を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>道白自身も大乗寺において道元の『正法眼蔵』の編集を行い、卍山本（89巻本）として現在に残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dohaku himself was engaged in compiling &quot;Shohogenzo&quot; at Daijo-ji Temple and his work 卍Yamabon (89 volumes) is existent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dohaku himself was engaged in compiling &quot;Shohogenzo&quot; at Daijo-ji Temple and his work 卍Yamabon (89 volumes) still exists.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dohaku himself was engaged in compiling &quot;Shohogenzo&quot; (Treasury of the Eye of True Teaching) at Daijo-ji Temple and his work Manzanbon (89 volumes) still exists.</e>
<cmt>補足し、用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="20">
<j>大乗寺を明州珠心にゆずった後、摂津国（現在の大阪府）の興禅寺に隠棲した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After handing over Daijo-ji Temple to Shushin MYOSHU, he lived in seclusion at Kozen-ji Temple in Settsu-no-Kuni (Osaka Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After handing over Daijo-ji Temple to Shushin MYOSHU, he lived in seclusion at Kozen-ji Temple in Settsu-no-Kuni (Osaka Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After handing over Daijo-ji Temple to Shushin MYOSHU, he lived in seclusion at Kozen-ji Temple in Settsu Province (present Osaka Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>元禄7年（1694年）、請われて山城国（現在の京都府）の臨済宗の古刹、源光庵を復興し、曹洞宗にあらためた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1694, he was asked to restore Genkoan Temple, an ancient temple of Rinzai Sect located in Yamashiro-no-Kuni, and converted it to the temple of Soto Sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1694, he was asked to restore Genkoan Temple, an ancient temple of Rinzai Sect located in Yamashiro-no-Kuni, and converted it to a temple of Soto Sect.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1694, he was asked to restore Genkoan Temple, an ancient temple of Rinzai Sect located in Yamashiro Province, and converted it to a temple of Soto Sect.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="22">
<j>道白の高名をきいた霊元天皇が、問法のため招請したが病と称して辞退した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Reigen, who came to know the reputation of Dohaku, invited him for monbo (hearing of Buddhism teachings) but he declined with the excuse of illness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Reigen, who came to know the reputation of Dohaku, invited him for monbo (hearing of Buddhism teachings) but he declined with the excuse of illness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Reigen, who came to know the reputation of Dohaku, invited him for monbo (hearing of Buddhism teachings) but he declined with the excuse of illness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>惜しんだ法皇は手許品の綿を下賜したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Cloistered Emperor who felt regret bestowed cotton which he possessed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Cloistered Emperor, who felt regret, bestowed cotton which he possessed.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Cloistered Emperor, who felt regret, bestowed cotton which he possessed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="24">
<j>正徳5年（1715年）、80歳で病没。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1715, Dohaku died of illness at the age of 80.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1715, Dohaku died of illness at the age of 80.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1715, Dohaku died of illness at the age of 80.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Oxhop(id:2551), Yanahan(id:2437), Kurihaya(id:132524), Kstigarbha(id:13376), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), Charenji(id:7908), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>