<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>ヘダラ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hedara (Eurya japonica)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hedara (Eurya japonica)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hedara</e>
<cmt>タイトルなので補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>ヘダラとは「供物の花」という意味の仏教用語である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The word &quot;Hedara (Eurya japonica)&quot; is a Buddhist terminology which means &apos;the flower for altarage.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The word &quot;Hedara (Eurya japonica)&quot; is a Buddhist terminology which means &apos;the flower for altarage.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word &apos;Hedara&apos; (Eurya japonica) is a Buddhist terminology which means &apos;the flower for altarage.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>京都丹後地方等で、法事や墓参の際、使用するヒサカキ等、華道で言うところの、いわゆる「枝もの」常緑樹を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It refers to the evergreen tree for what you call &apos;Edamono (an evergreen tree which brings out the beauty of flowers)&apos; in Kado flower arrangement such as Eurya japonica which is served at the time of memorial services (Buddhist services) and visits to graves in the Tango region, Kyoto and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It refers to the evergreen tree for what is referred to as &apos;Edamono (an evergreen tree which brings out the beauty of flowers)&apos; in Kado flower arrangement such as Eurya japonica which is served at the time of memorial services (Buddhist services) and visits to graves in the Tango region, Kyoto and others.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It refers to the evergreen tree for what is referred to as &apos;Edamono&apos; (an evergreen tree which brings out the beauty of flowers) in Kado flower arrangement such as Eurya japonica which is served at the time of memorial services (Buddhist services) and visits to graves in the Tango region, Kyoto and other regions.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>供える花とは区別される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is distinguished from the flowers for altarage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is distinguished from the flowers for altarage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is distinguished from the flowers for altarage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>お盆以外はヘダラ（ヒサカキ）を使うのが一般的だが、宮津地方ではお盆の時だけシキミを使うとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Hedara (Eurya japonica) is generally used except Obon festival (a Festival of the Dead or Buddhist All Soul&apos;s Day), it is said that Shikimi (Japanese star anise) is used only in Obon festival in the Miyazu region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Hedara (Eurya japonica) is generally used except for the Obon festival (a Festival of the Dead or Buddhist All Soul&apos;s Day), it is said that Shikimi (Japanese star anise) is used only in Obon festival in the Miyazu region.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Hedara (also known as Hisakaki) is generally used except for the Obon festival (a Festival of the Dead or Buddhist All Souls&apos; Day), it is said that Shikimi (Japanese star anise) is used only in Obon festival in the Miyazu region.</e>
<cmt>前出補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>また、地方によっては、下草、ヘンダラ、ドソク、ビシャコ、とも呼ばれ、宗派によってヘダラは異なると言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it is also called shitakusa (undergrowth), hendara, dosoku and bisyako, depending on the regions, and it is said that the kinds of Hedara are different among Buddhist sects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, it is also called shitakusa (undergrowth), hendara, dosoku and bisyako, depending on the regions, and it is said that the kinds of Hedara differ among Buddhist sects.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, it is also called shitakusa (undergrowth), hendara, dosoku, and bishako, depending on the regions, and it is said that the kinds of Hedara differ among Buddhist sects.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>関東ではこういった風習、名称は聞かれない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kanto region, such customs and names are not heard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kanto region, such customs and names are not heard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kanto region, such customs and names are not heard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>例えば、天橋立が一望できる成相寺に向かう途中で、道沿いに、「ヘダラ取るな」といった注意書きがされた看板を見つけることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, on the way to the Nariai-ji Temple where Amanohashidate can be seen, you can find a signboard on which a note of caution, &apos;Don&apos;t take Hedara,&apos; is written along the road.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, on the way to the Nariai-ji Temple where Amanohashidate can be seen, you can find a signboard on which a note of caution, &apos;Don&apos;t take Hedara,&apos; is written along the road.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, on the way to the Nariai-ji Temple where Amanohashidate can be seen, you can find a signboard on which a note of caution, &apos;Don&apos;t take Hedara,&apos; is written along the road.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>（丹後地方以外ではあまり見られない）これは植物保護の観点からの注意でもあるがヘダラを取りに林へ入ると、ニホンマムシに噛まれるといった危険もあるため、このような看板があるそうである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(This is not often seen in the other regions except Tango region) It is said that such a signboard is set not only for warning people from the viewpoint of the plants preservation but also for a caution against the danger to be bitten by Japanese copperhead in forests at the time of seeking Hedera.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(This is not often seen in other regions except for the Tango region) It is said that such a signboard is set not only to warn people in order to preserve plants, but also to serve as a warning against the danger of being bitten by Japanese copperheads in forests while seeking Hedera.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(This is not often seen in other regions except for the Tango region) It is said that such a signboard is set not only to warn people in order to preserve plants, but also to serve as a warning against the danger of being bitten by Japanese copperheads in forests while seeking Hedara.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>京都府京丹後市網野町に伝わる丹池伝説（あかいけでんせつ）にもヘダラという言葉が登場している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Akaike legend of the Amino-cho, Tango City, Kyoto Prefecture, there is also a word of Hedara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Akaike legend of the Amino-cho, Tango City, Kyoto Prefecture, the word Hedara also exists.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Akaike densetsu legend of the Amino-cho, Tango City, Kyoto Prefecture, the word Hedara also appears.</e>
<cmt>用語を他の記事に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Opponent(id:720), 大王大(id:163364), Moss(id:46638), R28Bot(id:177951), Ikazuchi(id:92573), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>