<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>行意</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gyoi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gyoi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gyoi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>行意（ぎょうい、1177年－1217年?）は、平安時代末から鎌倉時代初期にかけての天台宗の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gyoi (born 1177, died about 1217) was a priest of the Tendai Sect between the end of the Heian Era and the early period of the Kamakura Era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gyoi (born 1177, died about 1217) was a priest of the Tendai Sect between the end of the Heian Era and the early period of the Kamakura Era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gyoi (1177 - 1217 ?) was a priest of the Tendai Sect between the end of the Heian period and the early period of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は関白太政大臣藤原基房。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was FUJIWARA no Motofusa, the Chief Adviser to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was FUJIWARA no Motofusa, the Chief Adviser to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was FUJIWARA no Motofusa, kanpaku (the Chief Adviser to the Emperor) and Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>兄弟に左大臣藤原隆忠、摂政松殿師家、天台座主承円、興福寺別当実尊などがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His siblings include the sadaijin (the minister of left) FUJIWARA no Takatada, the regent Moroie MATSUDONO, the tendai-zasu Shoen, and the steward of Kofuku-ji Temple Jitsuson.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His siblings include the sadaijin (the minister of left) FUJIWARA no Takatada, the regent Moroie MATSUDONO, the tendai-zasu Shoen, and the steward of Kofuku-ji Temple Jitsuson.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His siblings include the sadaijin (the minister of left) FUJIWARA no Takatada, the regent Moroie MATSUDONO, the Tendai-zasu (head priest of the Tendai sect) Shoen, and betto (chief officer) of Kofuku-ji Temple Jitsuson.</e>
<cmt>用語を他の記事に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>山科僧正とも称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also called the archbishop of Yamashina.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also called the archbishop of Yamashina.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also called Yamashina sojo (high-ranking Buddhist priest).</e>
<cmt>用語を他の記事に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>新三十六歌仙の一人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was one of the newly selected thirty-six best kasen poets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was one of the newly selected thirty-six best kasen poets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was one of New thirty-six major poets.</e>
<cmt>用語を他の記事に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>従兄弟にあたる覚尊僧正の室に入り、出家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He entered the room of his cousin, the archbishop of Kakuson, to become a priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He entered the room of his cousin, the archbishop of Kakuson, to become a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He entered the room of his cousin, Kakuson sojo, to become a priest.</e>
<cmt>用語を他の記事に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>1193年（建久4年）一身阿闍梨となり、1197年（建久8年）真円から伝法灌頂を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became an isshin-ajari (a special class of the teaching priests, who are noble and permitted to play role of ajari) in 1193, and received the teachings of Buddhism as well as the enthronement initialtion known as kanjo in 1197.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became an isshin-ajari (a special class of the teaching priests, who are noble and permitted to play role of ajari) in 1193, and received the teachings of Buddhism as well as the enthronement initialtion known as kanjo in 1197.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became an isshin-ajari (a special class of the teaching priests, who are noble and permitted to play role of ajari (a master in esoteric Buddhism; a high priest)) in 1193, and received the teachings of Buddhism as well as denpo-kanjo (the consecration for the Transmission of the Dharma) by Shinen in 1197.</e>
<cmt>用語を他の記事に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>土御門天皇・順徳天皇両天皇の護持僧をつとめ、1204年（元久元年）と1211年（建暦元年）には修明門院藤原重子のために五檀法を修し、1207年（承元元年）には土御門天皇の病気平癒を祈願して北斗法を修している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served as the priest who prayed for the Emperor Tsuchimikado and the Emperor Juntoku, studied Godan-ho Method for Schumeimon-in FUJUWARA no Shigeko in 1204 and 1211, and studied Hokuto-ho Method to pray for the Emperor Tsuchimikado&apos;s recovery from disease in 1207.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served as the priest who prayed for Emperor Tsuchimikado and Emperor Juntoku, studied the Godan-ho method for Schumeimon-in FUJUWARA no Shigeko in 1204 and 1211, and studied the Hokuto-ho method to pray for Emperor Tsuchimikado&apos;s recovery from disease in 1207.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served as the priest who prayed for Emperor Tsuchimikado and Emperor Juntoku, studied the Godan-ho (the five wise men placing method) for Schumeimonin FUJUWARA no Shigeko in 1204 and 1211, and studied the Hokuto-ho (the method based on the stares called the Big Dipper) to pray for Emperor Tsuchimikado&apos;s recovery from disease in 1207.</e>
<cmt>「五檀法」は「五壇法」と解釈しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>1216年（建保4年）には園城寺長吏に任じられ、崇福寺別当を兼任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to the managing priest of Enjo-ji Temple and doubled as the steward of Sufuku-ji Temple in 1216.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed as the managing priest of Enjo-ji Temple and doubled as the steward of Sufuku-ji Temple in 1216.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed as Chori (chief priest) of Onjo-ji Temple and doubled as the betto (head priest) of Sufuku-ji Temple in 1216.</e>
<cmt>用語を他の記事に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>行意は和歌にも秀でており、1214年（建保2年）の内裏歌合などの歌合に参加している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also excelled at waka and joined waka competitions such as the one held in the Imperial Palace in 1214.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also excelled at waka and joined waka competitions such as the one held in the Imperial Palace in 1214.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also excelled at waka and joined waka competitions such as the one held in the Imperial Palace in 1214.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>「新勅撰和歌集」以下の勅撰和歌集にも入集している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His works were selected for &apos;chokusen-waka-shu&apos; (officially selected anthologies of waka) such as &apos;Shin-chokusen-waka-shu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「「新勅撰和歌集」以下の」は「「新勅撰和歌集」などの」の意味に解釈して訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His works were selected for &apos;chokusen-waka-shu&apos; (officially selected anthologies of waka) such as &apos;Shin-chokusen-waka-shu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His works were selected for chokusen waka shu (officially selected anthologies of waka) such as &apos;Shin Chokusen Wakashu&apos; (New Imperial Anthology of Japanese Poetry).</e>
<cmt>用語を他の記事に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Andee(id:20421), TakuyaMurata(id:156), Ks8823(id:130146), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), 日本一弱い男(id:92046), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>