<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>寺請制度</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Terauke Seido&quot; (The System To Force The Public To Become A Buddhist In The Edo Period)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Terauke Seido&quot; (the system of the Edo period that forced the public to become Buddhists)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Terauke Seido</e>
<cmt>タイトルなので、クォーテーション、補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>寺請制度（てらうけせいど）とは、近世初期の1664年（寛文4年）に江戸幕府がキリスト教や不受不施派を禁制として、信徒に対し改宗を強制することを目的として制定された制度。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Terauke seido&quot; was the system that was introduced in the early modern ages in 1664 by the Edo shogunate in order to ban the Christianity and the belief of &quot;Fujufuse Group&quot; (Not Receive and Not Give Group) and to force the believers to convert.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Terauke seido&quot; was a system introduced in 1664, during the early modern age, by the Edo shogunate in order to ban Christianity and the belief of the &quot;Fujufuse Group (Not Receive and Not Give Group),&quot; and to force the believers to convert.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Terauke seido was a system introduced in 1664, during the early modern age, by the Edo shogunate in order to ban Christianity and the belief of Fujufuse Group (Not Receive and Not Give Group), and to force the believers to convert.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>檀家制度（だんかせいど、だんけせいど）、寺檀制度（じだんせいど）とも言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Terauke seido&quot; was also called &quot;danka seido&quot; or &quot;jidan seido.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Terauke seido&quot; was also called &quot;danka seido&quot; or &quot;jidan seido.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Terauke seido was also called danka seido or jidan seido.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>具体的には、仏教の檀信徒であることの証明を寺院から請ける制度である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concretely, it was the system that had all people get the certification of a temple to be a Buddhist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Specifically, it was the system that had every person obtain the certification of their Buddhist faith from a temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Specifically, it was the system that had every person obtain the certification of their Buddhist faith from a temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>寺請制度の確立によって民衆は、いずれかの寺院を菩提寺と定め、その檀家となる事を義務付けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The establishment of terauke seido forced the public to choose a certain temple as their &quot;bodaiji&quot; (family temple) and to become &quot;danka&quot; (supporter of the temple).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The establishment of terauke seido forced the public to choose a certain temple as their &quot;bodaiji&quot; (family temple) and to become &quot;danka&quot; (supporters of the temple).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The establishment of terauke seido forced the public to choose a certain temple as their bodaiji (family temple) and to become danka (supporters of the temple).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>寺院では現在の戸籍に当たる宗門人別帳が作成され、旅行や住居の移動の際にはその証文（寺請証文）が必要とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Temples made up &quot;shumon ninbetsu cho&quot; (religious census register), which is today&apos;s family register, and the public needed to get a deed called &quot;terauke shomon&quot; (certificate of a Buddhist temple) when they set out on their travels or changed their residences.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Temples made up the &quot;shumon ninbetsu cho&quot; (religious census register), which is today&apos;s family register, and the public needed to obtain a deed called the &quot;terauke shomon&quot; (certificate of a Buddhist temple) when they set out on their travels or changed to different residences.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Temples made up Shumon ninbetsu cho (religious census register), which is today&apos;s family register, and the public needed to obtain a deed called Terauke shomon (certificate of a Buddhist temple) when they set out on their travels or changed to different residences.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>各戸には仏壇が置かれ、法要の際には僧侶を招くという慣習が定まり、寺院に一定の信徒と収入を保証される形となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the system introduced, every household had its Buddhist altar and made it a custom to invite a Buddhist priest to its Buddhist memorial service, which assured the temple of its getting believers and money to a certain degree.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the system thus introduced, every household had its Buddhist altar and made it a custom to invite a Buddhist priest to its Buddhist memorial service, which assured the temple of obtaining believers and, to a certain degree, money.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the system thus introduced, every household had its Buddhist altar and made it a custom to invite a Buddhist priest to its Buddhist memorial service, which assured the temple of obtaining believers and, to a certain degree, money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>一方、寺院の側からすれば、檀信徒に対して教導を実施する責務を負わされることとなり、仏教教団が幕府の統治体制の一翼を担うこととなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, the sytem obliged the temple to give religious instructions to its belivers, and had the Buddhist organizations play a role in the regime of the Edo shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, the system obliged the temple to give religious instructions to its believers, and had the Buddhist organizations play a role in the regime of the Edo shogunate.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, the system obliged the temple to give religious instructions to its believers, and had the Buddhist organizations play a role in the regime of the Edo shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>仏教教団側が負った打撃は、本末制度との相乗効果により、上記にとどまらなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the effect of terauke seido and &quot;honmatsu seido&quot; (the hierarchical system to control all temples) combined, the Buddhist organizations suffered other religious setbacks as well.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the combined effect of terauke seido and &quot;honmatsu seido&quot; (the hierarchical system by which to control all temples), the Buddhist organizations suffered other religious setbacks as well.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the combined effect of terauke seido and honmatsu seido (the hierarchical system by which to control all temples), the Buddhist organizations suffered other religious setbacks as well.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>すなわち、従来の教団活動の中で中心に位置していた門派・塔頭の機能を低下させられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is, their &quot;monpa&quot; (division of a Buddhist sect) and &quot;tacchu&quot; (minor temple), both of which played the central role in their Buddhist activities until then, were reduced in their organizational function.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is, their &quot;monpa&quot; (division of a Buddhist sect) and &quot;tacchu&quot; (minor temple), both of which had played the central role in their Buddhist activities, were reduced in their organizational function.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That is, their monpa (division of a Buddhist sect) and tatchu (minor temple), both of which had played the central role in their Buddhist activities, were reduced in their organizational function.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また他宗派の信徒への布教や新しい寺院の建立を禁止されその勢力の拡張が困難になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, they were banned from propagating their teachings to other sects&apos; believers, and from constructing new temples, so it became difficult for them to extend their influence.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, they were banned from propagating their teachings to the believers of other sects and from constructing new temples, so it became difficult for them to extend their influence.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, they were banned from propagating their teachings to the believers of other sects and from constructing new temples, so it became difficult for them to extend their influence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 文姫(id:66661), 伊勢山(id:188062), Mooko(id:36162), Nnh(id:474), Chi-Ham(id:143515), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Kenshiro.com(id:143072), 修理屋(id:131526), Kamakura(id:472), 伏儀(id:142093), TAMA(id:25299), JOQR(id:150111), 遠藤(id:30275), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>