<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>木食応其</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mokujiki Ogo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mokujiki Ogo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mokujiki Ogo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>木食応其（もくじきおうご、天文 (元号)5年（1536年）- 慶長13年10月1日 (旧暦)（1608年11月8日））は、安土桃山時代の真言宗の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mokujiki Ogo (1536-November 8, 1608) is a priest of Shingon sect in the Azuchi Momoyama Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mokujiki Ogo (1536-November 8, 1608) was a priest of the Shingon sect during the Azuchi Momoyama Period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mokujiki Ogo (1536 - November 8, 1608) was a priest of the Shingon sect during the Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>スペースを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>字は深覚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His azana (adult males nickname) was Shinkaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His azana (adult male nickname) was Shinkaku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His azana (adult male nickname) was Shinkaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>近江国の出身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ogo was from Omi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ogo was from Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ogo was from Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>もともとは越智阿波守の武士であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ogo was originally a samurai serving for Ochi Awa no kuni no kami (Governor of Awa Province).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ogo was originally a samurai serving for Ochi Awa no kuni no kami (Governor of Awa Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ogo was originally a samurai serving for Ochi Awa no kuni no kami (Governor of Awa Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>天正元年（1573年）に38歳で高野山において出家し、宝性院の政遍から受戒している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1573, Ogo entered into priesthood in the Koya-san Mountain at the age of 38 and received religious precepts from 政遍 of Hoshoin.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「政遍」読み不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1573, Ogo entered the priesthood on Koya-san Mountain at the age of 38 and received religious precepts from 政遍 of Hoshoin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1573, Ogo entered the priesthood on Mt. Koya at the age of 38 and received religious precepts from 政遍 of Hosho-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>Mt. Koya としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>（逆に政遍を受戒したという説もあり。未だ詳細は不明。京都は新京極にある誓願寺の勧進聖であったという説も有力。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(According to another theory, it was Ogo who gave religious precepts to 政遍.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(According to another theory, it was Ogo who gave religious precepts to 政遍.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(According to another theory, it was Ogo who gave religious precepts to 政遍. Details are yet to be known.In Kyoto, it is generally believed that it was one Kanjin Hijiri (fund-raising priests) of Seigan-ji Temple in Shinkyogoku, Kyoto.)</e>
<cmt>括弧内なので、セル10、11、12を全部ここにまとめました。京都　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>なお高野山入山のおり、十穀を絶つ穀断ちを行うことを発願している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon entering into the Koya-san Mountain, at the wish to attain enlightenment, Ogo practiced kokudachi training (training of eating no grains) by not eating various grains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon entering Koya-san Mountain, with the wish to attain enlightenment, Ogo practiced kokudachi training (training of eating no grain) by not eating various types grain.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon entering Mt. Koya, with the wish to attain enlightenment, Ogo practiced kokudachi (training of eating no grain) by not eating various types of grain.</e>
<cmt>Mt. Koya としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>その後は興山寺に住した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ogo spent the rest of his life at Kozan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ogo spent the rest of his life at Kozan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ogo spent the rest of his life at Kozan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>全国を行脚し寺社の勧進につとめる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went on a pilgrimage all over Japan, soliciting for contributions for temples.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He went on a pilgrimage all over Japan, soliciting for contributions for temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He went on a pilgrimage all over Japan, soliciting for contributions for temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>天正13年（1585年）豊臣秀吉が根来寺に攻め込んだ際には、秀吉との和議に臨んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI attacked Negoro-ji Temple in 1585, Ogo engaged in the negotiation process with Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI attacked Negoro-ji Temple in 1585, Ogo engaged in the negotiation process with Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI attacked Negoro-ji Temple in 1585, Ogo engaged in the negotiation process with Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その結果、高野山の復興援助を得、秀吉は高野山に金堂や大塔を建立し、高野山の再興にあたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently, Hideyoshi agreed to provide support for reconstruction of the Koya-san Mountain and founded Kon-do Hall (main hall of a Buddhist temple) and Daito pagoda at the Koya-san Mountain, contributing to revival of the Koya-san Mountain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, Hideyoshi agreed to provide support for the reconstruction of Koya-san Mountain and founded the Kon-do Hall (main hall of a Buddhist temple) and Daito pagoda on Koya-san Mountain, contributing to the revival of the Koya-san Mountain.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, Hideyoshi agreed to provide support for the reconstruction of Mt. Koya and founded the Kon-do Hall (main hall of a Buddhist temple) and Daito pagoda on Mt. Koya, contributing to the revival of Mt. Koya.</e>
<cmt>Mt. Koya としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その一方で応其も秀吉の方広寺造営に際しては協力している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In turn, Ogo helped Hideyoshi when Hideyoshi was building Hoko-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In turn, Ogo helped Hideyoshi when Hideyoshi was building Hoko-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In turn, Ogo helped Hideyoshi when Hideyoshi was building Hoko-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>天正15年（1587年）、秀吉と島津氏との和睦交渉での力を尽くした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1587, Ogo made effort to complete the reconciliatory negotiation between Hideyoshi and Shimazu clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1587, Ogo made an effort to complete the reconciliatory negotiation between Hideyoshi and the Shimazu clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1587, Ogo made an effort to complete the reconciliatory negotiation between Hideyoshi and the Shimazu clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>関ヶ原の戦いでは豊臣家との縁の深さから、近江国の大津城（守将：京極高次）や伊勢国の津城（守将：富田信高）における開城交渉にあたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the battle of Sekigahara, from his strong tie with the Toyotomi family, Ogo worked as a negotiator upon surrenders of the Otsu-jo Castle of Omi province (represented by Takatsugu KYOGOKU, defense general) and of the Tsu-jo Castle of Ise Province (represented by Nobutaka TOMITA, defense general).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the battle of Sekigahara, from his strong ties with the Toyotomi family, Ogo worked as a negotiator upon surrender of Otsu-jo Castle in Omi province (represented by Takatsugu KYOGOKU, defense general) and of Tsu-jo Castle in Ise Province (represented by Nobutaka TOMITA, defense general).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the battle of Sekigahara, from his strong ties with the Toyotomi family, Ogo worked as a negotiator upon surrender of Otsu-jo Castle in Omi Province (represented by Takatsugu KYOGOKU, defense general) and of Tsu-jo Castle in Ise Province (represented by Nobutaka TOMITA, defense general).</e>
<cmt>Province 大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>戦後は近江国飯道寺に隠棲し、入定。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the battle, Ogo went into a seclusion at Hando-ji Temple of Omi Province and fell into deep meditation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the battle, Ogo went into a seclusion at Hando-ji Temple of Omi Province and fell into deep meditation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the battle, Ogo went into a seclusion at Hando-ji Temple of Omi Province and fell into deep meditation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>高野山奥の院に程近い場所に廟所がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The mausoleum is laid close to Oku no in (inner sanctuary) of the Koya-san Mountain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The mausoleum is close to Oku no in (inner sanctuary) of Koya-san Mountain.</e>
<cmt>grammar, word spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The mausoleum is close to Okunoin cemetery of Mt. Koya.</e>
<cmt>Okunoin cemetery としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>応其寺（元は惣福寺）は和歌山県橋本市にあり、橋本町（当時）を開発、現在の高野山の麓としての橋本市の礎を築いたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ogo-ji Temple (originally, Sofuku-ji Temple) is in Hashimoto City of Wakayama Prefecture, contributing to the development of (then) Hashimoto-cho and founding the basis of Hashimoto City as the foot of the Koya-san Mountain now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ogo-ji Temple (originally, Sofuku-ji Temple) is in Hashimoto City of Wakayama Prefecture, contributing to the development of (then) Hashimoto-cho and founding the basis of Hashimoto City at the foot of the Koya-san Mountain now.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ogo-ji Temple (originally, Sofuku-ji Temple) is in Hashimoto City of Wakayama Prefecture, contributing to the development of (then) Hashimoto-cho and founding the basis of Hashimoto City at the foot of Mt. Koya now.</e>
<cmt>Mt. Koya としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>橋本は市内を流れる紀ノ川に架けた橋にちなんで付けられた地名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hashimoto was named after the bridge (hashi) crossing of the Kinokawa River that runs in the city.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hashimoto was named after the bridge (hashi) crossing of the Kinokawa River in the city.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hashimoto was named after the bridge (hashi) crossing of the Kino-kawa River in the city.</e>
<cmt>Kino-kawa としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="19">
<j>連歌の名手でもあり、当代きっての連歌の名手である、里村紹巴と親交があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ogo was a master of renga (linked verses) and had a close friendship with Joha SATOMURA, who was the best renga poet of the era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ogo was a master of renga (linked verses) and had a close friendship with Joha SATOMURA, who was the best renga poet of the era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ogo was a master of renga (linked verses) and had a close friendship with Joha SATOMURA, who was the best renga poet of the era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>そこから豊臣秀吉への繋がりを得たと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ogo&apos;s relationship with Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI is believed to have started with his friendship with Joha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ogo&apos;s relationship with Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI is believed to have started with his friendship with Joha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ogo&apos;s relationship with Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI is believed to have started with his friendship with Joha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="21">
<j>平成20年（2008年）は木食応其の没後400年遠忌に当たり、和歌山県立博物館にて、特別展が開催された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 2008, which was the 400th anniversary of the death of Mokujiki Ogo, a special exposition was convened at the Wakayama prefectural museum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 2008, which was the 400th anniversary of the death of Mokujiki Ogo, a special exposition was convened at the Wakayama prefectural museum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 2008, which was the 400th anniversary of the death of Mokujiki Ogo, a special exposition was convened at the Wakayama prefectural museum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>(2008年10月18日～2008年11月24日)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(October 18-November 24, 2008)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(October 18-November 24, 2008)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(October 18-November 24, 2008)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 M-sho-gun(id:88956), 田英(id:85936), Dr jimmy(id:111486), Mooko(id:36162), たね(id:10372), R28Bot(id:177951), Kanjy(id:36859), Nighthawks(id:36125), Point136(id:211299), トホホ川(id:50502), 11ChamOK(id:100638), 歴史研究家(id:108842), KENPEI(id:11349), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>