<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>一字金輪仏頂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ichiji Kinrin Butcho (a Buddhist deity with a golden wheel, represented by a sacred Sanskrit syllable)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ichiji Kinrin Butcho (a Buddhist deity with a golden wheel, represented by a sacred Sanskrit syllable)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ichiji Kinrin Buccho (a Buddhist deity with a golden wheel, represented by a sacred Sanskrit syllable)</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>一字金輪仏頂 （いちじきんりんぶっちょう）、サンスクリットエーカークシャラ・ウシュニーシャチャクラ (ekaakSara-uSNiiSacakra)は仏頂尊の一尊。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ichiji Kinrin Butcho (ekaakSara-uSNiiSacakra in Sanskrit) is one of the deities worshipped in Esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ichiji Kinrin Butcho (ekaakSara-uSNiiSacakra in Sanskrit) is one of the deities worshipped in Esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ichiji Kinrin Buccho (ekaakSara-uSNiiSacakra in Sanskrit) is one of the deities worshipped in Esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>深い瞑想の境地に至った如来が説いた一字の真言ボロン(bhruuM)を神格化したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a deity specifically associated with the sacred Sanskrit syllable, &quot;bhruuM,&quot; which was uttered by Shakyamuni to verbalize his thought while he was absorbed in profound meditation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s a deity specifically associated with the sacred Sanskrit syllable, &quot;bhruuM,&quot; which was uttered by Shakyamuni to verbalize his thought while he was absorbed in profound meditation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s a deity specifically associated with the sacred Sanskrit syllable, &quot;bhruuM,&quot; which was uttered by Shakyamuni to verbalize his thought while he was absorbed in profound meditation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>一字とは梵字一文字で表せるボロンを真言とすることに由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sanskrit syllable, &quot;bhruuM,&quot; is a single-syllable invocation word that represents the ultimate truth of the universe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sanskrit syllable &quot;bhruuM&quot; is an invocation word that represents the ultimate truth of the universe.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sanskrit syllable &quot;bhruuM&quot; is an invocation word that represents the ultimate truth of the universe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>金輪とは転輪聖王のうち最も優れた金輪王を意味し、仏頂尊の霊験が極めて優れたことを譬えたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The word &quot;kinrin&quot; (meaning golden wheel in Japanese), which refers to the highest king among the four sacred kings that rule the universe, symbolizes the miraculous power of this deity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The word &quot;kinrin&quot; (meaning golden wheel in Japanese), which refers to the highest king among the four sacred kings that rule the universe, symbolizes the miraculous power of this deity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word &quot;kinrin&quot; (meaning golden wheel in Japanese), which refers to the highest king among the four sacred kings that rule the universe, symbolizes the miraculous power of this deity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>そのため一字金輪曼荼羅では、転輪聖王が従えるという七つの宝（金輪、如意宝珠、女宝、馬宝、象宝、主蔵宝、主兵神宝）が、一字金輪仏頂と共に描かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, in mandalas that represent Ichiji Kinrin Butcho, seven treasures (a golden wheel, a Buddhist rosary, a queen, a horse, an elephant, a god of wealth and a god of war) that are believed to be possessed by the four sacred kings are depicted together with the deity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, in the mandalas that represent Ichiji Kinrin Butcho, seven treasures (a golden wheel, a Buddhist rosary, a queen, a horse, an elephant, a god of wealth and a god of war) that are believed to be possessed by the four sacred kings are depicted together with the deity.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, in the mandalas that represent Ichiji Kinrin Buccho, seven treasures (a golden wheel, a Buddhist rosary, a queen, a horse, an elephant, a god of wealth and a god of war) that are believed to be possessed by the four sacred kings are depicted together with the deity.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>所依の経典により、如来形の釈迦金輪（しゃかきんりん）と大日金輪（だいにちきんりん）の二つの姿が説かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Depending on different Buddhist sutras, Ichiji Kinrin Butcho is represented in two different forms - one as Shaka Kinrin (Shakyamuni Buddha with a golden wheel) and another as Dainichi Kinrin (great cosmic Buddha with a golden wheel).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ichiji Kinrin Butcho is represented in two different forms, depending on the Buddhist sutra: one as Shaka Kinrin (Shakyamuni Buddha with a golden wheel) and another as Dainichi Kinrin (great cosmic Buddha with a golden wheel).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ichiji Kinrin Buccho is represented in two different forms, depending on the Buddhist sutra: one as Shaka Kinrin (Shakyamuni Buddha with a golden wheel) and another as Dainichi Kinrin (great cosmic Buddha with a golden wheel).</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>釈迦金輪</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shaka Kinrin (Shakyamuni Buddha with a golden wheel)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shaka Kinrin (Shakyamuni Buddha with a golden wheel)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shaka Kinrin (Shakyamuni Buddha with a golden wheel)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>釈迦金輪は、釈迦如来所変の仏頂尊とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shaka Kinrin is believed to be a deity derived from Shaka Nyorai (Shakyamuni Buddha).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shaka Kinrin is believed to be a deity derived from Shaka Nyorai (Shakyamuni Buddha).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shaka Kinrin is believed to be a deity derived from Shaka Nyorai (Shakyamuni Buddha).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>三昧耶形は八輻輪(8本のスポークのある輪宝)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A wheel with eight spokes is the divine symbol that represents this deity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A wheel with eight spokes is the divine symbol that represents this deity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A wheel with eight spokes is the divine symbol that represents this deity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>種子 (密教)はボロン(bhruuM)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sanskrit syllable thought to contain the essence (seed) of Shaka Kinrin in Esoteric Buddhism is bhruuM.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sanskrit syllable thought to contain the essence (seed) of Shaka Kinrin in Esoteric Buddhism is bhruuM.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sanskrit syllable thought to contain the essence (seed) of Shaka Kinrin in Esoteric Buddhism is bhruuM.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="11">
<j>その姿は、実際の造形例では螺髪の通常の如来形で赤い衣服を纏う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shaka Kinrin is ordinarily depicted as a figure with crinkly hair wearing red clothes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shaka Kinrin is ordinarily depicted as a figure with crinkly hair wearing red clothes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shaka Kinrin is ordinarily depicted as a figure with crinkly hair wearing red clothes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>印相は定印にしてその両手の上に輪宝を乗せ、須弥山の上の月輪(全身を取り囲む白い光背)または日輪（赤い月輪）の中に座しているものが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In many representations, Shaka Kinrin is sitting on a sacred mountain surrounded by a ring of moonlight (a white halo surrounding the entire figure) or sunlight (a red halo), holding a golden wheel in its hands placed in the meditation mudra.</e>
<cmt>定印は&quot;meditation mudra&quot;と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In many representations, Shaka Kinrin is seated on a sacred mountain surrounded by a ring of moonlight (a white halo surrounding the entire figure) or sunlight (a red halo), holding a golden wheel in its hands, which are held in the meditation mudra.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In many representations, Shaka Kinrin is seated on a sacred mountain surrounded by a ring of moonlight (a white halo surrounding the entire figure) or sunlight (a red halo), holding a golden wheel in its hands, which are held in the meditation mudra.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また、光背の周縁に輪宝を巡らせてある場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sometimes the figure is depicted with a golden wheel surrounding the halo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sometimes the figure is depicted with a golden wheel surrounding the halo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sometimes the figure is depicted with a golden wheel surrounding the halo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="14">
<j>一方『陀羅尼集経第一』（大正新脩大蔵経No.901）には「体色は金色で七宝冠を戴き全身から光を放つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, the first volume of the Collection of Buddhist Sutras (Collection of Buddhist Sutras edited during the Taisho period, No. 901) describes Shaka Kinrin as a golden figure wearing a crown decorated with seven treasures and emitting light from its body.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, the first volume of the Collection of Buddhist Sutras (No 901, collection of Buddhist sutras edited during the Taisho period) describes Shaka Kinrin as a golden figure wearing a crown decorated with seven treasures and emitting light from its body.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, the first volume of the &quot;Collection of Buddhist Sutras&quot; (No 901, collection of Buddhist sutras edited during the Taisho period) describes Shaka Kinrin as a golden figure wearing a crown decorated with seven treasures and emitting light from its body.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>印を結んで七宝で飾られた蓮の花の上に結跏趺坐する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the description in this sutra, the figure represents a Buddhist deity sitting in a lotus position on a lotus throne decorated with seven treasures, with its hands held in a prayer position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the description given in this sutra, the figure represents a Buddhist deity seated in a lotus position on a lotus throne decorated with seven treasures, with its hands held in a prayer position.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the description given in this sutra, the figure represents a Buddhist deity seated in a lotus position on a lotus throne decorated with seven treasures, with its hands held in a prayer position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>座っている蓮華の下に輪宝、さらにその下に宝池がある」と記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is written in the same sutra that there is a golden wheel beneath its lotus throne and a pond of treasures beneath the golden wheel.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is written in the same sutra that there is a golden wheel beneath its lotus throne and a pond of treasures beneath the golden wheel.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is written in the same sutra that there is a golden wheel beneath its lotus throne and a pond of treasures beneath the golden wheel.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="17">
<j>釈迦金輪はその輪宝で九曜等の天体神を折伏するとされ、宿曜道では凶星のもたらす災いを避ける修法の本尊として重視される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shaka Kinrin is believed to have the ability to subdue star gods using its golden wheel and is worshipped in Indian astrology as a deity that has the magical power to avoid misfortunes caused by ominous stars.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shaka Kinrin is believed to have the ability to subdue star gods using its golden wheel, and it&apos;s worshiped in Indian astrology as a deity that has the magical power to avoid misfortunes caused by ominous stars.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shaka Kinrin is believed to have the ability to subdue star gods such as Kuyo (nine-planet crest) using its golden wheel, and it&apos;s worshiped in Indian astrology as a deity that has the magical power to avoid misfortunes caused by ominous stars.</e>
<cmt>such as Kuyo (nine-planet crest) 補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="18">
<j>大日金輪</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dainichi Kinrin (great cosmic Buddha with a golden wheel)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dainichi Kinrin (great cosmic Buddha with a golden wheel)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dainichi Kinrin (great cosmic Buddha with a golden wheel)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>大日金輪は、大日如来所変の仏頂尊とされ、金剛界大日如来が胎蔵界日輪三昧という瞑想の境地に入って唱えた「ボロン」の神格化とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dainichi Kinrin, which is believed to be a deity derived from great cosmic Buddha (Dainichi Nyorai in Japanese), is a deity associated with the Sanskrit syllable, &quot;bhruuM,&quot; which Dainichi Nyorai of the transcendental world uttered while he was absorbed in profound meditation in the world of physical phenomenon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dainichi Kinrin, which is believed to be a deity derived from the great cosmic Buddha (Dainichi Nyorai in Japanese), is associated with the Sanskrit syllable &quot;bhruuM,&quot; which Dainichi Nyorai of the transcendental world uttered while he was absorbed in profound meditation in the world of physical phenomenon.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dainichi Kinrin, which is believed to be a deity derived from the great cosmic Buddha (Dainichi Nyorai in Japanese), is associated with the Sanskrit syllable &quot;bhruuM,&quot; which Dainichi Nyorai of the transcendental world uttered while he was absorbed in profound meditation in the world of physical phenomenon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="20">
<j>三昧耶形は十二輻輪。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A wheel with twelve spokes is the divine symbol that represents this deity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A wheel with 12 spokes is the divine symbol that represents this deity.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A wheel with 12 spokes is the divine symbol that represents this deity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>種子は釈迦金輪と同じくボロン(bhruuM)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;BhruuM,&quot; the Sanskrit syllable associated with Shaka Kinrin, is also thought to contain the essence (seed) of Dainichi Kinrin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;BhruuM,&quot; the Sanskrit syllable associated with Shaka Kinrin, is also thought to contain the essence (seed) of Dainichi Kinrin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;BhruuM,&quot; the Sanskrit syllable associated with Shaka Kinrin, is also thought to contain the essence (seed) of Dainichi Kinrin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="22">
<j>その姿は、全身を五智宝冠等の装身具で飾り、印相は智拳印。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dainichi Kinrin is a deity decorated with a crown engraved with five images of Buddha, with its hands placed in the wisdom-fist mudra.</e>
<cmt>「智拳印」はwisdom-fist mudraと訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dainichi Kinrin is a deity decorated with a crown engraved with five images of Buddha, with its hands placed in the wisdom-fist mudra.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dainichi Kinrin is a deity decorated with a crown engraved with five images of Buddha, with its hands placed in the wisdom-fist mudra.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>七匹の獅子の支える白蓮華の上に座す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It sits on a white lotus throne supported by seven lions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It sits on a white lotus throne supported by seven lions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It sits on a white lotus throne supported by seven lions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>その姿は金剛界大日如来に酷似するが、大日如来が月輪の中に座すのに対し、大日金輪は日輪（赤い月輪）の中に座すのが特徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It bears a close resemblance to Dainichi Nyorai (great cosmic Buddha) of the transcendental world, but whereas Dainichi Nyorai is usually surrounding by a ring of moonlight, Dainichi Kinrin is surrounded by a ring of sunlight (a red halo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It bears a close resemblance to Dainichi Nyorai (great cosmic Buddha) of the transcendental world, but whereas Dainichi Nyorai is usually surrounded by a ring of moonlight, Dainichi Kinrin is surrounded by a ring of sunlight (a red halo).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It bears a close resemblance to Dainichi Nyorai (great cosmic Buddha) of the transcendental world, but whereas Dainichi Nyorai is usually surrounded by a ring of moonlight, Dainichi Kinrin is surrounded by a ring of sunlight (a red halo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>また、日輪の周縁に輪宝が配される場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A golden wheel is also sometimes placed around its ring of sunlight.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A golden wheel is also sometimes placed around its ring of sunlight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A golden wheel is also sometimes placed around its ring of sunlight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="26">
<j>大日金輪は、天台宗では蘇悉地法の本尊として金剛界・胎蔵界大日如来に並ぶ尊格とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Tendai Buddhism, Dainichi Kinrin is worshipped as a deity of the same importance as Dainichi Nyorai of the transcendental world and that of the world of physical phenomenon, and as the protector deity of an esoteric ritual that binds these two worlds together.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Tendai Buddhism, Dainichi Kinrin is worshipped as a deity of the same importance as Dainichi Nyorai of the transcendental world and that of the world of physical phenomenon, and as the protector deity of an esoteric ritual that binds these two worlds together.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Tendai Buddhism, Dainichi Kinrin is worshipped as a deity of the same importance as Dainichi Nyorai of the transcendental world and that of the world of physical phenomenon, and as the protector deity of an esoteric ritual that binds these two worlds together.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="27">
<j>また仏眼仏母と表裏一体の存在とも考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also regarded as the same entity as Butsugen Butsumo (a deity that symbolizes the eye of Buddha, representing the Buddhist truth).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also regarded as the same entity as Butsugen Butsumo (a deity that symbolizes the eye of Buddha, representing the Buddhist truth).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also regarded as the same entity as Butsugen Butsumo (a deity that symbolizes the eye of Buddha, representing the Buddhist truth).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>金剛界大日如来が胎蔵界日輪三昧の境地にある姿が大日金輪、胎蔵界大日如来が金剛界月輪三昧にある姿が仏眼仏母であるとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Dainichi Nyorai of the transcendental world mediating in the world of physical phenomenon is believed to be Dainichi Kinrin, Dainichi Nyorai of the world of physical phenomenon mediating in the transcendental world is believed to be Butsugen Butsumo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Dainichi Nyorai of the transcendental world mediating in the world of physical phenomenon is believed to be Dainichi Kinrin, Dainichi Nyorai of the world of physical phenomenon mediating in the transcendental world is believed to be Butsugen Butsumo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Dainichi Nyorai of the transcendental world mediating in the world of physical phenomenon is believed to be Dainichi Kinrin, Dainichi Nyorai of the world of physical phenomenon mediating in the transcendental world is believed to be Butsugen Butsumo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="29">
<j>また、一字金輪仏頂が折伏、仏眼仏母が摂受によって衆生を教化するという意味でも表裏一体である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ichiji Kinrin Butcho and Butsugen Butsumo also represent two different aspects of Buddhist preaching in the sense that while the former enlightens people by logical argument, the latter leads them to the truth by cultivating virtues among them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ichiji Kinrin Butcho and Butsugen Butsumo also represent two different aspects of Buddhist preaching in the sense that while the former enlightens people by logical argument, the latter leads them to the truth by cultivating virtues among them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ichiji Kinrin Buccho and Butsugen Butsumo also represent two different aspects of Buddhist preaching in the sense that while the former enlightens people by logical argument, the latter leads them to the truth by cultivating virtues among them.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="30">
<j>一字金輪仏頂の曼荼羅に仏眼仏母、仏眼仏母の曼荼羅に一字金輪仏頂を配して修法を行うのも、両者の補完関係を期待してのものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ichiji Kinrin Butcho mandala is used together with the Butsugen Butsumo mandala in the religious practice of esoteric Buddhism due to the complementary relationships between these two deities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ichiji Kinrin Butcho mandala is used together with the Butsugen Butsumo mandala in the religious practice of Esoteric Buddhism due to the complementary relationship that exists between these two deities.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ichiji Kinrin Buccho mandala is used together with the Butsugen Butsumo mandala in the religious practice of Esoteric Buddhism due to the complementary relationship that exists between these two deities.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>つまり、一字金輪仏頂の霊験の輪宝によって倒された悪神は、真実の眼を開く仏眼仏母によって善神として蘇るのだという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Evil deities that are subdued by the magical power of Ichiji Kinrin Butcho&apos;s golden wheel are believed to be reborn as benevolent deities by Butsugen Butsumo, who opens their eyes to the truth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Evil deities that are subdued by the magical power of Ichiji Kinrin Butcho&apos;s golden wheel are believed to be reborn as benevolent deities by Butsugen Butsumo, who opens their eyes to the truth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Evil deities that are subdued by the magical power of Ichiji Kinrin Buccho&apos;s golden wheel are believed to be reborn as benevolent deities by Butsugen Butsumo, who opens their eyes to the truth.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="32">
<j>なお、一字金輪仏頂を本尊とする修法はあまりに強力であり、その壇から五百由旬四方の場所で行われている他の修法は全て無効化されてしまうとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The miraculous power possessed by Ichiji Kinrin Butcho was believed to be so strong that it could nullify the effects of any ritual practiced within a distance of 500 yojana from its throne.</e>
<cmt>五百由旬は500 yojana と訳しました。Yojana は距離の単位だと思われますが、それがどれくらいの距離なのかは不明ですので、他の単位に換算せずにそのままにしてあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The miraculous power possessed by Ichiji Kinrin Butcho was believed to be so strong that it could nullify the effects of any ritual practiced within a distance of 500 yojana from its throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The miraculous power possessed by Ichiji Kinrin Buccho was believed to be so strong that it could nullify the effects of any ritual practiced within a distance of 500 yojana from its throne.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>そのため、真言宗では東寺の長者のみが修することを許されていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, only the highest priest of Toji Temple was allowed to practice rituals related to Ichiji Kinrin Butcho in Shingon Buddhism</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, in Shingon Buddhism only the highest priest of Toji Temple was allowed to practice rituals related to Ichiji Kinrin Butcho.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, in Shingon Buddhism only the highest priest of Toji Temple was allowed to practice rituals related to Ichiji Kinrin Buccho.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Peehyoro Acala(id:170), K. Takeda(id:119013), Urania(id:7213), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>