<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>隠元隆き</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">INGEN Ryuki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">INGEN Ryuki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">INGEN Ryuki (Also known as Yinyuan Longqi)</e>
<cmt>中国名を補足しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>隠元隆琦（いんげん りゅうき、特諡として大光普照国師、仏慈広鑑国師、径山首出国師、覚性円明国師、勅賜として真空大師、華光大師、万暦20年・文禄元年11月4日 (旧暦)(1592年12月7日) - 寛文13年4月3日 (旧暦)(1673年5月19日)）は、中国明末清初の禅宗の僧で、福建省福州福清の生まれで俗姓は林である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">INGEN Ryuki (December 7, 1592 – May 19, 1673) was a Chinese Zen Buddhist priest, who was born in Fuqing, Fuzhou of Fujian Province, China (福建省福州福清) and lived in the periods of the late Ming Dynasty and the early Qing Dynasty; his secular family name was Lin (林), and his imperially bestowed titles in Japan were Shinku daishi (daishi: a great teacher monk) and Kako daishi; and he was given posthumous Buddhist names, Daiko-fusho kokushi (kokushi: a posthumous Buddhist title given by the Emperor), Butsuji-kokan kokushi, Kinzan-shushutsu kokushi, and Kakusho-enmyo kokushi.</e>
<cmt>覚性円明国師→Kakusho-enmyo kokushi　(http://www.biwa.ne.jp/~m-sumita/jiten-ka.html)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">INGEN Ryuki (December 7, 1592 – May 19, 1673) was a Chinese Zen Buddhist priest, who was born in Fuqing, Fuzhou of Fujian Province, China (福建省福州福清) and lived in the periods of the late Ming Dynasty and the early Qing Dynasty; his secular family name was Lin (林), and his imperially bestowed titles in Japan were Shinku daishi (daishi: a great teacher monk) and Kako daishi; and he was given posthumous Buddhist names, Daiko-fusho kokushi (kokushi: a posthumous Buddhist title given by the Emperor), Butsuji-kokan kokushi, Kinzan-shushutsu kokushi, and Kakusho-enmyo kokushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">INGEN Ryuki (December 7, 1592 – May 19, 1673) was a Chinese Zen Buddhist priest in the periods of the late Ming Dynasty and the early Qing Dynasty, who was born in Fuqing, Fuzhou of Fujian Province, China; his secular family name was Hayashi (林), and his imperially bestowed titles in Japan were Shinku daishi (daishi: a great teacher monk) and Kako daishi; and he was given special posthumous Buddhist names, Daiko-fusho kokushi (kokushi: a posthumous Buddhist title given by the Emperor), Butsuji-kokan kokushi, Kinzan-shushutsu kokushi, and Kakusho-enmyo kokushi.</e>
<cmt>読み不明の日本語を残し、表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>独特の威儀を持ち、念仏禅を特徴とする明朝禅を日本に伝え、やや先に渡来した道者超元（? - 1660年, 1651年来朝、1658年帰国）と共に、当時の禅宗界に多大な影響を与え、臨済宗・曹洞宗二宗の復興運動にも大きな影響を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He introduced Zen Buddhism of the Ming Dynasty that was characterized by nenbutsu-zen (Zen training with prayers) to Japan, and keeping his unique solemn manner, he made a great impact on the Zen Buddhism world at that time to give a large stimulation to the recovery movement of the Rinzai sect and the Soto sect, along with Dosha Chogen (unknown – 1660: he came to Japan in 1651, and returned to China in 1658) who had come to Japan earlier than him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He introduced Zen Buddhism of the Ming Dynasty that was characterized by nenbutsu-zen (Zen training with prayers) to Japan, and keeping his unique solemn manner, he made a great impact on the Zen Buddhism world at that time to give large stimulation to the recovery movement of the Rinzai sect and the Soto sect, along with Dosha Chogen (unknown – 1660: he came to Japan in 1651, and returned to China in 1658) who had come to Japan earlier than him.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He introduced Zen Buddhism of the Ming Dynasty that was characterized by nenbutsu-zen (Zen training with Buddhist invocation) to Japan, and keeping his unique solemn manner, he made a great impact on the Zen Buddhism world at that time to give large stimulation to the recovery movement of the Rinzai Sect and the Soto Sect, along with Dosha Chogen (unknown – 1660: he came to Japan in 1651, and returned to China in 1658) who had come to Japan little earlier than him.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>また日本における煎茶道の開祖ともされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is also said to have been a founder of Sencha (green tea) tea service in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is also said to have been a founder of Sencha (green tea) tea service in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is also said to have been a founder of Senchado (green tea ceremony) in Japan.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>生い立ち～渡来前</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From his birth until his emigration to Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From his birth until his emigration to Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From His Birth Until His Emigration to Japan</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>福建省福州府福清県万安郷霊得里東林に生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born at Manango-reitokuri-torin (万安郷霊得里東林), Fuqing, Fuzhou of Fujian Province, China.</e>
<cmt>万安郷霊得里東林→ Manango-reitokuri-torin[読み不明，定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born at Manango-reitokuri-torin (万安郷霊得里東林), Fuqing, Fuzhou of Fujian Province, China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born at Manango-reitokuri-torin (万安郷霊得里東林), Fuqing, Fuzhou of Fujian Province, China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>俗名は、林曽炳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His secular name was Sohei LIN (林曽炳).</e>
<cmt>林曽炳→ Sohei LIN[読み不明，定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His secular name was Sohei LIN (林曽炳).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His secular name was Sohei LIN (林曽炳).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>10歳で仏教に発心する（16歳という説もあり）が、出家修道は母に許されなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he was awakened to Buddhism when he was ten years old (some say sixteen), his mother would not allowed him to become a priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he was awakened to Buddhism when he was ten years old (some say sixteen), his mother would not allow him to become a priest.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he was awakened to Buddhism when he was ten years old (some say sixteen), his mother would not allow him to become a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>23歳の時、普陀山（浙江省）の潮音洞主のもとに参じ、在俗信者として奉仕した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he was twenty-three he visited Choondoshu (潮音洞主) in Mount Putuo (Zhejiang province), where he served as a non-priest devotee.</e>
<cmt>潮音洞主→ Choondoshu[読み不明，定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he was twenty-three he visited Choondoshu (潮音洞主) in Mount Putuo (Zhejiang province), where he served as a non-priest devotee.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he was twenty-three he visited Chondoshu (潮音洞主) in Mt. Putuo (Zhejiang Province), where he served as a non-priest devotee.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>29歳で、生地である福清の古刹で、黄檗希運も住した黄檗山萬福寺 (中国福建省)の鑑源興寿の下で得度した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At twenty-nine, he entered the Buddhist priesthood under KANGEN Koju at Obakuzan Manpuku-ji Temple of Fuqing (Fujian province, China), which was an old temple at his birth place and once a residence of OBAKU Kiun (or Huangbo Xiyun in Chinese) (黄檗希運).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At twenty-nine, he entered the Buddhist priesthood under KANGEN Koju at Obakuzan Manpuku-ji Temple of Fuqing (Fujian province, China), which was an old temple at his birth place and once a residence of OBAKU Kiun (or Huangbo Xiyun in Chinese) (黄檗希運).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At twenty-nine, he entered the Buddhist priesthood under KANGEN Koju at Manpuku-ji Temple on Mt. Obaku of Fuqing (Fujian Province, China), which was an old temple at his birth place and once a residence of OBAKU Kiun (or Huangbo Xiyun in Chinese) (黄檗希運).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>33歳の時、金粟山広慧寺で密雲円悟禅師に参禅し、密雲が萬福寺に晋山するに際して、隠元も随行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At thirty-three, he practiced Zen under MITSUUN Engo (or Mi-yun Yuan-wu, 密雲円悟), a Zen priest, at Jinsushan Mountain Vang-un ghoul-un juu Temple, and later he followed Mistuun who took up a new position as chief priest at Manpuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At thirty-three, he practiced Zen under MITSUUN Engo (or Mi-yun Yuan-wu, 密雲円悟), a Zen priest, at Jinsushan Mountain Vang-un ghoul-un juu Temple, and later he followed Mistuun who took up a new position as chief priest at Manpuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At thirty-three, he practiced Zen under MITSUN Engo (Also known as Mi-yun Yuan-wu, 密雲円悟), a Zen priest, at Vang-un ghoul-un juu Temple on Mt. Jinsushan, and later Ingen followed Mistun who took up a new position as chief priest at Manpuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="10">
<j>35歳で、大悟した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At thirty-five, he became enlightened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At thirty-five, he became enlightened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At thirty-five, he became enlightened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="11">
<j>38歳の時、密雲は弟子の費隠通容に萬福寺を継席して退山したが、隠元はそのまま萬福寺に残り、45歳で費隠に嗣法した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Ingen was thirty-eight, Mitsuun gave his position over to his disciple HIIN Tsuyo and left the temple, but Ingen stayed at Manpuku-ji Temple to inherit the dharma from Hiin at forty-five.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Ingen was thirty-eight, Mitsuun gave his position over to his disciple HIIN Tsuyo and left the temple, but Ingen stayed at Manpuku-ji Temple to inherit the dharma from Hiin at forty-five.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Ingen was thirty-eight, Mitsun gave his position over to his disciple HIIN Tsuyo and left the temple, but Ingen stayed at Manpuku-ji Temple to inherit the dharma from Hiin at forty-five.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="12">
<j>その後隠元は萬福寺を出、獅子巌で修行していたが、費隠が退席した後の黄檗山の住持に招請されることとなり、明崇禎10年(1637年)に晋山した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, when Ingen was engaged himself in ascetic practices at Shishiiwa (獅子巌) after leaving Manpuku-ji Temple, he was invited to become a juji (a resident head of a temple) at Obakuzan succeeding Hiin, where he assumed the post in 1637.</e>
<cmt>獅子巌→Shishiiwa[中国の場所不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, when Ingen was engaged himself in ascetic practices at Shishiiwa (獅子巌) after leaving Manpuku-ji Temple, he was invited to become a juji (a resident head of a temple) at Obakuzan succeeding Hiin, where he assumed the post in 1637.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, when Ingen was engaged himself in ascetic practices at Shishiiwa (獅子巌) after leaving Manpuku-ji Temple, he was invited to become a juji (a resident head of a temple) on Mt. Obaku succeeding Hiin, where he assumed the position in 1637.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その後、退席したが、明末清初の動乱が福建省にも及ぶ中、順治3年（1646年）に再度晋山した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later he once left the Temple, but took the position again in 1646, when social upheavals of the transition era from the Ming Dynasty to the Qing Dynasty spread to Fujian province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later he once left the Temple, but took the position again in 1646, when the social upheavals in the transition period from the Ming Dynasty to the Qing Dynasty spread to Fujian province.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later he once left the Temple, but took the position again in 1646, when the social upheavals in the transition period from the Ming Dynasty to the Qing Dynasty spread to Fujian Province.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>渡来以降</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his immigration to Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his immigration to Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After His Immigration to Japan</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>江戸初期、長崎市の唐人寺であった崇福寺 (長崎市)の住持に空席が生じたことから、先に渡日していた興福寺 (長崎市)住持の逸然性融が、隠元を日本に招請した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early Edo period, as a juji position became vacant at Sofuku-ji Temple (Nagasaki City) that was a temple of Chinese priests, ITSUNEN Shoyu (逸然性融) who was in Japan and juji of Kofuku-ji Temple (Nagasaki City) invited Ingen to Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early Edo period, as a juji position became vacant at Sofuku-ji Temple (Nagasaki City) that was a temple of Chinese priests, ITSUNEN Shoyu (逸然性融) who was in Japan and juji of Kofuku-ji Temple (Nagasaki City) invited Ingen to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early Edo period, as a juji position became vacant at Sofuku-ji Temple (Nagasaki City) that was a temple of Chinese priests, ITSUNEN Shoyu (逸然性融) who was in Japan and juji of Kofuku-ji Temple (Nagasaki City) invited Ingen to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>当初、隠元は弟子の也嬾性圭を派遣したが、途中船が座礁して客死したことから、やむなく承応3年(1654年)に、隠元自ら、鄭成功が仕立てた船に乗り、多くの弟子を率いて来日した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first Ingen sent his disciple YARAN Shokei (也嬾性圭) off, but he was killed in a shipwreck on his way to Japan, so Ingen had to bring himself to Japan aboard a ship Seiko TEI (鄭成功) prepared with many disciples in tow in 1654.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first Ingen sent his disciple YARAN Shokei (也嬾性圭) off, but he was killed in a shipwreck on his way to Japan, so Ingen had to bring himself to Japan aboard a ship Seiko TEI (鄭成功) prepared with many disciples in tow in 1654.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first Ingen sent his disciple YARAN Shokei (也嬾性圭) off, but he was killed in a shipwreck on his way to Japan, so Ingen had to bring himself to Japan aboard a ship Seiko TEI (鄭成功) prepared with many disciples in tow in 1654.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>渡日当時、中国は明末清初の騒乱期であったことから、この騒乱を避けて来日したとされているが、残されている書簡や記録等からは、そのように判断する根拠は乏しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he is said to have come to Japan to avoid the social turmoil that China experienced in the transition era of the Ming Dynasty to the Qing Dynasty, this judgment has no grounds in remaining letters and records.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he is said to have come to Japan to avoid the social turmoil that China experienced in the transition period between the Ming Dynasty to the Qing Dynasty, this judgment has no grounds in remaining letters and records.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he is said to have come to Japan to avoid the social turmoil that China experienced in the transition period between the Ming Dynasty to the Qing Dynasty, this judgment has no grounds in remaining letters and records.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>隠元が入った興福寺には、明禅の新風と隠元の高徳を慕う具眼の僧や学者たちが雲集し、僧俗数千とも謂われる活況を呈した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A number of intelligent monks and scholars were attracted by Ingen&apos; s high virtue and the new Zen Buddhism of Ming to gather around Kofuku-ji Temple where Ingen first lived, and the temple is said to have been very active flocked by a few thousand monks and believers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A number of intelligent monks and scholars were attracted by Ingen&apos;s high virtue and the new Zen Buddhism of Ming to gather around Kofuku-ji Temple where Ingen first lived, and the temple is said to have been very active and was flocked to by several thousand monks and believers.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A number of intelligent monks and scholars were attracted by Ingen&apos;s high virtue and the new Zen Buddhism of Ming to gather around Kofuku-ji Temple where Ingen first lived, and the temple is said to have been very active and was flocked to by several thousand monks and believers.</e>
<cmt>半角カンマにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>明暦元年(1655年)、妙心寺元住持の龍渓性潜の懇請により、摂津国嶋上（現在の大阪府高槻市）の普門寺 (高槻市)に晋山するが、隠元の影響力を恐れた幕府によって、寺外に出る事を禁じられ、また寺内の会衆も200人以内に制限された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1655, RYOKEI Shosen, juji of Myosin-ji Temple, persuaded Ingen to become juji of Fumon-ji Temple in Shimagami, Settsu Province (present Takatsuki City of Osaka Prefecture), but the bakufu forbid him to go out of the temple and also restricted the number of attendants at the meetings the temple within 200, because the bakufu feared Ingen&apos;s religious influence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1655, RYOKEI Shosen, juji of Myosin-ji Temple, persuaded Ingen to become juji of Fumon-ji Temple in Shimagami, Settsu Province (present Takatsuki City of Osaka Prefecture), but the bakufu forbid him to go out of the temple and also restricted the number of attendants at the meetings in the temple to within 200, because the bakufu feared Ingen&apos;s religious influence.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1655, RYOKEI Shosen, juji of Myoshin-ji Temple, persuaded Ingen to become juji of Fumon-ji Temple in Shimagami, Settsu Province (present Takatsuki City of Osaka Prefecture), but the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) forbid him to go out of the temple and also restricted the number of attendants at the meetings in the temple to within 200, because the bakufu feared Ingen&apos;s religious influence.</e>
<cmt>補足などしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>隠元の渡日は、当初3年間の約束であり、本国からの再三の帰国要請もあって帰国を決意するが、龍渓らが引き止め工作に奔走し、万治元年（1658年）には、将軍徳川家綱との会見に成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he decided to return to China after three years which he at first promised to stay for, responding to the repeated requests of his home country to go home, Ryukei and other priests worked hard to set up a meeting of Ingen and Ietsuna TOKUGAWA, the Shogun, successfully in 1658.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he decided to return to China after the three years which he at first promised to stay for, responding to the repeated requests of his home country to go home, Ryukei and other priests worked hard to set up a meeting between Ingen and Ietsuna TOKUGAWA, the Shogun, successfully in 1658.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he decided to return to China after the three years which he at first promised to stay for, responding to the repeated requests of his home country to go home, Ryukei and other priests worked hard to detain him from going home and set up a meeting between Ingen and Ietsuna TOKUGAWA, the Shogun, successfully in 1658.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>その結果、万治3年（1660年）、山城国宇治市郡大和田に寺地を賜り、翌年、新寺を開創し、旧を忘れないという意味を込め、故郷の中国福清と同名の黄檗山萬福寺と名付けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently, in 1006, he was given a land for a temple at Owada of Uji-gun, Yamashiro Province, and the next year he built a new temple which he named Obakuzan Manpuku-ji Temple after the temple of his home Fuqing as he pledged to remember the old people and things.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, in 1006, he was given land for a temple at Owada of Uji-gun, Yamashiro Province, and the next year he built a new temple which he named Obakuzan Manpuku-ji Temple after the temple of his home Fuqing as he pledged to remember the old people and things.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, in 1660, he was given land for a temple at Owada of Uji-gun, Yamashiro Province, and the next year he built a new temple which he named Manpuku-ji Temple on Mt. Obaku after the temple of his home Fuqing as he pledged to remember the old people and things.</e>
<cmt>1660年とし、表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>寛文3年（1663年）には、完成したばかりの法堂で祝国開堂を行い、民衆に対しては、日本で初めての授戒「黄檗三壇戒会」を厳修した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1663, he held an opening ceremony at the newly completed hall to bless the country and conducted the Japan&apos;s first Jukai (handing down the precepts) called &apos;Obaku Sandankai-e&apos; (黄檗三壇戒会) for people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1663, he held an opening ceremony at the newly completed hall to bless the country and conducted Japan&apos;s first Jukai (handing down the precepts) called &apos;Obaku Sandankai-e&apos; (黄檗三壇戒会) for people.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1663, he held an opening ceremony at the newly completed hall to bless the country and conducted Japan&apos;s first Jukai (handing down the precepts) called &apos;Obaku Sandan kaie&apos; (Triple Ordination Platform Ceremony) for people.</e>
<cmt>半角クォーテーションにし、補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="22">
<j>以後、中国福清の黄檗山萬福寺は「古黄檗」と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Obakuzan Manpuku-ji Temple in Fuqing of China has been called &apos;Old Obaku&apos; ever since in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Obakuzan Manpuku-ji Temple in Fuqing of China has been called &apos;Old Obaku&apos; ever since in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Obakuzan Manpuku-ji Temple in Fuqing of China has been called &apos;Ko-obaku&apos; (literally, Old Obaku) ever since in Japan.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>黄檗宗開教以降</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the foundation of Obaku Sect</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the foundation of Obaku Sect</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Foundation of Obaku Sect</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>これによって、隠元は日本禅界の一派の開祖となったが、当初から黄檗宗と名乗っていたわけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This made Ingen a founder of a sect of Zen Buddhism in Japan, but initially, the sect did not call itself Obaku sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This made Ingen a founder of a sect of Zen Buddhism in Japan, but initially, the sect did not call itself Obaku sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This made Ingen a founder of a sect of Zen Buddhism in Japan, but initially, the sect did not call itself Obaku Sect.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>本人は歴とした臨済宗を嗣法している自負があったので、臨済正宗を名乗っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since he was proud of himself as a successor of authentic Rinzai sect, the sect called itself Rinzaiseishu sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since he was proud of himself as a successor of authentic Rinzai sect, the sect called itself Rinzaiseishu sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since he was proud of himself as a successor of authentic Rinzai Sect, the sect called itself Rinzaisei Sect.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>もっとも、宗風や叢林としての規矩清規は当時の中国・明時代の臨済禅に倣っていたことから、既に日本に根付いていた臨済宗とは趣を異にし、その違いにより、自ずから一派を形成する方向に向かったものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since its tradition and kiku shingi (規矩清規) (code of ethics and code of conduct) at the monastery followed the Rinzai Zen Buddhism of the Ming period in China, it was somewhat different from the Rinzai Zen that had already taken root in Japan, and the difference led it to form a new sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since its tradition and kiku shingi (規矩清規) (code of ethics and code of conduct) at the monastery followed the Rinzai Zen Buddhism of the Ming period in China, it was somewhat different from the Rinzai Zen that had already taken root in Japan, and the difference led it to form a new sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since its tradition and Kiku (regulation) and Shingi (daily regulations in Zen temples) at the monastery followed the Rinzai Zen Buddhism of the Ming Dynasty in China, it was somewhat different from the Rinzai Sect that had already taken root in Japan, and the difference led it to form a new sect.</e>
<cmt>表記などを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="26">
<j>隠元の『黄檗清規』は、乱れを生じていた当時の禅宗各派の宗統・規矩の更正に大きな影響を与え、特に卍山道白らによる曹洞宗の宗門改革では重要な手本とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ingen&apos;s &quot;Obaku-shingi&quot; (黄檗清規) (Obaku code of conduct) had a great impact on the rehabilitation of religious code of conduct of Japanese Zen sects who began to be lapsed at that time, and the book was viewed as a valued model for the religious reform movement of Soto sect led by MANZAN Dohaku (卍山道白).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ingen&apos;s &quot;Obaku-shingi&quot; (黄檗清規) (Obaku code of conduct) had a great impact on the rehabilitation of religious code of conduct of Japanese Zen sects which began to be lapsed at that time, and the book was viewed as a valued model for the religious reform movement of Soto sect led by MANZAN Dohaku (卍山道白).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ingen&apos;s &quot;Obaku-shingi&quot; (Obaku code of conduct) had a great impact on the rehabilitation of religious code of conduct of Japanese Zen sects which began to be lapsed at that time, and the book was viewed as a valued model for the religious reform movement of Soto Sect led by Dohaku MANZAN.</e>
<cmt>表記などを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="27">
<j>隠元には、後水尾天皇を始めとする皇族、幕府要人を始めとする各地の大名、多くの商人たちが競って帰依した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Gomizunoo, the Imperial family members, senior officials of the bakufu, rural feudal lords, and many merchants became believers of the Obaku sect of Ingen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Gomizunoo, the Imperial family members, senior officials of the bakufu, rural feudal lords, and many merchants became believers of the Obaku sect of Ingen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Gomizunoo, the Imperial family members, senior officials of the bakufu, rural feudal lords, and many merchants became believers of the Obaku Sect of Ingen.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="28">
<j>萬福寺の住職の地位にあったのは3年間で、寛文4年(1664年)9月に後席は弟子の木庵性瑫に移譲し、松隠堂に退いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He occupied the post of resident head priest of Manpuku-ji Temple for three years, and gave the post to his disciple MOKUAN Shoto (木庵性瑫) to retire in Shoin-do hall (松隠堂) in 1664.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He occupied the post of resident head priest of Manpuku-ji Temple for three years, and gave the post to his disciple MOKUAN Shoto (木庵性瑫) to retire in Shoin-do hall (松隠堂) in 1664.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He occupied the position of resident head priest of Manpuku-ji Temple for three years, and gave the position to his disciple MOKUAN Shoto to retire in Shoin-do hall in October, 1664.</e>
<cmt>9月、をグレゴリオ暦で補足し、日本語をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="29">
<j>松隠堂に退隠後、82才を迎えた寛文13年(1673年)正月、隠元は死を予知し身辺を整理し始め、3月になり、体調がますます衰え、4月2日には後水尾法皇から「大光普照国師」号が特諡された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After retiring in Shoin-do hall, at eighty-two years old in the New Year of 1673, he began putting his affairs in order in contemplation of his death, his health deteriorated rapidly in March, and he was given &apos;Daiko-fusho kokushi,&apos; a posthumous Buddhist name, by Emperor Gomizunoo on April 2.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After retiring in Shoin-do hall, at eighty-two years old in the New Year of 1673, he began putting his affairs in order in contemplation of his death, his health deteriorated rapidly in March, and he was given &apos;Daiko-fusho kokushi,&apos; a posthumous Buddhist name, by Emperor Gomizunoo on April 2.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After retiring in Shoin-do hall, at eighty-two years old in February, 1673, he began putting his affairs in order in contemplation of his death, his health deteriorated rapidly in April, and he was given &apos;Daiko-fusho kokushi,&apos; a posthumous Buddhist name, by Emperor Gomizunoo on May 18.</e>
<cmt>半角クォーテーションにし、グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>翌3日に遺偈を認めて示寂。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 3, he put down yuige (poem for teachings to disciples and posterity wrote by a deceasing venerable priest) before entering nirvana (he passed away).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 3, he put down yuige (poem for teachings to disciples and posterity written by a dying venerable priest) before entering nirvana (he passed away).</e>
<cmt>slight moification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the following day, May 19, he put down yuige (poem for teachings to disciples and posterity written by a dying venerable priest) before entering nirvana (he passed away).</e>
<cmt>翌、を補足し、グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>世壽82才。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was eighty-two years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was eighty-two years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was eighty-two years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="32">
<j>能書家としても知られ、木庵性瑫、即非如一とともに黄檗の三筆と称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also well-known as a great calligrapher, one of the best three calligraphers of Obaku, along with MOKUAN Shoto and SOKUHI Nyoitsu (即非如一).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also well-known as a great calligrapher, one of the best three calligraphers of Obaku, along with MOKUAN Shoto and SOKUHI Nyoitsu (即非如一).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also well-known as a great calligrapher, one of the best three calligraphers of Obaku, along with MOKUAN Shoto and Sokuhinyoitsu.</e>
<cmt>マイページに用語を合わせ日本語をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>語録・著作</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Analects and writings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Analects and writings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Analects and Writings</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="33">
<j>『隠元禅師語録』16巻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ingen-zenji-goroku&quot; (隠元禅師語録) (Analects of Ingen), sixteen volumes</e>
<cmt>定訳不明ですが，漢字の意味からの説明を加えました．</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ingen-zenji-goroku&quot; (隠元禅師語録) (Analects of Ingen), sixteen volumes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Ingen-zenji-goroku&quot; (Analects of Ingen), sixteen volumes</e>
<cmt>日本語をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>『普照国師広録』30巻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Fusho-kokkushi koroku&quot; (普照国師広録) (Analects of Ingen), thirty volumes</e>
<cmt>定訳不明ですが，漢字の意味からの説明を加えました．</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Fusho-kokkushi koroku&quot; (普照国師広録) (Analects of Ingen), thirty volumes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Fusho-kokushi koroku&quot; (Analects of Ingen), thirty volumes</e>
<cmt>日本語をのぞくなど変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>『黄檗隠元禅師雲涛集』1巻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Obaku Ingen-zenji Unto-shu&quot; (黄檗隠元禅師雲涛集). one volume</e>
<cmt>定訳不明ですが，漢字の意味からの説明を加えました．</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Obaku Ingen-zenji Unto-shu&quot; (黄檗隠元禅師雲涛集). one volume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Obaku Ingen Zenji Untoshu&quot; (Collection of Ingen&apos;s Poem) one volume</e>
<cmt>補足し、日本語をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>『弘戒法儀』1巻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Gukaihogi&quot; (弘戒法儀) (disciplines and precepts), one volume</e>
<cmt>定訳不明ですが，漢字の意味からの説明を加えました．</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Gukaihogi&quot; (弘戒法儀) (disciplines and precepts), one volume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Gukaihogi&quot; (disciplines and precepts), one volume</e>
<cmt>日本語をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>『黄檗山寺志』1巻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Obakusan-jishi&quot; (黄檗山寺志) (History of Obakuzan Manpuku-ji), one volume</e>
<cmt>定訳不明ですが，漢字の意味からの説明を加えました．</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Obakusan-jishi&quot; (黄檗山寺志) (History of Obakuzan Manpuku-ji), one volume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Obakusan-jishi&quot; (History of Manpuku-ji on Mt. Obaku), one volume</e>
<cmt>日本語をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>『黄檗清規』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Obaku-shingi&quot; (黄檗清規) (Obaku code of conduct)</e>
<cmt>定訳不明ですが，漢字の意味からの説明を加えました．</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Obaku-shingi&quot; (黄檗清規) (Obaku code of conduct)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Obaku-shingi&quot; (Obaku code of conduct)</e>
<cmt>日本語をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>弟子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Disciples</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Disciples</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Disciples</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="39">
<j>嗣法者は23名で、内3人が日本人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of teaching successors to Ingen was twenty-three including three Japanese priests.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of teaching successors to Ingen was twenty-three including three Japanese priests.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of teaching successors to Ingen was twenty-three including three Japanese priests.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="40">
<j>木庵性トウ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MOKUAN Shoto (木庵性トウ)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MOKUAN Shoto (木庵性トウ)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MOKUAN Shoto</e>
<cmt>日本語をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="41">
<j>即非如一</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SOKUHI nyoitsu (即非如一)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SOKUHI nyoitsu (即非如一)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sokuhinyoitsu</e>
<cmt>日本語をのぞき、表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="42">
<j>慧林性機</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ERIN Shoki (慧林性機)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ERIN Shoki (慧林性機)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">ERIN Shoki</e>
<cmt>日本語をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="43">
<j>龍渓性潜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">RYOKEI Shosen (the former chief priest of Myosin-ji Temple) (龍渓性潜)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">RYOKEI Shosen (the former chief priest of Myosin-ji Temple) (龍渓性潜)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">RYOKEI Shosen (the former chief priest of Myosin-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt>日本語をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="44">
<j>独湛性ケイ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">DOKUTAN Shokei (独湛性ケイ)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">DOKUTAN Shokei (独湛性ケイ)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">DOKUTAN Shokei</e>
<cmt>日本語をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="45">
<j>大眉性善</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">DAIBI Shozen (大眉性善)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">DAIBI Shozen (大眉性善)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">DAIBI Shozen</e>
<cmt>日本語をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="46">
<j>独照性円</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">DOKUSHO Shoen (独照性円)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">DOKUSHO Shoen (独照性円)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dokusho Shoen</e>
<cmt>マイページに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="47">
<j>独本性源</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">DOKUHON Shogen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">DOKUHON Shogen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">DOKUHON Shogen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>隠元豆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ingen-mame (隠元豆) (beans)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ingen-mame (隠元豆) (beans)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ingen-mame (隠元豆) (Common bean)</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="48">
<j>隠元が来日した際に日本に持ち込んだため、その名が付いたとされる「インゲンマメ」は、中南米原産のマメ科の作物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ingen-mame,&apos; which was named after Ingen who brought beans to Japan, is a farm product of a pea family native to Latin America.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ingen-mame,&apos; which was named after Ingen who brought beans to Japan, is a farm product of a pea family native to Latin America.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ingen-mame,&apos; which was named after Ingen who brought to Japan, is a farm product of a pea family native to Latin America.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>ヨーロッパに伝わった後、ユーラシア大陸を横断して中国から日本に伝来した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After it was introduced to Europe, it traveled across Eurasian Continent to China and then was imported to Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After it was introduced to Europe, it traveled across the Eurasian Continent to China and then was imported to Japan.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After it was introduced to Europe, it traveled across the Eurasian Continent to China and then was imported to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>但し、隠元が持ち込んだのは、現在の「フジマメ（藤豆）」だという説もあり、関西ではフジマメのことを「インゲンマメ」と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, some views explain that Ingen&apos;s bean was &apos;fuji-mame&apos; (hyacinth-bean) as we know them today, and people call fuji-mame &apos;Ingen-mame&apos; in the Kansai region (around Kyoto and Osaka Prefectures).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, some views explain that Ingen&apos;s bean was &apos;fuji-mame&apos; (hyacinth-bean) as we know them today, and people call fuji-mame &apos;Ingen-mame&apos; in the Kansai region (around Kyoto and Osaka Prefectures).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, some views explain that Ingen&apos;s bean was &apos;fuji-mame&apos; (hyacinth-bean) as we know them today, and people call fuji-mame &apos;Ingen-mame&apos; in the Kansai region (around Kyoto and Osaka Prefectures).</e>
<cmt>半角クォーテーションにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 JAnDbot(id:66507), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Tomzo(id:16777), Lobbyonce(id:195963), Hhaithait(id:37092), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Cprobot(id:97843), Charenji(id:7908), Wei Yuan(id:13342), Textex(id:27452), Ko-ken(id:49348), Sonic883(id:36201), Yas(id:739), 無空(id:17049), Kurihaya(id:132524), ウィキ豊(id:82961), 住谷瓜頂(id:22187), Maldoror(id:14782), M-sho-gun(id:88956), Izayohi(id:13095), พริกขี้หนู(id:131976), 与左衛門(id:159462), Chi-Ham(id:143515), ポピュラーポプラ(id:157724), COCKY(id:19672), Authority(id:10737), Himazin(id:22034), Kaznov17(id:68122), 遠藤(id:30275), Mikeneko(id:18205), Rusk(id:9895), Nakadati(id:26815), R28Bot(id:177951), 岡部碩道(id:182846), 蔭人(id:80171), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>