<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>閻魔</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emma</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emma</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enma</e>
<cmt>Enmaに修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>閻魔（えんま）は仏教・ヒンドゥー教などで地獄の主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Buddhism and Hindooism, Emma is the master of hell.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Buddhism and Hinduism, Emma is the master of Hell.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Buddhism and Hinduism, Enma is the master of Hell.</e>
<cmt>Enmaに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>また神とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is also considered Deity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is also considered to be a deity.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is also considered to be a deity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>冥界の王・総司として死者の生前の罪を裁くと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that Emma, as being the king of permanent dream land, has the authority to judge crimes committed by the dead while in life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that Emma, being the king of a permanent dreamland, has the authority to judge the crimes committed by the dead while in life.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that Enma, being the king of a permanent dreamland, has the authority to judge the crimes committed by the dead while in life.</e>
<cmt>Enmaに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>名称</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Appellation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Appellation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Appellation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>閻魔は、サンスクリット語及びパーリ語のヤマ (यम, Yama) の音訳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emma is a transliteration of Yama in Sanskrit and Pali.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emma is a transliteration of Yama in Sanskrit and Pali.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enma is a transliteration of Yama in Sanskrit and Pali.</e>
<cmt>Enmaに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>ヤマラージャ（यमराज, Yama-rāja、ラージャは王の意味）とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is also called Yama-rāja (rāja means a king).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is also called Yama-rāja (rāja means &quot;king&quot;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is also called Yama-rāja (rāja means &quot;king&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>音訳は閻魔羅闍（えんまらじゃ）、意訳は閻魔大王（えんまだいおう）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The transliteration is Emmaraja, and the free translation is Emma-daio.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The transliteration is Emmaraja, and the free translation is Emma-daio.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The transliteration is Enmaraja, and the free translation is Enma Daio (great king Enma).</e>
<cmt>Enmaに修正 閻魔大王の補足として　great king Enma　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>略して閻羅（えんら）、閻羅王（えんらおう）、閻王（えんおう）、閻（えん）とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For short, he is called Enra, Enra-o, En-o or En.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His name is abbreviated as Enra, Enra-o, En-o or En.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His name is abbreviated as Enra, Enra-o, En-o or En.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>Yama（閻魔）は、縛、雙世、雙王、静息、遮正、平等などと和訳される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yama (Emma) is translated into Japanese as baku (縛）、sosei (雙世), soo (雙王), seisoku (静息), shasei (遮正) or byodo(平等) etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yama (Emma) is translated into Japanese as baku (縛), sosei (雙世), soo (雙王), seisoku (静息), shasei (遮正) or byodo(平等), etc.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yama (Emma) is translated into Japanese as baku (縛), sosei (雙世), soo (雙王), seisoku (静息), shasei (遮正) or byodo(平等), etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>“縛”は罪人を捕縛する意、“雙世”は彼が世中、常に苦楽の2つの報いを受ける意、“雙王”は兄妹一対で2人並びたる王の意、また“平等”は罪人を平等に裁くとの意から、これらの和訳がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such Japanese translations derives from the the respective meaning of Chinese character; namely &quot;Baku (縛)&quot; means capturing criminals, &quot;sosei (雙世)&quot; means always suffering consequences of pain and joy, &quot;soo (雙王)&quot; means a king consisted of a pair of brother and sister and &quot;byodo (平等) means judging criminals fairly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such Japanese translations are derived from the respective meaning of Chinese character, namely &quot;Baku (縛),&quot; which means capturing criminals, &quot;sosei (雙世),&quot; which means always suffering the consequences of pain and joy; &quot;soo (雙王),&quot; which means a king consisting of a paired brother and sister, and &quot;byodo (平等),&quot; which means the fair judgment of criminals.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such Japanese translations are derived from the respective meaning of Chinese character, namely &quot;Baku (縛),&quot; which means capturing criminals, &quot;sosei (雙世),&quot; which means always suffering the consequences of pain and joy; &quot;soo (雙王),&quot; which means a king consisting of a paired brother and sister, and &quot;byodo (平等),&quot; which means the fair judgment of criminals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>各地の信仰</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Faith in various regions</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Faith in various regions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Faith in various regions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>本来はインド・イラン共通時代にまで遡る古い神格で、アヴェスターの聖王イマと同起源である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, he is a historic deity dating back to the era when India and Iran were unified and has the common origin with saint king Yima of Avesta.</e>
<cmt>アヴェスター→Avesta[http://rbedrosian.com/carn4.htm]イマ→Yima[http://rbedrosian.com/carn4.htm]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a deity that originated in the era when India and Persia were unified; he has the common origin with saintly king Yima of Avesta.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a deity that originated in the era when India and Persia were unified; he has the common origin with saintly king Yima of Avesta.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>『リグ・ヴェーダ』では人間の祖ともされ、ヤマとその妹ヤミーとの間に最初の人類が生まれ、人間で最初の死者となったゆえに死者の国の王となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ａｃｃｏｒｄｉｎｇ　ｔｏ　The Rig-Veda, he is considered to be the human ancester because the first human being was born of himself and his siter Yami and he bacame the king of the world of the dead since he was the first human being who died.</e>
<cmt>リグ・ヴェーダ→The Rig-Veda[英辞郎 on the WEB]ヤマ→Yama[http://www.aisf.or.jp/%7Ejaanus/]ヤミー→Yami[http://www.exoticindiaart.com/product/TN13/]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ａｃｃｏｒｄｉｎｇ　ｔｏ　the Rig-Veda, he is considered to be the human ancestor because the first human being was born of himself and his sister Yami; however, he became the king of the world of the dead because he was the first human being to die.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Rig-Veda,&quot; Yama is considered to be the human ancestor because the human race was born of Yama and his sister Yami; he became the king of the world of the dead because he was the first human being to die.</e>
<cmt>“himself” の意味が不明瞭なため、明確になるように修正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>虚空のはるか奥に住むという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is believed to be living in a far away universe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is believed to live in a far-away universe.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is believed to live in the deepest recesses of emptiness.</e>
<cmt>「虚空のはるか奥」の表現を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>インドでは、古くは生前によい行いをした人は天界にあるヤマの国に行くとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In ancient India, those who did benefaction while in life were believed to go to Yama&apos;s country located in the universe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In ancient India, those who performed benefactions in life were believed to go to Yama&apos;s country out in the universe.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In ancient India, those who performed benefactions in life were believed to go to Yama&apos;s country out in heaven.</e>
<cmt>天界をheaven　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>彼は時として“死”と同一視される向きもあったが、死者の楽園の王、死んで天界にある祖先を支配する神と考えられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sometimes he was identified with &quot;death&quot;, but generally he was perceived as the king of paradise of the dead or the deity who dominates ancestors residing in the universe after death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sometimes he was identified with &quot;death,&quot; but generally he was perceived as the king of the paradise of the dead or the deity that dominates ancestors residing in the universe after death.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sometimes he was identified with &quot;death,&quot; but generally he was perceived as the king of the paradise of the dead or the deity that dominates ancestors residing in the universe after death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし後に黄色い衣を着て頭に冠を被り、手に捕縄を持ち、それによって死者の霊魂を縛り、自らの住処・国に連行されると考えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But later, it was believed that he wore yellow vesture, held rope for arrest, bound the soul of the dead by this rope and bring them to the place where he resides.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, it was believed that he wore yellow vesture, held a rope for arrest, bound the soul of the dead with this rope and brought them to the place where he resided.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, it was believed that he wore yellow vesture and a wreath on his head, held a rope for arrest, bound the soul of the dead with this rope and brought them to the place where he resided.</e>
<cmt>冠を被り、を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>またさらに下界を支配して死者を裁き、地獄に落とす恐るべき神と考えられる様になり、ついには単なる死神としても描かれる様になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, he became being perceived as a dreadful deity who dominates the lower world, judges the daed and throws them into hell and eventually, he became being depicted as mere Death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, he became being perceived as a dreadful deity who dominated the lower world, judged the dead and threw them into Hell; eventually, he became a being depicted simply as Death.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, he became being perceived as a dreadful deity who dominated the lower world, judged the dead and threw them into Hell; eventually, he became a being depicted simply as Death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>骸骨の姿をした死の病魔「トゥルダク」を従える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is accompanied by Turdak, the devil of deadly disease, who has a shape of skelton.</e>
<cmt>トゥルダク→Turdak[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is accompanied by Turdak, the devil of deadly disease, who has the form of a skeleton.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is accompanied by &apos;Turdak,&apos; the devil of deadly disease, who has the form of a skeleton.</e>
<cmt>括弧追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>現在のインドでは、青い肌で水牛に乗った姿で描かれる（本来は黒い肌だが美術上の様式として青く描かれる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contemporary India, he is depicted as the one who has blue skin and is riding on a buffalow (although his skin is black-colored in nature, he is depicted as blue-colored due to the art style).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contemporary India he is depicted as the one who has blue skin and is riding on a buffalo (although his skin is black-colored in nature, he is depicted as blue-colored due to the artistic style).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contemporary India he is depicted as the one who has blue skin and is riding on a buffalo (although his skin is black-colored in nature, he is depicted as blue-colored due to the artistic style).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="20">
<j>のちに仏教に混入されて地獄の主と位置づけられるようになった、と一般的には考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is generally believed that he was mixed in Buddhism later on and became been deemed as the king of hell.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is generally believed that he was incorporated into Buddhism later and was deemed as the king of Hell.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is generally believed that he was incorporated into Buddhism later and was deemed to be the king of Hell.</e>
<cmt>表現スタイル。 “deemed as”=&gt;”deemed to be” もしくは“regarded as”</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="21">
<j>ただし一説には、本来はヴェーダのYamaという同一尊から二途に分かれていった、とも考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, one theory holds that the same deity, Yama of Rig-Veda, diverged into two genealogies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, one theory holds that the same deity, Yama of Rig-Veda, diverged into two genealogies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, one theory holds that the same deity, Yama of Rig-Veda, diverged into two genealogies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>その二途とは</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What are these two genealogy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What are these two genealogies?</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These two genealogies are as follows;</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="23">
<j>1つに、下界の暗黒世界、すなわち地獄界の王となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One went to a black world in lower world and became the king of hell.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One went to a black world in a lower realm and became the king of Hell.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One went to a black world in a lower realm and became the king of Hell.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>つまり本項の閻魔。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is Emma described in this section.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is Emma described in this section.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This section describes Enma.</e>
<cmt>文法。 “This is Enma described in this section.”=&gt;”This section describes Enma.“</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="25">
<j>2つに、上界の光明世界、すなわち六欲天の第3天である夜摩天、あるいは焔摩天。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The other went to a bright world in upper world and became Yamaten, the third heaven of the six heavens in the realm of desire in Buddhist cosmology, or Emmaten.</e>
<cmt>六欲天→the six heavens in the realm of desire in Buddhist cosmology[http://www.aisf.or.jp/%7Ejaanus/]夜摩天→Yamaten[http://www.aisf.or.jp/%7Ejaanus/]焔摩天→Emmaten[http://www.aisf.or.jp/%7Ejaanus/]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The other went to a bright world in an upper realm and became Yamaten, the third heaven of the six heavens in the realm of desire in Buddhist cosmology, or Emmaten.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The other went to a bright world in an upper realm and became Yamaten, the third heaven of the six heavens in the realm of desire in Buddhist cosmology, or Enmaten.</e>
<cmt>Enmaに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="26">
<j>しかし、閻魔はYama（ヤマ）であるが、夜摩・焔摩はYaamaあるいはYaamaa（ヤーマ、ヤーマー）なので、本来は関係ないが混同されたと考える向きもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, some people think that these two were basically not related but might have been confused because 閻魔 (Emma) is Yama while 夜摩・焔摩 (Yama/Emma) is Yaama or Yaamaa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, some people believe these two were basically unrelated but might have been confused because 閻魔 (Emma) is Yama while 夜摩・焔摩 (Yama/Emma) is Yaama or Yaamaa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, some people believe these two were basically unrelated but might have been confused because 閻魔 (Enma) is Yama while 夜摩・焔摩 (Yama/Enma) is Yaama or Yaamaa.</e>
<cmt>Enmaに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="27">
<j>中国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">China</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">China</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">China</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>中国に伝わると、道教の冥界思想と関連付けられていた泰山府君と習合した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After introduced in China, he amalgamated with Taizafukun, Taishanfuzhun, who were associated with the Taoism&apos;s philosophy of permanent dream land.</e>
<cmt>道教→Taoism[Webster Online Dictionary]泰山府君→Taizanfukun, Taishanfuzhun[http://www.aisf.or.jp/~jaanus/deta/j/juuou.htm]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he was introduced in China, he became amalgamated with Taizafukun, Taishanfuzhun, who were associated with the Taoist philosophy of a permanent dreamland.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he was introduced in China, he became amalgamated with Taizanfukun (Taishanfuzhun), who were associated with the Taoist philosophy of a permanent dreamland.</e>
<cmt>Taizanfukun (Taishanfuzhun)　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="29">
<j>やがて晩唐に撰述された偽経である『閻羅王授記四衆逆修生七往生浄土経』（略して『預修十王生七経』）により十王信仰と結び付けられ、地獄の裁判官の一人として「人が死ぬと裁く」という役割を担い、信仰の対象となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lator on, he was linked to the faith of Juo (ten kings) by the bogus sutra called &quot;Enra-o-juki Shishu Gyakushu Shoshichiojo Jodo-kyo Sutra&quot; (for short, &quot;Yoshu Juo Shoshici-kyo Sutra, Yuxiu Shiwang Shengdijing Sutra&quot;) which was compiled in the era of late Tans dynasty and became the object of faith as one of the judges of hell whose role is to judge persons after their death.</e>
<cmt>唐→Tang[英辞郎 on the WEB]閻羅王授記四衆逆修生七往生浄土経→Enra-o-juki Shishu Gyakushu Shoshichiojo Jodo-kyo Sutra[定訳不明, 読み不明]預修十王生七経→Yoshu Juo Shoshichi-kyo Sutra, Yuxiu Shiwang Shengqijing Sutra[http://www.city.iga.lg.jp/ctg/07980/07980.html, http://www.aisf.or.jp/%7Ejaanus/]十王→Juo, ten kings[http://www.aisf.or.jp/%7Ejaanus/]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eventually, he was linked to the faith of Juo (Ten Kings) by the bogus sutra called &quot;Enra-o-juki Shishu Gyakushu Shoshichiojo Jodo-kyo Sutra&quot; (abbreviated as &quot;Yoshu Juo Shoshichi-kyo Sutra, Yuxiu Shiwang Shengdijing Sutra&quot;), which was compiled in the era of the late Tang dynasty and became the object of faith as one of the judges of Hell, whose role was to judge persons after death.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eventually, he was linked to the faith of Juo (Ten Kings) by the bogus sutra called &quot;Enra-o-juki Shishu Gyakushu Shoshichiojo Jodo-kyo Sutra&quot; (abbreviated as &quot;Yoshu Juo Shoshichi-kyo Sutra, Yuxiu Shiwang Shengdijing Sutra&quot;), which was compiled in the era of the late Tang dynasty and became the object of faith as one of the judges of Hell, whose role was to judge persons after death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>現在よく知られるあの唐の官人風の衣を纏った姿はここで成立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His well-known figure with wearing Tang officials style vesture was established at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His well-known figure, clothed in the vestments of a Tang official, was established at that time.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His well-known figure, clothed in the familiar vestments of a Tang official, was established at that time.</e>
<cmt>よく知られた　を追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="31">
<j>日本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>日本仏教においては後に閻魔の本地とされる地蔵菩薩が奈良時代には『地蔵十輪経』によって伝来していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With regard to Japanese Buddhism, Jizo Bosatsu, which was deemed as Honji (Substance) of Emma later on, had been introduced in Nara Period through &quot;Jizojurin kyo Sutra&quot;</e>
<cmt>本地→Honji, Substance[http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110000448382/, http://www.aisf.or.jp/%7Ejaanus/]地蔵菩薩→Jizo Bosatsu奈良時代→Nara Period地蔵十輪経→Jizojurin-kyo Sutra[http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/guide/jj/jj8_1_sa.html]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding Japanese Buddhism, Jizo Bosatsu, which was later deemed to be the honji (substance) of Emma, had been introduced in the Nara period through &quot;Jizojurin kyo Sutra.&quot;</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding Japanese Buddhism, Jizo Bosatsu, which was later deemed to be the honji (substance) of Enma, had been introduced in the Nara period through &quot;Jizojurin-kyo Sutra.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Enma　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>しかし、現世利益優先の当時の世相のもとでは普及しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But it did not become widespread under the then social situation where worldly interest was prioritized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it did not become widespread under the social situation in which worldly interest was prioritized.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it did not become widespread under the social situation in which worldly interest was prioritized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="34">
<j>平安時代になって末法思想が蔓延するにしたがい源信_(僧侶)らによって平安初期には貴族、平安後期には一般民衆と広く布教されるようになり、鎌倉初期には預修十王生七経から更なる偽経の『地蔵菩薩発心因縁十王経』（略して『地蔵十王経』）が生み出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Heian Period when Mappo-shiso (the &quot;end of the world&quot; belief) prevailed, it was missionized by Genshin (monk) etc. to the nobility in early Heian Period and widely to ordinary people in late Heian Period and in early Kamakura Period, &quot;Jizo Bosatsu Hossin Innen Juo-kyo Sutra&quot; (&quot;Jizojuo-kyo&quot; for short), which was also a bogus sutra, was created based on Yoshu Juo Shoshichi-kyo Sutra (Yuxiu Shiwang Shengqijing).</e>
<cmt>末法思想→Mappo-shiso, the &quot;end of the world&quot; belief[http://www.aisf.or.jp/%7Ejaanus/] 地蔵菩薩発心因縁十王経→Jizo Bosatsu Hossin Innen Juo-kyo Sutra[http://www.aisf.or.jp/%7Ejaanus/]地蔵十王経→Jizojuo-kyo Sutra[http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110002706853/]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early Heian period when Mappo-shiso (the &quot;end of the world&quot; belief) prevailed, it was expounded by the monk Genshin and others to the nobility and then widely to ordinary people in the late Heian and early Kamakura periods; &quot;Jizo Bosatsu Hossin Innen Juo-kyo Sutra&quot; (&quot;Jizojuo-kyo&quot; for short), which was also a bogus sutra, was created based on Yoshu Juo Shoshichi-kyo Sutra (Yuxiu Shiwang Shengqijing).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early Heian period when Mappo-shiso (the &quot;end of the world&quot; belief) prevailed, it was expounded by the monk Genshin and others to the nobility in the early Heian period and then widely to ordinary people in the late Heian period, and early in the early Kamakura period, &quot;Jizo Bosatsu Hosshin Innen Juo-kyo Sutra&quot; (&quot;Jizojuo-kyo&quot; for short), which was also a bogus sutra, was created based on Yoshu Juo Shoshichi-kyo Sutra (Yuxiu Shiwang Shengqijing).</e>
<cmt>一部修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="35">
<j>これにより閻魔の本地が地蔵菩薩であるといわれ（ここから、一部で言われている「地蔵様 閻魔大魔王」の説が派生したと考えられるが、詳細は不明である）、地蔵のみならず十王信仰も普及するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thanks to the above, Jizo Bosatu was said to be the Honji of Emma (although it is conceivable that the theory claiming &quot;Jizo is Emma Daimao (Great Satan)&quot;was derived from this fact, details are unknown) and not only Jizo but also faith for Juo started to spread.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thanks to the above, the theory that Jizo Bosatsu was the honji of Emma (although it is conceivable that the theory claiming that &quot;Jizo is Emma Daimao (Great Satan)&quot;) was derived from this fact, though the details aren&apos;t known; however, not only did faith in Jizo spread but faith in Juo did as well.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thanks to the above, the theory that Jizo Bosatsu was the honji of Enma (although it is conceivable that the theory claiming that &apos;Jizo is Enma Daimao (Great Satan)&apos;) was derived from this fact, although the details aren&apos;t known; however, not only did faith in Jizo spread but faith in Juo did as well.</e>
<cmt>Enma　としました。though→althoughに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="36">
<j>閻魔は地獄と浄土を往来できるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emma is believed to be able to travel back and forth between the hell and the pure land.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emma is believed to be able to travel back and forth between Hell and the Pure Land.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enma is believed to be able to travel back and forth between Hell and the Pure Land.</e>
<cmt>Enma　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="37">
<j>なお前述の通り、十二天の焔摩天は同じルーツを持つ神ともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As previously mentioned, Emmaten, one of Juniten, is said to be the deity having a common ancestry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As previously mentioned, Emmaten, one of the Juniten, is said to be the deity with a common ancestry.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As previously mentioned, Enmaten, one of the Juniten (twelve deities), is said to have the same origins as Enma.</e>
<cmt>I deleted the second &quot;deity&quot; to avoid repetition.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>中国では閻魔天が閻魔大王に習合されていたが、日本に伝わった時にそれぞれ別個に伝わったため同一存在が二つに分かれたとも考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Emmaten was amalgamated with Emma-daio in China, these two were separately introduced into Japan and it might be the reason why the same being was split into two.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Emmaten was amalgamated with Emma-daio in China, the two were separately introduced into Japan, which might be the reason that the same was split into two.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Enmaten was amalgamated with Enma-daio in China, the two were separately introduced into Japan, which might be the reason that the same was split into two.</e>
<cmt>Enma　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="39">
<j>日本では、嘘をついた子供を叱る際「閻魔様に舌を抜いて貰う」という俗信による民間伝承がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When scolding a child who told a lie, there is a folk tradition in Japan to say &quot;I will ask Emma to yarn out your tongue&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When scolding a child who has told a lie, there is a folk tradition in Japan to say, &quot;I will ask Emma to yank out your tongue&quot;.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When scolding a child who has told a lie, there is a folk tradition in Japan to say, &apos;I will ask Enma to yank out your tongue.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Enma　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="40">
<j>大阪市浪速区には、閻魔を祀った西方寺閻魔堂（正式には「合邦辻閻魔堂西方寺」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saiho-ji-temple Emma-do (official name is &quot;Gappo-ga-tsuji Emma-do Saiho-ji Temple&quot;) located in Naniwa Ward Osaka enshrines Emma.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saiho-ji-temple Emma-do (official name is &quot;Gappo-ga-tsuji Emma-do Saiho-ji Temple&quot;) located in Naniwa Ward Osaka enshrines Emma.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saiho-ji Temple Enma-do (official name is &apos;Gappo-ga-tsuji Enma-do Saiho-ji Temple&apos;) located in Naniwa Ward, Osaka City enshrines Enma.</e>
<cmt>Enma　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>創建は伝・聖徳太子）があり、浄瑠璃の「摂州合邦辻」の舞台にもなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the temple was built by Prince Shotoku and is the scene of Sesshu Gappo-ga-tsuj, Joruri.</e>
<cmt>摂州合邦辻→Sesshu Gappo-ga-tsuji[http://www.lares.dti.ne.jp/~bunraku/guidance/top_gapp.html]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the temple was built by Prince Shotoku and is the scene of Sesshu Gappo-ga-tsuj (Joruri).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the temple was built by Prince Shotoku and is the scene of &apos;Sesshu Gappo-ga-tsuji&apos; (in Joruri (Japanese-type puppet play)).</e>
<cmt>浄瑠璃の補足として　(Japanese-type puppet play)　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Elppin(id:200058), Bakkai(id:7233), Nnh(id:474), 九鬼備助(id:45564), S.S.Exp.Hashimoto(id:4001), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Cureless(id:85558), Wei Yuan(id:13342), Tokek(id:17356), Knife(id:10235), Kamakura(id:472), Gombe(id:27), 犬養裕仁(id:96188), 水野麒麟(id:4014), セーラ(id:202326), Adbird(id:202973), 無空(id:17049), -1g(id:67660), ウィキ豊(id:82961), GENMEI(id:31879), Izayohi(id:13095), Peehyoro Acala(id:170), Jikk(id:34812), Whiteowl(id:11500), 水野白楓(id:22811), Authority(id:10737), Artfan(id:15278), Kamitani(id:30757), M-Falcon(id:1227), Nakadati(id:26815), Boca samba(id:137526), Iokseng(id:92490), ないです(id:68294), 小太刀(id:18154), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>