<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>証如</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shonyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shonyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shonyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>証如（しょうにょ、1516年12月13日（永正13年11月20日 (旧暦)） － 1554年9月9日（天文 (元号)23年8月13日 (旧暦)））は、戦国時代_(日本)の浄土真宗の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shonyo (December 13, 1516 (old lunar calendar) - August 13, 1554 (old lunar calendar)) was a priest of Jodo Shinshu sect in the age of civil war (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shonyo (December 13, 1516 (old lunar calendar) - August 13, 1554 (old lunar calendar)) was a priest of the Jodo Shinshu sect in the age of civil war (Japan).</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shonyo (December 23, 1516 - September 19, 1554) was a priest of Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) during the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリウス暦にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>本願寺第10世。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the 10th head priest of Hongwan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the 10th head priest of Hongwan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the 10th head priest of Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>諱は光教。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His posthumous name was Kokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His posthumous name was Kokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His posthumous name was Kokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>蓮如の曾孫で、円如（父実如からの継職前に死去したため本願寺歴代に入らない）の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a grandson of Rennyo and a son of Ennyo (who was not included in successive head priests because he had died before succession from his father Jitsunyo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a grandson of Rennyo and a son of Ennyo (who was not included among successive head priests because he had died before succession from his father Jitsunyo).</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a grandson of Rennyo and a son of Ennyo (who was not included among successive head priests because he had died before succession from his father Jitsunyo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>母は蓮如6男蓮淳の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of Renjun, the sixth son of Rennyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was a daughter of Renjun, the sixth son of Rennyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of Renjun, the sixth son of Rennyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>1525年、祖父実如の死去により、10歳で本願寺第10代門主となり、実如の弟で証如の母方の祖父である蓮淳の後見を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1525 he became the 10th Monshu, Hongwanji-ha head priest, at the age of 10 because of the death of his grandfather Jitsunyo, and was placed under the guardianship of Renjun, who was a brother of Jitsunyo and his maternal grandfather.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1525 he became the 10th Monshu, Hongwanji-ha head priest, at the age of 10 due to the death of his grandfather, Jitsunyo, and was placed under the guardianship of Renjun, who was a brother of Jitsunyo and his maternal grandfather.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1525 he became the 10th chief priest of Hongan-ji Temple at the age of 10 due to the death of his grandfather, Jitsunyo, and was placed under the guardianship of Renjun, who was a brother of Jitsunyo and his maternal grandfather.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>1527年には、当時の本願寺教団と中央権力との親睦を深め安泰を図るため、摂関家に接近して関白九条尚経の猶子となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1527 in order to promote friendship between Hongwan-ji group and central government and achieve peace and security, he approached to Sekkan-ke Regent Family (摂関家) and became an adopted child of Hisatsune KUJO, a chief adviser to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1527, in order to promote friendship between the Hongwan-ji group and the central government and to achieve peace and security, he approached the Sekkan-ke Regent Family (摂関家) and became an adopted child of Hisatsune KUJO, a chief adviser to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1527, in order to promote friendship between the Hongan-ji religious group and the central government and to achieve peace and security, he approached the Sekkan-ke (the families which produced regents) and became an adopted child of Hisatsune KUJO, a chief adviser to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>摂関家を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>1531年には本願寺教団内部で対立（後の山科本願寺焼討事件まで含めて享禄・天文の乱と呼ぶ）が起こるが、証如はこれを抑えて法主の指導力強化に努めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1531 a conflict within Hongwan-ji group occurred (it is called Kyoroku-Tembun no Ran (Kyoroku-Tembun Rebellion) including the later incident that Yamashina Hongwan-ji Temple was burned down), but Syonyo resolved this conflict and made effort to strengthen leadership of Hoshu (high priest).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1531, a conflict within the Hongwan-ji group occurred (it is called the Kyoroku-Tembun no Ran (Kyoroku-Tembun Rebellion) and includes the later incident where Yamashina Hongwan-ji Temple was burned down), but Syonyo resolved this conflict and made efforts to strengthen the leadership of Hoshu (high priest).</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1531, a conflict within the Hongan-ji religious group occurred (it is called the Kyoroku-Tenbun War (Kyoroku-Tenbun Rebellion) including the later incidents until when Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple was burned down), but Syonyo resolved this conflict and made efforts to strengthen the leadership of Hoshu (high priest).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>翌1532年年には、管領細川晴元の要請を受けて門徒を動員し、三好元長を敗死に追いやったが、晴元はこれによってかえって本願寺の実力を恐れ、京都の日蓮宗教団や六角定頼と手を結んで、当時の本願寺の本拠地であった山科本願寺を攻撃し、これを焼き討ちにした（天文法華の乱）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following year, 1532, he called out Monto (follower) according to a request by the control Harumoto HOSOKAWA, and subverted Motonaga MIYOSHI, by which Harumoto feared the power of Hongwan-ji Temple so that he attacked Yamashina Hongwan-ji Temple, the home of Hongwan-ji Temple at that time, and burned it down, holding hands with Nichiren sect and Sadayori ROKKAKU in Kyoto (Tembun-hokke no Ran (Tembun-hokke Rebellion)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following year, 1532, he called out Monto (follower) according to a request due to the control of Harumoto HOSOKAWA, and subverted Motonaga MIYOSHI, the result of which Harumoto feared the power of the Hongwan-ji Temple, so he attacked Yamashina Hongwan-ji Temple, the home of Hongwan-ji Temple at that time, and burned it down, joining forces with the Nichiren sect and Sadayori ROKKAKU in Kyoto (Tembun-hokke no Ran (Tembun-hokke Rebellion)).</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following year (1532), he mobilized his followers to subvert Motonaga Miyoshi at the request of Harumoto HOSOKAWA, who held the post of Kanrei (shogunal deputy); however, in fear of the power held by Hongan-ji Temple, Harumoto attacked and burned down Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple, which was home to the Hongan-ji Temple school at that time, in cooperation with the Nichiren sect groups and Sadayori ROKKAKU (this incident is known as the Tenbun-hokke Riot).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。In English, it&apos;s usual to identify whose followers you are talking about. I assume that &quot;he&quot; refers to Shonyo, and that the followers are his (i.e. Shonyo&apos;s). I also assume that &quot;Tenbun-hokke War&quot; is the name given to the incident in which Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple was burnt down. Finally, &quot;war&quot; seems a somewhat strong word to use as a rendering of 乱 so I have changed this to &quot;riot&quot; (and &quot;Hokke riot&quot; does seem to have some currency on Google). &quot;war&quot; may need to be changed to &quot;riot&quot; on other places too.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>山科本願寺を追われた証如は、居所を大阪の石山御坊に移し、石山本願寺を新たな教団の本拠地とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shyono, who escaped from Yamashina Hongwan-ji Temple, moved to Ishiyama Gobo in Osaka and made Ishiyama Hongwan-ji Temple the new home of the group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shyono, who escaped from Yamashina Hongwan-ji Temple, moved to Ishiyama Gobo in Osaka and made Ishiyama Hongwan-ji Temple the new home of the group.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shyono, who escaped from Yamashina Hongwan-ji Temple, moved to Ishiyama Gobo (branch temple) in Osaka and made Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple the new home of the group.</e>
<cmt>用語に英訳を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その後は晴元の養女如春尼（左大臣三条公頼の末娘。長姉は晴元に、次姉は武田信玄に嫁ぐ）を長男顕如の妻に迎えて晴元と和睦し、室町幕府とも親密な関係を築いて中央との関係修復に努め、本願寺の体制強化を進めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he made peace with Harumoto by making his first son Kennyo marry with Nyoenni, an adopted daughter of Harumoto (the youngest daughter of Sadaijin (minister of the left) Kinyori SANJO. Her eldest sister married with Harumoto and her second eldest sister married with Shingen TAKEDA.), built rapport with Muromachi Shogunate to mend a relationship with the central government and promoted to strengthen the system of Hongwan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he made peace with Harumoto by making his first son Kennyo marry Nyoenni, an adopted daughter of Harumoto (the youngest daughter of Sadaijin (minister of the left) Kinyori SANJO. Her eldest sister married Harumoto and her second eldest sister married Shingen TAKEDA.), and built rapport with the Muromachi Shogunate to mend the relationship with the central government and promote strengthening of the system of Hongwan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he made peace with Harumoto by making his first son Kennyo marry Nyoenni, an adopted daughter of Harumoto (the youngest daughter of Sadaijin (minister of the left) Kinyori SANJO. Her eldest sister married Harumoto and her second eldest sister married Shingen TAKEDA), and built rapport with the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) to mend the relationship with the central government and promote strengthening of the system of Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>用語の英訳を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また、天文法華の乱を教訓として、各地の一向一揆に対してもみだりに乱を起こさないように命じている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, he ordered Monto in various places not to rise in a riot of Ikko Ikki easily as a lesson of Tembun-hokke no Ran.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, he ordered Monto in various places not to rise in a riot of Ikko Ikki easily, as a Tembun-hokke no Ran lesson.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having learnt his lesson with the Tenbun-hokke riot, he also ordered followers of the Ikko Ikki (League of the Single-Minded, established by members of Jodo-shinshu) school of Buddhism in various places not to riot without good reason.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>1549年には後奈良天皇より『三十六人集』を下賜される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1549 he was given &quot;Sanjurokunin-shu&quot; by Emperor Gonara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1549 he was given &quot;Sanjurokunin-shu&quot; by Emperor Gonara.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1549 he was given &quot;Sanjurokunin-shu&quot; (Collected Poems of Thirty-six Poets) by Emperor Gonara.</e>
<cmt>用語の英訳を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これは、後に息子・顕如の時代に石山合戦の和議に尽くした前関白近衛前久に贈ろうとしたものの、「天下の宝物をみだりに遣り取りすべきでない」として辞退したという代物で現在も西本願寺に所蔵されている国宝である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is what Sakihisa KONOE, the former chief adviser to the Emperor, who made effort to make peace in Ishiyama War, was asked to be given at the later age of Shonyo&apos;s son Kennyo, but declined because &apos;a national treasure should not be given easily,&apos; and it has been in the possession of Hongwan-ji Temple as a national treasure still now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is what Sakihisa KONOE, the former chief adviser to the Emperor, who made efforts to make peace in the Ishiyama War, was asked to be given when Shonyo&apos;s son Kennyo was older, but was declined because &apos;a national treasure should not be given easily,&apos; and it has been in the possession of Hongwan-ji Temple as a national treasure up until the current time.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, in the days of Shonyo&apos;s son Kennyo, the book was to have been given to Sakihisa KONOE, the former chief adviser to the emperor who had worked to bring about peace during the Ishiyama War, but he refused to accept it on the grounds that &apos;a national treasure should not be given away without good reason,&apos; and the book has been in the possession of Hongan-ji Temple as a national treasure ever since.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>また、証如の代に本願寺は、加賀一向一揆の調停という形で北陸地方の門徒集団への介入を深め、1546年には金沢市に御坊を築いて同地方における門徒の統制を強化したが、これは朝倉氏との対立もあって、証如の時代には必ずしも十分に達成されなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, at the age of Shonyo, Hongwan-ji Temple intervened Monto group of Hokuriku District as mediation of Kaga Ikko Ikki and strengthen the control of Monto in that district by constructing Gobo in Kanazawa City in 1546, but this aim was no fully achieved at the age of Shonyo because of conflict with Asakura clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, during the age of Shonyo, Hongwan-ji Temple intervened with the Monto group of Hokuriku District to mediate the Kaga Ikko Ikki and strengthen the control of Monto in that district by constructing Gobo in Kanazawa City in 1546, but this aim was not fully achieved during the age of Shonyo because of conflict with the Asakura clan.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, during the days of Shonyo, Hongan-ji Temple began to intervene even more actively on behalf of their followers in the Hokuriku region by acting as a mediator in the Kaga Ikko Ikki (an uprising of Ikko sect followers in Kaga), and to strengthen the control of their followers in the region, they built a Gobo in Kanazawa City in 1546, but they did not fully succeed in their aim during Shonyo&apos;s lifetime as a result of a conflict with the Asakura clan.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。I have had to rewrite this quite a bit to get it to make sense in English.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>1554年に39歳の若さで死去し、後を12歳の長男の顕如が継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1554 he died at a young age of 39, and his eldest son Kennyo succeeded him at the age of 12.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1554 he died at the young age of 39, and his eldest son Kennyo succeeded him at the age of 12.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1554 he died at the young age of 39, and his eldest son Kennyo succeeded him at the age of 12.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Resto1578(id:168692), Tomzo(id:16777), Nnh(id:474), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), Kstigarbha(id:13376), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), Safkan(id:423), ブレイズマン(id:183852), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>