<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>玄旨帰命壇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genshi Kimyo-dan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genshi Kimyo-dan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genshi Kimyo-dan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>玄旨帰命壇（げんしきみょうだん）とは、かつて天台宗に存在した一派である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genshi Kimyo-dan was one of schools which used to exist in Tendai sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genshi Kimyo-dan was a school which used to exist in the Tendai sect.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genshi Kimyo-dan was a school which used to exist in the Tendai sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>のちに淫祠邪教扱いされ江戸時代には絶滅したといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said to be treated as Inshi jakyo (evil heresies) later and become extinct in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said to have been treated as Inshi jakyo (evil heresies) later and become extinct in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said to have been treated as Inshi jakyo (evil heresies) later and become extinct in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>比叡山の常行三昧堂の本尊である摩多羅神を祀って修する一種の口伝灌頂といわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said to be a kind of oral transmissions of kanjo (a ceremony to be the successor) to learn enshrining Matarashin which is honzon (principal image of Buddha) of Jogyo Zanmai-do Hall in Hiei-zan Mountain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said to be a kind of oral transmissions of kanjo (a ceremony to be the successor) to learn enshrining Matarashin which is honzon (principal image of Buddha) of Jogyo Zanmai-do Hall in Hiei-zan Mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said to be a kind of oral transmissions of kanjo (a ceremony to be the successor) to learn enshrining Matarashin which is honzon (principal image of Buddha) of Jogyo Zanmai-do Hall in Hiei-zan Mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>玄旨帰命檀は、玄旨檀と帰命檀を合わせたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genshi Kimyo-dan is the combination of Genshi-dan and Kimyo-dan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genshi Kimyo-dan is the combination of Genshi-dan and Kimyo-dan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genshi Kimyo-dan is the combination of Genshi-dan and Kimyo-dan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>玄旨檀とは、一心三観の深旨を口伝面授する玄旨灌頂であり、法華の法水を授者の頭頂部にそそぐ儀式である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genshi-dan is Genshi-kanjo to orally transmit the deep meaning of isshin sangan (threefold contemplation in a single mind), and the ceremony to pour Hosui of Hokke onto the top of head of the person to receive.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genshi-dan is Genshi-kanjo to orally transmit the deep meaning of isshin sangan (threefold contemplation in a single mind), and the ceremony to pour Hosui of Hokke onto the top of head of the person receiving.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genshi-dan is Genshi-kanjo to orally transmit the deep meaning of isshin sangan (threefold contemplation in a single mind), and the ceremony to pour Hosui of Hokke onto the top of head of the person receiving.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>帰命檀とは、衆生の命の根源は天台の理である一念三千にあるとして、それを実現する儀式である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kimyo-dan is the ceremony to realize that rise of lives of all living things exists in the Three Thousand Realms Contained in One Mind which is the reason of Tendai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kimyo-dan is the ceremony to realize that rise of lives of all living things exists in the Three Thousand Realms Contained in One Mind which is the reason for Tendai.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kimyo-dan is the ceremony to realize that rise of lives of all living things exists in the Three Thousand Realms Contained in One Mind which is the reason for Tendai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>『渓嵐拾葉集』第39「常行堂摩多羅神の事」に記されるように、摩多羅神は円珍が唐から帰国する際に感得して、常行堂に勧請したと伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As shown in the 39th article &apos;Jogyo-do Hall Matarashin no Koto&apos; of &quot;Keiran shuyo shu&quot; (a collection of oral transmissions in the Japanese Tendai Sect which contains four stories about Myoe), it was said that Enchin was inspired by Matarashin on the way back from Tang and ceremonially transferred to Jogyo-do Hall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As shown in the 39th article &apos;Jogyo-do Hall Matarashin no Koto&apos; of &quot;Keiran shuyo shu&quot; (a collection of oral transmissions in the Japanese Tendai Sect which contains four stories about Myoe), it was said that Enchin was inspired by Matarashin on the way back from Tang and ceremonially transferred to Jogyo-do Hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As shown in the 39th article &apos;Jogyo-do Hall Matarashin no Koto&apos; of &quot;Keiran shuyo shu&quot; (a collection of oral transmissions in the Japanese Tendai Sect which contains four stories about Myoe), it was said that Enchin was inspired by Matarashin on the way back from Tang and ceremonially transferred to Jogyo-do Hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし実際は、摩多羅神は平安時代から鎌倉時代にかけて成立した玄旨帰命壇の本尊として成立したものと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Matarashin was actually considered to establish as honzon of Genshi Kimyo-dan which was set up from the Heian period to the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Matarashin was actually considered to have been established as honzon of Genshi Kimyo-dan which was set up from the Heian period to the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Matarashin was actually considered to have been established as honzon of Genshi Kimyo-dan which was set up from the Heian period to the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>この修法は、中世に興った天台宗の口伝法流に源を発している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This learning method had its origin in the orally transmitting system of teachings of Tendai sect generated in the medieval period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This learning method had its origin in the orally transmitted system of teachings by theTendai sect generated during the medieval period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This learning method had its origin in the orally transmitted system of teachings by theTendai sect generated during the medieval period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その流派である恵檀二流のうち、檀那流を正嫡とし、恵心流を傍流として相承したといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of Edan niryu (two schools of the Japanese Tendai Sect; Eshin school and Danna school) from that school, Danna school is said to succeed as the head school and Eshin school as the branch.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of Edan niryu (two schools of the Japanese Tendai Sect; Eshin school and Danna school) from that school, Danna school is said to have succeeded as the head school and Eshin school as the branch.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of Edan niryu (two schools of the Japanese Tendai Sect; Eshin school and Danna school) from that school, Danna school is said to have succeeded as the head school and Eshin school as the branch.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>南北朝時代 (日本)にこの玄旨壇灌頂を受けた円観が、この教理を興隆に鋭意努め『天台灌頂玄旨』、『玄旨帰命檀法』を伝えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enkan who experienced this Genshi-dan kanjo in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan) made effort to prosper this doctrine and transmitted &quot;Tendai Kanjo Genshi&quot; and &quot;Genshi Kimyo-dan doctrine&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enkan who experienced this Genshi-dan kanjo in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan) made efforts to have the doctrine prosper transmitted &quot;Tendai Kanjo Genshi&quot; and &quot;Genshi Kimyo-dan doctrine&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enkan who experienced this Genshi-dan kanjo in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan) made efforts to have the doctrine prosper transmitted &quot;Tendai Kanjo Genshi&quot; and &quot;Genshi Kimyo-dan doctrine&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>一説に、円観と交流があった真言宗・小野流の文観が真言立川流を大成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One theory is that Monkan who was from Shingon sect Ono school and communicated with Enkan perfected Shingon Tachikawa School.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One theory is that Monkan who was from Shingon sect Ono school and communicated with Enkan perfected the Shingon Tachikawa School.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One theory is that Monkan who was from Shingon sect Ono school and communicated with Enkan perfected the Shingon Tachikawa School.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>それが次第に蔓延するに及び、ついにその影響が天台の檀那流の一派である慧光房流に波及し、神聖であった玄旨帰命壇が淫祠的な傾向を帯びたともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As it gradually penetrated, this influence finally reached Ekobo school which was one of Tendai sect Danna schools and holy Genshi Kimyo-dan tended to be evil.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処「慧光房流」については読み未確認</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As it gradually penetrated, this influence finally reached the Ekobo school which was one of the Tendai sect Danna schools while holy Genshi Kimyo-dan tended to be evil.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As it gradually penetrated, this influence finally reached the Ekobo school which was one of the Tendai sect Danna schools while holy Genshi Kimyo-dan tended to be evil.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>ただし立川流の教義・儀式は、批判弾圧した側の文献記述によるもので疑問視されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the doctrine and ceremony of Tachikawa school was questioned with the descriptions in the documents written by critics and repressing parties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the doctrine and ceremony of Tachikawa school was questioned with descriptions in the documents written by critics and repressing parties.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the doctrine and ceremony of Tachikawa school was questioned with descriptions in the documents written by critics and repressing parties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>のちに阿弥陀如来への浄土信仰も取り込まれ、本堂の壇上には阿弥陀仏の像を安置した、行者の呼吸の吸吐を阿弥陀の来迎浄土と感じ取り、そこに生死の根源を究めるとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It took in Jodo-shinko (the Pure Land faith) to Amida Nyorai (Amitabha Tathagata) later, putting Amidabutsu-zo (a statue of Amitabha) on the alter of Hondo (main sanctuary), and feels breathing of practitioners to be Pure Land for the descent of Amida where rise of lives lies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It took in Jodo-shinko (the Pure Land faith) to Amida Nyorai (Amitabha Tathagata) later, putting Amidabutsu-zo (a statue of Amitabha) on the alter of Hondo (main sanctuary), and treated the breath practitioners to be Pure Land for the descent of Amida where the rise of lives lie.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It took in Jodo-shinko (the Pure Land faith) to Amida Nyorai (Amitabha Tathagata) later, putting Amidabutsu-zo (a statue of Amitabha) on the alter of Hondo (main sanctuary), and treated the breath practitioners to be Pure Land for the descent of Amida where the rise of lives lie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>さらに日月の精気が父母和合のときの息風に乗り胎内に入ることに始まると説く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, it preaches that the origin of life generates from the lunisolar spirit coming into the body in the harmony between the father and mother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, it preaches that the origin of life is generated from the lunisolar spirit coming into the body from the harmony between the father and mother.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides, it preaches that the origin of life is generated from the lunisolar spirit coming into the body from the harmony between the father and mother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これらはいずれも生死の根源を観じて、悟りを得ようとするものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These are to awaken through seeing the origin of life.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These are awakened through seeing the origin of life.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These are awakened through seeing the origin of life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>しかし、室町時代に大成した本覚思想と相まって現実の世界や愛欲の煩悩を積極的に肯定して、交会（性行為）の儀式を以って悟りを得ようと解釈する向きが強まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, combined with Hongaku philosophy which was perfected in the Muromachi period, it actively accepted the real world and sexuality and tended to awaken by sex.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, combined with Hongaku philosophy which was perfected in the Muromachi period, it actively accepted the real world and sexuality and tended to awaken by sex.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, combined with Hongaku philosophy which was perfected in the Muromachi period, it actively accepted the real world and sexuality and tended to awaken by sex.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>このため真言立川流とよく対比されて論じられることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So, it is often discussed comparing with Shingon sect Tachikawa school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So, it is often discussed in comparison with the Shingon sect Tachikawa school.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So, it is often discussed in comparison with the Shingon sect Tachikawa school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="20">
<j>1689年（元禄2年）に、安楽院の霊空が『闢邪篇』（へきじゃへん）を著して批判し、輪王寺宮に上書したことで、典籍が没収され焚書にあい、玄旨帰命壇はついに禁断とされて絶滅したといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because Reiku in Anrakuin criticized it in his book &quot;Hekijahen&quot; and provided to Rinojinomiya, the book is said to be forfeited and burned, and Genshi Kimyo-dan finally become extinct due to its prohibition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Reiku in Anrakuin criticized it in his book &quot;Hekijahen&quot; and provided to Rinojinomiya, the book is said have been forfeited and burned, and the prohibition gradually lead to Genshi Kimyo-dan finally becoming extinct.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Reiku of Anraku-in Temple criticized it in his book &quot;Hekijahen&quot; and provided to Rinojinomiya, the book is said have been forfeited and burned, and the prohibition gradually lead to Genshi Kimyo-dan finally becoming extinct.</e>
<cmt>訳文を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Boca samba(id:137526), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>