<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>秘仏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hibutsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hibutsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hibutsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>秘仏（ひぶつ）とは、信仰上の理由により非公開とされ、厨子などの扉が閉じられたまま祀られる仏像を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hibutsu are Buddhist images that are normally withheld from public view for religious reasons; they are enshrined in zushi (miniature shrines in temples) with the doors closed.</e>
<cmt>「厨子などの扉が閉じられたまま」にあるように、仏像が厨子以外に納められることは考えられにくいので、「など」の部分の訳出はしませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hibutsu are Buddhist images that are normally withheld from public view for religious reasons; they are enshrined in zushi (miniature shrines in temples) with the doors closed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hibutsu are Buddhist images that are normally withheld from public view for religious reasons; they are enshrined in zushi (miniature shrines in temples) with the doors closed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>仏教寺院では、仏堂の扉を開いた際に仏像が見えるように祀るのが本来であるが、「秘仏」は開帳以外の時は厨子の扉を閉じたまま祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Buddhist temples, the doors of the Butsudo (Buddhist shrine) are normally open so that the Buddhist image can be seen from outside, but zushi that enshrine hibutsu are usually closed except for a certain period when the hibutsu are unveiled to the public.</e>
<cmt>「仏堂」の訳がTANGORINでは、buddhist templeになっていますが、これでは、仏教寺院＝Buddhist templeと同じになっていますので、神殿という意味に近い、Buddhist shrineを使用しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Buddhist temples, the doors of the Butsudo (Buddhist shrine) are normally open so that the Buddhist image can be seen from outside, but zushi that enshrine hibutsu are usually closed except for a certain period when the hibutsu are unveiled to the public.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Buddhist temples, the doors of the Butsudo (Buddhist shrine) are normally open so that the Buddhist image can be seen from outside, but zushi that enshrine hibutsu are usually closed except for a certain period when the hibutsu are unveiled to the public.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>元来、礼拝のための偶像である仏像を扉を閉じた厨子等に納め「秘仏」とすることは、東アジアの仏教圏の中でも特に日本に顕著な現象である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The practice of retaining Buddhist images, which were intended as idols for worship, in zushi with the doors closed is quite unique in Japan even among East Asian countries where Buddhism has prevailed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The practice of retaining Buddhist images, which were intended as idols for worship, in zushi with the doors closed is quite unique in Japan even among East Asian countries where Buddhism has prevailed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The practice of retaining Buddhist images, which were intended as idols for worship, in zushi with the doors closed is quite unique in Japan even among East Asian countries where Buddhism has prevailed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>この国では著名な寺院の本尊で秘仏とされているものが多く、西国三十三箇所の札所寺院をはじめ、札所、霊場などの庶民信仰に支えられた寺院の本尊にも秘仏が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this country, hibutsu are often found with Buddhist images that are the principal icons of well-known temples, as well as the temples that are deep-rooted in folk beliefs, including fudasho (amulet-issuing) temples on the Saigoku (West Japan) Kannon Pilgrimage and those in reijo (sacred ground).</e>
<cmt>ここでは、本尊を秘仏としている寺院について概略的な説明がなされていますが、著名な寺院と庶民信仰に基づく寺院、いづれにも、本尊を秘仏とする寺院があるいう内容だと思いますが、日本語の文章は、全体が流れるように書かれているため、少々、訳文が厳密に原文を反映していないかも知れません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this country, hibutsu are often found with Buddhist images that are the principal icons of well-known temples, as well as the temples that are deep-rooted in folk beliefs, including fudasho (amulet-issuing) temples on the Saigoku (West Japan) Kannon Pilgrimage and those in reijo (sacred ground).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this country, hibutsu are often found with Buddhist images that are the principal icons of well-known temples, as well as the temples that are deep-rooted in folk beliefs, including pilgrim stamp offices of the 33 Temples of Saigoku, fudasho (temples where amulets are collected) and those in reijo (sacred ground).</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>したがって、以下では専ら日本における秘仏について記述する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following, we&apos;ll focus on hibutsu in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following, we&apos;ll focus on hibutsu in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following, we&apos;ll focus on hibutsu in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>秘仏には、全く公開されない「絶対の秘仏」も一部にあるが、特定の日に限って公開（「御開帳」「開扉」などと称する）を行うことが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some hibutsu are so-called &quot;absolute hibutsu&quot;, which are completely withheld from public view, but most are unveiled to the public on specific days (this practice is called &quot;gokaicho&quot; or &quot;kaihi&quot;, both meaning &quot;opening the gate&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some hibutsu are so-called &quot;absolute hibutsu&quot;, which are completely withheld from public view, but most are unveiled to the public on specific days (this practice is called &quot;gokaicho&quot; or &quot;kaihi&quot;, both meaning &quot;opening the gate&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some hibutsu are so-called &apos;absolute hibutsu,&apos; which are completely withheld from public view, but most are unveiled to the public on specific days (this practice is called &apos;gokaicho&apos; or &apos;kaihi,&apos; both meaning &apos;opening the gate&apos;).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>長野・善光寺の阿弥陀三尊像のように、本尊像は絶対の秘仏で、「御開帳」の際に姿を見せるのが「お前立ち」と称する代わりの像になっている場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Like the Amida (Amitabha) triad image at Zenko-ji Temple (Nagano), some Buddhist images have never been unveiled to the public; a statue called &quot;omaedachi&quot;, a copy of the hibutsu (literally, &quot;standing in front&quot;), is exhibited on the day of &quot;gokaicho&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Like the Amida (Amitabha) triad image at Zenko-ji Temple (Nagano), some Buddhist images have never been unveiled to the public; a statue called &quot;omaedachi&quot;, a copy of the hibutsu (literally, &quot;standing in front&quot;), is exhibited on the day of &quot;gokaicho&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Like the Amida (Amitabha) triad image at Zenko-ji Temple in Nagano, some Buddhist images have never been unveiled to the public; a statue called &apos;omaedachi,&apos; a copy of the hibutsu (literally, &apos;standing in front&apos;), is exhibited on the day of &apos;gokaicho.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>秘仏の発生時期や要因については本格的な研究が進んでおらず、確かなことはわかっていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So far, no major progress has been made in the research on when and why hibutsu came into existence; the questions remain unanswered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So far, no major progress has been made in the research on when and why hibutsu came into existence; the questions remain unanswered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So far, no major progress has been made in the research on when and why hibutsu came into existence; the questions remain unanswered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>少なくとも奈良時代以前には特定の仏像が秘仏であるとする記録は知られていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At least, there is no record about hibutus in or before the Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At least, there is no record about hibutus in or before the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At least, there is no record about hibutsu in or before the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>京都・広隆寺の資財についての記録である「広隆寺資財交替実録帳」（寛平2年・890年頃成立）には、同寺金堂本尊の「霊験薬師仏」が鍵のかかる「内殿」に安置されていたことが明記され、この薬師像が遅くとも9世紀末には秘仏扱いされていたことを伺わせる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Koryu-ji Temple sizai kotai jitsuroku cho, an inventory list of Koryo-ji Temple&apos;s assets (completed around 890), the principal icon of its Kon-do hall, &quot;Reiken-yakushi-butsu&quot; (the Healing Buddha), was placed in the &quot;naiden&quot; (inner shrine) that can be locked; this reveals that the Yakushi Buddha image, the principal icon, was treated as a hibutsu by the end of the 9th century at the latest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Koryu-ji Temple sizai kotai jitsuroku cho, an inventory list of Koryo-ji Temple&apos;s assets (completed around 890), the principal icon of its Kon-do hall, &quot;Reiken-yakushi-butsu&quot; (the Healing Buddha), was placed in the &quot;naiden&quot; (inner shrine) that can be locked; this reveals that the Yakushi Buddha image, the principal icon, was treated as a hibutsu by the end of the 9th century at the latest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &apos;Koryu-ji Temple sizai kotai jitsuroku cho,&apos; an inventory list of Koryo-ji Temple&apos;s assets (completed around 890), the principal image of its Kon-do hall, &apos;Reiken-yakushi-butsu&apos; (the Healing Buddha), was placed in the &apos;naiden&apos; (inner shrine) that can be locked; this reveals that the Yakushi Buddha image was treated as a hibutsu by the end of the 9th century at the latest.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>秘仏の発生には神道の神社からの影響があるものとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some say that Shinto (indigenous religion of Japan) shrines may have affected the birth of hibutsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some say that Shinto (indigenous religion of Japan) shrines may have affected the birth of hibutsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some say that Shinto (indigenous religion of Japan) shrines may have affected the birth of hibutsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>神社の本殿の扉もまた、普段は閉じられており、特定の祭祀の時にのみ扉が開かれる場合があるからである（他に神棚や祖霊舎もまた、普段は扉が閉じられており、特定の祭祀の時にのみ扉が開かれる場合がある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The doors of the main hall of a Shinto shrine are usually closed and occasionally opened for special rituals as well (this practice is also seen in kamidana (household Shinto alters) and soreisha (alters that enshrine the souls of ancestors), which are usually closed and opened only for specific services.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The doors of the main hall of a Shinto shrine are usually closed and occasionally opened for special rituals as well (this practice is also seen in kamidana (household Shinto alters) and soreisha (alters that enshrine the souls of ancestors), which are usually closed and opened only for specific services.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The doors of the main hall of a Shinto shrine are usually closed and occasionally opened for special rituals as well (this practice is also seen in kamidana (household Shinto alters) and soreisha (alters that enshrine the souls of ancestors), which are usually closed and opened only for specific services).</e>
<cmt>カッコを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>神道の神は元来、姿の見えない神である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Primarily, Shinto deities are invisible.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Primarily, Shinto deities are invisible.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Primarily, Shinto gods are invisible.</e>
<cmt>godを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>仏像彫刻の影響を受けて、平安時代初期頃から神像、つまり神道の神の彫像も作られるようになるが、これらは「御神体」として社殿の奥深くに秘められ、一般の人の目に触れることはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Shinto deity images came into existence by the early Heian period under the influence of Buddhism sculpture, they were secretly placed deep inside the shrines as &quot;go-shintai&quot; (an object of worship) and were seldom unveiled to the public.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Shinto deity images came into existence by the early Heian period under the influence of Buddhist sculpture, they were secretly placed deep inside the shrines as &quot;go-shintai&quot; (an object of worship) and were seldom unveiled to the public.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Shinto god images came into existence by the early Heian period under the influence of Buddhist sculpture, they were secretly placed deep inside the shrines as &apos;go-shintai&apos; (an object of worship) and were seldom unveiled to the public.</e>
<cmt>godを使用、クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>秘仏を有する寺院は真言宗系、天台宗系に比較的多く、浄土教系、禅宗には比較的少ないことが指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the temples of the Shingon and Tendai sects relatively have more hibutsu than those of Jodo-kyo (literally, &quot;pure land teachings&quot;) and the Zen sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the temples of the Shingon and Tendai sects have relatively more hibutsu than those of Jodo-kyo (literally, &quot;pure land teachings&quot;) and the Zen sect.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the temples of the Shingon and Tendai Sects have relatively more hibutsu than those of Jodo (Pure Land) Sect and the Zen Sect.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>尊像別では、密教寺院の本尊とされることが多い薬師如来や、観音菩薩（十一面観音、千手観音、如意輪観音などを含む）、不動明王などが秘仏とされることが多いことから、密教との関連も指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When seen by Buddhist image, hibutus are more often found with Yakushi Nyorai (Buddha of Medicine and Healing) images, which are often worshipped as the principle icon of mikkyo (Esoteric Buddhism) temples, and with Kannon Bosatsu (Lord of Compassion, Goddess of Mercy), which includes Juichimen Kannon (literally, eleven-headed Kannon), Senju Kannon (literally, thousand-armed Kannon), and Nyoirin Kannon (literally, wish fulfilling Kannon), and Fudo Myoo (Chief protector deity of Esoteric Buddhism); thus, hibutsu are considered to have a bearing on mikkyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When seen by Buddhist image, hibutsu are more often found with Yakushi Nyorai (Buddha of Medicine and Healing) images, which are often worshipped as the principle icon of mikkyo (Esoteric Buddhism) temples, and with Kannon Bosatsu (Lord of Compassion, Goddess of Mercy), which includes Juichimen Kannon (literally, eleven-headed Kannon), Senju Kannon (literally, thousand-armed Kannon), and Nyoirin Kannon (literally, wish fulfilling Kannon), and Fudo Myoo (Chief protector deity of Esoteric Buddhism); thus, hibutsu are considered to have a bearing on mikkyo.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When seen by Buddhist image, hibutsu are more often found with Yakushi Nyorai (Buddha of Medicine and Healing) images, which are often worshipped as the principle image of Esoteric Buddhism temples, and with Kannon Bosatsu (Goddess of Mercy), which includes Juichimen Kannon (Eleven-faced Avalokiteshwara), Senju Kannon (Thousand Armed Avalokiteshwara), and Nyoirin Kannon (the Bodhisattva of Compassion), and Fudo Myoo (Acala, one of the Five Wisdom Kings); thus, hibutsu are considered to have a bearing on Esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>用語を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>歓喜天（聖天、象頭人身の男女が抱擁している姿に表わされる）のようにエロティックな像容に表わされ、「教義に対する誤解を招く恐れがある」と見なされる場合も秘仏となる場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Like Kankiten (also known as &quot;Shoten&quot;, the figure of a man and a woman with elephant heads and human bodies embracing each other), erotic designs may have been hidden from public view as they may have caused the misunderstanding of the doctrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Like Kankiten (also known as &quot;Shoten&quot;, the figure of a man and a woman with elephant heads and human bodies embracing each other), erotic designs may have been hidden from public view as they may have caused the misunderstanding of the doctrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Like Kangiten (Nandikesvara, Ganesh in the Buddhist pantheon) (the figure of a man and a woman with elephant heads and human bodies embracing each other), erotic designs may have been hidden from public view as &apos;they may have caused the misunderstanding of the doctrine.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>秘仏の分類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classification</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classification</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classification</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>宗派別</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By sect</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By sect</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By Sect</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>宗派別では、真言宗および天台宗の寺院に本尊を秘仏とするところが比較的多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When seen by sect, the temples of the Shingon and Tendai sects are more likely to withhold their principle images from public view.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When seen by sect, the temples of the Shingon and Tendai sects are more likely to withhold their principle images from public view.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When seen by sect, the temples of the Shingon and Tendai Sects are more relatively to withhold their principle images from public view.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>天台系の主要寺院では、延暦寺根本中堂本尊の薬師如来像、同寺西塔釈迦堂本尊の釈迦如来像、園城寺（三井寺）金堂本尊の弥勒菩薩像、同寺観音堂本尊の如意輪観音像などはいずれも秘仏である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the principal icons of the major temples of the Tendai sect, the images of the following Buddhist deities are all treated as hibutsu: Yakushi Nyorai at the Konpon-chudo hall of Enryaku-ji Temple, Shaka Nyorai (Shaka Buddha) at the Saito-shaka-do hall of Enryaku-ji Temple, Miroku Bosatsu (Buddha of the Future) at the Kon-do hall of Onjo-ji Temple (also known as Miidera Temple), and Nyoirin-kannon at the Kannon-do hall of Onjo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the principal icons of the major temples of the Tendai sect, the images of the following Buddhist deities are all treated as hibutsu: Yakushi Nyorai at the Konpon-chudo hall of Enryaku-ji Temple, Shaka Nyorai (Shaka Buddha) at the Saito-shaka-do hall of Enryaku-ji Temple, Miroku Bosatsu (Buddha of the Future) at the Kon-do hall of Onjo-ji Temple (also known as Miidera Temple), and Nyoirin-kannon at the Kannon-do hall of Onjo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the principal images of the major temples of the Tendai Sect, the images of the following Buddhist gods are all treated as hibutsu: Yakushi Nyorai at the Konpon-chudo hall of Enryaku-ji Temple, Shaka Nyorai (Shaka Buddha) at the Saito-shaka-do hall of Enryaku-ji Temple, Miroku Bosatsu (Buddha of the Future) at the Kon-do hall of Onjo-ji Temple (also known as Miidera Temple), and Nyoirin Kannon at the Kannon-do hall of Onjo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>真言宗では、高野山金剛峯寺金堂の本尊であった阿閦（あしゅく）如来像（薬師如来と同体ともいう）は1926年に堂とともに焼失してしまったが、厳重な秘仏で、写真撮影もされていなかったため、その像容は永遠に謎となってしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ashuku Nyorai (imperturbable Buddha, free from anger, considered identical to Yakushi Nyorai) image, the principal icon of the Kon-do hall of Koyasan Kongobu-ji Temple of the Shingon sect, was destroyed by the fire of 1926 together with the hall that had housed it, leaving the image forever unknown as they had been strictly hidden from public view and no photograph had been taken.</e>
<cmt>「真言宗では」と書き出しがはじまっているものの、流れから「真言宗の金剛峰寺」という意味に解釈して英訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ashuku Nyorai (imperturbable Buddha, free from anger, considered identical to Yakushi Nyorai) image, the principal icon of the Kon-do hall of Koyasan Kongobu-ji Temple of the Shingon sect, was destroyed by the fire of 1926 together with the hall that had housed it, leaving the image forever unknown as they had been strictly hidden from public view and no photograph had been taken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ashuku Nyorai (imperturbable Buddha, free from anger, considered identical to Yakushi Nyorai) image, the principal image of the Kon-do hall of Kongobu-ji Temple on Mt. Koya of the Shingon Sect, was destroyed by the fire of 1926 together with the hall that had housed it, leaving the image forever unknown as they had been strictly hidden from public view and no photograph had been taken.</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="21">
<j>浄土教系、禅宗系の寺院には秘仏は比較的少ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the temples of the Jodo-kyo and Zen sects, Hibutsu are relatively few in number.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the temples of the Jodo-kyo and Zen sects, Hibutsu are relatively few in number.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the temples of the Jodo Sect and Zen Sects, hibutsu are relatively few in number.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>ただし、これらの宗派に秘仏が皆無というわけではなく、たとえば浄土宗大本山の増上寺（東京都港区）安国殿本尊の阿弥陀如来像（通称黒本尊）は秘仏である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, this does not mean that no hibutus is found with these temples: Zojo-ji Temple (Minato Ward, Tokyo Prefecture), the main temple of the Jodo sect, for example, treats the principal icon of its Ankoku-den hall, the Amida Nyorai image (commonly known as &quot;Kuro-honzon&quot;) (literally, &quot;black principle image&quot;) as a hibutsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But, this does not mean that no hibutsu are found within these temples: Zojo-ji Temple (Minato Ward, Tokyo Prefecture), the main temple of the Jodo sect, for example, treats the principal icon of its Ankoku-den hall, the Amida Nyorai image (commonly known as &quot;Kuro-honzon&quot;) (literally, &quot;black principle image&quot;) as a hibutsu.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But, this does not mean that no hibutsu are found within these temples: Zojo-ji Temple (Minato-ku Ward, Tokyo Prefecture), the main temple of the Jodo Sect, for example, treats the principal image of its Ankoku-den hall, the Amida Nyorai image (commonly known as Kuro-honzon) (literally, black principle image) as a hibutsu.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>像種別</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By Buddhist image</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By Buddhist image</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By Buddhist Image</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>如来像、菩薩像、明王像、天部像のいずれにも秘仏となっているものがあり、厳密には「仏像」の範疇に入らないが、蔵王権現のような垂迹像、鑑真像のような祖師像にも秘仏となっているものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some images of Nyorai (Tathagata), Bosatsu (Bodhisattva), Myoo (Vidyaraja), and Tembe (Celestial beings) are treated as hibutsu, and statues that typically do not fall in the category of Buddhist image, including those of Suijaku (e.g. Zao Gongen (the highest-ranking deity worshipped in Japanese mountain asceticism)), and the Soshizo (sect founder images) icon, (e.g. the image of Ganjin (Jianzhen, a nationalized Chinese priest in the Nara period, who finally reached Japan in 753 on his sixth attempt, the founder of the Ritsu sect), are also treated as hibutsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some images of Nyorai (Tathagata), Bosatsu (Bodhisattva), Myoo (Vidyaraja), and Tembe (Celestial beings) are treated as hibutsu, and statues that typically do not fall in the category of Buddhist image, including those of Suijaku (e.g. Zao Gongen (the highest-ranking deity worshipped in Japanese mountain asceticism)), and the Soshizo (sect founder images) icon, (e.g. the image of Ganjin (Jianzhen, a nationalized Chinese priest in the Nara period, who finally reached Japan in 753 on his sixth attempt, the founder of the Ritsu sect), are also treated as hibutsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some images of Nyorai (Tathagata), Bosatsu (Bodhisattva), Myoo (Vidyaraja), and Tenbu (Celestial beings) are treated as hibutsu, and statues that typically do not fall in the category of &apos;Buddhist image,&apos; including those of Suijaku (literally, trace manifestation) as Zao Gongen (the highest-ranking deity worshipped in Japanese mountain asceticism), and the Soshizo (sect founder images), as the image of Jianzhen are also treated as hibutsu.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>像種別には薬師如来、観音菩薩、不動明王に秘仏となっているものが比較的多く、秘仏は総じて密教系の仏に多いということが言える（薬師如来は顕教系の仏だが密教寺院で本尊とされることが多い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When seen by Buddhist image, Yakushi Nyorai, Kannon Bosatsu, and Fudo Myoo are more likely to be treated as Hibutsu; in general, Buddhist icons worshipped at esoteric temples tend to be treated as hibutsu (Yakushi Nyorai, which is an exoteric Buddha, is often worshipped as the principle deity of esoteric temples.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When seen by Buddhist image, Yakushi Nyorai, Kannon Bosatsu, and Fudo Myoo are more likely to be treated as Hibutsu; in general, Buddhist icons worshipped at esoteric temples tend to be treated as hibutsu (Yakushi Nyorai, which is an exoteric Buddha, is often worshipped as the principle deity of esoteric temples.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When seen by Buddhist image, Yakushi Nyorai, Kannon Bosatsu, and Fudo Myoo are more likely to be treated as Hibutsu; in general, Buddhist images worshipped at Esoteric Buddhism temples tend to be treated as hibutsu (Yakushi Nyorai, which is an exoteric Buddha, is often worshipped as the principle god of esoteric temples).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>西国三十三箇所の札所寺院はすべて観音像を祀っているが、その大部分が秘仏であり、そうでないのは33か寺中、6番南法華寺（壺阪寺）、7番龍蓋寺（岡寺）、8番長谷寺、20番善峰寺の観音像のみとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although all the 33 fudasho (amulet issuing) temples on the Saigoku (West Japan) Kannon Pilgrimage worship the Kannon images, most of them treat the icons as hibutsu; out of 33 temples, those that treat them otherwise are limited to the following: Minamihokke-ji Temple (or known as Tsunosaka-dera Temple), the 6th temple on the pilgrimage, Ryugai-ji Temple (or Okadera Temple), the 7th, Hase-dera Temple, the 8th, and Yoshimine-dera Temple, the 20th.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although all the 33 fudasho (amulet issuing) temples on the Saigoku (West Japan) Kannon Pilgrimage worship the Kannon images, most of them treat the icons as hibutsu; out of 33 temples, those that treat them otherwise are limited to the following: Minamihokke-ji Temple (or known as Tsunosaka-dera Temple), the 6th temple on the pilgrimage, Ryugai-ji Temple (or Okadera Temple), the 7th, Hase-dera Temple, the 8th, and Yoshimine-dera Temple, the 20th.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although all pilgrim stamp office of the 33 Temples of Saigoku worship the Kannon images, most of them treat as hibutsu; out of 33 temples, those that treat them otherwise are limited to the following: Minamihokke-ji Temple (Also known as Tsunosaka-dera Temple), the 6th pilgrim stamp office, Ryugai-ji Temple (Also known as Oka-dera Temple), the 7th, Hase-dera Temple, the 8th, and Yoshimine-dera Temple, the 20th.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>公開時期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Times when hibutsu are unveiled</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Times when hibutsu are unveiled</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Times When Hibutsu are Unveiled</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>秘仏の公開時期にはさまざまなパターンがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are various patterns in which hibutsu are unveiled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various patterns in which hibutsu are unveiled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various patterns in which hibutsu are unveiled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="27">
<j>毎年春・秋などの一定の時期に比較的長く開扉されるもの（例：法隆寺の救世観音像、浄瑠璃寺の吉祥天像など）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hibutsu unveiled for a relatively long period in every spring and fall: Kuze Kannon image (the god of salvation) at Horyu-ji Temple and Kisshoten (the goddess of beauty and prosperity) image at Joruri-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hibutsu unveiled for a relatively long period in every spring and fall: Kuze Kannon image (the god of salvation) at Horyu-ji Temple and Kisshoten (the goddess of beauty and prosperity) image at Joruri-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hibutsu unveiled for a relatively long period in every spring and fall: Kuze Kannon image (the god of salvation) at Horyu-ji Temple and Kisshoten (the goddess of beauty and prosperity) image at Joruri-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>毎月1回決まった日に開扉されるもの（例：観音の縁日である毎月18日に開扉される、大阪・葛井寺の千手観音像など）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hibutsu unveiled once a month on a specific day: Senju Kannon image at Fujii-dera Temple (Osaka), where the icon is unveiled on the 18th of the month, the day believed to have a bearing on the kannon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hibutsu unveiled once a month on a specific day: Senju Kannon image at Fujii-dera Temple (Osaka), where the icon is unveiled on the 18th of the month, the day believed to have a bearing on the kannon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hibutsu unveiled once a month on a specific day: Senju Kannon image at Fujii-dera Temple in Osaka, where the image is unveiled on the 18th of each month, the day believed to have a bearing on the kannon.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>1年のうち、1日ないし数日しか開扉されないもの（例：毎年12月16日のみ開扉される、東大寺法華堂の執金剛神像など）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hibutsu unveiled only on one or several days in a year: Shukongoshin (a gate guardian) image at the Hokke-do hall of Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hibutsu unveiled only on one or several days in a year: Shukongoshin (a gate guardian) image at the Hokke-do hall of Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hibutsu unveiled only on one or several days in a year: Shukongoshin (a gate guardian) image at the Hokke-do hall of Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>数年ないし数十年に一度しか開扉されないもの（例：33年に一度の開扉とされている京都・清水寺本尊千手観音像など）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hibutsu unveiled only once in several years or decades: Senju Kannon image at Kiyomizu-dera Temple (Kyoto), which is unveiled to the public every 33 years.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hibutsu unveiled only once in several years or decades: Senju Kannon image at Kiyomizu-dera Temple (Kyoto), which is unveiled to the public every 33 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hibutsu unveiled only once in several years or decades: Senju Kannon, the principle image at Kiyomizu-dera Temple (Kyoto), which is unveiled to the public every 33 years.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>観音像に「33年に一度」の開扉とされるものが多いのは、観音は33の姿に変身して衆生を救うと経典に説かれていることによる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many Kannon images are unveiled once every 33 years because Kannon is believed to save the people by disguising itself into 33 different figures.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many Kannon images are unveiled once every 33 years because Kannon ise believed to save the people by disguising itself into 33 different figures.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many Kannon images are unveiled &apos;once every 33 years&apos; because Kannon is believed to save the people by disguising itself into 33 different figures.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="32">
<j>原則非公開で、開扉時期を特に定めていないもの（例：東寺御影堂の不動明王像など）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hibutsu not unveiled in principle or those with the exhibition period not determined: Fudo Myoo image at the Goei-do hall of To-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hibutsu not unveiled in principle or those with the exhibition period not determined: Fudo Myoo image at the Goei-do hall of To-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hibutsu not unveiled in principle or those with the exhibition period not determined: Fudo Myoo image at the Goei-do hall of To-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>絶対の秘仏で、写真も公開されていないもの（例：東大寺二月堂本尊十一面観音像など）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Absolute hibutus (those not unveiled at all), even with their pictures not disclosed: Juichimen Kannon image at the Nigatsu-do hall of Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Absolute hibutus (those not unveiled at all), even with their pictures not disclosed: Juichimen Kannon image at the Nigatsu-do hall of Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Absolute hibutsu (those not unveiled at all), even with their pictures not disclosed: Juichimen Kannon, the principle image at the Nigatsu-do hall of Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>著名な秘仏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Well-known hibutsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Well-known hibutsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Well-known Hibutsu</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>日本文化史上重要と思われるいくつかの事例について略説する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following are short descriptions of hibutsu considered historically and culturally important.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following are short descriptions of hibutsu considered historically and culturally important.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following are short descriptions of hibutsu considered historically and culturally important.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="35">
<j>法隆寺夢殿本尊　観音菩薩立像（救世観音）－夢殿は、聖徳太子が営んだ斑鳩宮の跡に建てられた法隆寺東院の中心堂宇である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kannon Bosatsu (Kuze Kannon) standing image, the principle image of the Yume-dono hall of Horyu-ji Temple; the hall is the central hall of Toin (the east wing) of Horyu-ji Temple, which was built in the site of Ikaruga no miya (literally, &quot;Palace of Ikaruga&quot;) operated by Shotoku Taishi (the first great patron of Buddhism in Japan and imperial regent in the early 7th century).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kannon Bosatsu (Kuze Kannon) standing image, the principle image of the Yume-dono hall of Horyu-ji Temple; the hall is the central hall of Toin (the east wing) of Horyu-ji Temple, which was built in the site of Ikaruga no miya (literally, &quot;Palace of Ikaruga&quot;) operated by Shotoku Taishi (the first great patron of Buddhism in Japan and imperial regent in the early 7th century).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kannon Bosatsu (Kuze Kannon) standing statue, the principle image of the Yume-dono hall of Horyu-ji Temple; the hall is the central hall of Toin (the east wing) of Horyu-ji Temple, which was built in the site of Ikaruga no miya (literally, Palace of Ikaruga) operated by Prince Shotoku.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>堂内中央の厨子に安置される救世観音像は聖徳太子等身の像と伝える飛鳥時代の木彫像であるが、各種史料によれば平安時代後期の12世紀にはすでに秘仏とされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kuze Kannon image housed in a zushi placed in the middle of the hall is a wooden sculpture of the Aska period and considered to be the exact image of Shotoku Taishi, and according to historical materials, this statue had already been treated as a hibutsu by the 12th century, the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kuze Kannon image housed in a zushi placed in the middle of the hall is a wooden sculpture of the Aska period and considered to be the exact image of Shotoku Taishi, and according to historical materials, this statue had already been treated as a hibutsu by the 12th century, the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kuze Kannon image housed in a zushi placed in the middle of the hall is a wooden sculpture of the Aska period and considered to be the exact image of Prince Shotoku, and according to historical materials, this statue had already been treated as a hibutsu by the 12th century, the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>通説では1884年（1886年とも）、法隆寺を訪れた岡倉天心（日本の美術教育、美術史研究の先駆者）とアーネスト・フェノロサ（アメリカ人の哲学者、美術史家）が寺僧の反対を押し切って厨子の扉を開け、観音像は数百年ぶりに姿を現わしたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the prevailing view, Tenshin OKAKURA (the forerunner of Japanese art educators and researchers) and Ernest Fenollosa (an American philosopher and an art historian), who visited Horyu-ji Temple in 1184 (or 1186), opened the door of the zushi by brushing aside the opposition from Buddhist priests; this is how the Kannon statue came into view for the first time in hundreds of years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the prevailing view, Tenshin OKAKURA (the forerunner of Japanese art educators and researchers) and Ernest Fenollosa (an American philosopher and an art historian), who visited Horyu-ji Temple in 1884 (or 1886), opened the door of the zushi by brushing aside the opposition from Buddhist priests; this is how the Kannon statue came into view for the first time in hundreds of years.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the prevailing view, Tenshin OKAKURA (the forerunner of Japanese art educators and researchers) and Ernest Fenollosa (an American philosopher and an art historian), who visited Horyu-ji Temple in 1884 (or 1886), opened the door of the zushi by brushing aside the opposition from Buddhist priests; this is how the Kannon statue came into view for the first time in hundreds of years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>この時、観音像は長い白布で覆われていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, the statue was covered with a white long cloth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, the statue was covered with a white long cloth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, the statue was covered with a white long cloth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>天心とフェノロサによる秘仏開扉のエピソードは半ば伝説化しており、それ以前の数百年間、誰もこの観音像を見た者がいなかったのかどうかについては疑問視する向きもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This story has almost become a legend; some say it unbelievable that the icon had been completely kept out of sight for as long as hundreds of years before it was finally opened by Tenshin and Fenollosa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This story has almost become a legend; some say it unbelievable that the icon had been completely kept out of sight for as long as hundreds of years before it was finally opened by Tenshin and Fenollosa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This story has almost become a legend; some say it unbelievable that the image had been completely kept out of sight for as long as hundreds of years before it was finally opened by Tenshin and Fenollosa.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="40">
<j>信州善光寺本尊　阿弥陀三尊像－寺伝によれば、6世紀に百済の聖明王から当時の日本へ献上された日本仏法最初の仏像が、さまざまな経緯で長野に運ばれたものが善光寺の本尊であるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amida triad statue, the principle image of Shinshu Zenko-ji Temple; according to a record kept by the temple, the first Buddhist image presented to Japan by Sho Myoo (the King of Kudara, an ancient Korean kingdom) in the 6th century was somehow carried all the way to Nagano to become the principal statue of the temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amida triad statue, the principle image of Shinshu Zenko-ji Temple; according to a record kept by the temple, the first Buddhist image presented to Japan by Sho Myoo (the King of Kudara, an ancient Korean kingdom) in the 6th century was somehow carried all the way to Nagano to become the principal statue of the temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amida triad statue, the principle image of Shinshu Zenko-ji Temple; according to a record kept by the temple, the first Buddhist image presented to Japan by Sho Myoo (the King of Kudara, an ancient Korean kingdom) in the 6th century was somehow carried all the way to Nagano to become the principal image of the temple.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>善光寺の本尊は鎌倉時代にはすでに秘仏であったことが知られ、現代に至るまで「絶対の秘仏」とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This statue, which is known to have been treated as a hibutsu as early as the Kamakura period, is still an &quot;absolute hibutsu&quot; even today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This statue, which is known to have been treated as a hibutsu as early as the Kamakura period, is still an &quot;absolute hibutsu&quot; even today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This statue, which is known to have been treated as a hibutsu as early as the Kamakura period, is still an &apos;absolute hibutsu&apos; even today.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>ただし、善光寺には秘仏本尊を模して作られたとされる「お前立ち像」（銅造、鎌倉時代作、重要文化財）があり、この像を通じて、秘仏本尊の像容を推測することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Zenko-ji Temple made a copy of the hibutu called &quot;omaedachi-zo&quot; (an important cultural property built in the Kamakura period, made of bronze), through which people can imagine what the hibutsu looks like.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Zenko-ji Temple made a copy of the hibutsu called &quot;omaedachi-zo&quot; (an important cultural property built in the Kamakura period, made of bronze), through which people can imagine what the hibutsu looks like.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Zenko-ji Temple made a copy of the hibutsu called &apos;omaedachi-zo&apos; (an important cultural property built in the Kamakura period, made of bronze), through which people can imagine what the hibutsu looks like.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>「お前立ち」像は中尊・両脇侍ともに立像で、三尊が1枚の大きな光背を背負っており（一光三尊形式という）、三尊の印相（両手の指で示す形）、服制、両脇侍の宝冠などにも特色がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Omaedachi-zo statue, made up of &quot;Chuson&quot; (the principal statue) and two &quot;Ryowakiji&quot; (statues standing at both sides of Chuson) features the &quot;Ikko-sanzon&quot; (meaning the three icons carrying one large halo) style, the deities&apos; inso (the shapes expressed with their fingers), the way they are dressed, and the hokan (crowns) worn by the Ryowakiji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Omaedachi-zo statue, made up of &quot;Chuson&quot; (the principal statue) and two &quot;Ryowakiji&quot; (statues standing at both sides of Chuson) features the &quot;Ikko-sanzon&quot; (meaning the three icons carrying one large halo) style, the deities&apos; inso (the shapes expressed with their fingers), the way they are dressed, and the hokan (crowns) worn by the Ryowakiji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Omaedachi-zo statue, made up of Chuson (the principal statue in a group of Buddhist statues) and two Ryowakiji (statues standing at both sides of Chuson) features the Ikko-sanzon (meaning the three icons carrying one large halo) and has characteristics in style, the gods&apos; inso (the shapes expressed with their fingers), the way they are dressed, and the hokan (crowns) worn by the Ryowakiji.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>これらの特色は朝鮮半島の三国時代の金銅仏にもみられるものであり、善光寺の秘仏本尊がかなり古い時代に朝鮮半島から渡来した像である可能性は高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These features are commonly seen in the kondo-butu statues (gilt bronze Buddhist statues of the Three Kingdoms period of the Korean Peninsula); it is highly likely that the hibutsu of Zenko-ji Temple came over to Japan from the peninsula in quite ancient times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These features are commonly seen in the kondo-butu statues (gilt bronze Buddhist statues of the Three Kingdoms period of the Korean Peninsula); it is highly likely that the hibutsu of Zenko-ji Temple came over to Japan from the peninsula in quite ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These features are commonly seen in the kondo-butsu statues (gilt bronze Buddhist statues of the Three Kingdoms period of the Korean Peninsula); it is highly likely that the hibutsu of Zenko-ji Temple came over to Japan from the peninsula in quite ancient times.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>日本各地の寺院にある「善光寺式阿弥陀三尊像」と呼ばれる三尊像も同様の形式のものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amida triad images of so-called &quot;Zenko-ji temple-style&quot;, which are seen in temples across Japan, are of the same style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amida triad images of so-called &quot;Zenko-ji temple-style&quot;, which are seen in temples across Japan, are of the same style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amida triad images of so-called &apos;Amida triad images of Zenko-ji temple-style,&apos; which are seen in temples across Japan, are of the same style.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変え補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>善光寺では7年目ごとに「御開帳」を行っているが（開帳の年を1年目と数えるため、実際は6年に一度）、この際も公開されるのは「お前立ち像」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zenko-ji Temple has the period of &quot;gokaicho&quot; (opening the gate) once every 7 years (more precisely, every 6 years, as the year of &quot;gokaicho&quot; is counted as the first year), and even in that period, it is the &quot;omaedachi-zo&quot; image, not the hibutsu, that is publicly displayed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zenko-ji Temple has the period of &quot;gokaicho&quot; (opening the gate) once every 7 years (more precisely, every 6 years, as the year of &quot;gokaicho&quot; is counted as the first year), and even in that period, it is the &quot;omaedachi-zo&quot; image, not the hibutsu, that is publicly displayed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zenko-ji Temple has the period of &apos;gokaicho&apos; (opening the gate) once every 7 years (more precisely, every 6 years, as the year of gokaicho is counted as the first year), and even in that period, it is the &apos;omaedachi-zo&apos; image, not the hibutsu, that is publicly displayed.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="47">
<j>東大寺二月堂本尊　十一面観音立像－東大寺二月堂は、大仏殿東方の山麓に位置し、「お水取り」の行事で知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Juichimen Kannon standing image, the principal image of the Nigatsu-do hall of Todai-ji Temple; the hall locates at the foot of the mountain east of Daibutsu-den (the Great Buddha Hall) and is famous for its water-drawing festival called &quot;Omizutori&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Juichimen Kannon standing image, the principal image of the Nigatsu-do hall of Todai-ji Temple; the hall locates at the foot of the mountain east of Daibutsu-den (the Great Buddha Hall) and is famous for its water-drawing festival called &quot;Omizutori&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juichimen Kannon standing statue, the principal image of the Nigatsu-do hall of Todai-ji Temple; the hall locates at the foot of the mountain east of Daibutsu-den (the Great Buddha Hall) and is famous for its water-drawing festival called &apos;Omizutori.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>「お水取り」は正式には修二会（しゅにえ）と言い、二月堂本尊の十一面観音に対してもろもろの罪や過ちを懺悔し、国家の安泰と人々の幸福を祈る行事である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Omizutori&quot; is officially called Shunie (a Buddhist mass held in February by the lunar calendar), where people repent and confess all their sins and mistakes to Juichimen Kannon, the hall&apos;s principal icon, and pray for their happiness and prosperity as well as their country&apos;s peace and stability.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Omizutori&quot; is officially called Shunie (a Buddhist mass held in February by the lunar calendar), where people repent and confess all their sins and mistakes to Juichimen Kannon, the hall&apos;s principal icon, and pray for their happiness and prosperity as well as their country&apos;s peace and stability.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omizutori&apos; is officially called Shunie (a Buddhist mass held in February by the lunar calendar), where people repent and confess all their sins and mistakes to Juichimen Kannon, the hall&apos;s principal image, and pray for their happiness and prosperity as well as their country&apos;s peace and stability.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>二月堂内陣には大観音（おおがんのん）、小観音（こがんのん）と称する2体の十一面観音像が安置されるが、いつの時代からか両方の像とも厳重な秘仏とされ、「お水取り」の行事を執り行う寺僧もこれらの像を目にすることはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An inner room called &quot;naijin&quot; in the Nigatsu-do hall houses two Juichimen Kannon statues called &quot;Oo-gannon&quot; (big kannon) and &quot;ko-gannon&quot; (small kannon), both of which have been treated as hibutsu and put under strict control, although it is not known since when they have been treated as such; even priests who perform the Omizutori ritual never get to see them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An inner room called &quot;naijin&quot; in the Nigatsu-do hall houses two Juichimen Kannon statues called &quot;Oo-gannon&quot; (big kannon) and &quot;ko-gannon&quot; (small kannon), both of which have been treated as hibutsu and put under strict control, although it is not known since when they have been treated as such; even priests who perform the Omizutori ritual never get to see them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An inner room called naijin in the Nigatsu-do hall houses two Juichimen Kannon statues called O-gannon (big kannon) and Ko-gannon (small kannon), both of which have been treated as hibutsu and put under strict control, although it is not known since when they have been treated as such; even priests who perform the &apos;Omizutori&apos; ritual never get to see them.</e>
<cmt>スペルなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>寛文7年（1667年）の二月堂火災の際に損傷した大観音の光背のみは別途保管され、公開されている（奈良国立博物館に寄託）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, only the halo of the Kannon which was damaged by the fire of the Nigatsu-do hall in 1667 has been retained in a different place and publicly exhibited (it has been deposited in Nara National Museum).</e>
<cmt>大観音とは、11面観音であることは明らかですが、Daikannnon とすると、べつの観音と理解される可能性もあるので、この場合は、Kannonとだけ訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, only the halo of the Kannon which was damaged by the fire of the Nigatsu-do hall in 1667 has been retained in a different place and publicly exhibited (it has been deposited in Nara National Museum).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, only the halo of the Kannon which was damaged by the fire of the Nigatsu-do hall in 1667 has been retained in a different place and publicly exhibited (it has been deposited in Nara National Museum).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>この光背は銅造で高さ226cmあり、破損が激しいが、全面に線刻で多くの仏菩薩の像が表わされており、奈良時代の制作と考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The halo, made of bronze, 226 cm high, carries the images of many Bosatsu Buddha carved on its surface although it is heavily damaged, and is considered to be made in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The halo, made of bronze, 226 cm high, carries the images of many Bosatsu Buddha carved on its surface although it is heavily damaged, and is considered to have been made in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The halo, made of bronze, 226 cm high, carries the images of many Bosatsu Buddha carved on its surface although it is heavily damaged, and is considered to have been made in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>日本における著名な秘仏の一覧</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A list of well-known hibutsu in Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A list of well-known hibutsu in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A List of Well-known Hibutsu in Japan</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="52">
<j>秘仏とされる仏像は日本各地に多く、本項でそのすべてを網羅することは不可能であるので、国宝指定物件をはじめ、著名なものに限った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As there are too many hibutsu in Japan, it is impossible to list them all here; we limit them to those well-known, including the ones designated as national treasures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As there are too many hibutsu in Japan, it is impossible to list them all here; we limit them to those that are well-known, including the ones designated as national treasures.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As there are too many hibutsu in Japan, it is impossible to list them all here; we limit them to those that are well-known, including the ones designated as national treasures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="53">
<j>毎年、春・秋などの一定期間に開扉されるもの</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hibutsu unveiled every year in a certain period, typically in spring and fall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hibutsu unveiled every year in a certain period, typically in spring and fall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hibutsu unveiled every year in a certain period, typically in spring and fall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>浄瑠璃寺（京都）吉祥天立像（重文）1月1日～15日、3月21日～5月20日、10月1日～11月30日開扉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kissho-ten standing image (important cultural property) at Jyoruri-ji Temple (Kyoto): unveiled on January 1- 15, March 21 - May 20, and October 1 - November 30.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kissho-ten standing image (important cultural property) at Jyoruri-ji Temple (Kyoto): unveiled on January 1- 15, March 21 - May 20, and October 1 - November 30.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kissho-ten standing statue (important cultural property) at Jyoruri-ji Temple (Kyoto): unveiled on January 1- 15, March 21 - May 20, and October 1 - November 30.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>法隆寺（奈良）夢殿本尊　観音菩薩立像（救世観音）（国宝）4月11日～5月5日、10月22日～11月3日開扉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kannon Bosatsu (Kuze Kannon) standing image, the principal icon of the Yume-dono hall (national treasure): unveiled on April 11 - May 5, October 22 - November 3.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kannon Bosatsu (Kuze Kannon) standing image, the principal icon of the Yume-dono hall (national treasure): unveiled on April 11 - May 5, October 22 - November 3.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kannon Bosatsu (Kuze Kannon) standing statue, the principal image of the Yume-dono hall (national treasure): unveiled on April 11 - May 5, October 22 - November 3.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>西大寺 (奈良市)（奈良）愛染明王坐像（重文）10月下旬～11月上旬開扉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aizen Myoo seated image (important cultural property) at Saidai-ji Temple (Nara): unveiled on the late October - early November.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aizen Myoo seated image (important cultural property) at Saidai-ji Temple (Nara): unveiled in late October - early November.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aizen Myoo (Ragaraja) seated statue (important cultural property) at Saidai-ji Temple (Nara): unveiled in late October - early November.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>法華寺（奈良）十一面観音立像（国宝）3月下旬～4月上旬、6月上旬、10月下旬～11月上旬開扉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Juichimen Kannon standing icon (national treasure) at Hokke-ji Temple (Nara); unveiled in the late March - early April, the early June, and the late October - early November.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Juichimen Kannon standing icon (national treasure) at Hokke-ji Temple (Nara); unveiled in late March - early April, early June, and late October - early November.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juichimen Kannon standing statue (national treasure) at Hokke-ji Temple (Nara); unveiled in late March - early April, early June, and late October - early November.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="58">
<j>毎月1回、特定の日に開扉されるもの</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hibutsu unveiled once a year on specific days</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hibutsu unveiled once a year on specific days</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hibutsu unveiled once a year on specific days</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>葛井寺（大阪）本尊　千手観音立像（国宝）毎月18日開扉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senju Kannon standing image (national treasure), a principle image of Fujii-dera Temple (Osaka): unveiled on the 18th of the month</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senju Kannon standing image (national treasure), a principle image of Fujii-dera Temple (Osaka): unveiled on the 18th of the month</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senju Kannon standing statue (national treasure), a principle image of Fujii-dera Temple (Osaka): unveiled on the 18th of each month</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>道明寺 (藤井寺市)（大阪）本尊　十一面観音立像（国宝）毎月18日、25日、1月1日～3日開扉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Juichimen Kannon standing image (national treasure), the principal image of Domyo-ji Temple (Fujiidera City): unveiled on the 18th and 25th of the month and January 1 - 3.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Juichimen Kannon standing image (national treasure), the principal image of Domyo-ji Temple (Fujiidera City): unveiled on the 18th and 25th of the month and January 1 - 3.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juichimen Kannon standing statue (national treasure), the principal image of Domyo-ji Temple (Fujiidera City): unveiled on the 18th and 25th of each month and January 1 - 3.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="61">
<j>1年のうち1日ないし数日のみ開扉されるもの</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hibutsu unveiled only on one or few days in a year</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hibutsu unveiled on only one or a few days per year</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hibutsu unveiled on only one or a few days per year</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>観心寺（大阪）本尊　如意輪観音坐像（国宝）4月17・18日開扉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nyoirin Kannon seated image (national treasure), the principle icon of Kanshin-ji Temple (Osaka): unveiled on April 17 and 18.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nyoirin Kannon seated image (national treasure), the principle icon of Kanshin-ji Temple (Osaka): unveiled on April 17 and 18.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nyoirin Kannon seated statue (national treasure), the principle image of Kanshin-ji Temple (Osaka): unveiled on April 17 and 18.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>東大寺（奈良）法華堂（三月堂）執金剛神立像（国宝）12月16日開扉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shukongoshin standing image (national treasure) at the Sangatsu-do hall of Todai-ji Temple (Nara): unveiled on December 16.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shukongoshin standing image (national treasure) at the Sangatsu-do hall of Todai-ji Temple (Nara): unveiled on December 16.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shukongoshin standing statue (national treasure) at the Sangatsu-do hall of Todai-ji Temple (Nara): unveiled on December 16.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>東大寺　俊乗上人坐像（国宝）7月5日、12月16日開扉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shunjo Shonin (a Buddhist priest from the late Heian period to the Kamakura period, who restored Todai-ji Temple which had been destroyed in wars between the Taira and Minamoto clans) seated image (national treasure) at Todai-ji Temple: unveiled on July 5 and December 16.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shunjo Shonin (a Buddhist priest from the late Heian period to the Kamakura period, who restored Todai-ji Temple which had been destroyed in wars between the Taira and Minamoto clans) seated image (national treasure) at Todai-ji Temple: unveiled on July 5 and December 16.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shunjo Shonin (a Buddhist priest from the late Heian period to the Kamakura period, who restored Todai-ji Temple which had been destroyed in wars between the Taira and Minamoto clans) seated statue (national treasure) at Todai-ji Temple: unveiled on July 5 and December 16.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>東大寺　良弁僧正坐像（国宝）12月16日開扉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoben Sojo (a Buddhist priest in the Nara period, who helped building Todai-ji Temple) seated image (national treasure) at Todai-ji Temple: unveiled on December 16.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoben Sojo (a Buddhist priest in the Nara period, who helped build Todai-ji Temple) seated image (national treasure) at Todai-ji Temple: unveiled on December 16.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoben Sojo (a Buddhist priest in the Nara period, who helped build Todai-ji Temple) seated statue (national treasure) at Todai-ji Temple: unveiled on December 16.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>東大寺　僧形八幡神坐像（国宝）10月5日開扉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sougyo Hachimanshin (literally, &quot;Hachiman Shinto deity disguised in a priest&quot;) seated image (national treasure) at Todai-ji Temple: unveiled on October 5.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sougyo Hachimanshin (literally, &quot;Hachiman Shinto deity disguised in a priest&quot;) seated image (national treasure) at Todai-ji Temple: unveiled on October 5.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sougyo Hachimanshin (literally, &quot;Hachiman Shinto deity disguised in a priest&quot;) seated statue (national treasure) at Todai-ji Temple: unveiled on October 5.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>興福寺（奈良）南円堂本尊　不空羂索観音坐像（国宝）10月17日開扉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukukenjaku Kannon (Amoghapasa (manifestation of Amalokitesvara)) seated image (national treasure), the principle icon of the Nanen-do hall of Kofukuji-Temple (Nara): unveiled on October 17.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukukenjaku Kannon (Amoghapasa (manifestation of Amalokitesvara)) seated image (national treasure), the principle icon of the Nanen-do hall of Kofukuji-Temple (Nara): unveiled on October 17.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukukenjaku Kannon (Amoghapasa (manifestation of Amalokitesvara)) seated statue (national treasure), the principle image of the Nanen-do hall of Kofukuji-Temple (Nara): unveiled on October 17.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>唐招提寺（奈良）鑑真和上坐像（国宝）6月5日～7日開扉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ganjin-wajo (Jianzhen) seated image (national treasure) at Toshodai-ji Temple (Nara): unveiled on June 5 - 7.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ganjin-wajo (Jianzhen) seated image (national treasure) at Toshodai-ji Temple (Nara): unveiled on June 5 - 7.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ganjin-wajo (Jianzhen) seated statue (national treasure) at Toshodai-ji Temple (Nara): unveiled on June 5 - 7.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>秋篠寺（奈良）大元帥明王立像（重文）6月6日開扉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daigensui Myoo (a Buddhist deity believed to have the virtue to convert impurity into purity) standing image (important cultural property) at Akishino-dera Temple (Nara): unveiled on June 6.</e>
<cmt>「大元帥明王」の内容的説明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daigensui Myoo (a Buddhist deity believed to have the virtue to convert impurity into purity) standing image (important cultural property) at Akishino-dera Temple (Nara): unveiled on June 6.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daigensui Myoo (a Buddhist deity believed to have the virtue to convert impurity into purity) standing statue (important cultural property) at Akishino-dera Temple (Nara): unveiled on June 6.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>法隆寺（奈良）聖霊院本尊　聖徳太子坐像・山背王（やましろおう）・殖栗王（えぐりおう）・卒末呂王（そまろおう）・恵慈法師坐像（国宝）3月22日~24日開扉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shotoku-taishi seated image, the principal icon of the Shoryo-in hall of Horyuji-Temple, and those of Yamashiro-o (Taishi&apos;s son), Eguri-o (Taishi&apos;s younger brother), Somaro-o (Taishi&apos;s younger brother), and Eji hoshi (a Buddhist priest from Korai, an ancient Korean kingdom) enshrined in the hall (all are national treasures): unveiled on March 22 - 24.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shotoku-taishi seated image, the principal icon of the Shoryo-in the hall of Horyuji-Temple, and those of Yamashiro-o (Taishi&apos;s son), Eguri-o (Taishi&apos;s younger brother), Somaro-o (Taishi&apos;s younger brother), and Eji hoshi (a Buddhist priest from Korai, an ancient Korean kingdom) enshrined in the hall (all are national treasures): unveiled on March 22 - 24.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Shotoku seated statue, the principal image of the Shoryoin the hall of Horyuji-Temple, and those of Yamashiro-o (Prince Shotoku&apos;s son), Eguri-o (Prince Shotoku&apos;s younger brother), Somaro-o (Prince Shotoku&apos;s younger brother), and Eji hoshi (a Buddhist priest from Korai, an ancient Korean kingdom) enshrined in the hall (all are national treasures): unveiled on March 22 - 24.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>法隆寺　上御堂本尊　釈迦三尊坐像（国宝）11月1日～3日開扉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shaka sanzon (Shaka triad) seated image, (national treasure), the principal icon of the Kami-no-mido hall of Horyu-ji Temple: unveiled on November 1 - 3.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shaka sanzon (Shaka triad) seated image, (national treasure), the principal icon of the Kami-no-mido hall of Horyu-ji Temple: unveiled on November 1 - 3.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shaka sanzon (Shaka triad) seated statue, (national treasure), the principal image of the Kami-no-mido hall of Horyu-ji Temple: unveiled on November 1 - 3.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>広隆寺（京都）本尊　聖徳太子立像 11月22日開扉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shotoku-taishi standing image, the principal icon of Koryu-ji Temple: unveiled on November 22.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shotoku-taishi standing image, the principal icon of Koryu-ji Temple: unveiled on November 22.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Shotoku standing statue, the principal image of Koryu-ji Temple: unveiled on November 22.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>広隆寺（京都）本尊　薬師如来立像（重文）11月22日開扉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yakushi Nyorai standing image (important cultural property), the principal icon of Koryu-ji Temple: unveiled on November 22.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yakushi Nyorai standing image (important cultural property), the principal icon of Koryu-ji Temple: unveiled on November 22.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yakushi Nyorai standing statue (important cultural property), the principal image of Koryu-ji Temple: unveiled on November 22.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="74">
<j>数年～数十年ごとに開扉されるもの</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hibutsu unveiled every few years or decades</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hibutsu unveiled every few years or decades</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hibutsu unveiled every few years or decades</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>元善光寺（長野）本尊　阿弥陀三尊立像　7年目ごとに開扉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amida triad standing image, the principal icon of Moto-zenko-ji Temple (Nagano): unveiled once every 7 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amida triad standing image, the principal icon of Moto-zenko-ji Temple (Nagano): unveiled once every 7 years.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amida triad standing statue, the principal image of Moto-zenko-ji Temple (Nagano): unveiled once every 7 years.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>園城寺（滋賀）観音堂本尊　如意輪観音坐像（重文）33年に1度開扉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nyoirin Kannon seated image (important cultural property), the principal icon of the Kannon-do hall of Onjo-ji Temple (Shiga): unveiled once every 33 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nyoirin Kannon seated image (important cultural property), the principal icon of the Kannon-do hall of Onjo-ji Temple (Shiga): unveiled once every 33 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nyoirin Kannon seated statue (important cultural property), the principal image of the Kannon-do hall of Onjo-ji Temple (Shiga): unveiled once every 33 years.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>石山寺（滋賀）本尊　如意輪観音坐像（重文）33年に一度と天皇即位の年に開扉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nyoirin Kannon seated icon (important cultural property), the principal icon of Ishiyama-dera Temple (Shiga): unveiled every 33 years and on the year of enthronement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nyoirin Kannon seated icon (important cultural property), the principal icon of Ishiyama-dera Temple (Shiga): unveiled every 33 years and on the year of enthronement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nyoirin Kannon seated statue (important cultural property), the principal image of Ishiyama-dera Temple (Shiga): unveiled every 33 years and on the year of enthronement.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>清水寺（京都）本尊　千手観音立像　33年に一度開扉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senju Kannon standing image, the principal icon of Kiyomizu-dera Temple (Kyoto): unveiled every 33 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senju Kannon standing image, the principal icon of Kiyomizu-dera Temple (Kyoto): unveiled every 33 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senju Kannon standing statue, the principal image of Kiyomizu-dera Temple (Kyoto): unveiled every 33 years.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>六波羅蜜寺（京都）本尊　十一面観音立像（国宝）辰年に開扉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Juichimen Kannon standing image (national treasure), the principal icon of Rokuharamitsu-ji Temple (Kyoto): unveiled on the Tatsu-doshi year (the year of the dragon, according to Chinese astrology).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Juichimen Kannon standing image (national treasure), the principal icon of Rokuharamitsu-ji Temple (Kyoto): unveiled on the Tatsu-doshi year (the year of the dragon, according to Chinese astrology).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juichimen Kannon standing statue (national treasure), the principal image of Rokuharamitsu-ji Temple (Kyoto): unveiled on the Tatsu-doshi year (the year of the dragon, according to Chinese astrology).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>慈尊院（和歌山）本尊　弥勒仏坐像（国宝）21年に一度開扉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miroku Buddha seated image (national treasure), the principal icon of Jisonin Temple (Wakayama): unveiled every 21 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miroku Buddha seated image (national treasure), the principal icon of Jisonin Temple (Wakayama): unveiled every 21 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miroku Buddha seated statue (national treasure), the principal image of Jisonin Temple (Wakayama): unveiled every 21 years.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="81">
<j>開扉時期を定めていないもの</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hibutsu whose exhibition periods are not determined</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hibutsu whose exhibition periods are not determined</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hibutsu whose exhibition periods are not determined</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>中尊寺（岩手）一字金輪坐像（重文）特別の行事の際などに不定期に公開される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ichijikinrin Butchou (Ekaaksarausnisacakra) seated image (important cultural property) at Chuson-ji Temple (Iwate): unveiled on an irregular basis for special occasions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ichijikinrin Butchou (Ekaaksarausnisacakra) seated image (important cultural property) at Chuson-ji Temple (Iwate): unveiled on an irregular basis for special occasions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ichijikinrin (Ekaaksarausnisacakra) seated statue (important cultural property) at Chuson-ji Temple (Iwate): unveiled on an irregular basis for special occasions.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="83">
<j>成田山新勝寺（千葉）本尊不動明王及び二童子像（重文）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fudo Myoo image, the principal icon of Naritasan Shinsho-ji Temple and its Nidoji (two children) images (all important cultural properties)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fudo Myoo image, the principal icon of Naritasan Shinsho-ji Temple and its Nidoji (two children) images (all important cultural properties)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fudo Myoo statue, the principal image at Shinsho-ji Temple on Mt. Narita and its Nidoji (two children) statues (all important cultural properties).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>浅草寺（東京）本尊　聖観音像　絶対の秘仏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sho-kannon image, the principal icon of Senso-ji Temple (Tokyo); never unveiled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sho-kannon image, the principal icon of Senso-ji Temple (Tokyo); never unveiled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sho-kannon statue, the principal image of Senso-ji Temple (Tokyo); never unveiled.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>写真なし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No picture has been taken.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No picture has been taken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No picture has been taken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="86">
<j>寛永寺（東京）本尊　薬師三尊立像（重文）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yakushi triad image, the principal icon at Kanei-ji Temple (Tokyo) (important cultural property)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yakushi triad image, the principal icon at Kanei-ji Temple (Tokyo) (important cultural property)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yakushi triad standing statue, the principal image at Kanei-ji Temple (Tokyo) (important cultural property).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>善光寺（長野）本尊　阿弥陀三尊立像　本尊は絶対の秘仏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amida triad standing image, the principal icon of Zenko-ji Temple (Nagano); never unveiled (&apos;absolute&apos; hibutsu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amida triad standing image, the principal icon of Zenko-ji Temple (Nagano); never unveiled (&apos;absolute&apos; hibutsu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amida triad standing statue, the principal image of Zenko-ji Temple (Nagano); never unveiled (&apos;absolute&apos; hibutsu).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>写真なし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No picture has been taken.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No picture has been taken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No picture has been taken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>前立ち像は7年目ごと（開帳の年を1年目とするので実際は6年に1回）開扉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Omaedachi-zo image is unveiled once every 7 years (more precisely, every 6 years as the year in which the hibutsu is unveiled is counted as the first year).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Omaedachi-zo image is unveiled once every 7 years (more precisely, every 6 years as the year in which the hibutsu is unveiled is counted as the first year).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Omaedachi-zo image is unveiled once every 7 years (more precisely, every 6 years as the year in which the hibutsu is unveiled is counted as the first year).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="90">
<j>甲斐善光寺（山梨）本尊　阿弥陀三尊像（重文）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amida triad image (important cultural property), the principal icon of Kai-Zenko-ji Temple (Yamanashi)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amida triad image (important cultural property), the principal icon of Kai-Zenko-ji Temple (Yamanashi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amida triad statue (important cultural property), the principal image of Kai-Zenko-ji Temple (Yamanashi)</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>延暦寺（滋賀）根本中堂本尊　薬師如来立像　1988年、2000年、2006年に開扉されたことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yakushi Nyorai standing image, the principal icon of the Kompon-chudo hall of Enryaku-ji Temple (Shiga): unveiled in 1998, 2000, and 2006.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yakushi Nyorai standing image, the principal icon of the Kompon-chudo hall of Enryaku-ji Temple (Shiga): unveiled in 1998, 2000, and 2006.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yakushi Nyorai standing statue, the principal image of the Konpon-chudo hall of Enryaku-ji Temple (Shiga): unveiled in 1998, 2000, and 2006.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="92">
<j>園城寺（滋賀）本尊　弥勒菩薩像　絶対の秘仏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miroku Bosatsu image, the principal icon of Onjo-ji Temple (Shiga): never unveiled (&apos;absolute&apos; hibutsu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miroku Bosatsu image, the principal icon of Onjo-ji Temple (Shiga): never unveiled (&apos;absolute&apos; hibutsu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miroku Bosatsu statue, the principal image of Onjo-ji Temple (Shiga): never unveiled (&apos;absolute&apos; hibutsu).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>写真なし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No picture has been taken.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No picture has been taken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No picture has been taken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="94">
<j>園城寺　智証大師（円珍）坐像（国宝）「中尊大師」、「御骨大師」の2体あり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two Chisho-daishi (the posthumous name of Enchin, a priest of the Tendai sect in the early Heian period, the fifth head of Enryaku-ji Temple)seated images (national treasures) at Onjo-ji Temple, called &quot;Chuson Daishi&quot; and &quot;Okotsu Daishi&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two Chisho-daishi (the posthumous name of Enchin, a priest of the Tendai sect in the early Heian period, the fifth head of Enryaku-ji Temple)seated images (national treasures) at Onjo-ji Temple, called &quot;Chuson Daishi&quot; and &quot;Okotsu Daishi&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two Chisho-daishi (the posthumous name of Enchin, a priest of the Tendai sect in the early Heian period, the fifth head of Enryaku-ji Temple) seated statues (national treasures) at Onjo-ji Temple, called &apos;Chuson Daishi&apos; and &apos;Okotsu Daishi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>前者は10月29日の祥忌法要で開扉されるが、後者は開扉なし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former is unveiled on October 29 in a shoki hoyo (a Buddhist memorial service held on the death anniversary), but the latter has never been publicly displayed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former is unveiled on October 29 in a shoki hoyo (a Buddhist memorial service held on the death anniversary), but the latter has never been publicly displayed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former is unveiled on October 29 in a shoki hoyo (a Buddhist memorial service held on the death anniversary), but the latter has never been publicly displayed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>特別展などで数回公開されたことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But it has been unveiled several times on special exhibitions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But it has been unveiled several times at special exhibitions.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But it has been unveiled several times at special exhibitions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="97">
<j>園城寺　新羅明神坐像（国宝）特別展などで数回公開されたことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was publicly displayed several times on special exhibitions, including those of Shinra Myojin (literally, &quot;the deity of Shiragi, a kingdom of the ancient Korea&quot; and the guardian deity of Onjo-ji Temple) seated image (national treasure).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was publicly displayed several times at special exhibitions, including those of Shinra Myojin (literally, &quot;the deity of Shiragi, a kingdom of the ancient Korea&quot; and the guardian deity of Onjo-ji Temple) seated image (national treasure).</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinra Myojin (literally, the god of Shiragi, a kingdom of the ancient Korea and the guardian god of Onjo-ji Temple) seated statue (national treasure): unveiled several times at special exhibitions.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="98">
<j>園城寺　不動明王像（黄不動、絵画、国宝）厳重な秘仏として知られ、寺では書籍等への写真掲載を厳しく制限している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Fudo Myoo (Yellow Fudo) image (a painting and a national treasure) at Onjo-ji Temple is known as a hibutsu which has been handled with special care; the temple does not allow its picture to appear in books or other publications.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Fudo Myoo (Yellow Fudo) image (a painting and a national treasure) at Onjo-ji Temple is known as a hibutsu which has been handled with special care; the temple does not allow its picture to appear in books or other publications.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Fudo Myoo (Acala, one of the Five Wisdom Kings) image (a painting and a national treasure) at Onjo-ji Temple is known as a hibutsu which has been handled with special care; the temple does not allow its picture to appear in books or other publications.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>特別展などで数回公開されたことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it has been unveiled several times on special exhibitions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it has been unveiled several times in special exhibitions.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it has been unveiled several times in special exhibitions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="100">
<j>善水寺（滋賀）本尊　薬師如来坐像（重文）1949年、2001年に開扉されたほか、2005年には京都国立博物館における「最澄と天台の国宝」展に出陳された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yakushi Nyorai seated image, the principal image of Zensui-ji Temple (Shiga) (important cultural property) was unveiled on 1949 and 2001, and in 2005, it was displayed on the exhibition titled &quot;Faith and Syncretism: Saicho and the Treasures of Tendai&quot; held in Kyoto National Museum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yakushi Nyorai seated image, the principal image of Zensui-ji Temple (Shiga) (important cultural property) was unveiled in 1949 and 2001, and in 2005, it was displayed in the exhibition titled &quot;Faith and Syncretism: Saicho and the Treasures of Tendai&quot; held in Kyoto National Museum.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yakushi Nyorai seated statue, the principal image at Zensui-ji Temple (Shiga) (important cultural property) was unveiled in 1949 and 2001, and in 2005, it was displayed in the exhibition titled &apos;Faith and Syncretism: Saicho and the Treasures of Tendai&apos; held in Kyoto National Museum.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="101">
<j>東寺（京都）御影堂　不動明王坐像（国宝）学術調査以外に公開された記録なし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Fudo Myoo seated image at the Mikage-do hall of Toji Temple (Kyoto) has never been unveiled to the public except for the purpose of academic research.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Fudo Myoo seated image at the Mikage-do hall of Toji Temple (Kyoto) has never been unveiled to the public except for the purpose of academic research.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Fudo Myoo seated statue at the Mikage-do hall of To-ji Temple (Kyoto): it never been unveiled to the public except for the purpose of academic research.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="102">
<j>東寺（京都）御影堂　弘法大師坐像（国宝）運慶の4男、康勝作。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kobo-daisi seated image (national treasure) at the Mikage-do hall of Toji Temple (Kyoto), carved by Kosho, the fourth son of Unkei (a sculptor of the late Heian and early Kamakura periods, who established a style of Buddhist sculpture that had an immense impact on Japanese art for centuries).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kobo-daisi seated image (national treasure) at the Mikage-do hall of Toji Temple (Kyoto), carved by Kosho, the fourth son of Unkei (a sculptor of the late Heian and early Kamakura periods, who established a style of Buddhist sculpture that had an immense impact on Japanese art for centuries).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kobo-daishi seated statue (national treasure) at the Mikage-do hall of To-ji Temple (Kyoto), carved by Kosho, the fourth son of Unkei (a sculptor of the late Heian and early Kamakura periods, who established a style of Buddhist sculpture that had an immense impact on Japanese art for centuries).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>学術調査以外に公開された記録なし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This image has never been unveiled to the public except for the purpose of academic research.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This image has never been unveiled to the public except for the purpose of academic research.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This statue has never been unveiled to the public except for the purpose of academic research.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="104">
<j>仁和寺（京都）霊明殿本尊　薬師如来坐像（国宝）1986年の学術調査で初めて開扉された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yakushi Nyorai seated image (national treasure), the principal image of the Reimei-den hall of Ninna-ji Temple (Kyoto) was unveiled to the public in 1986 for the first time for the purpose of academic research.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yakushi Nyorai seated image (national treasure), the principal image of the Reimei-den hall of Ninna-ji Temple (Kyoto) was unveiled to the public in 1986 for the first time for the purpose of academic research.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yakushi Nyorai seated statue (national treasure), the principal image of the Reimei-den hall of Ninna-ji Temple (Kyoto) was unveiled to the public in 1986 for the first time for the purpose of academic research.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="105">
<j>法輪寺 (京都市西京区)（京都）本尊　虚空蔵菩薩像　十三参りの本尊として信仰を集める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kokuzo Bosatsu image, the principal image of Horin-ji Temple (Saigyo Ward, Kyoto City) is worshipped by people as the deity of &quot;Jusanmairi&quot; (a practice of visiting the temple, cerebrating their sons and daughters attaining at manhood/womanhood at the age of thirteen).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kokuzo Bosatsu image, the principal image of Horin-ji Temple (Saigyo Ward, Kyoto City) is worshipped by people as the deity of &quot;Jusanmairi&quot; (a practice of visiting the temple, celebrating their sons and daughters attaining manhood/womanhood at the age of thirteen).</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kokuzo Bosatsu statue, the principal image of Horin-ji Temple (Saigyo-ku Ward, Kyoto City) is worshipped by people as the god of Jusanmairi (a practice of visiting the temple, celebrating their sons and daughters attaining manhood or womanhood at the age of thirteen).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>大正天皇が拝観して以来一般公開記録なし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The image has never been unveiled to the public since it was visited by Emperor Taisho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The image has never been unveiled to the public since it was visited by Emperor Taisho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The statue has never been unveiled to the public since it was visited by Emperor Taisho.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="107">
<j>東大寺（奈良）二月堂本尊　十一面観音立像　大観音、小観音の2体があるが、いずれも絶対の秘仏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Juichimen Kannon standing images, the principle image of the Nigatsu-do hall of Todai-ji Temple (Nara), come in two images, Oo-gannon and Ko-gannon both of which have never been unveiled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Juichimen Kannon standing images, the principle image of the Nigatsu-do hall of Todai-ji Temple (Nara), come in two images, Oo-gannon and Ko-gannon both of which have never been unveiled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Juichimen Kannon standing statues, the principle image of the Nigatsu-do hall of Todai-ji Temple (Nara), come in two statues, O-gannon and Ko-gannon both of which have never been unveiled.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>写真なし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No picture has been taken.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No picture has been taken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No picture has been taken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="109">
<j>金峯山寺（奈良）本尊　蔵王権現立像（重文）2004年から2005年にかけて、「紀伊山地の霊場と参詣道」の世界遺産登録を記念して開扉された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Zao Gongen standing image, the principal image of Kinpusen-ji Temple (Nara), was unveiled during 2004 - 2005, commemorating that holy places and pilgrim routes in the Kii Mountain range had been registered as World Heritage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Zao Gongen standing image, the principal image of Kinpusen-ji Temple (Nara), was unveiled during 2004 - 2005, commemorating that holy places and pilgrim routes in the Kii Mountain range had been registered as World Heritage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Zao Gongen standing statue, the principal image of Kinpusen-ji Temple (Nara), was unveiled during 2004 to 2005, commemorating that holy places and pilgrim routes in the Kii Mountain range had been registered as World Heritage.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Rusk(id:9895), Ｍ．Ｇ(id:27945), Nakadati(id:26815), Kouchiumi(id:19253), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Urania(id:7213), 人間学者(id:135122), Suisui(id:69), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>