<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>日親</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nisshin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nisshin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nisshin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>日親（にっしん、1407年（応永14年） - 1488年10月21日（長享2年9月17日 (旧暦)））は、室町時代の日蓮宗の僧である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nisshin (born 1407, died October 21, 1488 (old lunar calendar) (September 17, 1488)) was a priest of the Nichiren sect in the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nisshin (born 1407, died October 21, 1488 (old lunar calendar) (September 17, 1488)) was a priest of the Nichiren sect in the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nisshin (1407 - October 30, 1488) was a priest of the Nichiren Sect in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は埴谷重継。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Shigetsugu HANIYA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Shigetsugu HANIYA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Shigetsugu HANIYA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>「不受不施義」を初めて唱えたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is believed to have been the first advocate of &apos;Fuju-fuse-gi.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is believed to have been the first advocate of &apos;Fuju-fuse-gi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is believed to have been the first advocate of &apos;Fuju-fuse-gi&apos; (nothing could be received or given).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>下総国に生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Shimosa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Shimosa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Shimosa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>妙宣寺において父の実弟にあたる日英_(中山門流)に学び、中山法華経寺に入門する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He learned from the younger brother of his father, Nichiei (Nakayamamon-ryu school), at Myosen-ji Temple, and entered Nakayama Hokekyo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He learned from the younger brother of his father, Nichiei (Nakayamamon-ryu school), at Myosen-ji Temple, and entered Nakayama Hokekyo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He learned from the younger biological brother of his father, Nichiei (Nakayamamon School), at Myosen-ji Temple, and entered Nakayama Hokekyo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>用語補足、表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>1427年に上洛し、鎌倉や京都など各地で布教活動を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went to the capital in 1427, and conducted missionary work in various places including Kamakura and Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He went to the capital in 1427, and conducted missionary work in various places including Kamakura and Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He went to the capital in 1427, and conducted missionary work in various places including Kamakura and Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>1433年には肥前国へ赴く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went to Hizen Province in 1433.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He went to Hizen Province in 1433.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He went to Hizen Province in 1433.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>同年に再び上洛し、本法寺 (京都市)を開く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He revisited the capital in the same year to found Honpo-ji Temple (Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He revisited the capital in the same year to found Honpo-ji Temple (Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He revisited the capital in the same year to found Honpo-ji Temple (Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>日親は諸寺院を日蓮宗に改宗させ、6代将軍足利義教への説法の機会を得た際に他宗の喜捨を説いて建言を禁止される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nisshin, who made various temples converted to the Nichiren sect, advocated almsgiving of other sects when he had the opportunity to preach the sixth shogun, Yoshinori ASHIKAGA; as a result, he was forbidden to propose to the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nisshin, who made various temples convert to the Nichiren sect, advocated almsgiving of other sects when he had the opportunity to preach to the sixth shogun, Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, and as a result, he was forbidden to propose to the government.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nisshin, who made various temples convert to the Nichiren Sect, advocated almsgiving of other sects when he had the opportunity to preach to the sixth Shogun, Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, and as a result, he was forbidden to propose to the government.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>禁に背いたために投獄され、本妙寺は破却となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He broke the ban and was incarcerated; Honmyo-ji Temple was destroyed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He broke the ban and was incarcerated; Honmyo-ji Temple was destroyed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He broke the ban and was incarcerated; Honmyo-ji Temple was destroyed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>拷問を受けた際に灼熱の鍋を被せられたまま説法を説いたという伝説が誕生し、「鍋かぶり上人」、「鍋かぶり日親」等と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was nicknamed &apos;pan-wearing shonin&apos; and &apos;pan-wearing Nisshin&apos; based on the legend that he was tortured by being placed a burning pan put on his head but he did not stop preaching</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was nicknamed &apos;pan-wearing shonin&apos; and &apos;pan-wearing Nisshin&apos; based on the legend that he was tortured by a burning pan being placed on his head but he did not stop preaching</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was nicknamed &apos;pan-wearing shonin&apos; and &apos;pan-wearing Nisshin&apos; based on the legend that he was tortured by a burning pan being placed on his head but he did not stop preaching</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>1441年の嘉吉の乱で義教が殺されると赦免されるが、その後も8代将軍足利義政の上洛命令などを受け、投獄もされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was released after Yoshinori was killed in Kakitsu War in 1441; he was incarcerated again when he was ordered to come to Kyoto by the eighth shogun, Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was released after Yoshinori was killed in the Kakitsu War in 144. He was incarcerated again when he was ordered to come to Kyoto by the eighth shogun, Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was released after Yoshinori was killed in the Kakitsu War in 1441 and was incarcerated again when he was ordered to come to Kyoto by the eighth Shogun, Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>1文にし、補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>1463年には町衆の本阿弥清延の協力を得て本妙寺を再興する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honmyo-ji Temple was rebuilt with support from a machi-shu (merchant class) named Kiyonobu HONAMI in 1463.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honmyo-ji Temple was rebuilt with support from a machi-shu (merchant class) named Kiyonobu HONAMI in 1463.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honmyo-ji Temple was rebuilt with support from a machi-shu (merchant class) named Kiyonobu HONAMI in 1463.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>1488年に死去、享年82。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died in 1488, at age 82.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died in 1488, at age 82.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died in 1488, at age 82.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>日親と不受不施義</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nisshin and Fuju-fuse-gi (nothing could be received or given)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nisshin and Fuju-fuse-gi (nothing could be received or given)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nisshin and Fujufuse-gi</e>
<cmt>前出補足をのぞき、表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>日蓮の法華経に対する純粋な姿勢も、南北朝時代 (日本)の戦乱や室町時代に入ると宗派が勢力を拡大していく過程の中で、他宗派との妥協や他宗派の信者からの施しを平気で受けるなど、次第に変質していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His pure worship of Nichiren&apos;s Hokekyo (Lotus Sutra) gradually changed as the wars continued during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan) and other sects expanded their influence during the Muromachi Period; he compromised with other sects and did not hesitate to receive charity from believers of other sects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His pure worship of Nichiren&apos;s Hokekyo (Lotus Sutra) gradually changed as the wars continued during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan) and other sects expanded their influence during the Muromachi Period; he compromised with other sects and did not hesitate to receive charity from believers of other sects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nichiren&apos;s pure worship of Hoke-kyo (Lotus Sutra) gradually changed as the wars continued during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan) and other sects expanded their influence during the Muromachi period; he compromised with other sects and did not hesitate to receive charity from believers of other sects.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>特に中山法華経寺に代表される中山門流は本来他宗派に対して比較的寛容であったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular, Nakayamamon-ryu school represented by Nakayama Hokekyo-ji Temple was believed to be relatively tolerant to other sects.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, Nakayamamon-ryu school represented by Nakayama Hokekyo-ji Temple was believed to be relatively tolerant of other sects.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, Nakayamamon School represented by Nakayama Hokekyo-ji Temple was believed to be relatively tolerant of other sects from the beginning.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>同寺の寺宝である立正安国論が建武_(日本)3年（1336年）に律宗寺院であった鎌倉・普恩寺（現在は廃絶）に貸し与えられて書写されていた事が記録されている程である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the record, Rissho Ankoku-ron (a tract by Nichiren), which was the temple&apos;s treasure, had been rent out to Kamakura Fuon-ji Temple belonging to the Risshu sect (the temple no longer exists) in 1336.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the records, Rissho Ankoku-ron (a tract by Nichiren), which was the temple&apos;s treasure, had been lent out to Kamakura Fuon-ji Temple belonging to the Risshu sect (the temple no longer exists) in 1336.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the records, Rissho ankoku ron (the Treatise for Spreading Peace Throughout the Country by Establishing the True Teaching), which was the temple&apos;s treasure, had been lent out to Kamakura Fuon-ji Temple (no longer exists) of the Ritsu Sect to transcribe in 1336.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>このような状況の中で、日親は不受不施を主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amid the situation, Nisshin advocated Fuju-fuse-gi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amid the situation, Nisshin advocated Fuju-fuse-gi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amid the situation, Nisshin advocated Fujufuse-gi.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>日親の活動</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nisshin&apos;s activities</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nisshin&apos;s activities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nisshin&apos;s activities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>日親は京都一条戻橋で辻説法をはじめたが（1427）、比叡山延暦寺や将軍家の帰依を受けていた臨済宗などの他宗派から激しい弾圧を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nisshin began street preaching at Ichijo Modori-bashi Bridge in Kyoto (1427); other sects including Enryaku-ji Temple of Mt. Hiei and the Rinzai sect embraced by the shogunate family severely oppressed his activities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nisshin began street preaching at Ichijo Modori-bashi Bridge in Kyoto (1427). Other sects, including Enryaku-ji Temple of Mt. Hiei and the Rinzai sect, embraced by the shogunate family severely oppressed his activities.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nisshin began street preaching at Ichijo Modori-bashi Bridge in Kyoto (1427), however, other sects, including Enryaku-ji Temple on Mt. Hiei and the Rinzai Sect, embraced by the shogunate family severely oppressed his activities.</e>
<cmt>1文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>また日親は法華経によって、当時の乱れた世の中を救うべく（同時代は正長の土一揆や後南朝勢力の反乱などの動乱が続いた）、足利将軍家の日蓮宗への改宗を目論み「立正治国論」を著し、直訴を試みたが投獄された（1440）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To save the chaotic society by Hokekyo, Nisshin wrote &apos;Risshochikoku-ron&apos; in an attempt to convert the Ashikaga shogunate family to the Nichiren sect (During the era, unquiet days continued as the peasants&apos; uprising of Shocho era and rebellion of the Gonancho force occured); he was incarcerated for the attempted direct appeal (1440).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To save the chaotic society by Hokekyo, Nisshin wrote &apos;Risshochikoku-ron&apos; in an attempt to convert the Ashikaga shogunate family to the Nichiren sect (during this era, restless days continued as the peasants&apos; uprising of the Shocho era and the rebellion of the Gonancho force occured). He was incarcerated for the attempted direct appeal (1440).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To save the chaotic society by Hoke-kyo, Nisshin wrote &apos;Rissho jikoku ron&apos; (the Treatise on Establishing the True Teaching and Governing the Country) in an attempt to convert the Ashikaga shogunate family to the Nichiren Sect (during this era, restless days continued as the peasants&apos; uprising of the Shocho era and the rebellion of the Gonancho (Second Southern Court) force occurred) and was incarcerated for the attempted direct appeal (1440).</e>
<cmt>1文にし、補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>真っ赤に焼けた鉄鍋を頭に被せられるなどの拷問を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was tortured; his head was covered with a red-hot pan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was tortured; his head was covered with a red-hot pan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was tortured; his head was covered with a red-hot pan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>この鍋は伝承では終生頭から取れることは無かったといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the legend, the pan never left his head for the rest of his life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the legend, the pan never left his head for the rest of his life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the legend, the pan never left his head for the rest of his life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>著作</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Literary works</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Literary works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Literary Works</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>『折伏正義抄』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shakubuku-seigi-sho&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shakubuku-seigi-sho&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shakubuku-seigi-sho&quot; (abridgment of teaching of shakubuku (a method of propagating Buddhism which was practiced by Nichiren Daishonin))</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="24">
<j>『立正治国論』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Risshochikoku-ron&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Risshochikoku-ron&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Rissho jikoku ron&quot;</e>
<cmt>前出に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), Carkuni(id:79281), Tomzo(id:16777), Alex K(id:86829), R28Bot(id:177951), 水野白楓(id:22811), Cprobot(id:97843), Dream100(id:41924), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>