<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>現生正定聚</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genseishojoju (those guaranteed to be born in the Pure Land while still in this world)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genseishojoju (those guaranteed to be born in the Pure Land while still in this world)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genseishojoju (those guaranteed to be born in the Pure Land while still in this world)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>現生正定聚（げんしょうしょうじょうじゅ）とは、「現生不退（げんしょうふたい）」とも言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;Genseishojoju&quot; is also referred as &quot;gensho futai (the idea of &quot;not falling back in this world&quot;).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;Genseishojoju&quot; is also referred to as &quot;gensho futai (the idea of &quot;not falling back in this world&quot;).&quot;</e>
<cmt>added &quot;to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;Genseishojoju&quot; is also referred to as &apos;gensho futai (the idea of &quot;not falling back in this world&quot;).&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文「」の部分を &apos; &apos; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>また、日本仏教の宗派の一つである浄土真宗の教義の根幹を指す用語であり、親鸞の信心の特徴をあらわすもっとも端的にまとまった用語である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, this term denotes the doctrinal basis of the Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism), one of the traditional schools of Japanese Buddhism, and highlights Shinran&apos;s religious faith most succinctly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, this term denotes the doctrinal basis of the Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism), one of the traditional schools of Japanese Buddhism, and highlights Shinran&apos;s religious faith most succinctly.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, this term denotes the doctrinal basis of the Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism), one of the traditional schools of Japanese Buddhism, and highlights Shinran&apos;s religious faith most succinctly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>内容は、阿弥陀仏から回向された信心を受容すれば、浄土に往生することが定まり、悟りを開いて仏になることが、その時点で決定していることをいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What Shinran expounded about the term is that to accept faith devoted by Amida Buddha would affirm birth in the Pure Land, and attainment of enlightment, becoming a Buddha, at that moment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What Shinran expounded about the term is that accepting faith devoted by Amida Buddha would affirm birth in the Pure Land, and attainment of enlightment, becoming a Buddha, at that moment.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What Shinran expounded about the term is that accepting faith devoted by Amida Buddha would affirm birth in the Pure Land, and attainment of enlightenment, becoming a Buddha, at that moment.</e>
<cmt>enlightmentをenlightenmentに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>つまり、現時点で、仏となることが決まっているということである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, faith ensures that sentient beings would become a Buddha here and now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, faith ensures that sentient beings would become Buddhas here and now.</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OK</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>この言葉で表現されるように、親鸞は、それまでの浄土教義とは異なり、信心は阿弥陀仏から人間に与えられるものであり、その信心を受容することで、浄土に往生でき、現在・現時点で仏となることが決定している（一念発起住正定聚、平生業成、即得往生住不退転）とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As this term indicated, Shinran explained that unlike the creed of pure land teachings till then, he made faith, conferred upon the individual by Amida Buddha, the sole precondition for attainment of birth in the Pure Land and for guarantee to become a Buddha at this moment and in this world (Ichinenhokki jushojoju, Heizei-gogyo, and Sokutokuojo jufutaiten: all these verses expound the Shinran&apos;s concept of &quot;Genseishojoju&quot;)</e>
<cmt>一念発起→信心をひとたび起こすこと、住正定聚→必ず仏となるべき位（正定聚）に安住すること、平生業成→平常のときにおいて浄土に生まれる業が成立し終わっているということ、即得往生住不退転→真宗では、同時の即と理解し阿弥陀仏の明号を聞き、一念の信心を起こしたものは、その信の一念にすぐさま往生すべき身と定まり、現生において正定住不退転の位に住すると考える＜仏教語大辞典（中村元著、東京書籍出版）、これら３つの用語は「現生正定聚」の内容と同じであり、また追加情報であるため、内容説明より、「親鸞の考えを説明したものである」と補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As this term indicated, Shinran explained that, unlike the creed of pure land teachings until then, he made faith, conferred upon the individual by Amida Buddha, the sole precondition for attainment of birth in the Pure Land and for guarantee to become a Buddha at this moment and in this world (Ichinenhokki jushojoju, Heizei-gogyo, and Sokutokuojo jufutaiten: all these verses expound Shinran&apos;s concept of &quot;Genseishojoju&quot;)</e>
<cmt>punctuation, article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As this term indicated, Shinran explained that, unlike the creed of pure land teachings until then, he made faith, conferred upon the individual by Amida Buddha, the sole precondition for attainment of birth in the Pure Land and for guarantee to become a Buddha at this moment and in this world (Ichinenhokki jushojoju, Heizei-gogyo, and Sokutokuojo jufutaiten: all these verses expound Shinran&apos;s concept of &quot;Genseishojoju&quot;).</e>
<cmt>文末にピリオドをうちました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>そのため、（信心を得た後で）人間が称える「南無阿弥陀仏」という称名念仏は、その功徳により浄土へ往生しようとするためのものではなく、既に浄土へ行くことが決まっていることへの感謝の称名であると言うのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From this point of view, he interpreted that (after accepting faith), the recitation of nenbutsu (the name of Amida Buddha), &apos;namuamidabutsu (literally, I take my refuge in Amida Buddha)&apos; is not the invocation uttered in the hope of rebirth into the Pure Land by the salvific power of Amida Buddha, but in gratitude for ensuring birth in the Pure Land.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From this point of view, he interpreted that (after accepting faith), the recitation of nenbutsu (the name of Amida Buddha), &apos;namuamidabutsu (literally, I take my refuge in Amida Buddha)&apos; is not the invocation uttered in the hope of rebirth into the Pure Land by the salvific power of Amida Buddha, but in gratitude for ensuring birth in the Pure Land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From this point of view, he interpreted that (after accepting faith), the recitation of nenbutsu (the name of Amida Buddha), &apos;namuamidabutsu (literally, I take my refuge in Amida Buddha)&apos; is not the invocation uttered in the hope of rebirth into the Pure Land by the salvific power of Amida Buddha, but in gratitude for ensuring birth in the Pure Land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>親鸞の主著である『顕浄土真実教行証文類』には、下記の通り論じている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ken jodoshinjitsu kyogyosho monrui (Selected passages revealing the true teaching, practice and attainment of the Pure Land),&quot; the major work of Shinran, explained as follows:</e>
<cmt>文ではないので、「下記の通り論じている」を補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ken jodoshinjitsu kyogyosho monrui (Selected passages revealing the true teaching, practice and attainment of the Pure Land),&quot; the major work of Shinran, explained as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Ken jodoshinjitsu kyogyosho monrui (Selected passages revealing the true teaching, practice and attainment of the Pure Land),&quot; the major work of Shinran, explained as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>「かならず現生に十種の益を獲。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ten benefits would be attained in this world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ten benefits would be attained in this world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ten benefits would be attained in this world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>「なにものか十とする。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What the ten benefits would be.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What the ten benefits would be.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What the ten benefits would be.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>「一つには冥衆護持の益、二つには至徳具足の益、三つには転悪成善の益、四つには諸仏護念の益、五つには諸仏称讃の益、六つには心光常護の益、七つには心多歓喜の益、八つには知恩報徳の益、九つには常行大悲の益、十には正定聚に入る益なり。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are as follows; the first benefit of being protected by unseen divinities, the second one of attaining the utmost virtue, the third one of transforming all one&apos;s evils into good, the forth one of being protected by all Buddhas, the fifth one of being praised by all Buddhas, sixth one of being constantly protected by Amida&apos;s spiritual light, the seventh one of having much joy in mind, the eighth one of acknowledging Amida&apos;s benevolence and responding in gratitude to his virtue, and the ninth one of constant practicing great compassion, and the last one of entering &apos;shojoju&apos; (those guaranteed to be born in the Pure Land).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are as follows; the first benefit of being protected by unseen divinities, the second one of attaining the utmost virtue, the third one of transforming all one&apos;s evils into good, the fourth one of being protected by all Buddhas, the fifth one of being praised by all Buddhas, the sixth one of being constantly protected by Amida&apos;s spiritual light, the seventh one of having much joy in mind, the eighth one of acknowledging Amida&apos;s benevolence and responding in gratitude to his virtue, the ninth one of constant practicing great compassion, and the last one of entering &apos;shojoju&apos; (those guaranteed to be born in the Pure Land).</e>
<cmt>spelling, articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are as follows; the first benefit of being protected by unseen divinities, the second one of attaining the utmost virtue, the third one of transforming all one&apos;s evils into good, the fourth one of being protected by all Buddhas, the fifth one of being praised by all Buddhas, the sixth one of being constantly protected by Amida&apos;s spiritual light, the seventh one of having much joy in mind, the eighth one of acknowledging Amida&apos;s benevolence and responding in gratitude to his virtue, the ninth one of constant practicing great compassion, and the last one of entering &apos;shojoju&apos; (those guaranteed to be born in the Pure Land).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>それには、正定聚に入る益が含まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinran listed &apos;entering shojoju&apos; as the last benefit in &quot;Ken jodo shinjitsu kyogyosho monrui.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinran listed &apos;entering shojoju&apos; as the last benefit in &quot;Ken jodo shinjitsu kyogyosho monrui.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinran listed &apos;entering shojoju&apos; as the last benefit in &quot;Ken jodo shinjitsu kyogyosho monrui.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>これらの十種の利益（りやく）を得るのは、金剛の信心を獲得した者であり、そのためには真実行を行ずるだけで良く、それにより、阿弥陀仏から信心が廻向され、仏になることが定まると論じたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He concluded that only practicing &apos;shinjitsugyo&apos; (recitation of nenbutsu) allowed sentient beings to attain the ten benefits which led to &apos;true faith&apos;, conferred by Amida Buddha, promising to become a Buddha.</e>
<cmt>真実行→念仏をとなえること＜仏教語大辞典（中村元著、東京書籍出版）→shinjitsugyo→recitation of nenbutsuと訳出しました。金剛の信心→true faithと訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He concluded that only practicing &apos;shinjitsugyo&apos; (recitation of nenbutsu) allowed sentient beings to attain the ten benefits which led to &apos;true faith&apos;, conferred by Amida Buddha, promising to become a Buddha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He concluded that only practicing &apos;shinjitsugyo&apos; (recitation of nenbutsu) allowed sentient beings to attain the ten benefits which led to &apos;true faith&apos;, conferred by Amida Buddha, promising to become a Buddha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tiyoringo(id:70026), マイコン坊主(id:338), Dr jimmy(id:111486), 雲明(id:163481), ウィキ豊(id:82961), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>