<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>本仏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honbutsu (the Primordial Buddha)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honbutsu (the Primordial Buddha)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honbutsu (the Primordial Buddha)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>本仏（ほんぶつ）とは、無数の仏（如来）の中で、根本となる仏（如来）のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Honbutsu&quot; means the Primordial Buddha among numerous Buddha (Nyorai.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Honbutsu&quot; means the Primordial Buddha among numerous Buddha (Nyorai.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Honbutsu&quot; means the Primordial Buddha among numerous Buddha (Nyorai.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>もともと仏教では、過去七仏にみられるように釈迦仏が仏教という大宗教を成したのは単に釈迦一代のみの事業ではなく、過去においてすでに成道し成仏した仏陀たちの前世の功徳が累積した結果であるという思想があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally in Buddhism, as may be seen in the legend of Kako-shichibutsu (seven Buddha in the past,) Shakyamuni Buddha was believed to have successfully established such a great religion as Buddhism not within his generation but as a result of accumulated good conducts of his many predecessors Buddha who had attained enlightenment and Buddhahood in the past world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally in Buddhism, as may be seen in the legend of Kako-shichibutsu (seven Buddhas in the past,) Shakyamuni Buddha was believed to have successfully established such a great religion as Buddhism not within his generation, but as a result of the accumulated good conduct of his many predecessor Buddhas who had attained enlightenment and Buddhahood in the past world.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally in Buddhism, as may be seen in the legend of Kako-shichibutsu (seven Buddhas in the past), Shakyamuni Buddha was believed to have successfully established such a great religion as Buddhism not within his generation, but as a result of the accumulated good conduct of his many predecessor Buddhas who had attained enlightenment and Buddhahood in the past world.</e>
<cmt>カンマを括弧外へ移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>また異端とされる提婆達多派の仏教集団は釈迦を仏と認めず、それ以前に出現した賢劫の三仏を信仰の対象としていたことでも知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A group of Buddhists of Devadatta school which was regarded as heretical were known that they had not recognized Shakyamuni as Buddha and, instead, worshipped Kengo no San-butsu (the last three Buddha of one thousand Buddha who appeared in the period before Shakya-muni&apos;s generation.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A group of Buddhists of the Devadatta school regarded as heretical had known that they had not recognized Shakyamuni as Buddha and, instead, worshipped Kengo no San-butsu (the last three Buddhas of one thousand Buddhas who appeared during the period before Shakya-muni&apos;s generation.)</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A group of Buddhists of the Devadatta school regarded as heretical had known that they had not recognized Shakyamuni as Buddha and, instead, worshipped Kengo no San-butsu (the last three Buddhas of one thousand Buddhas who appeared during the period before Shakya-muni&apos;s generation.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>大乗仏教が広まってからの古代インドにおいては、仏は釈尊だけではなく、多くの人々が仏として尊崇されてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the ancient India, after Mahayana Buddhism became popular there, not only Shakyamuni but also many other persons were respected and adored as Buddha.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In ancient India, after Mahayana Buddhism became popular there, not only Shakyamuni, but also many other persons were respected and adored as Buddha.</e>
<cmt>gramamr, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In ancient India, after Mahayana Buddhism became popular there, not only Shakyamuni, but also many other persons were respected and adored as Buddha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>それらの仏達を迹仏（しゃくぶつ）と呼び、すべては本仏が仮の姿を現したものとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those Buddha other than Shakyamuni were called shaku-butsu, which were regarded as temporary figures of Hon-butsu (Primordial Buddha.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those Buddha other than Shakyamuni were called shaku-butsu, which were regarded as temporary figures of Hon-butsu (Primordial Buddha.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those Buddha other than Shakyamuni were called shaku-butsu, which were regarded as temporary figures of Honbutsu.</e>
<cmt>本仏の説明削除Hon-butsu→Honbutsu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>釈尊滅後、釈尊が仏になることができたのは、在世の修行のみならず、過去世における長い修行の結果であるという思想が生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, there emerged a belief among the people that the reason why Shakyamuni could become Buddha after his death was not only his ascetic practices he made during he was alive but also his long-lasted practices he had done in his past world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, there emerged a belief among the people that the reason why Shakyamuni could become Buddha after his death was not only because of his ascetic practices he made during he was alive, but also his long-lasting practices he had accomplished in his past world.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, there emerged a belief among the people that the reason why Shakyamuni could become Buddha after his death was not only because of his ascetic practices he made during he was alive, but also his long-lasting practices he had accomplished in his past world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また釈尊の過去世には無数の仏の下で修行したこととされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also Shakyamuni was believed that he had done many practices under hosts of Buddha in his past world.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also it was believed that Shakyamuni had conducted many practices under the hosts of Buddha in his past world.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also Shakyamuni was believed that he had done practices under hosts of many Buddha in his past world.</e>
<cmt>many は「仏」にかかるので訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>やがて、それらの仏のなかでも、一番の原因となる本仏が想定されるようになったと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And, Honbutsu (the Primordial Buddha) was assumed to have been one of those Buddha who gave the most causal influence to Shakyamuni.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And, Honbutsu (the Primordial Buddha) was assumed to have been one of those Buddha who gave the most causal influence to Shakyamuni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And, Honbutsu was assumed to have been one of those Buddha who gave the most causal influence to Shakyamuni.</e>
<cmt>本仏の説明削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>本仏思想は12世紀頃の天台宗に見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The thought of Honbutsu appeared in the Buddhist doctrine of Tendai sect in the twelfth century.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The thought of Honbutsu appeared in the Buddhist doctrine of the Tendai sect in the twelfth century.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The thought of Honbutsu appeared in the Buddhist doctrine of the Tendai sect in the 12th century.</e>
<cmt>数字表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>日蓮の本仏思想は、中古天台思想の影響といわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Nichiren&apos;s belief in honbutsu was affected by Chuko Tendai Shiso (literally, thought of half-old Tendai sect doctrine.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Nichiren&apos;s belief in honbutsu was affected by Chuko Tendai Shiso (literally, thought of half-old Tendai sect doctrine.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Nichiren&apos;s belief in honbutsu was affected by Chuko Tendai Shiso (literally, thought of half-old Tendai sect doctrine.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>現在の天台宗は本仏思想を説いていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Currently, Tendai sect is not preaching the thought of honbutsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently, the Tendai sect is not preaching the thought of honbutsu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Currently, the Tendai sect is not preaching the thought of Honbutsu.</e>
<cmt>honbutsu→Honbutsu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>本仏思想は日蓮宗勝劣派と呼ばれる宗派のみが積極的に主張している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, it is Shoretsu school of Nichiren sect only that strongly insist on the thought of Honbutsu..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present, it is the Shoretsu school of Nichiren sect only that strongly insists on the thought of Honbutsu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present, it is the Shoretsu school of Nichiren sect only that strongly insists on the thought of Honbutsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>日蓮本仏論</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nichiren Honbutsu-ron (an idea to identify Nichiren with Honbutsu):</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nichiren Honbutsu-ron (the idea to identify Nichiren with Honbutsu):</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nichiren Honbutsu-ron (the idea to identify Nichiren with Honbutsu):</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>初期の仏教では、釈尊が出家して6年間修行して悟りを啓いたとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early stage of Buddhism, Shakyamuni was believed to have been enlightened after completion of six-year-practices as a priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early stage of Buddhism, Shakyamuni was believed to have been enlightened after completion of six-year-practices as a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early stage of Buddhism, Shakyamuni was believed to have been enlightened after completion of six-year-practices as a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これを始成正覚（しじょうしょうかく）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This enlightenment of Shakyamuni was called Shijo-shokaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This enlightenment of Shakyamuni was called Shijo-shokaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This enlightenment of Shakyamuni was called Shijo-shokaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>しかし釈尊滅後、やや時代が下ると、法華経などのような一部の経典において、たとえば如来寿量品第十六には、「我実に成仏してより已来、無量無辺百千万億那由陀劫なり」などと書かれ、釈尊は、生まれる前にすでに仏であり長い間、法を説いていたという思想が生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, somewhat later in the period after Shakyamuni&apos;s death, there came to the world a thought that Shakyamuni had already been a Buddha preaching dharma for a long time before he was born to this mortal world, as written in some Buddhist sutra like Hokekyo (the Lotus Sutra,) which mentions in its Chapter Sixteen (the Life Span of the Tathagata,) for example, &quot;it has been immeasurable, boundless hundreds, thousands, ten thousands, millions of nayutas of kalpas since I in fact attained Buddhahood.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, somewhat later during the period after Shakyamuni&apos;s death, there came to the world a thought that Shakyamuni had already been a Buddha preaching dharma for a long time before he was born into this mortal world, as written in some Buddhist sutra like Hokekyo (the Lotus Sutra,) which mentions in its Chapter Sixteen (the Life Span of the Tathagata,) for example, &quot;it has been immeasurable, boundless hundreds, thousands, ten thousands, millions of nayutas of kalpas since I in fact attained Buddhahood.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, somewhat later during the period after Shakyamuni&apos;s death, there came to the world a thought that Shakyamuni had already been a Buddha preaching dharma for a long time before he was born into this mortal world, as written in some Buddhist sutra like Hokke-kyo Sutra (the Lotus Sutra), which mentions in its Chapter 16 (the Life Span of the Tathagata), for example, &apos;it has been immeasurable, boundless hundreds, thousands, ten thousands, millions of nayutas of kalpas since I in fact attained Buddhahood.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを括弧外へ移動&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;数字表記変更法華経の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>これらの思想は、現世における修行で仏になったのではなく、長い長い輪廻の間、気の遠くなるような修行（歴劫修行＝りゃっこうしゅぎょう）の果てに、ようやく成仏ができるという思想を生み出す元と成った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This thought has caused to bring about a belief that Buddhahood may be attained not through practices in this mortal world but only after completion of mind-boggling ryakko- shugyo (countless kalpas of practices to reach enlightenmment in Buddhism) through the long long circle of transmigration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This thought has caused to bring about a belief that Buddhahood may be attained not through practices in this mortal world, but only after completion of mind-boggling ryakko- shugyo (countless kalpas of practices to reach enlightenmment in Buddhism) through the long long circle of transmigration.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This thought has caused to bring about a belief that Buddhahood may be attained not through practices in this mortal world, but only after completion of mind-boggling ryakko-shugyo (countless kalpas of practices to reach enlightenmment in Buddhism) through the long long circle of transmigration.</e>
<cmt>shugyo の前のスペース短縮</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかし、一方では、そんな長く困難な修行は、とても出来ないという拒否反応を招くこととなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the otherhand, this thought provoked adverse reactions that no body could ever follow such a long hard practice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, this thought provoked adverse reactions that no body could ever follow such a long hard practice.</e>
<cmt>word separation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, this thought provoked adverse reactions that no body could ever follow such a long hard practice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>そこで登場したのが、末法思想である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, there appeared mappo-shiso (an idea of the latter days of the world quoted in Dharma.)</e>
<cmt>用語の検索・登録では、「末法」 は &quot;the latter days of Buddhism&quot;とか&quot;the end of the world&quot;などと訳されていますが、ここでは&quot;the latter days of the world quoted in Dharma&quot;としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, there appeared mappo-shiso (an idea of the latter days of the world quoted in Dharma.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, there appeared Mappo-shiso (the &quot;end of the world&quot; belief).</e>
<cmt>末法思想の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>釈尊は法華経に説かれるように五百塵点劫（ごひゃくじんてんごう）に始まる有始有終の仏である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As written in Hokke-kyo (the Lotus Sutra,) Shakyamuni had been Buddha for a definite period which began gohyaku-jintengo (unmeasurable long time) ago.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As written in Hokke-kyo (the Lotus Sutra,) Shakyamuni had been Buddha for a definite period which began gohyaku-jintengo (unmeasurable long time) ago.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As written in Hokke-kyo Sutra, Shakyamuni had been Buddha for a definite period which began gohyaku-jintengo (unmeasurable long time) ago.</e>
<cmt>法華経、既出のため説明削除して、表現変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>したがって釈尊の教えは、末法では役に立たない（白法隠没＝びゃくほうおおんもつ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, Shakyamuni&apos;s teachings will become useless at the age of mappo (the latter days of the world quoted in Dharma,) the idea of which is called Byakuho Oonmotsu (Dharma&apos;s decease.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, Shakyamuni&apos;s teachings will become useless at the age of mappo (the latter days of the world quoted in Dharma,) the idea of which is called Byakuho Oonmotsu (Dharma&apos;s decease.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, Shakyamuni&apos;s teachings will become useless at the age of Mappo (Age of the Final Dharma), the idea of which is called Byakuho Onmotsu (Dharma&apos;s decease).</e>
<cmt>末法の定訳Oonmotsu→Onmotsu （実際に「おんもつ」のようです。）ピリオドを括弧外へ移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>末法の世では釈尊の代わりに、無始無終の久遠元初の根本仏である日蓮の教えによって救われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the age of mappo (the latter days of the world quoted in Dharma,) people shall be rescued not by Shakyamuni Buddha but by Konpon-butsu (Primordial Buddha) existing in an infinite time frame which began from infinitely remote past.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the age of mappo (the latter days of the world quoted in Dharma,) people shall be rescued not by Shakyamuni Buddha, but by Konpon-butsu (Primordial Buddha) existing in an infinite time frame which began from infinitely remote past.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the age of Mappo, people shall be rescued not by Shakyamuni Buddha, but by Nichiren, Konpon-butsu (Primordial Buddha) existing in an infinite time frame which began from infinitely remote past.</e>
<cmt>末法の説明削除mappo→Mappo「日蓮」　訳漏れ対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>これが日蓮本仏論である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This idea is called Nichiren Honbutsu-ron (a theory to identify Nichiren as Konpon-butsu or the Primordial Buddha.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This idea is called Nichiren Honbutsu-ron (a theory to identify Nichiren as Konpon-butsu or the Primordial Buddha.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This idea is called Nichiren Honbutsu-ron.</e>
<cmt>既出のため説明削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>もっとも、日蓮本人は一言も本仏であると宣言したことはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nevertheless, Nichiren had never claimed himself as Primordial Buddha.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nevertheless, Nichiren had never claimed himself as Primordial Buddha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nevertheless, Nichiren had never claimed himself as Primordial Buddha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>日蓮の一部の弟子達が唱え始めた思想であり、異端派として消え行く存在になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was some disciples of Nichiren who initiated the idea to identify Nichiren with the Primordial Buddha, which idea was, though, doomed to perish as heretical.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was some disciples of Nichiren who initiated the idea to identify Nichiren with the Primordial Buddha, which idea was, though, doomed to perish as heretical.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was some disciples of Nichiren who initiated the idea of identifying Nichiren with the Primordial Buddha, but this idea was doomed to failure as it was considered heretical.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>釈迦本仏論</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shaka Honbutsu-ron (an idea to identify Shakyamuni as Primordial Buddha):</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shaka Honbutsu-ron (an idea to identify Shakyamuni as Primordial Buddha):</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shaka Honbutsu-ron (an idea to identify Shakyamuni as Primordial Buddha):</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>日蓮宗・法華宗下の教義のひとつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This idea is a part of Buddhist doctrines of Nichiren-shu or Hokke-shu sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This idea is a part of the Buddhist doctrines of Nichiren-shu or Hokke-shu sect.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This idea is a part of the Buddhist doctrines of Nichiren sect or Hokke sect.</e>
<cmt>「宗」の表記訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>上述の日蓮本仏論と対立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is antagonistic to the above mentioned Nichiren Honbutsu-ron.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is antagonistic to the above mentioned Nichiren Honbutsu-ron.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is antagonistic to the above mentioned Nichiren Honbutsu-ron.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>法華経の如来寿量品第十六の文中に無量長寿の釈迦牟尼仏が登場するが、この釈迦牟尼仏こそ本仏であるであるという教義。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Lotus Sutra&apos;s Chapter Sixteen: The Life Span of the Tathagata, Shakyamuni Buddha was described as having infinite life span, who should be recognized as Honbutsu (primordial Buddha) according to the creed of Hokekyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Lotus Sutra&apos;s Chapter Sixteen: The Life Span of the Tathagata, Shakyamuni Buddha was described as having an infinite life span, who should be recognized as Honbutsu (primordial Buddha) according to the creed of Hokekyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Hokke-kyo Sutra Chapter 16, The Life Span of the Tathagata, Shakyamuni Buddha was described as having an infinite life span, who should be recognized as Honbutsu according to the creed of Hokke-kyo.</e>
<cmt>the Lotus Sutra&apos;s Chapter Sixteen:→Hokke-kyo Sutra Chapter 16,(primordial Buddha)　削除Hokekyo→Hokke-kyo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>この本仏としての釈迦牟尼仏は久遠仏ないしは久遠実成本仏とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This Shakyamuni Buddha, recognized as Primordial Buddha, was also called Kuon-butsu or Kuon Jitstujo Honbutsu (Primordial Buddha with unmeasurable remote past.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Shakyamuni Buddha, recognized as the Primordial Buddha, was also called Kuon-butsu or Kuon Jitstujo Honbutsu (Primordial Buddha with unmeasurable remote past.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Shakyamuni Buddha, recognized as the Primordial Buddha, was also called Kuon-butsu or Kuon Jitstujo Honbutsu (Primordial Buddha with unmeasurable remote past.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>無量の諸仏はこの本仏の迹仏とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And, many other unaccountable number of Buddha were considered as Shakubutsu (temporary figures of Primordial Buddha.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And, many other unaccountable numbers of Buddha were considered as Shakubutsu (temporary figures of Primordial Buddha.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And, many other unaccountable numbers of Buddha were considered as Shakubutsu (temporary figures of Primordial Buddha.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>大乗仏教経典には十方の仏をはじめ、現在過去未来の無量の諸仏が登場するが、すべて本仏釈迦牟尼仏のコピーに過ぎず、単なる迹仏と言う論である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many Buddha appearing in the Sutra of Mahayana Buddhism, including various Buddha existing in all directions as well as in the past, present and future, were all Shakubutsu and no more than copies of Honbutsu (Primordial Buddha) or Shakyamuni Buddha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many Buddha appearing in the Sutra of Mahayana Buddhism, including various Buddha existing in all directions as well as in the past, present and future, were all Shakubutsu and no more than copies of Honbutsu (Primordial Buddha) or Shakyamuni Buddha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many Buddha appearing in the Sutra of Mahayana Buddhism, including various Buddha existing in all directions as well as in the past, present and future, were all Shakubutsu and no more than copies of Honbutsu or Shakyamuni Buddha.</e>
<cmt>(Primordial Buddha) 削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>この本仏は紀元前のユーラシア大陸のインドに生まれて肉体を持ち八十年生きたと言うゴータマ・シッダルタ（釈迦）とは論者により必ずしも同体ではないが、ユーラシア大陸に生まれたゴータマ・シッダルタ（釈迦）の精神とも言える存在である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This Honbutsu (Primordial Buddha) is not necessarily recognized as identical with Gotama Siddhattha (Shaka,) who was born in India of Eurasia continent before Christ and lived in flesh and blood for eighty years, but it may be considered as a spirit of Gotama Siddhattha himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Honbutsu (Primordial Buddha) is not necessarily recognized as identical with Gotama Siddhattha (Shaka,) who was born in India of Eurasia continent before Christ and lived in flesh and blood for eighty years, but it may be considered as the spirit of Gotama Siddhattha himself.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Honbutsu is not necessarily recognized as identical with Gotama Siddhattha (Shaka), who was born in India of Eurasia continent before Christ and lived in flesh and blood for eighty years, but it may be considered as the spirit of Gotama Siddhattha himself.</e>
<cmt>(Primordial Buddha)　削除カンマを括弧の外へ移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>この論では、日蓮は仏弟子であり、本仏ではないとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this theory, Nichiren is not recognized as Honbutsu (Primordial Buddha) but just a disciple of the Buddha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this theory, Nichiren is not recognized as Honbutsu (Primordial Buddha), but just a disciple of Buddha.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this theory, Nichiren is not recognized as Honbutsu, but just a disciple of Buddha.</e>
<cmt>(Primordial Buddha)　削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="33">
<j>なお涅槃経では、法華経の久遠実成を引継ぎつつ、それを更に発展昇華し、如来は入滅後においてもその仏性は永遠に存在すると説いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nehan-gyo (the Nirvana Sutra,) has succeeded the idea of Kuon-jitsujo (Buddha had attained Enlightenment in the eternal past) from Hokekyo (the Lotus Sutra,) and developed and sublimated it into an idea that the real nature of Budddha shall exist forever even after Nyorai (Buddha) entered nirvana.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nehan-gyo (the Nirvana Sutra,) has succeeded the idea of Kuon-jitsujo (Buddha had attained Enlightenment in the eternal past) from Hokekyo (the Lotus Sutra,) and developed and sublimated it into an idea that the real nature of Budddha shall exist forever even after Nyorai (Buddha) entered nirvana.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nehan-gyo (the Nirvana Sutra), has succeeded the idea of Kuon-jitsujo (Buddha had attained Enlightenment in the eternal past) from Hokke-kyo Sutra, and developed and sublimated it into an idea that the real nature of Budddha shall exist forever even after Nyorai (Buddha) entered nirvana.</e>
<cmt>カンマを括弧外へ移動法華経の表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>これを如来常住不変易、あるいは三宝一体常住不変易、また久遠常住という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This new idea was called &quot;Nyorai Joju Fuheni&quot;(Nyorai is always staying here without any change) or &quot;Sanbo Ittai Joju Fuheni&quot; (A set of three treasures of Buddhism is always staying here without any change) or &quot;Kuon Joju&quot; (Buddha is always staying here forever.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This new idea was called &quot;Nyorai Joju Fuheni&quot;(Nyorai is always staying here without any change) or &quot;Sanbo Ittai Joju Fuheni&quot; (A set of three treasures of Buddhism is always staying here without any change) or &quot;Kuon Joju&quot; (Buddha is always staying here forever.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This new idea was called &quot;Nyorai Joju Fuheni&quot; (Nyorai is always staying here without any change) or &quot;Sanbo Ittai Joju Fuheni&quot; (A set of three treasures of Buddhism is always staying here without any change) or &quot;Kuon Joju&quot; (Buddha is always staying here forever.)</e>
<cmt>Fuheni&quot;の後にスペース</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>また涅槃経では、末法思想は単なる段階的説法の方便説として最終的に否定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nehan-gyo has eventually denied mappo-shiso (an idea of the latter days of the world quoted in Dharma) as a theory of mere expediency for graded preaches.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nehan-gyo has eventually denied mappo-shiso (an idea of the latter days of the world quoted in Dharma) as a theory of mere expediency for graded preachings.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nehan-gyo has eventually denied mappo-shiso as a theory of mere expediency for graded preachings.</e>
<cmt>末法思想の説明削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>そして、「未来の世に、如来は入滅して既にこの世にいないと説く悪比丘が現れるために、この涅槃経を説く」と随所に説いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And, everywhere in its sutra, Nehan-gyo preached that it was necessary because wicked Buddhist priests may appear in the future to preach that Nyorai (Buddha) is no more existing after his death.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And, everywhere in its sutra, Nehan-gyo preached that it was necessary because wicked Buddhist priests may appear in the future to preach that Nyorai (Buddha) is no longer existing after his death.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And, everywhere in its sutra, Nehan-gyo preached that it was necessary because wicked Buddhist priests may appear in the future to preach that Nyorai (Buddha) is no longer existing after his death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 BitBucket(id:30999), Vapour(id:36031), Tetralemma(id:11903), Boca samba(id:137526), R28Bot(id:177951), ウィキ豊(id:82961), 大石寺信徒(id:59000), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>