<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>追説追泯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsuisetsu Tsuimin (the Nirvana Sutra Viewed as a Re-exposition of the Lotus Sutra)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsuisetsu Tsuimin (the Nirvana Sutra Viewed as a Re-exposition of the Lotus Sutra)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuisetsu Tsuimin</e>
<cmt>タイトルであり、次行に説明があるため、補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>追説追泯（ついせつついみん）とは、仏教において、天台宗や日蓮宗などの法華経一乗の立場から、『大般涅槃経』を指した語をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The expression &quot;tsuisetsu tsuimin&quot; (literally meaning &quot;re-exposition and re-effacement&quot;) is a Japanese Buddhist term that refers to an interpretation given to the Nirvana Sutra from the perspective (represented by the Tendai sect and Nichiren sect of Buddhism) that regards the Lotus Sutra as the fundamental sutra that brings salvation to the whole world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The expression &quot;tsuisetsu tsuimin&quot; (literally meaning &quot;re-exposition and re-effacement&quot;) is a Japanese Buddhist term that refers to an interpretation given to the Nirvana Sutra from the perspective (represented by the Tendai sect and Nichiren sect of Buddhism) that regards the Lotus Sutra as the fundamental sutra that brings salvation to the whole world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The expression &quot;tsuisetsu tsuimin&quot; (literally meaning &quot;re-exposition and re-effacement&quot;) is a Japanese Buddhist term that refers to an interpretation given to &quot;the Nirvana Sutra&quot; from the perspective (represented by the Tendai sect and Nichiren sect of Buddhism) that regards the Lotus Sutra as the fundamental sutra that brings salvation to the whole world.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを補足し、用語説明個所には原文にはないクォーテーションを付けたままにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>意味は、一度終った説法をさらに立ち戻って説いて、またさらに融泯（ゆうみん）すること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term literally means &quot;to explain teachings once again&quot; and &quot;to eliminate differences in views.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term literally means &quot;to explain teachings once again&quot; and &quot;to eliminate differences in views.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term literally means to explain teachings once again and to eliminate differences in views.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>天台大師智顗が判じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This interpretation of the Nirvana Sutra was originated by Chigi, a high priest of the Tendai School of Buddhism who lived during the 6th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This interpretation of the Nirvana Sutra was originated by Chigi, a high priest of the Tendai School of Buddhism who lived during the 6th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This interpretation of the Nirvana Sutra was originated by Chigi, a high priest of the Tendai School of Buddhism who lived during the sixth century.</e>
<cmt>スペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>「追説」とは、『法華経』の会座にいなかった（漏れて覚れなかった）人たちのために、華厳・阿含・方等・般若の小大乗の方便の教えを、『法華経』の意義を含みつつも、さらにもう一度方便の教えを説くことをいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This view interprets the Nirvana Sutra as a tsuisetsu, or a re-exposition of the Lotus Sutra sermons, which Buddha gave to people who failed to attend these sermons (or failed to understand their meaning) based on his Lotus Sutra sermons along with his other previous sermons on temporary truths contained in various Hinayana and Mahayana Buddhist sutras.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This view interprets the Nirvana Sutra as a tsuisetsu, or a re-exposition of the Lotus Sutra sermons, which Buddha gave to people who failed to attend these sermons (or failed to understand their meaning) based upon his Lotus Sutra sermons along with his other previous sermons on temporary truths contained in various Hinayana and Mahayana Buddhist sutras.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This view interprets the Nirvana Sutra as &apos;tsuisetsu&apos; (a re-exposition of the Lotus Sutra sermons), which Buddha gave to people who failed to attend these sermons (or failed to understand their meaning) based upon his Lotus Sutra sermons along with his other previous sermons on temporary truths contained in various Hinayana and Mahayana Buddhist sutras, such as Kegon (Flower Garland), Agon (Agama), Hodo (Expansion) and Hannya (Wisdom).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>「追泯」とは、『涅槃経』は『法華経』を説いた後なので、ただ方便教を説いただけではなく、『法華経』の意義をもって真実の仏性常住を説いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The view also interprets Buddha&apos;s sermons in the Nirvana Sutra, which were preached after his Lotus Sutra sermons, as not simply representing his teachings on temporary truths, but his teachings on eternal truths, which were taught based on his Lotus Sutra sermons in order to eliminate (&quot;tsuimin&quot;) differences.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The view also interprets Buddha&apos;s sermons in the Nirvana Sutra, which were preached after his Lotus Sutra sermons, as not simply representing his teachings on temporary truths, but his teachings on eternal truths, which were taught based on his Lotus Sutra sermons in order to eliminate (&quot;tsuimin&quot;) differences.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The view also interprets Buddha&apos;s sermons in &quot;the Nirvana Sutra,&quot; which were preached after his &quot;Lotus Sutra&quot; sermons, as not simply representing his teachings on temporary truths, but his teachings on eternal truths, which were taught based on his &quot;Lotus Sutra&quot; sermons in order to eliminate differences (&apos;tsuimin&apos;).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>これは追って説いたものを、また追ってその大小乗の教えや方便と真実という差別を泯（ほろぼ）すことをいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, according to this interpretation, the Buddha&apos;s teachings in the Nirvana Sutra were taught to eliminate the distinction between different views about his teachings and the distinction between temporary truths and eternal truths.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, according to this interpretation, the Buddha&apos;s teachings in the Nirvana Sutra were taught to eliminate the distinction between different views about his teachings and the distinction between temporary and eternal truths.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, according to this interpretation, it refers that the Buddha&apos;s teachings in the Nirvana Sutra were taught to eliminate the distinction between different views about his teachings and the distinction between temporary and eternal truths.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>法華一乗の涅槃経解釈</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Interpretation of the Nirvana Sutra from the perspective that regards the Lotus sutra as the most important sutra that brings salvation to the whole world</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Interpretation of the Nirvana Sutra from the perspective that regards the Lotus sutra as the most important sutra that brings salvation to the whole world</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Interpretation of the Nirvana Sutra from the perspective that regards the Lotus sutra as the most important sutra that brings salvation to the whole world</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>天台宗における教学では、釈迦一代の教説（経典）を、「蔵・通・別・円」と「化法の四教」に分ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tendai School of Buddhism groups teachings (sutras) given by Buddha during his lifetime into four categories (named &quot;zo,&quot; &quot;tsu,&quot; &quot;betsu&quot; and &quot;en&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tendai School of Buddhism groups teachings (sutras) given by Buddha during his lifetime into four categories (named &quot;zo,&quot; &quot;tsu,&quot; &quot;betsu&quot; and &quot;en&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tendai sect of Buddhism groups teachings given by Buddha during his lifetime into &apos;Keho-no-shikyo&apos; (Shakyamuni&apos;s four kinds of teaching of the content of the Truth accommodated to the capacity of his disciples) named &apos;zo, tsu, betsu, and en&apos; (Tripitaka, common, distinct, and perfect).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>蔵・通・別の前三教は、すでに『法華経』までの経典で説いた、そして『法華経』で円教を開会（かいえ）し説き終ったとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the Tendai School, Buddha had completed his teachings in the first three of these categories before his Lotus Sutra sermons, in which he explained the ultimate truth that he had finally grasped (the &quot;en&quot; (perfect truth) teachings).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the Tendai School, Buddha had completed his teachings in the first three of these categories before his Lotus Sutra sermons, in which he explained the ultimate truth that he had finally grasped (the &quot;en&quot; or perfect truth teachings).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddha had completed his teachings in the first three of these categories, zo, tsu and to, before his &quot;Lotus Sutra&quot; sermons, in which he explained the ultimate truth that he had finally grasped the teaching of en.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせ補足し、前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>しかし、なお機根の熟していない（あるいは低い）衆生の為に、さらにこれらの四教を『涅槃経』で説いたとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And in sermons contained in the Nirvana Sutra, Buddha explained the four categories of teachings that he had already preached, once again for the masses who were not yet ready (or not enlightened enough) to attain religious salvation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And in sermons contained in the Nirvana Sutra, Buddha explained the four categories of teachings that he had already preached, once again for the masses who were not yet ready (or not enlightened enough) to attain religious salvation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And in sermons contained in &quot;the Nirvana Sutra,&quot; Buddha explained the four categories of teachings that he had already preached, once again for the masses who were not yet ready (or not enlightened enough) to attain religious salvation.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>したがって『涅槃経』は『法華経』で既に述べた教説を機根の低い衆生に重ねて説いただけにすぎない、とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to this interpretation, the Nirvana Sutra is no more than an another version of Buddha&apos;s previous teachings revealed in his Lotus Sutra sermons, made particularly for the unenlightened masses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to this interpretation, the Nirvana Sutra is no more than another version of Buddha&apos;s previous teachings revealed in his Lotus Sutra sermons, made particularly for the unenlightened masses.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to this interpretation, &quot;the Nirvana Sutra&quot; is no more than another version of Buddha&apos;s previous teachings revealed in &quot;the Lotus Sutra&quot; sermons, made particularly for the unenlightened masses.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>また、『法華文句』には、次の通りある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hokke Mongu,&quot; a commentary of the Lotus Sutra written by Chigi in the 6th century, states:</e>
<cmt>法華文句[Hokke Mongu] http://kotobank.jp/word/法華文句　を参照しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hokke Mongu,&quot; a commentary of the Lotus Sutra written by Chigi in the 6th century, states:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, &quot;Hokke Mongu&quot; (Words and Phrases of the Lotus Sutra) states as follows.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。ルールに従い分割し直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>然るに本門の得道は衆経に数倍せり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The level of truths revealed in the Lotus Sutra far exceeds the level of other sutras.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The level of truths revealed in the Lotus Sutra far exceeds the level of other sutras.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The level of truths revealed in the Lotus Sutra far exceeds the level of other sutras.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>但だ数の多きのみにあらず。又、薫修して日久し。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Lotus Sutra contains many teachings that have been practiced over many years.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Lotus Sutra contains many teachings that have been practiced over many years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Lotus Sutra contains many teachings that have been practiced over many years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>元本より迹を垂るる、処処に開引し中間に相ひ値て数数成熟し、今世には五味に節節に調伏し、収羅結撮して法華に帰会す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buddha&apos;s entire thought, which gradually grew from its origin and was preached to the world on various occasions in various different ways, is revealed in this sutra in the most comprehensive form.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（日本語の原文の意味があまりよく理解できないまま一応英文にしてあります）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buddha&apos;s entire thought, which gradually grew from its origin and was preached to the world on various occasions in various different ways, is revealed in this sutra in the most comprehensive form.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddha&apos;s entire thought, which gradually grew from its origin and was preached to the world on various occasions in various different ways, is revealed in this sutra in the most comprehensive form.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>譬へば田家の春生じ夏長じ、耕種し耘治し、秋収め冬蔵て一時に穫刈するが如し。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This sutra presents Buddha&apos;s entire thought, as if a farmer would plant crops in spring, cultivate in summer to harvest them in fall for winter storage.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This sutra presents Buddha&apos;s entire thought, as if a farmer would plant crops in spring, cultivate in summer to harvest them in fall for winter storage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This sutra presents Buddha&apos;s entire thought, as if a farmer would plant crops in spring, cultivate in summer to harvest them in fall for winter storage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>法華より已後、得道有るは、捃拾の如くならんのみ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buddha&apos;s teachings preached after his Lotus Sutra sermons are just like gleanings collected after harvest.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buddha&apos;s teachings preached after his Lotus Sutra sermons are just like gleanings collected after a harvest.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddha&apos;s teachings preached after his Lotus Sutra sermons are just like gleanings collected after a harvest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>– 『法華文句』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(From &quot;Hokke Mongu&quot;)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(From the &quot;Hokke Mongu&quot;)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(From the &quot;Hokke Mongu&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="18">
<j>このように、『涅槃経』にある「秋収冬蔵」の経文を引き合いに出し、『涅槃経』の円常（円満なる常住の教説）を『法華経』に摂した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, paraphrasing a paragraph about &quot;harvesting in fall for winter storage&quot; discovered in the Nirvana Sutra, Chigi maintains that the Buddhist truths (perfect, eternal truths) revealed in the Nirvana Sutra have their origin in the Lotus Sutra.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, paraphrasing a paragraph about &quot;harvesting in fall for winter storage&quot; discovered in the Nirvana Sutra, Chigi maintains that the Buddhist truths (perfect, eternal truths) revealed in the Nirvana Sutra have their origin in the Lotus Sutra.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As stated above, paraphrasing a paragraph about &apos;harvesting in fall for winter storage&apos; discovered in &quot;the Nirvana Sutra,&quot; he maintained that the Buddhist truths (perfect, eternal truths) revealed in &quot;the Nirvana Sutra&quot; have their origin in &quot;the Lotus Sutra.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。ルールに従い分割し直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="19">
<j>涅槃宗は当初これらの智顗説に反論を呈したが、智顗の聡明なる智慧と実践力のもとに涅槃宗は次第に反論する機会を失い、天台宗に併合されることになったといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although supporters of the Nirvana Sutra initially objected to Chigi&apos;s interpretation, they were overpowered by his wisdom and energy and lost their power, finally merging into the Tendai School of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although supporters of the Nirvana Sutra initially objected to Chigi&apos;s interpretation, they were overpowered by his wisdom and energy and lost their power, finally merging into the Tendai School of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Nehan Sect initially objected to these Chigi&apos;s interpretation, they were overpowered by his wisdom and energy and lost their power, finally merging into the Tendai sect of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="20">
<j>これは、日蓮も『報恩抄』において、次のように述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Hoonsho,&quot; Nichiren also writes as follows:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Hoonsho,&quot; Nichiren also writes as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Hoonsho&quot; (On Repaying Debts of Gratitude), Nichiren also writes as follows:</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>また法華経に対する時は、是の経の出世は乃至法華の中の八千の声聞に記別を授くることを得て大菓実を成ずるが如し。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nirvana Sutra is believed to have owed its success to the Buddha&apos;s teachings revealed in the Lotus Sutra, which brought salvation to eight thousand disciples of his.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nirvana Sutra is believed to have owed its success to the Buddha&apos;s teachings revealed in the Lotus Sutra, which brought salvation to eight thousand disciples of his.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, when facing the Lotus Sutra, this sutra is believed to have owed its success to the Buddha&apos;s teachings revealed in the Lotus Sutra, which brought salvation to 8000 disciples of his.</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>秋収冬蔵して更に所作無きが如し等と云云。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was thus unable to add anything to what had already been harvested in fall for winter storage, as the author of the sutra states.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was thus unable to add anything to what had already been harvested in fall for winter storage, as the author of the sutra states.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was thus unable to add anything to what had already been harvested in fall for winter storage, as the author of the sutra states.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>我れと涅槃経は法華経には劣るととける経文なり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the Nirvana Sutra is inferior in value to the Lotus Sutra.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the Nirvana Sutra is inferior in value to the Lotus Sutra.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the sutra is understood the Nirvana Sutra and I are inferior in value to the Lotus Sutra.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>かう経文は分明なれども、南北の大智の諸人の迷うて有りし経文なれば、末代の学者能く能く眼をとどむべし</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since there have been disputes among scholars around the world over the value of the Nirvana Sutra, we need to examine it closely.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since there have been disputes among scholars around the world over the value of the Nirvana Sutra, we need to examine it closely.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since there have been disputes among scholars around the world over the value of the Nirvana Sutra, the scholars for generations need to examine it closely.</e>
<cmt>一部補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>– 日蓮『報恩抄』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Nichiren, &quot;Hoonsho&quot;)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Nichiren, &quot;Hoonsho&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Nichiren, &quot;Hoonsho&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>『涅槃経』優位における解釈</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Interpretations that emphasize the importance of the Nirvana Sutra</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Interpretations that emphasize the importance of the Nirvana Sutra</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Interpretations that emphasize the importance of the &quot;Nirvana Sutra&quot;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>上記の解釈に対し、『涅槃経』優位における解釈では、「秋収冬蔵」の典拠はその通りであるが、恣意的に前の文脈を省略しており、そのためにまったく逆の解釈がなされている、とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those who support interpretations that place greater emphasis on the independent value of the Nirvana Sutra argue that the paragraph about &quot;harvesting in fall for winter storage&quot; is correctly cited from the Nirvana Sutra but that Chigi&apos;s interpretation deliberately omits the statement preceding the paragraph, thereby giving rise to a serious misunderstanding.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those who support interpretations that place greater emphasis on the independent value of the Nirvana Sutra argue that the paragraph about &quot;harvesting in fall for winter storage&quot; is correctly cited from the Nirvana Sutra but that Chigi&apos;s interpretation deliberately omits the statement preceding the paragraph, thereby giving rise to a serious misunderstanding.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those who support interpretations that place greater emphasis on the independent value of &quot;the Nirvana Sutra&quot; argue that the paragraph about &apos;harvesting in fall for winter storage&apos; is correctly cited from the Nirvana Sutra but that his interpretation deliberately omits the statement preceding the paragraph, thereby giving rise to a serious misunderstanding.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="27">
<j>『涅槃経』巻9如来性品の経文の前文を省略せず述べると、次のとおりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The relevant paragraph in Volume 9 (on Buddha&apos;s teachings) of the Nirvana Sutra is the following:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The relevant paragraph in Volume 9 (on Buddha&apos;s teachings) of the Nirvana Sutra is the following:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The whole preamble of the relevant chapter Nyoraisho-bon (literally, chapter of Nyorai&apos;s nature), the volume nine of &quot;the Nirvana Sutra&quot; is the following:</e>
<cmt>スペルアウトし、クォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>譬(たと)えば闇夜に諸の営作する所が一切、皆(みな)息(や)むも、もし未だ訖(おわ)らざる者は、要(かな)らず日月を待つが如し。大乗を学する者が契経[1]、一切の禅定を修すといえども、要らず大乗大涅槃日を待ち、如来秘密の教えを聞きて然(しか)して後、及[2]当に菩提業を造り正法に安住すべし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Just as those who stop all activities at night are bound to resume their work on the next day unless they have completed their tasks, those who learn Mahayana Buddhism will never be able to achieve nirvana and live in peace without learning the ultimate Buddhist truths revealed in the Nirvana Sutra, even if they have read all other sutras and studied all other Buddha&apos;s teachings.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Just as those who stop all activities at night are bound to resume their work on the next day unless they have completed their tasks, those who learn Mahayana Buddhism will never be able to achieve nirvana and live in peace without learning the ultimate Buddhist truths revealed in the Nirvana Sutra, even if they have read all other sutras and studied all other Buddha&apos;s teachings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Just as those who stop all activities at night are bound to resume their work on the next day unless they have completed their tasks, those who learn Mahayana Buddhism will never be able to achieve nirvana and live in peace without learning the ultimate Buddhist truths revealed in the Nirvana Sutra, even if they have read all other sutras and studied all other Buddha&apos;s teachings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>猶(なお)し天雨の一切諸種を潤益し増長し、果実を成就して悉(ことごと)く飢饉を除き、多く豊楽を受けるが如し。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nirvana Sutra will bring them eternal salvation, just as rain from heaven helps plants to grow and to bear fruit, thereby preventing famines and bringing great benefits to the world.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nirvana Sutra will bring them eternal salvation, just as rain from heaven helps plants to grow and bear fruit, thereby preventing famines and bringing great benefits to the world.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nirvana Sutra will bring them eternal salvation, just as rain from heaven helps plants to grow and bear fruit, thereby preventing famines and bringing great benefits to the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>如来秘蔵無量の法雨も亦復(またまた)是(かく)の如し。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eternal salvation brought by Buddha is just like rain falling from heaven.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eternal salvation brought by Buddha is just like rain falling from heaven.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eternal salvation brought by Buddha is just like rain falling from heaven.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>悉くよく八種の病を除滅す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buddha&apos;s teachings will thus cure various diseases.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buddha&apos;s teachings will thus cure various diseases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddha&apos;s teachings will thus cure eight various diseases.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>この経（涅槃経）の世に出づる、彼の果実の一切を利益し安楽にする所、多きが如し。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This sutra (Nirvana Sutra) will greatly benefit the public, just like fruits that benefit everyone and enables him to live in peace.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This sutra (Nirvana Sutra) will greatly benefit the public, just like fruit that benefits everyone and enables them to live in peace.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This sutra (Nirvana Sutra) will greatly benefit the public, just like fruit that benefits everyone and enables them to live in peace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>能(よ)く衆生をして仏性を見せしむ、法華の中に八千の声聞の記別を受くることを得て大果実を成ずる如く、秋収め冬蔵(おさ)めて更に所作無きが如し。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Just as the teachings revealed in the Lotus Sutra achieved great success by enabling eight thousand disciples of Buddha to achieve religious salvation, this sutra will teach Buddhist truths to the unenlightened masses, who will have nothing more to learn, just as farmers who have harvested crops in fall for winter storage have nothing more to do,</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Just as the teachings revealed in the Lotus Sutra achieved great success by enabling eight thousand disciples of Buddha achieve religious salvation, this sutra will teach Buddhist truths to the unenlightened masses, who will have nothing more to learn, just as farmers who have harvested crops in fall for winter storage have nothing more to do,</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Just as the teachings revealed in the Lotus Sutra achieved great success by enabling 8000 disciples of Buddha achieve religious salvation, this sutra will teach Buddhist truths to the unenlightened masses, who will have nothing more to learn, just as farmers who have harvested crops in fall for winter storage have nothing more to do,</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>– 『涅槃経』巻9 如来性品, 前文</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Nirvana Sutra, Preamble to Volume 9 on Buddha&apos;s teachings)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Nirvana Sutra, Preamble to Volume 9 on Buddha&apos;s teachings)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Preamble to Volume nine Nyoraisho-bon, &quot;Nirvana Sutra&quot;)</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="35">
<j>したがって、『涅槃経』優位説の立場では、この経文はあくまでも『涅槃経』の利益を説いたものであり、「秋収冬蔵」というのは、『法華経』で声聞衆が記別を受けて大果実を得たように、この『涅槃経』の教えを修学すれば、「更に所作なきが如し（あとは何もすることがないのと同じである）」と説いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those who regard the Nirvana Sutra as the fundamental sutra maintain that this paragraph in the sutra is explaining the benefits of the sutra and that the expression &quot;harvesting in fall for winter storage&quot; means that those who have learned the Nirvana Sutra will have nothing more to learn, just like Buddha&apos;s disciples who have received great benefits by learning from Buddha in the Lotus Sutra.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those who regard the Nirvana Sutra as fundamental maintain that this paragraph in the sutra is explaining the benefits of the sutra and that the expression &quot;harvesting in fall for winter storage&quot; means that those who have learned the Nirvana Sutra will have nothing more to learn, just like Buddha&apos;s disciples who have received great benefits by learning from Buddha in the Lotus Sutra.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those who regard &quot;the Nirvana Sutra&quot; as fundamental maintain that this paragraph in the sutra is explaining the benefits of the sutra and that the expression &apos;harvesting in fall for winter storage&apos; means that those who have learned &quot;the Nirvana Sutra&quot; will have &apos;nothing more to learn,&apos; just like Buddha&apos;s disciples who have received great benefits by learning from Buddha in the Lotus Sutra.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>したがって『涅槃経』を修学しなければやり残したものがある、というのが、解釈を加えない経文そのものの真の意味である、と反論している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on these grounds, supporters of the Nirvana Sutra argue that the original meaning of the paragraph in the sutra is that those who have not studied the sutra have something left to learn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on these grounds, supporters of the Nirvana Sutra argue that the original meaning of the paragraph in the sutra is that those who have not studied the sutra have something left to learn.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on these grounds, supporters of &quot;the Nirvana Sutra&quot; argue that the original meaning of the paragraph in the sutra is that those who have not studied the sutra have something left to learn.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="37">
<j>また、もし『法華経』が最高の教えならば、機根の低い衆生を『涅槃経』に譲らなければならなかったのか、一切の衆生を済度する教えを一乗や円教と呼ぶのなら、機根の高低など関係なくすべてを済度するのが本当ではないか、と指摘している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They also point out that if the Lotus Sutra was in fact the most fundamental sutra, it is difficult to understand why the unenlightened masses had to wait for the Nirvana Sutra for their religious salvation and that the teachings revealed in the Lotus Sutra, which is believed to provide everyone with the perfect vehicle for salvation, should have been able to save not only Buddha&apos;s disciples but the unenlightened masses as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They also point out that if the Lotus Sutra was in fact the most fundamental sutra, it is difficult to understand why the unenlightened masses had to wait for the Nirvana Sutra for their religious salvation and that the teachings revealed in the Lotus Sutra, which is believed to provide everyone with the perfect vehicle for salvation, should have been able to save not only Buddha&apos;s disciples but the unenlightened masses as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They also point out that if &quot;the Lotus Sutra&quot; was in fact the most fundamental sutra, it is difficult to understand why the unenlightened masses had to wait for &quot;the Nirvana Sutra&quot; for their religious salvation and that the teachings revealed in the Lotus Sutra, which is believed to provide everyone with the perfect vehicle for salvation, should have been able to save not only Buddha&apos;s disciples but the unenlightened masses as well.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="38">
<j>さらに、この秋収冬蔵の譬喩説は、同じ涅槃経でも南本と北本のみにしかない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the paragraph about harvesting in fall for winter storage appears only in the southern and northern editions of the Nirvana Sutra.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the paragraph about harvesting in fall for winter storage appears only in the southern and northern editions of the Nirvana Sutra.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the paragraph about harvesting in fall for winter storage appears only in the southern and northern editions of the Nirvana Sutra.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>法顕・六巻本には、次のようにある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following paragraph is found in the six-volume Nirvana Sutra translated by a Chinese Buddhist monk, Hokken:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following paragraph is found in the six-volume Nirvana Sutra translated by a Chinese Buddhist monk, Hokken:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following paragraph is found in the six-volume Nirvana Sutra translated by a Chinese Buddhist monk, Hokken:</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。ルールに従い分割し直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>復、次に善男子、譬えば夜闇に閻浮提の人、一切の家業（けごう）は皆悉く休廃（くはい）し、日光出で已（おわ）って、其の諸の人民、家事（けじ）を修めることを得るが如し。是の如く、衆生、諸の契経及び諸の三昧を聞いて、猶夜闇に此の大乗の般泥洹経の微密の教えを聞くが如し。猶日出でて諸の正法を見るが如し。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Just as ordinary people stop all their worldly activities at night and start their work only when the sun rises, the masses can learn the correct teachings in broad daylight only when they have learned the eternal truths revealed in this great Nirvana Sutra at night after studying various sutras and practicing meditation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Just as ordinary people stop all their worldly activities at night and start their work only when the sun rises, the masses can learn the correct teachings in broad daylight only when they have learned the eternal truths revealed in this great Nirvana Sutra at night after studying various sutras and practicing meditation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Just as ordinary people stop all their worldly activities at night and start their work only when the sun rises, the masses can learn the correct teachings in broad daylight only when they have learned the eternal truths revealed in this great Nirvana Sutra at night after studying various sutras and practicing meditation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>彼の田夫（でんぷ）の夏時の雨に遇うが如く、摩訶衍（大乗）経は無量の衆生を皆悉く受決（じゅけつ）して如来性を現ず。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mahayana sutras promised all people in the world religious salvation in the future, just as rain brings benefits to all farmers in summer.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mahayana sutras promised all people in the world religious salvation in the future, just as rain brings benefits to all farmers in summer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mahayana sutras promised all people in the world religious salvation in the future, just as rain brings benefits to all farmers in summer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>八千の声聞は法華経に於いて記別を受けることを得たり。唯、冬氷の一闡提を除く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Lotus Sutra enabled eight thousand disciples of Buddha to achieve religious salvation, except for non believers of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Lotus Sutra enabled eight thousand disciples of Buddha to achieve religious salvation, except for non believers of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Lotus Sutra enabled 8000 disciples of Buddha to achieve religious salvation, except for non believers of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>– 大般泥洹経（法顕本、六巻本）問菩薩品第十七</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Nirvana Sutra (translated by Hokken, 6 volumes), Buddha&apos;s teachings 17)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Nirvana Sutra (translated by Hokken, 6 volumes), Buddha&apos;s teachings 17)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The 17 of Tobosatsu-bon (literally, chapter of dialogue of Bosatsu), Daihatsu Naion-gyo (A Chinese version of the Mahayana Nirvana Sutra) (also known as Hokken-bon (version translated by Hokken) or Rokkan-bon (the six-volume Nirvana Sutra))</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="44">
<j>このように、法顕が翻訳した六巻本には、「法華経の中で八千の声聞が記別を得た」との記述はあるものの、曇無讖が翻訳した北本及び、六巻本と北本を校合訂正した南本には「大果実を収めて秋収め冬蔵めて更に所作なきが如し」との文言は見当たらない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, although the 6-volume Nirvana Sutra translated by Hokken states that &quot;The Lotus Sutra enabled eight thousand disciples of Buddha to achieve religious salvation,&quot; neither the northern edition (translated by Dharmaraksana) nor the southern edition (compiled by making corrections to the 6-volume edition and the northern edition) contains the statement that the Lotus Sutra taught &quot;Buddhist truths to the unenlightened masses, who will have nothing more to learn, just as farmers who have harvested crops in fall for winter storage have nothing more to do.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, although the 6-volume Nirvana Sutra translated by Hokken states that &quot;The Lotus Sutra enabled eight thousand disciples of Buddha to achieve religious salvation,&quot; neither the northern edition (translated by Dharmaraksana) nor the southern edition (compiled by making corrections to the 6-volume edition and the northern edition) contains the statement that the Lotus Sutra taught &quot;Buddhist truths to the unenlightened masses, who will have nothing more to learn, just as farmers who have harvested crops in fall for winter storage have nothing more to do.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As stated above, although the six-volume Nirvana Sutra translated by Hokken states that &apos;The Lotus Sutra enabled 8000 disciples of Buddha to achieve religious salvation,&apos; neither the northern edition (translated by Dharmaraksana) nor the southern edition (compiled by making corrections to the six-volume edition and the northern edition) contains the statement that the Lotus Sutra taught &apos;Buddhist truths to the unenlightened masses, who will have nothing more to learn, just as farmers who have harvested crops in fall for winter storage have nothing more to do.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。ルールに従い分割し直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>したがって、六巻本においてもこの箇所は涅槃経の優位性を主張するための記述で、法華経での声聞記別は単にそのための引証でしかなかったことが伺える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, the paragraph found in the 6-volume Nirvana Sutra places emphasis on the value of the Nirvana Sutra itself and mentions the success of the Lotus Sutra among Buddha&apos;s disciples only to explain why the Nirvana Sutra is so important.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, the paragraph found in the 6-volume Nirvana Sutra places emphasis on the value of the Nirvana Sutra itself and mentions the success of the Lotus Sutra among Buddha&apos;s disciples only to explain why the Nirvana Sutra is so important.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, the paragraph found in the 6-volume Nirvana Sutra places emphasis on the value of the Nirvana Sutra itself and mentions the success of the Lotus Sutra among Buddha&apos;s disciples only to explain why the Nirvana Sutra is so important.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="46">
<j>また、智顗が述べたように、『涅槃経』は釈尊が成道してから行ってきた教説の要点を再び説いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Chigi pointed out, the Nirvana Sutra is a re-exposition of the teachings that Buddha preached after he achieved nirvana.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Chigi pointed out, the Nirvana Sutra is a re-exposition of the teachings that Buddha preached after he achieved nirvana.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Chigi pointed out, &quot;the Nirvana Sutra&quot; is a re-exposition of the teachings that Buddha preached after he achieved nirvana.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>しかしこれは単に同じ事を再説したのではなく、涅槃原理というさらに高い観点から四諦や空性などを再び説いたものであり、『法華経』も行程の中に含まれる、としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he did not simply repeat the same teachings in the Nirvana Sutra, but explained his previous teachings, including not only the four noble truths that lead to nirvana and the notion of emptiness but also the Lotus Sutra itself, from a higher perspective based on the nirvana principle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he did not simply repeat the same teachings in the Nirvana Sutra, but explained his previous teachings, including not only the four noble truths that lead to nirvana and the notion of emptiness but also the Lotus Sutra itself, from a higher perspective based on the nirvana principle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he did not simply repeat the same teachings in the Nirvana Sutra, but explained his previous teachings, including not only the four noble truths that lead to nirvana and the notion of emptiness but also &quot;the Lotus Sutra&quot; itself, from a higher perspective based on the nirvana principle.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Dignaaga(id:91287), Kurz(id:1601), 現代の魔女(id:136024), Boca samba(id:137526), Kaboyose-DSD(id:123658), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>