<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>菩提僊那</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bodai Senna (Bodhisena)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bodai Senna (Bodhisena)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bodai Senna (Bodhisena)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>菩提僊那（ぼだいせんな、ボーディセーナ、704年 - 760年）は、奈良時代の渡来僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bodai Senna (Bodhisena, 704-760) was a foreign priest in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bodai Senna (Bodhisena, 704-760) was a priest from a foreign country in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bodai Senna (Bodhisena, 704-760) was a priest from a foreign country in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>婆羅門僧正・菩提僧正とも称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also referred to as Baramon Sojo or Bodai Sojo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He has been also called Baramon Sojo or Bodai Sojo.</e>
<cmt>用語。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He has been also called Baramon Sojo or Bodai Sojo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>弟子の修栄が撰した『南天竺婆羅門僧正碑』及び『東大寺要録』中の「大安寺菩提伝来記」に伝記が残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The biography of his life remains on two historical materials, &quot;NanTenjiku Baramon-sojo Hi (stone monument bearing South Indian high Buddhist priest Barahman) compiled by Shuei, one of his disciples, and &apos;Daianji bosatsu denraiki (Transmission of bodhi (enlightenment) at Daian-ji Temple) of &quot;Todaiji Yoroku (The Digest Record of Todai-ji Temple).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His biography was recorded in &quot;NanTenjiku Baramon Sojo Hi&quot; (Stone Monument for Baramon Sojo [high Buddhist priest Barahman] from India) compiled by his disciple Shuei, and in &apos;Daianji Bodai Denraiki&apos; (Introduction of bodhi at Daian-ji Temple) of &quot;Todaiji Yoroku&quot; (the Digest Record of Todai-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>用語。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His biography was recorded in &quot;NanTenjiku Baramon Sojo Hi&quot; (Stone Monument for Baramon Sojo [high Buddhist priest Barahman] from India) compiled by his disciple Shuei, and in &apos;Daianji Bodai Denraiki&apos; (Introduction of bodhi at Daian-ji Temple) of &quot;Todaiji Yoroku&quot; (the Digest Record of Todai-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>菩提僊那は、インドのバラモン階級に生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bodai Senna was born a Brahmin in India.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bodai Senna was born a Brahmin in India.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bodai Senna was born a Brahmin in India.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>姓はバーラードヴァージャ（婆羅門遅）と伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His family name is said to be バーラードヴァージャ.</e>
<cmt>「バーラードヴァージャ」のスペルが不明でした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His family name has been said Baaraadovaja.</e>
<cmt>読み不明。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His family name has been said Baaraadovaja.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>彼は青年期に（唐 (王朝)）へローカタクシャや安世高の偉業を追って渡った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During his adolescence, he went to Tang Dynasty China, aspiring to great achievement of ローカタクシャ and An Shi-go.</e>
<cmt>「ローカタクシャ」のスペルが不明でした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During his adolescence, he went to the Tang Dynasty China following the great achievement of Rookataksya and An Shigao.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During his adolescence, he went to the Tang Dynasty China following the great achievement of Rookataksya and An Shigao.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>五台山 (中国)の文殊に会うためという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(One theory says that his worship to Manjusri brought him to Mt. Wutai Shan (China) (one of the four holy Buddhist Mountains, the dwelling place of Manjusri Bodhisattva)).</e>
<cmt>五台山→one of the four holy Buddhist Mountains, the dwelling place of Manjusri Bodhisattvaを補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some scholar say that it was because he tried to meet Manjusri in Mt. Wutai (China) (one of the four holy Buddhist Mountains, the dwelling place of Manjusri Bodhisattva).</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some scholar say that it was because he tried to meet Manjusri in Mt. Wutai (China) (one of the four holy Buddhist Mountains, the dwelling place of Manjusri Bodhisattva).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>唐では長安の崇福寺を拠点に活動していたようで、唐滞在中に日本からの入唐僧理鏡や第十次遣唐使副使中臣名代らの要請により、チャンパ王国出身の僧仏哲・唐の僧道璿とともに736年（天平8年）に来日した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is said to have preached, staying at Sofuku-ji Temple in Changan in Tang, during which stay he was requested to visit Japan by Rikyo, nyuto-priest (a priest who went to China from Japan for studying), and NAKATOMI no Nashiro, who was the tenth vice Kento-shi (a Japanese envoy to Tang Dynasty China), so that he came to Japan in 736, being accompanied by a priest from Kingdom of Champa, named Buttetsu, and Dosen from Tang.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He preached mainly at Chongfu-si Temple of Changan in Tang, and during staying in China he was requested to visit Japan by a learned priest from Japan Rikyo and an assistant envoy of the tenth Kento-shi (a Japanese envoy to the Tang Dynasty China) NAKATOMI no Nashiro, then he came to Japan in 736 with a priest from Kingdom of Champa Buttetsu and a priest from Tang Dosen (Daoxuan).</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He preached mainly at Chongfu-si Temple of Changan in Tang, and during staying in China he was requested to visit Japan by a learned priest from Japan Rikyo and an assistant envoy of the tenth Kento-shi (a Japanese envoy to the Tang Dynasty China) NAKATOMI no Nashiro, then he came to Japan in 736 with a priest from Kingdom of Champa Buttetsu and a priest from Tang Dosen (Daoxuan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>3人の僧ははじめ九州の大宰府に赴き、行基に迎えられて平城京に入り、その中の大安寺に住し、時服を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The three priests first visited Dazai-fu (local government office) in Kyushu, met Gyoki, entered Heijokyo (the capital of Japan in the Nara period), resided at Daian-ji Temple and was given jifuku (allocations of cloth, meaning economical support by the Imperial Court).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The three priests first visited Dazai-fu (local government office) in Kyushu, met Gyoki, entered Heijokyo (the capital of Japan in the Nara period), resided at Daian-ji Temple and was given jifuku (allocations of cloth, meaning economical support by the Imperial Court).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The three priests first visited Dazai-fu (local government office) in Kyushu, met Gyoki, entered Heijokyo (the capital of Japan in the Nara period), resided at Daian-ji Temple and was given jifuku (allocations of cloth, meaning economical support by the Imperial Court).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>僊那は、華厳経の諷誦にすぐれ、呪術にも通じていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senna was good at reciting the text of Kegon-kyo (Avatamsaka Sutra) and practicing an occult art.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senna was good at reciting the text of Kegon-kyo (Avatamsaka Sutra) and practicing an occult art.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senna was good at reciting the text of Kegon-kyo (Avatamsaka Sutra) and practicing an occult art.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>インド呪術は、僊那から日本僧の弟子へ伝授された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Indian occult art was transmitted from Senna to Japanese priests, his disciples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Indian occult art was taught from Senna to his Japanese disciples.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Indian occult art was taught from Senna to his Japanese disciples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>751年（天平勝宝3年）僧正に任じられ、翌752年（天平勝宝4年）4月9日には東大寺盧舎那仏像の開眼供養の導師をつとめている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 751, he was appointed Sojo (high-ranking Buddhist priest), and the following year on April 9, 752, served as a doshi (an officiating priest to consecrate a newly made Buddhist statue or image by inserting the eyes) of the ceremony in which Rushana Statue in Todai-ji Temple was given eyes, a ritual believed to invest the figure with sacred spirit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 751, he was appointed to Sojo (high-ranking Buddhist priest), and on April 9, 752, he served as a doshi (priest in charge of ceremonies) for Kaigan-kuyo (consecrating a newly made Buddhist statue or image by inserting the eyes) of the statue of Rushana-butsu in Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 751, he was appointed to Sojo (high-ranking Buddhist priest), and on April 9, 752, he served as a doshi (priest in charge of ceremonies) for Kaigan-kuyo (consecrating a newly made Buddhist statue or image by inserting the eyes) of the statue of Rushana-butsu in Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>760年（天平宝字4年）2月25日、僊那は大安寺にて西方を向いて合掌したまま死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 25, 760, he passed away facing westwards with folded hands at Daian-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 25, 760, he died facing the west and joining his palms together in Daian-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 25, 760, he died facing the west and joining his palms together in Daian-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>翌3月2日、登美山右僕射林に葬られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The next month, on March 2, he was buried in Ubokusanrin in Mt. Tomi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The next month, on March 2, he was buried in Ubokusanrin in Mt. Tomi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The next month, on March 2, he was buried in Ubokusanrin in Mt. Tomi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Shimoxx(id:9332), Carl Daniels(id:20253), Lobbyonce(id:195963), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), Nighthawks(id:36125), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>