<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>百済観音</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kudara Kannon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kudara Kannon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kudara Kannon (wooden statue of Kannon Bosatsu [Buddhist Goddess of Mercy])</e>
<cmt>説明追記</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>百済観音（くだらかんのん）は、奈良県斑鳩町の法隆寺が所蔵する飛鳥時代（7世紀中期 - 後半）作の木造観音菩薩像である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kudara Kannon is a wooden statue of Kannon Bosatsu (Buddhist Goddess of Mercy) which was made during the Asuka period (from the mid until the late seventh century) and is owned by Horyu-ji Temple in Ikaruga-cho, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kudara Kannon is a wooden statue of Kannon Bosatsu (Buddhist Goddess of Mercy) which was made during the Asuka period (from the mid until the late seventh century) and is owned by Horyu-ji Temple in Ikaruga-cho, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kudara Kannon is a wooden statue of Kannon Bosatsu (Buddhist Goddess of Mercy) which was made during the Asuka period (from the mid until the late seventh century) and is owned by Horyu-ji Temple in Ikaruga-cho, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日本の国宝に指定されている（指定名称は「木造観音菩薩立像（百済観音）1躯」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was designated as a national treasure of Japan (designated under the name &quot;One Statue of Mokuzo Kannon Bosatsu Ryu-zo&quot; (one wooden standing statue of Kannon Bosatsu) (Kudara Kannon)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was designated a national treasure of Japan (designated under the name &quot;One Statue of Mokuzo Kannon Bosatsu Ryu-zo&quot; (one wooden standing statue of Kannon Bosatsu) (Kudara Kannon)).</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was designated a national treasure of Japan (designated under the name &apos;One Statue of Mokuzo Kannon Bosatsu Ryu-zo&apos; [one wooden standing statue of Kannon Bosatsu] [Kudara Kannon]).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;括弧内の括弧を[]に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>日本における木造仏像彫刻の古例として貴重であるとともに、大正時代以降、和辻哲郎の『古寺巡礼』、亀井勝一郎の『大和古寺風物誌』などの書物で紹介され著名になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is valued as an old example of wooden Buddhist sculptures in Japan; after the Taisho period, it was introduced in writings such as &quot;Koji Junrei&quot; (A pilgrimage to ancient temples) by Tetsuro WATSUJI and &quot;Yamato Koji Fubutsushi&quot; (Pilgrimage to the ancient temples of the Yamato) by Katsuichiro KAMEI and became well-known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is valued as an old example of wooden Buddhist sculptures in Japan; after the Taisho period, it was introduced in writings such as &quot;Koji Junrei&quot; (A pilgrimage to ancient temples) by Tetsuro WATSUJI and &quot;Yamato Koji Fubutsushi&quot; (Pilgrimage to the ancient temples of the Yamato) by Katsuichiro KAMEI and became well-known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is valued as an old example of wooden Buddhist sculptures in Japan; after the Taisho period, it was introduced in writings such as &quot;Koji Junrei&quot; (A pilgrimage to ancient temples) by Tetsuro WATSUJI and &quot;Yamato Koji Fubutsushi&quot; (Pilgrimage to the ancient temples of Yamato) by Katsuichiro KAMEI and became well-known.</e>
<cmt>the Yamato→Yamato</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>像の概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Overview of the statue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Overview of the statue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Overview of the statue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>像高</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Height</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Height</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Height</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>210.9cm（『特別展百済観音』図録等による。「209.4cm」とする資料もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">210.9 cm (according to the pictorial records of &quot;Special Exhibition of Kudara Kannon&quot;, etc. and &quot;209.4 cm&quot; according to another material).</e>
<cmt>後列の【「209.4cm」とする資料もある）。】をこちらに移し、後列を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">210.9 cm (according to the pictorial records of &quot;Special Exhibition of Kudara Kannon&quot;, etc. and &quot;209.4 cm&quot; according to another material).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">210.9 cm (according to the pictorial records of &quot;Special Exhibition of Kudara Kannon&quot;, etc. and &apos;209.4 cm&apos; according to another material.)</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;ピリオドを括弧内へ移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>制作年代・作者</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Date of making and the artist</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Date of creation and the artist</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Date of creation and the artist</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>飛鳥時代、7世紀半ば～後半とするのが通説。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a popular theory, it was made in the Asuka period, from the middle until the late seventh century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a popular theory, it was made in the Asuka period, from the middle until the late seventh century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a popular theory, it was made in the Asuka period, from the middle until the late seventh century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>作者は不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The artist is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The artist is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The artist is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>像容</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Statue form</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Statue form</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Statue form</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>平面五角形の反花座（かえりばなざ。ハスの花を伏せたような形の台座）に接してに直立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Standing upright on a plane, pentagon-shaped kaeribanaza (inverted flower seat, a pedestal shaped like a turned lotus flower).</e>
<cmt>後列の【ハスの花を伏せたような形の台座）に接してに直立する。】をこちらに移し後列を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Standing upright on a plane, pentagon-shaped kaeribanaza (inverted flower seat, a pedestal shaped like a turned lotus flower).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Standing upright on a plane, pentagon-shaped kaeribanaza (inverted flower seat, a pedestal shaped like a turned lotus flower).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>通常の仏像に比べて著しく痩身で頭部が小さく、8頭身に近い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is notably slim compared to usual Buddhist statues, with a small head, and almost an eight-head figure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is notably slim compared to usual Buddhist statues, with a small head, and almost an eight-head figure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is notably slim compared to usual Buddhist statues, with a small head, and almost an eight-head figure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>右腕は肘でほぼ直角に曲げ、前膊（下腕）を観者の方へ向けて水平に突き出し、掌を上へ向ける（持物（じぶつ）はない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The right arm is bent at the elbow almost squarely, with the lower arm thrust horizontally toward onlookers, and the palm turned upward (holding no jibutsu (the hand-held attributes of a Buddhist image)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The right arm is bent at the elbow almost squarely, with the lower arm thrust horizontally toward onlookers, and the palm turned upward (holding no jibutsu (the hand-held attributes of a Buddhist image)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The right arm is bent at the elbow almost squarely, with the lower arm thrust horizontally toward onlookers, and the palm turned upward (holding no jibutsu [the hand-held attributes of a Buddhist image]).</e>
<cmt>括弧内の括弧を[]に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>左手は垂下し、肘を前方に軽くに曲げて手の甲を観者の方へ向け、水瓶（すいびょう）を持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The left hand is drooping and bent slightly forward at the elbow in such a way that the back of the statue&apos;s hand faces the onlookers, holding a water jar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The left hand is drooping and bent slightly forward at the elbow in such a way that the back of the statue&apos;s hand faces the onlookers, holding a water jar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The left hand is drooping and bent slightly forward at the elbow in such a way that the back of the statue&apos;s hand faces the onlookers, holding a water jar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>下半身には裳（巻きスカート状の衣服）を着け、天衣（てんね。仏像や天人像が身につけている薄く細長い布のこと）をまとう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The lower body is covered with mo (a long pleated skirt) and draped over with hagoromo (feather-robe, a thin strip of cloth worn by Buddhist statues and statues of tennin (heavenly beings)).</e>
<cmt>後列の【仏像や天人像が身につけている薄く細長い布のこと）をまとう。】をこちらに移し、後列を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lower body is covered with mo (a long pleated skirt) and draped over with hagoromo (feather-robe, a thin strip of cloth worn by Buddhist statues and statues of tennin (heavenly beings)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lower body is covered with mo (a long pleated skirt) and draped over with tenne (feather-robe, a thin strip of cloth worn by Buddhist statues and statues of tennin [heavenly beings]).</e>
<cmt>「天衣」は「てんね」と原文でなっているため、hagoromo→tenne としました。括弧内の括弧を[]に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>天衣は大腿部正面でX字状に交差し、両腕にかかり、両体側に垂下している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tennin is crossed before the thighs, then hanging on both arms down both sides of the body.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tennin is crossed before the thighs, then hangs on both arms and down both sides of the body.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenne is crossed before the thighs, then hangs on both arms and down both sides of the body.</e>
<cmt>Tennin→Tenne</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>頭髪は髻（もとどり）を結い、両肩に長く垂れ下がっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hair of head is done up in the style of motodori (hair tied together), the long hair hanging down both shoulders.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hair of the head is done up in the style of motodori (hair tied together), the long hair hanging down both shoulders.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hair of the head is done up in the style of motodori (hair tied together), the long hair hanging down both shoulders.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>宝冠、首飾、臂釧（ひせん）、腕釧（わんせん）などの装身具を付け、これらは銅製透かし彫りの別製とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is adorned with a crown, necklace, upper arm bracelet, and bracelet, etc., all of which are especially made of copper by openwork carving.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is adorned with a crown, necklace, upper arm bracelet, and bracelet, etc., all of which are especially made of copper by openwork carving.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is adorned with a crown, necklace, upper arm bracelet, and bracelet, etc., all of which are especially made of copper by openwork carving.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>光背は宝珠形の頭光（ずこう）で、中央部に八葉蓮華を表し、その周囲には同心円状の文様帯があり、その外側の周縁部には火焔文様を表す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The halo is in the shape of a lotus flower, with hachiyorenge (a kind of lotus flower) shown in the center and surrounded by a pattern of concentric circles, and the outer margins representing a flame pattern.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The halo is in the shape of a lotus flower, with hachiyorenge (a kind of lotus flower) shown in the center and surrounded by a pattern of concentric circles, with the outer margins representing a flame pattern.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The halo is in the shape of a lotus flower, with hachiyorenge (a kind of lotus flower) shown in the center and surrounded by a pattern of concentric circles, with the outer margins representing a flame pattern.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>光背支柱は竹を模した木製で、光背基部には山岳形の装飾がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The support of halo is made of wood representing bamboo, and the decoration of mountains is carved on the base of the halo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The support of halo is made of wood representing bamboo, and a decoration of mountains is carved on the base of the halo.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The support of halo is made of wood representing bamboo, and a decoration of mountains is carved on the base of the halo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>台座は前述の五角形の反花座の下に2段の框（かまち）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the pedestal, there is a two-stage kamachi (a frame) below the above-described kaeribanaza.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the pedestal, there is a two-stage kamachi (a frame) below the above-described kaeribanaza.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the pedestal, there is a two-stage kamachi (a frame) below the above-described pentagonal kaeribanaza.</e>
<cmt>「五角形の」　訳漏れ対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>構造材質</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Materials of construction</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Materials of construction</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Materials of construction</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>頭・体の根幹部分、さらには足下の蓮肉（台座の内側の部分）とその下の2つの枘（ほぞ）までを含んでクスノキの一材から彫り出した一木造である（飛鳥時代の木造彫刻はほとんどがクスノキ製）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is ichiboku-zukuri (wooden figure carved of one tree) carved out of a single camphor tree (most of wooden statues during the Asuka period are made of camphor trees), from which the base part consisting of the head and body, the renniku (lotus center) (the interior part of the pedestal) at the foot as well as the two hozo (the handle of tools) underneath are all carved out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is ichiboku-zukuri (wooden figure carved of one tree) carved out of a single camphor tree (most wooden statues during the Asuka period are made of camphor trees), from which the base part consisting of the head and body, the renniku (lotus center) (the interior part of the pedestal) at the foot, and the two hozo (the handle of tools) underneath are all carved out.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is ichiboku-zukuri (wooden figure carved of one tree) carved out of a single camphor tree (most wooden statues during the Asuka period are made of camphor trees), from which the base part consisting of the head and body, the renniku (lotus center) (the interior part of the pedestal) at the foot, and the two hozo (the handle of tools) underneath are all carved out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>両腕の肘から先、頭上の髻、体側に垂れる天衣などを別材矧ぎ付けとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The parts of both arms from elbows up, motodori on the head, and hagoromo hanging on the sides of the body, etc. are made by other materials attached to the main body.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The parts of both arms from the elbows up, motodori on the head, and hagoromo hanging on the sides of the body, etc. are made from other materials attached to the main body.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The parts of both arms from the elbows up, motodori on the head, and tenne hanging on the sides of the body, etc. are made from other materials attached to the main body.</e>
<cmt>hagoromo→tenne</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>左手に持つ水瓶も別材でこれはヒノキ材製である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The water jar held on the left hand is made of other material, this one being Japanese cypress.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The water jar held on the left hand is made of other material, this one being Japanese cypress.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The water jar held on the left hand is made of other material, this one being Japanese cypress.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>像表面には乾漆（漆に木粉や針葉樹の葉の粉などを混ぜたもの）を盛り上げて細部を仕上げている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The surface of the statue is painted with kanshitsu (dry lacquer, made by mixing lacquer with wood powder and powdered leaves of conifer) to finish the details.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The surface of the statue is painted with kanshitsu (dry lacquer, made by mixing lacquer with wood powder and powdered leaves of conifer) to finish the details.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The surface of the statue is painted with kanshitsu (dry lacquer, made by mixing lacquer with wood powder and powdered leaves of conifer) to finish the details.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>像表面には彩色を施すが、剥落が多く、当初の彩色は判然としない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the surface of the statue was colored, the color is peeled off for the most part and the original color remains unclear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the surface of the statue was colored, the color is peeled off for the most part and the original color remains unclear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the surface of the statue was colored, the color is peeled off for the most part and the original color remains unclear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>像内部は胸以下に内刳り（像の重量軽減や干割れ防止などのために内部を削って空洞にすること）を施す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The inside of the statue is hollowed from the breast down (the inside is hollowed for the purpose of lightening the weight and of preventing mud cracks of the statue).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The inside of the statue is hollowed from the breast down (the inside is hollowed for the purpose of lightening the weight and of preventing mud cracks of the statue).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The inside of the statue is hollowed from the breast down (the inside is hollowed for the purpose of lightening the weight and of preventing mud cracks of the statue).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>X線写真によれば、本体側面に縦の矧ぎ目があり、一木で制作した像をいったん前後に割り放し、内刳りを施したものと見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since an X-ray picture showed a vertical seam on the side of main body, it is assumed that the statue, which was originally made of a single tree, was split into two at the back and belly and then hollowed).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since an X-ray image shows a vertical seam on the side of main body, it is assumed that the statue, which was originally made of a single tree, was split into two at the back and belly and then hollowed).</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since an X-ray image shows a vertical seam on the side of main body, it is assumed that the statue, which was originally made of a single tree, was split into two at the back and belly and then hollowed.</e>
<cmt>文末の括弧削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>所在</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Location</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Location</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Location</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>法隆寺大宝蔵院の百済観音堂に安置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is enshrined in Kudara Kannon-do Hall of Dai-Hozo-In (Great Treasure Gallery) of Horyu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is enshrined in Kudara Kannon-do Hall of Dai-Hozo-In (Great Treasure Gallery) of Horyu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is enshrined in Kudara Kannon-do Hall of Daihozoin (Great Treasure Gallery) of Horyu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Dai-Hozo-In→Daihozoin</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>明治時代初期には金堂の北面に安置され、明治時代後期～昭和時代初期には奈良帝室博物館（現奈良国立博物館）に寄託されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was enshrined in the north face of the Kondo (golden hall) during the early part of the Meiji period; from the late part of the Meiji period until the early part of the Showa period, it was deposited in the Imperial Household Museum of Nara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was enshrined in the north face of the Kondo (golden hall) during the early part of the Meiji period; from the late part of the Meiji period until the early part of the Showa period, it was deposited in the Imperial Household Museum of Nara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was enshrined in the north face of the Kondo (golden hall) during the early part of the Meiji period; from the late part of the Meiji period until the early part of the Showa period, it was deposited in the Imperial Household Museum of Nara (present Nara National Museum).</e>
<cmt>（現奈良国立博物館）　訳漏れ対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>伝来</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Introduction</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Introduction</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Introduction</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="27">
<j>法隆寺の古い記録にはこの像に当たるものが見えないことから、造像当初から法隆寺にあったものではなく、後世、他の寺院から移されたものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since old records of Horyu-ji Temple contain no description about this statue, it is assumed that the statue was not in the Horyu-ji Temple since its construction but was transferred from another temple in later years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since old records of Horyu-ji Temple contain no description about this statue, it is assumed that the statue was not in the Horyu-ji Temple since its construction but was transferred from another temple in later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since old records of Horyu-ji Temple contain no description about this statue, it is assumed that the statue was not in the Horyu-ji Temple since its construction but was transferred from another temple in later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>いつ、どこの寺院から、いかなる事情により移されたかについては諸説あるが、正確なことは不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there are many theories regarding when, from which temple, and for what reason the statue was transferred, the truth remains unclear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there are many theories regarding when, from which temple, and for what reason the statue was transferred, the truth remains unclear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there are many theories regarding when, from which temple, and for what reason the statue was transferred, the truth remains unclear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>文化財指定</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Designation as a cultural property</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Designation as a cultural property</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Designation as a cultural property</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>明治30年（1897年）12月28日、「観世音菩薩乾漆立像（伝百済人作）1躯」として、古社寺保護法に基づく国宝（文化財保護法における「重要文化財」に相当）に指定。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 28, 1897, it was designated as a national treasure under the Ancient Temples and Shrines Protection Law as &quot;One Statue of Kanzeon Bosatsu Kanshitsu Ritsuzo&quot; (one dry lacquered standing statue of Kanzeon Bosatsu (the Buddhist Goddess of Mercy) (according to a legend, the work of someone of ancient Korean kingdom (Paekche or Kudara))&quot; (equivalent to an &quot;important cultural property&quot; under the Law for the Protection of Cultural Properties).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 28, 1897, it was designated a national treasure under the Ancient Temples and Shrines Protection Law as &quot;One Statue of Kanzeon Bosatsu Kanshitsu Ritsuzo&quot; (one dry lacquered standing statue of Kanzeon Bosatsu (the Buddhist Goddess of Mercy) (according to a legend, the work of someone of an ancient Korean kingdom (Paekche or Kudara))&quot; (equivalent to an &quot;important cultural property&quot; under the Law for the Protection of Cultural Properties).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 28, 1897, it was designated a national treasure under the Ancient Temples and Shrines Protection Law as &apos;One Statue of Kanzeon Bosatsu Kanshitsu Ritsuzo (one dry lacquered standing statue of Kanzeon Bosatsu) (according to a legend, the work of someone of an ancient Korean kingdom [Paekche or Kudara])&apos; (equivalent to an &apos;important cultural property&apos; under the Law for the Protection of Cultural Properties).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;括弧内の括弧を[]に変更しました。(the Buddhist Goddess of Mercy)　既出のため削除Ritsuzo&quot;→Ritsuzo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>昭和26年（1951年）6月9日、「木造観音菩薩立像（百済観音）1躯」として文化財保護法に基づく国宝に指定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 9, 1951, it was designated as a national treasure under the Law for the Protection of Cultural Properties as &quot;One Statue of Mokuzo Kannon Bosatsu Ryu-zo&quot; (one wooden standing statue of Kannon Bosatsu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 9, 1951, it was designated a national treasure under the Law for the Protection of Cultural Properties as &quot;One Statue of Mokuzo Kannon Bosatsu Ryu-zo&quot; (one wooden standing statue of Kannon Bosatsu).</e>
<cmt>omitted &apos;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 9, 1951, it was designated a national treasure under the Law for the Protection of Cultural Properties as &apos;One Statue of Mokuzo Kannon Bosatsu Ryu-zo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>(one wooden standing statue of Kannon Bosatsu) 既出のため削除&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>法隆寺の記録にみる百済観音</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kudara Kannon according to records of Horyu-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kudara Kannon according to records of Horyu-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kudara Kannon according to records of Horyu-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="31">
<j>法隆寺の根本史料である天平19年（747年）の『法隆寺資財帳』には百済観音に相当する仏像についての記載はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Horyu-ji Shizai Cho&quot; (Note of materials of Horyu-ji Temple), which existed from 747 and comprises the foundational materials of Horyu-ji Temple, no mention is made about a Buddha statue corresponding to Kudara Kannon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Horyu-ji Shizai Cho&quot; (Note of materials of Horyu-ji Temple), which existed from 747 and comprises the foundational materials of Horyu-ji Temple, no mention is made about a Buddha statue corresponding to Kudara Kannon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Horyu-ji Shizai Cho&quot; (Note of materials of Horyu-ji Temple), which existed from 747 and comprises the foundational materials of Horyu-ji Temple, no mention is made about a Buddha statue corresponding to Kudara Kannon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="32">
<j>11世紀後半成立の『金堂日記』には、当時法隆寺金堂内にあった仏像に関する詳細な記録があるが、ここにも百済観音に関する言及はなく、鎌倉時代の法隆寺の僧・顕真による『聖徳太子伝私記』も同様に百済観音には触れていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Kondo Nikki&quot; (Daily record of main temple structure), which was established in the late 11th century, contains a detailed description of Buddha statues which were enshrined in Kondo (the Golden Pavilion) of the Horyu-ji Temple at the time, but even here no mention is made about Kudara Kannon; similarly, &quot;Shotoku Taishi Denshiki&quot; (The private recollections on the life of Prince Shotoku) written by Kenshin, a monk of Horyu-ji Temple during the Kamakura period, does not mention Kudara Kannon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Kondo Nikki&quot; (Daily record of main temple structure), which was established in the late 11th century, contains a detailed description of Buddha statues which were enshrined in Kondo (the Golden Pavilion) of the Horyu-ji Temple at the time, but even here no mention is made about Kudara Kannon; similarly, &quot;Shotoku Taishi Denshiki&quot; (The private recollections on the life of Prince Shotoku) written by Kenshin, a monk of Horyu-ji Temple during the Kamakura period, does not mention Kudara Kannon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Kondo Nikki&quot; (Daily record of main temple structure), which was established in the late 11th century, contains a detailed description of Buddha statues which were enshrined in Kondo (the Golden Pavilion) of the Horyu-ji Temple at the time, but even here no mention is made about Kudara Kannon; similarly, &quot;Shotoku Taishi Denshiki&quot; (The private recollections on the life of Prince Shotoku) written by Kenshin, a monk of Horyu-ji Temple during the Kamakura period, does not mention Kudara Kannon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="33">
<j>百済観音に該当すると思われる像の存在が記録で確認できるのはようやく近世になってからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is only in early-modern times that a statue which seems to apply to Kudara Kannon can be confirmed in a historical record.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is only in early-modern times that a statue which seems to correspond to Kudara Kannon can be confirmed in a historical record.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is only in early-modern times that a statue which seems to correspond to Kudara Kannon can be confirmed in a historical record.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>元禄11年（1698年）の『法隆寺諸堂仏躰数量記』に「虚空蔵立像　長七尺五分」とあるのが、像高からみて百済観音に当たると推定され、これが百済観音の存在を記録する最古の文献とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is assumed that the mention of &quot;Kokuzo Ryu-zo&quot; (Standing statue of Kokuzo), seven shaku and five bu in height&quot; in &quot;Horyu-ji Shodo Butsutai Suryoki&quot; (Record of the number of Buddha at several halls of Horyu-ji Temple) in 1698 refers to Kudara Kannon, as judged from the height of the statue, and this is regarded as the oldest literature recording the existence of Kudara Kannon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is assumed that the mention of &quot;Kokuzo Ryu-zo&quot; (Standing statue of Kokuzo), seven shaku and five bu in height&quot; in &quot;Horyu-ji Shodo Butsutai Suryoki&quot; (Record of the number of Buddha at several halls of Horyu-ji Temple) in 1698 refers to Kudara Kannon, as judged from the height of the statue, and this is considered the oldest literature recording the existence of Kudara Kannon.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is assumed that the mention of &apos;Kokuzo Ryu-zo (Standing statue of Kokuzo), seven shaku and five bu in height&apos; in &quot;Horyu-ji Shodo Butsutai Suryoki&quot; (Record of the number of Buddha at several halls of Horyu-ji Temple) in 1698 refers to Kudara Kannon, as judged from the height of the statue, and this is considered the oldest literature recording the existence of Kudara Kannon.</e>
<cmt>Ryu-zo&quot;→Ryu-zo「」の&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="35">
<j>『法隆寺諸堂仏躰数量記』はこの「虚空蔵菩薩像」を「百済国から渡来した天竺（インド）製の像である」としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Horyu-ji Shodo Butsutai Suryoki&quot;, this &quot;Kokuzo Bosatsu-zo&quot; (statue of Akasagarbha Bodhisattva) is the &quot;Indian statue which was introduced from Kudara no kuni (Paekche).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Horyu-ji Shodo Butsutai Suryoki&quot;, this &quot;Kokuzo Bosatsu-zo&quot; (statue of Akasagarbha Bodhisattva) is the &quot;Indian statue which was introduced from Kudara no kuni (Paekche)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Horyu-ji Shodo Butsutai Suryoki&quot;, this &apos;Kokuzo Bosatsu-zo&apos; (statue of Akasagarbha Bodhisattva) is the &apos;Indian statue which was introduced from Kudara no kuni (Paekche).&apos;</e>
<cmt>「」の&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;ピリオドを &apos; &apos; 内に移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>延享3年（1746年）、法隆寺の僧・良訓（りょうきん）が著した『古今一陽集』にも「虚空蔵菩薩」とあり、「この像の由来は古記にはないが、古老の伝えるところでは異国将来の像である」と述べていて、当時すでにこの像の由来は不明であったことがわかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Kokon Ichiyo Shu&quot; (literally, collection of all ages, one sun) written in 1746 by Ryokin, a monk at Horyu-ji Temple, also mentions &quot;Kokuzo Bosatsu&quot;, indicating that &quot;the origin of this statue is not mentioned in ancient records, but elders tell us that it is a statue brought over from a foreign country&quot;; this tells us that the origin of this statue was already unclear at the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Kokon Ichiyo Shu&quot; (literally, collection of all ages, one sun) written in 1746 by Ryokin, a monk at Horyu-ji Temple, also mentions &quot;Kokuzo Bosatsu&quot;, indicating that &quot;the origin of this statue is not mentioned in ancient records, but elders tell us that it is a statue brought over from a foreign country&quot;; this tells us that the origin of this statue was already unclear at the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Kokon Ichiyo Shu&quot; (literally, collection of all ages, one sun) written in 1746 by Ryokin, a monk at Horyu-ji Temple, also mentions &apos;Kokuzo Bosatsu&apos;, indicating that &apos;the origin of this statue is not mentioned in ancient records, but elders tell us that it is a statue brought over from a foreign country&apos;; this tells us that the origin of this statue was already unclear at the time.</e>
<cmt>「」の&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>この像の旧所在については飛鳥の橘寺とする説（『法隆寺大鏡』、1917年）、斑鳩の中宮寺から移したものとする高田良信（法隆寺208世管主）の説などがあるがいずれも確証はなく、本像がいつ、どこで、誰によって造られ、どこの寺に安置されていたものか、正確なことは全く不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One theory has it that the old location of this statue was Tachibana-dera Temple in Asuka (&quot;Horyu-ji Okagami&quot; (The Great Art of the Horyu-ji Temple), 1917), and according to a theory by Ryoshin TAKADA (the 208th kannushi (Shinto priest) of Horyu-ji Temple), it was transferred from Chugu-ji Temple in Ikaruga (a town in Ikoma County, Nara Prefecture), among other theories; yet none of them is confirmed and it remains completely unclear how, when, and by whom this statue was made, and in which temple it was enshrined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One theory has it that the old location of this statue was Tachibana-dera Temple in Asuka (&quot;Horyu-ji Okagami&quot; (The Great Art of the Horyu-ji Temple), 1917), and according to a theory by Ryoshin TAKADA (the 208th kannushi (Shinto priest) of Horyu-ji Temple), it was transferred from Chugu-ji Temple in Ikaruga (a town in Ikoma County, Nara Prefecture), among other theories; yet none of them is confirmed and it remains completely unclear how, when, and by whom this statue was made, and in which temple it was enshrined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One theory has it that the old location of this statue was Tachibana-dera Temple in Asuka (&quot;Horyu-ji Okagami&quot; [The Great Art of the Horyu-ji Temple], 1917), and according to a theory by Ryoshin TAKADA (the 208th kannushi [Shinto priest] of Horyu-ji Temple), it was transferred from Chugu-ji Temple in Ikaruga (a town in Ikoma County, Nara Prefecture), among other theories; yet none of them is confirmed and it remains completely unclear how, when, and by whom this statue was made, and in which temple it was enshrined.</e>
<cmt>括弧内の括弧を[]に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>「百済観音」という名称</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name &quot;Kudara Kannon&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name &quot;Kudara Kannon&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name &apos;Kudara Kannon&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="38">
<j>近世から明治時代まで、法隆寺ではこの像を観音ではなく「虚空蔵菩薩」と呼んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the early-modern times until the Meiji period, this statue was called &quot;Kokuzo Bosatsu&quot; instead of Kannon at Horyu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the early-modern times until the Meiji period, this statue was called &quot;Kokuzo Bosatsu&quot; instead of Kannon at Horyu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the early-modern times until the Meiji period, this statue was called &apos;Kokuzo Bosatsu&apos; instead of Kannon at Horyu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>これは虚空蔵菩薩を聖徳太子の本地とする信仰に基づくものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is probably based on the religion in which Kokuzo Bosatsu was the honji (original ground or true nature) of Prince Shotoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is probably based on the religion in which Kokuzo Bosatsu was the honji (original ground or true nature) of Prince Shotoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is probably based on the religion in which Kokuzo Bosatsu was the honji (original ground or true nature) of Prince Shotoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="40">
<j>明治19年（1886年）、宮内省、内務省、文部省による法隆寺の宝物調査が実施された際の目録には「朝鮮風観音」とあり、この頃からこの像を「観音」と見なす説のあったことがわかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The list, which was made when a research was conducted on treasures of Horyu-ji Temple by the Imperial Household Ministry, Ministry of Interior, and Ministry of Education in 1886, indicated &quot;Korean-style Kannon&quot;; this tells us that there was a theory according to which this statue was regarded as &quot;Kannon&quot; since around this time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The list, which was compiled when research was conducted on treasures of Horyu-ji Temple by the Imperial Household Ministry, Ministry of Interior, and Ministry of Education in 1886, indicated &quot;Korean-style Kannon&quot;; this tells us that there was a theory according to which this statue was considered &quot;Kannon&quot; since around this time.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The list, which was compiled when research was conducted on treasures of Horyu-ji Temple by the Imperial Household Ministry, Ministry of Interior, and Ministry of Education in 1886, indicated &apos;Korean-style Kannon&apos;; this tells us that there was a theory according to which this statue was considered &apos;Kannon&apos; since around this time.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>この「朝鮮風観音」という名称については、確証はないが、当時奈良地方の文化財を調査していた岡倉天心の発案によるものかと推定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it is not certain, it is assumed that the name of this &quot;Korean-style Kannon&quot; was invented by Tenshin OKAKURA, who was researching on cultural properties in Nara area at the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is not certain, it is assumed that the name of this &quot;Korean-style Kannon&quot; was invented by Tenshin OKAKURA, who was researching cultural properties in the Nara area at the time.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is not certain, it is assumed that the name of this &apos;Korean-style Kannon&apos; was invented by Tenshin OKAKURA, who was researching cultural properties in the Nara area at the time.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>前述のとおり、この像が明治30年（1897年）、当時の国宝に指定された際の名称も「観世音菩薩」であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As described above, when this statue was designated as a national treasure in 1897, the name given was also &quot;Kanzeon Bosatsu&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As described above, when this statue was designated a national treasure in 1897, the name given was also &quot;Kanzeon Bosatsu&quot;.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As described above, when this statue was designated a national treasure in 1897, the name given was also &apos;Kanzeon Bosatsu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;ピリオドを &apos; &apos; 内へ移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>しかし、法隆寺側では「虚空蔵菩薩」の呼称にこだわりをもっており、明治38年（1905年）4月14日、住職佐伯定胤名で当時の奈良県知事あてに「観世音」から「虚空蔵」への名称訂正願を提出しているが、寺側の願いは聞き入れられなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Horyu-ji Temple was committed to using the name &quot;Kokuzo Bosatsu&quot;, and on April 14, 1905, a request for changing the name from &quot;Kanzeon&quot; to &quot;Kokuzo&quot; was submitted to the Governor of Nara Prefecture of the time, but the temple&apos;s request was not granted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Horyu-ji Temple was committed to using the name &quot;Kokuzo Bosatsu&quot;, and on April 14, 1905, a request for changing the name from &quot;Kanzeon&quot; to &quot;Kokuzo&quot; was submitted to the Governor of Nara Prefecture of the time, but the temple&apos;s request was not granted.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Horyu-ji Temple was committed to using the name &apos;Kokuzo Bosatsu&apos;, and on April 14, 1905, a request for changing the name from &apos;Kanzeon&apos; to &apos;Kokuzo&apos; was submitted to the Governor of Nara Prefecture of the time, but the temple&apos;s request was not granted.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>その後明治44年（1911年）になって、寺内の土蔵から本像の宝冠が新たに発見され、その宝冠の正面に阿弥陀如来の化仏（けぶつ、小型の仏像）が刻まれていることから、寺側でもこの像を「観音菩薩」と認めざるをえなくなった（菩薩像の頭上に阿弥陀如来の化仏があれば、その像は観音菩薩像であることを示している）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later in 1911, a crown of this statue was newly discovered from dozo (warehouse made of soil) in the temple; since Kebutsu (the Artificial Buddha, a small-sized statue of Buddha) of Amida Nyorai (Amitabha Tathagata) was engraved at the front of the crown, the temple had to acknowledge that the statue was &quot;Kannon Bosatsu&quot; (if there was Kebutsu of Amida Nyorai on the head of a statue of Bosatsu, then it meant that the statue was that of Kannon Bosatsu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, in 1911, a crown of this statue was newly discovered from dozo (warehouse made of soil) in the temple; since Kebutsu (the Artificial Buddha, a small-sized statue of Buddha) of Amida Nyorai (Amitabha Tathagata) was engraved at the front of the crown, the temple had to acknowledge that the statue was &quot;Kannon Bosatsu&quot; (if there was Kebutsu of Amida Nyorai on the head of a statue of Bosatsu, then it meant that the statue was that of Kannon Bosatsu).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, in 1911, a crown of this statue was newly discovered from dozo (warehouse made of soil) in the temple; since Kebutsu (the Artificial Buddha, a small-sized statue of Buddha) of Amida Nyorai (Amitabha Tathagata) was engraved at the front of the crown, the temple had to acknowledge that the statue was &apos;Kannon Bosatsu&apos; (if there was Kebutsu of Amida Nyorai on the head of a statue of Bosatsu, then it meant that the statue was that of Kannon Bosatsu.)</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;ピリオドを括弧内へ移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="45">
<j>この像の通称として20世紀以降著名になる「百済観音」という呼称はさほど古いものではなく、大正6年（1917年）の『法隆寺大鏡』の解説が初出であるとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name &quot;Kudara Kannon&quot;, which became well-known as the popular name of this statue after the 20th century, is not very old; it is said that the name was first used in the commentary of &quot;Horyu-ji Okagami&quot; in 1917.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name &quot;Kudara Kannon&quot;, which became well-known as the popular name of this statue after the 20th century, is not very old; it is said that the name was first used in the commentary of &quot;Horyu-ji Okagami&quot; in 1917.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name &apos;Kudara Kannon&apos;, which became well-known as the popular name of this statue after the 20th century, is not very old; it is said that the name was first used in the commentary of &quot;Horyu-ji Okagami&quot; in 1917.</e>
<cmt>「」の&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>和辻哲郎の『古寺巡礼』は大正8年（1919年）に刊行されたものだが、『法隆寺大鏡』の記述に影響されてか、この像を「百済観音」と呼んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Koji Junrei&quot; by Tetsuro WATSUJI which was published in 1919 calls this statue &quot;Kudara Kannon&quot;, maybe as influenced by the description of &quot;Horyu-ji Okagami&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Koji Junrei&quot; by Tetsuro WATSUJI, which was published in 1919, calls this statue &quot;Kudara Kannon&quot;, maybe as influenced by the description of &quot;Horyu-ji Okagami&quot;.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Koji Junrei&quot; by Tetsuro WATSUJI, which was published in 1919, calls this statue &apos;Kudara Kannon&apos;, maybe as influenced by the description of &quot;Horyu-ji Okagami&quot;.</e>
<cmt>「」の&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>考古学者の濱田青陵（濱田耕作）は大正15年（1926年）、『仏教芸術』誌上に「百済観音像」を発表し、後に発表した随筆集に『百済観音』という題を付けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1926, an archaeologist called Seiryo HAMADA presented &quot;Kudara Kannon-zo&quot; (Statue of Kudara Kannon) on a journal titled &quot;Buddhist Art&quot;, and gave the title &quot;Kudara Kannon&quot; to the collection of essays which was later presented.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1926, an archaeologist called Seiryo HAMADA presented &quot;Kudara Kannon-zo&quot; (Statue of Kudara Kannon) on a journal titled &quot;Buddhist Art&quot;, and gave the title &quot;Kudara Kannon&quot; to the collection of essays which was later presented.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1926, an archaeologist called Seiryo HAMADA (Kosaku HAMADA) presented &apos;Kudara Kannon-zo&apos; (Statue of Kudara Kannon) on a journal titled &quot;Buddhist Art&quot;, and gave the title &quot;Kudara Kannon&quot; to the collection of essays which was later presented.</e>
<cmt>「」の&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;（濱田耕作）　訳漏れ対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>このようにして、本像について「百済観音」という名称が次第に定着していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this manner, the name &quot;Kudara Kannon&quot; became gradually rooted for this statue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this manner, the name &quot;Kudara Kannon&quot; became gradually rooted for this statue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this manner, the name &apos;Kudara Kannon&apos; became gradually rooted for this statue.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>様式</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Style</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Style</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Style</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="49">
<j>本像は、法隆寺金堂本尊の釈迦三尊像のような止利式の仏像とは様式を異にしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This statue has a different style from that of Buddha statues which are Tori-Shiki (Tori style), such as the Shaka Sanzon-zo (the statues of Shakyamuni triads) of the Kondo Honzon (the Golden Hall) of Horyu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This statue has a different style from that of Buddha statues that are Tori-Shiki (Tori style), such as the Shaka Sanzon-zo (the statues of Shakyamuni triads) of the Kondo Honzon (the Golden Hall) of Horyu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>pronoun</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This statue has a different style from that of Buddha statues that are Tori-Shiki (Tori style), such as the Shaka Sanzon-zo (the statues of Shakyamuni triads), honzon (principal image of Buddha) of the Kondo of Horyu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>法隆寺金堂本尊の表記変更しました。　（法隆寺金堂の本尊としました。金堂の説明は既出のため削除。）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>止利式の仏像は正面観照性が強く、側面感がほとんど考慮されていない点、左右相称性が強く、図式的な衣文表現などに特色があるが、百済観音像では側面感はより自然になり、立体的な人体把握が進んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buddha statues of Tori-Shiki have a significant level of contemplation from the front, with little consideration given to the lateral side; as such, the statues are strongly symmetrical, and while there are unique features with the diagrammatic expression of clothes and the like, the lateral side of Kudara Kannon statue is more natural, with further understanding of the steric human body.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buddha statues of Tori-Shiki have a significant level of contemplation from the front, with little consideration given to the lateral side; as such, the statues are strongly symmetrical, and while there are unique features with the diagrammatic expression of clothes and the like, the lateral side of Kudara Kannon statue is more natural, with further understanding of the form of the human body.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddha statues of Tori-Shiki have a significant level of contemplation from the front, with little consideration given to the lateral side; as such, the statues are strongly symmetrical, and while there are unique features with the diagrammatic expression of clothes and the like, the lateral side of Kudara Kannon statue is more natural, with further understanding of the form of the human body.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>7世紀も早い頃の制作とされる法隆寺夢殿本尊の救世観音像を見ると、全体に正面性・左右対称性が顕著で、肩に垂れる垂髪は「蕨手状」と称される図式的なものであり、両腕から体側に垂れる天衣は鰭（ひれ）状の突起を表しながら左右方向へ平面的に広がっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When looking at the Kuze Kannon-zo (statue of Kuze Kannon) at honzon (principal object of worship at a temple) of Yumedono (Hall of Dreams) of Horyu-ji Temple, which is considered as a work of seven centuries earlier, overall frontality and symmetry are prominent, with the long flowing hair on the shoulders having the diagrammatic style called &quot;warabite-jo&quot; (literally, having the form of upturned bracken ferns), and the hagoromo hanging from both arms down the sides of the body spreads flatly in left and right directions, showing fin-like protrusions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When looking at the Kuze Kannon-zo (statue of Kuze Kannon) at honzon (principal object of worship at a temple) of Yumedono (Hall of Dreams) of Horyu-ji Temple, which is considered a work of seven centuries earlier, overall frontality and symmetry are prominent, with the long flowing hair on the shoulders having the diagrammatic style called &quot;warabite-jo&quot; (literally, having the form of upturned bracken ferns), and the hagoromo hanging from both arms down the sides of the body spreads flatly in left and right directions, showing fin-like protrusions.</e>
<cmt>omitted &apos;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When looking at the Kuze Kannon-zo (statue of Kuze Kannon) at honzon of Yumedono (Hall of Dreams) of Horyu-ji Temple, which is considered a work of seven centuries earlier, overall frontality and symmetry are prominent, with the long flowing hair on the shoulders having the diagrammatic style called &apos;warabite-jo&apos; (literally, having the form of upturned bracken ferns), and the tenne hanging from both arms down the sides of the body spreads flatly in left and right directions, showing fin-like protrusions.</e>
<cmt>hagoromo→tenne&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;「本尊」の説明削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>これに対して百済観音像の垂髪はより写実的に表現され、天衣はゆるやかなカーブを描いて前後方向に揺れるように表現されており、天衣のカーブの優美さは側面から見て初めて了解される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the contrary, the long flowing hair of Kudara Kannon-zo is expressed more realistically, with hagoromo depicted as swinging back and forth with a gentle curve; as such, the graceful curve of hagoromo can be acknowledged only when viewed from the side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the contrary, the long flowing hair of Kudara Kannon-zo is expressed more realistically, with hagoromo depicted as swinging back and forth with a gentle curve; as such, the graceful curve of hagoromo can be acknowledged only when viewed from the side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the contrary, the long flowing hair of Kudara Kannon-zo is expressed more realistically, with tenne depicted as swinging back and forth with a gentle curve; as such, the graceful curve of tenne can be acknowledged only when viewed from the side.</e>
<cmt>hagoromo→tenne</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>両手も各指が違ったカーブを描き、写実的に表現されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each finger of both hands also draws different curves, expressing a realistic representation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fingers of both hands all draw different curves, expressing a realistic representation.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fingers of both hands all draw different curves, expressing a realistic representation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>こうした点から、百済観音は夢殿本尊像などよりはやや年代が下るが、初唐彫刻の影響が見られる薬師寺東院堂の聖観音像や法隆寺の夢違観音像などよりは古く、おおむね7世紀半ばから後半の作とする点で研究者の意見はほぼ一致している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on these points, researchers agree on the most part that while Kudara Kannon-zo was made at a later time than the statue at the honzon of Yumedono and others, it is older than the Sho Kannon-zo (statue of Sho Kannon) at Yakushi-ji Temple Toin-do and Yume-Chigai Kannon-zo (statue of Yume-Chigai Kannon) at Horyu-ji Temple, among others, which show the influence of the sculpture of Shoto period, and that it is the work of roughly around the middle to late seventh century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on these points, researchers agree on the most part that while Kudara Kannon-zo was made at a later time than the statue at the honzon of Yumedono and others, it is older than the Sho Kannon-zo (statue of Sho Kannon) at Yakushi-ji Temple Toin-do and Yume-Chigai Kannon-zo (statue of Yume-Chigai Kannon) at Horyu-ji Temple, among others, which show the influence of the sculpture of the Shoto period, and that it is the work of roughly around the middle to late seventh century.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on these points, researchers agree on the most part that while Kudara Kannon-zo was made at a later time than the statue at the honzon of Yumedono and others, it is older than the Sho Kannon-zo (statue of Sho Kannon) at Yakushi-ji Temple Toin-do and Yume-Chigai Kannon-zo (statue of Yume-Chigai Kannon) at Horyu-ji Temple, among others, which show the influence of the sculpture of the early Tang period, and that it is the work of roughly around the middle to late seventh century.</e>
<cmt>Shoto→early Tang</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>しかし、この像の作風の源流をどこに求めるかについては諸説あり定説をみない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there are many theories as to where to seek the roots of the style of this statue, none of which is established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there are many theories as to where to seek the roots of the style of this statue, none of which is established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there are many theories as to where to seek the roots of the style of this statue, none of which is established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>中国の南北朝時代の南朝の作風が影響したものとする説が古くからある一方で（久野健、松原三郎などの説）、北斉・北周・隋の仏像に様式的源流を見る説（上野照夫、水野清一など）もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On one hand, there is a theory (as supported by Takeshi KUNO, Saburo MATSUBARA, etc.) according to which the style of the Southern Dynasty of the Northern and Southern Dynasties in China influenced the style of this statue; on the other hand, there is a theory (as supported by Teruo UENO, Seiichi MIZUNO, etc.) according to which the roots of the style are with the Buddha statues of Northern Qi, Northern Zhou, and Sui Dynasties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On one hand, there is a theory (as supported by Takeshi KUNO, Saburo MATSUBARA, etc.) according to which the style of the Southern Dynasty of the Northern and Southern Dynasties in China influenced the style of this statue; on the other hand, there is a theory (as supported by Teruo UENO, Seiichi MIZUNO, etc.) according to which the roots of the style are with the Buddha statues of Northern Qi, Northern Zhou, and Sui Dynasties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On one hand, there is a theory (as supported by Takeshi KUNO, Saburo MATSUBARA, etc.) according to which the style of the Southern Dynasty of the Northern and Southern Dynasties in China influenced the style of this statue; on the other hand, there is a theory (as supported by Teruo UENO, Seiichi MIZUNO, etc.) according to which the roots of the style are with the Buddha statues of Northern Qi, Northern Zhou, and Sui Dynasties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>後者の説によれば、法隆寺金堂釈迦三尊像のような7世紀前半の像は北魏の作風を源流とするものと見、それよりも3次元的空間把握の進んだ像を時代の下がる北斉・北周・隋の影響下にあるものと見る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the latter theory, statues of the early seventh century, such as the Shaka Sanzon-zo of Kondo of Horyu-ji Temple, are regarded as having the roots in the style of the Northern Wei Dynasty, and the statues with further understanding of three-dimensional space are regarded as having been influenced by Northern Qi, Northern Zhou, and Sui Dynasties that are dated later in history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the latter theory, statues of the early seventh century, such as the Shaka Sanzon-zo of Kondo of Horyu-ji Temple, are regarded as having their roots in the style of the Northern Wei Dynasty, and the statues with further understanding of three-dimensional space are regarded as having been influenced by Northern Qi, Northern Zhou, and Sui Dynasties that are dated later in history.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the latter theory, statues of the early seventh century, such as the Shaka Sanzon-zo of Kondo of Horyu-ji Temple, are regarded as having their roots in the style of the Northern Wei Dynasty, and the statues with further understanding of three-dimensional space are regarded as having been influenced by Northern Qi, Northern Zhou, and Sui Dynasties that are dated later in history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>日本文化への影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Influence on Japanese culture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Influence on Japanese culture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Influence on Japanese culture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="58">
<j>本像の特異な様式、謎に満ちた伝来などは、多くの人々の関心を呼び、随筆、短歌等でしばしば取り上げられ絶賛されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The unique style of this statue as well as its mysterious introduction, among other factors, aroused the interest of many people; they are often used as the subject of essays and tanka (thirty-one syllables&apos; poem) and the like, and are highly praised.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The unique style of this statue as well as its mysterious introduction, among other factors, aroused the interest of many people; they are often used as the subject of essays and tanka (thirty-one syllables&apos; poem) and the like, and are highly praised.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The unique style of this statue as well as its mysterious introduction, among other factors, aroused the interest of many people; they are often used as the subject of essays and tanka (thirty-one syllables&apos; poem) and the like, and are highly praised.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>和辻哲郎は奈良帝室博物館に寄託されていた本像を見た感想を『古寺巡礼』（1919年）で述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tetsuro WATSUJI made remarks in &quot;Koji Junrei&quot; (1919) about this statue, which was deposited at the Imperial Household Museum of Nara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tetsuro WATSUJI made remarks in &quot;Koji Junrei&quot; (1919) about this statue, which was deposited at the Imperial Household Museum of Nara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tetsuro WATSUJI made remarks in &quot;Koji Junrei&quot; (1919) about this statue, which was deposited at the Imperial Household Museum of Nara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>和辻はこの像には「縹渺（ひょうびょう）とした含蓄」があると言い、その様式的源流はインド・ガンダーラにまでさかのぼるものだと述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He stated that this statue has &quot;broad and immeasurable implication&quot;, and that the roots of the style date back to Gandhara of India.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He stated that this statue has &quot;broad and immeasurable implication&quot;, and that the roots of the style date back to Gandhara of India.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He stated that this statue has &apos;broad and immeasurable implication&apos;, and that the roots of the style date back to Gandhara of India.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>亀井勝一郎は『大和古寺風物誌』（1943年）においてこの像を「大地から燃えあがった永遠の焔」のような像だと絶賛した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsuichiro KAMEI acclaimed this statue as being like &quot;eternal flame blazing from the earth&quot; in &quot;Yamato Koji Fubutsushi&quot; (1943).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsuichiro KAMEI acclaimed this statue as being like &quot;eternal flame blazing from the earth&quot; in &quot;Yamato Koji Fubutsushi&quot; (1943).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsuichiro KAMEI acclaimed this statue as being like &apos;eternal flame blazing from the earth&apos; in &quot;Yamato Koji Fubutsushi&quot; (1943).</e>
<cmt>「」の&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>会津八一、吉野秀雄、吉井勇らは百済観音を題材とした短歌を作っており、その他多くの文筆家によって本像が取り上げられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People such as Yaichi AIZU, Hideo YOSHINO, and Isamu YOSHII produced tanka which featured Kudara Kannon; many other writers took up this statue as the subject of their works.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People such as Yaichi AIZU, Hideo YOSHINO, and Isamu YOSHII produced tanka which featured Kudara Kannon; many other writers took up this statue as a subject of their works.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People such as Yaichi AIZU, Hideo YOSHINO, and Isamu YOSHII produced tanka which featured Kudara Kannon; many other writers took up this statue as a subject of their works.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="63">
<j>1997年にはパリのルーヴル美術館で百済観音の特別展示が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1997, a special exhibition on Kudara Kannon was held at the Louvre Museum in Paris.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1997, a special exhibition on Kudara Kannon was held at the Louvre Museum in Paris.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1997, a special exhibition on Kudara Kannon was held at the Louvre Museum in Paris.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>1997年から1999年にかけて「フランスにおける日本年」および「日本におけるフランス年」という趣旨で、両国において多くの記念行事が行われたが、その際、両国の国宝級美術品1点ずつを相手国で公開することとなり、日本からは百済観音が、フランスからはウジェーヌ・ドラクロワの代表作『民衆を導く自由の女神』が選ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From 1997 until 1999, under the concepts of &quot;Japanese years in France&quot; and &quot;French years in Japan&quot;, many commemorative ceremonies took place in both countries; it was decided that one work of art, of the level of a national treasure, of each country be exhibited, and Kudara Kannon from Japan and a representative work by Eugene de La Croix titled &quot;La Liberte guidant le people&quot; were selected.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 1997 until 1999, under the concepts of &quot;Japanese years in France&quot; and &quot;French years in Japan&quot;, many commemorative ceremonies took place in both countries; it was decided that one work of art, of the level of a national treasure, of each country be exhibited, and Kudara Kannon from Japan and a representative work by Eugene de La Croix titled &quot;La Liberte guidant le people&quot; were selected.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 1997 until 1999, under the concepts of &apos;Japanese years in France&apos; and &apos;French years in Japan&apos;, many commemorative ceremonies took place in both countries; it was decided that one work of art, of the level of a national treasure, of each country be exhibited, and Kudara Kannon from Japan and a representative work by Eugene de La Croix titled &quot;La Liberte guidant le people&quot; were selected.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ReijiYamashina(id:29567), Urania(id:7213), くっちゃめ(id:86793), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>