<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>愚管抄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gukansho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gukansho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gukansho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>愚管抄（ぐかんしょう）とは、天台宗僧侶の慈円著による、鎌倉時代初期の史論書。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gukansho is a history book written by Jien, a priest of Tendai sect in the early Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Gukansho&quot; is a history book written by Jien, a priest of the Tendai sect, in the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Gukansho&quot; is a history book written by Jien, a priest of the Tendai sect, in the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>全7巻。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is seven volumes long.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It comprises seven volumes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It comprises seven volumes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>承久の乱の直前、朝廷と幕府の緊張が高まった時期の承久2年（1220年）ごろ成立したが、乱後に修訂が加えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was written around 1220 amid the rising tension between imperial court and Shogunate just before Jokyu no Ran, Jokyu Rebellion, but it was revised after that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was written around 1220 amid the rising tension between the Imperial Court and the shogunate, just before Jokyu no Ran (the Jokyu Rebellion), but subsequently it was revised.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was written around 1220 amid the rising tension between the Imperial Court and the shogunate, just before Jokyu no Ran (the Jokyu Rebellion), but subsequently it was revised.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>概略</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>神武天皇から順徳天皇までの歴史を、貴族の時代から武士の時代への転換と捕らえ、末法思想と「道理」の理念とに基づいて、仮名文で述べたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It regarded history from Emperor Jinmu to Emperor Juntoku as transition from the age of aristocracy to the age of warriors and described it by Kana-bun, publication in kana alone, based on Mappo-shiso, the &quot;end of the world&quot; belief and the idea of &apos;Dori (Order).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It regarded history from Emperor Jinmu to Emperor Juntoku as the transition from the age of aristocracy to the age of warriors, and described it in Kana-bun (publication in kana alone) based on Mappo-shiso (the &quot;end of the world&quot; belief) and the idea of &apos;Dori (Order).&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It regarded history from the Emperor Jinmu to the Emperor Juntoku as the transition from the age of aristocracy to the age of warriors, and described it in Kana-bun (publication in kana alone) based on Mappo-shiso (the &quot;end of the world&quot; belief) and the idea of &apos;Dori (Order).&apos;</e>
<cmt>theを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>慈円は朝廷側の一員であるが、源頼朝の政治を道理にかなっていると評価している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jien was a member of imperial court, but appreciated the government of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jien was a member of the Imperial Court, but he appreciated the government of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jien was a member of the Imperial Court, but he appreciated the government of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また、慈円自身の父である藤原忠通が父（慈円にとっては祖父）藤原忠実と不仲であった事を暗に批判したり、同母兄弟である九条家流を持ち上げて異母兄弟である近衛家流を非難するなど、摂関家の一員としての慈円本人の複雑な事情を垣間見る事の出来る記事も存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, there are descriptions which show complicated situation around Jien as a member of Sekkan-ke Regent Family (摂関家), such as he criticized his father FUJIWARA no Tadamichi because of being at outs with his father FUJIWARA no Tadazane (grandfather of Jien) implicitly and blamed Konoe Clan, his half brother&apos;s clan, as opposed to praising Kujo Clan, his brother&apos;s clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, there are descriptions that show the complicated situation around Jien as a member of the Sekkan-ke regent family (摂関家), such as that he implicitly criticized his father FUJIWARA no Tadamichi for being at odds with his own father, FUJIWARA no Tadazane (the grandfather of Jien), and blamed Konoe Clan, his half-brother&apos;s clan, as opposed to praising the Kujo Clan, his brother&apos;s clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, there are descriptions that show the complicated situation around Jien as a member of the Sekkan-ke regent family (摂関家), such as that he implicitly criticized his father FUJIWARA no Tadamichi for being at odds with his own father, FUJIWARA no Tadazane (the grandfather of Jien), and blamed the Konoe clan, his half-brother&apos;s clan, as opposed to praising the Kujo clan, his brother&apos;s clan.</e>
<cmt>文法。定冠詞必要。 “blamed Konoe”=&gt;”blamed the Konoe”</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>構成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Composition</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Composition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Composition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>『愚管抄』の内容は性格の異なる三部分から成り立っており：巻1から巻2までは神武天皇以来の天皇年代記、巻3から巻6までは道理の推移を中心とする歴史述叙、そして巻7は道理についての総括となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Gukansho&quot; consists of three parts which have different characters: the volume 1 and 2 are Emperors&apos; chronicle since Emperor Jinmu, the volume 3 to 6 are history at the center of transition of Dori, and the volume 7 is a general overview on Dori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Gukansho&quot; consists of three parts, each of which has a different character: volumes 1 and 2 chronicle the emperors since Jinmu, volumes 3 to 6 center on the transition to Dori, and volume 7 is a general overview on Dori.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Gukansho&quot; consists of three parts, each of which has a different character: volumes 1 and 2 chronicle the emperors since Jinmu, volumes 3 to 6 center on the transition of Dori together with the descriptions of history, and volume 7 is a general overview on Dori.</e>
<cmt>「歴史叙述」を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>弘前大学教授鈴木正道によると当初巻3から書き始められ、最後に天皇年代記が書き継がれたとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Masamichi SUZUKI, a professor of Hirosaki University, it was began to be written from the volume 3 and Emperors&apos; chronicle was added at the end.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Masamichi SUZUKI, a professor at Hirosaki University, the writing began with volume 3 and the Emperors&apos; chronicle was added at the end.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Masamichi SUZUKI, a professor at Hirosaki University, the writing began with volume 3 and the Emperors&apos; chronicle was added at the end.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>巻7に至り、一切の法は道理であり其の道理に基づいて世の直し方の方法を論述している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the volume 7, he described that everything was based on Dori and that the way to reform society should be implemented by Dori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In volume 7 he described that everything was based on Dori and that the way to reform society should be implemented by Dori.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In volume 7 he described that everything was based on Dori and that the way to reform society should be implemented by Dori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>版本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Editions</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Editions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Editions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>日本古典文学大系本〔旧大系〕（岩波書店、1967年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nihon Koten-bungaku Taikeibon (old Taikei) (Iwanami Shoten, 1967)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nihon Koten-bungaku Taikeibon (old Taikei) (Iwanami Shoten, 1967)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nihon Koten-bungaku Taikeibon (old Taikei) (Iwanami Shoten, 1967)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>新訂増補国史大系本『古今著聞集・愚管抄』（吉川弘文館、2000年） ISBN 4642003207</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shintei Zouho Kokushi Taikeibon &quot;Kokon Chomon-ju and Gukansho&quot; (Yoshikawa Kobunkan Inc., 2000) ISBN 4642003207</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shintei Zouho Kokushi Taikeibon, &quot;Kokon Chomon-ju and Gukansho&quot; (Yoshikawa Kobunkan Inc., 2000) ISBN 4642003207</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shintei Zoho Kokushi Taikeibon, &quot;Kokon Chomon-ju and Gukansho&quot; (Yoshikawa Kobunkan Inc., 2000) ISBN 4642003207</e>
<cmt>zoho　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Ligar(id:12623), 月下薄氷(id:47743), Papamaruchan22(id:71152), Rupert660(id:93405), 玄史生(id:43670), ZZZ(id:9462), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), Andee(id:20421), Alexbot(id:157199), Louperibot(id:128971), 小者(id:172526), Zippin(id:9885), Chuta(id:10457), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>