<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>法華堂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hokke-do Hall</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hokke-do Hall</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hokke-do Hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>法華堂（ほっけどう）は、法華三昧堂の略で天台宗の法華経三昧の行 (仏教)を行う仏堂のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hokke-do Hall, abbreviation of Hokke Sanmaido Hall, is a Buddhist temple in which Tendai-shu sect&apos;s Hokekyo sanmai no gyo (religious austerities to concentrate on the Lotus Sutra in Buddhism) is performed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hokke-do Hall, abbreviation of Hokke Sanmaido Hall, is a Buddhist temple in which Tendai-shu sect&apos;s Hokekyo sanmai no gyo (religious austerities to concentrate on the Lotus Sutra in Buddhism) is performed.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hokke-do Hall, abbreviation of Hokke Sanmaido Hall, is a Buddhist temple in which Tendai-shu sect&apos;s Hokekyo sanmai no gyo (religious austerities to concentrate on the Lotus Sutra in Buddhism) is performed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>また、法華会を行う堂も法華堂という（例：東大寺法華堂・通称「三月堂」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Buddhist temple in which Hokke-e (Lotus Sutra ceremony) is held is also called Hokke-do Hall (example: Hokke-do Hall of Todai-ji Temple, commonly known as &apos;Sangatsu-do&apos;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Buddhist temple in which Hokke-e (Lotus Sutra ceremony) is held is also called Hokke-do Hall (example: Hokke-do Hall of Todai-ji Temple, commonly known as &apos;Sangatsu-do&apos;).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Buddhist temple in which Hokke-e (Lotus Sutra ceremony) is held is also called Hokke-do Hall (example: Hokke-do Hall of Todai-ji Temple, commonly known as &apos;Sangatsu-do&apos;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>法華三昧は、天台宗における四種三昧の1つである半行半坐三昧のうち、法華経に基づいて行われるもので37日間行われる行である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hokkezanmai is a Hangyo hanza sanmai (religious austerities with concentration, which combines standing-style one and sitting-style one), one of Shishuzanmai (the Four kinds of samadhi) in Tendai-shu sect, that is based on Hoke-kyo Sutra and performed for 73 days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hokkezanmai is a Hangyo hanza sanmai (religious austerities with concentration, which combines a standing-style one and a sitting-style one), one of Shishuzanmai (the Four kinds of samadhi) in Tendai-shu sect, that is based on Hoke-kyo Sutra and performed for 73 days.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hokkezanmai is a Hangyo hanza sanmai (religious austerities with concentration, which combines a standing-style one and a sitting-style one), one of Shishuzanmai (the Four kinds of samadhi) in Tendai-shu sect, that is based on Hoke-kyo Sutra and performed for 37 days.</e>
<cmt>73を37に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>その後、法華堂は皇族や貴族などの墓所などに立てられる堂を指すようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Hokke-do became to mean a hall that is build in graveyard of imperial familes and nobles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Hokke-do changed to mean a hall that is built in graveyards of imperial families and nobles.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Hokke-do changed to mean a hall that is built in graveyards of the Imperial family and nobility.</e>
<cmt>imperial families and noblesをthe Imperial family and nobilityに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 与左衛門(id:159462), ウィキ豊(id:82961), くっちゃめ(id:86793), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>