<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>善珠</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zenshu (Zenju)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zenshu (Zenju)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zenshu</e>
<cmt>タイトルなので前者の読みを採用しました。次行の説明で読み補足しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>善珠（ぜんしゅ・ぜんじゅ、養老7年（723年） - 延暦16年4月21日 (旧暦)（797年5月25日））は、奈良時代から平安時代前期にかけての僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zenshu (Zenju) (723-May 25, 797) was a Buddhist priest who lived from the Nara period to the beginning of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zenshu (Zenju) (723 - May 25, 797) was a Buddhist priest who lived from the Nara period to the beginning of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zenshu (also known as Zenju, 723 - May 25, 797) was a Buddhist priest who lived from the Nara period to the beginning of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>(also known as Zenju, 723 - May 25, 797)補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>俗姓は阿刀氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His secular surname was Ato.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His secular surname was Ato.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His secular surname was Ato.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>大和国の出身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>秋篠寺の開基とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that he founded the Akishino-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that he founded Akishino-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that he founded Akishino-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>法相六祖の１人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was one of the Hosso Rokuso (Six High Priests of the Hosso Sect).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was one of the Hosso Rokuso (Six High Priests of the Hosso Sect).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was one of the Hosso Rokuso (Six High Priests of the Hosso Sect).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>玄ボウに師事して法相宗・因明に通じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zenshu studied under Genbo, then he became expert of the Inmyo (Buddhist logic) of the Hosso (Dharma Characteristics) school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zenshu studied under Genbo, and later he acquired expertise in Inmyo (Buddhist logic) of the Hosso (Dharma Characteristics) school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zenshu studied under Genbo, and later he acquired expertise in Inmyo (Buddhist logic) of the Hosso (Dharma Characteristics) school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>793年（延暦12年）比叡山文殊堂供養の堂達を、翌794年（延暦13年）には延暦寺根本中堂落慶の導師をつとめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 793, he was assigned as the chief priest of the kuyo (a memorial service for the dead) at the Monju-do Hall on Mt. Hiei, and in 794 the next year, he conducted the completion ceremony of the Enryaku-ji Temple Konpon-chudo Hall as the doshi (head priest).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 793, he was assigned as the chief priest of the kuyo (a memorial service for the dead) at Monju-do Hall on Mt. Hiei, and the following year he conducted the completion ceremony of Enryaku-ji Temple&apos;s Konpon-chudo Hall as the doshi (head priest).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 793, he was assigned as the chief priest of the kuyo (a memorial service for the dead) at Monju-do Hall on Mt. Hiei, and the following year, in 794, he conducted the completion ceremony of Enryaku-ji Temple&apos;s Konpon-chudo Hall as the doshi (head priest).</e>
<cmt>in 794補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>796年（延暦15年）には桓武天皇の命により故物部古麻呂のための法華経供養の導師をつとめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 796, he conducted the memorial ceremony with the Hokekyo (Lotus Sutra) for late MONONOBE no Komaro held by a command of Emperor Kammu, as the doshi (head priest).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 796, as the doshi (head priest), he conducted the memorial ceremony with the Hokekyo (Lotus Sutra) for the late MONONOBE no Komaro held at the command of Emperor Kammu.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 796, as the doshi (head priest), he conducted the memorial ceremony with the Hokekyo (Lotus Sutra) for the late MONONOBE no Komaro held at the command of Emperor Kammu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>797年（延暦16年）には皇太子安殿親王（後の平城天皇）の病気平癒祈願の功により僧正に任じられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 797, he was assigned as the sojo (the official Buddhist priest in the highest position) due to his achievement in playing for cure of the disease of the Imperial Prince Ate (Emperor Heizei).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 797, he was assigned as the sojo (the official Buddhist priest in the highest position) due to his achievement in praying for the cure of the disease that had afflicted Imperial Prince Ate (Emperor Heizei).</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 797, he was assigned as the sojo (the official Buddhist priest in the highest position) due to his achievement in praying for the cure of the disease that had afflicted Imperial Prince Ate (Emperor Heizei).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その後間もなくして75歳で没。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shortly after that, he died at the age of 75.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shortly after that, he died at the age of 75.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shortly after that, he died at the age of 75.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>奈良仏教の歴史の上で有数の著述家で、『唯識義燈増明記』・『唯識分量決』など20余りの著作が残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was one of foremost writers in the history of the Nara Buddhism, and he left more than 20 literary works such as &quot;Yuishikigi tozomyoki&quot; (an annotation of Buddhist scriptures) and &quot;Yuishiki bunryo ketsu.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was one of foremost writers in the history of Nara Buddhism, and he left more than 20 literary works such as &quot;Yuishikigi tozomyoki&quot; (an annotation of Buddhist scriptures) and &quot;Yuishiki bunryo ketsu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was one of foremost writers in the history of Nara Buddhism, and he left more than 20 literary works such as &quot;Yuishikigi tozomyoki&quot; (an annotation of Buddhist scriptures) and &quot;Yuishiki bunryo ketsu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MIO(id:31681), Ha～Ha(id:36403), R28Bot(id:177951), 松茸(id:27535), Dream100(id:41924), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>