<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>正法寺 (京都市東山区)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shobo-ji Temple (Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shobo-ji Temple (Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shobo-ji Temple (Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>正法寺（しょうぼうじ）は、京都市東山区にある時宗の寺院。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shobo-ji Temple is a temple of Ji sect, which is located in Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shobo-ji Temple, located in Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City, is a temple of the Ji sect.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shobo-ji Temple, located in Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City, is a temple of the Ji sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>山号は霊山（りょうざん）または霊鷲山。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its sango (literally, &quot;mountain name&quot;), which is the title prefixed to the name of a Buddhist temple, is Ryozan or Ryojusen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its sango (literally, &quot;mountain name&quot;), which is the title prefixed to the name of a Buddhist temple, is Ryozan or Ryojusen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its sango (literally, &quot;mountain name&quot;), which is the title prefixed to the name of a Buddhist temple, is Ryozan or Ryojusen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>院号は無量寿院。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its title given to a Buddhist temple is Muryoju-in Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its title given to a Buddhist temple is Muryoju-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its ingo, title given to a Buddhist temple, is Muryoju-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>用語を統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>本尊は釈迦如来。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its honzon (principal image of Buddha) is Shaka Nyorai (Shakyamuni).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its honzon (principal image of Buddha) is Shaka Nyorai (Shakyamuni).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its honzon (principal image of Buddha) is Shaka Nyorai (Shakyamuni).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>この寺は、最澄の開山により創建された天台宗の寺院に始まると伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said to have started as a temple of Tendai Sect, which was built by Saicho, the kaisan (a founder of temple as the first chief priest).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said to have originated as a temple of the Tendai sect, having been built by Saicho, the kaisan (a founder of temple as the first chief priest).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said to have originated as a temple of the Tendai sect, having been built by Saicho, the kaisan (a founder of temple as the first chief priest).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>はじめは霊山寺と称し、光孝天皇・宇多天皇の勅願所となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, it was called Ryosen-ji Temple and became the place of imperial prayer for Emperor Koko and Emperor Uda.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially it was called Ryosen-ji Temple and became the place of imperial prayer for the emperors Koko and Uda.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially it was called Ryosen-ji Temple and became the place of imperial prayer for the emperors Koko and Uda.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>鎌倉時代初期には法然がこの寺で別時念仏を修したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that Honen learned Betsuji Nenbutsu in this temple in the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that Honen studied Betsuji Nenbutsu in this temple during the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that Honen studied Betsuji Nenbutsu in this temple during the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その後荒廃していたが、1383年（永徳3年）に時宗の僧国阿が再興して正法寺と改め時宗の寺院となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that it was ruined, but as Kokua, a monk of Ji sect, revived this temple in 1383, its name was changed to Shobo-ji Temple and it became a temple of Ji sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently it was ruined, but when Kokua, a monk of the Ji sect, revived the temple in 1383, it came under the Ji sect and was renamed at Shobo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently it was ruined, but when Kokua, a monk of the Ji sect, revived the temple in 1383, it came under the Ji sect and was renamed at Shobo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>室町幕府3代将軍足利義満の帰依を受け寺運は興隆した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The temple&apos;s fortune rose by accepting the conversion of Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, the third shogun of the Muromachi bakufu, to Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The temple&apos;s fortune rose by accepting the conversion of Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, the third shogun of the Muromachi bakufu, to Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The temple&apos;s fortune rose by accepting the conversion of Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, the third shogun of the Muromachi bakufu, to Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>江戸時代には江戸幕府から朱印状を与えられ、塔頭十余宇を有したが、明治以降衰退し、現在は本堂（釈迦堂）・庫裏などを残すのみとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period, it was given Shuinjo (shogunate license to trade) by the Edo bakufu and had around 10 tatchu (sub-temples in the site of main temple); however, it has come to decline since Meiji period, and accordingly, today it only has a Hondo (Shaka-do Hall), Kuri (the priest&apos;s living quarters or the kitchen of a temple), etc.</e>
<cmt>「余宇」の意味が調べきれませんでした。「10程の」という解釈を致しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period, it was given Shuinjo (shogunate license to conduct trade) by the Edo bakufu and had approximately ten tatchu (sub-temples on the site of the main temple); however, it has declined since the Meiji period, and today it has only a hondo (Shaka-do Hall) and a kuri (the priest&apos;s living quarters or the kitchen of a temple), etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period, it was given Shuinjo (shogunate license to conduct trade) by the Edo bakufu and had approximately ten tatchu (sub-temples on the site of the main temple); however, it has declined since the Meiji period, and today it has only a hondo (Shaka-do Hall) and a kuri (the priest&apos;s living quarters or the kitchen of a temple), etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>また、当時正法寺で授けたお札は「柏のお札」といって柏の葉の形の中に「伊勢熊野参詣輩」「許永代汚穢」（永代の汚穢を許す）の文言が刷られていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Ofuda (paper charms) provided at Shobo-ji Temple at that time were called &quot;Ofuda of Kashiwa Oak&quot; whose shape was a leaf of Kashiwa Oak, and words, such as &quot;伊勢熊野参詣輩&quot; (visit to Ise and Kumano) and &quot;許永代汚穢&quot; (forgive the impurity of Eitai), were printed on Ofuda.</e>
<cmt>「伊勢熊野参詣輩」の「輩」をどう訳すべきか判断できませんでした。ここの（）内の英語の説明上では「輩」は無視しております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, the Ofuda (paper charms) provided at Shobo-ji Temple at that time were called &quot;Ofuda of Kashiwa Oak,&quot; whose shape was that of a Kashiwa oak leaf, and words, such as &quot;伊勢熊野参詣輩&quot; (visit to Ise and Kumano) and &quot;許永代汚穢&quot; (forgive the impurity of Eitai), were printed on the Ofuda.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, the Ofuda (paper charms) provided at Shobo-ji Temple at that time were called &apos;Ofuda of Kashiwa Oak,&apos; whose shape was that of a Kashiwa oak leaf, and words, such as &apos;伊勢熊野参詣輩&apos; (visit to Ise and Kumano) and &apos;許永代汚穢&apos; (forgive the impurity of Eitai), were printed on the Ofuda.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>所在地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Address</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Address</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Address</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>京都府京都市東山区清閑寺霊山町35</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">35 Seikanji Ryozan-cho, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">35 Seikanji Ryozan-cho, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">35 Seikanji Ryozan-cho, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Oochin(id:201280), 与左衛門(id:159462), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>