<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>行慶</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gyokei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gyokei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gyokei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>行慶（ぎょうけい、生年不詳 - 永万元年7月16日 (旧暦)（1165年8月24日））は、平安時代後期の天台宗の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gyokei (year of birth unknown-August 31, 1165) was a priest of Tendai Sect in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>「永万元年7月16日 (旧暦)」＝グレゴリオ暦「西暦1165年8月31日」、出典：http://maechan.net/kanreki</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gyokei (year of birth unknown-August 31, 1165) was a priest of the Tendai sect in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Tendai&quot;; made &quot;Sect&quot; lowercase for consistency with other articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gyokei (year of birth unknown-August 31, 1165) was a priest of the Tendai sect in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は白河天皇。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Emperor Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Emperor Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Emperor Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は備中守源政長の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of Bicchu no kami (governor of Bicchu Province) MINAMOTO no Masanaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was the daughter of MINAMOTO no Masanaga who was the Bicchu no Kami (governor of the Bicchu Province).</e>
<cmt>Rearranged sentece to read more smoothly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was the daughter of MINAMOTO no Masanaga who was the Bicchu no Kami (governor of the Bicchu Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>狛僧正・桜井僧正とも称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also called Kashiwa Sojo or Sakurai Sojo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also called Kashiwa Sojo and Sakurai Sojo.</e>
<cmt>&quot;and&quot; seems more appropriate then &quot;or&quot; here</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also called &quot;Koma Sojo&quot; and &quot;Sakurai Sojo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Kashiwa Sojo を&quot;Koma Sojo&quot; に修正しました。定訳不明ですが、kashiwa （柏）でないことはたしかだと思われます。「狛」の読み（こま）は以下のリンクページを参照しました。http://www.cantonese.jp/pages/search_c/%E7%8B%9BSakurai Sojo にダブルクォーテーションを追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>出家して園城寺に住し、1128年（大治 (日本)3年）には大僧正に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became a priest and lived in Onjo-ji Temple, and in 1128 he was appointed Daisojo (a Buddhist priest of the highest order).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gyokei became a priest living in the Onjo-Temple and was appointed to Daisojo (a Buddhist priest of the highest order) in 1128.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;He&quot; to &quot;Gyokei&quot; since this is the beginning of a paragraph; rearranged the sentence to read more smoothly; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gyokei became a priest living in the Onjo-ji Temple and was appointed to Daisojo (a Buddhist priest of the highest order) in 1128.</e>
<cmt>Onjo-Temple を Onjo-ji Temple に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その後、1135年（保延元年）に四天王寺別当、1152年（仁平2年）には園城寺長吏に任じられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward, he was appointed the steward of Shitenno-ji Temple in 1135 and Chori (chief priest) of Onjo-ji Temple in 1152.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, he was appointed as the steward of the Shitenno-ji Temple in 1135 and the Chori (chief priest) of the Onjo-ji Temple in 1152.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Subsequently&quot; seems more natural here as &quot;Afterward&quot; is a little ambiguous</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, he was appointed as the Shitenno-ji betto (the head priest of Shitenno-ji Temple) in 1135 and the Chori (chief priest) of the Onjo-ji Temple in 1152.</e>
<cmt>別当the steward of the Shitenno-ji Temple をShitenno-ji betto (the head priest of Shitenno-ji Temple) に修正しました（※）。※ steward 「管財人」の意味で使用していると思われますが、同じ訳語を掲載しているサイトの中に &quot;head of institution, esp., religious&quot;という記載もあります。よって、steward よりも head priest の方が適訳と判断しました。 http://tangorin.com/words/別当</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>近衛天皇・後白河天皇・二条天皇の三代に亘って天皇の護持僧となるが、特に後白河院の信任が厚かったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served three generations of Emperor Konoe, Emperor Goshirakawa and Emperor Nijo as Gojiso (a priest who prays to guard the emperor) and is considered to have been highly trusted especially by Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gyokei served three periods of emperors, including Emperor Konoe, Emperor Goshirakawa and Emperor Nijo as a Gojiso (a priest who prays to guard the emperor) and is said to have been particularly highly trusted by Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>three generations→three periods of emperors; fixed grammar to read more smoothly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gyokei served three periods of emperors, including Emperor Konoe, Emperor Goshirakawa and Emperor Nijo as a Gojiso (a priest who prays to guard the emperor) and is said to have been particularly highly trusted by Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、藤原忠通が出家する際、御戒師を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, he served as precepts priest when FUJIWARA no Tadamichi entered into priesthood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, he served as a precepts priest when FUJIWARA no Tadamichi entered into the priesthood.</e>
<cmt>Also→Additionally; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, he served as a precepts priest when FUJIWARA no Tadamichi entered into the priesthood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Masyu(id:31065), Snap55(id:89773), たね(id:10372), BAKU(id:55205), 代言人(id:33675), R28Bot(id:177951), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>