<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>安土宗論</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Azuchi Shuron</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Azuchi Shuron</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Azuchi Shuron</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>安土宗論（あづちしゅうろん）とは、、安土城下の浄厳院で行われた浄土宗と法華宗（日蓮宗）の宗論。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Azuchi Shuron was a religious debate waged between the Jodo sect and the Hokke sect at Jogonin Temple in the town of the Azuchi castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Azuchi Shuron was a religious debate waged between the Jodo sect and the Hokke sect at Jogonin Temple in the town of Azuchi castle.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Azuchi Shuron was a religious debate waged between the Jodoshu sect and the Hokkeshu sect (Nichirenshu sect) at Jogon-in Temple in the town of Azuchi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>（日蓮宗）→訳漏れのため訳出、統一事項より、Jodoshu sect、Hokkeshu sect、Jogon-in Temple、Azuchi-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>安土問答とも称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also referred to as Azuchi Mondo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also referred to as Azuchi Mondo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also referred to as Azuchi Mondo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>信長の命により、浄土宗の僧貞安・霊誉らと、日蓮僧日珖・日諦・日雄（後に日淵と改名）らの間で行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the command of Nobunaga, the debate took place between the Jodo sect monks Teian (also known as Joan), Reiyo, and others, and the Nichiren sect monks Nichiko, Nittai, Nichiyuu (later renamed Nichien.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the command of Nobunaga, the debate took place between the Jodo sect monks Teian (also known as Joan), Reiyo, and others, and the Nichiren sect monks Nichiko, Nittai, and Nichiyuu (later renamed Nichien.)</e>
<cmt>conjunction</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the command of Nobunaga, the debate took place between the Jodoshu sect monks Teian (also known as Joan), Reiyo, and others, and the Nichirenshu sect monks Nichiko, Nittai, and Nichiyu (later renamed Nichien).</e>
<cmt>Nichiyuu→Nichiyuに修正、Jodoshu sect、Nishirenshu sectとし、ピリオドの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>しかし、これは当時、京都を中心に勢力を伸ばし他宗と衝突を繰り返していた日蓮宗を抑制するために、織田信長が仕掛けたとされ、信長は浄土宗側に加担したともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Nobunaga ODA engineered the debate to suppress the Nichiren sect that repeated conflicts with other sects, extending its influence centering around Kyoto in those days, and that Nobunaga supported the Jodo sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Nobunaga ODA engineered the debate to suppress the Nichiren sect, which started repeated conflicts with other sects, extending its influence centering around Kyoto in those days, and that Nobunaga supported the Jodo sect.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Nobunaga ODA engineered the debate to suppress the Nichirenshu sect, which started repeated conflicts with other sects, extending its influence centering around Kyoto in those days, and that Nobunaga supported the Jodoshu sect.</e>
<cmt>Jodoshu sect、Nishirenshu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>詳細は後述する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The details will be described later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The details will be described later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The details will be described later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>なお日蓮宗は敗れて処罰者を出し、以後他宗への法論を行わないことを誓わされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nichiren sect was defeated and some monks were executed, and the sect was forced to take the oath never to challenge other sects to a religious debate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nichiren sect was defeated and some monks were executed, and the sect was forced to take the oath never to challenge other sects to a religious debate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nichirenshu sect was defeated and some monks were executed, and the sect was forced to take the oath never to challenge other sects to a religious debate.</e>
<cmt>Nishirenshu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>宗論の契機</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cause of the debate</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cause of the debate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cause of the debate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>信長公記などによると、5月中旬、関東の浄土宗の霊誉玉念（れいよぎょくねん）という長老が上方へ出てきて安土の町で説法をしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the chronicle of Nobunaga &apos;Nobunaga Koki&apos;, an elder Jodo sect monk Reiyo Gyokunen came from the Kanto region, eastern Japan, up to Kamigata region, Kyoto-Osaka area, during the middle of May and preached the Jodo sect Buddhism in the town of Azuchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the chronicle of Nobunaga &apos;Nobunaga Koki&apos;, an elder Jodo sect monk Reiyo Gyokunen came from the Kanto region, eastern Japan, up to the Kamigata region, the Kyoto-Osaka area, during the middle of May and preached Jodo sect Buddhism in the town of Azuchi.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the chronicle of Nobunaga, Nobunaga Koki, an elder Jodoshu sect monk Reiyo Gyokunen came from the Kanto region, eastern Japan, up to the Kamigata region, the Kyoto-Osaka area, during the middle of May and preached Jodoshu sect Buddhism in the town of Azuchi.</e>
<cmt>Nobunaga Kokiのクォーテーション削除、カンマ追加、Jodoshu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>そこに法華宗の建部紹智と大脇伝介が議論をふっかけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There came Shochi TAKEBE and Densuke OOWAKI, and challenged Reiyo to an argument.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There came Shochi TAKEBE and Densuke OOWAKI, who challenged Reiyo to an argument.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There came Shochi TAKEBE and Densuke OWAKI, who challenged Reiyo to an argument.</e>
<cmt>OOWAKI→OWAKIに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>霊誉長老は以下のように答えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The elder monk Reiyo answered, &apos;If I answer you now, you, young fellows, cannot understand the deep idea of dhamma.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The elder monk Reiyo answered, &apos;If I answer you now, you, being young fellows, cannot understand the deep idea of dhamma.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;being&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The elder monk Reiyo answered as follows:</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」split sampleに基づき原文･訳文を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>「年若い方々に申し開きをいたしましても、仏法の奥深いところは御理解できますまい。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When you take the Hokke sect monk you can trust, I will answer the question.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When you take along a Hokke sect monk you can trust, I will answer the question.&apos;</e>
<cmt>added &quot;along&quot;, article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If I answer you now, you, being young fellows, cannot understand the deep idea of dhamma.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>「お二人がこれぞと思う法華宗のお坊様をお連れ下されば、御返答しましょう。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When you take along a Hokkeshu sect monk you can trust, I will answer the question.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」Hokkeshu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>説法の期間は7日の予定だったが、11日に延長して法華宗の方へ使者を出させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reiyo originally set seven days for his preaching, but now he extended the period to eleven days and sent a messenger to the Hokke sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reiyo originally set seven days for his preaching, but he then extended the period to eleven days and sent a messenger to the Hokke sect.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reiyo originally set seven days for his preaching, but he then extended the period to eleven days and sent a messenger to the Hokkeshu sect.</e>
<cmt>Hokkeshu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>法華宗の方も、では宗論をやろうと京都の頂妙寺の日珖、常光院の日諦、久遠院の日淵、妙顕寺の大蔵坊、境の油屋の当主の弟で、妙国寺の僧普伝という歴々の僧たちが来ることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hokke sect accepted the plan of debate and sent distinguished monks of Nichiko from Chomyoji Temple, Nittai form Jokoin Temple, Nichien from Kuonin Temple, and Daizobo from Myokenji Temple in Kyoto, and a monk Fuden, who was a younger brother of the then shopowner of a wholesale dealer in oil, from Myokokuji Temple in Sakai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hokke sect accepted the plan of debate and sent distinguished monks of Nichiko from Chomyoji Temple, Nittai from Jokoin Temple, Nichien from Kuonin Temple, and Daizobo from Myokenji Temple in Kyoto, and a monk Fuden, who was the younger brother of the then shopowner of a wholesale dealer in oil, from Myokokuji Temple in Sakai.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hokkeshu sect accepted the plan of debate and sent distinguished monks of Nichiko from Chomyo-ji Temple, Nittai from Joko-in Temple, Nichien from Kuon-in Temple, and Daizobo from Myoken-ji Temple in Kyoto, and a monk Fuden, who was the younger brother of the then shopowner of a wholesale dealer in oil, from Myokoku-ji Temple in Sakai.</e>
<cmt>Hokkeshu sect、Chomyo-ji Temple、Joko-in Temple、Kuon-in Temple、Myoken-ji Temple、Myokoku-ji Templeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>そしてこの噂が広まり、京都・安土内外の僧俗が安土に集まると騒ぎは大きくなり、信長も伝え聞く事になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This rumor spread widely and monks and seculars gathered from inside and outside the town of Azuchi in Kyoto and made an uproar, which was eventually known to Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This rumor spread widely and monks and seculars gathered from inside and outside the town of Azuchi in Kyoto and made an uproar, which eventually became known to Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This rumor spread widely and monks and seculars gathered from inside and outside of Kyoto and Azuchi and made an uproar, which eventually became known to Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>「京都の安土内外」ではなく、「京都や安土内外」の意味と思われるため、inside and outside the town of Azuchi in Kyoto→inside and outside of Kyoto and Azuchiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>信長は「当家の家臣にも法華の宗徒は大勢いるので、信長の考えで斡旋をするから、大げさなことはせぬように」と、菅谷長頼・矢部家定・堀秀政・長谷川秀一らを使者として両宗に伝えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga sent Nagayori SUGAYA, Iesada YABE, Hidemasa HORI, and Hidekazu HASEGAWA as messengers to the both sects to give a message that &apos;As a large number of retainers of the Oda family are Hokke followers and I&apos;m ready to use my influence, so, do not be belligerent.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga sent Nagayori SUGAYA, Iesada YABE, Hidemasa HORI, and Hidekazu HASEGAWA as messengers to both sects to give a message that &apos;As a large number of retainers of the Oda family are Hokke followers and I&apos;m ready to use my influence, do not be belligerent.&apos;</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;so&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga sent Nagayori SUGAYA, Iesada YABE, Hidemasa HORI, and Hidekazu HASEGAWA as messengers to both sects to give a message that &apos;As a large number of retainers of the Oda family are Hokke followers and I&apos;m ready to use my influence, do not be belligerent.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし、浄土宗側ではどのような指示でも信長に従うと返答したが、法華宗側は勝つ見込みで奢っていたため承諾せず、ついに宗論をすることになってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Jodo sect answered that they would follow Nobunaga&apos;s command, but on the other hand, the Hokke sect was arrogant enough to think that they would win the debate and did not accept the Nobunaga&apos;s arbitration; therefore, the two sects were to engage in the debate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Jodo sect answered that they would follow Nobunaga&apos;s command, but on the other hand, the Hokke sect was arrogant enough to think that they would win the debate and did not accept Nobunaga&apos;s arbitration; therefore, the two sects were to engage in the debate.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Jodoshu sect answered that they would follow Nobunaga&apos;s command, but on the other hand, the Hokkeshu sect was arrogant enough to think that they would win the debate and did not accept Nobunaga&apos;s arbitration; therefore, the two sects were to engage in the debate.</e>
<cmt>Jodoshu sect、Hokkeshu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>そこで信長は「それなら審判者を派遣するから、経過を書類にして勝負の経過を報告せよ」と申し、京都五山のうちでも指折りの博学で評判の、日野に住む南禅寺の長老・景秀鉄叟（けいしゅうてつそう）を審判者に招いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Nobunaga commanded &apos;Therefore, I will send a judge. Make a document on the development of the debate and report it to me&apos;, and asked an elder monk Keishu Tetsusso in Nanzenji Temple lived in Hino who was renowned for his prominent knowledge among the five great Zen temples of Kyoto known as &apos;Kyoto Gozan.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Nobunaga commanded &apos;Therefore, I will send a judge. Make a document on the development of the debate and report it to me&apos;, and asked an elder monk, Keishu Tetsusso in Nanzenji Temple, who lived in Hino and was renowned for his prominent knowledge among the five great Zen temples of Kyoto known as &apos;Kyoto Gozan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Nobunaga commanded &apos;Therefore, I will send a judge. Make a document on the development of the debate and report it to me,&apos; and asked an elder monk, Keishu Tetsuso in Nanzen-ji Temple, who lived in Hino and was renowned for his prominent knowledge among the five great Zen temples of Kyoto known as &apos;Kyoto Gozan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去、カンマの位置を移動、Tetsusso→Tetsuso、Nanzen-ji Templeに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>そして折り良く因果居士（いんがこじ）が安土に来ていたので、彼も審判に加えて、安土の町外れにある浄土宗の寺浄厳院の仏殿において宗論を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a monk Ingakoji was timely staying in Azuchi, Nobunaga added him as the judge and let them debate in the main hall of Jogonin Temple, which was a Jodo sect temple located in outside the town of Azuchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a monk Ingakoji was staying in Azuchi at the time, Nobunaga added him as the judge and let them debate in the main hall of Jogonin Temple, which was a Jodo sect temple located outside the town of Azuchi.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a monk Ingakoji was staying in Azuchi at the time, Nobunaga added him as the judge and let them debate in the main hall of Jogon-in Temple, which was a Jodoshu sect temple located outside the town of Azuchi.</e>
<cmt>Jogon-in Temple、Jodoshu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>寺内の警備に、織田信澄・菅谷長頼・矢部家定・堀秀政・長谷川秀一の5人が派遣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga sent his five retainers Nobuzumi ODA, Nagayori SUGAYA, Iesada YABE, Hidemasa HORI, and Hidekazu HASEGAWA for guarding inside the temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga sent his five retainers Nobuzumi ODA, Nagayori SUGAYA, Iesada YABE, Hidemasa HORI, and Hidekazu HASEGAWA to guard inside the temple.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga sent his five retainers Nobuzumi ODA, Nagayori SUGAYA, Iesada YABE, Hidemasa HORI, and Hidekazu HASEGAWA to guard inside the temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>法華宗側はきらびやかな法衣を着飾り、頂妙寺日珖、常光院日諦、久遠院日淵、妙国寺普伝、そして妙顕寺の大蔵坊の5人が記録係として、法華経八巻と筆記用具を持って登場。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the Hokke sect, gorgeously attired five monks Chomyoji Nichiko, Jokoin Nittai, Kuonin Nichien, Myokokuji Fuden, and Myokenji Daizobo attended as clerks with eight volumes of the sutra Hokkekyo and writing tools.</e>
<cmt>「そして妙顕寺の大蔵坊の5人が記録係として、」は「そして妙顕寺の大蔵坊が記録係として、計5人が」の誤りと思われますが、原文通りに訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the Hokke sect, five gorgeously attired monks Chomyoji Nichiko, Jokoin Nittai, Kuonin Nichien, Myokokuji Fuden, and Myokenji Daizobo attended as clerks with eight volumes of the sutra Hokkekyo and writing tools.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the Hokkeshu sect, five gorgeously attired monks Nichiko from Chomyo-ji Temple, Nittai from Joko-in Temple, Nichien from Kuon-in Temple, Fuden from Myokoku-ji Temple, and Daizobo from Myoken-ji Temple attended as clerks with eight volumes of the sutra Hokkekyo and writing tools.</e>
<cmt>Hokkeshu sectとし、「頂妙寺日珖」「常光院日諦」「久遠院日淵」「妙国寺普伝」「妙顕寺の大蔵坊」の表記を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>浄土宗側は、黒染めの衣で、質素ないでたち、関東の霊誉と、安土田中の西光寺の聖誉・貞安（せいよていあん）、信誉洞庫、知恩院助念の4人が筆記用具を持って登場。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the Jodo sect, four monks in simple black robes, Reiyo from Kanto region, Seiyo Teian from Saikoji Temple in Azuchitanaka, Shinyo Doko, and Chionin Jonen appeared with writing tools.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the Jodo sect, four monks in simple black robes, Reiyo from the Kanto region, Seiyo Teian from Saikoji Temple in Azuchitanaka, Shinyo Doko, and Chionin Jonen appeared with writing tools.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the Jodoshu sect, four monks in simple black robes, Reiyo from the Kanto region, Seiyo Teian from Saiko-ji Temple in Azuchitanaka, Shinyo Doko, and Chionin Jonen appeared with writing tools.</e>
<cmt>Jodoshu sect、Saiko-ji Templeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>法論の出席者は以下の通り。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The present company of the debate is shown below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The present company of the debate is shown below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The present company of the debate is shown below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="23">
<j>浄土宗側―霊誉玉念･聖誉定(貞)安(西光寺)･信誉洞庫(正福寺)・知恩院助念（記録者）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jodo sect: Reiyo Gyokunen, Seiyo Teian from Saikoji Temple, Shinyo Doko from Shofukuji Temple, and Chionin Jonen from Kuonin Temple as a clerk</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jodo sect: Reiyo Gyokunen, Seiyo Teian from Saikoji Temple, Shinyo Doko from Shofukuji Temple, and Chionin Jonen from Kuonin Temple serving as clerks</e>
<cmt>added &quot;serving, plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jodoshu sect: Reiyo Gyokunen, Seiyo Teian from Saiko-ji Temple, Shinyo Doko from Shofuku-ji Temple, and Chionin Jonen (a recorder)</e>
<cmt>Jodoshu sectとし、from Kuonin Temple→原文にないため削除、serving as clerks→(a recorder)、Saiko-ji Temple、Shofuku-ji Temple、としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>法華宗側―常光院日諦・頂妙寺日珖・久遠院日淵･妙国寺普伝・久遠院大蔵坊（記録者）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hokke secret: Jokoin Nittai, Chomyoji Nichiko, Kuonin Nichien, Myokokuji Fuden, and Kuonin Daizobo as a clerk</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hokke secret: Jokoin Nittai, Chomyoji Nichiko, Kuonin Nichien, Myokokuji Fuden, and Kuonin Daizobo serving as clerks</e>
<cmt>added &quot;serving, plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hokkeshu sect: Nittai from Joko-in Temple, Nichiko from Chomyo-ji Temple, Nichien from Kuon-in Temple, Fuden from Myokoku-ji Temple, and Daizobo from Kuon-in Temple (a recorder)</e>
<cmt>Hokkeshu sectとし、secret→sectに修正、常光院日諦・頂妙寺日珖・久遠院日淵･妙国寺普伝・久遠院大蔵坊（記録者）の表記を修正しました。(*前出の文には「妙顕寺の大蔵坊」とあり、内容が矛盾しますが、あえてそのまま訳してあります)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>判定者―正明寺の鉄叟景秀・華渓正稷・因果居士・法隆寺仙覚坊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Judges: Tesso Keishu, Kakei Seishoku and Ingakoji from Shomyoji Temple, and Senkakubo from Horyuji Temple</e>
<cmt>「正稷」の読みが不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Judges: Tesso Keishu, Kakei Seishoku and Ingakoji from Shomyoji Temple, and Senkakubo from Horyuji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Judges: Tesso Keishu, Kakei Seishoku (正稷) and Ingakoji from Shomyo-ji Temple, and Senkakubo from Horyu-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>読み方不明のため、Seishoku (正稷)とし、Shomyo-ji Temple、Horyu-ji Templeに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>名代―津田信澄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobusumi ODA representing Nobunaga ODA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobusumi ODA representing Nobunaga ODA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobuzumi TSUDA (ODA) representing Nobunaga ODA</e>
<cmt>Nobusumi ODA→Nobuzumi TSUDA (ODA)としました。(参照: http://kotobank.jp/word/%E6%B4%A5%E7%94%B0%E4%BF%A1%E6%BE%84)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>奉行―菅谷長頼・堀秀政･長谷川秀一</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Magistrate: Nagayori HASE, Hidemasa HORI, and Hidekazu HASEGAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Magistrates: Nagayori HASE, Hidemasa HORI, and Hidekazu HASEGAWA</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Magistrates: Nagayori HASE, Hidemasa HORI, and Hidekazu HASEGAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>目付役―矢部家定･森成利</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Superintended officer: Iesada YABE, Naritoshi MORI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Superintending officers: Iesada YABE, Naritoshi MORI</e>
<cmt>word choice, plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Superintending officers: Iesada YABE, Naritoshi MORI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>法論の内容</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The contents of the debate</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The contents of the debate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The contents of the debate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>信長公記などによると法論の概要は以下の通り。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &apos;Nobunaga Koki&apos;, the debate is summarized as below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &apos;Nobunaga Koki&apos;, the debate is summarized as below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the Nobunaga Koki, the debate is summarized as below.</e>
<cmt>the Nobunaga Kokiとし、クォーテーション削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="30">
<j>霊誉「私が言い出したことなので、私から発言しましょう」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reiyo: As I proposed this debate, I will start the debate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reiyo: As I proposed this debate, I will start the debate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reiyo: As I proposed this debate, I will start the debate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>しかし、貞安はそれをさえぎって早口で問いを発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But Teian interrupted Reiyo and rapidly asked a question.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But Teian interrupted Reiyo and rapidly asked a question.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But Teian interrupted Reiyo and rapidly asked a question.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="32">
<j>貞安（浄土宗側）問う　法華八軸（8巻）の内に念仏はありや。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Teian (Jodo sect) asks: Do the eight volumes of the sutra Hokkekyo contain a Buddhist invocation &apos;Nenbutsu&apos;?</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Teian (Jodo sect) asks: Do the eight volumes of the sutra Hokkekyo contain a Buddhist invocation &apos;Nenbutsu&apos;?</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Teian (Jodo sect) asks: Do the eight volumes of the sutra Hokkekyo contain a Buddhist invocation &apos;Nenbutsu&apos;?</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="33">
<j>法華側答う　念仏あり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hokke sect answers: Yes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hokke sect answers: Yes.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hokkeshu sect answers: Yes.</e>
<cmt>Hokkeshu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="34">
<j>浄土側問う　念仏の義あらば、何ゆえ法華は念仏無間（日蓮が説いた四箇格言の一つ）地獄に落ちると説くや。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jodo sect asks: Although Hokke sect teaches &apos;Nenbutsu&apos;, why it preaches against &apos;Nenbutsu&apos; by saying that reciting of &apos;Nenbutsu&apos; makes people fall into the Hell of No Respite &apos;Nenbutsu Muken&apos;?--&apos;Nenbutsu Muken&apos; is one of the four dictums the founder Nichiren stated to denounce other sects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Jodo sect asks: Although the Hokke sect teaches &apos;Nenbutsu&apos;, why does it preach against &apos;Nenbutsu&apos; by saying that reciting of &apos;Nenbutsu&apos; makes people fall into the Hell of No Respite &apos;Nenbutsu Muken&apos;?--&apos;Nenbutsu Muken&apos; is one of the four dictums the founder Nichiren stated to denounce other sects.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Jodoshu sect asks: Although the Hokkeshu sect teaches &apos;Nenbutsu,&apos; why does it preach against &apos;Nenbutsu&apos; by saying that reciting of &apos;Nenbutsu&apos; makes people fall into the Hell of No Respite &apos;Nenbutsu Muken?&apos;--&apos;Nenbutsu Muken&apos; is one of the four dictums the founder Nichiren stated to denounce other sects.</e>
<cmt>Jodoshu sect、Hokkeshu sectとし、クォーテーションの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="35">
<j>法華側答う　法華の弥陀（阿弥陀如来）と浄土の弥陀とは一体や、別体や。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hokke sect asks: Is Amitabha the Hokke sect worships and Amitabha the Jodo sect worships are the same or different?</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hokke sect asks: Are Amitabha that the Hokke sect worships and Amitabha the the Jodo sect worships the same or different?</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hokkeshu sect asks: Are Amitabha that the Hokkeshu sect worships and Amitabha the the Jodoshu sect worships the same or different?</e>
<cmt>Hokkeshu sect、Jodoshu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="36">
<j>浄土側曰く　弥陀は何処にあろうと、弥陀一体なり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jodo sect says: Wherever Amitabha is, Amitabha is the same.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Jodo sect says: Wherever Amitabha is, Amitabha is the same.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Jodoshu sect says: Wherever Amitabha is, Amitabha is the same.</e>
<cmt>Jodoshu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="37">
<j>法華側答う　左様ならば、何ゆえ浄土門は法華の弥陀を「捨閉閣抛（しゃへいかくほう）」として捨てるや。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hokke sect asks: If it is true, why the Jodo sect denies Amitabha the Hokke sect worships by the word &apos;abandon it&apos;--&apos;Shaheikakuho&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hokke sect asks: If it is true, why does the Jodo sect deny Amitabha that the Hokke sect worships by the word &apos;abandon it&apos;--&apos;Shaheikakuho&apos;.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hokkeshu sect asks: If it is true, why does the Jodoshu sect deny Amitabha that the Hokkeshu sect worships by the word &apos;abandon it&apos;--&apos;Shaheikakuho.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Hokkeshu sect、Jodoshu sectとし、クォーテーションの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="38">
<j>浄土側曰く　それは念仏を捨てよというにあらず。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jodo sect says: That does not mean to abandon &apos;Nenbutsu&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Jodo sect says: That does not mean to abandon &apos;Nenbutsu&apos;</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Jodoshu sect says: That does not mean to abandon &apos;Nenbutsu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Jodoshu sectとし、ピリオド追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>念仏をする前に念仏の外の雑行を捨てよとの意なり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That means people should abandon all the wrong trainings before reciting &apos;Nenbutsu&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That means people should abandon all the wrong trainings before reciting &apos;Nenbutsu&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That means people should abandon all the wrong trainings before reciting &apos;Nenbutsu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="40">
<j>法華側答う　念仏をする前に法華を捨てよと言う経文はありや。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hokke sect asks: Is there any sentence in sutras saying &apos;abandon Hokke before you recite &apos;Nenbutsu&apos;?</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hokke sect asks: Is there any sentence in sutras saying &apos;abandon Hokke before you recite &apos;Nenbutsu&apos;?</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hokkeshu sect asks: Is there any sentence in sutras saying &apos;abandon Hokke before you recite &apos;Nenbutsu?&apos;</e>
<cmt>Hokkeshu sectとし、クォーテーションの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="41">
<j>浄土側曰く　法華を捨つるとの経文あり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jodo sect says: There is a sentence in a sutra saying &apos;abandon Hokke&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Jodo sect says: There is a sentence in a sutra saying &apos;abandon Hokke&apos;.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Jodoshu sect says: There is a sentence in a sutra saying &apos;abandon Hokke.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Jodoshu sectとし、クォーテーションの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>浄土経には善立方便顕示三乗とあり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the sutra Jodokyo, it is said that &apos;Zenritsu Hoben Kenji Sanjo&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the sutra Jodokyo, it is said &apos;Zenritsu Hoben Kenji Sanjo&apos;.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;that&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the sutra Jodokyo, it is said &apos;Zenritsu Hoben Kenji Sanjo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>また一向専念無量寿仏ともあり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that &apos;Ikko Sennen Muryojubutsu&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said &apos;Ikko Sennen Muryojubutsu&apos;.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;that&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said &apos;Ikko Sennen Muryojubutsu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="44">
<j>法華の無量義経には、以方便力、四十余年未顕真実とあり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sutra Hokkekyo says &apos;Iho Benryoku Shijuyonen Miken Shinjitsu&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sutra Hokkekyo says &apos;Iho Benryoku Shijuyonen Miken Shinjitsu&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sutra Hokkekyo says &apos;Iho Benryoku Shijuyonen Miken Shinjitsu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="45">
<j>浄土側曰く　釈尊が四十余年の修行をもって以前の経を捨つるなら、汝は方座第四の「妙」の一字を捨てるか、捨てざるか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jodo sect says: If Shakyamuni trained forty-odd years and abandoned the sutra he learned before, do you abandon a letter &apos;Myo&apos; of the fourth Hoza?</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Jodo sect says: If Shakyamuni trained forty-odd years and abandoned the sutra he learned before, do you abandon a letter &apos;Myo&apos; of the fourth Hoza?</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Jodoshu sect says: If Shakyamuni trained forty-odd years and abandoned the sutra he learned before, do you abandon a letter &apos;Myo&apos; of the fourth Hoza?</e>
<cmt>Jodoshu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="46">
<j>法華側答う　今言うは、四十余年の四妙中のいずれや。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hokke sect asks: Which Myo of the Shakyamuni&apos;s forty-odd years teachings do you mean?</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hokke sect asks: Which Myo of the Shakyamuni&apos;s forty-odd years teachings do you mean?</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hokkeshu sect asks: Which Myo of the Shakyamuni&apos;s forty-odd years teachings do you mean?</e>
<cmt>Hokkeshu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>（←40年余の説法のどこにある妙か？、ととぼけた）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Hokke sect pretended not to know which &apos;Myo&apos; is it in the Shakyamuni&apos;s forty-odd years teachings.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The Hokke sect pretended not to know which &apos;Myo&apos; is it in the Shakyamuni&apos;s forty-odd years teachings.)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The Hokkeshu sect pretended not to know which &apos;Myo&apos; is it in the Shakyamuni&apos;s forty-odd years teachings.)</e>
<cmt>Hokkeshu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="48">
<j>浄土側曰く　法華の妙よ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jodo sect says: It is &apos;Myo&apos; in Hokke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Jodo sect says: It is &apos;Myo&apos; in Hokke.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Jodoshu sect says: It is &apos;Myo&apos; in Hokke.</e>
<cmt>Jodoshu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>汝知らざるか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Don&apos;t play dumb.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Don&apos;t play dumb.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Don&apos;t play dumb.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="50">
<j>法華側返答なし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hokke sect does not answer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hokke sect does not answer.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hokkeshu sect did not answer.</e>
<cmt>Hokkeshu sectとし、does not→did notとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>閉口す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were silenced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were silenced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were silenced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="52">
<j>浄土側重ねて曰く　捨てるか、捨てざるか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jodo sect says: Do you abandon it or not?</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Jodo sect says: Do you abandon it or not?</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Jodoshu sect says: Do you abandon it or not?</e>
<cmt>Jodoshu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>重ねて問いしところ、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jodo sect asked again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Jodo sect asked again.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Jodoshu sect asked again.</e>
<cmt>Jodoshu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="54">
<j>法華側無言。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hokke sect kept silence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hokke sect kept silence.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hokkeshu sect kept silence.</e>
<cmt>Hokkeshu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>其の時、判者を始め満座一同どっと笑い、法華の袈裟を剥ぎ取る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All the attendants including the judges burst into laughter, and stripped the robes off the Hokke sect monks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All the attendants, including the judges, burst into laughter, and stripped the robes off the Hokke sect monks.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All the attendants, including the judges, burst into laughter, and stripped the robes off the Hokkeshu sect monks.</e>
<cmt>Hokkeshu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="56">
<j>天正七年己卯年五月二十七日辰刻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">8:00 am, July 1, 1579</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">8:00 am, July 1, 1579</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">8:00 am, July 1, 1579</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>宗論後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the debate</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the debate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the debate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="57">
<j>宗論が終った直後、頂妙寺の日珖は「妙」の一字に答えられず、群集に打擲され、法華八巻は破り捨てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Nichiko from Chomyoji Temple could not answer the question about the letter &apos;Myo&apos;, he was beaten by the crowd immediately after the debate, and the eight volumes of the sutra Hokkekyo they had carried were broken and thrown away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Nichiko from Chomyoji Temple could not answer the question about the letter &apos;Myo&apos;, he was beaten by the crowd immediately after the debate, and the eight volumes of the sutra Hokkekyo they had carried were broken and thrown away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Nichiko from Chomyo-ji Temple could not answer the question about the letter &apos;Myo,&apos; he was beaten by the crowd immediately after the debate, and the eight volumes of the sutra Hokkekyo they had carried were broken and thrown away.</e>
<cmt>Chomyo-ji Templeとし、カンマの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>法華宗の僧や宗徒たちは逃げ散ったが、これを織田信澄らが捕え、宗論の記録を信長の下へ届けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobuzumi ODA and others caught monks and followers of the Hokke sect who were trying to run away, and brought the record of the debate to Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobuzumi ODA and others caught monks and followers of the Hokke sect who were trying to run away, and brought the record of the debate to Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobuzumi ODA and others caught monks and followers of the Hokkeshu sect who were trying to run away, and brought the record of the debate to Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>Hokkeshu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>信長は時を移さず、安土から浄厳院へ出向き、法華宗・浄土宗の当事者を召し出して、霊誉と聖誉に扇と団扇を贈り、大いに褒め称えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga immediately left Azuchi and came to Jogonin Temple where he summoned the participants from both sects to his presence, admired and gave Reiyo and Seiyo a folding fun and a round fun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga immediately left Azuchi and came to Jogonin Temple where he summoned the participants from both sects to his presence, admired and gave Reiyo and Seiyo a folding fan and a round fan.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga immediately left Azuchi and came to Jogon-in Temple where he summoned the participants from both sects to his presence, admired and gave Reiyo and Seiyo a folding fan and a round fan.</e>
<cmt>Jogon-in Templeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>審判者の景秀鉄叟には杖を進呈した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To the judge Keishu Tetsusso, he presented a cane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To the judge Keishu Tetsusso, he presented a cane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To the judge Keishu Tetsuso, he presented a cane.</e>
<cmt>Tetsusso→Tetsusoに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="61">
<j>そして大脇伝介を召しだして、以下のように厳重に申し渡して真っ先に斬首した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Nobunaga called Densuke OOWAKI and rebuked him &apos;Even a ruler of a province or a region should not do such a shameful thing. You are merely a secular sault seller.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Nobunaga called Densuke OOWAKI and rebuked him &apos;Even a ruler of a province or a region should not do such a shameful thing. You are merely a secular sault seller.</e>
<cmt>I don&apos;t understand the intended meaning of &quot;sault.&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Nobunaga called Densuke OWAKI and immediately beheaded him after rebuking him as follows:</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」split sampleに基づき、原文･訳文を修正しました。OOWAKI→OWAKIに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>「一国一群を支配する身分でもすべきことではないのに、お前は俗人の塩売りの町人ではないか。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, you provided a lodging for the elder monk Reiyo, but did not support him, instead, you were tempted by someone to challenge Reiyo to a debate and made an uproar inside and outside of Kyoto and Azuchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, you provided lodging for the elder monk Reiyo, but did not support him; instead, you were tempted by someone to challenge Reiyo to a debate and made an uproar inside and outside of Kyoto and Azuchi.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even a ruler of a province or a region should not do such a shameful thing; you are merely a secular salt seller.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」sault→saltに修正、ピリオド→セミコロンに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>「この度は霊誉長老の宿を引き受けたにもかかわらず、長老の応援もせず、人にそそのかされて問答を挑み、京都・安土内外に騒動を起こした。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You are inexcusable&apos;, and immediately beheaded him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You are inexcusable&apos;, and immediately beheaded him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, you provided lodging for the elder monk Reiyo, but did not support him; instead, you were tempted by someone to challenge Reiyo to a debate and made an uproar inside and outside of Kyoto and Azuchi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>「不届きである。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You are inexcusable.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="65">
<j>また、普伝を召しだして普伝の業績を問いただした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Next, Nobunaga called Fuden to his presence and asked his achievement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Next, Nobunaga called Fuden to his presence and asked of his achievement.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Next, Nobunaga called Fuden to his presence and asked of his achievement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>普伝は一切経のどこにどんな文句があるか諳んじるほど博識である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fuden was well-read in Buddhism so much that he learned the sutra Issaikyo by heart.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fuden was so well-read in Buddhism that he had learned the sutra Issaikyo by heart.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fuden was so well-read in Buddhism that he had learned the sutra Issaikyo by heart.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>しかし、何宗にも属していない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But he did not belong to a certain Buddhist sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But he did not belong to any particular Buddhist sect.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But he did not belong to any particular Buddhist sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>彼の行状は、ある時は小梅の小袖、ある時は摺箔の衣装など結構なものを着て、ぼろぼろになると、仏縁を結ぶと称して、これを人々に与えていたそうである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He would sometimes wear stylish kimono with an apricot pattern or sometimes wear a gorgeous costume patterned with the impressed gold or silver leaf, and when the garments were worn out, he gave them to other people under the pretext of having them in contact with the Buddha&apos;s providence by the garments.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He would sometimes wear stylish kimono with an apricot pattern or sometimes wear a gorgeous costume patterned with an impressed gold or silver leaf, and when the garments were worn out, he gave them to other people under the pretext of bringing them in contact with the Buddha&apos;s providence by the garments.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He would sometimes wear stylish kimono with an apricot pattern or sometimes wear a gorgeous costume patterned with an impressed gold or silver leaf, and when the garments were worn out, he gave them to other people under the pretext of bringing them in contact with the Buddha&apos;s providence by the garments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>得意顔をしていたが、よくよく調べてみると小袖は値打ちのない紛い物であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was puffed up with self-importance, but his stylish kimono turned out to be a cheep imitation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was puffed up with self-importance, but his stylish kimono turned out to be a cheap imitation.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was puffed up with self-importance, but his stylish kimono turned out to be a cheap imitation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>博識の普伝が納得して法華宗に入ったとなれば、法華宗はますます繁栄するからと懇願され、金品を受け取ってこのたび法華宗に属したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the Hokke sect earnestly appealed to Fuden to enter the sect because if the well-read Fuden was convinced to be a follower of the sect, the sect would further prosper, he entered the sect in exchange for money and kind.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Hokke sect earnestly appealed to Fuden to enter the sect, because if the well-read Fuden was convinced to be a follower of the sect the sect would further prosper, he entered the sect in exchange for money in kind.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Hokkeshu sect earnestly appealed to Fuden to enter the sect, because if the well-read Fuden was convinced to be a follower of the sect the sect would further prosper, he entered the sect in exchange for money in kind.</e>
<cmt>Hokkeshu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>よい年をして嘘をついていたわけである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He told a lie at his age.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He told a lie about his age.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He told a lie about his age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>「今度の宗論に勝ったら、一生不自由しないようにしてやろうと法華宗から堅い約束をされ、金品を受け取って、役所にも届を出さずに安土に来たことは、日ごろの言い分に反し、不届きである」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga said &apos;You came here under agreement with the sect that if you make the Hokke sect win the debate, the sect would make you live in comfort, and in exchange for money and kind, you entered the town of Azuchi without notifying the public office. You did such an illegal thing in contrast with your daily claims.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga said &apos;You came here under agreement with the sect that if you make the Hokke sect win the debate, the sect would make you live in comfort, and in exchange for money in kind, you entered the town of Azuchi without notifying the public office. You did such an illegal thing in contrast with your daily claims.&apos;</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga said &apos;You came here under agreement with the sect that if you make the Hokkeshu sect win the debate, the sect would make you live in comfort, and in exchange for money in kind, you entered the town of Azuchi without notifying the public office; you did such an illegal thing in contrast with your daily claims.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Hokkeshu sectとし、余分なスペース消去、文中のピリオド→セミコロンに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="73">
<j>さらに信長は追及して「さらに、宗論の場では自分は発言せず、他人に問答をさせて、勝ち目になったらしゃしゃり出ようと待ち構えていた。卑劣なたくらみで、まことにけしからぬ」と、普伝の首も斬った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga still continued &apos;You kept silent during the debate to make the other members of your sect to make a statement, being ready to join the debate if the Hokke sect would gain an advantage over the Jodo sect. You played such a dirty trick., which was unpardonable.&apos; and also beheaded Fuden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga still continued &apos;You kept silent during the debate to make the other members of your sect make a statement, being ready to join the debate if the Hokke sect would gain an advantage over the Jodo sect. You played such a dirty trick., which was unpardonable,&apos; and he also beheaded Fuden.</e>
<cmt>verb</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga still continued &apos;You kept silent during the debate to make the other members of your sect make a statement, being ready to join the debate if the Hokkeshu sect would gain an advantage over the Jodoshu sect. You played such a dirty trick, which was unpardonable,&apos; and he also beheaded Fuden.</e>
<cmt>Hokkeshu sect、Jodoshu sectとし、不要なピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>残った法華宗の歴々の僧たちへは、次のように言い渡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga said to the other monks of the Hokke sect,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga said to the other monks of the Hokke sect,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga said to the other monks of the Hokkeshu sect as follows:</e>
<cmt>Hokkeshu sectとし、文末のカンマ→as follows: としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>「だいたい、武士たちは軍役を日々勤めて苦労しているのに、僧職の者たちは寺庵を結構に造り、贅沢な暮らしをしている。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrast to samurai warriors who have hard times in serving in the army, you, monks, build and live in good temples and indulge in luxury.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast to samurai warriors who have hard times in serving in the army, you, monks, build and live in good temples and indulge in luxury.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast to samurai warriors who have hard times in serving in the army, you, monks, build and live in good temples and indulge in luxury.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>「それにもかかわらず、学問もせず『妙』の一字にも答えられなかったのは誠に許しがたい。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What is worse, you neglected your studies and could not answer the question about a letter &apos;Myo&apos;, you are also unpardonable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What is worse, you neglected your studies and could not answer the question about a letter &apos;Myo&apos;; you are also unpardonable.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What is worse, you neglected your studies and could not answer the question about a letter &apos;Myo&apos;; you are also unpardonable.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>「ただし法華宗は口が達者である。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You, Hokke sect monks are sophists.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You Hokke sect monks are sophists.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You Hokkeshu sect monks are sophists.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション追加、Hokkeshu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>「後日、宗論に負けたとは多分言うまい」、そして「宗門を変更して浄土宗の弟子になるか、さもなくば、この度宗論に負けた以上は今後は他宗を誹謗しない、との誓約書を出すがよい」と申し渡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You will never admit that the Hokke sect lost the debate,&apos; and Nobunaga commanded them &apos;Change your sect and become disciples of the Jodo sect, or, submit a written pledge that you never slander the other sects as you lost the debate.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You will never admit that the Hokke sect lost the debate,&apos; and Nobunaga commanded them &apos;Change your sect and become disciples of the Jodo sect, or, submit a written pledge that you will never slander the other sects, as you lost the debate.&apos;</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You will never admit that the Hokkeshu sect lost the debate,&apos; and Nobunaga commanded them &apos;Change your sect and become disciples of the Jodoshu sect, or, submit a written pledge that you will never slander the other sects, as you lost the debate.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Hokkeshu sect、Jodoshu sectとし、クォーテーション追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>詫び証文の概要は以下の通り。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hokke sect submitted the deed of apology as below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hokke sect submitted the deed of apology as below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hokke sect submitted the deed of apology as below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="80">
<j>敬白　起請文（きしょうもん）の事</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gentlemen, Written vows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gentlemen, Written vows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hokkeshu sect submitted the deed of apology as below.</e>
<cmt>Hokkeshu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="81">
<j>今度（このたび）近江の浄厳院に於いて浄土宗と宗論をいたし、法花宗が負け申すに付いて、京都の坊主普伝、並びに塩屋伝介が仰せ付けられ候事。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As we debated the Jodo sect at Jogonin Temple in Omi and lost the debate, Fuden, a monk in Kyoto, and a sault-seller Densuke were sentenced to death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As we debated the Jodo sect at Jogonin Temple in Omi and lost the debate, Fuden, a monk in Kyoto, and a sault-seller Densuke were sentenced to death.</e>
<cmt>I don&apos;t understand the intended meaning of &quot;sault.&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As we debated the Jodoshu sect at Jogon-in Temple in Omi and lost the debate, Fuden, a monk in Kyoto, and a salt-seller Densuke were sentenced to death.</e>
<cmt>Jodoshu sect、Jogon-in Templeとし、sault-seller→salt sellerに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="82">
<j>向後他宗に対し一切法難（非難）致し可からざる之事（今後は、他宗に対し決して非難はいたしません）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">We will never slander the other sects henceforth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">We will never slander the other sects henceforth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">We will never slander the other sects henceforth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="83">
<j>法花一分之儀立て置かる可き之旨、忝く存じ奉り候（法華宗に寛大な御処置を賜りまして、誠にありがたい思いです）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">We thank Nobunaga for his lenient sentence on the Hokke sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">We thank Nobunaga for his lenient sentence on the Hokke sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">We thank Nobunaga for his lenient sentence on the Hokkeshu sect.</e>
<cmt>Hokkeshu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>私ども法華宗の僧はいったん宗門を離れ、改めて御許可を得てから前職に就かせていただきます。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">We, the Hokke sect monks, will leave the sect, and will return to the former position by permission of Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">We, the Hokke sect monks, will leave the sect, and will return to our former positions by permission of Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">We, the Hokkeshu sect monks, will leave the sect, and will return to our former positions by permission of Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>Hokkeshu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="85">
<j>天正七年五月二十七日　法花宗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July, 1, 1579 Hokke sect</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July, 1, 1579 Hokke sect</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July, 1, 1579 Hokkeshu sect</e>
<cmt>Hokkeshu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="86">
<j>上様、浄土宗様</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the Lord, the Jodo sect</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the Lord, the Jodo sect</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">the Lord, the Jodoshu sect</e>
<cmt>Jodoshu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="87">
<j>このような証文を出した 上に「宗論に負けました」と書いてしまったからには、法華宗が負けたことを女子供までもが後の代まで聞き知ることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the Hokke sect handed in the deed of apology that stated &apos;we lost the debate&apos;, everyone including women and children knew the fact for generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Hokke sect handed in the deed of apology that stated &apos;we lost the debate&apos;, everyone, including women and children, knew the fact for generations.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Hokkeshu sect handed in the deed of apology that stated &apos;we lost the debate,&apos; everyone, including women and children, knew the fact for generations.</e>
<cmt>Hokkeshu sectとし、カンマの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>別の文句がいくらでもあったのに失敗した、と歴々の僧たちが後悔していると伝え聞いて、またまた世人はこれを笑いものにした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The public made a mockery of the Hokke sect when they heard that the high-ranked monks of the sect regretted that they should have used another expression instead of &apos;lost the debate.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The public made a mockery of the Hokke sect when they heard that the high-ranked monks of the sect regretted that they should have used another expression instead of &apos;lost the debate.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The public made a mockery of the Hokkeshu sect when they heard that the high-ranked monks of the sect regretted that they should have used another expression instead of &apos;lost the debate.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Hokkeshu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="89">
<j>建部紹智は境（大阪の泉州・堺市附近）の港まで逃げたが捕縛された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shochi TAKEBE fled to the port in Sakai (Senshu in Osaka, near Sakai) and arrested.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shochi TAKEBE fled to the port in Sakai (Senshu in Osaka, near Sakai) and was arrested.</e>
<cmt>verb</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shochi TAKEBE fled to the port in Sakai (Senshu in Osaka, near Sakai) and was arrested.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>この度の騒動は大脇伝介と建部紹智が発端となったのだから、紹智も首を斬られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Densuke OOWAKI and Shochi TAKEBE created the disturbance, Shochi TAKEBE was also beheaded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Densuke OOWAKI and Shochi TAKEBE had created the disturbance, Shochi TAKEBE was also beheaded.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Densuke OWAKI and Shochi TAKEBE had created the disturbance, Shochi TAKEBE was also beheaded.</e>
<cmt>OOWAKI→OWAKIに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="91">
<j>以上、信長公記の記述による。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The incident has been summarized above according to &apos;Nobunaga koki.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The incident has been summarized above according to &apos;Nobunaga koki.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The incident has been summarized above according to the Nobunaga Koki.</e>
<cmt>the Nobunaga Kokiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="92">
<j>ポイント</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Point</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Point</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Point</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>この宗論で最大のポイントとなるのは「方座第四の『妙』」という言葉である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The biggest point of the debate was the word &apos;the fourth &quot;Myo&quot;in Hoza.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The biggest point of the debate was the word &apos;the fourth &quot;Myo&quot;in Hoza.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The biggest point of the debate was the word &apos;the fourth &quot;Myo&quot;in Hoza.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>この宗論は一般的に信長の策略により、浄土宗側の意味不明なその言葉・発言に嵌められたと解釈されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is generally considered that Nobunaga trapped the Hokke sect into lose the debate by using unclear wording of the Jodo sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is generally considered that Nobunaga trapped the Hokke sect into losing the debate by using the unclear wording of the Jodo sect.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is generally considered that Nobunaga trapped the Hokkeshu sect into losing the debate by using the unclear wording of the Jodoshu sect.</e>
<cmt>Hokkeshu sect、Jodoshu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>古来より法華宗側では、この発言を「貞安の卑怯な手」で相手を煙に捲いたとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Hokke sect, it is said that &apos;Teian confused his opponent with his dirty tricks.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Hokke sect, it is said that &apos;Teian confused his opponent with his dirty tricks.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Hokkeshu sect, it is said that &apos;Teian confused his opponent with his dirty tricks.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Hokkeshu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="96">
<j>また他の法華系宗派では、以下のように説明している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the other branches in the Hokke sect, the word is described as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the other branches in the Hokke sect, the word is described as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the other branches in the Hokkeshu sect, the word is described as follows.</e>
<cmt>Hokkeshu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="97">
<j>華厳の妙</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kegon no Myo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kegon no Myo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kegon no Myo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>阿含の妙</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Agon no Myo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Agon no Myo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Agon no Myo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>方等の妙</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoto no Myo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoto no Myo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoto no Myo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>般若の妙</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hannya no ho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hannya no ho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hannya no Myo</e>
<cmt>ho→Myoに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="101">
<j>この4つを総称して爾前（法華経より前）の妙といい、法華の妙と対比すると説明し、五時八教の教相判釈五時八教説（天台）では、浄土三部経は方等部に位置づけられるから、方座「第三」の妙と言うべき所を、方座「第四」の妙と嘘をつき、捨てるか捨てないのかと質問した詐欺師だ、などと判じている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was described that these four &apos;Myo&apos; were collectively called &apos;the Myo before the Hokke sect&apos;, which was opposite to &apos;the Myo of the Hokke sect&apos;, and as the three sutras in the Jodo sect are categorized in Hotobu according to the categorization called Gojihakkyosetsu, the Jodo sect should have said &apos;the third&apos; Myo of Hoza in the debate but they intentionally used the wrong expression &apos;the fourth&apos; Myo of Hoza in asking the Hokke sect whether they would abandon the Myo or not.</e>
<cmt>「五時八教の教相判釈五時八教説（天台）では、」はリンクになっているため、言葉が重複しております。「五時八教の教相判釈では、」として訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was described that these four &apos;Myo&apos; were collectively called &apos;the Myo before the Hokke sect&apos;, as opposed to &apos;the Myo of the Hokke sect&apos;, and as the three sutras in the Jodo sect are categorized in Hotobu according to the categorization called Gojihakkyosetsu, the Jodo sect should have said &apos;the third&apos; Myo of Hoza in the debate but they intentionally used the wrong expression &apos;the fourth&apos; Myo of Hoza in asking the Hokke sect whether or not they would abandon the Myo.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was described that these four &apos;Myo&apos; were collectively called &apos;the Myo before the Hokkeshu sect,&apos; as opposed to &apos;the Myo of the Hokkeshu sect,&apos; and as the three sutras in the Jodoshu sect are categorized in Hotobu according to the categorization called Gojihakkyosetsu, the Jodoshu sect should have said &apos;the third&apos; Myo of Hoza in the debate but they intentionally used the wrong expression &apos;the fourth&apos; Myo of Hoza in asking the Hokkeshu sect whether or not they would abandon the Myo.</e>
<cmt>Hokkeshu sect、Jodoshu sectとし、カンマの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>この質問に混乱した法華側が1～4のどの妙の話なのかと問い返したところ、浄土側は嘘に嘘を重ねて法華の妙だと回答したので、法華側が思考停止に陥ってしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the confused Hokke sect monks asked which of the first to the fourth Myo did the Jodo sect monks talked about, the Jodo sect monks further lied in their answer that they talked about the Myo of the Hokke, which brought the thought of the Hokke sect monks to standstill.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the confused Hokke sect monks asked which of the first to the fourth Myo the Jodo sect monks were talking about, the Jodo sect monks further lied in their answer that they talked about the Myo of the Hokke, which brought the thoughts of the Hokke sect monks to a standstill.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the confused Hokkeshu sect monks asked which of the first to the fourth Myo the Jodoshu sect monks were talking about, the Jodoshu sect monks further lied in their answer that they talked about the Myo of the Hokke, which brought the thoughts of the Hokkeshu sect monks to a standstill.</e>
<cmt>Hokkeshu sect、Jodoshu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="103">
<j>田中智學は以下のように言及し激しく非難した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A religious figure in the later period Chigaku TANAKA rebuked the Jodo sect &apos;It was quite out of the question. Even Shakyamuni might have not be aware of the trick.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A religious figure in the later period, Chigaku TANAKA, rebuked the Jodo sect &apos;It was quite out of the question. Even Shakyamuni might have been unaware of the trick.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A religious figure in the later period, Chigaku TANAKA, rebuked the Jodoshu sect as follows:</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」split sampleに基づき、原文･訳文を修正しました。Jososhu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>「こんな事は全く話にならない、それこそお釈迦様でも気がつかない事だ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The founder of Daiunin Temple, Kyorensha Tairo Daiosho Seiyo Teian Shonin was the only person in the world throughout the history who knew the secret.</e>
<cmt>「退魯」の読みが不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The founder of Daiunin Temple, Kyorensha Tairo Daiosho Seiyo Teian Shonin, was the only person in the world throughout the history who knew the secret.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was quite out of the question, even Shakyamuni might have been unaware of the trick.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」文中のピリオド→カンマに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>「知って居るのは、世界中に唯一人、劫初（こうしょ＝この世の初め）以来何億万年にも誰一人、その唯の一人しか知るものは無い、それは大雲院開山教蓮社退魯大和尚聖誉貞安上人唯一人である。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He tried to confuse the opponent by using such a strange &quot;sham term&quot; that had not been registered in any of &quot;Sutras&quot;, &quot;Thesis&quot;, and &quot;Commentary&quot;, which was the problem of his personality before talking about the problem of dhamma.&apos; (according to a magazine &quot;Dokku, Junkyogo&quot; p.67, published by Shishiobunko)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He tried to confuse the opponent by using such a strange &quot;sham term&quot; that had not been registered in any of &quot;Sutras&quot;, &quot;Thesis&quot;, and &quot;Commentary&quot;, which was a problem of his personality before talking about the problem of dhamma.&apos; (according to a magazine &quot;Dokku, Junkyogo&quot; p.67, published by Shishiobunko)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The founder of Daiun-in Temple, Kyorensha Tairo Daiosho Seiyo Teian Shonin, was the only person in the world throughout the history who knew the secret.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」Daiun-in Templeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>「『経文』にも『論文』にも『釈義』にも、かつて登録されない珍妙怪奇の『造り名目（つくりみょうもく）』を以て、相手を煙に捲かうといふのは、モー法義論談の分域を通り越して、残るところは貞安の人格問題だ」（雑誌『毒鼓・殉教号』67頁、獅子王文庫発行）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He tried to confuse the opponent by using such a strange &quot;sham term&quot; that had not been registered in any of &quot;Sutras,&quot; &quot;Thesis,&quot; and &quot;Commentary,&quot; which was a problem of his personality before talking about the problem of dhamma.&apos; (according to a magazine &quot;Dokku, Junkyogo&quot; p.67, published by Shishiobunko)</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」カンマの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="107">
<j>ただし田中智學はこうも述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chigaku TANAKA also stated in the magazine,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chigaku TANAKA also stated in the magazine,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chigaku TANAKA also stated in the magazine as below:</e>
<cmt>文末のカンマ→as below:としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>「“方座第四の『妙』”といふのは、追究したら恐らく『方等会座四教並説中第四円教所談の妙』というつもりであらう」（前掲書68頁）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seiyo Teian probably said &quot;the fourth Myo in Hoza&quot; to indicate &quot;Hotoeza Shikyo Heisetsu chu Daishi Enkyo shodan no Myo&quot; in a strict sense (p. 68 in the same magazine.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seiyo Teian probably said &quot;the fourth Myo in Hoza&quot; to indicate &quot;Hotoeza Shikyo Heisetsu chu Daishi Enkyo shodan no Myo&quot; in a strict sense (p. 68 in the same magazine.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seiyo Teian probably said &quot;the fourth Myo in Hoza&quot; to indicate &quot;Hotoeza Shikyo Heisetsu chu Daishi Enkyo shodan no Myo&quot; in a strict sense&apos; (p. 68 in the same magazine).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション追加、ピリオドの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="109">
<j>浄土宗の学僧、林彦明（はやしげんみょう）は「専修学報第1号・安土宗論の真相に就て」で、これを指摘した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A learned priest of the Jodo sect Genmyo HAYASHI indicated the same point in &apos;Senshugakuho No. 1, Azuchi Shuron no Sinso ni tsuite&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A learned priest of the Jodo sect, Genmyo HAYASHI, indicated the same point in &apos;Senshugakuho No. 1, Azuchi Shuron no Sinso ni tsuite&quot;.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A learned priest of the Jodoshu sect, Genmyo HAYASHI, indicated the same point in &apos;Senshugakuho No. 1, Azuchi Shuron no Sinso ni tsuite.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Jodoshu sectとし、クォーテーション表記修正、ピリオドの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>また作家の井沢元彦も『逆説の日本史』10「戦国覇王編 - 天下布武と信長の謎」において、この一言で法華宗の負けが決まったと指摘した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A novelist Motohiko IZAWA stated in his book &quot;Gyakusetsu no Nihonshi&quot; Vo. 10 &apos;Sengoku hao hen - Tenka fubu to Nobunaga no nazo&apos; that the word decided the loss of the Hokke sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A novelist, Motohiko IZAWA, stated in his book &quot;Gyakusetsu no Nihonshi&quot; Vo. 10 &apos;Sengoku hao hen - Tenka fubu to Nobunaga no nazo&apos; that the word decided the loss of the Hokke sect.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A novelist, Motohiko IZAWA, indicated in his book &quot;Gyakusetsu no Nihonshi&quot; (The Paradox of Japanese History) Vol. 10, &apos;The Lord of the Sengoku Period - the mystery of the unification of Japan and Nobunaga&apos; that this statement determined the loss of the Hokkeshu sect.</e>
<cmt>Hokkeshu sectとしました。また表現を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="111">
<j>すなわち、もしこの発言が従来より法華宗側が言っている「浄土宗側が卑怯な手を使った」のであれば、法華宗側はその場において「方座第四の『妙』」を意味不明・解釈不能であるという態度を徹底的に貫かねばならず、それをしなかった法華宗側は『造り名目』でないことを認めてしまったことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">IZAWA states &apos;That is to say, if &apos;the Jodo sect misled the Hokke sect by the word &quot;the fourth Myo in Hoza&quot;&apos; as the Hokke sect claimed, the Hokke sect should have insisted that the word made no sense so that they could not understand the question during the debate, but in reality, they did not do that, which meant they did not deny the word as &quot;sham term&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">IZAWA states &apos;That is to say, if &apos;the Jodo sect misled the Hokke sect by the word &quot;the fourth Myo in Hoza&quot;&apos; as the Hokke sect claimed, the Hokke sect should have insisted that the word made no sense so that they could not understand the question during the debate, but in reality, they did not do that, which meant they did not deny the word as &quot;sham term&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">IZAWA states &apos;That is to say, if &apos;the Jodoshu sect misled the Hokkeshu sect by the word &quot;the fourth Myo in Hoza&quot;&apos; as the Hokkeshu sect claimed, the Hokkeshu sect should have insisted that the word made no sense so that they could not understand the question during the debate, but in reality, they did not do that, which meant they did not deny the word as &quot;sham term.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Hokkeshu sect、Jodoshu sectとし、ピリオドの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>つまり田中智学も認める通り「方等会座（方等座）における四教並説中の『円教』に所談（語っている所）の『妙』である」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, as Chigaku TANAKA said, the word meant &apos;&quot;Myo&quot; mentioned in &quot;Enkyo&quot; in Shikyo Heisetsu of Hotoeza, i.e., Hotoza.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, as Chigaku TANAKA said, the word meant &apos;&quot;Myo&quot; mentioned in &quot;Enkyo&quot; in Shikyo Heisetsu of Hotoeza, i.e., Hotoza.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, as Chigaku TANAKA said, the word meant &apos;&quot;Myo&quot; mentioned in &quot;Enkyo&quot; in Shikyo Heisetsu of Hotoeza, i.e., Hotoza.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="113">
<j>五時八教の教判では、釈迦仏は華厳・阿含・方等・般若・法華涅槃の五時に分けて教えを説いたが、方等時で「蔵・通・別・円」の四教を並説したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the theory of Gojihakkyosetsu, Shakyamuni preached by dividing his teachings into five periods of time like Kegon, Agon, Hoto, Hannya, and Hokke Nehan and in the category of Hoto, Shakyamuni preached four items of &apos;Zo, Tsu, Betsu, En&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the theory of Gojihakkyosetsu, Shakyamuni preached by dividing his teachings into five periods of time: Kegon, Agon, Hoto, Hannya, and Hokke Nehan, and in the category of Hoto, Shakyamuni preached four items of &apos;Zo, Tsu, Betsu, En&apos;.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;like&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the theory of Gojihakkyosetsu, Shakyamuni preached by dividing his teachings into five periods of time: Kegon, Agon, Hoto, Hannya, and Hokke Nehan, and in the category of Hoto, Shakyamuni preached four items of &apos;Zo, Tsu, Betsu, En.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>このうち「蔵・通・別」は小乗の教えで、第4番目の「円」が大乗の最高の教えとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the four items, &apos;Zo, Tsu, Betsu&apos; are teachings of Hinayana Buddhism, and the fourth item &apos;En&apos; is the highest teaching of Mahayana Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the four items, &apos;Zo, Tsu, Betsu&apos; are teachings of Hinayana Buddhism, and the fourth item &apos;En&apos; is the highest teaching of Mahayana Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the four items, &apos;Zo, Tsu, Betsu&apos; are teachings of Hinayana Buddhism, and the fourth item &apos;En&apos; is the highest teaching of Mahayana Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>「円教」では当然、妙（妙法蓮華経＝法華経）に象徴される完全な教えを説いたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the theory of Gojihakkyosetsu, it is considered that, as a matter of course, Shakyamuni preached a perfect teaching as symbolized by Myo, which means Myohorengekyo, i.e., the sutra Hokkekyo, in &apos;Enkyo&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the theory of Gojihakkyosetsu, it is considered that, as a matter of course, Shakyamuni preached a perfect teaching as symbolized by Myo, which means Myohorengekyo; i.e., the sutra Hokkekyo, in &apos;Enkyo&apos;.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the theory of Gojihakkyosetsu, it is considered that, as a matter of course, Shakyamuni preached a perfect teaching as symbolized by Myo, which means Myohorengekyo; i.e., the sutra Hokkekyo, in &apos;Enkyo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>この教判は天台宗の教学で智顗が考案し、それを後の法華宗や日蓮宗が採用継承した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This theory was formulated by Chigi and adopted by the Tendai sect as education, which has been handed down by the Hokke sect and the Nichiren sect later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This theory was formulated by Chigi and adopted by the Tendai sect as education, which has been handed down by the Hokke sect and later by the Nichiren sect.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This theory was formulated by Chigi and adopted by the Tendaishu sect as education, which has been handed down by the Hokkeshu sect and later by the Nichirenshu sect.</e>
<cmt>Tendaishu sect、Hokkeshu sect、Nichirenshu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="117">
<j>つまり、貞安の問いである「方座第四の「妙」の一字を捨てるか、捨てざるか」というのは、「もし天台教学の考えを以って、法華以前の教えをすべて“方便（真実に導く手だて・手段）”として否定するなら、方等時において説いた円教＝妙も捨てるのか、捨てないのか？」というのが真相であるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently, the Teian&apos;s question &apos;Do you abandon a letter &apos;Myo&apos; of the fourth Hoza?&apos; really meant that &apos;If you deny the Shakyamuni&apos;s teachings before he established Hokke as merely &quot;a means to lead people to the truth&quot; according to the education of the Tendai sect, do you abandon Enkyo, i.e., Myo, that Shakyamuni preached in his Hoto?&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, the Teian&apos;s question &apos;Do you abandon a letter &apos;Myo&apos; of the fourth Hoza?&apos; really meant that &apos;If you deny the Shakyamuni&apos;s teachings before he established Hokke as merely &quot;a means to lead people to the truth&quot; according to the education of the Tendai sect, do you abandon Enkyo; i.e., Myo, that Shakyamuni preached in his Hoto?&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, the Teian&apos;s question &apos;Do you abandon a letter &apos;Myo&apos; of the fourth Hoza?&apos; really meant that &apos;If you deny the Shakyamuni&apos;s teachings before he established Hokke as merely &quot;a means to lead people to the truth&quot; according to the education of the Tendaishu sect, do you abandon Enkyo; i.e., Myo, that Shakyamuni preached in his Hoto?&apos;</e>
<cmt>Tendaishu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="118">
<j>したがって、他の日蓮宗派が解釈する「方座『第三』の妙と言うべき所を、方座『第四』の妙と嘘をついた」というのは、単なる誤解であり、第四とは「蔵・通・別・円」の「円教＝妙」のことであり、また田中智学が述べた「造り名目」でもないことが明らかと指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it is now stated that it was apparently a simple misunderstanding about the matter that the Jodo sect intentionally used the wrong word &apos;Myo&apos; of the fourth Hoza when they should have used &apos;Myo&apos; of the third Hoza that was to be understood by the other branches of the Nichiren sect, because &apos;the fourth&apos; indicated &apos;Enkyo, i.e., Myo&apos; among &apos;Zo, Tsu, Betsu, En&apos; and far from &apos;sham term&apos; as Chigaku TANAKA said.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it is now stated that it was apparently a simple misunderstanding about the matter that the Jodo sect intentionally used the wrong word &apos;Myo&apos; of the fourth Hoza when they should have used &apos;Myo&apos; of the third Hoza that was to be understood by the other branches of the Nichiren sect, because &apos;the fourth&apos; indicated &apos;Enkyo, i.e., Myo&apos; among &apos;Zo, Tsu, Betsu, En&apos; and far from &apos;sham term&apos; as Chigaku TANAKA said.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it is now stated that it was apparently a simple misunderstanding about the matter that the Jodoshu sect intentionally used the wrong word &apos;Myo&apos; of the fourth Hoza when they should have used &apos;Myo&apos; of the third Hoza that was to be understood by the other schools of the Nichirenshu sect, because &apos;the fourth&apos; indicated &apos;Enkyo, i.e., Myo&apos; among &apos;Zo, Tsu, Betsu, En&apos; and far from &apos;sham term&apos; as Chigaku TANAKA said.</e>
<cmt>Jodoshu sect、other branches of the Nichiren sect→other schools of the Nichirenshu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="119">
<j>また法華宗側の日珖・日諦が、後に詫び証文を書いた（書かされたとも解釈される）のは、「方座第四の「妙」」の意味すら分らなかったからに他ならず、だからこそ素直に詫び証文を書いたといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nikko and Nittai in the Hokke sect obediently wrote--or it is considered as they were forced to write--the deed of apology, only because they admitted that they could not even understand the meaning of &apos;&apos;Myo&apos; of the fourth Myo in Hoza&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nikko and Nittai in the Hokke sect obediently wrote--or it is considered they were forced to write--the deed of apology, only because they admitted that they could not even understand the meaning of &apos;&apos;Myo&apos; of the fourth Myo in Hoza&apos;.</e>
<cmt>omitted &apos;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nikko and Nittai in the Hokkeshu sect obediently wrote - or it is considered they were forced to write - the deed of apology, only because they admitted that they could not even understand the meaning of &apos;&apos;Myo&apos; of the fourth Myo in Hoza.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Hokkeshu sectとし、ハイフン修正、ピリオドの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>井沢元彦も「もし信長が日蓮法華宗を嵌めたのなら、なぜ素直に詫び証文を書いたのか、また当時の宗教は世俗の権力に徹底的に反抗するのが常であり、大規模な法華一揆を起こさなかったのか」と指摘している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motohiko IZAWA pointed out that if Nobunaga tricked the Nichien Hokke sect, the sect should not have obediently wrote the deed, and in those days, as religious sects were consistently resistant to the secular power, a big uprising should have broken out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motohiko IZAWA pointed out that if Nobunaga tricked the Nichien Hokke sect, the sect should not have obediently written the deed, and in those days, as religious sects were consistently resistant to the secular power, a big uprising should have broken out.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motohiko IZAWA pointed out that if Nobunaga tricked the Nichiren Hokkeshu sect, the sect should not have obediently written the deed, and in those days, as religious sects were consistently resistant to the secular power, a big uprising should have broken out.</e>
<cmt>Nichien Hokke sect→Nichiren Hokkeshu sectに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="121">
<j>したがって、信長が日蓮法華宗を不当に弾圧したという歴史学上の見解には疑義が提出されているが、一方では、信長の陰謀というより、かねてから法華宗をどう諌めようか想定していた所へ、折も折、法論を契機として、それを口実にして乗っかっただけ、という指摘や、その後浄土真宗の一向一揆に対して行ったような大規模な弾圧が行われていないことより、経済的に豊かであった日蓮法華宗寺院及び信者から矢銭を調達するための策略であったとする指摘もされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, a doubt has been cast on the historical opinion that Nobunaga wrongfully oppressed the Nichien Hokke sect, but on the other hand, there are other opinions, including one that Nobunaga had thought he should have somehow remonstrate the the Hokke sect and he found a timely opportunity in the debate and he decided to merely take advantage of that instead of laying a plot; and that as the Nichiren Hokke sect and its followers were rich, Nobunaga plotted to raise his war funds from the sect and followers, which was why he did not seriously oppress the sect unlike his actions on the Ikko-ikki uprisings of the Jodo Shinshu sect that occurred later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, a doubt has been cast on the historical opinion that Nobunaga wrongfully oppressed the Nichien Hokke sect, but on the other hand, there are other opinions, including one that Nobunaga had thought he should have somehow remonstrate the the Hokke sect and he found a timely opportunity in the debate and he decided to merely take advantage of that instead of laying a plot; and that as the Nichiren Hokke sect and its followers were rich, Nobunaga plotted to raise his war funds from the sect and followers, which was why he did not seriously oppress the sect unlike his actions on the Ikko-ikki uprisings of the Jodo Shinshu sect that occurred later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, a doubt has been cast on the historical opinion that Nobunaga wrongfully oppressed the Nichiren Hokkeshu sect, but on the other hand, there are other opinions, including one that Nobunaga had thought he should have somehow remonstrate the the Hokkeshu sect and he found a timely opportunity in the debate and he decided to merely take advantage of that instead of laying a plot; and that as the Nichiren Hokkeshu sect and its followers were rich, Nobunaga plotted to raise his war funds from the sect and followers, which was why he did not seriously oppress the sect unlike his actions on the Ikko-ikki uprisings of the Jodo Shinshu sect (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) that occurred later.</e>
<cmt>Nichien→Nichirenに修正、Hokkeshu sectとし、「浄土真宗」→統一リストの表記に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Izayohi(id:13095), 青子守歌(id:37161), Boca samba(id:137526), Chi-Ham(id:143515), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), R28Bot(id:177951), くっちゃめ(id:86793), 竹田(id:72642), BAKU(id:55205), 建長(id:119884), ウィキ豊(id:82961), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>