<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>五山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gozan (a term related to Zen temples)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gozan (a term relating to Zen temples)</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gozan (a term relating to Zen temples)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>五山（ござん）とは、中国・日本における禅林（禅宗寺院）の格式であり、十刹・諸山の上。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gozan indicates the status of Zenrin (a temple of the Zen sect) in China and Japan that is ranked above jissatsu (for ten important temples of the Rinzai sect) and shozan (for ordinary Zen temples).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gozan indicates the status of a Zenrin (temple of the Zen sect) in China and Japan that is ranked above jissatsu (for the ten important temples of the Rinzai sect) and shozan (for ordinary Zen temples).</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gozan indicates the status of a Zenrin (temple of the Zen sect) in China and Japan that is ranked above jissatsu (for the ten important temples of the Rinzai sect) and shozan (for ordinary Zen temples).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>五山の由来</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of gozan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of gozan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of gozan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>元は南宋の寧宗_(宋)がインドの5精舎10塔所（天竺五精舎）の故事に倣って径山・雲隠・天童・浄慈・育王の5寺を「五山」として保護を与えたのが由来と言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term is said originated in that Neiso in Southern Sung Dynasty protected the five temples of Keizan, Unin, Tendo, Joji, and Ikuo as &quot;gozan&quot; (literally, five mountains), after the historical fact of five Shoja and ten pagodas (five Shoja in India) in India).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term is said to have originated from the fact that Neiso of the Southern Sung Dynasty protected the five temples of Keizan, Unin, Tendo, Joji, and Ikuo as &quot;gozan&quot; (literally, five mountains), in emulation of India&apos;s five Shoja and ten pagodas (The Five Shoja of India).</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term is said to have originated from the fact that Neiso of the Southern Sung Dynasty protected the five temples of Keizan, Unin, Tendo, Joji, and Ikuo as &quot;gozan&quot; (literally, five mountains), in emulation of India&apos;s five Shoja and ten pagodas (The Five Shoja of India).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>鎌倉時代後期には日本にも禅宗の普及に伴って広まるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the latter half of the Kamakura period, temples with the gozan status appeared in Japan aw well, corresponding to an increase in the number of believers of Zen principles.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the latter half of the Kamakura Period temples with gozan status appeared in Japan as well, corresponding to an increase in the number of believers of Zen principles.</e>
<cmt>Capitalized.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the latter half of the Kamakura Period temples with gozan status appeared in Japan as well, corresponding to an increase in the number of believers of Zen principles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>正安元年（1299年）には鎌倉幕府執権北条貞時が浄智寺を「五山」とするように命じたのが日本における最古と伝わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the oldest temple with this status was Jochi-ji Temple, which was ordered by Regent Sadatoki HOJO of the Kamakura bakufu in 1299 to have the status of &quot;gozan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the oldest temple with this status was Jochi-ji Temple, after Regent Sadatoki HOJO of the Kamakura bakufu in 1299 proclaimed it as &quot;gozan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the oldest temple with this status was Jochi-ji Temple, after Regent Sadatoki HOJO of the Kamakura bakufu in 1299 proclaimed it as &quot;gozan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>京都五山と鎌倉五山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto gozan and Kamakura gozan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto gozan and Kamakura gozan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto gozan and Kamakura gozan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>鎌倉時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kamakura period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamakura Period</e>
<cmt>Grammar, capitalized.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamakura Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>鎌倉幕府の五山制度については詳細は明らかではないものの、鎌倉の建長寺・円覚寺・寿福寺及び京都の建仁寺の4ヶ寺が「五山」に含まれていたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The details of the gozan system of the Kamakura bakufu are not known clearly, but it is considered that the four temples of Kencho-ji Temple, Enkaku-ji Temple and Jufuku-ji Temple in Kamakura and Kennin-ji Temple in Kyoto were included in the &quot;gozan&quot; temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The details of the gozan system of the Kamakura bakufu are not known clearly, but it is believed that the four temples of Kencho-ji Temple, Enkaku-ji Temple and Jufuku-ji Temple in Kamakura and Kennin-ji Temple in Kyoto were included among the &quot;gozan&quot; temples.</e>
<cmt>Word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The details of the gozan system of the Kamakura bakufu are not known clearly, but it is believed that the four temples of Kencho-ji Temple, Enkaku-ji Temple and Jufuku-ji Temple in Kamakura and Kennin-ji Temple in Kyoto were included among the &quot;gozan&quot; temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>同様に後醍醐天皇の建武の新政においても「五山」が制定され、南禅寺と大徳寺の両寺が五山の筆頭とされ、東福寺と建仁寺が含まれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Similarly, &quot;gozan&quot; temples were specified in Kemmu Restoration by Emperor Godaigo as well, and included Nanzen-ji Temple, Daitoku-ji Temple, Tofuku-ji Temple and Kennin-ji Temple, with the first two temples placed at the head of them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similarly, &quot;gozan&quot; temples were specified during the Kemmu Restoration by Emperor Godaigo as well, and included Nanzen-ji Temple, Daitoku-ji Temple, Tofuku-ji Temple and Kennin-ji Temple, with the first two temples placed at the head of them.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similarly, &quot;gozan&quot; temples were specified during the Kemmu Restoration by Emperor Godaigo as well, and included Nanzen-ji Temple, Daitoku-ji Temple, Tofuku-ji Temple and Kennin-ji Temple, with the first two temples placed at the head of them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>室町時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Muromachi period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Muromachi Period</e>
<cmt>Grammar, capitalized.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Muromachi Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>その後、室町幕府を開いた足利尊氏は、天竜寺を建立したが、天竜寺を五山に加えることを望んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Takauji ASHIKAGA, who established the Muromachi bakufu, built Tenryu-ji Temple and wanted the temple to be added to the gozan temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Takauji ASHIKAGA, who established the Muromachi bakufu, built Tenryu-ji Temple and wanted the temple to be added to the gozan temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Takauji ASHIKAGA, who established the Muromachi bakufu, built Tenryu-ji Temple and wanted the temple to be added to the gozan temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>これに対して北朝_(日本)は暦応4年（1341年）に院宣を出して尊氏に五山の決定を一任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this, the Northern Court (in Japan) issued inzen (a decree from the retired Emperor) in 1341 to entrust to Takauji the selection of gozan temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this, the Northern Court (in Japan) issued an inzen (decree from the retired Emperor) in 1341 to entrust Takauji with the selection of gozan temples.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this, the Northern Court (in Japan) issued an inzen (decree from the retired Emperor) in 1341 to entrust Takauji with the selection of gozan temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>これに応えて同年に尊氏は第一位に南禅寺・建長寺、第二位に円覚寺・天竜寺、第三位に寿福寺（鎌倉）・第四位に建仁寺（京都）・第五位に東福寺（京都）・准五山（次席）に浄智寺（鎌倉）を選定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then in the same year, Takauji selected Nanzen-ji Temple and Kencho-ji Temple for the first grade gozan, Enkaku-ji Temple and Tenryu-ji Temple for the second grade gozan, Jufuku-ji Temple (in Kamakkura) for the third grade gozan, Kennin-ji Temple (in Kyoto) for the fourth grade gozan, Tofuku-ji Temple for the fifth grade gozan, and Jochi-ji Temple (in Kamakura) for the quasi-gozan (ranked next to the temples described above).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then in the same year Takauji selected Nanzen-ji Temple and Kencho-ji Temple for the first grade gozan, Enkaku-ji Temple and Tenryu-ji Temple for the second grade gozan, Jufuku-ji Temple (in Kamakura) for the third grade gozan, Kennin-ji Temple (in Kyoto) for the fourth grade gozan, Tofuku-ji Temple for the fifth grade gozan, and Jochi-ji Temple (in Kamakura) for the quasi-gozan (ranked lower than the temples described above).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, spelling, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then in the same year Takauji selected Nanzen-ji Temple and Kencho-ji Temple for the first grade gozan, Enkaku-ji Temple and Tenryu-ji Temple for the second grade gozan, Jufuku-ji Temple (in Kamakura) for the third grade gozan, Kennin-ji Temple (in Kyoto) for the fourth grade gozan, Tofuku-ji Temple (in Kyoto) for the fifth grade gozan, and Jochi-ji Temple (in Kamakura) for the quasi-gozan (ranked lower than the temples described above).</e>
<cmt>(in Kyoto)を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>これ以後、五山の決定及びその住持の任免権は足利氏征夷大将軍個人に帰するという慣例が成立することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this, it became customary that the right to specify a gozan temple and to appoint/dismiss the chief priest of such a temple was attributed to the seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who is to subdue the barbarians&quot;) of Ashikaga clan himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this, it became customary that the right to specify gozan temples and to appoint or dismiss the chief priest of such temples resided with the seii taishogun (literally &quot;great general who is to subdue the barbarians&quot;) of the Ashikaga clan.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this, it became customary that the right to specify gozan temples and to appoint or dismiss the chief priest of such temples resided with the seii taishogun (literally &quot;great general who is to subdue the barbarians&quot;) of the Ashikaga clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その後、延文3年（1358年）に2代将軍足利義詮がこれを改訂して浄智寺を第五位に昇格させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later in 1358, Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA, the second shogun, revised the above specification, and raised the grade of Jochi-ji Temple to the fifth gozan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later in 1358, the second shogun Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA revised the above specification, and raised the grade of Jochi-ji Temple to that of fifth gozan.</e>
<cmt>Word order, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later in 1358, the second shogun Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA revised the above specification, and raised the grade of Jochi-ji Temple to that of fifth gozan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>それとともに同じく第五位に鎌倉から浄妙寺、京都からは万寿寺を加えて計4寺として京都と鎌倉からそれぞれ5寺ずつが五山に選ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, he added Jomyo-ji Temple in Kamakura and Manju-ji Temple in Kyoto for the fifth grade gozan as well, increasing the number of the fifth grade gozan temples to four in total, resulting in that five temples in Kyoto and the equal number of temples in Kamamura were selected as gozan temples.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, he added Jomyo-ji Temple in Kamakura and Manju-ji Temple in Kyoto to the fifth grade gozan, increasing the number of fifth grade gozan temples to four, resulting in five temples in both Kyoto and Kamamura being set as gozan temples.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, he added Jomyo-ji Temple in Kamakura and Manju-ji Temple in Kyoto to the fifth grade gozan, increasing the number of fifth grade gozan temples to four, resulting in five temples in both Kyoto and Kamamura being set as gozan temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その後、3代将軍足利義満の時代に管領細川頼之の要望を聞き入れて臨川寺を五山に加える（永和 (日本)3年（1377年）- 康暦元年（1379年））</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, the third shogun, added Rinsen-ji Temple to the gozan temples at the request of Shogunal Deputy Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA (in the period from 1377 to 1379).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, the third shogun, added Rinsen-ji Temple to the gozan temples at the request of Shogunal Deputy Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA between 1377 and 1379.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, the third shogun, added Rinsen-ji Temple to the gozan temples at the request of Shogunal Deputy Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA between 1377 and 1379.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>しかしながら、康暦の政変で頼之が失脚すると外された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the gozan status of Rinsen-ji Temple was removed when Yoriyuki lost his governmental position due to Koryaku Coup.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the gozan status of Rinsen-ji Temple was removed when Yoriyuki lost his governmental position due to the Koryaku Coup.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the gozan status of Rinsen-ji Temple was removed when Yoriyuki lost his governmental position due to the Koryaku Coup.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>ところが、義満が足利将軍家の菩提寺として相国寺を建立すると、至徳 (日本)3年7月10日_(旧暦)（1386年）に義堂周信・絶海中津らの意見を容れて五山制度の大改革を断行、南禅寺を「五山の上」として全ての禅林の最高位とする代わりに相国寺を「五山」に入れ、更に五山を京都五山と鎌倉五山に分割した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, after building Shokoku-ji Temple as his family temple, Yoshimitsu reformed the gozan system drastically on July 10 (in the old calendar) in 1336 taking into account of opinions of Shushin GIDO, Chushin ZEKKAI and others in the following way: &quot;The status above gozan&quot; should be given to Nanzen-ji Temple, placing the temple at the highest rank of all Zen temples, and instead of that, Sokoku-ji Temple should be included in the gozan temples, and furthermore, the gozan status was divided into Kyoto gozan and Kamakura gozan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after building Shokoku-ji Temple as his family temple, Yoshimitsu reformed the gozan system drastically on July 10 (in the old calendar) 1386 taking into account the opinions of Shushin GIDO, Chushin ZEKKAI and others in the following way: &quot;A status above gozan&quot; should be given to Nanzen-ji Temple, placing the temple at the highest rank of all Zen temples, and in its place Sokoku-ji Temple should be included among the gozan temples, while furthermore, the gozan status was divided into Kyoto gozan and Kamakura gozan.</e>
<cmt>Year altered, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after building Shokoku-ji Temple as his family temple, Yoshimitsu reformed the gozan system drastically on July 10 (in the old calendar) 1386 taking into account the opinions of Shushin GIDO, Chushin ZEKKAI and others in the following way: &quot;A status above gozan&quot; should be given to Nanzen-ji Temple, placing the temple at the highest rank of all Zen temples, and in its place Sokoku-ji Temple should be included among the gozan temples, while furthermore, the gozan status was divided into Kyoto gozan and Kamakura gozan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>両五山はこの格式で固定し、現在に至っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The temples with these gozan statuses have been fixed since then.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The temples with these gozan statuses have remained fixed since then.</e>
<cmt>Word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The temples with these gozan statuses have remained fixed since then.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Asthma bronchiale(id:140161), Alecs.bot(id:194707), VolkovBot(id:105371), Boca samba(id:137526), Novo(id:87875), Chi-Ham(id:143515), 水野白楓(id:22811), 果心居士(id:248111), R28Bot(id:177951), くっちゃめ(id:86793), 663highland(id:18755), Point136(id:211299), K. Takeda(id:119013), Bue(id:237847), Dream100(id:41924), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>