<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>写経</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shakyo (copying of a sutra)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shakyo (copying of a sutra)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shakyo (copying of a sutra)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>写経（しゃきょう）とは、仏教において経典を書写すること、またはその書写された経典のことを指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shakyo is a Buddhist practice to copy Buddhist scriptures, and it also means Buddhist scriptures that have been copied.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shakyo is a Buddhist practice to copy Buddhist scriptures, and it also means Buddhist scriptures that have been copied.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shakyo is a Buddhist practice to copy Buddhist scriptures, and it also means Buddhist scriptures that have been copied.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>写経は、印刷技術が発展していなかった時代には仏法を広めるため、またはひとつの寺院でも複数の僧侶で修行・講義・研究するために必要なことであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shakyo was necessary to spread Buddhism in a time when printing technology had not been developed, and it was also necessary for many priests in a single temple to conduct ascetic practice, to give lectures, and to conduct research.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shakyo was necessary to spread Buddhism in a time when printing technology had not been developed, and it was also necessary for many priests in a single temple to conduct ascetic practice, to give lectures, and to conduct research.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shakyo was necessary to spread Buddhism in a time when printing technology had not been developed, and it was also necessary for many priests in a single temple to conduct ascetic practice, to give lectures, and to conduct research.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>その後、写経することに功徳があることが説かれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, it started to be reasoned that the practice of shakyo would bring blessings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, it started to be reasoned that the practice of shakyo would bring blessings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, it started to be reasoned that the practice of shakyo would bring blessings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>中国では、六朝時代に写経が定型化され、隋・唐のころに盛んに写経が行われるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In China, shakyo was stylized in the Rikucho period, and the practice of shakyo started to be popularized in the time of Sui and Tang Dynasties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In China, shakyo was stylized in the Rikucho period, and the practice of shakyo started to be popularized in the time of the Sui and Tang Dynasties.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In China, shakyo was stylized in the Rikucho period, and the practice of shakyo started to be popularized in the time of the Sui and Tang Dynasties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>日本では673年（天武天皇2年）に川原寺で一切経の写経が行われたのを創始とし、奈良時代には官立の写経所が設けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, complete Buddhist scriptures were copied in the Kawara-dera Temple in 673 for the first time, and a public shakyo center was established in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また東大寺などにも設置され、専門の写経生たちによって、国家事業としてに写経が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, complete Buddhist scriptures were copied in the Kawara-dera Temple in 673 for the first time, and a public shakyo center was established in the Nara period. A public shakyo center was also established in the Todai-ji Temple, and shakyo was practiced by those who practiced shakyo as a profession under a national project.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処写経所は、public shakyo centerと訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, complete Buddhist scriptures were copied in the Kawara-dera Temple in 673 for the first time, and a public shakyo center was established in the Nara period. A public shakyo center was also established in the Todai-ji Temple, and shakyo was practiced by those who practiced shakyo as a profession under a national project.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A public shakyo center was also established in the Todai-ji Temple, and shakyo was practiced by those who practiced shakyo as a profession under a national project.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>平安時代以降は、仏法を広めるということよりも個人的な祈願成就など信仰のために行われるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Heian period and afterward, shakyo started to be practiced out of religious beliefs to fulfill personal prayers, not to spread Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>末法思想が流行すると写経した経典を経筒に納めて埋納する経塚造営が行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Heian period and afterward, shakyo started to be practiced out of religious beliefs to fulfill personal prayers, not to spread Buddhism. When pessimism spread due to decadent-age theory, kyozuka (a mound of Buddhist scriptures) started to be built to put copied Buddhist scriptures in kyozutsu (a tube in which rolled Buddhist scriptures were kept) for burial.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Heian period and afterward, shakyo started to be practiced out of religious beliefs to fulfill personal prayers, not to spread Buddhism. When pessimism spread due to decadent-age theory, kyozuka (a mound of Buddhist scriptures) started to be built to put copied Buddhist scriptures in kyozutsu (a tube in which rolled Buddhist scriptures were kept) for burial.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When pessimism spread due to decadent-age theory, kyozuka (a mound of Buddhist scriptures) started to be built to put copied Buddhist scriptures in kyozutsu (a tube in which rolled Buddhist scriptures were kept) for burial.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>また、亡くなった家族や知人の供養のために、生前に書き残した手紙などを漉返紙や紙背文書として用いて写経する例がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were also instances where people copied Buddhist scriptures on sukigaeshi gami (paper made from dissolved old paper) and as shihai monjo (an old document which was written on the other side of a piece of used paper) made of remaining letters that had been written by deceased family members and friends in order to hold a religious service for them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were also instances where people copied Buddhist scriptures on sukigaeshi gami (paper made from dissolved old paper) and as shihai monjo (an old document which was written on the other side of a piece of used paper) made of remaining letters that had been written by deceased family members and friends in order to hold a religious service for them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were also instances where people copied Buddhist scriptures on sukigaeshi gami (paper made from dissolved old paper) and as shihai monjo (an old document which was written on the other side of a piece of used paper) made of remaining letters that had been written by deceased family members and friends in order to hold a religious service for them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>前者の例として『日本三代実録』に清和天皇の没後に后の1人である藤原多美子が生前の手紙を漉き返して法華経を写経したと記録されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As an example of the former case, it is recorded in Nihon Sandal Jitsuroku (a history book written in the Heian period) that FUJIWARA no Tamiko, one of the wives of Emperor Seiwa copied the Lotus Sutra on paper made of melted letters that had been written by the Emperor when he was alive.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As an example of the former case, it is recorded in Nihon Sandal Jitsuroku (a history book written in the Heian period) that FUJIWARA no Tamiko, one of the wives of Emperor Seiwa copied the Lotus Sutra on paper made of melted letters that had been written by the Emperor when he was alive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As an example of the former case, it is recorded in &quot;Nihon Sandal Jitsuroku&quot; (a history book written in the Heian period) that FUJIWARA no Tamiko, one of the wives of Emperor Seiwa copied the Lotus Sutra on paper made of melted letters that had been written by the Emperor when he was alive.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Nihon Sandal Jitsuroku&quot; としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>後者の例として妙蓮寺 (京都市)所蔵の伏見天皇宸翰法華経が父・後深草天皇宸翰の書状を紙背として用いていることで知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As an example of the latter case, it is known that Fushimi tenno shinkan hokkekyo (the Lotus Sutra written by Emperor Fushimi himself) stored in the Myoren-ji Temple (Kyoto) was written on the other side of a letter written by his father, Emperor Gofukakusa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As an example of the latter case, it is known that Fushimi tenno shinkan hokkekyo (the Lotus Sutra written by Emperor Fushimi himself) stored in the Myoren-ji Temple (Kyoto) was written on the other side of a letter written by his father, Emperor Gofukakusa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As an example of the latter case, it is known that Fushimi tenno shinkan hokkekyo (the Lotus Sutra written by Emperor Fushimi himself) stored in the Myoren-ji Temple (Kyoto City) was written on the other side of a letter written by his father, Emperor Gofukakusa.</e>
<cmt>City補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>書写された経典を「写経」と呼ぶのに対して、北宋代以降に盛行した木版印刷による経典の方は「刊経」と呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whereas copied Buddhist scriptures are called shakyo, Buddhist scriptures that are created as woodblock prints are called kankyo and kankyo became popular in the Northern Sung Dynasty and afterward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whereas copied Buddhist scriptures are called shakyo, Buddhist scriptures that are created as woodblock prints are called kankyo and kankyo became popular in the Northern Sung Dynasty and afterwards.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whereas copied Buddhist scriptures are called shakyo, Buddhist scriptures that are created as woodblock prints are called kankyo and kankyo became popular in the Northern Sung Dynasty and afterwards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="13">
<j>現代日本の各寺院では、写経と言えば、『般若心経』を写経することを指すのが一般的になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For today&apos;s Japanese temples, shakyo generally means the practice of copying the Heart Sutra.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For today&apos;s Japanese temples, shakyo generally means the practice of copying the Heart Sutra.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For today&apos;s Japanese temples, shakyo generally means the practice of copying the Heart Sutra.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), 岡部碩道(id:182846), Ko-ken(id:49348), 水野白楓(id:22811), ウィキ豊(id:82961), くっちゃめ(id:86793), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>