<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>崇伝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suden</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>崇伝（すうでん、1569年（永禄12年） - 1633年2月28日（寛永10年1月20日 (旧暦)））は、安土桃山時代から江戸時代の臨済宗の僧、幕府の政治家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suden (1569 - February 28, 1633) was a person who lived from the Azuchi-Momoyama period to the Edo period, acting as a priest of the Rinzai sect of Buddhism and serving the Tokugawa shogunate as a politician.</e>
<cmt>「幕府の政治家」：後続の記述より、ここでの幕府は徳川幕府のことだと考えられるので、そのように訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suden (1569 - February 28, 1633) was a person who lived from the Azuchi-Momoyama period to the Edo period, acting as a priest of the Rinzai sect of Buddhism and serving the Tokugawa shogunate as a politician.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suden (1569 - February 28, 1633) was a priest of the Rinzai Sect and a politician serving the Tokugawa shogunate from the Azuchi-Momoyama period to the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>表現を他と合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は足利将軍家家臣の一色秀勝。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Hidekazu ISSHIKI, who was a vassal of the Ashikaga family, which inherited the shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Hidekazu ISSHIKI, who was a vassal of the Ashikaga family, which inherited the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Hidekazu ISSHIKI, who was a vassal of the Ashikaga Shogunal family.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>以心崇伝、金地院崇伝（こんちいん すうでん）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also known as Ishin Suden or Konchi-in Suden.</e>
<cmt>以心崇伝→Suden ISHIN[http://kotobank.jp/word/%E4%BB%A5%E5%BF%83%E5%B4%87%E4%BC%9D]→Ishin Suden[「以心」が姓に当たるものであるのか否かを判断できず、インターネット検索（Google, book search）を行いました。&quot;Ishin Suden&quot;の方が&quot;Suden Ishin&quot;よりも圧倒的に多くヒットしましたので、&quot;Ishin Suden&quot;としました。]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also known as Ishin Suden or Konchi-in Suden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also known as Ishin Suden or Konchiin Suden.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>「黒衣の宰相」と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is called a &quot;Prime Minister in Black Robes&quot; (a Buddhist priest who rendered political service as if he were a prime minister).</e>
<cmt>「黒衣の宰相」：&quot;Prime Minister in Black Robes&quot;の後に訳注を付けました。不要であれば削除してください。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is called a &quot;Prime Minister in Black Robes&quot; (a Buddhist priest who rendered political service as if he were a prime minister).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was called a &apos;Prime Minister in Black Robes&apos; (a Buddhist priest who rendered political service as if he were a prime minister).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変え過去形にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>1569年（永禄12年）、京都に生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suden was born in Kyoto in 1569.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suden was born in Kyoto in 1569.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suden was born in Kyoto in 1569.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>父の没後に南禅寺で玄圃霊三に師事し、南禅寺塔頭の金地院の靖叔徳林に嗣法、さらに醍醐寺三宝院で学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his father&apos;s death, Suden studied Buddhism under Genpo Reisan at Nanzen-ji Temple, then inherited Buddhist doctrines from Tokurin SEISHUKU, the chief priest of Konchi-in subtemple of Nanzen-ji Temple, and thereafter further studied Buddhism at Sanbo-in subtemple of Daigo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>玄圃霊三→Reisan GENPOU→Reisan GENPO→Genpo Reisan[仮表記です。「玄圃」が俗人の姓に相当するものなのか否かを判断できませんでした。Googleのbook searchを行いましたが、&quot;Genpo Reisan&quot;、&quot;Reisan Genpo&quot;が同一の書籍内でヒットしました。判断の根拠となり得るデータが少なく、いずれを採用すべきか判断できませんでした。本ファイルの他の僧侶の名前と同様に、暫定的に前者を採用しました。]塔頭→subtemple (especially one founded to commemorate the death of a high priest)[括弧内の訳注は、今回の翻訳では省略しました（この原文では、「塔頭」の定義が大きなウェイトを占めておらず、訳注を併記することで訳文が冗長になり、かえって読みづらくなると判断したからです）。]靖叔徳林→Tokurin SEISHUKU[http://www.lib.city.minato.tokyo.jp/yukari/j/man-detail.cgi?name=%E4%BB%A5%E5%BF%83%E5%B4%87%E4%BC%9D]→Seishuku Tokurin[仮表記です。「靖叔」が俗人の姓に相当するものなのか否かを判断できませんでした。Googleのbook searchを行いましたが、&quot;Seishuku Tokurin&quot;、&quot;Tokurin Seishuku&quot;のいずれもヒットせず、いずれを採用すべきか判断できませんでした。暫定的に前者を採用しました。]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his father&apos;s death, Suden studied Buddhism under Genpo Reisan at Nanzen-ji Temple, then inherited Buddhist doctrines from Tokurin SEISHUKU, the chief priest of Konchi-in subtemple of Nanzen-ji Temple, and thereafter further studied Buddhism at Sanbo-in subtemple of Daigo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his father&apos;s death, Suden studied Buddhism under Genpo Reisan at Nanzen-ji Temple, then inherited Buddhist doctrines from Tokurin SEISHUKU, the chief priest of Konchiin Subtemple of Nanzen-ji Temple, and thereafter further studied Buddhism at Sanboin Subtemple of Daigo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>福厳寺や禅興寺、建長寺などの住職となり、1605年(慶長10年)には南禅寺の270世住職となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having served as chief priest of Fukugon-ji, Zenko-ji and Kencho-ji Temples, Suden became the 270th chief pries of Nanzen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>福厳寺→Fukugon-ji Temple[「福厳寺」という名前の寺院は複数あり、この原文で言及されているものがそのうちのどれであるかを特定できませんでした。多くのものが「ふくごんじ」と読まれているようですので、これに倣い&quot;Fukugon-ji Temple&quot;としました（暫定）。]禅興寺→Zenko-ji Temple[「禅興寺」という名前の寺院は複数あり（現存しないものも含めて）、この原文で言及されているものがそのうちのどれであるかを特定できませんでした。そのうちのいくつかが「ぜんこうじ」と読まれているようですので、これに倣い&quot;Zenko-ji Temple&quot;としました（暫定）。]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having served as chief priest of Fukugon-ji, Zenko-ji and Kencho-ji Temples, Suden became the 270th chief priest of Nanzen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having served as chief priest of Fukugon-ji, Zenko-ji and Kencho-ji Temples, Suden became the 270th chief priest of Nanzen-ji Temple in 1605.</e>
<cmt>年号を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>1608年には豊臣政権に代わり江戸幕府を開いた徳川家康に招かれて駿府へ赴き、没した西笑承兌に代わり外交関係の書記を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1608, Suden was invited to Sunpu by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, who located the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) in Edo by superseding the Toyotomi government, and served as a diplomatic secretary in place of Jotai SAISHO.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1608, Suden was invited to Sunpu by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, who located the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) in Edo by superseding the Toyotomi government, and served as a diplomatic secretary in place of Jotai SAISHO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1608, Suden was invited to Sunpu by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, who located the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) in Edo by superseding the Toyotomi government, and served as a diplomatic secretary in place of last Jotai SAISHO.</e>
<cmt>没した、を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>やがて幕政にも参加するようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After a while, he came to have an involvement in shogunal administration.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After a while, he came to have involvement in shogunal administration.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After a while, he came to have involvement in shogunal administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>閑室元佶や板倉勝重とともに寺社行政に携わり、キリスト教の禁止や、寺院諸法度、幕府の基本方針を示した武家諸法度、朝廷権威に制限を加える禁中並公家諸法度の制定などに関係する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Engaged in administration concerning Buddhist temple/Shinto shrine affairs together with Genkitsu KANSHITSU and Katsushige ITAKURA, he was involved in projects, including the prohibition of the Christian religion, as well as the establishment of the Acts for the Buddhist Temples, the Acts for the Military Houses, where the basic policies of the bakufu were laid out, and the Acts Governing the Imperial Court and Nobility.</e>
<cmt>寺院諸法度→→Acts for the Buddhist Temples[定訳不明、仮訳です。]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Engaged in administration concerning Buddhist temple/Shinto shrine affairs together with Genkitsu KANSHITSU and Katsushige ITAKURA, he was involved in projects, including the prohibition of the Christian religion, as well as the establishment of the Acts for the Buddhist Temples, the Acts for the Military Houses, where the basic policies of the bakufu were laid out, and the Acts Governing the Imperial Court and Nobility.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Engaged in administration concerning Buddhist temple and Shinto shrine affairs together with Genkitsu KANSHITSU and Katsushige ITAKURA, he was involved in projects, including the prohibition of the Christian religion, as well as the establishment of Jiin shohatto (the Acts for the Buddhist Temples), Buke shohatto (the Acts for the Military Houses) where the basic policies of the bakufu were laid out, and Kinchu narabini kuge shohatto (a set of regulations that applied to the emperor and the Kyoto nobles).</e>
<cmt>マイページに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>豊臣家との戦いである大坂の役の発端にもなった方広寺鐘銘事件にも関与する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also involved in the Incident of Hoko-ji Temple, where Hideyoshi TOYTOMI and Ieyasu TOKUGAWA were confronted with each other concerning the text that Hideyoshi had inscribed on the bell of Hoko-ji Temple, (this incident triggered the Siege of Osaka Castle, a battle between the Tokugawa family and Toyotomi family).</e>
<cmt>方広寺鐘銘事件→→the Incident of Hoko-ji Temple, where Hideyoshi TOYTOMI and Ieyasu TOKUGAWA were confronted with each other concerning the text that Hideyoshi had inscribed on the bell of Hoko-ji Temple[固有名詞としての定訳はないようですが、暫定的に&quot;the Incident of Hokoji-Temple&quot;としました。]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also involved in the Incident of Hoko-ji Temple, where Hideyoshi TOYTOMI and Ieyasu TOKUGAWA confronted each other concerning the text that Hideyoshi had inscribed on the bell of Hoko-ji Temple, (this incident triggered the Siege of Osaka Castle, a battle between the Tokugawa family and Toyotomi family).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also involved in the Incident of Hoko-ji Temple Bell which triggered the Siege of Osaka, a battle against Toyotomi family).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>1616年(元和 (日本)2年)に家康が死去すると神号を巡り天海と争った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Ieyasu in 1616, Suden had a dispute against Tenkai concerning the shingo (a name given to a deified person) to be given to the late Ieyasu, who was to be made a Shinto deity..</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処神号→→shingo (a name given to a deified person)[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Ieyasu in 1616, Suden had a dispute with Tenkai concerning the shingo (a name given to a deified person) to be given to the late Ieyasu, who was to be made a Shinto deity..</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Ieyasu in 1616, he had a dispute with Tenkai concerning the shingo (literally, &quot;shrine name&quot;), which is the title given to a Shinto shrine.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>崇伝は明神として祀る事を主張するが、最終的には天海の主張する権現に決定する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suden insisted on deifying Ieyasu under the name of Myojin (meaning the manifestation of a deity) while Tenkai insisted on deifying him under the name of Gongen (meaning the incarnation of a deity), which resulted in Gongen being adopted.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suden insisted on deifying Ieyasu under the name of Myojin (meaning the manifestation of a deity) while Tenkai insisted on deifying him under the name of Gongen (meaning the incarnation of a deity), which resulted in Gongen being adopted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suden insisted on deifying Ieyasu under the name of Myojin (a gracious god) while Tenkai insisted on deifying him under the name of Gongen (meaning the incarnation of a god), which was adopted eventually.</e>
<cmt>マイページに合わせ、最終的に、を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>1618年(元和4年)には江戸に金地院 (東京都港区)を建立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1618, Suden raised Konch-in Temple in Edo (Minato Ward, Tokyo Metropolis, as it is known today).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1618, Suden raised Konch-in Temple in Edo (Minato Ward, Tokyo Metropolis, as it is known today).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1618, Suden raised Konchin Temple (Minato-ku Ward, Tokyo Prefecture) in Edo.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>翌1619年には僧録となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following 1619, he took office as soroku (official who was to supervise Zen temples and manage personnel affairs at those temples).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following year, 1619, he took office as soroku (official to supervise Zen temples and manage personnel affairs at those temples).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following year, 1619, he assumed the position of Soroku (highest-ranking priest of the Gozan, the leader of the Zen sect).</e>
<cmt>統一リストなどに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>以後、金地院僧録は崇伝の法系に属する僧で占められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, the office of soroku, which was to be held by the chief priest of Konchi-in subtemple of Nanzen-ji Temple, was held by the priest who inherited the Buddhist doctrines directly from Suden and the following generations who inherited such doctrines in the same manner.</e>
<cmt>法系→Buddhist lineage[定訳不明。単語レベルでは&quot;Buddhist lineage&quot;が妥当と思われますが、この原文については、単語レベルで逐語的に訳出することができなかったため、より具体的な表現を用いて訳出しております。]金地院僧録→the office of soroku, which was to be held by the chief priest of Konchi-in subtemple of Nanzen-ji Temple[金地院僧録という職名が存在していたのか否かを確認できませんでした。インターネット検索により、僧録職には南禅寺金地院の院主が任じられることが分かり、この原語もその事実に基づくものであると解釈しました。よって、「金地院僧録」という職名としては扱わず、上記のように訳出しました。]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, the office of soroku, which was to be held by the chief priest of Konchi-in subtemple of Nanzen-ji Temple, was held by the priest who inherited the Buddhist doctrines directly from Suden and the following generations inherited such doctrines in the same manner.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, the position of soroku of Konchiin Subtemple was succeeded by the priests who inherited the Buddhist doctrines directly from Suden.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>南禅寺(金地院)と江戸の金地院を往還しながら政務を執り、天海と共に黒衣の宰相と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suden administered affairs of the bakufu, moving between Nanzen-ji Temple (Konchi-in subtemple) and Konchi-in Temple in Edo, and was called &quot;Prime Minister in Black Robes&quot;, as Tenkai was.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suden administered the affairs of the bakufu, moving between Nanzen-ji Temple (Konchi-in subtemple) and Konchi-in Temple in Edo, and was called &quot;Prime Minister in Black Robes&quot;, as Tenkai was.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suden administered the affairs of the bakufu, moving between Nanzen-ji Temple (Konchiin Subtemple) and Konchiin Temple in Edo, and both he and Tenkai were called Prime Minister in Black Robes.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>また、南禅寺や建長寺の再建復興にも力を尽くし、古書の収集や刊行などの文芸事業も行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Suden strived for the reconstruction/restoration of Nanzen-ji Temple and Kencho-ji Temple, and also undertook literary activities, such as the collection and publication of ancient books.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Suden strived for the reconstruction/restoration of Nanzen-ji Temple and Kencho-ji Temple, and also undertook literary activities, such as the collection and publication of ancient books.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Suden strived for the reconstruction and restoration of Nanzen-ji Temple and Kencho-ji Temple, and also undertook literary activities, such as the collection and publication of ancient books.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>1627年（寛永4年）に起こった紫衣事件に対する幕府の強硬措置に、反対意見書を提出した沢庵宗彭、玉室宗珀、江月宗玩の3人を遠島の厳罰に処すつもりであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With regard to the Shie Incident, where the Emperor Gomizunoo permitted a priest to wear a purple robe for a high-ranking priest without consent of the Edo bakufu in violation of the Acts Governing the Imperial Court and Nobility, Suden intended to punish Soho TAKUAN, Sohaku GYOKUSHITSU and Sogan KOGETSU, who presented written objection to the tough measures taken by the bakufu in response to the incident, by exiling them to a remote island.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With regard to the Shie Incident, where Emperor Gomizunoo permitted a priest to wear the purple robe of a high-ranking priest without the consent of the Edo bakufu, in violation of the Acts Governing the Imperial Court and Nobility, Suden intended to punish Soho TAKUAN, Sohaku GYOKUSHITSU and Sogan KOGETSU, who presented written objection to the tough measures taken by the bakufu in response to the incident, by exiling them to a remote island.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suden intended to punish Soho TAKUAN, Sohaku GYOKUSHITSU and Sogan KOGETSU, who presented written objection to the tough measures taken by the bakufu with the Shie Incident in 1627, by exiling them to a distant island.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>しかし天海や柳生宗矩らのとりなしによって、沢庵は出羽上山に、玉室は奥州棚倉へ配流、江月はお咎めなしとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, through the intervention of Tenkai and Munenori YAGYU, Takuan and Gyokushitu were exiled to Kaminoyama in the Province of Dewa and Tanagura in the Province of Mutsu, respectively, and Kogetsu was subjected to no punishment.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, through the intervention of Tenkai and Munenori YAGYU, Takuan and Gyokushitu were exiled to Kaminoyama in the Province of Dewa and Tanagura in the Province of Mutsu, respectively, and Kogetsu was subjected to no punishment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, through the intervention of Tenkai and Munenori YAGYU, Takuan and Gyokushitu were exiled to Kaminoyama in Dewa Province and Tanagura in Mutsu Province, respectively, and Kogetsu was subjected to no punishment.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>1633年2月28日（寛永10年1月20日）に死去、享年64。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 28, 1633, Suden passed away at the age of 64.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 28, 1633, Suden passed away at the age of 64.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 28, 1633, Suden passed away at the age of 64.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="22">
<j>著作に日記の『本光国師日記』『本光国師語録』、外交関係の記録に『異国日記』。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He left behind the following literary works: &quot;Honko Kokushi Nikki&quot; (journal; the term &quot;Honko Kokushi&quot; is a portion of his posthumous title); &quot;Honko Kokushi Goroku&quot; (collection of sayings); &quot;Ikoku Nikki&quot; (journal concerning diplomatic affairs).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He left behind the following literary works: &quot;Honko Kokushi Nikki&quot; (journal; the term &quot;Honko Kokushi&quot; is a portion of his posthumous title); &quot;Honko Kokushi Goroku&quot; (collection of sayings); &quot;Ikoku Nikki&quot; (journal concerning diplomatic affairs).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He left behind the following literary works: &quot;Honko Kokushi Nikki&quot; (journal; the term &quot;Honko Kokushi&quot; is a portion of his posthumous title); &quot;Honko Kokushi Goroku&quot; (collection of sayings); &quot;Ikoku Nikki&quot; (journal concerning diplomatic affairs).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="23">
<j>その権勢の大きさと、方広寺鐘銘事件時のような強引とも思える政治手法により、世人から「大欲山気根院僭上寺悪国師」とあだ名されたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that people gave him the nickname, &apos;Daiyokuzan Kikon-in Senjo-ji Akukokushii&apos;, which implicates his greediness, powerfulness, obtrusiveness and unpopularity, because he was very powerful and used political techniques that seems somewhat forcible in the Incident of Hoko-ji Temple and so forth.</e>
<cmt>大欲山気根院僭上寺悪国師→Daiyokuzan Kikon-in Senjo-ji Akukokushi[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that people gave him the nickname, &apos;Daiyokuzan Kikon-in Senjo-ji Akukokushii&apos;, which implicates his greediness, powerfulness, obtrusiveness and unpopularity, because he was very powerful and used political techniques that seem somewhat strong in the Incident of Hoko-ji Temple and so forth.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that people gave him the nickname, &apos;Daiyokuzan Kikonin Senjo-ji Akukokushii,&apos; which implicates his greediness, powerfulness, obtrusiveness and unpopularity, because he was very powerful and used political techniques that seem somewhat strong in the Incident of Hoko-ji Temple Bell and so forth.</e>
<cmt>Bellを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Izayohi(id:13095), Y.Sanada(id:36926), Tomzo(id:16777), Kstigarbha(id:13376), 水野白楓(id:22811), Cprobot(id:97843), 味っ子(id:17086), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), 黒砂糖(id:38164), 遠藤(id:30275), Ｈｉｒｏ２００６(id:59115), パの字(id:34188), Yonoemon(id:55450), R28Bot(id:177951), Loveless(id:129239), Carl Daniels(id:20253), Corwin(id:973), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>