<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>還相回向</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genso-eko (還相回向)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genso-eko (還相回向)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genso-eko</e>
<cmt>漢字をのぞきました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>還相回向（げんそうえこう）は、浄土教の重要な教義のひとつである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genso-eko (Amida&apos;s directing of virtue for our return to this world from the Pure Land) is one of the important dogmas of Jodo-kyo (the Pure Land teaching).</e>
<cmt>黄色ハイライトセルはThe Collected Works of Shinran (http://www.shinranworks.com/)からの引用です。同サイトからの引用とそうでない訳とが混在している場合には、同サイトからの引用部をボールド字体で示してあります。往相回向ファイルでは著者は「浄土真宗の重要な教義・・」と記していますが、ここでは「浄土教」となっており、上記サイトのglossaryで浄土教はPure Land teachingとなっているので、その訳語をあてはめました。同参考資料に関してAlfred Bloom(a pioneer of Jodo Shinshu studies in the English-speaking world.=Wikipedia)という浄土真宗研究の第一人者（という紹介がある）が次のように述べています：The Collected Works of Shinran, the product of over 20 years of serious effort by the Hongwanji International Center, is a competent, creative and courageous endeavor to offer Shin Buddhism to the world. (http://www.shindharmanet.com/documents/collectedworks.htm)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genso-eko (Virtue as instructed by Amida for returing from the Pure Land to this world) is one of the important Jodo-kyo doctrines (teachings of the Pure Land).</e>
<cmt>rewritten</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genso-eko (Virtue as instructed by Amida for retiring from the Pure Land to this world) is one of the important Jodo Sect doctrines (teachings of the Pure Land).</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>阿弥陀如来よりたまわる２種類の回向のあり方のひとつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of the two aspects of Eko (Amida Tathagata&apos;s directing of virtue).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is one of the two aspects of Eko (Amida Tathagata&apos;s directing of virtue).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is one of the two aspects of Eko (Amida Tathagata&apos;s directing of virtue).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>もう一方の「往相回向」と合わせ、「往還二回向」とよび、浄土真宗における、中心教義である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Including Oso-eko (往相回向; Amida&apos;s directing of virtue for our going forth to the Pure Land), the other of the said two kinds, the two Eko are collectively called &apos;O-Kan Ni-eko&apos; (往還二回向) forming the primary dogma of Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Including Oso-eko (往相回向; Virtue as instructed by Amida for going to the Pure Land), the alternative of the two types, both Eko together are called &apos;O-Kan Ni-eko&apos; (往還二回向) forming the primary Jodo Shinshu doctrine (True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism).</e>
<cmt>rewriteen</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Including Oso-eko (Virtue as instructed by Amida for going to the Pure Land), the alternative of the two types, both Eko together are called &apos;O-Kan Ni-eko&apos; forming the primary doctrine of Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism).</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>曇鸞が、その主著『無量寿経優婆提舎願生偈註』（『往生論註』） の中で、下記の通り「還相回向」を釈している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">T&apos;an-luan(early Chinese Pure Land thinker and popularizer) explains Genso-eko in his main literary work Muryoju-kyo Ubadaisha Ganshoge-chu (Commentary on [Vasubandhu&apos;s] Upadesa on the Sutra of Immeasurable Life)(also known as Ojoron-chu or Wangsheng lun zhu (Notes on the Treatise on Birth [in the Pure Land]) as follows.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処原文は完結しておらず、一セル一文の原則通りになっていません。よってB10セルの内容を加え、「以下のごとく説いている」いう訳文にしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">T&apos;an-luan(early Chinese Pure Land philosopher and popularizer) explains Genso-eko in his main literary work Muryoju-kyo Ubadaisha Ganshoge-chu (Commentary on [Vasubandhu&apos;s] Upadesa on the Sutra of Immeasurable Life) (also known as Ojoron-chu or Wangsheng lun zhu - Notes on the Treatise about Birth [in the Pure Land]) as follows:</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">T&apos;an-luan (early Chinese Pure Land philosopher and popularizer) explains Genso-eko in his main literary work &quot;Muryoju-kyo Ubadaisha Ganshoge-chu&quot; (Commentary on [Vasubandhu&apos;s] Upadesa on the Sutra of Immeasurable Life) (also known as Ojoron-chu or Wangsheng lun zhu - Notes on the Treatise about Birth (in the Pure Land)) as follows:</e>
<cmt>ルールに従い、原文を分割修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>還相とは、かの土に生じをはりて、奢摩他・毘婆舎那・方便力成就することを得て、生死の稠林に回入して、一切衆生を教化して、ともに仏道に向かへしむるなり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Directing virtue for return to this world means that after being born in that land, fulfilling samatha and vipasyana, and gaining the power of compassionate means, one returns and enters the thick forests of birth-and-death, teaches and guides all sentient beings, and brings all to enter the Buddha-way together.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Instructions on virtue for returning to this world teaches that after being born in the pure land and completing the requirements for samatha and vipasyana, attaining the power of compassion, one can return and enter the deep forests of birth-and-death, teach and guide sentient beings, and bring together all who enter the Buddha-wayr.</e>
<cmt>rewritten</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Instructions on virtue for returning to this world teaches that after being born in the pure land and completing the requirements for samatha and vipasyana, attaining the power of compassion, one can return and enter the deep forests of birth-and-death, teach and guide sentient beings, and bring together all who enter the Buddha-wayr.</e>
<cmt>ルールに従い、原文を分割修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>続けて、下記の通り二種の回向を釈している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He continues to explain the two kinds of eko as follows.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（B15セルの内容を合わせて訳してあります）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He continues to explain the two types of eko as follows.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He continues to explain the two types of eko as follows.</e>
<cmt>ルールに従い、原文を分割修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>もしは往、もしは還、みな衆生を抜いて生死海を度せんがためなり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whether with regard to the aspect for going forth or the aspect for return, all is entirely for the sake of bringing sentient beings across the ocean of birth-and-death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whether one is going forth or returning, it is all entirely for the sake of leading sentient beings across the sea of birth-and-death.</e>
<cmt>rewritten</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whether one is going forth or returning, it is all entirely for the sake of leading sentient beings across the sea of birth-and-death.</e>
<cmt>ルールに従い、原文を分割修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>このゆゑに、「回向を首として大悲心を成就することを得たまへるがゆゑなり」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus it is stated, &quot;It is to fulfill the mind of great compassion, taking the directing of virtue as foremost.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, &quot;It is to fulfill a compassionate mind by accepting virtue as first priority.&quot;</e>
<cmt>rewritten</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, &apos;It is to fulfill a compassionate mind by accepting virtue as first priority.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ルールに従い、原文を分割修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>（意訳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Broad meaning:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Broad meaning:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Broad meaning:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>還相回向というのは、阿弥陀如来の浄土に往生して、止観行を成就し教化する力を獲得し、生死の世界、つまりこの世に還り来たって、すべての衆生を教化して、一緒に仏道に向かわせようとする力を、阿弥陀如来から与えられること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genso-eko means that one is endowed by Amida Tathagata with the ability to attain birth in the Pure Land of Amida Tathagata; to fulfill the practice of concentration and observation; to gain power of enlightening; to return to the world of birth-and-death, i.e. this world; to convert all sentient beings; and to guide them to follow the Buddha&apos;s way together.</e>
<cmt>D9セルの訳文は原文ほど難解ではありませんが、that land、samatha and vipasyana、power of compassionate means、thick forests of birth-and-death等の具体的な意味が不明瞭なので「意訳」部分も英訳し、Broad meaningと名付けました。意訳中最後の行にある「とする力」が何を対象とした「力」かが不明確ですが、「すべて阿弥陀のおかげ」という浄土教の基本的なスタンスから「往生・・成就・・獲得・・還り・・教化」のすべてを対象とするものと解釈しました。「仏道に向かう」に対応する表現らしきものとして&quot;to follow the Buddhist&apos;s way&quot;の使用例が多くみられるので採用しましたが、あくまでも仮訳です。また、意訳中の「止観」は研究社新和英大辞典からの引用で、天台宗の言葉という解説がありましたがそのまま使用しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genso-eko means that one is endowed by Amida Tathagata with the ability to attain birth in the Pure Land of Amida Tathagata; to fulfill the practice of concentration and observation; to gain the power of enlightenment; to return to the world of birth-and-death, i.e. this world; to convert all sentient beings; and guide them to follow the way of Buddha together.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genso-eko means that one is endowed by Amida Tathagata with the ability to attain birth in the Pure Land of Amida Tathagata; to fulfill the practice of concentration and observation; to gain the power of enlightenment; to return to the world of birth-and-death, i.e. this world; to convert all sentient beings; and guide them to follow the way of Buddha together.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>ここで注意したいのは、これを単に、浄土に往生した者が、菩薩の相をとり再び穢土に還り来て、衆生を救済するはたらきを阿弥陀如来から与えられること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What should be noted here is that if Genso-eko is interpreted as that a being who attained birth in the Pure Land is bestowed by Amida with the ability to return to the defiled land taking the form of a bodisattva to save people, one is inclined to conceptualize something like the spirit which has returned from the Pure Land to this world.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処原文が次の2セルにわたって分散していますが、一文に纏めざるを得ませんでした。３セルの原文は、単につなぎ合わせればいいと思いますが、ルール上それが許されるかどうかが不明だったのでそのままにしてあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What should be noted here is that if Genso-eko is interpreted as that a being who attained birth in the Pure Land is bestowed by Amida with the ability to return to the defiled land taking the form of a bodisattva to save people, one is inclined to conceptualize something like a spirit which has returned from the Pure Land to this world.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What should be noted here is that if Genso-eko is a being who attained birth in the Pure Land is bestowed by Amida with the ability to return to the defiled land taking the form of a bodhisattva to save people.</e>
<cmt>原文を1文にし、訳文を分けました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>このように解釈すると、浄土から帰ってきた霊魂のようなものを想定してしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処(E20のコメントを参照してください）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Interpreted as that, one is inclined to conceptualize something like a spirit which has returned from the Pure Land to this world.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。「このように・・・」と原文を変更し、上訳文を分けました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>学者の中にも、そのように理解している者もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact some scholars do understand that way.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact some scholars do interpret it that way.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact some scholars do interpret it that way.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="14">
<j>しかし、妙好人の庄松（しょうま）が、オラが喜んで捨てた「南無阿弥陀仏」を、拾うて喜ぶ者がおると端的に表現したように、還相回向を、念仏者の口から出てくる名号を聞いて、称名をする人間がいることを、阿弥陀如来のはたらきととらえ、自らが称えた名号を指して浄土から還ってきた相（すがた）と解する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as indicated in a very forthright statement made by Shoma, a well known myokonin (a religious person): &apos;Some guys happily pick up Namu-amida-butsu which I delightedly spitted out of my mouth,&apos; Genso-eko can be interpreted as follows.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処B25, B26のセル内全文とB27セルの「と端的に表現したように」までと「還相回向を・・・解する」の部分を一文として訳出しましたが、原文は変更していません。かなり大幅な変更が必要になり、原文変更の原則との兼ね合いが分かりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as indicated in a very forthright statement made by Shoma, a well known myokonin (a religious person): &apos;Some have happily picked up Namu-amida-butsu which I have happily spit from my mouth,&apos; Genso-eko can be interpreted as follows.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as indicated in a very forthright statement made by Shoma, a well known myokonin (a religious person): Some have happily picked up Namu-amida-butsu which I have happily spit from my mouth,&apos; Genso-eko can be interpreted as hearing someone chanting the Name of the Buddha (Namu-amida-butsu), the sentient beings grasp that the existence that someone chanting the Name is the works of Amida Tathagata, and that the Name they themselves chant is the very form of returning from the Pure Land.</e>
<cmt>原文が途中で分割されていたので、訳文と合わせて1文に統合しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>こちらが浄土教における、還相回向の本来の概念である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the primary concept of Genso-eko in the Pure Land teaching.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the primary a concept of Genso-eko in the Pure Land teachings.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the primary a concept of Genso-eko in the teachings of Jodo sect.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="16">
<j>また親鸞が、『顕浄土真実教行証文類』において、下記の通り釈した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Genso-eko should be interpreted as the practice of benefitting others, as Shinran explains in &apos;A Collection of Passages Revealing the True Teaching, Practice and Realization of the Pure Land Way&apos; as follows.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処B30とB36のセルの内容を合わせて訳してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, Genso-eko should be interpreted as the practice of benefitting others, as Shinran explains in &apos;A Collection of Passages Revealing the True Teaching, the Practice and Realization of the Pure Land Way&apos; as follows;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also Shinran explains in &quot;A Collection of Passages Revealing the True Teaching, the Practice and Realization of the Pure Land Way&quot; as follows:</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。ルールに従い原文・訳文を分割し、原文に「下記の通り釈した」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>還相の利益は利他の正意を顕すなり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Benefiting in the aspect of return expresses the true intent of benefiting others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Benefiting from returning is an example of one&apos;s true intention of benefiting others.</e>
<cmt>rewritten</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Benefiting from returning is an example of one&apos;s true intention of benefiting others.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>ここをもつて論主（世親）は広大無碍の一心を宣布して、あまねく雑染堪忍の群萌を開化す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, the author of the Treatise, Vasubandhu, proclaims the vast and unhindered mind that is single, thereby universally awakening</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this regard, Vasubandhu, the author, says the single broad unfettered mind awakens universally</e>
<cmt>rewritten</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this regard, Vasubandhu, the author, says the single broad unfettered mind awakens universally.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>宗師（曇鸞）は大悲往還の回向を顕示して、ねんごろに他利利他の深義を弘宣したまへり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Master T&apos;an-luan clarifies Amida&apos;s compassionate directing of virtue for our going to the Pure Land and our return to this world; and he widely teaches, with care and concern, the profound significance of benefited by the Other and of benefiting others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amida&apos;s compassionate instructions of virtue necessary for reaching the Pure Land and then returning again to this world, is made clear by the MasterT&apos;an-luan; and with concern and care, he teaches the significance of those who are benefited and then go on to benefit others.</e>
<cmt>rewritten</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amida&apos;s compassionate instructions of virtue necessary for reaching the Pure Land and then returning again to this world, is made clear by the MasterT&apos;an-luan; and with concern and care, he teaches the significance of those who are benefited and then go on to benefit others.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>仰いで奉持すべし、ことに頂戴すべしと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reverently embrace these words; receive them in deepest homage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reverently embrace these words; receive them in deepest homage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reverently embrace these words; receive them in deepest homage.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>このように、還相回向は利他行と解するべきである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As above, Genso-eko should be interpreted as ritagyo (altruistic practices).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。原文を「このように」と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="22">
<j>さらに親鸞は、『浄土文類聚鈔』において、下記の通り釈した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinran further refers in &apos;Passages on the Pure Land Way&apos; to the Twenty-second Vow of the Forty-eight Vows of Amida as the basis for his explanation as follows.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（B43の内容を加えて訳してありますが、原文は動かしていません）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinran further refers in &apos;Passages on the Pure Land Way&apos; to the Twenty-second Vow from the Forty-eight Vows of Amida as the basis for his explanation as follows.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinran further explains in &quot;Passages on the Pure Land Way&quot; as follows:</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。ルールに従い原文・訳文を分割し、原文に「下記の通り釈した」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>二つに還相回向といふは、すなはち利他教化地の益なり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Second is Amida&apos;s directing of virtue for our return to this world. This is the benefit we receive, the state of benefiting and guiding others.</e>
<cmt>参考訳文は２文にわかれています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The state of benefiting and guiding others is the benefit we receive as explained by Amida&apos;s instructions concerning virtue, in order to return to this world.</e>
<cmt>rewritten</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Second, Genso-eko is benefit of Ritakyoke-chi (competency to enlighten others to head for the True Pure Land).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>すなはちこれ四十八願第二十二願より出でたり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It arises from the Vow of necessary attainment of the rank next to Buddhahood, also known as &quot;the Vow for the attainment of Buddhahood after one lifetime.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「四十八願第二十二願」という願番号は原文の著者が便宜上使用した可能性があります。原著である浄土文類聚鈔の本来の文章では願番号ではなく具体的に「願の名称と２つの別名」が記載されているようで、それが英訳文に反映されています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This comess from making a Vow for the necessary attainment of being ranked next to the Buddhahood, in otherwords; &quot;after living one&apos;s life, the Vow to achieve Buddhahood&quot;</e>
<cmt>rewritten</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It came out from the 22th Vow of the 48 Vows.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。原文どおり訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>また一生補処の願と名づけ、また還相回向の願と名づくべし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It may further be called &quot;the Vow of directing virtue for our return to this world.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「また一生補処の願と名づけ」に対応する訳はD40のセルに含まれています＝also known as以下</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">We can also say: &quot;the Vow to manage virtue in order to return to this world.&quot;</e>
<cmt>rewritten</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also I named it as issho fusho no gan (Vow of succession to Buddhahood after one lifetime) or Genso-eko no gan (Vow of Genso-eko).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。原文どおり訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="26">
<j>このように、四十八願の内、第二十二願を根拠として挙げている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（E38のコメントを参照してください）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As above, he points the 22 Vow from the 48 Vows of Amida as the basis for his explanation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。原文を「このように」と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 マイコン坊主(id:338), Resto1578(id:168692), 無空(id:17049), けんち(id:5147), Chi-Ham(id:143515), 木もれ陽(id:120323), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>