<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>教如</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyonyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyonyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyonyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>教如（きょうにょ、永禄元年9月16日 (旧暦)（1558年10月27日） - 慶長19年10月5日 (旧暦)（1614年11月6日））は、石山本願寺の第12代門主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyonyo (27 October, 1558 - 6 November 1614) the twelfth chief priest of the Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyonyo (27 October, 1558 - 6 November 1614) the twelfth chief priest of the Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyonyo (6 November, 1558 - 6 November, 1614) the twelfth chief priest of the Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>諱は光寿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His imina, or personal name, is Koju.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His imina, or personal name, is Koju.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His imina (personal name) was Koju.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>第11代門主・顕如の長男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the first son of eleventh chief priest, Kennyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the first son of eleventh chief priest, Kennyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the first son of eleventh chief priest, Kennyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>朝倉義景の娘と婚約していたが破談となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was engaged to daughter of Yoshikage ASAKURA, but it was broken off.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was engaged to a daughter of Yoshikage ASAKURA, but it was broken off.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was engaged to a daughter of Yoshikage ASAKURA, but it was broken off.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>1570年、織田信長との間で石山戦争が始まると、父を助けて信長と徹底して戦った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Ishiyama War broke out against Nobunaga ODA in 1570, he helped his father and fought exhaustively against Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Ishiyama War broke out against Nobunaga ODA in 1570, he helped his father and fought exhaustively against Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Ishiyama War broke out against Nobunaga ODA in 1570, he helped his father and fought exhaustively against Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>しかし1580年、信長の猛攻の前に父が正親町天皇との勅命講和を受け入れて石山本願寺を退去しようとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But in 1580, his father tried to leave Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple after the violent attacks by Nobunaga, accepting the Imperial order by Emperor Ogimachi to make peace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But in 1580, his father tried to leave Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple after the violent attacks by Nobunaga, accepting the Imperial order by Emperor Ogimachi to make peace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But in 1580, his father tried to leave Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple after the violent attacks by Nobunaga, accepting the Imperial order by Emperor Ogimachi to make peace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>このとき教如はあくまでも徹底抗戦を主張し、勅命講和を無視してなおも本願寺に立て籠もって信長に抗戦したため、父親から義絶されてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyonyo claimed to resist to the last and fought against Nobunaga ignoring the Imperial order for peace and shutting himself in Hongan-ji Temple, and was disowned by his father.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyonyo claimed to resist to the last and fought against Nobunaga ignoring the Imperial order for peace and shutting himself in Hongan-ji Temple, and was disowned by his father.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyonyo claimed to resist to the last and fought against Nobunaga ignoring the Imperial order for peace and shutting himself in Hongan-ji Temple, and was disowned by his father.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>その後、教如は大和国、近江国、紀伊国、山城国、摂津国、安芸国など諸国を転々と流浪する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he wandered through many regions such as Yamato Province, Omi Province, Kii Province, Yamashiro Province, Settsu Province, and Aki Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he wandered through many regions such as Yamato Province, Omi Province, Kii Province, Yamashiro Province, Settsu Province, and Aki Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he wandered through many regions such as Yamato Province, Omi Province, Kii Province, Yamashiro Province, Settsu Province, and Aki Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>1582年、信長が本能寺の変で死去すると、父と和解した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1582, when Nobunaga died in Honnoji Incident, he reconciled with his father.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1582, when Nobunaga died in the Honnoji Incident, he reconciled with his father.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1582, when Nobunaga died in the Honnoji Incident, he reconciled with his father.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>1592年に顕如が死去した後、長男である教如は本願寺住職の座を継ごうとしたが、それに対して豊臣秀吉がかつて父に義絶されたこと、信長と徹底抗戦した経緯などを理由に教如は後継者にふさわしくないと反対し、教如の異母弟の准如を後継者に指名した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Kennyo died in 1592, his first son Kyonyo tried to succeed the chief priest of Hongan-ji Temple, but Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI opposed to the succeeding by Kyonyo with reasons that he was once disowned by his father, he resisted exhaustively against Nobunaga in the past, and so on, and appointed Junnyo, his half-brother, as the successor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Kennyo died in 1592, his first son Kyonyo tried to succeed the chief priest of Hongan-ji Temple, but Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI opposed the succession by Kyonyo with the reasons that he was once disowned by his father, he resisted exhaustively against Nobunaga in the past, and so on, and appointed Junnyo, his half-brother, as the successor.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Kennyo died in 1592, his first son Kyonyo tried to succeed the chief priest of Hongan-ji Temple, but Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI opposed the succession by Kyonyo with the reasons that he was once disowned by his father, he resisted exhaustively against Nobunaga in the past, and so on, and appointed Junnyo, his half-brother, as the successor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>このため、教如は後を継ぐことができなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this, Kyonyo could not succeed the chief priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this, Kyonyo could not succeed to become the chief priest.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this, Kyonyo could not succeed to his father&apos;s position.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし秀吉死後に徳川家康が政権を掌握すると、家康はかつて一向宗に苦しめられたことがあるという経緯からこの教如と准如の争いに介入する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when Ieyasu TOKUGAWA came into power after Hideyoshi&apos;s death, from the reason that Ieyasu was once troubled by the Ikko sect, started to intervene in the quarrel between Kyonyo and Junnyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when Ieyasu TOKUGAWA came into power after Hideyoshi&apos;s death, because of the reason that Ieyasu was once troubled by the Ikko sect, he started to intervene in the quarrel between Kyonyo and Junnyo.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when Ieyasu TOKUGAWA came into power after Hideyoshi&apos;s death, because of the reason that Ieyasu was once troubled by the Ikko Sect, he started to intervene in the quarrel between Kyonyo and Junnyo.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>家康は教如に肩入れすることとなり、関ヶ原の戦い前夜の諜報活動（これが石田三成方に察知されて、辞世の句を認めるほど危険な目にも遭ったが、織田秀信らの協力や門徒の奮戦もあって無事帰洛を果たしている）を経て1602年、後陽成天皇の勅許を背景にして京都七条の烏丸に真宗本廟を建立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ieyasu became to support Kyonyo, and after experiencing the espionage in the night before the Battle of Sekigahara (it was sensed by the Mitsunari ISHIDA side and was encountered in such dangerous situation that he had wrote farewell poem, but with the helps by Hidenobu ODA and others and hard fighting by his followers, he at last returned to Kyoto), he erected Shinshu-honbyo Mausoleum in Karasuma in Shichijo of Kyoto in 1602, with the Imperial sanction by the Emperor Goyosei on his background.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ieyasu came to support Kyonyo, and after experiencing espionage on the night before the Battle of Sekigahara (it was sensed by the Mitsunari ISHIDA side and was encountered in such a dangerous situation that he had written a farewell poem, but with the help of Hidenobu ODA and others and hard fighting by his followers, he at last returned to Kyoto), he erected Shinshu-honbyo Mausoleum in Karasuma in Shichijo in Kyoto in 1602, with Imperial sanction from the Emperor Goyosei in the background.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ieyasu came to support Kyonyo, and after experiencing espionage on the night before the Battle of Sekigahara (it was sensed by the Mitsunari ISHIDA side and was encountered in such a dangerous situation that he had written a farewell poem, but with the help of Hidenobu ODA and others and hard fighting by his followers, he at last returned to Kyoto), he erected Shinshu-honbyo Mausoleum in Karasuma in Shichijo in Kyoto in 1602, with Imperial sanction from the Emperor Goyozei in the background.</e>
<cmt>読みを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>このため准如が継承した七条堀川の本願寺は西本願寺と呼ばれるようになり、本願寺教団は東西に分裂した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this, Hongan-ji Temple in Shichijo Horikawa, succeed by Junnyo, became to be called Nishi Hongan-ji Temple, and the religious community of Hongan-ji Temple was split into East and West.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this, Hongan-ji Temple in Shichijo Horikawa, succeed by Junnyo, came to be called Nishi Hongan-ji Temple, and the religious community of Hongan-ji Temple was split into East and West.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this, Hongan-ji Temple in Shichijo Horikawa, succeed by Junnyo, came to be called Nishi Hongan-ji Temple, and the religious community of Hongan-ji Temple was split into East and West.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>1614年、57歳で死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1614, he died in the age of 57.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1614, he died at the age of 57.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1614, he died at the age of 57.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Resto1578(id:168692), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), R28Bot(id:177951), Charenji(id:7908), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), 調声人(id:126495), Kogane(id:28186), Kenryu(id:181554), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), シェーラ(id:17988), Ons(id:21830), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), Kagetudo(id:163875), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>