<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>釈迦如来</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shakanyorai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shakanyorai</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shakanyorai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>釈迦如来（しゃかにょらい、しきゃじらい）または釈迦牟尼仏は、仏教の開祖釈迦〔姓名：瞿曇悉達多（クドンシッタルタ）梵語：Gautama siddhaartha（ガウタマ・シッダールタ）パーリ語：Gotama Siddhattha（ゴータマ・シッダッタ）〕を仏（仏陀）として敬う呼び方。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shakanyorai, Shikyajirai or Shakamuni-butsu is a title of respect for Shaka (Kudonshittaruta, Gautama Siddhaartha in Sanskrit, Gotama Siddhatthaa in Pali), a founder of Buddhism, as Buddha.</e>
<cmt>英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shakanyorai (Shikyajirai or Shakamuni-butsu) is a title of respect for Shaka (Kudonshittaruta, Gautama Siddhaartha in Sanskrit, Gotama Siddhatthaa in Pali), a founder of Buddhism, as Buddha.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shakanyorai (Shikyajirai or Shakamuni-butsu) is a title of respect for Shaka (Kudonshittaruta, Gautama Siddhaartha in Sanskrit, Gotama Siddhatthaa in Pali), a founder of Buddhism, as Buddha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>上座部仏教における釈迦牟尼仏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shakamuni-butsu in Theravada Buddhism</e>
<cmt>上座部仏教→http://www.clio.ne.jp/home/sigeru-t/tripinttherauniv1.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shakamuni-butsu in Theravada Buddhism</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shakamuni-butsu in Theravada Buddhism</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>上座部仏教（いわゆる小乗仏教）では、釈迦牟尼仏は現世における唯一の仏とみなされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Theravada Buddhism (so-called Hinayana) Shakamuni-butsu is regarded as the sole Buddha in this world.</e>
<cmt>小乗仏教→Webster Online Dictionary</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Theravada Buddhism (so-called Hinayana), Shakamuni-butsu is regarded as the sole Buddha in this world.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Theravada Buddhism (so-called Hinayana), Shakamuni-butsu is regarded as the sole Buddha in this world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>最高の悟りを得た仏弟子は阿羅漢（アラカン　如来十号の一）と呼ばれ、仏である釈迦の教法によって解脱した聖者と位置づけられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The disciple who achieve supreme enlightenment was called Arakan and placed as a saint who was delivered from earthly bondage by sermons of Shaka as Buddha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The disciple who achieved supreme enlightenment was called Arakan, and he was positioned as a saint who was delivered from earthly bondage by the sermons of Shaka as Buddha.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The disciple who achieved supreme enlightenment was called Arakan, and he was positioned as a saint who was delivered from earthly bondage by the sermons of Shaka as Buddha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>大乗仏教における釈迦牟尼仏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Syakamuni-butsu in Mahayana Buddhism</e>
<cmt>大乗仏教→Webster Online Dictionary</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Syakamuni-butsu in Mahayana Buddhism</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shakamuni-butsu in Mahayana Buddhism</e>
<cmt>shakamuni-butsuとしました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>諸仏の一仏としての釈迦牟尼仏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Syakamuni-butsu as one of the Buddha</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Syakamuni-butsu as one of the Buddhas</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shakamuni-butsu as one of the Buddhas</e>
<cmt>shakamuni-butsuとしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>大乗仏教では、釈迦牟尼仏（釈迦如来）は十方（東南西北とその中間である四隅の八方と上下）三世（過去、未来、現在）の無量の諸仏の一仏で、現在の娑婆（サハー、堪忍世界）の仏である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Mahayana Buddhism, Syakamuni-butsu (Syakanyorai) is one of the immeasurable Buddha at the ten directions (east, south, west and north, each middles of these, up and down) and three worlds (past, future and present) and a Buddha in this corrupt world.</e>
<cmt>娑婆（サハー、堪忍世界）→Webster Online Dictionary</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Mahayana Buddhism, Syakamuni-butsu (Syakanyorai) is one of the immeasurable BuddhaS at the ten directions (east, south, west and north, each middles of these, up and down) and three worlds (past, future and present) as well as a Buddha in this corrupt world.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Mahayana Buddhism, Shakamuni-butsu (Shakanyorai) is one of the immeasurable Buddhas at the ten directions (east, south, west and north, each midpoint, up and down) and three worlds (past, future and present) as well as a Buddha in this corrupt world.</e>
<cmt>BuddhaS→Buddhas　syaka →shaka</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また、三身説では仏が現世の人々の前に現れた姿であるとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, Trikaya, three bodies of Buda, considers Buddha as a figure in front of the people of present world.</e>
<cmt>三身説→http://www.kheper.net/topics/Buddhism/trikaya.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, Trikaya, the three bodies of Buddha, considers Buddha a figure in front of the people of the present world.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, Trikaya, the three bodies of Buddha, considers Buddha a figure in front of the people of the present world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>本仏としての釈迦牟尼仏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Syakamuni-butsu as Original Buddha</e>
<cmt>本仏→http://www.lioncity.net/buddhism/index.php?s=bc3b58726ae5c7b16fcdc666f3c716b0&amp;showtopic=74520&amp;pid=1143194&amp;st=40&amp;#entry1143194</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Syakamuni-butsu as the original Buddha</e>
<cmt>article, lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shakamuni-butsu as the original Buddha</e>
<cmt>syaka →shaka</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>大乗仏教の中でも、日蓮宗・法華宗では宗派の本尊とする本仏が誰かという論争が有り、釈迦本仏論と日蓮本仏論の対立がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among Mahayana Buddhism sects, there is a dispute that who is the main image in Nichiren and Hokke sects and there is a conflict between a thesis which considers Shaka as Original Buddha and another which considers Nichiren as one.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the Mahayana Buddhism sects, there is a dispute over who is the main image in Nichiren and Hokke sects; additionally, there is a conflict between a thesis that considers Shaka to be the original Buddha and another that considers it to be Nichiren.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the Mahayana Buddhism sects, there is a dispute over who is the main image in Nichiren and Hokke sects; additionally, there is a conflict between a thesis that considers Shaka to be the original Buddha and another that considers it to be Nichiren.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>このうち釈迦本仏論の本尊が本仏としての釈迦牟尼仏である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among these, the main image of the former is Shakamuni-butsu as Original Buddha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among these, the main image of the former is Shakamuni-butsu as the original Buddha.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among these, the main image of the former is Shakamuni-butsu as the original Buddha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>かつて天台宗においても唱えられていたようであるが、今では日蓮宗・法華宗でしきりに論じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was argued in Tendai sect before, but is often discussed among Nichiren and Hokke sects these days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was argued in the Tendai sect before, but today it is often discussed among the Nichiren and Hokke sects.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was argued in the Tendai sect before, but today it is often discussed among the Nichiren and Hokke sects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>法華経の如来寿量品第十六に登場する無量長寿の釈迦牟尼世尊がこれに当たる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This means Shakamuni-seson who has an immeasurable long life (無量長寿） in Nyorai Juryo Hon No.16 in Hoke-kyo Sutra.</e>
<cmt>如来寿量品→http://comet.endless.ne.jp/users/fnwo/h-16.htm、無量長寿→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This means Shakamuni-seson, who has an immeasurably long life (無量長寿) in Nyorai Juryo Hon No. 16 of the Hoke-kyo sutra.</e>
<cmt>grammar, space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This means Shakamuni-seson, who has an immeasurably long life (無量長寿) in Nyorai Juryo Hon No. 16 of the Hoke-kyo sutra.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>ユーラシア大陸の古代インドで活躍し肉体を持ったゴータマ・シッダルタ（釈迦）を指すのではなく、インドで肉体を持って生誕した前の悠久の昔から存在し、入寂の後も遥か将来まで存在して行くという信仰上の釈迦牟尼世尊である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This does not mean historical Gautama Siddhartha (Shaka), who was flourished at ancient India in Eurasian Continent but means religious Shakamuni-seson who exists from ancient time before he was born in India and continues to exist in future after his nirvana.</e>
<cmt>入寂→Webster Online Dictionary</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This does not mean the historical Gautama Siddhartha (Shaka), who flourished in ancient India on the Eurasian Continent, but instead it means the religious Shakamuni-seson, who has existed from ancient times before he was born in India and continues to exist in the future after his nirvana.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This does not mean the historical Gautama Siddhartha (Shaka), who flourished in ancient India on the Eurasian Continent, but instead it means the religious Shakamuni-seson, who has existed from ancient times before he was born in India and continues to exist in the future after his nirvana.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>無量の諸仏を迹仏とし、本仏釈尊のコピーに過ぎず、言わば、本仏釈尊を月とすれば諸仏は千枚田に映る千の月であるという論である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to that thesis, other immeasurable Buddha are the Trace Buddha, only copies of Original Buddha Syakuson, so that if you see him as the moon, other Buddha are 1,000 moons reflected in the rice terrace.</e>
<cmt>迹仏→http://www.lioncity.net/buddhism/index.php?showtopic=87439&amp;st=20、千枚田→英辞郎on the WEB　（棚田として英訳）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to that thesis, other immeasurable Buddhas are the Trace Buddha, who is only a copy of the original Buddha Syakuson, so that if you see him as the moon other Buddha will be 1,000 moons reflected in the rice terrace.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to that thesis, other immeasurable Buddhas are the Trace Buddha, who is only a copy of the original Buddha Shakuson, so that if you see him as the moon the other Buddha will be 1,000 moons reflected in a rice terrace.</e>
<cmt>sya →sha</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>釈迦本仏論の宗門の信仰の対象である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is an object of faith for the groups who consider Shaka as Original Buddha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is an object of faith for the groups that consider Shaka to be the original Buddha.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is an object of faith for the groups that consider Shaka to be the original Buddha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>久遠本仏とも呼び、日蓮宗総本山身延山久遠寺（山梨県南巨摩郡）の寺名にもなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Kuon Honbutsu, which is reflected on the temple&apos;s name, Nichiren Sect of Buddhism Grand Head Temple Minobusan Kuonji Temple (Minamikomagun Yamanashi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>日蓮宗総本山身延山久遠寺→http://nichiren-shu.org/AboutUs/major/minobu.html、山梨県南巨摩郡→http://www.post.japanpost.jp/cgi-zip/zipcode.php?pref=19&amp;city=1193631</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called Kuon Honbutsu, which is reflected in the temple&apos;s name, Nichiren Sect of Buddhism Grand Head Temple Minobusan Kuonji Temple (Minamikomagun Yamanashi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called Kuon Honbutsu, which is reflected in the temple&apos;s name as the Nichiren Sect of Buddhism grand head temple Minobusan Kuon-ji Temple (Minamikoma-gun, Yamanashi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>Kuon-ji grand head templeとしました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>なお、法華経では、釈迦如来はインドの菩提樹下で始めて覚ったのではなく五百塵点劫の遠い過去に成仏していたと説かれるが、涅槃経ではさらに未来について強く言及し、如来は常住不変であると説き、末法も最終的には方便説として否定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, in Hoke-kyo Sutra it is described that Shakanyorai did not become Buddha under the line tree for the first time but had already awaked in an immeasurable past time; in Nehan-gyo there are more descriptions about future, which says Nyorai exists forever without any change and denies Mappo, Age of the Final Dharma, finally as an expediency.</e>
<cmt>末法→http://www.jodo.org/terminology/japanese.html#M</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, in the Hoke-kyo sutra it is described that Shakanyorai did not become Buddha under the line tree for the first time but had already awaked in an immeasurable past time; in Nehan-gyo there are more descriptions about the future, which states that Nyorai exists forever without any change and ultimately denies Mappo, Age of the Final Dharma, as an expediency.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, in the Hoke-kyo Sutra it is stated that Shakanyorai did not become Buddha under the line tree for the first time but had already awakened in an immeasurable past time; in Nehan-gyo sutra there are more descriptions about the future, which states that Nyorai exists forever without any change and ultimately denies Mappo (Age of the Final Dharma) as an expediency.</e>
<cmt>awaked →awakened　Nehan-gyo sutraとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>したがって法華経では久遠実成を説き、涅槃経では久遠常住を説いたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it is said that Hoke-kyo teaches Kuonjitsuzyo (久遠実成) and Nehan-gyo teaches Kuonshochu (久遠常住).</e>
<cmt>久遠実成、久遠常住→http://jisho.dnuts.jp/word/%E4%B9%85%E9%81%A0%E5%B8%B8%E4%BD%8F</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it is said that Hoke-kyo teaches Kuonjitsuzyo (久遠実成) and Nehan-gyo teaches Kuonshochu (久遠常住).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it is said that Hoke-kyo Sutra teaches Kuonjitsujo (久遠実成) and Nehan-gyo Sutra teaches Kuonshochu (久遠常住).</e>
<cmt>Kuonjitsujoとしました。　sutra追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>造形化された釈迦如来</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shakanyorai shaped to an image</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shakanyorai shaped into an image</e>
<cmt>preposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shakanyorai shaped into an image</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>釈迦如来は、インド以来、広く仏教の流布した地域で造像されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Statues of Shakanyorai were shaped at broad areas where Buddhism had spread from India.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Statues of Shakanyorai were shaped over wide-ranging areas, where Buddhism had spread from India.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Statues of Shakanyorai were shaped over wide-ranging areas, where Buddhism had spread from India.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>その中心は、実在の釈迦の伝記としての仏伝を絵解き風に造形化したもの、あるいは、その一場面を単独で造像したものなどであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of them were designed to explain real Shaka&apos;s biography in a picture or shaped its one scene separately.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of them were designed to describe the real Shaka&apos;s biography as a picture or to shape a particular scene separately.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of them were designed to describe the real Shaka&apos;s biography as a picture or to shape a particular scene separately.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>日本では、誕生像、苦行像、降魔像、説法像、涅槃像などとして造像が行なわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, statue of birth, statue of training, statue of struggling against devil, statue of sermon and statue of nirvana were shaped.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, statue of birth, statue of training, statue of struggling against the devil, statue of a sermon being given and statue of nirvana were shaped.</e>
<cmt>articlegrammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, statue of birth, statue of training, statue of struggling against the devil, statue of a sermon being given and statue of nirvana were shaped.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>なかでも説法像が一番一般的な造形であり、説法印などによって、釈迦が法を説く姿を表現している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among them, statue of sermon is the most popular and expresses the figure of Shaka who preaches Dharma by seppo-in, his gesture for sermon.</e>
<cmt>説法印→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them, the &quot;sermon&quot; statue is the most popular; it expresses the figure of Shaka, who preaches Dharma as indicated by seppo-in, his gesture for a sermon.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them, the &quot;sermon&quot; statue is the most popular; it expresses the figure of Shaka, who preaches Dharma as indicated by seppo-in, his gesture for a sermon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="20">
<j>作例としては、奈良の法隆寺金堂、京都の蟹満寺の銅像、奈良の室生寺金堂、京都の大報恩寺の木像などが著名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, bronze statues at Horyu-ji Temple Kondo in Nara and at Kaniman-ji Temple in Kyoto, and wooden figures of Muroo-ji Temple Kondo in Nara and Daihoon-ji Temple in Kyoto are famous.</e>
<cmt>法隆寺金堂→定訳不明、蟹満寺→http://www.city.kizugawa.lg.jp/article.php?id=435&amp;f=275&amp;t=cat、室生寺金堂→定訳不明、大報恩寺→http://www.y-morimoto.com/s_saigoku/s_saigoku16.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, the bronze statues at Horyu-ji Temple Kondo in Nara and at Kaniman-ji Temple in Kyoto are famous, as are the wooden figures of Muroo-ji Temple Kondo in Nara and Daihoon-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, the bronze statues at Horyu-ji Temple Kondo in Nara and at Kaniman-ji Temple in Kyoto are famous, as are the wooden figures of Muroo-ji Temple Kondo in Nara and Daihoon-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>また、京都清凉寺の瑞像を模した清凉寺式釈迦如来も広範に流布している形式である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the style of Seiryoji-type Shakanyorai which modeled on Zuizo of Seiryo-ji Temple in Kyoto is also spread widely.</e>
<cmt>京都清凉寺→http://kaiwai.city.kyoto.jp/search/whole_search.php?lcode=all&amp;keyword=%B5%FE%C5%D4%C0%B6%D1%DA%BB%FB&amp;lang=ja&amp;submit_search=true、瑞像→http://www.aisf.or.jp/~jaanus/deta/z/zuizou.htm、清凉寺式釈迦如来→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, the style of the Seiryoji-type Shakanyorai, which was modeled on Zuizo of Seiryo-ji Temple in Kyoto, is also widespread.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, the style of the Seiryoji-type Shakanyorai, which was modeled on Zuizo of Seiryo-ji Temple in Kyoto, is also widespread.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="22">
<j>釈迦三尊として祭壇に置かれる場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is often placed on alters Shaka triad.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is often placed on the altars of the Shaka triad.</e>
<cmt>completed</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is often placed on the altars of the Shaka triad.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>脇侍は文殊菩薩と普賢菩薩が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two attendants are often Monju Bosatsu and Fugen Bosatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The two attendants are often Monju Bosatsu and Fugen Bosatsu.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The two attendants are often Monju Bosatsu and Fugen Bosatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>法華宗・日蓮宗では三宝尊（一塔両尊）の形式がとられることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Hoke and Nichiren sects the style of Sanposon (三宝尊) (Ittoryozon, 一塔両尊) is often adopted.</e>
<cmt>三宝尊（一塔両尊）→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Hoke and Nichiren sects, the style of Sanposon (三宝尊) (Ittoryozon, 一塔両尊) is often adopted.</e>
<cmt>comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Hokke and Nichiren sects, the style of Sanposon (三宝尊) (Ittoryozon, 一塔両尊) is often adopted.</e>
<cmt>Hoke→ Hokke</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>これは中心が題目の書かれた多宝塔（宝塔）で両脇に釈迦如来と多宝如来が祭祀者から見て左右に並び、その下に僧としての日蓮像がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this style, Taho Pagoda (pagoda) in which Nichiren chant is written, is placed at the center, Shakanyorai on the left side and Tahonyorai on the right side seen from the person who enshrines, and a statue of Nichiren as a monk is placed under them.</e>
<cmt>題目→http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=%E9%A1%8C%E7%9B%AE&amp;dtype=3&amp;stype=0&amp;dname=2na&amp;ref=1&amp;index=00553200、多宝塔→http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110003880984/、宝塔→Webster Online Dictionary</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this style the Taho Pagoda (pagoda), in which the Nichiren chant is written, is placed at the center, with Shakanyorai on the left side and Tahonyorai on the right side as seen by the person who enshrines, and a statue of Nichiren as a monk is placed under them.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this style the Taho Pagoda (pagoda), in which the Nichiren chant is written, is placed at the center, with Shakanyorai on the left side and Tahonyorai on the right side as seen by the person who enshrines, and a statue of Nichiren as a monk is placed under them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>真言</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mantora, Shingon</e>
<cmt>英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mantora, Shingon</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mantora, Shingon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>ノウマク・サンマンダ・ボダナン・バク</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noumaku Samanda Bodanan Baku</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noumaku Samanda Bodanan Baku</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noumaku Sanmanda Bodanan Baku</e>
<cmt>sanmandaとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>フィクションにおける釈迦如来</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shakanyorai in fiction</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shakanyorai in fictional works</e>
<cmt>completed</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shakanyorai in fictional works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="27">
<j>西遊記 - 孫悟空を諌め、三蔵法師を天竺へ導く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Journey to West&quot; - remonstrates with Goku SON, Sun Wu Kong, and leads Sanzohoshi to Tenjiku, India.</e>
<cmt>孫悟空→http://www.onedayinmay.net/AllGodsChildren/SunWuKong.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Journey to the West&quot; remonstrates with Goku Son, Sun Wu Kong, and leads Sanzohoshi to Tenjiku, India.</e>
<cmt>lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Journey to the West&quot; remonstrates with Goku SON (Sun Wu Kong), and leads Sanzohoshi to Tenjiku, India.</e>
<cmt>SONとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="28">
<j>お釈迦様 - 西遊記 (フジテレビ系テレビドラマ)…（堺正章）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oshakasama -&quot;Journey to West&quot; (TV drama of Fuji Television Network, Inc) (Masaaki SAKAI)</e>
<cmt>フジテレビ→http://www.fujitv.co.jp/en/about_us/corprate_data.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oshakasama, &quot;Journey to the West&quot; (TV drama from Fuji Television Network, Inc.) (Masaaki Sakai)</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The role of &quot;Oshakasama&quot; in &quot;Journey to the West&quot; (a TV drama from Fuji Television Network, Inc.) was played by Masaaki SAKAI.</e>
<cmt>構成を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Izayohi(id:13095), ロリ(id:613), U3002(id:66126), Enthousiasme(id:42600), Charenji(id:7908), 優曇華(id:6461), Authority(id:10737), Setu(id:88), Bokemiann(id:10834), るがこむ(id:181), 文姫(id:66661), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Boca samba(id:137526), Nakadati(id:26815), GURAX(id:107578), Ash(id:15625), Shikai shaw(id:14306), あお。(id:39226), 無空(id:17049), 210.(id:9838), Suisui(id:69), ウィキ豊(id:82961), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>