<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>文覚</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mongaku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mongaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mongaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>文覚（もんがく、保延5年（1139年） - 建仁3年7月21日 (旧暦)（1203年8月29日））は平安時代から鎌倉時代初期にかけての真言宗の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mongaku (1139 - August 29, 1203) was a person who lived from the Heian Period to the early Kamakura Period as a priest of the Shingon Sect of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mongaku (1139 - August 29, 1203) was a person who lived from the Heian Period to the early Kamakura Period as a priest of the Shingon Sect of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mongaku (1139 - September 5, 1203) was a priest of the Shingon Sect of Buddhism who lived from the Heian period to the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>弟子には上覚、明恵らがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had several disciples, including Jokaku and Myokei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had several disciples, including Jokaku and Myokei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had several disciples, including Jokaku and Myokei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>俗名は遠藤盛遠（えんどうもりとお）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His name as a layman was Moritoo ENDO.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His name as a layman was Moritoo ENDO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His secular name was Morito ENDO.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>元は摂津源氏傘下の摂津国渡辺党の武士であり、鳥羽天皇の皇女統子内親王（上西門院）に仕えていた北面の武士だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being originally a samurai belonging to Watanabe party in the Province of Settsu, which was under the umbrella of Settsu-Genji (Minamoto clan), he served Imperial Prince Muneko (Empress Dowager Josai), a daughter of the Emperor Toba, as a Hokumen samurai (samurai on guard at the ex-emperor&apos;s palace).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Being originally a samurai belonging to the Watanabe party in the Province of Settsu, which was under the umbrella of Settsu-Genji (Minamoto clan), he served Imperial Prince Muneko (Empress Dowager Josai), a daughter of Emperor Toba, as a Hokumen samurai (samurai on guard at the ex-emperor&apos;s palace).</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Being originally a samurai belonging to the Watanabe party in Settsu Province, which was under the umbrella of Settsu-Genji (Minamoto clan), he served Imperial Princess Muneko (Josaimonin), a daughter of Emperor Toba, as a Hokumen samurai (samurai on guard at the ex-emperor&apos;s palace).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>従兄弟で同僚の渡辺渡（わたなべわたる）の妻、袈裟御前に横恋慕し、誤って殺してしまったことから出家したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is said to have loved Kesa Gozen, the wife of Wataru WATANABE, who was his male cousin and worked together with him, killed her by mistake, and consequently become a priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is said to have loved Kesa Gozen, the wife of Wataru WATANABE, who was his male cousin and worked together with him, killed her by mistake, and consequently become a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is said to have loved Kesa Gozen, the wife of Wataru WATANABE, who was his male cousin and worked together with him, killed her by mistake, and consequently become a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>（この事件を元にして明治期に長唄『鳥羽の恋塚』が作られた。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Based on this incident, the nagauta (ballad sung to samisen accompaniment, sometimes with other instruments) &quot;Toba no Koizuka&quot; was created in the Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Based on this incident, the nagauta (ballad sung to samisen accompaniment, sometimes with other instruments) &quot;Toba no Koizuka&quot; was created in the Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Based on this incident, the nagauta (ballad sung to samisen accompaniment, sometimes with other instruments) &quot;Toba no Koizuka&quot; (tomb of the lover in Toba) was created in the Meiji period.)</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>荒廃しきっていた神護寺を再興するため後白河天皇に強訴したため、渡辺党の棟梁の摂津源氏の源頼政の知行国であった伊豆国に配流された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wishing to revive Jingo-ji Temple, where priests were absolutely corrupt, Mongaku presented a direct petition to the Emperor Goshirakawa, which resulted in Mongaku being exiled to the Province of Izu, which was the feudal domain of MINAMOTO no Yorimasa of Settsu-Genji (Minamoto clan), the head of Watanabe party.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wishing to revive Jingo-ji Temple, where priests were absolutely corrupt, Mongaku presented a direct petition to Emperor Goshirakawa, which resulted in Mongaku being exiled to the Province of Izu, which was the feudal domain of MINAMOTO no Yorimasa of Settsu-Genji (Minamoto clan), the head of the Watanabe party.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wishing to revive Jingo-ji Temple, where priests were absolutely corrupt, Mongaku presented a direct petition to Emperor Goshirakawa, which resulted in Mongaku being exiled to Izu Province, which was the feudal domain of MINAMOTO no Yorimasa of Settsu-Genji (Minamoto clan), the head of the Watanabe party.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>そこで同じく配流の身だった源頼朝に平家打倒の挙兵を促す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mongaku persuaded MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, who was also exiled to the Province of Izu, to take up arms against the Taira family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mongaku persuaded MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, who was also exiled to the Province of Izu, to take up arms against the Taira family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mongaku persuaded MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, who was also exiled to Izu Province, to take up arms against the Taira family.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その後、頼朝や後白河法皇の庇護を受けて各地の寺院を修復した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, he restored temples of various places under the patronage of Yoritomo and the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, he restored temples in various places under the patronage of Yoritomo and the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, he restored temples in various places under the patronage of Yoritomo and the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>頼朝が死去すると後鳥羽天皇に疎まれて佐渡国へ流罪となり客死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Yoritomo&apos;s death, however, Mongaku got on the wrong side of the Emperor Gotoba, then was exiled to the Province of Sado and died there.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Yoritomo&apos;s death, however, Mongaku got on the wrong side of Emperor Gotoba, and was then exiled to the Province of Sado and died there.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Yoritomo&apos;s death, however, Mongaku got on the wrong side of Emperor Gotoba, and was then exiled to Sado Province and died there.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>カンヌ国際映画祭でグランプリを受賞した『地獄門』（監督・衣笠貞之助）は、長谷川一夫が遠藤盛遠に扮し、渡辺渡（山形勲）の妻の袈裟御前（京マチ子）に横恋慕し、出家にいたるドラマを描いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Jigokumon (Gates of Hell)&quot;, a film directed by Teinosuke KINUGASA that won the Grand Prix at the Cannes Film Festival, depicts a drama where Moritoo Endo (whose role was played by Kazuo HASEGAWA) loved Kesa Gozen (whose role was played by Machiko KYO), the wife of Wataru WATANABE (whose role was played by Isao YAMAGATA), and consequently became a priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Jigokumon (Gates of Hell)&quot;, a film directed by Teinosuke KINUGASA that won the Grand Prix at the Cannes Film Festival, depicts a drama where Moritoo Endo (whose role was played by Kazuo HASEGAWA) loved Kesa Gozen (whose role was played by Machiko KYO), the wife of Wataru WATANABE (whose role was played by Isao YAMAGATA), and consequently became a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Jigokumon&quot; (Gates of Hell), a film directed by Teinosuke KINUGASA that won the Grand Prix at the Cannes Film Festival, depicts a drama where Morito ENDO (whose role was played by Kazuo HASEGAWA) loved Kesa Gozen (whose role was played by Machiko KYO), the wife of Wataru WATANABE (whose role was played by Isao YAMAGATA), and consequently became a priest.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>手塚治虫の「火の鳥 (漫画)乱世編」には遠藤盛遠と文覚が別人として両方登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hinotori (the Phoenix): Turbulent Times&quot; (manga) depicts Moritoo ENDO and Mongaku as different persons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hinotori (the Phoenix): Turbulent Times&quot; (manga) depicts Moritoo ENDO and Mongaku as different persons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Hinotori (the Phoenix): Turbulent Times&quot; (cartoon) by Osamu TEZUKA depicts Morito ENDO and Mongaku as different persons.</e>
<cmt>表記を変え、手塚治虫、を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Amler(id:101250), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), Hannah(id:15935), Sayosayo(id:109202), Dignaaga(id:91287), Trilingual(id:48344), Junger(id:10282), 沢田(id:40580), Ons(id:21830), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>