<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>玄叡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>玄叡（げんえい、生年不詳 - 承和 (日本)7年（840年））は、平安時代前期の三論宗の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genei (year of birth unknown – July, 840) is a monk of the Sanron Sect of Busshism who lived in the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genei (year of birth unknown – July, 840) was a monk of the Sanron Sect of Busshism who lived during the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genei (year of birth unknown – 840) was a priest of the Sanron sect of Buddhism who lived during the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>出自については不詳である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His place of origin is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His place of origin is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His place of origin is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>大安寺安澄に三論教学を学び、その後は奈良西大寺 (奈良市)に住した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He learned Sanron teachings from Ancho of the Daian-ji Temple, and thereafter lived in Nara Saidai-ji Temple (Nara City).</e>
<cmt>Yahoo百科事典に、「安澄（あんちょう）」 については「安澄大徳」ともいう、「大安寺に住して」とあるので、「大安寺の安澄」と解釈しました。http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/%E5%AE%89%E6%BE%84/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He learned Sanron teachings from Ancho of the Daian-ji Temple, and thereafter lived in Nara Saidai-ji Temple (Nara City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He learned Sanron teachings from Ancho of the Daian-ji Temple, and thereafter lived in Nara Saidai-ji Temple (Nara City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>826年（天長3年）権律師に任じられ、翌827年（天長4年）には宮中薬師如来像慶讃の法座で宗義を講じ律師に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 826 he was appointed to Gon Risshi (supernumerary master of discipline) and to Risshi (the third rank of priest following Sojo and Sozu) in 827, the next year, after he lectured in the court on the doctrine of the sect at the Buddhist religious service of the memorial ceremony for the completion of Yakushi Nyorai-zo (statue of Yakushi Nyorai, the Healing Buddha).</e>
<cmt>下のアドレスの論文の本文(pp. 98-108)を見ると、いろいろな宗派において律師は権律師よりも上ですが、上から3番目ではなくかなり下の方です。ただ玄叡の頃は高かったのかもしれませんので、Risshi (the third rank of priest following Sojo and Sozu)とそのまま書きました。http://nels.nii.ac.jp/els/110004646398.pdf?id=ART0007367600&amp;type=pdf&amp;lang=en&amp;host=cinii&amp;order_no=&amp;ppv_type=0&amp;lang_sw=&amp;no=1267018470&amp;cp=</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 826 he was appointed to Gon Risshi (supernumerary master of discipline) and to Risshi (the third rank of priest following Sojo and Sozu) in 827, the next year, after he lectured in the court on the doctrine of the sect at the Buddhist religious service of the memorial ceremony for the completion of Yakushi Nyorai-zo (statue of Yakushi Nyorai, the Healing Buddha).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 826 he was appointed to Gon no Risshi (generally in Shingon sect, fifteenth-ranking Buddhist priest, literally, &quot;supernumerary master of discipline&quot;) and to Risshi (the third rank of priest following Sojo and Sozu) in 827, the next year, after he lectured in the court on the doctrine of the sect at the Buddhist religious service of the memorial ceremony for the completion of Yakushi Nyorai-zo (statue of Yakushi Nyorai, the Healing Buddha).</e>
<cmt>権律師　の補足を追加しました。スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>830年（天長7年）淳和天皇の命による天長六本宋書の一つとして、三論宗を代表して「大乗三論大乗三論大義鈔」を撰述し、その中では主に当時三論宗に対して攻勢にあった法相宗の宗義を論破しながら三論宗義を展開した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 830 as one of the Tencho Rokupon Shusho (six books compiled at Imperial command by the six Buddhism sects during the Tencho era. Each sect described the spirit and the characteristics of its own teachings) ordered by Emperor Junna, on behalf of the Sanron Sect he compiled &apos;Daijo Sanron Daigisho&apos; (notes of religious teachings of the Sanron Sect), where he mainly developled the doctorine of his own sect, arguing down that of the Hosso Sect (Japanese equivalent of the Chinese Faxiang Sect) which was in those days aggressive against the Sanron Sect.</e>
<cmt>望月信亨(1954)『佛教大辞典』p. 3268では、「大乗三論大義鈔」は「だいじょうさんろんたいぎしょう」と読み、「大乗三論宗の要義を述べ、外道小乗法相等の所説を破せるもの」とあります。また今泉淑夫(1999)『日本仏教史辞典』p. 741では、「天長六本宋書」は「てんちょう（ちょくせん）ろくぽんしゅうしょ」と読み、「淳和天皇の詔勅により、(三論、法相など）6宗がそれぞれの教学的精髄・特徴をまとめて上進した書」とあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 830 as one of the Tencho Rokupon Shusho (six books compiled at Imperial command by the six Buddhism sects during the Tencho era. Each sect described the spirit and the characteristics of its own teachings) ordered by Emperor Junna, on behalf of the Sanron Sect he compiled &apos;Daijo Sanron Daigisho&apos; (notes of religious teachings of the Sanron Sect), where he mainly developed the doctorine of his own sect, arguing down that of the Hosso Sect (Japanese equivalent of the Chinese Faxiang Sect) which in those days was aggressive against the Sanron Sect.</e>
<cmt>spelling, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 830 as one of the Tencho Rokupon Shusho (six books compiled at Imperial command by the six Buddhism sects during the Tencho era; each sect described the spirit and the characteristics of its own teachings) ordered by Emperor Junna, on behalf of the Sanron sect he compiled &apos;Daijo Sanron Daigisho&apos; (notes of religious teachings of the Sanron sect), where he mainly developed the doctrine of his own sect, arguing down that of the Hosso sect (Japanese equivalent of the Chinese Faxiang sect) which in those days was aggressive against the Sanron sect.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 R28Bot(id:177951), Saaki(id:43602), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>