<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>松本明慶</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myokei MATSUMOTO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myokei MATSUMOTO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myokei MATSUMOTO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>松本明慶（まつもと みょうけい, 1945年(昭和20年) -）は、現代日本の仏師であり、慶派に属するとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myokei MATSUMOTO (1945-) is the present day Busshi (Buddhist statue sculptor), who belongs in the Keiha School.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myokei MATSUMOTO (1945-) is the present-day Busshi (sculptor of Buddhist statues) who belongs to the Keiha school.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myokei MATSUMOTO (1945 -) is the present-day Busshi (sculptor of Buddhist statues) who belongs to the Keiha School.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>京都市生まれ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>1962年(昭和37年)に、京仏師の野崎宗慶のもとに弟子入り。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1962: He became a disciple of Sokei NOZAKI, who was the Kyobussi (sculptor of Buddhist Statues in Kyoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1962: He became a disciple of Sokei NOZAKI, who was the Kyobusshi (sculptor of Buddhist statues in Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1962: He became a disciple of Sokei NOZAKI, who was the Kyobusshi (sculptor of Buddhist statues in Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>1980年(昭和55年)、京都仏像彫刻展で、京都市長賞を受賞する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1980: He was given the Kyoto Mayor&apos;s Prize at Kyoto Buddhist Sculpture Exhibit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1980: He was given the Kyoto Mayor&apos;s Prize at the Kyoto Buddhist Sculpture Exhibition.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1980: He was given the Kyoto Mayor&apos;s Prize at the Kyoto Buddhist Sculpture Exhibition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>1985年(昭和60年)、京都仏像彫刻展で、京都府知事賞を受賞する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1985: He was awarded with Kyoto Governor&apos;s Prize at Kyoto Buddhist Sculpture Exhibit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1985: He was awarded the Kyoto Governor&apos;s Prize at the Kyoto Buddhist Sculpture Exhibition.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1985: He was awarded the Kyoto Governor&apos;s Prize at the Kyoto Buddhist Sculpture Exhibition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>1988年(昭和63年)、パリのギメ東洋美術館の仏像100体を修理する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1988: He repaired a hundred Buddhist statues of Guimet Musée national des Arts Asiatiques in Paris.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1988: He repaired a hundred Buddhist statues of Guimet Musée national des Arts Asiatiques, in Paris.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1988: He repaired a hundred Buddhist statues of Guimet Musée national des Arts Asiatiques, in Paris.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="7">
<j>1991年(平成3年)、大仏師の称号を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1991: He was given a title of Daibusshi (great sculptor of Buddhist Statues).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1991: He was given the title of Daibusshi (great sculptor of Buddhist statues).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1991: He was given the title of Daibusshi (great sculptor of Buddhist statues).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="8">
<j>その工房は、松本工房という名称で、京都市西京区大原野の、善峰寺や十輪寺 (京都市)の近辺にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His studio is called Matsumoto Kobo (studio) and located at Oharano, Nishikyo-ku Ward, Kyoto City near Yoshimine-dera and Jurin-ji Temples (Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His studio, called Matsumoto Kobo (studio), is located at Oharano, Nishikyo-ku Ward, Kyoto City, near the Yoshimine-dera and Jurin-ji temples (Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His studio, called Matsumoto Kobo (studio), is located at Oharano, Nishikyo-ku Ward, Kyoto City, near the Yoshimine-dera and Jurin-ji temples (Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>京都仏像彫刻家協会会長。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is a chairmen of Kyoto sculptors of Buddhist Statues Association.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is the chairman of Kyoto sculptors of the Buddhist Statues Association.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is the chairman of Kyoto sculptors of the Buddhist Statues Association.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="10">
<j>2006年(平成18年)6月18日、京都市上京区に松本明慶佛像彫刻美術館が開館する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 18, 2006: He established Matsumoto Myokei Buddhist Statue Carvings Museum in Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 18, 2006: He established the Matsumoto Myokei Buddhist Statue Carvings Museum in Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 18, 2006: He established the Matsumoto Myokei Buddhist Statue Carvings Museum in Kamigyo-ku Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>同年9月には、日本放送協会制作の『にんげんドキュメント』で「大仏に挑む　平成の仏師・技と心」として、その工房の製作活動が放送された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September of the same year, &quot;Ningen Document&quot; (Human Document) produced by Japan Broadcasting Association (NHK) aired the production activity of that studio as &apos;Skill and Heart of Heisei Era Busshi challenging on Daibutsu (great Buddhist statue).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September of the same year, &quot;Ningen Document (Human Document),&quot; produced by the Japan Broadcasting Association (NHK), aired the production activity of that studio as &apos;Skill and Heart of Heisei Era Busshi challenging Daibutsu (Great Buddhist Statue).&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September of the same year, &quot;Ningen Document&quot; (Human Document), produced by the Japan Broadcasting Association (NHK), aired the production activity of that studio as &apos;Skill and Heart of Heisei period Busshi challenging Daibutsu&apos; (Great Buddhist Statue).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 安藤夏樹(id:171701), Mooko(id:36162), 与左衛門(id:159462), Cprobot(id:97843), Adonis(id:24011), D.h(id:79056), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>