<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>火葬</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cremation</e>
<cmt>固有名詞は原則、統一用語に従いました。その他の場合は出典を記入しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cremation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cremation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>火葬（かそう）は、死体を葬るための処理の一つで、遺体を燃焼することである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cremation is a way of treatment to put a dead person in the ground after cramating the body</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cremation is a way of treatment before putting a dead person in the ground after cremating the body</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cremation is a type of treating the dead by incinerating the body.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>また、遺体の焼却を伴う葬儀全体。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also means the whole process of the funeral including the incineration of the dead body.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also means the complete process of the funeral including the incineration of the dead body.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also means the complete process of the funeral including the incineration of the dead body.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>火葬をおこなう施設や建築物を火葬場と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The installation or building in which the cremation is taken place is called crematorium.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The installation or building in which the cremation is taken place is called crematorium.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The facility or building in which the cremation takes place is called a crematorium.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>日本では、火葬の後の「焼骨」は骨壷に収（拾）骨され、土中に土葬（法律的には「焼骨の埋蔵」）されるか、納骨堂等に収蔵されることになる（墓地、埋葬等に関する法律第2条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, after the cremation, the cremated remains, or &apos;bones left after cremation,&apos; are collected and placed in a Kotsutsubo (a pot for cremated bones) and buried in the ground (legally it is defined as &apos;the burial of the cremated bones,&apos;) or stored in an ossuary (Act Concerning Graveyard, Burial, etc., Article 2).</e>
<cmt>「焼骨」→定訳不明：the cremated remains, or &apos;bones left after cremation,&apos;としました。　骨壷→定訳不明：Kotsutsubo (a pot for cremated bones) としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, after the cremation, the cremated remains, or &apos;bones left after cremation,&apos; are collected and placed in a Kotsutsubo (a pot for cremated bones) and buried in the ground (legally it is defined as &apos;the burial of the cremated bones,&apos;) or stored in an ossuary (Act Concerning Graveyard, Burial, etc., Article 2).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, after the cremation, the cremated remains, or &apos;bones left after cremation,&apos; are collected and placed in a Kotsutsubo (a pot for cremated bones) and buried in the ground (legally it is defined as &apos;the burial of the cremated bones,&apos;) or stored in an ossuary (Act Concerning Graveyard, Burial, etc., Article 2).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>従って、「葬儀の方法の一つ」というよりも、その、一過程であるという考え方もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, it is also considered as a process of the funeral rather than &apos;a type of funeral.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, it is also considered as a process of the funeral rather than &apos;a type of funeral.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, it is also considered as a process of the funeral rather than &apos;a type of funeral.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また、安定化、減容化処理の方法と言うことも出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be also said that it is a way of treatment to stabilize and reduce the volume of the body.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be also said that it is a way of treatment to stabilize and reduce the volume of the body.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can also be said that it is a method to stabilize and reduce the volume of the body.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>公衆衛生的な利益と言う面も見逃せない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The benefit from the public hygiene point of view should be noted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The benefit from the public hygiene point of view should be noted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The benefit from the public hygiene point of view should be noted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>廃棄物の衛生的処理と同じ考え方とも言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be also said that it follows the principle of the hygienic waste treatment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be also said that it follows the principle of hygienic waste treatment.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can also be said that it is close in thinking to hygienic waste treatment.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>死体がいわゆる「生ゴミ」と全く同じ性質のものであるからだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because the dead body has the same characteristics as the so called &apos;raw garbage&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the dead body has the same characteristics as so called &apos;raw garbage&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because a dead body has the same characteristics as &apos;raw garbage.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>散骨される場合もあるが、現在では条例等により禁止・規制している地方公共団体も出現している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some cases, the ashes of the deceased are scattered, nowadays, there are some local public authorities which prohibit or control the ash dispersal by the regulations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some cases, the ashes of the deceased are scattered, nowadays, there are some local public authorities which prohibit or control ash dispersal with regulations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some cases, the ashes of the deceased are scattered, nowadays, there are some local public authorities which prohibit or control ash dispersal with regulations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>日本の火葬</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cremation in Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cremation in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cremation in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>日本では、仏教の伝来と共に伝わったというのが有力説である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The most dominant theory is that it came down to Japan with the Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The most dominant theory is that it came down to Japan with the Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The most dominant theory is that it entered Japan together with Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これは釈迦が火葬されたことにちなむ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This theory derives from the fact that Shaka&apos;s body was cremated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This theory derives from the fact that Shaka&apos;s body was cremated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This theory derives from the fact that Shaka&apos;s body was cremated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>現代でも「火葬にする」の意味で用いられる言葉として「荼毘に付す」がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present the expression to &apos;practice Dabi&apos; means &apos;to cremate.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「荼毘に付す」→&apos;practice Dabi&apos;文脈からとしました。 一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present the expression to &apos;practice Dabi&apos; means &apos;to cremate.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present the expression to &apos;practice Dabi&apos; means &apos;to cremate.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>この荼毘（だびとも）は火葬を意味する梵語 jhpetaに由来し、仏教用語である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This &apos;Dabi&apos; comes from a word of Sanskrit, jhpeta, which is a Buddhist term and means cremation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This &apos;Dabi&apos; comes from a word of Sanskrit, jhpeta, which is a Buddhist term and means cremation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This &apos;Dabi&apos; comes from a word of Sanskrit, jhpeta, which is a Buddhist term and means cremation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>『続日本紀』によると、日本で最初に火葬された人は僧道昭であり、文武天皇四年（700年）のことであるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), the fist person whose body was cremated is said to be Buddhist monk Dosho, and it took place in the year 700.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), the first person whose body was cremated is said to be Buddhist monk Dosho, and it took place in the year 700.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Shoku Nihonshoki&quot; Second Chronicles of Japan), the first person whose body was cremated is said to be Buddhist monk Dosho and this took place in 700.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>また天皇で最初に火葬されたのは持統天皇である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first emperor who was cremated is Emperor Jito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first emperor who was cremated is Emperor Jito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first emperor who was cremated is Emperor Jito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>ただし、近年の知見によるとそれに先行して火葬がおこなわれていた可能性が強くなってきている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the recent years&apos; findings have gradually showed us the possibility that the cremation had been practiced prior to that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the recent years&apos; findings have gradually showed us the possibility that the cremation had been practiced prior to that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the recent years&apos; findings have gradually showed us the possibility that the cremation had been practiced prior to that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>古墳の様式のひとつに「かまど塚」「横穴式木芯粘土室」などと呼ばれるスタイルのものがあり、そのなかには火葬がおこなわれた痕跡があるものが認められる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One style of the tumulus is called &apos;furnace tumulus&apos; (Kamadozuka) or &apos;horizontal wood-core clay chamber&apos; (Yokoanashiki mokushin nendoshitsu), and some of this style tumulus have traces that the cremation had been practiced there.</e>
<cmt>「横穴式木芯粘土室」→定訳不明：&apos; &apos;horizontal wood-core clay chamber&apos; (Yokoanashiki mokushin nendoshitsu)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One style of tumulus is called &apos;furnace tumulus&apos; (Kamadozuka) or &apos;horizontal wood-core clay chamber&apos; (Yokoanashiki mokushin nendoshitsu), and some of these style tumulus have traces that the cremation had been practiced there.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One style of kofun (ancient Japanese burial mounds) is called &apos;Kamadozuka&apos; (furnace mound) or &apos;Yokoanashiki mokushin nendoshitsu&apos; (horizontal wood-core clay chamber) and some examples of this style show traces that cremation had been practiced there.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>それらは6世紀後半から出現しており、研究が進めば日本における火葬史は100年以上遡ることになるものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those tumulus papered in the late 6th century, and the advance of the study would probably make the Japanese cremation history extend back more than 100 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those tumulus appeared in the late 6th century, and the advance of the study would probably make Japanese cremation history extend back more than 100 years.</e>
<cmt>spelling, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These burial mounds appeared in the late 6th century, and if these findings are confirmed by more research, the history of Japanese cremation history may be more than 100 years older than previously thought.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="22">
<j>近世までは、仏教徒を含め、主流はむしろ棺桶を使った土葬であり、一部には鳥葬に代表される曝葬の習慣もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To the early modern ages, most of the people, including the Buddhists, had been buried under the earth using a casket, and in some cases, the bodies were left exposed to the vultures (sky burial) and other natural actions.</e>
<cmt>鳥葬→ sky burial [英辞郎 on the WEB] 鳥葬に代表される曝葬→定訳不明：the bodies were left exposed to the vultures (sky burial) and other natural actionsとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To the early modern ages, most of the people, including the Buddhists, had been buried under the earth using a casket, and in some cases, the bodies were left exposed to the vultures (sky burial) and other natural actions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Up until the early modern ages, most people including Buddhists, were buried under the earth in a coffin, and in some cases, the bodies were left exposed to the vultures (sky burial) and other natural forces.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>火葬は多くの薪などの燃料を必要とし、また技術も求められるため、費用がかかる葬儀様式であったことは否定できない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the cremation requires not only a lot of fuel such as firewood, but also certain skills, and it cannot be denied that it was a costly funeral style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the cremation requires not only a lot of fuel such as firewood, but also certain skills, and it cannot be denied that it was a costly funeral style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As cremation requires not only a lot of fuel such as firewood, but also certain skills, it cannot be denied that it was a costly funeral method.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="24">
<j>近代に入ると、明治政府は明治6年に神道による挙国一致を目指した神仏分離令に関連して火葬禁止令を布告した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the modern era, the Meiji Government issued the Ordinance Prohibiting the Cremation in 1873, in relation with the Ordinance Distinguishing Shinto and Buddhism, which was formulated with the purpose of national unity.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。 火葬禁止令→定訳不明：Ordinance Prohibiting the Cremationとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the modern era, the Meiji Government issued an Ordinance Prohibiting Cremation in 1873, in relation with the Ordinance Distinguishing Shinto and Buddhism, which was formulated with the purpose of national unity.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the modern era, the Meiji Government issued an ordinance that prohibited cremation in 1873 in relation with the Ordinance Distinguishing Shinto and Buddhism, which was formulated with the purpose of national unity.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>仏教徒からの反発や衛生面の理由から明治8年には禁止令を廃止している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, In 1875, the government abolished this ordinance because of the backlash of the Buddhists and the hygienic reasons.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, In 1875, the government abolished this ordinance because of the backlash of the Buddhists and for the hygienic reasons.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in 1875, the government abolished this ordinance because of the backlash from the Buddhists and for hygienic reasons.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>その後火葬技術が進歩したこともあり、近現代の日本では火葬が飛躍的に普及した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, along with the progress of the cremation technique, in the modern and contemporary Japanese society, the practice of cremation has extended drastically to date.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, along with the progress of cremation technique, in modern and contemporary Japanese society, the practice of cremation was extended drastically to date.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, along with the progress of cremation techniques, the practice of cremation became extensively widespread in modern and contemporary Japanese society,</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="27">
<j>現代における火葬</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cremation in the modern age</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cremation in the modern age</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cremation in the modern age</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>現代の日本では、離島や山間部の住民を除いてほとんど全ての遺体は火葬される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan nowadays, almost of all the bodies are cremated, except for the residents in isolated islands and mountainous areas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan nowadays, almost of all the bodies are cremated, except for the residents in isolated islands and mountainous areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan nowadays, almost of all bodies are cremated, except for the residents in isolated islands and mountainous areas.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>その理由としては以下の点が挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reasons are as follows:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reasons are as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reasons are as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="30">
<j>事実上無宗教の人が多く、埋葬の方法にこだわりがない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a matter of fact, many of the people do not practice any religion and they don&apos;t seriously adhere to the way of burial.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a matter of fact, many of the people do not practice any religion and they don&apos;t seriously adhere to a way of burial.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most people do not practice any religion and do not have any fixed ideas about which burial method they prefer.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>火葬率がほぼ100%である現代の日本では、火葬がごく普遍的なものとなっており、世間体にも無難なものとして受け入れられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In actual Japan, where the cremation ratio is almost 100%, the cremation is quite universally practiced, and it is also socially accepted as a common style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In actual Japan, where the cremation ratio is almost 100%, the cremation is quite universally practiced, and it is also socially accepted as a common style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In modern Japan, the percentage of cremation is almost 100% and is the standard form of funeral that is also socially accepted as the most uncontroversial.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="32">
<j>日本で一定の力を持つ仏教では、仏陀にちなみ、火葬が尊ばれてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buddhism that maintains a certain influence in Japan, in connection with Buddha, the cremation has been respected, and above all, historically Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) sect has promoted the cremation in an active manner</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buddhism that maintains a certain influence in Japan, in connection with Buddha, cremation has been respected, and above all, historically Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) sect has promotedcremation in an active manner</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddhism maintains a certain influence in Japan and cremation is respected because Buddha was cremated as well</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>特に浄土真宗などでは火葬を強く推進してきたという経緯があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) sect has actively promoted cremation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="34">
<j>都市に人口が集中しており、その都市部では土葬で埋葬するために必要な土地が確保することができない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The population is concentrated in cities, and in these urban areas, it is difficult to secure the burial sites.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The population is concentrated in cities, and in these urban areas, it is difficult to secure burial sites.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The population is concentrated in cities, and in these urban areas, it is difficult to secure burial sites.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="35">
<j>墓は家が単位と考える人が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many people think that a family is a unit for the grave.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many people think that a family is a unit for the grave.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many people consider graves in terms of family units.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>そのため、家（一族）と同じ墓に入れるようにするため火葬する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the body is cremated to be placed together with his family members in the same grave.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the body is cremated to be placed together with his family members in the same grave.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the body is cremated to be placed together with family members in the same grave.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="37">
<j>しかし多様な文化的理由から、火葬の普及は必ずしも諸手を挙げての賛同を得ているわけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, with diversified cultural reasons, the extension of the cremation is not wholeheartedly supported</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, for diversified cultural reasons, the extension of cremation is not wholeheartedly supported</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, for various cultural reasons, the spread of cremation is not wholeheartedly supported.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>以下は代表的な例である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following examples are some of the typical objections.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following examples are some of the typical objections.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following examples are some of the typical objections.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="39">
<j>神道家の一部には火葬を仏教徒の残虐な葬儀法として禁忌する思想がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of the Shinto families taboo the cremation, based on the thinking that it is a cruel way of funeral practiced by the Buddhists.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of the Shinto families taboo the cremation, based on the thinking that it is a cruel way of funeral practiced by the Buddhists.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of the Shinto leaders consider cremation as a cruel method of funeral practiced by Buddhists and prohibit it.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="40">
<j>琉球における洗骨葬のような地域的な文化への圧迫と受け止められる場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also considered as an oppression toward local cultures of such regions as Ryukyu, where the burial after washing the deceased&apos;s bones has been practiced.</e>
<cmt>洗骨葬→定訳不明：the burial after washing the deceased&apos;s bonesとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also considered as an oppression toward local cultures of such regions as Ryukyu, where burial after washing the deceased&apos;s bones has been practiced.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some cases, t is also considered as oppression toward local culture in regions such as Ryukyu, where burial by exposure of the body has been practiced.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="41">
<j>世界的にみて、イスラームなど、火葬を禁忌とする戒律を有する文化が少なくない（後述世界における火葬）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the world, there not a few cultures in which the cremation is tabooed in its religious prospect, like Islam (the cremation in the world is touched later).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the world, there are many cultures where cremation is tabooed in its religious prospect, like Islam (the cremation in the world is touched upon later).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the world, there are many cultures such as Islam, where cremation is prohibited by religious law (cremation throughout the world is mentioned later).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="42">
<j>近年では国内の日本人・外国人のなかでムスリムの人口が増加しており、彼らのうち戒律に厳格な者の努力により、土葬地を確保し火葬によらない葬儀を行う例もみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In these years, the percentage of Muslim population is increasing among Japanese and foreign people living in Japan, and thanks to the efforts of those who are strict Muslims among them, in some cases, the burial site is secured to celebrate a funeral without cremation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In these years, the percentage of Muslim population is increasing among Japanese and foreign people living in Japan, and thanks to the efforts of those who are strict Muslims among them, in some cases, the burial site is secured to celebrate a funeral without cremation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent years, the percentage of Muslim population is increasing among Japanese and foreign people living in Japan, and thanks to the efforts of those who are strictly adhere to Muslim values, in some cases, funerals at burial sites are allowed without cremation.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="43">
<j>法的側面</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Legal aspects</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Legal aspects</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Legal aspects</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>日本の法律上は、原則として、死体（もしくは妊娠7箇月以上の胎児）は死後（もしくは死産後）24時間以内は火葬してはならないとされている（墓地、埋葬等に関する法律第3条。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Japanese law, the dead body (or fetus of 7months or more after the pregnancy) should not be cremated within 24 hours after the death (or after the stillbirth) (Article 3, Act of Burial, Cremation, etc.</e>
<cmt>墓地、埋葬等に関する法律→Act of Burial, Cremation, etc.[英辞郎 on the WEB]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Japanese law, the dead body (or fetus of 7months or more after the pregnancy) should not be cremated within 24 hours after the death (or after the stillbirth) (Article 3, Act of Burial, Cremation, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japanese law, a dead body (or fetus of seven months or more) should not be cremated within 24 hours after death (or after stillbirth) (Article 3, Act of Burial, Cremation, etc.)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>但し、伝染病予防法で定められていた法定伝染病による死亡の場合はこの限りでない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the death caused by a legal communicable disease controlled by the Infectious Diseases Prevention Law is not subject to this article.)</e>
<cmt>伝染病予防法→定訳不明：Infectious Diseases Prevention Lawとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, death caused by a legal communicable disease controlled by the Infectious Diseases Prevention Law is not subject to this article.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, death caused by a designated communicable disease under the Infectious Diseases Prevention Law is not subject to this rule.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>また、火葬をおこなう場合には、当該死体に係る死亡届等を受理した市町村長の許可が必要であり（墓地、埋葬等に関する法律第5条）、この許可を受けずに火葬した場合には、墓地、埋葬等に関する法律違反となるほか（「罰則」規定同法第21条）、刑法190条「死体遺棄・死体損壊罪」に問われる可能性もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the cremation is undertaken, the permission of the head of a municipality, who accepted the death notification related to the dead body, is required (Article 5, Act of Burial, Cremation, etc.), and in case that the cremation is took place without this permission, it not only constitutes an offense of the Act of Burial, Cremation, etc. (Article 21of the Act, &apos;Punitive&apos; clause) but also can be considered as a violation of the Penal Code, Article 190, &apos;Abandonment of a Corps.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「罰則」規定→定訳不明：&apos;Punitive&apos; clauseとしました。　刑法190条「死体遺棄・死体損壊罪」→定訳不明：Penal Code, Article 190, &apos;Abandonment of a Corps&apos;としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When cremation is undertaken, permission of the head of the municipality, who accepted the death notification related to the dead body, is required (Article 5, Act of Burial, Cremation, etc.), and in case that cremation takes place without this permission, it not only constitutes an offense of the Act of Burial, Cremation, etc. (Article 21of the Act, &apos;Punitive&apos; clause) but also can be considered as a violation of the Penal Code, Article 190, &apos;Abandonment of a Corps.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When cremation is undertaken, permission of the head of the municipality, who received the death notification for the deceased is required (Article 5, Act of Burial, Cremation, etc.), and in case cremation takes place without this permission, it not only constitutes an offense of the Act of Burial, Cremation, etc. (Article 21of the Act, &apos;Punitive&apos; clause) but also can be considered as a violation of the Penal Code, Article 190, &apos;Abandonment of a Corpse.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="47">
<j>なお、土葬など火葬以外の方法が禁じられているわけではないが、その風習が残る場所の居住者がおこなう場合を除いて、高い費用がかかる敷居の高いものとなってしまっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Burials other than cremation are not prohibited, but except for the residents living in areas in which the custom of such a burial still remains, undertaking other way of burial is costly and less accessible.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Burials other than cremation are not prohibited, but except for the residents living in areas in which the custom of such a burial still remains, undertaking other way of burial is costly and less accessible.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Burials other than cremation are not prohibited, but except for those residents living in areas in which the custom of such a burial still remains, undertaking other ways of burial is costly and not readily available.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>また、環境衛生面から行政としては火葬を推進する事を奨励している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the environmental hygiene point of view, the government encourages to promote the cremation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the environmental hygiene point of view, the government encourages the promotion of cremation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the environmental hygiene point of view, the government encourages the promotion of cremation.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="49">
<j>世界における火葬</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cremation in the world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cremation in the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cremation in the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>仏教と関連が深いヒンドゥー教でも、最も多い葬送は火葬である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the world of Hinduism, which has a close relationship with Buddhism, the commonest funeral is the cremation-burial.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the world of Hinduism, which has a close relationship with Buddhism, the commonest funeral is cremation-burial.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the world of Hinduism, which has a close relationship with Buddhism, the commonest funeral is cremation-burial.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>通常、遺体は棺桶に入れず、布でくるまれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Usually the dead body is not placed in a casket but shrouded in cloth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Usually the dead body is not placed in a casket but shrouded in cloth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Usually the dead body is not placed in a casket but shrouded in cloth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>火葬は火葬場か墓地でされるが、いずれにしても屋外で、薪（火葬用のもの）で焼かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The cremation is took place in a crematory or a burial ground, and in all cases, it is practiced outside and the body is cremated using firewood (for the cremation).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cremation takes place in a crematory or a burial ground, and in all cases, it is practiced outside and the body is cremated using firewood.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cremation takes place in a crematory or the burial ground, and it is practiced outside and the body is cremated using firewood (especially for cremation) in all cases.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>遺骨は川に散骨する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The cremains are scattered in the river.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The cremains are scattered in the river.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The cremains are scattered in the river.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>水葬同様、ガンジス川の人気が高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Like in the case of burial at river, the Ganges River is very popular.</e>
<cmt>水葬→定訳不明： burial at riverとしました。通常はburial at seaと言うようですが、ガンジス川に流すとあるのでat riverとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Like in the case of burial in the river, the Ganges River is very popular.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ganges River is very popular as for water burials.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="55">
<j>しかし、世界的に見れば、火葬は必ずしも普通の習慣ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the world the cremation is not always a common custom.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the world, cremation is not always a common custom.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, cremation is not a popular custom throughout the world.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="56">
<j>儒教では火葬は身体の毀損行為であり、中国の歴代王朝の法典においても禁止が明記されている（中純夫「樗村沈錥における華夷観念と小中華思想」「京都府立大学学術報告人文・社会」2003年12月ISSN13433946）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Confucianism, the cremation is an act of mutilation to the body, and in the codes of Chinese successive dynasties, its prohibition is clearly stated.(Sumio NAKA &apos;Centric vs. Barbarian concept and small Sinocentrism in the theory of 樗村沈錥,&apos; &quot;Scientific Reports of Kyoto Prefectural University, Humanities and social science,&quot; Dec. 2003: ISSN13433946)</e>
<cmt>「樗村沈錥における華夷観念と小中華思想」→定訳・人名読み不明：&apos;Centric vs. Barbarian concept and small Sinocentrism in the theory of 樗村沈錥&apos;としました。 「京都府立大学学術報告人文・社会」→&quot;Scientific Reports of Kyoto Prefectural University, Humanities and social science&quot; [京都府立大学HP: http://kpu-lib.kpu.ac.jp/]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Confucianism, cremation is an act of mutilation to the body, and in the codes of Chinese successive dynasties, its prohibition is clearly stated.(Sumio NAKA &apos;Centric vs. Barbarian concept and small Sinocentrism in the theory of 樗村沈錥,&apos; &quot;Scientific Reports of Kyoto Prefectural University, Humanities and social science,&quot; Dec. 2003: ISSN13433946)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Confucianism, cremation is an act of mutilation to the body, and in the codes of Chinese imperial dynasties, its prohibition is clearly stated (Sumio NAKA, &apos;A study on Jeo chon Sim Yuk&apos;s Thought of Hwayi and of So Junghwa&apos; (A study on Centric vs. Barbarian concept and Small Sino centrism in Jeo chon Sim Yuk (literary remains of Jeo chon, edited by Sim Yuk)), &apos;Academic Report of Kyoto Prefectural University, Humanities and Social Science,&apos; December 2003: ISSN13433946).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>これを踏まえて火葬日本の火葬に立ち戻るなら、その儒教の国（唐）から渡来した仏教の僧道昭が、日本における火葬の嚆矢となったことは非常に興味深い事実といえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Looking back the cremation in Japan, where cremation-burial is widely practiced, based on these situations, it is very interesting that Buddhist monk Dosho, who came to Japan from the Confucian country (Tang) played the pivotal role in the extension of cremation-burial in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Looking back the cremation in Japan, where cremation-burial is widely practiced, based on these situations, it is very interesting that Buddhist monk Dosho, who came to Japan from the Confucian country (Tang) played the pivotal role in the extension of cremation-burial in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Looking back to cremation in Japan, where cremation is widely practiced, it is very interesting that the Buddhist monk Dosho, who came to Japan from a Confucian country (Tang) played a pivotal role in the spread of cremation in Japan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="58">
<j>また、ユダヤ教およびこれに起源を持つキリスト教、イスラームでは、最後の審判における死者の復活の教義を持ち、この際もとの体が必要と考えられているため、火葬への禁忌が強いが最近では火葬も増えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Judaism and Christianity, originated from it, as well as Islam have teachings of resurrection in the Great Inquest, and at this account the original body is considered necessary, there fore they have a strong sense of taboo to the cremation, but recently, cremation-burials are increasing in number.</e>
<cmt>最後の審判→Great Inquest 死者の復活の教義→teachings of resurrection　「教義」の英訳が宗教により異なるためteachingを使いました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Judaism and Christianity, as well as Islam have teachings of resurrection in the Great Inquest, and at this account the original body is considered necessary, therefore they have a strong sense of taboo regarding cremation, but recently, cremation-burials are increasing in number.</e>
<cmt>spelling, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Judaism, Christianity and Islam have teachings of resurrection with a great judgment where the original body is considered necessary and therefore they have a strong taboo regarding cremation, but recently, cremations are increasing in number.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>アメリカ合衆国での火葬率は、プロテスタント保守派の間で禁忌が強いこともあり20%強にとどまるといわれるものの、一方で、同じキリスト教圏にあるともいえるイギリス、及び同国の影響下にある、あった国々の多くでは、いずれの70%強、ないしこれに準ずるの火葬率を示していることから、火葬と、これを禁忌とする素因を宗教的側面については、一定の留保をもって臨む姿勢が求められるであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that in the United States the cremation rate only reaches as high as a little more than 20%, because there is a strong taboo among the conservative Protestants, but on the other hand, in the United Kingdom, a Christian country as well, and many of the countries which had been under British influence, the ratio is more than 70% or a similar figure, and therefore, a certain reservation is required when you considerer the cremation in relation with the religious aspect that conceives a taboo to the cremation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the United States the cremation rate only reaches as high as a little more than 20%, because there is a strong taboo among the conservative Protestants, but on the other hand, in the United Kingdom, a Christian country as well, and many of the countries which had been under British influence, the ratio is more than 70% or a similar figure, and therefore, a certain reservation is required when you considerer cremation in relation to religious aspects cremation is taboo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the United States the cremation rate only reaches a little more than 20%, because there is a strong taboo among the conservative Protestants, but on the other hand, in the United Kingdom, another Christian country, and many of the countries which were or have been under British influence, the rate is around 70% and therefore, looking to religious aspects for reasons against cremation may not necessarily be correct.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="60">
<j>火葬が主流の日本国内で暮らすイスラム教徒が、土葬が行い得る墓地を自力で確保した事例もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are cases in which the Muslims living in Japan, where the cremation-burial is predominant, secured the burial place by themselves in order to be able to directly bury the dead body under the earth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are cases in which Muslims living in Japan, where the cremation-burial is predominant, secured the burial place by themselves in order to be able to directly bury the dead body under the earth.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are cases in which Muslims living in Japan, where cremation is predominant, secured burial sites for themselves in order to be able to directly bury the dead body under the earth.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>一般的には、これらの宗教圏では、遺体を焼くことは死者への侮辱と取られる場合すらあるといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that in this religious sphere in general, burning the dead body might be considered even as an insult to the dead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that in this religious sphere in general, burning the dead body might be considered even as an insult to the dead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that in this religious sphere in general, burning the dead body might be considered as an insult to the dead.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>しかし、このイスラームの場合も、宗派によって温度差はあり、世俗的、温和的宗派の場合には許容する姿勢を見せる場合もあるともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, among the Muslims, there is an enthusiasm gap depending on the sects, and it is said that some of them show the posture of acceptance if they belong to the secular and moderate sects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, among the Muslims, there is an enthusiasm gap depending on the sects, and it is said that some of them show the posture of acceptance if they belong to the secular and moderate sects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, among the Muslims, there is a difference depending on the sects, and it is said that the more secular and moderate sects show some signs of acceptance.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Vapour(id:36031), Snake Head 1995(id:146125), きな粉パン(id:286823), MIsogi(id:20599), Kstigarbha(id:13376), 0null0(id:582), Swirliehead(id:217048), Kotoito(id:21045), Kamakura(id:472), Mishika(id:276), Greenland4(id:114494), タビックスJapan(id:52714), こうのいち(id:1215), 嫦娥(id:81469), らりた(id:1327), Hamilton(id:6033), Kanoe(id:17203), Naokiss(id:22121), Bow(id:16755), Sumaru(id:20609), Maldoror(id:14782), Hibiki-c(id:171692), Carbuncle(id:346), Bergmann(id:85282), Arsenia(id:265409), Snowy(id:4029), Robbot(id:3063), Setomanko(id:3051), ΑΩ(id:197298), 墓堀人サム(id:220225), SuisuiBot(id:10165), Abc root(id:219803), Nekosuki600(id:21263), NDR(id:5500), ウミユスリカ(id:9504), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>