<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>顕教</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenkyo (Kengyo)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenkyo (Kengyo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenkyo</e>
<cmt>(Kengyo)削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>顕教（けんきょう、けんぎょう）とは、仏教の中で、秘密にせず明らかに説かれた教えのこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenkyo (exoteric Buddhism) is a disclosed teaching of the Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenkyo (exoteric Buddhism) is the disclosed teaching of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenkyo (also pronounced Kengyo) (exoteric Buddhism) is the disclosed teaching of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>(also pronounced Kengyo) 補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>密教の反対語。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An antonym of Mikkyo (Esoteric Buddhism).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the antonym of Mikkyo (Esoteric Buddhism).</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the antonym of Esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>真言宗の開祖である空海が、密教が勝れているという優位性の観点から分類した教相判釈の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of Kyoso Hanjaku (evaluations of sutras) classified by Kukai, the founder of the Shingon sect, in perspective of superiority of Mikkyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is one of the Kyoso Hanjaku (evaluations of sutras) classified by Kukai, the founder of the Shingon sect, from the perspective of the superiority of Mikkyo.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is one of the Kyoso Hanjaku (evaluations of sutras) classified by Kukai, the founder of the Shingon sect, from the perspective of the superiority of Esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>空海は、顕教と密教を次のように区別した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kukai distinguished Kenkyo from Mikkyo in the following manner.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kukai distinguished Kenkyo from Mikkyo through the following:</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kukai distinguished Kenkyo from Esoteric Buddhism through the following:</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>顕教</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenkyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenkyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenkyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>衆生を教化するために姿を示現した釈迦如来が、秘密にすることなく明らかに説き顕した教え。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A teaching clearly disclosed by Shaka Nyorai (Buddha Shakamuni) who revealed himself to enlighten all living things.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A teaching clearly disclosed by Shaka Nyorai (Buddha Shakamuni) who revealed himself to enlighten all living things.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A teaching clearly disclosed by Shaka Nyorai (Buddha Shakamuni) who revealed himself to enlighten all living things.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>密教</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mikkyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mikkyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Esoteric Buddhism</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>真理そのものの姿で容易に現れない大日如来が説いた教え。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A teaching taught by Dainichi Nyorai (Mahavairocana) in the form of shinri (literally the truth) itself who seldom reveals himself.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A teaching of Dainichi Nyorai (Mahavairocana), who seldom reveals himself, in the form of shinri (literally the truth) itself.</e>
<cmt>Order changed, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A teaching of Dainichi Nyorai (Mahavairocana), who seldom reveals himself, in the form of shinri (literally the truth) itself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その奥深い教えである故に容易に明らかにできない秘密の教え。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A secret teaching that cannot be easily disclosed because of its profoundness.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A secret teaching that cannot be easily disclosed because of its profoundness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A secret teaching that cannot be easily disclosed because of its profoundness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>また、空海の解釈では、経典をそれぞれ次のように位置づけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to an interpretation by Kukai, scriptures are graded as follows:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Kukai&apos;s interpretation, scriptures are graded as follows:</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Kukai&apos;s interpretation, scriptures are graded as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="11">
<j>顕教の経典</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Scriptures of Kenkyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenkyo Scriptures</e>
<cmt>Made more natural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenkyo scriptures</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>- 華厳経・法華経・般若経（一部を除く）・涅槃経など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kegon-kyo Sutra, Lotus Sutra, Hannya-kyo Sutra (except a part of it), Nehan-gyo Sutra, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kegon-kyo Sutra, Lotus Sutra, Hannya-kyo Sutra (except one section), Nehan-gyo Sutra, among others.</e>
<cmt>Made more formal.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kegon-kyo Sutra, Lotus Sutra, Hannya-kyo Sutra (except one section), Nehan-gyo Sutra, among others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="13">
<j>密教の経典</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Scriptures of Mikkyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mikkyo Scriptures</e>
<cmt>Made more natural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Esoteric Buddhism scriptures</e>
<cmt>用語統一文頭のみ大文字</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>- 大日経・金剛頂経・理趣経など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dainichi-kyo (Mahavairocana Sutra), Vajrasekhara Sutra, Rishu-kyo (Principle of Wisdom Sutra), etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dainichi-kyo (Mahavairocana Sutra), Vajrasekhara Sutra, Rishu-kyo (Principle of Wisdom Sutra), among others.</e>
<cmt>Made more formal.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dainichi-kyo (Mahavairocana Sutra), Vajrasekhara Sutra, Rishu-kyo (Principle of Wisdom Sutra), among others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="15">
<j>なお、最澄は中国の天台宗とは趣を異にした日本独自の天台教学の確立を目標に、法華経を中心としつつ他の仏教の経典を包摂しようと試みた四宗兼学という立場から、円密一致を説いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saicho taught Enmitsu icchi (Agreement of Tendai Integrate Teachings and Esoteric Teachings) at a standpoint of Shishu/Yonshu kengaku (learning the four sects) trying to subsume Buddhist scriptures centered at the Lotus Sutra, aiming to establish Tendai doctrine unique to Japan and different from the Chinese Tendai sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On a related note, Saicho taught Enmitsu icchi (Agreement of Tendai Integrate Teachings and Esoteric Teachings) from the standpoint of Shishu/Yonshu kengaku (learning the four sects) in an attempt to subsume Buddhist scriptures centering on the Lotus Sutra, and with the aim of establishing a Tendai doctrine unique to Japan and different from the Chinese Tendai sect.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity and to connect with the rest of the article, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On a related note, Saicho taught Enmitsu icchi (Agreement of Tendai Integrate Teachings and Esoteric Teachings) from the standpoint of Shishu (also pronounced Yonshu) kengaku (learning the four sects) in an attempt to subsume Buddhist scriptures centering on the Lotus Sutra, and with the aim of establishing a Tendai doctrine unique to Japan and different from the Chinese Tendai sect.</e>
<cmt>also pronounced 補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), Boca samba(id:137526), Chi-Ham(id:143515), Johncapistrano(id:969), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>