<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>愛染明王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aizen Myoo, Ragaraja</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aizen Myoo (Ragaraja)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aizen Myoo (Ragaraja)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>愛染明王（あいぜんみょうおう）は、仏教の信仰対象であり、密教特有の尊格である明王の1つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aizen Myoo, Ragaraja, is one of the Myoos, who is worshipped in Buddhism and a venerable status specific to Mikkyo, Esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aizen Myoo (Ragaraja) is one of the Myoos, being worshipped in Buddhism and having venerable status specific to Mikkyo (Esoteric Buddhism).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aizen Myoo (Ragaraja) is one of the Myoos (king of wisdom), being worshipped in Buddhism and having venerable status specific to Mikkyo (Esoteric Buddhism).</e>
<cmt>明王の説明としてking of wisdomを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>梵名ラーガ・ラージャ(Ragaraja)は、インドなどの仏典にその名は見られず、また、インドでの作例もない忿怒尊である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanskrit name, Ragaraja, is not seen in Buddhist sutras such as those in India and it is Funnu-son, deity with fierce expression (忿怒尊) of which works are not seen as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sanskrit name, Ragaraja, is not seen in Buddhist sutras such as those in India, but it is Funnu-son, a deity with a fierce expression (忿怒尊) whose works are not seen either.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having a Sanskrit name, Ragaraja, which is not seen in Buddhist sutras such as those of India, is a Funnu-son--a deity with a fierce expression (忿怒尊)--whose works are not found in India either.</e>
<cmt>文章の構成を修正した。</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>愛染明王の像容と信仰</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Features of the statue and faith for Aizen Myoo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Features of the statue and faith for Aizen Myoo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Features of the statue and faith for Aizen Myoo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>衆生が仏法を信じない原因の一つに「煩悩・愛欲により浮世のかりそめの楽に心惹かれている」ことがあるが、愛染明王は「煩悩と愛欲は人間の本能でありこれを断ずることは出来ない、むしろこの本能そのものを向上心に変換して仏道を歩ませる」とする功徳を持っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the reasons why living things do not believe Buddhism is that &apos;they are fascinated by temporal pleasures by Bonno (earthly desires) and sexual desire,&apos; but Aizen Myoo practices pious act as &apos;Bonno and sexual desire are human&apos;s instincts which are difficult to cease them so that I change these instinct themselves into ambitions and make living things believe Buddhism.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the reasons living things do not believe in Buddhism is that &apos;they are fascinated by temporal pleasures such as bonno (earthly desires) and sexual desire,&apos; but Aizen Myoo practices pious acts because &apos;bonno and sexual desire are human&apos;s instincts that are difficult to cease, so that I change these instincts into ambitions and make living things believe in Buddhism.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the reasons living things do not believe in Buddhism is that &apos;they are fascinated by temporal pleasures such as bonno (earthly desires) and sexual desire,&apos; but Aizen Myoo practices pious acts because &apos;bonno and sexual desire are human&apos;s instincts that are difficult to cease, so that I change these instincts into ambitions and make living things believe in Buddhism.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>愛染明王は一面六臂で他の明王と同じく忿怒相であり、頭にはどのような苦難にも挫折しない強さを象徴する獅子の冠をかぶり、叡知を収めた宝瓶の上に咲いたハスの華の上に結跏趺坐で座るという、大変特徴ある姿をしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aizen Myoo has one face and six arms with Funnuso, an angry expression found on Buddhist images, as well as other Myoos, and it has very distinct features such as putting on a crown of lion which symbolizes the strength enough to bear any troubles</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aizen Myoo has one face and six arms with Funnuso, an angry expression found on Buddhist images, as well as other Myoos&apos; and it has very distinct features such as wearing a lion&apos;s crown, which symbolizes the strength to bear any problem.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aizen Myoo has one face and six arms with Funnu-so (an angry expression found on Buddhist images just like other Myoos), and it has highly distinctive features such as a lion&apos;s crown, which symbolizes the strength to bear any problem, as well as a seated lotus position on a lotus flower blossoms in a hobyo (a flower vase), which is filled with wisdom.</e>
<cmt>訳を一部追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>もともと愛を表現した神であるためその身色は真紅であり、後背に日輪を背負って表現されることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since it was a god to express love originally, the body color is red and it is often expressed with luminous halo.</e>
<cmt>「後背」は「光背」の誤記と判断しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because it was originally a god to express love, the body color is red and it is often depicted with a luminous halo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because it was originally a god to express love, the body color is red and it is often depicted with a luminous halo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>また天に向かって弓を引く容姿で描かれた姿（高野山に伝えられる「天弓愛染明王像」等）や、双頭など異形の容姿で描かれた絵図も現存する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, there exists a figure of Aizen Myoo who draws a bow against heaven (such as &apos;the statue of Aizen Myoo with celestial bow&apos; in Mt. Koya) and pictures on which different features are drawn such as two heads.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, there exists a figure of Aizen Myoo that draws a bow toward Heaven (such as &apos;the statue of Aizen Myoo with celestial bow&apos; at Mt. Koya) and pictures on which different features are drawn, such as two heads.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, there exists a figure of Aizen Myoo that draws a bow toward Heaven (such as &apos;the statue of Aizen Myoo with celestial bow&apos; at Mt. Koya) and pictures on which different features are drawn, such as two heads.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="7">
<j>額に第三の目を持つが、俗にこれを女性器を表したものだという説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has the third eye on the forehead and some people says this shows female genitals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has a third eye on the forehead, and some people say this depicts female genitalia.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has a third eye on the forehead, and some people say this depicts female genitalia.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>しかしその出典は不明で、真偽の程はわからない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the reason of that view is not known and it is not sure that it is true or not.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the reason for that view is not known and it is uncertain whether it is true.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the reason for that view is not known and it is uncertain whether it is true.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="9">
<j>愛染明王信仰はその名が示すとおり「恋愛・縁結び・家庭円満」などをつかさどる仏として古くから行われており、また「愛染＝藍染」と解釈し、染物・織物職人の守護神としても信仰されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aizen Myoo has been worshipped from ancient times as a Buddha who controls &apos;love, marriage and household harmony&apos; as its name shows, and also has been worshipped as a guardian deity of dye and textile manufacturer by interpreting &apos;Aizen(愛染) as Aizen (藍染), that is, indigo.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aizen Myoo has been worshipped since ancient times as a Buddha that controls &apos;love, marriage and household harmony,&apos; as its name shows; moreover, it has been worshipped as a guardian deity of dye and textile manufacturers by interpreting &apos;Aizen(愛染) as Aizen (藍染), or indigo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aizen Myoo has been worshipped since ancient times as a Buddha that controls &apos;love, marriage and household harmony,&apos; as its name shows; moreover, it has been worshipped as a guardian deity of dye and textile manufacturers by interpreting &apos;Aizen(愛染) as Aizen (藍染), or indigo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>さらに愛欲を否定しないことから、古くは遊女、現在では水商売の女性の信仰対象にもなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, since it does not deny sexual desire, it was worshipped by prostitutes in ancient times and it is worshipped by women who work in the nighttime entertainment industry at present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, because it does not deny sexual desire, it was worshipped by prostitutes in ancient times and is worshipped by women of the present day who work in the nighttime entertainment industry.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, because it does not deny sexual desire, it was worshipped by prostitutes in ancient times and is worshipped by women of the present day who work in the nighttime entertainment industry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="11">
<j>日蓮系各派の本尊（曼荼羅）にも不動明王と相対して愛染明王が書かれているが、空海によって伝えられた密教の尊格であることから日蓮以来代々梵字で書かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aizen Myoo is also drawn on Mandara picture, a principal image of Nichiren sects, facing of Fudo Myoo and has been written in Sanskrit since Nichiren through the ages because it is a venerable status of Mikkyo transmitted by Kukai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aizen Myoo is also depicted in pictures of the Mandara, a principal image of the Nichiren sects, facing Fudo Myoo; and it has been written in Sanskrit since Nichiren through the ages because it has a venerable status of Mikkyo transmitted by Kukai.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aizen Myoo is also depicted in pictures of the Mandala, a principal image of the Nichiren sects, facing Fudo Myoo; and it has been written in Sanskrit since Nichiren through the ages because it has a venerable status of Mikkyo transmitted by Kukai.</e>
<cmt>Mandara→Mandala に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>なお日蓮の曼荼羅における不動明王は生死即涅槃を表し、これに対し愛染明王は煩悩即菩提を表しているとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, it is said that Fudo Myoo in Mandara of Nichiren sects shows the idea that the sufferings of birth and death are nirvana while Aizen Myoo shows the idea that earthly desires are a pure aspiration to enlightenment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, it is said that Fudo Myoo in the Mandara of Nichiren sects shows the idea that the sufferings of birth and death are nirvana while Aizen Myoo shows the idea that earthly desires are a pure aspiration to enlightenment.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, it is said that Fudo Myoo in the Mandala of Nichiren sects shows the idea that the sufferings of birth and death are nirvana while Aizen Myoo shows the idea that earthly desires are a pure aspiration to enlightenment.</e>
<cmt>Mandara→Mandala に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>愛染明王の起源</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of Aizen Myoo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of Aizen Myoo</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of Aizen Myoo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>愛染明王（あいぜんみょうおう）の起源は、学説的には不明だが、愛染明王の真言のひとつ「フーン　タッキ　フーン　ジャハ　フーン」から推察するに、後期密教における十忿怒尊のタッキ・ラージャ（カーマ・ラージャ）と関連あると思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of Aizen Myoo is not known as a theory, but judging from one of the mantras of Aizen Myoo, &apos;Fun Takki Fun Jaha Fun,&apos; it seems to relate with Takkiraja (Kama Raja （カーマ・ラージャ)), the tenth Funnuson in the latter part of Mikkyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The theoretical origin of Aizen Myoo is not known, but judging from one of the mantras of Aizen Myoo, &apos;Fun Takki Fun Jaha Fun,&apos; it seems related to Takkiraja (Kama Raja （カーマ・ラージャ)), the tenth Funnuson in the latter stage of Mikkyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The theoretical origin of Aizen Myoo is not known, but judging from one of the mantras of Aizen Myoo, &apos;Fun Takki Fun Jaha Fun,&apos; it seems related to Takkiraja (Kama Raja （カーマ・ラージャ)), the tenth Funnu-son in the latter stage of Mikkyo.</e>
<cmt>Funnu-son　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>タッキは愛とか死を意味するとも言われるが、正確な語源は不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Takki means love or death, but the exact origin of the word is not known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the word &quot;takki&quot; means love or death, but the exact origin of the word is not known.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the word &quot;takki&quot; means love or death, but the exact origin of the word is not known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>タッキをダーキニー（茶枳尼天）に求める説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a theory that Takki originates from Dakini (ダーキニー) (Dakiniten).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a theory that Takki originates from Dakini (ダーキニー) (Dakiniten).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a theory that Takki originates from Dakini (ダーキニー) (Dakiniten).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>ダーキニーはしばしば魔女とされることから、タッキ・ラージャを邦訳するならば魔女の王といったところか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dakini is often considered to be a witch so that Takkiraja could be translated as the king of witches in Japanese.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dakini is often considered to be a witch, and therefore Takkiraja could be translated as the king of witches in Japanese.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dakini is often considered to be a witch, and therefore Takkiraja could be translated as the king of witches in Japanese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>タッキはあるいは、失われた神格か俗語なのかもしれない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Or Takki might be a lost god or a slang term.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Alternatively, Takki might be a lost god or a slang term.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Alternatively, Takki might be a lost god or a slang term.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>弓をもつ愛欲の神カーマ（マーラ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A god of love, Kama (カーマ)(Mara) with a bow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A god of love, Kama (カーマ)(Mara) with a bow.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A god of love, Kama (カーマ)(Mara) with a bow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>カーマとは修行中のシヴァ神に誘惑の矢を放って焼き殺された愛の神である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kama is a god of love, who was burned to death because she released an arrow against Shiva during ascetic practices.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kama is a goddess of love who was burned to death because she released an arrow against Shiva during ascetic practices.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kama is a goddess of love who was burned to death because she released an arrow against Shiva during ascetic practices.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>カーマ神は別名をマーラ（魔羅）ともいい、ブッダを誘惑している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The god Kama is called Mara in another name and seduced Buddha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The goddess Kama, which is also called Mara, seduced Buddha.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The goddess Kama, which is also called Mara, seduced Buddha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>マーラには、ラーガーという娘もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mara has a daughter named Raga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mara has a daughter named Raga.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mara has a daughter named Raga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="21">
<j>詳しくはカーマ (ヒンドゥー教)の項目を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For details, see the article of Kama (Hinduism).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For details, see the article on Kama (Hinduism).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For details, see the article on Kama (Hinduism).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>弓をもつ天界の最高神マーラ（他化自在天）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The supreme god with a bow in heaven, Mara (Take-jizai-ten, heaven where one can partake of the pleasures created in other heavens).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The supreme god with a bow in Heaven, Mara (Take-jizai-ten, or the heaven where one can partake of the pleasures created in other heavens).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The supreme god with a bow in Heaven, Mara (Take-jizai-ten, or the heaven where one can partake of the pleasures created in other heavens).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>マーラは第六天に住む天界の最高神であり、他化自在天や第六天魔王ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mara is the supreme god in heaven who lives in the sixth heaven and is also called Take-jizai-ten, heaven where one can partake of the pleasures created in other heavens, or the sixth Tenmao.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mara is the supreme god who lives in the sixth heaven, which is also called Take-jizai-ten (the heaven where one can partake of the pleasures created in other heavens) or the sixth tenmao.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mara is the supreme god who lives in the sixth heaven, which is also called Take-jizai-ten (the heaven where one can partake of the pleasures created in other heavens) or the sixth tenmao (devil).</e>
<cmt>sixth tenmao に (devil)　と補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>詳しくは（天魔）の項目で。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For details, see the article of Tenma.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For details, see the article on Tenmao.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For details, see the article on Tenma.</e>
<cmt>Tenmaとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>（天界の最高神ではあるが、仏教では、その上にさらに多くの世界が存在することをご理解いただきたい）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(It is the supreme god in heaven, but please notice that there are more worlds over heaven in Buddhism.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Kama is the supreme god in Heaven, but please notice that there are more worlds over heaven in Buddhism.)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Kama is the supreme god in Heaven, but please note that there are more worlds over heaven in Buddhism.)</e>
<cmt>表現スタイル。 “please notice ”=&gt;”please note”</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>他化自在天は弓をもった姿で描かれ、この世のすべてを自在に操り他人を楽しませ、自分も楽しむ神である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Take-jizai-ten is expressed in a figure with a bow and it is a god to control everything in this world at will, makes others enjoy and enjoys by itself.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Take-jizai-ten is expressed as a figure with a bow, and it is a god that controls everything in this world at will, makes others enjoy and enjoys by itself.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Take-jizai-ten is expressed as a figure with a bow, and it is a god that controls everything in this world at will, makes others enjoy and enjoys by itself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>見方を変えれば誘惑者であり、また、楽しい気持ちにさせてくれる神である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the other view, it is a seducer and a god who makes a person feel happy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the other perspective, it is a god and a seducer that makes a person feel happy.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the other perspective, it is a god and a seducer that makes a person feel happy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>大日如来はこの他化自在天の王宮で説法したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Dainichinyorai preached at the palace of this Take-jizai-ten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Dainichinyorai preached at the palace of Take-jizai-ten.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Dainichinyorai preached at the palace of Take-jizai-ten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>愛染明王も、愛に対する見方を変え極めた仏といえよう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aizen Myoo could be said to be a god who changed the viewpoint against love and mastered it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aizen Myoo could be said to be a god that changed the viewpoint against love and mastered it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aizen Myoo could be said to be a god that changed the viewpoint against love and mastered it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>弓をもつ四大菩薩の金剛愛菩薩と愛染明王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kongoai Bosatsu with a bow in the four major Bosatsus and Aizen Myoo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kongoai Bosatsu, with a bow in the four major bosatsus, and Aizen Myoo.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kongoai Bosatsu, with a bow in the four major bosatsus, and Aizen Myoo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>金剛愛菩薩がもっとも尊格としては近く、愛の弓を引くおそらく、弓をもつ愛の神を取りいれ、密教の菩薩として解釈されたのが金剛愛菩薩であり、その憤怒尊が愛染明王ではないかと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that Kongoai Bosatsu is the nearest as a venerable status and was incorporated from a god who drew a bow of love or a god of love with a bow and interpreted as a Bosatsu in Mikkyo so that its Funnuson corresponds to Aizen Myoo.</e>
<cmt>「愛の弓を引くおそらく、弓をもつ愛の神を取りいれ」→原文の意味不明ですが、なるべくそのまま訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that Kongoai Bosatsu is the nearest as a venerable status and was incorporated from a god who drew a bow of love or a god of love with a bow; it is interpreted as a Bosatsu in Mikkyo so that its Funnuson corresponds to Aizen Myoo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that Kongoai Bosatsu is the nearest as a venerable status and was incorporated from a god who drew a bow of love or a god of love with a bow; it is interpreted as a Bosatsu in Mikkyo so that its Funnu-son corresponds to Aizen Myoo.</e>
<cmt>Funnu-sonとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>愛染明王を安置する寺院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Temples which enshrine Aizen Myoo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Temples that enshrine Aizen Myoo</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Temples that enshrine Aizen Myoo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="30">
<j>愛染明王は眷属として祀られることが多いが、以下のように本尊としている例も存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Aizen Myoo is often enshrined as an attendant, there are examples that it is enshrined as principal image as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Aizen Myoo is often enshrined as an attendant, there are examples in which it is enshrined as the principal image, as follows:</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Aizen Myoo is often enshrined as an attendant, there are examples in which it is enshrined as the principal image, as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="31">
<j>愛染明王を本尊とする寺院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Temples which enshrine Aizen Myoo as principal image</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Temples that enshrine Aizen Myoo as the principal image</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Temples that enshrine Aizen Myoo as the principal image</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="32">
<j>愛染堂（勝鬘院）（大阪市天王寺区） - 聖徳太子建立の四天王寺四院の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aizen-do (Shoman-in Temple) (Tennoji Ward Osaka City) - one of the four halls of Shitenno-ji Temple built by Prince Shotoku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aizen-do (Shoman-in Temple) (Tennoji ward, Osaka City) - one of the four halls of Shitenno-ji Temple built by Prince Shotoku</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aizen-do (Shoman-in Temple) (Tennoji Ward, Osaka City) - one of the four halls of Shitenno-ji Temple built by Prince Shotoku</e>
<cmt>Ward　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>西国愛染霊場の一番札所）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first Fudasho, a temple which issues amulets, of Saigoku Aizen Reijo (holy grounds related with Aizen Myoo in west districts of Japan) (西国愛染霊場).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first Fudasho, a temple that issues amulets, of Saigoku Aizen Reijo (holy grounds related to Aizen Myoo in the western districts of Japan) (西国愛染霊場).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first Fudasho, a temple that issues amulets, of Saigoku Aizen Reijo (holy grounds related to Aizen Myoo in the western districts of Japan) (西国愛染霊場).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="34">
<j>金剛三昧院（和歌山県高野町） - 北条政子所縁の寺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kongosanmaiin Temple (Koya-cho Wakayama Prefecture) - the temple related with Masako HOJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kongosanmaiin Temple (Koya-cho, Wakayama Prefecture) - the temple related to Masako HOJO.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kongosanmai-in Temple (Koya-cho, Wakayama Prefecture) - the temple related to Masako HOJO.</e>
<cmt>Kongosanmai-in　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>源頼朝の念持佛である愛染明王を祀る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It enshrines Aizen Myoo, which was Nenjibutsu, a Buddhist image which is kept at close proximity for personal daily worship, of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It enshrines Aizen Myoo, which was Nenjibutsu (a Buddhist image that is kept in close proximity for personal daily worship) of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It enshrines Aizen Myoo, which was Nenjibutsu (a Buddhist image that is kept in close proximity for personal daily worship) of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>本尊は国の重要文化財）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The principal image is an important cultural property of government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The principal image is an important cultural property of the government.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The principal image is a national important cultural property.</e>
<cmt>national important cultural property　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="37">
<j>舎那院（滋賀県長浜市） - 本尊は鎌倉時代の作で国の重要文化財。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shana-in Temple (Nagahama City Shiga Prefecture) - the principal image is made in Kamakura Period and an important cultural property of government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shana-in Temple (Nagahama City, Shiga Prefecture) - the principal image is made in the Kamakura period and an important cultural property of the government.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shana-in Temple (Nagahama City, Shiga Prefecture) - the principal image is made in the Kamakura period and a national important cultural property.</e>
<cmt>national important cultural property　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>豊臣秀吉が奉献したとされる）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that it was consecrated by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that it was consecrated by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that it was consecrated by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="39">
<j>愛染院 (東京都練馬区)（東京都練馬区） - 本尊の愛染明王像は秘仏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aizen-in Temple (Nerima Ward Tokyo) - the principal image is the statue of Aizen Myoo, which is a Buddhist image not usually shown to the public.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aizen-in Temple (Nerima ward, Tokyo) - the principal image is the statue of Aizen Myoo, which is a Buddhist image not usually shown to the public.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aizen-in Temple (Nerima Ward, Tokyo) - the principal image is the statue of Aizen Myoo, which is a Buddhist image not usually shown to the public.</e>
<cmt>Ward</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="40">
<j>光明山愛染院 (板橋区)（東京都板橋区） - 地元の染物業者の信仰対象となっている）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Komyosan Aizen-in Temple (光明山愛染院) (Itabashi Ward Tokyo) - worshipped by local dye manufacturers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Komyosan Aizen-in Temple (光明山愛染院) (Itabashi ward, Tokyo) - worshipped by local dye manufacturers</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Komyosan Aizen-in Temple (光明山愛染院) (Itabashi Ward, Tokyo) - worshipped by local dye manufacturers</e>
<cmt>Ward</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="41">
<j>その他、愛染明王を祀る代表的な寺院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other representative temples which enshrine Aizen Myoo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other representative temples that enshrine Aizen Myoo</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other representative temples that enshrine Aizen Myoo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="42">
<j>西大寺 (奈良市)（奈良県奈良市） - 重要文化財の愛染明王像は善円の作。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saidai-ji Temple (Nara City Nara Prefecture) - the statue of Aizen Myoo (important cultural property) is made by Zenen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saidai-ji Temple (Nara City, Nara Prefecture): This statue of Aizen Myoo (important cultural property) was made by Zenen.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saidai-ji Temple (Nara City, Nara Prefecture): This statue of Aizen Myoo (an important cultural property) was made by Zenen.</e>
<cmt>an 追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>京都御所の近衛公政所御殿を移築した愛染堂に安置</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is placed at Aizen Hall which was former Konoe-ko Mandokoro Goten(近衛公政所御殿) in Kyoto Imperial Palace and relocated there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is placed at Aizen Hall, which was formerly Konoe-ko Mandokoro Goten(近衛公政所御殿) in Kyoto Imperial Palace but was relocated there.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is placed at Aizen Hall, which was formerly Konoe-ko Mandokoro Goten(近衛公政所御殿) in Kyoto Imperial Palace but was relocated there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="44">
<j>神護寺（京都市右京区） - 重要文化財の愛染明王像は仏師康円の作。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jingo-ji Temple (Ukyo Ward Kyoto City) - the statue of Aizen Myoo (important cultural property) was made by Koen who was a Busshi, a sculptor of Buddhist statues.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jingo-ji Temple (Ukyo ward, Kyoto City) - the statue of Aizen Myoo (important cultural property) was made by Koen, who was a busshi (sculptor of Buddhist statues).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jingo-ji Temple (Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City) - the statue of Aizen Myoo (an important cultural property) was made by Koen, who was a busshi.</e>
<cmt>Ward、 an 追加　busshiの補足は既出のため削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="45">
<j>神童寺（京都府相楽郡山城町 (京都府)） - 天弓愛染像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jindo-ji Temple (Yamashiro-cho Soraku-gun Kyoto Prefecture) - the statue of Aizen Myoo with celestial bow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jindo-ji Temple (Yamashiro-cho, Soraku-gun, Kyoto Prefecture) - the statue of Aizen Myoo with celestial bow</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jindo-ji Temple (Yamashiro-cho, Soraku-gun, Kyoto Prefecture) - the statue of Aizen Myoo with celestial bow</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="46">
<j>奈良国立博物館像 - 重要文化財の愛染明王像は鎌倉時代の仏師快成の作。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The statue in Nara National Museum - the statue of Aizen Myoo (important cultural property) was made byKaisei, a Busshi in Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A statue in the Nara National Museum - the statue of Aizen Myoo (important cultural property) was made byKaisei, a busshi in the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A statue in the Nara National Museum - the statue of Aizen Myoo (an important cultural property) was made byKaisei, a busshi in the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>an 追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="47">
<j>覚園寺（鎌倉市二階堂） - 愛染堂の愛染明王坐像は鎌倉時代後期の作。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kakuon-ji Temple (Nikaido Kamakura City) - the seated statue of Aizen Myoo at Aizen Hall was made in the latter part of Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kakuon-ji Temple (Nikaido, Kamakura City) - the seated statue of Aizen Myoo at Aizen Hall was made during the latter part of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kakuon-ji Temple (Nikaido, Kamakura City) - the seated statue of Aizen Myoo at Aizen Hall was made during the latter part of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Dummyoscar(id:26399), Nnh(id:474), 与左衛門(id:159462), 石川修(id:93406), 0null0(id:582), MIsogi(id:20599), Urania(id:7213), Centaurus(id:33865), CommonsDelinker(id:84593), くしなだ(id:16095), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), Yanahan(id:2437), SMR(id:39987), Makotozushi(id:4545), Layna(id:135377), Ghaz(id:1137), Boca samba(id:137526), Knua(id:66861), あお。(id:39226), 663highland(id:18755), 無空(id:17049), Alexbot(id:157199), Louperibot(id:128971), ウィキ豊(id:82961), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>