<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>戒壇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ordination Platform</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ordination Platform</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaidan (Ordination Platform)</e>
<cmt>ローマ字を補足しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>戒壇（かいだん）とは仏教用語で、戒律を授ける（授戒）ための場所を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &apos;ordination platform&apos; (kaidan in Japanese) is a Buddhist term that refers to a place for giving the precepts of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &apos;ordination platform&apos; (kaidan in Japanese) is a Buddhist term that refers to a place for giving the precepts of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term kaidan (ordination platform) is a Buddhist term that refers to a place for giving the precepts of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>戒壇は戒律を受けるための結界が常に整った場所である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An ordination platform is a place where a person who intends to become a Buddhist priest or priestess is given the precepts of Buddhism, the bounds of which are kept fixed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An ordination platform is a place where a person who intends to become a Buddhist priest or priestess is given the precepts of Buddhism, the bounds of which are kept fixed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaidan is a place where a person who intends to become a Buddhist priest or priestess is given the precepts of Buddhism, the bounds of which are kept fixed.</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>授戒を受けることで出家者が正式な僧尼として認められることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such a person needs to be given the precepts of Buddhism to be duly authorized as a Buddhist priest or priestess.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such a person needs to be given the precepts of Buddhism to be duly authorized as a Buddhist priest or priestess.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such a person needs to be given the precepts of Buddhism to be duly authorized as a Buddhist priest or priestess.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>日本に仏教が伝わったのは538年であるが、その際に伝わった戒律は、不完全なものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buddhism was imported into Japan in 538, and the precepts imported at that time were imperfect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buddhism was imported into Japan in 538, and the precepts imported at that time were imperfect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddhism was introduced into Japan in 538, and the precepts introduced at that time were imperfect.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>当時、出家は税を免除されていたため、税を逃れるために出家して得度を受けない輩（私度僧）が多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those days, Buddhist priests were exempted from taxation, and therefore there were many people who took the tonsure but did not enter the Buddhist priesthood (illegally ordained priests).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those days, Buddhist priests were exempted from taxation, and therefore there were many people who took the tonsure but did not enter the Buddhist priesthood (illegally ordained priests).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those days, Buddhist priests were exempted from taxation, and therefore there were many people who took the tonsure but did not enter the Buddhist priesthood (illegally ordained priests) to evade taxes.</e>
<cmt>税を逃れるために、を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>出家といえど修行もせず堕落した僧が多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, there were many corrupt priests who did not even train themselves in Buddhist ascetic practices.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, there were many corrupt priests who did not even train themselves in Buddhist ascetic practices.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, there were many corrupt priests who did not even train themselves in Buddhist ascetic practices.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その為、唐より鑑真が招かれ、戒律が伝えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In response to this situation, Jianzhen was invited from Tang to introduce the precepts of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In response to this situation, Jianzhen was invited from Tang to introduce the precepts of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response to this situation, Jianzhen was invited from Tang to introduce the precepts of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>この戒律を守れるものだけが僧として認められることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, only persons who could observe those precepts were authorized as Buddhist priests.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, only persons who could observe those precepts were authorized as Buddhist priests.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, only persons who could observe those precepts were authorized as Buddhist priests.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その結果、仏教界の規律は守られるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently, disciplines came to be observed in the Buddhist society.</e>
<cmt>仏教界→Buddhist society[定訳不明。仮訳です。]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, disciplines came to be observed in Buddhist society.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, disciplines came to be observed in Buddhist society.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>鑑真は754年、東大寺に戒壇を築き、同年4月に聖武天皇をはじめ430人に授戒を行なった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jianzhen had an ordination platform built at Todai-ji Temple in 754, and gave the precepts of Buddhism to 430 people including the Emperor Shomu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jianzhen had an ordination platform built at Todai-ji Temple in 754, and gave the precepts of Buddhism to 430 people including the Emperor Shomu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jianzhen had kaidan built at Todai-ji Temple in 754, and gave the precepts of Buddhism to 430 people including the Emperor Shomu in April of the same year.</e>
<cmt>同年4月に、を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>これが最初の戒壇である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the oldest ordination platform.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the oldest ordination platform.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the oldest kaidan.</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その後、東大寺に戒壇院を建立し、筑紫の太宰府の観世音寺、下野国（現在の栃木県）の薬師寺 (下野市)に戒壇を築いた（天下の三戒壇）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, Jianzhen had a building to house an ordination platform in at Todai-ji Temple, and had an ordination platform at Kanzeon-ji Temple located at the site of Dazaifu (Kyushu branch government) in Tsukushi and Yakushi-ji Temple in the Province of Shimotsuke (Tochigi Prefecture as it is known today) (more specifically, Shimotsuke City, as it is known today) (these ordination platforms are called the &apos;three major ordination platforms in Japan&apos;).</e>
<cmt>天下の三戒壇→→the three major ordination platforms in Japan[定訳不明。仮訳です。]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, Jianzhen had a building to house an ordination platform in at Todai-ji Temple, and had an ordination platform at Kanzeon-ji Temple located at the site of Dazaifu (Kyushu branch government) in Tsukushi and Yakushi-ji Temple in the Province of Shimotsuke (Tochigi Prefecture as it is known today) (more specifically, Shimotsuke City, as it is known today) (these ordination platforms are called the &apos;three major ordination platforms in Japan&apos;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, Jianzhen had a building to house Kaidanin at Todai-ji Temple, and had kaidan at Kanzeon-ji Temple in Dazaifu in Tsukushi Province and Yakushi-ji Temple in Shimotsuke Province (present Shimotsuke City, Tochigi Prefecture) (Three Major Kaidan in Japan).</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>これ以降、僧になるためには、いずれかの戒壇で授戒して戒牒を受けることが必須となり、国（国分寺）が僧を管理することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, it has been mandatory to be given the precepts of Buddhism at one of the three ordination platforms mentioned above and have a certificate to that effect (called &apos;kaicho&apos; in Japanese) issued, and priests have been under the supervision of the State (each provincial temple established by the State).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, it has been mandatory to be given the precepts of Buddhism at one of the three ordination platforms mentioned above and have a certificate to that effect (called &apos;kaicho&apos; in Japanese) issued, and priests have been under the supervision of the State (each provincial temple established by the State).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, it has been mandatory to be given the precepts of Buddhism at one of the three kaidan mentioned above and have kaicho (a certificate to that effect) issued, and priests have been under the supervision of the State (provincial monastery).</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>が、822年、最澄の死後、延暦寺に戒壇の勅許が下され、戒壇が建立された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Saicho, however, in 822, Imperial sanction for the construction of an ordination platform at Enryaku-ji Temple, and an ordination platform was raised there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Saicho, however, in 822, Imperial sanction for the construction of an ordination platform at Enryaku-ji Temple was given, and an ordination platform was built there.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Saicho in 822, however, Imperial sanction for the construction of kaidan at Enryaku-ji Temple was given, and kaidan was built there.</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>大乗戒壇と呼ばれることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This ordination platform is called a Mahayana ordination platform in some cases.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This ordination platform is called a Mahayana ordination platform in some cases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is called Daijo kaidan (a Mahayana ordination platform) in some cases.</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>当時は、中国の仏教界は延暦寺の大乗戒壇を、戒壇としては認めておらず、ここで受戒した僧は、中国では僧侶として認められなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those days, the Buddhist society in China did not approve the Mahayana ordination platform at Enryaku-ji Temple, and the priests who had been given the precepts of Buddhism at that temple were not recognized as priests in China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those days, the Buddhist society in China did not approve the Mahayana ordination platform at Enryaku-ji Temple, and the priests who had been given the precepts of Buddhism at that temple were not recognized as priests in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those days, the Buddhist society in China did not approve the Daijo kaidan at Enryaku-ji Temple, and the priests who had been given the precepts of Buddhism at that temple were not recognized as priests in China.</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>また、官立寺院（官寺）ではない延暦寺に戒壇設置を認められたことに東大寺をはじめとする南都（奈良）の寺院の反発を抱き、両者の対立の原因の一つとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Todai-ji Temple and other temples in Nanto (Nara) had antipathy toward the sanction for the construction of an ordination platform at Enryaku-ji Temple, a non-State-founded temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Todai-ji Temple and other temples in Nanto (Nara) had antipathy toward the sanction for the construction of an ordination platform at Enryaku-ji Temple, a non-State-founded temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Todai-ji Temple and other temples in Nanto (Nara) had antipathy toward the sanction for the construction of kaidan at Enryaku-ji Temple, which was not kanji (state-sponsored temples).</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>両者の対立の原因の一つとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This became one of the cause of the conflict between Enryaku-ji Temple and temples in Nanto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This became one of the causes of the conflict between Enryaku-ji Temple and temples in Nanto.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This became one of the causes of the conflict between Enryaku-ji Temple and temples in Nanto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>大乗戒壇は権力闘争の原因ともなり、天台宗の山門寺門の争いは有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mahayana ordination platform also caused power struggles, among which a power struggle between the two sub-sects of the Tendai Sect of Buddhism, that is, Sanmon (referring to Enryaku-ji Temple) and Jimon (referring to Onjo-ji Temple), is well-known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mahayana ordination platform also caused power struggles, among which a power struggle between the two sub-sects of the Tendai Sect of Buddhism, that is, Sanmon (referring to Enryaku-ji Temple) and Jimon (referring to Onjo-ji Temple), is well-known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Daijo kaidan also caused power struggles, among which one between Sanmon (referring to Enryaku-ji Temple) and Jimon (referring to Onjo-ji Temple) of the Tendai Sect is well-known.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>また、戒壇で授戒を受けた僧侶の中にも修行もせず堕落した僧侶も多くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the construction of the Mahayana ordination platform resulted in an increase in corrupt priests who had been given the precepts of Buddhism at an ordination platform but did not even train themselves in Buddhist ascetic practices.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the construction of the Mahayana ordination platform resulted in an increase in corrupt priests who had been given the precepts of Buddhism at an ordination platform but did not even train themselves in Buddhist ascetic practices.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, among the priests who had been given the precepts of Buddhism at kaidan, more of them did not even train themselves in Buddhist ascetic practices and corrupted.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>鎌倉時代の叡尊は元々真言宗僧であったが、後に鑑真が伝えた律宗を学んで両者を統合した真言律宗を起こした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eison, a person who lived as a Buddhist priest in the Kamakura period, originally belonged to the Shingon Sect, but later learned the doctrines of the Ritsu Sect and then founded the Shingon Ritsu Sect by combining the doctrines of both sects.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（3文に分割）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eison, a person who lived as a Buddhist priest in the Kamakura period, originally belonged to the Shingon Sect, but later learned the doctrines of the Ritsu Sect and then founded the Shingon Ritsu Sect by combining the doctrines of both sects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eison, in the Kamakura period, was originally belonged to the Shingon Sect, but later learned the doctrines of the Ritsu Sect introduced by Jianzhen to found the Shingon Ritsu Sect by combining the doctrines of both sects.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>三戒壇や延暦寺の戒壇は実態を失って授戒を行うに値しないと批判して、戒律に則って結界を築き正しい手順に従って儀式を行えば授戒は成立すると唱えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He criticized the three major ordination platforms and the one at Enryaku-ji Temple for being no longer what they should be and being unworthy as a place to give the precepts of Buddhism, and advocated that the giving of the Buddhist precepts be effected by fixing the bounds of a sacred place to give those precepts in conformity with the precepts and performing a rite in accordance with proper procedure.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（3文に分割）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He criticized the three major ordination platforms and the one at Enryaku-ji Temple for being no longer what they should be and being unworthy as a place to give the precepts of Buddhism, and advocated that the giving of the Buddhist precepts be effected by fixing the bounds of a sacred place to give those precepts in conformity with the precepts and performing a rite in accordance with proper procedure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He criticized the three major kaidan and the one at Enryaku-ji Temple for being no longer what they should be and being unworthy as a place to give the precepts of Buddhism, and advocated that the giving of the Buddhist precepts be effected by fixing the bounds of a sacred place to give those precepts in conformity with the precepts and performing a rite in accordance with proper procedure.</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>自ら仲間とともに東大寺において改めて授戒を行い、更に西大寺 (奈良市)に独自の戒壇を創設した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He gave the Buddhist precepts at Todai-ji Temple in person in collaboration with other like-minded priests, and also founded an original ordination platform at Saidai-ji Temple (located in Nara City as it is known today).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（3文に分割）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He gave the Buddhist precepts at Todai-ji Temple in person in collaboration with other like-minded priests, and also founded an original ordination platform at Saidai-ji Temple (located in Nara City as it is known today).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He gave the Buddhist precepts at Todai-ji Temple in person again in collaboration with other like-minded priests, and also founded an original kaidan at Saidai-ji Temple (Nara City).</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>続いて、延暦寺の僧侶であった円観も比叡山を離れて独自の戒壇を置いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following this, Enkan, who had served as a priest at Enryaku-ji Temple in Mt. Hiei, left there to place an original ordination platform.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following this, Enkan, who had served as a priest at Enryaku-ji Temple in Mt. Hiei, left there to place an original ordination platform.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following this, Enkan, who had served as a priest at Enryaku-ji Temple on Mt. Hiei, left there to place an original kaidan.</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>以後、南都や延暦寺と対立する形で成立した鎌倉新仏教も独自の得度・授戒の儀式を行うようになっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, in the Kamakura New Buddhism, which was founded as a result of the conflict with temples in Nanto and Enryaku-ji Temple, original rites for entrance into the Buddhist priesthood and giving the precepts of Buddhism came to be performed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, in the Kamakura New Buddhism, which was founded as a result of the conflict with temples in Nanto and Enryaku-ji Temple, original rites for entrance into the Buddhist priesthood and giving the precepts of Buddhism came to be performed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, in the Kamakura New Buddhism, which was founded as a result of the conflict with temples in Nanto and Enryaku-ji Temple, original rites for entrance into the Buddhist priesthood and giving the precepts of Buddhism came to be performed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>その一方で、東大寺や延暦寺の戒壇も由緒あるものとして尊重され、江戸時代の終わりまで授戒が行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the ordination platforms at Todai-ji and Enryaku-ji Temples were respected as time-honored ones, and the precepts of Buddhism were given there until the end of the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the ordination platforms at Todai-ji and Enryaku-ji Temples were respected as time-honored ones, and the precepts of Buddhism were given there until the end of the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the kaidan at Todai-ji and Enryaku-ji Temples were respected as time-honored ones, and the precepts of Buddhism were given there until the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Histwr(id:15646), Malta (-20090401)(id:11210), Tetralemma(id:11903), Boca samba(id:137526), 地図帳(id:122587), Kstigarbha(id:13376), R28Bot(id:177951), 水野白楓(id:22811), Sketch(id:102), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>