<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>三大秘法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sandaihiho, The Three Great Secret Dharmas</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sandaihiho: the Three Great Secret Dharmas</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sandaihiho: the Three Great Secret Dharmas</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>三大秘法（さんだいひほう）とは、日蓮の仏教における根本的教義であり、本門の本尊、本門の戒壇、本門の題目の3つからなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sandaihiho, The Three Great Secret Dharmas, is the fundamental dharmas in Buddhism by Nichiren and consists of Honmon no Honzon (the Object of Veneration of the Essential Teachings of the Lotus Sutra), Honmon no Kaidan (the Platform for the Receipt of the Precepts and Place of Practice of the Essential Teachings of the Lotus Sutra) and Honmon no Daimoku (the Sacred Title of the Essential Teachings of the Lotus Sutra).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sandaihiho (the Three Great Secret Dharmas) comprises the fundamental dharmas in Buddhism by Nichiren and consists of Honmon no Honzon (the Object of Veneration of the Essential Teachings of the Lotus Sutra), Honmon no Kaidan (the Platform for the Receipt of the Precepts and Place of Practice of the Essential Teachings of the Lotus Sutra) and Honmon no Daimoku (the Sacred Title of the Essential Teachings of the Lotus Sutra).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sandaihiho (the Three Great Secret Dharmas) comprises the fundamental dharmas in Buddhism by Nichiren and consists of Honmon no Honzon (the Object of Veneration of the Essential Teachings of the Lotus Sutra), Honmon no Kaidan (the Platform for the Receipt of the Precepts and Place of Practice of the Essential Teachings of the Lotus Sutra) and Honmon no Daimoku (the Sacred Title of the Essential Teachings of the Lotus Sutra).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>『報恩抄』『法華取要抄』『三大秘法抄』などに記述が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was described in &quot;Hoon-sho,&quot; &quot;Hokke-shuyo-sho,&quot; &quot;Sandaihiho-sho&quot; and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been described in &quot;Hoon-sho,&quot; &quot;Hokke-shuyo-sho,&quot; &quot;Sandaihiho-sho&quot; and so on.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been described in &quot;Hoon-sho,&quot; &quot;Hokke-shuyo-sho,&quot; &quot;Sandaihiho-sho&quot; and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>正式には「法華本門の三大秘法」と言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Formally it is called &apos;Hokke Honmon-no-Sandaihiho (法華本門の三大秘法).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Formally, it is called &apos;Hokke Honmon-no-Sandaihiho (法華本門の三大秘法).&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Formally, it is called &apos;Hokke Honmon-no-Sandaihiho (法華本門の三大秘法).&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>法華経の中心部分の文の底に秘して沈められた法門との意である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It means the Homon, dharma-gate, which is sunk secretly at the bottom of central sentences in Hoke-kyo Sutra.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It means the Homon (dharma gate), which is secretly embedded within key sentences in the Hoke-kyo Sutra.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It means the Homon (dharma gate), which is secretly embedded within key sentences in the Hoke-kyo Sutra.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>他宗教との比較検討の上から自宗の相対的優位を示すことに主眼が置かれた五綱判（宗教の五箇）に対して、三大秘法は宗旨の三箇と称せられ、絶対的慈悲の立場から一切の対立を超越し包み込もうとする原理として一般には理解される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As opposed to Goko-han (五綱判) (Shukyo-no-Goka (宗教の五箇)) which focuses on relative advantage of the sect compared to the other sects, Sandaihiho is called Shushi-no-Sanka (宗旨の三箇) and generally understood as a principle to transcend and enroll all conflicts from the viewpoint of absolute mercy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As opposed to Goko-han (五綱判) (Shukyo-no-Goka (宗教の五箇)), which focuses on the relative advantage of the sect as compared to other sects, Sandaihiho is called Shushi-no-Sanka (宗旨の三箇) and is generally understood as a principle of transcending and resolving all conflicts from the viewpoint of absolute mercy.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As opposed to Goko-han (五綱判) (Shukyo-no-Goka (宗教の五箇)), which focuses on the relative advantage of the sect as compared to other sects, Sandaihiho is called Shushi-no-Sanka (宗旨の三箇) and is generally understood as a principle of transcending and resolving all conflicts from the viewpoint of absolute mercy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>解釈は法華宗各派でそれぞれ異なるが、以下、代表的な両極端の例として、日蓮宗と日蓮正宗の例を挙げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each Hokke sect interprets it differently, and the following interpretations of Nichiren sect and Nichiren Shohu sect are representative examples for both ends of the spectrum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each Hokke sect interprets it differently, but the following interpretations of the Nichiren sect and Nichiren Shohu sect are representative examples for both ends of the spectrum.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each Hokke sect interprets it differently, but the following interpretations of the Nichiren sect and Nichiren Shohu sect are representative examples for both ends of the spectrum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>日蓮宗/法華宗（一般的日蓮系）における三大秘法の解釈</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Interpretation of Sandaihiho by Nichiren sect/Hokke sect (Nichiren linage in general)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Interpretation of Sandaihiho by the Nichiren sect/Hokke sect (Nichiren lineage in general)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Interpretation of Sandaihiho by the Nichiren sect/Hokke sect (Nichiren lineage in general)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>「本門の本尊」：本門の本尊は、伽耶成道の釈尊が、寿量品でみずから久遠常住の如来であることを開顕された仏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honmon no Honzon&apos; : Honmon no Honzon is a Buddha, that is, Sakyamuni in Gaya Jodo (伽耶成道), who recognized himself as Nyorai since the eternal past in Juryo-bon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honmon no Honzon&apos;: Honmon no Honzon is a Buddha, that is, Sakyamuni in Gaya Jodo (伽耶成道), who had recognized himself as Nyorai since the eternal past in Juryo-bon.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honmon no Honzon&apos;: Honmon no Honzon is a Buddha, specifically Sakyamuni in Gaya Jodo (伽耶成道), who has recognized himself as Nyorai throughout the eternal past, which is written in &quot;Juryo-bon&quot; (a part of the sutra).</e>
<cmt>括り始め脱落。“ Honmon no Honzon&apos;: ” →“ &apos;Honmon no Honzon&apos;: ”</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>「本門の戒壇」：即是道場の事の戒壇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honmon no Kaidan&apos; : Koto-no-Kaidan (事の戒壇) of Sokuzedojo (即是道場)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honmon no Kaidan&apos;: Koto-no-Kaidan (事の戒壇) of Sokuzedojo (即是道場)</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honmon no Kaidan&apos;: The place where Daimoku (Namu Myohorenge-kyo) is recited in front of the Honzon (principal image) is known as the &quot;dojo,&quot; a place for training (Sokuzedojo (即是道場)).</e>
<cmt>分かりやすい説明を追加するため、サイト（http://www.honge.jp/kenkyuusitu/sub512.sken1.kaidan.html　など）を参考に、修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>「本門の題目」：釈尊の悟りの一念三千である南無妙法蓮華経</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honmon no Daimoku&apos; : Namu Myohorenge-kyo, which is The Three Thousand Realms Contained in One Mind of enlightenment by Sakyamuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honmon no Daimoku&apos;: Namu Myohorenge-kyo, which is The Three Thousand Realms Contained in One Mind of enlightenment by Sakyamuni.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honmon no Daimoku&apos;: Namu Myohorenge-kyo, which is The Three Thousand Realms Contained in One Mind of enlightenment by Sakyamuni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>一致派をはじめとする主流派では、これらは概念上のもの、心の中にあるものとされ、日蓮宗が決めた本尊に向かって、題目を唱えれば、そこが「本門の戒壇」になる、とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the mainstream such as Icchi-ha sect, these are regarded as general ideas in one&apos;s mind and if one recites Nichiren chant in front of principal image which is determined by Nichiren sect, the place will turn to be &apos;Honmon no Kaidan.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the mainstream thinking (such as that of the Icchi-ha sect), these are regarded as general ideas in one&apos;s mind, and if one recites the Nichiren chant in front of the principal image--as determined by the Nichiren sect--the place will become &apos;Honmon no Kaidan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the mainstream thinking (such as that of the Icchi-ha sect), these are regarded as general ideas in one&apos;s mind, and if one recites the Nichiren chant in front of the principal image--as determined by the Nichiren sect--the place will become &apos;Honmon no Kaidan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>日蓮正宗における三大秘法の解釈</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Interpretation of Sandaihiho in Nichiren Shoshu sect</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Interpretation of Sandaihiho in the Nichiren Shoshu sect</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Interpretation of Sandaihiho in the Nichiren Shoshu sect</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>「本門の本尊 (日蓮正宗)」：人の本尊は日蓮大聖人、法の本尊は事の一念三千の南無妙法蓮華経。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honmon no Honzon (Nichiren Shoshu sect)&apos; : Hito-no-Honzon (human principal image) is Nichiren Daishonin (大聖人) and Ho-no-Honzon (principal image of dharma) is Namu Myohorenge-kyo of koto-no-ichinensanzen (事の一念三千), The Three Thousand Realms Contained in One Mind.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honmon no Honzon (Nichiren Shoshu sect)&apos;: Hito-no-Honzon (human principal image) is Nichiren Daishonin (大聖人) and Ho-no-Honzon (principal image of dharma) is Namu Myohorenge-kyo of koto-no-ichinensanzen (事の一念三千), (the Three Thousand Realms Contained in One Mind).</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honmon no Honzon (Nichiren Shoshu sect)&apos;: Hito-no-Honzon (human principal image) is Nichiren Daishonin (大聖人) and Ho-no-Honzon (principal image of dharma) is Namu Myohorenge-kyo of koto-no-ichinensanzen (事の一念三千), (the Three Thousand Realms Contained in One Mind).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>（大曼荼羅に、この両義が備わっている）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Great Mandara includes both dharmas)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The Great Mandara includes both dharmas.)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The Great Mandala includes both dharmas.)</e>
<cmt>Mandara→Mandala に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>「本門の戒壇」：事の戒壇は本門戒壇大御本尊を安置する処、義の戒壇は御本尊所住の処。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honmon no Kaidan&apos; : Koto-no-kaidan is a place where Honmon Kaidan Dai-Gohonzon (principal image) is enshrined and Gi-no-kaidan is a place where Gohonzon stays.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honmon no Kaidan&apos;: Koto-no-kaidan is a place where Honmon Kaidan Dai-Gohonzon (principal image) is enshrined, and Gi-no-kaidan is a place where Gohonzon stays.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honmon no Kaidan&apos;: Koto-no-kaidan is a place where Honmon Kaidan Dai-Gohonzon (principal image) is enshrined, and Gi-no-kaidan is a place where Gohonzon stays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>「本門の題目」：信の題目は本門戒壇大御本尊を信じること、行の題目は南無妙法蓮華経と我も唱え、人にも勧めること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honmon no Daimoku&apos; : Nichiren chant of belief (信の題目) is to believe Honmon Kaidan Dai-Gohonzon and Nichiren chant of practice (行の題目) is to recite Namu Myohorenge-kyo by oneself and recommend it to other people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honmon no Daimoku&apos;: The Nichiren chant of belief (信の題目) is to believe Honmon Kaidan Dai-Gohonzon, and the Nichiren chant of practice (行の題目) is to recite Namu Myohorenge-kyo by oneself and recommend it to other people.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honmon no Daimoku&apos;: The Nichiren chant of belief (信の題目) is to believe Honmon Kaidan Dai-Gohonzon, and the Nichiren chant of practice (行の題目) is to recite Namu Myohorenge-kyo by oneself and recommend it to other people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>三大秘法の中では、本尊を随一のものとして考えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among Sandaihiho, it considers the principal image as uniqueness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among Sandaihiho, it considers the principal image to be its uniqueness.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the Sandaihiho, the principal image is considered to be the supreme entity.</e>
<cmt>「随一」の意味は、unique（唯一）ではなく、「最高の」、「一番」等の意味のようです。（←http://thesaurus.weblio.jp/content/%E9%9A%8F%E4%B8%80）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>弘安二年（1279年）10月12日宗祖所顕と伝えられる本門戒壇の大御本尊を根源として三大秘法は生み出されているのであり、これを開くと人と法の本尊・事と義の戒壇・信と行の題目の六大秘法となり、さらに開くと仏教八万四千の法門すべてになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sandaihiho was created as the root of Dai-Gohonzon of Honmon no Kaidan, which was said to appear in front of the founder of the sect on October 12, 1279, and if one opens this, this turns to Rokudaihiho (the Six Great Secret Dharmas) of principal images of human and dharma, Koto-no-kaidan and Gi-no-kaidan, and Nichiren chants of belief and practice, and if one opens it more, it turns to be all Homon of 84,000 in Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sandaihiho was created as the root of Dai-Gohonzon of Honmon no Kaidan, which was said to have appeared before the founder of the sect on October 12, 1279, and if one opens this it will become Rokudaihiho (the Six Great Secret Dharmas) of the principal images of human and dharma (Koto-no-kaidan and Gi-no-kaidan) and the Nichiren chants of belief and practice; but if one opens it more, it becomes all 84,000 Homon in Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sandaihiho was created as the root of Dai-Gohonzon of Honmon no Kaidan, which was said to have appeared before the founder of the sect on October 12, 1279, and if one opens this it will become Rokudaihiho (the Six Great Secret Dharmas) of the principal images of human and dharma (Koto-no-kaidan and Gi-no-kaidan) and the Nichiren chants of belief and practice; but if one opens it more, it becomes all 84,000 Homon in Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>一大秘宝とは本門の本尊のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ichidaihiho, the One Great Secret Dharma, means Honmon no Honzon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ichidaihiho (the One Great Secret Dharma) means Honmon no Honzon.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ichidaihiho (the One Great Secret Dharma) means Honmon no Honzon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>すなわち三大秘法総在の大御本尊をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, it means Dai-Gohonzon which includes all Sandaihiho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words it means Dai-Gohonzon, which includes all Sandaihiho.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words it means Dai-Gohonzon, which includes all Sandaihiho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>開けば三大秘法となり、六代秘法となるのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If it is opened, it turns to be Sandaihiho and Rokudaihiho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If it is opened, it becomes Sandaihiho and Rokudaihiho.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If it is opened, it becomes Sandaihiho and Rokudaihiho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>合すれば一大秘法となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If they are combined, it turns to be Ichidaihiho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When combined, they become Ichidaihiho.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When combined, they become Ichidaihiho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>（六巻抄の依儀判文抄参照）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(See Egihanmon-sho in Rokkan-sho)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(See Egihanmon-sho in Rokkan-sho.)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(See Egihanmon-sho in Rokkan-sho (Six-volume Writings).)</e>
<cmt>六巻抄 に(Six-volume Writings) と補足しました。（→http://www.geocities.com/chris_holte/Buddhism/IssuesInBuddhism/nichikan.html）</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>o</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>第2次世界大戦での敗戦前の国柱会、戦後昭和３０年代の日蓮正宗・創価学会、（のち、正本堂建立数年前に批判を受け国立戒壇論を撤回）冨士大石寺顕正会などでは、国立戒壇論の絶対化を掲げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokuchu-kai before defeat in the World War Second, Nichiren Shohu Soka Gakkai (withdrew a proposition for national kaidan later before construction of Shohon-do), Fuji Taiseki-ji Kensho-kai and others aimed to absolutize a proposition for national Kaidan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokuchu-kai: Before defeat in World War II, Nichiren Shohu Soka Gakkai withdrew a proposition for national kaidan later (before the construction of Shohon-do), Fuji Taiseki-ji Kensho-kai and others aimed to finalize a proposition for national Kaidan.</e>
<cmt>gp</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokuchu-kai (before the defeat in World War II), Nichiren Shohu and Soka Gakkai (during the post-war period from 1955 to 1965), Fuji Taiseki-ji Kensho-kai and others endeavored to finalize a proposition for a national kaidan (although Nichiren Shohu and Soka Gakkai eventually withdrew the proposition for a national kaidan a few years before the construction of Shohon-do).</e>
<cmt>一部表現を修正しました。日蓮正宗・創価学会は別個の団体と解釈し、Nichiren Shohu and Soka Gakkai としました（andを追加）。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>戒壇を中心に三大秘法を解釈しようとした稀有な例と言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are said to be rare examples that they tried to interpret Sandaihiho around Kaidan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are said to be rare examples in that they tried to interpret Sandaihiho around Kaidan.</e>
<cmt>g</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are said to be rare examples in that they tried to interpret Sandaihiho around Kaidan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="24">
<j>また、特に1951年開始された創価学会の折伏大行進以降になるとスラング的用法として折伏の被害者、熱心な信者即ち加害者双方から信教の自由、民事不介入、少年法の３つが行政、警察、裁判所等公的機関の及び腰な姿勢を示す言葉として三大秘法と表現されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, especially after Shakubuku big March of Soka Gakkai which was started in 1951, the three of the freedom of religion, nonintervention against civil affairs and Juvenile Act have been expressed as Sandaihiho in slang expression, showing shilly-shallying of public administrations such as government, police and court of law from both sides of victims of Shakubuku and assailants, that is, devout believers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, particularly after the great Shakubuku march of Soka Gakkai, which was started in 1951, the three of the freedom of religion, nonintervention against civil affairs and the Juvenile Act have been given the slang expression Sandaihiho, to show the shilly-shallying of public administrations such as the government, police and courts of law from both sides of the victims of Shakubuku and assailants, meaning devout believers.</e>
<cmt>gp</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, particularly after the great march of the Shakubuku (an evangelistic technique, in Japanese meaning &quot;break and subdue&quot;) of Soka Gakkai, which was started in 1951, the three of the freedom of religion, nonintervention against civil affairs and the Juvenile Act have been given the slang expression Sandaihiho in order to show the shilly-shallying of public administrations such as the government, police and courts of law from both sides, specifically the victims of Shakubuku and the assailants (the devout believers).</e>
<cmt>折伏大行進 を the great march of the Shakubuku (an evangelistic technique, in Japanese meaning &quot;break and subdue&quot;) と補足しました。参考サイト→encyclopedia Britannica under &quot;Shakubuku&quot; [http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/83184/Buddhism/68723/The-Mahayana-schools-and-their-texts#ref=ref300428]</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>特に急進派の団体では若年会員に「強引な折伏で脅迫、放火、逮捕監禁等の罪に実際に問われても、未成年で1回目なら不起訴（ここでは罪を認めた上での『起訴猶予処分』も含む）で済む」とベテラン会員からの指導がなされることも時としてあると各所から情報が発信されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially, there are information that some experienced members in radical associations advice young members that &apos;even if your aggressive Shakubuku is actually accused of the crimes such as threatening, arson, abduction and confinement for the first time, you will be exempted from prosecution as long as you are under age (this includes &quot;suspension of prosecution&quot; as a result of admitting crimes).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially, there is information that some experienced members in radical associations advise young members that &apos;even if your aggressive Shakubuku is actually accused of the crimes such as threatening, arson, abduction and confinement for the first time, you will be exempted from prosecution as long as you are underage (this includes &quot;suspension of prosecution&quot; as a result of admitting crimes).</e>
<cmt>gp</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially, there is information that some experienced members in radical associations advise young members that &apos;even if your aggressive Shakubuku is in fact accused of the crimes such as threatening, arson, abduction and confinement for the first time, you will be exempted from prosecution as long as you are underage (this includes &quot;suspension of prosecution&quot; as a result of admitting crimes).</e>
<cmt>actually→in fact に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>各分派ごとで用語、同解釈がまちまちなのが常の日蓮系仏教において珍しく被害者加害者双方で全く同じ用語、解釈となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This term is used in the same sense on both sides of victims and assailants, which is rarely seen among Buddhism sects of Nichiren linage, because they usually use different terms and interpretations.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This term is used in the same sense on both sides--victims and assailants--which is rarely seen among Buddhist sects of Nichiren lineage, because they usually use different terms and interpretations.</e>
<cmt>gp</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This term is used in the same sense on both sides--victims and assailants--which is rarely seen among Buddhist sects of Nichiren lineage, because they usually use different terms and interpretations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Avanzare(id:34657), Nnt(id:184127), Tetralemma(id:11903), KMT(id:1772), Boca samba(id:137526), Cinnamon(id:11208), 無空(id:17049), Kane(id:6812), Mikomaid(id:56139), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>