<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>源仁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gennin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gennin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gennin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>源仁（げんにん、弘仁9年（818年）- 仁和3年11月22日 (旧暦)（887年12月14日））は、平安時代前期の真言宗の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gennin (818 - December 14, 887) was a priest of Shingon sect in the early period of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gennin (818 - December 14, 887) was a priest of the Shingon sect early in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gennin (818 - December 14, 887) was a priest of the Shingon sect early in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>出自については不詳である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His origin is not known for sure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His exact origin is not known.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His exact origin is not known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>池上僧都・南池院僧都・成願寺僧都とも称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is also called Ikegami no Sozu, Nanchiin Sozu, or Joganji Sozu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also called Ikegami no Sozu, Nanchiin Sozu and Joganji Sozu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also called Ikegami no Sozu, Nanchiin Sozu and Joganji Sozu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>護命（ごみょう）に法相教学を、ついで実恵（じちえ）に密教を学び，真雅・宗叡に灌頂を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He learned Hosso kyogaku (Dharmalogy of the Hosso Study) under Gomyo, then learned Esoteric Buddhism under Jichie, and was held kanjo (a ceremony to be the successor) by Shinga and Shuei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He learned Hosso kyogaku (the dharmalogy of the Hosso study) under Gomyo and studied Esoteric Buddhism under Jichie, and his kanjo (a ceremony to be the successor) was held by Shinga and Shuei.</e>
<cmt>c</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He learned Hosso kyogaku (the dharmalogy of the Hosso study) under Gomyo and studied Esoteric Buddhism under Jichie, and his kanjo (a ceremony to be the successor) was held by Shinga and Shuei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>878年（元慶2年）内供奉十禅師に任じられ、以後883年（元慶7年）に権律師、885年（仁和元年）に少僧都・東寺二長者に至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 878, he was appointed as naikubu-juzenshi (the ten selected excellent priests for a Buddhist service in the Imperial Court), and later was appointed as Gon no Risshi (a provisional rank in the lowest managerial position) in 883 and finally became as Shosozu (junior secondary prelate) and the second manager of the To-ji Temple in 885.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 878, he was appointed as naikubu-juzenshi (the ten selected excellent priests for a Buddhist service in the Imperial Court), and in 883 was appointed as Gon no Risshi (a provisional rank in the lowest managerial position); then, in 885 he became Shosozu (junior secondary prelate) and the second manager of To-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 878, he was appointed as naikubu-juzenshi (the 10 selected excellent priests for a Buddhist service in the Imperial Court), and in 883 was appointed as Gon no Risshi (a provisional rank in the lowest managerial position); then, in 885 he became Shosozu (junior secondary prelate) and the second manager of To-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>学名が高く南池院成願寺を建立して宗義を講じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was famous for being a good scholar, and he established Nanchi-in Jogan-ji Temple and taught religious doctrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Famed for his abilities as a scholar, he established Nanchi-in Jogan-ji Temple and taught religious doctrine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Famed for his abilities as a scholar, he established Nanchi-in Jogan-ji Temple and taught religious doctrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>弟子の益信が広沢流を、聖宝が小野流を開いて、以後東密はこの2流に分かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His disciple Yakushin opened the Hirosawa school and Shobo opened the Ono school, so later on the Tomitsu (eastern esotericism) was divided into these two schools.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His disciples, Yakushin and Shobo, opened the Hirosawa school and Ono school, respectively, and eventually the Tomitsu (eastern esotericism) was divided into these two schools.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His disciples, Yakushin and Shobo, opened the Hirosawa school and Ono school, respectively, and eventually the Tomitsu (eastern esotericism) was divided into these two schools.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>