<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>浄土院 (京都市左京区)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jodo-in Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jodo-in Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jodo-in Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>浄土院（じょうどいん）は、京都市左京区銀閣寺町にある浄土宗の寺院。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jodo-in Temple is a temple of Jodo (Pure Land) Sect, located in Ginkakuji-cho, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jodo-in Temple, located in Ginkakuji-cho, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City, is a temple of the Jodo (Pure Land) sect..</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jodo-in Temple, located in Ginkakuji-cho, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City, is a temple of the Jodo (Pure Land) sect.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>本尊は阿弥陀如来。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its honzon (principal image of Buddha) is Amida Nyorai (Amitabha Tathagata.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its honzon (principal image of Buddha) is Amida Nyorai (Amitabha Tathagata).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its honzon (principal image of Buddha) is Amida Nyorai (Amitabha Tathagata).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>五山送り火のひとつ「大文字」を管理することから「大文字寺」とも称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This temple is also called &quot;Daimonji-dera Temple,&quot; because it administrates &quot;Daimonji&quot; (the Great Bonfire Event) which is one of Gozan Okuribi (Bonfire Events on Five Mountains.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s also called &quot;Daimonji-dera Temple,&quot; because it administrates &quot;Daimonji (the Great Bonfire Event),&quot; which is one of the Gozan Okuribi (Bonfire Events on Five Mountains).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s also called &apos;Daimonji-dera Temple,&apos; because it administrates &apos;Daimonji&apos; (the Great Bonfire Event), which is one of the Gozan Okuribi (Bonfire Events on Five Mountains).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>この寺は、かつて慈照寺（銀閣寺）の場所に浄土寺という天台宗寺院があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once there was a temple of Tendai Sect, called Jodo-ji Temple, in the place which is now occupied by Jisho-ji Temple (Ginkaku-ji Temple.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once there was a temple of the Tendai sect, called Jodo-ji Temple, but that site is now occupied by Jisho-ji Temple (Ginkaku-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once there was a temple of the Tendai sect, called Jodo-ji Temple, but that site is now occupied by Jisho-ji Temple (Ginkaku-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>この浄土寺の創建年代等については不詳であるが、986年（寛和2年）浄土寺で有明親王（醍醐天皇の皇子）の妃である藤原暁子が出家し、有明親王の子明救（みょうぐ）が入寺している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though nothing is clear in detail about this Jodo-ji Temple, including the years of its foundation, it is known that FUJIWARA no Gyoshi, the spouse of Imperial prince Ariakira, the son of the Emperor Godaigo, entered the priesthood in this Jodo-ji Temple in 986, and that Myogu, the son of Imperial prince Ariakira, also entered this temple as a priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though nothing is clear in detail about this Jodo-ji Temple, including the year of its establishment, it is known that FUJIWARA no Gyoshi, the spouse of Imperial Prince Ariakira, the son of Emperor Godaigo, entered the priesthood in this Jodo-ji Temple in 986, and that Myogu, the son of Imperial Prince Ariakira, also entered this temple as a priest.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though nothing is clear in detail about this Jodo-ji Temple, including the year of its establishment, it is known that FUJIWARA no Gyoshi, the spouse of Imperial Prince Ariakira, the son of Emperor Godaigo, entered the priesthood in this Jodo-ji Temple in 986, and that Myogu, the son of Imperial Prince Ariakira, also entered this temple as a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その後、、皇室との関係が深かったが、室町幕府8代将軍足利義政が山荘（後の慈照寺銀閣）を建てるにあたり、相国寺付近に移されその後廃絶した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then it had kept close relationship with the Imperial families, but was forced to move to the vicinity of Sokoku-ji Temple when the eighth Shogun of Muromachi bakufu, Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, constructed his mountain villa which was later called Jisho-ji Ginkaku Temple, on the same site of the Jodo-ji Temple, and subsequently the Jodo-ji Temple was abolished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then it had maintained a close relationship with the Imperial Family, but it was forced to move to the vicinity of Sokoku-ji Temple when the eighth shogun of the Muromachi bakufu, Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, constructed his mountain villa, which was later called Jisho-ji Ginkaku Temple, on the same site of Jodo-ji Temple, and subsequently Jodo-ji Temple was abolished.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then it had maintained a close relationship with the Imperial Family, but it was forced to move to the vicinity of Sokoku-ji Temple when the eighth shogun of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, constructed his mountain villa, which was later called Jisho-ji Ginkaku Temple, on the same site of Jodo-ji Temple, and subsequently Jodo-ji Temple was abolished.</e>
<cmt>英語説明補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その浄土寺の跡を引き継ぐにあたり享保年間（1716年～1736年）に建てられたのがこの寺とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the wake of the abolished Jodo-ji Temple, the current Jodo-in Temple was built during the years from 1716 to 1736.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the wake of the abolished Jodo-ji Temple, the current Jodo-in Temple was built during the period from 1716 to 1736.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the wake of the abolished Jodo-ji Temple, the current Jodo-in Temple was built during the period from 1716 to 1736.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>所在地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Location</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Location</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Location</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>京都府京都市左京区銀閣寺町30</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ginkakuji-cho 30, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ginkakuji-cho 30, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">30 Ginkakuji-cho, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>住所表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 与左衛門(id:159462), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>