<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>広如</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Konyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Konyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Konyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>広如（こうにょ、寛政10年（1798年）－明治4年（1871年）8月19日は、幕末の浄土真宗の僧、西本願寺20世宗主、大僧正。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Konyo (1798-August 19, 1871) was a priest of the Jodo Shin (True Pure Land) sect in the end of the Edo period, the twentieth head priest of the Nishi Hongan-ji Temple, and daisojo (a Buddhist priest of the highest order).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Konyo (1798-August 19, 1871) was a priest of the Jodo Shin (True Pure Land) sect in the end of the Edo period, the twentieth head priest of the Nishi Hongan-ji Temple, and daisojo (a Buddhist priest of the highest order).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Konyo (1798 - August 19, 1871) was a priest of the Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) in the end of the Edo period, the 20th head priest of the Nishi Hongan-ji Temple, and daisojo (a Buddhist priest of the highest order).</e>
<cmt>用語を他の記事に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>諱は光澤。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His imina (personal name) was Kotaku (光澤).</e>
<cmt>「光澤」の読み方が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His imina (personal name) was Kotaku (光澤).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His imina (personal name) was Kotaku (光澤).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>幕末には勤皇の旗幟を鮮明にし、明治以後の教団を方向付けた『御遺訓御書』をのこしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of the Edo period, he showed the flag of imperialist and left &quot;Goikun Gosho (instructions for descendant)&quot; which decided the direction of the religious community after the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of the Edo period, he flew the imperialistflag and left &quot;Goikun Gosho (instructions for descendant)&quot; which decided the direction of the religious community after the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of the Edo period, he flew the imperialist flag and left &quot;Goikun Gosho&quot; (instructions for descendant) which decided the direction of the religious community after the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Character</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Character</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>用語を他の記事に合わせました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>寛政10年、河内顕証寺 (八尾市)近松暉宣の次子に生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1798 he was born as the second child of Chikamatsu Kisen (暉宣) of the Kensho-ji temple in Kawachi Province (Yao City).</e>
<cmt>「暉宣」の読み方が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1798 he was born as the second child of Chikamatsu Kisen (暉宣) of the Kensho-ji temple in Kawachi Province (Yao City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1798 he was born as the second child of Chikamatsu Kisen (暉宣) of the Kensho-ji Temple in Kawachi Province (Yao City).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>一旦は顕証寺住職に就くが、第19世宗主本如（暉宣の兄）の養子となり、文政9年（1823年）に第20世宗主を継職。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was assigned to the head priest of the Kensho-ji Temple at once, but he was adopted by the nineteenth head priest Honnyo (a brother of Kisen) as a son and was assigned to the twentieth head priest in 1823.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was assigned to the head priest of the Kensho-ji Temple at once, but he was adopted by the nineteenth head priest Honnyo (a brother of Kisen) as a son and was assigned to the twentieth head priest in 1823.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He assumed the position of head priest of the Kensho-ji Temple at once, but he was adopted by the 19th head priest Honnyo (a brother of Kisen) as a son and assumed the position of the 20th head priest in 1823.</e>
<cmt>用語を他の記事に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>1男4女をもうけるも早世、鷹司家より迎えた養子も早世したが、その後光尊（後の明如）が誕生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although his one son and four daughters died early and his adopted son from the Takatsukasa family also died early, Koson (later Myonyo) was born later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although his one son and four daughters died early and his adopted son from the Takatsukasa family also died early, Koson (later Myonyo) was born later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although his one son and four daughters died early and his adopted son from the Takatsukasa family also died early, Koson (later Myonyo) was born later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>顕証寺より迎えた徳如（継職前に死去）、明如の3門跡が揃う一時期があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a time when there were three monzeki (successor of a temple) including Tokunyo (died before succession) and Myonyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a time when there were three monzeki (successor of a temple) including Tokunyo (died before succession) and Myonyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a time when there were three monzeki (successor of a temple) including Tokunyo (died before succession) and Myonyo from Kensho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>尊皇の宗制</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The religious system of reverence for the emperor</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The religious system of reverence for the emperor</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Religious System of Reverence for the Emperor</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>黒船来航後の混乱にあった安政年間、尊皇攘夷の機運が高まるなかで勤皇僧として著名であった周防の月性を重役に登用させ、広如自身も朝権への傾倒を強めていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Ansei era among the confusion after the coming of Kurofune (The Black Ships of Commodore Matthew Perry), on the background of the gathering momentum of Sonno Joi (slogan advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners), he adopted Gessho, who was a famous priest as an imperialist, as an executive and grew involved with the Imperial court by himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Ansei era among the confusion after the coming of Kurofune (The Black Ships of Commodore Matthew Perry), and admist the gathering momentum of Sonno Joi (slogan advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners), he adopted Gessho, who was a famous priest as an imperialist, as an executive and grew involved with the Imperial court by himself.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During 1854 and 1859 among the confusion after the coming of Kurofune (The Black Ships of Commodore Matthew Perry), and among the gathering momentum of Sonno Joi (slogan advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners), he adopted Gessho, who was a famous priest as an imperialist, as an executive and grew involved with the Imperial court by himself.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>1863年（文久3年）には朝廷に10,000両を献納し、宗派全体に尊皇攘夷の徹底を諭す文を出している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1863 he presented 10,000 ryo (old currency unit) to the Imperial court and sent a letter to carry out thorough Sonno Joi to the whole religious community.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1863 he presented 10,000 ryo (old currency unit) to the Imperial court and sent a letter to carry out thorough Sonno Joi to the whole religious community.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1863 he presented 10,000 ryo (old currency unit) to the Imperial Court and sent a letter to carry out thorough Sonno Joi to the whole religious community.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>翌元治元年（1864）年には亀山天皇陵の修復、同年の禁門の変では幕軍に追われた長州藩士数十名を門内に匿って逃がすなどしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following year, 1864, he had the grave of the Emperor Kameyama repaired, and in the Kinmon Incident of the same year he hid dozens of the feudal retainers of Choshu Domain who were chased by Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) army and made them escape.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following year, 1864, he had the grave of the Emperor Kameyama repaired, and in the Kinmon Incident of the same year he hid dozens of feudal retainers of the Choshu Domain who were chased by Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) army and made them escape.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following year, 1864, he had the grave of the Emperor Kameyama repaired, and in the Kinmon Incident of the same year he hid dozens of feudal retainers of the Choshu clan who were chased by the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) army and made them escape.</e>
<cmt>clanを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>幕府は西本願寺の勤皇姿勢に警戒を強め、長州藩士を匿ったことを理由に、会津藩に命じて新撰組屯所を壬生から本願寺門内に移させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Edo bakufu tightened security at the stance of imperialist of the Nishi Hongan-ji Temple, so that it ordered the Aizu clan to move Shinsengumi headquarter from Mibu to the inside of the Hongan-ji Temple by the reason for having given shelter to the feudal retainers of Choshu Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Edo bakufu tightened security at the stance of the imperialist Nishi Hongan-ji Temple, it ordered the Aizu clan to move the Shinsengumi headquarters from Mibu to the inside of the Hongan-ji Temple as they had given shelter to the feudal retainers of Choshu Domain.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Edo bakufu tightened security at the stance of the imperialist Nishi Hongan-ji Temple, it ordered the Aizu clan to move the Shinsengumi (a group who guarded Kyoto during the end of Tokugawa Shogunate) headquarters from Mibu to the inside of the Hongan-ji Temple as they had given shelter to the feudal retainers of the Choshu clan.</e>
<cmt>用語を他の記事に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MKT(id:6704), Resto1578(id:168692), R28Bot(id:177951), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>