<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>孤雲懐奘</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ejo KOUN</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ejo KOUN</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ejo KOUN</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>孤雲懐奘（こうんえじょう、建久9年（1198年）- 弘安3年8月24日 (旧暦)（1280年9月19日））は鎌倉時代の禅宗僧侶。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ejo KOUN (1198-September 19, 1280) was a monk of Zen Sect who was active in Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ejo KOUN (1198-September 19, 1280) was a monk of the Zen Sect who was active in the Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ejo KOUN ((1198 - September 26, 1280) was a priest of the Zen Sect in the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し、かっこを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>曹洞宗の第2祖、永平寺の第2世（在任、建長5年（1253年）7月-文永4年（1267年）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the second founder of Soto Sect and the second chief priest of Eihei-ji Temple (he was in office from July 1253 until 1267).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the second founder of the Soto Sect and the second chief priest of Eihei-ji Temple (he was in office from July 1253 until 1267).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the second founder of the Soto Sect and the second chief priest of Eihei-ji Temple (the period of his term; August 1253 - 1267).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し表現を変えました。ネイティブチェックをお願いします。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>再任、文永9年（1272年）2月-弘安3年8月）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was reappointed and was in office from February in 1972 until 1280.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was reappointed and was in office from February in 1272 until 1280.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was reappointed and was in office from March in 1272 until September in 1280).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しかっこを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>諡号は道光普照国師（どうこうふしょうこくし）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Shigo (posthumous name) is Dokofusho Kokushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Shigo (posthumous name) is Dokofusho Kokushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His shigo (posthumous name) was Dokofusho Kokushi.</e>
<cmt>過去形にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>九条為通の子として京都に生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Kyoto as a son of Tamemichi KUJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Kyoto as a son of Tamemichi KUJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Kyoto as a son of Tamemichi KUJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>幼少の頃より比叡山に上り、18歳で出家し天台宗の学僧になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went up to Hieizan(Mt.Hiei)when he was a child and bacame a monk of Tendai Sect when he was 18 years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He went up to Hieizan(Mt.Hiei)when he was a child and bacame a monk of the Tendai Sect when he was 18 years old.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He went up to Mt. Hiei when he was a child and became a learned priest pursuing his studies of the Tendai Sect when he was 18 years old.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>学識に優れ将来を嘱望されるが、実母に「学問だけをして偉くなるよりも、黒衣の非俗として菅笠裸足で往来し、済度衆生を果たしなさい」と諭され下山。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he excelled in scholarship and was a promising monk, he left a temple because of his mother&apos;s admonition saying &quot;You should endeavor to enlighten people as an inconspicuous monk by preaching them with putting on a sedge hat and no sandals, rather than pursuing a high status only through studying&quot;.</e>
<cmt>この部分は意訳しておりますので、ご了承ください。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he excelled in scholarship and was a promising monk, he left the temple because of his mother&apos;s admonition saying &quot;You should endeavor to enlighten people as an inconspicuous monk by preaching to them whilst wearing a sedge hat and no sandals, rather than by pursuing high status only through studying&quot;.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he excelled in scholarship and was a promising priest, he left the temple because of his mother&apos;s admonition saying &apos;You should endeavor to enlighten people as an inconspicuous priest by preaching to them whilst wearing a sedge hat and no sandals, rather than by pursuing high status only through studying.&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語、クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>24歳で浄土宗西山派の証空について浄土教学を修めるが得心せず、さらに26歳の時、大和国多武峯（とうのみね）に日本達磨宗の覚晏を訪ね禅を学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he was 24 years old, he completed the study of Jodo-kyo under the guidance of Shoku, a monk of Seizan school of Jodo Sect, but he was not persuaded and when he was 26 years old, he started to study Zen under the guidance of Kakuan, a monk of Nihon Daruma Sect who resided at Tonomine in Yamato-no-Kuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he was 24 years old, he completed the study of Jodo-kyo under the guidance of Shoku, a monk of the Seizan school of the Jodo Sect, but he was not persuaded and when he was 26 years old, he started to study Zen under the guidance of Kakuan, a monk of the Nihon Daruma Sect who resided at Tonomine in Yamato-no-Kuni.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he was 24 years old, he completed the study of teaching of Jodo Sect under the guidance of Shoku, a priest of the Seizan school of the Jodo Sect, but he was not persuaded and when he was 26 years old, he started to study Zen under the guidance of Kakuan, a priest of the Nihon Daruma Sect who resided at Tonomine in Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>懐奘は覚晏より印可を受け高弟となるが、安貞2年（1228年）、興福寺衆徒の焼き討ちを受け避難を余儀なくされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ejo obtained Inka from Kakuan and became his leading disciple but in 1228, he was forced to evacuate because of the fire set on by many priests of Kofukuji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ejo obtained Inka from Kakuan and became his leading disciple, but in 1228 he was forced to evacuate because of a fire set by many priests of Kofukuji Temple.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ejo obtained Inka (Certification of spiritual achievement) from Kakuan and became his leading disciple, but in 1228 he was forced to evacuate because of a fire set by many priests of Kofuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>用語補足、表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>このような混乱の中、宋 (王朝)から帰り建仁寺に寄寓していた道元の評判を聞き、法戦を挑む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under such chaotic situation, he heard the reputation of Dogen, who stayed at Kennin-ji Temple after returning from Sun (dynasty), and challenged Dogen to have Doctrinal Debate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under such a chaotic situation, he heard about the reputation of Dogen, who stayed at Kennin-ji Temple after returning from Sun (dynasty), and challenged Dogen to a Doctrinal Debate.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under such a chaotic situation, he heard about the reputation of Dogen, who stayed at Kennin-ji Temple after returning from Sung (dynasty), and challenged Dogen to a doctrinal debate.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>法戦は数日に及んだが、ついに道元の所見が優れていることを認め、道元の方が2歳年下ではあったが、師事を願いでる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After a few days of Doctrinal Debate, he finally admitted that Dogen&apos;s views are superior to his views and asked for Dogen&apos;s guidance, although Dogen was younger than him by 2 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After several days of Doctrinal Debate, he finally admitted that Dogen&apos;s views were superior to his and asked for Dogen&apos;s guidance, although Dogen was younger than him by 2 years.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After several days of the doctrinal debate, he finally admitted that Dogen&apos;s views were superior to his and asked for Dogen&apos;s guidance, although Dogen was younger than him by 2 years.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>この時は、道元自身が仮寓の身であることを理由に断られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, Dogen declined because he was staying at temporary residence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, Dogen declined because he was staying at a temporary residence.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this occasion, Dogen declined it because he was staying at a temporary residence.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>文暦元年（1234年）、建仁寺を出て山城国深草に草庵を結んでいた道元を訪ね、再び師事を願いでて許される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1234, Ejo visited Dogen, who had left Kennin-ji Temple and was staying at his tea hut located at Fukakusa in Yamashiro-no-Kuni, asked for his guidance once again and was allowed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1234, Ejo visited Dogen, who had left Kennin-ji Temple and was staying at his tea hut located at Fukakusa in Yamashiro-no-Kuni, and asked for his guidance once again and was allowed.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1234, Ejo visited Dogen, who had left Kennin-ji Temple and was staying at his tea hut located at Fukakusa in Yamashiro Province, and asked for his guidance once again and was allowed.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>嘉禎2年（1236年）、道元が興聖寺を開山すると首座に任じられ大衆の長老となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1236 when Dogen founded Kosho-ji Temple, Ejo was appointed to Shuza and became the doyen of believers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1236, when Dogen founded Kosho-ji Temple, Ejo was appointed to Shuza and became the doyen of believers.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1236, when Dogen founded Kosho-ji Temple, Ejo was assumed the position of shuso (the leader of monks practicing asceticism) and became the patriarch of believers.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>以後、常に道元の身辺に随身し、道元の教えを記録し広めることにつとめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, he served Dogen at all times and strived to record and spread Dogen&apos;s teachings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, he served Dogen at all times and strived to record and spread Dogen&apos;s teachings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, he served Dogen at all times and strived to record and spread Dogen&apos;s teachings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>道元の著作『正法眼蔵』のほぼ全てを整理・筆写し、現在残されている同書は全て懐奘写本を底本としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As he put Dogen&apos;s &quot;Shobogenzo&quot; in order and transcribed it, all of existent &quot;Shobogenzo&quot; is based on Ejo&apos;s manuscript copy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since he put Dogen&apos;s &quot;Shobogenzo&quot; in order and transcribed it, all existent &quot;Shobogenzo&quot; are based on Ejo&apos;s manuscript copy.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since he put most of Dogen&apos;s writings &quot;Shobogenzo&quot; (Treasury of the Eye of True Teaching) in order and transcribed them, all existent &quot;Shobogenzo&quot; are based on Ejo&apos;s manuscript copy.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また、道元が日ごろ大衆に語った法語をまとめた『正法眼蔵随聞記』を著した（現在の研究では懐奘の書き残した遺稿を、没後、高弟達が編集し完成させたとするのが定説になっている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also wrote &quot;Shobogenzo-zuimonki&quot; which compiled Buddhist sermons that Dogen usually preached to people (according to the commonly-accepted view at present, this book is believed to have been edited and completed by his leading disciples based on his posthumous manuscript).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also wrote &quot;Shobogenzo-zuimonki&quot; which was a compilation of Buddhist sermons that Dogen usually preached to people (according to the commonly-accepted view at present, this book is believed to have been edited and completed by his leading disciples based on his posthumous manuscript).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also wrote &quot;Shobogenzo-zuimonki&quot; which was a compilation of Buddhist sermons that Dogen usually preached to people (according to the commonly-accepted view at present, this book is believed to have been edited and completed by his leading disciples based on Ejo&apos;s posthumous manuscript).</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>同書は道元の思想や当時の禅界の事情を知る上で欠くことのできない一級資料とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This book is deemed as first-class materials in order to study the philosophy of Dogen as well as the state of things in Zen Sect at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This book is deemed first-class material in order to study the philosophy of Dogen as well as the state of things in the Zen Sect at that time.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This book is deemed first-class material in order to study the philosophy of Dogen as well as the state of things in the Zen Sect at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>懐奘のもう一つの著作『光明蔵三昧』は優れた禅文学として評価され、夏目漱石は「コレハわけノ分カッタ人ノ云条ナリ。真ノ常識ナリ‥‥」と賛辞を残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Komyozozanmai&quot;, another book written by Ejo, is valued as an excellent Zen literature and Soseki NATSUME acclaimed it by saying &quot;the content of this book should be written by a person who knows things. It is real common sense&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Komyozozanmai&quot;, another book written by Ejo, is valued as excellent Zen literature and Soseki NATSUME acclaimed it by saying &quot;the contents of this book were written by a person who knows things. It is real common sense&quot;.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Komyozozanmai&quot; (Samadhi of the Treasury of the Radiant Light), another book written by Ejo, is valued as excellent Zen literature and Soseki NATSUME acclaimed it by saying &apos;the contents of this book were written by a person who knows things. It is real common sense.&apos;</e>
<cmt>補足し、クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="20">
<j>仁治2年（1241年）、日本達磨宗の僧数十人が道元門下に改宗する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1241, dozens of monks who had belonged to Nihondaruma Sect converted to Dogen&apos;s school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1241, dozens of monks who had belonged to Nihondaruma Sect converted to Dogen&apos;s school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1241, dozens of priests who had belonged to Nihon Daruma Sect converted to Dogen&apos;s school.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に表記を合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>この改宗に懐奘がどの程度関与していたのかは明確ではないが、少なからぬ役割を果たしていたことは容易に推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it is not clear to what extent Ejo was involved in this conversion, it can easily be surmised that he played a no small role.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is not clear to what extent Ejo was involved in this conversion, it can easily be surmised that he played a not small role.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is not clear to what extent Ejo was involved in their conversion, it can easily be surmised that he played a not small role.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="22">
<j>建長5年（1253年）、道元入寂後、跡を継いで永平寺2世となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Dogen passed away in 1253, Ejo succeeded as the 2nd chief priest of Eihei-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Dogen passed away in 1253, Ejo succeeded him as the 2nd chief priest of Eihei-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Dogen passed away in 1253, Ejo succeeded his position of the 2nd chief priest of Eihei-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>当時の永平寺は、道元の遺風を守ろうとする保守派と、衆生教化のために道元が不要とした法式も取り入れようとする開放派（その多くが日本達磨宗の法系に属していた）が対立し、懐奘は常に双方の調停・融和に努めなければならなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inside of Eihei-ji Temple at that time, there was a conflict between conservative monks who stuck to Dogen&apos;s old traditions and reformist monks who tried to introduce, for the purpose of educating people, ritual rules that Dogen had insisted unnecessary (most of them belonged to the school of Nihondaruma Sect) and under such circumstances, Ejo constantly had to strive to mediate/concilliate both groups.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Within Eihei-ji Temple at that time, there was a conflict between conservative monks who stuck to Dogen&apos;s old traditions and reformist monks who tried to introduce, for the purpose of educating people, ritual rules that Dogen had insisted unnecessary (most of them belonged to the school of Nihondaruma Sect) and under such circumstances, Ejo constantly had to strive to mediate/concilliate both groups.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Within Eihei-ji Temple at that time, there was a conflict between conservative priests who stuck to Dogen&apos;s old traditions and reformist priests who tried to introduce, for the purpose of educating people, ritual rules that Dogen had insisted unnecessary (most of them belonged to the school of Nihon Daruma Sect) and under such circumstances, Ejo constantly had to strive to mediate and conciliate both groups.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="24">
<j>文永4年（1267年）4月、日本達磨宗時代からの法弟である徹通義介に住職を譲るが、両派の対立が激化（三代相論）する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1267, he handed over the position of the chief priest to Gikai TETTSU, who was his disciple since the era of Nihondaruma Sect, but the conflict between two groups became intensified (Sandai Soron).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1267, he handed over the position of chief priest to Gikai TETTSU, who was his disciple from the era of the Nihondaruma Sect, but the conflict between two groups became intensified (Sandai Soron).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1267, he handed over the position of chief priest to Gikai TETTSU, who was his disciple from the period of the Nihon Daruma Sect, but the conflict between two groups became intensified (Sandai Soron (third-generation differentiation)).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>このため、文永9年（1272年）2月、義介が辞任下山し、懐奘が再任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to such situation, Gikai resigned and left the temple in February 1272 and Ejo was reappointed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to such a situation, Gikai resigned and left the temple in February 1272 and Ejo was reappointed.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to such a situation, Gikai resigned and left the temple in March 1272 and Ejo was reappointed.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="26">
<j>永平寺の住職となった後も道元の侍者であるとの姿勢を終生変えず、道元の霊廟の脇に居室を建て、道元の頂相に生前同様に仕えたといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after becoming the chief priest of Eihei-ji Temple, Ejo is said to have kept the attitude of being an attendant of Dogen throughout his life, built his residence beside the mausoleum of Dogen and served Dogen&apos;s effigy in a same manner as he had done while Dogen had been in life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after becoming the chief priest of Eihei-ji Temple, Ejo is said to have kept the attitude of being an attendant of Dogen throughout his life, built his residence next to the mausoleum of Dogen and served Dogen&apos;s effigy in the same manner as he had done while Dogen had been alive.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after assuming the position of the chief priest of Eihei-ji Temple, Ejo is said to have kept the attitude of being an attendant of Dogen throughout his life, built his residence next to the mausoleum of Dogen and served Dogen&apos;s effigy in the same manner as he had done while Dogen had been alive.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>また、自分が歴住として道元と同列に祀られることをおそれ「自分の遺骨は先師（道元）の墓所の侍者の位置に埋め、忌日には先師の墓前に向かい供養読経するべし」と遺言した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, as he was afraid that he might be enshrined in the same category with Dogen as one of successive chief priests, he left a will saying &quot;My cremains should be buried at the place of Dogen&apos;s attendants and on the anniversary of my death, memorial service and sutra chanting should be conducted while facing the tomb of Dogen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, as he was afraid that he might be enshrined in the same category as Dogen as one of the successive chief priests, he left a will saying &quot;My remains should be buried at the place of Dogen&apos;s attendants and on the anniversary of my death, a memorial service and sutra chanting should be conducted while facing the tomb of Dogen.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, as he was afraid that he might be enshrined in the same category as Dogen as one of the successive chief priests, he left a will saying &apos;My remains should be buried at the place of Dogen&apos;s attendants and on the anniversary of my death, a memorial service and sutra chanting should be conducted while facing the tomb of Dogen.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="28">
<j>弘安3年8月24日、病没。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died of illness on September 19, 1280.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died of illness on September 19, 1280.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died of illness on September 26, 1280.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>自分のために特別に法要が営まれる事を厭い、8日間営まれる先師道元の忌日法要の1日の回向に与ることを願い、願い通りになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As he disliked special memorial service for him, he hoped his memorial service was to be conducted on a certain day during 8-day memorial service conducted on the anniversary of Dogen&apos;s death and his hope was realized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As he disliked a special memorial service for himself, he hoped his memorial service would be conducted on a certain day during the 8-day memorial service conducted on the anniversary of Dogen&apos;s death and his hope was realized.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As he disliked a special memorial service for himself, he hoped his memorial service would be conducted on a certain day during the 8-day memorial service conducted on the anniversary of Dogen&apos;s death and his hope was realized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="30">
<j>永平寺では承陽殿（道元の廟所）入口の扉を常に少し開けておく事が慣例となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Eihei-ji Temple, keeping the entrance door of Shoyoden (mausoleum of Dogen) slightly open is a custom.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At Eihei-ji Temple, keeping the entrance door of Shoyoden (mausoleum of Dogen) slightly open is a custom.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At Eihei-ji Temple, keeping the entrance door of Shoyoden (mausoleum of Dogen) slightly open is a custom.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>これは現在でも懐奘が道元の廟所を見廻りに上るとされているためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is because even at present, Ejo is believed to go around Dogen&apos;s mausoleum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because even at present, Ejo is believed to move around Dogen&apos;s mausoleum</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because even at present, Ejo is believed to make the rounds of Dogen&apos;s mausoleum.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>また、夜中の役寮点検（責任者の山内巡視）は懐奘と行き当たる事のないよう、子の刻（午前0時）を外して行われているという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, inspection of yakuryo (an inspection of the temple&apos;s premises conducted by a responsible monk) is said to be conducted at other time than midnight in order not to meet Dogen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, inspection of yakuryo (inspection of the temple premises conducted by a responsible monk) is said to be conducted at times other than midnight in order not to meet Dogen.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, inspection of yakuryo (inspection of the temple premises conducted by a responsible monk) is said to be conducted at times other than midnight in order not to meet Ejo.</e>
<cmt>Ejoとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kstigarbha(id:13376), 水野白楓(id:22811), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>