<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>得度</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokudo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokudo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokudo</e>
<cmt>OK(trans1の訳文、コメントを正しいセルにコピーペーストしました。)</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>得度（とくど）は仏教における僧侶となるための出家の儀式。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokudo is a ceremony in Buddhism to enter into priesthood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokudo is a ceremony in Buddhism to enter into priesthood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokudo is a ceremony in Buddhism to enter into priesthood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>本来、僧侶になるには、仏教教団の10名の先輩構成員（三師七証）の承認があり、戒律を護る事を誓えば誰にでもなれるものであったが、中国や日本に於いては、労働、納税、兵役を免除されていたため、僧侶になる者が続出し、国家の財政を脅かす事態となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, everyone could become a monk if he had approvals of ten senior members of Buddhist society (sanshi nanasho) and an oath to obey religious precepts, but because they were exempted from labors, tax payments, and military services in China and in Japan, people became monks one after another and became a situation to frighten the national finance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, everyone could become a monk if he had the approval of ten senior members of Buddhist society (sanshi nanasho) and an oath to obey religious precepts, but because they were exempted from labors, tax payments, and military service in China and in Japan, many people became monks one after the other ant developed into a situation threatening the national finances.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, everyone could become a priest if he had the approval of ten senior members of Buddhist society (sanshi-shichisho (three leaders and seven witnesses) and an oath to obey religious precepts, but because they were exempted from labors, tax payments, and military service in China and in Japan, many people became priests one after the other and developed into a situation threatening the national finances.</e>
<cmt>用語を補足、スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>そこで国家は年度や地域毎に僧侶になる人数を制限するために、得度を国家の許可制とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, to limit the number of people to become monks in every years and regions, government made the tokudo as national license system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, to limit the number of people who became monks every year and in the regions, government created the tokudo as a national license system.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, to limit the number of people who became priests every year and in the regions, government created the tokudo as a national license system.</e>
<cmt>priestを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>中国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">China</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">China</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">China</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>インドで興起した仏教が中国に伝来すると、仏教本来の教団規律の他に、国家による統制を受けなければならなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Buddhism, originated in India, was introduced to China, it had to take in the control by the government, other than its original Buddhist religious precepts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Buddhism originated in India, it was introduced to China, and it had to taken control of by the government, in opposition to its original Buddhist religious precepts.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Buddhism originated in India was introduced to China, it had to be taken control of by the government, in addition to its original Buddhist religious precepts.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>北宋の賛寧は、その著である『大宋僧史略』の巻中「僧籍弛張」において次のように述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zanning of Northern Sung, in the chapter &apos;Soseki Shicho&apos; (tensioning and loosening of priesthood) of his writing &quot;The Essential History of Great-Song Monks,&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zanning of Northern Sung, in the chapter &apos;Soseki Shicho&apos; (tensioning and loosening of priesthood) of his writing &quot;The Essential History of Great-Song Monks,&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zanning of Northern Sung mentioned in the chapter &apos;Soseki Shicho&apos; (tensioning and loosening of priesthood) of his writing &quot;The Essential History of Great-Song Monks&quot; as follows.</e>
<cmt>原文14行目を含めました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>仏教は本来は国家の統制を受けるような筋合いのものではないのだが、真実の求道者だけではなく、僧侶の生活が優雅閑雅であることを羨んで、または、徭役を免れようとするような目的によって出家を志す者が頻出するようになり、僧伽の戒律のみでは、その弊風を抑制することが無理になってしまい、そこで、国家による統制が加えられることとなり、僧官の設置、僧尼の造籍を見るに至ったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, Buddhism has no reason to be controlled by the government, but because not only ones that seek the truth but also ones that envy the elegance and gracefulness of monk&apos;s life and ones that wish to escape from labors by entering the priesthood have increased so much, that it became impossible for Buddhist precepts alone to restrain the evil custom, and government have started to take control by the establishment of monk officials and registration of monks and nuns.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, Buddhism had no reason to be controlled by the government, but because not only those that seek the truth, but also those who envy the elegance and gracefulness of a monk&apos;s life, and those that wished to escape from labor by entering the priesthood, increased so much, it became impossible for Buddhist precepts alone to restrain evil customs, and government thus started to take control by the establishment of monk officials and registration of monks and nuns.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, Buddhism had no reason to be controlled by the government, but because not only those that seek the truth, but also those who envy the elegance and gracefulness of a priest&apos;s life, and those that wished to escape from labor by entering the priesthood, increased so much, it became impossible for Buddhist precepts alone to restrain evil customs, and government thus started to take control by the establishment of priest officials and registration of priests and priestess.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>確かに中国では、僧侶に徭役免除の特権が付与されたため、徭役免除を目的とした出家者が数多く現われ、そのために、国家が出家得度に定数を定めるなどの諸々の抑制策や規制を設けるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Indeed in China, since the special privilege of exemption of labor was given to monks, many monks with purposes to be exempted from the labors have appeared, and because of that, the government has established various restraint policies and regulations, such as the limiting of numbers of monks receiving tokudo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Indeed in China, since the special privilege of exemption from labor was given to monks, many monks with the purpose of exemption from labor appeared, and because of that, the government established various restraining policies and regulations, such as limiting the numbers of monks receiving tokudo.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Indeed in China, since the special privilege of exemption from labor was given to priests, many priests with the purpose of exemption from labor appeared, and because of that, the government established various restraining policies and regulations, such as limiting the numbers of priests receiving tokudo.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>さらに、国家公認の僧は僧籍に編成されることとなり、その統制に拍車がかかることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, the monks officially recognized by the government were made to be organized in priesthood, and that accelerated the control by the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, the monks officially recognized by the government were forced to become organized in priesthood, and this accelerated the control by the government.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, the priests officially recognized by the government were forced to become organized in priesthood, and this accelerated the control by the government.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>同時に、国家の手によって国家公認の僧であることの証明書としての度牒が発給され、その統制を更に一層強化することとなったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Simultaneously, official certificates as the monks who are officially recognized by the government were issued by the government, and its control was further strengthened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Simultaneously, official certificates as monks who were officially recognized by the government were issued by the government, and its control was further strengthened.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Simultaneously, official certificates as priests who were officially recognized by the government were issued by the government, and its control was further strengthened.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>日本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>日本の古代、律令制度下において、剃髪して僧籍に入ること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In ancient times in Japan, it meant to join priesthood with tonsure under the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the Ritsuryo code).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In ancient times in Japan, it meant to join priesthood with tonsure under the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the Ritsuryo code).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In ancient times in Japan, it meant to join priesthood with tonsure under the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the Ritsuryo code).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>年に一定数の得度を許す年分度と臨時度があり、原則は定員10名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were nenbundo, which approve fixed numbers of tokudo each year, and rinjido, which approve tokudo in special occasions, and generally, the number of tokudo approved were ten each year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were nenbundo, which approved fixed numbers of tokudo each year, and rinjido, which approved tokudo on special occasions, and generally, the number of tokudo approved were ten each year.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were nenbundo, which approved fixed numbers of tokudo each year, and rinjido (approved tokudo on special occasions), and generally, the number of tokudo approved were limited to ten.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>ともに試験に及第して官許された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both were officially approved by passing examinations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both were officially approved by passing examinations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both were officially approved by passing examinations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>度者には、官から得度を証明する文書として度牒が発給され、得度者の氏名や年齢、本貫地などを師僧が保障し、玄蕃寮、治部省などの官人や僧網の署名を得た後、太政官印を受けて支給された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ones that were approved were issued an official certificate to prove the tokudo by government, and after the priestly teacher of the approved person guaranteed his name, age, and place where his family is officially registered, signed by officials and monks of Genbaryo and Jibusho (both ministry to manage diplomatic and registrations of monks), it was provided with a seal by Daijokan (Grand Council of State).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ones that were approved were issued an official certificate to prove the tokudo by government, and after the priestly teacher of the approved person guaranteed his name, age, and place where his family was officially registered, signed by officials and monks of Genbaryo and Jibusho (both ministries to manage diplomacy and registration of monks), it was provided with a seal by Daijokan (Grand Council of State).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ones that were approved were issued an official certificate to prove the tokudo by government, and after the priestly teacher of the approved person guaranteed his name, age, and place where his family was officially registered, signed by officials and priests of Genbaryo and Jibusho (both ministries to manage diplomacy and registration of monks), it was provided with a seal by Daijokan (Grand Council of State).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>得度者には課役を免除される特権があり、官の許可なく僧となる農民などが出現し、これらは私度、そうした僧は私度僧と呼ばれ、律令の編目である戸婚律や僧尼令で禁じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ones that were approved had a privilege to be exempted from labors, and farmers who became monks without the official approvals, which is called shido, and ones who became monks this way is called shidoso, have appeared, and was prohibited by Kokonritsu (Penal Law on Households and Marriage) and Soniryo (Regulations for Monks and Nuns), which were both part of Ritsuryo code.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those that were approved had the privilege to be exempted from labor, and farmers who became monks without official approvals, which was called shido, and ones who became monks this way were called shidoso, appeared, and were prohibited by Kokonritsu (Penal Law on Households and Marriage) and Soniryo (Regulations for Monks and Nuns), which were both part of Ritsuryo code.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As those that were approved had the privilege to be exempted from labor, farmers who became priests without official approvals were appeared, that was called shido, and priests by shido, called shidoso, were prohibited by Kokonritsu (Penal Law on Households and Marriage) and Soniryo (Regulations for Monks and Nuns), which were both part of Ritsuryo code.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また、臨時度としては官寺における定員の不足、天皇などの貴人の病気回復などを祈願したもの、貴族などへの褒賞の一環として当該貴族に特定人数の得度（の推挙）を許してその貴族による善行の積み重ねを助けたものなどが挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, rinjido were approved when there is a shortage of monks in official temples, to ones who prayed for restoration from illness and so on to nobilities such as the Emperor, and to ones that helped nobilities, who were permitted to approve fixed number of tokudo as an award by the government to nobilities, to accumulate good deeds.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, rinjido were approved when there was a shortage of monks in official temples, to those who prayed for restoration from illness and so on to nobilities such as the Emperor, and to those that helped nobilities, who were permitted to approve fixed number of tokudo as an award by the government to nobilities, to accumulate good deeds.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, rinjido were hold in the occasions such as a shortage of priests in official temples, praying for restoration from illness and so on to nobilities such as the Emperor, and helping nobilities, who were permitted to approve fixed number of tokudo as an award by the government to nobilities, to accumulate good deeds.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>もっとも、私度僧であっても僧侶としての修行・活動がきちんと行われているものに関しては寛容に見られていた節もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, even when the monk was shidoso, that person seems to be treated with tolerance when he had made proper ascetic practices and activities as a monk.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, even when the monk was shidoso, that person seems to be treated with tolerance when he has made proper ascetic practices and activities as a monk.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, even when the priest was shidoso, that person seems to be treated with tolerance when he has made proper ascetic practices and activities as a priest.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>『続日本紀』天平宝字2年（758年）8月朔日（1日）条には天下の諸国で山林などに隠れて10年以上修行を積んでいる「清行逸士」には得度を許したという記事がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In article of August 1, 758 of &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued), there is a writing about tokudo approved to &apos;seiko isshi&apos; (清行逸士) in various regions around the country, who have accumulated ascetic practices for more than ten years hiding in mountains and forests.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In article of August 1, 758 of &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicles of Japan, Continued), there is writing about tokudo approved to &apos;seiko isshi&apos; (清行逸士) in various regions around the country, who have accumulated ascetic practices for more than ten years hiding in mountains and forests.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In article of September 11, 758 of &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicles of Japan, Continued), there is writing about tokudo approved to &apos;seiko isshi&apos; (清行逸士) in various regions around the country, who have accumulated ascetic practices for more than ten years hiding in mountains and forests.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これは「清行逸士」という表現こそ用いているが、度牒を持たないまま長期にわたって修行してきた私度僧が処罰を受けるどころか、逆に正式な僧侶として認められることもあったという事実を示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It does use the expression &apos;siko isshi&apos; (ones with pure actions), but it shows a fact that sometimes shidoso, even though making ascetic practices without official certificate, was not punished, but even was approved as a monk.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It does use the expression &apos;siko isshi&apos; (ones with pure actions), but it shows the fact that sometimes shidoso, even though making ascetic practices without an official certificate, were not punished, but were even approved as monks.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It does use the expression &apos;seiko isshi&apos; (ones with pure actions), but it shows the fact that sometimes shidoso, even though making ascetic practices without an official certificate, were not punished, but were even approved as monks.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>以後も六国史などには修行者に得度を許すために試験を行ったという記事が何回も記されており、その受験者の多くが私度僧であったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, in writings such as Rikkokushi (the Six National Histories), there are articles mentioned again and again about the examinations held to approve tokudo to ones that make ascetic practices, and it is believed that many of those examinees were shidoso.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, in writings such as Rikkokushi (the Six National Histories), there are articles that are mentioned again and again about the examinations held to approve tokudo to ones that make ascetic practices, and it is believed that many of those examinees were shidoso.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, in writings such as Rikkokushi (the Six National Histories), there are articles that are mentioned again and again about the examinations held to approve tokudo to ones that make ascetic practices, and it is believed that many of those examinees were shidoso.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>私度僧は違法であり取締りの対象ではあったが、実情においては2本立ての方針が存在し、課役忌避を目的とした私度僧に対しては厳しい取締りが行われた一方で、僧侶としての実態のあるものについてはある程度までは容認されており、その中の優秀者は処罰の対象ではなく、むしろ得度させて体制の中に積極的に取り込む方針があったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shidoso was illegal and was an object to be regulated, but actually, it is believed that there were two different policies, and on one hand, strict regulations were made against ones that became shidoso as a purpose of exempting from labors, but on the other hand, to some extent, ones that hold actual activities as monks were approved, and ones that have excellent results were not an object to be punished, but rather was an object to be approved tokudo and actively taken into the system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shidoso was illegal and was an object to be regulated, but actually, it is believed that there were two different policies. On the one hand, strict regulations were made against those that became shidoso for the purpose of exemption from labor, but on the other hand, to some extent, those that held actual activities as monks were approved, and those that had excellent results were not objects to be punished, but rather were objects to be approved as tokudo and actively taken into the system.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shidoso was illegal and was an object to be regulated, but actually, it is believed that there were two different policies; on the one hand, strict regulations were made against those that became shidoso for the purpose of exemption from labor, but on the other hand, to some extent, those that held actual activities as monks were approved, and those that had excellent results were not objects to be punished, but rather were objects to be approved as tokudo and actively taken into the system.</e>
<cmt>１文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>なお、私度僧で大成した者には空海や円澄（最澄の高弟）、景戒（『日本霊異記』著者）などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, there are Kukai, Encho (a leading disciple of Saicho), Kyokai (the author of &quot;Nihon Ryoiki,&quot; or Miraculous Stories from the Japanese Buddhist Tradition, written in the early Heian period), and so on as the ones that succeeded as shidoso.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, there are Kukai, Encho (a leading disciple of Saicho), Kyokai (the author of &quot;Nihon Ryoiki,&quot; or Miraculous Stories from the Japanese Buddhist Tradition, written in the early Heian period), and so on as the ones that succeeded as shidoso.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, there are Kukai, Encho (a leading disciple of Saicho), Kyokai (the author of &quot;Nihon Ryoiki&quot; (Miraculous Stories from the Japanese Buddhist Tradition, written in the early Heian period)), and so on as the ones that succeeded as shidoso.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 BoB774(id:148281), Mooko(id:36162), A-Taul(id:41790), Kstigarbha(id:13376), R28Bot(id:177951), Adonis(id:24011), Potty(id:32434), Johncapistrano(id:969), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>