<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>通夜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsuya (wake)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsuya (Wake)</e>
<cmt>Capitalized.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuya (Wake)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>通夜（つや）とは葬儀前夜に夜通しで行う儀式の事。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsuya is a ritual held throughout the night before the day of the funeral.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A tsuya is a ritual held throughout the night before the day of the funeral.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A tsuya is a ritual held throughout the night before the day of the funeral.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>仏教においてのみならず、神道、キリスト教においても行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsuya is a Shinto and Catholic ritual as well as Buddhist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They can be a Shinto or Catholic as well as Buddhist ritual.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They can be a Shinto or Catholic as well as Buddhist ritual.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>仏教の通夜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buddhist Tsuya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buddhist Tsuya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddhist Tsuya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>仏教の通夜は故人の成仏を祈る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buddhist tsuya is held to pray for the soul of the dead to peacefully leave this world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buddhist tsuya are held to pray for the soul of the dead to peacefully leave this world.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddhist tsuya are held to pray for the soul of the dead to peacefully leave this world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>起源は、釈迦の入滅後、悲しんだ弟子たちが遺体を守りながら夜通し説法を行ったという故事によるのが通説だが、『古事記』に記された天若日子（あめのわかひこ）の葬送を起源とする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of tsuya is commonly believed to be the story that when Buddha died, the disciples of Buddha read his teachings throughout the night in grief while protecting his body. However, there is another view that that it originates in the funeral of Ameno Wakahiko, which is depicted in Kojiki, a record of ancient matters.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳分例外処理。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of tsuya is commonly believed to stem from the story that when Buddha died, the disciples of Buddha read his teachings throughout the night in grief while protecting his body, although there is another view that it originated from the funeral of Ameno Wakahiko, which is depicted in the Kojiki, a record of ancient matters.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, sentences unified, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of tsuya is commonly believed to stem from the story that when Buddha died, the disciples of Buddha read his teachings throughout the night in grief while protecting his body, although there is another view that it originated from the funeral of Ameno Wakahiko, which is depicted in the Kojiki, a record of ancient matters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>古代日本で行われた殯に由来するとも言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another view is that it originates in an ancient custom of placing the dead in a coffin and waiting for a few days to make sure that the person has really died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another view is that it originates in an ancient custom of placing the dead in a coffin and waiting for a few days to make sure that the person had really died.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another view is that it originates in an ancient custom of placing the dead in a coffin and waiting for a few days to make sure that the person had really died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>通夜は本来、夜通しで行うとされるが最近では夜6時ごろから9時ごろまで一般の参列者を招き僧侶の読経も1回のみという形の『半通夜』にする場合が多くなってきている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsuya was traditionally held throughout the night, but in modern times it is usually shortened to a half-tsuya, which is held from around six to nine pm, inviting general mourners and having the priest reading from the Buddhist script only once.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsuya were traditionally held throughout the night, but in modern times they are usually shortened to a half-tsuya, which is held from around six to nine pm, open to all mourners and having the priest reading from the Buddhist script only once.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuya were traditionally held throughout the night, but in modern times they are usually shortened to a half-tsuya, which is held from around six to nine pm, open to all mourners and having the priest reading from the Buddhist script only once.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その後は、翌日の葬儀まで、近親者が夜通し付き添うのが習わしになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the half-tsuya, it is the custom for the family members to take turn being with the dead until the funeral the next day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the half-tsuya, it is the custom for family members to take turns being with the dead until the funeral the next day.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the half-tsuya, it is the custom for family members to take turns being with the dead until the funeral the next day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>よって線香、蝋燭を絶やしてはならないから起きておかねばならないというのは逆で、絶える間が無いとあるべきである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result incense and candles will not cease to burn, and it is putting the cart before the horse to say that someone has to stay awake to make sure that they do not burn out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, rather than someone having to stay awake to make sure that the candles and incense do not burn out, it is more appropriate to say that they do not have time to burn out.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, rather than someone having to stay awake to make sure that the candles and incense do not burn out, it is more appropriate to say that they do not have time to burn out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>近年、葬儀当日に寝不足になることを不満に持つ喪主が増えている事も事実であり、まさに本末転倒である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent times, it is true that some moshu (host of the funeral) feel unhappy about being short of sleep for the funeral, but this is really getting one&apos;s priorities wrong.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent times, it is true that some moshu (hosts of the funeral) feel unhappy about being short of sleep for the funeral, but this is really an example of getting one&apos;s priorities wrong.</e>
<cmt>Grammar. The final part sounds rather subjective.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent times, it is true that some moshu (hosts of the funeral) feel unhappy about being short of sleep for the funeral, but this is really an example of getting one&apos;s priorities wrong.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>現在では線香を一晩持つ蚊取り線香で代用するなど、負担が減らされる傾向にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is now a tendency to lessen the burden of the family, for example by using mosquito incense, which lasts throughout a night, in place of the proper incense.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is now a tendency to lessen the burden on the family, for example by using mosquito incense, which lasts throughout the night, in place of the established incense.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is now a tendency to lessen the burden on the family, for example by using mosquito incense, which lasts throughout the night, in place of the established incense.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>通夜は遺体を納棺した後祭壇を組んで行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsuya is conducted after the body is placed in a coffin and the alter is built.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tsuya is conducted after the body is placed in a coffin and the altar is set up.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tsuya is conducted after the body is placed in a coffin and the altar is set up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>最近は寺院や葬儀専用ホールなどで行われることが多く、自宅あるいは葬祭場などで遺体を納棺した後、寝台車で式場へ搬送し祭壇に安置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsuya is now often conducted in a temple or a funeral hall, so after the body is placed in a coffin at a home or a funeral house, the coffin is driven to where tsuya will be held and placed at the alter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsuya are now often conducted in a temple or a funeral hall, so after the body is placed in a coffin at the home or sosaijo (funeral house), the coffin is driven to where the tsuya will be held and placed at the altar.</e>
<cmt>Grammar. The term &apos;funeral house&apos; is difficult to distinguish from &apos;funeral hall&apos; and perhaps needs a clearer explanation in English.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuya are now often conducted in a temple or a funeral hall, so after the body is placed in a coffin at the home or sosaijo (funeral house), the coffin is driven to where the tsuya will be held and placed at the altar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="14">
<j>神道の通夜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinto tsuya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinto tsuya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinto tsuya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>神式の通夜は『通夜祭』と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A shinto tsuya is called Tsuya-sai festival.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A shinto tsuya is called Tsuya-sai festival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A shinto tsuya is called Tsuya-sai festival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="16">
<j>キリスト教の通夜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Catholic tsuya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Catholic tsuya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Catholic tsuya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="17">
<j>正教会にはギリシャ語の語源で「夜通しの祈り」を意味する、「パニヒダ」という永眠者の為の式典がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Orthodox church, there is a memorial service for the deceased called Panikhida, which has its linguistic root in a Greek word meaning praying throughout the night.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Orthodox church, there is a memorial service for the deceased called panikhida, which has its linguistic roots in a Greek word meaning praying throughout the night.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, no capital necessary.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Orthodox church, there is a memorial service for the deceased called panikhida, which has its linguistic roots in a Greek word meaning praying throughout the night.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>語源の語義が似通っている事から日本正教会では葬式前晩のパニヒダを通夜と呼ぶ事を忌避していない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the origins of the words are similar, the Orthodox Church of Japan does not avoid calling Panikhida a tsuya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the origins of the words are similar, the Orthodox Church of Japan does not avoid calling a panikhida a tsuya.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, no capital necessary.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the origins of the words are similar, the Orthodox Church of Japan does not avoid calling a panikhida a tsuya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="19">
<j>西方教会では『前夜式』、『通夜式』などと呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Western Christianity, such a service is called Zenya-shiki service or Tsuya-shiki service.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Western Christianity, such a service is called a Zenya-shiki service or Tsuya-shiki service.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Western Christianity, such a service is called a Zenya-shiki service or Tsuya-shiki service.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="20">
<j>地域差</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regional differences</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regional differences</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regional differences</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>地方によっては、通夜を行わない風習を持つ地域もある（秋田県の一部など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are regions where a tsuya is not performed, such as in some parts of the Akita prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are regions where tsuya are not performed, such as in some parts of Akita Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, capitalized.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are regions where tsuya are not performed, such as in some parts of Akita Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>秋田市では一般的に火葬を行ってから、通夜（逮夜）・告別式を行うケースが多い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Akita city, it is common to have a tsuya and a funeral after cremation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Akita City it is common to have the tsuya and funeral after the cremation.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, capitalized.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Akita City it is common to have the tsuya and funeral after the cremation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>また、昼間に勤務などで葬儀に参列できないなどで、近親者以外は通夜のみ出席をし、葬儀には出席しないのが一般的な地域もある（北海道の一部の地域など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are regions, such as in some parts of Hokkaido prefecture, where it is common for non-family members to attend only tsuyas and not funerals as it is more difficult to attend funerals because of work.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are regions, such as in some parts of Hokkaido, where it is common for non-family members to attend only the tsuya and not the funeral as it is more difficult to attend funerals because of work.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are regions, such as in some parts of Hokkaido, where it is common for non-family members to attend only the tsuya and not the funeral as it is more difficult to attend funerals because of work.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>逆に通夜は近親者のみ出席をし、一般の参列者は葬儀にのみ出席するのが一般的な地域もある（東北地方の一部の地域など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, in other regions, such as in some parts of northeastern Japan, it is more common for the general mourners to attend funerals, and tsuyas are attended only by family members.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, in other regions, such as in some parts of northeastern Japan, it is more common for the funeral to be open to all mourners, with tsuya attended only by family members.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, in other regions, such as in some parts of northeastern Japan, it is more common for the funeral to be open to all mourners, with tsuya attended only by family members.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), Asterisk(id:81766), Tanuki Z(id:612), Bergmann(id:85282), 経済準学士(id:22656), Kstigarbha(id:13376), 武蔵小金井(id:151909), R28Bot(id:177951), Ribbon(id:172), Loveless(id:129239), PixelBot(id:166734), Kliment.A.K.(id:161714), Tjan(id:17305), Dome2000(id:15142), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>