<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>印可</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inka</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inka (Certification of achievement)</e>
<cmt>説明補足</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>印可（いんか）とは、師がその道に熟達した弟子に与える許可のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inka refers to the license which a master grants to his disciple who has mastered his teachings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inka refers to the license which a master grants to a disciple who has mastered his teachings.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inka refers to the license which a master grants to a disciple who has mastered his teachings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>その証として作成される書面は印可状と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The written document issued as a certificate is called inkajo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The written document issued as a certificate is called inkajo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The written document issued as a certificate is called inkajo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>いわゆる“お墨付き”のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inka means the state of so-called &quot;osumi-tsuki&quot; (&quot;with endorsement&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inka means the state of so-called &quot;osumi-tsuki&quot; (with endorsement).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inka means the state of so-called &quot;osumi-tsuki&quot; (with endorsement).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>禅宗では、悟りを開いたと認められた弟子の僧侶が、師の肖像を絵師に描いてもらい、師はその肖像の上に「偈文」という漢詩の形を取った説法をしたため、これを一種の卒業証書とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Zen sect, the disciple who was acknowledged as having attained enlightenment had his master&apos;s portraint drawn by a painter; the master then wrote his preaching on the portrait based on the style of Chinese poetry called &quot;ge&quot;, and this portrait was used as a kind of diploma.</e>
<cmt>Webで確認し、【偈】を【偈文】に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Zen sect, a disciple who was acknowledged as having attained enlightenment had his master&apos;s portrait drawn by a painter; the master then wrote his preaching on the portrait based on the style of Chinese poetry called &quot;ge&quot;, and this portrait was used as a kind of diploma.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, spelling.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Zen sect, a disciple who was acknowledged as having attained enlightenment had his master&apos;s portrait drawn by a painter; the master then wrote his preaching on the portrait based on the style of Chinese poetry called &quot;gemon&quot;, and this portrait was used as a kind of diploma.</e>
<cmt>翻訳者コメントどおり、「偈文」が正しいので、原文訳文ともに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>これに倣い武道（剣術、槍術、柔術など）、茶道、あるいは算術などにおいても印可が与えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Similarly, inka is given to pupils in martial arts (such as the art of swordmanship, spearmanship, and Japanese traditional self-defense martial art), sado (tea ceremony), sanjutsu (arithmetic), or the like.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similarly, inka are given to pupils in martial arts (such as the art of swordmanship, spearmanship, and Japanese traditional self-defense martial arts), sado (tea ceremony), sanjutsu (arithmetic), and the like.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similarly, inka are given to pupils in martial arts (such as the art of swordmanship, spearmanship, and Japanese traditional self-defense martial arts), sado (tea ceremony), sanjutsu (arithmetic), and the like.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>現在残されている印可状の中には国宝や文化財とされている物もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of the inkajo which remain today have been designated as national treasures and cultural properties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of the inkajo which remain today have been designated as national treasures and cultural properties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of the inkajo which remain today have been designated as national treasures and cultural properties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Foldingfan(id:234775), VolkovBot(id:105371), Kstigarbha(id:13376), 0null0(id:582), Tmonzenet(id:92869), R28Bot(id:177951), Loveless(id:129239), Corwin(id:973), Louperibot(id:128971), SieBot(id:126695), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>