<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>春屋妙葩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myoha SHUNOKU</e>
<cmt>読み方は、しゅんおくみょうはの誤記と思われます。[kotobank,Yahoo辞書]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myoha SHUNOKU</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myoha SHUNOKU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>春屋妙葩（しゅんのくみょうは、応長元年（1311年） - 元中5年/嘉慶 (日本)2年10月2日 (旧暦)（1388年11月9日））は、室町時代の臨済宗の禅僧である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myoha SHUNOKU (1311-October 2nd in 1388 (old lunar calendar) (November 9th in 1388)) is a zen priest of Rinzai sect in Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>読み方は、しゅんおくみょうはの誤記と思われます。[kotobank,Yahoo辞書]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myoha SHUNOKU (1311-October 2nd, 1388 (old lunar calendar) (November 9th, 1388)) was a Zen priest of the Rinzai sect in the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myoha SHUNOKU (1311 - November 9, 1388) was a Zen priest of the Rinzai sect in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>年号表記などを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>室町幕府の帰依を得て天龍寺や臨川寺の住職となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was believed by Muromachi Shogunate and became the chief priest of Tenryu-ji Temple and Rinsei-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was trusted by the Muromachi Shogunate and became the chief priest of Tenryu-ji Temple and Rinsei-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was trusted by the Muromachi Shogunate and became the chief priest of Tenryu-ji Temple and Rinsei-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>知覚普明国師。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chikaku Fumyo Kokushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chikaku Fumyo Kokushi.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikaku Fumyo Kokushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>甲斐国（山梨県）の生まれ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Kai Province (Yamanashi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Kai Province (Yamanashi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Kai Province (Yamanashi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>母方の叔父である夢窓疎石のもとで受戒する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He vowed to follow the precepts under Soseki MUSO, his maternal uncle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He vowed to follow the precepts under Soseki MUSO, his maternal uncle.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He vowed to follow the precepts under Soseki MUSO, his maternal uncle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>天龍寺の住職となり、幕府に対して五山第一の南禅寺の楼門（山門）新築を提言し、幕府は楼門建設の援助をしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became the chief priest of Tenryu-ji Temple and advised Shogunate to built Romon (Sanmon, temple gate) of Nanzen-ji Zen Temple, against which Shogunate sponsored.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became the chief priest of Tenryu-ji Temple and advised the Shogunate to built Romon (Sanmon, temple gate) of Nanzen-ji Zen Temple, which the Shogunate sponsored.</e>
<cmt>Slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became the chief priest of Tenryu-ji Temple and advised the Shogunate to build Romon (Sanmon, temple gate) of Nanzen-ji Temple, the first temple of gozan (Zen temples highly ranked by the government), which the Shogunate sponsored.</e>
<cmt>五山第一の、を補足するなどしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>楼門建設には南禅寺と紛争状態であった園城寺が抗議し、比叡山の門徒もこれに加わり楼門撤去や妙葩の配流を求め、紛争は政治問題にまで発展する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onjo-ji Temple, which was in trouble with Nanzen-ji Zen Temple, protested against this and Monto (follower) of Mt.Hiei-zan joined and requested to remove temple gate and expel Myoha, so that this conflict led to the political issue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onjo-ji Temple, which was in trouble with Nanzen-ji Zen Temple, protested against this and Monto (follower) of Mt.Hiei-zan joined and requested removal of the temple gate and expelling of Myoha, so that this conflict led to the political issue.</e>
<cmt>Slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Together with the Monto (followers) of Mt. Hiei, Onjo-ji Temple, which was in conflict with Nanzen-ji Temple, protested against the construction of the Romon, requesting its removal and Myoha&apos;s banishment, and this resulted in the conflict becoming a political issue.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。I have had to rewrite this quite a bit to get it to make some sort of sense in English.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>1369年(応安2/長慶24)に管領の細川頼之は楼門を撤去させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1369 the Control Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA ordered to remove temple gate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1369 the Controller Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA ordered removal of the temple gate.</e>
<cmt>Slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1369, Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA, who held the position of kanrei (shogunal deputy), ordered the removal of Romon.</e>
<cmt>用語を他の記事に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>妙葩は頼之と対立して天龍寺住職を辞して勝光院、さらに丹後国の雲門寺に隠棲する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myoha, who opposed Yoriyuki, resigned the chief priest of Tenryu-ji Temple and retired at Shoko-in Temple and later at Unmon-ji Temple in Tango Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myoha, who opposed Yoriyuki, resigned as the chief priest of Tenryu-ji Temple and retired at Shoko-in Temple and later at Unmon-ji Temple in Tango Province.</e>
<cmt>Slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myoha, who opposed Yoriyuki, resigned as the chief priest of Tenryu-ji Temple and retired at Shokoin Temple and later at Unmon-ji Temple in Tango Province.</e>
<cmt>用語表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>頼之は妙葩との和解のために会談を求めるが妙葩は拒絶し、頼之は門徒の僧籍剥奪を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoriyuki asked Myoha to see him for reconciliation, but Myoha rejected, so that Yoriyuki deprived the title of priest from Monto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriyuki asked Myoha to see him for reconciliation, but Myoha rejected this, and Yoriyuki stripped Monto of the title of priest.</e>
<cmt>Slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriyuki asked Myoha to see him for reconciliation, but Myoha rejected this, and Yoriyuki stripped Monto of the title of priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>1379年(康暦元/天授 (日本)5)の康暦の政変で頼之が失脚した後に入京し、南禅寺住職として復帰する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myoha went back to Kyoto after Yoriyuki fell from power in Koryaku no seihen (Koryaku political change) in 1379, and returned to the chief priest of Nanzen-ji Zen Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myoha went back to Kyoto after Yoriyuki fell from power in the Koryaku no seihen (Koryaku political change) in 1379, and returned to be the chief priest of Nanzen-ji Zen Temple.</e>
<cmt>Slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myoha went back to Kyoto after Yoriyuki fell from power in the Koryaku Coup in 1379, and returned to be the chief priest of Nanzen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>用語表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>妙葩は頼之が失脚する直前に丹後を出立しており、政変への関与も考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Myoha had left Tango before Yoriyuki fell from power, he could have been related to that political change.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Myoha had left Tango before Yoriyuki fell from power, he may have been involved in this political change.</e>
<cmt>Slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Myoha had left Tango before Yoriyuki fell from power, he may have been involved in this political change.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>3代将軍足利義満の帰依を受け、康暦元年10月10日_(旧暦)初代の僧録となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was believed by the third Shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, and became the first Soroku on October 10, 1379.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was trusted by the third Shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, and became the first Soroku on October 10, 1379.</e>
<cmt>Slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was trusted by the third Shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, and became the first Soroku (highest-ranking priest of the Gozan, the leader of the Zen sect) on November 27, 1379.</e>
<cmt>西暦に直したりしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>相国寺を開き、五山派を興す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He founded Shokoku-ji Temple and established Gozan-ha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He founded Shokoku-ji Temple and established Gozan-ha.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He founded Shokoku-ji Temple and established Gozanha (group of the highest-ranked temples in Zen sect).</e>
<cmt>用語表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>五山版の刊行なども行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He published books called Gozan-ban.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He published books called Gozan-ban.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He published books called Gozanban (literally, Five Mountains Editions).</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また多くの弟子を育て、彼らは日明貿易を行う際に幕府の外交顧問となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, he fostered many disciples, who played a role as diplomatic counselor in the Trade between the Ming Dynasty and Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, he fostered many disciples, who played roles as diplomatic counselors in the trade between the Ming Dynasty and Japan.</e>
<cmt>Slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, he fostered many disciples, who played roles as diplomatic counselors in the trade between the Ming Dynasty and Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>『春屋妙葩頂相』　吉山明兆筆　光源院所蔵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;SHUNOKU Myoha Chinso&quot; was written by Mincho KICHIZAN in the possestion of Kogen-in Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;SHUNOKU Myoha Chinso&quot; was written by Mincho KICHIZAN and is in the possesion of Kogen-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>Slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shunoku Myoha Chinzo&quot; (Portrait of Myoha SHUOKU) was written by Mincho KICHIZAN and is in the possession of Kogenin Temple.</e>
<cmt>用語を他の記事に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), Izayohi(id:13095), Nnh(id:474), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Auf(id:633), R28Bot(id:177951), 水野白楓(id:22811), Cprobot(id:97843), Sho-gun(id:74168), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Tcyiswalk(id:7279), Akab(id:40239), Corwin(id:973), 遠藤(id:30275), Kagetudo(id:163875), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>