<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>佐田介石</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaiseki SATA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaiseki SATA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaiseki SATA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>佐田 介石（さた かいせき、文政元年4月8日 (旧暦)（1818年5月12日）- 明治15年（1882年）12月9日）は、肥後国出身の幕末から明治初頭にかけての浄土真宗本願寺派（晩年は天台宗）の僧侶。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaiseki SATA (May 12, 1818, which was April 8 according to the old calendar - December 9, 1882) was a Higo Province native Buddhist monk in the Jodo Shinshu sect Hongwan-ji school (later years Tendai sect), from the end of the Edo period to the beginning to the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaiseki SATA (May 12, 1818, which was April 8 according to the old calendar - December 9, 1882) was a Higo Province native Buddhist monk in the Jodo Shinshu sect Hongwan-ji school (later years Tendai sect), from the end of the Edo period to the beginning of Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaiseki SATA (May 12, 1818 to December 9, 1882) from Higo Province was a Jodo Shinshu sect monk of Hongan-ji school (In his later years, he was a Tendai sect monk) from the end of the Edo period to the beginning of Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>攘夷運動・梵暦運動の指導者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the leader of the Joi Movement (the Movement advocating the expulsion of foreigners) and the Bonreki (Buddhist calendar) movement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the leader of the Joi Movement (the Movement advocating the expulsion of foreigners) and the Bonreki (Buddhist calendar) movement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a leader of the Joi Movement (the Movement advocating the expulsion of foreigners) and the Bonreki (Buddhist calendar) movement.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>号は等象斎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Buddhist name was Toshosai.</e>
<cmt>等象斎→読みが見つかりませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Buddhist name was Toshosai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Buddhist name was Toshosai (等象斎).</e>
<cmt>定訳不明のため、日本語を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Character</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Character</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Character</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>肥後国八代郡種山村（現在の熊本県八代市）の浄立寺住職・広瀬慈博の子に生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaisai was born in Taneyama Village, Yatsushiro-gun in Higo Province (Yatsushiro City, Kumamoto of today) as the son of Jihaku HIROSE, a chief priest of Joritsu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>広瀬慈博→読み方が見つかりませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaisai was born in Taneyama Village, Yatsushiro-gun in Higo Province (Yatsushiro City, Kumamoto of today) as the son of Jihaku HIROSE, a chief priest of Joritsu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaiseki was born in Taneyama-mura, Yatsushiro-gun in Higo Province (Yatsushiro City, Kumamoto Prefecture of today) as the son of Jihaku HIROSE, a chief priest of Joritsu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>住所表記他を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>幼名は観霊。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was Kanryo.</e>
<cmt>観霊→読みが見つかりませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Kanryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Kanryo (観霊).</e>
<cmt>定訳不明のため、日本語を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>後に同国飽田郡正泉寺住職であった佐田氏の養子となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later he was adopted by Sata family who served as the chief priest of Shosen-ji Temple in Higo Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later he was adopted by Sata family who served as the chief priest of Shosen-ji Temple in Higo Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later he was adopted by the Sata family, who served as the chief priest of Shosen-ji Temple in Akita-gun, Higo Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>少年時代は熊本藩の藩校で儒学を学び、後に西本願寺において修行に励んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his youth, he studied Confucianism at hanko (a domain school) of the Kumamoto Domain, and thereafter, he underwent training at the Nishihongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his youth, he studied Confucianism at hanko (a domain school) of the Kumamoto Domain, and thereafter, he underwent training at the Nishihongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his childhood, he studied Confucianism at Hanko (a domain school) of the Kumamoto Domain, and after that, underwent ascetic training at Nishihongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました寺院名のtheを省きました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>幕末に入ると、日本は開国をして西洋の文物が流入するようになると、介石は憂国の志を抱くようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of the Edo period, when Japan opened its doors to the world and products from western culture pored into Japan, Kaiseki began to exhibit the desire to protect Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of the Edo period, when Japan opened its doors to the world and products from western culture pored into Japan, Kaiseki began to exhibit the desire to protect Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">#At the end of the Edo period, when Japan put an end to its isolation and cultural ideas and products poured into Japan from the West, Kaiseki started to worry about the future of Japan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>特に開国後の貿易開始に伴う経済の困難と西洋の学問の流入に関心を抱いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He showed interest in economic difficulties associated with the start of trade after the opening of the country and the inflow of western learning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He showed interest in economic difficulties associated with the start of trade after the opening of the country and the inflow of western learning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was especially interested in economic difficulties and inflow of western learning associated with the initiation of trade after Japan opened its country.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>特に天文学の地動説は仏教経典にある須弥山中心とする宇宙秩序に真っ向から反する考えであり、このような考えが広まれば仏教そのものが滅亡してしまうと考えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He particularly feared that spread of the Copernican theory of the astronomy would destroy Buddhism, since the theory directly conflicts with universal order of Mt. Sumeru (in Buddhism - said to be the highest mountain rising in the center of the world) stated in the Buddhist scriptures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He particularly feared that spread of the Copernican theory of the astronomy would destroy Buddhism, since the theory directly conflicts with universal order of Mt. Sumeru (in Buddhism - said to be the highest mountain rising in the center of the world) stated in the Buddhist scriptures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was particularly feared that spread of the Copernican theory might destroy Buddhism itself; the theory was directly opposed to the universal order described by Buddhist scriptures, saying that Mt. Sumeru (in Buddhism - said to be the highest mountain rising in the center of the world) was the center of it.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>だが、当時の仏教界は仏暦に関して余りにも無関心であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The world of Buddhism at the time had been far too unconcerned with Butsureki (Buddhist calendar).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The world of Buddhism at the time had been far too unconcerned with Butsureki (Buddhist calendar).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The world of Buddhism at the time was too indifferent to Butsureki (Buddhist calendar).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>そこで介石は故郷に戻り自らの手で仏教天文学の研究を極めようと勉学に勤しんだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaiseki, therefore, returned to his hometown and delved into the studying Buddhist astronomy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaiseki, therefore, returned to his hometown and concentrated on studying Buddhist astronomy.</e>
<cmt>vocabulary</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Kaiseki returned to his hometown and concentrated on studying Buddhism astronomy by himself in order to master it.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>1862年、介石は『鎚地球略説』を著す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1862, Kaiseki wrote &quot;Tui Chikyu Ryakusetsu (Outline of the Earth)&quot;</e>
<cmt>鎚地球略説→定訳不明。読みが見つかりませんでした。意味も推測です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1862, Kaiseki wrote &quot;Tui Chikyu Ryakusetsu (Outline of the Earth)&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1862, Kaiseki wrote &quot;Tsui Chikyu Ryakusetsu (鎚地球略説, Outline of the Earth)&quot;</e>
<cmt>原文の『鎚地球略説』は、『鎚地球説略』を指すと思われますが、定訳不明のため、原文どおりのローマ字読みで表記しました。参考[http://base1.nijl.ac.jp/infolib/meta_pub/KTGSearch.cgi]</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>彼は「視実等象論」を主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the book, he asserted theory of shijitsu tosho.</e>
<cmt>視実等象論→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the book, he asserted the theory of shijitsu tosho.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">#In the book, he advocated &apos;the theory of Shijitsu Tosho&apos; (視実等象論, &quot;the theory of the spheres&quot;).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>これは見かけの天体（視象天）と実際の天体（実象天）には区別があり、その格差には一定の法則がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The theory stated that the visual sky and the actual sky are different and that there is a fixed rule in the variance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The theory stated that the visual sky and the actual sky are different and that there is a fixed rule in the variance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The theory explained that what the astral body looked was different from what it really was and that there was a fixed rule in the difference.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>すなわちそれが垂孤の法則（天は本来平面であるが、見た目には観察者の頭上を中心に東西南北に垂れ下がり、あたかも半円のように見える）と縮象の法則（頭上に近いあたりは広く、地面に近いあたりは狭く見える錯覚を起こす）という主張である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, he asserted Law of 垂孤 (the sky is flat, but from the eyes of observers, it looks as though the sky hangs down in four directions with the location above the observer as the center, and the sky will look like it is semicircle) and the Law of Shukusho (illusion that the area over head is wide and the area near the ground is narrow).</e>
<cmt>垂孤→読み不明垂孤の法則→定訳不明、括弧内に説明文を入れてます。）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, he asserted Law of 垂孤 (the sky is flat, but from the eyes of observers, it looks as though the sky hangs down in four directions with the location above the observer as the center, and the sky will look like it is semicircle) and the Law of Shukusho (illusion that the area over head is wide and the area near the ground is narrow).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That is to say, he explained the two laws; Law of Suiko (although the sky is originally flat, from the eyes of an observer, it looks as though it hung down in four directions with the space above the observer as the center, and it also looks like a semicircle); and the Law of Shukusho (the observer has an illusion that the area near his/her head looks spacious and the area near the ground looks narrow).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しましたスペルミスを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>そして発明家として著名な田中久重に依頼して視実等象論の宇宙を実体化した「視実等象儀」を制作させて自己の思想を広めようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaiseki requested that Hisashige TANAKA create &quot;Shijitsu tasho gi&quot; that materialized the shajitu tasho universe theory and spread his idea.</e>
<cmt>視実等象儀→意味不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaiseki requested that Hisashige TANAKA create &quot;Shijitsu tasho gi&quot; that materialized the shajitu tasho universe theory and spread his idea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaiseki asked Hisashige TANAKA, a famous inventor to create &quot;Shijitsu tosho gi&quot; (a globe of shijitsu tosho), which materialized the Shijitsu tosho universe theory and tried to spread his theory.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>介石の理論は西洋天文学に比しては非科学的であったが、仏教経典と自己の独創性のみによってこれだけの理論を打ち立てた彼の才能は評価に値する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaiseki&apos;s theory was unscientific compared to western astrology, but his ability to come up with this theory from Buddhist scriptures and his audacity in pushing it deserve praise.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaiseki&apos;s theory was unscientific compared to western astrology, but his ability to come up with this theory from Buddhist scriptures and his audacity in pushing it deserves praise.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaiseki&apos;s theory was non-scientific, compared with western astrology, but his ability to establish such theory only from Buddhist scriptures and his own originality was worth praising.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="20">
<j>また、政治面においては、江戸幕府が進める長州征伐に反対してこれを止めるように意見書を出す一方で、興正寺門跡を擁して長州藩に赴き、幕府との和議を斡旋した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the political realm, he opposed the Choshu conquest by the Edo Bakufu and submitted minority report wishing to stop it, and he went to Choshu Domain with organized Kosho-ji monseki to mediate between Choshu and bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the political realm, he opposed the Choshu conquest by the Edo Bakufu and submitted minority report wishing to stop it, and he went to the Choshu Domain with an organized Kosho-ji monseki to mediate between Choshu and bakufu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the political field, he was against the Choshu conquest by the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), submitted a report in order to stop it, and went to the Choshu Domain with the title of Kosho-ji monzeki to mediate between Choshu and Bakufu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>明治に入ってからも『栽培経済論』を表して文明開化を痛烈に批判して農本主義・鎖国体制の堅持・国産品推奨を主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Entering the Meiji period, he expressed &quot;Saibaikeizairon&quot; and severely criticized civilization and enlightenment, asserting agricultural fundamentalism, national seclusion and the use of domestically produced goods.</e>
<cmt>栽培経済論→意味不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Entering the Meiji period, he expressed &quot;Saibaikeizairon&quot; and severely criticized civilization and enlightenment, asserting agricultural fundamentalism, national seclusion and the use of domestically produced goods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Entering the Meiji period, he expressed &quot;Saibai Keizairon&quot; (literally, &quot;the theory of cultivating the economies&quot;) and severely criticized cultural enlightenment, asserting agricultural fundamentalism, national seclusion and the use of domestically produced goods.</e>
<cmt>英訳を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>これらの主張は経済の実情を分析した上での理論展開がなされていたが、国産品推奨・外国製品排斥を主張する余り、次第に「ランプ亡国論」・「鉄道亡国論」・「牛乳大害論」・「蝙蝠傘四害論」・「太陽暦排斥論」・「簿記印記無用論」といった一種のトンデモ論に堕してしまったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These assertions were theoretically developed through the analysis of the economic status; however, his extravagant demand for the use of domestically produced goods and the exclusion of foreign goods led to nonsense theory including &quot;discourse concerning the lamp as a Perished Country,&quot; &quot;discourse concerning the railroad as a Perished Country,&quot; &quot;the curse of milk,&quot; &quot;the four curses of the umbrella,&quot; &quot;boycott of the solar calendar,&quot; and &quot;uselessness of bookkeeping.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These assertions were theoretically developed through the analysis of the economic status; however, his extravagant demand for the use of domestically produced goods and the exclusion of foreign goods led to nonsense theory including &quot;discourse concerning the lamp as a Perished Country,&quot; &quot;discourse concerning the railroad as a Perished Country,&quot; &quot;the curse of milk,&quot; &quot;the four curses of the umbrella,&quot; &quot;boycott of the solar calendar,&quot; and &quot;uselessness of bookkeeping.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although these assertions were theoretically developed through the analysis of the actual economic situation, his excessive demand for the use of domestic products and the exclusion of foreign goods resulted in a sort of meaningless claims, including &quot;a theory that lamps will destroy our country,&quot; &quot;a theory that railroads will perish our country,&quot; &quot;the curse caused by milk,&quot; &quot;the four curses caused by umbrellas,&quot; &quot;boycott of the solar calendar,&quot; and &quot;a theory about uselessness of bookkeeping.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="23">
<j>また、天文学においては『星学疑問』（1874年）、『天地論征論』（1881年）を著して西洋天文学と徹底的に対決した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the study of astronomy, he wrote &quot;Seigaku gimon&quot; (1874) and &quot;Tenchiron seiron&quot; (1881) coming in full conflict with Western astronomy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the study of astronomy, he wrote &quot;Seigaku gimon&quot; (1874) and &quot;Tenchiron seiron&quot; (1881) coming in full conflict with Western astronomy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the field of astronomy, he was completely against Western astronomy by writing &quot;Seigaku gimon&quot; (literally, &quot;questions of studies of stars&quot; (1874) and &quot;Tenchiron seiron&quot;(1881).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>このような彼の言動に対して明治政府は「神道国教化」政策の推進の障害になることを危惧して1876年に「須弥山」説の禁止を命じたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Meiji government feared his words and actions would hinder the political movement to establish Shinto as a state religion and prohibited the Mt. Sumeru theory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Meiji government feared his words and actions would hinder the political movement to establish Shinto as a state religion and prohibited the Mt. Sumeru theory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Meiji government feared his words and actions would hinder the political movement to establish Shinto as a state religion and prohibited the Mt. Sumeru theory in 1876.</e>
<cmt>「in 1876」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="25">
<j>だが、その後も介石は積極的に活動を続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaiseki, however, actively continued with his movements.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaiseki, however, actively continued with his movements.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, even after that, Kaiseki positively continued his activities.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しましたスペルミスを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>この頃、天台宗の僧侶であった唯我紹舜と親交を持った介石はその門人となって浅草新堀にある本光院の住職を任されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At about this time, Kaiseki established a friendship with Yuiga Shoshun, who was a Tendai Sect Buddhist monk, and he became a follower of the sect and was appointed Chief Priest of Honko-in Temple located at Asakusa Shinbori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At about this time, Kaiseki established a friendship with Yuiga Shoshun, who was a Tendai Sect Buddhist monk, and he became a follower of the sect and was appointed Chief Priest of Honko-in Temple located at Asakusa Shinbori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around that time, Kaiseki established a friendship with Yuiga Shoshun, who was a Tendai Sect Buddhist monk, and became a follower of the sect and was appointed to Chief Priest of Honko-in Temple located at Asakusa Shinbori.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>1882年新潟県高田（現在の上越市）で講演中に急死。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1882, he died unexpectedly while giving lecture at Takada, Niigata (Joetsu City of today)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1882, he died unexpectedly while giving lecture at Takada, Niigata (Joetsu City of today)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1882, he unexpectedly passed away while giving a lecture at Takada (Joetsu City of today), Niigata Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>本願寺派門主大谷光尊は介石が生前に同派を離脱したにも拘らずその人柄を慕って「嘯月院」という諡号を授け、漢方医の浅田宗伯が浅草寺に建てられた墓の碑文を書くなどして、その一途な生き様を偲んだという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koson OTANI, head of the Hongwan-ji School, favored Kaiseki, even though he had broken away from the school, mourned his passionate life, awarding him posthumous Buddhist name &quot;Shogetsuin,&quot; and having Sohaku ASADA, a doctor of Chinese medicine, write the inscription on his gravestone set up at Asakusa-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koson OTANI, head of the Hongwan-ji School, favored Kaiseki, even though he had broken away from the school, mourned his passionate life, awarding him posthumous Buddhist name &quot;Shogetsuin,&quot; and having Sohaku ASADA, a doctor of Chinese medicine, write the inscription on his gravestone set up at Asakusa-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koson OTANI, the head of the Hongan-ji School, favoured Kaisei, mourned Kaisei&apos;s passionate life and, even though Kaisei had left the school before his death, gave him the posthumous Buddhist name &quot;Shogetsuin&quot;; Koson also wrote the inscription on Kaisei&apos;s gravestone, which Sohaku ASADA, a doctor of Chinese medicine, established at Asakusa-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しましたhis→the</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>また、理論的には問題があるものの、彼の貿易論を日本の保護貿易論の先駆として評価する意見もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are also some that commented on and valued his protectionist theory of Japanese trade, in spite of its logical problems.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are also some that commented on and valued his protectionist theory of Japanese trade, in spite of its logical problems.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Kaisei&apos;s theory of trade has some logical problems, some evaluate the theory, saying that it went ahead of Japanese trade protectionism.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="30">
<j>だが、彼の死とともに梵暦運動も仏教天文学もその歴史的役目を終える事となるのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With his death, Bonreki (Buddhist calendar) activities and Buddhist astronomy ended their historical role in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With his death, Bonreki (Buddhist calendar) activities and Buddhist astronomy ended their historical role in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, with Kaisei&apos;s death, Bonreki (Buddhist calendar) movements and Buddhist astronomy finished their historical roles.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Resto1578(id:168692), Mait(id:73947), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>