<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>真仏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinbutsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinbutsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinbutsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>真仏（しんぶつ、承元3年2月10日 (旧暦)（1209年3月17日） - 正嘉2年3月8日 (旧暦)（1258年4月13日））は、鎌倉時代中期の浄土真宗の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinbutsu (17th March 1209 - 13th April 1258) was a Pure Land Sect Buddhist monk who lived during the mid-Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinbutsu (17th March 1209 - 13th April 1258) was a Pure Land Sect Buddhist monk who lived during the mid-Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinbutsu (March 17, 1209 - April 13, 1258) was a Pure Land Sect Buddhist priest in the mid-Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました生没年の表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>専修寺本寺専修寺2世、佛光寺2世。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the 2nd head priest of both Senju-ji Temple and Bukko-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the 2nd head priest of both Senju-ji Temple and Bukko-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the second head priest of the main temple of Senju-ji Temple, and also of Bukko-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>親鸞直弟「二十四輩」の第二番。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was number 2 of the &quot;Niju Yohai&quot;, who were 24 direct disciples of Shinran.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was number 2 of the &quot;Niju Yohai&quot;, who were 24 direct disciples of Shinran.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the second disciple of the &quot;Niju Yohai (twenty-four apprentices of Shinran and temples which were founded by the apprentices).&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>真壁椎尾氏の庶子で、俗名は椎尾弥三郎春時。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As an illegitimate child of the Shiio Clan of Makabe, his secular name was Shiio Yasaburo Shunji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As an illegitimate child of the Shiio Clan of Makabe, his secular name was Shiio Yasaburo Shunji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a child born out of Makabe&apos;s wedlock, belonging to the Shiio Clan, and his secular name was Shunji Yasaburo SHIIO.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>1224年（元仁元年）ごろ稲田草庵（現在茨城県笠間市稲田にある西念寺）で親鸞に師事してその教を受け、翌1225年（嘉禄元年）に親鸞より剃髪を受けたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Circa 1224: Studied under Shinran at Inada Soan (now Sainen-ji Temple in Inada, Kasama City, Ibaraki Prefecture), where is said to have underwent tonsure by Shinran.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Circa 1224: Studied under Shinran at Inada Soan (now Sainen-ji Temple in Inada, Kasama City, Ibaraki Prefecture), where he is said to have undergone tonsure by Shinran.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Shinbutsu studied under Shinran at Inada Soan (now Sainen-ji Temple in Inada, Kasama City, Ibaraki Prefecture) around 1224 and he had Shinran shave his head to become a priest in 1225.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しましたスペースを挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>1227年（安貞元年）上洛し、師の命により興正寺（仏光寺）の寺主となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1227: Travelled to Kyoto and became the patron of Kosho-ji Temple (Bukko-ji Temple) on the order of his master.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1227: Travelled to Kyoto and became the patron of Kosho-ji Temple (Bukko-ji Temple) on the order of his master.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1227, Shinbutsu went to Kyoto and became the chief priest of Kosho-ji Temple (Bukko-ji Temple) under the order of his mentor.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>1232年（貞永元年）興正寺を源海に譲って下野国高田如来堂（のちの専修寺）を継ぎ、諸国をめぐって浄土教を広める一方、東北では当地で広まっていた異義を正している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1232: Passed Kosho-ji Temple over to Genkai and inherited Nyorai-do Temple (which later became Senju-ji Temple) in Takada, Shimotsuke Province before travelling around the country to preach Pure Land Buddhism while rectifying the incorrect teachings that had been spread throughout the northeast.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1232: Passed Kosho-ji Temple over to Genkai and inherited Nyorai-do Temple (which later became Senju-ji Temple) in Takada, Shimotsuke Province before travelling around the country to preach Pure Land Buddhism while rectifying the incorrect teachings that had been spread throughout the northeast.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1232, he gave Kosho-ji Temple to Genkai and became the chief priest of Nyorai-do Temple (latter-day Senju-ji Temple) in Takada, Shimotsuke Province; he also travelled around the country to preach Pure Land Buddhism while correcting the wrong teachings that had been spread throughout the Tohoku region.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しましたaroundが重複していたのでひとつ省きました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>1257年（正嘉元年）に一旦帰京し親鸞に拝謁したが、再び関東に下向している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1257: Temporarily returned to Kyoto where he had an audience with Shinran but once again departed for the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1257: Temporarily returned to Kyoto where he had an audience with Shinran but once again departed for the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1257, he came back to Kyoto, where he had an audience with Shinran, and soon left for the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>親鸞の関東教化の拠点であった下野国高田の如来堂を中心に高田門徒が形成され、真仏はその中心的な存在であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nyorai-do Temple in Takada, Shimotsuke Province, which served as Shinran&apos;s center of teaching in the Kanto region, formed the Takada Sect that was centered around Shinbutsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nyorai-do Temple in Takada, Shimotsuke Province, which served as Shinran&apos;s center of teaching in the Kanto region, formed the Takada Sect that was centered around Shinbutsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nyorai-do Temple in Takada, Shimotsuke Province, was the center of Shinran&apos;s teaching in the Kanto region, and the Takada Sect was formed around it, and Shinbutsu was a leading figure of the Sect.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Resto1578(id:168692), 0太郎(id:7375), ベルゼブブ(id:184141), Tukushiko(id:216497), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), Nighthawks(id:36125), くっちゃめ(id:86793), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>