<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>義堂周信</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shushin GIDO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shushin GIDO</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shushin GIDO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>義堂 周信（ぎどう しゅうしん、1325年3月1日（正中 (元号)2年1月16日 (旧暦)） - 1388年5月10日（元中5年/嘉慶 (日本)2年4月4日 (旧暦)））は、南北朝時代 (日本)から室町時代の臨済宗の僧である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shushin GIDO (January 16, 1325 (lunar calendar) - May 10, 1388 (lunar calendar)) is a priest of Rinzai sect who was active in Southern and Northern Dynasties period (Japan) and Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shushin GIDO (January 16, 1325 (lunar calendar) - May 10, 1388 (lunar calendar)) was a priest of the Rinzai sect who was active in the Southern and Northern Dynasties period (Japan) and the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>Slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shushin GIDO (February 8, 1325 - May 18, 1388) was a priest of the Rinzai sect who was active from the period of the Northern and Southern Courts to the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>空華道人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Donin KUGE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Donin KUGE</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Donin KUGE.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>土佐国高岡(高知県高岡郡津野町)の生まれ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Takaoka of Tosa-no-Kuni (Tsuno-cho, Takaoka-gun, Kochi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Takaoka of Tosa-no-Kuni (Tsuno-cho, Takaoka-gun, Kochi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Takaoka of Tosa Province (Tsuno-cho, Takaoka-gun, Kochi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>Provinceを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>京都比叡山で足利将軍家とも親密であった夢窓疎石の弟子となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Hieizan(Mt.Hiei),he became a disciple of Soseki MUSO who was closely acquainted with Ashikaga Shogun family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At Hieizan(Mt.Hiei),he became a disciple of Soseki MUSO who was closely acquainted with the Ashikaga Shogun family.</e>
<cmt>Slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At Mt. Hiei, he became a disciple of Soseki MUSO who was closely acquainted with the Ashikaga Shogun family.</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>1359年（延文4）に幕府が関東地方の統治のために設置した鎌倉公方の足利基氏に招かれて鎌倉へ赴き、基氏や関東管領の上杉氏などに禅宗を教える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1359, he moved to Kamakura in response to the invitation of Motouji ASHIKAGA, then Kamakura Kubo, the positin which bakufu established for the purpose of governing Kanto region, and taught Zen sect to Motouji as well as the Uesugi clan whose member is supposed to assume the position of Kanto kanrei(A shogunal deputy for the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1359, he moved to Kamakura in response to the invitation of Motouji ASHIKAGA, then the Kamakura Kubo, the position which bakufu established for the purpose of governing the Kanto region, and taught the Zen sect to Motouji as well as the Uesugi clan whose members were supposed to assume the position of Kanto Kanrei(Shoguna deputies for the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>Slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1359, he moved to Kamakura in response to the invitation of Motouji ASHIKAGA, then the Kamakura kubo (Governor-general of the Kanto region), the position which bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) established for the purpose of governing the Kanto region, and taught the Zen sect to Motouji as well as the Uesugi clan of Kanto Kanrei (A shogunal deputy for the Kanto region).</e>
<cmt>用語補足し、表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>1379年（康暦元）に上京し、3代将軍足利義満の家庭教師的存在となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1379, he went up to Kyoto and became something like a private tutor for 3rd shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1379, he went up to Kyoto and became something simliar to a private tutor for the 3rd shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>Slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1379, he went up to Kyoto and became something similar to a private tutor for the 3rd shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>相国寺建立を進言し、建仁寺住職、1386年には南禅寺の住職となり、等持寺住職も務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He exhorted the construction of Shokoku-ji Temple, served as the chief priest of Kennin-ji Temple, became the chief priest of Nanzen-ji Temple in 1386 and further served as the chief priest of Toji-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He exhorted the construction of Shokoku-ji Temple, served as the chief priest of Kennin-ji Temple, became the chief priest of Nanzen-ji Temple in 1386 and further served as the chief priest of Toji-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He exhorted the construction of Shokoku-ji Temple, served as the chief priest of Kennin-ji Temple, became the chief priest of Nanzen-ji Temple in 1386 and further served as the chief priest of Toji-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>春屋妙葩や絶海中津と並び中国文化に通じた京都五山を代表する学問僧とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Along with Myoha SHUNOKU and Chushin ZEKKAI, he is well-known for his familiarity with Chinese culture and is deemed as a representative learning priest of Kyoto Gozan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Along with Myoha SHUNOKU and Chushin ZEKKAI, he is well-known for his familiarity with Chinese culture and is considered as a representative Kyoto Gozan academic priest.</e>
<cmt>Slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Along with Myoha SHUNOKU and Chushin ZEKKAI, he is well-known for his familiarity with Chinese culture and is considered as a representative Kyoto Gozan (Five Great zen Temples of Kyoto) academic priest.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), Izayohi(id:13095), Tnm(id:58695), 代言人(id:33675), Kstigarbha(id:13376), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), UMBRO(id:100484), Tcyiswalk(id:7279), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), NDR(id:5500), 一休(id:17559), 遠藤(id:30275), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>