<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>蓮悟</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rengo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rengo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rengo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>蓮悟（れんご、応仁2年（1468年）- 天文 (元号)12年7月16日 (旧暦)（1543年8月16日））は、室町時代中期から戦国時代 (日本)にかけての浄土真宗の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rengo (1468 - August 16, 1543) was a priest of Jodo Shinshu sect (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) over the middle of the Muromachi period and the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rengo (1468 - August 26, 1543) was a priest of Jodo Shinshu sect (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) over the middle of the Muromachi period and the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States).</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rengo (1468 - August 26, 1543) was a priest of Jodo Shinshu sect (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) over the middle of the Muromachi period and the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>本願寺8世蓮如の七男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the seventh son of Rennyo, the eighth chief priest of Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the seventh son of Rennyo, the eighth chief priest of Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the seventh son of Rennyo, the eighth chief priest of Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>幼名は光寿丸。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was Kojumaru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Kojumaru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Kojumaru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>兄蓮乗の養子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was an adopted child of his older brother Renjo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was an adopted child of his older brother Renjo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was an adopted child of his older brother Renjo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>幼少時代に兄の元に養子に出されたと見られ、兄とともに加賀国・越中国を転々とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was believed to have been put up for adoption to his older brother in his childhood and he moved from Kaga Province to Ecchu Province with his older brother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rengo was believed to have been adopted as infants by his older brother who moved from Kaga to Etchu Provinces with Rengo.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rengo was believed to have been adopted as infants by his older brother who moved from Kaga to Etchu Provinces with Rengo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>加賀一向一揆が一揆側の勝利に終わり、加賀国内が一応の安定を見た文明 (日本)14年（1483年）に父の名代として加賀を訪れた長兄順如の手によって得度した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaga Ikko Ikki (an uprising of Ikko sect followers in Kaga Province) ended with a victory of Ikko sect followers, and in 1483 when Kaga Province was stabilized more or less, Rengo did tokudo (enter the Buddhist priesthood) by his eldest brother Junnyo who visited Kaga Province as myodai (a substitute) of his father.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaga Ikko Ikki (an uprising of Ikko sect followers in Kaga Province) ended with a victory of Ikko sect followers, and in 1483 when Kaga Province was stabilized more or less, Rengo did tokudo (enter the Buddhist priesthood) by his oldest brother Junnyo who visited Kaga Province as myodai (a substitute) of his father.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaga Ikko Ikki (an uprising of Ikko sect followers in Kaga Province) ended with a victory of Ikko sect followers, and in 1483 when Kaga Province was stabilized more or less, Rengo did tokudo (enter the Buddhist priesthood) by his oldest brother Junnyo who visited Kaga Province as myodai (a substitute) of his father.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>養父となった兄・蓮乗は蓮如の次男であり北陸地方の門徒のまとめ役になる事を期待されていたが、病気がちであり、蓮悟の得度の際にあわせて本泉寺を継承している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His older brother Renjo, who became foster father of Rengo, was the second son of Rennyo and he was expected to be a consensus builder of followers in the Hokuriku region, but he was prone to illness and he inherited Honsen-ji Temple when Rengo did tokudo (enter the Buddhist priesthood).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His older brother Renjo, who became foster father of Rengo, was the second son of Rennyo and he was expected to be a consensus builder of followers in the Hokuriku region, but he was prone to illness and he inherited Honsen-ji Temple when Rengo did tokudo (enter the Buddhist priesthood).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His older brother Renjo, who became foster father of Rengo, was the second son of Rennyo and he was expected to be a consensus builder of followers in the Hokuriku region, but he was prone to illness and he inherited Honsen-ji Temple when Rengo did tokudo (enter the Buddhist priesthood).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>やがて蓮悟は三兄である蓮綱とともに北陸門徒のまとめ役となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Rengo became a consensus builder of Hokuriku monto (followers of the Jodo Shinshu sect in the Hokuriku region) along with the third oldest brother Renko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Rengo became a consensus builder of Hokuriku monto (followers of the Jodo Shinshu sect in the Hokuriku region) along with the third oldest brother Renko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Rengo became a consensus builder of Hokuriku monto (followers of the Jodo Shinshu sect in the Hokuriku region) along with the third oldest brother Renko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>長享元年（1487年）、本泉寺を河北郡若松荘（現在の石川県金沢市）に移転した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1487, he moved Honsen-ji Temple to Wakamatsu-so, Kawakita-gun (present Kanazawa City, Ishikawa Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1487, he moved Honsen-ji Temple to Wakamatsu no sho, Kawakita County (present Kanazawa City, Ishikawa Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1487, he moved Honsen-ji Temple to Wakamatsu no sho, Kawakita County (present Kanazawa City, Ishikawa Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>翌年に守護富樫政親が倒された長享の一揆には直接の関与の明証は無いものの、その後の加賀の支配が蓮悟と蓮綱主導の「両御山」体制に移されている事から、何らかのつながりがあったとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there was no evidence of direct involvement in Chokyo no Ikki where Shugo (provincial constable) Masachika TOGASHI was defeated the following year, since control of Kaga Province was thereafter moved to &quot;Ryo-Gozan&quot; system led by Rengo and Renko, they were believed to have some sort of connection with Chokyo no Ikki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there was no evidence of direct involvement, they were believed to have some sort of connection with the Revolt of the Chokyo era, which Shugo (provincial constable) Masachika TOGASHI was defeated the following year, since the control of Kaga Province was thereafter moved to &apos;Two Temples&apos; system led by Rengo and Renko.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there was no evidence of direct involvement, they were believed to have some sort of connection with the Revolt of the Chokyo era, which Shugo (provincial constable) Masachika TOGASHI was defeated the following year, since the control of Kaga Province was thereafter moved to &apos;Two Temples&apos; system led by Rengo and Renko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>やがて異母弟の実悟（後に加賀を「百姓の持ちたる国」と呼んだ事で知られる）を養子に迎えるが、永正2年（1505年）に実悟の同母兄実賢を法主の擁立しようとする陰謀（「大坂一乱」）が発覚し、更に同5年（1508年）実子の実教が生まれるとこれを疎んじた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Rengo adopted his younger paternal brother Jitsugo (who was known to call Kaga Province &apos;country governed by peasants&apos;), but Rengo disfavored Jitsugo when a conspiracy that Jikken, Jitsugo&apos;s older maternal brother, was put up to be hoshu (the head of a Buddhist sect) (&apos;Osaka Ichiran&apos;) was discovered in 1505 and furthermore when he had his own child Sanenori in 1508.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Rengo adopted his younger paternal brother Jitsugo (who was known to call Kaga Province &apos;country governed by peasants&apos;), but Rengo disfavored Jitsugo when a conspiracy that Jikken, Jitsugo&apos;s older maternal brother, was put up to be the head of the sect (&apos;Osaka Ichiran&apos; [Osaka-ichi War]) was discovered in 1505 and furthermore when Jitsugo had his biological child Sanenori in 1508.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Rengo adopted his younger paternal brother Jitsugo (who was known to call Kaga Province &apos;country governed by peasants&apos;), but Rengo disfavored Jitsugo when a conspiracy that Jikken, Jitsugo&apos;s older maternal brother, was put up to be the head of the sect (&apos;Osaka Ichiran&apos; [Osaka-ichi War]) was discovered in 1505 and furthermore when Jitsugo had his biological child Sanenori in 1508.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>やがて、生母が一向一揆と敵対する畠山氏出身であるという理由で末寺の住職に移された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then Jitsugo was transferred to the chief priest of a branch temple for the reason that his real mother was from the Hatakeyama clan who fought against an uprising of Ikko sect followers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then Jitsugo was transferred to the chief priest of a branch temple for the reason that his biological mother was from the Hatakeyama clan who fought against an uprising of Ikko sect followers.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then Jitsugo was transferred to the chief priest of a branch temple for the reason that his biological mother was from the Hatakeyama clan who fought against an uprising of Ikko sect followers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>以後の蓮悟の実悟への仕打ちは続き、永正16年（1519年）に本願寺に「一門一家制」を導入した際に実悟は蓮如の子という事で最上級の「連枝」になる可能性もあったにも関わらず、蓮悟の意見で最下級の「一家」に編入されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, the unjust treatment of Jitsugo by Rengo continued, and in 1519 when &apos;Ichimon-Ikke System&apos; (system divided the Hongan-ji families into Ichimonshu [clansman, for legitimate son] and Ikkeshu [the same lineage people as the Hongan-ji Temple, for second son and younger]) was introduced in Hongan-ji Temple, Jitsugo was placed in the lowest grade &quot;Ikke&quot; due to Rengo&apos;s opinion, although there was a possibility that Jitsugo would be placed in the highest grade &quot;Renshi&quot; because Jitsugo was a biological child of Rennyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, the unjust treatment of Jitsugo by Rengo continued, and in 1519 when &apos;Ichimon-Ikke System&apos; (system divided the Hongan-ji families into Ichimonshu [clansman, for legitimate son] and Ikkeshu [the same lineage people as the Hongan-ji Temple, for second son and younger]) was introduced in Hongan-ji Temple, Jitsugo was placed in the lowest grade &apos;Ikke&apos; due to Rengo&apos;s opinion, although there was a possibility that Jitsugo would be placed in the highest grade &apos;Renshi&apos; because Jitsugo was a biological child of Rennyo.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, the unjust treatment of Jitsugo by Rengo continued, and in 1519 when &apos;Ichimon-Ikke System&apos; (system divided the Hongan-ji families into Ichimonshu [clansman, for legitimate son] and Ikkeshu [the same lineage people as the Hongan-ji Temple, for second son and younger]) was introduced in Hongan-ji Temple, Jitsugo was placed in the lowest grade &apos;Ikke&apos; due to Rengo&apos;s opinion, although there was a possibility that Jitsugo would be placed in the highest grade &apos;Renshi&apos; because Jitsugo was a biological child of Rennyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>更に蓮悟らによって進められた越前国朝倉氏攻め失敗の煽りを受けて越前を追放された本覚寺の蓮恵が蓮悟に対して越前追放を受けた責任を追及しようとしたところ、逆に法主実如に蓮恵の破門を進言して最終的に屈服させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Ren-e of Hongaku-ji Temple, who was banished from Echizen Province as a result of failure in attack against the Asakura clan in Echizen Province which has been advanced by Rengo and others, tried to blame Rengo for Ren-e&apos;s banishment from Echizen Province, then, in return, Rengo suggested hoshu (the head of a Buddhist sect) Jitsunyo to excommunicate Ren-e and he finally made him yield.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Rene of Hongaku-ji Temple tried to blame Rengo for his banishment from Echizen Province as a result of failure in attack against the Asakura clan in the province which has been advanced by Rengo and others, but in return, he finally yielded to Rengo who suggested Rene&apos;s excommunication to the head of the sect Jitsunyo.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Rene of Hongaku-ji Temple tried to blame Rengo for his banishment from Echizen Province as a result of failure in attack against the Asakura clan in the province which has been advanced by Rengo and others, but in return, he finally yielded to Rengo who suggested Rene&apos;s excommunication to the head of the sect Jitsunyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>末寺や門徒に対して厳しい態度を取る事が多く、恨みを買う事が多かったといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this way, it was said that Rengo took often a severe attitude toward branch temples and followers and therefore incurred often their hostility.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this way, it was said that Rengo took often a severe attitude toward branch temples and followers and therefore incurred often their hostility.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this way, it was said that Rengo took often a severe attitude toward branch temples and followers and therefore incurred often their hostility.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>ところが、本願寺の法主が証如の代に入ると証如とその後見である蓮淳（蓮如の六男で証如の外祖父）は法主による一門統制を強める政策を採った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, after Shonyo became hoshu of Hongan-ji Temple, Shonyo and his koken (guardian) Renjun (the sixth son of Rennyo and maternal grandfather of Shonyo) adopted a policy of strengthening Ichimon (group of priests of the same sect) regulation by hoshu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after Shonyo became the head of Hongan-ji Temple, Shonyo and his guardian Renjun (the sixth son of Rennyo and maternal grandfather of Shonyo) adopted a policy of strengthening Ichimon (group of priests of the same sect) regulation by the head.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after Shonyo became the head of Hongan-ji Temple, Shonyo and his guardian Renjun (the sixth son of Rennyo and maternal grandfather of Shonyo) adopted a policy of strengthening Ichimon (group of priests of the same sect) regulation by the head.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>その遂行のために蓮淳の娘婿で加賀の末寺の一つ超勝寺（元は越前にあり前述の本泉寺とともに追放されていた）の住持であった実顕が代官に任じられて「両御山」体制を否認する命令を加賀各地に出す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to carry out the policy, Jikken, who was Renjun&apos;s adopted son-in-law and the chief priest of Chosho-ji Temple which was one of branch temples in Kaga Province (originally it has been in Echizen Province, but it was banished as with Honsen-ji Temple described above) was appointed as daikan (deputy) and he issued an order to deny &apos;Ryo-Gozan&apos; system throughout Kaga Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to carry out the policy, Jikken, who was Renjun&apos;s adopted son-in-law and the chief priest of Chosho-ji Temple, one of branch temples in Kaga Province (originally it has been in Echizen Province, but it was banished as with Honsen-ji Temple mentioned previously) was appointed as deputy and issued an order to deny &apos;Two Temples&apos; system throughout Kaga Province.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to carry out the policy, Jikken, who was Renjun&apos;s adopted son-in-law and the chief priest of Chosho-ji Temple, one of branch temples in Kaga Province (originally it has been in Echizen Province, but it was banished as with Honsen-ji Temple mentioned previously) was appointed as deputy and issued an order to deny &apos;Two Temples&apos; system throughout Kaga Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これに対して蓮悟や蓮慶（蓮綱の嫡子）は蓮如・実如が定めた一門衆の指導への服従を定めた規則に反するとして超勝寺の討伐のための一揆を起こした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In response to this, Rengo and Renkei (Renko&apos;s legitimate child) staged an uprising for putting down Chosho-ji Temple for the reason that Jikken&apos;s order violated the rules established by Rennyo and Jitsunyo under which obedience of Ichimonshu (clansman) to instructions was provided.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In response to this, Rengo and Renkei (Renko&apos;s legitimate child) staged an uprising for putting down the Chosho-ji Temple for the reason that Jikken&apos;s order violated the rules established by Rennyo and Jitsunyo under which obedience of Ichimonshu (clansman) to instructions was provided.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response to this, Rengo and Renkei (Renko&apos;s legitimate child) staged an uprising for putting down the Chosho-ji Temple for the reason that Jikken&apos;s order violated the rules established by Rennyo and Jitsunyo under which obedience of Ichimonshu (clansman) to instructions was provided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>ところが、この報を受けた蓮淳は逆に法主の代理である実顕を討つ事は本願寺法主に対する反逆であるとして畿内・東海地方の門徒に超勝寺救援の命令を発したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in return, upon hearing the news of the uprising, Renjun issued an order to assist Chosho-ji Temple to followers in the Kinai (provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara) and Tokai regions for the reason that attacking the deputy of hoshu Jikken was a rebellion against hoshu in Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in return, upon hearing the news of the uprising, Renjun issued an order to assist the Chosho-ji Temple to the followers in the Kinai (provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara) and Tokai regions for the reason that attacking the deputy of the head Jikken was a rebellion against the head of the Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in return, upon hearing the news of the uprising, Renjun issued an order to assist the Chosho-ji Temple to the followers in the Kinai (provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara) and Tokai regions for the reason that attacking the deputy of the head Jikken was a rebellion against the head of the Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>これを知った加賀門徒は動揺して分裂、享禄4年（1531年）蓮悟は能登国に逃れた（大小一揆）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Kaga-monto (followers in Kaga Province) knew about the order, they were disturbed and separated from each other and in 1531 Rengo escaped to Noto Province (Daisho Ikki).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Kaga-monto (followers in Kaga Province) knew about the order, they were disturbed and separated from each other and in 1531 Rengo escaped to Noto Province (Daisho Ikki [Big League-Little League War]).</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Kaga-monto (followers in Kaga Province) knew about the order, they were disturbed and separated from each other and in 1531 Rengo escaped to Noto Province (Daisho Ikki [Big League-Little League War]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="21">
<j>蓮淳は証如の名において蓮悟とその家族を破門し、更に反逆者として門徒が彼らを処刑する事を許した（一説には蓮淳は蓮悟の同母兄でありながら、宗門内での出世が弟より遅れていた事を深く恨んでいたとも言われる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Renjun excommunicated Rengo and his family in the name of Shonyo and furthermore allowed followers to execute them as traitors (one theory holds that Renjun had deep resentment against Rengo because Renjun didn&apos;t get promoted in the sect as fast as Rengo although Renjun was Rengo&apos;s older maternal brother).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Renjun excommunicated Rengo and his family in the name of Shonyo and furthermore allowed the followers to execute them as traitors (one theory holds that Renjun had deep resentment against Rengo because Renjun didn&apos;t get promoted in the sect as fast as Rengo although Renjun was Rengo&apos;s older maternal brother).</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Renjun excommunicated Rengo and his family in the name of Shonyo and furthermore allowed the followers to execute them as traitors (one theory holds that Renjun had deep resentment against Rengo because Renjun didn&apos;t get promoted in the sect as fast as Rengo although Renjun was Rengo&apos;s older maternal brother).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>命令は忠実に実行され、翌享禄5年1月26日 (旧暦)（1532年）には潜伏先の越前で蓮悟最愛の嫡男・実教が毒殺された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Renjun&apos;s order was faithfully carried out and Sanenori, Rengo&apos;s beloved legitimate son, was poisoned to death on March 2, 1532 in Echizen Province where Rengo and Sanenori have hidden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Renjun&apos;s order was faithfully carried out and Sanenori, Rengo&apos;s beloved legitimate son, was poisoned to death on March 12, 1532, the following year, in Echizen Province where Rengo and Sanenori have hidden.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し、補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Renjun&apos;s order was faithfully carried out and Sanenori, Rengo&apos;s beloved legitimate son, was poisoned to death on March 12, 1532, the following year, in Echizen Province where Rengo and Sanenori have hidden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>蓮悟は辛うじて自治都市である和泉国堺市に逃げ込む事が出来た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rengo was barely able to escape into Sakai City, Izumi Province, which was an autonomous city.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rengo was barely able to escape into Sakai City, Izumi Province, which was an autonomous city.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rengo was barely able to escape into Sakai City, Izumi Province, which was an autonomous city.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>証如や蓮淳も堺に手を出す事は憚られたために蓮悟は辛うじて生き延びられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rengo barely survived because Shonyo and Renjun hesitated to intervene in Sakai City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rengo barely survived because Shonyo and Renjun hesitated to intervene in Sakai City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rengo barely survived because Shonyo and Renjun hesitated to intervene in Sakai City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>だが、破門は解かれる事はなく、堺で零落したまま76歳の生涯を閉じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he was not absolved from an excommunication and he has fallen on hard times in Sakai and ended his life of 76 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he was not absolved from an excommunication and he had fallen on hard times in Sakai and ended his life of 76 years.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he was not absolved from an excommunication and he had fallen on hard times in Sakai and ended his life of 76 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), ZassouTori(id:136771), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>