<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>竺雲等連</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jikuun-Toren</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jikuun-Toren</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jikun Toren</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>竺雲等連（じくうんとうれん、永徳3年/弘和3年（1383年） － 文明 (日本)3年1月7日 (旧暦)（1471年1月27日））は、室町時代中期の臨済宗の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jikuun-Toren (1383 - January 27, 1471) was a Rinzai sect priest in the middle of the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jikuun-Toren (1383 - January 27, 1471) was a Rinzai sect priest in the middle of the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jikun Toren (1383 - February 5, 1471) was a Rinzai Sect priest in the middle of the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>俗姓は井伊氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His secular surname was Ii.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His secular surname was Ii.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His secular surname was Ii.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>諱は等連。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His imina (leagal name) was Toren.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His imina (legal name) was Toren.</e>
<cmt>Spelling.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His imina (personal name) was Toren.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>字は竺雲。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was commonly called Jikuun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was commonly called Jikuun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was commonly called Jikun.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>号は自彊・小朶子・重艮叟。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Buddhist name was Jikyo, Shodaishi, and Chogonso.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Buddhist names were Jikyo, Shodaishi, and Chogonso.</e>
<cmt>Made plural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He called himself Jikyo, Shodaishi (小朶子), and Chogonso (重艮叟).</e>
<cmt>読みが未確認の漢字を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>遠江国の出身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He came from Totomi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He came from Totomi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He came from Totomi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>京都天龍寺の大岳周崇に師事して修学しその法を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He studied under Taigaku-Shusu of Tenryu-ji Temple in Kyoto-city and succeeded his doctrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He studied under Taigaku-Shusu of Tenryu-ji Temple in Kyoto City and continued the espousal of his doctrine.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He studied under Taigaku Shusu of Tenryu-ji Temple in Kyoto and continued the espousal of his doctrine.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>応永年間（1394年－1427年）に中国の明に渡った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went to China of the Ming dynasty in 1394 - 1427.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He went to Ming dynasty China from 1394 to 1427.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He went to Ming dynasty China from 1394 to 1427.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>帰国した後、京都相国寺を経て、1444年（文安元年）南禅寺の住持となり、1455年（康正元年）には相国寺の鹿苑院に住して僧録司に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he came back to Japan, he served at Shokoku-ji Temple in Kyoto, and became the chief priest of the Nanzen-ji Temple in 1444, and stayed to be appointed Sorokushi (a managing priest in a Zen temple) in Rokuonin in Sokoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>「住して僧録司に任じられた」文字通りに訳しましたが「stayed to be」は意味的には不要と思われます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he came back to Japan, he served at Shokoku-ji Temple in Kyoto, and became the chief priest of Nanzen-ji Temple in 1444, being appointed Sorokushi (a managing priest in a Zen temple) in Rokuonin in Sokoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he came back to Japan, he served at Shokoku-ji Temple in Kyoto, and assumed the position of chief priest of Nanzen-ji Temple in 1444, being assumed the position of Sorokushi (a managing priest in a Zen temple) in Rokuonin in Sokoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その後は嵯峨の天龍寺性智院に隠退している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he sequestered himself in Shochiin in Tenryu-ji Temple in Saga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he sequestered himself in Shochiin in Tenryu-ji Temple in Saga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he sequestered himself in Shochiin in Tenryu-ji Temple in Saga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>漢書の訓点に秀で、特に易学の研究に優れ、その後の五山における史書研究の基礎を築いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was good at translating Chinese into Japanese (by Kunten adding work), especially good at studying art of divination, and established the basis for history books study at gosan (Zen temples highly ranked by the government).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was good at translating Chinese into Japanese (through adding kunten), especially good at studying the art of divination, and established the basis for the study of history books at gosan (Zen temples highly ranked by the government).</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity. Perhaps it would be better to describe &apos;kunten&apos; in English.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was good at translating Chinese into Japanese through adding kunten (puctuation marks), especially good at studying the art of divination, and established the basis for the study of history books at gosan (Zen temples highly ranked by the government).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Novo(id:87875), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>