<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>末法思想</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mappo-shiso</e>
<cmt>末法思想（まっぽうしそう）→Mappo-shiso, the &quot;end of the world&quot; belief[http://www.aisf.or.jp/%7Ejaanus/]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mappo-shiso</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mappo-shiso</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>末法思想（まっぽうしそう）とは、仏教の予言思想の一種であり、釈迦の立教以来1,000年（500年とする説もある）の時代を正法（しょうぼう）、次の1,000年を像法（ぞうぼう）、その後10,000年を末法の三時観で分けて考える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mappo-shiso is a kind of Buddhism prediction philosophy under which the period of 1,000 years (also said to be 500 years) after the establishment of Buddhism by Shaka is called Shobo, following period of 1,000 years is called Zobo and the following period of 10,000 years is called Mappo and these three periods are considered as defferent ones.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処　釈迦→Shaka正法（しょうぼう）→Shobo, Age of the Right Dharma像法（ぞうぼう）→Zobo, Age of the Semblance Dharma末法→Mappo, Age of the Final Dharma[http://www.jsri.jp/English/Terminology/eng-jap.html]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mappo-shiso is a kind of Buddhist prediction philosophy under which the period of 1,000 years (also said to be 500 years) after the establishment of Buddhism by Shaka is called Shobo, and the following period of 1,000 years is called Zobo and the following period of 10,000 years is called Mappo and these three periods are considered as different.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mappo-shiso is a kind of Buddhist prediction philosophy under three periods which the period of 1,000 years (also said to be 500 years) after the establishment of Buddhism by Shaka is called Shobo, and the following period of 1,000 years is called Zobo and the following period of 10,000 years is called Mappo and these three periods are considered as different.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>釈迦の教えが及ばなくなった末法においては、仏法が正しく行なわれなくなるという、仏教（特に大乗仏教）における下降史観である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a view of history on the decline of Buddhism (especially Mahayana Buddhism) and according to it, Buddhism will not be practiced correctly in Mappo since Shaka&apos;s teaching will have lost its influence.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処　仏法→Buddhism[英辞郎 on the WEB]大乗仏教→Mahayana Buddhism[Webster Online Dictionary]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a view of history on the decline of Buddhism (especially Mahayana Buddhism) and according to it, Buddhism will not be practiced correctly in Mappo since Shaka&apos;s teaching will have lost influence.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a view of history on the decline of Buddhism (especially Mahayana Buddhism) and according to it, Buddhism would not be practiced correctly in Mappo since Shaka&apos;s teaching would have lost influence.</e>
<cmt>仮定法にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>「世も末（すえ）だ」と言う表現はこれに由来するといわれるように、これを終末論と同意義と捉えられることも多いが、これは事実誤認である（後述）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the expression of &quot;it is the end of the world &quot; is said to have derived from Mappo shiso, sometimes this is understood as equivalent to eschatology but such understanding is wrong (to be mentioned below).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the expression of &quot;it is the end of the world &quot; is said to have been derived from Mappo shiso, sometimes this is understood as equivalent to eschatology but such understanding is wrong (to be mentioned below).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the expression of &apos;it is the end of the world&apos; is said to have been derived from Mappo shiso, sometimes this is understood as equivalent to eschatology but such understanding is wrong (to be mentioned below).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>なお、釈迦の入滅の年代は諸説あるため、末法の年代設定にも諸説あり定まっていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As there are various views on the date of Shaka&apos;s death, the era of Mappo is not defined clearly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As there are various views on the date of Shaka&apos;s death, the era of Mappo is not defined clearly.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As there are various views on the date of Shaka&apos;s death, the period of Mappo is not defined clearly.</e>
<cmt>前出に合わせてperiodを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>終末論と末法思想の違い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Difference between eschatology and Mappo shiso</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Difference between eschatology and Mappo shiso</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Difference Between Eschatology and Mappo Shiso</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>中世以降の日本では末法思想を、この世の終わりとする終末論的なものであると捉えることも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the medieval ages, Mappo shiso has often been understood in Japan as the one similar to eschatology, which means the end of the world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the medieval age, Mappo shiso has often been understood in Japan as similar to eschatology, which means the end of the world.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the medieval age, Mappo shiso has often been understood in Japan as similar to eschatology, which means the end of the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>しかし末法思想はあくまでも仏法の衰退、つまり仏の教えが時代を経て次第に通用しなくなる事のみを指しており、そこに世情不安や天変地異は含まれない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Mappo shiso solely points to the decline of Buddhism, namely it is the prediction that Buddhism will lose its influence over time and it doesn&apos;t relate to social unrest and natuaral catastrophe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Mappo shiso solely points to the decline of Buddhism, namely it is the prediction that Buddhism will lose its influence over time and it does not relate to social unrest and natural catastrophe.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Mappo shiso solely points to the decline of Buddhism, namely it is the prediction that Buddhism would lose its influence over time and it does not relate to social unrest and natural catastrophe.</e>
<cmt>wouldとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>したがって末法思想は「この世の終わり」を意味するものではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Mappo shiso doesn&apos;t mean &quot;the end of the world&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Mappo shiso does not mean &quot;the end of the world&quot;.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Mappo shiso does not mean &apos;the end of the world.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>なお、仏法の衰退と共に社会情勢の不安や天変地異も説く『法滅尽経』などもあるが、一般的にはこれは後世になって創作された偽経とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although some sutras assert that the decline of Buddhism is accompanied by social unrest and natural catastrophe, such as &quot;Hometsujin-kyo Sutra&quot;, it is generally believed that these are bogus sutras that were created in later stage of history.</e>
<cmt>法滅尽経→Hometsujin-kyo Sutra</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although some sutras assert that the decline of Buddhism is accompanied by social unrest and natural catastrophe, such as &quot;Hometsujin-kyo Sutra&quot;, it is generally believed that these are bogus sutras that were created in the later stages of history.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although some sutras assert that the decline of Buddhism is accompanied by social unrest and natural catastrophe, such as &quot;Hometsujin-kyo Sutra&quot; (Decline of the Law Sutra), it is generally believed that these are bogus sutras that were created in the later stages of history.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>また大乗仏教では、空論の展開から「不増不減」や「無始無終」を説いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mahayana Buddhism advocates &quot;no increase, no decrease&quot; and &quot;no beginning, no end&quot; as the development of Kuron.</e>
<cmt>空論→Kuron[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mahayana Buddhism advocates &quot;no increase, no decrease&quot; and &quot;no beginning, no end&quot; as the development of Kuron.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mahayana Buddhism advocates &apos;no increase, no decrease&apos; and &apos;no beginning, no end&apos; as the development of Kuron (theory of Ku (mind that is not bound by anything)).</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースをのぞき、クォーテーションを変え、補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>さらに『涅槃経』では末法である仏法の衰退時において再び仏法が世に出現することを説き、末世における悲観的な見方を根本的に否定している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, Nehan-gyo Sutra fundamentally denies the pessimistic view on Mappo by advocating that Buddha will reappear in this world in Mappo era when Buddhism declined.</e>
<cmt>涅槃経→Nehan-gyo Sutra</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, Nehan-gyo Sutra fundamentally denies the pessimistic view on Mappo by advocating that Buddha will reappear in this world in the Mappo era when Buddhism has declined.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, &quot;Nehan-gyo Sutra&quot; (the Nirvana Sutra) fundamentally denies the pessimistic view on Mappo by advocating that Buddha will reappear in this world in the Mappo period when Buddhism has declined.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション、英訳など補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>したがって末法思想＝終末論とはいえない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Mappo shiso is not equivalent to eschatology.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Mappo shiso is not equivalent to eschatology.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Mappo shiso is not equivalent to eschatology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>末法思想の典拠</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The source of Mappo shiso</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The source of Mappo shiso</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Source of Mappo Shiso</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>末法思想は、『大集経』（正式には『大方等大集経』）の「我が滅後に於て五百年の中は解脱堅固、次の五百年は禅定堅固、次の五百年は読誦多聞堅固、次の五百年は多造塔寺堅固、次の五百年は我が法の中に於て闘諍言訟して白法隠没せん」などを典拠とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The source of Mappo shiso is the description of &quot;Daijkkyo Sutra&quot; (officially, &quot;Daihododaijikkyo Sutra&quot;) saying, &quot; Gedatsu will remain solid for 500 years after my death, Dhyana will remain solid for following 500 years, Tokusho-tabun will remain solid for following 500 years, Tazoto-ji Temple will remain solid for following 500 years and in the following 500 years, there will be disputes concerning my teaching and correct teaching will be forgotten&quot;.</e>
<cmt>大集経→Daijkkyo Sutra大方等大集経→Daihododaijikkyo Sutra解脱→Gedatsu, being liberated from earthly desires and the woes of man, (reaching) nirvana, moksha, mukti禅定→Dhyana - Meditation, Mental Concentration[http://www.shantideva.net/assembly/paramita_00.htm] 読誦多聞→Tokusho-tabun</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The source of Mappo shiso is the description of &quot;Daijkkyo Sutra&quot; (officially, &quot;Daihododaijikkyo Sutra&quot;) saying, &quot; Gedatsu will remain solid for 500 years after my death, Dhyana will remain solid for the following 500 years, Tokusho-tabun will remain solid for the following 500 years, Tazoto-ji Temple will remain solid for the following 500 years and in the following 500 years, there will be disputes concerning my teaching and correct teaching will be forgotten&quot;.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The source of Mappo shiso is the description of &quot;Daijkkyo Sutra&quot; (officially, &quot;Daihododaijikkyo Sutra&quot; (Mahsamnipata sutra)) saying, &apos;Gedatsu Kengo (Age of enlightenment) will remain solid for 500 years after my death, Zenjo kengo (the age of meditation) will remain solid for the following 500 years, Dokuju tamon kengo (the age of reading, reciting, and listening) will remain solid for the following 500 years, Tazo toji kengo (the age of building temples and stupas) will remain solid for the following 500 years and in the following 500 years, there will be disputes concerning my teaching and correct teaching will be forgotten.&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語補足、クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>つまり最後の五百年では仏教徒の間で論争が闘わされ正しい教えが隠没してしまう、ということである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In essence, there will be disputes among Buddhists and correct teaching will be forgotten in the period of fianal 500 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In essence, there will be disputes among Buddhists and correct teaching will be forgotten in the period of the final 500 years.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In essence, there will be disputes among Buddhists and correct teaching will be forgotten in the period of the final 500 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>末法思想は、中国では隋・唐代に盛んとなり、三階教や浄土教の成立に深いかかわりを持った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In China, Mappo shiso became prevalent during the era of Sui and Tang Dynasties and it closely related to the establishment of Sangaikyo or Jodo-kyo.</e>
<cmt>隋・唐代→Sui and Tang Dynasties三階教→Sangaikyo, Sanjiejiao浄土教→pure land teachings, Jodo-kyo[Webster Online Dictionary]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In China, Mappo shiso became prevalent during the era of the Sui and Tang Dynasties and it is closely related to the establishment of Sangaikyo or Jodo-kyo.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In China, Mappo shiso became prevalent during the era of the Sui and Tang Dynasties and it is closely related to the establishment of Sangai-kyo (Three Stages Sect) or Jodo-kyo (Jodo (Pure Land) sect).</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>その早期の例としては、北斉・陳 (南朝)の天台宗二祖・慧思によって記された「立誓願文」に見られるし、隋代以降1000年にわたって継続される房山の石経事業も、末法思想によるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its early example is seen in Ryusei Ganmon which was written by Eshi, the second founder of Tendai sect, during the era of Northern Ch&apos;i and Chen (southern dynasty) and Stone Sutra Project at Fangshan which has been continuing over 1000 years since the era of Sui dynasty is also based on Mappo shiso.</e>
<cmt>北斉・陳 (南朝)→Northern Ch&apos;i and Chen天台宗→Tendai sect慧思→Eshi立誓願文→Ryusei Ganmon房山→Fangshan[http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110002663499/]石経事業→Stone Sutra Project</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its early example is seen in Ryusei Ganmon which was written by Eshi, the second founder of the Tendai sect, during the era of Northern Ch&apos;i and Chen (southern dynasty) and the Stone Sutra Project at Fangshan, which has been continuing for over 1000 years since the era of the Sui dynasty, is also based on Mappo shiso.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its early example is seen in &apos;Ryusei Ganmon&apos; which was written by Eshi, the second founder of the Tendai sect, during the period of Northern Ch&apos;i and Chen (southern dynasty) and the Stone Sutra Project at Fangshan, which had been continuing for over 1,000 years since the period of the Sui dynasty, was also based on Mappo shiso.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション補足、過去形にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>日本では平安時代のころから現実化してきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, it became a reality in Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, it became a reality in the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, it became a reality in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>特に1052年（永承7年）は末法元年とされ人々に恐れられ、さかんに経塚造営が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially, the year of 1052 was deemed as the first year of Mappo and many sutra mounds were built since people were scared.</e>
<cmt>経塚→sutra mound</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially, the year of 1052 was deemed as the first year of Mappo and many sutra mounds were built since people were scared.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially, the year of 1052 was deemed as the first year of Mappo and many sutra mounds were built since people were scared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>この時代は貴族の摂関政治が衰え、代わって武士が台頭しつつある動乱期で、治安の乱れも激しく民衆の不安は増大しつつあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this era, warrior class was increasing its power while Sekkan seiji was declining and people&apos;s anxiety was growing due to the unstable and dangerous society.</e>
<cmt>摂関政治→Sekkan seiji, regency government</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this era, the warrior class was increasing its power while Sekkan seiji was declining and people&apos;s anxiety was growing due to the unstable and dangerous society.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this period, the warrior class was increasing its power while regency of nobility was declining and people&apos;s anxiety was growing due to the unstable and dangerous society.</e>
<cmt>貴族の、を補足、表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>また仏教界も天台宗をはじめとする諸寺の腐敗や僧兵の出現によって退廃していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buddhism society also deteriorated due to corruption at many temples, including Tendai sect, and the emergence of priest soldiers.</e>
<cmt>僧兵→priest soldier[Webster&apos;s Online Dictionary]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buddhism society also deteriorated due to corruption at many temples, including the Tendai sect, and the emergence of priest soldiers.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddhism society also deteriorated due to corruption at many temples, including the Tendai sect, and the emergence of priest soldiers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>このように仏の末法の予言が現実の社会情勢と一致したため人々の現実社会への不安は一層深まり、この不安から逃れるため厭世的な思想に傾倒していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Buddhism prediction of Mappo coincided with real social situations, people&apos;s anxiety for real society deepened and they became addicted to pessimistic phylosophy in order to escape from such anxiety.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Buddhist prediction of Mappo coincided with the real social situation, people&apos;s anxiety for real society deepened and they became addicted to pessimistic philosophy in order to escape from such anxiety.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Buddhist prediction of Mappo coincided with the real social situation, people&apos;s anxiety for real society deepened and they became addicted to pessimistic philosophy in order to escape from such anxiety.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="21">
<j>鎌倉時代には、法然の浄土宗や親鸞の浄土真宗などは末法思想に立脚し、念仏により死後に西方極楽浄土の阿弥陀如来の御許への往生を唱えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kamakura period, Honen of Jodo sect and Shinran of Jodo Shinshu sect called for, based on Mappo shiso, repeating the name of Buddha in order to be able to go to Amidanyorai at Saiho Gokuraku Jodo after death.</e>
<cmt>鎌倉時代→Kamakura Period[英辞郎 on the WEB]法然→Honen[kotobank]浄土宗→Jodo sect親鸞→Shinran浄土真宗→Jodo Shinshu sect西方極楽浄土→Saiho Gokuraku Jodo, Western Pure Land阿弥陀如来→Amidanyorai</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kamakura period, Honen of the Jodo sect and Shinran of the Jodo Shinshu sect called for, based on Mappo shiso, repeating the name of Buddha in order to be able to go to Amidanyorai at Saiho Gokuraku Jodo after death.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kamakura period, Honen of the Jodo sect and Shinran of the Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) called for, based on Mappo shiso, repeating the name of Buddha in order to be able to go to Amidanyorai (Amitabha Tathagata) at Saiho Gokuraku Jodo (The West Pure Land (of Amida Buddha)) after death.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また日蓮も、同時期に法華一乗を唱えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nichiren also called for Hokke-ichijo in the same era.</e>
<cmt>日蓮→Nichiren法華一乗→Hokke-ichijo</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nichiren also called for Hokke-ichijo in the same era.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nichiren also called for hokke-ichijo (the doctrines called the Single Vehicle of the Lotus) in the same period.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>しかし曹洞宗を開いた道元は、釈迦在世でも愚鈍で悪事を働いた弟子もいたことや、末法を言い訳にして修行が疎かになることを批判し、末法思想を否定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Dogen, the founder of Soto sect, denied Mappo shiso asserting that there were some dull desciples who committed evil deed while Shaka was in life and people may use Mappo as an excuse for not doing ascetic training.</e>
<cmt>曹洞宗→Soto sect道元→Dogen[Yahoo辞書]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Dogen, the founder of the Soto sect, denied Mappo shiso asserting that there were some dull desciples who committed evil deeds while Shaka was in life and people may use Mappo as an excuse for not doing ascetic training.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Dogen, the founder of the Soto sect, denied Mappo shiso asserting that there were some dull disciples who committed evil deeds while Shaka was in life and people might use Mappo as an excuse for not doing ascetic training.</e>
<cmt>時制を合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Straysheep(id:42448), Nighthawks(id:36125), Wei Yuan(id:13342), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), トシ坊(id:19003), Rc21(id:5187), 彩華1226(id:64711), 幣原外交(id:97257), でここ(id:9565), Kurz(id:1601), Mooko(id:36162), Boca samba(id:137526), Bendono(id:85524), Kanashimi(id:74205), R28Bot(id:177951), ブレービー(id:108476), Utty(id:53824), MasanoriAoki(id:100934), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>