<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>伊藤真乗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinjo ITO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinjo ITO</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinjo ITO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>伊藤真乗（いとう しんじょう、俗名：伊藤文明（いとう ふみあき）、明治39年（1906年）3月28日 - 平成元年（1989年）7月19日）は、日本の宗教家で、在家仏教教団・真如苑の開祖。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinjo ITO (Fumiaki ITO, March 28, 1906 - July 19, 1989) was a religious leader who founded Shinnyoen, the lay Buddhist Organization.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinjo ITO (Fumiaki ITO, March 28, 1906 - July 19, 1989) was a religious leader who founded Shinnyoen, the lay Buddhist Organization.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinjo ITO (Fumiaki ITO, March 28, 1906 - July 19, 1989) was a religious leader who founded Shinnyoen, the lay Buddhist Organization.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>また真如三昧耶流の創始者である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also a founder of Shinnyo Sanmaya School.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also a founder of Shinnyo Sanmaya School.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also a founder of Shinnyo Sanmaya School.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>なお俗名の「文明」は「ふみあき」が正式名称であるが、｢ぶんめい｣と音読みする場合も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His secular name &quot;文明&quot; read as &quot;Fumiaki&quot; was his official name but may often read as &quot;Bunmei&quot; by its Chinese-derived pronunciation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His secular name &quot;文明&quot; read as &quot;Fumiaki&quot; was his official name but may often read as &quot;Bunmei&quot; by its Chinese-derived pronunciation.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His secular name &quot;文明&quot; read as &apos;Fumiaki&apos; was his official name but may often read as &apos;Bunmei&apos; by its Chinese-derived pronunciation.</e>
<cmt>&quot;を &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>人物・エピソード</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personal Profile and Episode</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personal Profile and Episode</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal Profile and Episode</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>山梨県北巨摩郡長坂町出身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He came from Nagasaka-cho, Kitakoma district, Yamanashi Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He came from Nagasaka-cho, Kitakoma district, Yamanashi Prefecture</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Nagasaka-cho, Kitakoma district, Yamanashi Prefecture</e>
<cmt>came fromをwas born inに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>父・文二郎の本厄年に生まれたので、村の風習に随って、いったん路地に捨てられ、近所の人に拾ってもらい、1週間後に再び実家に戻されたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said the he was once abandoned on an alley, picked up by neighbors, and returned to his parents&apos; home a week later according to the customs of the neibourhood, because he was born the climacteric year for his father,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he was once abandoned in an alley, picked up by neighbors, and returned to his parents&apos; home a week later according to the customs of the neighborhood, because he was born in the climacteric year for his father,</e>
<cmt>Grammar, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he was once abandoned in an alley, picked up by neighbors, and returned to his parents&apos; home a week later according to the customs of the neighborhood, because he was born in the climacteric year for his father,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>幼少時から周囲より神童と呼ばれ、人の生死を予言するなど不思議な能力を持っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was regarded as child prodigy from his infancy and had mysterious power of predicting people&apos;s birth and death and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was regarded as a child prodigy from his infancy and had the mysterious power of predicting people&apos;s birth and death and others.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was regarded as a child prodigy from his infancy and had the mysterious power of predicting people&apos;s birth and death and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>伊藤家は、作男を雇うほどの富裕農家であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the Ito family was such a wealthy farming household that it employed farm hands.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ito family was such a wealthy farming household that it employed farm hands.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ito family was such a wealthy farming household that it employed farm hands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>父・文二郎は秋田村の役場で収入役職に就いていたが、後に村会議員にもなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father Bunjiro took office of chamberlain of Akita village and later even became a member of a village assembly.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father Bunjiro took office as chamberlain of Akita village and later even became a member of a village assembly.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father Bunjiro took office as chamberlain of Akita village and later even became a member of a village assembly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>当時は珍しかった新聞の定期購読を行っていたほどであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His family was rare in those days enough to subscribe newspapers are.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His family subscribed to newspapers, which was rare in those days.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His family subscribed to newspapers, which was rare in those days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>収入役の時分には税金を納められない村人の分を、自身が代りに納めていたという篤志家でもあった</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father, when taking office of chamberlain, was a benefactor to pay taxes of villagers on behalf.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father, when taking office as chamberlain, was a benefactor who paid taxes for villagers on their behalf.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father, when taking office as chamberlain, was a benefactor who paid taxes for villagers on their behalf.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>のちにたくさんの納税の領収書が入っていた大きな箱が伊藤家の土蔵の中から出てきたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that a large box containing receipts of those taxes was found later in the earthen storehouse (a storehouse with thick earth and mortar walls) of the Ito.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that a large box containing receipts of those taxes was found later in the earthen storehouse (a storehouse with thick earth and mortar walls) of the Ito.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that a large box containing receipts of those taxes was found later in the earthen storehouse (a storehouse with thick earth and mortar walls) of the Ito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>ただし裕福といわれるも、このような行為から決して楽ではなかったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, however, these generous activities never made his family so well-off. although his family was said to be wealthy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, however, these generous activities never made his family so well-off. although his family was said to be wealthy.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, however, these generous activities never made his family so well-off, although his family was said to be wealthy.</e>
<cmt>well-offのあとのピリオドをカンマに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>また、母・よしえの旧姓は山本であるが、武田信玄の軍師である山本勘助の流れを汲む家系ともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The maiden name of his mother, Yoshie, was Yamamoto, a family tree that is said to come from Kansuke YAMAMOTO, who had been a strategist of Shingen TAKEDA.</e>
<cmt>「また」訳し出ししていません。一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The maiden name of his mother, Yoshie, was Yamamoto, a family tree that is said to come from Kansuke YAMAMOTO, who had been a strategist of Shingen TAKEDA.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The maiden name of his mother, Yoshie, was Yamamoto, and the family tree is said to reach to Kansuke YAMAMOTO, who had been a strategist of Shingen TAKEDA.</e>
<cmt>一部、翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>（ただし、その家系を辿るのは難しいとされる。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(However tracing the family is said to be difficult.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(However tracing the family is said to be difficult.)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(However tracing the family line is said to be difficult.)</e>
<cmt>family の後にlineを加えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>よしえの父・彙治（しげはる）は小学校校長を務めたほどの名士であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshie&apos;s father, Shigeharu, was a prominent figure to serve as the principal of an elementary school.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshie&apos;s father, Shigeharu, was a prominent figure and served as the principal of an elementary school.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshie&apos;s father, Shigeharu, was a prominent figure and served as the principal of an elementary school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>その葬儀も村始まって以来の盛大なものだったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His funeral service is said to be of the largest scale ever in the village.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His funeral service is said to be of the largest scale ever in the village.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His funeral service is said to be of the largest scale ever in the village.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかし、これらのことから村では伊藤家は旧家の名士といわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ito family was said to be a prominent and old-established family of the village because of these facts.</e>
<cmt>「しかし」は逆説の意味はないので訳し出ししていません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ito family was said to be a prominent and old-established family of the village because of these facts.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ito family was said to be a prominent and old-established family of the village because of these facts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>父が曹洞宗の檀家総代を務めていたことから禅の影響を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was influenced by Zen Buddhism because his father took the office of the representative of family which supports a temple of the Soto sect of Zen Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was influenced by Zen Buddhism because his father took the office of the representative of a family which supported a temple of the Soto sect of Zen Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was influenced by Zen Buddhism because his father took the office of the representative of a family which supported a temple of the Soto sect of Zen Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>伊藤家家伝の易学で武田信玄の兵法『甲陽軍鑑』をベースとする「甲陽流病筮鈔（びょうぜいしょう）」を口伝により6人兄弟姉妹の中でただ一人受け継ぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among his six brothers and sisters, he was the only person that the art of divination &quot;Koyoryu byozeisho (Selections on Divination of Illness of Koyo-ryu school)&quot; based on &quot;Koyo Gunkan,&quot; the art of warfare of Shingen TAKEDA was handed down by word of mouth as had been passed down for generations to the family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among his six brothers and sisters, he was the only person that the art of divination &quot;Koyoryu byozeisho (Selections on Divination of Illness of Koyo-ryu school)&quot; based on &quot;Koyo Gunkan,&quot; the art of warfare of Shingen TAKEDA was handed down by word of mouth as had been passed down for generations to the family.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among his six brothers and sisters, he was the only person that the art of divination &apos;Koyoryu byozeisho (Selections on Divination of Illness of Koyo-ryu school)&apos; based on &quot;Koyo Gunkan,&quot; the art of warfare of Shingen TAKEDA was handed down by word of mouth as had been passed down for generations to the family.</e>
<cmt>&quot;を &apos; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>「甲斐国志」によると永田徳本という漢方医の達人がこの易学を以って武田家将軍の診察に当っており、また伊藤家の祖先の名前も万生山妙喜院（朝陽山清光禅寺の末寺）を寄進建立したとして記載されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kai koku shi (Records of Kai Province)&quot; describes that Tokuhon NAGATA, a noted Chinese medicine doctor, examined shogun of the Takeda family according to this art of divination, and that the Ito&apos;s ancestor was listed as a donator for the buildinging of Manseizan Myoki-in Temple (a branch temple of Choyozan Seikozen-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kai koku shi (Records of Kai Province)&quot; describes that Tokuhon NAGATA, a noted Chinese medicine doctor, examined shogun of the Takeda family according to this art of divination, and that the Ito&apos;s ancestor was listed as a donor for the building of Manseizan Myoki-in Temple (a branch temple of Choyozan Seikozen-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kai koku shi (Records of Kai Province)&apos; describes that Tokuhon NAGATA, a noted Chinese medicine doctor, examined shogun of the Takeda family according to this art of divination, and that the Ito&apos;s ancestor was listed as a donor for the building of Manseizan Myoki-in Temple (a branch temple of Choyozan Seikozen-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>&quot;を &apos; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="21">
<j>この易学は口伝であるため書物がない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This art of divination, kuden (oral instruction), has no script.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This art of divination, kuden (oral instruction), has no script.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This art of divination, kuden (oral instruction), has no script.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>「びょうぜいしょう」は父親が名付けたものであるが、どういう漢字で書くか父に教わっていなかったので文明（後の真乗）が「病筮鈔」と当て字した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Umiaki (later Shinjo) his father named was not taught how to write in kanji &quot;byoseishon,&quot; so he gave it &quot;病筮鈔.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Umiaki (later Shinjo) was not taught how to write his name &quot;byoseishon&quot;in kanji by his father so he wrote it as &quot;病筮鈔.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fumiaki (later Shinjo) was not taught how to write his name &apos;byozeisho&apos;in kanji by his father so he wrote it as &apos;病筮鈔.&apos;</e>
<cmt>UmiakiをFumiakiに変更しました。byoseishoをbyozeishoに変更しました。&quot;を &apos; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="23">
<j>苦学を志し英語を勉強するために上京、すぐに神田錦町の写真機材店「大盛堂」に勤める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He left for Tokyo with an ambition to work hard for mastering English and soon worked for &quot;Taiseido shop,&quot; a photographic apparatus shop located in Kandanishiki-cho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He left for Tokyo with an ambition to work hard at mastering English and soon worked for &quot;Taiseido shop,&quot; a photographic apparatus shop located in Kandanishiki-cho.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He left for Tokyo with an ambition to work hard at mastering English and soon worked for &apos;Taiseido shop,&apos; a photographic apparatus shop located in Kandanishiki-cho.</e>
<cmt>&quot;を &apos; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>英語で書かれたラジオの配線図を入手し、これを文明が翻訳して組み立てたものが同店から発売された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He obtained and translated the diagram written in English and the shop built a radio based on it for sales.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He obtained and translated the diagram written in English and the shop built a radio based on it for sales.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He obtained and translated the diagram written in English and the shop built a radio based on it for sales.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>当時のラジオブームに乗って大ヒット商品となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The radio was a big hit riding the crest of the radio boom in those days.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The radio was a big hit riding the crest of the radio boom in those days.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The radio became a big hit riding the crest of the radio boom in those days.</e>
<cmt>wasをbecameに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>また趣味の写真も相当なものであったという評判で、昭和9年の読売新聞立川専売局及び通信部主催のコンクールで1等を受賞、また翌10年にも多摩雅光会主催の「第１回写真展覧会」でも2等1席を獲得。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He got such a high reputation as an amateur photographer that he won the highest prize in the photo contest hosted by Tachikawa Monopoly Bureau and communications department of the Yomiuri Shinbun in 1934 as well as in &quot;the First Photo Constest&quot; hosted by Tamagako kai (organization of Tamagako) in 1834.</e>
<cmt>「通信部」の正式名称は調べられませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He got such a high reputation as an amateur photographer that he won the highest prize in the photo contest hosted by Tachikawa Monopoly Bureau and communications department of the Yomiuri Shinbun in 1934 as well as in &quot;the First Photo Constest&quot; hosted by Tamagako kai (organization of Tamagako) in 1834.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He got such a high reputation as an amateur photographer that he won the highest prize in the photo contest hosted by Tachikawa Monopoly Bureau and communications department of the Yomiuri Shinbun in 1934 as well as in &apos;the First Photo Constest&apos; hosted by Tamagako kai (organization of Tamagako) in 1834.</e>
<cmt>&quot;を &apos; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>さらに同年の月刊誌「現代」4月号の巻頭で、室生犀星の詩「光」と共に文明の写真が掲載されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the April issue of monthly magazine &quot;Gendai&quot; carried a photo of Fumiaki on its opening page along with a poem titled &quot;Light&quot; of Saisei MUROO in the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the April issue of monthly magazine &quot;Gendai&quot; carried a photo of Fumiaki on its opening page along with a poem titled &quot;Light&quot; of Saisei MUROO in the same year.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the April issue of monthly magazine &apos;Gendai&apos; carried a photo of Fumiaki on its opening page along with a poem titled &apos;Light&apos; of Saisei MUROO in the same year.</e>
<cmt>&quot;を &apos; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="28">
<j>後に伊藤は立川飛行機の技術者になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He later became an engineer of Tachikawa Aircraft and got married.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He later became an engineer of Tachikawa Aircraft and got married.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He later became an engineer of Tachikawa Aircraft.</e>
<cmt>and got marriedを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>昭和7年には、またいとこの間柄にある伊藤友司と結婚する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1932, he got married with his second cousin, Tomoji ITO.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1932, he got married with his second cousin, Tomoji ITO.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1932, he got married his second cousin, Tomoji ITO.</e>
<cmt>withを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>技術者として勤務していたことで、「ライカ買おうか、家買おか」と言われた当時、高価なライカのカメラを買えるほど生活は安定していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His life was settled enough because he workd as an engineer; he bought an expensive camera of Leica in those days when people described it as saying, &quot;Let&apos;s get a Leica or house.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His life was settled enough because he worked as an engineer; he bought an expensive camera from Leica in those days when people described it as saying, &quot;Let&apos;s get a Leica or house.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since he worked as an engineer; his life was settled enough to buy an expensive camera from Leica in those days when people described it as saying, &quot;Let&apos;s get a Leica or house.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一部、翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>しかし、結婚直後に文明（真乗）の仕事面や健康面に変調があり、それらを通してお互いの背景にある宗教的使命を感じるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Immediately after the marriage, however, the couple began to realize their religious missions behind their own backgrounds through abnormalities in the health and career of Fumiaki (Shinjo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Immediately after the marriage, however, the couple began to realize their religious missions behind their own backgrounds through abnormalities in the health and career of Fumiaki (Shinjo).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Immediately after the marriage, however, the couple began to realize their religious missions behind their own backgrounds through abnormalities in the health and career of Fumiaki (Shinjo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>なお、友司は祖母の宝珠院から薬師如来と観音の信仰をもっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way, Tomoji had faith in Yakushi Nyorai (the Healing Buddha) and Ykushi Kannon and had faith in them because she was taught them by her grandmother, Hojuin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the way, Tomoji had believed in Yakushi Nyorai (the Healing Buddha) and Yakushi Kannon and had faith in them because she was taught them by her grandmother, Hojuin.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the way, Tomoji had believed in Yakushi Nyorai (the Healing Buddha) and Yakushi Kannon and had faith in them because she was taught them by her grandmother, Hojuin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>また真乗は実姉の勧めでキリスト教のプロテスタントにも関心を持ち研鑚したが、友司が馴染めなかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also Tomoji is said to have get accustomed to Protestantism of Christianity Shinjo had had faith in and practiced on the advice of his elder sister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also Tomoji is said to have gotten accustomed to Protestantism of Christianity Shinjo had had faith in and practiced on the advice of his elder sister.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also Shinjo had had faith in Protestantism of Christianity and practiced it on the advice of his elder sister, however Tomoji was said to had difficulty in getting accustomed to it.</e>
<cmt>一部、翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>この当時から観音信仰や病筮鈔によって同好者が増えてくるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time they began to have an increasing number of followers with Kannon Worship and Byozeisho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time they began to have an increasing number of followers with Kannon Worship and Byozeisho.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time they began to have an increasing number of followers with Kannon Worship and Byozeisho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="35">
<j>立川飛行機の同僚で先輩だったある人物が、池袋で占い師に見てもらったとき、伊藤の名前を出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When an elder ex-colleague of Tachikawa Aircraft had his fortune told in Ikebukuro, he mentioned the name of ITO.</e>
<cmt>「立川の伊藤さんのお知り合いですか」は後ろの文とつなげてあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When an elder ex-colleague of Tachikawa Aircraft had his fortune told in Ikebukuro, he mentioned the name of ITO.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When an elder ex-colleague of Tachikawa Aircraft had his fortune told in Ikebukuro, he mentioned the name of ITO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>「立川の伊藤さんのお知り合いならば見料はいりません」といわれたという話がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fortune-teller hearing of ITO is said to have said, &quot;You do not have to pay any fee if you are an acquaintance of ITO. &quot;</e>
<cmt>前の「立川の伊藤さんのお知り合いですか」をつなげてあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fortune-teller hearing of ITO is said to have said, &quot;You do not have to pay any fee if you are an acquaintance of ITO. &quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fortune-teller hearing of ITO is said to have said, &quot;You do not have to pay any fee if you are an acquaintance of ITO. &quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>また陸軍の監督官までもが相談に訪れるほど信頼があったといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinjo is also said to have such a high confidence that even a control officer of Army visited him for advice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinjo is also said to have such a high confidence that even a control officer of Army visited him for advice.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinjo is also said to have such a high confidence that even a control officer of Army visited him for advice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>また立川飛行機の庶務課より丑寅の方角を警戒するようにと示されたので、関係者に注意し消化設備に万全を期した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He gave a warning to General Affairs Division of Tachikawa Aircraft to be on guard in the direction of northeast and instructed those concerned to carefully set up fire-extinguishing equipment.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He gave a warning to General Affairs Division of Tachikawa Aircraft to be on guard in the direction of northeast and instructed those concerned to carefully set up fire-extinguishing equipment.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He gave a warning to General Affairs Division of Tachikawa Aircraft to be on guard in the direction of northeast and instructed those concerned to carefully set up fire-extinguishing equipment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>1週間後に当該場所より出火。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A fire broke out a week later at a predicted site.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A fire broke out a week later at a predicted site.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A fire broke out a week later at a predicted site.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>しかし消火設備が万全だったので大事に至らずに済んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, thanks to the carefully established fire-extinguishing equipment, the fire did not turn into serious situations.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, thanks to the carefully established fire-extinguishing equipment, the fire did not turn into a serious situations.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, thanks to the carefully established fire-extinguishing equipment, the fire did not turn into a serious situations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>会社側は金を払って諸問題の経決や経営診断などを専属でやってもらいたいと文明に申し出たが、営利の為の易は禁ずるという家訓により断ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the company offered Fumiaki an exclusive contract for the service of solving problems and determining business conditions but he declined the offer because of his family&apos;s kakun (family percept) that divination is not allowed for the pursuit of profit.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the company offered Fumiaki an exclusive contract for the service of solving problems and determining business conditions but he declined the offer because of his family&apos;s kakun (family percept) that divination is not allowed for the pursuit of profit.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the company offered Fumiaki an exclusive contract for the service of solving problems and determining business conditions but he declined the offer because of his family&apos;s kakun (family percept) that divination is not allowed for the pursuit of profit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="42">
<j>昭和8,9年頃に1人の真言僧が「易学を教えてほしい、代わりに真言密教を呈上するので」と訪ねてきたことにより真言密教と結縁した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around 1933 or 1934, he had a connection with Shingon Esoteric Buddhism after a Shingon Buddhist vested him and sad, &quot;Please teach the art of divination in exchange for Shingon Esoteric Buddhism.&quot;</e>
<cmt>後ろの文の「代わりに真言密教を呈上するので」と訪ねてきたことにより真言密教と結縁し」をつなげてあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around 1933 or 1934, he had a connection with Shingon Esoteric Buddhism after a Shingon Buddhist visited him and said, &quot;Please teach the art of divination in exchange for Shingon Esoteric Buddhism.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around 1933 or 1934, he had a connection with Shingon Esoteric Buddhism after a Shingon Buddhist visited him and said, &quot;Please teach the art of divination in exchange for Shingon Esoteric Buddhism.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>翌昭和10年に仏師の大家である仲丸奥堂師より運慶一刀三礼（いっとう・さんらい）の作で北条時政公の御持仏と口伝され、平常眼（へいじょうがん）という非常に珍しい大日大聖不動明王（だいにちだいしょう・ふどうみょうおう）像を勧請した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the next year, he was asked by Nakamaru okunodoshi, a sculptor master of Buddhist statues, to call up and infuse the spirit of the statue of Dainichi Daisho Fudo Myoo, a very precious statue with heijogan (literally, normal eyes) --gojibutsu of Tokimasa HOJO belived to be made by Unkei Itto-Sanrai (to worship three times with every stroke on scalpturing statues) and believed to be gojibutsu of Tokimasa HOJO.</e>
<cmt>前の文の「代わりに真言密教を呈上するので」と訪ねてきたことにより真言密教と結縁し」をつなげてあります。Nakamaru okunodoshi 読み方・定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the next year, he was asked by Nakamaru okunodoshi, a sculptor master of Buddhist statues, to call up and infuse the spirit of the statue of Dainichi Daisho Fudo Myoo, a very precious statue with heijogan (literally, normal eyes) --gojibutsu of Tokimasa HOJO belived to be made by Unkei Itto-Sanrai (to worship three times with every stroke on scalpturing statues) and believed to be gojibutsu of Tokimasa HOJO.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the next year, he was asked by Nakamaru okunodoshi, a sculptor master of Buddhist statues, to call up and infuse the spirit of the statue of Dainichi Daisho Fudo Myoo, a very precious statue with heijogan (literally, normal eyes) --gojibutsu of Tokimasa HOJO believed to be made by Unkei Itto-Sanrai (to worship three times with every stroke on sculpturing statues) and believed to be gojibutsu of Tokimasa HOJO.</e>
<cmt>一つ目のbelivedをbelievedに変更しました。scalpturingを sculpturingに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>なお真乗は当初、その仏像と同じものを刻んでほしいと頼み、その仏像を購入する予定であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinjo at first had asked the sculptor to make the identical statue of the Buddha and intended to buy it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinjo at first had asked the sculptor to make an identical statue of the Buddha and intended to buy it.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinjo at first had asked the sculptor to make an identical statue of the Buddha and intended to buy it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>しかし仲丸師によれば「どうしてもこの不動明王が先生（文明）のもとへ行きたいといって彫らせてくれない」という不思議な体験があったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, master MAKAMARU is said to have had an extraordinary experience as he quoted, &quot;The statue made him unwilling to make the identical because the it wants to go to the Fumiaki&quot;</e>
<cmt>「先生」は呼び名なので訳し出ししていません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, master MAKAMARU is said to have had an extraordinary experience as he quoted, &quot;The statue made him unwilling to make an identical copy because it wants to go to the Fumiaki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, master NAKAMARU is said to have had an extraordinary experience as he quoted, &quot;The statue made him unwilling to make an identical copy because it wants to go to the Fumiaki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>MAKAMARUをNAKAMARUに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>仲丸師はこの体験から家宝である不動明王像を無償で譲ることを申し出た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Master MAKAMARU, after his experience, offered Fumiaki to give the statue for nothing but Fumiaki paid</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Master MAKAMARU, after his experience, offered to give Fumiaki the statue for nothing.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Master MAKAMARU, after this experience, offered to give the statue to Fumiaki for nothing.</e>
<cmt>一部、翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>しかし、伊藤はそれでは申し訳ないということから、金三百円を謝礼として払い自宅に迎えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However he thought obliged to him and paid three million yen in token of his gratitude to receive the statue at his home.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However he felt obliged and paid three million yen in token of his gratitude to receive the statue at his home.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However Ito felt obliged and paid three million yen in token of his gratitude to receive the statue at his home.</e>
<cmt>heをItoに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>なおこれは、鎌倉期作といわれる仏像に払う金額としては破格の安さではあるが、決して少ない額ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The three million yen is a great bargains to pay for a statue of Buddha made in the Kamakura period but never a small amount.</e>
<cmt>「なお」は特に意味がないので訳し出ししていません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The three million yen is a great bargain to pay for a statue of Buddha made in the Kamakura period but never a small amount.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The three million yen is a great bargain to pay for a statue of Buddha made in the Kamakura period but never a small amount.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>当時の勤め人の平均月給は五十円程度の時代で、伊藤はまだ会社勤務の技術者だったため、平均月給よりも高給を得ていたが、所持していた高価なカメラなどを処分しても三百円に足りなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those days when an average of the monthly wages fro salaried workers is about 50 yen, ITO&apos;s salary as an engineer was higher than the average but the money he managed to raise by selling his expensive camera and others was short of 3 million yen.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those days when the average monthly wages for salaried workers was about 50 yen, ITO&apos;s salary as an engineer was higher than the average but the money he managed to raise by selling his expensive camera and others was short of the 3 million yen.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those days when the average monthly wages for salaried workers was about 50 yen, ITO&apos;s salary as an engineer was higher than the average but the money he managed to raise by selling his expensive camera and others was short of the 3 million yen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>病筮鈔を信じて集まっていた人々に不動尊像を迎えたいと洩らしたところ、賛同を得て浄財が集まり捻出されたものであるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that people who gathered with faith in Byozeisho heard of his intention to buy the statue of Fudo-son and gave him jozai (donation) so he was able to raise the money.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that people who gathered with faith in Byozeisho heard of his intention to buy the statue of Fudo-son and gave him jozai (donation) so he was able to raise the money.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that people who gathered with faith in Byozeisho heard of his intention to buy the statue of Fudo-son and gave him jozai (donation) so he was able to raise the money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>この事は立教前の時点で既に講組織が自然発生的に出来つつあったことを表している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This shows that the religious organization had been already spontaenously growing before the organization was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This shows that the religious organization had been already spontaneously growing before the organization was established.</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This shows that the religious organization had been already spontaneously growing before the organization was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="52">
<j>なお不動尊像譲渡当日の朝は雪が降っていたが午後1時ごろにはそれも止んで晴れ渡った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was snowing on the morning when the statue of Fudo-son was given but it stopped snowing and cleared up in the afternoon.</e>
<cmt>「なお」は訳し出ししていません。一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was snowing on the morning when the statue of Fudo-son was given but it stopped snowing and cleared up in the afternoon.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was snowing on the morning when the statue of Fudo-son was given but it stopped snowing and cleared up around 1 p.m.</e>
<cmt>in the afternoon.をaround 1 p.m.に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>帰宅途中のタクシーの車中からエンジンのあたりに、夕方でもないのに五色の雲が棚引いて車と共に走っているのを文明や仲丸師の2人の娘など一行が見たという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Fumiaki and two daughters of master MAKAMARU, when they were in the taxi on his way home, saw clouds in five colors trailing from the engine of the car, although it was not in the evening.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Fumiaki and two daughters of master MAKAMARU, when they were in the taxi on his way home, saw clouds in five colors trailing from the engine of the car, although it was not in the evening.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Fumiaki and two daughters of master NAKAMARU, when they were in the taxi on his way home, saw clouds in five colors trailing from the engine of the car, although it was not in the evening.</e>
<cmt>MAKAMARUをNAKAMARUに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>これは仏教で非常によい兆しとされる彩雲であったことが後にわかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that these clouds were found out to be saiun (glowing clouds) beloved to be a good omen in Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that these clouds were found out to be saiun (glowing clouds) beloved to be a good omen in Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that these clouds were found out to be saiun (glowing clouds) believed to be a good omen in Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>belovedをbelievedに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="55">
<j>年明け早々・1月4日から寒修行として水垢離（みずごり）をとり、満願前の1月31日の友司の透視をする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He took mizugori (cold-water ablutions) from April 4, at the very beginning of the year, to January 31 before completion (fulfillment) of a vow, when Tumuli showed the power of see through.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He took mizugori (cold-water ablutions) from April 4, at the very beginning of the year, to January 31 before completion (fulfillment) of a vow, when Tumuli showed the power of see through.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He took mizugori (cold-water ablutions) from January 4, at the very beginning of the year, to January 31 before completion (fulfillment) of a vow, when Tomoji showed the power of see through.</e>
<cmt>AprilをJanuaryに変更しました。 (fulfillment)のかっこ内のスペースをつめました。TumuliをTomojiに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>それを切っ掛けに　2月8日に仕事を辞め宗教の道ひとすじに立つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This made him decide to quit the job on February 8 and start devoting himself to the field of religion.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This made him decide to quit his job on February 8 and start devoting himself to the field of religion.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This made him decide to quit his job on February 8 and start devoting himself to the field of religion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>この寒修行満願の日（2月3日）前後に関して文明は、仕事をやめて宗教の道に入る不安が夫婦ともにあり、片一方が仏道を提唱すると片一方は反対し、また逆になったりして、仏と人間との斗（たたか）いであったと回想している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He looked back on the days around the completion day of a vow (February 3) in kanshugyo (ascetic practices in cold weather), saying that the coupled feeling uncertainty of devoting themselves to the field of religion were as if they had fought between Buddha and a man; one proposed to get devoted to the religion while the other opposed to it and vice versa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He looked back on the days around the completion day of the vow (February 3) in kanshugyo (ascetic practices in cold weather), saying that the coupled feeling uncertainty of devoting themselves to the field of religion were as if they had fought between Buddha and a man; one proposed to get devoted to the religion while the other opposed to it and vice versa.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He looked back on the days around the completion day of the vow (February 3) in kanshugyo (ascetic practices in cold weather), saying that the coupled feeling uncertainty of devoting themselves to the field of religion were as if they had fought between Buddha and a man; one proposed to get devoted to the religion while the other opposed to it and vice versa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>これを境に不自由のない安定した生活から一転し生活が困窮するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This made them turn their lives into financial difficulty from well-to-do lives.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This made them turn their lives into financial difficulty from well-to-do lives.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This made them turn their lives into financial difficulty from well-to-do lives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="59">
<j>また不動明王を勧請して寒修行を行なった時に「このような立派な尊像は、普通の人では護り切れないから、自分の弟子になれ」と勧めた1人の先達がいたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that, when he called up and infused the spirit of Fudo Myoo and had kanshugyo, a sendatsu (a guide) advised him by saying, &quot;it is better for you to become a decipline of mine because ordinary people can not protect such a outstanding statue of image.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that, when he called up and infused the spirit of Fudo Myoo and had kanshugyo, a sendatsu (a guide) advised him by saying, &quot;it is better for you to become a disciple of mine because ordinary people can not protect such a outstanding statue of image.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that, when he called up and infused the spirit of Fudo Myoo and had kanshugyo, a sendatsu (a guide) advised him by saying, &quot;it is better for you to become a disciple of mine because ordinary people can not protect such a outstanding statue of image.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>文明が一向に応じないため業を煮やして憤然として去った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sendatsu lost patient and returned home with an angry with Fumiaki, who did not accept the advice.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sendatsu lost patience and returned home with an angry with Fumiaki, who did not accept the advice.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sendatsu lost patience and returned home in frustration with Fumiaki, who did not accept the advice.</e>
<cmt>with an angry をin frustrationに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>未だにそのようにしか推量できないが、と断った上で「その先達は、この希有な尊像が欲しくなったのであろう。」と述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He said, &quot;This in only what I can still guess, but I believe he wanted this precious statue.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He said, &quot;This is only what I can still guess, but I believe he wanted this precious statue.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He said, &quot;This is only what I can still guess, but I believe he wanted this precious statue.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>文明は、価値あるモノと見るような、宗教家としてあるまじき相(すがた)に、かえって哀れを感じ、これを狭量に解釈すれば、腹も立ち相手を責める気持ちに自分も苦しんでいったに違いない、と感じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But Fumiaki rather felt a pity for the way the sendatsu saw it as only valuable things and no religious leader should do, and thought that the sendatsu might have suffered from the angry and blame the sendatsu put on Fumiaki from a different point of view.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処「狭量に解釈すれば」は「別の見方をすれば」と訳してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But Fumiaki rather felt a pity for the way the sendatsu saw it as only valuable things and no religious leader should do that, and thought that the sendatsu might have suffered from the anger and blame the sendatsu put on Fumiaki from a different point of view.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But Fumiaki rather felt a pity for the way the sendatsu saw it as only valuable things and no religious leader should do that, and thought that the sendatsu might have suffered from the anger and blame the sendatsu put on Fumiaki from a different point of view.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>文明はまた、ひとたび自分を、相手の立場において考えてみると、この事象に対応して、常に不動心に燃え、その先達を凌駕するだけの宗教家になろう、と決意しさらに修行に徹した。.</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fumiaki also thought that he needed to put himself in another person&apos;s place and, in consideration of this issue, he decided to always earnestly pursue a calm mind and train himself to become a religious leader superior to the sendatsu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処「狭量に解釈すれば」は「別の見方をすれば」という意味に解釈し、訳してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fumiaki also thought that he needed to put himself in another person&apos;s place and, in consideration of this issue, he decided to always earnestly pursue a calm mind and train himself to become a religious leader superior to the sendatsu.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fumiaki also thought that he needed to put himself in another person&apos;s place and, in consideration of this issue, he decided to always earnestly pursue a calm mind and train himself to become a religious leader superior to the sendatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>それもみ仏が与えてくださったありがたい教訓であり、言外に余る慈悲溢れるお諭しであった、と述懐している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He recalled this event and expressed his thoughts that this is the grateful lesson that Lord Buddha gave me and the admonition with deep mercy beyond expression.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He recalled this event and expressed his thoughts that this is the grateful lesson that Lord Buddha gave me and the admonition with deep mercy beyond expression.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He recalled this event and expressed his thoughts that this is the grateful lesson that Lord Buddha gave me and the admonition with deep mercy beyond expression.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="65">
<j>醍醐寺にて恵印灌頂に続き、金胎両部伝法灌頂を法畢した年（昭和16年)の12月8日は日米開戦の日である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The teachings of the school, Kintai-ryobu denpo-kanjo was completed after Ein Kanjo (the ceremony to be the successor of a ritual of the Ein School) was held at Daigo-ji Temple in 1941, the year when war between Japan and the United States broke out. on December 8.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The teachings of the school, Kintai-ryobu denpo-kanjo was completed after Ein Kanjo (the ceremony to be the successor of a ritual of the Ein School) was held at Daigo-ji Temple in 1941, the year when war between Japan and the United States broke out on December 8.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The teachings of the school, Kintai-ryobu denpo-kanjo was completed after Ein Kanjo (the ceremony to be the successor of a ritual of the Ein School) was held at Daigo-ji Temple in 1941, the year when war between Japan and the United States broke out on December 8.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>その前年・15年暮れに「来年は、大変な年になりますよ。と友司から告げられた。、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December of the previous year, 1940, he was told by tomoji, &quot;Something serious will happen next year.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処「と友司から告げられた。」を加えてあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December of the previous year, 1940, he was told by tomoji, &quot;Something serious will happen next year.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of the previous year, 1940, he was told by Tomoji, &quot;Something serious will happen next year.</e>
<cmt>In DecemberをAt the endに変更しました。tomijiをTomijiに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>それも12月、よほど心していかないと･････。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular, take care in December. &quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, take care in December. &quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, take care in December. &quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>真乗も16年の3月3日の晩に、ベニート・ムッソリーニとアドルフ・ヒトラーとスターリンが会談している夢を見て、“戦争”を感じ、しかも大戦争になることを予感したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that, on March 3, 1941, Shinjo also saw Benito MUSSOLINI, Adolf Hitler, and Stalin having a meeting in his dream and had a feeling that &quot;war,&quot; even a great war is going to start.</e>
<cmt>「」と友司から告げられ、」は上に入れたので削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that, on March 3, 1941, Shinjo also saw Benito MUSSOLINI, Adolf Hitler, and Stalin having a meeting in his dream and had a feeling that &quot;war,&quot; even a great war is going to start.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that, on March 3, 1941, Shinjo also saw Benito MUSSOLINI, Adolf Hitler, and Stalin having a meeting in his dream and had a feeling that &quot;war,&quot; even a great war is going to start.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>昭和19年になると戦争が更に激しくなり立川も爆撃され、友司と子供を疎開させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1944, the war raged and bombs were dropped in Tachikawa and Tomoji and children evacuated to a countryside.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1944, the war raged and bombs were dropped in Tachikawa and Tomoji and children evacuated to the countryside.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1944, the war raged and bombs were dropped in Tachikawa and Tomoji and children evacuated to the countryside.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>真乗が疎開先に訪ねる度に空襲になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tachikawa suffered air raids every time Shinjo visited them, Tokyo suffered an air raid</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tachikawa suffered air raids every time Shinjo visited them, Tokyo suffered an air raid.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tachikawa suffered air raids every time Shinjo visited them.</e>
<cmt>Tokyo suffered an air raidを除去しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>周囲の人からは「本堂に無線装置があって連絡があるのではないか。」と言われたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Neighbors are said to said, &quot;A radiotelegraph must be within the temple for communication.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Neighbors are said to have said, &quot;A radiotelegraph must be within the temple for communication.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been said that neighbors said, &quot;A radiotelegraph must be within the temple for communication.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一部、翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>「でなければ、あんなに田舎に帰って避けられるはずがない」と、スパイの噂もかけられたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Neighbors also suspected that he might be a spy by saying, &quot;Without such a equipment, he could not have avoided the air raids by going to a country side. &quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Neighbors also suspected that he might be a spy by saying, &quot;Without such a equipment, he could not have avoided the air raids by going to the country side. &quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Neighbors also suspected that he might be a spy by saying, &quot;Without such a equipment, he could not have avoided the air raids by going to the country side. &quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>なお昭和20年の終戦によって、合同真言宗は解体し、それぞれもとの宗派に分かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the end of the war, Godo Shingon shu (joint Shingon sect) broke up into individual original schools.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the end of the war, Godo Shingon shu (joint Shingon sect) broke up into individual original schools.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the end of the war, Godo Shingon shu (joint Shingon sect) broke up into individual original schools.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>「立川不動尊教会」は真言宗を離脱し、大般涅槃経を所依とする、いずれの束縛も受けない独立の教団として「まこと教団」を発足した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tachikawa Fudoson Kyokai&quot; seceded from the Shingon sect and established &quot;Makoto religious organization,&quot; a nonalinged and independent organization whose authority is the Nirvana Sutra.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Tachikawa Fudoson Kyokai&quot; seceded from the Shingon sect and established &quot;Makoto religious organization,&quot; a nonaligned and independent organization whose authority is the Nirvana Sutra.</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tachikawa Fudoson Kyokai&apos; seceded from the Shingon sect and established &apos;Makoto religious organization,&apos; a nonaligned and independent organization whose authority is the Nirvana Sutra.</e>
<cmt>&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="75">
<j>のちに「まこと教団事件」と呼ばれる法難が勃発。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later a religious persecution called &quot;Makoto kyodan jiken (Makoto religious organization incidence)&quot; occurred.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later a religious persecution called &quot;Makoto kyodan jiken (Makoto religious organization incidence)&quot; occurred.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later a religious persecution called &apos;Makoto kyodan jiken (Makoto religious organization incidence)&apos; occurred.</e>
<cmt>&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>一人の元弟子の告訴により監獄に入れられた際、「あなたが宗教家なら、このような人も助けることができるだろう」と兇暴な尊属殺人犯と同房にされたことがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he was put into jail as the result of an accusation by an ex-follower, he was in a cell with a vicious parricide murderer because he was told, &quot;A religious leader like you must have an ability to give a hand to such a vicious man. &quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he was put into jail as the result of an accusation by an ex-follower, he was in a cell with a vicious parricide murderer because he was told, &quot;A religious leader like you must have an ability to give a hand to such a vicious man. &quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he was put into a jail as the result of an accusation by an ex-follower, he was in a cell with a vicious parricide murderer because he was told, &quot;A religious leader like you must have an ability to give a hand to such a vicious man.&quot;</e>
<cmt>jailの前にaを挿入しました。manの後のスペースを除去しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>（※真乗は「尊属」殺人犯と述べているが、彼は自分の甥を殺害した男なので、「尊属」殺人犯ではなく「卑属」殺人犯である）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Shijo told that the man was a parricide murderer, but he was not a parricide murderer but the man was a lineal murderer because he killed his nephew.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Shinjo was told that the man was a parricide murderer, but he was not a parricide murderer but the man was a lineal murderer because he killed his nephew.)</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Shinjo was told that the man was a parricide murderer, but he was not a parricide murderer but the man was a lineal murderer because he killed his nephew.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>初めのうち、その殺人犯は真乗に乱暴を仕掛けてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the beginning, the man did violence against him.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the beginning, the man acted out in violence against him.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the beginning, the man acted out in violence against him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>しかし獄舎の中では貴重な水を手ぬぐいに浸して額を冷やし、不動明王の霊咒を唱えて看病すると、次第に素直になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he came to open his mind, after Shinjo looked after him, when he was sick, by cooling his forehead with a towel soaked with water valuable in a jail, and chanting ryoju of Fudo Myoo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he came to open his mind, after Shinjo looked after him, when he was sick, by cooling his forehead with a towel soaked with water valuable in a jail, and chanting ryoju of Fudo Myoo.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he came to open his mind, after Shinjo looked after him, when he was sick, by cooling his forehead with a towel soaked with water valuable in a jail, and chanting ryoju of Fudo Myoo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>「お前」と呼ばれていたのが「旦那」、「先生」と変わり、素直に話を聞くようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the man used an impolite way of addressing Shijo like &quot;Omae,&quot; he began to use polite and respectful ways, such as &quot;Dannna (sir)&quot; or &quot;Sensei (teacher)&quot; and listen to him with an open mind.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the man used an impolite way of addressing Shijo like &quot;Omae,&quot; he began to use polite and respectful ways, such as &quot;Dannna (sir)&quot; or &quot;Sensei (teacher)&quot; and listen to him with an open mind.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the man used an impolite way of addressing Shijo like &apos;Omae,&apos; he began to use polite and respectful ways, such as &apos;Dannna (sir)&apos; or &apos;Sensei (teacher)&apos; and listen to him with an open mind.</e>
<cmt>&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>これを見ていた別の罪人が「落魄(おちぶ)れて袖に涙のかかるとき　人の心の奥ぞ知らるる」という刺青を真乗に見せたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seeing this change, a different prisoner is said to have showed Shinjo a tattoo written as &quot;You know the deepest mind of others when you come down in the world and shed tears to wet a sleeve.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seeing this change, a different prisoner is said to have showed Shinjo a tattoo written as &quot;You know the deepest mind of others when you come down in the world and shed tears to wet a sleeve.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seeing this change, another prisoner is said to have showed Shinjo a tattoo written as &apos;You know the deepest mind of others when you come down in the world and shed tears to wet a sleeve.&apos;</e>
<cmt>a differentをanotherに変更しました。&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>こういうことがあり刑務所内で信者ができたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this way, Shinjo had followers in the prison.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this way, Shinjo had followers in the prison.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this way, Shinjo had followers in the prison.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>また刑務所内では密教大辞典全3刊を何度も何度も読み返し本がボロボロになったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that Shinjo read all the three volumes of Mikkyo daijiten (Encyclopedia of Esoteric Buddhism) many times until they became worn out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that Shinjo read all the three volumes of Mikkyo daijiten (Encyclopedia of Esoteric Buddhism) many times until they became worn out.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that Shinjo read all the three volumes of Mikkyo daijiten (Encyclopedia of Esoteric Buddhism) many times until they became worn out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="84">
<j>この法難における裁判では、当初は信徒の知り合いなどの弁護士がついた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a trial over this religious persecution, his lawyers were at first acquaintances of followers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a trial over this religious persecution, his lawyers were at first acquaintances of followers.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a trial over this religious persecution, his lawyers were at first acquaintances of followers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>しかし、どの方もあまり教団のためにならないと判断した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However they were regarded as being no benefit to the religious organization.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However they were regarded as being no benefit to the religious organization.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However they were regarded as being no benefit to the religious organization.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>そのため、摂受院が人づてから当時の第3次吉田内閣の国務大臣で、また同郷山梨の出身で法学者でもある樋貝詮三の自宅を訪ね、事情を懇々と説明したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And then Shojuin was referred to and visited the home of Senzo HIGAI, Minister of State of the second Yoshida cabinet, who was from the same prefecture as he (Yamanashi Prefecture) and a legal scholar, and explained the details of what happened.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And then Shojuin was referred to and visited the home of Senzo HIGAI, Minister of State of the second Yoshida cabinet, who was from the same prefecture as he (Yamanashi Prefecture) and a legal scholar, and explained the details of what happened.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And then Shojuin visited the home of Senzo HIGAI, who was a Minister of State of the second Yoshida cabinet, and was from the same town, Yamanashi Prefecture and also a legal scholar, and explained the details of what happened.</e>
<cmt>一部、翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>樋貝の子女の証言によると「伊藤さんは報じられているような人物ではない、あの教団は残しておかなければならない」と述べた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A daughter of HIGAI said, &quot;My father considered it necessary for the religious organization to be remained because Mr. Ito was not what had been reported.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A daughter of HIGAI said, &quot;My father considered it necessary for the religious organization to remain because Mr. Ito was not what had been reported.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A daughter of HIGAI said, &quot;My father considered it necessary for the religious organization to remain because Mr. Ito was not what had been reported.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>金銭抜きで教団の擁護として弁護士を紹介した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">HIGAI introduced a lawyer to support the organization without receiving any money.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">HIGAI introduced a lawyer to support the organization without receiving any money.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">HIGAI introduced a lawyer to support the organization without receiving any money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>樋貝は事件の解決、裁判の行方を見届けず他界した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">HIGAI died without seeing how the incident was settled and how the trial was concluded.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">HIGAI died without seeing how the incident was settled and how the trial was concluded.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">HIGAI died without seeing how the incident was settled and how the trial was concluded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>のちに「まこと教団」は「真如苑」と改称許可が文部省から下り、教団の存続は許された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that Ministry of Education authorized the organization to change its name from &quot;Makoto religious organization&quot; to &quot;Shinnyoen Buddhist&quot; and continue to exist.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, the Ministry of Education authorized the organization to change its name from &quot;Makoto religious organization&quot; to &quot;Shinnyoen Buddhis&quot; and continue to exist.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, the Ministry of Education authorized the organization to change its name from &apos;Makoto religious organization&apos; to &apos;Shinnyoen Buddhist&apos; and continue to exist.</e>
<cmt>&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>そこで真乗と摂受院は「お世話になった樋貝先生に報告かたがた、お墓参りをしたい」と申し出たという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then Shinjo and Shojuin said, &quot;we would like to pay a visit to the grave of Mr. HIGAI to express gratitude and report the survival of the organization. &quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then Shinjo and Shojuin said, &quot;we would like to pay a visit to the grave of Mr. HIGAI to express gratitude and report the survival of the organization. &quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then Shinjo and Shojuin said, &quot;We would like to pay a visit to the grave of Mr. HIGAI to express gratitude and report the survival of the organization. &quot;</e>
<cmt>weをWeに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>樋貝の娘はこの1回きりだと思っていたが、それから毎月の命日に欠かさず千駄ヶ谷の墓地にお参りしたことに驚いたと述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">HIGAI&apos;s daughter told that she was surprised to hear that they never failed to visit the grave in Sendagaya on the date of HIGAI&apos;s death every month although she thought they would pay a visit only once.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">HIGAI&apos;s daughter said that she was surprised to hear that they never failed to visit the grave in Sendagaya on the date of HIGAI&apos;s death every month although she thought they would pay a visit only once.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">HIGAI&apos;s daughter said that she was surprised to hear that they never failed to visit the grave in Sendagaya on the date of HIGAI&apos;s death every month although she thought they would pay a visit only once.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="93">
<j>なお、裁判の方は「もう一歩で裁判上で無罪を勝ち取ることができる」と弁護士団から勧められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the trial, a team of defense lawyers advised, &quot;you are a just a step away from innocence.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the trial, a team of defense lawyers advised, &quot;you are a just a step away from innocence.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the trial, a team of defense lawyers advised, &quot;You are a just a step away from innocence.&quot;</e>
<cmt>youをYouに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>しかし、真乗自身は「裁判より人を救う時間が惜しい」として上告せず、有罪判決が確定している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However Shinjo himself did not made a final appeal and his conviction was decided and said, &quot;I want to spend more time to save people than keeping my mind to the trial.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However Shinjo himself did not made a final appeal and his conviction was decided and said, &quot;I want to spend more time to save people than keeping my mind on the trial.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However Shinjo himself did not made a final appeal and his conviction was decided and said, &quot;I want to spend more time to save people than keeping my mind on the trial.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="95">
<j>かつて増上慢から破戒行為を犯して、教師の資格を剥奪され追放（すなわち破門）となった弟子がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of his disciples who committed sabotage out of conceit in Buddhism had been deprived of his qualification of teacher and purged (or expelled).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of his disciples who committed sabotage out of conceit in Buddhism had been deprived of his qualification of teacher and purged (or expelled).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of his disciples who committed sabotage out of conceit in Buddhism had been deprived of his qualification of teacher and purged (or expelled).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>その弟子の話によると「師と弟子の縁はどんなことがあっても一生切らないから必ず帰ってきなさい」と言って世間に送り出したことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the disciple, he was sent to the world with words, &quot;Remember to return, because I will never break off relations between a mentor and disciples.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the disciple, he was sent to the world with words, &quot;Remember to return, because I will never break off relations between a mentor and disciples.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the disciple, he was sent to the world with words, &quot;Remember to return, because I will never break off relations between a mentor and disciples.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>その弟子は懺悔してお参りに行くと、会った人の体調が悪くなったりして誰からも相手にしてもらえず、目の前で門を閉められたことも度々あったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The disciple repented of his sins and visited the temple but was ignored by any followers or turned away at the door many times, because those who met him got ill.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The disciple repented his sins and visited the temple but was ignored by any followers or turned away at the door many times, because those who met him got ill.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The disciple repented his sins and visited the temple but was ignored by any followers or turned away at the door many times, because those who met him got ill.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>しかし真乗と摂受院だけは唯一「帰ってきたか」と温かく迎えられたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However only Shinjo and Shoji welcome him cordially by saying, &quot;Welcome back.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However only Shinjo and Shoji welcome him cordially by saying, &quot;Welcome back.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However only Shinjo and Shoji welcomed him cordially by saying, &quot;Welcome back.&quot;</e>
<cmt>welcomeをwelcomedに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>この弟子はかつての罪障を滅し、その慈悲に報いるには布施波羅蜜しかないと立願した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This disciple thought what he could do to repay the mercy was to clean the sins he had committed and do fuseharamitsu (perfection of generosity) and desired to do so.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This disciple thought that what he could do to repay the mercy was to clean the sins he had committed and do fuseharamitsu (perfection of generosity) and desired to do so.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This disciple thought that what he could do to repay the mercy was to clean the sins he had committed and do fuseharamitsu (perfection of generosity) and desired to do so.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>それを実践し再び教師としなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He put his decision into practice and became a teacher again.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He put his decision into practice and became a teacher again.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He put his decision into practice and became a teacher again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>なお、これがのちに教団の歓喜制度になった（現在は制度としては廃止されている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This led to the establishment of kangi seido (the contribution system) of the religious organization.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This led to the establishment of kangi seido (the contribution system) of the religious organization.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This led to the establishment of kangi seido (the contribution system) of the religious organization.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>（現在は制度としては廃止されている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The system does not exist nay more.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The system does not exist anymore.)</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The system does not exist anymore.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="103">
<j>また、真乗はヘビースモーカーで知られていたが、煙草をやめることを思い立った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinjo known as a heavy smoker thought of giving up smoking.</e>
<cmt>「また」は訳し出ししていません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinjo known as a heavy smoker thought of giving up smoking.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinjo known as a heavy smoker thought of giving up smoking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>ただしやめるというと寂しいので「休む」ことにしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However he still felt attached to smoking and planed to &quot;suspend.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However he still felt attached to smoking and planned to &quot;suspend it.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However he still felt attached to smoking and planned to &apos;suspend it.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>ある日、信徒から最近煙草を吸わない事を問われて、「いや、今、休んでいる」と答えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One day, when asked by a follower if he had stop smoking, he responded, &quot;I just suspend it,&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One day, when asked by a follower if he had stop smoking, he responded, &quot;I just suspended it.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One day, when asked by a follower if he had stop smoking, he responded, &quot;I just suspended it.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>その信徒が他の人たちに「教主さまは、煙草を止め、私たち信徒のために健康に留意される云々」などと語った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The follower said to other followers, &quot; our head is taking care of his health for us followers by quitting smoking.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The follower said to other followers, &quot; our head is taking care of his health for us followers by quitting smoking.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The follower said to other followers, &quot;Our head is taking care of his health for us followers by quitting smoking.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ourをOurに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>それを聞いた真乗は「休む」という曖昧な心得を捨てなければいけないと意を決したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hearing this, Shinjo thought he had to abandon his halfhearted resolution of &quot;suspending&quot; and made up his mind.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hearing this, Shinjo thought he had to abandon his halfhearted resolution of &quot;suspending&quot; and made up his mind.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hearing this, Shinjo thought he had to abandon his halfhearted resolution of &apos;suspending&apos; and made up his mind.</e>
<cmt>&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="108">
<j>真乗は、自分の長女と次女を破門しているが、釈尊の子であるといわれる善星と優波摩那が道をまっとうしなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinjo excommunicated his own first and second daughters,and. Zensho and Upamaana, believed to be children of Shakyamuni did not fulfill their discipline．</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinjo excommunicated his own first and second daughters,and. Zensho and Upamaana, believed to be children of Shakyamuni did not fulfill their discipline．</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinjo excommunicated his own first and second daughters, and. Zensho and Upamaana, believed to be children of Shakyamuni did not fulfill their discipline．</e>
<cmt>daughtersの後の、を,に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>羅ご羅だけが修行を終えて悟りを得た、という三子のたとえをもって教化(きょうげ)している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinjo enlightened people by giving the metaphor of three diciples that only Ragora, Rahula completed his discipline to achieve spiritual enlightenment.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinjo enlightened people by giving the metaphor of three diciples that only Ragora, Rahula completed his discipline to achieve spiritual enlightenment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinjo enlightened people by giving the metaphor of three diciples that only Ragora, Rahula completed his discipline to achieve spiritual enlightenment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>しかしこの件に関しては、他にも浄土真宗の開祖である親鸞が息子の善鸞を破門したことも例に挙げている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding this, he also gave another example that Shinran, the foundered of Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism), excommunicated his son Zenran.</e>
<cmt>「しかし」は逆説の意味はないので訳し出ししていません。一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding this, he also gave another example that Shinran, the foundered of Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism), excommunicated his son Zenran.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding this, he also gave another example that Shinran, the founder of Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism), excommunicated his son Zenran.</e>
<cmt>founderedをfounderに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>浄土真宗は「肉食妻帯」を肯定する在家仏教を唱導しているが、その中には法の道が枉（ま）げずに貫かれいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jodo Shinshu advocates Zaike Bukkyo that agrees with &quot;meat and matrimony (Buddhism),&quot; in which the road to Buddhism is strictly pursued.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jodo Shinshu advocates Zaike Bukkyo that agrees with &quot;meat and matrimony (Buddhism),&quot; in which the road to Buddhism is strictly pursued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jodo Shinshu advocates Zaike Bukkyo that agrees with &apos;meat and matrimony (Buddhism),&apos; in which the road to Buddhism is strictly pursued.</e>
<cmt>&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>親鸞の家族に対する厳しい姿勢から思いを深くした、と語っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinjo said that he realized what a strict stance Shinran had toward his family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinjo said that he realized what a strict stance Shinran had toward his family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinjo said that he realized what a strict stance Shinran had toward his family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="113">
<j>真如苑は昭和50~60年に急激に信徒数が増えたことで、教団と共に伊藤真乗の名前も広く知られることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With a dramatical increase in number of followers between 1970 and 1990, Shinnyoen Buddhist and the name of Shinjo ITO became widely known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With a dramatical increase in the number of followers between 1970 and 1990, Shinnyoen Buddhist and the name of Shinjo ITO became widely known.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With a dramatic increase in the number of followers between 1970 and 1990, Shinnyoen Buddhist and the name of Shinjo ITO became widely known.</e>
<cmt>dramaticalをdramaticに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>したがってそれまでは宗教界の一部でしか知られることがなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">before tha, thus, Shinnyoen Buddhist and his name had been known to only a part of the religious world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before that, Shinnyoen Buddhist and his name had been known to only a part of the religious world.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before that, Shinnyoen Buddhist and his name had been known to only a part of the religious world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>このため真乗は、当時の宗教界から「宗教界のいぶし銀」という評価があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore Shinjo was regarded as &quot;oxidized silver in the religious world&quot; in those days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore Shinjo was regarded as &quot;oxidized silver in the religious world&quot; in those days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore Shinjo was regarded as &apos;oxidized silver in the religious world&apos; in those days.</e>
<cmt>&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>このことは真乗教主が遷化した際に、妙智会教団の会長であった宮本丈靖も中外日報紙上で述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeyasu MIYAMOTO, who was the president of Myochikai Kyodan (religious group), said so in the paper of &quot;Chugai Nippo,&quot; when Shinjo, the head of the organization, died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takeyasu MIYAMOTO, who was the president of Myochikai Kyodan (religious group), said so in the paper of &quot;Chugai Nippo,&quot; when Shinjo, the head of the organization, died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeyasu MIYAMOTO, who was the president of Myochikai Kyodan (religious group), said so in the paper of &quot;Chugai Nippo,&quot; when Shinjo, the head of the organization, died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>昭和の仏師</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Busshi (Sculptor of Buddhist Statues) of Showa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Busshi (Sculptor of Buddhist Statues) of Showa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Busshi (Sculptor of Buddhist Statues) of Showa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="117">
<j>真如苑の本尊など、多くの仏像は真乗自身の手による謹刻である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many Buddha statues, such as honzon (principal images of Buddha) were made by Shinjo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many Buddha statues, such as honzon (principal images of Buddha) were made by Shinjo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many Buddha statues, such as honzon (principal images of Buddha) were made by Shinjo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>しかし空海や日蓮以降、近代に至るまで宗祖の立場にある人物がこのように尊像を刻んだり描いたりしたことがほとんどなくなっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there had been few founder of a religious sect except Shinjo that engraved and painted statue of a noble character from the days of Kukai and Nichirenno until modern ages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there had been few founders of a religious sects except Shinjo that engraved and painted statues of noble characters from the days of Kukai and Nichirenno until modern ages.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there had been few founders of a religious sects except Shinjo that engraved and painted statues of noble characters from the days of Kukai and Nichirenno until modern ages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>昭和32年の接心道場の大涅槃像開眼式に招かれた新日本宗教団体連合会の大石秀典はこの点を指摘した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shuten OISHI of Federation of New Religious Organizations of Japan pointed out this, when he was invited to the dainehan-zo kaigan-shiki (Opening of the Eyes Ceremony of statue of Great Nirvana) held at Sesshin dojo (concentration hall (used for martial arts training)) in 1957.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shuten OISHI of Federation of New Religious Organizations of Japan pointed out this, when he was invited to the dainehan-zo kaigan-shiki (Opening of the Eyes Ceremony of statue of Great Nirvana) held at Sesshin dojo (concentration hall (used for martial arts training)) in 1957.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shuten OISHI of Federation of New Religious Organizations of Japan pointed out this, when he was invited to the dainehan-zo kaigan-shiki (Opening of the Eyes Ceremony of statue of Great Nirvana) held at Sesshin dojo (concentration hall (used for martial arts training)) in 1957.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>そのため宗教界から「昭和の仏師」などと称せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, Shinjo was called &quot;Busshi of Showa.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, Shinjo was called &quot;Busshi of Showa.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, Shinjo was called &apos;Busshi of Showa.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="121">
<j>仏師の松本明慶は、真乗作の仏像を「今までになかった眼。」と評価してた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myokei MATSUMOTO, a busshi, evaluated Buddha statues made by shinjo by saying, &quot;The eyes do not look like anything that I have ever seen. &quot;</e>
<cmt>」と言って評価した。を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myokei MATSUMOTO, a busshi, evaluated Buddha statues made by shinjo by saying, &quot;The eyes do not look like anything that I have ever seen. &quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myokei MATSUMOTO, a busshi, evaluated Buddha statues made by shinjo by saying, &quot;The eyes do not look like anything that I have ever seen. &quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>また「仏の意味あいの姿が表現されているから高い評価を受けるのだと思う。」とも述べた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also said, &quot;Those statues are highly appreciated because what people expect of the figure of Buddha is expressed in them.&quot;</e>
<cmt>また、「」述べた、を加えました。仏の意味あいの姿,は「仏に人々が求めるもの」と意訳してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also said, &quot;Those statues are highly appreciated because what people expect of the figure of Buddha is expressed in them.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also said, &quot;Those statues are highly appreciated because what people expect of the figure of Buddha is expressed in them.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>「我々職人の作るものとは違うし、やっと私が境地に入ったところをもうすでに感じとられて作っておられたということに驚愕する」と評している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also commented, &quot;Those statues are different from what our experts make and I am astonished that he already felt a state of mind that I finally attained with difficulty in making those statues.</e>
<cmt>２文を1文にしてあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also commented, &quot;Those statues are different from what our experts make and I am astonished that he already felt a state of mind that I finally attained with difficulty in making those statues.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also commented, &quot;Those statues are different from what our experts make and I am astonished that he already felt a state of mind that I finally attained with difficulty in making those statues.&quot;</e>
<cmt>文末に&quot;を加えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>年譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chronological Record</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chronological Record</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chronological Record</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="124">
<j>1906(明治39)年、3月28日に、伊藤文二郎・よしえの二男として出生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 28, he was born to be the second son between Bunjiro ITO and Yoshie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 28, he was born the second son of Bunjiro ITO and Yoshie.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born as the second son of Bunjiro ITO and Yoshie on March 28, 1906.</e>
<cmt>1906, asを加え、日付を文末に移動させました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>（6人兄弟姉妹の３番目）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(He was the third child among six brothers and sisters.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(He was the third child among six brothers and sisters.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(He was the third child among six brothers and sisters.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="126">
<j>1923(大正12)年、苦学を志し上京。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1923, he left for Tokyo for studying hard.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1923, he left for Tokyo for studying hard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1923, he left for Tokyo for studying hard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>中央電信局(現日本電信電話）の購買部に勤務するかたわら夜学に励む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He studied hard in the evening while he worked for the purchase department of Chuo Denshin Kyoku (Central Telegraph Office) (present-day Nippon Telegraph and Telephone Corporation)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He studied hard in the evening while he worked for the purchase department of Chuo Denshin Kyoku (Central Telegraph Office) (present-day Nippon Telegraph and Telephone Corporation)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He studied hard in the evening while he worked for the purchase department of Chuo Denshin Kyoku (present Central Telegraph Office) Nippon Telegraph and Telephone Corporation, as of now).</e>
<cmt>present-dayをpresentに変更しました。文末にピリオドを打ちました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="128">
<j>1924（T13)年、正則英語学校（現正則学園）の普通科に入学。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1924, he entered a general course of Seisoku English School (present-day Seisoku-gakuen School).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1924, he entered a general course for Seisoku English School (present-day Seisoku-gakuen School).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1924, he entered a general course for Seisoku English School (present Seisoku-gakuen School).</e>
<cmt>present-dayをpresentに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="129">
<j>1925(T14)年、高等科に進学するが、１ヶ月後、規則により高等科を退学し青年訓練所に入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1925, a month after he went to an advanced course, he had to left school because of the school rule and entered seinen kunrensho (Young Men&apos;s Military Training Corps).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1925, a month after he went to an advanced course, he had to leave school because of a school rule and entered seinen kunrensho (Young Men&apos;s Military Training Corps).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He went to an advanced course in 1925, but one month later, he had to leave school because of a school rule and entered seinen kunrensho (Young Men&apos;s Military Training Corps).</e>
<cmt>一部、翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>また電信局の購買部を退社し写真機材店に勤務。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He quitted the purchase department of Chuo Denshin Kyoku amd started work for a photographic apparatus shop.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He quit the purchase department of Chuo Denshin Kyoku and started work for a photographic apparatus shop.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He quit the purchase department of Chuo Denshin Kyoku and started work for a photographic apparatus shop.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="131">
<j>1927(昭和2)年、大正15年の徴集兵により、立川の近衛飛行第5連隊に入隊、写真科に編入。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1927, he joioned Konoe hiko dai 5 renrai (the Fifth Regiment of Imperial Guards aviation) according to the order for calling up in 1926 and assigned to photograph department.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1927, he joined Konoe hiko dai 5 renrai (the Fifth Regiment of Imperial Guards aviation) according to the order for calling up in 1926 and assigned to the photograph department.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1927, he joined Konoe hiko dai 5 rentai (the Fifth Regiment of Imperial Guards aviation) according to the order for calling up in 1926 and assigned to the photograph department.</e>
<cmt>renraiをrentaiに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="132">
<j>1928(S3)年、12月10日に軍隊を除隊。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 10, he was discharged from military service.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 10, he was discharged from military service.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was discharged from military service on December 10, 1928.</e>
<cmt>1928を加え、日時を文末に移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="133">
<j>1929(S4)年、1月中旬に石川島飛行機の技術部に勤務。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the middle of January, 1929, he started to work for the engineering department of the Ishikawajima Aircraft Manufacturing Company.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the middle of January, 1929, he started to work for the engineering department of the Ishikawajima Aircraft Manufacturing Company.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the middle of January, 1929, he started to work for the engineering department of the Ishikawajima Aircraft Manufacturing Company.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>同僚との縁から浄土教学や易学、日蓮宗や法華経などを研鑚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He started to study the Jodo Sect, art of divination, Nichiren school of Buddhism, and Hokekyo (Lotus Sutra) with an influence of his colleague.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He started to study the Jodo Sect, art of divination, Nichiren school of Buddhism, and Hokekyo (Lotus Sutra) with an influence of his colleague.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He started to study the Jodo Sect, art of divination, Nichiren school of Buddhism, and Hokekyo (Lotus Sutra) with an influence of his colleague.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="135">
<j>1932(S７）年　内田友司（のちの伊藤友司）と結婚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1932, he got married with Tomoji UCHIDA (later Tomoji ITO).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1932, he got married with Tomoji UCHIDA (later Tomoji ITO).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1932, he got married with Tomoji UCHIDA (later Tomoji ITO).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>真乗と友司は同郷で、またいとこの間柄であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinojo and Tomoji came from the same village and second cousins of each other.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinojo and Tomoji came from the same village and second cousins of each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinojo and Tomoji came from the same village and second cousins of each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>お互いの家系に伝わる宗教的背景を感得し、次第に仏教を研鑚する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were inspired by each other&apos;s religious background handed down to each family line and gradually studied Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were inspired by each other&apos;s religious background handed down to each family line and gradually studied Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were inspired by each other&apos;s religious background handed down to each family line and gradually studied Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="138">
<j>1935（S11）年に、大日大聖不動明王を勧請、友司と共に宗教専従の道に立つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1935, he called up and infused the spirit of the statue of Dainichi Daisho Fudo Myoo, and get engaged in shukyosenju (working exclusively for religion) with Tomoji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1935, he called up and infused the spirit of the statue of Dainichi Daisho Fudo Myoo, and get engaged in shukyosenju (working exclusively for religion) with Tomoji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1935, he called up and infused the spirit of the statue of Dainichi Daisho Fudo Myoo, and get engaged in shukyosenju (working exclusively for religion) with Tomoji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>同年5月、真言宗醍醐派総本山醍醐寺（京都市）にて出家得度。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May of the same year, he entered the the priesthood to become a monk at Daigo-ji Temple of the headquarters of Shingon-shu Diago sect (Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May of the same year, he entered the the priesthood to become a monk at Daigo-ji Temple of the headquarters of Shingon-shu Diago sect (Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May of the same year, he entered the priesthood to become a monk at Daigo-ji Temple of the headquarters of Shingon-shu Diago sect (Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>重複していたtheを一つ取りました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="140">
<j>1936（S11）年、不動明王の縁から真言宗成田山新勝寺の講中として成田山立川立照講を設立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1936, he established Naritasan tachikawa tachisho ko ((Buddhist) lecture meeting of Naritasan tachikawa tachisho) as the kochu (religious groups) of Naritasan Shinsho-ji Temple of Shingon sect in association with Fudo Myoo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1936, he established Naritasan tachikawa tachisho ko ((Buddhist) lecture meeting of Naritasan tachikawa tachisho) as the kochu (religious groups) of Naritasan Shinsho-ji Temple of Shingon sect in association with Fudo Myoo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1936, he established Naritasan tachikawa tachisho ko ((Buddhist) lecture meeting of Naritasan tachikawa tachisho) as the kochu (religious groups) of Naritasan Shinsho-ji Temple of Shingon sect in association with Fudo Myoo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="141">
<j>1938（S13）年、鐙檠山真澄寺を建立、「真言宗醍醐派・立川不動尊教会」と改称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1938, he established Tokeizan Shincho-ji Temple and changed its name to &quot;Shingon sect Daigoha school, Tachikawa Fudoson Kyokai.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1938, he established Tokeizan Shincho-ji Temple and changed its name to &quot;Shingon sect Daigoha school, Tachikawa Fudoson Kyokai.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1938, he established Tokeizan Shincho-ji Temple and changed its name to &apos;Shingon sect Daigoha school, Tachikawa Fudoson Kyokai.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="142">
<j>1939（S14）年、醍醐寺にて在家の大法である恵印灌頂を法畢する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1939, at Daigo-ji Temple, he completed the teachings of Ein Kanjo (the ceremony to be the successor of a ritual of the Ein School), Daiho (great traditions of Esoteric practices) for lay believers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1939, at Daigo-ji Temple, he completed the teachings of Ein Kanjo (the ceremony to be the successor of a ritual of the Ein School), Daiho (great traditions of Esoteric practices) for lay believers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1939, at Daigo-ji Temple, he completed the teachings of Ein Kanjo (the ceremony to be the successor of a ritual of the Ein School), Daiho (great traditions of Esoteric practices) for lay believers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="143">
<j>1941（S18）年、醍醐寺にて出家の大法である金胎両部伝法灌頂を法畢し、大阿闍梨となるが、醍醐寺の座主を目指すことなく自身の教団運営と教法の確立に専念。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1941, at Daigo-ji Temple, he completed the teachings of Kintai-ryobu denpo-kanjo, Daiho (great traditions of Esoteric practices) for priests to become Great Ajari, but he devoted himself to the management of his own religious sect and the establishment of his own teachings without aiming to become zasu(temple&apos;s head priest)of Daigo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1941, at Daigo-ji Temple, he completed the teachings of Kintai-ryobu denpo-kanjo, Daiho (great traditions of Esoteric practices) for priests to become Great Ajari, but he devoted himself to the management of his own religious sect and the establishment of his own teachings without aiming to become zasu(temple&apos;s head priest)of Daigo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1941, at Daigo-ji Temple, he completed the teachings of Kintai-ryobu denpo-kanjo, Daiho (great traditions of Esoteric practices) for priests to become Great Ajari, but he devoted himself to the management of his own religious sect and the establishment of his own teachings without aiming to become zasu (temple&apos;s head priest) of Daigo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>（temple&apos;s head priest）の前後にスペースを空けました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>戦後、真言宗から独立して「まこと教団」を設立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After World War Two, he became independent from the Shingon sect and established &quot;Makoto religious organization.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After World War Two, he became independent from the Shingon sect and established &quot;Makoto religious organization.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After World War II, he became independent from the Shingon sect and established &apos;Makoto religious organization.&apos;</e>
<cmt>twoをIIに変更しました。&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="145">
<j>1950（S25）年、以前の内弟子が告訴し、真乗逮捕。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1950, Shinjo was arrested on an accusation of his former private pupil. (accused him and</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1950, Shinjo was arrested on an accusation of his former private pupil.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1950, Shinjo was arrested on an accusation of his former private pupil.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>（「まこと教団事件」発生）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(&quot;Makoto kyodan jiken (Makoto religious organization incidence)&quot; occurred.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(&quot;Makoto kyodan jiken (Makoto religious organization incidence)&quot; occurred.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(&apos;Makoto kyodan jiken (Makoto religious organization incidence)&apos; occurred.)</e>
<cmt>&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="147">
<j>1952（S26）年、「まこと教団」を「真如苑」と改称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1952, the name of &quot;Makoto religious organization&quot; was changed to &quot;Shinnyoen Buddhist.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1952, the name of &quot;Makoto religious organization&quot; was changed to &quot;Shinnyoen Buddhist.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1952, the name of &apos;Makoto religious organization&apos; was changed to &apos;Shinnyoen Buddhist.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>かねてから研鑚していた大般涅槃経を根本経典として教団の新体制を発足。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He established the new system of the religious organization on the basis of the Nirvana Sutra he had studied long as nemoto scriptures</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He established the new system of the religious organization on the basis of the Nirvana Sutra he had studied long as nemoto scriptures</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He established the new system of the religious organization on the basis of the Nirvana Sutra he had studied long as Konpon kyoten (primal scripture).</e>
<cmt>nemoto scripturesをKonpon kyoten (primal scripture).と変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="149">
<j>1953（S28）年、新たに施行された宗教法人法のもと、文部省が宗教法人として「真如苑」を認証。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1953, &quot;Shinnyoen Buddhist&quot; was authorized as a religious organization by Ministry of Education under newly enforced Religious Corporation Act.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1953, &quot;Shinnyoen Buddhist&quot; was authorized as a religious organization by Ministry of Education under newly enforced Religious Corporation Act.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1953, &apos;Shinnyoen Buddhist&apos; was authorized as a religious organization by Ministry of Education under newly enforced Religious Corporation Act.</e>
<cmt>&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="150">
<j>1957（S32）年、本尊となる久遠常住釈迦牟尼如来（大涅槃尊像）を謹刻。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1957, he made Kuonshochushakamuninyorai (kind of statue) (Dai nehan sonzo (statue of great Nirvana), the principal image.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1957, he made Kuonshochushakamuninyorai (kind of statue) (Dai nehan sonzo (statue of great Nirvana), the principal image.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1957, he made Kuonshochushakamuninyorai (kind of statue) (Dai nehan sonzo (statue of great Nirvana), the principal image.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="151">
<j>1966（S41）年3月、祖山醍醐寺から大僧正位を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March 1966, he received the title of Daiso Jyoi from Shisoyama Daigo-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March 1966, he received the title of Daiso Jyoi from Shisoyama Daigo-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March 1966, he received the title of Daiso Jyoi from Shisoyama Daigo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>文末にピリオドを打ちました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>11月、タイ王国国で開催された「第8回世界仏教徒会議」に日本仏教界代表として出席。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November, he attended &quot;the Second World Fellowship of Buddhists&quot; held in Kingdom of Thailand as a representative of Japanese Buddhist Society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November, he attended &quot;the Second World Fellowship of Buddhists&quot; held in the Kingdom of Thailand as a representative of Japanese Buddhist Society.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November, he attended &apos;The Second World Fellowship of Buddhists&apos; held in the Kingdom of Thailand as a representative of Japanese Buddhist Society.</e>
<cmt>&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。theをTheに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="153">
<j>1967（S42）年、「欧州宗教交流国際親善使節団」団長としてヨーロッパ8カ国を歴訪、ローマ法王パウロ6世と会見し涅槃像を贈る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1967, he visited eight European countries as the head of European religious communication international goodwill envoy and met Pope Paul VI, and gave Nehanzo (an image of the Buddha immediately after his death).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1967, he visited eight European countries as the head of European religious communication international goodwill envoy and met Pope Paul VI, and gave Nehanzo (an image of the Buddha immediately after his death).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1967, he visited eight European countries as the head of &apos;European religious communication international goodwill envoy&apos; and met Pope Paul VI, and gave Nehanzo (an image of the Buddha immediately after his death).</e>
<cmt>を入れました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="154">
<j>1970（S45）年、アメリカ合衆国カリフォルニア州モンテベロ市に寄贈した聖徳太子像の贈呈式が行われ名誉市民となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1970, a presentation ceremony for Shotoku Taishi zo (Statue of Prince Shotoku) donated by him was held in Montebello City, California, United States of America, where he was given its hornor citizen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1970, a presentation ceremony for Shotoku Taishi zo (Statue of Prince Shotoku) donated by him was held in Montebello City, California, United States of America, where he was made an honorary citizen.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1970, a presentation ceremony for Shotoku Taishi zo (Statue of Prince Shotoku) donated by him was held in Montebello City, California, United States of America, where he was made an honorary citizen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="155">
<j>1979（S54）年、発祥第二精舎落慶　本尊十一面観世音菩薩入仏開眼法要を厳修。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1979, he made Honzon Juichimen Kanzeon Bosatsu nyubutsukaigan hoyo (Buddhist memorial service of enshrining a Buddhist image and opening eyes of 11 faced Buddhist Goddess of Mercy) for the celebration of the construction of the second Shoja temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1979, he made Honzon Juichimen Kanzeon Bosatsu nyubutsukaigan hoyo (Buddhist memorial service of enshrining a Buddhist image and opening eyes of 11 faced Buddhist Goddess of Mercy) for the celebration of the construction of the second Shoja temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1979, he made Honzon Juichimen Kanzeon Bosatsu nyubutsukaigan hoyo (Buddhist memorial service of enshrining a Buddhist image and opening eyes of 11 faced Buddhist Goddess of Mercy) for the celebration of the construction of the second Shoja temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="156">
<j>1979（S54）年、「真如苑宗教交流親善使節団」として欧州5カ国を巡教。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1979, he visited five European countries as &quot;Shinnyoen Buddhist religious communication good will envoy&quot; for preachment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1979, he visited five European countries as &quot;Shinnyoen Buddhist religious communication good will envoy&quot; for preachment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1979, he visited five European countries as &apos;Shinnyoen Buddhist religious communication good will envoy&apos; for preachment.</e>
<cmt>&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="157">
<j>1984（S59）年、醍醐寺の命を承け、金堂において教主導師により弘法大師御入定一千百五十年御遠忌法要を執行。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1984, he was asked by Daigo-ji Temple to conduct the ceremony for the 1150 anniversary of Kobo Daishi&apos;s &quot;Nyujo&quot; (falling into deep meditation).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1984, he was asked by Daigo-ji Temple to conduct the ceremony for the 1150 anniversary of Kobo Daishi&apos;s &quot;Nyujo&quot; (falling into deep meditation).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1984, he was asked by Daigo-ji Temple to conduct the ceremony for the 1150 years anniversary of Kobo Daishi&apos;s &quot;Nyujo&quot; (falling into deep meditation).</e>
<cmt>yearsを挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="158">
<j>1989（H1）年、7月19日（午前0時23分）遷化。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 19, 1989, he died (at 0:23) at the age of 83.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 19, 1989, he died (at 0:23) at the age of 83.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 19, 1989, he died (at 0:23).</e>
<cmt>at the age of 83を除きました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>享年83。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was died at the age of 83.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 83.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Died at the age of 83.</e>
<cmt>Heを除きました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>醍醐寺より「真如教主金剛身院常住救鳳真乗大本位」の法号が贈られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was given hogo (a Buddhist name) of &quot;真如教主金剛身院常住救鳳真乗大本位&quot; by Daigo-ji Temple．</e>
<cmt>「真如教主金剛身院常住救鳳真乗大本位」　読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was given hogo (a Buddhist name) of &quot;真如教主金剛身院常住救鳳真乗大本位&quot; by Daigo-ji Temple．</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was given hogo (a Buddhist name) of &apos;真如教主金剛身院常住救鳳真乗大本位&apos; by Daigo-ji Temple．</e>
<cmt>&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tommy6-bot(id:171289), MikeAz800o(id:58193), BOTarate(id:185620), 蒲生直義(id:235164), 0null0(id:582), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Cprobot(id:97843), ブリキの太鼓叩き(id:3586), Makotozushi(id:4545), Call Tenderas(id:169753), Nakadati(id:26815), Boca samba(id:137526), R28Bot(id:177951), Fumisha(id:103507), Toki-ho(id:10691), きまま(id:183217), Bankokuya(id:91191), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>