<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>善如</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zennyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zennyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zennyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>善如（ぜんにょ）は、南北朝時代 (日本)の浄土真宗の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zennyo was a monk of Jodo shin shu (True Pure Land Sect Buddhism) during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts. (Japan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zennyo was a monk of Jodo shin shu (the True Pure Land sect of Buddhism) during the Northern and Southern Courts period (Japan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zennyo was a monk of Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は従覚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Jukaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Jukaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Jukaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>本願寺四世。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fourth head of Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the fourth head of Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the fourth head of Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>本ページでは、暦の正確性、著作との整合を保つ為、旧暦表示とし、南北朝時代の元号は、北朝（京都）で表記する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this page it is shown in the old calendar style for the accuracy of the calendar and to keep the coordination with the book, the name of a Japanese era is shown in Northern dynasty style. (Kyoto)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this page it is shown in the old calendar style for the sake of the accuracy of the calendar, and to maintain coordination with the book, the name of a Japanese era is shown in style of the Northern Dynasty (Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this page it is shown in the old calendar style for the sake of the accuracy of the calendar, and to maintain coordination with the book, the name of a Japanese era of the period of the Northern and Southern Courts is shown in style of the Northern Dynasty (Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>正慶2年2月2日（1333年2月24日）、生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born on 24 February, 1333.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born on February 24, 1333.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born on February 2, 1333 (February 24, 1333 in new calendar).</e>
<cmt>10行目セルに「旧暦で表示」とありますが、括弧に新暦がありましたので、どちらも記載しております。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>幼い頃より京都青蓮院にて天台の教えを学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He learned the Tendai sect at Shoren-in Temple since his childhood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had studied the Tendai sect at Shoren-in Temple since his childhood.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had studied the Tendai sect at Shoren-in Temple since his childhood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>観応元年（1350年）、覚如より本願寺別当職を継承。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1350 he succeeded the position of Betto shoku of Hongan-ji Temple from Kakunyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1350 he succeeded the position of Betto shoku of Hongan-ji Temple from Kakunyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1350 he succeeded the position of Betto shoku of Hongan-ji Temple from Kakunyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>延文4年（1359年）には、存覚に歎徳文の再編を依頼、それ移行、報恩講で読まれることになったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1359 he asked Zonkaku to reorganize 歎徳文, and since then it is said it was decided to be read at Hon-ko. (a memorial services for Shinran)</e>
<cmt>歎徳文→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1359, he asked Zonkaku to reorganize 歎徳文, and since then it has been said that it was decided to be read at Hon-ko (a memorial service for Shinran).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1359, he asked Zonkaku to reorganize Tandokumon (In Praise of the Virtue (of the Venerable Master Shinran)), and since then it has been said that it was decided to be read at Hoon-ko (a memorial service for Shinran).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="9">
<j>康応元年2月29日（1389年4月4日）、57歳（数え年）にて死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died on April 4, 1389 when he was fifty seven years old. (counting in the old Japanese way)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died on April 4, 1389, when he was 57 years old (as counted the old Japanese way).</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died on February 29, 1389 (April 4, 1389 in new calendar), when he was 57 years old (as counted the old Japanese way).</e>
<cmt>10行目セルに「旧暦で表示」とありますが、括弧に新暦がありましたので、どちらも記載しております。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Resto1578(id:168692), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), R28Bot(id:177951), 松茸(id:27535), 水野白楓(id:22811), 調声人(id:126495), Suika(id:10985), Pack372sd(id:191577), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>