<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>池坊専慶</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senkei IKENOBO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senkei IKENOBO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senkei IKENOBO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>池坊 専慶（いけのぼう せんけい、生没年不詳）は、室町時代中期の京都頂法寺（六角堂）池坊の僧侶。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senkei IKENOBO (the date of his birth and death is not clear) was a Buddhist priest of Kyoto Choho-ji Temple (Rokkakudo) who was active in the middle of Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senkei IKENOBO (the dates of his birth and death are not clear) was a Buddhist priest of Kyoto Choho-ji Temple (Rokkakudo) who was active in the middle of the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senkei IKENOBO (the dates of his birth and death were unknown) was a Buddhist priest of Kyoto Choho-ji Temple (Rokkakudo) in the middle of the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>文明 (日本)年間（1469年-1487年）立花（たてばな）の上手として有名となり、京都東福寺の僧月渓聖澄による「百瓶華序」（1600年に成立）によると池坊の流祖とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became famous during the period from 1469 till 1487 as a superior of Tatebana and according to &quot;Hyakubinkajo&quot; (completed in 1600) compiled by Shocho GEKKEI, a buddhist monk of Kyoto Tofuku-ji Temple, he is deemed as the founder of Ikenobo school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became famous during the period from 1469 until 1487 as a superior of Tatebana and according to &quot;Hyakubinkajo&quot; (completed in 1600) compiled by Shocho GEKKEI, a buddhist monk of Kyoto Tofuku-ji Temple, he is deemed as the founder of Ikenobo school.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became famous during the period from 1469 until 1487 as a superior of Tatebana (standing flowers) and according to &apos;Hyakuhei Kanojo&apos; (records of flower arrangement by a hundred people) (completed in 1600) compiled by Shocho GEKKEI, a Buddhist monk of Kyoto Tofuku-ji Temple, he is deemed as the founder of Ikenobo School.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>禅僧大極が記した「碧山日録」（1459年-1463年、1465年-1468年）によれば、1462年（寛正3年）近江国守護佐々木氏に招かれて金瓶に草花数十枝を挿し、洛中の好事家が競って見物したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;hekisannichiroku&quot; (1459 - 1464, 1465 - 1468) written by Zen priest Taikyoku, Senkei in 1462 arranged tens of flowers in a golden vase responding to the invitation of Sasaki clan, shugo (constable) of Omi-no-Kuni, and many of dilettantes inside the capital competed in seeing it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;hekisannichiroku&quot; (1459 - 1464, 1465 - 1468) written by Zen priest Taikyoku, Senkei in 1462 arranged tens of flowers in a golden vase responding to the invitation of the Sasaki clan, shugo (constable) of Omi-no-Kuni, and many of the dilettantes inside the capital competed to see it.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &apos;Hekizan Nichiroku&apos; (a diary of the monk Daikyoku, 15th century) (1459 - 1464, 1465 - 1468) written by Zen priest Daikyoku, Senkei in 1462 arranged tens of flowers in a golden vase responding to the invitation of the Sasaki clan, shugo (constable) of Omi Province, and many of the dilettantes inside the capital competed to see it.</e>
<cmt>用語補足、変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Izayohi(id:13095), 代言人(id:33675), Kstigarbha(id:13376), R28Bot(id:177951), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>