<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>賦算</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fusan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fusan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fusan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>賦算（ふさん）とは浄土系仏教の一派時宗において「南無阿弥陀仏、決定往生六十万人」と記した札を配ることである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fusan means a distribution of ofuda (paper charms) written with &quot;南無阿弥陀仏、決定往生六十万人&quot; in Ji sect, one of Pure Land sects of the Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fusan is the distribution of ofuda (paper charms) on which the words &quot;南無阿弥陀仏、決定往生六十万人&quot; are written, practised in the Ji sect, a Pure Land sect of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, changed for clarity. A loose translation of 南無阿弥陀仏、決定往生六十万人 would be helpful for the reader, I think.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fusan is the distribution of ofuda (paper charms) on which the words &apos;南無阿弥陀仏、決定往生六十万人&apos; are written, practiced in the Ji sect, a Pure Land sect of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>一遍が熊野権現の神勅に基づいて始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ippen started it based on an oracle of Kumano Gongen Deity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was started by Ippen based on an oracle of the Kumano Gongen deity.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was started by Ippen based on an oracle of the Kumano Gongen deity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>これと踊念仏によって時宗は鎌倉時代から室町時代にかけて大いに発展した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ji sect greatly evolved from Kamakura Period to Muromachi Period because of fusan and odori-nenbutsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ji sect greatly evolved between the Kamakura Period and the Muromachi Period because of both fusan and odori-nenbutsu.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ji sect greatly evolved between the Kamakura period and the Muromachi period because of both fusan and odori-nenbutsu.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 小太刀(id:18154), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>