<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>三代相論</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sandai Soron</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sandai Soron</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sandai Soron</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>三代相論（さんだいそうろん）は、文永4年（1267年）からおよそ50年間にわたった曹洞宗内の宗門対立の総称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sandai Soron is a general name for religious conflict in Soto sect which started in 1267 and lasted for about fifty years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sandai Soron is a general name for a religious conflict in the Soto sect, which started in 1267 and lasted for about 50 years.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sandai Soron is a general name for a religious conflict in the Soto sect, which started in 1267 and lasted for about 50 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>開祖道元の遺風を遵守する保守派と民衆教化を重視した改革派の対立とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is regarded as a conflict between conservatives, who comply the relic teaching of Dogen, the founder of the sect, and reformists, who put more importance on propagation among the common people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is regarded as a conflict between conservatives, who complied with the relic teachings of the sect&apos;s founder Dogen, and reformists, who attached more importance to propagation among the common people.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is regarded as a conflict between conservatives, who complied with the relic teachings of the sect&apos;s founder Dogen, and reformists, who attached more importance to propagation among the common people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>永平寺3世義介の就任から退任までを1期、義介の再任と再退任までを2期、後に義介を3世と認めるか否かで生じた対立を3期とする見方がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sometimes, the period in which Gikai was appointed as the third chief priest of Eihei-ji Temple through his resign is regarded as the first period, the period in which Gikai was re-appointed and was resigned again is regarded as the second period, and the period in which a conflict arose whether or not to accept Gikai as the third head priest in the later years is regarded as the third period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Occasionally, the period in which Gikai was appointed as the third chief priest of Eihei-ji Temple through his resign is regarded as the first period, the period in which Gikai was reappointed and again resigned is regarded as the second period, and the period in which a conflict arose in the later years as to whether to accept Gikai as the third head priest is regarded as the third period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Occasionally, the period in which Gikai was appointed as the third chief priest of Eihei-ji Temple through his resign is regarded as the first period, the period in which Gikai was reappointed and again resigned is regarded as the second period, and the period in which a conflict arose in the later years as to whether to accept Gikai as the third head priest is regarded as the third period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>第1期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>曹洞宗の開祖道元が建長5年（1253年）8月に入寂すると、弟子の孤雲懐奘が永平寺住職を継ぎ、曹洞宗2祖となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Dogen, the founder of the Soto sect, died in September of 1253, his disciple, Koun Ejo, succeeded the position of the chief priest of Eihei-ji Temple and became as the second head priest of the Soto sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Dogen died in September 1253, his disciple Koun Ejo succeeded to the position of chief priest of Eihei-ji Temple and became the second head priest of the Soto sect.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Dogen died in September 1253, his disciple Koun Ejo succeeded to the position of chief priest of Eihei-ji Temple and became the second head priest of the Soto sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>当時の曹洞宗僧団は、道元の宋 (王朝)からの帰朝以来の直弟子達と京都深草に興聖寺を開いた後に日本達磨宗から集団改宗した一派の2流があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were 2 groups in the Soto sect at that time, a group of direct disciples of Dogen after he came back from Sung (dynasty), and a group of priests who converted to the Soto sect form the Nihon Daruma sect in a group after Dogen established Kosho-ji Temple at Fukakusa, Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were two groups in the Soto sect at that time: a group of direct disciples of Dogen after he came back from the Sung (dynasty), and a group of priests who converted to the Soto sect from the Nihon Daruma sect as a group after Dogen established Kosho-ji Temple at Fukakusa, Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were two groups in the Soto sect at that time: a group of direct disciples of Dogen after he came back from the Sung (dynasty), and a group of priests who converted to the Soto sect from the Nihon Daruma sect as a group after Dogen established Kosho-ji Temple at Fukakusa, Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>懐奘は日本達磨宗の法系に属する人であったが温厚篤実で両派の融和調停に尽力したため、両派の軋轢は表面化する事がなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ejo belonged to the group of the Nihon Daruma sect, but since he was courteous and sincere, he made effort to make harmony and mediate the 2 groups and the conflict between the 2 groups didn&apos;t come out on the surface.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ejo belonged to the group of the Nihon Daruma sect, but since he was courteous and sincere he endeavored to achieve harmony and mediate the two groups; consequently, the conflict between the groups didn&apos;t rise to the surface.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ejo belonged to the group of the Nihon Daruma sect, but since he was courteous and sincere he endeavored to achieve harmony and mediate the two groups; consequently, the conflict between the groups didn&apos;t rise to the surface.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>懐奘は道元の遺風を忠実に守る一方で永平寺の伽藍、規矩の整備に着手し、法甥にあたる徹通義介を弘長2年（1262年）に宋に派遣し調査、資料の将来にあたらせている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On one hand Ejo faithfully complied the relic of Dogen, and on the other hand, he constructed the cathedral and established rules of the Eihei-ji Temple, sending Gikai TETTSU, his 法甥, to Sung to collect researches and documents in 1262.</e>
<cmt>法甥→読み、定訳不明です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ejo, on one hand, faithfully complied with the relic of Dogen, but on the other hand he constructed the cathedral and established the rules of Eihei-ji Temple, sending Gikai TETTSU, his 法甥, to Sung to collect research and documents in 1262.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ejo, on one hand, faithfully complied with the relic of Dogen, but on the other hand he constructed the cathedral and established the rules of Eihei-ji Temple, sending Gikai TETTSU, his priestly nephew, to Sung to collect research and documents in 1262.</e>
<cmt>法甥→「宗派上の甥」と考え、priestly nephewとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="10">
<j>文永4年（1267年）、懐奘が退任を決意すると整備改革のさらなる推進を図る義介と遺風遵守を第一とする義演のいずれを後任とするかで対立が生じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Ejo decided to resign in 1267, a conflict arose whether Gikai, who planned to advance the maintenance and restructuring, or Gien, who regarded the compliance of the relic as the primal duty, should succeed the position of the head priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Ejo decided to resign in 1267, a conflict arose as to whether Gikai, who planned to proceed with maintenance and restructuring, or Gien, who regarded the compliance with the relic as the primal duty, should succeed the position as head priest.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Ejo decided to resign in 1267, a conflict arose as to whether Gikai, who planned to proceed with maintenance and restructuring, or Gien, who regarded the compliance with the relic as the primal duty, should succeed the position as head priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>結局、義介が永平寺3世・曹洞宗3世となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Gikai became as the third chief priest of the Eihei-ji Temple and the third head priest of the Soto sect.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処置です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Gikai became as the third chief priest of Eihei-ji Temple and the third head priest of the Soto sect.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Gikai became as the third chief priest of Eihei-ji Temple and the third head priest of the Soto sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし急速な革新に対する反発は次第に高まり義介の定めた行持に従わない者が続出するなどして、ついに文永9年（1272年）2月に義介は退任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, repulse against the rapid restructuring arose gradually, and ones who does not practice the activities decided by Gikai appeared one after another, making Gikai resign in between March - April, 1272 (February 1272 in old lunar calendar).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, repulse against the rapid restructuring arose gradually, and those who did not practice the activities decided by Gikai appeared one after another, compelling Gikai to resign in the period of March to April of 1272 (February 1272 in the old lunar calendar).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, repulse against the rapid restructuring arose gradually, and those who did not practice the activities decided by Gikai appeared one after another, compelling Gikai to resign in the period of March to April of 1272.</e>
<cmt>旧暦の表記は不要と考え削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="13">
<j>第2期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>義介が退任した後、懐奘が再任するが弘安3年（1280年）に入寂する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Gikai resigned, Ejo was re-appointed, but died in 1280.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Gikai resigned, Ejo was reappointed, but he died in 1280.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Gikai resigned, Ejo was reappointed, but he died in 1280.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>再び後任問題が持ち上がるが保守派からは人を得ず、懐奘の遺志により義介が再び永平寺に入ることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The problem of the successor arose again, but since there was no right person in the conservative group and from the wish of Ejo, Gikai was re-appointed in the Eihei-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The problem of choosing a successor arose again, but there was no right person in the conservative group so, based on the wish of Ejo, Gikai was reappointed in Eihei-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The problem of choosing a successor arose again, but there was no right person in the conservative group so, based on the wish of Ejo, Gikai was reappointed in Eihei-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="16">
<j>義介は自ら定めた行持を古規に戻すなど反対派との融和を図るが対立は深まる一方であり、7年後の弘安10年（1287年）永平寺を下山し加賀国大乗寺に移った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gikai tried to reconcile with the opposing group by changing rules he made to the old ones and so on, but since the conflict seems to be only deepen, after 7 years had past, in 1287, he left Eihei-ji Temple and moved to Daijo-ji Temple in Kaga Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gikai tried to reconcile with the opposing group by changing the rules he had made to the old ones and so on, but since the conflict seemed to deepen, in 1287, after seven years had passed, he left Eihei-ji Temple and moved to Daijo-ji Temple in Kaga Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gikai tried to reconcile with the opposing group by changing the rules he had made to the old ones and so on, but since the conflict seemed to deepen, in 1287, after seven years had passed, he left Eihei-ji Temple and moved to Daijo-ji Temple in Kaga Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>この時、義介に従う多くの弟子も大乗寺に移り、道元の法系は永平寺と大乗寺に分かれることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the occasion, many disciples who follow Gikai moved to Daijo-ji Temple, also, resulting in the division of Dogen&apos;s group into Eihei-ji Temple and Daijo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On that occasion, many disciples who followed Gikai moved to Daijo-ji Temple also, resulting in the division of Dogen&apos;s group into Eihei-ji Temple and Daijo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On that occasion, many disciples who followed Gikai moved to Daijo-ji Temple also, resulting in the division of Dogen&apos;s group into Eihei-ji Temple and Daijo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="18">
<j>第3期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The third period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The third period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The third period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="19">
<j>義介の下山後、義演が永平寺住職に就任したが論争による寺内の疲弊は甚だしく、また義演が開基波多野氏の信頼を得られなかったこともあって寺勢は急速に衰える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Gikai left, Gien was appointed as the chief priest of Eihei-ji Temple, but since the temple was impoverished by the conflict and also since Gien couldn&apos;t earn the trust of the Hatano clan, the Kaiki (patron of a temple in its founding) of the Soto clan, the power of the temple lowered rapidly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Gikai left, Gien was appointed as the chief priest of Eihei-ji Temple, but since the temple was impoverished due to the conflict and because Gien couldn&apos;t earn the trust of the Hatano clan, the Kaiki (patron of a temple in its founding) of the Soto clan, the power of the temple rapidly diminished.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Gikai left, Gien was appointed as the chief priest of Eihei-ji Temple, but since the temple was impoverished due to the conflict and because Gien couldn&apos;t earn the trust of the Hatano clan, the Kaiki (patron of a temple in its founding) of the Soto clan, the power of the temple rapidly diminished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>後に義演も退任し『日本洞上聯灯録』によれば小庵に閑居し再び世に出ることはなかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later Gien resigned, too, and according to &quot;Nihon Tojo rentoroku,&quot; he secluded in a small temple and never showed up again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eventually Gien resigned too, and according to &quot;Nihon Tojo rentoroku,&quot; he secluded himself in a small temple and never showed up again.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eventually Gien resigned too, and according to &quot;Nihon Tojo rentoroku,&quot; he secluded himself in a small temple and never showed up again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="21">
<j>永平寺はしばらく無住状態になったと思われるが、正和3年（1314年）10月に義演が入寂し義雲が後任になると、永平寺の世代（歴代住職）に義介を数えるか否かで再び論争が起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that there was no chief priest in Eihei-ji Temple for a while, but when Gien died and Giun succeeded the position in November - December, 1314 (October 1314 in old lunar calendar), a dispute arose whether or not to count Gikai as one of the successive chief priests of Eihei-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that there was no chief priest in Eihei-ji Temple for a while, but when Gien died and Giun succeeded the position in November or December of 1314 (October 1314 in the old lunar calendar), a dispute arose as to whether Gikai should be counted as one of the successive chief priests of Eihei-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that there was no chief priest in Eihei-ji Temple for a while, but when Gien died and Giun succeeded the position in November or December of 1314, a dispute arose as to whether Gikai should be counted as one of the successive chief priests of Eihei-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>旧暦は不要と考え削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>この論争は義介を3世として認める形で決着するが、それまで義介に与えられていた「中興」の尊称は取り下げられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This dispute settled by accepting Gikai as the third chief priest, but the honorable title &apos;Chuko&apos; (restorer) given to Gikai until then was withdrawn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This dispute was settled by accepting Gikai as the third chief priest, but the honorary title of &apos;Chuko&apos; (restorer) that Gikai had retained until then was withdrawn.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This dispute was settled by accepting Gikai as the third chief priest, but the honorary title of &apos;Chuko&apos; (restorer) that Gikai had retained until then was withdrawn.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>義介が正式に永平寺の世代に数えられたのは、さらに時代が下り江戸時代後期になってからとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is even a theory stating that it was later in the latter period of the Edo period that Gikai was officially counted as one of the successive chief priests of Eihei-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is even a theory that it was late in the Edo period that Gikai was officially counted as one of the successive chief priests of Eihei-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is even a theory that it was late in the Edo period that Gikai was officially counted as one of the successive chief priests of Eihei-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>備考</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Remarks</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Remarks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Remarks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>義介、義演は共に日本達磨宗の法系に属しており、対立は必ずしも道元直系派と日本達磨宗派の対立として割り切ることはできない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Gikai and Gien both belonged to the group of Nihon Daruma sect, the conflict can&apos;t simply be regarded as the conflict between the group under the direct lineage of Dogen and the group of Nihon Daruma sect.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処置です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Gikai and Gien both belonged to the group of the Nihon Daruma sect, the conflict shouldn&apos;t be regarded merely as a conflict between the group under the direct lineage of Dogen and the group of the Nihon Daruma sect.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Gikai and Gien both belonged to the group of the Nihon Daruma sect, the conflict shouldn&apos;t be regarded merely as a conflict between the group under the direct lineage of Dogen and the group of the Nihon Daruma sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>しかし義演が義介を非難する際に懐奘から道元禅と日本達磨宗の法統を重複して嗣法している点を挙げていることから、根底には両派の派閥対立の性格が認められる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since Gien pointed out that Gikai have redundantly made shiho (to inherit the dharma from a priest master) from Ejo the Zen of Dogen and the teaching of Nihon Daruma sect when he was criticizing Gikai, fundamentally, the characteristic as the conflict between the two groups can be seen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since Gien pointed out that Gikai had redundantly transformed shiho (to inherit the dharma from a priest master) from Ejo into the Zen of Dogen and the teaching of the Nihon Daruma sect when he was criticizing Gikai, fundamentally the characteristic as a conflict between the two groups can be seen.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since Gien pointed out that Gikai had redundantly transformed shiho (to inherit the dharma from a priest master) from Ejo into the Zen of Dogen and the teaching of the Nihon Daruma sect when he was criticizing Gikai, fundamentally the characteristic as a conflict between the two groups can be seen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Yanahan(id:2437), Straysheep(id:42448), Kstigarbha(id:13376), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>