<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>真如寺 (京都市北区)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinnyo-ji Temple (Kita Ward, Kyoto City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinnyo-ji Temple (Kita Ward, Kyoto City)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinnyo-ji Temple (Kita Ward, Kyoto City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>真如寺（しんにょじ）は、京都府京都市北区 (京都市)等持院北町に存在する臨済宗相国寺派の寺院である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shinnyo-ji Temple is a temple of the Shokoku-ji Temple school of the Rinzai sect, located in Tojiin Kitamachi, Kita Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture (Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinnyo-ji Temple, located in Tojiin Kitamachi, Kita Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture (Kyoto City) is a temple of the Shokoku-ji Temple school of the Rinzai sect.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinnyo-ji Temple, located in Tojiin Kitamachi, Kita Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture is a temple of the Shokoku-ji Temple school of the Rinzai sect.</e>
<cmt>(Kyoto City)削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>山号は万年山。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sango (literally, &quot;mountain name,&quot; which is the title prefixed to the name of a Buddhist temple) is Mannen-zan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its sango (literally, &quot;mountain name,&quot; the title prefixed to the name of a Buddhist temple) is Mannen-zan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its sango (literally, &quot;mountain name,&quot; the title prefixed to the name of a Buddhist temple) is Mannen-zan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>鹿苑寺・慈照寺とともに相国寺の3つの山外塔頭を構成する寺院の1つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shinnyo-ji Temple is one of the three sub-temples outside Shokoku-ji Temple site along with the Rokuon-ji Temple and the Jisho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinnyo-ji Temple is one of the three sub-temples outside the Shokoku-ji Temple site, along with the Rokuon-ji and Jisho-ji temples.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinnyo-ji Temple is one of the three sub-temples outside the Shokoku-ji Temple site, along with the Rokuon-ji and Jisho-ji temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>十刹第8位、後京都十刹第3位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was ranked the eighth in Jissatsu (ten important temples of Rinzai sect, second in significance to the Kyoto Gozan, Five Great Zen Temples of Kyoto), later becoming the third in Kyoto Jissatsu (ten great temples in Kyoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was once ranked eighth in the Jissatsu (ten important temples of Rinzai sect, second in significance to the Kyoto Gozan, or the Five Great Zen Temples of Kyoto), but later it became third in the Kyoto Jissatsu (ten great temples of Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was once ranked eighth in the Jissetsu (ten important temples of Rinzai sect, second in significance to the Kyoto Gozan, or the Five Great Zen Temples of Kyoto), but later it became third in the Kyoto Jissetsu (ten great temples of Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>開山は無学祖元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was founded by Sogen MUGAKU.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was founded by Sogen MUGAKU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was founded by Sogen MUGAKU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>無学祖元の死後の弘安9年（1286年）、彼を慕う如大尼（安達泰盛の娘・金沢顕時の妻で本名は千代野であると伝えられている）が無学の塔所として「正脈庵」と呼ばれる庵を築いたのが始まりとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Sogen MUGAKU in 1286, Nyotaini (she was considered Yasumori ADACHI&apos;s daughter and Akitoki KANAZAWA&apos;s wife; her real name was Chiyono), who adored Mugaku, built a hermitage called &quot;Shomyaku-an&quot; as his graveyard; that was probably a beginning of the Shinnyo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Sogen MUGAKU in 1286, Nyotaini (who was considered Yasumori ADACHI&apos;s daughter and Akitoki KANAZAWA&apos;s wife; her real name was Chiyono), who adored Mugaku, built a hermitage called &quot;Shomyaku-an&quot; as his graveyard, and this was probably the beginning of Shinnyo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Sogen MUGAKU in 1286, Nyotaini (who was considered Yasumori ADACHI&apos;s daughter and Akitoki KANAZAWA&apos;s wife; her real name was Chiyono), who adored Mugaku, built a hermitage called &apos;Shomyaku-an&apos; as his graveyard, and this was probably the beginning of Shinnyo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>暦応3年（1340年）に高師直が庵を東側に移して寺院として整備して、この際に真如寺と命名された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1340, KO no Moronao moved the hermitage to the east side and fixed it up as a temple, which was named Shinnyo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1340, KO no Moronao moved the hermitage to the east side and refurbished it as a temple, which was then called Shinnyo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1340, KO no Moronao moved the hermitage to the east side and refurbished it as a temple, which was then called Shinnyo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>翌年8月23日_(旧暦)に十刹に加えられるなど、室町幕府の手厚い保護を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October 12 next year, it was included in Jissatsu, deriving considerable support from the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt>旧暦を新暦に計算し、左記のようになりました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October 12 of the following year, it was included in the Jissatsu, deriving considerable support from the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October 12 of the following year, it was included in the Jissetsu, deriving considerable support from the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>スペル英語説明補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>だが、寛正2年（1461年）に焼失後、応仁の乱の混乱もあり、寺は事実上の廃寺状態となったが、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, after devastated by fire in 1461, the temple virtually closed amid the confusion in the wake of the Onin War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after a devastating fire in 1461, the temple virtually closed amid the confusion in the wake of the Onin War.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after a devastating fire in 1461, the temple virtually closed amid the confusion in the wake of the Onin War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>江戸時代に入った明暦2年（1656年）に後水尾院によって再興されて、以後相国寺に属することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Edo period in 1656, the temple was restored by Gomizuoin; and it has belonged to the Shokoku-ji Temple since then.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1656, during the Edo period, the temple was restored by Gomizuoin; since then it has belonged to Shokoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1656, during the Edo period, the temple was restored by Gomizuoin; since then it has belonged to Shokoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kansai explorer(id:48975), R28Bot(id:177951), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>