<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>覚猷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kakuyu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kakuyu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kakuyu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>覚猷（かくゆう、天喜元年（1053年） - 保延6年9月15日 (旧暦)（1140年10月27日））は、平安時代後期の天台宗僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kakuyu (1053 - October 27, 1140) was a Buddhist monk of Tendai Sect who was active in the late Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kakuyu (1053 - October 27, 1140) was a Buddhist monk of the Tendai Sect who was active in the late Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kakuyu (1053 - November 3, 1140) was a Buddhist priest of the Tendai Sect in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>鳥羽僧正（とばそうじょう）と世に呼ばれ、日本仏教界の重職を務めた高僧であるのみならず、絵画にも精通し、鳥獣人物戯画などの作者に擬せられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is well known by people as Toba Sojo and although he was a high-ranking monk who played important roles in Japanese Buddhism society, he was also well versed in paintings and is being assumed as the painter of Choju-Giga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is well known by people as Toba Sojo and although he was a high-ranking monk who played important roles in Japanese Buddhist society, he was also well versed in paintings and is assumed to be the painter of Choju-Giga.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was well known by people as Toba Sojo (high-ranking Buddhist priest) and although he was a high-ranking priest who played important roles in Japanese Buddhist society, he was also well versed in paintings and is assumed to be the painter of Choju-Jinbutsu-giga (scrolls of frolicking animals and humans).</e>
<cmt>用語を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>そのユニークでユーモアあふれる作風から、漫画の始祖とされることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thanks to his humorous style, he is sometimes mentioned as the originator of cartoons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thanks to his humorous style, he is sometimes mentioned as the originator of cartoons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thanks to his humorous style, he was sometimes mentioned as the originator of cartoons.</e>
<cmt>過去形にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>覚猷は、1053年に源隆国の第9子として出生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kakuyu was born in 1053 as 9th son of MINAMOTO no Takakuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kakuyu was born in 1053 as the 9th son of MINAMOTO no Takakuni.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kakuyu was born in 1053 as the 9th son of MINAMOTO no Takakuni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>若年時に出家し、園城寺にて天台仏教・密教を修めながら、画技にも長じるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became a priest in his youth and while studying Tendai Buddhism and Esoteric Buddhism at Onjo-ji Temple, he also became excelled in painting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became a priest in his youth and whilst studying Tendai Buddhism and Esoteric Buddhism at Onjo-ji Temple, he also came to excel in painting.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became a priest in his youth and while studying Tendai Buddhism and Esoteric Buddhism at Onjo-ji Temple, he also came to excel in painting.</e>
<cmt>whileを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>ながらく園城寺法輪院に住し、密教図像の集成と絵師の育成に大きな功績を残したほか、自らの画術研鑽にも努めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He resided at Horin-in of Onjo-ji Temple for a long time and made a great contribution in collecting Esoteric Buddhism arts as well as nurturing painters while striving to develop his own painting technique.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He resided at Horin-in of Onjo-ji Temple for a long time and made a great contribution in collecting Esoteric Buddhist art as well as nurturing artists whilst striving to develop his own painting technique.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He resided at Horinin of Onjo-ji Temple for a long time and made a great contribution in collecting Esoteric Buddhist art as well as nurturing artists while striving to develop his own painting technique.</e>
<cmt>whileを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>四天王寺別当、法成寺別当、園城寺長吏など大寺社の要職を歴任する間、1132年には僧正へ、1134年には大僧正へ任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While successively holding important positions at big temples/shrines, such as the head priest of Shitenno-ji Temple, the head priest of Hosei-ji Temple and chori of Onjo-ji Temple, he became Sojo (high-ranking Buddhist priest) in 1132 and Daisojo (the highest ranking Buddhist priest) in 1134.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While successively holding important positions at big temples/shrines, such as the head priest of Shitenno-ji Temple, the head priest of Hosei-ji Temple and Chori of Onjo-ji Temple, he became Sojo (high-ranking Buddhist priest) in 1132 and Daisojo (the highest ranking Buddhist priest) in 1134.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While successively holding important positions at big temples and shrines, such as betto (a monk who manages the affairs of a temple) of Shitenno-ji Temple, betto of Hosei-ji Temple and chori (the head priest) of Onjo-ji Temple, he became Sojo (high-ranking Buddhist priest) in 1132 and Daisojo (the highest ranking Buddhist priest) in 1134.</e>
<cmt>用語表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>1138年、47世座主となったが3日で退任し、厚い帰依を寄せていた鳥羽天皇が住む鳥羽離宮の証金剛院へ移り、同離宮の護持僧となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became the forty-seventh head priest of the temple in 1138, resigned 3 days later, moved to Shokongoin of Toba-Rikyu Palace where Emperor Toba, a devout believer in Kakuyu, resided and became the monk to pray for Toba-Rikyu Palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became the forty-seventh head priest of the temple in 1138, resigned 3 days later, moved to Shokongoin of Toba-Rikyu Palace, where Emperor Toba, a devout believer in Kakuyu, resided, and became the monk to pray for the Toba-Rikyu Palace.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He assumed the position of the forty-seventh head priest of the temple in 1138, resigned 3 days later, moved to Shokongoin of Toba-Rikyu Palace, where Emperor Toba, a devout believer in Kakuyu, resided, and assumed the position of gojiso (a priest who prays to guard the emperor) in the Toba-Rikyu Palace.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>以後、鳥羽僧正と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, he was called Toba Sojo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, he was called Toba Sojo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, he was called Toba Sojo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>保延6年(1140)9月15日 (旧暦)、覚猷は90歳近い高齢で死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kakuyu died on September 15, 1140 (lunar calendar) at an advanced age of near 90.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kakuyu died on September 15, 1140 (lunar calendar) at the advanced age of almost 90.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kakuyu died on November 3, 1140 at the advanced age of almost 90.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その際、弟子から遺産分与に関する遺言を求められ、「遺産の処分は腕力で決めるべし」と遺したと伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he was requested by his disciples to leave will concerning the division of his property, he is said to have left his will saying &quot;Division of property should be decided according to physical strength&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he was requested by his disciples to leave a will concerning the division of his property, he is said to have left a will saying &quot;Division of property should be decided according to physical strength&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he was requested by his disciples to leave a will concerning the division of his property, he is said to have left a will saying &apos;Division of property should be decided according to physical strength.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>人物像・戯画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personality・Caricatures</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personality・Caricatures</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal Profile and Caricatures</e>
<cmt>用語表現を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>覚猷の画は、ユーモアと風刺精神に富んでおり、戯画と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His paintings are called caricature since they are full of humor and satire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His paintings are called caricature since they are full of humor and satire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His paintings are called caricature since they are full of humor and satire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>遺言の逸話が示すように、覚猷自身、笑いのセンスに長けた人物のようであり、『宇治拾遺物語』にも覚猷のいたずら好きで無邪気な人柄が描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the anecdote of his last will indicates, he seemed to have been a person of humorous personality and he is depicted as a person of mischievous and innocent personality in &quot;Uji-shui-monogatari&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the anecdote of his last will indicates, he seemed to have been a person of humorous personality and he is depicted as a person with a mischievous and innocent personality in &quot;Uji-shui-monogatari&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the anecdote of his last will indicates, he seemed to have been a person of humorous personality and he is depicted as a person with a mischievous and innocent personality in &quot;Uji Shui Monogatari&quot; (a collection of the Tales from Uji).</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また、覚猷は仏教界の要職を歴任しながら、当時の仏教界と政治のあり方に批判的な眼を持っていたともされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, Kakuyu is believed to have been critical of Buddhism society as well as politics at the time in spite of the fact that he successively held important posts in Buddhism society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, Kakuyu is believed to have been critical of Buddhist society, as well as the politics of the time, in spite of the fact that he successively held important posts in Buddhist society.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, Kakuyu is believed to have been critical of Buddhist society, as well as the politics of the time, in spite of the fact that he successively held important posts in Buddhist society.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>国宝『鳥獣人物戯画』（鳥獣戯画）、『放屁合戦』、『陽物くらべ』などが伝鳥羽僧正作とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to legend, national treasure &quot;Choju-Giga&quot; (Choju-Giga), &quot;&quot;Hohi Kassen&quot; and &quot;Yobutsu Kurabe&quot; are believed to be his works.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to legend, the national treasures &quot;Choju-Giga&quot; (Choju-Giga), &quot;&quot;Hohi Kassen&quot; and &quot;Yobutsu Kurabe&quot; are believed to be his work.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to legend, the national treasures &quot;Choju-Jinbutsu-giga&quot; (Choju-Giga), &quot;Hohi Kassen&quot; (Battle of breaking wind) and &quot;Yobutsu Kurabe&quot; (Measuring phallus) are believed to be his work.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>いずれも一見単純な明るい笑いの画のようでありながら、深い批判精神を含む作品群であり、鳥羽僧正の作に擬せられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although these works look like simple, cheerful and humorous paintings at a glance, they are rich with satire spirit and are assumed to be Toba Sojo&apos;s works.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although at a glance these works appear to be simple, cheerful and humorous paintings, they are rich with satire spirit and are assumed to be Toba Sojo&apos;s works.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although at a glance these works appear to be simple, cheerful and humorous paintings, they are rich with satire spirit and are assumed to be Toba Sojo&apos;s works.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>実のところ、美術史学上、覚猷をこれらの絵画の作者とする確証はないとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the viewpoint of art history, however, there is no established evidences that prove the fact that Kakuyu is the painter of these paintings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the viewpoint of art history, however, there is no established evidence that proves the fact that Kakuyu was the painter of these paintings.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the viewpoint of art history, however, there is no established evidence that proves the fact that Kakuyu was the painter of these paintings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>ただし、これらの絵画は覚猷の画風をよく表しているともいわれ、鳥獣人物戯画の一部を覚猷の筆とする見解もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, these paintings are said to represent Kakuyu&apos;s painting style well and there exists opinions asserting that a part of &quot;Choju-Giga&quot; must have been painted by Kakuyu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, these paintings are said to represent Kakuyu&apos;s painting style well and there are opinions asserting that a part of &quot;Choju-Giga&quot; must have been painted by Kakuyu.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, these paintings are said to represent Kakuyu&apos;s painting style well and there are opinions asserting that a part of Choju-Jinbutsu-giga must have been painted by Kakuyu.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Bueller 007(id:30970), 代言人(id:33675), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), Shimoxx(id:9332), Charon(id:9162), Andee(id:20421), かんな文移(id:136115), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>