<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>安東蓮聖</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rensho ANDO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rensho ANDO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rensho ANDO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>安東 蓮聖（あんどう れんしょう、延応元年（1239年）- 嘉暦4年1月19日 (旧暦)（1329年2月18日））は、鎌倉時代後期の武将で、鎌倉幕府執権北条氏得宗家の被官（御内人）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rensho ANDO (1239 - January 19, 1329 (old lunar calendar)(February 18, 1329)) was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the late Kamakura period who was low-level bureaucrat (Miuchibito (private vassals) of the Tokuso Family of the regent Hojo clan of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rensho ANDO (1239 - January 19, 1329 (old lunar calendar)(February 18, 1329)) was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the late Kamakura period who was a low-level bureaucrat (Miuchibito (private vassals) of the Tokuso Family of the regent Hojo clan of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rensho ANDO (1239 - February 18, 1329) was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the late Kamakura period who was a low-level bureaucrat (Miuchibito (private vassals) of the Tokuso family of the regent Hojo clan of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>旧暦表示を削除Family→family</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父母、諱ともに不詳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">None of his father, mother, or imina (real personal name) is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Neither his father, mother, or imina (real personal name) are known.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">None of his father, mother, or imina (personal name) is unknown.</e>
<cmt>realを削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>通称は平右衛門。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His common name was Heiemon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His common name was Heiemon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His common name was Heiemon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>蓮聖は律宗僧としての法名で蓮性と表記することもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rensho is his homyo (a name given to a person who enters the Buddhist priesthood) as a priest of Ritsu sect, and it is written in Kanji characters as 蓮聖 or 蓮性.</e>
<cmt>漢字表記を残しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rensho was his homyo (a name given to a person who enters the Buddhist priesthood) as a priest of Ritsu sect, and was written in Kanji characters as 蓮聖 or 蓮性.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rensho was his homyo (a name given to a person who enters the Buddhist priesthood) as a priest of Ritsu sect, and was written in Kanji characters as 蓮聖 or 蓮性.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>官は右衛門尉。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His rank was Uemon no jo (the third ranked official of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His rank was Uemon no jo (the third ranked official of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His rank was Uemon no jo (the third ranked official of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>安東平右衛門入道と呼ばれたことから平氏姓と考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since he was called as ANDO Heiemon Nyudo, he is considered as a member of Taira clan (the same kanji character is used for &quot;Hei&quot; and &quot;Taira&quot;).</e>
<cmt>「平」という漢字の説明を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since he was called as ANDO Heiemon Nyudo, he is considered to have been a member of Taira clan (the same kanji character is used for &quot;Hei&quot; and &quot;Taira&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since he was called as ANDO Heiemon Nyudo, he is considered to have been a member of Taira clan (the same kanji character is used for &quot;Hei&quot; and &quot;Taira&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>子に安東円恵（安東治右衛門助泰）がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of his children was Ene ANDO (Haruemon Sukeyasu ANDO).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of his children was Ene ANDO (Haruemon Sukeyasu ANDO).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of his children was Ene ANDO (Haruemon Sukeyasu ANDO).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>本貫地については諸説あり、駿河国北安東荘（静岡県静岡市）、陸奥国津軽地方十三湊（青森県五所川原市）、豊後国佐賀郷（大分県大分市）などが候補として挙げられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many theories about his honganchi (the place where one&apos;s family register was placed), including Kitaandosho, Suruga Province (Shizuoka City, Shizuoka Prefecture), Tosaminato Tsugaru district, Mutsu Province (Goshogawara City, Aomori Prefecture), and Saganogo, Bungo Province (Oita City, Oita Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many theories about his honganchi (the place where one&apos;s family register was placed), including Kitaandosho, Suruga Province (Shizuoka City, Shizuoka Prefecture), Tosaminato Tsugaru district, Mutsu Province (Goshogawara City, Aomori Prefecture), and Saganogo, Bungo Province (Oita City, Oita Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many theories about his honganchi (the place where one&apos;s family register was placed), including Kitaandosho, Suruga Province (Shizuoka City, Shizuoka Prefecture), Tosaminato Tsugaru district, Mutsu Province (Goshogawara City, Aomori Prefecture), and Saganogo, Bungo Province (Oita City, Oita Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>摂津国、和泉国を中心とした瀬戸内海沿岸一帯に所領をもち、主に西日本の得宗領の管理や海運、金融に携わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His territories covered the coast of the Seto Inland Sea, mainly in Izumi Province, and he dealt with management of Tokuso ryo (estate owned by the head of the direct line of Hojo clan) in western Japan, shipping, and finance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His territories covered the coast of the Seto Inland Sea, mainly in Izumi Province, and he dealt with management of Tokuso ryo (estate owned by the head of the direct line of Hojo clan) in western Japan, shipping, and finance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His territories covered the coast of the Seto Inland Sea, mainly in Settsu and Izumi Provinces, and he dealt with management of Tokuso ryo (estate owned by the head of the direct line of Hojo clan) in western Japan, shipping, and finance.</e>
<cmt>Settsu Provincesを補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>御内人が有徳人化した代表的な例とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was regarded as a typical example of Miuchibito turned into Utokujin (wealthy person).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was regarded as a typical example of Miuchibito turned into Utokujin (wealthy person).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was regarded as a typical example of Miuchibito turned into Utokujin (wealthy person).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>北条時頼の被官として、弘長2年（1262年）に西大寺_(奈良市)叡尊への使者となり、翌3年（1263年）には信濃国善光寺に時頼が不断経衆の免田を寄附した際の沙汰をしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a hikan (low-level bureaucrat) of Tokiyori HOJO, he played a role of messenger to Eison at Saidai-ji Temple (Nara City) in 1262 and in the following year, he adjudicated when Tokiyori donated the tax-exempt rice field of people who read Buddhist scriptures every day to Zenko-ji Temple in Shinano Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a hikan (low-level bureaucrat) of Tokiyori HOJO, he played the role of messenger to Eison at Saidai-ji Temple (Nara City) in 1262 and in the following year, he adjudicated when Tokiyori donated the tax-exempt rice field of people who read Buddhist scriptures every day to Zenko-ji Temple in Shinano Province.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a hikan (low-level bureaucrat) of Tokiyori HOJO, he played the role of messenger to Eison at Saidai-ji Temple (Nara City) in 1262 and in the following year, he adjudicated when Tokiyori donated the tax-exempt rice field of fudangyo-shu (people who read Buddhist scriptures every day) to Zenko-ji Temple in Shinano Province.</e>
<cmt>fudangyo-shu (people who read Buddhist scriptures every day)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>一方で文永年間には京で延暦寺の僧と結び借上を営んでおり、文永8年（1271年）には幕府の禁制を犯し近江国堅田浦で仁和寺の年貢運上船を差し押さえ、醍醐寺領越中国石黒荘山田郷の雑掌から訴えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, he made a connection with priests of Enryaku-ji Temple in Kyoto during Bunei Era; in 1271, he violated the Bakufu&apos;s kinzei (prohibition) by seizing ships of the Ninna-ji Temple to transport tribute at Katata-no-ura, Omi Province, and therefore was sued by zassho (a person in charge of miscellaneous tasks) of the territory of the Daigo-ji Temple in Yamadago Ishigurosho, Etchu Province</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, he made a connection with priests of Enryaku-ji Temple in Kyoto during Bunei Era; in 1271, he violated the Bakufu&apos;s kinzei (prohibition) by seizing ships of the Ninna-ji Temple to transport tribute at Katata-no-ura, Omi Province, and therefore was sued by zassho (a person in charge of miscellaneous tasks) of the territory of the Daigo-ji Temple in Yamadago Ishigurosho, Etchu Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, with the assistance of priests of Enryaku-ji Temple in Kyoto, he was running a money-lending business during Bunei Era; in 1271, he violated the Bakufu&apos;s kinzei (prohibition) by seizing ships of the Ninna-ji Temple to transport tribute at Katata-no-ura, Omi Province, and therefore was sued by zassho (a person in charge of miscellaneous tasks) of the territory of the Daigo-ji Temple in Yamadago Ishigurosho, Etchu Province</e>
<cmt>借上を営む表現が抜けていたので補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>御内人でありながら悪党の側面も持っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a Miuchibito with a face of villain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a Miuchibito with the face of a villain.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a Miuchibito with the face of a villain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>文永10年（1273年）摂津国多田院造営の惣奉行に就く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1273, he was appointed to sobugyo for building the Tada-in Temple in Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1273, he was appointed to sobugyo for building the Tada-in Temple in Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1273, he was appointed to sobugyo for building the Tada-in Temple in Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>建治 3年（1277年）には和泉国久米田寺の別当職を買得。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1277, he bought the position of betto (the head priest) of Kumeda-dera Temple in Izumi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1277, he bought the position of betto (the head priest) of Kumeda-dera Temple in Izumi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1277, he bought the position of betto (the head priest) of Kumeda-dera Temple in Izumi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>所領を寄進し律宗の寺として再興、弘安5年（1282年）には叡尊を請じ堂供養を催行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He donated his territories to the temple to restore it as a temple of Ritsu sect, and in 1282, he invited Eison to hold do kuyo (a memorial service of the temple).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He donated his territories to the temple to restore it as a temple of Ritsu sect, and in 1282, he invited Eison to hold do kuyo (a memorial service of the temple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He donated his territories to the temple to restore it as a temple of Ritsu sect, and in 1282, he invited Eison to hold do-kuyo (a memorial service of the temple).</e>
<cmt>誤解を呼びそうなので「do kuyo」を「do-kuyo」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>弘安7年（1284年）守護北条兼時の元、摂津国守護代に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1284, under the shugo (military governor) Kanetoki HOJO, he was appointed to shugodai (provincial governor) of Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1284, under the shugo (military governor) Kanetoki HOJO, he was appointed to shugodai (provincial governor) of Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1284, under the shugo (military governor) Kanetoki HOJO, he was appointed to shugodai (provincial governor) of Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>乾元元年（1302年）には数百貫の私財を投じて播磨国福泊港を修築している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1302, he refurbished the Fukudomari Port in Harima Province at his own expense of hundreds of kan (obsolete unit of currency).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1302, he refurbished the Fukudomari Port in Harima Province at his own expense of hundreds of kan (obsolete unit of currency).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1302, he refurbished the Fukudomari Port in Harima Province at his own expense of hundreds of kan (obsolete unit of currency).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="19">
<j>嘉暦4年（1329年）、京五条の私邸で91歳で死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1329, he died at his own house in Gojo Ward of Kyoto at the age of 91.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1329, he died at his own house in Gojo Ward of Kyoto at the age of 91.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1329, he died at his own house in Gojo Ward of Kyoto at the age of 91.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>久米田寺に伝わっている「絹本著色安東蓮聖像」は国の重要文化財に指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kempon Chakushoku Ando Rensho Zo&quot; that has been handed down in the Kumeda-dera Temple is designated as a national important cultural property.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kempon Chakushoku Ando Rensho Zo&quot; that has been handed down in the Kumeda-dera Temple is designated as a national important cultural property.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kempon Chakushoku Ando Rensho Zo&apos; that has been handed down in the Kumeda-dera Temple is designated as a national important cultural property.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), 健ちゃん(id:60346), Kstigarbha(id:13376), R28Bot(id:177951), Urania(id:7213), Saaki(id:43602), 松茸(id:27535), Law soma(id:45202), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>