<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>実如</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jitsunyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jitsunyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jitsunyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>実如（じつにょ、長禄2年8月10日 (旧暦)（1458年9月17日） － 大永5年2月2日 (旧暦)（1525年2月23日））は、室町時代中期から戦国時代 (日本)にかけての浄土真宗の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jitsunyo (born September 17, 1458, died February 23, 1525) was a Buddhist priest of the Jodo Shinshu (True Pure Land) sect who lived from the mid-Muromachi period into the Sengoku (warring states) period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jitsunyo (born September 17, 1458, died February 23, 1525) was a Buddhist priest of the Jodo Shinshu (True Pure Land) sect who lived from the mid-Muromachi period into the Sengoku (warring states) period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jitsunyo (September 26, 1458 - March 5, 1525) was a Buddhist priest of the Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) who lived from the mid-Muromachi period into the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>本願寺8世蓮如の第8子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the eighth son of the Buddhist priest Rennyo, who himself was the eighth abbot of Honganji temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the eighth son of the Buddhist priest Rennyo, who himself was the eighth abbot of Honganji temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the eighth son of the Buddhist priest Rennyo of the eighth abbot of Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>諱は光兼。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His personal name was Mitsukane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His personal name was Mitsukane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His imina (personal name) was Mitsukane.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>本願寺第9世。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became the ninth abbot of Honganji temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became the ninth abbot of Honganji temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became the ninth abbot of Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>1467年（文正2年）延暦寺から「仏敵」とされ京都を追われた父・蓮如がやむなく延暦寺に屈した時に蓮如の隠居と長男順如の廃嫡、そして当時光養丸と呼ばれていた実如への家督継承が強要されるが、本願寺の勢力回復とともに有耶無耶となり、元のように順如が法嗣とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1467 his father Rennyo was declared an enemy of Buddhism by Enryakuji temple and driven away from Kyoto; during the period Rennyo was depressed by Enyrakuji&apos;s persecution, he was forced to live in retirement, to disinherit his eldest sun Junnyo, and to transfer the family headship to Jitsunyo, who at that time was known as Mitsunanemaru, but Rennyo regained his influence following the resurgence in Honganji temple&apos;s own power, which left the inheritance question up in the air, until eventually things went back to the way they had been, with Junnyo reinstalled as his successor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1467 his father Rennyo was declared an enemy of Buddhism by Enryakuji temple and driven away from Kyoto; during the period Rennyo was depressed by Enyrakuji&apos;s persecution, he was forced to live in retirement, to disinherit his eldest sun Junnyo, and to transfer the family headship to Jitsunyo, who at that time was known as Mitsunanemaru, but Rennyo regained his influence following the resurgence in Honganji temple&apos;s own power, which left the inheritance question up in the air, until eventually things went back to the way they had been, with Junnyo reinstalled as his successor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1467 his father Rennyo was declared &apos;an enemy of Buddhism&apos; by Enryaku-ji Temple and driven away from Kyoto; during the period Rennyo was depressed by Enryaku-ji Temple&apos;s persecution, he was forced to live in retirement, to disinherit his eldest sun Junnyo, and to transfer the family headship to Jitsunyo, who at that time was known as Mitsutanemaru (光養丸), but Rennyo regained his influence following the resurgence in Hongan-ji Temple&apos;s own power, which left the inheritance question up in the air, until eventually things went back to the way they had been, with Junnyo reinstalled as his successor.</e>
<cmt>仮読みの漢字を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>1483年（文明_(日本)15年）長兄である順如の死没により改めて法嗣となり（そのため、法主が後継者指名に用いた譲状が実如には2枚存在する）、1489年（延徳8年）父蓮如のあとを受けて本願寺第9世となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But in 1483, with the death of his eldest brother Junnyo, Jitsunyo was once again made successor (and for that reason, there are actually two letters of inheritance, used by his father the chief priest to name his successor, in existence that designate Jitsunyo his heir), and in 1489, he succeeded his father Rennyo and became the ninth abbot of Honganji temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But in 1483, with the death of his eldest brother Junnyo, Jitsunyo was once again made successor (and for that reason, there are actually two letters of inheritance, used by his father the chief priest to name his successor, in existence that designate Jitsunyo his heir), and in 1489, he succeeded his father Rennyo and became the ninth abbot of Honganji temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But in 1483, with the death of his eldest brother Junnyo, Jitsunyo was once again made successor (and for that reason, there are actually two letters of inheritance, used by his father the chief priest to name his successor, in existence that designate Jitsunyo his heir), and in 1489, he succeeded his father Rennyo and became the ninth abbot of Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>1499年（明応8年）に蓮如が亡くなった後も、父の代に急激に拡大した教団の規模を維持する必要があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And even after Rennyo passed away iin 1499, Jitsunyo found it necessary to handle the maintenance of a religious organization that had suddenly expanded a great deal in scale during his father&apos;s time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And even after Rennyo passed away iin 1499, Jitsunyo found it necessary to handle the maintenance of a religious organization that had suddenly expanded a great deal in scale during his father&apos;s time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And even after Rennyo passed away in 1499, Jitsunyo found it necessary to handle the maintenance of a religious organization that had suddenly expanded a great deal in scale during his father&apos;s time.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>特に実如が重視したのは管領細川政元との関係である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jitsunyo placed particular importance on his relationship with the Kanrei (shogunal deputy) Masamoto HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jitsunyo placed particular importance on his relationship with the Kanrei (shogunal deputy) Masamoto HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jitsunyo placed particular importance on his relationship with the Kanrei (shogunal deputy) Masamoto HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>かつて加賀一向一揆が守護富樫政親を攻め滅ぼした際に征夷大将軍足利義尚が本願寺に討伐令を下そうとしていた折に政元がこれに強く反対して討伐令を撤回させたという経緯があったために、実如は大きな恩義を感じていたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Formerly, after forces of the Kaga Ikko Ikki (a popular revolt by the Ikko sect) attacked and destroyed the Kaga daimyo Masachika TOGASHI, just as the Sei-I taishogun (Shogun) Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA was preparing to issue an order to destroy Honganji temple, Masamoto came out strongly against issuing such an order and managed to have the order repealed, and because of this chain of events, Jitsunyo felt a major debt of gratitude towards Masamoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Formerly, after forces of the Kaga Ikko Ikki (a popular revolt by the Ikko sect) attacked and destroyed the Kaga daimyo Masachika TOGASHI, just as the Sei-I taishogun (Shogun) Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA was preparing to issue an order to destroy Honganji temple, Masamoto came out strongly against issuing such an order and managed to have the order repealed, and because of this chain of events, Jitsunyo felt a major debt of gratitude towards Masamoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Formerly, after forces of the Kaga Ikko Ikki (a popular revolt by the Ikko sect) attacked and destroyed the Shugo (provincial constable) Masachika TOGASHI, just as the seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA was preparing to issue an order to destroy Hongan-ji Temple, Masamoto came out strongly against issuing such an order and managed to have the order repealed, and because of this chain of events, Jitsunyo felt a major debt of gratitude towards Masamoto.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>このため、1495年（明応4年）には加賀一揆の指導者で反政元派の河井宣久の粛清を容認している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, in 1495 Jitsunyo gave his approval to purge Senji KAWAI, leader of the Kaga Ikki (revolt) and member of the anti-Masamoto faction, from the religious establishment.</e>
<cmt>It seemed necessary to explain from what group Kawai was being purged.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, in 1495 Jitsunyo gave his approval to purge Senji KAWAI, leader of the Kaga Ikki (revolt) and member of the anti-Masamoto faction, from the religious establishment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, in 1495 Jitsunyo gave his approval to purge Senji KAWAI, leader of the Kaga Ikki (revolt) and member of the anti-Masamoto faction, from the religious establishment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>だが、1506年（永正3年）、細川政元の要請を受けて畠山義英討伐への協力に応じると、畠山氏との関係が深かった摂津国・河内国の門徒が猛反発し、実如の異母弟で畠山氏の血を引く実賢（後に近江国称徳寺）を石山御坊にて擁立して法主交替を求める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But in 1506, when Jitsunyo agreed to Masamoto HOSOKAWA&apos;s request to cooperate in the subjugation of Yoshihide HATAKEYAMA, Jodo Shinshu followers from Settsu and Kawachi provinces, who had strong ties to the Hatakeyama clan, furiously opposed him, and consequently Jitsunyo&apos;s younger brother by a different mother, Jitsugen, himself descended from the Hatakeyama clan, demanded--with the backing of Ishiyama Honganji temple (also called Ishiyama Gobo, it later became Omi province&apos;s Shotokuji temple)--that he replace Jitsunyo as high priest of the Jodo Shinshu sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But in 1506, when Jitsunyo agreed to Masamoto HOSOKAWA&apos;s request to cooperate in the subjugation of Yoshihide HATAKEYAMA, Jodo Shinshu followers from Settsu and Kawachi provinces, who had strong ties to the Hatakeyama clan, furiously opposed him, and consequently Jitsunyo&apos;s younger brother by a different mother, Jitsugen, himself descended from the Hatakeyama clan, demanded--with the backing of Ishiyama Honganji temple (also called Ishiyama Gobo, it later became Omi province&apos;s Shotokuji temple)--that he replace Jitsunyo as high priest of the Jodo Shinshu sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But in 1506, when Jitsunyo agreed to Masamoto HOSOKAWA&apos;s request to cooperate in the subjugation of Yoshihide HATAKEYAMA, Jodo Shinshu followers from Settsu and Kawachi Provinces, who had strong ties to the Hatakeyama clan, furiously opposed him, and consequently Jitsunyo&apos;s younger brother by a different mother, Jitsugen, himself descended from the Hatakeyama clan, demanded, with the backing of Ishiyama Gobo (later became Omi Province&apos;s Shotoku-ji Temple), that he replaced Jitsunyo as Hoshu (high priest) of the Jodo Shinshu Sect.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>実如はこれを力づくで抑え込む（「大坂一乱」）が、続いて細川澄之が政元を暗殺して細川澄元と争うと、その争いに巻き込まれた実如は澄元によって一時山科本願寺を追放されてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jitsunyo, invigorated by this challenge to his authority, managed to outmaneuver his opponents and retain power (in what was called the &quot;Osaka Ichiran&quot; or &quot;Osaka War&quot;), but following this, when Sumiyuki HOSOKAWA had Masamoto assassinated and began fighting with Sumimoto HOSOKAWA, Jitsunyo, who was caught in the middle of this conflict, was eventually banished temporarily to Yamashina Honganji temple by Sumimoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jitsunyo, invigorated by this challenge to his authority, managed to outmaneuver his opponents and retain power (in what was called the &quot;Osaka Ichiran&quot; or &quot;Osaka War&quot;), but following this, when Sumiyuki HOSOKAWA had Masamoto assassinated and began fighting with Sumimoto HOSOKAWA, Jitsunyo, who was caught in the middle of this conflict, was eventually banished temporarily to Yamashina Honganji temple by Sumimoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jitsunyo, invigorated by this challenge to his authority, managed to outmaneuver his opponents and retain power (in what was called the &apos;Osaka War&apos;), but following this, when Sumiyuki HOSOKAWA had Masamoto assassinated and began fighting with Sumimoto HOSOKAWA, Jitsunyo, who was caught in the middle of this conflict, was eventually banished temporarily to Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple by Sumimoto.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>この事態に苦慮した実如は、弟蓮淳・息子円如とともに北陸門徒に対し一揆の禁止をはじめとする3か条の戒めを発布したり、本願寺の一族を一門衆（嫡男）と一家衆（次男以下）に分ける一門一家制を設けたり、蓮如の文書の中から80通を選んで5帖に編集し御文とよんで宗門信条の基本とするなどの策を講じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jitsunyo, racking his mind for what to do amongst these circumstances, planned several responses, notably: 1) promulgating--together with his younger brother Renjun and his son Ennyo--three different punitive admonitions, the most notable of which was the one focused on Jodo Shinshu followers in the Hokuriku region (central-north Japan) that outlawed Ikki; 2) establishing a system that split the household at Honganji temple into the Ichimonshu (the lineage of the eldest son) and the Ikkashu (the lineage of the second and other sons); and 3) selecting 80 documents from among Rennyo&apos;s writings, compiling them into five volumes, calling them the &quot;Gobun&quot; (Epistles) and using them as the fundamental doctrinal creed of the sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jitsunyo, racking his mind for what to do amongst these circumstances, planned several responses, notably: 1) promulgating--together with his younger brother Renjun and his son Ennyo--three different punitive admonitions, the most notable of which was the one focused on Jodo Shinshu followers in the Hokuriku region (central-north Japan) that outlawed Ikki; 2) establishing a system that split the household at Honganji temple into the Ichimonshu (the lineage of the eldest son) and the Ikkashu (the lineage of the second and other sons); and 3) selecting 80 documents from among Rennyo&apos;s writings, compiling them into five volumes, calling them the &quot;Gobun&quot; (Epistles) and using them as the fundamental doctrinal creed of the sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jitsunyo, racking his mind for what to do amongst these circumstances, planned several responses, notably: 1) promulgating--together with his younger brother Renjun and his son Ennyo--three different punitive admonitions, the most notable of which was the one focused on Jodo Shinshu followers in the Hokuriku region (central-north Japan) that outlawed Ikki; 2) establishing Ichimon-Ikka System that split the household at Hongan-ji Temple into the Ichimonshu (the lineage of the eldest son) and the Ikkashu (the lineage of the second and other sons); and 3) selecting 80 documents from among Rennyo&apos;s writings, compiling them into five volumes, calling them the Gobun (also referred as Ofumi, literally Epistles) and using them as the fundamental doctrinal creed of the sect.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Resto1578(id:168692), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), R28Bot(id:177951), 松茸(id:27535), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), Nighthawks(id:36125), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>