<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>伽藍神</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Garanjin (tutelary deities of temple compounds)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Garanjin (tutelary deities of temple compounds)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Garanjin</e>
<cmt>説明削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>伽藍神（がらんじん）は、寺院を守護する神。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Garanjin is a deity that guards temples and shrines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Garanjin is a deity that guards temples and shrines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Garanjin is a deity that guards temples and shrines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>護伽藍神（ごがらんじん）・守護伽藍神・寺神ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also referred to as Gogaranjin, Shugogaranjin, and Jishin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also referred to as Gogaranjin, Shugogaranjin, and Jishin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also referred to as Gogaranjin, Shugogaranjin, and Jishin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>伽藍神を祀る堂を伽藍堂という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A hall in which Garanjin is enshrined is referred to as Garan-do.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A hall in which Garanjin is enshrined is referred to as Garan-do.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A hall in which Garanjin is enshrined is referred to as Garan-do.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>「伽藍を守護する」という点では、鎮守も、伽藍神の一種であるといえるが、通例「伽藍神」といえば、禅宗寺院の仏殿等に祀られる、道教神の姿をした像をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In terms of guarding Garan (Buddhist temples), Chinju (local Shinto deity) can be also considered as one of the Garanjin, but &quot;Garanjin&quot; generally refers to a statue in the shape of a Taoism deity enshrined in a Buddhist sanctum of a temple of Zen sect or the like.</e>
<cmt>伽藍の説明を挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In terms of guarding Garan (Buddhist temples), Chinju (local Shinto deity) can be also considered one of the Garanjin, but &quot;Garanjin&quot; generally refers to a statue in the shape of a Taoism deity enshrined in a Buddhist sanctum of a temple of the Zen sect or the like.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In terms of guarding Garan (Buddhist temples), Chinju (local Shinto deity) can be also considered one of the Garanjin, but &apos;Garanjin&apos; generally refers to a statue in the shape of a Taoism deity enshrined in a Buddhist sanctum of a temple of the Zen sect or the like.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>日本では、この種の像は中国宋 (王朝)代仏教の影響を受け、鎌倉時代中頃から制作・安置されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, influenced by Buddhism in Sung period, China, this type of statues started to be produced and enshrined in the mid Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, influenced by Buddhism in the Sung period, China, this type of statue started to be produced and enshrined in the mid Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, influenced by Buddhism in the Sung period, China, this type of statue started to be produced and enshrined in the mid Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>中国（宋）の寺院では、土地堂（つちどう/どじどう）に道教神を祀ったが、それが日本に伝えられたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In temples in China (Sung), the Taoism deities were enshrined in Dojido (hall of the guardian deity), and it was conveyed to Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In temples in China (Sung), the Taoism deities were enshrined in Dojido (hall of the guardian deity), and it was conveyed to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In temples in China (Sung), the Taoism deities were enshrined in Dojido (hall of the guardian deity), and it was conveyed to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>禅宗寺院のほか、真言宗の泉涌寺（京都市）や、その末寺である覚園寺などの宋代仏教の影響が大きい寺院にも祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to temples of Zen sect, Garanjin is enshrined in such temples and shrines greatly influenced by Sung Buddhism as Senyuji Temple of Shingon sect (Kyoto City) and its branch temple, Kakuon-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to temples of the Zen sect, Garanjin is enshrined in temples and shrines greatly influenced by Sung Buddhism, such as Senyuji Temple of the Shingon sect (Kyoto City) and its branch temple, Kakuon-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to temples of the Zen sect, Garanjin is enshrined in temples and shrines greatly influenced by Sung Buddhism, such as Senyu-ji Temple of the Shingon sect (Kyoto City) and its branch temple, Kakuon-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>伽藍神像は、仏殿の隅などに数体まとまって安置されていることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In many cases, several Garanjin are enshrined together in a corner of a Buddhist sanctum or the like.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In many cases, several Garanjin are enshrined together in a corner of a Buddhist sanctum or the like.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In many cases, several Garanjin are enshrined together in a corner of a Buddhist sanctum or the like.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>像の形態は立像、倚像（いぞう、腰掛けた形の像）が多く、その服装、ポーズ、表情などはさまざまであるが、中国風の道服を着て冠を被るものが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of the statues are standing or sitting in various clothes and poses with various expressions, and many of them wear a Chinese Taoism costume and a crown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of the statues are standing or sitting in various clothes and poses with various expressions, and many of them wear a Chinese Taoism costume and a crown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of the statues are standing or sitting in various clothes and poses with various expressions, and many of them wear a Chinese Taoism costume and a crown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 水野白楓(id:22811), R28Bot(id:177951), Urania(id:7213), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>