<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>黄不動</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kifudo painting (Yellow Cetaka)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kifudo painting (Yellow Cetaka)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kifudo painting</e>
<cmt>(Yellow Cetaka)削除</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>黄不動（きふどう）は、滋賀県大津市の園城寺、通称三井寺に秘仏として伝わる、全身が黄色の不動明王立像の仏画である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kifudo painting is a &apos;hibutsu&apos; (Buddhist image normally withheld from public view) of a standing statue of Fudomyoo (cetaka) of which entire body is yellow handed down to Onjo-ji Temple commonly called Mii-dera Temple in Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kifudo painting is a &apos;hibutsu&apos; (Buddhist image normally withheld from public view) of a standing statue of Fudomyoo (cetaka), the entire body of which is yellow, handed down to Onjo-ji Temple, commonly called Mii-dera Temple, in Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kifudo painting is a &apos;hibutsu&apos; (Buddhist image normally withheld from public view) of a standing statue of Fudomyoo (cetaka), the entire body of which is yellow, handed down to Onjo-ji Temple, commonly called Mii-dera Temple, in Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>平安時代前期の作で、国宝に指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a product of early Heian period and designated as a National Treasure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a product of the early Heian period and designated a National Treasure.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a product of the early Heian period and designated a National Treasure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>円珍が感得した像を描いたものとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that it depicted the image with which a priest Enchin was in the state of enlightenment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that it depicts the image with which a priest Enchin was in the state of enlightenment.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that it depicts the image with which a priest Enchin was in the state of enlightenment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>三不動の一であり、別名、金色不動明王。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of the 3 major Fudo, and has another name of Konjiki Fudomyoo (Litreally, Gold Cetaka.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is one of the 3 major Fudo, and has another name, Konjiki Fudomyoo (Litreally, Gold Cetaka.)</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is one of the 3 major Fudo, and has another name, Konjiki Fudomyoo (literally, Gold Cetaka).</e>
<cmt>スペルピリオド位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>京都・曼殊院等に伝わる多くの模写像は、磐座上に立つが、本像は、円珍が実際に感得した際のさまを表現しているため、虚空上に立つ姿を本紙いっぱいに描いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although many facsimiles of fudomyoo handed down to Manshu-in Temple in Kyoto, etc. stand on iwakura (dwelling place of a god, usually in reference to a large rock), this one was painted as standing on the empty sky fully on paper because it depicted the actual scene of the state of enlightenment of Enchin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although many facsimiles of fudomyoo handed down to Manshu-in Temple in Kyoto, etc. stand on iwakura (dwelling place of a god, usually in reference to a large rock), this one was painted as standing on the empty sky fully on paper, because it depicted the actual scene of the state of enlightenment of Enchin.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although many facsimiles of fudomyoo handed down to Manshu-in Temple in Kyoto, etc. stand on iwakura (dwelling place of a god, usually in reference to a large rock), this one was painted as standing on the empty sky fully on paper, because it depicted the actual scene of the state of enlightenment of Enchin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また、背景も虚空の状景を表すため、何も描かれていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And also nothing is painted in the background to show the state of emptiness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, nothing is painted in the background, to show the state of emptiness.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, nothing is painted in the background, to show the state of emptiness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>円珍は、比叡山や渡唐上で、この黄不動に再三感得し、身の危険を救われたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enchin was in the state of enlightenment with this Kifudo many times at Hiei-zan mountain and on the way to Tang Dynasty, and he was helped by it when he was in fear of his life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enchin was in the state of enlightenment with this Kifudo many times at Hiei-zan mountain and on the way to the Tang Dynasty, and he was helped by it when he was in fear of his life.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enchin was in the state of enlightenment with this Kifudo many times on Mt. Hiei and on the way to the Tang Dynasty, and he was helped by it when he was in fear of his life.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 あお。(id:39226), ウィキ豊(id:82961), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>