<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>融通念仏宗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yuzu Nenbutsu sect</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yuzu Nenbutsu sect</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yuzu Nenbutsu sect</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>融通念仏宗（ゆうずうねんぶつしゅう・融通念佛宗）は、浄土教の宗派の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yuzu Nenbutsu sect is one sect of pure land teachings, Jodo-kyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yuzu Nenbutsu sect is one of the sects of pure land teachings, Jodo-kyo.</e>
<cmt>Slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yuzu Nenbutsu sect is one of the sects of pure land teachings, Jodo-kyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>平安時代末期の永久 (元号)5年5月15日 (旧暦)（1117年6月16日）に天台宗の僧侶である聖応大師良忍が大原来迎院 (京都市左京区)にて修行中、阿弥陀如来から速疾往生（阿弥陀如来から誰もが速やかに仏の道に至る方法）の偈文「一人一切人 一切人一人 一行一切行 一切行一行 十界一念 融通念仏 億百万編 功徳円満」を授かり開宗した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Shoo taishi Ryonin, a priest of Tendai sect, were performing the ascetic practices at Ohara Raigo-in Temple (Sakyo Ward Kyoto City) on May 15th in 1117 (old lunar calendar) (June 16th in 1117) during Heian Period, he was given Gemon of 速疾往生 (the way for anyone to reach Buddhism quickly from Amidanyorai), &apos;一人一切人 一切人一人 一行一切行 一切行一行 十界一念 融通念仏 億百万編 功徳円満&apos; from Amidanyorai and founded Yuzu Nenbutsu sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Shoo taishi Ryonin, priests of the Tendai sect, were performing the ascetic practices at Ohara Raigo-in Temple (Sakyo Ward Kyoto City) on May 15th in 1117 (old lunar calendar) (June 16th in 1117) during the Heian Period, he was given Gemon of 速疾往生 (the way for one to reach Buddhism quickly from Amidanyorai), &apos;一人一切人 一切人一人 一行一切行 一切行一行 十界一念 融通念仏 億百万編 功徳円満&apos; from Amidanyorai and founded the Yuzu Nenbutsu sect.</e>
<cmt>Slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Sho Taishi Ryonin, priests of the Tendai sect, were performing the ascetic practices at Ohara Raigo-in Temple (Sakyo-ku Ward, Kyoto City) on June 16, 1117 during the end of Heian period, he was given Gemon of 速疾往生 (the way for one to reach Buddhism quickly from Amida Nyorai(Amitabha Tathagata)), &apos;一人一切人 一切人一人 一行一切行 一切行一行 十界一念 融通念仏 億百万編 功徳円満&apos; from Amida Nyorai and founded the Yuzu Nenbutsu sect.</e>
<cmt>音引き表現をあわるなどしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>大念仏宗（だいねんぶつしゅう）とも言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Dainenbutsu sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called Dainenbutsu sect.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called Dainenbutsu sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>総本山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Grand Head Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Grand Head Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Grand Head Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>大念仏寺（大阪市平野区）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dainenbutsu-ji Temple (Hirano Ward Osaka City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dainenbutsu-ji Temple (Hirano Ward Osaka City)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dainenbutsu-ji Temple (Hirano Ward, Osaka City)</e>
<cmt>カンマを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>大治2年（1127年）に鳥羽天皇の勅願により、宗祖良忍が開創した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was built by Ryonin, the founder of sect, according to imperial prayer of Emperor Toba in 1127.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was built by Ryonin, the founder of the sect, according to the imperial prayers of Emperor Toba in 1127.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was built by Ryonin, the founder of the sect, according to the imperial prayers of the Emperor Toba in 1127.</e>
<cmt>the を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>坂上田村麻呂の次男で、平安時代にこの地域を開発したといわれる「平野殿」こと坂上広野の私邸内に建てられた修楽寺が前身と伝わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that it was the former Shuraku-ji Temple which was built in the personal residence of SAKANOUE no Hirono, who was the second son of SAKANOUE no Tamuramaro and was commonly called &apos;Hirano-dono,&apos; who developed this area in Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that it was the former Shuraku-ji Temple, which was built in the personal residence of SAKANOUE no Hirono, who was the second son of SAKANOUE no Tamuramaro and was commonly called &apos;Hirano-dono,&apos; who developed this area in the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that it was the former Shuraku-ji Temple, which was built in the personal residence of SAKANOUE no Hirono, who was the second son of SAKANOUE no Tamuramaro and was commonly called &apos;Hirano-dono,&apos; who developed this area in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>「period」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>日本最初の念仏道場である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the first Buddhist invocation dojo, place of Buddhist practice or meditation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the first Buddhist invocation dojo, or place of Buddhist practice or meditation.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was the first Buddhist invocation dojo, or place of Buddhist practice or meditation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>教義</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dharma</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dharma</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dharma</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>『華厳経』・『法華経』を正依とし、『無量寿経仏説無量寿経』・『観無量寿経』・『阿弥陀経』を傍依として、「1人の念仏が万人の念仏に通じる」という立場から、口称の念仏で浄土に生まれると説く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its main sutras (正依) are &quot;Kegon-kyo Sutra&quot; and &quot;Hoke-kyo Sutra&quot; and minor sutras (傍依) are &quot;Muryojyu-kyo Bussetsu Muryojyu-kyo Sutra&quot; and &quot;Kanmuryoju-kyo Sutra&quot; and &quot;Amida-kyo Sutra,&quot; and it preaches that reciting Buddhist invocation makes people reincarnated in Jodo, pure land, from the viewpoint that &apos;Buddhist invocation by one person equals to all people&apos; Buddhist invocation.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its main sutras (正依) are &quot;Kegon-kyo Sutra&quot; and &quot;Hoke-kyo Sutra&quot; and minor sutras (傍依) are &quot;Muryojyu-kyo Bussetsu Muryojyu-kyo Sutra&quot; and &quot;Kanmuryoju-kyo Sutra&quot; and &quot;Amida-kyo Sutra,&quot; and it preaches that reciting Buddhist invocation makes people reincarnated in Jodo, pure land, from the viewpoint that &apos;Buddhist invocation by one person equals Buddhist invocation to all people.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its main sutras (正依) are &quot;Kegon-kyo Sutra&quot;(Avatamska Sutra) and &quot;Hoke-kyo Sutra&quot; (Lotus Sutra) and minor sutras (傍依) are &quot;Muryoju-kyo Bussetsu Muryoju-kyo Sutra&quot;(Sutra of Infinite Life) and &quot;Kanmuryoju-kyo Sutra&quot; (&apos;The Sutra of Visualization of the Buddha of Measureless Life,&apos; meaning Amida) and &quot;Amida-kyo Sutra&quot; (Amida Sutra), and it preaches that reciting Buddhist invocation makes people reincarnated in Jodo, pure land, from the viewpoint that &apos;Buddhist invocation by one person equals Buddhist invocation to all people.&apos;</e>
<cmt>英訳を補足しました。jyu→juに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>良忍が始めた融通念仏は当初は勧進行脚が主で、仏教宗派としての組織を持たず集団運動の中から発展したものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yuzu Nenbutsu which Ryonin began was mainly temple solicitation and pilgrimage at first and developed from the collective motion having no organization as a Buddhism sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yuzu Nenbutsu, which Ryonin began, was mainly temple solicitation and pilgrimage at first and developed from a collective motion having no organization as a Buddhism sect.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yuzu Nenbutsu, which Ryonin began, was mainly temple solicitation and pilgrimage at first and developed from a collective motion having no organization as a Buddhism sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>大阪の平野 (大阪市)の大念仏寺をはじめ、京都の清凉寺や壬生寺などで融通念仏が盛んになり、壬生寺や清凉寺、引接寺 (京都市)、神泉苑には融通念仏の中興者である円覚上人による大念仏狂言が伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yuzu Nenbutsu became popular such as in Dainenbutsu-ji Temple at Hirano (Osaka City) in Osaka and Seiryo-ji Temple and Mibu-dera Temple in Kyoto, and Dainenbutsu-kyogen by Engaku Shonin, the restorer of Yuzu Nenbutsu, has been transmitted at Mibu-dera Temple, Seiryo-ji Temple, Injo-ji Temple (Kyoto City) and Shinsen-en.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yuzu Nenbutsu became popular, such as in Dainenbutsu-ji Temple at Hirano (Osaka City) in Osaka and Seiryo-ji Temple and Mibu-dera Temple in Kyoto, and Dainenbutsu-kyogen by Engaku Shonin, the restorer of Yuzu Nenbutsu, and has been transmitted at Mibu-dera Temple, Seiryo-ji Temple, Injo-ji Temple (Kyoto City) and Shinsen-en.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yuzu Nenbutsu became popular, such as in Dainenbutsu-ji Temple at Hirano (Osaka City) in Osaka and Seiryo-ji Temple and Mibu-dera Temple in Kyoto, and Dainenbutsu-kyogen Dainenbutsu Kyogen (Kyogen (farce played during a No play cycle) to teach Buddhism to the public) by Engaku Shonin, the restorer of Yuzu Nenbutsu, and has been transmitted at Mibu-dera Temple, Seiryo-ji Temple, Injo-ji Temple (Kyoto City) and Shinsen-en.</e>
<cmt>英訳を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="14">
<j>南北朝時代 (日本)の第七世法明が中興とされ、大念仏寺住職を選出する六別時制度を定めたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 7th Homyo in Nambokucho Period (Japan) was regarded as the restorer and established the system of 六別時制度 which selected chief priest of Dainenbutsu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 7th Homyo in the Nambokucho Period (Japan) was regarded as the restorer and established the system of 六別時制度 which selected the chief priest of Dainenbutsu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 7th Homyo in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan) was regarded as the restorer and established the system of Roku Betsuji (六別時制度) which selected the chief priest of Dainenbutsu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>六別時制度は、以下サイトを参考にローマ字表記しました。[http://www.shin-ibs.edu/documents/pwj3-6/06Blum36.pdf]、また他の用語を他の記事にあわせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="15">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)の頃から宗派としての色合いを帯びはじめたが、大念仏寺の法統が何度も絶え、融通念仏の寺も他宗派の寺院となり勢いは振るわなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It began to have a color as a sect around the age of civil war (Japan), but tradition of Dainenbutsu-ji Temple was ceased several times and the temples of Yuzu Nenbutsu sect became other sect&apos;s temples and lost traction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It began to have color as a sect around the age of civil war (Japan), but the tradition of Dainenbutsu-ji Temple was stopped several times and the temples of the Yuzu Nenbutsu sect became other sect&apos;s temples and lost traction.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It began to have color as a sect around the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States), but the tradition of Dainenbutsu-ji Temple was stopped several times and the temples of the Yuzu Nenbutsu sect became other sect&apos;s temples and lost traction.</e>
<cmt>用語を他の記事にあわせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>元禄年間（1688～1703）に、融通念仏再興の祖とされる大念仏寺第46世の融観が融通念仏の復興に努め、「融通円門章」等により教義を明文化し、一宗としての制規を定め、学寮も設けるなかで融通念仏宗として整備されていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From 1688 to 1703, Yukan of the 46th of Dainenbutsu-ji Temple, who was regarded as a founder of the reemergence of Yuzu Nenbutsu, tried to revive Yuzu Nenbutsu by putting dharma in the statutory form by &apos;Yuzuenmonsho,&apos; determine rules as a sect and providing dormitory, which led to the establishment of Yuzu Nenbutsu sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 1688 to 1703, the Yukan of the 46th Dainenbutsu-ji Temple, who was regarded as a founder of the reemergence of Yuzu Nenbutsu, tried to revive Yuzu Nenbutsu by putting dharma in the statutory form by &apos;Yuzuenmonsho,&apos; determine rules as a sect and providing dormitory, which led to the establishment of the Yuzu Nenbutsu sect.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 1688 to 1703, the Yukan of the 46th head priest of Dainenbutsu-ji Temple, who was regarded as a founder of the reemergence of Yuzu Nenbutsu, tried to revive Yuzu Nenbutsu by putting dharma in the statutory form by &apos;Yuzu enmonsho&apos; (Outlines of the Yuzu-Nembutsu Theology), determining rules as a sect and providing dormitory, which led to the establishment of the Yuzu Nenbutsu sect.</e>
<cmt>英訳を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>「融通円門章」は漢文体で難解なため、その弊を補うために和文形式で書かれた「融通念仏信解章」も広く普及した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since &apos;Yuzuenmonsho&apos; was written in kanbun, classical Chinese, &apos;Yuzu nenbutsu shingesho,&apos; which was written in Japanese, were widespread in order to cover negative effect of the former.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since &apos;Yuzuenmonsho&apos; was written in kanbun, classical Chinese, &apos;Yuzu nenbutsu shingesho,&apos; which was written in Japanese, were widespread in order to cover the negative effects of the former.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since &apos;Yuzu enmonsho&apos; was written in kanbun, classical Chinese, &apos;Yuzu nenbutsu shingesho&apos; (document for understanding and mastering Yuzu nenbutsu), which was written in Japanese, were widespread in order to cover the negative effects of the former.</e>
<cmt>英訳を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="18">
<j>特徴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Character</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Character</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Character</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>融通念仏の最大の特徴は、観想念仏から称名念仏の重要視に変えた事であり、融通念仏宗では、毎朝西方に向かって良忍の説いた十界一念・自他融通の浄土往生を期する念仏（融通念仏）を十唱することなどを日課とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The largest character of Yuzu Nenbutsu is that it put higher value on Invocation of the Buddha&apos;s Name than Kanso Nenbustu (観想念仏), so that Yuzu Nenbutsu sect makes reciting Buddhism invocation (Yuzu Nenbutsu), which was preached by Ryonin and expects 十界 (ten spiritual realms) 一念 (a single repetition of a prayer) and rebirth in Jodo of 自他融通, ten times toward west every morning a daily duty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The greatest characteristic of Yuzu Nenbutsu is that it put higher value on Invocation of the Buddha&apos;s Name than Kanso Nenbustu (観想念仏), so that the Yuzu Nenbutsu sect makes reciting Buddhism invocation (Yuzu Nenbutsu), which was preached by Ryonin and expects 十界 (ten spiritual realms) 一念 (a single repetition of a prayer) and rebirth in Jodo of 自他融通, ten times toward the west every morning as a daily duty.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The greatest characteristic of Yuzu Nenbutsu is that it put higher value on Invocation of the Buddha&apos;s Name than Kanso Nenbustu (Buddha ideation through chanting and visualization), so that the Yuzu Nenbutsu sect makes reciting Buddhism invocation (Yuzu Nenbutsu), which was preached by Ryonin and expects Jikkai (ten spiritual realms) Ichinen (a single repetition of a prayer) and rebirth in Jodo of Jita Yuzu (自他融通, literally, Yuzu Nenbutsu for oneself and others), ten times toward the west every morning as a daily duty.</e>
<cmt>「観想念仏」を補足[http://www.geocities.com/jw372.geo/byodoin.html]、自他融通を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="20">
<j>専修念仏の先駆であり、より純粋な天台系の浄土教仏教を伝えており、その後の浄土宗や浄土真宗の先行的形態と内容を持つともいえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a pioneering work of Senshu Nenbutsu (専修念仏) and transmitted purer Jodo-kyo Buddhism of Tendai sect, so that it can be said to have advance form and content of later Jodo sect and Jodo Shinshu sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the pioneering work of Senshu Nenbutsu (専修念仏) and transmitted the purer Jodo-kyo Buddhism of the Tendai sect, so that it can be said to have the advanced form and content of the later Jodo and Jodo Shinshu sects.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was the pioneering work of Senshu Nenbutsu (the Single-Minded Recitation of the Nenbutsu) and transmitted the purer Jodo-kyo Buddhism of the Tendai sect, so that it can be said to have the advanced form and content of the later Jodo and Jodo Shinshu sects.</e>
<cmt>用語を他の記事にあわせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Resto1578(id:168692), Izayohi(id:13095), ロリ(id:613), 浩(id:70121), 与左衛門(id:159462), 春野秋葉(id:36725), Wei Yuan(id:13342), 葉月(id:25674), 沢田(id:40580), Amaki bo(id:13580), Shimotsuke(id:19741), Nakadati(id:26815), Ko-ken(id:49348), NPD(id:58640), Ash(id:15625), 無空(id:17049), Avxz(id:123412), Junger(id:10282), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>