<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>本門佛立宗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honmon Butsuryushu (Honmon Butsuryu Sect)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honmon Butsuryushu (Honmon Butsuryu Sect)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honmon Butsuryu Sect</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>本門佛立宗（ほんもんぶつりゅうしゅう）は、長松清風によって開かれた、日蓮を宗祖と仰ぐ、法華系の一派である新宗教。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honmon Butsuryushu was the new religious sect of the school of Hokke Sect founded by Seifu NAGAMATSU of a school of Nichiren and worshiped Nichiren as the origin of the sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honmon Butsuryushu was the new religious sect of the school of the Hokke sect; it was founded by Seifu NAGAMATSU, who was of a school of Nichiren, and worshiped Nichiren as the origin of the sect.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honmon Butsuryu Sect was the new religious sect of the school of the Hokke sect; it was founded by Seifu NAGAMATSU, who was of a school of Nichiren, and worshiped Nichiren as the origin of the sect.</e>
<cmt>前出に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>開祖</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Founder</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Founder</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Founder</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>長松清風</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seifu NAGAMATSU</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seifu NAGAMATSU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seifu NAGAMATSU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>長松清風（日扇）は、人生への懐疑から法華経本門の教えに帰依して出家したがあきたらず、やがて独自の道を歩み、1857年（安政4年）41歳のとき京都蛸薬師に在家主義の本門佛立講を開いたのに始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seifu NAGAMATSU (Nissen) embraced the main school of Lotus Sutra from being skeptical about his life and underwent shukke (become a Buddhist monk) but found it disappointing, and went on an independent path to open doors of Honmon Butsuryu association that stressed on Zaike shugi (lay people doctrine) in Takoyakushi in Kyoto when he was forty-one years old in 1857.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seifu NAGAMATSU (Nissen), who had been skeptical about his life, embraced the main school of Lotus Sutra and underwent shukke (to become a Buddhist monk) but found it disappointing; subsequently, in 1857 at 41 years of age he took an independent path by opening the the doors of Honmon Butsuryu association, which stressed Zaike shugi (lay people doctrine) in Takoyakushi, Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seifu NAGAMATSU (also known as Nissen), who had been skeptical about his life, embraced the Honmon (main school) of the Lotus Sutra and became a Buddhist monk but didn&apos;t satisfied only by it; subsequently, in 1857 at 41 years of age he took an independent path by opening the doors of Honmon Butsuryu ko association, which stressed Zaike shugi (lay people doctrine) in Takoyakushi, Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>清風（日扇）の教えは、どこまでも南無妙法蓮華経の唱題の利益を信じることこそ第一とし、また目に見える現世的利益の現証を強調するものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The teachings of Seifu (Nissen) was that it was important to see the benefit of intonation of the Nichiren chant of Namu Myohorenge-kyo and stressed on the Genseriyaku (spiritual (material) benefit gained in this world through observance of the Buddhist teachings) seen by eyes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The teachings of Seifu (Nissen) were that it was important to see the benefit of intonation of the Nichiren chant of Namu Myohorenge-kyo and that it stressed the Genseriyaku (spiritual (material) benefit gained in this world through the observance of the Buddhist teachings) as seen through the eyes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The teachings of Seifu (Nissen) were that it was important to see the benefit of intonation of the Nichiren chant of Namu Myohorenge-kyo Sutra and that it stressed the spiritual (material) benefit gained in this world through the observance of the Buddhist teachings as seen through the eyes.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>寺院・僧侶の意義を認めない徹底した在家主義は、やがて徒党を組む既成寺院の僧侶から度重なる当局への讒言となり、清風（日扇）は弟子とともに逮捕されること2回、遠足止めなどの弾圧を受けるが、1878年（明治11年）には清風（日扇）自ら「花洛佛立講三十三組、人数凡1万人」というほど敎線を伸ばした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Zaike shugi not accepted by temples and monks led to the frequent slanders from monks of the league of existing temples to his temple, and Seifu (Nissen) was suppressed by being arrested twice along with his disciples and was stopped from going afar, but increased his sect size of having &apos;thirty groups of Karakufurritu-ko and around ten thousand people.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Zaike shugi, having found no acceptance by temples and monks, led to frequent slander from monks of the league of existing temples in regard to his temple, and Seifu (Nissen) was suppressed by being arrested twice along with his disciples and was stopped from going afar; however, he increased the size of his sect to one having &apos;30 groups of Karakufurritu-ko and about 10,000 people.&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Zaike shugi, having found no acceptance by temples and monks, led to frequent slander from monks of the league of existing temples in regard to his temple, and Seifu (Nissen) was suppressed by being arrested twice along with his disciples and was stopped from going afar; however, in 1878 he increased the size of his sect to one having &apos;30 groups of Karaku (Kyoto) butsuryu-ko and about 10,000 people.&apos;</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>このため本門法華宗宗門と少なからず軋轢が起こり、1869年には活動の拠点としていた本能寺から退去、宥清寺に赴いて本拠とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, there were constant frictions with the doctrine of the Honmon Hokke Sect and took leave of Honno-ji Temple which he made as a headquarter of his activities in 1869 and turned Yusei-ji Temple into his new base.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, there was ongoing friction with the doctrine of the Honmon Hokke sect; in 1869 he took leave of Honno-ji Temple, which he made the headquarters of his activities, and turned Yusei-ji Temple into his new base.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, there was ongoing friction with the doctrine of the Honmon Hokke sect; in 1869 he took leave of Honno-ji Temple, which he made the headquarters of his activities, and turned Yusei-ji Temple into his new base.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>その後清風（日扇）の遷化後、在家中心主義と僧侶との位置づけの問題・現世利益の強調など様々な論争を経て、離脱や分派が相次ぐ(分派と影響)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Seifu (Nissen) passed away, there were continuous branching of schools and desertion from various debates concerning the problem of localizing between the Zaike dogma and monks and the stressing of the Genseriyaku (Division of schools and Influence).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Seifu (Nissen) passed away, there occurred the continuous branching of schools and desertion from various debates concerning the problem of localization between the Zaike dogma and monks and the emphasis of the Genseriyaku (division of schools and influence).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Seifu (Nissen) passed away, there occurred the continuous branching of schools and desertion from various debates concerning the problem of localization between the Zaike dogma and monks and the emphasis of the Genseriyaku (spiritual (material) benefit gained in this world through observance of the Buddhist teachings) (division of schools and influence).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>第2次世界大戦後の1947年（昭和22年）本門法華宗から独立して本門佛立宗となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It became Honmon Butsuryushu by becoming independent from Honmon Hokke Sect after the World War II in 1947.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It became Honmon Butsuryushu in 1947, shortly after the end of World War II, when it attained independence from the Honmon Hokke.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It became Honmon Butsuryu Sect in 1947, shortly after the end of World War II, when it attained independence from the Honmon Hokke Sect.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>本山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honzan (Head Temple)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honzan (Head Temple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honzan (Head Temple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>宥清寺（京都府）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yusei-ji Temple (Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yusei-ji Temple (Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yusei-ji Temple (Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>由緒寺院として誕生寺（京都市）、長松寺（京都市）、佛立寺（大津市）、義天寺（守口市）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were historical temples of Tanjo-ji (Kyoto City), Chosho-ji (Kyoto City), Butsuryu-ji (Otsu City), and Giten-ji (Moriguchi City) Temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were the historical temples of Tanjo-ji (Kyoto City), Chosho-ji (Kyoto City), Butsuryu-ji (Otsu City) and Giten-ji (Moriguchi City).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were the historical temples of Tanjo-ji (Kyoto City), Chosho-ji (Kyoto City), Butsuryu-ji (Otsu City) and Giten-ji (Moriguchi City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="13">
<j>教義</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Creed</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Creed</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Creed</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>在家仏教主義</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zaike Bukkyo shugi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zaike Bukkyo shugi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zaike Bukkyo shugi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>本来の本門佛立講は、日蓮の説いた教義の布教や実践・化儀を在家の信者が自ら率先して行うことを説いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The original Honmon Butsuryu association were the individual Zaike taking the lead of actual missionary works, actual practice, and the way of Buddha teaching the human kind lectured by Nichiren.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The original Honmon Butsuryu association was the individual Zaike taking the lead in actual missionary work, practice and the way of Buddha teaching humankind, as lectured by Nichiren.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The original Honmon Butsuryu Ko association was the individual Zaike (lay believers) taking the lead in actual missionary work, practice and the way of Buddha teaching humankind, as lectured by Nichiren.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>もっとも指導教師としての僧侶は存在するものの、活動の主体は在家の信者と信者が集まって結成する講であり、殊に教えの導き手たる講親と弟子の結びつきは強調されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there was a presence of a monk as the leading teacher, the main part of the activity was the Ko (association) formed by the gathering of believers of Zaike and stressed on the connection of the leading lecturer and the disciple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there was the presence of a monk as the leading teacher, the main part of the activity was the Ko (association) formed by the gathering of believers of Zaike, which emphasized the connection between the leading lecturer and the disciple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there was the presence of a monk as the leading teacher, the main part of the activity was the Ko (association) formed by the gathering of believers of Zaike, which emphasized the connection between the leading lecturer and the disciple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>その後、僧侶が活動において指導・監督する度合いは強くなっていたが、今日でも在家の講の役割は大きいものになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The degree of leading and monitoring the activities became stronger later, but the role of the Ko remains strong even present day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The degree of leading and monitoring the activities eventually increased, but even today the role of the Ko remains strong.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The degree of leading and monitoring the activities eventually increased, but even today the role of the Ko remains strong.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="18">
<j>現世利益と他宗攻撃</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genseriyaku and Attacks from Other Sects</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genseriyaku and Attacks from Other Sects</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genseriyaku and Attacks from Other Sects</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>布教にあたっては正信の証として現世利益を強調することが強く、加えて他宗・他宗教に対する批判も激しかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It strongly stressed on the Genseriyaku as the proof of the right religion during the preaching and greatly criticized other sects and religious groups.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its preaching emphasized the Genseriyaku as proof of the right religion, and strongly criticized other sects and religious groups.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its preaching emphasized the Genseriyaku as proof of the right religion, and strongly criticized other sects and religious groups.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>入信に当たっては他宗・他宗教のお守りや札・像を破却するという、いわゆる謗法払いも佛立講が最初に行ったものであり、これらの布教方法は明治初年に大津法難を初めとする圧迫を生む一因となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Butsuryushu was the one that first carried out the abandoning of charms, notes, or statues of different sect or religion and exorcism of Hobo (the greatest punishment in Buddhism) that this missionary methods became a reason to trigger Otsu Attacks in the beginning years of Meiji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Butsuryushu was the one that first carried out the abandonment of charms, notes or statues of different sects or religions, and the exorcism of Hobo (the greatest punishment in Buddhism); thus its missionary methods became a reason to trigger the Otsu Attacks in the early years of Meiji.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Butsuryu Sect was the one that first carried out the abandonment of charms, notes or statues of different sects or religions, and the exorcism of Hobo (the greatest punishment in Buddhism); thus its missionary methods became a reason to trigger the Otsu Attacks in the early years of Meiji.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="21">
<j>御教歌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gokyoka (Religious Song)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gokyoka (Religious Song)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gokyoka (Religious Song)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>万人に、誰にでも分かりやすく御仏の教えを広めようと、御教歌と呼ばれる仏教の教義を和歌へ盛り込んだものなど、その教えは現代においても非常に分かりやすい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to make the Buddha teachings comprehensible for anyone, it used Gokyoka that incorporated the Buddhist creed into waka (Japanese poems) and is very easy to understand even now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to make the Buddha teachings comprehensible by anyone, it used Gokyoka, which incorporated the Buddhist creed into waka (Japanese poems) and is very easy to understand even in the present day.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to make the Buddha teachings comprehensible by anyone, it used Gokyoka, which incorporated the Buddhist creed into waka (Japanese poems) and is very easy to understand even in the present day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="23">
<j>ちなみに長松清風は、書画においては江戸末期の三筆と言われたり、当時の知識層などが掲載された平安人物誌、西京人物誌にその名が掲載されたり明治天皇の和歌の教師であった高崎正風が清風の詠んだ歌を優れた歌として明治天皇に紹介し、明治天皇から清風の歌を非常に賞賛されていることを知らせる使者が清風の元に使わされており、明治天皇以外にも三条実美などの公家にも清風の短冊を所望する声が多かったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The paintings and writings Sanpitsu (three great calligraphers) of the end of Edo Period, his name was published in the Heian Jinbutsushi (Heian People Magazine) and Saikyo Jinbutsushi (Saikyo People Magazines), and Masakaze TAKASAKI introduced the poem read by Seifu as the great poem to Emperor Meiji, and the messenger was sent to Seifu that the Emperor Meiji greatly praised his song, and even kuge (court noble) such as Sanetomi SANJO other than Emperor Meiji desired the tanzaku (long, narrow card on which Japanese poems are written vertically) of Seifu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thanks to the paintings and writings the Sanpitsu (three great calligraphers) of the end of Edo period, his name was published in the Heian Jinbutsushi (Heian People Magazine) and Saikyo Jinbutsushi (Saikyo People Magazine); moreover, Masakaze TAKASAKI introduced a poem by Seifu as a great poem to Emperor Meiji, and the messenger was sent to Seifu stating that the Emperor Meiji greatly praised his song, and even kuge (court noble) such as Sanetomi SANJO (other than Emperor Meiji) desired the tanzaku (a long, narrow card on which Japanese poetry is written vertically) of Seifu.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thanks to the paintings and writings the Sanpitsu (three great calligraphers) of the end of Edo period, his name was published in the Heian Jinbutsushi (Record of Heian Notables) and Saikyo Jinbutsushi (Record of Saikyo (Kyoto) Notables); moreover, Masakaze TAKASAKI introduced a poem by Seifu as a great poem to Emperor Meiji, and the messenger was sent to Seifu stating that the Emperor Meiji greatly praised his song, and even kuge (court noble) such as Sanetomi SANJO (other than Emperor Meiji) desired the tanzaku (a long, narrow card on which Japanese poetry is written vertically) of Seifu.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>江戸末期から明治を代表する優れた文化人とも言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He could be said as an excellent man of culture who represented the period from the end of Edo to Meiji Era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He can be described as an excellent man of culture who represented the period from the end of the Edo to the Meiji.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He can be described as an excellent man of culture who represented the period from the end of the Edo to the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="25">
<j>御教歌の例</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Example of Gokyoka</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Example of Gokyoka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Example of Gokyoka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="26">
<j>知恵ありて　仏になれぬ　学者かな　信の一字で　無智は成仏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even with the knowledge, one is probably an academia who cannot become Buddha but with one word of shin (believe), one can achieve nirvana with ignorance</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even with that knowledge, one is probably an academic who cannot become Buddha, but with one word of shin (believe) one of ignorance can achieve nirvana.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even with that knowledge, one is probably an academic who cannot become Buddha, but with one word of shin (believe) one of ignorance can achieve nirvana.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="27">
<j>衣着て　頭まろめて　人だます　寺住みの者　僧と思うな</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Don&apos;t think that the one that wears robe, with rounded head, deceives people, and lives in a temple is a monk</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Don&apos;t think that the one that wears robe, with rounded head, deceives people, and lives in a temple is a monk</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Don&apos;t think that the one that wears robe, with rounded head, deceives people, and lives in a temple is a monk</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="28">
<j>現証の　利益も見ずに　おろかにも　法の邪正を　あげつらうかな</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not seeing the benefit of Gensho but lets look at the evil and good of codes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Without seeing the benefit of Gensho, let us look at the evil and good of codes</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Without seeing the benefit of Gensho, let us look at the evil and good of codes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="29">
<j>など</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">as follows:</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And so on.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>分派と影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Branch Schools and Influence</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Branch Schools and Influence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Branch Schools and Influence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>清風入滅の後、講の運営に対する僧侶の関与や現世利益の強調・本門法華宗との関係のあり方など多くの論争を生み、その中から大日本獅子吼会や日蓮主義佛立講などの分派を生んでいった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Seifu there were many debates concerning the interference on monk due to the management of Ko and Genseriyakua and this gave birth to branch schools such as Dainihon Shishikukai and Nichirenshugi Butsuryuko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Seifu there were many debates concerning the interference by monks due to the management of Ko and Genseriyakua, and this gave birth to branch schools such as Dainihon Shishikukai and Nichirenshugi Butsuryuko.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Seifu there were many debates concerning the interference by monks due to the management of Ko and Genseriyaku, and this gave birth to branch schools such as Dainihon Shishikukai and Nichiren shugi (doctrine) Butsuryu-ko.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="32">
<j>また、在家主導の組織運営・現世利益の強調・他宗攻撃などのスタンスは、その後の法華系の新宗教に広く影響を与え、佛立講から霊友会へと入信して妙智会教団を創設した宮本ミツの様な遍歴を重ねるものもいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, its stance on the management of the organization, stress on Genseriyaku, and attack on other sects strongly influenced later new sects of Lotus Sutra, and there were some that went on a pilgrimage similar to Mitsu MIYAMOTO, who established Myochikaikyodan from Reiyukai from Butsuryu Ko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, its stance regarding the management of the organization, the emphasis on Genseriyaku and attacks on other sects strongly influenced later new sects of Lotus Sutra, and some went on pilgrimages similar to that of Mitsu MIYAMOTO, who established Myochikaikyodan from Reiyukai, which was in turn from Butsuryu Ko.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, its stance regarding the management of the organization, the emphasis on Genseriyaku and attacks on other sects strongly influenced later new sects of the Lotus Sutra, and some went on pilgrimages similar to that of Mitsu MIYAMOTO, who established Myochikai Kyodan from Reiyukai, which was in turn from Butsuryu Ko.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>また、霊友会の小谷喜美は佛立講と直接の関わりがないものの、御教歌を久保継成に聞かせていたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Kimi KOTANI of Reiyukai did not have a direct connection with Butsyryuko, she made Tsugunari KUBO listen to Gokyoka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Kimi KOTANI of Reiyukai didn&apos;t have a direct connection to Butsyryuko, she had Tsugunari KUBO listen to Gokyoka.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Kimi KOTANI of Reiyukai didn&apos;t have a direct connection to Butsuryu-ko, she had Tsugunari KUBO listen to Gokyoka.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="34">
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Developmental History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History and Development</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History and Development</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>1817年（文化14年）に長松清風は京都で生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1817: Seifu NAGAMATSU was born in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1817: Seifu NAGAMATSU was born in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1817: Seifu NAGAMATSU was born in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="36">
<j>1849年（嘉永2年）に長松清風は本門法華宗の隆泉寺（兵庫県南あわじ市津井）で出家する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1849: He underwent shukke (become a Buddhist monk) at Ryusen-ji Temple (Tsui, Minami Awaji City (South Awaji City), Hyogo Prefecture) of Honmon Butsuryushu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1849: He underwent shukke (to become a Buddhist monk) at Ryusen-ji Temple (Tsui, Minami Awaji City (South Awaji City), Hyogo Prefecture) of Honmon Butsuryushu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1849: He became a Buddhist monk at Ryusen-ji Temple (Tsui, Minami Awaji City, Hyogo Prefecture) of Honmon Butsuryu Sect.</e>
<cmt>前出に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>師僧は日耀上人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The monk, who was his priestly teacher, was Nichiyo Shonin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The monk, who was his priestly teacher, was Nichiyo Shonin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The monk, who was his priestly teacher, was Nichiyo Shonin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>得度名は無貪。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name he received as a monk was Muton.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name he received as a monk was Muton.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name he received as a monk was Muton.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="39">
<j>1857年（安政4年）に本門法華宗の内部に前身の本門佛立講を開く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1857: He opened up the former Honmon Butsuryuko within Honmon Hokke Sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1857: He opened the former Honmon Butsuryuko within the Honmon Hokke sect.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1857: He opened the former Honmon Butsuryu-ko within the Honmon Hokke sect.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="40">
<j>1869年（明治2年）に本門法華宗から宥清寺（京都府）を譲り受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1869: He received Yusei-ji Temple (Kyoto Prefecture) from Honmon Hokke sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1869: He received Yusei-ji Temple (Kyoto Prefecture) from the Honmon Hokke sect.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1869: He received Yusei-ji Temple (Kyoto Prefecture) from the Honmon Hokke sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="41">
<j>1890年（明治23年）に長松清風は入滅する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1890: Seifu NAGAMATSU passed away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1890: Seifu NAGAMATSU passed away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1890: Seifu NAGAMATSU passed away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="42">
<j>1899年（明治32年）に本門法華宗は長松清風に対し、日扇上人の号を贈る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1899: Honmonhokke sect gave the posthumous go (Buddhist title) of Nissen Shonin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1899: The Honmonhokke sect granted the posthumous go (Buddhist title) of Nissen Shonin.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1899: The Honmon Hokke Sect granted the posthumous go (Buddhist title) of Nissen Shonin.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="43">
<j>1912年（明治45年）に本門法華宗は長松清風に対し、日扇大僧正の位を贈る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1912: Honmonhokkeshu gave posthumous title of Nissen Daisojo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1912: Honmonhokkeshu granted the posthumous title of Nissen Daisojo.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1912: Honmon Hokke Sect granted the posthumous title of Nissen Daisojo (a Buddhist priest of the highest order).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="44">
<j>1947年（昭和22年）に本門法華宗から独立し、本門佛立宗と公称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1947: It became independent from Honmonhokkeshu and officially named itself as Honmonbutsuryo sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1947: It became independent from Honmonhokkeshu and officially renamed itself as the Honmonbutsuryo sect.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1947: It became independent from Honmon Hokke Sect and officially renamed itself as the Honmon Butsuryu Sect.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 杉山真大(id:2297), Mnd(id:15140), 浩(id:70121), Kstigarbha(id:13376), R28Bot(id:177951), Ramat ram ne(id:46376), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>