<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>霊場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reijo (sacred places)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reijo (Sacred Places)</e>
<cmt>Capitalized</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reijo (Sacred Places)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>霊場（れいじょう）は、人間の魂が集まるとされる場のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A reijo indicates a place where human souls are said to gather.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A reijo is a place where human souls are said to gather after death.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, added for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A reijo is a place where human souls are said to gather after death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>古くから信仰の対象になっており、現在でもお遍路さんや修験者などの往来の多いところがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Worshipped by people from old times, reijo are visited even today by many ohenro san (pilgrims) as well as many ascetic Buddhist monks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Worshipped by people since ancient times, reijo are visited even today by many ohenro san (pilgrims) as well as many ascetic Buddhist monks.</e>
<cmt>Word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Worshipped by people since ancient times, reijo are visited even today by many ohenro san (pilgrims) as well as many ascetic Buddhist monks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>恐山、比叡山、高野山など数多くの霊場が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There exist many reijo, including Osore-zan Mountain, Mt. Hiei, and Koya-san Mountain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many reijo, including Osore-zan Mountain, Mt. Hiei, and Koya-san Mountain.</e>
<cmt>Word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many reijo, including Osore-zan Mountain, Mt. Hiei, and Koya-san Mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>その多くは山岳信仰に根ざしたものであるが、全ての霊場が山にあるとは限らない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of them are based on mountain worship, but not all of the reijo exist in mountains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of them have roots in mountain worship, but not all reijo exist on mountains.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of them have roots in mountain worship, but not all reijo exist on mountains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>志度寺（四国八十八箇所）のように海沿いの霊場や、弁天洞窟（東京都稲城市）のような地下霊場も存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of them are located along the coast, for example, Shido-ji Temple (one of the Shikoku&apos;s eighty-eight sacred places), and some others underground, for example, Benten Dokutsu (Benten Cave) (located in Inagi City, Tokyo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of them are located along the coast, for example Shido-ji Temple (one of Shikoku&apos;s eighty-eight sacred places), and others underground, such as Benten Dokutsu (Benten Cave) located in Inagi City, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of them are located along the coast, for example Shido-ji Temple (one of Shikoku&apos;s eighty-eight sacred places), and others underground, such as Benten Dokutsu (Benten Cave) located in Inagi City, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>山岳信仰以外には、歴史的な戦闘が行われた戦場の跡などの場所がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to places based on mountain worship, reijo also include sites where historical battles were fought.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to places connected to mountain worship, reijo also include sites where historical battles were fought.</e>
<cmt>Word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to places connected to mountain worship, reijo also include sites where historical battles were fought.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また、近年では戦争などで多くの人が犠牲となった場も霊場の扱いを受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, recently, places where many persons died in wars have been dealt with as reijo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, recently places where many people died in wars have been treated as reijo.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, recently places where many people died in wars have been treated as reijo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>このため、慰霊を行う霊場は日本以外の激戦地などにもあり、毎年、日本からも巡礼団が渡航する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the reijo where a memorial service is to be held are also located in foreign places where furious battles were fought, and pilgrim parties from Japan visit these reijo every year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, many reijo where furious battles were fought are also located outside Japan, and groups of pilgrims from Japan visit these reijo every year to hold memorial services.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, many reijo where furious battles were fought are also located outside Japan, and groups of pilgrims from Japan visit these reijo every year to hold memorial services.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>また、日本では西国三十三箇所、坂東三十三箇所、秩父三十四箇所を合わせて日本百観音と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, the total of a hundred temples of Saigoku Sanjusankasho (33 temples for pilgrimage in the western region), Bando Sanjusankasho (33 temples for pilgrimage in the Kanto region) and Chichibu Sanjuyonkasho (34 temples for pilgrimage in the Chichibu area) are called the hundred Kannons (Deity of Mercy) in Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, the Saigoku Sanjusankasho (thirty-three temples for pilgrimage in the western region), Bando Sanjusankasho (thirty-three temples for pilgrimage in the Kanto region) and Chichibu Sanjuyonkasho (thirty-four temples for pilgrimage in the Chichibu area) are together called the hundred Kannon Temples (after the Deity of Mercy).</e>
<cmt>Style, changed for clarity, repetition removed, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, the Saigoku Sanjusankasho (thirty-three temples for pilgrimage in the western region), Bando Sanjusankasho (thirty-three temples for pilgrimage in the Kanto region) and Chichibu Sanjuyonkasho (thirty-four temples for pilgrimage in the Chichibu area) are together called the hundred Kannon Temples (after the Deity of Mercy).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>「百観音」という言葉そのものは平安時代からあり、その内容は時代と共に移り変わってきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term of &quot;the hundred Kannons&quot; existed from the Heian period, what the term indicated varied over time</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;the hundred Kannon&quot; has existed since the Heian Period, although what the term refers to has varied over time</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;the hundred Kannon&quot; has existed since the Heian Period, although what the term refers to has varied over time</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかいながらが、現在は西国三十三箇所、坂東三十三箇所、秩父三十四箇所を「百観音」とする定義が一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, nowadays, &quot;the hundred Kannons&quot; generally indicate the total of a hundred temples of Saigoku Sanjusankasho (33 temples for pilgrimage in the western region), Bando Sanjusankasho (33 temples for pilgrimage in the Kanto region) and Chichibu Sanjuyonkasho (34 temples for pilgrimage in the Chichibu area).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, nowadays, &quot;the hundred Kannon&quot; generally indicates the hundred temples of Saigoku Sanjusankasho, Bando Sanjusankasho and Chichibu Sanjuyonkasho as described above.</e>
<cmt>Repetition removed, punctuation, added for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, nowadays, &quot;the hundred Kannon&quot; generally indicates the hundred temples of Saigoku Sanjusankasho, Bando Sanjusankasho and Chichibu Sanjuyonkasho as described above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 海が好き(id:67125), Soudyui(id:213462), Negotiation(id:84503), Yard(id:59322), ととりん(id:31982), 暗黒な方(id:44101), Eno(id:18745), Youtetsu(id:7844), Enthousiasme(id:42600), R28Bot(id:177951), Charenji(id:7908), Nikm(id:245385), LaaknorBot(id:220851), 柑橘類(id:112137), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>