<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>年忌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nenki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nenki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nenki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>年忌（ねんき）とは、命日。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nenki is an anniversary of the death of a person.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nenki is an anniversary of the death of a person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nenki is an anniversary of the death of a person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>また、その日に営まれる仏事のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nenki also means the Buddhist service held on that day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nenki also refers to the Buddhist service held on that day.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nenki also refers to the Buddhist service held on that day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>日本の仏教において、定められた年に故人に対して営まれる法要を、年忌法要（年回法要）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Japanese Buddhism, a hoyo (Buddhist memorial service) held in the year certain number of years after the person&apos;s death is called &quot;Nenki hoyo&quot; (Nenkai hoyo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japanese Buddhism, a hoyo (Buddhist memorial service) held in a certain number of years after the person&apos;s death is called &quot;Nenki hoyo&quot; (Nenkai hoyo).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japanese Buddhism, a hoyo (Buddhist memorial service) held in a certain number of years after the person&apos;s death is called &quot;Nenki hoyo&quot; (Nenkai hoyo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>供養のために営まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nenki hoyo is held for kuyo (to pray for the repose of the dead).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nenki hoyo is held for kuyo (to pray for the repose of the dead).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nenki hoyo is held for kuyo (to pray for the repose of the dead).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>浄土真宗では追善供養を行わないため、仏法にふれる機縁の法要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the believers of the Jodo Shishu sect do not pray for the dead, nenki hoyo is a chance to touch the teaching of the Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the believers of the Jodo Shishu sect do not pray for the dead, nenki hoyo is a chance to touch the teachings of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the believers of the Jodo Shishu sect do not pray for the dead, nenki hoyo is a chance to touch the teachings of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>中陰（忌明け）後、命日から100日目に「百ヶ日」の法要が行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the chuin (a period of mourning lasting seven weeks) (end of chuin also called &quot;kiake&quot; which means the end of mourning), on the one hundredth day after the death, a hoyo of hyakkanichi (one hundredth day) is held.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the chuin (a period of mourning lasting seven weeks) (the end of chuin is also called &quot;kiake,&quot; which means the end of mourning), on the one hundredth day after the death, a hoyo of hyakkanichi (one hundredth day) is held.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the chuin (a period of mourning lasting seven weeks) (the end of chuin is also called &quot;kiake,&quot; which means the end of mourning), on the one hundredth day after the death, a hoyo of hyakkanichi (one hundredth day) is held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>この「百ヶ日」と「一周忌」、「三回忌」の3つの法要は、中国の儒教の祭祀の影響によって付加されたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The three types of hoyo including hyakkanichi, isshuki (the first anniversary of one&apos;s death) and sankaiki (second anniversary of one&apos;s death) were added by the influence from the religious services of the Chinese Confucianism.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The three types of hoyo, hyakkanichi, isshuki (the first anniversary of one&apos;s death), and sankaiki (second anniversary of one&apos;s death), were added by the influence of religious services of Chinese Confucianism.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The three types of hoyo, hyakkanichi, isshuki (the first anniversary of one&apos;s death), and sankaiki (second anniversary of one&apos;s death), were added by the influence of religious services of Chinese Confucianism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>これは、亡者が「初七日」～「七七日（四十九日）」と「百ヶ日」を含めた8つの忌日と、「一周忌」、「三回忌」の2つの年忌の、合計10度の時点で、冥界の十人の王に審判を受けるという「十王信仰」に基づいている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These are based on the belief called &apos;jyuoshinko&apos; in which a dead should get ten judgments, from each of the ten kings of the realm of the dead, on ten specific days consisting of eight kinichi (specific days after death) of every seventh day starting from the shonanoka (the sixth day after the death) till the shijukunichi (the forty-ninth day after death), and two nenki, the isshuki and the sankaiki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These are based on the belief called &apos;jyuoshinko&apos; in which the dead should receive ten judgments, from each of the ten kings of the realm of the dead, on ten specific days consisting of eight kinichi (specific days after death) of every seventh day starting from the shonanoka (the sixth day after the death) until the shijukunichi (the forty-ninth day after death), and two nenki, the isshuki and the sankaiki.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These are based on the belief called &apos;jyuoshinko&apos; in which the dead should receive ten judgments, from each of the ten kings of the realm of the dead, on ten specific days consisting of eight kinichi (specific days after death) of every seventh day starting from the shonanoka (the sixth day after the death) until the shijukunichi (the forty-ninth day after death), Hyakkanichi (the one-hundredth day after death) and two nenki, the isshuki and the sankaiki.</e>
<cmt>Hyakkanichi (the one-hundredth day after death)を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>この、十王信仰は、仏教が伝来した後に、中国で生まれた信仰であり、道教とも共有しているものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The jyuoshinko began in China after the introduction of Buddhism and has been shared with the Taoism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jyuoshinko began in China after the introduction of Buddhism and has been shared with Taoism.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jyuoshinko began in China after the introduction of Buddhism and has been shared with Taoism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その審判の時に、遺族による追善供養による功徳で、亡者の審判に資することを期すのが、忌日と年忌の法要の持つ意味あいである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the meaning of the hoyo of kinichi and nenki to hope that the pious act of tsuizen (ceremony as a memorial) kuyo held by the bereaved may be help for the dead at the judgment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The meaning of the hoyo of kinichi and nenki is to hope that the pious act of tsuizen (ceremony as a memorial) kuyo held by the bereaved may provide help for the dead at the judgment.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The meaning of the hoyo of kinichi and nenki is to hope that the pious act of tsuizen (ceremony as a memorial) kuyo held by the bereaved may provide help for the dead at the judgment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>「七回忌」以降の法要は、日本で独自に付加されたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoyo of shichikaiki (the sixth anniversary of one&apos;s death) and after were added originally in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoyo of shichikaiki (the sixth anniversary of one&apos;s death) and after were added originally in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoyo of shichikaiki (the sixth anniversary of one&apos;s death) and after were added originally in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>日本では11世紀以降に、十王信仰が広まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The jyuoshinko had spread in eleventh century and after in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jyuoshinko spread in Jpaan in the eleventh century and after.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jyuoshinko spread in Japan in the eleventh century and after.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>さらにその後、鎌倉時代に、「七回忌」、「十三回忌」、「三十三回忌」が行われるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, in the Kamakura period, sichikaiki. jyusankaiki (the twelfth anniversary of one&apos;s death) and sanjyusankaiki (the 32nd anniversary of one&apos;s death) were begun to be held.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, in the Kamakura period, sichikaiki. jyusankaiki (the twelfth anniversary of one&apos;s death) and sanjyusankaiki (the 32nd anniversary of one&apos;s death) begun to be held.</e>
<cmt>verb form</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, in the Kamakura period, sichikaiki. jyusankaiki (the twelfth anniversary of one&apos;s death) and sanjyusankaiki (the 32nd anniversary of one&apos;s death) begun to be held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これは、「十三仏信仰」に基づいている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are based on the Jusanbutsu shinko (Thirteen Buddha belief).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are based on the Jusanbutsu shinko (Thirteen Buddha beliefs).</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are based on the Jusanbutsu shinko (Thirteen Buddha beliefs).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>これは、十王信仰の各王を垂迹と見て、それぞれの王に本地となる仏菩薩を擬定している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Jusanbutsushinko regards each king of the jyuoshinko as suijaku (temporary manifestation) of Buddha and the original Buddha or Bosatsu has been assigned to each of the ten kings.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Jusanbutsushinko regards each king of the jyuoshinko as a suijaku (temporary manifestation) of Buddha, and the original Buddha or Bosatsu has been assigned to each of the ten kings.</e>
<cmt>article. Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Jusanbutsushinko regards each king of the jyuoshinko as a suijaku (temporary manifestation) of Buddha, and the original Buddha or Bosatsu has been assigned to each of the ten kings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>それぞれの法要の時には、その仏菩薩を本尊として法要を行うというものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hoyo of each time is held with each Buddha or Bosatsu as the honzon (principal object of worship).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hoyo of each time is held with each Buddha or Bosatsu as the honzon (principal object of worship).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hoyo of each time is held with each Buddha or Bosatsu as the honzon (principal object of worship).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>また、神道では三十三回忌をもって荒御霊が和御霊（祖霊）になるとするため、三十三回忌を区切りとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Shinto religion, as it is considered that when the sanjyusankaiki is reached the aramitama (stormy spirit) changes to nigimitama (mild spirit) and to mioyanomitama (ancestor&apos;s spirit), the sanjyusankaiki is treated as a turning point.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Shinto religion, as it is considered that when the sanjyusankaiki is reached the aramitama (stormy spirit) changes to nigimitama (mild spirit) and to mioyanomitama (ancestor&apos;s spirit), the sanjyusankaiki is treated as a turning point.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Shinto religion, as it is considered that when the sanjyusankaiki is reached the aramitama (stormy spirit) changes to nigimitama (mild spirit) and to mioyanomitama (ancestor&apos;s spirit), the sanjyusankaiki is treated as a turning point.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>日本の仏教の一部では、神仏習合の影響により、三十三回忌・五十回忌をめどに「祖先神」として一体化すると考える場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some Buddhist sects in Japan, it may be considered by the influence of the syncretism of Shinto and Buddhism that individual spirit will become unified with the sosen shin (ancestral god) at the time of the sanjyusankaiki or the gojyukaiki (the 49th anniversary of one&apos;s death).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some Buddhist sects in Japan, it may be considered by the influence of the syncretism of Shinto and Buddhism that the individual spirit will become unified with the sosen shin (ancestral god) at the time of the sanjyusankaiki or the gojyukaiki (the 49th anniversary of one&apos;s death).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some Buddhist sects in Japan, it may be considered by the influence of the syncretism of Shinto and Buddhism that the individual spirit will become unified with the sosen shin (ancestral god) at the time of the sanjyusankaiki or the gojyukaiki (the 49th anniversary of one&apos;s death).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="19">
<j>さらに、上記以外の年忌も含めて三ないし七にて勤めるのは、一般的に儒家の三魂七魄に基づいている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is based on the sankonshichihaku of the Confucianism that all the nenki including other than above mentioned are held generally at interval of multiples of three or seven.</e>
<cmt>「三魂七魄」の訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is based on the sankonshichihaku of Confucianism that all the nenki, including other than those mentioned above, are held generally at intervals of multiples of three or seven.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is based on the sankonshichihaku of Confucianism that all the nenki, including other than those mentioned above, are held generally at intervals of multiples of three or seven.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="20">
<j>あと、「十三回忌」は、十二支が一巡する事をもとに勤めると考え「二十五回忌」は、十二支が二巡したとも五十回遠忌の半分とも考える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The jyusankaiki may also be considered as one round of jyunishi (twelve signs of the Chinese zodiac) and the nijjyugokaiki (the 24th anniversary of one&apos;s death) as two rounds or as a half of the gojyukai onki (the 49th anniversary of one&apos;s death).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The jyusankaiki may also be considered one round of jyunishi (twelve signs of the Chinese zodiac) and the nijjyugokaiki (the 24th anniversary of one&apos;s death) two rounds or half of the gojyukai onki (the 49th anniversary of one&apos;s death).</e>
<cmt>omitted &apos;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The jyusankaiki may also be considered one round of jyunishi (twelve signs of the Chinese zodiac) and the nijjyugokaiki (the 24th anniversary of one&apos;s death) two rounds or half of the gojyukai onki (the 49th anniversary of one&apos;s death).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>そして、普通五十回忌からは遠忌（おんき）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally, the gojyukaiki and after it are called onki (far nenki).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, the gojyukaiki and the nenki after it are called onki (far nenki).</e>
<cmt>inserted words</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, the gojyukaiki and the nenki after it are called onki (far nenki).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>年忌法要一覧</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">List of nenki hoyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">List of nenki hoyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">List of nenki hoyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>故人の祥月命日の内、定められた年に営まれる法要が、年忌法要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoyo held on the shotsuki meinichi (the same month and the same day of month of death) in certain years are called nenki hoyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoyo held on the shotsuki meinichi (the same month and the same day of month of death) in certain years are called nenki hoyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoyo held on the shotsuki meinichi (the same month and the same day of month of death) in certain years are called nenki hoyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>宗旨、地域によっても異なるが、一般に下記の法要が営まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally, these hoyo listed below are held although some difference may exist depending on sect and region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, these hoyo listed below are held, although some difference may exist depending on the sect and region.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, these hoyo listed below are held, although some difference may exist depending on the sect and region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>また、祥月命日に営むのが最善ではあるが、当日に都合が付かない場合は、事前に営むのが一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it is best for hoyo to be held on the shotsuki meinichi, generally it will be held before the day if it were impossible to be held on the day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is best for hoyo to be held on the shotsuki meinichi, if it is impossible to be held on the day, it generally will be held before the day.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is best for hoyo to be held on the shotsuki meinichi, if it is impossible to be held on the day, it generally will be held before the day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>百ヶ日…卒哭忌（そっこうき）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hyakkanichi - also called &quot;Sokkoki&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hyakkanichi - also called &quot;Sokkoki&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hyakkanichi - also called &quot;Sokkoki&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="26">
<j>一周忌…没後、最初（翌年）の祥月命日。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Isshuki - the first shotsuki meinichi after the death (the next year).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Isshuki - the first shotsuki meinichi after death (the next year).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Isshuki - the first shotsuki meinichi after death (the next year).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>一般に、この日までが「喪中」とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally, the period from the death to this day are called &quot;mochu&quot; (period of mourning).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, the period from the death to this day are called &quot;mochu&quot; (period of mourning).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, the period from the death to this day are called &quot;mochu&quot; (period of mourning).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>明治時代の服忌令に基づき13ヶ月とする場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a case that period of mochu is thirteen month according to the low of mourning in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a case that the period of mochu is thirteen months according to the law of mourning in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>plural, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a case that the period of mochu is thirteen months according to the law of mourning in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="29">
<j>三回忌…没後、2年目の祥月命日。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sankaiki - the shotsuki meinichi after two years of the death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sankaiki - the shotsuki meinichi two years after death.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sankaiki - the shotsuki meinichi two years after death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>一般に三回忌まで、親類を呼ぶ場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally, relatives are gathered until the sankaiki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, relatives are gathered until the sankaiki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, relatives are gathered until the sankaiki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="31">
<j>七回忌…没後、6年目の祥月命日。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shichikaiki - the shotsuki meinichi after six years of the death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shichikaiki - the shotsuki meinichi six years after death.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shichikaiki - the shotsuki meinichi six years after death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="32">
<j>十三回忌…没後、12年目の祥月命日。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jyusankaiki - the shotsuki meinichi after twelve years of the death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jyusankaiki - the shotsuki meinichi twelve years after death.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jyusankaiki - the shotsuki meinichi twelve years after death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="33">
<j>十七回忌…没後、16年目の祥月命日。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jyushichikaiki - the shotsuki meinichi after sixteen years of the death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jyushichikaiki - the shotsuki meinichi sixteen years after death.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jyushichikaiki - the shotsuki meinichi sixteen years after death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="34">
<j>二十三回忌…没後、22年目の祥月命日。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nijyusankaiki - the shotsuki meinichi after twenty two years of the death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nijyusankaiki - the shotsuki meinichi twenty two years after death.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nijyusankaiki - the shotsuki meinichi twenty two years after death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="35">
<j>二十五回忌…没後、24年目の祥月命日。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nijyugokaiki - the shotsuki meinichi after twenty four years of the death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nijyugokaiki - the shotsuki meinichi twenty four years after death.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nijyugokaiki - the shotsuki meinichi twenty four years after death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="36">
<j>二十七回忌…没後、26年目の祥月命日。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nijyushichikaiki - the shotsuki meinichi after twenty six years of the death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nijyushichikaiki - the shotsuki meinichi twenty six years after death.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nijyushichikaiki - the shotsuki meinichi twenty six years after death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="37">
<j>三十三回忌…没後、32年目の祥月命日。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanjyusankaiki - the shotsuki meinichi after thirty two years of the death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanjyusankaiki - the shotsuki meinichi thirty two years after death.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanjyusankaiki - the shotsuki meinichi thirty two years after death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="38">
<j>三十七回忌…没後、36年目の祥月命日。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanjyushichikaiki - the shotsuki meinichi after thirty six years of the death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanjyushichikaiki - the shotsuki meinichi thirty six years after death.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanjyushichikaiki - the shotsuki meinichi thirty six years after death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="39">
<j>五十回（遠）忌…没後、49年目の祥月命日。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gojyukaiki or Gojyukai onki - the shotsuki meinichi after forty nine years of the death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gojyukaiki or Gojyukai onki - the shotsuki meinichi forty nine years after death.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gojyukaiki or Gojyukai onki - the shotsuki meinichi forty nine years after death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="40">
<j>以降50年毎に、百回遠忌（99年目）、百五十回遠忌（149年目）…と営む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, nenki with a period of fifty years are held such as the Hyakkai onki (ninety ninth year), the Hyakugojyukai onki (one hundred and forty ninth year) and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, nenki with a period of fifty years are held, such as the Hyakkai onki (ninety ninth year), the Hyakugojyukai onki (one hundred and forty ninth year), and so on.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, nenki with a period of fifty years are held, such as the Hyakkai onki (ninety ninth year), the Hyakugojyukai onki (one hundred and forty ninth year), and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="41">
<j>宗派、地域によって異なるものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are differences in nenki depending on sect and region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are differences in nenki depending on sect and region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are differences in nenki depending on sect and region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="42">
<j>「二十三回忌」、「二十五回忌」、「二十七回忌」、「三十七回忌」は、宗旨や地域による差が特に大きい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such differences are significant on the Nijyusankaiki, Nijyugokaiki, Nijyushichikaiki and Sanjyushichikaiki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such differences are significant on the Nijyusankaiki, Nijyugokaiki, Nijyushichikaiki and Sanjyushichikaiki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such differences are significant on the Nijyusankaiki, Nijyugokaiki, Nijyushichikaiki and Sanjyushichikaiki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="43">
<j>「二十三回忌」と「二十七回忌」を営む場合や「二十五回忌」のみ営む場合。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are cases such as to perform Nijyusankaiki and Nijyushichikaiki or to perform Nijyugokaiki only.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are cases such as performing Nijyusankaiki and Nijyushichikaiki or performing Nijyugokaiki only.</e>
<cmt>verb form</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are cases such as performing Nijyusankaiki and Nijyushichikaiki or performing Nijyugokaiki only.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>「三十七回忌」は、営まないなど。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also there is a case not to perform the Sanjyushichikaiki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also there is a case of not performing the Sanjyushichikaiki.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also there is a case of not performing the Sanjyushichikaiki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="45">
<j>「三十三回忌」、もしくは「五十回（遠）忌」を最後の年忌にするのが一般的であり、それを「弔い上げ」、あるいは、「問切り」と呼んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is general to let the Sanjyusankaiki or the Gojyukai onki to be the last nenki, and the last nenki are called &quot;tomuraiage&quot; or &quot;toikiri&quot; (both the last memorial service).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is general practice to let the Sanjyusankaiki or the Gojyukai onki be the last nenki, and the last nenki are called &quot;tomuraiage&quot; or &quot;toikiri&quot; (both the last memorial service).</e>
<cmt>added &quot;practice&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is general practice to let the Sanjyusankaiki or the Gojyukai onki be the last nenki, and the last nenki are called &quot;tomuraiage&quot; or &quot;toikiri&quot; (both the last memorial service).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>その時に、寺への寄進や永代供養を行う場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, often donation to the temple is made requesting eitai kuyo (to do memorial service by the temple for a longer period).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, donationis often made to the temple requesting eitai kuyo (to perform memorial service for a longer period).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, donationis often made to the temple requesting eitai kuyo (to perform memorial service for a longer period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Resto1578(id:168692), Keito771(id:67804), 経済準学士(id:22656), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Oomiya(id:97179), Wei Yuan(id:13342), Ajax(id:11202), Yatobi(id:9686), ウィキ豊(id:82961), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>