<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>普賢菩薩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fugen Bosatsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fugen Bosatsu</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fugen Bosatsu (Samantabhadra Bodhisattva)</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>普賢菩薩（ふげんぼさつ）、サンスクリットサマンタ・バドラ (samanta bhadra)は、大乗仏教における崇拝の対象である菩薩の一尊。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fugen Bosatsu, samanta bhadra in Sanskrit, is a venerable entity of Bosatsu, Bodhisattva, which is worshipped in Mahayana Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fugen Bosatsu, samanta bhadra in Sanskrit, is a venerable Bosatsu entity and is Bodhisattva, which is worshipped in Mahayana Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>Slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fugen Bosatsu, samanta bhadra in Sanskrit, is a venerable Bosatsu entity and is Bodhisattva, which is worshipped in Mahayana Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>三昧耶形は剣、五鈷杵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanmayagyo Symbol is a sword and Gokosho, a short club with five prongs at each end, usually made of gilt bronze.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanmayagyo Symbol is a sword and Gokosho, a short club with five prongs at each end, are usually made of gilt bronze.</e>
<cmt>Slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanma yagyo (characteristic things of the Buddha) is a sword and Gokosho (A short club with five prongs at each end, usually made of gilt bronze).</e>
<cmt>用語を他の記事にあわせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>種子 (密教)（種字）はアン(aM)、ウーン(huuM)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shushi (Mikkyo, Esoteric Buddhism) (Shuji) is aM and huuM.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shushi (Mikkyo, Esoteric Buddhism) (Shuji) is aM and huuM.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shushi (Mikkyo, Esoteric Buddhism) is aM and huuM.</e>
<cmt>重複を除きました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>梵名のサマンタ・バドラとは「普く賢い者」の意味であり、彼が世界にあまねく現れ仏の慈悲と理知を顕して人々を救う賢者である事を意味する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sanskrit name samanta bhadra means &apos;far and widewise man&apos; and that he is a wise man who appears in the far and wide world and relieve people with Buddha&apos;s mercy and intelligence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sanskrit name samanta bhadra means &apos;far and widewise man&apos; and that he is a wise man who appears in the far and wide world and relieves people with Buddha&apos;s mercy and intelligence.</e>
<cmt>Slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sanskrit name samanta bhadra means &apos;far and widewise man&apos; and that he is a wise man who appears in the far and wide world and relieves people with Buddha&apos;s mercy and intelligence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また、女人成仏を説く法華経に登場することから、特に女性の信仰を集めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, since it is seen in Hoke-kyo Sutra, it has been worshipped by women in special.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, since it is seen in Hoke-kyo Sutra, it has been especially worshipped by women.</e>
<cmt>Slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, since it is seen in Hoke-kyo Sutra which preaches Nyonin Jobutsu (Attainment of Buddhahood by women), it has been especially worshipped by women.</e>
<cmt>「女人成仏を説く」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>密教では菩提心(真理を究めて悟りを求めようという心)の象徴とされ、同じ性格を持つ金剛薩埵と同一視される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Mikkyo it is regarded as a symbol of aspiration for Buddhahood (a mind to seek enlightenment through mastering the truth) and seen as the same entity as Kongosatta which has the same character.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Mikkyo it is regarded as a symbol of aspiration for Buddhahood (a mind to seek enlightenment through mastering the truth) and seen as the same entity as Kongosatta which has the same character.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Mikkyo it is regarded as a symbol of aspiration for Buddhahood (a mind to seek enlightenment through mastering the truth) and seen as the same entity as Kongosatta which has the same character.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そのため普賢菩薩はしばしば金剛薩埵の別名でもある金剛手菩薩(こんごうしゅぼさつ)とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, Fugen Bosatsu is often called Kongoshu Bosatsu, another name of Kongosatta, as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, Fugen Bosatsu is often called Kongoshu Bosatsu, another name for Kongosatta, as well.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, Fugen Bosatsu is often called Kongoshu Bosatsu, another name for Kongosatta, as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>中国・四川省の峨眉山が普賢菩薩の霊場とされ、文殊菩薩とともに釈迦如来の脇侍を勤める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gabisan mountain, Emeishan mountain, in Sichuan Province of China is regarded as Reijo, sacred ground, of Fugen Bosatsu and its statue is placed as Kyoji, attendant figure, of Shakanyorai with Monju Bosatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gabisan and Emeishan mountains in Sichuan Province, China are regarded as Reijo, sacred ground, of the Fugen Bosatsu and statues are placed as Kyoji, attendant figures, of Shakanyorai with Monju Bosatsu.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mt. Gabi (Emeishan) in Sichuan Province, China are regarded as Reijo, sacred ground, of the Fugen Bosatsu and statues are placed as Kyoji, attendant figures, of Shakanyorai with Monju Bosatsu (Manjusri).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>（参照：釈迦三尊）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(See Shaka sanzon, Shaka triad.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(See Shaka sanzon, Shaka triad.)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(See Shaka sanzon, Shaka triad.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>像容・作例</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Features of statue and works</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Features of statue and works</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Features of statue and works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>独尊としては、蓮華座を乗せた六牙の白象に結跏趺坐して合掌する姿で描かれるのが、最も一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As an individual Buddha, the most common figure is expressed as a figure which joins its hands in prayer in lotus position on the white elephant which has six ivories and puts Rengeza (padmasana, Lotus base) on the back.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As an individual Buddha, the most common figure is expressed as a figure which joins its hands in prayer in the lotus position on a white elephant that has six ivory tusks and has Rengeza (padmasana, Lotus base) on the back.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As an individual Buddha, the most common figure is expressed as a figure which joins its hands in prayer in the lotus position on a white elephant that has six ivory tusks and has Rengeza (padmasana, Lotus base) on the back.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>密教では、左手に宝剣を立てた蓮茎を持る姿や、金剛薩たと全く同じ左手に五鈷鈴、右手に五鈷杵を執る姿で表される他、如意や蓮華、経典を手に持つ作例も見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Mikkyo it is expressed as a figure which has a stem of lotus on which a treasure sword is put in the left hand and a figure which has gokorei (five-pronged bell) in the left hand and Gokosho in the right hand in the same way as Kongosatta, and figures which has nyoi (an implement carried by Buddhist priests at a ceremony or during formal preaching), lotus flower and scriptures as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Mikkyo it is expressed as a figure which has a lotus stem on which a treasure sword is placed in the left hand and a figure which has gokorei (a five-pronged bell) in the left hand and Gokosho in the right hand in the same way as Kongosatta, and figures which have nyoi (an implement carried by Buddhist priests at a ceremony or during formal preaching), lotus flower and scriptures as well.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Mikkyo it is expressed as a figure which has a lotus stem on which a treasure sword is placed in the left hand and a figure which has gokorei (a five-pronged bell) in the left hand and Gokosho in the right hand in the same way as Kongosatta, and figures which have nyoi (an implement carried by Buddhist priests at a ceremony or during formal preaching), lotus flower and scriptures as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>日本では平安中期以降、女性の救済を説く法華経の普及によって、主に貴婦人たちからの信仰を集めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan since the middle of the Heian Period it was worshipped mainly from noble women in accordance with prevalence of Hoke-kyo Sutra which preaches women&apos;s relief.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan from the middle of the Heian Period, it was worshipped mainly by noble women in accordance with the prevalence of Hoke-kyo Sutra, which preaches women&apos;s relief.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan from the middle of the Heian period, it was worshipped mainly by noble women in accordance with the prevalence of Hoke-kyo Sutra, which preaches women&apos;s relief.</e>
<cmt>「period」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>日本では絵画・彫像とも作例が多く、彫像の作例としては、大倉集古館の平安時代後期の木像（国宝）などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan there are many works of pictures and statues, such as the wooden statue (national treasure) at The Okura Shukokan Museum of Fine Arts in the latter part of Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan there are many pictures and statues, such as the wooden statue (national treasure) at The Okura Shukokan Museum of Fine Arts in the latter part of Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan there are many pictures and statues, such as the wooden statue (national treasure) of Fine Arts in the latter part of Heian period at The Okura Shukokan Museum.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>より密教的な姿として「普賢延命菩薩」という尊格があり、22手を持つ強力な尊とされ、日本でも作例は少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fugen Enmei Bosatsu,&apos; one venerable status which was more strongly influenced by Mikkyo, is regarded as a strong venerable entity to have 22 hands and many works have been made in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fugen Enmei Bosatsu,&apos; has venerable status and was more strongly influenced by Mikkyo, and is regarded as a strong venerable entity with 22 hands and many examples of this work have been made in Japan.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fugen Enmei Bosatsu,&apos; has venerable status and was more strongly influenced by Mikkyo, and is regarded as a strong venerable entity with 22 hands and many examples of this work have been made in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>絵画作品としては東京国立博物館の普賢菩薩騎象像（国宝、平安時代後期）が代表的な作例である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As to pictures, the picture of Fugen Bosatsu on an elephant in Tokyo National Museum (national treasure, in the latter part of Heian Period) is a representative work.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concerning pictures, the picture of Fugen Bosatsu on an elephant in Tokyo National Museum (national treasure from the latter part of the Heian Period) is a representative work.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concerning pictures, the picture of Fugen Bosatsu on an elephant in Tokyo National Museum (national treasure, the latter part of the Heian period) is a representative work.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>他に鳥取県豊乗寺（ぶじょうじ）本（国宝）、奈良国立博物館本（重要文化財）などが代表作として知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The book of Bujo-ji Temple in Tottori Prefecture (national treasure), the book of Nara National Museum (important cultural property) and others are known as representative works.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The book of Bujo-ji Temple in Tottori Prefecture (national treasure) and the book of Nara National Museum (important cultural property) and others are known as representative works.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The book of Bujo-ji Temple in Tottori Prefecture (national treasure) and the book of Nara National Museum (important cultural property) and others are known as representative works.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>眷属</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenzoku, Disciples or followers of Buddha</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenzoku, Disciples or followers of Buddha</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenzoku, Disciples or followers of Buddha</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>普賢菩薩の眷属は十羅刹女とされ、また時として十羅刹女たちの母鬼子母神も眷属とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that kenzoku of Fugen Bosatsu is ju-rasetsunyo, ten demonesses, and sometimes Kishimo-jin, a mother of ju-rasetsunyos, are placed as kenzoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the kenzoku of Fugen Bosatsu is ju-rasetsunyo, or ten demonesses, and that sometimes Kishimo-jin, a mother of the ju-rasetsunyos, is placed as kenzoku.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the kenzoku of Fugen Bosatsu is ju-rasetsunyo, or ten demonesses, and that sometimes Kishimo-jin, a mother of the Ju-rasetsunyos, is placed as kenzoku.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>初期の十羅刹女は唐装束であるが、国風の影響を受けた和装の羅刹女の作例も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jju-rasetsunyo of an early date put on Tang dynasty Chinese costume but there are also many works of ju-rasetsunyo who put on Japanese costume influenced by Japanese culture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At an early date, Jju-rasetsunyo put employed Tang dynasty Chinese costumes, but there are also many works of ju-rasetsunyo using Japanese costumes influenced by Japanese culture.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At an early date, Ju-rasetsunyo put employed Tang dynasty Chinese costumes, but there are also many works of Ju-rasetsunyo using Japanese costumes influenced by Japanese culture.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>これは、法華経において普賢菩薩と十羅刹女が共に「法華経を護持する者を守る」と誓っていることによるが、これらの女神がそばにいることも、 女性からの信仰を厚くする一因となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is because Fugen Bosatsu and ju-rasetsunyo swear &apos;to guard people who defend Hoke-kyo Sutra&apos; together in Hoke-kyo Sutra, and it became a reason for women&apos;s belief of Fugen Bosatsu that these goddess stay around Fugen Bosatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because Fugen Bosatsu and ju-rasetsunyo swear &apos;to guard people who defend Hoke-kyo Sutra&apos; together in Hoke-kyo Sutra, and it became the reason for women&apos;s belief that these goddess`s stay close to Fugen Bosatsu.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because Fugen Bosatsu and Ju-rasetsunyo swear &apos;to guard people who defend Hoke-kyo Sutra&apos; together in Hoke-kyo Sutra, and it became the reason for women&apos;s belief that these goddess&apos;s stay close to Fugen Bosatsu.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>なお、小説『封神演義』には普賢真人、文殊広法天尊という仙人が登場しており、この作品では、彼等が後に仏門に帰依しそれぞれ普賢菩薩、文殊菩薩となったとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, in the novel &quot;Feng-Shen-Yen-I,&quot; the Sennin (wizard) named Fugen Shinjin and Monju Koho Tenson appeared, became to believe Buddhism later, and became each Fugen Bosatsu and Monji Bosatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, in the novel &quot;Feng-Shen-Yen-I,&quot; the Sennin (wizards) named Fugen Shinjin and Monju Koho Tenson appeared and later came to believe in Buddhism, and subsequently became Fugen Bosatsu and Monji Bosatsu, respectively.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, in the novel &quot;Feng-Shen-Yen-I&quot; (Popular Account of the Promotion to Divinity), the Sennin (wizards) named Fugen Shinjin and Monju Koho Tenson appeared and later came to believe in Buddhism, and subsequently became Fugen Bosatsu and Monji Bosatsu, respectively.</e>
<cmt>『封神演義』の英訳を補足しました。[http://www.bibliotecapleyades.net/hamlets_mill/hamletmill23.htm]</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>真言</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mantra, Shingon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mantra, Shingon</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mantra, Shingon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>オン・サンマヤ・サトバン</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On Sanmaya Sabaton.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On Sanmaya Sabaton.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On Sanmaya Sabaton.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Five-toed-sloth(id:85878), JAnDbot(id:66507), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Peehyoro Acala(id:170), Tomzo(id:16777), Idioma-bot(id:129667), Drblack(id:116617), Urania(id:7213), Charenji(id:7908), Eskimbot(id:29676), VOPDS(id:78316), Escarbot(id:59151), Maha simha(id:209475), Pontormo(id:12606), ＮｉＫｅ(id:7512), R28Bot(id:177951), あお。(id:39226), Loveless(id:129239), 無空(id:17049), 宗治(id:111540), Corwin(id:973), Qurren(id:20140), ナメネコ(id:27476), ウィキ豊(id:82961), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>