<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>能円</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>能円（のうえん、保延6年（1140年） - 正治元年（1199年）は平安時代末期の僧侶。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noen (1140-1199) was a Buddhist monk at the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noen (1140-1199) was a Buddhist monk who lived at the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noen (1140-1199) was a Buddhist monk who lived at the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>皇后宮亮藤原顕憲の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the son of FUJIWARA no Akinori, who was kogogu no suke (an official responsible for managing the empress&apos;s household).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the son of FUJIWARA no Akinori, who was kogogu no suke (an official responsible for managing the empress&apos;s household).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the son of FUJIWARA no Akinori, who was kogogu no suke (an official responsible for managing the empress&apos;s household).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は令子内親王に仕えた下女で、異父同母兄姉に平時子、平時忠らがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a maid who served Imperial Princess Reishi, and TAIRA no Tokiko and TAIRA no Tokitada are half-siblings by the same mother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was a maid who served Imperial Princess Reishi, and TAIRA no Tokiko and TAIRA no Tokitada were half-siblings by the same mother.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was a maid who served Imperial Princess Reishi, and TAIRA no Tokiko and TAIRA no Tokitada were half-siblings by the same mother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>同父異母兄弟には藤原盛憲、藤原憲親、藤原経憲、玄顕らがあり、息女には源在子（承明門院）、藤原信子らがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had several half-brothers by the same father such as FUJIWARA no Morinori, FUJIWARA no Norichika, FUJIWARA no Tsunenori and Genken, and had daughters such as MINAMOTO no Zaishi (Shomeimonin) and FUJIWARA no Nobuko.</e>
<cmt>玄顕、藤原信子については、読み方の確認ができなかったため、ひとまず玄顕→げんけん、藤原信子→ふじわらののぶこ　として訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had several half-brothers by the same father, such as FUJIWARA no Morinori, FUJIWARA no Norichika, FUJIWARA no Tsunenori and Genken, and he had daughters such as MINAMOTO no Zaishi (Shomeimonin) and FUJIWARA no Nobuko.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had several half-brothers by the same father, such as FUJIWARA no Morinori, FUJIWARA no Norichika, FUJIWARA no Tsunenori and Genken, and he had daughters such as MINAMOTO no Zaishi (Shomeimonin) and FUJIWARA no Nobuko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>異父姉の時子から目をかけられ、その養子となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His half-sister Tokiko favored him and received him into her family as a son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His half-sister Tokiko favored him and received him into her family as a son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His half-sister Tokiko favored him and received him into her family as a son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>時子の夫平清盛が平氏政権を樹立していくのに従って立身し、法勝寺の執行に任ぜられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He rose in the world following the establishment of Taira clan government by TAIRA no Kiyomori, Tokiko&apos;s husband, and was appointed as the shigyo (executor) of Hossho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He rose in the world following the establishment of the Taira clan government by TAIRA no Kiyomori, Tokiko&apos;s husband, and was appointed as the shigyo (executor) of Hossho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He rose in the world following the establishment of the Taira clan government by TAIRA no Kiyomori, Tokiko&apos;s husband, and was appointed as the shigyo (executor) of Hossho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>僧侶の身ではあったが藤原範兼の娘の藤原範子と結婚し、一女・在子を儲けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he was a Buddhist monk, he married Fujiwara no Noriko, the daughter of Fujiwara no Norikane, and had a daughter, Zaishi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he was a Buddhist monk, he married Fujiwara no Noriko, the daughter of Fujiwara no Norikane, and had a daughter, Zaishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he was a Buddhist monk, he married FUJIWARA no Noriko, the daughter of FUJIWARA no Norikane, and had a daughter, Zaishi.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>範子が高倉天皇の第四皇子尊成親王の乳母になると、宮廷にも人脈を拡大した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Noriko became the nurse of Imperial Prince Takahira, the fourth prince of Emperor Takakura, he also expanded his network of contacts at the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Noriko became the nurse of Imperial Prince Takahira, the fourth prince of Emperor Takakura, he expanded his network of contacts at the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Noriko became the wet nurse of Imperial Prince Takahira, the fourth prince of Emperor Takakura, he expanded his network of contacts at the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>しかし、寿永2年（1183年）の伊勢平氏一門の都落ちに従ったことから運命が暗転する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, his fortunes underwent a rapid deterioration after he followed the flight of the Ise-Heishi (Taira clan) from Kyoto in 1183.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, his fortunes underwent a rapid deterioration after he followed the flight of the Ise-Heishi (Taira clan) from Kyoto in 1183.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, his fortunes underwent a rapid deterioration after he followed the flight of the Ise-Heishi (Taira clan) from Kyoto in 1183.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>直後に尊成親王は後鳥羽天皇として即位するが、能円は遠く西海にあり、虚しくその報を聞くのみであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Immediately after that, Imperial Prince Takahira ascended the throne as Emperor Gotoba, but Noen was at the west sea far from the capital and heard the news to no avail.</e>
<cmt>原文中の「西海」は、ここでは瀬戸内の海と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Immediately afterward, Imperial Prince Takahira ascended the throne as Emperor Gotoba, but Noen was at the west sea far from the capital and heard the news to no avail.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Immediately afterward, Imperial Prince Takahira ascended the throne as Emperor Gotoba, but Noen was at the west sea far from the capital and heard the news to no avail.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>やがて元暦元年（1185年）に壇ノ浦の合戦で平家が滅亡すると、捕虜として都に送られ、裁きの上備中国への流罪となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Taira family was destroyed at the Battle of Dan no Ura in 1185, he was sent to the capital as a captive, judged and condemned to exile in Bicchu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Taira family was destroyed at the Battle of Dan no Ura in 1185, he was sent to the capital as a captive, whereupon he was judged and condemned to exile in Bicchu Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Taira family was destroyed at the Battle of Dan no Ura in 1185, he was sent to the capital as a captive, whereupon he was judged and condemned to exile in Bicchu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>この間都に残っていた範子は、在子を連れて源通親と再婚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noriko, who had been in the capital during this period, remarried with MINAMOTO no Michichika, and took Zaishi with her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noriko, who had been in the capital during that period, remarried MINAMOTO no Michichika and took Zaishi with her.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noriko, who had been in the capital during that period, remarried MINAMOTO no Michichika and took Zaishi with her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>能円は文治5年（1189年）に赦免され帰洛するが、範子は既に通親との間に源定通、源通方らを産み、更に懐妊中という状態であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noen was pardoned and went back to Kyoto in 1189, but Noriko had already given birth to MINAMOTO no Sadamichi and MINAMOTO no Michikata by Michichika, and was carrying another child.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noen was pardoned and went back to Kyoto in 1189, but Noriko had already given birth to MINAMOTO no Sadamichi and MINAMOTO no Michikata by Michichika, and was carrying another child.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noen was pardoned and went back to Kyoto in 1189, but Noriko had already given birth to MINAMOTO no Sadamichi and MINAMOTO no Michikata by Michichika, and was carrying another child.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>在子は後鳥羽天皇の寵愛を受け、建久6年（1196年）に皇子為仁親王を生む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zaishi won the favor of Emperor Gotoba, and gave birth to Imperial Prince Tamehito in 1196.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zaishi won the favor of Emperor Gotoba, and gave birth to Imperial Prince Tamehito in 1196.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zaishi won the favor of Emperor Gotoba, and gave birth to Imperial Prince Tamehito in 1196.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>同親王は建久9年（1198年）に土御門天皇として即位し、能円は血縁上は天皇の外祖父となったが、それに相応しい厚遇を受けることはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he ascended the throne as Emperor Tsuchimikado in 1198, Noen became the maternal grandfather of an Emperor by blood relationship, but never received treatment befitting that fact.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he ascended the throne as Emperor Tsuchimikado in 1198, Noen became the maternal grandfather of an emperor by blood relationship, but he never received treatment befitting that fact.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he ascended the throne as Emperor Tsuchimikado in 1198, Noen became the maternal grandfather of an emperor by blood relationship, but he never received treatment befitting that fact.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>通親の権勢が増していくのを横目に、正治元年（1199年）に死去している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With sidelong glances at Michichika&apos;s increasing influence, he died in 1199.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With sidelong glances at Michichika&apos;s increasing influence, he died in 1199.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With sidelong glances at Michichika&apos;s increasing influence, he died in 1199.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Andee(id:20421), 小者(id:172526), R28Bot(id:177951), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>