<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>唯善</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yuizen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yuizen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yuizen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>唯善（ゆいぜん、建長5年（1253年）- 文保元年2月2日 (旧暦)（1317年3月15日））は、鎌倉時代後期の浄土真宗の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yuizen (1253-March 23, 1317) was a priest of Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) in the late Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>「文保元年2月2日」＝グレゴリオ暦「西暦1317年3月23日 」、出典：http://maechan.net/kanreki</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yuizen (1253-March 23, 1317) was a priest of Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) in the late Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yuizen (1253-March 23, 1317) was a priest of the Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) in the late Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>Jodo Shinshu に the を追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は小野宮禅念。母は親鸞の娘覚信尼。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Zennen ONOMIYA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Zennen ONOMIYA and his mother was a daughter of Shinran, Kakushinni.</e>
<cmt>combined this sentence with the one below to reduce sentence fragmentation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Zennen ONOMIYA and his mother was a daughter of Shinran, Kakushinni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>名は弘雅。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His name was Hiromasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His given name was Hiromasa.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;given&quot; for clarity and to reduce sentence fragmentation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His given name was Hiromasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>大納言阿闍梨と称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was called Dainagon (chief councilor of state) Ajari (a master in esoteric Buddhism; a high priest).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was called Dainagon (chief councilor of state) Ajari (a master in Esoteric Buddhism; a high priest).</e>
<cmt>fixed spacing; capitalized &quot;Esoteric&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was called Dainagon (chief councilor of state) Ajari (a master in Esoteric Buddhism; a high priest).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>下総国関宿西光院（現在の常敬寺）の開山。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was kaisan (a founder of temple as the first chief priest) of Saiko-in Temple (Jokyo-ji Temple as it is known today) in Sekishuku, Shimofusa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the kaisan (a founder of a temple as the first chief priest) of Saiko-in Temple (Jokyo-ji Temple as it is known today) in Sekishuku, Shimofusa Province.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the kaisan (a founder of a temple as the first chief priest) of Saiko-in Temple (Jokyo-ji Temple as it is known today) in Sekishuku, Shimofusa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>初め少将輔時の猶子となり、ついで大納言雅忠の猶子となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was first adopted by Shosho Suketoki and next by Dainagon Masatada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was first adopted by Shosho Suketoki and then by Dainagon Masatada.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was first adopted by Shosho (minor captain) Suketoki and then by Dainagon Masatada.</e>
<cmt>Shosho に (minor captain) を追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>当初密教を学ぶ一方修験道をあわせて修めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While he learned about Mikkyo (Esoteric Buddhism) at first, he also pursued the way of Shugendo (Japanese mountain asceticism-shamanism incorporating Shinto and Buddhist concepts).</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While he began his studies learning about Mikkyo (Esoteric Buddhism), he also pursued the way of Shugendo (Japanese mountain asceticism-shamanism incorporating Shinto and Buddhist concepts).</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While he began his studies learning about Esoteric Buddhism, he also pursued the way of Shugendo (Japanese mountain asceticism-shamanism incorporating Shinto and Buddhist concepts).</e>
<cmt>密教Mikkyo (Esoteric Buddhism) を Esoteric Buddhism に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その後唯円（河和田の唯円）により他力法門に接して浄土真宗に改宗した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward, he had a chance to encounter other-power (tariki) teaching by Yuien (Yuien of Kawada) and was converted to Jodo Shinshu.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Yuizen received outside help from Yuien (Yuien of Kawada) and converted to Jodo Shinshu.</e>
<cmt>他力: outside help; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Yuizen received outside help from Yuien (Yuien of Kawada) and converted to Jodo Shinshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>兄の覚恵に請われて京都大谷に住した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He lived in Otani, Kyoto as requested by his elder brother, Kakue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As requested by his elder brother Kakue, Yuizen lived in Otani.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As requested by his elder brother Kakue, Yuizen lived in Otani, Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>京都大谷「京都」訳漏れのため, Kyoto を追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>1303年（嘉元元年）関東における専修念仏が禁止されそうになると、関東にくだりこれを護った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Senju Nenbutsu (the Single-Minded Recitation of the Nenbutsu) was threatened to be prohibited in Kanto region in 1303, he went down to Kanto for protection.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Senju Nenbutsu (the Single-Minded Recitation of the Nenbutsu) was threatened to be prohibited in the Kanto region in 1303, Yuizen went down to Kanto to protect it.</e>
<cmt>&quot;went down to Kanto for protection&quot; is ambiguous, so I changed it to &quot;went down to Kanto to protect it&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Senju Nenbutsu (the Single-Minded Recitation of the Nenbutsu) was threatened to be prohibited in the Kanto region in 1303, Yuizen went down to Kanto to protect it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その後覚恵の子覚如と大谷廟堂の相続について争いがあり、それに敗れて祖像の首を持って相模国鎌倉に下った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward, he had a dispute with Kakunyo, Kakue&apos;s child about the succession of Otani-byodo Mausoleum, in which he was defeated, and went down to Kamakura, Sagami Province with the head of the founder&apos;s statue.</e>
<cmt>「祖像の首」は、直訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He then had a dispute with Kakunyo, Kakue&apos;s child, about the succession of the Otani-byodo Mausoleum and capitulated, returning to Kamakura in Sagami Province with the head of the founder&apos;s statue.</e>
<cmt>For &quot;敗れる&quot; I changed &quot;was defeated&quot;→&quot;capitulated&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He then had a dispute with Kakunyo, Kakue&apos;s child, about the succession of the Otani-byodo Mausoleum and capitulated, returning to Kamakura in Sagami Province with the head of the founder&apos;s statue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 こぶまき(id:38278), Point136(id:211299), Kenryu(id:181554), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), Nighthawks(id:36125), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>