<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>土佐坊昌俊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoshun TOSANOBO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoshun TOSANOBO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoshun TOSANOBO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>土佐坊 昌俊（とさのぼう しょうしゅん、康治2年（1143年） - 文治元年10月26日 (旧暦)（1185年11月19日））は、平安時代末期の武将・僧侶。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoshun TOSANOBO (1143 - November 19, 1185) was busho (Japanese military commander) as well as a Buddhist monk who was active in the last Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoshun TOSANOBO (1143 - November 19, 1185) was busho (Japanese military commander) as well as a Buddhist monk who was active in the last Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoshun TOSANOBO (1143 - November 26, 1185) was busho (Japanese military commander) as well as a Buddhist priest in the last Heian period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦にし、表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>土佐坊昌俊は法名であり、本名は渋谷金王丸という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoshun TOSANOBO was his priest&apos;s name and his real name was Konnomaru SHIBUYA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoshun TOSANOBO was his priest&apos;s name and his real name was Konnomaru SHIBUYA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoshun TOSANOBO was his priest&apos;s name and his real name was Konnomaru SHIBUYA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>桓武平氏秩父流の渋谷重家の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a son of Shigeie SHIBUYA, who belonged to Kanmu Heishi Chichiburyu clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a son of Shigeie SHIBUYA, who belonged to Kanmu Heishi Chichiburyu clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a son of Shigeie SHIBUYA, who belonged to the Chichibu lineage of Kanmu Heishi (the Taira clan).</e>
<cmt>用語表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>なかなか子の授からない渋谷重家が祈願すると、金剛夜叉明王のお告げがあり、程なく男子が誕生したことから、金剛夜叉明王の上下の文字を戴き「金王丸」と命名したと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Shigeie SHIBUYA, who had been with no child for long, prayed for the birth of a child, he received the oracle of Kongoyashamyoo (金剛夜叉明王) and was blessed with a baby boy soon and therefore, he named his son Konnomaru (金王丸) using the first and last Chinese character of 金剛夜叉明王 (Kongoyashamyoo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Shigeie SHIBUYA, who had been without child for a long time, prayed for the birth of a child, he received the oracle of Kongoyashamyoo (金剛夜叉明王) and was blessed with a baby boy soon and therefore, he named his son Konnomaru (金王丸) using the first and last Chinese characters of 金剛夜叉明王 (Kongoyashamyoo).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Shigeie SHIBUYA, who had been without child for a long time, prayed for the birth of a child, he received the oracle of Kongoyashamyoo (金剛夜叉明王) and was blessed with a baby boy soon and therefore, he named his son Konnomaru (金王丸) using the first and last Chinese characters of 金剛夜叉明王 (Kongoyashamyoo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>早くから源義朝の小姓として仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo as a page from his early years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo as a page from his early years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo as a page from his early years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>平治元年（1159年）の平治の乱でも義朝に従っていたが、義朝が平清盛に敗れると、義朝に従って戦線離脱し、尾張まで赴く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He accompanied Yoshitomo for Heiji no Ran occurred in 1159, but after Yoshitomo was defeated by TAIRA no Kiyomori, he went to Owari along with Yoshitomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He accompanied Yoshitomo for the Heiji no Ran that occurred in 1159, but after Yoshitomo was defeated by TAIRA no Kiyomori, he went to Owari along with Yoshitomo.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He accompanied Yoshitomo for the Heiji War in 1159, but after Yoshitomo was defeated by TAIRA no Kiyomori, he went to Owari along with Yoshitomo who left from the battle line.</e>
<cmt>用語など表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そして永暦元年（1160年）に尾張において義朝が長田忠致のために謀殺されると、その仇を討とうとしたが果たせず、長田の兵士に取り囲まれる中で敵兵数十名を斬り殺すという凄腕を見せて満身創痍になりながらも敵中を突破する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yoshitomo was murdered by Tadamune OSADA in Owari in 1160, he tried to revenge but failed, and broke through the enemy&apos;s line by slaying tens of Osada&apos;s soldiers while being covered all over with wounds.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yoshitomo was murdered by Tadamune OSADA in Owari in 1160, he tried to take revenge but failed, and broke through the enemy line by slaying tens of Osada&apos;s soldiers while covered all over with wounds.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yoshitomo was murdered by Tadamune OSADA in Owari in 1160, he tried to take revenge but failed, and broke through the enemy line by slaying tens of Osada&apos;s soldiers while covered all over with wounds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>そして、京都に戻り常盤御前に義朝の死を知らせた後、義朝の菩提を弔うために出家し、興福寺西金堂の衆徒となり、土佐坊昌俊と号した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After returning to Kyoto, he informed Tokiwa Gozen of Yoshitomo&apos;s death and thereafter, he entered priesthood as a priest of Kofuku-ji Temple Saikon-do in order to pray for Yoshitomo and named himself Shoshun TOSANOBO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After returning to Kyoto, he informed Tokiwa Gozen of Yoshitomo&apos;s death and thereafter, he entered the priesthood as a priest of Kofuku-ji Temple Saikon-do in order to pray for Yoshitomo and named himself Shoshun TOSANOBO.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After returning to Kyoto, he informed Tokiwa Gozen of Yoshitomo&apos;s death and thereafter, he entered the priesthood as a priest of Saikon-do of Kofuku-ji Temple in order to pray for Yoshitomo and called himself Shoshun TOSANOBO.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>その後、大和国針の荘において乱暴を働いたことから、土肥実平によって捕らえられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, he was captured by Sanehira DOI because he committed an outrage in Yamoto-no Kuni Hari no so.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, he was captured by Sanehira DOI because he committed an outrage in Yamoto-no Kuni Hari no so.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, he was captured by Sanehira DOI because he committed an outrage in Hari no sho Manor in Yamoto Province.</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし、自らも平治の乱を戦い、父の義朝に従うかつての渋谷金王丸の記憶を持つ源頼朝が父に対する忠誠心などを評価したため、罪を許して家臣として迎えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, who was also engaged in Heiji no Ran and remembered Konnomaru SHIBUYA, appreciated Shoshun&apos;s loyalty to his father and employed Shoshun as a vassal with pardoning crime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, who was also engaged in Heiji no Ran and remembered Konnomaru SHIBUYA, appreciated Shoshun&apos;s loyalty to his father and employed Shoshun as a vassal whilst pardoning the crime.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, who was also engaged in the Heiji War and remembered Konnomaru SHIBUYA, appreciated Shoshun&apos;s loyalty to his father and employed Shoshun as a vassal whilst pardoning the crime.</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>文治元年10月（1185年11月）、頼朝の密命を受けて京都堀河にある源義経屋敷を襲撃し、義経暗殺を謀ったが失敗する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the secret behest of Yoritomo, he tried in November of 1185 to assassinate Yoshitsune by assaulting his residence located at Kyoto Horikawa but failed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the secret behest of Yoritomo, he tried in November of 1185 to assassinate Yoshitsune by assaulting his residence, located at Kyoto Horikawa, but failed.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the secret behest of Yoritomo, he tried in November of 1185 to assassinate Yoshitsune by assaulting his residence, located at Horikawa in Kyoto, but failed.</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その後、鞍馬山に逃走したが義経の手勢によって捕縛され、同年10月26日に六条河原にて斬首のうえ、晒し首とされたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Susequently he ran away to Kuramayama but was captured by Yoshitsune&apos;s soldiers and on November 26, he was decapitated at Rokujo Gawara and his head was kept on public display.</e>
<cmt>日付が１０月２６日となっていますが、西暦の１１月と解釈しております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, he escaped to Kuramayama but was captured by Yoshitsune&apos;s soldiers and on November 26, he was decapitated at Rokujo Gawara and his head was kept on public display.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, he escaped to Mt. Kurama but was captured by Yoshitsune&apos;s soldiers and on November 26, he was decapitated at the Rokujo-gawara riverbed and his head was kept on public display.</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>享年43。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His age at death was 43.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His age at death was 43.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at 43.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>金王八幡神社（金王八幡宮）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Konno Hachiman Shrine (Konno Hachiman-gu shrine)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Konno Hachiman Shrine (Konno Hachiman-gu shrine)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Konno Hachiman Shrine (Konno Hachiman-gu shrine)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>金王八幡神社（こんのうはちまんじんじゃ）が鎮座する東京都の渋谷は、土佐坊昌俊の祖父、桓武天皇の孫高望王の子孫と名乗る秩父党の河崎冠者基家(かわさきの・かじゃ・もといえ)が、1051年（永承6年）に、前九年の役での武功により与えられた武蔵国豊島郡谷盛庄（としまぐん・やもりのしょう）にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shibuya in Tokyo where Konno Hachiman Shrine is located coincides with Musashi-no Kuni Toshima-gun Yamori no sho that was awarded in 1051 to Kawasaki no Kaja Motoie of Chichibu-to, who was a grandfather of Shoshin TOSANOBO and insisted that he was a descendant of Takamochi-no-O, a grand son of the Emperor Kanmu, for his military exploits in Zen Kunen no Eki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shibuya in Tokyo, where Konno Hachiman Shrine is located, coincides with Musashi-no Kuni Toshima-gun Yamori no sho that was awarded in 1051 to Kawasaki no Kaja Motoie of Chichibu-to, who was a grandfather of Shoshin TOSANOBO and insisted that he was a descendant of Takamochi-no-O, a grandson of Emperor Kanmu, for his military exploits in Zen Kunen no Eki.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shibuya in Tokyo, where Konno Hachiman-jinja Shrine is located, coincides with Yamori no sho Manor of Toshima-gun in Musashi Province that was awarded in 1051 to KAWASAKi no Kaja Motoie of Chichibu Party, who was a grandfather of Shoshin TOSANOBO and insisted that he was a descendant of Prince Takamochi, a grandson of Emperor Kanmu, for his military exploits in Zen Kunen no Eki (Former Nine Years&apos; Campaign).</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また同八幡神社は渋谷氏歴代の居城渋谷城址の一部で、1092年（寛治6年）に河崎基家が城内の一角に創建したと伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that Hachiman shrine occupies a part of the site of former Shibuya castle, which used to be the catsle of successive Shibuya clan, and it was constructed in 1092 by Motoie KAWASAKI at a corner of the castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that Hachiman shrine occupies a part of the site of the former Shibuya castle, which used to be the castle of successive Shibuya clans, and it was constructed in 1092 by Motoie KAWASAKI at a corner of the castle.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that Hachiman-jinja Shrine occupies a part of the site of Shibuya-jo Castle, which used to be the castle of successive Shibuya clans, and it was constructed in 1092 by Motoie KAWASAKI at a corner of the castle.</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>今も金王八幡神社の一隅には、土佐坊昌俊こと渋谷金王丸を祀る金王丸影堂があり、傍らに「渋谷城・砦の石」と伝わる石塊が残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even at presnt, Konnomaru-eido which enshrines Shoshin TOSANOBO, namely Konnomaru, is located at the corner of Konno Hachiman Shrine and next to it, there exists a stone that has been handed down as &quot;the stone used for the fortress of Shibuya Castle&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even at present, Konnomaru-eido, which enshrines Shoshin TOSANOBO, namely Konnomaru, is located at the corner of Konno Hachiman Shrine and next to it, there exists a stone that has been handed down as &quot;the stone used for the fortress of Shibuya Castle&quot;</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even at present, Konnomaru-eido Hall, which enshrines Shoshin TOSANOBO, namely Konnomaru SHIBUYA, is located at the corner of Konno Hachiman-jinja Shrine and next to it, there exists a stone that has been handed down as &apos;the stone used for the fortress of Shibuya Castle.&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>所在地：東京都渋谷区渋谷3-5-12</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Address : 3-5-12 Shibuya, Shibuya Ward, Tokyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Address : 3-5-12 Shibuya, Shibuya Ward, Tokyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Address: 3-5-12 Shibuya, Shibuya-ku Ward, Tokyo Prefecture</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>祭神：応神天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enshrined deity : the Emperor Ojin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enshrined deity : the Emperor Ojin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enshrined deity: the Emperor Ojin</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 M-sho-gun(id:88956), パの字(id:34188), ゐ(id:795), 代言人(id:33675), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), Matsubara-kou(id:41153), Andee(id:20421), Ho13(id:33287), Kogane(id:28186), Junger(id:10282), 沢田(id:40580), シェーラ(id:17988), 小者(id:172526), Kamitani(id:30757), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>