<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>真言宗醍醐派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Daigo school of the Shingon sect</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Daigo School of the Shingon Sect</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Daigo School of the Shingon Sect</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>真言宗醍醐派（しんごんしゅうだいごは）は、日本における真言系仏教宗派のひとつで、古義真言宗に属する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Daigo school of the Shingon sect is one of the Shingon Buddhist sects of Japan, and belongs to the Kogi Shingon (Old Shingon) school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Daigo school of the Shingon sect, one of the Shingon Buddhist sects of Japan, belongs to the Kogi Shingon (Old Shingon) school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Daigo school of the Shingon sect, one of the Shingon Buddhist sects of Japan, belongs to the Kogi Shingon (Old Shingon) school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>総本山は醍醐寺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The head temple is Daigo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The head temple is Daigo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The head temple is Daigo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>宗祖　弘法大師</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The founder of the sect: Kobo Daishi (a posthumous title of the priest Kukai)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sect was founded by Kobo Daishi (a posthumous title of the priest Kukai)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sect was founded by Kobo Daishi (a posthumous title of the priest Kukai).</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>派祖　理源大師（聖宝）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The founder of the school: Rigen Daishi (Shobo, the Great Master of Holy Treasures)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The school was founded by Rigen Daishi (Shobo, the Great Master of Holy Treasures)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The school was founded by Rigen Daishi (Shobo, the Great Master of Holy Treasures).</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足全角削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>中興　義演准后</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The restorer: Gien, who was given the title &quot;Jugo&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The restorer was Gien, who was given the title &quot;Jugo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The restorer was Gien, who was given the title Jugo.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>宗紋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shumon (the crest of the sect)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shumon (the crest of the sect)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shumon (the crest of the sect)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>五七桐(慣用で使用)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goshichi no kiri (literally, five-seven paulownia) (in customary use)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goshichi no kiri (literally, five-seven paulownia) (in customary use)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goshichi no kiri (literally, five-seven paulownia) (in customary use)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>寺格（順不同）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The status of related Buddhist temples (in random order)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The status of related Buddhist temples (in random order)</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The status of related Buddhist temples (in random order)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>総本山 醍醐寺（京都市伏見区）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The head temple: Daigo-ji Temple (Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The head temple: Daigo-ji Temple (Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City)</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The head temple: Daigo-ji Temple (Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>大本山 三宝院（醍醐寺山内 京都市伏見区）・転法輪寺（奈良県御所市）・西国寺（広島県尾道市）・道隆寺（香川県多度津町）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daihonzan (the main temples) : Sanbo-in (in the precincts of Daigo-ji Temple Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City), Tenporin-ji Temple (Gose City, Nara Prefecture), Saigokuji-Temple (Onomichi City, Hiroshima Prefecture), Doryu-ji Temple (Tadotsu-cho, Kagawa Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daihonzan (the main temples): Sanbo-in (in the precincts of Daigo-ji Temple Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City), Tenporin-ji Temple (Gose City, Nara Prefecture), Saigokuji-Temple (Onomichi City, Hiroshima Prefecture), Doryu-ji Temple (Tadotsu-cho, Kagawa Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daihonzan (the main temples): Sanbo-in (in the precincts of Daigo-ji Temple Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City), Tenporin-ji Temple (Gose City, Nara Prefecture), Saigokuji-Temple (Onomichi City, Hiroshima Prefecture), Doryu-ji Temple (Tadotsu-cho, Kagawa Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>別格本山 金剛王院（京都市伏見区）、理性院（醍醐寺山内）、報恩院（醍醐寺山内）、無量寿院（醍醐寺山内）、品川寺（東京都品川区）、塩船観音（東京都青梅市）、大明王院（川崎市高津区）、永安寺（石川県金沢市）、法界寺（京都市伏見区）、金胎寺（京都府和束町）、松尾寺 (大和郡山市)（奈良県大和郡山市）、千光寺 (生駒郡平群町)（奈良県平群町）、龍泉寺 (天川村)（奈良県天川村）、龍華寺（広島県世羅町）、十波羅蜜寺（香川県三豊市）、西山興隆寺（愛媛県西条市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bekkaku-honzan (special head temples): Kongoo-in (Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City), Risho-in Temple (in the precincts of Daigo-ji Temple), Hoon-in (in the precincts of Daigo-ji Temple), Muryoju-in (in the precincts of Daigo-ji Temple), Honsen-ji Temple (Shinagawa Ward, Tokyo), Shiofune Kannon (Ome city, Tokyo), Daimyoo-in Temple (Takatsu Ward, Kawasaki City), Eian-ji Temple (Kanazawa City, Ishikawa Prefecture), Hokai-ji Temple (Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City), Kontai-ji Temple (Wazuka-cho, Kyoto Prefecture), Matsuo-dera Temple (Yamatokoriyama City, Nara Prefecture), Senko-ji Temple (Heguri-cho, Ikoma County, Nara Prefecture), Ryusen-ji Temple (Tenkawa-mura, Nara Prefecture), Ryuge-ji Temple (Sera-cho, Hiroshima Prefecture), Toharamitsu-ji Temple (Mitoyo City, Kagawa Prefecture), and Nishiyamakoryu-ji Temple (Saijo City, Ehime Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>原文中地名がダブっておりますので、「松尾寺 (大和郡山市)（奈良県大和郡山市）」→「松尾寺 (奈良県大和郡山市）」へ、「千光寺 (生駒郡平群町)（奈良県平群町）」→(奈良県生駒郡平群町)、「龍泉寺 (天川村)（奈良県天川村）」→（奈良県天川村）とダブりをなくしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bekkaku-honzan (special head temples): Kongoo-in (Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City), Risho-in Temple (in the precincts of Daigo-ji Temple), Hoon-in (in the precincts of Daigo-ji Temple), Muryoju-in (in the precincts of Daigo-ji Temple), Honsen-ji Temple (Shinagawa Ward, Tokyo), Shiofune Kannon (Ome city, Tokyo), Daimyoo-in Temple (Takatsu Ward, Kawasaki City), Eian-ji Temple (Kanazawa City, Ishikawa Prefecture), Hokai-ji Temple (Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City), Kontai-ji Temple (Wazuka-cho, Kyoto Prefecture), Matsuo-dera Temple (Yamatokoriyama City, Nara Prefecture), Senko-ji Temple (Heguri-cho, Ikoma County, Nara Prefecture), Ryusen-ji Temple (Tenkawa-mura, Nara Prefecture), Ryuge-ji Temple (Sera-cho, Hiroshima Prefecture), Toharamitsu-ji Temple (Mitoyo City, Kagawa Prefecture), and Nishiyamakoryu-ji Temple (Saijo City, Ehime Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bekkaku-honzan (special head temples): Kongoo-in (Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City), Risho-in Temple (in the precincts of Daigo-ji Temple), Hoon-in (in the precincts of Daigo-ji Temple), Muryoju-in (in the precincts of Daigo-ji Temple), Honsen-ji Temple (Shinagawa Ward, Tokyo), Shiofune Kannon (Ome City, Tokyo), Daimyoo-in Temple (Takatsu Ward, Kawasaki City), Eian-ji Temple (Kanazawa City, Ishikawa Prefecture), Hokai-ji Temple (Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City), Kontai-ji Temple (Wazuka-cho, Kyoto Prefecture), Matsuo-dera Temple (Yamatokoriyama City, Nara Prefecture), Senko-ji Temple (Heguri-cho, Ikoma County, Nara Prefecture), Ryusen-ji Temple (Tenkawa-mura, Nara Prefecture), Ryuge-ji Temple (Sera-cho, Hiroshima Prefecture), Toharamitsu-ji Temple (Mitoyo City, Kagawa Prefecture), and Nishiyamakoryu-ji Temple (Saijo City, Ehime Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>準別格本山 道仙寺（岡山県美作市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jun-bekkaku-honzan (Associate Head Temple) : Dosen-ji Temple (Mimasaka City, Okayama Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jun-bekkaku-honzan (associate head temple): Dosen-ji Temple (Mimasaka City, Okayama Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jun-bekkaku-honzan (associate head temple): Dosen-ji Temple (Mimasaka City, Okayama Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>別院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Branch temples</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Branch temples</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Branch temples</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>一般寺院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Local temples</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Local temples</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Local temples</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>真言宗醍醐派の歴史は醍醐寺の開創に始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The history of the Daigo school of the Shingon sect starts with the foundation of Daigo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The history of the Daigo school of the Shingon sect starts with the foundation of Daigo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The history of the Daigo school of the Shingon sect starts with the foundation of Daigo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>聖宝が如意輪観音・准胝観音を彫刻して深雪山山上に祀ったことが醍醐寺の起源となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shobo curved statues of Juntei Kannon and Nyoirin Kannon and deified them at the top of Mt.Miyuki, which became the origin of Daigo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shobo carved statues of Juntei Kannon and Nyoirin Kannon and deified them at the top of Mt. Miyuki, which became the origin of Daigo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shobo carved statues of Juntei Kannon and Nyoirin Kannon and deified them at the top of Mt. Miyuki, which became the origin of Daigo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>醍醐天皇・朱雀天皇が誕生されるに当って、皇室より聖宝に対して祈祷の依頼があり、無事に出産、誕生されたために、皇室の帰依を得るようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial household had requested Shobo to make prayers for Emperor Daigo and Emperor Suzaku before they were born, and when the babies were born safe and healthy, the Imperial family became a supporter of the temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Household had asked Shobo to make prayers for Emperor Daigo and Emperor Suzaku before they were born, and when the babies were born safe and healthy the Imperial Family became a supporter of the temple.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Household had asked Shobo to make prayers for Emperor Daigo and Emperor Suzaku before they were born, and when the babies were born safe and healthy the Imperial Family became a supporter of the temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>この後より、伽藍の整備が整い、現在の醍醐寺の基礎が確立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The temples buildings have developed since then, forming the basis of the present Daigo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The temples buildings have developed since then, forming the basis of the present Daigo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The temples buildings have developed since then, forming the basis of the present Daigo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>平安時代、摂関政治が隆盛を極めるころには、皇室の保護が薄くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Heian period, when the regency government was at its zenith of prosperity, the protection of the Imperial Family grew weaker.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Heian period, when the regency government was at its peak of prosperity, the protection of the Imperial Family grew weaker.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Heian period, when the regency government was at its peak of prosperity, the protection of the Imperial Family grew weaker.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>院政期になると、醍醐天皇系統の宇多・村上源氏が財政的・人事的にも醍醐寺を護持する中心となり、伽藍・諸堂の拡充、醍醐寺座主を輩出することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time of cloister government, the Uda Genji and Murakami Genji (the Minamoto clan), which belonged to the line of Emperor Daigo, played the pivotal role in preserving the finances and the personnel of Daigo-ji Temple, and they expanded the temple buildings and halls and produced abbots for the temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time of the cloister government, the Uda Genji and Murakami Genji (the Minamoto clan), which belonged to the line of Emperor Daigo, were instrumental in preserving the finances and personnel of Daigo-ji Temple; they expanded the temple buildings and halls, and produced abbots for the temple.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time of the cloister government, the Uda-Genji and Murakami-Genji (the Minamoto clan), which belonged to the line of Emperor Daigo, were instrumental in preserving the finances and personnel of Daigo-ji Temple; they expanded the temple buildings and halls, and produced abbots for the temple.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="20">
<j>真言宗の事相（真言密教の儀礼・実践方法）の法流の一つである小野流の研究が盛んであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monks there eagerly studied the Ono school, one of the &quot;jiso&quot; teachings of Shingon (a method of ceremony and practice in Shingon Esoteric Buddhism).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Monks there eagerly studied the Ono school, one of the &quot;jiso&quot; teachings of Shingon (a method of ceremony and practice in Shingon Esoteric Buddhism).</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Monks there eagerly studied the Ono school, one of the &quot;jiso&quot; teachings of Shingon (a method of ceremony and practice in Shingon Esoteric Buddhism).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>事相研究でも特に図像研究では中心寺院として知られていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was known as the central temple for the study of jiso, especially Buddhist iconology.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was known as the central temple for the study of jiso, especially Buddhist iconology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was known as the central temple for the study of jiso, especially Buddhist iconology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="22">
<j>応仁の乱では伽藍の多くを失い、衰微した時期があったが、当時の座主であった義演が豊臣氏と友好的な関係であったため、豊臣氏が財政的な援助を行って伽藍を建立し、本格的な復興を果たした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Onin war, it lost many of its buildings and declined for a while, but thanks to friendly relations with the Toyotomi clan and Gien, the abbot in those days, its temples were built and a full-scale restoration was done with the help of financial aid from the clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Onin War, it lost many of its buildings and declined for a while, but thanks to friendly relations with the Toyotomi clan and Gien, the abbot in those days, its temples were built and a full-scale restoration was done with financial aid from the clan.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Onin War, it lost many of its buildings and declined for a while, but thanks to friendly relations with the Toyotomi clan and Gien, the abbot in those days, its temples were built and a full-scale restoration was done with financial aid from the clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="23">
<j>明治時代に入ると、政府に寺領・特権を返上して衰微したが、文化財保護が重要視されるようになり、伽藍の整備・寺宝の保護が図られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When it came to the Meiji period, it returned its temple estates and privileges to the government and declined, but because the preservation of cultural properties came to be valued highly, its temple buildings were maintained and the treasures that the temple owned were preserved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the advent of the Meiji period, it returned its temple estates and privileges to the government and declined, but because the preservation of cultural properties had become highly valued its temple buildings were maintained and the treasures that the temple owned were preserved.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the advent of the Meiji period, it returned its temple estates and privileges to the government and declined, but because the preservation of cultural properties had become highly valued its temple buildings were maintained and the treasures that the temple owned were preserved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="24">
<j>真言宗系修験道を支配する寺院であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the temple that controlled the Shingon Shugendo (Japanese mountain asceticism-shamanism incorporating Shinto and Buddhist concepts).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the temple that controlled the Shingon Shugendo (Japanese mountain asceticism-shamanism incorporating Shinto and Buddhist concepts).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was the temple that controlled the Shingon Shugendo (Japanese mountain asceticism-shamanism incorporating Shinto and Buddhist concepts).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>明治時代に修験寺院の廃止が決定すると、寺院内に恵印部を設けて、修験寺院の統制を行ったが、1919年（大正8年）には恵印部を廃し、修験寺院を末寺とすることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When it was decided to discontinue temples for Shugendo monasteries (Shugendo is Japanese mountain asceticism-shamanism incorporating Shinto and Buddhist concepts) in the Meiji period, Daigo-ji Temple founded a section called Ein-bu in it and controlled the Shugendo monasteries, but in 1919, it discontinued Ein-bu and made them into branch temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When it was decided to discontinue temples for Shugendo monasteries (Shugendo is Japanese mountain asceticism/shamanism incorporating Shinto and Buddhist concepts) in the Meiji period, Daigo-ji Temple founded a section called Ein-bu within it and controlled the Shugendo monasteries; however, in 1919 it discontinued Ein-bu and made them into branch temples.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When it was decided to discontinue temples for Shugendo monasteries (Shugendo is Japanese mountain asceticism/shamanism incorporating Shinto and Buddhist concepts) in the Meiji period, Daigo-ji Temple founded a section called Ein-bu within it and controlled the Shugendo monasteries; however, in 1919 it discontinued Ein-bu and made them into branch temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="26">
<j>1879年（明治12年）、東寺の傘下に入り、定額寺・大本山として、醍醐寺・三宝院がともに列したが、1905年（明治38年）には独立して、真言宗醍醐派を公称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The temple came under the umbrella of To-ji Temple in 1879, and Daigo-ji Temple and Sanbo-in had their names on the lists of Jogaku-ji (a limited number of private temples protected by the officials) and main head temples, but they became independent and publicly declared the Daigo school of the Shingon sect in 1905.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The temple came under the umbrella of To-ji Temple in 1879, and Daigo-ji Temple and Sanbo-in had their names on the lists of Jogaku-ji (a limited number of private temples protected by officials) and main head temples, but they became independent and publicly declared the &quot;Daigo School of the Shingon Sect&quot; in 1905.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The temple came under the umbrella of To-ji Temple in 1879, and Daigo-ji Temple and Sanbo-in had their names on the lists of Jogaku-ji (a limited number of private temples protected by officials) and main head temples, but they became independent and publicly declared the Daigo School of the Shingon Sect in 1905.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="27">
<j>太平洋戦争中に、政府の宗教政策により、古義真言宗と新義真言宗の合同が計られ、大真言宗に統合された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Pacific War, the Kogi Shingon (Old Shingon) sect and the Shingi Shingon (New Shingon) sect were combined and united with the Dai-Shingon sect (literally, the Great Shingon sect) due to the government&apos;s religious policy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Pacific War, the Kogi Shingon (Old Shingon) sect and the Shingi Shingon (New Shingon) sect were combined and united with the Dai-Shingon sect (literally, the Great Shingon sect) due to the government&apos;s policy on religion.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Pacific War, the Kogi Shingon (Old Shingon) sect and the Shingi Shingon (New Shingon) sect were combined and united with the Dai-Shingon sect (literally, the Great Shingon sect) due to the government&apos;s policy on religion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>1946年（昭和21年）、大真言宗より独立し、真言宗醍醐派と公称して現在に至っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1946, it became independent from the Great Shingon sect, declared itself as the Daigo school of the Shingon sect and it has continued to the present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1946, it became independent from the Great Shingon sect, declaring itself as the &quot;Daigo School of the Shingon Sect,&quot; and has continued to the present day.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1946, it became independent from the Great Shingon sect, declaring itself as the Daigo School of the Shingon Sect, and has continued to the present day.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>宗務組織</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Religious affairs organization</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Religious affairs organization</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Religious affairs organization</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>管長（醍醐寺座主・三宝院門跡を兼職する者）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The chief abbot (a person who is simultaneously the abbot of Daigo-ji Temple and the &quot;monzeki&quot; (historically, a noble or an Imperial prince appointed as the chief priest) of Sanbo-in)</e>
<cmt>原文「三宝院門跡」の「門跡」は、ここでは「出家して特定の寺院（門跡寺院）の長となった人物」の称号と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The chief abbot (a person who is simultaneously the abbot of Daigo-ji Temple and the &quot;monzeki&quot; (historically, a noble or an imperial prince appointed as the chief priest) of Sanbo-in)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The chief abbot (a person who is simultaneously the abbot of Daigo-ji Temple and the monzeki (historically, a noble or an imperial prince appointed as the chief priest) of Sanbo-in)</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>宗務所（醍醐寺内に設置）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The temple office (set up in Daigo-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The temple office (set up within Daigo-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The temple office (set up within Daigo-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>宗務総長</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The head of the temple office</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The head of the temple office</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The head of the temple office</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>執行長</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The head of the executors</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The head of the executors</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The head of the executors</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>執行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigyo (executors)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigyo (executors)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigyo (executors)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>庶務部（部長・主事・書記を置く）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">General Affairs Department (with a department director, a secretary and a clerk)</e>
<cmt>文脈上主事と書記が何名か不明ですが、ひとまず一人ずつとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">General Affairs Department (with a department director, a secretary and a clerk)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">General Affairs Department (with a department director, a secretary and a clerk)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>教務部（部長・主事・書記を置く）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Educational Department (with a department director, a secretary and a clerk)</e>
<cmt>文脈上主事と書記が何名か不明ですが、ひとまず一人ずつとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Educational Department (with a department director, a secretary and a clerk)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Educational Department (with a department director, a secretary and a clerk)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>財務部（部長・主事・書記を置く）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Finance Department (with a department director, a secretary and a clerk)</e>
<cmt>文脈上主事と書記が何名か不明ですが、ひとまず一人ずつとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Finance Department (with a department director, a secretary and a clerk)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Finance Department (with a department director, a secretary and a clerk)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>真言宗醍醐派宗会</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Committee of the Daigo school of the Shingon sect</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Committee of the Daigo School of the Shingon Sect</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Committee of the Daigo School of the Shingon Sect</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>公選議員10名・特任議員2名（計12名）で構成。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It consists of ten elective members and two specially appointed members (twelve people).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It consists of ten elective members and two specially appointed members (totaling 12 people).</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It consists of ten elective members and two specially appointed members (totaling 12 people).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>任期4年。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their tenure is four years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their tenure is four years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their tenure is four years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="40">
<j>地方宗務</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Local religious affairs</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Local religious affairs</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Local religious affairs</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>宗務支所（北海道・山形北部・山形南部・新潟・山梨・静岡・三河東・三河西・尾張・岐阜・三重・京都・奈良・大阪・兵庫・備前・備中・美作・広島・山口・鳥取・島根・高知・香川・愛媛・福岡・大分・熊本・肥前）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The branches temple offices (Hokkaido, the northern Yamagata Prefecture, the southern Yamagata Prefecture, Niigata Prefecture, Yamanashi Prefecture, Shizuoka Prefecture, the eastern Mikawa area, western Mikawa area, Owari area, Gifu Prefecture, Mie Prefecture, Kyoto Prefecture, Nara Prefecture, Osaka Prefecture, Hyogo Prefecture, Bizen area, Bicchu area, Mimasaka area ・Hiroshima Prefecture, Yamaguchi Prefecture, Tottori Prefecture, Shimane Prefecture, Kochi Prefecture, Kagawa Prefecture, Ehime Prefecture, Fukuoka Prefecture, Oita Prefecture, Kumamoto Prefecture, Hizen area)</e>
<cmt>原文中、旧藩名と現在の都道府県名が混ざっておりますが、旧藩名＝地域と解釈しました。そのため、例えば尾張は、Owari area　と訳しております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The branches&apos; temple offices (Hokkaido, northern Yamagata Prefecture, southern Yamagata Prefecture, Niigata Prefecture, Yamanashi Prefecture, Shizuoka Prefecture, eastern Mikawa area, western Mikawa area, Owari area, Gifu Prefecture, Mie Prefecture, Kyoto Prefecture, Nara Prefecture, Osaka Prefecture, Hyogo Prefecture, Bizen area, Bicchu area, Mimasaka area ・Hiroshima Prefecture, Yamaguchi Prefecture, Tottori Prefecture, Shimane Prefecture, Kochi Prefecture, Kagawa Prefecture, Ehime Prefecture, Fukuoka Prefecture, Oita Prefecture, Kumamoto Prefecture, Hizen area)</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The branches&apos; temple offices (Hokkaido, northern Yamagata Prefecture, southern Yamagata Prefecture, Niigata Prefecture, Yamanashi Prefecture, Shizuoka Prefecture, eastern Mikawa area, western Mikawa area, Owari area, Gifu Prefecture, Mie Prefecture, Kyoto Prefecture, Nara Prefecture, Osaka Prefecture, Hyogo Prefecture, Bizen area, Bicchu area, Mimasaka area, Hiroshima Prefecture, Yamaguchi Prefecture, Tottori Prefecture, Shimane Prefecture, Kochi Prefecture, Kagawa Prefecture, Ehime Prefecture, Fukuoka Prefecture, Oita Prefecture, Kumamoto Prefecture, Hizen area)</e>
<cmt>全角削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>直轄支所（外国を含む）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Branches under the direct control Daigo-ji Temple (including branches abroad)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Branches under the direct control Daigo-ji Temple (including branches abroad)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Branches under the direct control Daigo-ji Temple (including branches abroad)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>僧階（全15階級）・布教師</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buddhist monks&apos; rank (there are fifteen ranks) and Buddhist evangelists</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buddhist monks&apos; rank (there are 15 ranks) and Buddhist evangelists</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddhist monks&apos; rank (there are 15 ranks) and Buddhist evangelists</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="43">
<j>括弧内は法衣の色</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The word inside the second parentheses shows the color of religious vestment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The word inside the second set of parentheses shows the color of religious vestment.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word inside the second set of parentheses shows the color of religious vestment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>1級 大僧正（緋）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First rank: Dai sojo (the highest position, upper grade)(cardinal)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First rank: Dai sojo (the highest position, upper grade)(cardinal)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First rank: Dai sojo (the highest position, upper grade)(cardinal)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>2級 権大僧正（紫）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Second rank: Gon Daisojo (the provisional highest position, upper grade) (purple)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Second rank: Gon Daisojo (the provisional highest position, upper grade) (purple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Second rank: Gon Daisojo (the provisional highest position, upper grade) (purple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>3級 中僧正（紫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Third rank: Chu sojo (the highest position, middle grade)(purple)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Third rank: Chu sojo (the highest position, middle grade)(purple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Third rank: Chu sojo (the highest position, middle grade)(purple)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>4級 権中僧正（紫）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fourth rank: Gon Chu sojo (the provisional highest position, middle grade)(purple)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fourth rank: Gon Chu sojo (the provisional highest position, middle grade)(purple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fourth rank: Gon Chu sojo (the provisional highest position, middle grade)(purple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>5級 少僧正（紫）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fifth rank: Sho sojo (the highest position, lower grade)(purple)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fifth rank: Sho sojo (the highest position, lower grade)(purple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fifth rank: Sho sojo (the highest position, lower grade)(purple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>6級 権小僧正（紫）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sixth rank: Gon Sho sojo (the provisional highest position, lower grade)(purple)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sixth rank: Gon Sho sojo (the provisional highest position, lower grade)(purple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sixth rank: Gon Sho sojo (the provisional highest position, lower grade)(purple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>7級 大僧都（萌葱）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seventh rank: Dai sozu (the second highest position, upper grade) (yellow-green)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seventh rank: Dai sozu (the second-highest position, upper grade) (yellow-green)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seventh rank: Dai sozu (the second-highest position, upper grade) (yellow-green)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>8級 権大僧都（萌葱）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eighth rank: Gon dai sozu (the provisional second highest position, upper grade) (yellow-green)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eighth rank: Gon dai sozu (the provisional second-highest position, upper grade) (yellow-green)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eighth rank: Gon dai sozu (the provisional second-highest position, upper grade) (yellow-green)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>9級 中僧都（萌葱）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ninth rank: Chu sozu (the second highest position, middle grade)(yellow-green)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ninth rank: Chu sozu (the second-highest position, middle grade)(yellow-green)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ninth rank: Chu sozu (the second-highest position, middle grade)(yellow-green)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>10級 権中僧都（萌葱）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenth rank: Gon Chu sozu (the provisional second highest position, middle grade)(yellow green)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenth rank: Gon Chu sozu (the provisional second-highest position, middle grade)(yellow green)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenth rank: Gon Chu sozu (the provisional second-highest position, middle grade)(yellow green)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>11級 少僧都（浅葱）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eleventh rank: Sho sozu (the third highest position, lower grade)(pale blue)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eleventh rank: Sho sozu (the third-highest position, lower grade) (pale blue)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eleventh rank: Sho sozu (the third-highest position, lower grade) (pale blue)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>12級 権小僧都（浅葱）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Twelfth rank: Gon Chu sozu (the provisional third highest position, lower grade) (pale blue)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Twelfth rank: Gon Chu sozu (the provisional third-highest position, lower grade) (pale blue)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Twelfth rank: Gon Chu sozu (the provisional third-highest position, lower grade) (pale blue)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>13級 大律師（浅葱）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thirteenth rank: Dai-Risshi (literally, &quot;master of discipline&quot;, upper grade)(pale blue)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thirteenth rank: Dai-Risshi (literally, &quot;master of discipline,&quot; upper grade) (pale blue)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thirteenth rank: Dai-Risshi (literally, &quot;master of discipline,&quot; upper grade) (pale blue)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>14級 律師（浅葱）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fourteenth rank: Risshi (literally, &quot;master of discipline&quot;)(pale blue)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fourteenth rank: Risshi (literally, &quot;master of discipline&quot;) (pale blue)</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fourteenth rank: Risshi (literally, &quot;master of discipline&quot;) (pale blue)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>15級 権律師（浅葱）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fifteenth rank: Gon-Risshi (literally, &quot;supernumerary master of discipline&quot;)(pale blue)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fifteenth rank: Gon-Risshi (literally, &quot;supernumerary master of discipline&quot;) (pale blue)</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fifteenth rank: Gon-Risshi (literally, &quot;supernumerary master of discipline&quot;) (pale blue)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="59">
<j>布教師</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Evangelist</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Evangelist</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Evangelist</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="60">
<j>本山布教師</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Evangelist of the head temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Evangelist of the head temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Evangelist of the head temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>布教師</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Evangelist</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Evangelist</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Evangelist</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>布教師補</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Assistant evangelist</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Assistant evangelist</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Assistant evangelist</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>僧籍</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To be formally entered as a Buddhist monk</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To be formally entered as a Buddhist monk</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To be formally entered as a Buddhist monk</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="63">
<j>得度（度牒）、四度加行の後、伝法灌頂に入壇。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After &quot;tokudo&quot; (entrance into the Buddhist priesthood) (or &quot;docho&quot;, an official certificate for it) and finishing shidokegyo (literally, &quot;the four trainings&quot; indispensable to be a priest), they initiate the participants with denpo-kanjo (the consecration for the Transmission of the Dharma).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After &quot;tokudo&quot; (entrance into the Buddhist priesthood) (or &quot;docho,&quot; an official certificate for it) and finishing shidokegyo (literally, &quot;the four trainings&quot; indispensable to be a priest), they initiate the participants with denpo-kanjo (the consecration for the Transmission of the Dharma).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After tokudo (entrance into the Buddhist priesthood) (or docho, an official certificate for it) and finishing shidokegyo (literally, the four trainings indispensable to be a priest), they initiate the participants with denpo-kanjo (the consecration for the Transmission of the Dharma).</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>さらに布教師に補された者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those further appointed as evangelists.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those further appointed as evangelists</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those further appointed as evangelists</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>年中行事</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regular Annual Events</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regular Annual Events</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regular annual events</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="65">
<j>1月5日 年頭式・初護摩供養</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 5th: The New Year ceremony and the first goma kuyo (holy fire memorial service) of the year</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 5: The New Year&apos;s ceremony and the first goma kuyo (holy fire memorial service) of the year</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 5: The New Year&apos;s ceremony and the first goma kuyo (holy fire memorial service) of the year</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>1月6日 初聖宝会</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 6th: Hatsu Syobo-e</e>
<cmt>行事の内容については、醍醐寺のHPでも説明がありませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 6: Hatsu Syobo-e</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 6: Hatsu Shobo-e</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>2月15日～21日 五大力尊仁王会前行・御遷座式</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From February 15th through 21th: ceremonies for Godairikison Ninno-e festival</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From February 15 - 21: Ceremonies for Godairikison Ninno-e festival</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From February 15 - 21: Ceremonies for Godairikison Ninno-e festival</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>2月23日　五大力尊仁王会</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 23th: Godairikison Ninno-e festival</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 23: Godairikison Ninno-e festival</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 23: Godairikison Ninno-e festival</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>3月第1日曜日 奥之院初回峯行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first Sunday in March: Okunoin-hatsu-kaihogyo</e>
<cmt>行事の内容については醍醐寺のHPにも説明がないため、字面から毎年最初に行われる回峰行のことではと考えましたが、詳細不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first Sunday in March: Okunoin-hatsu-kaihogyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first Sunday in March: Okunoin-hatsu-kaihogyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>3月18日～24日 春季彼岸法要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From March 18th through 24th: Spring Higan ceremony(week of the spring equinox)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From March 18 - 24: Spring Higan ceremony(week of the spring equinox)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From March 18 - 24: Spring Higan ceremony(week of the spring equinox)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>3月24日～5月6日 霊宝館開館 ・国宝金堂特別内拝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From March 24th through May 6th: Spring exhibition at Reihokan (the museum), including a special exhibition of inside Kon-do Hall (main hall of a Buddhist temple), which is a national treasure</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 24 - May 6: Spring exhibition at Reihokan (the museum), including a special exhibition of the interior of Kon-do Hall (main hall of a Buddhist temple), which is a national treasure</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 24 - May 6: Spring exhibition at Reihokan (the museum), including a special exhibition of the interior of Kon-do Hall (main hall of a Buddhist temple), which is a national treasure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>4月1日～21日 清瀧大権現例祭桜会・大般若転読法要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From April 1st through 21th: Seiryu-daigongen reisaioe, Daihannya tendoku hoyo (a memorial service of reading the part of &quot;Dai Hannya kyo&quot; to believers (in Sanskrit, Mahaprajnaparamita-sutra))</e>
<cmt>「清瀧大権現例祭桜会」の内容については、醍醐寺のHPでも説明がなく、詳細不明でした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 1 - 21: Seiryu-daigongen reisaioe, Daihannya tendoku hoyo (a memorial service of reading the part of &quot;Dai Hannya kyo&quot; to believers (in Sanskrit, Mahaprajnaparamita-sutra))</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1 - 21: Seiryu-daigongen reisaioe, Daihannya tendoku hoyo (a memorial service of reading the part of &quot;Dai Hannya kyo&quot; to believers (in Sanskrit, Mahaprajnaparamita-sutra))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>4月第2日曜　豊太閤花見行列</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second Sunday in May: Ho-Taiko Hanami Gyoretsu(Toyotomi Hideyoshi&apos;s cherry blossom viewing parade)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Second Sunday in May: Ho-Taiko Hanami Gyoretsu(Toyotomi Hideyoshi&apos;s cherry-blossom viewing parade)</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Second Sunday in May: Ho-Taiko Hanami Gyoretsu(Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI&apos;s cherry-blossom viewing parade)</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>5月18日 西国三十三ヶ所観音霊場第11番札所・本尊准胝観音御開扉法要厳修</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May 18th: The ceremony of exhibiting the Juntei Kannon, which is the principal image in the temple and the eleventh of 33 Kannon pilgrimage temples in Saigoku (Kinki area)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">May 18: The ceremony of exhibiting the Juntei Kannon, the principal image in the temple and the eleventh of 33 Kannon pilgrimage temples in Saigoku (Kinki area)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 18: The ceremony of exhibiting the Juntei Kannon, the principal image in the temple and the stamp office for temple number 11 of the Saigoku Sanjusankasho (the 33 temples that are visited during the Kansai Kannon Pilgrimage)</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>5月21日 三宝院流得度式</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May 21th: Sanbo-in school tokudo (entrance into the Buddhist priesthood) ceremony</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">May 21: Sanbo-in school tokudo (entrance into the Buddhist priesthood) ceremony</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 21: Sanbo-in school tokudo (entrance into the Buddhist priesthood) ceremony</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>6月7～9日　三宝院門跡大峰山花供入峰</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From June 7th to 9th: Sanbo-in Monzeki Omine-san Hanakunyubu Syugyo (a sort of Shugendo training: an event of offering lotus flowers at the sacred place in the mountains)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 7 to 9: Sanbo-in Monzeki Omine-san Hanakunyubu Syugyo (a sort of Shugendo training: an event of offering lotus flowers at the sacred place in the mountains)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 7 to 9: Sanbo-in Monzeki Omine-san Hanakunyubu Shugyo (a sort of Shugendo training: an event of offering lotus flowers at the sacred place in the mountains)</e>
<cmt>全角削除スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>6月15日 宗祖弘法大師降誕会法要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 15th: June 15th Kobo-Daishi Gotan-e (a memorial service on the anniversary of the birth of the founder, Kobo Daishi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 15: Kobo-Daishi Gotan-e (a memorial service on the anniversary of the birth of the founder, Kobo Daishi)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 15: Kobo-Daishi Gotan-e (a memorial service on the anniversary of the birth of the founder, Kobo Daishi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>7月7日 葛城山花供入峰</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 7th: Katsuragi-san Hanakunyubu Syugyo (a sort of Shugendo training: an event of offering lotus flowers at the sacred place in Mt.Katsuragi)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 7: Katsuragi-san Hanakunyubu Syugyo (a sort of Shugendo training; an event of offering lotus flowers at the sacred place on Mt. Katsuragi)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 7: Katsuragi-san Hanakunyubu Shugyo (a sort of Shugendo training; an event of offering lotus flowers at the sacred place on Mt. Katsuragi)</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>7月13日～15日 盂蘭盆会法要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From July 13th through 15th: Urabone ceremony</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 13 - 15: Urabone ceremony</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 13 - 15: Urabone ceremony</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>7月下旬（4日間） 少年少女の集い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toward the end of July (for four days): a gathering of boys and girls</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toward the end of July (for four days): A gathering of boys and girls</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toward the end of July (for four days): A gathering of boys and girls</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>7月19～23日　三宝院門跡奥駈修行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From July 19th through 23th: Sanbo-in Monzeki Okugake Syugyo (a sort of Shugendo practice performed in the mountains)</e>
<cmt>行事の内容については、醍醐寺のHPでも説明がありませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 19 - 23: Sanbo-in Monzeki Okugake Syugyo (a sort of Shugendo practice performed in the mountains)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 19 - 23: Sanbo-in Monzeki Okugake Shugyo (a sort of Shugendo practice performed in the mountains)</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>8月5日　醍醐山萬燈供養会</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 5th: Mt.Daigo Manto Kuyo-e (praying for the ancestors)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 5: Mt. Daigo Manto Kuyo-e (praying for the ancestors)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 5: Mt. Daigo Manto Kuyo-e (praying for the ancestors)</e>
<cmt>全角削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>8月6日（午前10時） 開山忌竪義会（開山理源大師御命日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 6th (at 10 a.m.): Kaizanki ceremony (the anniversary of the death of the founder, Rigen Daishi)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 6 (10 a.m.): Kaizanki ceremony (the anniversary of the death of the founder, Rigen Daishi)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 6 (10 a.m.): Kaizanki ceremony (the anniversary of the death of the founder, Rigen Daishi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>9月20日～26日 秋季彼岸法要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From September 20th through 26th: Autumn Higan ceremony (week of the spring equinox)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 20 - 26: Autumn Higan ceremony (week of the spring equinox)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 20 - 26: Autumn Higan ceremony (week of the spring equinox)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>10月第1土曜日　霊宝館開館・国宝金堂特別内拝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first Saturday of October Autumn exhibition at Reihokan (the museum), including a special exhibition of inside Kon-do Hall (main hall of a Buddhist temple), which is a national treasure</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First Saturday of October: Autumn exhibition at Reihokan (the museum), including a special exhibition of the interior of Kon-do Hall (main hall of a Buddhist temple), which is a national treasure</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First Saturday of October: Autumn exhibition at Reihokan (the museum), including a special exhibition of the interior of Kon-do Hall (main hall of a Buddhist temple), which is a national treasure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>12月第1日曜日　霊宝館開館・国宝金堂特別内拝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first Sunday of December: An exhibition at Reihokan (the museum), including a special exhibition of inside Kon-do Hall (main hall of a Buddhist temple), which is a national tresure</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First Sunday of December: An exhibition at Reihokan (the museum), including a special exhibition of the interior of Kon-do Hall (main hall of a Buddhist temple), which is a national treasure</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First Sunday of December: An exhibition at Reihokan (the museum), including a special exhibition of the interior of Kon-do Hall (main hall of a Buddhist temple), which is a national treasure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>10月23日 五大力講世話方総会</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 23th: Godairiki-ko Sewagata conference</e>
<cmt>行事の内容については、醍醐寺のHPでも説明がありませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 23: The Godairiki-ko Sewagata conference</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 23: The Godairiki-ko Sewagata conference</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>12月上旬 修験伝法教校</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The beginning of December: Shugen denpo kyoko (a sort of Shugendo training seminar)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The beginning of December: Shugen denpo kyoko (a sort of Shugendo training seminar)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The beginning of December: Shugen denpo kyoko (a sort of Shugendo training seminar)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>12月21日 三宝院流伝法灌頂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 21th: Sanbo-in school denpo-kanjo (the consecration for the Transmission of the Dharma)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 21: Sanbo-in school denpo-kanjo (the consecration for the Transmission of the Dharma)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 21: Sanbo-in school denpo-kanjo (the consecration for the Transmission of the Dharma)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>教育機関</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Educational institutions</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Educational institutions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Educational institutions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="90">
<j>醍醐山伝法学院（醍醐寺内）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daigosan Denpo Academy (inside Daigo-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daigosan Denpo Academy (inside Daigo-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daigosan Denpo Academy (inside Daigo-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>種智院大学（協同経営）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shuchiin University (joint management)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shuchiin University (joint management)</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shuchiin University (joint management)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>洛南高等学校・附属中学校（協同経営）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rakunan high school and junior high school (joint management)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rakunan high school and junior high school (joint management)</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rakunan high school and junior high school (joint management)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>教義</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Doctrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Doctrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Doctrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="93">
<j>古義真言宗の教義に準じる</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It follows the doctrine of the Kogi Shingon (Old Shingon) school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It follows the doctrine of the Kogi Shingon (Old Shingon) school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It follows the doctrine of the Kogi Shingon (Old Shingon) school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>施設</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Facilities</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Facilities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Facilities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="94">
<j>醍醐寺文化財研究所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daigoji bunkazai kenkyujo (Daigoji research institute for cultural properties)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daigoji bunkazai kenkyujo (Daigoji research institute for cultural properties)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daigoji bunkazai kenkyujo (Daigoji research institute for cultural properties)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="95">
<j>霊宝館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reihokan (Museum)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reihokan (Museum)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reihokan (Museum)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Chiew(id:39745), 浩(id:70121), ころぷー(id:192438), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>