<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大谷尊由</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Son-yu OTANI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Son-yu OTANI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sonyu OTANI</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大谷 尊由（おおたに そんゆ、1886年（明治19年）8月19日 - 1939年（昭和14年）8月1日）は、浄土真宗の僧侶、政治家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Son-yu OTANI (August 19, 1886 ~ August 1, 1939) is a priest and a statesman of Jodo shinshu (True Pure Land Sect Buddhism).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Son-yu OTANI (August 19, 1886 - August 1, 1939) was a priest and statesman of Jodo shinshu (the True Pure Land sect of Buddhism).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sonyu OTANI (August 19, 1886 - August 1, 1939) was a priest and statesman of Jodo shinshu (the True Pure Land sect of Buddhism).</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>来歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Historical trail</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historical trail</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historical trail</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>浄土真宗本願寺派第21世門主大谷光尊（明如）の4男として京都市に生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Kyoto City as the 4th son of the twenty-first chief priest of the Jodo Shinshu sect Hongan-ji school, Koson OTANI (Meinyo).</e>
<cmt>「明如」の読みがわかりませんでした。仮に「めいにょ」としています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Kyoto City as the fourth son of Koson OTANI (Meinyo), the twenty-first chief priest of the Jodo Shinshu sect&apos;s Hongan-ji school.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Kyoto City as the fourth son of Koson OTANI (Meinyo), the twenty-first chief priest of the Jodo Shinshu sect&apos;s Hongan-ji school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>兄は第22世門主大谷光瑞（鏡如）、妹は九条武子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His elder brother is the twenty-second chief priest Kozui OTANI (Kyonyo) and his younger sister is Takeko KUJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His elder brother was the twenty-second chief priest, Kozui OTANI (Kyonyo), and his younger sister was Takeko KUJO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His elder brother was the twenty-second chief priest, Kozui OTANI (Kyonyo), and his younger sister was Takeko KUJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>兄と共に博識で知られ、後藤新平などが早くからその人物を評価していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Together with his brother, they were known as knowledgeable, and Shinpei GOTO, etc appreciated the person early on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Together with his brother, they were known as knowledgeable, and early on they gained the respect of people such as Shinpei GOTO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Together with his brother, they were known as knowledgeable, and early on they gained the respect of people such as Shinpei GOTO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>成人してからは連枝として兄の宗政を助け、本願寺執行長、本願寺派護持会財団理事長、管長事務取扱（管長代理）などを歴任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he came of age, he helped his elder brother&apos;s religious administration as a brother, and he successively fill various posts such as the head regent of Hongan-ji Temple, the head of Hongan-ji school Gojikai (an association to defend Buddhisn) Foundation, the chief abbot office clerk (the deputy chief abbot), etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he came of age, he assisted his elder brother&apos;s religious administration, and he successively filled various posts such as the head regent of Hongan-ji Temple, the head of the Hongan-ji school&apos;s Gojikai (an association to defend Buddhism) Foundation, the chief abbot office clerk (the deputy chief abbot), etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he came of age, he assisted his elder brother&apos;s religious administration, and he successively filled various posts such as the head regent of Hongan-ji Temple, the head of the Hongan-ji school&apos;s Gojikai (an association to defend Buddhism) Foundation, the chief abbot office clerk (the deputy chief abbot), etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>この間、日露戦争に際した従軍布教の陣頭指揮にあたり、自身も中国各地を度々慰問している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the meantime, he led his men who were engaged in campaign and missionary work at Russo-Japanese war, and he often expressed sympathy for the soldiers at many places in China himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the meantime, he led his men who were engaged in campaign and missionary work at the Russo-Japanese War, and he often expressed sympathy for the soldiers in locations throughout China.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the meantime, he led his men who were engaged in campaign and missionary work at the Russo-Japanese War, and he often expressed sympathy for the soldiers in locations throughout China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>数々の教団改革をすすめ、大谷探検隊を財政面から助けたが、後に多額の負債を教団に残すこととなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He led many reforms of the religious community, and backed up the Otani Expedition financially, however, he left large sum of debt to the community due to it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He led many reforms of the religious community, and backed up the Otani Expedition financially, but consequently he left a large debt to the community.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He led many reforms of the religious community, and backed up the Otani Expedition financially, but consequently he left a large debt to the community.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>1914年、疑獄事件により門主の座を退いた兄に代わって次期門主が期待されたが、自身も事件に連座して宗政の第一線から身を退いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though he was expected to become the next chief priest in place of his elder brother who resigned its position by the suspected bribery case, he was also involved with the case himself and retired from the front line of the religious world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though he was expected to become the next chief priest in place of his elder brother, who resigned his position due to a case of suspected bribery, he was also involved with the case himself and retired from the front line of the religious world.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1914, though he was expected to become the next chief priest in place of his elder brother, who resigned his position due to a case of suspected bribery, he was also involved with the case himself and retired from the front line of the religious world.</e>
<cmt>In 1914補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>1928年、勅選により貴族院議員となり、第1次近衛内閣で拓務大臣、1938年には内閣参議に就く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1928, he became a member of the House of Peers by the imperial selection, and designated as the minister of Colonial Ministry (Takumu-sho) of the 1st Konoe cabinet, and in 1938, he was posted to Naikaku sangi (Advisor to the cabinet.)</e>
<cmt>「内閣参議」が分かりませんでした。&quot;Advisor to the Cabinet&quot;としています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1928, he became a member of the House of Peers by imperial selection and was designated as the minister of Colonial Ministry (Takumu-sho) of the first Konoe cabinet; in 1938, he was assigned the post of Naikaku sangi (advisor to the cabinet).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1928, he became a member of the House of Peers by imperial selection and was designated as the minister of Colonial Ministry (Takumu-sho) of the first Konoe cabinet; in 1938, he was assigned the post of Naikaku sangi (advisor to the cabinet).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>兄と共に度々大陸へ渡り、当地の事情に精通していたこともあって、同年に国策の北支那開発会社初代総裁に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As he traveled to Mainland China frequently with his elder brother and had detailed knowledge of the country, he was installed as the 1st director-genera of a national policy concern, Kita Shina Kaihatsu Kabushikigaisha (company which was established to develop Chinese economy in The Great Japanese Empire era) in 1938.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because he frequently traveled to the Chinese mainland with his elder brother and had an in-depth knowledge of the country, in 1938 he was installed as the first director-general of a national policy concern, Kita Shina Kaihatsu Kabushikigaisha (a company established to develop the Chinese economy during the era of the Great Japanese Empire).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because he frequently traveled to the Chinese mainland with his elder brother and had an in-depth knowledge of the country, in 1938 he was installed as the first director-general of a national policy concern, Kita Shina Kaihatsu Kabushikigaisha (a company established to develop the Chinese economy during the era of the Great Japanese Empire).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかしながら、志半ばの1939年、病に倒れ命終、行年54。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in 1939, he died of illness without fulfilling his life ambition at the age of 54.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in 1939 he died of illness at 54 years of age, with his life&apos;s ambition still unfulfilled.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in 1939 he died of illness at 54 years of age, with his life&apos;s ambition still unfulfilled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="13">
<j>子の益子は小坂財閥の小坂善太郎に、高子は岡崎財閥の岡崎真一にそれぞれ嫁いでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His daughters Masuko married Zentaro KOSAKA of Kosaka Zaibatsu (finance group) and Takako married Shinichi OKAZAKI of Okazaki Zaibatsu (literally financial cliques) respectively.</e>
<cmt>「益子」の読みは推定です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His daughter Masuko married Zentaro KOSAKA of Kosaka Zaibatsu (a financial group), and his other daughter Takako married Shinichi OKAZAKI of Okazaki Zaibatsu (literally, financial clique).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His daughter Masuko married Zentaro KOSAKA of Kosaka Zaibatsu (a financial group), and his other daughter Takako married Shinichi OKAZAKI of Okazaki Zaibatsu (literally, financial clique).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MKT(id:6704), 千早スパイラル(id:180323), 廬舎那憂(id:168188), R28Bot(id:177951), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), 陽一(id:92099), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>