<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>了然</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryonen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryonen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryonen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>了然（りょうねん、正保3年（1646年） － 正徳 (日本)元年9月18日 (旧暦)（1711年10月29日））は、江戸時代前期から中期にかけての黄檗宗の尼僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryonen (1646 - October 29, 1711) was a Buddhist nun of Obaku Sect in the early Edo period to mid-Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryonen (1646 - October 29, 1711) was a Buddhist nun of the Obaku sect who lived from the early Edo Period to the mid-Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryonen (1646 - October 29, 1711) was a Buddhist nun of the Obaku Sect who lived from the early Edo period to the mid-Edo period.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>武田信玄の曾孫葛山長爾の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was a daughter of Choji KATSURAYAMA, a great-grandchild of Shingen TAKEDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was a daughter of Choji KATSURAYAMA, who was a great-grandchild of Shingen TAKEDA.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was a daughter of Choji KATSURAYAMA, who was a great-grandchild of Shingen TAKEDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>名は総。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her secular name was So.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her secular name was So.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her secular name was So.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>字は了然。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her azana (another personal name) was Ryonen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her azana (another kind of personal name) was Ryonen.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her azana (adult males nickname) was Ryonen.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>諱は元総。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her imina (real personal name) was Genso.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her imina (real personal name) was Genso.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her imina (real personal name) was Genso.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>京都の出身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She hailed from Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was born in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Made less colloquial.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was born in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>初め後水尾天皇の中宮東福門院に出仕したのち、松田晩翠と結婚し2男3女を生んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After serving Tofukumonin, Chugu (a second consort of the emperor) of the Emperor Gomizunoo, she married Bansui MATSUDA and had two boys and three daughters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After serving Tofukumonin, Chugu (second consort of the emperor) of the Emperor Gomizunoo, she married Bansui MATSUDA and had two boys and three daughters.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After serving Tofukumonin, Chugu (second consort of the emperor) of the Emperor Gomizunoo, she married Bansui MATSUDA and had two boys and three daughters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし、1672年（寛文12年）松田の家を出て、中宮東福門院の孫にあたる好君に使えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, she left Matsuda family in 1672 and served Takagimi, a grandchild of Chugu Tofukumonin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, she left the Matsuda family in 1672 and served Takagimi, a grandchild of Chugu Tofukumonin.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, she left the Matsuda family in 1672 and served Takagimi, a grandchild of Chugu Tofukumonin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>好君の没後、京都宝鏡寺の理忠女王（後水尾天皇の皇女）に師事して剃髪した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Takagimi, she studied under Richu-nyoo, a princess of the Emperor Gomizunoo, and entered into prieshood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Takagimi, she studied under Richu-nyoo, daughter of Emperor Gomizunoo, and entered into the prieshood.</e>
<cmt>The phrase &apos;a princess of the Emperor&apos; is unclear. Is it correct that 皇女 refers to daughter?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Takagimi, she studied under Princess Richu in Hokyo-ji Temple in Kyoto, daughter of Emperor Gomizunoo, and entered into the priesthood.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>江戸にくだり黄檗宗の禅僧白翁道泰に入門を願ったが、美貌のため許されず、自ら顔面を焼いて入門を許された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She then went down to Edo and asked Michiyasu HAKUO, a Zen monk of Obaku Sect, to take up her as his disciple, but her request was refused because of her good looks and eventually she was allowed to become his disciple after burning her face.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She then went to Edo and asked Michiyasu HAKUO, a Zen monk of the Obaku sect, to take her in as his disciple, but her request was refused because of her good looks and only eventually was she allowed to become his disciple after burning her face.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She then went to Edo and asked Michiyasu HAKUO, a Zen monk of the Obaku Sect, to take her in as his disciple, but her request was refused because of her good looks and only eventually was she allowed to become his disciple after burning her face.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>1693年（元禄6年）武蔵国上落合村（現在東京都新宿区）に泰雲寺を創建し、白翁を勧請開山にむかえ、自らは2世を称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1693, she founded Taiun-ji Temple in Kamiochiai village, Musashi Province (Shinjuku Ward, Tokyo) with HAKUO its founder and called herself second founder.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1693, she co-founded Taiun-ji Temple in Kamiochiai village, Musashi Province (now Shinjuku Ward, Tokyo) with its founder HAKUO and called herself second founder.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1693, she built Taiun-ji Temple in Kamiochiai village, Musashi Province (now Shinjuku-ku Ward, Tokyo Prefecture) with having HAKUO as kaizan (a founder of temple as the first chief priest) and called herself second founder.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>