<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>数珠</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Juzu (beadroll)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Juzu (beadroll)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juzu (beadroll)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>数珠（じゅず、ずず）は穴が貫通した多くの珠に糸の束を通し輪にした法具。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Juzu is a Buddhist ritual implement and a kind of ring composed of many beads which are linked by piercing a bundle of threads into a hole made on each bead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Juzu is a Buddhist ritual implement and a kind of ring composed of many beads which are linked by piercing a bundle of threads into a hole made on each bead.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juzu (数珠) is a Buddhist ritual implement and a kind of ring composed of many beads which are linked by piercing a bundle of threads into a hole made on each bead.</e>
<cmt>後で「数珠」の漢字についての記述があるため、漢字を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>仏を念ずる時に用いる珠との意味から「念珠（ねんじゅ）」とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As it means beads that are used when praying to Buddha, it is also called &quot;nenju&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As it means beads that are used when praying to Buddha, it is also called &quot;nenju&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As it means beads that are used when praying to Buddha, it is also called &apos;nenju&apos; (praying beadroll).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変え補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>梵語で「ハソマ」という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Sanskrit, it is called &quot;hasoma&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Sanskrit, it is called &quot;hasoma&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Sanskrit, it is called &apos;hasoma.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変え補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>念仏の際に音を立てて揉んだり、真言・念仏の回数を数えるのに珠をつまぐる目的などで用いる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While praying to Buddha, it is used for the purpose of rubbing, jjingling and/or counting frequency of mantra and Buddhist invocation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While praying to Buddha, it is used for the purpose of rubbing, jjingling and/or counting frequency of mantra and Buddhist invocation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While praying to Buddha, it is used for the purpose of rubbing, jingling and/or counting frequency of mantra and Buddhist invocation.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>念仏の回数を問題にしない浄土真宗などの場合は、仏前での崇敬の念の表れとして用いる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In sects that don&apos;t care about the frequency of Buddhist invocation, such as Jodo Shinshu, it is used as a symbol of reverence to Buddha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In sects that do not care about the frequency of Buddhist invocation, such as Jodo Shinshu, it is used as a symbol of reverence to Buddha.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In sects that do not care about the frequency of Buddhist invocation, such as Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism), it is used as a symbol of reverence to Buddha.</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>一般に仏事・法要の際、仏・菩薩・物故者の霊位などに礼拝するときに、合掌した手にかける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally, it is hung on hands that are put flat together on the occasions of Buddhist rite, Buddhist memorial service and/or praying to Buddha ・ Bodhisattva ・ memorial tablet of the deceased.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, it is hung on hands that are put flat together on the occasions of Buddhist rites, Buddhist memorial services and/or praying to Buddha ・ Bodhisattva ・ memorial tablet of the deceased.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, it is hung on hands that are put flat together on the occasions of Buddhist rites, Buddhist memorial services and/or praying to Buddha, Bodhisattva, memorial tablet of the deceased.</e>
<cmt>・をカンマにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>手へのかけ方は宗派によって相違がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The way to hang on hands is different from sect to sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The way to hang on the hands is different from sect to sect.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The way to hang on the hands is different from sect to sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>僧侶が手ではなく首にかけて用いる場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monks sometimes hang it on a neck instead of hands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Monks sometimes hang it on the neck instead of hands.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Monks sometimes hang it on the neck instead of hands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>起源は諸説あるが、古代インドのバラモン教で用いられていた道具を原型とするとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concerning its origin, there are various views but it is generally believed that the tool used by Brahmanism in Ancient India is the origin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concerning its origin, there are various views but it is generally believed that the tool used by Brahmanism in Ancient India is the origin.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concerning its origin, there are various views but it is generally believed that the tool used by Brahmanism in Ancient India is the origin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>それが、釈尊により用いられ、後に中国に伝わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above tool was used by Sakyamuni and introduced into China later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above tool was used by Sakyamuni and introduced into China later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The above tool was used by Sakyamuni and introduced into China later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>そして仏教伝来とともに飛鳥時代には日本に伝わったされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, it was introduce into Japan in Asuka Period along with the introduction of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, it was introduced into Japan in the Asuka Period along with the introduction of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, it was introduced into Japan in the Asuka period along with the introduction of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>鎌倉時代に入り、浄土教が流行し称名念仏が盛んになるとともに一般にも普及する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In kamakura Period when Jodo-kyo (pure land teachings) prevailed and Chengming nianfo became popular, it spread widely among ordinary people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kamakura Period, when Jodo-kyo (pure land teachings) prevailed and Chengming nianfo became popular, it spread widely among ordinary people.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kamakura period, when Jodo-kyo (pure land teachings) prevailed and Invocation of the Buddha&apos;s Name became popular, it spread widely among ordinary people.</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>最近では腕輪念珠（腕珠）と呼ばれる、数珠を小型化し中糸をゴムなどにして腕に着けられるようにしたブレスレット的な数珠がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, there exists bracelet-type juzu, called Round Brace nenju (wanju), which is miniaturized juzu that uses elastic as an inner string so that it can be hung on arms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present, there are bracelet-type juzu, called Round Brace nenju (wanju), which are miniaturized juzu that uses elastic as an inner string so that it can be hung on the arms.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present, there are bracelet-type juzu, called udewa nenju (or wanju, bracelet nenju), which are miniaturized juzu that uses elastic as an inner string so that it can be hung on the arms.</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>ただし腕輪念珠は、数珠本来の用途に用いるには大きさに無理がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Round Brace nenju is not suitable to use for the original purpose of juzu due to its size.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Round Brace nenju is not suitable for use for the original purpose of juzu, due to its size.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, udewa nenju is not suitable for use for the original purpose of juzu, due to its size.</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>数珠を取扱う上での注意</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Matters to be attended to when handling juzu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Matters to be attended to when handling juzu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Matters to be Attended to When Handling Juzu</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>法具なので、大切に扱う事。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It must be handled with care since it is a Buddhist ritual implement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It must be handled with care since it is a Buddhist ritual implement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It must be handled with care since it is a Buddhist ritual implement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>携帯時には、数珠袋（念珠袋）など専用の袋にいれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When carrying it, it must be put into an exclusive bag such as a juzu bag (nenju bag).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When carrying it, it must be put into an exclusive bag such as a juzu bag (nenju bag).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When carrying it, it must be put into an exclusive bag such as a juzu bag (nenju bag).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>置く時は、鞄や念珠袋の上、ハンカチなどの上に置き、畳の上などには直に置いてはならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When putting it, it must be put on a bag, a nenju bag or a handkerchief and must not be directly put on tatami mat etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When placing it, it must be put on a bag, a nenju bag or a handkerchief and must not be directly put on tatami mats etc.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When placing it, it must be put on a bag, a nenju bag or a handkerchief and must not be directly put on tatami mats, and so on.</e>
<cmt>and so onを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="18">
<j>一般的に数珠を持つ場合は、房を下に垂らし左手に持つか、左の手首に下げるとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is generally believed that juzu should be held by a left hand with a tassel hanging down or should be hung on a left wrist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is generally believed that juzu should be held by the left hand with a tassel hanging down or should be hung on the left wrist.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is generally believed that juzu should be held by the left hand with a tassel hanging down or should be hung on the left wrist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>珠の数</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Number of beads</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Number of beads</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Number of Beads</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>108という数は煩悩の数を表すとされ、数珠の珠はそれぞれの煩悩を司る108の仏を表し、人間のあらゆる煩悩を数珠が受けるとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that the number of 108 represents the number of earthly desires, each bead of juzu represents 108 Buddha who preside over each earthly desire and juzu suffers all earthly desires of human being.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that the number of 108 represents the number of earthly desires, each bead of juzu represents 108 Buddha who preside over each earthly desire and juzu suffers all earthly desires of human beings.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that the number of 108 represents the number of earthly desires, each bead of juzu represents 108 Buddha who preside over each earthly desire and juzu suffers all earthly desires of human beings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>「本連」または「二連」、「二輪」と呼ばれる数珠は、「主珠（おもだま）」（珠の名称を参照）が108珠ある数珠の事。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Juzu that is called &quot;Honren-juzu&quot;, &quot;Niren-juzu (two loops Juzu)&quot; or &quot;Nirin-juzu&quot; is the one that is composed of 108 beads of &quot;Omodama&quot; (refer to the name of beads)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Juzu that are called &quot;Honren-juzu&quot;, &quot;Niren-juzu (two loops Juzu)&quot; or &quot;Nirin-juzu&quot; are ones that are composed of 108 beads of &quot;Omodama&quot; (refer to the name of beads)</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juzu that are called &apos;Honren&apos; (main strand), &apos;Niren&apos; (two strand) or &apos;Nirin&apos; (two loops) are ones that are composed of 108 beads of &apos;Omodama&apos; (main beads) (refer to the name of beads).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変え、用語表記を本文に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>二重にして使用する事が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is usually used with making it into double rings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is usually used by making it into double rings.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is usually used by making it into double rings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="22">
<j>「片手」または「略式」と呼ばれる数珠は、本来は108珠である主珠の数を簡略化した数珠の事。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Juzu that is called &quot;one hand juzu&quot; or &quot;informal juzu&quot; is the one that is composed of decreased number of Omodama instead of original number of 108.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Juzu that are called &quot;one handed juzu&quot; or &quot;informal juzu&quot; are ones that are composed of a decreased number of Omodama instead of the original number of 108.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juzu that are called &apos;one handed&apos; or &apos;informal&apos; are ones that are composed of a decreased number of Omodama instead of the original number of 108.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変え、用語表記を本文に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>主珠の数は108珠の半数の54珠、三分一の36珠、四分の一の27珠、六分の一の18珠などさまざまである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of Omodama varies widely from 54 beads, half of 108, 36 beads, one third of 108, 27 beads, a quarter of 108 to 18 beads, one sixth of 108.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of Omodama varies widely from 54 beads, half of 108, 36 beads, one third of 108, 27 beads, a quarter of 108 to 18 beads, one sixth of 108.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of Omodama varies widely from 54 beads which is half of 108, 36 beads which is one third of 108, 27 beads which is a quarter of 108 to 18 beads which is one sixth of 108.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>最近では、22珠や25珠など珠の数にあまりこだわらず、仕上がりの輪の大きさ（手の大きさ）に合わせた珠の数で製作されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent years, juzu that is composed of proper number of beads suitable for the size of ring (size of a hand), instead of sticking to particular number like 22 beads or 25 beads, is produced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent years, juzu that are composed of the proper number of beads suitable for the size of the ring (size of a hand), instead of sticking to a particular number like 22 beads or 25 beads, are produced.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent years, juzu that are composed of the proper number of beads suitable for the size of the ring (size of a hand), instead of sticking to a particular number like 22 beads or 25 beads, are produced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="25">
<j>百万遍念珠と呼ばれる、1080珠ある数珠もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There exists juzu that is composed of 1080 beads called &quot;Hyakumanben-nenju&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There exist juzu that are composed of 1080 beads called &quot;Hyakumanben-nenju&quot;.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There exist juzu that are composed of 1080 beads called Hyakumanben-nenju (literally, one hundred times of nenju).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションをのぞき補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="26">
<j>珠の数え方には、「○○珠」以外にも「○○玉」や「○○顆」と呼ぶ事がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for a unit in counting the number of beads, &quot;OOballs (玉)&quot; or &quot;OOgrains (顆)&quot; are also used other than &quot;OO beads (珠)&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for a unit in counting the number of beads, &quot;OOballs (玉)&quot; or &quot;OOgrains (顆)&quot; are also used other than &quot;OO beads (珠)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for a unit in counting the number of beads, &apos;... ball&apos; (玉, tama) or &apos;... grain&apos; (顆, ka) are also used other than &apos;... bead&apos; (珠, tama).</e>
<cmt>○○を... にし、クォーテーションをのぞき表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>本文では、「珠」で統一する事にする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this column, &quot;beads (珠)&quot; is to be used consistently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this column, &quot;beads (珠)&quot; is to be used consistently.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this column, &apos;bead&apos; (珠) is to be used consistently.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>珠の名称</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Name of beads</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Name of beads</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Name of Beads</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>本連数珠の場合、一番大きい珠（1珠ないし2珠）の事を「親珠（おやだま）」または「母珠（もしゅ）」と呼び、輪を主に構成する108珠ある珠の事を「主珠（おもだま）」と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In case of Honren-juzu, the biggest bead (one bead or 2 beads) is called &quot;Oyadama(parent bead)&quot; or &quot;Moshu (mother bead)&quot; and 108 beads which mainly compose a ring are called &quot;Omodama&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of Honren-juzu, the biggest bead (one bead or 2 beads) is called &quot;Oyadama(parent bead)&quot; or &quot;Moshu (mother bead)&quot; and the 108 beads which mainly compose a ring are called &quot;Omodama&quot;.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of Honren-juzu, the biggest bead (one bead or 2 beads) is called &apos;Oyadama&apos; (parent bead) or &apos;Moshu&apos; (mother bead) and the 108 beads which mainly compose a ring are called &apos;Omodama.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>主珠の間に挟まれている、主球より小さい四つの珠の事を「四天珠（してんだま）」と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">4 beads which are smaller than Omodama and lie between Omodama are called &quot;Shitendama&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">4 beads which are smaller than Omodama and lie between Omodama are called &quot;Shitendama&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">4 beads which are smaller than Omodama and lie between Omodama are called &apos;Shitendama.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>その他に、房の部分に「弟子球（でしだま）」「記子（きこ）とも」、「浄名（じょうみょう）」、「つゆ」、「副珠」と呼ばれる珠がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than the above, beads which are called &quot;Deshidama&quot;, &quot;Kikotomo&quot;, &quot;Jomyo bead&quot;, &quot;Tsuyudama(dewdrop-beads)&quot; and &quot;Fukudama&quot; respectively are attached to tassels.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than the above, beads which are called &quot;Deshidama&quot;, &quot;Kikotomo&quot;, &quot;Jomyo bead&quot;, &quot;Tsuyudama(dewdrop-beads)&quot; and &quot;Fukudama&quot; respectively are attached to tassels.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than the above, beads which are called &apos;Deshidama&apos; (disciple bead), &apos;Kikotomo,&apos; &apos;Jomyo&apos; (pure bead), &apos;Tsuyu&apos; (dewdrop beads) and &apos;Fukudama&apos; (sub bead) respectively are attached to tassels.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>〔宗旨により用いられる珠に違いがあるため、詳細は後述。〕</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">〔Details is to be mentioned later since different beads are used depending on religious Doctrines.〕</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">〔Details to be mentioned later since different beads are used depending on religious Doctrines.〕</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">〔Details to be mentioned later since different beads are used depending on religious Doctrines.〕</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="32">
<j>片手数珠の場合は、親玉が一珠のみで、親玉と房の間に「ぼさ（菩薩）」と呼ばれる管状の珠が入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In case of one hand juzu, the number of Oyadama is only 1 and a tube-like bead called &quot;bosa (Bodhisattva) is inserted between Oyadama and tassel.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of one hand juzu, the number of Oyadama is only 1 and a tube-like bead called &quot;bosa (Bodhisattva) is inserted between Oyadama and tassel.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of one hand juzu, the number of Oyadama is only 1 and a tube-like bead called &apos;bosa&apos; (Bodhisattva) is inserted between Oyadama and tassel.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>輪を主に構成する多数の珠は、二重数珠と同じく主珠と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many beads which mainly compose a ring are called Omodama likewise the case of Niju-juzu (double rings juzu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many beads which mainly compose a ring are called Omodama, likewise in the case of Niju-juzu (double ring juzu).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many beads which mainly compose a ring are called Omodama, likewise in the case of Niju-juzu (double ring juzu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>主珠より小さい二つの珠の事を「二天珠（にてんだま）」と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">2 beads which are smaller than Omodama are called &quot;Nitendama&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">2 beads which are smaller than Omodama are called &quot;Nitendama&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2 beads which are smaller than Omodama are called &apos;Nitendama&apos; (literally, beads of two celestial).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変え補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="35">
<j>名称には、「珠」の字以外にも「玉」の字も用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Chinese character of &quot;玉&quot; is also used, other than &quot;珠&quot;, for the name of beads.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Chinese character of &quot;玉&quot; is also used, other than &quot;珠&quot;, for the name of beads.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Chinese character of &apos;玉&apos; (tama) is also used, other than &apos;珠&apos; (tama), for the name of beads.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>本文では、「珠」で統一する事にする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;珠&quot; is to be used in this column consistently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;珠&quot; is to be used in this column consistently.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">珠&apos; is to be used in this column consistently.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>珠の形について</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shape of beads</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shape of beads</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shape of Beads</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="37">
<j>数珠の珠のかたちは、概ね以下の3種類に分けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By and large, the shape of juzu beads are categorized into following 3 kinds.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By and large, the shapes of juzu beads are categorized into the following 3 kinds.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By and large, the shapes of juzu beads are categorized into the following three kinds.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="38">
<j>丸玉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Marudama(round-bead)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Marudama(round-bead)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Marudama (round-bead)</e>
<cmt>半角カッコにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="39">
<j>みかん玉　真言・念仏の回数を数えるときに珠を繰りやすい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mikandama(elliptic type) - It can be easily handled when counting the frequency of mantra and Buddhist invocation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mikandama(elliptic type) - It can be easily handled when counting the frequency of mantra and Buddhist invocation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mikandama (elliptic type) - It can be easily handled when counting the frequency of mantra and Buddhist invocation.</e>
<cmt>半角カッコにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>数珠に仕立てたときに肉厚で重厚感があるように見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Juzu that is composed of Mikandama looks meaty and sublime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Juzu that is composed of Mikandama looks meaty and sublime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juzu that is composed of Mikandama looks meaty and sublime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>数珠の繰りやすさと美観の利点から、（宗派によって差異があるが）僧侶がみかん玉を好む傾向が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monks tend to prefer Mikandama because of its easiness in handling and fine appearance (though there is a difference depending on sects).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Monks tend to prefer Mikandama because of ease of handling and fine appearance (though there is a difference depending on sects).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Monks tend to prefer Mikandama because of ease of handling and fine appearance (though there is a difference depending on sects).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="42">
<j>平玉　天台宗で使われることがあるが、日蓮宗では使用しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiradama(flat-bead) - It is sometimes used in Tendai sect but not in Nichiren sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiradama(flat-bead) - It is sometimes used in the Tendai sect but not in the Nichiren sect.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiradama (flat-bead) - It is sometimes used in the Tendai sect but not in the Nichiren sect.</e>
<cmt>半角カッコにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>材質</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Materials</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Materials</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Materials</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="43">
<j>古い文献には七宝が良いとされるが、現在では菩提樹など様々な材質の珠が用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although cloisonne enamel was recommended in old documents, beads made from various materials, such as lime tree, are used today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although cloisonne enamel was recommended in old documents, beads made from various materials, such as lime tree, are used today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although cloisonne enamel was recommended in old documents, beads made from various materials, such as lime tree, are used today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>珠の材料により価格には、大きな差がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prices of juzu widely vary depending on the materials of beads.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prices of juzu widely vary depending on the bead materials.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prices of juzu widely vary depending on the bead materials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>本水晶や珊瑚など明るい色合いのものは女性に好まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Women prefer fine-colored juzu that are made from crystal or coral.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Women prefer fine-colored juzu that are made from crystal or coral.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Women prefer fine-colored juzu that are made from crystal or coral.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>高級な数珠用の素材としては、金線入り水晶（ルチルクォーツ）、本翡翠（ビルマ翡翠）、象牙、ラピスラズリ、天竺菩提樹などが用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As materials for high grade juzu, crystal with gold line (rutile quartz), feicui (Burma feicui), ivory, lapis lazuli and Bo tree etc. are used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As materials for high grade juzu, crystal with gold line (rutile quartz), feicui (Burma feicui), ivory, lapis lazuli and Bo tree etc. are used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As materials for high grade juzu, crystal with gold line (rutile quartz), feicui (Burma feicui), ivory, lapis lazuli and Bo tree, and so on, are used.</e>
<cmt>and so onを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>安価な数珠用には、石や珊瑚に似せたガラスや樹脂製の珠も用いられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For cheap juzu, glass beads and/or plastic beads which resemble to stone beads or coral beads are used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For cheap juzu, glass beads and/or plastic beads which resemble stone beads or coral beads are used.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For cheap juzu, glass beads and/or plastic beads which resemble stone beads or coral beads are used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>宗旨･宗派により、材質や色、房の形に決まりがある場合があるので注意が必要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Attention should be paid to the fact that there could be different rules on materials, color and the shape of tassels depending on doctrines and/or sects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Attention should be paid to the fact that there could be different rules on materials, color and the shape of tassels depending on doctrines and/or sects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Attention should be paid to the fact that there could be different rules on materials, color and the shape of tassels depending on doctrines and/or sects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="49">
<j>主な珠の材質</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ptincipal materials for beads</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ptincipal materials for beads</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ptincipal Materials for Beads</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="50">
<j>宝石･貴石　水晶類（本水晶･紫水晶･茶水晶など）、メノウ（オニキス）、本ヒスイ（ビルマ翡翠）、インドヒスイ、珊瑚類、トルマリンなど</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jewelry/precious stones - crystal and the like (crystal/ amethyst/smoky quartz etc.), agate (onyx), feicui (Burma feicui), green aventurine, coral and the like and tourmaline etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jewelry/precious stones - crystal and the like (crystal/ amethyst/smoky quartz etc.), agate (onyx), feicui (Burma feicui), green aventurine, coral and the like and tourmaline etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jewelry and precious stones - crystal and the like (crystal, amethyst, smoky quartz, and so on), agate (onyx), feicui (Burma feicui), green aventurine, coral and the like and tourmaline, and so on.</e>
<cmt>・を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="51">
<j>木　黒檀、紫檀、タガヤサン（鉄刀木）、ツゲ（柘植）、センダン（栴檀）、琥珀など</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wood - ebony, rosewood, Bombay black wood, Japanese box tree, White cedar and amber etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wood - ebony, rosewood, Bombay black wood, Japanese box tree, White cedar and amber etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wood - ebony, rosewood, Bombay black wood, Japanese box tree, White cedar and amber, and so on.</e>
<cmt>and so onを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="52">
<j>木の実　天竺菩提樹、金剛菩提樹、鳳眼菩提樹、龍眼菩提樹、虎眼菩提樹など</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nuts of trees - Bo tree, Rudraksha, hogan linden, ryugan linden and kogan linden etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nuts of trees - Bo tree, Rudraksha, hogan linden, ryugan linden and kogan linden etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nuts of trees - Bo tree, Rudraksha, hogan linden, ryugan linden and kogan linden, and so on.</e>
<cmt>and so onを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="53">
<j>草の実　星月菩提樹、蓮華菩提樹など</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nuts of grass - seigetsu linden and renge linden etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nuts of grass - seigetsu linden and renge linden etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nuts of grass - seigetsu linden and renge linden, and so on.</e>
<cmt>and so onを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="54">
<j>香木　白檀、伽羅など</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fragrant wood - sandal wood and dwarf Japanese yew etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fragrant wood - sandal wood and dwarf Japanese yew etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fragrant wood - sandal wood and dwarf Japanese yew, and so on.</e>
<cmt>and so onを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="55">
<j>象牙</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ivory</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ivory</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ivory</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="56">
<j>ガラス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Glass</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Glass</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Glass</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="57">
<j>セルロイド</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Celluloid</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Celluloid</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Celluloid</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>中糸・房の材質</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Materials for an inner string and tassels</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Materials for an inner string and tassels</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Materials for an Inner String and Tassels</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="58">
<j>正絹と人絹（ポリエステル）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pure silk and rayon (polyester) is used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Pure silk and rayon (polyester) is used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Pure silk and rayon (polyester) is used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="59">
<j>房の形は頭付房、切房、撚房、四ツ目紐房、菊房（梵天房）、利休房（手毬房）などがあり、職人によって更に細かい種類がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the shape of tassel, there are several basic patterns such as kashiratsuki tassel, kiri tassel, yori tassel, yotsumehimo tassel, kiku tassel (Brahma tassel) and Rikyu tassel (temari tassel) but depending on craftsmen, these could be further broken down.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the shape of tassel, there are several basic patterns such as kashiratsuki tassel, kiri tassel, yori tassel, yotsumehimo tassel, kiku tassel (Brahma tassel) and Rikyu tassel (temari tassel) but depending on craftsmen, these could be further broken down.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the shape of tassel, there are several basic patterns such as kashiratsuki tassel (literally, tassel with a head), kiri tassel (cutting tassel), yori tassel (getting together tassel), yotsumehimo tassel (four-eyed string tassel), kiku tassel (or Brahma tassel, chrysanthemum tassel) and Rikyu tassel (or temari ball tassel) but depending on craftsmen, these could be further broken down.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>材質別の注意点</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Matters to be attended to depending on materials</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Matters to be attended to depending on materials</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Matters to be Attended to Depending on Materials</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="60">
<j>天竺菩提樹など、虫害に弱い珠は桐箱に入れて保管するか、防虫剤を使用する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Beads which are vulnerable to harmful insects, such as the one made from Bo tree, must be kept in a paulownia box or treated with insecticide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Beads which are vulnerable to harmful insects, such as those made from Bo tree, must be kept in a paulownia box or treated with insecticide.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Beads which are vulnerable to harmful insects, such as those made from Bo tree, must be kept in a paulownia box or treated with insecticide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="61">
<j>珊瑚･真珠など傷つきやすい柔らかい素材の珠は、特に扱いを気をつける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Particular caution is required in handling fragile and/or soft beads such as the one made from coral or pearl.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Particular caution is required in handling fragile and/or soft beads such as those made from coral or pearl.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Particular caution is required in handling fragile and/or soft beads such as those made from coral or pearl.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="62">
<j>ラピスラズリ･赤珊瑚･真珠･孔雀石などの珠は、汗に弱いので保管するときは拭取ってから桐箱などに入れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the beads made from lapis lazuli, red coral, pearl or malachite are vulnerable to sweat, these must be kept in a paulownia box after wiping off sweat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the beads made from lapis lazuli, red coral, pearl or malachite are vulnerable to sweat, these must be kept in a paulownia box after wiping off sweat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the beads made from lapis lazuli, red coral, pearl or malachite are vulnerable to sweat, these must be kept in a paulownia box after wiping off sweat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>各宗派用の本式数珠</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Formal juzu for each sect</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Formal juzu for each sect</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Formal Juzu for Each Sect</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="63">
<j>以下は一般的な在家用の本式数珠の形式である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The followings are general explanation concerning the forms of formal juzu for ordinary lay believers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following are general explanations concerning the forms of formal juzu for ordinary lay believers.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following are general explanations concerning the forms of formal juzu for ordinary lay believers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>菩提寺などに確認をするか、専門店で相談するべきである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In selecting juzu, it is vital to confirm with a family temple or consult with a specialty store.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In selecting juzu, it is vital to confirm with a family temple or consult with a specialty store.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In selecting juzu, it is vital to confirm with a family temple or consult with a specialty store.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>天台宗用</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tendai sect</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tendai sect</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juzu for Tendai Sect</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="65">
<j>天台宗用の数珠は、輪の部分に主珠を108珠・親珠を1珠・四天珠を4珠を用いる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Juzu for Tendai sect uses 108 beads of Omodama, a bead of Oyadama and 4 beads of Shitendama to compose a ring.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Juzu for the Tendai sect uses 108 beads of Omodama, a bead of Oyadama and 4 beads of Shitendama to compose a ring.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juzu for the Tendai sect uses 108 beads of Omodama, a bead of Oyadama and 4 beads of Shitendama to compose a ring.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="66">
<j>珠の配置は、親珠1珠→主珠7珠→四天珠1珠→主珠14珠→四天珠1珠→主珠66珠→四天珠1珠→主珠14珠→四天珠1珠→主珠7珠で一周して輪になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These beads are arranged in order of &quot;1 bead of Oyadama=&gt;7 beads of Omodama=&gt;1 bead of Shitendama=&gt;14 beads of Omodama=&gt;1 bead of Shitendama=&gt;66 beads of Omodama=&gt;1 bead of Shitendama=&gt;14 beads of Omodama=&gt;1 bead of Shitendama=&gt;7 beads of Omodama&quot; and finally they shape a ring.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These beads are arranged in order of &quot;1 bead of Oyadama=&gt;7 beads of Omodama=&gt;1 bead of Shitendama=&gt;14 beads of Omodama=&gt;1 bead of Shitendama=&gt;66 beads of Omodama=&gt;1 bead of Shitendama=&gt;14 beads of Omodama=&gt;1 bead of Shitendama=&gt;7 beads of Omodama&quot; and finally they are shaped as a ring.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These beads are arranged in the following order; 1 bead of Oyadama=&gt;7 beads of Omodama=&gt;1 bead of Shitendama=&gt;14 beads of Omodama=&gt;1 bead of Shitendama=&gt;66 beads of Omodama=&gt;1 bead of Shitendama=&gt;14 beads of Omodama=&gt;1 bead of Shitendama=&gt;7 beads of Omodama, and finally they are shaped as a ring.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="67">
<j>親珠の下の房の結び目には、「浄名」と呼ばれる小珠が一珠付く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1 small bead called &quot;Jomyodama&quot; is attached at the knot of tassel made under Oyadama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1 small bead called &quot;Jomyodama&quot; is attached at the knot of a tassel made under Oyadama.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1 small bead called &apos;Jomyo&apos; is attached at the knot of a tassel made under Oyadama.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション、用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="68">
<j>浄名の下には2本の房が付く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">2 tassels are attached under Jomyodama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">2 tassels are attached under Jomyodama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2 tassels are attached under Jomyo.</e>
<cmt>前出に用語を合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>房の形は、いろいろな形が用いられる。（菊房や利休房（蹴鞠房）を用いる事が多い。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various shapes are used for tassels (kiku tassel and Rikyu tassel (kemari tassel) are often used).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various shapes are used for tassels (kiku tassel and Rikyu tassel (kemari tassel) are often used).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various shapes are used for tassels (kiku tassel and Rikyu tassel (kemari tassel) are often used).</e>
<cmt>「蹴鞠房」は「手毬房」(temari ball tassel)を指すと思われますが、そのまま訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="70">
<j>房には弟子珠が付く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Deshidama is attached to each tassel.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Deshidama is attached to each tassel.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Deshidama is attached to each tassel.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>弟子珠の形は、片方の房は丸珠が10珠, もう片方には、平珠が20珠と特徴がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each Deshidama has its characteristics since Deshidama attached to one tassel is composed of 10 beads of marudama and Deshidama attached to the other tassel is composed of 20 beads of hiradama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each Deshidama has its characteristics since Deshidama attached to one tassel is composed of 10 beads of marudama and Deshidama attached to the other tassel is composed of 20 beads of hiradama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each Deshidama has its characteristics since Deshidama attached to one tassel is composed of 10 beads of Marudama and Deshidama attached to the other tassel is composed of 20 beads of Hiradama.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>それぞれの弟子珠の先に「つゆ」と呼ばれる涙型の珠が付く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A tear-shaped bead called &quot;Tsuyudama&quot; is attached to the tip of each Deshidama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A tear-shaped bead called &quot;Tsuyudama&quot; is attached to the tip of each Deshidama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A tear-shaped bead called &apos;Tsuyu&apos; is attached to the tip of each Deshidama.</e>
<cmt>前出に用語を合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="73">
<j>天台宗の数珠の特徴は、主珠に平珠（そろばん珠）と呼ばれる扁平の珠が用いられる事である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The characteristics of Tendai sect&apos;s juzu is that flat beads called Hiradama (Sorobandama) are used for Omodama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The characteristics of the Tendai sect juzu is that flat beads called Hiradama (Sorobandama) are used for Omodama.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The characteristics of the Tendai sect juzu is that flat beads called Hiradama (Sorobandama) are used for Omodama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>真言宗用</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shingon sect</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shingon sect</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juzu for Shingon Sect</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="74">
<j>持ち方 （中院流の場合） 右手の中指に母珠を掛け、左手の人指し指に緒留を掛ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The way of holding (in case of Chuinryu) - A prayer should hang Moshu on the middle finger of right hand and hang odome on the forefinger of left hand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The way of holding (in case of Chuinryu) - A prayer should hang Moshu on the middle finger of the right hand and hang odome on the forefinger of the left hand.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The way of holding (in case of Chuin school) - A prayer should hang Moshu on the middle finger of the right hand and hang odome (literally, lacing up the thong) on the forefinger of the left hand.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>そのときに、念珠の輪の形がＸ（エックス）の形になるように1回だけねじる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, a prayer should twist Nenju once so that its shape becomes a shape of X.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, a prayer should twist Nenju once so that its shape becomes the shape of an X.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, a prayer should twist nenju once so that its shape becomes the shape of an X.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>合掌するときに、両方の房を手のひらの中に入れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When putting hands flat together in prayer, a prayer should put both tassels into the palms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When putting hands flat together in prayer, a prayer should put both tassels into the palms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When putting hands flat together in prayer, a prayer should put both tassels into the palms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>そして、左手を上にしてふせて、右手を下にして、仰げて軽く２～３度すり合わせ、右手を手前にして引いて止める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, a prayer should rub them 2 to 3 time slightly with a left hand up and its palm downward while a right hand down and its palm upward and then stop rubbing by pulling a right hand toward himself/herself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, a prayer should rub them 2 to 3 times slightly with the left hand up and the palm downward, while the right hand is down and its palm upward and should then stop rubbing by pulling the right hand towards himself/herself.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, a prayer should rub them 2 to 3 times slightly with the left hand up and the palm downward, while the right hand is down and its palm upward and should then stop rubbing by pulling the right hand towards himself/herself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>数珠を一双(いっそう)（一つの輪）にして持つときは、左手首へ掛けるが、その時には、母珠が左手首の上になるように掛ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When holding juzu in Isso (a ring), it should be hung on a left hand and in this case, it should be hung in a manner that Moshu is placed on the wrist of left hand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When holding juzu in Isso (a ring), it should be hung on the left hand and in this case, it should be hung in a manner where Moshu is placed on the wrist of the left hand.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When holding juzu in Isso (a ring), it should be hung on the left wrist and in this case, it should be hung in a manner where Moshu is placed on the wrist of the left hand.</e>
<cmt>writstを使いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>数珠を一双に持つと、右手が使えるので経本を右手に持って読経をすることが出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If and when a prayer holds juzu in Isso, he/she can make sutra recitation while holding a sutra text in the right hand since the right hand is free.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If and when a prayer holds juzu in Isso, he/she can make a sutra recitation while holding a sutra text in the right hand since the right hand is free.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If and when a prayer holds juzu in Isso, he/she can make a sutra recitation while holding a sutra text in the right hand since the right hand is free.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>在家（壇信徒）が中院流の持ち方をしても差支えはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no problem for lay believers (Buddhist supporters) to hold juzu according to Chuinryu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no problem for lay believers (Buddhist supporters) to hold juzu according to Chuinryu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no problem for lay believers (Buddhist supporters) to hold juzu according to Chuin school.</e>
<cmt>schoolを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="81">
<j>真言宗用の数珠は、輪の部分に用いられる主珠・四天珠の数は天台宗用と同じだが、親珠は2珠となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for juzu for Shingon sect, the number of Omodama and Shitendama used for a ring is same with juzu for Tendai sect but the number of Oyadama is 2 beads.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for juzu for the Shingon sect, the number of Omodama and Shitendama used for a ring is the same as with juzu for the Tendai sect but the number of Oyadama is 2 beads.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for juzu for the Shingon sect, the number of Omodama and Shitendama used for a ring is the same as with juzu for the Tendai sect but the number of Oyadama is 2 beads.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>珠の配置は、親珠1珠→主珠7珠→四天珠1珠→主珠14珠→四天珠1珠→主珠33珠→親珠1珠→主珠33珠→四天珠1珠→主珠14珠→四天珠1珠→主珠7珠で一周して輪になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These beads are arranged in the order of &quot;1 bead of Oyadama=&gt;7 beads of Omodama=&gt;1 bead of Shitendama=&gt;14 beads of Omodama=&gt;1 bead of Shitendama=&gt;33 beads of Omodama=&gt;1 bead of Oyadama=&gt;33 beads of Omodama=&gt;1 bead of Shitendama=&gt;14 beads of Omodama=&gt;7 beads of Omodama&quot; and they finally shape a ring.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These beads are arranged in the order of &quot;1 bead of Oyadama=&gt;7 beads of Omodama=&gt;1 bead of Shitendama=&gt;14 beads of Omodama=&gt;1 bead of Shitendama=&gt;33 beads of Omodama=&gt;1 bead of Oyadama=&gt;33 beads of Omodama=&gt;1 bead of Shitendama=&gt;14 beads of Omodama=&gt;7 beads of Omodama&quot; and they finally form the shape of a ring.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These beads are arranged in the following order; 1 bead of Oyadama=&gt;7 beads of Omodama=&gt;1 bead of Shitendama=&gt;14 beads of Omodama=&gt;1 bead of Shitendama=&gt;33 beads of Omodama=&gt;1 bead of Oyadama=&gt;33 beads of Omodama=&gt;1 bead of Shitendama=&gt;14 beads of Omodama=&gt;1 bead of Shitendama=&gt;7 beads of Omodama, and they finally form the shape of a ring.</e>
<cmt>→1 bead of Shitendamaを補足、表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="83">
<j>四天玉に近い側の親珠に付く房の結び目にのみ、浄名が一珠付く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One bead of Jomyodama is attached only to the knot of tassel that is attached to Oyadama situated on the side of Shitendama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One bead of Jomyodama is attached only to the knot of a tassel that is attached to Oyadama situated on the side of Shitendama.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One bead of Jomyo is attached only to the knot of a tassel that is attached to Oyadama situated on the side of Shitendama.</e>
<cmt>既出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="84">
<j>2つの親珠には、房が2本ずつ付く（計4本）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">2 tassels are attached to each of 2 Oyadama (4 tassels in total).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">2 tassels are attached to each of 2 Oyadama (4 tassels in total).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2 tassels are attached to each of 2 Oyadama (4 tassels in total).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>房の形は、いろいろな形が用いられる （菊房や利休房〈蹴鞠房〉を用いる場合が多い)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various shapes are used for tassels (kiku tassel and Rikyu tassel (kemari tassel) are often used).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various shapes are used for tassels (kiku tassel and Rikyu tassel (kemari tassel) are often used).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various shapes are used for tassels (kiku tassel and Rikyu tassel (kemari tassel) are often used).</e>
<cmt>「蹴鞠房」は「手毬房」(temari ball tassel)を指すと思われますが、そのまま訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="86">
<j>各房に弟子珠が5珠と「つゆ」が1珠付く（弟子珠・計20珠、つゆ・計4珠。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">5 beads of Deshidama and 1 bead of &quot;Tsuyudama&quot; are attached to each tassel (Deshidama : 20 beads in total, Tsuyudama : 4 beads in total).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">5 beads of Deshidama and 1 bead of &quot;Tsuyudama&quot; are attached to each tassel (Deshidama : 20 beads in total, Tsuyudama : 4 beads in total).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">5 beads of Deshidama and 1 bead of &apos;Tsuyu&apos; are attached to each tassel (Deshidama: 20 beads in total, Tsuyu: 4 beads in total).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変え、既出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="87">
<j>女性用の八寸の真言宗用の本連は、八宗用と呼ばれて販売されていて、宗派を問わず用いる事ができるとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Formal juzu of Shingon sect for females, of which length is 8 suns(Japanese measurement unit, approx. 24.24 cm), is called juzu for eight sects and is on sale as the one that is usable irrespective of sects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Formal juzu of the Shingon sect for females, for which the length is 8 suns(Japanese measurement unit, approx. 24.24 cm), are called juzu for eight sects and are on sale as one whicht is usable irrespective of sect.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Formal juzu of the Shingon sect for females, for which the length is approximately 24 cm, are called juzu for Hasshu sect (eight sects) and are on sale as one which is usable irrespective of sect.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="88">
<j>真言宗の僧侶が用いる数珠の仕様の一例を挙げれば、108珠・貫線を赤色・房を白色にする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An example in the design of juzu used by monks of Shingon sect is the one which is composed of 108 beads, red kansen and white tassels.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An example in the design of juzu used by monks of the Shingon sect is the one which is composed of 108 beads, red kansen and white tassels.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An example in the design of juzu used by monks of the Shingon sect is the one which is composed of 108 beads, red kansen (string to connect beads) and white tassels.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>貫線を赤色にする理由については、さまざまな説があり、定説はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the reason why kansen is colored red, there are many theses but no established thesis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the reason why kansen is colored red, there are many theses but no established thesis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the reason why kansen is colored red, there are many theses but no established thesis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>数珠には命（魂）が宿っているものと見なし、貫線を血管、血液に見立てている説などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One thesis asserts that kansen represents a blood vessel and/or blood since a life (a soul) dwells in juzu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One thesis asserts that kansen represents a blood vessel and/or blood since a life (a soul) dwells in juzu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One thesis asserts that kansen represents a blood vessel and/or blood since a life (a soul) dwells in juzu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>数珠の仕様は真言宗では事相（真言密教の儀礼・作法）の分野に入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Shigon sect, designs of juzu belong to the category of phenomenon (courtesy and/or manners).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Shigon sect, designs of juzu belong to the category of phenomenon (courtesy and/or manners).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Shingon sect, designs of juzu belong to the category of phenomenon (courtesy and/or manners of Shingon Esoteric Buddhism).</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>僧侶用の数珠（108珠で貫線が赤色・房を白色）を在家（壇信徒）が使っても特に差し支えはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no problem for lay believers (Buddhist supporters) to use juzu for monks (108 beads, red kansen, white tassels).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no problem for lay believers (Buddhist supporters) to use juzu for monks (108 beads, red kansen, white tassels).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no problem for lay believers (Buddhist supporters) to use juzu for monks (108 beads, red kansen, white tassels).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="93">
<j>五大力念珠（ごだいりきねんじゅ） 醍醐山伝法学院長・服部如実が感得して作らせた念珠。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Godairiki Nenju - This is Nenju which Nyojitsu HOTTORI, the president of Daigosan Denpo Academy, ordered to produce when his hope was achieved through devotion to Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>「感得」は広辞苑の記載を英訳しております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Godairiki Nenju - This is Nenju which Nyojitsu HOTTORI, the president of the Daigosan Denpo Academy, ordered to be produced when his hope was achieved through devotion to Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Godairiki nenju - This is nenju which Nyojitsu HOTTORI, the president of the Daigosan Denpo Gakuin (Denpo (the teachings of Buddhism) Academy on Mt. Daigo), ordered to be produced when his hope was achieved through devotion to Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>真言宗108珠の念珠であるが、2種類の材質の珠を用い、房を5色の紐（ひも）にしているが特徴。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it is Nenju of Shingon sect which is composed of 108 beads, its characteristics are the use of beads made from two kinds of materials as well as tassels composed of strings of five different colors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is Nenju of the Shingon sect, which is composed of 108 beads, its characteristics are the use of beads made from two kinds of materials, as well as tassels composed of strings of five different colors.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is nenju of the Shingon sect, which is composed of 108 beads, its characteristics are the use of beads made from two kinds of materials, as well as tassels composed of strings of five different colors.</e>
<cmt>半角スペースにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>醍醐寺において授与品として販売されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is on sale at Daigo-ji temple as a prize for awarding.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is on sale at Daigo-ji temple as a prize for awarding.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is on sale at Daigo-ji Temple as a prize for awarding.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>浄土宗・時宗用</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jodo sect ・ Ji sect</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jodo sect ・ Ji sect</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juzu for Jodo Sect and Ji Sect</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="96">
<j>浄土宗・時宗用の数珠は、二つの数珠を交差させたような独特の形。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Juzu of Jodo sect ・ Ji sect has a unique shape which looks like the one that crossed two juzu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Juzu of Jodo sect ・ Ji sect has a unique shape which looks like one that has mixed the two juzu.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juzu for Jodo Sect and Ji Sect has a unique shape which looks like one that has mixed the two juzu.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>男性用と女性用とで、主珠などの数に違いがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There exists some differences, such as the number of Omodama, between juzu for males and that for females.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There exist some differences, such as the number of Omodama, between juzu for males and for females.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There exist some differences, such as the number of Omodama, between juzu for males and for females.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="98">
<j>二つの輪には、それぞれ親珠があるが、房を直接親玉に付けない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oyadama is attached to each of 2 rings but tassels are not directly attached to Oyadama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oyadama is attached to each of 2 rings but tassels are not directly attached to Oyadama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oyadama is attached to each of 2 rings but tassels are not directly attached to Oyadama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="99">
<j>二つの輪のうち、片方にのみ「副珠」と呼ばれる小粒の珠が、主珠と交互に入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A small bead called &quot;Fukudama&quot; is attached to one of two rings alternately with Omodama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A small bead called &quot;Fukudama&quot; is attached to one of two rings alternately with Omodama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A small bead called &apos;Fukudama&apos; is attached to one of two rings alternately with Omodama.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="100">
<j>房は、副珠がある方の輪に金属製の二連の丸環を付け、その環に2房付けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A metal double-ring is attached to the ring to which Fukudama is attached and 2 tassels are attached to it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A metal double-ring is attached to the ring to which Fukudama is attached and 2 tassels are attached to it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A metal double-ring is attached to the ring to which Fukudama is attached and 2 tassels are attached to the ring.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>房の形は、菊房や利休房（手毬房）が主に用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the shape of tassels, kiku tassel and Rikyu tassel (temari tassel) are mainly used).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the shape of tassels, kiku tassel and Rikyu tassel (temari tassel) are mainly used).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the shape of tassels, kiku tassel and Rikyu tassel (temari ball tassel) are mainly used.</e>
<cmt>かっこをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="102">
<j>房の結び目に浄名が1珠付く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1 bead of Jomyodama is attached to the knot of tassel.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1 bead of Jomyodama is attached to the knot of the tassel.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1 bead of Jomyo is attached to the knot of the tassel.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="103">
<j>房には弟子珠が付く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Deshidama is attached to tassels.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Deshidama is attached to tassels.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Deshidama is attached to tassels.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>片側は丸珠が6珠、もう片方は、平珠が10珠付く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">6 beads of Marudama are attached to the one tassel and 10 beads of Hiradama are attached to the other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">6 beads of Marudama are attached to the one tassel and 10 beads of Hiradama are attached to the other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">6 beads of Marudama are attached to the one tassel and 10 beads of Hiradama are attached to the other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>弟子珠の先に「つゆ」が一つずつ付く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1 bead of &quot;Tsuyudama&quot; is attached to the tip of each Deshidama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1 bead of &quot;Tsuyudama&quot; is attached to the tip of each Deshidama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1 bead of &apos;Tsuyu&apos; is attached to the tip of each Deshidama.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="106">
<j>日課念珠とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Nikka(daily) nenju.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called Nikka(daily) nenju.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called Nikka (daily) nenju.</e>
<cmt>スペースを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="107">
<j>浄土宗では、本式念珠を用いるのが好ましいとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Jodo sect, it is believed to be desirable to use formal Nenju.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Jodo sect, it is believed to be desirable to use formal Nenju.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Jodo Sect, it is believed to be desirable to use formal Nenju.</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>この他にも、携帯用の36珠の物や百万遍念珠と呼ばれる大念珠も用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than the above, portable juzu that is composed of of 36 beads or dai (big)-nenju called Hyakumanben-nenju are also used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than the above, a portable juzu that is composed of of 36 beads or dai (big)-nenju called Hyakumanben-nenju are also used.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than the above, a portable juzu that is composed of 36 beads or dai (big)-nenju called Hyakumanben-nenju are also used.</e>
<cmt>不要なofをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="109">
<j>男性用は、三万浄土（三万繰）と呼ばれ、片方の輪の主珠が27珠、もう片方は、主珠20珠に副珠21珠が交互に入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Juzu for males is called sanmanjodo (sanman-guri) of which one ring is composed of 27 beads of Omodama and the other is composed of 20 beads of Omodama and 21 beads of Fukudama which are allocated alternately.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Juzu for males is called sanmanjodo (sanman-guri) of which one ring is composed of 27 beads of Omodama and the other is composed of 20 beads of Omodama and 21 beads of Fukudama which are allocated alternately.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juzu for males is called Sanman jodo (literally, thirty thousands of pure land, or Sanman-guri (thirty thousands of telling)) of which one ring is composed of 27 beads of Omodama and the other is composed of 20 beads of Omodama and 21 beads of Fukudama which are allocated alternately.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>念仏を唱える時繰り、副珠以外のすべての珠を使って繰ると27×20×6×10＝32,400遍唱えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is used for counting while reciting Buddhist invocation, and it is possible to count as many as 32,400 times (27*20*6*10) by using all beads other than Fukudama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is used for counting while reciting Buddhist invocation, and it is possible to count as many as 32,400 times (27*20*6*10) by using all beads other than Fukudama.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is used for telling the juzu while reciting Buddhist invocation, and it is possible to recite 32,400 times (27 times 20 times 6 times10 makes 32,400) by telling the juzu with all beads other than Fukudama.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>そこからこの名がつく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above is the origin of the name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above is the origin of the name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The above is the origin of the name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="112">
<j>女性用は八寸浄土（六万繰）と呼ばれ、片方の輪が主珠40珠、もう片方は、主珠27珠･副珠28珠からできている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Juzu for females is called hassun jodo (rokuman-guri) of which one ring is composed of 40 beads of Omodama and the other is composed of 27 beads of Omodama and 28 beads of Fukudama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Juzu for females is called hassun jodo (rokuman-guri) of which one ring is composed of 40 beads of Omodama and the other is composed of 27 beads of Omodama and 28 beads of Fukudama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juzu for females is called Hassun jodo (literally, 24 cm of pure land, or Rokuman-guri (sixty thousands of telling)) of which one ring is composed of 40 beads of Omodama and the other is composed of 27 beads of Omodama and 28 beads of Fukudama.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>弟子珠の数は三万浄土と同じ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of Deshidama is same with that of sanmanjodo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of Deshidama is the same as that of sanmanjodo.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of Deshidama is the same as that of Sanman jodo.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>つまり副珠以外のすべての珠を使って繰ると、男性用の倍40×27×6×10＝64,800遍唱えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it is possible to count as many as 64,800 times (40*27*6*10), twice the one for male, by using all beads other than Fukudama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it is possible to count as many as 64,800 times (40*27*6*10), twice the number for males, by using all beads other than Fukudama.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it is possible to recite 64,800 times (40 times 27 times 6 times 10 makes 64,800), twice the number for males, by telling the juzu with all beads other than Fukudama.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>浄土真宗用</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jodo Shinshu sect</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jodo Shinshu sect</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juzu for Jodo Shinshu Sect</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="115">
<j>浄土真宗では、念珠を繰りながら念仏を唱える事が無い為、珠の数は関係無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Jodo Shinshu, there is no practice to count the frequency of Buddhist invocation by using Nenju and therefore, no rule exists concerning the number of beads.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Jodo Shinshu, there is no practice to count the frequency of Buddhist invocation by using Nenju and therefore, no rule exists concerning the number of beads.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Jodo Shinshu Sect, there is no practice to telling the nenju while reciting Buddhist invocation and therefore, no rule exists concerning the number of beads.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>珠の材質に関しても制限はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No rule exists concerning the materials of beads either.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No rule exists concerning the materials of beads either.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No rule exists concerning the materials of beads either.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>形状には拘らないが、合掌礼拝の際に用いる法具として大切にする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The form of Nenju doesn&apos;t matter but it is highly esteemed as a ritual implement to be used while putting hands flat together in prayer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The form of Nenju does not matter, but it is highly esteemed as a ritual implement to be used while putting hands flat together in prayer.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The form of the nenju does not matter, but it is highly esteemed as a ritual implement to be used while putting hands flat together in prayer.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="118">
<j>男性門徒の場合：片手念珠の紐房を用いる事が好ましいとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In case of male believers : It is believed to be desirable to use himo (code) tassel of one-hand Nenju.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of male believers : It is believed to be desirable to use a himo (code) tassel of one-handed Nenju.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of male believers : It is believed to be desirable to use a himo (code) tassel of one-handed nenju.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>主珠の数に決まりは無く、大きさで決められ18～27珠の念珠が用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As there is no rule on the number of Omodama, the number is decided depending on the size of beads and Nenju that is composed of 18-27 beads is generally used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As there is no rule on the number of Omodama, the number is decided depending on the size of beads, and Nenju that is composed of 18-27 beads are generally used.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As there is no rule on the number of Omodama, the number is decided depending on the size of beads, and the nenju that is composed of 18 to 27 beads are generally used.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="120">
<j>浄土真宗本願寺派（お西）の女性門徒：女性も、本連の念珠を用いない事を勧められる場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Female believers of Hongan-ji temple school of the Jodo Shinshu Sect (O-nishi(Nishi Hongan-ji Temple)) : Female believers are often recommended not to use Honren Nenju.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Female believers of the Hongan-ji temple school of the Jodo Shinshu Sect (O-nishi(Nishi Hongan-ji Temple)) : Female believers are often recommended not to use Honren Nenju.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Female believers of the Hongan-ji School of the Jodo Shinshu Sect (O-nishi (Nishi Hongan-ji Temple)): Female believers are often recommended not to use Honren Nenju.</e>
<cmt>前出にあわせて表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>なお玉の数は、女性用片手念珠の場合36珠などだが、やはり数に決まりは無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although one-hand Nenju for female is usually composed of 36 beads, there is no particular rule on the number of beads.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although a one-handed Nenju for females is usually composed of 36 beads, there is no particular rule on the number of beads.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although a one-handed nenju for females is usually composed of 36 beads, there is no particular rule on the number of beads.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>女性用片手念珠は、切房・頭無しの撚房（新松房）・頭付撚房が主に用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For one-hand Nenju for female, kiri tassel, kashiranashi yori tassel (shinmatsu tassel) and kashiratsuki yori tassel are mainly used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For one-hand Nenju for females, kiri tassel, kashiranashi yori tassel (shinmatsu tassel) and kashiratsuki yori tassel are mainly used.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For one-hand nenju for females, kiri tassel, kashiranashi yori tassel (twisted tassel, or shinmatsu tassel (new pine tassel) and kashiratsuki yori tassel (twisted tassels with head) are mainly used.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="123">
<j>真宗大谷派（お東）の女性門徒：お西同様に、片手念珠で構わない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Female believers of Otani school of the Jodo Shinshu Sect (O-higashi(Higashi Hongan-ji Temple)): Likewise the case of O-nishi, one-hand Nenju can be used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Female believers of the Otani school of the Jodo Shinshu Sect (O-higashi(Higashi Hongan-ji Temple)): Likewise the case of O-nishi, one-hand Nenju can be used.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Female believers of the Otani School of the Jodo Shinshu Sect (O-higashi (Higashi Hongan-ji Temple): Likewise the case of O-nishi, one-hand nenju can be used.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>房は、切房や新松房が主に用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiri tassel and shinmatsu tassel are mainly used for tassels.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiri tassel and shinmatsu tassel are mainly used for tassels.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiri tassel and shinmatsu tassel are mainly used for tassels.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>しかし女性が、一般に八寸門徒と呼ばれる本連念珠を用いても問題は無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Notwithstanding the above, there is no problem for females to use Honren Nenju which is generally called hassun monto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Notwithstanding the above, there is no problem for females to use Honren Nenju which is generally called hassun monto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Notwithstanding the above, there is no problem for females to use Honren nenju which is generally called hassun monto (literally, 24 cm for followers).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>八寸門徒の形は、主珠・親珠の数、四天珠の配置は真言宗の数珠と同じ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shape, number of Omodama and Oyadama, allocation of Shitendama is same with the juzu of Shingon Sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shape, number of Omodama and Oyadama, allocation of Shitendama is the same as the juzu of Shingon Sect.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In hassun monto, number of Omodama and Oyadama, allocation of Shitendama are the same as the juzu of Shingon Sect.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>房に特徴があり、数取りが出来ない様に蓮如上人が考案した「蓮如結び」と呼ばれる独特な結び方がしてある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tassels have have a distinctive feature because they are knotted in a unique manner, called &quot;rennyo-musubi&quot; devised by Rennyo Shonin, so that they cannot be used for counting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tassels have have a distinctive feature because they are knotted in a unique manner, called &quot;rennyo-musubi&quot; devised by Rennyo Shonin, so that they cannot be used for counting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tassels have a distinctive feature because they are knotted in a unique manner, called &apos;rennyo-musubi&apos; devised by Rennyo Shonin, so that they cannot be used for counting.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>四天珠がある側の親珠に付く房は、浄名が一つ、弟子珠は親珠から5珠目ずつの所で結ばれその先に5珠ずつ付く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One bead of Jomyo is attached to the tassel attached to Oyadama of Shitendama side and 5 beads of Deshidama are attached to the tip of each tassel knotted at the position of 5th bead from Oyadama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One bead of Jomyo is attached to the tassel attached to Oyadama of the Shitendama side and 5 beads of Deshidama are attached to the tip of each tassel knotted at the position of the 5th bead from Oyadama.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One bead of Jomyo is attached to the tassel attached to Oyadama of the Shitendama side and 5 beads of Deshidama are attached to the tip of each tassel knotted at the position of the 5th bead from Oyadama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>弟子珠の先には、それぞれ「つゆ」が一つ付く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One bead of Tsuyudama is attached to the tip of each Deshidama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One bead of Tsuyudama is attached to the tip of each Deshidama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One bead of &apos;Tsuyu&apos; is attached to the tip of each Deshidama.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションをつけました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>つまり弟子珠をX型に上に詰めて動かないようしてある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other word, Deshidama is packed upward in X shape so that they are fixed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, Deshidama is packed upwards in an X shape so that they are fixed.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, Deshidama is packed upwards in an X shape so that they are fixed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>反対側の親玉に付く房は、結び目（蓮如結び）を付ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A knot is made on the tassel attached to Oyadama of the opposite side (rennyo-musubi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A knot is made on the tassel attached to Oyadama on the opposite side (rennyo-musubi).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A knot (rennyo-musubi) is made on the tassel attached to Oyadama on the opposite side.</e>
<cmt>位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>その先には、弟子珠・「つゆ」を入れずに房を付ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tassel is attached without attaching Deshidama and Tsuyudama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tassel is attached without attaching Deshidama and Tsuyudama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tassel is attached without attaching Deshidama and &apos;Tsuyu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションをつけ前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>房の形は、頭付房をつける場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the shape of tassels, Kashiratsuku tassel is mainly used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the shape of tassels, Kashiratsuku tassel is mainly used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the shape of tassels, kashiratsuki tassel is mainly used.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="134">
<j>本連念珠を持つ時の持ち方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The way of holding Honren Nenju</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The way of holding Honren Nenju</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Way of Holding Honren Nenju</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="135">
<j>大谷派の場合は、二重にして2つの親珠を親指の所で挟み、4つの房を左側に垂らす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In case of Otani school, it should be used in the form of double ring with 2 beads of Oyadama fixed at a thumb and 4 tassels hung down on the left side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of the Otani school, it should be used in the form of a double ring with 2 beads of Oyadama fixed at a thumb and 4 tassels hung down on the left side.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of the Otani School, it should be used in the form of a double ring with 2 beads of Oyadama fixed at a thumb and 4 tassels hung down on the left side.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>その時、弟子珠がある方の親珠を指先側に、蓮如結びがある方の親玉を手前側にして手に掛ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It should be hung on a hand with Oyadama of Deshidama side situated at fingertip side and Oyadama of rennyo-musubi side situated at body side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It should be hung on a hand with Oyadama of the Deshidama side situated at the fingertip side and Oyadama of the rennyo-musubi side situated at the body side.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It should be hung on a hand with Oyadama of the Deshidama side situated at the fingertip side and Oyadama of the rennyo-musubi side situated at the body side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="137">
<j>本願寺派の場合は、二重にして房を下に垂らす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In case of Hongan-ji temple school, it should be used in the form of double ring and the tassels should be hung down.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of Hongan-ji temple school, it should be used in the form of a double ring and the tassels should be hung down.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of Hongan-ji School, it should be used in the form of a double ring and the tassels should be hung down.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="138">
<j>なお男性用サイズの尺二寸以上の大型で、長房の本連念珠も見かけるが、本来は僧侶用の装束念珠である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although large-sized Honren Nenju for males, whose length is over 2 sun and which has nagafusa(long tassel), is seen, it is basically shozoku nenju for monks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although large-sized Honren Nenju for males, with a length of over 2 sun and which have a nagafusa(long tassel), are seen, it is basically shozoku nenju for monks.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although large-sized Honren nenju for males, with a length of over 38 cm and which have a nagafusa (long tassel), are seen, it is basically shozoku nenju (nenju for costume) for monks.</e>
<cmt>センチメートルに置き換えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>臨済宗用</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rinzai Sect</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rinzai Sect</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juzu for Rinzai Sect</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="139">
<j>臨済宗用の数珠は、主珠・親珠・四天珠の個数と配置は、天台宗用の数珠と同じ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for juzu of Rinzai Sect, the number and allocation of Omodama, Oyadama and Shitendama is same with that of Tendai Sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for juzu of the Rinzai Sect, the number and allocation of Omodama, Oyadama and Shitendama is the same as that of the Tendai Sect.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for juzu of the Rinzai Sect, the number and allocation of Omodama, Oyadama and Shitendama are the same as those of the Tendai Sect.</e>
<cmt>複数形にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>ただし、主珠の形は丸珠。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the shape of Omodama is marudama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the shape of Omodama is marudama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the shape of Omodama is marudama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="141">
<j>親珠の下に「ぼさ」が付く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Bosa&quot; is attached to Oyadama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Bosa&quot; is attached to Oyadama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bosa&apos; (literally, Bosatsu (Bodhisattava)) is attached to Oyadama.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変え補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>浄名・弟子珠は無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jomyodama and Deshidama is not attached.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jomyodama and Deshidama are not attached.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jomyo and Deshidama are not attached.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="143">
<j>房の形は紐房が多いが、切房なども用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While himo tassel is often used, kiri tassel is also used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While himo tassel is often used, kiri tassel is also used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While himo tassel is often used, kiri tassel is also used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>曹洞宗用</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soto Sect</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soto Sect</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juzu for Soto Sect</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="144">
<j>曹洞宗用の数珠は、主珠・親珠・四天珠の個数と配置は、真言宗の数珠と同じ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for juzu of Soto Sect, the number and allocation of Omodama, Oyadama and Shitendama is same with that of Shingon Sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for juzu of the Soto Sect, the number and allocation of Omodama, Oyadama and Shitendama is the same as that of the Shingon Sect.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for juzu of the Soto Sect, the number and allocation of Omodama, Oyadama and Shitendama are the same as those of the Shingon Sect.</e>
<cmt>複数形にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="145">
<j>房は、四天珠のある側の親玉にのみ付く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A tassel is attached only to Oyadama of Shitendama side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A tassel is attached only to Oyadama on the Shitendama side.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A tassel is attached only to Oyadama on the Shitendama side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>房の形は、臨済宗に准ずる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shape of tassel is almost similar to that of Rinzai Sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shape of the tassel is almost the same as that of the Rinzai Sect.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shape of the tassel is almost the same as that of the Rinzai Sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="147">
<j>房の付く親珠の方が、付かない親玉より若干大きい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oyadama to which a tassel is attached is slightly bigger than the one to which a tassel is not attached.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oyadama to which a tassel is attached is slightly bigger than one to which a tassel is not attached.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oyadama to which a tassel is attached is slightly bigger than one to which a tassel is not attached.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="148">
<j>「ぼさ」も房のある親珠のみ付く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Bosa&quot; also is attached to Oyadama to which a tassel is attached.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Bosa&quot; also is attached to Oyadama to which a tassel is attached.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bosa&apos; also is attached to Oyadama to which a tassel is attached.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="149">
<j>臨済宗の数珠に似ているが、曹洞宗の数珠は百八環金と呼ばれる金属製の環が通してある事が特徴。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it looks like juzu of Rinzai Sect, juzu of Soto Sect has a distinctive feature of using a metal ring called hyakuhachi-kankin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it looks like juzu of the Rinzai Sect, juzu of the Soto Sect have a distinctive feature of using a metal ring called hyakuhachi-kankin.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it looks like juzu for Rinzai Sect, juzu for Soto Sect have a distinctive feature of using a metal ring called hyakuhachi-kankin (literally, one hundred and eight golden ring).</e>
<cmt>表現を変え、補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>高級な数珠には、銀製の環を用いることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A ring made from silver is sometimes used for high-grade juzu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A ring made from silver is sometimes used for high-grade juzu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A silver ring is sometimes used for high-grade juzu.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="151">
<j>日蓮宗用</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nichiren Sect</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nichiren Sect</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juzu for Nichiren Sect</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="152">
<j>日蓮宗用の数珠は、主珠・親珠・四天珠の個数と配置は、真言宗の数珠と同じ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for juzu of Nichiren Sect, the number and allocation of Omodama, Oyadama and Shitendama is same with that of Shingon Sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for juzu of the Nichiren Sect, the number and allocation of Omodama, Oyadama and Shitendama is the same as that of the Shingon Sect.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for juzu for the Nichiren Sect, the number and allocation of Omodama, Oyadama and Shitendama are the same as those of the Shingon Sect.</e>
<cmt>複数形にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="153">
<j>房に特徴があり、親珠から出る房の形が対称では無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tassels have a distinctive feature since tassels attached to Oyadama are not symmetrical.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tassels have a distinctive feature since tassels attached to Oyadama are not symmetrical.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tassels have a distinctive feature since tassels attached to Oyadama are not symmetrical.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="154">
<j>四天珠がある側（右手の中指に掛ける側）の親珠〔浄名珠とも〕に付く房は2本で、浄名が一つ、弟子珠は親珠から5珠目ずつの所で結ばれその先に5珠ずつ付く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">2 tassels with a bead of Jomyodama are attached to Oyadama (also called Jomyodama) situated on Shitendama side (the side to be hung on the middle finger of right hand) and knots are made on each tassel at the position of 5th beads from Oyadama and 5 beads of Deshidama are attached on their tips.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">2 tassels with a bead of Jomyodama are attached to Oyadama (also called Jomyodama) situated on the Shitendama side (the side to be hung on the middle finger of the right hand) and knots are made on each tassel at the position of the 5th beads from Oyadama and 5 beads of Deshidama are attached on their tips.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2 tassels with a bead of Jomyo are attached to Oyadama (also called Jomyodama) situated on the Shitendama side (the side to be hung on the middle finger of the right hand) and knots are made on each tassel at the position of the 5th beads from Oyadama and 5 beads of Deshidama are attached on their tips.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>それぞれの弟子珠先にはに「つゆ」が付く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tsuyudama&quot; is attached to the tip of each Deshidama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Tsuyudama&quot; is attached to the tip of each Deshidama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuyu&apos; is attached to the tip of each Deshidama.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>四天珠が無い側（左手の中指に掛ける側）の親珠〔緒留とも〕に付く房は3本で、親珠の下に結び目がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">3 tassels are attached to Oyadama (also called odome) situated on the side where Shitendama doesn&apos;t exist (the side to be hung on the middle finger of left hand) and a knot is situated under Oyadama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">3 tassels are attached to Oyadama (also called odome) situated on the side where Shitendama doesn&apos;t exist (the side to be hung on the middle finger of the left hand) and a knot is situated under Oyadama.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">3 tassels are attached to Oyadama (also called odome) situated on the side where Shitendama doesn&apos;t exist (the side to be hung on the middle finger of the left hand) and a knot is situated under Oyadama.</e>
<cmt>半角アポストロフィにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>3本の内の2本は、弟子珠がそれぞれ5珠ずつ付き、「つゆ」もそれぞれに付く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Out of 3 tassels, 5 beads of Deshidama as well as &quot;Tsuyudama&quot;are attached to 2 tassels for each.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Out of 3 tassels, 5 beads of Deshidama as well as &quot;Tsuyudama&quot;are attached to 2 tassels for each.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Out of 3 tassels, 5 beads of Deshidama as well as &apos;Tsuyu&apos; are attached to 2 tassels for each.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>残りの一本は、『数取』と呼ばれ他の2本より長さが短く、弟子珠が10珠付く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Remaining 1 tassel called &quot;kazutori (counting)&quot; is shorter than other 2 tassels and 10 beads of Deshidama are attached to it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The remaining 1 tassel called &quot;kazutori (counting)&quot; is shorter than the other 2 tassels and 10 beads of Deshidama are attached to it.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The remaining 1 tassel called &quot;kazutori&quot; (counting) is shorter than the other 2 tassels and 10 beads of Deshidama are attached to it.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>『数取』には「つゆ」が付かない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tsuyudama&quot; is not attached to &quot;kazutori&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Tsuyudama&quot; is not attached to &quot;kazutori&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuyu&apos; is not attached to &quot;kazutori.&quot;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置などを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="160">
<j>日蓮宗の場合、在家信者も必ず本式念珠を用いる事になっている（略式念珠を用いない)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Nichiren Sect, even lay believers must use formal Nenju (informal Nenju must not be used).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Nichiren Sect, even lay believers must use formal Nenju (informal Nenju must not be used).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Nichiren Sect, even lay believers must use formal nenju (informal nenju is not be used).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="161">
<j>●上記は、主に在家用の数珠についてである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">● The avove explanations are basically made regarding juzu for lay believers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">● The above explanations are basically made regarding juzu for lay believers.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">- The above explanations are basically made regarding juzu for lay believers.</e>
<cmt>●を半角ハイフンにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>僧侶用は、装束などにより細かい規定があり、この限りではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for juzu for monks, the above may not be applicable since there are more detailed rules concerning costumes etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for juzu for monks, the above may not be applicable since there are more detailed rules concerning costumes etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for juzu for monks, the above may not be applicable since there are more detailed rules concerning costumes, and so on.</e>
<cmt>and so onを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="163">
<j>●宗旨・宗派によっても、数珠の仕様に細かな点で違いがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">● There are subtle differences in the designs of juzu depending on sects/schools.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">● There are subtle differences in the designs of juzu depending on sects/schools.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">- There are subtle differences in the designs of juzu depending on sects/schools.</e>
<cmt>●を半角ハイフンにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="164">
<j>●地方によっては、珠や房の色に決まりがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">● In some regions, there are restrictions on the color of beads and/or tassels.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">● In some regions, there are restrictions on the color of beads and/or tassels.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">- In some regions, there are restrictions on the color of beads and/or tassels.</e>
<cmt>●を半角ハイフンにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>（葬儀には、主珠（白又は透明）･房（白色）、法要には、主珠（色のある物）･房（色房）など）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(for funeral : Omodama (white or transparent / tassels (white), for Buddhist memorial service : Omodama (colored ones) / tassels (colored tassels) etc.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(for funeral : Omodama (white or transparent / tassels (white), for Buddhist memorial service : Omodama (colored ones) / tassels (colored tassels) etc.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(For funeral, Omodama (white or transparent), tassels (white); for Buddhist memorial service, Omodama (colored ones), tassels (colored tassels), and so on.)</e>
<cmt>and so onを使用し表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>数珠のオーダーメイド</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Custom-made juzu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Custom-made juzu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Custom-Made Juzu</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="166">
<j>念珠専門店などでは、オーダーメイドにて製作してくれる店もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Custom made juzu is available at some stores specialized in Nenju.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Custom-made juzu are available at some stores specialized in Nenju.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Custom-made juzu are available at some shops specialized in nenju.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>本水晶と紫水晶を用いてのグラデーションの数珠を作るなど、市販品にはない凝った物も入手できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Juzu of gradation such as the one made from crystal or amethyst that is not available on the market is also available.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Juzu of gradation, such as the ones made from crystal or amethyst, which is not available on the market, are also available.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juzu of gradation, such as the ones made from crystal or amethyst, which is not available on the market, are also available.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>数珠の修理について</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Repair of juzu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Repair of juzu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Repair of Juzu</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="168">
<j>数珠は、中糸が切れる前に修理に出す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Juzu should be repaired before its inner string is broken.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Juzu should be repaired before the inner string is broken.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juzu should be repaired before the inner string is broken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="169">
<j>房が痛んだ場合も、通常は交換できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When tassels are damaged, they can be replaced under normal conditions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When tassels are damaged, they can be replaced under normal conditions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When tassels are damaged, they can be replaced under normal conditions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="170">
<j>高価な数珠はもちろんの事、形見の数珠などは中糸を交換する事により永く使用することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By replacing inner string, juzu, especially the expensive one or the one of a keepsake, can be used for a long time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By replacing the inner string, juzu, especially the expensive one or the one of a keepsake, it can be used for a long time.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By replacing the inner string, juzu, especially the expensive one or the one of a keepsake, can be used for a long time.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="171">
<j>天竺菩提樹や星月菩提樹（無漂白な物）などは、時間とともに飴色に変わっていき味わいが増すとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the color of juzu made from Bo tree or seigetsu linden (unbleached one) will become amber over time and have depth to its color.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the color of juzu made from Bo tree or seigetsu linden (unbleached) will become amber over time and have depth to its color.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the color of juzu made from Bo tree or seigetsu linden (unbleached) will gradually change the color in amber over time and have depth to its color.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="172">
<j>修理は、念珠専門店、数珠修理に対応している仏壇店などで引受けてもらえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Repairs are undertaken by stores specialized in Nenju or Buddhist altars stores which deal with the repair of juzu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Repairs are undertaken by stores specializing in Nenju or Buddhist altar stores which deal with the repair of juzu.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Repairs are undertaken by shops specializing in nenju or Buddhist altar stores which deal with the repair of juzu.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="173">
<j>厄が切れるとの考えから、交換しない場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There exists some people who don&apos;t replace an inner string based on the thought that the cutting of string leads to the cutting of mishap.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There exist some people who do not replace an inner string based on the thought that the cutting of string leads to the cutting of mishap.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There exist some people who do not replace an inner string based on the thought that the cutting of string leads to the cutting of mishap.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="174">
<j>また、自然に切れた場合も、前記の理由により縁起が悪い訳では無いとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the same reason, it is believed that natural cutting of string doesn&apos;t necessarily mean bad luck.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the same reason, it is believed that the natural cutting of string doesn&apos;t necessarily mean bad luck.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the same reason, it is believed that the natural cutting of string doesn&apos;t necessarily mean bad luck.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="175">
<j>『南総里見八犬伝』に登場する8つの霊玉は、伏姫の持っていた水晶の数珠のうち8つの大玉が飛び散った物で、残りの100個の小玉は連ねられ、ゝ大法師が所持する数珠となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">8 reidama (spirit beads) which appear in Nanso Satomi hakken den are 8 big beads flown from crystal-made juzu that was possessed by Fusehime and remaining 100 small beads are connected and becomes juzu that ゝ daihoshi possesses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">8 reidama (spirit beads) which appear in Nanso Satomi hakken den are 8 big beads that flown from crystal-made juzu that was possessed by Fusehime and the remaining 100 small beads are connected and becomes juzu that ゝ daihoshi possesses.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">8 reidama (spirit beads) which appear in &quot;Nanso Satomi hakken den&quot; (The story of eight dog samurai and a princess of Satomi family in Nanso region) are 8 big beads that flown from crystal-made juzu that was possessed by Princess Fusehime and the remaining 100 small beads are connected and becomes juzu that Chudai hoshi possesses.</e>
<cmt>用語補足、およびChudai hoshiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="176">
<j>他宗教でも、例えばキリスト教ではロザリオのように、同様の物が使用されることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Similar things are used in other religions, such as Rosario in Christianity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similar things are used in other religions, such as Rosario in Christianity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similar things are used in other religions, such as Rosario in Christianity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="177">
<j>字の前後を入れ替えて「珠数」と書く場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sometimes juzu is written in Chinese character as &quot;珠数&quot; instead of &quot;数珠 by changing the order of each Chinese character.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sometimes juzu is written in Chinese characters as &quot;珠数&quot; instead of &quot;数珠 by changing the order of each Chinese character.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sometimes juzu is written in Chinese characters as &apos;珠数&apos; instead of &apos;数珠&apos; by changing the order of each Chinese character.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="178">
<j>「じゅず」という読みを「数珠」と書くのは、この熟語を作った中国の文法では動詞を先にする事になっているからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the grammar of Chinese language, which is the origin of a pair of this Chinese cgaracters, a verb should be placed before a noun and this is the reason why &quot;juzu&quot; is written as &quot;数珠&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the grammar of the Chinese language, which is the origin of a pair of these Chinese characters, a verb should be placed before a noun and this is the reason why &quot;juzu&quot; is written as &quot;数珠&quot;</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the grammar of the Chinese language, which is the origin of a pair of these Chinese characters, a verb should be placed before a noun and this is the reason why &apos;juzu&apos; is written as &apos;数珠.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="179">
<j>「珠を数える」を中国語では「数珠」と書く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Chinese, &quot;to count the number of beads&quot; is written as &quot;数珠&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Chinese, &quot;to count the number of beads&quot; is written as &quot;数珠&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Chinese, &apos;to count the number of beads&apos; is written as &apos;数珠.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ロリ(id:613), Suguri F(id:11127), Michey.M(id:906), 釣本直紀(id:85142), たね(id:10372), 草薙(id:23262), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Backflip(id:135197), Authority(id:10737), テオフィロ(id:18904), Revth(id:12179), Corwin(id:973), Taoka(id:106371), Pack372sd(id:191577), Gik-boz(id:21470), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>