<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>貞暁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jogyo (or Teigyo)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jogyo (or Teigyo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jogyo</e>
<cmt>タイトルなので補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>貞暁（じょうぎょう／ていぎょう、文治2年2月26日 (旧暦)（1186年3月18日） - 寛喜3年2月22日 (旧暦)（1231年3月27日） は平安時代末期から鎌倉時代初期にかけての僧侶。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jogyo (or Teigyo, March 18th, 1186-March 27th, 1231) was a monk living from the end of Heian period to the beginning of Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jogyo (or Teigyo, March 18th, 1186-March 27th, 1231) was a monk living from the end of the Heian Period to the beginning of the Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jogyo (also known as Teigyo, March 25, 1186 - April 3, 1231) was a monk living from the end of the Heian period to the beginning of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し、表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>源頼朝の三男（庶子）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the third son (child born out of wedlock) of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the third son (out of wedlock) of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the third son (out of wedlock) of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は伊達氏の祖と言われる常陸入道念西（藤原時長、伊達朝宗）の娘・大進局。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was Daishin no Tsubone, a daughter of Hitachi-nyudo (monk) Nensai (also called in two ways, FUJIWARA no Tokinaga and Tomomune DATE), the founder of Date family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was Daishin no Tsubone, a daughter of the Hitachi-nyudo monk Nensai (also called by the names FUJIWARA no Tokinaga and Tomomune DATE), the founder of the Date family.</e>
<cmt>Grammar. Parentheses removed for ease of reading.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was Daishin no Tsubone, a daughter of the Hitachi-nyudo monk Nensai (also called by the names FUJIWARA no Tokinaga and Tomomune DATE), the founder of the Date family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>通称を鎌倉法印といった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His by-name was Kamakura-Hoin (a highest-ranking priest).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was himself also known as Kamakura-Hoin (a high-ranking priest).</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was himself also known as Kamakura Hoin (the highest rank in the hierarchy of Buddhist priests).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>母・大進局は鎌倉幕府に出仕する侍女であったが、頼朝の寵愛を受け懐妊する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother, Daishin no Tsubone, was a lady&apos;s maid serving the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), who was favored by Yoritomo and became pregnant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother, Daishin no Tsubone, was a lady&apos;s maid serving the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), who was favored by Yoritomo and became pregnant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother, Daishin no Tsubone, was a lady&apos;s maid serving the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), who was favored by Yoritomo and became pregnant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし頼朝の正室・北条政子がこれに気づいたため、その怒りを畏れた頼朝によって遠ざけられ、家臣の長門景遠の宅にて男児を出産する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Masako HOJO, the lawful wife of Yoritomo, noticed her pregnancy, Daishin no Tsubone was avoided by Yoritomo who feared Masako&apos;s anger, and bore a baby boy at a residence of Kageto NAGATO (長門景遠), a retainer of Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>長門景遠の読みが確認できませんでした</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Masako HOJO, the lawful wife of Yoritomo, noticed her pregnancy, Daishin no Tsubone was kept at a distance by Yoritomo who feared Masako&apos;s anger, and she bore a baby boy at the residence of Kageto NAGATO (長門景遠), one of his retainers.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Masako HOJO, the lawful wife of Yoritomo, noticed her pregnancy, Daishin no Tsubone was kept at a distance by Yoritomo who feared Masako&apos;s anger, and she bore a baby boy at the residence of Kageto NAGATO, one of his retainers.</e>
<cmt>読みを確認し漢字をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>政子の嫉妬を恐れて出産の儀式は省略され、景遠は母子を匿った事を知った政子の勘気を蒙り、子を連れて逃げ深沢の辺りに隠居した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ceremony of birth was omitted for fear of Masako&apos;s envy, meanwhile, Kageto NAGATO retired in the vicinity of Fukazawa after running away with his children, because he had been fired by Masako who learned that he had harbored Daishin no Tsubone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The child&apos;s birth ceremony was not performed for fear of arousing Masako&apos;s envy, and Kageto NAGATO retired to the vicinity of Fukazawa after running away with his children, because he had been cut off by Masako after she discovered that he had harbored Daishin no Tsubone.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, changed for clarity, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The child&apos;s birth ceremony was not performed for fear of arousing Masako&apos;s envy, and Kageto retired to the vicinity of Fukazawa after running away with his children, because he had been cut off by Masako after she discovered that he had harbored Daishin no Tsubone.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その後も政子を恐れて乳母のなり手がないなど、人目を憚るようにして育てられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was in such a pitiful condition as no one accepted to become his menoto (a woman providing breast-feed to a highborn baby) for fear of Masako, therefore his mother raised him shunning the public eye.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was in such a pitiful condition as no one would agree to become his menoto (a woman who breast-fed a baby from a noble family) for fear of Masako, therefore his mother raised him away from the public eye.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was in such a pitiful condition as no one would agree to become his wet nurse for fear of Masako, therefore his mother raised him away from the public eye.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>建久3年（1192年）5月19日、7歳の時に出家のため上洛する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went to Kyoto to become a priest at the age of seven on May 19th, 1192.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He went to Kyoto to become a priest at the age of seven on May 19th, 1192.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He went to Kyoto to become a priest at the age of seven on July 7, 1192.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>頼朝は出発の夜、密かに息子の元を訪れ、刀を渡している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoritomo secretly visited his son at night of his departing day to pass a sword.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoritomo secretly visited his son on the evening he was due to depart in order to pass him a sword.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoritomo secretly visited his son on the evening he was due to depart in order to pass him a sword.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>仁和寺に入って法名を「能寛」と名乗り、更に修行を重ねた後、法名を貞暁と改め、高野山に登ってより一層俗界から遠ざかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He changed his Homyo (a name given to a person who entered the Buddhist priesthood) from Nokan, which he used soon after he became a priest at Ninna-ji Temple, to Jogyo (or Teigyo) after practicing asceticism further, keeping himself away from the world of everyday affairs by climbing Koya-san Mountain to confine himself for religious training..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He changed his Homyo (a name given to a person who enters the Buddhist priesthood) from Nokan, which he used soon after he became a priest at Ninna-ji Temple, to Jogyo (or Teigyo) after practicing asceticism further, keeping himself away from the world of everyday affairs by climbing Koya-san Mountain to confine himself for religious training.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He changed his Homyo (a name given to a person who enters the Buddhist priesthood) from &apos;Nokan,&apos; which he used soon after he became a priest at Ninna-ji Temple, to Jogyo (also referred as Teigyo) after practicing asceticism further, keeping himself away from the world of everyday affairs by climbing Mt. Koya to confine himself for religious training.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>これ以降、源氏一族が権力闘争の中で次々に命を落とす中で、世間と隔絶した中で一人修行に励み、人々の尊崇を集めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the members of the Minamoto clan were killed one after another amid a struggle of power, he devoted himself to the religious practice in the world completely isolated from the general world, as the result that he was respected by people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the members of the Minamoto clan were killed one after another amid a struggle for supremacy, he devoted himself to religious practice completely isolated from the general world, and as a result he earned respect from many people.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the members of the Minamoto clan were killed one after another amid a struggle for supremacy, he devoted himself to religious practice completely isolated from the general world, and as a result he earned respect from many people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>その晩年には遂に政子も貞暁に帰依し、彼に源氏一族の菩提を弔わせるべく援助・出資を行なった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Masako finally became a believer of Jogyo (or Teigyo), and asked him to pray to Buddha for the happiness of the dead in the Minamoto clan by providing him with aid and money.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Masako finally became one of Jogyo (or Teigyo)&apos;s believers, and asked him to pray to Buddha for the happiness of the dead in the Minamoto clan, providing him with aid and money.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Masako finally became one of Jogyo&apos;s believers, and asked him to pray to Buddha for the happiness of the dead in the Minamoto clan, providing him with aid and money.</e>
<cmt>補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>これを受けて貞暁は、高野山の経智坊に丈六堂という阿弥陀堂を建立、この中に安置した阿弥陀如来座像の胎内に父・頼朝の遺髪を納めて供養したほか、異母弟・三代将軍源実朝に対しても五輪塔を設営して追善を行なっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, establishing an Amida-do Hall (temple hall having an enshrined image of Amitabha) called Joroku-do in Kyochi-bo, Koya-san Mountain, Jogyo (or Teigyo) put the hair of his departed father Yoritomo into the sitting statue of Amitabha enshrined in the hall for the repose of his soul, and furthermore, he held a religious service for the repose of the soul of the 3rd Shogun MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, a half younger brother with the same father, by establishing gorinto (a gravestone composed of five pieces piled up one upon another).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, establishing an Amida-do Hall (temple hall having an enshrined image of Amitabha) called Joroku-do in Kyochi-bo, Koya-san Mountain, Jogyo (or Teigyo) put the hair of his departed father Yoritomo into the sitting statue of Amitabha which was enshrined in the hall for the repose of his soul, and furthermore, he held a religious service for the repose of the soul of the 3rd Shogun MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, a half younger brother with the same father, by erecting a gorinto (gravestone composed of five pieces set one upon another).</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, establishing an Amida-do Hall (temple hall having an enshrined image of Amitabha) called Joroku-do in Kyochi-bo, Mt. Koya, Jogyo put the hair of his departed father Yoritomo into the sitting statue of Amitabha which was enshrined in the hall for the repose of his soul, and furthermore, he held a religious service for the repose of the soul of the third Shogun MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, a half younger brother with the same father, by erecting a gorinto (gravestone composed of five pieces set one upon another).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>一説によると、実朝の死後その野心を政子に疑われ、四代将軍就任を打診されたが、片眼をえぐり出してこれを拒否したと伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a story that when he was sounded about his willingness to assume the post of the fourth shogun by Masako who had a suspicion that he had an evil intention for the succession after the death of MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, he proved his innocent by taking out one of his eyeballs and thoroughly rejected her offer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to one story, when Masako approached him about his ambition to become the fourth shogun, suspecting him of having evil intentions regarding the succession after the death of MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, he proved his innocence by taking out one of his eyeballs and thoroughly rejecting her offer.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to one story, when Masako approached him about his ambition to become the fourth shogun, suspecting him of having evil intentions regarding the succession after the death of Sanetomo, he proved his innocence by taking out one of his eyeballs and thoroughly rejecting her offer.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>政子は貞暁の潔さに落涙し、二度と彼を疑うことがなかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Masako, who shed tears for the honesty of Jogyo (or Teigyo), never suspected him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Masako, who shed tears at the display of honesty, never suspected him again.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Masako, who shed tears at the display of honesty, never suspected him again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>寛喜3年（1231年）、高野山にて46歳で死去（自害したという説もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died in Koya-san Mountain at the age of 46 in 1231, while there is also a story that he killed himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died on Koya-san Mountain at the age of 46 in 1231, one theory suggesting that he killed himself.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died on Mt. Koya at the age of 46 in 1231, one theory suggesting that he killed himself.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>これにより、頼朝の男系子孫は断絶した（女系子孫も3年後の竹御所死去により途絶える）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His death resulted in the extinction of the male line of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, as well as the death of Take no Gosho 3 years later the female line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His death resulted in the extinction of the male line of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, and with the death of Take no Gosho 3 years later the female line was also extinguished.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His death resulted in the extinction of the male line of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo (with the death of Take no Gosho three years later, the female line was also extinguished).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>なお、『』は貞暁と能寛を別人としているが、これは誤りである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Jogyo (or Teigyo) and Nokan are dealt as different people in &quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku&quot; (Lineage Sects of Noble and Humble), it is wrong.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Jogyo (or Teigyo) and Nokan are treated as different people in &quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku&quot; (Lineage Sects of Noble and Humble), this is mistaken.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, made less informal.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Jogyo and Nokan are treated as different people in &quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku&quot; (Bloodlines of Noble and Base), this is mistaken.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 味っ子(id:17086), Andee(id:20421), BAKU(id:55205), 小者(id:172526), きまま(id:183217), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>