<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>富士門流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fujimonryu (Fujimon school)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fujimonryu (Fujimon school)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fujimon School</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>富士門流（ふじもんりゅう）は、日蓮系の諸宗派のうち、日蓮の6人の高弟「六老僧」のひとり日興の法脈を継承する諸本山とその末寺に対する総称のひとつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fujimonryu is one of the generic names for numbers of honzan temples (head temples) and their branch temples in Nichiren sect, which succeed the dharma lineage of Nikko, who was one of 6 high-caliber disciples of Nichiren.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fujimonryu is one of the generic names for numbers of honzan temples (head temples) and their branch temples in Nichiren sect, which succeed the dharma lineage of Nikko, who was one of 6 high-caliber disciples of Nichiren.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fujimon School is one of the generic names for numbers of honzan temples (head temples) and their branch temples in Nichiren Sect, which succeed the dharma lineage of Nikko, who was one of 6 high-caliber disciples of Nichiren.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>中世-近世以来もちいられてきた古くからの総称としては、他に日興門流、大石寺派など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are also Nikkomonryu (Nikkomon school), Taisekijiha (Taiseki-ji Temple school), and so on, as the old generic names used in and from medieval period and early-modern period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are also Nikkomonryu (Nikkomon school), Taisekijiha (Taiseki-ji Temple school), and so on, as the old generic names used in and from the medieval period and the early-modern period.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are also Nikkomon School, Taisekiji School, and so on, as the old generic names used in and from the medieval period and the early-modern period.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>明治時代に単一の宗派を形成したこともあったが、その後分裂や日蓮宗との合同などをへて、現在、富士門流の主要本山8ヶ寺のうち、5ヶ寺は日蓮正宗をはじめいくつかの独立した宗派を形成、3ヶ寺は、組織上は日蓮宗に所属しつつ、教義面では、この門流の伝統の勝劣派・日蓮本仏論を維持している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They once formed a unified sect in the Meiji period, and after that, going through split and the uniting with the Nichiren sect, from 8 major honzan temples of Fujimonryu, 5 of them formed independent sect, starting with Nichirenshoshu sect, and 3 of them, belonging to the Nichiren sect as an organization, kept Nichiren Honbutsu Ron (a creed which regard Nichiren as the principal image) of Shoretsuha (Shoretsu school), which is a tradition in this monryu (lineage).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They once formed a unified sect in the Meiji period, and after that, going through splits and uniting with the Nichiren sect, from 8 major honzan temples of Fujimonryu, 5 of them formed an independent sect, starting with Nichirenshoshu sect, and 3 of them, belonging to the Nichiren sect as an organization, kept Nichiren Honbutsu Ron (a creed which regard Nichiren as the principal image) of Shoretsuha (Shoretsu school), which is a tradition in this monryu (lineage).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They once formed a unified sect in the Meiji period, and after that, going through splits and uniting with the Nichiren Sect, from 8 major honzan temples of Fujimon School, 5 of them formed an independent sect, starting with Nichiren Sho Sect, and 3 of them, belonging to the Nichiren Sect as an organization, kept Nichiren Honbutsu Ron (a creed which regard Nichiren as the principal image) of Shoretsu School, which is a tradition in this monryu (lineage).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>教義</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Creed</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Creed</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Creed</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>勝劣派、すなわち所依の経典法華経二十八品を前半の「迹門」、後半の「本門」に二分、本門に法華経の極意があるとする一派に属する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They belong to Shoretsu school, which divide their dependent sutra, twenty-eight scriptures of Lotus Sutra, into to two and call the first half as &apos;Shakumon&apos; and the second half as &apos;Honmon,&apos; and regard the master secrets of the Lotus Sutra to be included in Honmon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They belong to the Shoretsu school, which divides their dependent sutra, twenty-eight scriptures of Lotus Sutra, into two and call the first half &apos;Shakumon&apos; and the second half &apos;Honmon,&apos; and regard the master secrets of the Lotus Sutra to be included in Honmon.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They belong to the Shoretsu School, which divides their dependent sutra, twenty-eight chapters of Hokke-kyo Sutra (Lotus Sutra), into two and call the first half &apos;Shakumon&apos; and the second half &apos;Honmon,&apos; and regard the master secrets of the Hokke-kyo Sutra to be included in Honmon.</e>
<cmt>chapterを使用し、他のファイルに合わせて表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>（これに対し、二十八品全体を一体のものとして扱うべきとする一派が「一致派」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Against this, a school which regards the twenty-eight scriptures to be handled as unified sutra is called &apos;Icchiha,&apos; or Icchi school).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Against this, a school which regards the twenty-eight scriptures to be handled as unified sutra is called &apos;Icchiha,&apos; or Icchi school).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Against this, a school which regards the twenty-eight chapters to be handled as unified sutra is called &apos;Icchi School&apos;).</e>
<cmt>前出に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>日蓮を「久遠の本仏」とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They regard Nichiren as &apos;Kuon no Honbutsu&apos; (eternal principal image).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They regard Nichiren as &apos;Kuon no Honbutsu&apos; (eternal principal image).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They regard Nichiren as &apos;Kuon no Honbutsu&apos; (eternal principal image).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>富士門流の主要寺院と現在の所属宗派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main temples of Fujimonryu and their belonging sects</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main temples of Fujimonryu and their belonging sects</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Main Temples of Fujimon School and Their Belonging Sects</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>富士五山（静岡県内）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fuji Gozan (5 temples of Fujimonryu in Shizuoka Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fuji Gozan (5 temples of Fujimonryu in Shizuoka Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fuji Gozan (5 temples of Fujimon School in Shizuoka Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>大石寺（日蓮正宗）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taiseki-ji Temple (Nichirenshoshu sect)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taiseki-ji Temple (Nichirenshoshu sect)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taiseki-ji Temple (Nichiren Sho Sect)</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>重須本門寺（日蓮宗）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omosu Honmon-ji Temple (Nichiren sect)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omosu Honmon-ji Temple (Nichiren sect)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omosu Honmon-ji Temple (Nichiren Sect)</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>西山本門寺（単立）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nishiyama Honmon-ji Temple (independent)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nishiyama Honmon-ji Temple (independent)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nishiyama Honmon-ji Temple (independent)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>妙蓮寺 (富士宮市)（日蓮正宗）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myoren-ji Temple (Fujinomiya City) (Nichirenshoshu sect)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myoren-ji Temple (Fujinomiya City) (Nichirenshoshu sect)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myoren-ji Temple (Fujinomiya City) (Nichiren Sho Sect)</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>小泉久遠寺（日蓮宗）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koizumi Kuon-ji Temple (Nichiren sect)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koizumi Kuon-ji Temple (Nichiren sect)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koizumi Kuon-ji Temple (Nichiren Sect)</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="13">
<j>興門八本山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Komon Hachi Honzan (8 honzan temples succeeding the dharma lineage of Nikko)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Komon Hachi Honzan (8 honzan temples succeeding the dharma lineage of Nikko)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Komon Hachi Honzan (8 honzan temples succeeding the dharma lineage of Nikko)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="14">
<j>富士五山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fuji Gozan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fuji Gozan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fuji Gozan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="15">
<j>要法寺（京都府、 日蓮本宗）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yobo-ji Temple (Kyoto Prefecture, Nichirenhonshu sect)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yobo-ji Temple (Kyoto Prefecture, Nichirenhonshu sect)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yobo-ji Temple (Kyoto Prefecture, Nichiren Hon Sect)</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="16">
<j>保田妙本寺（千葉県、 単立）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hota Myohon-ji Temple (Chiba Prefecture, independent)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hota Myohon-ji Temple (Chiba Prefecture, independent)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hota Myohon-ji Temple (Chiba Prefecture, independent)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="17">
<j>伊豆実成寺（静岡県、 日蓮宗）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Izu Jitsujo-ji Temple (Shizuoka Prefecture, Nichiren sect)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Izu Jitsujo-ji Temple (Shizuoka Prefecture, Nichiren sect)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Izu Jitsujo-ji Temple (Shizuoka Prefecture, Nichiren Sect)</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>古くは富士門流・日興門流・大石寺派と称し、浄土真宗にみられるような強固な単一組織はつくらなかったが、人的交流、学問的交流を通じ、ゆるやかに結びついていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In old days they called themselves Fujimonryu, Nikkomonryu, and Taiseki-jiha, and even though they did not form strong unified organization like seen in Jodo Shinshu sect, they were connected loosely through personal and academic exchanges.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In old days they called themselves Fujimonryu, Nikkomonryu, and Taiseki-jiha, and even though they did not form a strong unified organization like that seen in the Jodo Shinshu sect, they were connected loosely through personal and academic exchanges.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In old days they called themselves Fujimon School, Nikkomon School, and Taiseki-ji School, and even though they did not form a strong unified organization like that seen in the Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism), they were connected loosely through personal and academic exchanges.</e>
<cmt>補足、表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>明治維新直後の廃仏毀釈の後、明治政府は仏教各派に対し一宗一管長制を打ち出し、1872年（明治5年）日蓮を宗祖とする諸門流は日蓮宗を形成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Haibutsu-kishaku (a movement to abolish Buddhism) which followed the Meiji Restoration, the Meiji government came out with policy of one leader for one religious sect against every Buddhist sect, and in 1872, number of schools which had Nichiren as the founder formed Nichiren sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Haibutsu-kishaku (a movement to abolish Buddhism) which followed the Meiji Restoration, the Meiji government came out with a policy of one leader for one religious sect against every Buddhist sect, and in 1872, a number of schools which had Nichiren as the founder formed the Nichiren sect.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Haibutsu-kishaku (a movement to abolish Buddhism) which followed the Meiji Restoration, the Meiji government came out with Isshu-Ikkancho system (a system in which each sect was allowed only one chief abbot) against every Buddhist sect, and in 1872, a number of schools which had Nichiren as the founder formed the Nichiren Sect.</e>
<cmt>マイページに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>この日蓮宗はまず、1874年（明治7年）教義の違いから一致派と勝劣派に分裂、富士門流は勝劣派に属した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, in 1874, this Nichiren sect was split into Icchiha and Shoretsuha, and Fujimonryu belonged to Shoretsuha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, in 1874, this Nichiren sect was split into Icchiha and Shoretsuha, and Fujimonryu belonged to Shoretsuha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, in 1874, this Nichiren Sect was split into Icchi School and Shoretsu School, and Fujimon School belonged to Shoretsu School.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>さらに、1876年（明治9年）日蓮宗勝劣派は教義や門流の違いにより解体、富士門流は興門八本山の本山、末寺からなる統一教団として本門宗を組織した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further in 1876, from the discrepancies of creed and monryu, Shoretsuha of Nichiren sect was dissolved, and Fujimonryu organized Honmon sect as unified religious community, which was formed by honzan temples and their branch temples of Komon Hachi Honzan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further in 1876, from the discrepancies of creed and monryu, Shoretsuha of Nichiren sect was dissolved, and Fujimonryu organized Honmon sect as a unified religious community, which was formed by honzan temples and their branch temples of Komon Hachi Honzan.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further in 1876, from the discrepancies of creed and monryu, Shoretsu School of Nichiren Sect was dissolved, and Fujimon School organized Honmon Sect as a unified religious community, which was formed by honzan temples and their branch temples of Komon Hachi Honzan.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>宗務院は静岡県富士宮市の重須本門寺におかれ、八本山より輪番制で管長法主を選出するなどの組織機構が整えられ、1899年（明治32年）には本門宗と改称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its shumuin (office for religious management) was put in Omosu Honmon-ji Temple and its organization systems, such as the selection of the head of the sect in rotations of Hachi Honzan, were arranged, and in 1899, it changed its name to Honmonshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its shumuin (office for religious management) were put in Omosu Honmon-ji Temple and its organizational systems, such as the selection of the head of the sect in rotations of Hachi Honzan, were arranged, and in 1899, it changed its name to Honmonshu.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its shumuin (office for religious management) were put in Omosu Honmon-ji Temple and its organizational systems, such as the selection of the head of the sect in rotations of Hachi Honzan, were arranged, and in 1899, it changed its name to Honmon Sect.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="23">
<j>しかし、1900年（明治33年）大石寺とその末寺87ヶ寺が日蓮宗富士派として分離、1912年（明治45年）6月に日蓮正宗と改称して現在に至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However in 1900, Taiseki-ji Temple and its eighty-seven branch temples separated as Nichiren sect Fujiha (Fuji School), and in 1912, changed its name to Nichirenshoshu and kept its form until present days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However in 1900, Taiseki-ji Temple and its eighty-seven branch temples separated as Nichiren sect Fujiha (Fuji School), and in 1912, changed its name to Nichirenshoshu and has kept its form until the present day.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However in 1900, Taiseki-ji Temple and its eighty-seven branch temples separated as Fuji School of Nichiren Sect, and in June 1912, changed its name to Nichiren Sho Sect and has kept its form until the present day.</e>
<cmt>6月を補足、表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="24">
<j>1941年、当局は宗祖を同じくする仏教諸派に組織を統合するよう圧力をかけ、それまで9派あった日蓮系の諸宗派は4派に統合された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1941, the authority pressured numbers of Buddhist schools with the same founder to be unified, and 9 schools of Nichiren sect were unified in to 4 schools.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1941, the authority pressured a number of Buddhist schools with the same founder to be unified, and 9 schools of the Nichiren sect were unified in to 4 schools.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1941, the authority pressured a number of Buddhist schools with the same founder to be unified, and 9 schools of the Nichiren Sect were unified in to 4 schools.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>富士門流においては、日蓮正宗がそのまま独立を保ったが、本門宗は、顕本法華宗、日蓮宗とともに「三派合同」を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for Fujimonryu, Nichirenshoshu sect kept its independence, but Honmon sect, along with Kenpon Hokke sect and Nichiren sect, carried out &apos;Sanpa Godo&apos; (3 jointed sects).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for Fujimonryu, Nichirenshoshu sect kept its independence, but Honmon sect, along with Kenpon Hokke sect and Nichiren sect, carried out &apos;Sanpa Godo&apos; (3 joined sects).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for Fujimon School, Nichiren Sho Sect kept its independence, but Honmon Sect, along with Kenpon Hokke Sect and Nichiren Sect, carried out &apos;Sanpa Godo&apos; (3 joined sects).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>1945年、終戦によって統合の強要はなくなったが、富士門流の七本山とその旧末寺は、単一の宗派として独立を回復することはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1945, by the end of the war, the demand for the unity disappeared, but 7 honzan temples and their former branch temples of Fujimonryu did not regained their independency as unified sect,</e>
<cmt>原文が途中で終わっています</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1945, by the end of the war, the demand for unity disappeared, but 7 honzan temples and their former branch temples of Fujimonryu did not regain their independence as a unified sect,</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1945, by the end of the war, the demand for unity disappeared, but 7 honzan temples and their former branch temples of Fujimon School did not regain their independence as a unified sect,</e>
<cmt>原文を修正し、表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="27">
<j>重須本門寺、小泉久遠寺、伊豆実成寺の三本山とその旧末寺、および西山本門寺の旧末寺全12ヶ寺は「合同」を維持。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Twelve temples, including 3 honzan temples, Omosu Honzan-ji Temple, Koizumi Kuon-ji Temple, and Izu Jitsujo-ji Temple, their former branch temples, and the former branch temples of Nishiyama Honmon-ji Temple, kept their &apos;Godo.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Twelve temples, including 3 honzan temples, Omosu Honzan-ji Temple, Koizumi Kuon-ji Temple, and Izu Jitsujo-ji Temple, their former branch temples, and the former branch temples of Nishiyama Honmon-ji Temple, kept their &apos;Godo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Twelve temples, including 3 honzan temples, Omosu Honzan-ji Temple, Koizumi Kuon-ji Temple, and Izu Jitsujo-ji Temple, their former branch temples, and the former branch temples of Nishiyama Honmon-ji Temple, kept their &apos;Godo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="28">
<j>要法寺とその末寺約50ヶ寺は、1950年、日蓮本宗として日蓮宗から独立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoho-ji Temple and about fifty branch temples belonging to it became independent from Nichiren sect as Nichirenhonshu sect in 1950.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoho-ji Temple and about fifty branch temples belonging to it became independent from Nichiren sect as Nichirenhonshu sect in 1950.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoho-ji Temple and about fifty branch temples belonging to it became independent from Nichiren Sect as Nichiren Hon Sect in 1950.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>旧末寺34ヶ寺は「合同」を維持して日蓮宗に残留。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thirty-four former branch temples kept &apos;Godo&apos; and remained in Nichiren sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thirty-four former branch temples kept &apos;Godo&apos; and remained in Nichiren sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thirty-four former branch temples kept &apos;Godo&apos; and remained in Nichiren Sect.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="30">
<j>妙蓮寺 (富士宮市)とその旧末寺6ヶ寺は、1950年12月、日蓮正宗に合流。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myoren-ji Temple (Fujinomiya City) and its former 6 branch temples joined Nichirenshoshu sect in December 1950.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myoren-ji Temple (Fujinomiya City) and its former 6 branch temples joined Nichirenshoshu sect in December 1950.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myoren-ji Temple (Fujinomiya City) and its former 6 branch temples joined Nichiren Sho Sect in December 1950.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>旧末寺1ヶ寺は「合同」を維持して日蓮宗に残留。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Former 1 branch temple kept &apos;Godo&apos; and remained in Nichiren sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Former 1 branch temple kept &apos;Godo&apos; and remained in Nichiren sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Former 1 branch temple kept &apos;Godo&apos; and remained in Nichiren Sect.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="32">
<j>西山本門寺は、1957年3月、本山のみ単独で日蓮正宗へ合流。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nishiyama Honmon-ji Temple joined Nichirenshoshu sect alone by honzan temple itself in March 1957.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nishiyama Honmon-ji Temple joined Nichirenshoshu sect alone by honzan temple itself in March 1957.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nishiyama Honmon-ji Temple joined Nichiren Sho Sect alone by honzan temple itself in March 1957.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>のち単立の宗教法人として独立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later became an independent religious corporation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later became an independent religious corporation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later became an independent religious corporation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="34">
<j>保田妙本寺とその旧末寺4ヶ寺は、1957年4月、日蓮正宗に合流。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hota Myohon-ji Temple and its former 4 branch temples joined Nichirenshoshu sect in April 1957.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hota Myohon-ji Temple and its former 4 branch temples joined Nichirenshoshu sect in April 1957.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hota Myohon-ji Temple and its former 4 branch temples joined Nichiren Sho Sect in April 1957.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>1993年、保田妙本寺は単立の宗教法人として独立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1993, Hota Myohon-ji Temple became an independent religious corporation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1993, Hota Myohon-ji Temple became an independent religious corporation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1993, Hota Myohon-ji Temple became an independent religious corporation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>旧末寺9ヶ寺は「合同」を維持して日蓮宗に残留。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Former 9 branch temples kept &apos;Godo&apos; and remained in Nichiren sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Former 9 branch temples kept &apos;Godo&apos; and remained in Nichiren sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Former 9 branch temples kept &apos;Godo&apos; and remained in Nichiren Sect.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="37">
<j>かつて本門宗の総本山で、宗務院がおかれていた重須本門寺は、日蓮宗の七大本山のひとつに列せられ、富士門流の他の本山や末寺とともに、一致派、本仏釈迦本仏論が主流の日蓮宗の内部で、日興門流独自の教義を維持している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omosu Honmon-ji Temple, which was former sohonzan (grand head temple) of Honmon sect with shumuin, is counted as one of the 7 grand honzan temples of Nichiren sect, and with other honzan temples and branch temples of Fujimonryu, keeps its original creed as Nikkomonryu inside the Nichiren sect, which has Icchiha and Shaka Honbutsu Ron (creed which regards Shaka as the principal image) as its mainstream.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omosu Honmon-ji Temple, which was former sohonzan (grand head temple) of Honmon sect with shumuin, is counted as one of the 7 grand honzan temples of Nichiren sect, and with other honzan temples and branch temples of Fujimonryu, keeps its original creed as Nikkomonryu inside the Nichiren sect, which has Icchiha and Shaka Honbutsu Ron (creed which regards Shaka as the principal image) as its mainstream.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omosu Honmon-ji Temple, which was former sohonzan (grand head temple) of Honmon Sect with shumuin, is counted as one of the 7 grand honzan temples of Nichiren Sect, and with other honzan temples and branch temples of Fujimon School, keeps its original creed as Nikkomon School inside the Nichiren Sect, which has Icchi School and Shaka Honbutsu Ron (creed which regards Shaka as the principal image) as its mainstream.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>合同を維持している富士門流寺院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fujimonryu Temples Keeping Godo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fujimonryu Temples Keeping Godo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fujimon School Temples Keeping Godo</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>重須本門寺とその旧末寺36ヶ寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omosu Honmon-ji Temple and its former thirty-six branch temples</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omosu Honmon-ji Temple and its former thirty-six branch temples</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omosu Honmon-ji Temple and its former thirty-six branch temples</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="38">
<j>小泉久遠寺とその旧末寺4ヶ寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koizumi Kuon-ji Temple and its former 4 branch temples</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koizumi Kuon-ji Temple and its former 4 branch temples</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koizumi Kuon-ji Temple and its former 4 branch temples</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="39">
<j>伊豆実成寺とその旧末寺4ヶ寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Izu Jitsujo-ji Temple and its former 4 branch temples</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Izu Jitsujo-ji Temple and its former 4 branch temples</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Izu Jitsujo-ji Temple and its former 4 branch temples</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="40">
<j>妙蓮寺 (富士宮市)の旧末寺1ヶ寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Former 1 branch temple of Myoren-ji Temple (Fujinomiya City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Former 1 branch temple of Myoren-ji Temple (Fujinomiya City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Former 1 branch temple of Myoren-ji Temple (Fujinomiya City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="41">
<j>保田妙本寺の旧末寺9ヶ寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Former 9 branch temples of Hota Myohon-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Former 9 branch temples of Hota Myohon-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Former 9 branch temples of Hota Myohon-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="42">
<j>京都要法寺の旧末寺34ヶ寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Former thirty-four branch temples of Kyoto Yoho-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Former thirty-four branch temples of Kyoto Yoho-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Former thirty-four branch temples of Kyoto Yoho-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="43">
<j>西山本門寺の旧末寺12ヶ寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Former twelve branch temples of Nishiyama Honmon-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Former twelve branch temples of Nishiyama Honmon-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Former twelve branch temples of Nishiyama Honmon-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 サンプ(id:25012), 尽誠通天(id:188583), Tetralemma(id:11903), Mait(id:73947), Clarin(id:60278), Dalaibaatur(id:16203), Mikomaid(id:56139), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>