<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>荼枳尼天</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dakiniten</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dakiniten</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dakiniten</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>荼枳尼天（だきにてん、荼吉尼天とも）は、仏教の神。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dakiniten (written as &quot;荼枳尼天&quot; or &quot;荼吉尼天&quot; in kanji) is a Buddhist deity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dakiniten (written as &quot;荼枳尼天&quot; or &quot;荼吉尼天&quot; in kanji) is a Buddhist deity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dakiniten (written as 荼枳尼天 or 荼吉尼天 in kanji characters) is a Buddhist goddess.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションをのぞき、用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「荼吉尼」は梵語のダーキニー（英字：Dakini）を音訳したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;Dakini (荼吉尼)&quot; is the transliteration of the Sanskrit term &quot;dākinī&quot; (spelled &quot;Dakini&quot; in English).</e>
<cmt>梵語がカタカナで表記されていますが、これは訳文中では使用できません。原語は下記より引用しました。http://www.newworldencyclopedia.org/entry/Dakini</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;Dakini (荼吉尼)&quot; is the transliteration of the Sanskrit term &quot;dākinī&quot; (spelled &quot;Dakini&quot; in English).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &apos;Dakini&apos; is the transliteration of the Sanskrit term dākinī (spelled Dakini in English).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>元はインドの女神であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dakiniten derives from a female deity that was believed in in India.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dakiniten derives from a female deity from India.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dakiniten derives from a goddess from India.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>元々は農業神であったが、後に性や愛欲を司る神とされ、さらには人肉、もしくは生きた人間の心臓を食らう夜叉神とされるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dakiniten was originally a deity of farming, but later came to be assumed to govern sexual desire and further later came to be assumed to be a female demon eating human flesh or alive human hearts.</e>
<cmt>「性や愛欲」：「性」と「愛欲」の区別がはっきりしません。今回の翻訳では、それぞれを区別せず、&quot;sexual desire&quot;として訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dakiniten was originally a deity of farming, but later came to be assumed to govern sexual desire and later came to be assumed to be a female demon eating human flesh or live human hearts.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dakiniten was originally a goddess of farming, but later came to be assumed to govern sexual desire and later came to be assumed to be a female fierce god eating human flesh or live human hearts.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また、ヒンドゥー教ではカーリーの眷属とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Hinduism, this deity is assumed to be a dependent of Kali (a Hindu deity).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Hinduism, this deity is assumed to be a dependent of Kali (a Hindu deity).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Hinduism, this goddess is assumed to be a dependent of Kali (a Hindu goddess).</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>この神が仏教に取り入れられ、大日如来が化身した大黒天によって調伏されて、死者の心臓であれば食べることを許可されたとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This deity was introduced into Buddhism, and it was supposed that she had been exorcised by Daikokuten (the Deity of Wealth), that is, the incarnation of Dainichi Nyorai (Cosmic Buddha), and then permitted to eat human hearts, if dead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This deity was introduced into Buddhism, and it was supposed that she had been exorcised by Daikokuten (the Deity of Wealth), that is, the incarnation of Dainichi Nyorai (Cosmic Buddha), and then permitted to eat human hearts, if dead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This goddess was introduced into Buddhism, and it was supposed that she had been exorcised by Daikokuten (the god of Wealth), that is, the incarnation of Dainichi Nyorai (Cosmic Buddha), and then permitted to eat human hearts, if dead.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>自由自在の通力を有し、六月前に人の死を知り、その人の心臓をとってこれを食べるといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She is said to have unrestricted supernatural power, know the death of a person six months ahead, and take and eat the person&apos;s heart.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She is said to have unrestricted supernatural powers, knows the death of a person six months ahead, and takes and eats the person&apos;s heart.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She is said to have unrestricted supernatural powers, knows the death of a person six months ahead, and takes and eats the person&apos;s heart.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>日本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Belief in Dakiniten in Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Belief in Dakiniten in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Belief in Dakiniten in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>真言密教では、胎蔵界の外金剛院・南方に配せられ、形像は小天狗の白狐にまたがる形をしているため、辰狐王菩薩（しんこおうぼさつ）とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the esoteric Shingon sect of Buddhism, Dakiniten is located in the southern part of Gekongoin (the most peripheral section of the Womb World) of the Womb World (one of the two worlds in esoteric Buddhism, representing Dainichi Nyorai&apos;s spirit of salvation having every possibility of generation as a womb, where a fetus grows, has), and this deity is depicted as a small tengu (mountain spirit (portrayed as winged and having a long nose)) sitting astride a white fox; therefore, this deity is also called &quot;Shinkoo Bosatsu&quot; (Fox King).</e>
<cmt>「小天狗の白狐にまたがる形をしている」：白狐にまたがった小天狗と解釈しました。左記訳文中の&quot;Dakiniten is located in the southern part of Gekongoin (the most peripheral section of the Womb World) of the Womb World (one of the two worlds in esoteric Buddhism, representing Dainichi Nyorai&apos;s spirit of salvation having every possibility of generation as a womb, where a fetus grows, has)&quot;については、「日本語の語句をローマ字で音訳する場合はその直後に簡単な訳注を併記する」との翻訳指示に従いましたが、&quot;Womb World&quot;という単語を重複記載することになり、読みづらくなっています。下記のようにした方が読みやすくなると思います。Dakiniten is located in the southern part of Gekongoin (the most peripheral section of the Womb World (one of the two worlds in esoteric Buddhism, representing Dainichi Nyorai&apos;s spirit of salvation having every possibility of generation as a womb where a fetus grows, has))</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the esoteric Shingon sect of Buddhism, Dakiniten is located in the southern part of Gekongoin (the most peripheral section of the Womb World) of the Womb World (one of the two worlds in esoteric Buddhism, representing Dainichi Nyorai&apos;s spirit of salvation having every possibility of generation as a womb, where a fetus grows), and this deity is depicted as a small tengu (mountain spirit (portrayed as winged and having a long nose)) sitting astride a white fox; therefore, this deity is also called &quot;Shinkoo Bosatsu&quot; (Fox King).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Shingon Esoteric Buddhism, Dakiniten is located in the southern part of Gekongoin (the most peripheral section of the Womb World) of the Womb World (one of the two worlds in Esoteric Buddhism, representing Dainichi Nyorai&apos;s spirit of salvation having every possibility of generation as a womb, where a fetus grows), and this goddess is depicted as a small tengu (mountain spirit (portrayed as winged and having a long nose)) sitting astride a white fox; therefore, she is also called Shinkoo Bosatsu (Fox King).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションをのぞき、用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>また天皇の即位灌頂儀礼においてダキニ天を祀っていたという記録も存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There exists a record showing that prays were offered for Dakiniten at an esoteric Buddhist ceremony that was performed on the occasion of an emperor&apos;s enthronement.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処即位灌頂儀礼→esoteric Buddhist ceremony that was performed on the occasion of an emperor&apos;s enthronement[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There exist records showing that prayers were offered for Dakiniten at an esoteric Buddhist ceremony performed on the occasion of an emperor&apos;s enthronement.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There exist records showing that prayers were offered for Dakiniten at an Esoteric Buddhism ceremony performed on the occasion of an emperor&apos;s enthronement.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>平清盛や後醍醐天皇などがダキニ天の修法を行っていたことでも知られ、『源平盛衰記』には平清盛はこの修法を途中で止めた旨が記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, several persons including TAIRA no Kiyomori and the Emperor Godaigo are known to have performed incantation to worship Dakiniten; however, &quot;Genpei Josuiki/Genpei Seisuiki&quot; (a war chronicle written in the Kamakura period) states that TAIRA no Kiyomori discontinued this incantation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, several persons including TAIRA no Kiyomori and Emperor Godaigo are known to have performed incantations to worship Dakiniten, however, &quot;Genpei Josuiki/Genpei Seisuiki&quot; (a war chronicle written in the Kamakura period) states that TAIRA no Kiyomori discontinued this incantation.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, several persons including TAIRA no Kiyomori and Emperor Godaigo were known to have performed a method of Dakiniten in esoteric Buddhism, however, &quot;Genpei Seisuiki&quot; (The Rise and Decline of the Minamoto and Taira clans) states that TAIRA no Kiyomori discontinued this method.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし、この尊天は祀るのが非常に難しく、一度祀ると自分の命と引きかえに最後までその信仰を受持することが必須とされ、もしその約束を破ると、その修法を止めた途端に没落する、あるいは災禍がもたらされるとも考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This deity is extraordinarily difficult to enshrine because it is supposed that any person is required, once enshrines this deity, to keep believing therein in exchange for his/her life until his/her last moment and also that should such a duty be neglected (in other words, should incantation to worship the deity be discontinued), any person will immediately become ruined or meet with disaster.</e>
<cmt>尊天→deity[この場合の訳。「尊天」は本来「とはすべての生命の生かし存在させる宇宙エネルギー」を意味するようですが、左記原文においては、荼枳尼天を言い換えているだけだと思われますので、&quot;deity&quot;で良いと思います。]「信仰を受持する」：「受持する」とは、「教えを受け、それをしっかり覚えておくこと」を意味しますが、この場合は「信仰」が目的語になっているので、「維持する」と読み替えるのが妥当と考えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This deity is extraordinarily difficult to enshrine because it is supposed that any person is required, once this deity is enshrined, to keep believing therein in exchange for his/her life until his/her last moment and also that should such a duty be neglected (in other words, should incantation to worship the deity be discontinued), such a person will immediately become ruined or meet with disaster.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This goddess is extraordinarily difficult to enshrine because it is supposed that any person is required, once this goddess is enshrined, to keep believing therein in exchange for his or her life until his or her last moment and also that should such a duty be neglected (in other words, should incantation to worship the deity be discontinued), such a person would immediately become ruined or meet with disaster.</e>
<cmt>用語、表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>したがって、これは外法として考えられ忌まれる信仰でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, the belief in Dakiniten was considered to be a non-Buddhist religion and tabooed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, Dakiniten was considered to be a non-Buddhist religion and belief in it tabooed.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, Dakiniten was considered to be a non-Buddhist religion and belief in it tabooed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>元々インドにおいてダーキニーはジャッカルにまたがるとされていたが、中国や日本に伝わった時（中国や日本にはジャッカルはいないため）代わりに狐を当てたともいわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some say that Dakini was supposed in India to sit astride a jackal but that a fox was substituted for a jackal in China and Japan, where this deity was introduced, (because no jackal exists therein).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some say that Dakini was supposed, in India, to sit astride a jackal but that a fox was substituted for the jackal in China and Japan, where this deity was introduced, (because jackals are not present in those conuntries).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dakini was originally supposed to sit astride a jackal in India but the fox was substituted for the jackal in introduction to China and Japan (because jackals were not present in those countries).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>すなわち、狐（夜干）に乗るダキニ天の像というのは、（大元のインドには存在せず）胎蔵曼荼羅や正当な密教経典・儀記には記されない姿であり、中世の日本などで生み出された姿・像である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, an image of Dakiniten riding a fox (corresponding to a present Japanese term &quot;kitsune (狐)&quot; and an ancient Japanese term &quot;yakan (夜干)&quot;), which has not existed in India, that is, the origin of Dakiniten, has not been depicted in mandalas of the Womb World or the orthodox scriptures or ritual manuals of esoteric Buddhism but was created in medieval Japan and the like.</e>
<cmt>「正当な」：文脈より、「正統な」の誤植であると判断し、&quot;orthodox&quot;と訳出しました。原文中で「狐」と「夜干」の2語がどのような意図で併記されているのかが不明です。古い時代の事実に言及しているからかもしれませんが、読者には意図が分かり難いのではないかと思いました。訳文では、&quot;(corresponding to a present Japanese term &quot;kitsune (狐)&quot; and an ancient Japanese term &quot;yakan (夜干)&quot;)&quot;と訳出しましたが、これがなくても十分に文意は伝わると思います。混乱を招くことを避けるために、削除しても良いのではないかと思います。ご検討ください。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, an image of Dakiniten riding a fox (corresponding to the present Japanese term &quot;kitsune (狐)&quot; and an ancient Japanese term &quot;yakan (夜干)&quot;), which has not existed in India, that is, the origin of Dakiniten, has not been depicted in mandalas of the Womb World or the orthodox scriptures or ritual manuals of esoteric Buddhism but was created in medieval Japan and the like.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, an image of Dakiniten riding a fox (which has not existed in India) has not been depicted in Taizo Mandala (Womb Realm Mandala) or the orthodox scriptures or ritual manuals of Esoteric Buddhism and was created in medieval Japan and the like.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>それによって日本では、神道の稲荷と習合するきっかけとなった、とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is supposed that the creation of the above image of Dakiniten resulted in Dakiniten coming to be syncretized with a Shintoist deity, Inari (the fox deity) in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is supposed that the creation of the above image of Dakiniten resulted in Dakiniten coming to be syncretized with a Shintoist deity, Inari (the fox deity) in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is supposed that the creation of the above image resulted in Dakiniten coming to be syncretized with a Shintoist god, Inari (the fox god) in Japan.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="17">
<j>日本では福徳神として信仰される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, Dakiniten is believed in as a deity of good fortune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, Dakiniten is believed to be a deity of good fortune.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, Dakiniten is believed to be a goddess of good fortune.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="18">
<j>インドでのその後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Belief in Dakini in later India</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Belief in Dakini in later India</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Belief in Dakini in later India</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>日本に密教が伝わっていった後の後期密教においては、性的なイメージが付加され、裸体でシャレコウベなどをもつ女神の姿で描かれるようになっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In later esoteric Buddhism, that is, esoteric Buddhism preached in India after the introduction of esoteric Buddhism to Japan, a sexual image was added to Dakini, which resulted in the deity coming to be depicted as a naked goddess having a weatherbeaten skull.</e>
<cmt>後期密教→later esoteric Buddhism[仮訳]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In later esoteric Buddhism, that is, esoteric Buddhism preached in India after the introduction of esoteric Buddhism to Japan, a sexual image was added to Dakini, which resulted in the deity coming to be depicted as a naked goddess having a weatherbeaten skull.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In later Esoteric Buddhism after the introduction to Japan, a sexual image was added to Dakini, which resulted her to be depicted as a naked goddess having a skull.</e>
<cmt>weatherbeatenをのぞき表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="20">
<j>立川流 (密教)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tachikawa-ryu (esoteric Buddhism)</e>
<cmt>立川流→Tachikawa-ryu[この用語については、本文中に詳しい定義があるので、訳注を付けておりません。]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tachikawa-ryu (esoteric Buddhism)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tachikawa School (Esoteric Buddhism)</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>荼枳尼天は後々に性愛を司る神と解釈されたため、日本では鎌倉時代から南北朝時代 (日本)にかけて、真言密教立川流 (密教)という密教の一派が次第に形成され興隆を極めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dakiniten later came to be deemed as a deity governing sexual love, which resulted in, in Japan, Tachikawa-ryu, a subsect of the esoteric Shingon sect of Buddhism being gradually founded over a period from the Kamakura period until the Southern and Northern Dynasties period (of Japanese history) and then flourishing.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「後々に」：いつの時代を指すのかを特定できなかったので、曖昧ですが&quot;later&quot;と訳出するに留めました。「密教」という用語が重複して使用されておりますが、これらをその都度訳出すると功徳なるので、必要な箇所においてのみ訳出しました。「南北朝時代」の直後の「（日本）」については、文脈から、日本の南北朝時代を指すことを容易に理解できるので、不要かとも思いましたが、念のため訳出しました。不要であれば削除してください。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dakiniten later came to be deemed as a deity governing sexual love, which resulted in, in Japan, Tachikawa-ryu, a subsect of the esoteric Shingon sect of Buddhism being gradually founded over a period from the Kamakura period until the Southern and Northern Dynasties period (of Japanese history) and then flourishing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dakiniten later came to be deemed as a goddess governing sexual love, which resulted in Tachikawa School of Shingon Esoteric Buddhism being gradually founded from the Kamakura period until the period of the Northern and Southern Courts and flourished in Japan.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>しかしこれは荼枳尼天を祀り髑髏を本尊とし性交の儀式を以って即身成仏を体現したとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is supposed that, in Tachikawa-ryu, attaining Buddhahood while still in the flesh was embodied by worshiping Dakiniten, having a skeleton enshrined as the main object of worship, and having sexual intercourse as a rite.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is supposed that, in Tachikawa-ryu, attaining Buddhahood while still in the flesh was embodied by worshiping Dakiniten, having a skeleton enshrined as the main object of worship, and having sexual intercourse as a rite.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is supposed to enshrine Dakiniten, set a skull as a principle image and attain Buddhahood while still in the flesh by sexual intercourse as a rite.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>立川流はこれを理由として邪教視され、江戸時代にはついに途絶えたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, Tachikawa-ryu is said to have been regarded as a heresy and finally exterminated in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, Tachikawa-ryu is said to have been regarded as a heresy and was finally exterminated in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, Tachikawa School was said to be regarded as a heresy and was finally exterminated in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>しかしこれは、すべて立川流を邪教視して弾圧した側の文献に依るもので、肝心の立川流の文献はほぼ焚書扱いになっており、また南朝側と北朝側の政治背景から権力闘争に巻き込まれ邪教扱いされたという背景もあるため、それらの教義や儀式などが事実であったかどうかは現在でも議論されるところとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is still in controversy whether the doctrine and rites of Tachikawa-ryu mentioned above was true or not because: the above theories are all based on documents written by those who regarded Tachikawa-ryu as a heresy and oppressed it; most of the documents written by devotees of Tachikawa-ryu, which are vital for the verification of the genuineness of those theories, were subjected to book burning, Tachikawa-ryu was treated as a heresy against the backdrop of its involvement in the political power struggle between the Southern and Northern Dynasties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is still controversial as to whether the doctrines and rites of Tachikawa-ryu mentioned above were true or not because the above theories are all based on documents written by those who regarded Tachikawa-ryu as a heresy and oppressed it, and most of the documents written by devotees of Tachikawa-ryu, which are vital for verification of the genuineness of those theories, were subjected to book burning. Tachikawa-ryu was treated as a heresy against the backdrop of its involvement in the political power struggle between the Southern and Northern Dynasties.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is still controversial as to whether the doctrines and rites of Tachikawa School mentioned above were true or not because the above theories are all based on documents written by those who regarded Tachikawa School as a heresy and oppressed it, and most of the documents written by devotees of Tachikawa School, which are vital for verification of the genuineness of those theories, were subjected to book burning and Tachikawa School was treated as a heresy against the backdrop of its involvement in the political power struggle between the Southern and Northern Dynasties.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Alecs.bot(id:194707), いなり(id:152088), 浩(id:70121), Nnh(id:474), Kenpei(id:11349), Boca samba(id:137526), Stanislaus(id:1806), R28Bot(id:177951), セーラ(id:202326), PixelBot(id:166734), Alexbot(id:157199), ベルゼブブ(id:184141), Louperibot(id:128971), ウィキ豊(id:82961), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>