<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>月僊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gessen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gessen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gessen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>月僊（げっせん、寛保元年（1741年） － 文化 (元号)6年1月12日 (旧暦)（1809年2月25日））は、江戸時代中期から後期にかけての画僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gessen (1741-February 25, 1809) was a priest and artist painter living between the mid and late Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gessen (1741-February 25, 1809) was a priest and artist painter living between the mid and late Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gessen (1741 - February 25, 1809) was a priest and artist painter living between the mid and late Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>名は玄瑞・元瑞。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His name was Genzui (玄瑞 or 元瑞.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His name was Genzui (玄瑞 or 元瑞.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His name was Genzui (玄瑞 or 元瑞.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>字は玉成。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His aza (popular name) was Tamanari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His aza (popular name) was Tamanari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His azana (adult males nickname) was Tamanari.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯と業績</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography and achievements</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography and achievements</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography and Achievements</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>尾張国名古屋の味噌商の家に生まれたが、浄土宗の僧となって江戸増上寺に住み、桜井雪館に画を学んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in a merchant family manufacturing miso (bean paste) in Owari Nagoya, but after he became a priest of the Jodo Sect, he resided at Zojo-ji Temple in Edo and studied painting under Sekkan SAKURAI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in a merchant family manufacturing miso (bean paste) in Owari Nagoya, but after he became a priest of the Jodo Sect, he resided at Zojo-ji Temple in Edo and studied painting under Sekkan SAKURAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in a merchant family manufacturing miso (bean paste) in Nagoya of Owari Province, but after he became a priest of the Jodo (Pure Land) Sect, he resided at Zojo-ji Temple in Edo and studied painting under Sekkan SAKURAI.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>その後上洛して知恩院に住し、円山応挙に師事して写実的画風の感化を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, he went to Kyoto to live in Chion-in Temple, and was inspired by Okyo MARUYAMA about his realistic painting style as his teacher.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, he went to Kyoto to live in Chion-in Temple, and was inspired by Okyo MARUYAMA about his realistic painting style as his teacher.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, he went to Kyoto to live in Chionin Temple, and was inspired by Okyo MARUYAMA about his realistic painting style as his teacher.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また、与謝蕪村の影響も受け、さらに諸派に学んで独自の画風を確立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also influenced by YOSA no Buson and after studying various styles, he established his own painting style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also influenced by YOSA no Buson and after studying various styles, he established his own painting style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also influenced by YOSA no Buson and after studying various styles, he established his own painting style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>山水・人物を得意とし、人物の形影が寂寥としていることを特長とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was good at drawing Sansui (landscape, hills and rivers) and figures, and his artistic feature is that shadow added to a target figure feels sad and lonely.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was good at drawing Sansui (landscape, hills and rivers) and figures, and his artistic feature is that of shadows added to a target figure that feels sad and lonely.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was good at drawing Sansui (landscape, hills and rivers) and figures, and his artistic feature is that of shadows added to a target figure that feels sad and lonely.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>誰に乞われても必ず画料を取るところから「乞食月僊」と世に知られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whoever the customer was, he requested drawing fees, and was widely known as &apos;beggar Gessen.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whoever the customer was, he requested drawing fees, and was widely known as &apos;beggar Gessen.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whoever the customer was, he requested drawing fees, and was widely known as &apos;beggar Gessen.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>知恩院の貫主に懇願されて、1774年（安永3年）伊勢国宇治山田（現在・三重県伊勢市）の寂照寺を再興するために入山。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the sincere request of the chief priest of Chion-in Temple, he entered the mountains in order to reconstruct Josho-ji Temple in Uji Yamada, Ise Province (currently, Ise City, Mie Prefecture) in 1774.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the sincere request of the chief priest of Chion-in Temple, he entered the mountains in order to reconstruct Josho-ji Temple in Uji Yamada, Ise Province (currently, Ise City, Mie Prefecture) in 1774.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the sincere request of the chief priest of Chionin Temple, he entered the mountains in order to reconstruct Josho-ji Temple in Uji Yamada, Ise Province (present-day, Ise City, Mie Prefecture) in 1774.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>画名が高まり画を請う者が絶えず、巨万の富を積みさらに銭をむさぼること甚だしいため、譏る人も多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As he became famous for his painting, he received constant requests for drawing, and since he furthermore attempted to make excessive profits over accumulated enormous wealth, there were a lot of people who were criticizing him for that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As he became famous for his painting, he received constant requests for drawing, and since he furthermore attempted to make excessive profits over accumulated enormous wealth, there were a lot of people who were criticizing him for that.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As he became famous for his painting, he received constant requests for drawing, and since he furthermore attempted to make excessive profits over accumulated enormous wealth, there were a lot of people who were criticizing him for that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかしのちに寺の伽藍・山門を建て、経典を購入して倉におさめ、山道の改修・天明飢饉の施米・宮川架橋・文化年間の伊勢大火罹災者の救済などに尽くす姿を見せ、人はみなその功徳に服すようになったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, afterward, he constructed a Buddhist temple and Sammon gate (temple gate,) bought Buddhist scriptures to put it in storage, reconstructed mountain trails, donated rice in the Tenmei Famine, constructed a bridge over Miyakawa River and helped victims in the Great Fire of Ise between 1804 and 1817, and all people who saw his sincere attitude working for others respected and appreciated his merits.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, afterwards, he constructed a Buddhist temple and Sammon gate (temple gate), bought Buddhist scriptures to put in storage, reconstructed mountain trails, donated rice in the Tenmei Famine, constructed a bridge over Miyakawa River and helped victims in the Great Fire of Ise between 1804 and 1817, and all people who saw his sincere attitude working for others respected and appreciated his merits.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, afterwards, he constructed a Buddhist temple and Sanmon gate (temple gate), bought Buddhist scriptures to put in storage, reconstructed mountain trails, donated rice in the Tenmei Famine, constructed a bridge over the Miya-kawa River and helped victims in the Great Fire of Ise between 1804 and 1817, and all people who saw his sincere attitude working for others respected and appreciated his merits.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>死に臨んで遺言し、窮身永代救済に千五百両を奉行所へ寄託する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He left a will at his death and donated fifteen hundred ryo (currency unit) to Bugyosho (a magistrate&apos;s office) for 窮身永代救済.</e>
<cmt>調べましたが、”窮身永代救済”の意味が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He left a will at his death and donated fifteen hundred ryo (currency unit) to Bugyosho (a magistrate&apos;s office) for 窮身永代救済.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He left a will at his death and donated 1500 ryo (currency unit) to Bugyosho (a magistrate&apos;s office) as Kyushin Eidai Kyusai (fund for saving poor people).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>京都妙法院・愛知県岡崎市昌光律寺・寂照寺に作品が残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His products are kept at Myoho-ji Temple in Kyoto, Shokoritsu-ji Temple in Okazaki City, Aichi Prefecture and Josho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His products are kept at Myoho-ji Temple in Kyoto, Shokoritsu-ji Temple in Okazaki City, Aichi Prefecture and Josho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His products are kept at Myoho-ji Temple in Kyoto, Shokoritsu-ji Temple in Okazaki City, Aichi Prefecture and Josho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>「列仙図賛」「耕織図」「月僊画譜」などの作品がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He produced Ressenzusan,&apos; &apos;Koshokuzu,&apos; &apos;Gessengafu,&apos; etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He produced Ressenzusan,&apos; &apos;Koshokuzu,&apos; &apos;Gessengafu,&apos; etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He produced &apos;Ressen zusan&apos; (Ressen Zenden (&apos;Collected Biography of Chinese Hermits&apos; written by Seitei O.) illustrated by Gessho), &apos;Koshokuzu&apos; (painting of cultivation and sericulture), &apos;Gessen Gafu&apos; (picture book of Gessen), and so on.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 R28Bot(id:177951), Hannah(id:15935), Cprobot(id:97843), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>