<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>蓮乗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Renjo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Renjo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Renjo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>蓮乗（れんじょう、文安3年（1446年）－永正元年2月21日 (旧暦)（1504年3月7日））は、室町時代中期から戦国時代_(日本)にかけての浄土真宗の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Renjo (1446 -March 7, 1504) was the monk of Jodo shin shu (True Pure Land Sect Buddhism) during middle of Muromachi period to the age of civil war. (Japan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Renjo (1446 - March 7, 1504) was a monk of Jodo shin shu (True Pure Land sect of Buddhism) during the middle of Muromachi period and up to the age of civil war (Japan).</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Renjo (1446 - March 17, 1504) was a monk of Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) during the middle of Muromachi period and up to the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) (Japan).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>本願寺8世蓮如の次男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the second son of eighth head of the Hongan-ji Temple, Rennyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the second son of Rennyo, the eighth head of the Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the second son of Rennyo, the eighth head of the Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>実名は兼鎮、幼名は光養。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His real name was Kenchin, childhood&apos;s name was 光養.</e>
<cmt>光養→読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His real name was Kenchin, and his childhood name was 光養.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His real name was Kenchin, and his childhood name was Koyo (光養).</e>
<cmt>仮読みを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>幼い頃、本願寺は衰退期であったために南禅寺に喝食として出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Hongan-ji Temple was declining in power when he was small, he was sent to Nanzen-ji Temple as Kasshiki. (postulant)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Hongan-ji Temple was declining in power when he was small, he was sent to Nanzen-ji Temple as Kasshiki (postulant).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Hongan-ji Temple was declining in power when he was a child, he was sent to Nanzen-ji Temple as Kasshiki (postulant).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>15歳となった寛正元年1月26日_(旧暦)（1460年2月18日）、加賀国二俣房(後の本泉寺)の住持であった蓮如の叔父如乗（実名宣祐）が死亡したため、その娘を娶って後継者になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 18, 1460, when Renjo was fifteen years old, after Rennyo&apos;s uncle, Nyojo (real name was Senyu) died who was the chief priest of 二俣房 (later called Honsen-ji Temple), he married to Nyojo&apos;s daughter and succeeded to the head of the temple.</e>
<cmt>二俣房→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 18, 1460, when Renjo was 15 years old, after the death of Rennyo&apos;s uncle, Nyojo (whose real name was Senyu), who was the chief priest of 二俣房 (later called Honsen-ji Temple), he married Nyojo&apos;s daughter and succeeded to a position as the head of the temple.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 27, 1460, when Renjo was 15 years old, after the death of Rennyo&apos;s uncle, Nyojo (whose real name was Senyu), who was the chief priest of Futamatabo (二俣房, later called Honsen-ji Temple) in Kaga Province, he married Nyojo&apos;s daughter and succeeded to a position as the head priest of the temple.</e>
<cmt>「二俣房」は地名より読みを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>如乗はかつては本願寺の本寺である青蓮院の僧であったが、門主の義円と張り合っていたため、義円が還俗して室町幕府第6代征夷大将軍足利義教となると、追われる身となって各地を流浪した末に越中国 瑞泉寺 (南砺市)を経て加賀に落ち着いたのであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Nyojo was monk of Shorei-in Temple which was the main temple of Hongan-ji Temple, he had conflict with the chief priest, Gien, after Gien returned to secular life and became the sixth Barbarian Subduing Generalissimo of the Muromachi bakufu, Yoshimichi Ashikaga, Nyojo was chased by the oppositions and wandered around place to place, finally he went to Zuisen-ji Temple (Nanto City) of Ecchu Province and then settled into Kaga Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Nyojo was a monk of Shorei-in Temple, which was the main temple of Hongan-ji Temple, he had a conflict with the chief priest, Gien, after Gien returned to secular life and became Yoshimichi Ashikaga, the sixth Barbarian Subduing Generalissimo of the Muromachi bakufu, Nyojo was chased by the opposition and wandered from place to place, but finally he went to Zuisen-ji Temple (Nanto City) of Ecchu Province and then settled into Kaga Province.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Nyojo was a monk of Shorei-in Temple, which was the main temple of Hongan-ji Temple, he had a conflict with the chief priest, Gien, after Gien returned to secular life and became Yoshimichi ASHIKAGA, the sixth seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), Nyojo was chased by the opposition and wandered from place to place, but finally he went to Zuisen-ji Temple (Nanto City) of Etchu Province and then settled into Kaga Province.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>後に如乗は兄・存如死後の家督争いで庶長子の蓮如の才能を見込んで反対派を押さえ込んで後継者に擁立した事があり、如乗の死後にその未亡人の要請で本泉寺の寺号を与えるとともに蓮乗を派遣したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later on, when his brother died and there was a conflict to decide the successor for his position, once Nyojo appointed Rennyo as the successor of his brother, since he thought the oldest son, Rennyo had talent to do so, even oppositions went against it, after Nyojo died, his mistress whished to give Terago title of Honsen-ji Temple and sent Renjo there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, when his brother died and there was a conflict in deciding upon a successor for his position, once Nyojo appointed Rennyo as his brother&apos;s successor, since he thought the oldest son Rennyo had the talent for it, even the opposition went against it, and after Nyojo died his mistress wanted to bestow the Terago title of Honsen-ji Temple and sent Renjo there.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, when Nyojo&apos;s brother Zonnyo died and there was a conflict in deciding upon a successor for his position, once Nyojo appointed Rennyo as his brother&apos;s successor, since he thought the oldest son Rennyo had the talent for it, even the opposition went against it, and after Nyojo died his mistress wanted to bestow the jigo (literally, &quot;temple name,&quot; which is the title given to a Buddhist temple) of Honsen-ji Temple and sent Renjo there.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>文明_(日本)3年（1471年）、延暦寺の圧力を逃れて北陸に布教の旅に出た父・蓮如は吉崎御坊と本泉寺を足がかりに布教に努めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1471 his father, Rennyo went to a trip of missionary work to Hokuriku to escaped from the political pressure of Enryaku-ji Temple, he started to propagate from Yoshizaki Gobo and Honsen-ji Temple and spent his time there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1471, his father Rennyo embarked on a trip of missionary work to Hokuriku to escape from the political pressure of Enryaku-ji Temple, whereupon he started to propagate from Yoshizaki Gobo and Honsen-ji Temple and spent his time there.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1471, Renjo&apos;s father Rennyo embarked on a trip of missionary work to Hokuriku region to escape from the political pressure of Enryaku-ji Temple, whereupon he started to propagate from Yoshizaki Gobo and Honsen-ji Temple and spent his time there.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>ところが、文明6年（1474年）、後の加賀一向一揆のきっかけとなる富樫氏の内紛に巻き込まれ、翌年蓮如は吉崎を退去、蓮乗も本泉寺を追われて本願寺の末寺となっていた瑞泉寺に退いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in 1471, he was involved in the internal conflict of the Togashi clan, which became the cause of an upraising of Ikko sect followers in Kaga, he left Yoshizaki on the following year, Renjo was forced to leave Honsen-ji Temple and escaped to Zuisen-ji Temple, which was the branch temple of Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in 1471 he was involved in the internal conflict of the Togashi clan, which became the cause of an uprising of Ikko sect followers in Kaga, so he left Yoshizaki in the following year; Renjo was forced to leave Honsen-ji Temple and escaped to Zuisen-ji Temple, which was a branch temple of Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in 1474 he was involved in the internal conflict of the Togashi clan, which became the cause of an uprising of Ikko Sect followers in Kaga, so he left Yoshizaki in the following year; Renjo was forced to leave Honsen-ji Temple and escaped to Zuisen-ji Temple, which was a branch temple of Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>年号を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>更に文明13年（1481年）には今度は越中で門徒の弾圧が行われた事を機に一向一揆が発生して砺波郡が門徒の支配下に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, after there was an oppression of the believers in Ecchu, it also caused an uprising of Ikko sect followers,(1481) Tonami County became under the control of the believers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, due to the oppression of the believers in Ecchu, it also caused an uprising of the Ikko sect followers (1481), and Tonami County came under the control of the believers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, due to the oppression of the believers in Etchu, it also caused an uprising of the Ikko Sect followers (in 1481), and Tonami County came under the control of the believers.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>だが、蓮乗は越中退去の頃にあった落馬からの回復が思わしくなく、弟の蓮悟に娘を娶わせて後継者にする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since Renjo was not well after he fell from the horse while escaping from Ecchu, he made his younger brother marry his daughter and let him became the successor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since Renjo wasn&apos;t well after a fell from his horse while escaping from Ecchu, he had his younger brother marry his daughter and let him became the successor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since Renjo wasn&apos;t well after a fell from his horse while escaping from Etchu, he had his younger brother Rengo marry his daughter and let him became the successor.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>長享元年（1487年）には再興した本泉寺に復帰するが、病状は悪化して明応8年（1499年）の蓮如危篤の際にも駆けつける事が出来なかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1487, although he returned to Honsen-ji Temple which was restored, it is said he did not get better and he was not well enough to be able to see Rennyo when Rennyo was in the critical condition in 1499.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1487, although he returned to Honsen-ji Temple, which was restored, it is said that he didn&apos;t improve and wasn&apos;t well enough to see Rennyo when the latter was in critical condition in 1499.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1487, although he returned to Honsen-ji Temple, which was restored, it is said that he didn&apos;t improve and wasn&apos;t well enough to see Rennyo when the latter was in critical condition in 1499.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その5年後に59歳で病死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died five years after this when he was fifty nine years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died five years later, when he was 59 years of age.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died of illness five years later, when he was 59 years of age.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>