<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>古市澄胤</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Choin FURUICHI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Choin FURUICHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Choin FURUICHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>古市 澄胤（ふるいち ちょういん、享徳元年（1452年） - 永正5年7月26日 (旧暦)（1508年8月22日））は、戦国時代 (日本)の僧・武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Choin FURUICHI (1452 - August 22, 1508) was a priest and busho (military commander) who lived in the Sengoku period (period of warring states) (in Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Choin FURUICHI (1452 - August 22, 1508) was a priest and busho (military commander) who lived in the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Capitalized.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Choin FURUICHI (1452 - August 22, 1508) was a priest and busho (military commander) who lived in the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>奈良興福寺の衆徒。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a monk-soldier at Kofuku-ji Tempe in Nara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a monk-soldier at Kofuku-ji Temple in Nara.</e>
<cmt>Spelling.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a monk-soldier at Kofuku-ji Temple in Nara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>父は古市胤仙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Insen FURUICHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Insen FURUICHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Insen FURUICHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>越智家秀の娘を妻とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His wife was a daughter of Iehide OCHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His wife was a daughter of Iehide OCHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His wife was a daughter of Iehide OCHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>播磨公・播磨法師・播磨律師とも称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also called Harima-no-kimi, Harima-hoshi (Buddhist priest) or Harima-risshi (Buddhist priest)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also called Harima-no-kimi, Harima-hoshi, or Harima-risshi (Buddhist priest).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation. Does Harima-no-kimi also mean Buddhist priest?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also called Harima-no-kimi, Harima-hoshi, or Harima-risshi (Buddhist priest).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>叔父宣胤のいる興福寺発心院に入って14歳で出家、倫勧房と号した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He entered Hosshinin of Kofuku-ji Temple where Nobutane, his uncle, lived and became a priest at the age of 14, using Rinkambo as his priest name.</e>
<cmt>倫勧房：　正しい読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He entered Hosshin-in at Kofuku-ji Temple where Nobutane, his uncle, lived, and became a priest at the age of fourteen, using Rinkambo as his priest name.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation, style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He entered Hosshin-in at Kofuku-ji Temple where Nobutane, his uncle, lived, and became a priest at the age of fourteen, using Rinkanbo as his priest name.</e>
<cmt>Rincombo→Rinkanbo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>興福寺大乗院門跡の六方衆となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became ropposhu (a monk-soldier) at Daijo-in Monzeki (an especially high-ranked temple) of Kofuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became a ropposhu (monk-soldier) of Daijo-in Monzeki (an especially high-ranked temple) at Kofuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became a ropposhu (monk-soldier) of Daijo-in Monzeki (an especially high-ranked temple) at Kofuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>1475年（文明 (日本)7年）兄の古市胤栄を隠居させて寺を出、家督を相続した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1475, he had Ine FURUICHI, his older brother, retired from the active life, and, ending the temple life, inherited the family head position,.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1475, he had his older brother Ine FURUICHI retire from active life, and leaving temple life himself, he inherited the position of head of the family.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1475, he had his older brother Ine FURUICHI retire from active life, and leaving temple life himself, he inherited the position of head of the family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>興福寺衆徒を統率し、また越智氏と結んで筒井氏を圧倒した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Leading the monk-soldiers at Kofuku-ji Temple, he overwhelmed the Tsutsui clan in cooperation with the Ochi clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Leading the monk-soldiers at Kofuku-ji Temple, he overwhelmed the Tsutsui clan in cooperation with the Ochi clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Leading the monk-soldiers at Kofuku-ji Temple, he overwhelmed the Tsutsui clan in cooperation with the Ochi clan.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>1493年（明応2年）大和国守護代として南山城に入って国一揆を鎮圧した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1493, he entered Minami-Yamashiro Castle as Shugodai (deputy of Shugo, provincial constable) of Yamato Province, and suppressed kuni ikki (an uprising in the province).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1493, he entered Minami-Yamashiro Castle as Shugodai (Deputy of Shugo, and Provincial Constable) of Yamato Province, and suppressed the kuni ikki (an uprising in the province).</e>
<cmt>Capitalized, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1493, he entered Minami-Yamashiro Castle as Shugodai (Deputy of Shugo, and Provincial Constable) of Yamato Province, and suppressed the kuni ikki (an uprising in the province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その後は細川政元配下の武将赤沢宗益の大和国への侵攻に協力している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he cooperated with Soeki AKAZAWA, busho under control of Masamoto HOSOKAWA, in Soeki&apos;s invasion to Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he cooperated with Soeki AKAZAWA, a busho under the control of Masamoto HOSOKAWA, in Soeki&apos;s invasion of Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he cooperated with Soeki AKAZAWA, a busho under the control of Masamoto HOSOKAWA, in Soeki&apos;s invasion of Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>1508年（永正5年）細川澄元配下の武将赤沢長経に属して河内国高屋城の畠山尚順を攻めたが、敗走してその途中で自害している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1508, belonging to Nagatsune AKAZAWA, busho under control of Sumimoto HOSOKAWA, he attacked Hisanobu HATAKEYAMA at Takaya Castle in Kawachi Province, but defeated, killed himself while fleeing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1508, under Nagatsune AKAZAWA, a busho under the control of Sumimoto HOSOKAWA, he attacked Hisanobu HATAKEYAMA at Takaya Castle in Kawachi Province, but was defeated, and killed himself during his escape.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1508, under Nagatsune AKAZAWA, a busho under the control of Sumimoto HOSOKAWA, he attacked Hisanobu HATAKEYAMA at Takaya Castle in Kawachi Province, but was defeated, and killed himself during his escape.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>一方で連歌師猪苗代兼載から『心敬僧都庭訓』を、茶人村田珠光から『心の文』をうけ、また謡（うたい）・尺八にも優れ、文人としても有名であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, he was presented with &quot;Shinkei sozu teikin&quot; by Kensai INAWASHIRO, a renga poet (linked-verse poet), and with &quot;Kokoro no Fumi&quot; (Letter of Heart) by Juko MURATA, a chajin (master of the tea ceremony), was good at Utai (the chanting of Noh text) and at playing Shakuhachi bamboo flute, and was also famous as man of literature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, he was presented with &quot;Shinkei Sozu Teikin&quot; by Kensai INAWASHIRO, a renga (linked-verse) poet, and with &quot;Kokoro no Fumi&quot; (Letter from the Heart) by Juko MURATA, a chajin (master of the tea ceremony), was good at Utai (the chanting of Noh text) and at playing the shakuhachi bamboo flute, and was also famous as man of literature.</e>
<cmt>Capitalized, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, he was presented with &quot;Shinkei Sozu Teikin&quot; by Kensai INAWASHIRO, a renga (linked-verse) poet, and with &quot;Kokoro no Fumi&quot; (Letter from the Heart) by Juko MURATA, a chajin (master of the tea ceremony), was good at Utai (the chanting of Noh text) and at playing the shakuhachi bamboo flute, and was also famous as man of literature.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>『山上宗二記』には、古市播磨（澄胤）が能阿弥・千利休とともに茶道の「三大名人」として挙げられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Yamanoue Soji ki&quot; (The Record of Soji YAMANOUE), Harima (Choin) FURUICHI is listed as one of &quot;the three great masters of tea ceremony&quot; together with Noami and SEN no Rikyu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Yamanoue Soji Ki&quot; (The Record of Soji YAMANOUE), Harima (Choin) FURUICHI is listed as one of &quot;the three great masters of the tea ceremony&quot; together with Noami and SEN no Rikyu.</e>
<cmt>Capitalized, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Yamanoue Soji Ki&quot; (The Record of Soji YAMANOUE), Harima (Choin) FURUICHI is listed as one of &quot;the three great masters of the tea ceremony&quot; together with Noami and SEN no Rikyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>弟子に珠光伝来の松屋三名物を秘蔵した松屋久行がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His disciples included Hisayuki MATSUYA who treasured the three special products of Matsuya inherited from Juko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His disciples included Hisayuki MATSUYA who treasured the three special products of Matsuya inherited from Juko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His disciples included Hisayuki MATSUYA who treasured the three special products of Matsuya inherited from Juko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Novo(id:87875), Nevylax(id:38464), 松茸(id:27535), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), Nighthawks(id:36125), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>