<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>禅定</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zenjo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zenjo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zenjo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>禅定（ぜんじょう、サンスクリット：dhyaana、パーリ語：jhaana）は、心を統一して瞑想し、真理を観察すること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zenjo (dhyaana in Sanskrit, jhaana in Pali) is to meditate and observe the truth while concentrating one&apos;s mind.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zenjo (dhyaana in Sanskrit, jhaana in Pali) is to meditate and observe the truth while focusing one&apos;s mind.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zenjo (dhyaana in Sanskrit, jhaana in Pali) is to meditate and observe the truth while focusing one&apos;s mind.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>またそれによって心身ともに動揺することがなくなった、安定した状態を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also means the stable state attained through Zenjo under which neither one&apos;s mind nor body is unsettled by anything.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also means the stability attained through Zenjo under which neither one&apos;s mind nor body is unsettled by anything.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also means the stability attained through Zenjo under which neither one&apos;s mind nor body is unsettled by anything.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>サンスクリット語の dhyaana の音写である「禅」と、その意訳した「定」の複合語で、三昧と同義語である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the compound term of &quot;zen&quot;, a transcription of Sanskrit dhyaana, and its free translation &quot;jo&quot;, and has the same meaning with zanmai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the compound term of &quot;zen,&quot; a transcription of Sanskrit dhyaana, and its free translation &quot;jo,&quot; which has the same meaning as zanmai.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the compound term of &apos;zen,&apos; a transcription of Sanskrit dhyaana, and its free translation &apos;jo,&apos; which has the same meaning as zanmai.</e>
<cmt>スペースをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>元来は、大乗仏教の菩薩が実践すべき修行徳目である六波羅蜜のうちの第五禅那波羅蜜（ぜんなはらみつ）のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, it was Daigo Zenna haramitsu, one of six haramitsu that bosatsu (Bodhisattva) of Mahayana Buddhism was obliged to practice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, it was Daigo Zenna haramitsu, one of six haramitsu that bosatsu (Bodhisattva) of Mahayana Buddhism was obliged to practice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, it was Daigo Zenna haramitsu (paramita), one of six haramitsu that bosatsu (Bodhisattva) of Mahayana Buddhism was obliged to practice.</e>
<cmt>用語集より補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>禅那 (Dhyāna) は「禅定」と訳され、真理を思惟して散乱の心を定止することを指している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zenna (Dhyāna) is translated as &quot;Zenjo&quot; and it means stabilizing the unsettled mind by thinking the truth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zenna (Dhyāna) is translated as &quot;Zenjo&quot; and means stabilizing the unsettled mind by thinking the truth.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zenna (Dhyāna) is translated as &apos;Zenjo&apos; and means stabilizing the unsettled mind by thinking the truth.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>阿含経典では、この状態に至る過程には、まず初禅から第四禅までの4段階があるとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the process of attaining such state, according to Agama Sutra, there are four stages from shozen (the first Dhyana) to daishizen (the fourth Dhyana).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the process of attaining such a state, according to Agama Sutra, there are four stages ranging from shozen (the first Dhyana) to daishizen (the fourth Dhyana).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the process of attaining such a state, according to Agama Sutra, there are four stages ranging from shozen (the first Dhyana) to daishizen (the fourth Dhyana).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>これが「四静慮（四禅）」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These are collectively called &quot;Shijoryo (Shizen).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These are collectively called &quot;Shijoryo (Shizen).&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These are collectively called &apos;Shijoryo&apos; (also referred as Shizen).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>次に空無辺処・識無辺処・無所有処・非想非非想処の4段階があるとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, according to the sutra, there are another four stages called Kumuhenkyo, Shikimuhenkyo, Mushoyusho and Hisohihisokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, according to the sutra, there are another four stages called Kumuhenkyo, Shikimuhenkyo, Mushoyusho and Hisohihisokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, according to the sutra, there are another four stages called Kumuhensho (the lowest heaven of Mushikikai (the realm of non-form)),Shikimuhensho (the second lowest heaven of Mushikikai), Musho-usho (the third lowest heaven of Mushikikai) and Hisohihisosho (the highest heaven of Mushikikai).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>これが、「四無色定」であり、さらに九次第定、百八三昧とつづく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These are collectively called &quot;Shimushikijo&quot; and it is followed by Kushidaijo and Hyakuhachizanmai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These are collectively called &quot;Shimushikijo&quot; and are followed by Kushidaijo and Hyakuhachizanmai.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These are collectively called &apos;Shimushikijo&apos; (four concentrations of the formless realm) and are followed by Kushidaijo (Nine Successive Stages of Concentration) and Hyakuhachi zanmai (one hundred eight kinds of samadhi).</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>また、「戒・定・慧」と言われるように、仏教においては戒律を守ることと禅定と智慧とはセットになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Buddhism, religious precepts, Zenjo and wisdom are treated as a set as the often-used phrase &quot;kai (precepts), jo and kei (wisdom)&quot; indicates.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Buddhism, religious precepts, Zenjo and wisdom are referred to collectively with the common phrase &quot;kai (precepts), jo and kei (wisdom).&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Buddhism, religious precepts, Zenjo and wisdom are referred to collectively with the common phrase &apos;kai (precepts), jo (zenjo) and kei (wisdom).&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>（禅定と智慧との関係については、止観を参照）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Regarding the relation between Zenjo and wisdom, refer to Shikan (Tendai meditation).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Regarding the relationship between Zenjo and wisdom, refer to Shikan (Tendai meditation).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Regarding the relationship between Zenjo and wisdom, refer to Shikan (Tendai meditation)).</e>
<cmt>かっこを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>禅定と坐禅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zenjo and Zazen (meditation)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zenjo and Zazen (meditation)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zenjo and Zazen (meditation)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>中国では、この禅定による修行を廃し頓悟を目指す禅宗が成立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zen Sect, which abolished Zengyo practices and pursued Tongo (prompt enlightenment), was established in China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Zen sect, which abolished Zengyo practices and pursued Tongo (prompt enlightenment), was established in China.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Zen sect, which abolished Zenjo practices and pursued Tongo (prompt enlightenment), was established in China.</e>
<cmt>前出表記に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>それは禅定（＝坐禅）に新しい定義を与え、従前の仏教を真向から否定するような面を持つものだったが、唐代に隆盛を極めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although this sect brought a new definition of Zenjo (=Zazen) and had the aspect of completely denying the existing Buddhism, it prospered in the era of Tang Dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although this sect brought forth a new definition of Zenjo (i.e., Zazen) and had the aspect of completely denying the existing Buddhism, it prospered in the era of the Tang Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although this sect brought forth a new definition of Zenjo (i.e., Zazen) and had the aspect of completely denying the existing Buddhism, it prospered in the era of the Tang Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>南宋代に栄西・道元らによって日本にもたらされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zen Sect was introduced into Japan by Eisai/Dogen in the Southern Sun Dynasty period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Zen sect was introduced into Japan by Eisai/Dogen during the period of the Southern Sung Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Zen sect was introduced into Japan by Eisai and Dogen during the period of the Southern Sung Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>そこでは再び禅定修行が復活し、武士の主要徳目ともなり流行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, Zenjo practices revived again and became popular as the principal tokumoku (virtue) of samurai (warriors).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, Zenjo practices were revived again and became popular as the principal tokumoku (virtue) of samurai (warriors).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, Zenjo practices were revived again and became popular as the principal tokumoku (virtue) of samurai (warriors).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), Izayohi(id:13095), Kstigarbha(id:13376), R28Bot(id:177951), Dignaaga(id:91287), マイコン坊主(id:338), Authority(id:10737), Dhamma(id:158623), Yas(id:739), Saburo(id:18511), サイユ(id:25887), Greenland4(id:114494), ウィキ豊(id:82961), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>