<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>快川紹喜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaisen Joki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaisen Joki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaisen Joki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>快川 紹喜（かいせん じょうき、生年不詳 - 天正10年4月3日 (旧暦)（1582年4月25日））は、戦国時代 (日本)、安土桃山時代の臨済宗の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaisen Joki (Birthday unknown - April 25, 1582, which was April 3 according to the old calendar) was a priest of the Rinzai Sect of Buddhism during the warring states period and Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaisen Joki (Birthday unknown - April 25, 1582, which was April 3 according to the old calendar) was a priest of the Rinzai Sect of Buddhism during the warring states period and Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaisen Joki (year of birth unknown - April 25, 1582) was a priest of the Rinzai Sect of Buddhism from the Warring States period and the Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました生没年の表記を修正Warring Statesを大文字にしました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>俗姓は土岐氏で、美濃国の出身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His secular surname was Toki and he was from Mino Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His secular surname was Toki and he was from Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was from Mino Province and his secular surname was Toki.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>諱は紹喜。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His imina (personal name) was Joki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His imina (personal name) was Joki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Imina (personal name) was Joki.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>字は快川。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His azana (adult male nickname)was Kaisen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His azana (adult male nickname)was Kaisen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Azana (adult male&apos;s nickname) was Kaisen.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>妙心寺の仁岫宗寿の法を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He inherited the position of Jinyu Shoju ho of Myoshin-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He inherited the position of Jinyu Shoju ho of Myoshin-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He inherited the position of Jinyu Shoju ho of Myoshin-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>美濃国の寺院を経て妙心寺の43世に就任し、美濃国の崇福寺 (岐阜市)から甲斐国に移った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was transferred and appointed the 43rd priest of Myoshin-ji Temple in Kai Province after training at Sofuku-ji Temple in Mino Province (Gifu City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was transferred and appointed the 43rd priest of Myoshin-ji Temple in Kai Province after training at Sofuku-ji Temple in Mino Province (Gifu City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After serving at a temple in Mino Province, he became the 43rd priest of Myoshin-ji Temple; he later moved from Sofuku-ji Temple in Mino Province (Gifu City) to Kai Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しましたAfterを入れて、修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>武田信玄に迎えられて塩山恵林寺に入寺し、信玄に機山の号を授けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was received by Shingen TAKEDA, entered Shioyama Erin-ji Temple and was given the name Kizan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was received by Shingen TAKEDA, entered Shioyama Erin-ji Temple and was given the name Kizan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was welcomed by Shingen TAKEDA, entered Shioyama Erin-ji Temple and gave Shingen the priest name, Kizan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>織田信長の武田征伐により武田氏が滅亡して領内が混乱した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the conquest of Takeda by Nobunaga ODA leading to the fall of the Takeda family, there was confusion within the domain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the conquest of Takeda by Nobunaga ODA leading to the fall of the Takeda family, there was confusion within the domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga ODA conquered and killed the Takeda clan, making Takeda&apos;s domain chaotic.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しましたtheを追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>そして中世において寺院は聖域であるとする社会的観念があったため信長に敵対した六角義治らを恵林寺にかくまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During medieval period there was a social notion that temples and shrines were places of sanctuary, and Yoshiharu ROKKAKU and others who opposed Nobunaga were sheltered in Erin-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the medieval period, there was a social notion that temples and shrines were places of sanctuary, and Yoshiharu ROKKAKU and others who opposed Nobunaga were sheltered in Erin-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since there was a social consensus in the Middle Ages that temples and shrines were sacred, Kaisen gave shelter to Yoshiharu ROKKAKU and others who fought against Nobunaga in Erin-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>すると織田信忠の引渡し要求を拒否したことから焼討ちにあい、一山の僧とともに焼死を遂げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because the temple members refused the request from Nobutada ODA to turn them over, the temple was set on fire and Joki and other monks died.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the temple members refused the request from Nobutada ODA to turn them over, the temple was set on fire and Joki and other monks died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the temple members refused Nobutada ODA&apos;s order to hand them over, Nobutada put fire on the temple and Joki and other priests were killed.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>このとき残した「安禅必ずしも山水を用いず、心頭滅却すれば火も亦た涼し」の辞世で知られる（杜荀鶴の原典は「…火も自ずから涼し」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is famous for the death Haiku &quot;安禅必ずしも山水を用いず、心頭滅却すれば火も亦た涼し (meaning that you will not feel hardship or pain if you see it from a different angle.) &quot; (original by Jukukaku TO is &quot;…火も自ずから涼し &quot;)</e>
<cmt>辞世の訳はできませんでしたが、その意味はインターネット上に載ってました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is famous for the death Haiku &quot;安禅必ずしも山水を用いず、心頭滅却すれば火も亦た涼し (meaning that you will not feel hardship or pain if you see it from a different angle.) &quot; (original by Jukukaku TO is &quot;…火も自ずから涼し &quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Joki has been famous for his farewell poem (composed before his death), saying &quot;Meditation does not always require a quiet place. If you have established your own philosophy, nothing will trouble you as if you would feel fire cool.(安禅必ずしも山水を用いず、心頭滅却すれば火も亦た涼し&quot; (The original text written by Jukukaku TO says &quot;as if fire itself would be cool.(火も自ずから涼し) &quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>これは『甲乱記』では快川と問答した高山和尚の言葉とされており、同時代文献には見られず近世の編纂物に登場していることから、本来は快川の逸話でなかった可能性が指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Koranki&quot; the Haiku is said to be written by Takayama Osho, and the haiku does not appear in the document of the period but appears in the modern document, suggesting possibility of it being Kaisen&apos;s anecdote.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処高山和尚→定訳不明。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Koranki&quot; the Haiku is said to have been written by Takayama Osho, and does not appear in documents of the period but appears in modern documents, suggesting the possibility of it being Kaisen&apos;s anecdote.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is suggested that the farewell poem was not made by Kaisen; &quot;Koranki,&quot; said that the poem was written by Takayama Osho, who held a dialogue with Kaisen; that poem was not found in any documents of that period but in modern documents.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>また、快川紹喜は明智光秀と同じく美濃国の土岐氏出身であり、同族であったと見られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaisen Joki was originally of the Toki lineage of Mino Province as was Mitsuhide AKECHI, and belonged to the same clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaisen Joki was originally of the Toki lineage of Mino Province as was Mitsuhide AKECHI, and belonged to the same clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also considered that Kaisen Joki and Mitsuhide AKECHI, who was also born in Mino Province, belonged to the same Toki clan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しましたスペルミスを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>このため、本能寺の変において光秀が信長・信忠父子を討ち取った事件に、彼の死が影響したとする見方もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, some believe that Joki&apos;s death influenced Mitsuhide&apos;s attack on Nobunaga and Nobuhide at Honno-ji Temple in the Honnoji Incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, some believe that Joki&apos;s death influenced Mitsuhide&apos;s attack on Nobunaga and Nobuhide at Honno-ji Temple in the Honnoji Incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, some believe that Joki&apos;s death influenced Mitsuhide&apos;s attack on Nobunaga and Nobutada at Honno-ji Temple in the Honnoji Incident.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しましたNobuhide→Nobutada</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>「滝のぼる 鯉の心は 張り弓の 緩めば落つる 元の川瀬に」という言葉でも知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is also known for writing &quot;Carp climbing the waterfall with intense mind shall fall when tension is released (meaning don&apos;t let your guard down.)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is also known for writing &quot;Carp climbing the waterfall with intense mind shall fall when tension is released (meaning don&apos;t let your guard down.)&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is also known for writing &quot;Carp climbing the waterfall with intense mind shall fall when tension is released (meaning don&apos;t let your guard down).&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>弟子には伊達政宗の教育の師として有名な虎哉宗乙がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His disciples included Kosai Sootsu who was famous for being the teacher of Masamune DATE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His disciples included Kosai Sootsu who was famous for being the teacher of Masamune DATE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of his disciples was Kosai Sootsu, who was famous for tutoring Masamune DATE..</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), Carkuni(id:79281), Tnm(id:58695), ゐ(id:795), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 果心居士(id:248111), R28Bot(id:177951), 松茸(id:27535), Yas(id:739), 青心(id:173433), Kamitani(id:30757), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>