<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>阿字観</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ajikan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ajikan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ajikan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>阿字観（あじかん）は、平安時代に空海によって伝えられた瞑想法。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;Ajikan&quot; refers to a method of meditation introduced by Kukai (Buddhist priest) during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;Ajikan&quot; refers to a method of meditation introduced by Kukai (a Buddhist priest) during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;Ajikan&quot; refers to a method of meditation introduced by Kukai (a Buddhist priest) during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>阿字観ヨーガ・密教ヨーガとも言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also referred as Ajikan Yoga, or Mikkyo (Esoteric Buddhism) Yoga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also referred to as Ajikan Yoga, or Mikkyo (Esoteric Buddhism) Yoga.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also referred to as Ajikan Yoga, or Mikkyo (Esoteric Buddhism) Yoga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>大日如来を表す梵字が月輪の中、蓮華の上に描かれた軸を見つめ、姿勢と呼吸を整え瞑想する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sitting with the back perfectly upright, breathing in a natural rhythmical way, practitioners meditate watching the Bonji (Sanskrit characters) which is a manifestation of Dainichi Nyorai (Mahavairocana) in the Gachirin (a perfect round circle meant to represent the full moon, and the Buddha&apos;s knowledge and virtue which are considered perfect and all-compassing) on a lotus flower painted on a hanging scroll.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sitting with the back perfectly upright, breathing in a natural rhythmical way, practitioners meditate while watching the Bonji (Sanskrit characters) which is a manifestation of Dainichi Nyorai (Mahavairocana) in the Gachirin (a perfect round circle meant to represent the full moon, and the Buddha&apos;s knowledge and virtue which are considered perfect and all-compassing) on a lotus flower painted on a hanging scroll.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;while&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sitting with the back perfectly upright, breathing in a natural rhythmical way, practitioners meditate while watching the Bonji (Sanskrit characters) which is a manifestation of Dainichi Nyorai (Mahavairocana) in the Gachirin (a perfect round circle meant to represent the full moon, and the Buddha&apos;s knowledge and virtue which are considered perfect and all-encompassing) on a lotus flower painted on a hanging scroll.</e>
<cmt>all-compassingを all-encompassingに変更しました（用語統一）。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>元々、真言宗の僧侶が鍛錬の方法として実践していたもので、真言寺院に伝えられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, Ajikan was practiced by monks of the Shingon sect as the method to refine the mind, and transmitted among the temples of the Shingon sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, Ajikan was practiced by monks of the Shingon sect as a method to refine the mind, and was transmitted among the temples of the Shingon sect.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, Ajikan was practiced by monks of the Shingon sect as a method to refine the mind, and was transmitted among the temples of the Shingon sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>トレーニングの瞑想法として、息数観、阿息観、月輪観がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meditative practice methods include Susokukan (Breath counting meditation), Asokukan (Breathing meditation), and Gachirinkan (Moon Disc meditation).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meditative practice methods include Susokukan (Breath counting meditation), Asokukan (Breathing meditation), and Gachirinkan (Moon Disc meditation).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meditative practice methods include Susokukan (Breath counting meditation), Asokukan (Breathing meditation), and Gachirinkan (Moon Disc meditation).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Dignaaga(id:91287), Izayohi(id:13095), Mait(id:73947), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Ikawa Hitoshi(id:117844), ウィキ豊(id:82961), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>