<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>弥勒菩薩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miroku Bosatsu, Maitreya Bodhisattva</e>
<cmt>http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110004872513/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miroku Bosatsu, Maitreya Bodhisattva</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miroku Bosatsu, Maitreya Bodhisattva</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>弥勒菩薩（みろくぼさつ）、サンスクリットマイトレーヤ (maitreya)は仏教の仏菩薩の一尊である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miroku Bosatsu, Maitreya Bodhisattva in Sanskrit, is one of the Buddhas of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miroku Bosatsu (Maitreya Bodhisattva in Sanskrit) is one of the Buddhas of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miroku Bosatsu (Maitreya Bodhisattva in Sanskrit) is one of the Buddhas of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>梵名を意訳して慈氏菩薩ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is called Jishi Bosatsu, translated Sanskrit name freely.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is called Jishi Bosatsu, as freely translated from the Sanskrit name.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is called Jishi Bosatsu, as freely translated from the Sanskrit name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>字は阿逸多 Ajita といい、無勝等と訳す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Azana (字), another name, is Ajita and is translated as 無勝等.</e>
<cmt>字→定訳不明、無勝等→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Azana (字), another name, is Ajita and is translated as 無勝等.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Azana (字), another name, is Ajita and is translated as 無勝等.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>インドの波羅奈（パラナシー）国に生まれ釈迦仏の化導を受け、未来に成仏するという記を与えられたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Varanasi of India, taught by Shakabutsu and was given a clarification to become Buddha in future.</e>
<cmt>波羅奈（パラナシー）国→http://www.sgilibrary.org/search_dict.php?id=2576</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Varanasi, India, studied under Shakabutsu and was given a clarification to become Buddha in the future.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Varanasi, India, studied under Shakabutsu and was given a clarification to become Buddha in the future.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>三昧耶形は蓮華上の塔、賢瓶(水瓶)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanmayagyo Symbol is a tower on lotus and a wise bottle (suihei, a small water bottle.)</e>
<cmt>三昧耶形→http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110004644722/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The symbol of Sanmayagyo is a tower on a lotus and a wise bottle (suihei, a small water bottle).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The symbol of Sanmayagyo is a tower on a lotus and a wise bottle (suihei, a small water bottle).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>種子 (密教)（種字）はユ(yu)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shushi, Shuji, Bija in Mikkyo is yu.</e>
<cmt>種子（種字）→http://opac.ndl.go.jp/articleid/10189239/jpn</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shushi, Shuji, Bija in Mikkyo is yu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shushi, Shuji, Bija in Mikkyo is yu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>未来仏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Future Buddha</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Future Buddha</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Future Buddha</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>弥勒はゴータマ・シッダールタ（釈迦牟尼仏、現在仏）の次に仏陀となることが約束された菩薩で、ゴータマ・シッダールタの入滅後56億7千万年後の未来に姿をあらわし多くの人々を救済するとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miroku, Maitreya is a Bosatsu who is promised to be Buddha next to Gotama Siddhattha (Shakamuni-butsu, Buddha at present) and is said that he appears in future 5670 million years after Gotama Siddhartha&apos;s demise and relieve many people.</e>
<cmt>弥勒→英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miroku (Maitreya) is a Bosatsu who is promised to become Buddha next to Gotama Siddhartha (Shakamuni-butsu, Buddha at present); it is said that he appears in the future 5670 million years after Gotama Siddhartha&apos;s demise and will bring relief to many people.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miroku (Maitreya) is a Bosatsu who is promised to become Buddha next to Gotama Siddhartha (Shakamuni-butsu, Buddha at present); it is said that he appears in the future 5670 million years after Gotama Siddhartha&apos;s demise and will bring relief to many people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>現在は、兜率天で修行（あるいは説法）しているといわれ、中国・朝鮮半島・日本では、弥勒菩薩の兜率天に往生しようと願う信仰（上生信仰）が流行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he is on ascetic training (or preaches) at Tosotsuten at present and the faith for going to Tosotsuten of Miroku Bosatsu (上生信仰) after death was popular in China, Korea and Japan.</e>
<cmt>上生信仰→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he is presently in ascetic training (or that he preaches) at Tosotsuten; the belief in going to Tosotsuten of Miroku Bosatsu (上生信仰) after death was popular in China, Korea and Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he is presently in ascetic training (or that he preaches) at Tosotsuten; the belief in going to Tosotsuten of Miroku Bosatsu (上生信仰) after death was popular in China, Korea and Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>一般に弥勒の下生は56億7千万年後とされているが、この気の遠くなる年数は、弥勒の兜卒天での寿命は4000年であり、兜卒天の1日は地上の400年に匹敵するという説から、下生までに4000×400×360＝5億7600万年かかるという計算に由来する（後代に5億7600万年が56億7000万年に入れ替わったと考えられている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally it is believed that Miroku appears 5670 million years later; these enormous years come from following calculating formula, 4000×400×360＝576000000, by a belief that the life of Miroku at Tosotsuten is 4000 years and a day at Tosotsuten equals to 400 years in this world (it is thought that 576000000 years changed to 5670000000 years in later age.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, it is believed that Miroku appears 5670 million years later; such enormous years originating from the formula 4000×400×360＝576000000, based on the belief that the life of Miroku at Tosotsuten is 4000 years and a day at Tosotsuten equals 400 years in this world (it is thought that 576000000 years changed to 5670000000 years during a later age).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, it is believed that Miroku appears 5670 million years later; such enormous years originating from the formula 4000×400×360＝576000000, based on the belief that the life of Miroku at Tosotsuten is 4000 years and a day at Tosotsuten equals 400 years in this world (it is thought that 576000000 years changed to 5670000000 years during a later age).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>他の古い仏教の経典では3000年後説もあり、その未来仏の出現する時代は厳密には定かではなく「遠い未来」の比喩ではないかとの説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The other old Buddhism sutra describes that he appears 3000 years later so that the time when future Buddha appears is not sure in a precise sense, and another thesis says it is a metaphor for &apos;the distant future.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The other old Buddhism sutra asserts that he appears 3000 years later, so that the time when future Buddha appears is not certain in a precise sense; another thesis claims it&apos;s a metaphor for &apos;the distant future.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The other old Buddhism sutra asserts that he appears 3000 years later, so that the time when future Buddha appears is not certain in a precise sense; another thesis claims it&apos;s a metaphor for &apos;the distant future.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>弥勒菩薩はバラモンとして娑婆世界に出世して、シッダールタ同様に出家したのち竜華樹下(りゅうげじゅ)で悟りを得て、三度にわたり説法を行い多くの人々を救うという（これを竜華三会という）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Miroku Bosatsu appears as Brahman in this corrupt world, gets an enlightenment under Ryuge-ju tree (竜華樹) after becoming a priest in the same way as Siddhattha and reliefs people by preach three times (this is called Ryuge-sankai, three preaches at Ryuge.)</e>
<cmt>竜華樹→定訳不明、http://dictionary.goo.ne.jp/leaf/jn/203345/m0u/%E7%AB%9C%E8%8F%AF%E6%A8%B9/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Miroku Bosatsu appears as Brahman in this corrupt world, obtains enlightenment under the Ryuge-ju tree (竜華樹) after becoming a priest in the same way as Siddhartha, and brings people relief by preaching three times (which is called Ryuge-sankai, the three sermons at Ryuge).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Miroku Bosatsu appears as Brahman in this corrupt world, obtains enlightenment under the Ryuge-ju tree (竜華樹) after becoming a priest in the same way as Siddhartha, and brings people relief by preaching three times (which is called Ryuge-sankai, the three sermons at Ryuge).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>『弥勒下生経』には、初会96億、二会94億、三会92億の衆生を済度すると説いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a discription in &quot;Maitreyavyakaranas&quot; that he reliefs 9.6 billion people in the first time, 9.4 billion people in the second time and 9.2 billion people in the third time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a description in &quot;Maitreyavyakaranas&quot; that he brings relief to 9.6 billion people the first time, 9.4 billion people the second time and 9.2 billion people the third time.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a description in &quot;Maitreyavyakaranas&quot; that he brings relief to 9.6 billion people the first time, 9.4 billion people the second time and 9.2 billion people the third time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>なお、56億7千万年後の下生の姿を先取りして弥勒如来、弥勒仏と呼ばれることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, he is called Miroku-nyorai or Miroku-butsu by taking in advance the figure of appearance 5670million years later in some cases.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, he is called Miroku-nyorai or Miroku-butsu by taking in advance the figure of appearance 5670 million years later in some cases.</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, he is called Miroku-nyorai or Miroku-butsu by taking in advance the figure of appearance 5670 million years later in some cases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>東大寺の「試みの大仏」と呼ばれる像は高さ40cm足らずの小像ながら、ずっしりとした質感を持つ「弥勒如来坐像」（木造）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The statue called &apos;Great Buddha of trial&apos; of Todai-ji Temple, is &apos;the seated statue of Miroku-nyorai (wooden figure)&apos;, which is small, less than 40cm high, but looks heavy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The statue called &apos;Great Buddha of Trial&apos; at Todai-ji Temple is &apos;the seated statue of Miroku-nyorai (wooden figure)&apos;, which is small at less than 40 cm high, but it looks heavy.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The statue called &apos;Great Buddha of Trial&apos; at Todai-ji Temple is &apos;the seated statue of Miroku-nyorai (wooden figure)&apos;, which is small at less than 40 cm high, but it looks heavy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>弥勒信仰には、上生信仰とともに、下生信仰も存在し、中国においては、こちらの信仰の方が流行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the faith for Miroku, there are 下生信仰 as well as 上生信仰, and the former was more popular in China.</e>
<cmt>下生信仰→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the faith for Miroku, there are 下生信仰 as well as 上生信仰, and the former was more popular in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the faith for Miroku, there are 下生信仰 as well as 上生信仰, and the former was more popular in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>下生信仰とは、弥勒菩薩の兜率天に上生を願う上生信仰に対し、弥勒如来の下生が56億7千万年の未来ではなく現に「今」なされるからそれに備えなければならないという信仰である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While 上生信仰 is a wish to relive again at Tosotsuten of Miroku Bosatsu, 下生信仰 is a faith that we have to be ready for Miroku Bosatsu&apos;s appearance &apos;at present&apos; rather than in 5670million years future.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While 上生信仰 is a wish to be relieved again at Tosotsuten of Miroku Bosatsu, 下生信仰 is the faith that we have to be ready for Miroku Bosatsu&apos;s appearance &apos;at present&apos; rather than 5670 million years in the future.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While 上生信仰 is a wish to be relieved again at Tosotsuten of Miroku Bosatsu, 下生信仰 is the faith that we have to be ready for Miroku Bosatsu&apos;s appearance &apos;at present&apos; rather than 5670 million years in the future.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>浄土信仰に類した上生信仰に対して、下生信仰の方は、弥勒下生に合わせて現世を変革しなければならないという終末論、救世主待望論的な要素が強い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As opposed to 上生信仰 which is similar to the Pure Land Faith, 下生信仰 is a kind of eschatology and a hope for savior&apos;s appearance such as this world should be changed in accordance with Miroku&apos;s appearance (下生.)</e>
<cmt>浄土信仰→http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110002660867/、下生→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As opposed to 上生信仰, which is similar to the Pure Land Faith, 下生信仰 is a kind of eschatology and a hope for the savior&apos;s appearance such as that this world should be changed in accordance with Miroku&apos;s appearance (下生).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As opposed to 上生信仰, which is similar to the Pure Land Faith, 下生信仰 is a kind of eschatology and a hope for the savior&apos;s appearance such as that this world should be changed in accordance with Miroku&apos;s appearance (下生).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>そのため、反体制の集団に利用される、あるいは、下生信仰の集団が反体制化する、という例が、各時代に数多く見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, there were many examples in each period that 下生信仰 was utilized by dissident groups or 下生信仰 groups became antiestablishment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason there were many examples in each period where 下生信仰 was utilized by dissident groups or 下生信仰 groups became anti-establishment.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason there were many examples in each period where 下生信仰 was utilized by dissident groups or 下生信仰 groups became anti-establishment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>北魏の大乗の乱や、北宋・南宋・元 (王朝)・明・清の白蓮教が、その代表である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">大乗の乱 of the northern Wei dynasty and Byakuren sect in the northern song dynasty, the Southern Sungs,Yuan,Ming Dynasty and Qing Dynasty were good examples for them.</e>
<cmt>大乗の乱→定訳不明、北宋、南宋→Webster Online Dictionary、元（王朝）、清→英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">大乗の乱 of the northern Wei dynasty and Byakuren sect in the northern Sung dynasty, the southern Sung, the Yuan, the Ming dynasty and the Qing dynasty were good examples of them.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">大乗の乱 of the northern Wei dynasty and Byakuren sect in the northern Sung dynasty, the southern Sung, the Yuan, the Ming dynasty and the Qing dynasty were good examples of them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="20">
<j>日本でも戦国時代 (日本)に、弥勒仏がこの世に出現するという信仰が流行し、ユートピアである「弥勒仏の世」の現世への出現が期待された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the age of civil war in Japan, the faith that Miroku Bosatsu would appear in this world was popular and the appearance of &apos;the world of Miroku-butsu&apos; as Utopia in this world was expected.</e>
<cmt>戦国時代→Webster Online Dictionary</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the age of civil war in Japan, the faith that Miroku Bosatsu would appear in this world was popular and the appearance of &apos;the world of Miroku-butsu&apos; as Utopia in this world was expected.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the age of civil war in Japan, the faith that Miroku Bosatsu would appear in this world was popular and the appearance of &apos;the world of Miroku-butsu&apos; as Utopia in this world was expected.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>一種のメシアニズムであるが、弥勒を穀霊とし、弥勒の世を稲の豊熟した平和な世界であるとする農耕民族的観念が強い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it is a kind of messianism, it shows a strong idea of agricultural people which considers Miroku as a spirit of grain and that the world of Miroku is a peaceful world with good harvest of rice.</e>
<cmt>メシアニズム→http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=%E3%83%A1%E3%82%B7%E3%82%A2%E3%83%8B%E3%82%BA%E3%83%A0&amp;stype=0&amp;dtype=0</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is a kind of messianism, it shows the strong idea of an agricultural people that considers Miroku as a spirit of grain and that the world of Miroku is a peaceful world with a good harvest of rice.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is a kind of messianism, it shows the strong idea of an agricultural people that considers Miroku as a spirit of grain and that the world of Miroku is a peaceful world with a good harvest of rice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>この観念を軸とし、東方海上から弥勒船の到来するという信仰が、弥勒踊りなどの形で太平洋沿岸部に展開した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on this idea, a belief that Miroku ship came from the Eastern sea spread at the coastal areas of the Pacific Ocean, which can be seen as a style of Miroku Odori Dance (弥勒踊り.)</e>
<cmt>弥勒踊り→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on this idea, the belief that Miroku&apos;s ship came from the Eastern sea spread along the coastal areas of the Pacific Ocean, which can be seen as a style of the Miroku Odori dance (弥勒踊り).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on this idea, the belief that Miroku&apos;s ship came from the Eastern sea spread along the coastal areas of the Pacific Ocean, which can be seen as a style of the Miroku Odori dance (弥勒踊り).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>江戸時代には富士信仰とも融合し、元禄年間に富士講の行者、食行身禄が活動している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Edo Period, it was mixed with the faith for Fuji and trainees of Fyji-ko and Jikigyo Miroku were seen from 1688 to 1703.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo period it was mixed with the faith for Fuji, and trainees of Fyji-ko and Jikigyo Miroku were seen from 1688 to 1703.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period it was mixed with the faith for Fuji, and trainees of Fuji-ko and Jikigyo Miroku were seen from 1688 to 1703.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>また百姓一揆、特に世直し一揆の中に、弥勒思想の強い影響があることが指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it is pointed out that peasant&apos;s revolt, especially revolt for social reform, was influenced by Miroku faith strongly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, it is pointed out that peasant revolts, particularly the revolt for social reform, was strongly influenced by the Miroku faith.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, it is pointed out that peasant revolts, particularly the revolt for social reform, was strongly influenced by the Miroku faith.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="25">
<j>観弥勒菩薩上生兜率天経、弥勒下生経、弥勒大成仏経 の3本で弥勒三部経と呼ぶことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">観弥勒菩薩上生兜率天経, Maitreyavyakaranas, 弥勒大成仏経 are called Miroku sanbukyo in some cases.</e>
<cmt>観弥勒菩薩上生兜率天経、弥勒大成仏経→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">観弥勒菩薩上生兜率天経, Maitreyavyakaranas, 弥勒大成仏経 are in some cases called Miroku sanbukyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">観弥勒菩薩上生兜率天経, Maitreyavyakaranas, 弥勒大成仏経 are in some cases called Miroku sanbukyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>また、浄土宗系の無量寿経 には、阿弥陀仏の本願を後世の苦悩の衆生に説き聞かせるようにと、釈迦牟尼仏から弥勒菩薩に付属されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, in Muryoju-kyo Sutra of Jodo sect Shakamuni-butsu asked Miroku Bosatsu to preach Hongwan (本願) of Amitabha Buddha against people in anguish of later age.</e>
<cmt>阿弥陀仏→英辞郎 on the WEB、本願→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, in the Muryoju-kyo sutra of the Jodo sect, Shakamuni-butsu asked Miroku Bosatsu to preach the Hongwan (本願) of Amitabha Buddha against people in anguish of a later age.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, in the Muryoju-kyo sutra of the Jodo sect, Shakamuni-butsu asked Miroku Bosatsu to preach the Hongwan (本願) of Amitabha Buddha against people in anguish of a later age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="27">
<j>仏教の中に未来仏としての弥勒菩薩が登場するのはかなり早く、すでに阿含経 に記述が見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miroku Bosatsu appears as future Buddha at the very early stage of Buddhism and is described in Agon-kyo Sutra.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miroku Bosatsu appears as a future Buddha at the very early stage of Buddhism, and is described in the Agon-kyo sutra.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miroku Bosatsu appears as a future Buddha at the very early stage of Buddhism, and is described in the Agon-kyo sutra.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>この未来仏の概念は過去七仏から発展して生まれたものと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The idea of future Buddha is thought to be developed from the idea of past seven Buddhas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The concept of a future Buddha is thought to have developed from that of the &quot;past seven Buddhas.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The concept of a future Buddha is thought to have developed from that of the &quot;past seven Buddhas.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>唯識論師</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Master of Vijnaptimatra</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Master of Vijnaptimatra</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Master of Vijnaptimatra</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>300年前後に、インドの瑜伽行唯識学派の論師として唯識説を説く開祖の一人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the founders of Yogacaravada of India who preached Vijnaptimatra around 300.</e>
<cmt>瑜伽行唯識学派→http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110002661463/、唯識説→http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110004708407/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was one of the founders of Yogacaravada, of India, who preached Vijnaptimatra around 300.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was one of the founders of Yogacaravada, of India, who preached Vijnaptimatra around 300.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>後世の伝説によって、前述の未来仏としての弥勒菩薩と同一視された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was regarded as the same person as Miroku Bosatsu, above future Buddha, by a legend of later age.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was considered to be the same person as Miroku Bosatsu (mentioned above as a future Buddha) in a legend of a later age.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was considered to be the same person as Miroku Bosatsu (mentioned above as a future Buddha) in a legend of a later age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>著作に『瑜伽師地論』、『大乗荘厳経論』、『中弁分別論』、『現観荘厳論』、『法法性弁別論』などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His works are &quot;Yugashijiron&quot;, &quot;Daijo-shougonkyoron&quot;,&quot;中弁分別論&quot;,&quot;現観荘厳論&quot;,&quot;法法性弁別論&quot;, and so on.</e>
<cmt>『瑜伽師地論』→http://www.bdk.or.jp/activity/list.html#list064、『大乗荘厳経論』→Yahoo辞書、『中弁分別論』、『現観荘厳論』、『法法性弁別論』→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His works are &quot;Yugashijiron,&quot; &quot;Daijo-shougonkyoron,&quot; &quot;中弁分別論,&quot;&quot;現観荘厳論,&quot; &quot;法法性弁別論,&quot; and so on.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His works are &quot;Yugashijiron,&quot; &quot;Daijo-shougonkyoron,&quot; &quot;中弁分別論,&quot;&quot;現観荘厳論,&quot; &quot;法法性弁別論,&quot; and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="32">
<j>チベットでは、瑜伽師地論は無着菩薩造となっており、究竟一乗宝性論が弥勒菩薩造となっているが、漢訳では堅慧造としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Tibet it is said that Yugashijiron is made by Muchaku Bosatsu and Kukyoichijohoshoron is made by Miroku Bosatsu, while it is regarded to be made by Kenne Bosatsu (堅慧) in a translation of Chinese.</e>
<cmt>堅慧→定訳不明、http://www.kanji.zinbun.kyoto-u.ac.jp/~wittern/can/can4/aut/aut00292.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Tibet it is said that Yugashijiron is made by Muchaku Bosatsu and Kukyoichijohoshoron is made by Miroku Bosatsu, while it is regarded to be made by Kenne Bosatsu (堅慧) in a translation of Chinese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Tibet it is said that Yugashijiron is made by Muchaku Bosatsu and Kukyoichijohoshoron is made by Miroku Bosatsu, while it is regarded to be made by Kenne Bosatsu (堅慧) in a translation of Chinese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>ミスラ神との関係</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Relationship with ミスラ神</e>
<cmt>ミスラ神→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Relationship with ミスラ神</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Relationship with ミスラ神</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="33">
<j>弥勒菩薩は、西アジアで崇められた太陽神ミスラが仏教に取り入れられ、菩薩として信仰されたものとする説もあり、その救世主的性格はここに由来するという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is another thesis that Miroku Bosatsu was created by incorporating the sun god ミスラ who had been admired in Western Asia and believed as Bosatsu, so that its character as savior stemmed from this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another thesis asserts that Miroku Bosatsu was created by incorporating the sun god ミスラ, who had been admired in Western Asia and believed in as Bosatsu, so that its character as the savior stemmed from this.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another thesis asserts that Miroku Bosatsu was created by incorporating the sun god ミスラ, who had been admired in Western Asia and believed in as Bosatsu, so that its character as the savior stemmed from this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="34">
<j>ミスラはインド神話におけるアーディティヤ神群の一柱ミトラと起源を同じくし、古くは古代アーリアにおいて信仰されていた契約の神だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ミスラ has the same origin as Mitra which is one of the gods of Aditya (アーディティヤ神群) in Indian myth and was a god of contract who was admired in ancient Aryan.</e>
<cmt>アーディティヤ神群→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ミスラ has the same origin as Mitra, which is one of the gods of Aditya (アーディティヤ神群) in Indian mythology and was a god of contracts who was admired in the ancient Aryan civilization.</e>
<cmt>punctuation; Mithra is of Persian origin</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">ミスラ has the same origin as Mitra, which is one of the gods of Aditya (アーディティヤ神群) in Indian mythology and was a god of contracts who was admired in the ancient Aryan civilization.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>ゾロアスター教においては中級神ヤザタの一柱とされ、英雄神、太陽神として重要な役割を持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Zoroastrianism it is one of the gods of middle class god, Yazata, and has an important role as hero and the sun god.</e>
<cmt>ゾロアスター教→定訳不明、ヤザタ→http://home.att.ne.jp/gamma/dug/sinmei/ya.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Zoroastrianism it is one of the middle-class gods, Yazata, and it has an important role as a hero and sun god.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Zoroastrianism it is one of the middle-class gods, Yazata, and it has an important role as a hero and sun god.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>また、古代ギリシャ・ローマにおいてはミトラースと呼ばれ、太陽神・英雄神として崇められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, in ancient Greece and Roma, it was called ミトラース and admired as the sun god and hero.</e>
<cmt>ミトラース→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, in ancient Greece and Rome it was called ミトラース and was admired as the sun god and a hero.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, in ancient Greece and Rome it was called ミトラース and was admired as the sun god and a hero.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>ミスラはクシャーナ朝ではバクトリア語形のミイロ(Miiro)と呼ばれ、この語形が弥勒の語源になったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kusana, ミスラ was called Miiro, which was Bactrian, and it is thought that this form of a word became the origin of Miroku.</e>
<cmt>クシャーナ朝→http://www.tcat.ne.jp/~eden/Hst/dic/kusana.html、バクトリア語→http://www.gengo.l.u-tokyo.ac.jp/~hkum/bactri_j.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kusana, ミスラ was called Miiro, a name of Bactrian origin, and it is thought that this form of the word became the origin of Miroku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kusana, ミスラ was called Miiro, a name of Bactrian origin, and it is thought that this form of the word became the origin of Miroku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>ミイロの神格は太陽神であるということ以外不明であるが、定方晟はマニ教の影響なども考慮して、救世主的側面があったのではないかと推測している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Miiro&apos;s character as god is not known except the sun god, Akira SADATAKA guesses that it had a character as savoir, considering the influence by Manichaeism.</e>
<cmt>定方晟→http://www6.plala.or.jp/Djehuti/508.htm、マニ教→Webster Online Dictionary</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Miiro&apos;s character as a god is not known other than as the sun god, Akira SADATAKA assumes that it had a character as a savoir, considering the influence of Manichaeism.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Miiro&apos;s character as a god is not known other than as the sun god, Akira SADATAKA assumes that it had a character as a savoir, considering the influence of Manichaeism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="39">
<j>弥勒の梵名「マイトレーヤ」は、ミスラ神の名と語源を同じくする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miroku&apos;s Sanskrit name &apos;Maitreya&apos; has the same origin as the name of ミスラ神.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miroku&apos;s Sanskrit name &apos;Maitreya&apos; has the same origin as the name of ミスラ神.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miroku&apos;s Sanskrit name &apos;Maitreya&apos; has the same origin as the name of ミスラ神.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>「mitra/miθra」は本来「契約」というほどの意味だが、後には転じて契約によって結ばれた親密な関係にある「盟友」をも意味するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitra/miθra&apos; originally meant only &apos; contract&apos; but changed to mean &apos;a sworn friend&apos; with an intimate relationship by contract later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitra/miθra&apos; originally meant only &apos;contract&apos; but later meant &apos;a sworn friend&apos; with an intimate relationship by contract.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitra/miθra&apos; originally meant only &apos;contract&apos; but later meant &apos;a sworn friend&apos; with an intimate relationship by contract.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>マイトレーヤはその派生形容詞/名詞で「友好的な、友情に厚い、慈悲深い(者)」の意味となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maitreya means &apos;amicable, friendly and merciful (person)&apos; in its derived adjective and noun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maitreya means &apos;amicable, friendly and merciful (person)&apos; in its derived adjective and noun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maitreya means &apos;amicable, friendly and merciful (person)&apos; in its derived adjective and noun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="42">
<j>ミルク神</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Milk god</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Milk god</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Milk god</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>沖縄では、「ミルク神」、「ミルクさん」と呼び、弥勒信仰が盛んである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Okinawa Miroku Bosatsu is called &apos;Milk god&apos; or &apos;Milk-san&apos;, and the belief of Mitoku is popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Okinawa Miroku Bosatsu is called &apos;the milk god&apos; or &apos;Milk-san&apos;, and the belief of Mitoku is popular.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Okinawa Miroku Bosatsu is called &apos;the milk god&apos; or &apos;Milk-san,&apos; and the belief in Miｒoku is popular.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="44">
<j>祭りでは、笑顔のミルク仮面をつけたミルク神が歩き回る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a festival, Milk god who put a mask of Milk walks around with a smile.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a festival, the milk god who wears a mask of milk walks around with a smile.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a festival, the milk god who wears a mask of milk walks around with a smile.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="45">
<j>弥勒菩薩の化身とされた布袋尊との関係が指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is pointed out to have a relation with Hotei-son which was considered as an incarnation of Miroku Bosatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is pointed out as being related to Hotei-son, which was considered to be an incarnation of Miroku Bosatsu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is pointed out as being related to Hotei-son, which was considered to be an incarnation of Miroku Bosatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>仏像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Statues of Miroku Bosatsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Statues of Miroku Bosatsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Statues of Miroku Bosatsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="46">
<j>弥勒菩薩像はインドでは水瓶を手にする像として造形されたが、中国においては、唐までは足を交差させ椅子に座る像として造像され、元明時代以降は弥勒の化身とされた布袋として肥満形で表された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While in India Miroku Bosatsu was shaped as a statue having suihei in his hand, in China it was shaped as seated statue with crossing legs on a chair until Tang and showed as a corpulent figure of Hotei, an incarnation of Miroku after Yuan and Ming Dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While in India Miroku Bosatsu was shaped as a statue having suihei in his hand, in China it was shaped as a statue sitting cross-legged on a chair until the Tang and was shown as a corpulent figure of Hotei, an incarnation of Miroku after the Yuan and Ming dynasties.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While in India Miroku Bosatsu was shaped as a statue having suihei in his hand, in China it was shaped as a statue sitting cross-legged on a chair until the Tang and was shown as a corpulent figure of Hotei, an incarnation of Miroku after the Yuan and Ming dynasties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>一方、飛鳥時代の日本では半跏思惟像として造像が行なわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, during Asuka Period in Japan it was shaped as a hanka-shiyui image (半跏思惟像.)</e>
<cmt>半跏思惟像→定訳不明、http://kaiwai.city.kyoto.jp/search/view_sight.php?ManageCode=1000073&amp;InforKindCode=4</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, during the Asuka period in Japan it was shaped as a hanka-shiyui image (半跏思惟像).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, during the Asuka period in Japan it was shaped as a hanka-shiyui image (半跏思惟像).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>椅坐して左足を下ろし、右足を上げて左膝上に置き、右手で頬づえを付いて瞑想する姿である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a figure meditating with right foot on left knee and right arm softly on the cheek, seated on a chair.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a figure meditating with the right foot on the left knee and the right hand softly on the cheek, being seated on a chair.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a figure meditating with the right foot on the left knee and the right hand softly on the cheek, being seated on a chair.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>大阪・野中寺の金銅像（重文）が「弥勒菩薩」という銘文をもつ最古の半跏思惟像である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The gold and bronze statue of Yachu-ji Temple in Osaka (important cultural property) is the oldest hanka-shiyui image which has an inscription of &apos;Miroku Bosatsu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>野中寺→http://www.kiis.or.jp/kansaida/habikino/habikino15.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The gold-and-bronze statue of Yachu-ji Temple in Osaka (an important cultural property) is the oldest hanka-shiyui image having the inscription &apos;Miroku Bosatsu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The gold-and-bronze statue of Yachu-ji Temple in Osaka (an important cultural property) is the oldest hanka-shiyui image having the inscription &apos;Miroku Bosatsu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>京都の広隆寺の弥勒菩薩像（木像）は特によく知られており、国宝に指定されている（→弥勒菩薩半跏思惟像）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Miroku Bosatsu statue of Koryu-ji Temple in Kyoto (a wooden statue) is especially known and designated as a national treasure (see Bangasayusang.)</e>
<cmt>弥勒菩薩半跏思惟像→http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bangasayusang</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Miroku Bosatsu statue of Koryu-ji Temple in Kyoto (a wooden statue) is especially well known and is designated as a national treasure (see Bangasayusang).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Miroku Bosatsu statue of Koryu-ji Temple in Kyoto (a wooden statue) is especially well known and is designated as a national treasure (see Bangasayusang).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>ただし、半跏思惟像だからといって弥勒菩薩像であるとは限らない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, a hanka-shiyui image is not always a statue of Miroku Bosatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, a hanka-shiyui image is not always a statue of Miroku Bosatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, a hanka-shiyui image is not always a statue of Miroku Bosatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>平安時代・鎌倉時代には、半跏思惟像は見られなくなり、立像や坐像として表されるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Heian and Kamakura Period any hanka-shiyui image was not seen and standing or seated images were produced.</e>
<cmt>鎌倉時代→英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Heian and Kamakura periods, no hanka-shiyui image would be seen, but standing or seated images were produced.</e>
<cmt>logic</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Heian and Kamakura periods, no hanka-shiyui image would be seen, but standing or seated images were produced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>京都・醍醐寺の快慶作の木像などがその作例である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The wooden statue of Daigo-ji Temple in Kyoto made by Kaikei is its good example.</e>
<cmt>醍醐寺→http://www.daigoji.or.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The wooden statue of Daigo-ji Temple in Kyoto, made by Kaikei, is a good example.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The wooden statue of Daigo-ji Temple in Kyoto, made by Kaikei, is a good example.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="54">
<j>弥勒如来像としては、前述の奈良の東大寺の木像（通称「試みの大仏」）（重文）や、当麻寺金堂の塑像（奈良時代、国宝）、興福寺北円堂の運慶一門作の木像（国宝）などが知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The statues of Miroku Nyorai such as the wooden statue of Todai-ji Temple in Nara (known as &apos;Great Buddha of trial&apos;) (important cultural property) mentioned above, and the statue of Taima-dera Temple Kondo (made in Nara Period, national treasure), and the wooden statue shaped by Unkei group of Kofuku-ji Temple Hokuendo (national treasure) are known.</e>
<cmt>北円堂→yahoo辞書</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The statues of Miroku Nyorai, such as the wooden statue of Todai-ji Temple in Nara (known as the &apos;Great Buddha of Trial,&apos; an important cultural property) mentioned above, and the statue of Taima-dera Temple Kondo (made during the Nara period and now a national treasure) and the wooden statue shaped by the Unkei group of Kofuku-ji Temple Hokuendo (a national treasure) are known.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The statues of Miroku Nyorai, such as the wooden statue of Todai-ji Temple in Nara (known as the &apos;Great Buddha of Trial,&apos; an important cultural property) mentioned above, and the statue of Taima-dera Temple Kondo (made during the Nara period and now a national treasure) and the wooden statue shaped by the Unkei group of Kofuku-ji Temple Hokuendo (a national treasure) are known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>真言</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mantra, Shingon</e>
<cmt>英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mantra, Shingon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mantra, Shingon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="55">
<j>オン・マイタレイヤ・ソワカ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">オン・マイタレイヤ・ソワカ</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">オン・マイタレイヤ・ソワカ</e>
<cmt>NOT TRANSLATED</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aum Maitreya svaahaa</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>布袋像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The statue of Hotei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The statue of Hotei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The statue of Hotei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="56">
<j>日本では七福神の一人として知られる布袋尊和尚は、中国では、弥勒の化身とされ、下生した弥勒如来として仏堂の正面にその破顔と太鼓腹で膝を崩した風姿のまま祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A preist Hotei-son, who is known as one of the seven deities of good luck in Japan, is considered as an incarnation of Miroku in China and enshrined with a relaxed figure of a smile and fat stomach as Miroku Nyorai appeared in this world at the front of Buddhism hall.</e>
<cmt>七福神→Webster Online Dictionary</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The priest Hotei-son, who is known in Japan as one of the seven deities of good luck, is considered to be an incarnation of Miroku in China; he is enshrined and depicted as a relaxed figure with a smile and a fat stomach, as Miroku Nyorai appeared in this world at the front of the Buddhist hall.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The priest Hotei-son, who is known in Japan as one of the seven deities of good luck, is considered to be an incarnation of Miroku in China; he is enshrined and depicted as a relaxed figure with a smile and a fat stomach, as Miroku Nyorai appeared in this world at the front of the Buddhist hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 JAnDbot(id:66507), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), KMT(id:1772), Mait(id:73947), Urania(id:7213), Charenji(id:7908), Eskimbot(id:29676), Wei Yuan(id:13342), Katekate(id:95362), PipepBot(id:146181), Akiyoshi&apos;s Room(id:146283), るがこむ(id:181), Opponent(id:720), Jugger90(id:17088), Snow steed(id:9428), らりた(id:1327), ReijiYamashina(id:29567), Ｍ．Ｇ(id:27945), Kwjbot(id:191419), 興梠健(id:40000), Riku(id:16088), Ko-ken(id:49348), くっちゃめ(id:86793), うぃき野郎(id:53567), 斉藤一(id:141943), あお。(id:39226), Chobot(id:20846), マイコン坊主(id:338), 無空(id:17049), FlaBot(id:30804), Calvero(id:38360), Izayohi(id:13095), Toroia(id:31889), Peehyoro Acala(id:170), とらでじこ(id:11570), Enthousiasme(id:42600), Maris stella(id:10043), Stanislaus(id:1806), ラスト番長(id:188377), PixelBot(id:166734), Tomos(id:10), Setu(id:88), 256(id:11889), Trisahasra(id:160332), Fryed-peach(id:63402), Rusk(id:9895), Thijs!bot(id:69644), Mooko(id:36162), 唯(id:15499), Boca samba(id:137526), YurikBot(id:18605), Fromm(id:71291), Αιων(id:93884), Adacom(id:303), Mitra(id:15447), Jedi(id:732), Louperibot(id:128971), Suisui(id:69), SieBot(id:126695), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>