<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>衆徒</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shuto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shuto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shuto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>衆徒（しゅと）は、堂衆（どうしゅ/どうしゅう）とも呼ばれ、本来は平安時代以後に大寺院に居住して学問・修行の他に寺内の運営実務にあたった僧侶身分のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;shuto,&quot; which is also called &quot;doshu,&quot; refers to a status of the priest who originally resided in a big temple and was in charge of management and practical business of the temple as well as studying and practicing ascetic trainings after the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;shuto,&quot; for which &quot;doshu&quot; is also used, is a term from after the Heian period that referred to the status of a priest who originally resided in a big temple and was in charge of the management and practical business of the temple as well as studying and practicing ascetic training.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;shuto,&quot; for which &quot;doshu&quot; is also used, is a term from after the Heian period that referred to the status of a priest who originally resided in a big temple and was in charge of the management and practical business of the temple as well as studying and practicing ascetic training.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>大衆_(仏教)の主力であり、衆徒のみを指して「大衆」と呼ぶ場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the main force of daishu (Buddhism) and in some cases the term &quot;daishu&quot; refers to only shuto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the main force of daishu (Buddhism), and in some cases the term &quot;daishu&quot; refers only to shuto.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was the main force of daishu (Buddhism), and in some cases the term &apos;daishu&apos; refers only to shuto.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>特に興福寺が守護職を務めた大和国では、国内の武士を自寺の衆徒として組み入れたために同国の武士（大和武士（やまとぶし））を指して衆徒と呼ぶ場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since in the Yamato Province, where the Kofuku-ji Temple was in charge of shugoshiki (post of provincial constable), it incorporated warriors as its own shuto, some people call the warrior in the Yamato Province (Yamato warrior) as &quot;shuto.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because in Yamato Province, where Kofuku-ji Temple was in charge of shugoshiki (post of the provincial constable), it incorporated warriors as its own shuto, some people refer to the warrior in Yamato Province (Yamato warrior) as &quot;shuto.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because in Yamato Province, where Kofuku-ji Temple was in charge of shugoshiki (post of the provincial constable), it incorporated warriors as its own shuto, some people refer to the warrior in Yamato Province (Yamato warrior) as shuto.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>一般的に学侶よりも下位、行人_(仏教)よりも上位とされ、寺院内の警備や管理運営などの実務なども扱った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally it was regarded lower than Gakuryo (studying monk) and higher than Gyonin (practitioner of austerities in mountains) and put in charge of practical business including security and administrative operation of the temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally it was regarded as being lower than Gakuryo (studying monk) but higher than Gyonin (practitioner of austerities in mountains) and was put in charge of practical business, including the security and administrative operation of the temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally it was regarded as being lower than Gakuryo (studying monk) but higher than Gyonin (practitioner of austerities in mountains) and was put in charge of practical business, including the security and administrative operation of the temple.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>中下級の貴族や武家・荘官などの出身者が多かったため、武術などの心得を持つものもあり、武装化して僧兵を構成したのもこの身分が中心であった（ただし、延暦寺では衆徒をより上級貴族出身が占め、このクラスや衆徒から放逐された者達が別に「堂衆」を組織するなど、寺院ごとに組織のあり方に違いがあった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many shuto were from aristocracy of the middle and low classes, samurai family and shokan (an officer governing shoen (manor)), some of whom were good at martial art, and as a result, they made up a large share of Sohei (priest soldier) (However, the component of the shuto was different among temples, for example, in the Enryaku-ji Temple, the shuto was made up by the priests of higher aristocrat origin, and others who were excluded from shuto organized &apos;doshu&apos; separately).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many shuto were from aristocracy or the middle and low classes, as well as samurai families and shokan (an officer governing shoen (manor)), some of whom were skilled in martial arts, and as a result they made up a large share of Sohei (priest soldiers); however, the component of the shuto was different among temples, so that in Enryaku-ji Temple the shuto was made up of the priests of higher aristocratic origin, and others who were excluded from shuto organized &apos;doshu&apos; separately.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many shuto were from aristocracy of the middle and low classes, as well as samurai families and shokan (an officer governing shoen (manor)), some of whom were skilled in martial arts, and as a result they made up a large share of Sohei (priest soldiers); however, the component of the shuto was different among temples, so that in Enryaku-ji Temple the shuto was made up of the priests of higher aristocratic origin, and others who were excluded from shuto organized &apos;doshu&apos; separately.</e>
<cmt>or→of</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>大衆僉議や強訴など寺院内部の意思決定やその実力行使に中心的な役割を果たした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It played the central role in the decision making and recourse to force of the temple such as conference and direct petition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It played the central role in the decision-making and recourse to the force of the temple, such as by conferences and direct petitions.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It played the central role in the decision-making and recourse to the force of the temple, such as by conferences and direct petitions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>後に僧侶の身分分化が進み、公卿などの出身である学侶が寺院内の要職を独占して寺院の経営にも関与しようとすると、行人とともに激しく抵抗した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, after the status of the priest had been subdivided and Gakuryo of an aristocrat origin occupied the important posts in the temple and tried to involve the management of the temple, it resisted hardly with Gyonin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, once the status of the priest was subdivided and Gakuryo of aristocratic origins occupied the important posts in the temple and tried to become involved in the management of the temple, Gyonin offered barely any resistance.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, once the status of the priest was subdivided and Gakuryo of aristocratic origins occupied the important posts in the temple and tried to become involved in the management of the temple, Gyonin offered strong resistance.</e>
<cmt>barely any →strong</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>大和武士</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamato warrior</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamato warrior</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamato warrior</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>摂関家とのつながりが強かった大和国の興福寺は鎌倉時代に入ると、南都奈良やがて大和一国の支配権を得るようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kofuku-ji Temple in the Yamato Province which had a strong tie with Sekkan-ke (line of regents and advisers), became to control Nanto (southern capital (Nara)) and later the Yamato Province as a whole.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kofuku-ji Temple in Yamato Province, which had strong ties with Sekkan-ke (the line of regents and advisers), came to control Nanto (the southern capital (Nara)) and later Yamato Province as a whole.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kofuku-ji Temple in Yamato Province, which had strong ties with Sekkan-ke (the line of regents and advisers), came to control Nanto (the southern capital (Nara)) and later Yamato Province as a whole in Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>in Kamakura period補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>本来同寺の衆徒は太政官符によって20名と定められ、別当や三綱の補佐にあたることになっていた（官符衆徒）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, the number of the shuto of the Kofuku-ji Temple was determined to 20 by Daijokanpu (official documents issued by Daijokan, Grand Council of State) and they were put in charge of the assistance of betto (the superior of a temple) and Sango (three monastic positions with management roles at a temple) (kanpu-shuto).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially, the number of shuto of Kofuku-ji Temple was determined as 20 by the Daijokanpu (official documents issued by Daijokan, Grand Council of State), and they were put in charge of the assistance of betto (the superior of a temple) and Sango (three monastic positions with management roles at a temple) (kanpu-shuto).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially, the number of shuto of Kofuku-ji Temple was determined as 20 by the Daijokanpu (official documents issued by Daijokan, Grand Council of State), and they were put in charge of the assistance of betto (the superior of a temple) and Sango (three monastic positions with management roles at a temple) (kanpu-shuto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>次第に一乗院・大乗院などといった有力な門跡が自己の発言力の増大のために国内の武士や名主などを御家人などと称して自己の衆徒に組み入れ、自院の学侶に率いさせて寺内や奈良の町の検断などに従事させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gradually the influential monzeki (temple formerly led by founder of sect, temple in which resided a member of nobility or imperial family) such as the Ichijoin Temple and the Daijoin Temple incorporated warriors and myoshu (owner of rice fields) as gokenin (an immediate vassal of the Shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi) in order to strengthen their say, and made them put in charge of works such as trials in the temple and the city of Nara.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gradually the influential monzeki (temple formerly led by the founder of the sect, or the temple in which resided a member of nobility or the Imperial Family), such as Ichijoin Temple and Daijoin Temple, incorporated warriors and myoshu (owners of rice fields) as gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi periods) in order to strengthen their influence, and put them in charge of duties such as trials in the temple and the city of Nara.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gradually the influential monzeki (temple formerly led by the founder of the sect, or the temple in which resided a member of nobility or the Imperial Family), such as Ichijoin Temple and Daijoin Temple, incorporated warriors and myoshu (owners of rice fields) as gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi periods) in order to strengthen their influence, and put them in charge of duties such as trials in the temple and the city of Nara lead by Gakuryo.</e>
<cmt>lead by Gakuryo補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、神仏習合によって興福寺と一体化していた春日社の神人に組み入れられて同様の役割を果たすこともあり、こうした春日社神人を「国民」と呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it sometimes played the same role as above, incorporated into the jinin (associates of Shinto shrines) of the Kasuga-sha Shrine which was integrated with the Kofuku-ji Temple by syncretism of Shinto and Buddhism, and such jinin of the Kasuga-sha Shrine was called &apos;Kokumin.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also sometimes played the same role as above, incorporated into the jinin (associates of Shinto shrines) of Kasuga-sha Shrine, which was integrated with Kofuku-ji Temple by the syncretism of Shinto and Buddhism, and such jinin of Kasuga-sha Shrine was called &apos;Kokumin.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also sometimes played the same role as above, incorporated into the jinin (associates of Shinto shrines) of Kasuga-sha Shrine, which was integrated with Kofuku-ji Temple by the syncretism of Shinto and Buddhism, and such jinin of Kasuga-sha Shrine was called &apos;Kokumin.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>代表的な大和の衆徒として一乗院傘下の筒井氏・越智氏、大乗院傘下の十市氏・古市氏などがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The major shuto of the Yamato Province includes the Tsutsui clan and the Ochi clan under the Ichijoin Temple and the Tochi clan and the Furuichi clan under the Daijoin Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The major shuto of Yamato Province include the Tsutsui and Ochi clans under Ichijoin Temple, and the Tochi and Furuichi clans under Daijoin Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The major shuto of Yamato Province include the Tsutsui and Ochi clans under Ichijoin Temple, and the Tochi and Furuichi clans under Daijoin Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>南北朝時代_(日本)以後、これらの衆徒は自らの支配地域を獲得して領主化し、興福寺の権威を背景に更なる勢力拡大を図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Nanbokucho period (Japan), these shuto had become the lords of their ruling areas and tried to expand their powers furthermore with a background of the power of the Kofuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Nanbokucho period (Japan), these shuto became the lords of their ruling areas and tried to expand their powers against the background of the power of Kofuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), these shuto became the lords of their ruling areas and tried to expand their powers against the background of the power of Kofuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>室町幕府第6代征夷大将軍足利義教は、大和国内に幕府の支配権を確立するために両門跡の人事に介入し、更に筒井氏を大和国守護代に任じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, the sixth seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), edged into the human affairs of the both monzeki in order to establish bakufu&apos;s power in the Yamato Province, and assigned the Tsutsui clan as Shugodai (deputy of Shugo, provincial constable) of the Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, the sixth seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), edged into the human affairs of the both monzeki in order to establish the bakufu&apos;s power in Yamato Province, and assigned the Tsutsui clan as Shugodai (deputy of Shugo, provincial constable) of the province.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, the sixth seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), edged into the human affairs of the both monzeki in order to establish the bakufu&apos;s power in Yamato Province, and assigned the Tsutsui clan as Shugodai (deputy of Shugo, provincial constable) of the province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>これに反発した越智氏などが反幕府・反筒井氏の動きを見せ、そこに有力守護大名も介入して応仁の乱を挟んだ長期の内紛へと発展した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ochi clan and others opposed to this and showed the movements against bakufu and the Tsutsui clan, and influential Shugo daimyo (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable) intervened as well, which led to the long-term infighting which lasted before and after the Onin War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ochi clan and others were opposed to this, and showed the movements against bakufu and the Tsutsui clan, and the influential Shugo daimyo (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable) intervened as well, which led to the long-term infighting which preceded the Onin War and continued thereafter.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ochi clan and others were opposed to this, and showed the movements against bakufu and the Tsutsui clan, and the influential Shugo daimyo (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable) intervened as well, which led to the long-term infighting which preceded the Onin War and continued thereafter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>応仁の乱では東軍の筒井順永と西軍の越智家栄・古市澄胤が激しく争い、以後大和国内は彼らの子孫たちによって群雄割拠された状態で戦国時代_(日本)を迎えることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Onin War, Junei TSUTSUI of the Eastern Camp and Iehide OCHI and Choin FURUICHI of the Western Camp fought a hard battle, and after that, their descendants had continued fighting in the Yamato Province until the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Onin War, Junei TSUTSUI of the Eastern Camp and Iehide OCHI and Choin FURUICHI of the Western Camp fought a hard battle, and after that their descendants continued fighting in Yamato Province until the Sengoku (Warring States) period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Onin War, Junei TSUTSUI of the Eastern Camp and Iehide OCHI and Choin FURUICHI of the Western Camp fought a hard battle, and after that their descendants continued fighting in Yamato Province until the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States).</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>戦国時代には筒井順昭が一時国内の大半を平定して戦国大名化を進めるが、順昭が急死して幼少の筒井順慶が後を継ぐと、越智氏らが反撃して筒井氏の支配は解体した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Sengoku period, Junsho TSUTSUI became a daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) by ruling the most of the province temporarily, but after he died suddenly and infant Junkei TSUTSUI succeeded him, the Ochi clan fought back and broke the control of the Tsutsui clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Sengoku period, Junsho TSUTSUI became a daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) by ruling the majority of the province temporarily, but after he died suddenly and the infant Junkei TSUTSUI succeeded him, the Ochi clan fought back and broke the control of the Tsutsui clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Sengoku Period, Junsho TSUTSUI became a daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) by ruling the majority of the province temporarily, but after he died suddenly and the infant Junkei TSUTSUI succeeded him, the Ochi clan fought back and broke the control of the Tsutsui clan.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>更にその間隙を縫って三好長慶配下の松永久秀が大和に攻め込んで順慶を追放、越智氏らを屈服させて永禄2年（1559年）興福寺から大和国守護職の地位を奪った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, threading his way through them, Hisashide MATSUNAGA invaded into Yamato Province, exiled Junkei and defeated the Ochi clan and others, and gained the position of Shugoshiki of the Yamato Province from the Kofuku-ji Temple in 1559.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, threading his way through them, Hisashide MATSUNAGA invaded Yamato Province, sent Junkei into exile and defeated the Ochi clan and others, and thereby obtained the position of Shugoshiki of Yamato Province from Kofuku-ji Temple in 1559.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, threading his way through them, Hisahide MATSUNAGA who served under Nagayoshi MIYOSHI invaded Yamato Province, sent Junkei into exile and defeated the Ochi clan and others, and thereby obtained the position of Shugoshiki of Yamato Province from Kofuku-ji Temple in 1559.</e>
<cmt>who served under Nagayoshi MIYOSHI補足人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>その後、織豊政権政権のもとで大和一国の大名として復活した筒井順慶は、対外的には大和国主として国内的には父祖代々継承してきた官符衆徒の代表として法印僧都の地位に就くという二面性を持った支配体制を確立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Junkei TSUTSUI came back to the daimyo of the Yamato Province under the Shokuho government (the government of Nobunaga ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI. &quot;Shoku&quot; and &quot;ho&quot; are the initial letters of Oda and Toyotomi), he established the ruling system which had two aspects of the lord of the Yamato Province externally and the hoin-sozu (the highest rank among Buddhist priests) as the representative of the kanpu-shuto which was succeeded for generations in the province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, Junkei TSUTSUI came back to the daimyo of Yamato Province under the Shokuho government (the government of Nobunaga ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, &quot;shoku&quot; and &quot;ho&quot; being the initial letters of Oda and Toyotomi), he established a ruling system that had two aspects of the lord of Yamato Province externally and the hoin-sozu (highest rank among Buddhist priests) as the representative of the kanpu-shuto, which was succeeded for generations in the province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, Junkei TSUTSUI came back to the daimyo of Yamato Province under the Shokuho government (the government of Nobunaga ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, &quot;shoku&quot; and &quot;ho&quot; being the initial letters of Oda and Toyotomi), he established a ruling system that had two aspects of the lord of Yamato Province externally and the hoin-sozu (highest rank among Buddhist priests) as the representative of the kanpu-shuto, which was succeeded for generations in the province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>だが、順慶の死後には豊臣秀吉が弟の豊臣秀長に大和一国を与えて、既存の支配体制を否定、衆徒・国民を強制的に解散させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, after Junkei&apos;s death, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI gave the Yamato Province to his brother Hidenaga TOYOTOMI, to deny the conventional ruling system, and broke up the shuto and Kokumin by compulsion.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after Junkei&apos;s death Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI gave Yamato Province to his brother Hidenaga TOYOTOMI, thus defying the conventional ruling system, and broke up the shuto and Kokumin by compulsion.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after Junkei&apos;s death Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI gave Yamato Province to his brother Hidenaga TOYOTOMI, thus defying the conventional ruling system, and broke up the shuto and Kokumin by compulsion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>興福寺に対しては官符衆徒本来の20氏（名）のみを寺内の事務・警備要員として採用して総計380石を与えることを認めたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He admitted the Kofuku-ji Temple to adopt only original 20 kanpu-shuto as office worker or security and give them 380 koku in total.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He allowed Kofuku-ji Temple to adopt only original 20 kanpu-shuto as office workers or security, and give them 380 koku in total.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He allowed Kofuku-ji Temple to adopt only original 20 kanpu-shuto as office workers or security, and give them 380 koku in total.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 地図帳(id:122587), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>