<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>仁実</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ninjitsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ninjitsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ninjitsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>仁実（にんじつ、寛治5年（1091年）- 天承元年6月8日 (旧暦)（1131年7月4日））は、平安時代後期の天台宗の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ninjitsu (1091-July 11, 1131) was a monk of the Tendai sect in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>「天承元年6月8日 (旧暦)」＝グレゴリオ暦「西暦1131年7月11日」、出典：http://maechan.net/kanreki</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ninjitsu (1091-July 11, 1131) was a priest of the Tendai sect in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;monk&quot; to &quot;priest&quot; for consistency with other articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ninjitsu (1091-July 11, 1131) was a priest of the Tendai sect in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原公実の次男。母は藤原光子（藤原隆方女）。待賢門院藤原璋子の異母兄。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the second son of FUJIWARA no Kinzane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the second son of FUJIWARA no Kanzane, his mother was FUJIWARA no Koshi (a daughter of FUJIWARA no Takakata) and he was a half brother to Taikenmonin FUJIWARA no Shoshi.</e>
<cmt>All three of these sentences are extremely short, so I combined them into one.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the second son of FUJIWARA no Kinzane, his mother was FUJIWARA no Koshi (a daughter of FUJIWARA no Takakata) and he was an older paternal half-brother to Taikenmonin FUJIWARA no Shoshi.</e>
<cmt>藤原公実FUJIWARA no Kanzane をFUJIWARA no Kinzane に修正しました。異母兄older paternal half-brother に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>比叡山に上り、仁覚・仁源・慶朝・仁豪・相覚・宗観などに師事して天台教学を学んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He entered Hiei-zan Mountain and learned about the Tendai Sect studying under Ninkaku, Ningen, Keicho, Ningo, Shokaku, Sokan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ninjitsu entered the temple on Mt. Hiei-zan and learned about the Tendai Sect while studying under Ninkaku, Ningen, Keicho, Ningo, Shokaku and Sokan.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;He&quot; to &quot;Ninjitsu&quot; since this is a new paragraph; fixed grammar and commas; added &quot;temple&quot; as &quot;Hiei-zan Mountain&quot; is not specific; changed &quot;Hiei-zan Mountain&quot; &quot;Mt. Hiei&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ninjitsu entered the temple on Mt. Hiei and learned about the Tendai Sect while studying under Ninkaku, Ningen, Keicho, Ningo, Shokaku and Sokan.</e>
<cmt>比叡山　Mt. Hiei-zan を Mt. Hiei に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>鳥羽院・崇徳院の護持僧を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served Tobain and Sutokuin as Gojiso (a priest who prays to guard the emperor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a Gojiso (a priest who prays to guard the Emperor), he served Tobain and Sutokuin.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a Gojiso (a priest who prays to guard the Emperor), he served Tobain and Sutokuin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>1123年（保安 (元号)4年）33歳の若さで天台座主に就任したが、これは40歳未満の天台座主就任の初例とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1123, he assumed the post of Tendai-zasu (head priest of the Tendai sect) at the young age of 33, which was understood as the first case of the assumption of the post of Tendai-zasu at the age of younger than 40.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1123, assuming the post of Tendai-zasu (the head priest of the Tendai sect) at the youthful age of 33, Ninjitsu was the first case of anyone assuming the post younger than the age of 40.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1123, assuming the post of Tendai-zasu (the head priest of the Tendai sect) at the youthful age of 33, Ninjitsu was the first case of anyone assuming the post younger than the age of 40.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>最勝寺・尊勝寺の灌頂大阿闍梨を務め、大治 (日本)5年（1131年）に座主を辞退。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He filled the post of Kanjo Daiajari of Saisho-ji Temple and Sonsho-ji Temple and retired from Tendai-zasu in 1131.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Filling the post of Kanjo Daiajari of Saisho-ji Temple and Sonsho-ji Temple, Ninjitsu retired from his post as Tendai-zasu in 1131.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Filling the post of Kanjo Daiajari (a priest who has received the special anointment transmitting the teaching and rituals of esoteric Buddhism) of Saisho-ji Temple and Sonsho-ji Temple, Ninjitsu retired from his post as Tendai-zasu in 1131.</e>
<cmt>Kanjo Daiajari に (a priest who has received the special anointment transmitting the teaching and rituals of esoteric Buddhism) を追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>翌年の天承元年（1131年）証菩提院別当・法勝寺権別当となるが、同年6月8日に没した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following year 1131, he became Shobodai-in betto (the head priest of Shobodai-in Temple) and Hosho-ji Gon no betto (acting head priest of Hosho-ji Temple), but died July 11 of that year.</e>
<cmt>「天承元年6月8日」＝グレゴリオ暦「西暦1131年7月11日」、出典：http://maechan.net/kanreki</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later on, Ninjitsu became the Shobodai-in betto (the head priest of Shobodai-in Temple) and Hosho-ji Gon no betto (acting head priest of Hosho-ji Temple), but died on July 11th, 1131.</e>
<cmt>Without translating the names of the eras in every case, the translation needs to be changed from the original to make sense in situations like these: &quot;The following year&quot;in the Daiji era is the &quot;same year&quot; in the Gregorian calendar. I fixed this by changing &quot;The following year&quot; to &quot;Later on&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later on, Ninjitsu became the Shobodai-in betto (the head priest of Shobodai-in Temple) and Hosho-ji Gon no betto (acting head priest of Hosho-ji Temple), but died on July 11th, 1131.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 代言人(id:33675), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), Point136(id:211299), Andee(id:20421), YOSHI438(id:174755), 伏儀(id:142093), Kamitani(id:30757), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>