<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>聖宝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shobo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shobo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shobo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>聖宝（しょうぼう、天長9年(832年) - 延喜9年7月6日 (旧暦)(909年8月29日)）は、平安時代初期の真言宗の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shobo was a Shingon sect priest (born in 832 and passed away on July 6th, (August 29th on the old calendar) 909).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shobo was a Shingon sect priest (born in 832 and passed away on July 6th, (August 29th on the old calendar) 909).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shobo (832 - July 30, 909) was a Shingon Sect priest in the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>平安時代初期の、を補足し、表現を他のファイルと合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>当山派修験道の祖。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the founder of mountaineering asceticism of Tozan school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the founder of the mountaineering asceticism of Tozan school.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the founder of the mountaineering asceticism of Tozan School.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>俗名は恒蔭王。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His secular name was Tsunekageo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His secular name was Tsunekageo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His secular name was Prince Tsunekage.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>天智天皇の6世孫にあたり、父は葛声王（かどなおう）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a sixth generation-descendent of the Emperor Tench and his father was Kadonao.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a sixth generation-descendent of the Emperor Tench and his father was Kadonao.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a sixth generation-descendent of the Emperor Tenchi and his father was Prince Kadona.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>諡号は理源大師。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His posthumous title was Rigen Daishi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His posthumous title was Rigen Daishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His shigo (a posthumous name) was Rigen Daishi.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>空海の実弟真雅の室に入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He studied under Shinga, Kukai&apos;s brother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He studied under Shinga, Kukai&apos;s brother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He studied under Shinga, Kukai&apos;s biological brother.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>真言密教（真言宗）の教学を学び、南都に遊学して大乗教学（三論宗・法相宗・華厳宗）を修めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shobo studied the doctrine of Shingon Esoteric Buddhism (Shingon-shu sect), traveling to Nanto to study the doctrine of Mahayana Buddhism (Sanron Sect, Hosso sect and Kegon sect).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shobo studied the doctrine of Shingon Esoteric Buddhism (Shingon-shu sect), traveling to Nanto to study the doctrine of Mahayana Buddhism (Sanron Sect, Hosso sect and Kegon sect).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shobo studied the doctrine of Shingon Esoteric Buddhism (Shingon Sect), traveling to Nanto (southern capital (Nara)) to study the doctrine of Mahayana Buddhism (Sanron Sect, Hosso Sect and Kegon Sect).</e>
<cmt>補足などしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>貴顕社会との交流を重視した師真雅に対して、華美や権勢と一定の距離を置いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While his mentor, Shinga had quite a lot of importance for the intercommunion with the aristocratic society, Shobo kept himself detached from the society.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While his mentor, Shinga had importance for intercommunion with aristocratic society, Shobo kept himself detached from the society.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While his mentor, Shinga had importance for intercommunion with aristocratic society, Shobo kept himself detached from the society.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>清廉潔白・豪胆な人柄として知られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was known to live a clean life and have a faultless/doubtless character.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was known to live a clean life and have a faultless/doubtless character.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was known to live a clean life and have a faultless and doubtless character.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>この点から真雅との確執すらも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The differences even suggested that there was a conflict between Shinga and himself.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The differences even suggested that there was a conflict between Shinga and himself.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The differences even suggested that there was a conflict between Shinga and himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>吉野の金峰山（きんぷせん）で山岳修行を行い、また役行者に私淑して、以降途絶えていた修験道、即ち大峯山での修験道修行を復興したことで、真雅の活動と好対照とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shobo&apos;s following activities were thought to form a marked contrast to Shinga&apos;s behavior: Shobo conducted mountain ascetic practices on Mt. Kinpu in Yoshino, and, by adoring En no Gyoja in his heart, revived the mountaineering asceticism training in Mt. Omine, which was thought to have been abondoned after the disappearance of EN no Gyoja.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shobo&apos;s following activities were thought to form a marked contrast to Shinga&apos;s behavior: Shobo conducted mountain ascetic practices on Mt. Kinpu in Yoshino, and, by adoring En no Gyoja in his heart, revived the mountaineering asceticism training in Mt. Omine, which was thought to have been abandoned after the disappearance of EN no Gyoja.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shobo&apos;s following activities were thought to form a marked contrast to Shinga&apos;s behavior: Shobo conducted mountain ascetic practices on Mt. Kinpu in Yoshino, and, by adoring EN no Gyoja (A semi-legendary holy man noted for his practice of mountain asceticism during the second half of the 7 century) in his heart, revived the mountaineering asceticism training in Mt. Omine, which was thought to have been abandoned after the disappearance of EN no Gyoja.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>真雅からは受明灌頂と無量寿法を受法。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shobo received Jumyo- kanjo initiation and Muryojuho (Immesurable Law) from Shinga.</e>
<cmt>無量寿法の英訳がわかりませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shobo received Jumyo- kanjo initiation and Muryojuho (Immesurable Law) from Shinga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shobo received Jumyo Kanjo (a water rite to be a disciple) and Muryoju-ho (teachings of Sutra of Immeasurable Life) from Shinga.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>師の死後、49歳で高野山に上がり、真雅の資（弟子）真然から金胎両部の秘法を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his mentor&apos;s death, Shinga(?) climbed up Mt. Koya at the age of 49, and received a secret art of Kintai-ryobu from Shinzen, Shinga&apos;s Shi (disciple).</e>
<cmt>資の英訳がわかりませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his mentor&apos;s death, Shinga(?) climbed up Mt. Koya at the age of 49, and received a secret art of Kintai-ryobu from Shinzen, Shinga&apos;s Shi (disciple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his mentor&apos;s death, he climbed up Mt. Koya at the age of 49, and received a secret art of both the vajra (the Diamond Realm) and garbha (the Womb Realm) mandalas from Shinzen, Shinga&apos;s disciple.</e>
<cmt>表現を変え、用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>53歳で東寺南池院源仁から伝法灌頂を受け、56歳で阿闍梨位を得て、空海以来の真言密教正嫡となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the age of 53, Shobo received denpo-kanjo from Gennin of Nanchi-in of To-ji temple. Shobo was given the position of Ajari (a master in esoteric Buddhism; a high priest) and became the head of Shingon Esoteric Buddhism, succeeding Kukai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the age of 53, Shobo received denpo-kanjo from Gennin of Nanchi-in of To-ji temple. Shobo was given the position of Ajari (a master in esoteric Buddhism; a high priest) and became the head of Shingon Esoteric Buddhism, succeeding Kukai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He received denpo-kanjo (the consecration for the Transmission of the Dharma) from Gennin of Nanchiin of To-ji Temple at the age of 53, was given the position of Ajari (a master in Esoteric Buddhism; a high priest) to became the head of Shingon Esoteric Buddhism succeeding Kukai at the age of 56.</e>
<cmt>56歳で、を補足、1文にし表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>京都山科の地（現在の伏見区山科）に醍醐寺を開山した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shobo founded Daigo-ji temple in Yamashina, Kyoto (present day, Yamashina, Fushimi Ward).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shobo founded Daigo-ji temple in Yamashina, Kyoto (present day, Yamashina, Fushimi Ward).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shobo founded Daigo-ji Temple in Yamashina, Kyoto (present day, Yamashina, Fushimi-ku Ward).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>一方で東大寺に東南院を建立して三論教学の拠点を築いたが、これは聖宝の中観／般若空重視の態度という観点からだけではなく、宗祖空海によって実施された南都大寺における儀礼の真言密教化という観点からも見落とすべきではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also made a base of San-lun Teachings by establishing Tonan-in Temple in Todai-ji temple. It should be considered from the two following viewpoints; Shobo&apos;s high evaluation of Chukan/Hannyaku and Kukai&apos;s adjusting ceremonies to Shingon Esoteric Buddhism at major temples at Nanto.</e>
<cmt>般若空の英訳がわかりませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also made a base of San-lun Teachings by establishing Tonan-in Temple in Todai-ji temple. It should be considered from the two following viewpoints; Shobo&apos;s high evaluation of Chukan/Hannyaku and Kukai&apos;s adjusting ceremonies to Shingon Esoteric Buddhism at major temples at Nanto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also made a base of San-lun (Three Shastras) Teachings by establishing Tonanin Temple in Todai-ji Temple, which should not be overlooked by the two following viewpoints; Shobo&apos;s high evaluation of Chugan (Intermediate) or Hannya-ku (the truth that nothing is substantial, void, taught in the Heart Sutra) and Kukai&apos;s adjusting ceremonies to Shingon Esoteric Buddhism at major temples at Nanto.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>そもそも真言教学それ自体は、華厳経の教説を基盤として展開するものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shingon Esoteric Buddhism itself developed based on the doctrine of the Kegon-kyo Sutra.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shingon Esoteric Buddhism itself developed based on the doctrine of the Kegon-kyo Sutra.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shingon Esoteric Buddhism itself developed based on the doctrine of the Kegon-kyo (Avatamsaka Sutra).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>言い換えると、華厳教学が秘密曼荼羅十住心論において第八（天台法華）ではなく第九住心に配置された意味を併せて考えれば、即身成仏義の重重帝網（無碍）が、一即多・多即一という華厳教学を象徴的にする哲理を重要な基礎として、実践作法の理論的基礎に展開したものとして見ることできるからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, from the fact that the Kegon doctrine was placed not as the eighth (Tendai Hokke) but as the ninth Jushin in Himitsu Mandala Jujushinron (Ten Abiding Stages on the Secret Mandalas), 重重帝網 (無碍) of Sokushinjobutsu-gi can be thought to have developed into theoretical foundation of practical code based on the philosophy which symbolized the Kegon doctrine that one is equal to many, many to one.</e>
<cmt>第九住心, 重重帝網(無碍),一即多・多即一の英訳がわかりませんでした。重重帝網(無碍)は読み方もわかりませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, from the fact that the Kegon doctrine was placed not as the eighth (Tendai Hokke) but as the ninth Jushin in Himitsu Mandala Jujushinron (Ten Abiding Stages on the Secret Mandalas), 重重帝網 (無碍) of Sokushinjobutsu-gi can be thought to have developed into a theoretical foundation of practical code based on the philosophy which symbolized the Kegon doctrine that one is equal to many, many to one.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, from the fact that the Kegon (a thought of virtues are correctly provided due to trainings and performing acts of charity) doctrine was placed not as the eighth (Tendai Hokke) but as the ninth Jushin (stages of Mind Development) in Himitsu Mandala Jujushinron (Ten Abiding Stages on the Secret Mandalas), Juju taimo (endlessly interconnected net of Indra) (unobstructed) of Sokushin Jobutsu gi (Principle of Attaining Buddhahood with the Present Body) can be thought to have developed into a theoretical foundation of practical code based on the philosophy which symbolized the Kegon doctrine of Ichi-soku-ta and Ta-soku-ichi (one is equal to many, many to one).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>『この世界は仏の身体である（六大）』として、沈黙する存在としてばかり考えられていたビルシャナ仏が自ら説法すると宣言した意味は大きいのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is very meaningful that Vairocana, who had been considered a silent existence, described as &quot;this world is Buddha&apos;s body (rokudai),&quot;declared that he, himself would preach.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is very meaningful that Vairocana, who had been considered a silent existence, described as &quot;this world is Buddha&apos;s body (rokudai),&quot;declared that he, himself would preach.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is very meaningful that Vairocana, who had been considered a silent existence, described as &quot;this world is Buddha&apos;s body (rokudai),&quot;declared that he, himself would preach.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>方便を極めて重要視する密教信仰において、理論から実践への橋渡しをすることは、大乗仏教興隆の観点からも大きく肯定されるべきものとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Mikkyo faith, which puts strong emphasis on measures, moving from theory to practice should be approved from the viewpoint of Mahayana Buddhism prosperity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Mikkyo faith, which puts strong emphasis on measures, moving from theory to practice should be approved from the viewpoint of Mahayana Buddhism prosperity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Esoteric Buddhism faith, which puts strong emphasis on measures, moving from theory to practice should be approved from the viewpoint of Mahayana Buddhism prosperity.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>この点に聖宝が宗祖空海の直系を自覚して、東大寺における活動を推進した根本義が表れていると見るべきである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It should be intepreted that because of the idea, Shobo, recognizing that he was in a direct line of Kukai, the founder of the Mikkyo, promoted activities at Todaiji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It should be intepreted that because of the idea, Shobo, recognizing that he was in a direct line of Kukai, the founder of the Mikkyo, promoted activities at Todaiji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It should be interpreted that because of the idea, Shobo, recognizing that he was in a direct line of Kukai, the founder, promoted activities at Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また曼荼羅それ自体が、華厳経の教説『普賢菩薩の行の総体』を基盤としていることにも注意すべきであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It should be noted that Mandala, itself, is based on the Kagen-kyo doctorine, &quot;the integral of Fugen Bosatsu&apos;s trainings.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It should be noted that Mandala, itself, is based on the Kagen-kyo doctorine, &quot;the integral of Fugen Bosatsu&apos;s trainings.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It should be noted that Mandala, itself, is based on the Kegon-kyo doctrine, &quot;the integral of Fugen Bosatsu&apos;s trainings.&quot;</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="23">
<j>その後も東大寺華厳宗の別当職、東寺長者等を務め、顕密両教の研鑽に努めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shobo served as Todai-ji Temple of Kegon Sect Betto shoku and To-ji choja, and so forth and studied both exoteric Buddhism and Esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shobo served as Todai-ji Temple Kegon Sect Betto shoku and To-ji choja, and so forth and studied both exoteric Buddhism and Esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shobo served as betto (steward) of Kegon Sect of Todai-ji Temple and To-ji choja (the chief abbot of To-ji Temple), and so on, and studied both Exoteric Buddhism and Esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>一方、山科小野の地に曼荼羅寺を建立して密教修行の活動拠点を築いた東密小野流の開祖／仁海、御室仁和寺で宇多天皇に灌頂を授けた益信の後進にして、広沢池ほとりに遍照寺を建立した東密広沢流の開祖／寛朝らが事相面の法孫として対照されるが、広沢流／益信とともに、後世野沢三十六流と呼ばれる真言事作法分流における重要な基点を創った法匠として捉える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ningai, the founder of the Ono Lineage of Tomitsu, established Mandala-ji Temple at Ono, Yamashina and founded the base for Mikkyo practice. Kancho, younger than Yakushin, who received the kanjo from the Emperor Uda at Omuro-Ninnaji temple, founded Hirosawa Lineage of Tomitsu (Shingon sect&apos;s esoteric teaching) and established Henshoji Temple along the shore of Hirosawa-no-ike Pond. Ningai and Kancho are thought to have been successors in practical training and contrasted with Shobo. However, it should be interpreted that Shobo as well as Hirosawa school and Yakushin made important foundations in Shingon jisaho bunryu, which was later called Yataku Sanjuiroku-ryu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ningai, the founder of the Ono Lineage of Tomitsu, established Mandala-ji Temple at Ono, Yamashina and founded the base for Mikkyo practice. Kancho, younger than Yakushin, who received the kanjo from Emperor Uda at Omuro-Ninnaji temple, founded the Hirosawa Lineage of Tomitsu (Shingon sect&apos;s esoteric teaching) and established Henshoji Temple along the shores of Hirosawa-no-ike Pond. Ningai and Kancho are thought to have been successors in practical training and contrasted with Shobo. However, it should be interpreted that Shobo as well as the Hirosawa school and Yakushin made important foundations in Shingon jisaho bunryu, which was later called Yataku Sanjuiroku-ryu.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ningai, the founder of the Ono School of Tomitsu (Shingon Sect&apos;s esoteric teaching), established Mandala-ji Temple at Ono, Yamashina and founded the base for Esoteric Buddhism&apos;s practice, and Kancho, younger than Yakushin, who received the kanjo (a ceremony to be the successor) from Emperor Uda at Omuro-Ninna-ji Temple, founded the Hirosawa School of Tomitsu and established Hensho-ji Temple along the shores of Hirosawa-no-ike Pond, and others are thought to have been successors in practical training and contrasted with Shobo, however, it should be interpreted that Shobo as well as the Hirosawa School of Yakushin made important foundations in Shingon-ji Saho Bunryu (branch schools in manners of Shingon Sect), which was later called Yataku Sanjuroku-ryu (thirty-six schools of yataku (Ono School and Hirosawa School)).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="25">
<j>聖宝は如意輪観音・准胝観音の両観音を尊崇して上醍醐笠取山上に祭祀し、朱雀天皇・村上天皇両帝の誕生を祈ったことが記録される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was recorded that Shobo admired Nyoirin Kannon and Juntei Kannon, ran rites and festivals for them at Kami Daigo Kasatori-yama Mountain, prayed for the births of the Emperors Suzaku and Murakami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was recorded that Shobo admired Nyoirin Kannon and Juntei Kannon, ran rites and festivals for them at Kami Daigo Kasatori-yama Mountain, and prayed for the births of the Emperors Suzaku and Murakami.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was recorded that Shobo admired both Nyoirin Kannon (the Bodhisattva of Compassion) and Juntei Kannon, ran rites and festivals for them at Mt. Kasatori, also known as Kami Daigo, and prayed for the births of the Emperors Suzaku and Murakami.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>同時に如意輪観音には、空海が帰朝する際に付き従った清滝権現（清瀧権現）（せいりょうごんげん）の化身であるとの信仰が護持伝承されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The belief was also traditionally maintained that Nyoirin Kannon was the incarnation of Seiryo Gongen, who accompanied Kukai when he came back to Japan.</e>
<cmt>清瀧権現は発音をローマ字表記しております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The belief was also traditionally maintained that Nyoirin Kannon was the incarnation of Seiryo Gongen, who accompanied Kukai when he came back to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The belief was also traditionally maintained that Nyoirin Kannon was the incarnation of Seiryo Gongen (A protective god associated with the Chinese temple Ch&apos;ing-lung), who accompanied Kukai when he came back to Japan.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="27">
<j>正嫡には、弘法大師号を弟子淳祐 (僧)を伴い高野山奥の院に奉告し、空海後の真言宗団の組織興隆化を図った醍醐寺第一世座主観賢とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kangen, zasu (Daigo-ji temple&apos;s head priest) was considered to be Shobo&apos;s direct disciple. Kangen, accompanied by Junyu, his disciple, dedicated Kobo Daishi-go title to Koya-san Oku no in. He also intended for the prosperity of the post-Kukai Shingon organization.</e>
<cmt>正嫡,奉告の英訳に関しては、自身がありません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kangen, zasu (Daigo-ji temple&apos;s head priest) was considered to be Shobo&apos;s direct disciple. Kangen, accompanied by Junyu, his disciple, dedicated Kobo Daishi-go title to Koya-san Oku no in. He also intended for the prosperity of the post-Kukai Shingon organization.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kangen, the first zasu (head priest) of Daigo-ji Temple, was considered to be Shobo&apos;s legal child, who accompanied by Junyu, his disciple, dedicated Kobo Daishi-go title to Oku no in (inner sanctuary) on Mt. Koya, and intended for the prosperity of the post-Kukai Shingon organization.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="28">
<j>聖宝を祖とする当山派修験道においては、一方で『修験恵印総漫拏羅』を通じて表現された不二一乗の世界観をもって大日如来による秘奥の説法を示すものとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tozan-ha (Shingon Sect) branch of Shugendo, in which Shobo is regarded as the founder, is thought to demonstrate profound preaching by Dainichi Nyorai with the sole perspective of the world, which was expressed through &quot;Shugen keiin so mandara.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修験恵印総漫拏羅は、発音をローマ字表記しております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tozan-ha (Shingon Sect) branch of Shugendo, for which Shobo is regarded as the founder, is thought to demonstrate profound preaching by Dainichi Nyorai with the sole perspective of the world, which was expressed through &quot;Shugen keiin so mandara.&quot;</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shugendo (Japanese mountain asceticism-shamanism incorporating Shinto and Buddhist concepts) in Tozan School, which Shobo was founded, is thought to demonstrate profound preaching by Dainichi Nyorai with Funi Ichijo (most important of the Shingon principles which states to climb the mountain of Ichijo (truth), Mt. Omine, and pray for obtaining the body of funi (a thought that Ri (the innate reason) and Chi (knowledge) are non-two)), which was expressed through &quot;Shugen Ein So Mandala&quot; (literally, mandala of Shugendo under the teaching of Ein (Dainichi Nyorai&apos;s most secret teachings)).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>一般に真言密教においては、金胎両部の曼荼羅を通じて、密教宇宙の理と智に係わるそれぞれの所謂『大（法身大日）・三（意密）・法（口密）・羯（身密）』パノラマで、或いは六大（体）・四曼（相）・三密（用）などの多元的な視点と、重重帝網（無碍）という統合的視点から大日如来の教えを展開／把握することが知られるが（即身成仏義）、聖宝においてはこの時代において理と智を一元論的な手法をオモテにして示していることは、修験道という日本的アニミスティック神霊信仰の点から注目される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally speaking, it is known that the preaching of Dainichi Nyorai should be developed and grasped both from pluralistic perspective, including Rokudai (tai), Shiman (so), Sanmitsu (yo), in the so-called &quot;dai (hoshin dainichi), san (imitsu), hou (koumitsu), katsu (shinmitsu)&quot; panorama, related with the reason and wisdom of Mikkyo univers and from integrative perspective of 重重帝網(無碍). It should be noted that Shobo exhibited reason and wisdom in a monastic way when he practiced in mountaineering asceticism, Japanese animistic belief in holy spirit.</e>
<cmt>『大（法身大日）・三（意密）・法（口密）・羯（身密）』六大（体）・四曼（相）・三密（用）重重帝網（無碍）は、英語表現がわかりませんでした。重重帝網（無碍）は、発音もわかりませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally speaking, it is known that the preachings of Dainichi Nyorai should be developed and grasped both from a pluralistic perspective, including Rokudai (tai), Shiman (so), Sanmitsu (yo), in the so-called &quot;dai (hoshin dainichi), san (imitsu), hou (koumitsu), katsu (shinmitsu)&quot; panorama, related to the reason and wisdom of the Mikkyo universe and from the integrative perspective of 重重帝網(無碍). It should be noted that Shobo exhibited reason and wisdom in a monastic way when he practiced mountaineering asceticism, the Japanese animistic belief in holy spirit.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally speaking, it is known that the preaching of Dainichi Nyorai should be developed and grasped through both the vajra (the Diamond Realm) and garbha (the Womb Realm) mandalas, whether in so-called &quot;dai (Great Mandala) (hoshin (Buddhism&apos;s highest form of existence) Dainichi), san (sanmaya mandala) (imitsu (mystery of mind)), ho (Buddhist Law Mandala) (kumitsu (esoteric speech)), katsu (katsuma mandala (action mandala)) (shinmitsu (bodily mystery))&quot; panorama, which are related with Ri and Chi of Esoteric Buddhism world, or in both a pluralistic perspective including rokudai (six great elements; that is Dainichi Nyorai) (tai (body)), shiman (four mandala) (so (match)), sanmitsu (three mysteries) (yu (function)), and a general perspective of Juju taimo (unobstructed) (Sokushin Jobutsu gi), but in the viewpoint of mountaineering asceticism, the Japanese animistic belief in holy spirit, it should be noted that Shobo, at this time, exhibited the Ri and the Chi in a monastic way.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>これは平安後期の覚鑁興教大師以降、『金剛界／胎蔵界』という並立的表現方法が顕著となる以前の出来事であり、日本固有の信仰観について、後の応永の大成を頂点とする二而不二／不二而二に係わる各法匠の立場／背景、さらには日本の密教思想史、殊に事教二相を実践／検討する上で銘記するべき事象として理解することを求められよう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shobo&apos;s idea had been shown before the parallel mode of expression, &quot;Kongokai (Diamond Realm)/Taizokai (Womb Realm),&quot; by Kakuban Kokyo Daishi became remarkable in the latter Heian period. His idea should be kept in mind in conducting/discussing the religious belief particular to the Japanese, each master&apos;s standpoint/background related with 二而不二/不二而二, in which Oeiki&apos;s great work reached the summit, and Japanese intellectual history of Mikkyo, especially 事教二相.</e>
<cmt>二而不二／不二而二、重重帝網（無碍）は、発音もわかりませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shobo&apos;s idea had been shown before the parallel mode of expression, &quot;Kongokai (Diamond Realm)/Taizokai (Womb Realm),&quot; by Kakuban Kokyo Daishi became remarkable in the latter Heian period. His idea should be kept in mind in conducting/discussing the religious beliefs particular to the Japanese, each master&apos;s standpoint/background related with 二而不二/不二而二, in which Oeiki&apos;s great work reached the summit, and Japanese intellectual history of Mikkyo, especially 事教二相.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This happened before the parallel mode of expression, &quot;Kongokai (Diamond Realm) or Taizokai (Womb Realm),&quot; became remarkable after Kakuban Kokyo Daishi in the latter Heian period, and should be understood as an epoch, regarding the religious beliefs particular to the Japanese, in conducting and discussing each master&apos;s standpoint or background related with Nini-Funi (also known as Funi-Nini (two sides of the same coin)) in which Oei no Taisei (Perfection in Oei era) reached the summit, more over in the Japanese intellectual history of Esoteric Buddhism, especially practicing or considering Jikyo niso (Jiso (method to practice the doctrine) and Kyoso (logical study of doctrines)).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="31">
<j>聖宝が遺した『実修実証』の言葉は、当山派修行者の実践過程において、常に護持すべき修験道の心とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term, &quot;Jishu jisho,&quot; left by Shobo, should be the mind of mountaineering asceticism and always maintained by practitioners of Tozan school in the process of practice.</e>
<cmt>実修実証は、発音を推測して表記しております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term, &quot;Jishu jisho,&quot; left by Shobo, should be the mind of mountaineering asceticism and always maintained by practitioners of Tozan school in the process of practice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term, &quot;Jisshu Jissho&quot; (Discipline to prove the teaching) left by Shobo, should be the mind of mountaineering asceticism and always maintained by practitioners of Tozan School in the process of practice.</e>
<cmt>補足し、表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>その実修根本となる『最勝恵印三昧耶法』（恵印灌頂）は、『理智不二界会礼讃』の具現化であり、正嫡の観賢だけでなく、大和鳥栖真言院鳳閣寺において貞崇に授けたと伝える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Saisho Ein Sanma Yaho (Dainichi Nyorai&apos;s most secret teachings)Ein Kanjo (the ceremony to be the successor of a ritual of the Ein School),&quot; which should be the base for practice, was the realization of &quot;理智不二界会礼讃.&quot; It is said that it was given not only to Kangen, his direct disciple, but also to Teisu at Hokaku-ji Temple, Shingon-in, Yamato tosu.</e>
<cmt>理智不二界会礼讃は発音もわかりませんでした。大和鳥栖の英語表記に自身がありません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Saisho Ein Sanma Yaho (Dainichi Nyorai&apos;s most secret teachings)Ein Kanjo (the ceremony to be the successor of a ritual of the Ein School),&quot; which should be the base for practice, was the realization of &quot;理智不二界会礼讃.&quot; It is said that it was given not only to Kangen, his direct disciple, but also to Teisu at Hokaku-ji Temple, Shingon-in, Yamato tosu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Saisho Ein Sanma Yaho&quot; (Dainichi Nyorai&apos;s most secret teachings) (Ein Kanjo (the ceremony to be the successor of a ritual of the Ein School)),&quot; the base for practice, was the realization of &quot;Richi funi Kai Kai Raisan&quot; (worship of the Shingon conceptual world with the nonduality of knowledge and principle) and it is said that it was given not only to Kangen, his legal child, but also to Teisu at Hokaku-ji Temple, Shingonin, Yamato tosu.</e>
<cmt>1文にし表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>当山派恵印法は、龍樹菩薩による霊異相承の伝から峰受法流とも呼ばれ、本山派峰中法流と対照されることがあるが、両派に共通する肝心は、実践第一を旨とし、世間の言語／思考に依るところの一切戯論を断絶して、山岳、或いは、人里の道場においても、ひたすら修行に打ち込むところにあると言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ein Ho of Tozan School is also called 峰受法流 because of Rei sojo (the initiation in a unseen and wondrous method) by Ryuju Bosatsu and is sometimes contrasted with 峰中法流 of Honzan School. It can be said that the main point common in both schools is to put the priority on practice; practitioners of austerity completely give up any meaningless discussion based on worldly words/thoughts; they only concentrate on practice in mountains or in training halls near which people live.</e>
<cmt>峰受法流は発音もわかりませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ein Ho of Tozan School is also called 峰受法流 because of Rei sojo (initiation in an unseen and wondrous method) by Ryuju Bosatsu and is sometimes contrasted with 峰中法流 of Honzan School. It can be said that the main point common in both schools is to put the priority on practice; practitioners of austerity completely give up any meaningless discussion based on worldly words/thoughts; they only concentrate on practice in mountains or in training halls near which people live.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ein Ho (ritual) of Tozan School is also called Bujuho (practice on the mountain) School because of Rei sojo (initiation in an unseen and wondrous method) by Ryuju Bosatsu and is sometimes contrasted with Buchuho (practice on the mountains) School of Honzan School, however, it can be said that the main point common in both schools is to put the priority on practice; practitioners of austerity completely give up any meaningless discussion based on worldly words and thoughts; they only concentrate on practice in mountains or in training halls near which people live.</e>
<cmt>補足し、表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>このことは、神秘直感を通じて般若空の真理に直参せんとした大乗仏教中観派の法匠たる龍樹菩薩の教えを忠実にすることに通じるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is connected with following the teaching of Ryuju Bosatsu, the master of Chukan school of Mahayana Buddhism, who tried to reach directly the truth of Hannyaku through mystic instinct.</e>
<cmt>般若空の英訳がわかりませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is connected with following the teaching of Ryuju Bosatsu, the master of Chukan school of Mahayana Buddhism, who tried to reach directly the truth of Hannyaku through mystic instinct.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is connected with following the teaching of Ryuju Bosatsu, the master of Chukan School of Mahayana Buddhism, who tried to reach directly the truth of Hannya-ku through mystic instinct.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>また理智不二礼讃によって明かされる清浄菩提心に向かう祈りの実践は、真言第三祖／龍猛ナーガルジュナの直系たることを自覚するものであり、同時に、全ては普門総徳大日如来から生み出される別徳諸仏諸菩薩の理趣を体得せんとして在る真言密教への篤信と確信に繋がるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The practice of prayer directed to pure bodhisattva&apos;s spiritual awakening which is opened by 理智不二礼讃 is done in order that the prayer recognizes that he/she is in a direct line of Shingon&apos;s third founder/ 龍猛ナーガルジュ; at the same time, the practice is connected to the belief in and assuarance of Shingon Esoteric Buddhism, which exists so as that its believers try to realize rishu of 別徳諸仏諸菩薩, which are made from Fumon Sotoku Dainichi Nyorai (the Tathagata Mahavairocana).</e>
<cmt>理智不二礼讃発音もわかりませんでした。真言第三祖龍猛ナーガルジュ別徳諸仏諸菩薩についても、わかりませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The practice of prayer directed to pure bodhisattva&apos;s spiritual awakening which is opened by 理智不二礼讃 is done in order that the prayer recognizes that he/she is in a direct line of Shingon&apos;s third founder/ 龍猛ナーガルジュ. At the same time, the practice is connected to the belief in and assuarance of Shingon Esoteric Buddhism, which exists so as that its believers try to realize rishu of 別徳諸仏諸菩薩, which are made from Fumon Sotoku Dainichi Nyorai (the Tathagata Mahavairocana).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The practice of prayer directed to pure bodhisattva&apos;s spiritual awakening which is opened by Richi funi Raisan is done in order that the prayer recognizes that he or she is in a direct line of Shingon&apos;s third founder, Naagaarjuna (Ryuju), and at the same time, the practice is connected to the belief in and assurance of Shingon Esoteric Buddhism, which exists so as that its believers try to realize rishu (the Principle of the Perfection of Wisdom) of bettoku (Distinguished virtue) Buddhas and Bodhisattvas, which all are made from Dainichi Nyorai as Fumon Sotoku (all virtues of Universal Gateway).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), Nnh(id:474), 与左衛門(id:159462), Boca samba(id:137526), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), Andee(id:20421), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>