<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>般若心経秘鍵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hannyashin-gyo Hiken</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hannyashin-gyo Hiken</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hannyashin-gyo Hiken</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>『般若心経秘鍵』（はんにゃしんぎょう ひけん）は、818年頃に空海によって書かれた『般若心経』の注釈書である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hannyashin-gyo Hiken&quot; was a commentary on &quot;the Wisdom Sutras (Hannya Shingyo)&quot; and the commentary was written by Kukai around 818.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hannyashin-gyo Hiken&quot; was a commentary on &quot;the Wisdom Sutras (Hannya Shingyo)&quot; and was written by Kukai around 818.</e>
<cmt>omitted unnecessary words</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Hannyashin-gyo Hiken&quot; was a commentary on &quot;Hannya Shingyo&quot; (the Wisdom Sutras) and was written by Kukai around 818.</e>
<cmt>&quot;位置調整</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>真言宗系の宗派によっては、『般若心経秘鍵』を枕経として読む場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some schools of Shingon sect sometimes read &quot;Hannyashin-gyo Hiken&quot;as makura-gyo Death Guidance(pillow sutra).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some schools of the Shingon sect sometimes read &quot;Hannyashin-gyo Hiken&quot; as makura-gyo Death Guidance (pillow sutra).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some schools of the Shingon sect sometimes read &quot;Hannyashin-gyo Hiken&quot; as makura-gyo Death Guidance (pillow sutra).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>内容</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Content</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Content</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Content</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>まず、『般若心経』の鳩摩羅什訳と大遍覚三蔵（玄奘）訳との異同点を指摘し、次いで『般若心経』を般若菩薩の大心真言による深い禅定に入るための教えと定義している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It points out the similarities and differences between Kumaraju&apos;s translation of &quot;Hannya Shingyo&quot; and Daihenkaku Sanjo&apos;s (Xuan Zang) translation and it also defines &quot;Hannya Shingyo&quot;as a teaching to dive into deep meditation with the help of Daishin Shingon mantra of Hannya-bosatsu.</e>
<cmt>大遍覚三蔵の英語表記が不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It points out the similarities and differences between Kumaraju&apos;s translation of &quot;Hannya Shingyo&quot; and Daihenkaku Sanjo&apos;s (Xuan Zang) translation and it also defines &quot;Hannya Shingyo&quot;as a teaching to dive into deep meditation with the help of Daishin Shingon mantra of Hannya-bosatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It points out the similarities and differences between Kumaraju&apos;s translation of &quot;Hannya Shingyo&quot; and Daihenkaku Sanjo&apos;s (Xuan Zang) translation and it also defines &quot;Hannya Shingyo&quot; as a teaching to dive into deep meditation with the help of Daishin Shingon mantra of Hannya-bosatsu.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>そして、龍に蛇の鱗があると雖も、両者を同じと見てはならない事と同様に、『般若心経』に『大般若波羅蜜多経』と同じ文言があるからといって混同してはならないと説いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It preaches that &quot;Hannya Shingyo&quot;should not be mixed with &quot;Daihannyaharamitta-kyo Sutra&quot; because both contian same phrases just as dragons shouldn&apos;t be considered the same as snakes because both have the same squamas.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It preaches that &quot;Hannya Shingyo&quot;should not be mixed with &quot;Daihannyaharamitta-kyo Sutra,&quot; because they contain the same phrases, just as dragons shouldn&apos;t be considered the same as snakes because both have the same scales.</e>
<cmt>word choice, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It preaches that &quot;Hannya Shingyo&quot; should not be mixed with &quot;Daihannyaharamitta-kyo Sutra,&quot; because they contain the same phrases, just as dragons shouldn&apos;t be considered the same as snakes because both have the same scales.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>『般若心経』を『大般若経』600巻の要約とする見方を批判している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It criticizes the perspective to consider &quot;Hannya Shingyo&quot; as the summary of 600 volumes of &quot;Dai Hannya Shingyo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It criticizes the perspective of considering &quot;Hannya Shingyo&quot; to be the summary of 600 volumes of &quot;Dai Hannya Shingyo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It criticizes the perspective of considering &quot;Hannya Shingyo&quot; to be the summary of 600 volumes of &quot;Dai Hannya Shingyo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>また、最後の部分に真言がされている事に着目し、『般若心経』を読誦するのではなく、観誦（真言念誦による瞑想）の対象とし、その実践を勧めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also pays attention to Shingon granted to the last part and recommends that you should not read &quot;Hannya Shingyo&quot; but make it the object for kansho (meditation based on Shingon nenju) and practice it.</e>
<cmt>観誦の英語表現が不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also pays attention to Shingon granted to the last part and recommends that you should not read &quot;Hannya Shingyo&quot; but make it the object for kansho (meditation based on Shingon nenju) and practice it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also pays attention to Shingon granted to the last part and recommends that you should not read &quot;Hannya Shingyo&quot; but make it the object for kansho (meditation based on Shingon nenju) and practice it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), Taikan(id:24791), Kstigarbha(id:13376), R28Bot(id:177951), ウィキ豊(id:82961), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>