<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>性信</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoshin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoshin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoshin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>性信（しょうしん、文治3年（1187年） - 建治元年7月17日 (旧暦)（1275年8月9日））は、鎌倉時代中期の浄土真宗の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoshin (1187-August 9, 1275) is a monk of the Jodo- Shinshu (True Pure Land) Sect of Buddhism who lived in the middle of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoshin (1187-August 9, 1275) is a monk of the Jodo- Shinshu (True Pure Land) Sect of Buddhism who lived during the middle of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoshin (1187 - August 16, 1275) is a Buddhist priest of the Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) who lived during the middle of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>俗姓は大中臣与四郎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His secular name is ONAKATOMI no Yoshiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His secular name is ONAKATOMI no Yoshiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His secular name is ONAKATOMI no Yoshiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>常陸国の出身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is from the Hitachi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is from Hitachi Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is from Hitachi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>親鸞二十四輩の筆頭。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is the top of the twenty-four apprentices of Shinran (founder of the Jodo-Shinshu Sect).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is the top of the twenty-four apprentices of Shinran (founder of the Jodo-Shinshu Sect).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is the top of the twenty-four apprentices of Shinran (founder of the Jodo Shinshu).</e>
<cmt>Jodo Shinshu としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>1204年（元久元年）出家して法然に師事して浄土教を学び、のちに親鸞に帰依した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After becoming a priest in 1204, he studied Jodo (Pure Land) Sect of Buddhism under Honen (founder of Jodo Sect) and later became a biliever in Shinran&apos;s teachings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After becoming a priest in 1204, he studied Jodo (Pure Land) Sect of Buddhism under Honen (founder of Jodo Sect) and later became a biliever in Shinran&apos;s teachings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After becoming a priest in 1204, he studied Jodo (Pure Land) sect of Buddhism under Honen (founder of Jodo sect) and later became a believer in Shinran&apos;s teachings.</e>
<cmt>Jodo sect としました。スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>下総国横曾根（現在茨城県常総市）に報恩寺を建立し、横曾根・飯沼を中心とする横曾根門徒の中心的人物となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He built Hoon-ji Temple in Yokozone of the Shimousa Province (the present Joso City, Ibaraki Prefecture) and became a leading figure of the Yokozone monto (followers in Yokozone) centering around Yokozone and Iinuma</e>
<cmt>下総は「しもうさ」または「しもふさ」の両方ありますが、地元では「しもうさ」のようです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He built Hoon-ji Temple in Yokozone of the Shimousa Province (the present Joso City, Ibaraki Prefecture) and became a leading figure of the Yokozone monto (followers in Yokozone) centering around Yokozone and Iinuma</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He built Hoon-ji Temple in Yokozone of the Shimosa Province (the present Joso City, Ibaraki Prefecture) and became a leading figure of the Yokozone monto (followers in Yokozone) centering around Yokozone and Iinuma.</e>
<cmt>Shimosa としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>親鸞の子善鸞が起こした異端事件では、その解決に尽力したことで知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Heretical Incident (it refers to an incident that Zenran caused confusion among followers by spreading false teachings of Shinran) caused by Zenran, Shinran&apos;s son, Shoshin is known for his devotion to solution of the problem.</e>
<cmt>善鸞http://kotobank.jp/word/%E5%96%84%E9%B8%9E</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Heretical Incident (it refers to an incident where Zenran caused confusion among followers by spreading false teachings of Shinran) caused by Zenran, Shinran&apos;s son, Shoshin known for his devotion to solution of the problem.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Heretical Incident (it refers to an incident where Zenran caused confusion among followers by spreading false teachings of Shinran) caused by Zenran, Shinran&apos;s son, Shoshin was known for his devotion to solution of the problem.</e>
<cmt>shoshin was としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Sprinkler(id:14399), 0太郎(id:7375), R28Bot(id:177951), 水野白楓(id:22811), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), 電田蒸(id:249216), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>