<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大休宗休</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daikyu Sokyu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daikyu Sokyu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daikyu Sokyu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大休宗休（だいきゅうそうきゅう、応仁2年（1468年） － 天文 (元号)18年8月24日 (旧暦)（1549年9月15日））は、戦国時代 (日本)の臨済宗の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daikyu Sokyu (born 1468, died September 15, 2549) was a Sengoku (Warring States) period Zen Buddhist monk of the Rinzai school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daikyu Sokyu (born 1468, died September 15, 2549) was a Sengoku (Warring States) period Zen Buddhist monk of the Rinzai school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daikyu Sokyu (1468 - September 25, 1549) was a priest of Rinzai Sect in the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>出自については不詳である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nothing is known of his birthplace or family lineage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nothing is known of his birthplace or family lineage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nothing is known of his birthplace or family lineage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>諱は宗休。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His personal name was Sokyu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His personal name was Sokyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His imina (personal name) was Sokyu.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>道号は大休。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His self-chosen Buddhist name was Daikyu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His self-chosen Buddhist name was Daikyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His dogo (a pseudonym as a priest) was Daikyu.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>諡号は円満本光国師。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His posthumous religious name was &quot;Enman Hoko Kokushi&quot; (Perfect Source of Light who Teaches the Lands).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His posthumous religious name was &quot;Enman Hoko Kokushi&quot; (Perfect Source of Light who Teaches the Lands).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His shigo (a posthumous name) was Enman Hoko Kokushi (Perfect Source of Light who Teaches the Lands).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>幼いとき京都の東福寺永明庵で出家して学び、のち龍安寺の特芳禅傑に師事して参禅し、その印可を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he was still a boy, he took the tonsure (became a priest) at Tofukuji temple in Kyoto and began his religious studies there; later he took Tokuho Zenketsu (a Zen Buddhist priest) of Ryoanji temple as his mentor and began training in Zen meditation, formally receiving the transmission of the dharma from his master Tokuho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he was still a boy, he took the tonsure (became a priest) at Tofukuji temple in Kyoto and began his religious studies there; later he took Tokuho Zenketsu (a Zen Buddhist priest) of Ryoanji temple as his mentor and began training in Zen meditation, formally receiving the transmission of the dharma from his master Tokuho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he was a child, he took the tonsure (became a priest) at Yomeian of Tofuku-ji Temple in Kyoto and began his religious studies there; later he took Tokuho Zenketsu (a Zen Buddhist priest) of Ryoan-ji Temple as his mentor and began training in Zen meditation, formally receiving the transmission of the dharma from his master Tokuho.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>特芳の死後は西源院・龍安寺の住持を経て妙心寺の住持となったが、晩年は霊雲院を開創してそこに住した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Tokuho&apos;s death, Daikyu became the chief priest of Saigenin and Ryoanji temples before eventually becoming chief priest of Myoshinji temple; in his later years, he founded Ryounin temple and took up residence there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Tokuho&apos;s death, Daikyu became the chief priest of Saigenin and Ryoanji temples before eventually becoming chief priest of Myoshinji temple; in his later years, he founded Ryounin temple and took up residence there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Tokuho&apos;s death, Daikyu assumed the position of chief priest of Saigenin and Ryoan-ji Temples before eventually becoming chief priest of Myoshin-ji Temple; in his later years, he founded Ryounin Temple and took up residence there.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>今川義元の招きにより、駿河国に臨済寺 (静岡市)を開山したが、のち妙心寺・尾張国瑞泉寺等を歴住した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the invitation of Yoshimoto IMAGAWA, he also founded Rinsaiji temple in Sagawa province (modern-day Okayama Prefecture); thereafter, he served successively as chief priest at other temples, including Myoshinji and then Zuisenji, the latter of which was located in Owari province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the invitation of Yoshimoto IMAGAWA, he also founded Rinsaiji temple in Sagawa province (modern-day Okayama Prefecture); thereafter, he served successively as chief priest at other temples, including Myoshinji and then Zuisenji, the latter of which was located in Owari province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the invitation of Yoshimoto IMAGAWA, he also founded Rinsai-ji Temple in Suruga Province (present-day Shizuoka City); thereafter, he served successively as chief priest at other temples, including Myoshin-ji Temple and then Zuisen-ji Temple, the latter of which was located in Owari Province.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>後奈良天皇に臨済宗の宗義を進講し、円満本光国師の諡号を賜った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daikyu also gave a lecture on the doctrine of the Rinzai school in the presence of Emperor Gonara, and was honored with the posthumous name &quot;Enman Honko Kokushi&quot; (Perfect Source of Light who Teaches the Lands).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daikyu also gave a lecture on the doctrine of the Rinzai school in the presence of Emperor Gonara, and was honored with the posthumous name &quot;Enman Honko Kokushi&quot; (Perfect Source of Light who Teaches the Lands).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daikyu also gave a lecture on the doctrine of the Rinzai Sect in the presence of Emperor Gonara, and was honored with the posthumous name Enman Honko Kokushi.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), R28Bot(id:177951), ウィキ豊(id:82961), Cprobot(id:97843), Nighthawks(id:36125), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>