<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>禅定道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Zenjodo&quot; (A Path Up The Sacred Mountain)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Zenjodo&quot; (the path up a sacred mountain)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zenjodo</e>
<cmt>タイトルであり、次セルに説明があるため補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>禅定道（ぜんじょうどう）とは、禅頂（山頂）に登ぼるまでの山道を言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Zenjodo&quot; is the mountain path that leads to &quot;zencho&quot; (the peak of a sacred mountain).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Zenjodo&quot; is the mountain path that leads to &quot;zencho&quot; (the peak of a sacred mountain).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zenjodo is the mountain path that leads to zencho (the peak of a sacred mountain).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>富士山・立山・白山などの霊山に登って修行することを禅定という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the ascetic deeds on a sacred mountain, such as Mt. Fuji, Mt. Tateyama and Mt. Hakusan, are called &quot;zenjo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>・「立山」や「白山」も「富士山」の表記に合わせるとしたら&quot;Mt. Tate&quot; &quot;Mt. Haku&quot; かもしれませんが、これはあまり聞かない表現です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ascetic deeds performed on a sacred mountain, such as Mt. Fuji, Mt. Tateyama or Mt. Hakusan, are called &quot;zenjo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ascetic deeds performed on a sacred mountain, such as Mt. Fuji, Mt. Tateyama or Mt. Hakusan, are called zenjo.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>奈良時代より、高い山や、美しい山は霊山として山岳信仰の対象とされ、山地に於いて修行する者も現れ、それらは後に修験道へと発展していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the Nara period, high or beautiful mountains in Japan have been the object of a mountain religion, so some people began to implement their ascetic deeds on a mountain, and afterwards, these deeds developed into &quot;shugendo&quot; (Japanese mountain asceticism-shamanism incoporating Shinto and Buddhist concepts).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Nara period, high or beautiful mountains in Japan have been the object of a mountain religion, so some people began to implement their ascetic deeds on mountains; subsequently, these deeds developed into &quot;shugendo&quot; (Japanese mountain asceticism/shamanism incorporating Shinto and Buddhist concepts).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Nara period, high or beautiful mountains in Japan have been the object of a mountain religion, so some people began to implement their ascetic deeds on mountains; subsequently, these deeds developed into shugendo (Japanese mountain asceticism and shamanism incorporating Shinto and Buddhist concepts).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Lennon(id:20471), Akimoto(id:6951), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Khhy(id:13490), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>