<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大谷祖廟</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otani Sobyo Mausoleum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otani Sobyo Mausoleum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otani Sobyo Mausoleum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>大谷祖廟（おおたにそびょう）は、京都府京都市東山区にある、真宗大谷派（東本願寺）の宗祖親鸞の墓。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otani Sobyo Mausoleum is the grave of Shinran, the founder of the Shinshu sect Otani school (the Higashi Hongan-ji Temple), which is located in Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otani Sobyo Mausoleum is the grave of Shinran, the founder of the Shinshu sect Otani school (Higashi Hongan-ji Temple), which is located in Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otani Sobyo Mausoleum is the grave of Shinran, the founder of the Shinshu sect Otani school (Higashi Hongan-ji Temple), which is located in Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>通称・東大谷。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is commonly called Higashi Otani.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is commonly called Higashi Otani.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is commonly called Higashi Otani.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>（同じ京都市東山区内に、浄土真宗本願寺派（西本願寺）が宗祖親鸞の墓所としている大谷本廟（西大谷）があるため）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(This is because there is also Otani Honbyo Mausoleum (Nishi Otani) which the Jodo Shin (True Pure Land) sect Hongan-ji school (Nishi Hongan-ji Temple) considers as the grave of Shinran, the founder of its sect, in the Higashiyama Ward.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(This is because there is also the Otani Honbyo Mausoleum (Nishi Otani) which the Jodo Shin (True Pure Land) sect Hongan-ji school (Nishi Hongan-ji Temple) considers as the grave of Shinran, the founder of its sect, in Higashiyama Ward.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(This is because there is also the Otani Honbyo Mausoleum (Nishi Otani) which the Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) Hongan-ji school (Nishi Hongan-ji Temple) considers as the grave of Shinran, the founder of its sect, in Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City.)</e>
<cmt>Kyoto City補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>1272年（文永9年）に東山大谷の地に建立された親鸞の祖廟大谷廟堂（のちの大谷本願寺）に由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It originates from the Otani-byodo Mausoleum (later Otani Hongan-ji Temple), which was the grave of Shinran built at Otani, Higashiyama Ward in 1272.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It originates from the Otani-byodo Mausoleum (later called Otani Hongan-ji Temple), which was the grave of Shinran built at Otani, Higashiyama Ward in 1272.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It originates from the Otani-byodo Mausoleum (later called Otani Hongan-ji Temple), which was the grave of Shinran built at Otani, Higashiyama Ward in 1272.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>1670年（寛文10年）に祖廟を現在地に改葬した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1670, the grave of the founder was reburied at the present place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1670, the grave of the founder was relocated to the present place.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1670, the grave of the founder was relocated to the present place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>境内の御廟や真宗大谷派（東本願寺）の門信徒による多くの墓碑が建ち並ぶ東大谷墓地には墓参の信徒が絶えない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many believers of the Shinshu sect Otani school (the Higashi Hongan-ji Temple) continuously visit the Mausoleum in precinct and Higashi Otani Cemetery where there are many graves of their ancestors for worship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many believers of the Shinshu sect Otani school (the Higashi Hongan-ji Temple) continuously visit the Mausoleum in the precinct and at Higashi Otani Cemetery where there are many graves of their ancestors to worship.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many believers of the Shinshu sect Otani school (the Higashi Hongan-ji Temple) continuously visit the Mausoleum in the precinct and at Higashi Otani Cemetery where there are many graves of their ancestors to worship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>毎年お盆（8月14日～16日）の夜に「東大谷万灯会」（ひがしおおたにまんとうえ）が行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the nights of Obon festival (a Festival of the Dead or Buddhist All Soul&apos;s Day) (August 14-16) every year, &apos;Higashi Otani Mantoe Festival&apos; is held.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the nights of Obon festival (a Festival of the Dead or Buddhist All Soul&apos;s Day) (August 14-16) every year, the &apos;Higashi Otani Mantoe Festival&apos; is held.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the nights of Obon festival (a Festival of the Dead or Buddhist All Soul&apos;s Day) (August 14-16) every year, the &apos;Higashi Otani Mantoe Festival&apos; is held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>1272年（文永9年）　親鸞の祖廟、大谷廟堂（のちの本願寺）建立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1272 the Otani-byodo Mausoleum (later Higashi Hongan-ji Temple), the grave of Shinran, was built.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1272 the Otani-byodo Mausoleum (later Higashi Hongan-ji Temple), the grave of Shinran, was built.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1272 the Otani-byodo Mausoleum (later Higashi Hongan-ji Temple), the grave of Shinran, was built.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>（本願寺の歴史の詳細は本願寺の歴史の項目を参照）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(For the detail of the history of Hongan-ji Temple, see the article of the history of the Hongan-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(For the details on the history of Hongan-ji Temple, see the article about the history of the Hongan-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(For the details on the history of Hongan-ji Temple, see the article about the history of the Hongan-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>1465年（寛正6年）　延暦寺西塔の衆徒らによって大谷本願寺破却される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1465 the Otani Hongan-ji Temple was destroyed by monk-soldiers of Enryaku-ji Temple Saito (West Tower).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1465 the Otani Hongan-ji Temple was destroyed by monk-soldiers from Enryaku-ji Temple Saito (West Tower).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1465 the Otani Hongan-ji Temple was destroyed by monk-soldiers from Enryaku-ji Temple Saito (West Tower).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>破却後は井上願知なる人物によって祖墳が守護され、大谷道場と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After destruction, the founder&apos;s grave was preserved by a person named Ganchi INOUE and it became to be called Otani Dojo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After destruction, the founder&apos;s grave was preserved by a person named Ganchi INOUE and it came to be called Otani Dojo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After destruction, the founder&apos;s grave was preserved by a person named Ganchi INOUE and it came to be called Otani Dojo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>1532年（天文 (日本)元年）　山科本願寺破却（天文の錯乱）、大谷道場も破却される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1532 the Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple was destroyed (Tenbun War) and Otani Dojo was also destroyed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1532 the Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple was destroyed (Tenbun War) and the Otani Dojo was also destroyed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1532 the Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple was destroyed (Tenbun War) and the Otani Dojo was also destroyed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>願知の子孫・祐願によって復興。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was revived by Yugan (祐願), a descendant of Ganchi.</e>
<cmt>「祐願」の読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was restored by Yugan (祐願), a descendant of Ganchi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was restored by Yugan, a descendant of Ganchi.</e>
<cmt>(祐願)削除→読み方不明</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>1571年（元亀2年）　石山合戦に際し、大谷道場破却される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1571, Otani Dojo was destroyed at the time of Ishiyama War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1571, the Otani Dojo was destroyed at the time of the Ishiyama War.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1571, the Otani Dojo was destroyed at the time of the Ishiyama War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>1589年（天正17年）　祐願の妻・妙祐と子息・祐誓、大谷道場の復興にあたって豊臣秀吉から地銭免除の朱印状を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1589 Yugan&apos;s wife Myoyu and his son Yusei (祐誓) were given Shuinjo(Shogunate license to trade)for land tax free by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI for the restoration.</e>
<cmt>「祐誓」の読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1589 Yugan&apos;s wife Myoyu and son Yusei (祐誓) were given Shuinjo(Shogunate license to trade)for land tax free by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI for the restoration.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1589 Yugan&apos;s wife Myoyu and son Yusei were given Shuinjo(Shogunate license to trade)for land tax free by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI for the restoration.</e>
<cmt>(祐誓) 削除→読み方不明</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="16">
<j>1602年（慶長7年）　本願寺の東西分立に際して、東本願寺第12代教如が東本願寺境内に親鸞及び本願寺歴代の仮墓を建立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1602 when the Hongan-ji Temple split into east and west, Kyonyo, the twelfth head priest of the Higashi Hongan-ji Temple had the tentative grave of Shinran and successive heads of Hongan-ji Temple built.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1602 when the Hongan-ji Temple split into east and west, Kyonyo, the twelfth head priest of the Higashi Hongan-ji Temple had the tentative grave of Shinran and successive heads of Hongan-ji Temple built.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1602 when the Hongan-ji Temple split into east and west, Kyonyo, the twelfth head priest of the Higashi Hongan-ji Temple had the tentative grave of Shinran and successive heads of Hongan-ji Temple built.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="17">
<j>1603年（慶長8年）　知恩院拡張造営に際し、祐誓の妹婿の善了の申し出により、親鸞荼毘の延仁寺の旧地と伝えられる鳥部山に代替地を拝領する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1603 when the Chion-in Temple was constructed for expansion, it was given the alternative land in Mt. Toribe, which was said to be the former land of the Ennin-ji Temple where Shinran was cremated by a proportion of Zenryo (善了), the husband of Yusei&apos;s sister.</e>
<cmt>「善了」の読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1603 when the Chion-in Temple was expanded, it was given more land on Mt. Toribe, which was said to belong to the Ennin-ji Temple where Shinran was cremated by a proportion of Zenryo (善了), the husband of Yusei&apos;s sister.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1603 when the Chion-in Temple was expanded, it was given more land on Mt. Toribe, which was said to belong to the Ennin-ji Temple where Shinran was cremated by a proportion of Zenryo, the husband of Yusei&apos;s sister.</e>
<cmt>(善了)削除→読み方不明</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="18">
<j>大谷道場の御堂は、知恩院造営に先立って1600年（慶長5年）に教如の命によって祐誓が四条富小路に移し、徳勝寺（現・徳正寺。真宗大谷派寺院）を創建した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hall of Otani Dojo was moved to Shijo Tomino-koji by Yusei and had the Tokusho-ji (徳勝寺) Temple (present Tokusho-ji (徳正寺) Temple. A temple of the Shinshu sect Otani school) built in 1600 before the construction of the Chion-in Temple by an order of Kyonyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Otani Dojo hall was moved to Shijo Tomino-koji by Yusei and it had the Tokusho-ji (徳勝寺) Temple (present day Tokusho-ji (徳正寺) Temple. A temple of the Shinshu sect Otani school) built in 1600 before the construction of the Chion-in Temple by an order of Kyonyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Otani Dojo hall was moved to Shijo Tomino-koji by Yusei and it had the Tokusho-ji (徳勝寺) Temple (present day Tokusho-ji (徳正寺) Temple. A temple of the Shinshu sect Otani school) built in 1600 before the construction of the Chion-in Temple by an order of Kyonyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="19">
<j>鳥部山の寺地拝領後、善了は大谷道場を改めて勝久寺を創建した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After receiving the land for temple in Mt.Toribe, Zenryo had the Shokyu-ji Temple built, changing its name from Otani Dojo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After receiving the land for temple on Mt.Toribe, Zenryo had the Shokyu-ji Temple built, changing its name from Otani Dojo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After receiving the land for temple on Mt. Toribe, Zenryo had the Shokyu-ji Temple built, changing its name from Otani Dojo.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="20">
<j>旧地には知恩院塔頭崇泰院が建立されたが、知恩院作事奉行の一人、勝誉道清によって祖墳遺跡が残されることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the former land, the Sotai-in Temple, a tatchu (small housing) of the Chion-in Temple was built and the monument of founder&apos;s grave was left by Michikiyo SHOYO (勝誉道清), one of the construction officers of the Chion-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>「勝誉道清」の読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the former land, the Sotai-in Temple, a tatchu (small housing) of the Chion-in Temple was built and the monument of founder&apos;s grave was left by Michikiyo SHOYO (勝誉道清), one of the construction officers of the Chion-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the former land, the Sotai-in Temple, a tatchu (small housing) of the Chion-in Temple was built and the monument of founder&apos;s grave was left by Michikiyo SHOYO, one of the construction officers of the Chion-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>(勝誉道清)削除→読み方不明</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="21">
<j>1639年（寛永16年）　勝久寺、西本願寺に属する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1639 the Shokyu-ji Temple became a subsidiary of the Nishi Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1639 the Shokyu-ji Temple became a subsidiary of the Nishi Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1639 the Shokyu-ji Temple became a subsidiary of the Nishi Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="22">
<j>その後、勝久寺は西本願寺の親鸞廟所として整備され、大谷本廟（西大谷）となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, the Shokyu-ji Temple was maintained as the grave of Shinran of the Nishi Hongan-ji Temple and became the Otani Sobyo Mausoleum (Nishi Otani).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, the Shokyu-ji Temple was maintained as the grave of Shinran of the Nishi Hongan-ji Temple and became the Otani Sobyo Mausoleum (Nishi Otani).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, the Shokyu-ji Temple was maintained as the grave of Shinran of the Nishi Hongan-ji Temple and became the Otani Sobyo Mausoleum (Nishi Otani).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="23">
<j>大谷本願寺旧跡由緒の勝久寺が西本願寺の傘下に入ったことにより、東本願寺第14世琢如の代になって、東本願寺では新祖廟造営が求められるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Shokyu-ji Temple which originated from the ruin of Otani Hongan-ji Temple became a subsidiary of the Nishi Hongan-ji Temple, Takunyo, the fourteenth head priest of the Higashi Hongan-ji Temple, was requested to built a new Mausoleum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Shokyu-ji Temple originating from the ruins of the Otani Hongan-ji Temple became a subsidiary of the Nishi Hongan-ji Temple, Takunyo, the fourteenth head priest of the Higashi Hongan-ji Temple, was requested to build a new Mausoleum.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Shokyu-ji Temple originating from the ruins of the Otani Hongan-ji Temple became a subsidiary of the Nishi Hongan-ji Temple, Takunyo, the fourteenth head priest of the Higashi Hongan-ji Temple, was requested to build a new Mausoleum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="24">
<j>1670年（寛文10年）　琢如、東本願寺境内の親鸞及び本願寺歴代の仮墓を、教如・宣如の両墓と共に現在地に移し、大谷御坊と称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1670, Takunyo moved the tentative graves of Shinran and the successive heads of Hongan-ji Temple in the precincts of the Higashi Hongan-ji Temple to the present place with both graves of Kyonyo and Sennyo, and named them as Otani Gobo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1670, Takunyo moved the tentative graves of Shinran and the successive heads of the Hongan-ji Temple in the precincts of the Higashi Hongan-ji Temple to their present location with both graves of Kyonyo and Sennyo, and named them Otani Gobo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1670, Takunyo moved the tentative graves of Shinran and the successive heads of the Hongan-ji Temple in the precincts of the Higashi Hongan-ji Temple to their present location with both graves of Kyonyo and Sennyo, and named them Otani Gobo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="25">
<j>1699年（元禄12年）　東本願寺第15世一如 (僧)、祖廟改築を着工。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1699 Ichinyo, the fifteenth head priest of the Higashi Hongan-ji Temple, began to have the Mausoleum reconstructed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1699 Ichinyo, the fifteenth head priest of Higashi Hongan-ji Temple, started reconstruction of the Mausoleum.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1699 Ichinyo, the fifteenth head priest of Higashi Hongan-ji Temple, started reconstruction of the Mausoleum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="26">
<j>翌年に一如入滅によって工事は一時中断するが、1701年（元禄14年）、東本願寺第16世真如は一周忌厳修の後に工事を再開、この年に祖墳の改葬を行われ、本堂が完成。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following year, the work of construction was interrupted by the nirvana of Ichinyo, but in 1701 Shinnyo, the sixteenth head priest of the Higashi Hongan-ji Temple, started the construction again after the stately ceremonial of first anniversary of his death, and reburied the founder&apos;s grave in this year and completed the construction of the main hall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following year, construction was interrupted by the nirvana of Ichinyo, but in 1701 Shinnyo, the sixteenth head priest of the Higashi Hongan-ji Temple, restarted the construction after the stately ceremony on first anniversary of his death, and relocated the founder&apos;s grave and completed the construction of the main hall.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following year, construction was interrupted by the nirvana of Ichinyo, but in 1701 Shinnyo, the sixteenth head priest of the Higashi Hongan-ji Temple, restarted the construction after the stately ceremony on first anniversary of his death, and relocated the founder&apos;s grave and completed the construction of the main hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="27">
<j>1703年（元禄16年）　真如、遷仏会を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1703 Shinyo held the ceremony for the transmission of the grave.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1703 Shinyo held the ceremony for the grave.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1703 Shinyo held the ceremony for the grave.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="28">
<j>1709年（宝永6年）　虎石を祖墳上に置く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1709 Toraishi (虎石, literally, &apos;a stone of tiger&apos;) was put on the founder&apos;s grave.</e>
<cmt>「虎石」の読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1709 Toraishi (虎石, literally, &apos;a stone of tiger&apos;) was placed on the founder&apos;s grave.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1709 Toraishi (literally, &apos;a stone of tiger&apos;) was placed on the founder&apos;s grave.</e>
<cmt>虎石, 削除→読み方不明</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="29">
<j>1745年（延享2年）　幕府より一万坪の寄付を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1745 it was donated the land of 33,000 square meters by bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1745 33,000 square meters of land was donated by the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1745 33,000 square meters of land was donated by the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="30">
<j>1820年（文政3年）　大谷新道を開く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1820 a new road of Otani was constructed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1820 a new road for Otani was constructed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1820 a new road for Otani was constructed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="31">
<j>1857年（安政4年）　大谷新道南北の畑地を買い取る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1857 it bought the dry field on the north and south sides of the new road of Otani.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1857 a dry field on the north and south sides of the new road of Otani was purchased.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1857 a dry field on the north and south sides of the new road of Otani was purchased.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>四脚門移建。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yotsuashimon Gate (four-legged gate) was moved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yotsuashimon Gate (four-legged gate) was moved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yotsuashimon Gate (four-legged gate) was moved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="33">
<j>名称については、江戸時代は大谷御坊と呼ばれたが、1872年（明治5年）に大谷管刹（かんさつ）、1876年（明治9年）に大谷別院と改称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was called Otani Gobo during the Edo period, but changed its name to Otani Kansatsu in 1872 and Otani Betsuin in 1876.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was called Otani Gobo during the Edo period, but its name was changed to Otani Kansatsu in 1872 and to Otani Betsuin in 1876.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was called Otani Gobo during the Edo period, but its name was changed to Otani Kansatsu in 1872 and to Otani Betsuin in 1876.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>1952年（昭和27年）に東本願寺の飛び地境内と定められて大谷本廟と称し、1981年（昭和56年）に現在の名称である大谷祖廟となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was defined as the outland precinct of the Higashi Hongan-ji Temple and changed the name to Otani Honbyo in 1952, and changed the name to the present Otani Sobyo in 1981.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was defined as the outland precinct of Higashi Hongan-ji Temple and the name was changed to Otani Honbyo in 1952, and then the name was changed to the present Otani Sobyo in 1981.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was defined as the outland precinct of Higashi Hongan-ji Temple and the name was changed to Otani Honbyo in 1952, and then the name was changed to the present Otani Sobyo in 1981.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="35">
<j>東本願寺は江戸時代に4度の火災に遭っているが、その際には大谷祖廟が御真影（親鸞の影像）の避難所となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Higashi Hongan-ji Temple suffered fire four times in the Edo period, and the Otani Sobyo Mausoleum was the evacuation center of goshin-ei (portrait) of Shinran at each time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Higashi Hongan-ji Temple suffered fire four times during the Edo period, and the Otani Sobyo Mausoleum was the evacuation center for goshin-ei (portrait) of Shinran each time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Higashi Hongan-ji Temple suffered fire four times during the Edo period, and the Otani Sobyo Mausoleum was the evacuation center for goshin-ei (portrait) of Shinran each time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>1823年（文政6年）の2度目の火災は11月15日であったため、この年の7昼夜の御正忌報恩講は大谷祖廟において勤められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the second fire was happened on November 15, Goshoki Hon-ko (a memorial services for Shinran held in the head temple of Jodoshin sect) of this year was performed at the Otani Sobyo Mausoleum for seven days and nights.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the second fire was happened on November 15, Goshoki Hon-ko (a memorial services for Shinran held in the head temple of Jodoshin sect) of this year was performed at the Otani Sobyo Mausoleum for seven days and nights.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the second fire was happened on December 16, Goshoki Hon-ko (a memorial services for Shinran held in the head temple of Jodo Shinshu sect) of this year was performed at the Otani Sobyo Mausoleum for seven days and nights.</e>
<cmt>用語統一グレゴリオ歴に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>所在地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Location</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Location</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Location</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="37">
<j>京都府京都市東山区円山町477番地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">477, Maruyama-cho, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">477, Maruyama-cho, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">477, Maruyama-cho, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>交通アクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="38">
<j>京阪電気鉄道京阪本線 四条駅 (京阪)から徒歩15分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fifteen minutes walk from Shijo Station (Keihan) on the Keihan Main Line, which is operated by the Keihan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>現在の駅名は「祇園四条」ですが、そのまま訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fifteen minutes walk from Shijo Station (Keihan) on the Keihan Main Line,operated by the Keihan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fifteen minutes walk from Shijo Station (Keihan) on the Keihan Main Line, operated by the Keihan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="39">
<j>阪急電鉄阪急京都本線 河原町駅 (京都府)から徒歩20分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Twenty minutes walk from Kawaramachi Station (Kyoto Prefecture) on the Hankyu Kyoto Line, operated by the Hankyu Corporation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Twenty minutes walk from Kawaramachi Station (Kyoto Prefecture) on the Hankyu Kyoto Line, operated by Hankyu Corporation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Twenty minutes walk from Kawaramachi Station (Kyoto Prefecture) on the Hankyu Kyoto Line, operated by Hankyu Corporation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="40">
<j>京都市営地下鉄京都市営地下鉄東西線 東山駅 (京都府)から徒歩20分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Twenty minutes walk from Higashiyama Station (Kyoto Prefecture) on the Tozai Line, operated by the Kyoto Municipal Subway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Twenty minutes walk from Higashiyama Station (Kyoto Prefecture) on the Tozai Line, operated by the Kyoto Municipal Subway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Twenty minutes walk from Higashiyama Station (Kyoto Prefecture) on the Tozai Line, operated by the Kyoto Municipal Subway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="41">
<j>京都市営バス 祇園バス停下車、徒歩10分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ten minutes walk from Gion bus stop of the Kyoto City Bus.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ten minutes walk from Gion bus stop of the Kyoto City Bus.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ten minutes walk from Gion bus stop of the Kyoto City Bus.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>近隣情報</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Neighboring Information</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Neighboring Information</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Neighboring information</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="42">
<j>知恩院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Chion-in Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Chion-in Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Chion-in Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="43">
<j>高台寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kodai-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kodai-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kodai-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="44">
<j>八坂神社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yasaka-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yasaka-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yasaka-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="45">
<j>円山公園 (京都府)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maruyama Park (Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maruyama Park (Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maruyama Park (Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="46">
<j>長楽寺 (京都市東山区)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Higashiyama Choraku-ji Temple (Higashiyama-ku Ward, Kyoto City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Higashiyama Choraku-ji Temple (Higashiyama-ku Ward, Kyoto City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Higashiyama Choraku-ji Temple (Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City)</e>
<cmt>住所表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="47">
<j>雙林寺 (京都市)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sorin-ji Temple (Kyoto City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sorin-ji Temple (Kyoto City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sorin-ji Temple (Kyoto City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Si-take.(id:91094), Kenryu(id:181554), 健ちゃん(id:60346), R28Bot(id:177951), 海獺(id:153448), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>