<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>血脈相承 (日蓮正宗)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kechimyaku Sojo (Nichiren Shoshu sect)</e>
<cmt>血脈相承（けちみゃくそうじょう）→Kechimyaku Sojo[定訳不明]日蓮正宗→Nichiren Shoshu sect[http://www.nichirenshoshu.or.jp/]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kechimyaku Sojo (Nichiren Shoshu sect)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kechimyaku Sojo (Nichiren Shoshu sect)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>血脈相承（けちみゃくそうじょう）は、仏教で師から弟子へと法 (仏教)が伝えられることを指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Buddhism, Kechimyaku Sojo means handing down of law, dhama, from a mentor to a desciple.</e>
<cmt>法 (仏教)→law, dharma[http://www.eudict.com/?lang=engjpk&amp;word=law,%20act,%20principle;%20method;%20(ling)%20mood;%20(Buddh)%20dharma]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Buddhism, Kechimyaku Sojo means the handing down of law (dharma) from a mentor to a disciple.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Buddhism, Kechimyaku Sojo means the handing down of law (dharma) from a mentor to a disciple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">General information</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">General information</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>他の記事での既出箇所と統一</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>日蓮の相承宣言</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Declaration of Sojo by Nichiren</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Declaration of Sojo by Nichiren</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Declaration of Sojo by Nichiren</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>宗祖日蓮は自らを、『妙法蓮華経』の如来神力品第二十一において、結要付属（けっちょうふぞく）を直授された上行菩薩の再誕であると宣言（『文永11年12月の万年救護本尊』脇書、1274年。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nichiren declared himself as the reincarnation of Jogyo Bosatsu who was directly bestowed Kecchofuzoku based on No.21 of Nyoraijinrikihon of Myohorenge-kyo (Annex of &quot; Mannen Kugo-honzon of December, 1274&quot;).</e>
<cmt>妙法蓮華経→Myohorenge-kyo如来神力品→Nyoraijinrikihon結要付属（けっちょうふぞく）→Kecchofuzoku[定訳不明]上行菩薩→Jogyo Bosatsu[Yahoo辞書]文永11年→in 1274[http://www.asahi-net.or.jp/~HD1T-SITU/nendai/127400.html]万年救護本尊→Mannen Kugo-honzon[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nichiren declared himself to be the reincarnation of Jogyo Bosatsu, who was directly bestowed Kecchofuzoku based on No. 21 of Nyoraijinrikihon of Myohorenge-kyo (Annex of &quot;Mannen Kugo-honzon of December, 1274&quot;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nichiren, who was the founder of the sect, declared himself to be the reincarnation of Jogyo Bosatsu, who was directly bestowed Kecchofuzoku based on No. 21 of Nyoraijinrikihon of &quot;Myohorenge-kyo&quot; (Annex of &quot;Mannen Kugo-honzon of December, 1274&quot;).</e>
<cmt>宗祖の　追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>その他典拠多数）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are a lot of other authorities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many other authorities.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many other authorities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>また併せて、真言密教の「大日如来より日蓮に至る二十三代嫡々相承」までも受けたと主張（『不動・愛染感見記』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, he also asserted that he received Shingon Mikkyo&apos;s &quot;23rd. Chakuchaku Sojo which extended from Dainichinyorai to Nichiren&quot;(Fudo Aizen Kankenki).</e>
<cmt>不動・愛染感見記→Fudo Aizen Kankenki[http://21dzk.l.u-tokyo.ac.jp/INBUDS/search.php?m=trdd&amp;usid=48119&amp;a=]嫡々相承→Chakuchaku Sojo[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, he asserted that he received Shingon Mikkyo&apos;s &quot;23rd Chakuchaku Sojo, extended from Dainichinyorai to Nichiren&quot;(Fudo Aizen Kankenki).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, he asserted that he received Shingon Mikkyo&apos;s &apos;twenty-third chakuchaku (legitimate) sojo, as extended from Dainichinyorai to Nichiren&apos; (from &quot;Fudo Aizen Kankenki,&quot; a posthumous writing by Nichiren).</e>
<cmt>嫡々の説明として　legitimate　と付け加えました。　『不動・愛染感見記』が、(Fudo Aizen Kankenki)だけでは意味が不十分なため、a posthumous writing by Nichiren　と補則しました。(『不動・愛染感見記』は日蓮が残した「遺文」です。)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>なお、醍醐寺の『理性院血脈』の記（金沢文庫蔵）には、確かに25番目に「日蓮」の名があり、大日如来とこの「日蓮」の間は二十三代となって符合するのだが、この『理性院血脈』の「日蓮」と宗祖が同一人物であるかどうかは定かではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the description of &quot;Risho-in Kechimyaku&quot; of Daigo-ji Temple (collection of Kanazawa-Bunko), the name of &quot;Nichiren&quot; appears 25th and this position coincides with 23rd from Dainichinyorai but it is not clear whether &quot;Nichiren&quot; in &quot;Risho-in Kechimyaku&quot; and the founder is the same person or not.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the description of &quot;Risho-in Kechimyaku&quot; of Daigo-ji Temple (collection of Kanazawa-Bunko), the name &quot;Nichiren&quot; appears twenty-fifth, and this position coincides with twenty-third from Dainichinyorai; however, it is not clear whether &quot;Nichiren&quot; in &quot;Risho-in Kechimyaku&quot; and the founder are one and the same.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the description of &quot;Risho-in Kechimyaku&quot; of Daigo-ji Temple (collection of Kanazawa-Bunko), the name &quot;Nichiren&quot; appears twenty-fifth, and this position coincides with the name at the twenty-third position from Dainichinyorai; however, it is not clear whether &quot;Nichiren&quot; in &quot;Risho-in Kechimyaku&quot; and the founder are one and the same.</e>
<cmt>意味不明瞭、冠詞にも問題があるり、全体を修正。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>教団での位置付け</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Positioning at the religious community</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Positioning at the religious community</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Positioning within the religious community</e>
<cmt>within　としました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>以来、唯授一人の血脈相承（ゆいじゅいちにん の けちみゃくそうじょう）が、日蓮正宗の正統性を主張し、また、時の法主による広宣流布指揮の絶対性、教義論争裁定・本尊書写・各種称号授与の専有性を保障するものとして、法主から次期法主へと伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, the sole person who were bestowed Kechimyaku Sojo asserted the legitimacy of Nichiren Shoshu and such position which gurantees the absolute authority in controling propagation activities as well as the exclusive power to adjudicate the dispute concerning the doctrine,to give the permission for depicting the principal image and to bestow various titles has been inherited from incumbent Hossu to next Hossu.</e>
<cmt>法主　→Hossu　[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, the sole person who was bestowed Kechimyaku Sojo asserted the legitimacy of Nichiren Shoshu and such position, which guarantees absolute authority in controlling propagation activities as well as the exclusive power to adjudicate disputes concerning the doctrine, to give permission for depicting the principal image and to bestow various titles, has been inherited from the incumbent Hossu to the next Hossu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, the sole inheritor of Kechimyaku Sojo has asserted the legitimacy of Nichiren Shoshu sect, and this position has been passed from the incumbent Hossu (chief priest) to his successor; the position itself guarantees absolute authority in controlling propagation activities, as well as the exclusive power to adjudicate on disputes concerning doctrine, to give permission for depicting the principal icon of a temple, and to bestow various titles.</e>
<cmt>意味不明瞭なため、全体的に修正。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>「物体として捉える事が出来ない種々の要素（信仰態度や霊性、累積された功徳など）が、金紙や口伝によって相続される」などと、神秘化して考えられる場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kechimyaku Sojo is often mystified by saying, for example, &quot;various elements which can not be captured as objects (such as the attitude for faith, spirituality and accumulated pius acts etc.) are inherited by golden paper or through oral transmission &quot;.</e>
<cmt>霊性→spirituality, divine nature[Webster&apos;s Online Dictionary]功徳→pious act[Webster&apos;s Online Dictionary]口伝→tradition, oral instruction, oral tradition [Webster&apos;s Online Dictionary]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kechimyaku Sojo is often mystified by saying, for example, &quot;various elements that cannot be captured as objects (such as the attitude for faith, spirituality and accumulation of pious acts, etc.) are inherited by golden paper or through oral transmission.&quot;</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kechimyaku Sojo is often mystified by saying, for example, &apos;various elements that cannot be captured as objects (such as the attitude for faith, spirituality and accumulation of pious acts, etc.) are inherited by golden paper or through oral transmission.&apos;</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし、血脈相承の最重要の根幹は「本門戒壇の大御本尊」授受の一点のみに存する、とのシンプルな捉え方も一方にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, there is also a simple understanding of Kechimyaku Sojo that its most important core element exists only in the transfer of Honmonkaidan-no-Daigohonzon.</e>
<cmt>本門戒壇の大御本尊→Honmonkaidan-no-Daigohonzon[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, there is a simple understanding of Kechimyaku Sojo that its most essential core element exists only in the transfer of Honmonkaidan-no-Daigohonzon.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, there is a simple understanding of Kechimyaku Sojo that its most essential core element exists only in the transfer of &apos;Honmonkaidan-no-Daigohonzon&apos; (principal image of the Nichiren Shoshu sect).</e>
<cmt>本門戒壇の大御本尊 の説明として(principal image of the Nichiren Shoshu sect)　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>血脈相承は時と場合により、当分の間は公表しない内証形式がとられることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Depending on times and circumstances, Ｋｅｃｈｉｍｙａｋｕ　Sojo could be done in the form of confidential affairs that are expected not to be made public for a while.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Depending on the times and circumstances, Ｋｅｃｈｉｍｙａｋｕ　Sojo could be done in the form of confidential affairs whose dissemination to the public would not be expected for some time to come.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Depending on the times and circumstances, Kechimyaku Sojo could be done in the form of confidential affairs whose dissemination to the public would not be expected for some time to come.</e>
<cmt>二バイト文字修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>過去には3祖日目から4世日道へ、66世日達から67世日顕への相承が内証形式で行われたとされるが、日顕への相承については否定する者もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that in the past, Sojo from the third, Nichimoku, to the 4th, Nichido and from the 66th, Nichidatsu, to the 67th, Nikkenn was done in the form of confidential affairs, but some denies as to the case of Sojo to Nikken.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that in the past, Sojo from the third (Nichimoku) to the 4th (Nichido) and from the 66th (Nichidatsu) to the 67th (Nikkenn) was done in the form of confidential affairs, but some deny that regarding the case of Sojo to Nikken.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that in the past, Sojo from the third (Nichimoku) to the 4th (Nichido) and from the sixty-sixth (Nichidatsu) to the sixty-seventh (Nikken) was done in the form of confidential affairs, but some deny that regarding the case of Sojo to Nikken.</e>
<cmt>スペルミス。 “sisty”→ “sixty”.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>法華系各派の解釈</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Interpretations ｂｙ various sects belonging to Hokke group</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Interpretations ｂｙ various sects belonging to the Hokke group</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Interpretations by various sects belonging to the Hokke group</e>
<cmt>二バイト文字修正</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>日蓮正宗と日蓮宗の論争</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Disputes between Nichiren shoshu sect and Nichiren sect</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Disputes between the Nichiren Shoshu sect and the Nichiren sect</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Disputes between the Nichiren Shoshu sect and the Nichiren sect</e>
<cmt>二バイト文字修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>日蓮正宗では日蓮-日興-日目以降の歴代大石寺住職のみに伝わるとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nichiren Shoshu sect asserts that after Nichiren-Nikko-Nichimoku, only the chief priests of Taiseki-ji Temple inherited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nichiren Shoshu sect asserts that after Nichiren-Nikko-Nichimoku, only the chief priests of Taiseki-ji Temple inherited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nichiren Shoshu sect asserts that only the chief priests of Taiseki-ji Temple inherited after Nichiren-Nikko-Nichimoku.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかしながら、日蓮宗サイドでは、下記の理由を根拠にこれを否定している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nichiren sect rebuffs the assertion of Nichiren Shoshu sect on the following ground.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nichiren sect rebuffs the assertion of the Nichiren Shoshu sect on the following grounds:</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Nichiren sect rebuffs the assertion of the Nichiren Shoshu sect on the following grounds:</e>
<cmt>However を補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>日蓮正宗の主張が真実なら、宗祖の本弟子六老僧の中で後に反・日興となった五老僧は全て謗法化した人物ということになるが、なぜ宗祖は、彼ら五人の謗法化を予見することもできずに本弟子として認めたのか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If the assertion of Nichiren Shoshu sect is true, it means out of 6 old monks who were the desciples of the founder, 5 old monks who became anti Nikko were persons who defamed the law, dharma, but why the founder could not predict their behavior and acknowledged them as desciples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If the assertion of the Nichiren Shoshu sect is true, it means that out of six old monks who were the disciples of the founder, five old monks who became anti Nikko were persons who had defamed the law (dharma), which is why the founder could not predict their behavior or acknowledge them as disciples.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If the assertion of the Nichiren Shoshu sect is true, it means that out of six old monks who were the disciples of the founder, five old monks who became anti Nikko were persons who had defamed the law (dharma); the question remains as to why the founder could not have predicted their behavior and acknowledged them as disciples.</e>
<cmt>文法問題。 “ could not predict their behavior ”=&gt; “could not have predicted their behavior. ”意味不明確。 “or acknowledged”=&gt;”and acknowledged”</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>日蓮正宗の主張の根拠である「池上相承書」「身延相承書」の二箇相承は、興門流の初期の記録には存在しないから偽書である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Niko Sojo, consisted of &quot;Ikegami Sojo-sho&quot; and &quot;Minobu Sojo-sho&quot;, on which Nichiren Shoshu sect&apos;s assertion based are bogus because it doesn&apos;t appear in the early record of komon-ryu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Niko Sojo, which consisted of &quot;Ikegami Sojo-sho&quot; and &quot;Minobu Sojo-sho,&quot; on which the Nichiren Shoshu sect&apos;s assertion is based, is bogus because it doesn&apos;t appear in the early record of Komon-ryu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nika (two) Sojo, which consisted of two notes, &apos;Ikegami Sojo-sho&apos; and &apos;Minobu Sojo-sho,&apos; on which the Nichiren Shoshu sect&apos;s assertion is based, is bogus because it does not appear in the early record of Komon-ryu school.</e>
<cmt>二つの書、という補足（two notes）を追加しました。　「にかそうじょう」と読むことが分かりましたので、そのように修正しました。　興門流を Komon-ryu school　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>身延相承の日付けと日蓮の行動が一致しないから偽書である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minobu Sojo is bogus because its date and the activities of Nichiren don&apos;t coincide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minobu Sojo is bogus because its date and the activities of Nichiren don&apos;t coincide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minobu Sojo is bogus because its date and the activities of Nichiren don&apos;t coincide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>二箇相承は日興が日目に譲った大石寺ではなく、日興が晩年隠居した重須談所（現在の北山本門寺）に保管されていたとされる文書である上に、原本は現在では行方不明であるから論議の対象にすらならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Niko Sojo cannot be the subject of discussion because it was stored at Omosu-dansho (current Kitayama-ji Temple) where Nikko lived after retirement, not at Taiseki-ji Temple which Nikko ceded to Nichimoku, and its original copy is missing at present.</e>
<cmt>二箇相承→Niko Sojo [定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Niko Sojo cannot be the subject of discussion because it was stored at Omosu-dansho (currently Kitayama-ji Temple) where Nikko lived after retirement, not at Taiseki-ji Temple, which Nikko had ceded to Nichimoku, and its original copy is now missing.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nika Sojo cannot even be the subject of discussion because it was stored at Omosu-dansho (an institute established in Omosu for the purpose of educating disciples; currently Kitayama Honmon-ji Temple), where Nikko lived after retirement, not at Taiseki-ji Temple which Nikko had ceded to Nichimoku, and because its original document is now missing.</e>
<cmt>“original copy” は意味が不明確。“original”なのか“original ”のコピーなのかととられかねない。→”original document&quot;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>なお、二箇相承の原本の所在については、下記のような説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the whereabout of Niko-Sojo, there are some views.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the whereabouts of Niko-Sojo, there are various assessments.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the whereabouts of Nika Sojo, there are various assessments.</e>
<cmt>Nika Sojo　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>武田勝頼軍の略奪に伴い完全に紛失した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One view holds that it was completely lost due to the loot by the army of Katsuyori Takeda and</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One view holds that it was completely lost due to the looting by the army of Katsuyori Takeda.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One view holds that it was completely lost due to looting by the army of Katsuyori TAKEDA.</e>
<cmt>文法間違い。 “to the looting ”=&gt;”to looting ”</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>徳川家康が二箇相承真筆を披見した記録があるから紛失説は誤りで、実は北山本門寺が秘蔵・隠蔽している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The other view holds that it was not lost because there is a record that Ieyasu Tokugawa read its original copy and in truth, Kitayama Honmon-ji Temple is storing it confidentially.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The other view holds that it was not lost because there is a record that Ieyasu Tokugawa read the original copy and Kitayama Honmon-ji Temple is actually storing it in confidence.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The other view holds that it was not lost because there is a record that Ieyasu TOKUGAWA read the original copy and Kitayama Honmon-ji Temple is in fact storing it in confidence.</e>
<cmt>TOKUGAWA　としました。actually→in fact に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>富士門流諸派の解釈</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Interpretation by Fujimon-ryu Sects</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Interpretation by the Fujimon-ryu sects</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Interpretation by the Fujimon-ryu school</e>
<cmt>Fujimon-ryu school としました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>北山本門寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kitayama Honmon-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kitayama Honmon-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kitayama Honmon-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>北山本門寺では、伝統的に言っても、血脈相承というもの自体を極めて軽視してきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Traditionally, Kitayama Honmon-ji Temple has been thinking little of Kechimyaku Sojo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Traditionally, Kitayama Honmon-ji Temple has given little consideration to Kechimyaku Sojo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Traditionally, Kitayama Honmon-ji Temple has given little consideration to Kechimyaku Sojo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="21">
<j>まずその出発点からして、日興から重須を譲られた日代は、一山大衆の手によって追放の憂き目に遭っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the very beginning, Nichidai, who were ceded Omosu by Nikko, was expelled by the people adherent to Omosu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the very beginning, Nichidai, who was ceded Omosu by Nikko, was expelled by the people adherent to Omosu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the very beginning, Nichidai, who was ceded Omosu by Nikko, was expelled by the people adherent to Omosu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>当然、日興から日目への血脈相承も認めなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naturally, it didn&apos;t approve Kechimyaku Sojo from Nikko to Nichimoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naturally, it didn&apos;t approve the transfer of Kechimyaku Sojo from Nikko to Nichimoku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naturally, the temple did not approve the transfer of Kechimyaku Sojo from Nikko to Nichimoku.</e>
<cmt>the temple　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="23">
<j>さらに現在では、二箇相承も否定して、ひたすら「日蓮宗大本山」としての地位の保全に努めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, it even denies Niko Sojo and is solely striving to preserve the status of the &quot;head temple of Nichiren- shu sect&quot;.</e>
<cmt>日蓮宗大本山→head temple of Nichiren-shu sect[http://honmonji.jp/english/english.html]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently, it even denies Niko Sojo and strives solely to preserve the status of the &quot;head temple of the Nichiren-shu sect.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Currently, it even denies Nika Sojo and strives solely to preserve the status of the &apos;head temple of the Nichiren-shu sect.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Nika Sojo　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>西山本門寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nishiyama Honmon-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nishiyama Honmon-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nishiyama Honmon-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>西山本門寺では、日興から日目への血脈相承を認めず、『八通譲り状』を根拠に日代正統説を立てて分派。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nishiyama Honmon-ji Temple didn&apos;t approve Kechimyaku Sojo from Nikko to Nichimoku and split off with claiming the legitimacy of Nichidai based on &quot;Hattsu Yuzurijo&quot;,</e>
<cmt>八通譲り状→Hattsu Yuzurijo 「定訳不明」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nishiyama Honmon-ji Temple didn&apos;t approve Kechimyaku Sojo from Nikko to Nichimoku but instead split off, claiming the legitimacy of Nichidai based on &quot;Hattsu Yuzurijo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nishiyama Honmon-ji Temple did not approve Kechimyaku Sojo from Nikko to Nichimoku but instead split away, claiming the legitimacy of Nichidai based on &quot;Hattsu Yuzurijo (eight notes that document the will to transfer the property or possession to the offspring or disciples).&quot;</e>
<cmt>八通譲り状の説明として、 (eight notes that document the will to transfer the property or possession to the offspring or disciples)を加えました。 →[http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=%E3%82%86%E3%81%9A%E3%82%8A&amp;dtype=0&amp;stype=0&amp;dname=0na&amp;pagenum=1&amp;index=21896618779600]を参考にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>保田妙本寺・小泉久遠寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hota Myohon-ji Temple, Koizumi Kuon-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hota Myohon-ji Temple, Koizumi Kuon-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hota Myohon-ji Temple, Koizumi Kuon-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>保田妙本寺・小泉久遠寺では、日目から日道への血脈相承を認めず、日郷正統説を立てて分派。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hota Myohon-ji Temple and Koizumi Kuon-ji Temple didn&apos;t approve Kechimyaku Sojo from Nichimoku to Nichido and split off with claiming the legitimacy of Nichigo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hota Myohon-ji Temple and Koizumi Kuon-ji Temple did not approve Kechimyaku Sojo from Nichimoku to Nichido but instead split off, claiming the legitimacy of Nichigo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hota Myohon-ji Temple and Koizumi Kuon-ji Temple did not approve Kechimyaku Sojo from Nichimoku to Nichido but instead split off, claiming the legitimacy of Nichigo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>昭和32年、大石寺に一旦は帰属したが、創価学会と宗門の争いを見て、平成になって再び独立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They once came under the jurisdiction of Taiseki-ji Temple in 1957 but became independent again in Heisei period after seeing the conflict between Soka Gakkai and the sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They once came under the jurisdiction of Taiseki-ji Temple in 1957 but became independent again in the Heisei period after seeing the conflict between Soka Gakkai and the sect.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They once came under the jurisdiction of Taiseki-ji Temple in 1957 but became independent again in the Heisei period after seeing the conflict between Soka Gakkai and the sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>要法寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yobo-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yobo-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yobo-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="27">
<j>京都要法寺では、初代日尊の時代には、日目から日道への血脈相承も認めていたし、江戸時代には大石寺の最有力の末寺として9代連続で法主を輩出したこともあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the era of Nichizon, its original chief priest, Kyoto Yobo-ji Temple acknoledged Kechimyaku Sojo from Nichimoku to Nichido and during Edo Period, it turned out nine consecutive Hossu as being the most overriding branch temple of Taiseki-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>末寺→branch temple[Webster&apos;s Online Dictionary]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the era of Nichizon, its original chief priest (of Kyoto Yobo-ji Temple) acknowledged Kechimyaku Sojo from Nichimoku to Nichido, and during the Edo period it turned out nine consecutive hossu as being the most overriding branch temple of Taiseki-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the era of Nichizon, its original chief priest (of Kyoto Yobo-ji Temple) acknowledged Kechimyaku Sojo from Nichimoku to Nichido, and during the Edo period it turned out nine consecutive hossu as being the most overriding branch temple of Taiseki-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="28">
<j>しかし、長い年月の中で徐々に独立的傾向が高まっていき、遂に血脈相承を否定して大石寺との本末関係を解消するに至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it gradually became independent over the years and eventually dissolved the affiliation with Taiseki-ji Temple by denying Kechimyaku Sojo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, over the years it gradually became independent and dissolved the affiliation with Taiseki-ji Temple by denying Kechimyaku Sojo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, over the years it gradually became independent and dissolved the affiliation with Taiseki-ji Temple by denying Kechimyaku Sojo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="29">
<j>現在では「日蓮本宗」の本山として自立している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, it is independent as the head temple of &quot;Nichiren Honshu sect&quot;.</e>
<cmt>日蓮本宗→Nichiren Honshu</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently, it is independent as the head temple of the &quot;Nichiren Honshu sect.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Currently, it is independent as the head temple of the &apos;Nichiren Honshu sect.&apos;</e>
<cmt>括弧を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>法華系新興宗教の解釈</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Interpretation by the new religion sects belonging to Hokke group</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Interpretation by the new religious sects belonging to the Hokke group</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Interpretation by the new religious sects belonging to the Hokke group</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>正信会</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoshin-kai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoshin-kai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoshin-kai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="30">
<j>正信会では、1980年の僧侶5名擯斥処分直後に、日達から日顕へ血脈相承した形跡がないので、管長の資格が無いとして、管長地位不存在確認を裁判所に提訴した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soon after the expulsion of five monks in 1980, Shoshin-kai filed the litigation to the court requesting the confirmation of the non-existance of the position of chief abbot (superintendentpriest) on the ground that Kechimyaku Sojo from Nichidatsu to Nikken doesn&apos;t appear to have been done and therfore the chief abbot in question lacks qualification.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon after the expulsion of five monks in 1980, Shoshin-kai filed court litigation requesting a confirmation of the non-existence of the position of the chief abbot (superintendent priest) on the grounds that Kechimyaku Sojo from Nichidatsu to Nikken doesn&apos;t appear to have been done, and that consequently the chief abbot in question lacked qualification.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon after the expulsion of five monks in 1980, Shoshin-kai filed court litigation requesting a confirmation of the non-existence of the position of the chief abbot (superintendent priest) on the grounds that Kechimyaku Sojo from Nichidatsu to Nikken doesn&apos;t appear to have been done, and that consequently the chief abbot in question lacked qualification.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>以後、日顕及び日蓮正宗への攻撃材料として様々な側面から日蓮正宗の血脈相承を否定。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, it has been denying Kechimyaku Sojo from various aspects as the ammunition for attacking Nikken and Nichire Shoshu sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, it has continued to deny Kechimyaku Sojo in various respects, doing so as the ammunition for attacking the Nikken and Nichiren Shoshu sects.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, it has continued to deny Kechimyaku Sojo in various respects, doing so as ammunition for attacking the Nikken and Nichiren Shoshu sects.</e>
<cmt>定冠詞不必要。”as the ammunition”→”as ammunition ”</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="32">
<j>なお、裁判自体は正信会による寺院占拠問題と同じように、信仰次元の問題なので、裁判の対象ではない。として棄却された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The litigation itself was dismissed on the ground that the subject matter cannot be the subject of litigation because, like the problem of temple occupation, it is the matter of faith.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The litigation itself was dismissed on the grounds that the subject matter cannot be the subject of litigation because, like the problem of temple occupation, it is a matter of faith.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The litigation itself was dismissed on the grounds that the subject matter cannot be the subject of litigation because, like the problem of temple occupation, it is a matter of faith.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>（いわゆる部分社会論の法理として有名な判例）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Well-known judicial precedent concerning the legal theory of partial society.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(A well-known judicial precedent concerning the legal theory of a partial society)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(A well-known judicial precedent concerning the legal theory of a partial society)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="34">
<j>また、最近、一部僧侶が日達から日顕への血脈相承があったと発言している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently, some monks made remarks that Kechimyaku Sojo from Nichidatsu to Nikken was done.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently, some monks have remarked that Kechimyaku Sojo from Nichidatsu to Nikken was done.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently, some monks have remarked that Kechimyaku Sojo from Nichidatsu to Nikken was done.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>当人によれば、実際にはあったが、攻撃材料としてなかったことにしようというものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to them, Kechimyaku Sojo was actually done but they pretended otherwise as the ammunition for attack.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to them, Kechimyaku Sojo was actually done but they pretended otherwise as the ammunition for attack.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to them, Kechimyaku Sojo was in fact performed but they had pretended otherwise as it provided ammunition for attack.</e>
<cmt>文法間違いを修正。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>創価学会</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soka Gakkai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soka Gakkai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soka Gakkai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="36">
<j>創価学会では、1991年の破門以降は、血脈相承はとうの昔に切れていると主張している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the excommunication in 1991, Soka Gakkai asserts that Kechimyaku Sojo ended long ago.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the excommunication in 1991, Soka Gakkai has asserted that Kechimyaku Sojo ended long ago.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the excommunication in 1991, Soka Gakkai has asserted that Kechimyaku Sojo ended long ago.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>冨士大石寺顕正会</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fuji Taiseki-ji Kensho-kai</e>
<cmt>冨士大石寺顕正会→Fuji Taiseki-ji Kensho-kai[http://www.kenshokai.or.jp/kenshou/index.html]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fuji Taiseki-ji Kensho-kai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fuji Taiseki-ji Kensho-kai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="37">
<j>冨士大石寺顕正会では、1999年4月12日の本部指導会以降、正信会の主張に相乗りする形で、教義変更の仏罰で日達は急死したため、血脈相承を誰にも授けられなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the headquarter instruction meeting held on April 12, 1999, Fuji Taiseki-ji Kensho-kai asserts, in the form of echoing with the assertion of Shoshin-kai, that Nichidatsu could not bestow Kechimyaku Sojo to anyone because he suddenly died of Buddha&apos;s penalty relating to the change of doctrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the headquarters instruction meeting held on April 12, 1999, Fuji Taiseki-ji Kensho-kai asserts, in the form of echoing the assertion of Shoshin-kai, that Nichidatsu could not bestow Kechimyaku Sojo to anyone because he had died suddenly as a consequence of Buddha&apos;s penalty relating to the change of doctrine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the headquarters instruction meeting held on April 12, 1999, Fuji Taiseki-ji Kensho-kai asserts, in the form of echoing the assertion of Shoshin-kai, that Nichidatsu could not bestow Kechimyaku Sojo to anyone because he had died suddenly as a consequence of Buddha&apos;s penalty relating to the change of doctrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>日顕は、血脈相承を受けてないのに受けたと詐称して登座した。と主張し始めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It further asserts that Nikken assumed the position of Hossu by pretending he had been bestowed Kechimyaku Sojo though he had not been bestowed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It further asserts that Nikken assumed the position of Hossu by pretending that he had been bestowed Kechimyaku Sojo, even though it had not occurred.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It further asserts that Nikken assumed the position of Hossu by pretending that he had been bestowed Kechimyaku Sojo, even though it had not occurred.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kstigarbha(id:13376), Cprobot(id:97843), Petrov(id:13070), Authority(id:10737), Kane(id:6812), Hogué(id:18263), 杉山真大(id:2297), はま(id:93561), Tetralemma(id:11903), まるゆ(id:4371), Oddmake(id:29591), 毎月60万円(id:136235), Falcosapiens(id:221), バナナ売り(id:93369), Aðalstjórn(id:26381), Dobby(id:5361), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>