<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>毘沙門天</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bishamonten, Vaisravana</e>
<cmt>毘沙門天（びしゃもんてん）→http://www.eudict.com/?lang=engjpk&amp;word=(Buddh)%20Vaisravana%20(Buddhist%20deity)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bishamonten, Vaisravana</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bishamonten, Vaisravana</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>毘沙門天（びしゃもんてん）、サンスクリットヴァイシュラヴァナ (vaizravaNa)とは、仏教における天部の仏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bishamonten, vaizravaNa in Sanskrit, is a Buddha of Tembu, Deities who reside in a heavenly realm, one of six realms in which the souls of living beings transmigrate from one to another, in Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>天部→http://www.kcn-net.org/e_kama_history/glossary/glossary.htm、仏→英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bishamonten (vaizravaNa in Sanskrit) is a Buddha of the Tembu, deities who reside in a heavenly realm, this being one of six realms in which the souls of living beings transmigrate from one to another, in Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bishamonten (vaizravaNa in Sanskrit) is a Buddha of the Tenbu, deities who reside in a heavenly realm, this being one of six realms in which the souls of living beings transmigrate from one to another, in Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>Tembu→Tenbuに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>持国天、増長天、広目天と共に四天王の一尊に数えられる武神である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a war god and one of the Shitenno, Four Guardian Kings, with Jikokuten (Dhrtarastra), Zochoten (Virudhaka) and Komokuten (Virupaksa).</e>
<cmt>持国天→http://www.eudict.com/?lang=engjpk&amp;word=(Buddh)%20Vaisravana%20(Buddhist%20deity)、増長天→http://aoki.tirirenge.com/m/4tennou.html、広目天→http://www.eudict.com/?lang=engjpk&amp;word=(Buddh)%20Vaisravana%20(Buddhist%20deity)、四天王→http://www.aisf.or.jp/%7Ejaanus/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a war god and one of the shitenno (four guardian kings) with Jikokuten (Dhrtarastra), Zochoten (Virudhaka) and Komokuten (Virupaksa).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a war god and one of the Shitenno (four guardian kings) with Jikokuten (Dhrtarastra), Zochoten (Virudhaka) and Komokuten (Virupaksa).</e>
<cmt>四天王を大文字に。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>また四天王の一員としてだけでなく、中央アジア、中国など日本以外の広い地域でも、独尊として信仰の対象となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it is not only one of the Shitenno but is worshipped individually in a broad region such as Central Asia and China other than in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, it is not only one of the shitenno but is worshiped individually over a broad region, such as Central Asia and China (other than in Japan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, it is not only one of the shitenno but is worshiped individually over a broad region, such as Central Asia and China (other than in Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>インド神話の財宝神クベーラを前身とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its predecessor is Kubera, a treasure god in Indian myth.</e>
<cmt>クベーラ→http://www.geocities.co.jp/HeartLand/2935/t-zatu4.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its predecessor is Kubera, a treasure god in Indian myth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its predecessor is Kubera, a treasure god in Indian myth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>ヴァイシュラヴァナという称号は本来「ヴィシュラヴァス(vizravas)神の息子」という意味で、彼の父親の名に由来するが、「よく聞く所の者」という意味にも解釈できるため、多聞天 (たもんてん)とも訳される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The title of vaizravaNa originally means &apos; the son of vizravas&apos; so that it originated from his father&apos;s name, but it can be interpreted as &apos;a man who listen to well&apos; so that it is also translated as Tamonten.</e>
<cmt>多聞天 (たもんてん)→http://www.eudict.com/?lang=engjpk&amp;word=(Buddh)%20Vaisravana%20(Buddhist%20deity)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The title of vaizravaNa originally meant &apos;the son of vizravas,&apos; so it originated from his father&apos;s name, but it can be interpreted as &apos;a man who listens very well&apos; so that it is also translated as Tamonten.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The title of vaizravaNa originally meant &apos;the son of vizravas,&apos; so it originated from his father&apos;s name, but it can be interpreted as &apos;a man who listens very well&apos; so that it is also translated as Tamonten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>日本では四天王の一尊として造像安置する場合は「多聞天」、独尊像として造像安置する場合は「毘沙門天」と呼ぶのが通例である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, when it is shaped to a statue and placed as one of the Shitenno it is usually called &apos;Tamonten&apos; and when it is shaped to a statue and placed individually it is usually called &apos;Bishamonten.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, when it is shaped as a statue and placed as one of the Shitenno it is usually called &apos;Tamonten,&apos; but when in the form of a statue and placed individually it is usually called &apos;Bishamonten.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, when it is shaped as a statue and placed as one of the Shitenno it is usually called &apos;Tamonten,&apos; but when in the form of a statue and placed individually it is usually called &apos;Bishamonten.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>三昧耶形は宝棒(仏敵を打ち据える護法の棍棒)、宝塔。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanmayagyo Symbol is a treasure club (a club to defeat the enemy of Buddhism in order to protect Buddhism dharma), and a pagoda.</e>
<cmt>三昧耶形→http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110004644722/、宝塔→Webster Online Dictionary</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sanmayagyo symbol is a treasure club (a club with which to defeat the enemy of Buddhism in order to protect the Buddhist dharma) as well as a pagoda.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sanmayagyo symbol is a treasure club (a club with which to defeat the enemy of Buddhism in order to protect the Buddhist dharma) as well as a pagoda.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>種子 (密教)はベイ (vai)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shushi (Shuji, Bija) in Mikkyo, Esoteric Buddhism, is vai.</e>
<cmt>種子→http://opac.ndl.go.jp/articleid/10189239/jpn、密教→http://www.koyasan.or.jp/english/shingonshu/mikkyo.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shushi (Shuji, Bija) in Mikkyo (Esoteric Buddhism) is vai.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shushi (Shuji, Bija) in Mikkyo (Esoteric Buddhism) is vai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>毘沙門天に捧げられた真言としては「オン ベイシラマナヤ ソワカ」(oM vaizravaNaaya svaahaa 『オーム (聖音)、ヴィシュラヴァスの御子よ。スヴァーハー』)等がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The mantra (Shingon) for Bishamonten is &apos;On Beishiramanayasowaka (oM vaizravaNaaya svaahaa, that is, om (saint sound), the son of vizravas, svaahaa) and so on.</e>
<cmt>真言→英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The mantra (shingon) for Bishamonten is &apos;On Beishiramanayasowaka (oM vaizravaNaaya svaahaa, that is, om (saintly sound), the son of vizravas, svaahaa), etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The mantra (shingon) for Bishamonten is &apos;On Beishiramanayasowaka (oM vaizravaNaaya svaahaa, that is, om (saintly sound), the son of vizravas, svaahaa), etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>その姿には様々な表現があるが(後述)、日本では一般に革製の甲冑を身に着けた唐代の武将風の姿で表される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there are various figures (as bellow), it is generally expressed as a warrior figure of Tang Dynasty which puts on leather armor in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there are various figures (as below), in Japan it is generally expressed as a warrior figure of the Tang dynasty that dons leather armor.</e>
<cmt>spell</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there are various figures (as below), in Japan it is generally expressed as a warrior figure of the Tang dynasty that dons leather armor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>持物は宝塔が一般的。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its belongings is a pagoda in general.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its belongings generally consist of a pagoda.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its belongings generally consist of a pagoda.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また、邪鬼と呼ばれる鬼形の者の上に乗ることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, it often stands on a ogre which is called Jaki (邪鬼).</e>
<cmt>邪気→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, it often stands on an ogre called Jaki (邪鬼).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, it often stands on an ogre called Jaki (邪鬼).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="13">
<j>例えば密教の両界曼荼羅では甲冑に身を固めて右手は宝棒、左手は宝塔を捧げ持つ姿で描かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, in Ryokai Mandara (Mandala of the Two Realms) of Mikkyo, it is drawn as a figure which has a treasure club in the right hand and a pagoda in the left hand with putting on an armor.</e>
<cmt>両界曼荼羅→http://www.bambooweb.com/articles/m/a/Mandala_of_the_Two_Realms.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, in the Ryokai Mandara (Mandala of the Two Realms) of Mikkyo, it is drawn as a figure that has a treasure club in the right hand and a pagoda in the left hand and is wearing armor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, in the Ryokai Mandala (Mandala of the Two Realms) of Mikkyo, it is drawn as a figure that has a treasure club in the right hand and a pagoda in the left hand and is wearing armor.</e>
<cmt>Mandara→Mandalaに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="14">
<j>ただし、東大寺戒壇堂の四天王像では右手に宝塔を捧げ持ち、左手で宝棒を握る姿で造像されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Shitenno statue in Todai-ji Temple Kaidan-do is shaped as a figure which has a pagoda in the right hand and a treasure club in the left hand.</e>
<cmt>東大寺戒壇堂→http://store.shopping.yahoo.co.jp/7andy/30772561.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Shitenno statue in Todai-ji Temple Kaidan-do is shaped as a figure that has a pagoda in the right hand and a treasure club in the left hand.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Shitenno statue in Todai-ji Temple Kaidan-do is shaped as a figure that has a pagoda in the right hand and a treasure club in the left hand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>（奈良當麻寺でも同様に右手で宝塔を捧げ持っている。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The statue in Nara Taima-dera Temple has a pagoda in the right hand as well.)</e>
<cmt>奈良當麻寺→http://www.taimadera.org/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The statue in Nara Taima-dera Temple has a pagoda in the right hand as well.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The statue in Nara Taima-dera Temple has a pagoda in the right hand as well.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="16">
<j>インドにおいては財宝神とされ、戦闘的イメージは殆ど無かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In India, it was considered as a treasure god and hardly had an image of warrior.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In India, it was considered as a treasure god and was hardly depicted as a warrior.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In India, it was considered as a treasure god and was hardly depicted as a warrior.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>この頃の性格についてはクベーラの項を参照の事。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As to the character in this age, see the article of Kubera.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As to the character in this age, see the article on Kubera.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As to the character in this age, see the article on Kubera.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>中央アジアを経て中国に伝わる過程で武神としての信仰が生まれ、四天王の一尊たる武神・守護神とされるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the process which was transmitted to China through Central Asia, the faith as a war god was created and it became to be a guardian deity, one of the Shitenno.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the process that was transmitted to China through Central Asia, the faith as a war god was created and it came to be a guardian deity as one of the shitenno.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the process that was transmitted to China through Central Asia, the faith as a war god was created and it came to be a guardian deity as one of the Shitenno.</e>
<cmt>四天王を大文字に。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>そして帝釈天の配下として、仏の住む世界を支える須弥山の北方、水精埵の天敬城に住み、或いは古代インドの世界観で地球上にあるとされた4つの大陸のうち北倶盧洲（ほっくるしゅう）を守護するとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, as a following of Taishakuten, it is said to live in Tengyo-jo Castle of Suishota, which is the north of Mt.Shumisen (Mt.Sumeru) or guard Hokkurushu (uttara-kuru), one of the four continents in the world-view of ancient India.</e>
<cmt>須弥山→http://www.aisf.or.jp/%7Ejaanus/、水精埵→http://www.ac.auone-net.jp/~kk-uchu/3zensekai-9sen8kai.pdf、天敬城→http://www.butsu-zou.com/bisyamonten.html、北倶盧洲（ほっくるしゅう）→Yahoo辞書</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, as a following of Taishakuten it is said to live in Tengyo-jo Castle of Suishota, which is the north of Mt. Shumisen (Mt. Sumeru) or to guard Hokkurushu (uttara-kuru), one of the four continents in the world view of ancient India.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, as a following of Taishakuten it is said to live in Tengyo-jo Castle of Suishota, which is the north of Mt. Shumisen (Mt. Sumeru) or to guard Hokkurushu (uttara-kuru), one of the four continents in the world view of ancient India.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>また、夜叉や羅刹といった鬼神を配下とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, it subordinates devils such as Yasha, a class of semidivine being usually considered to be of a benevolent and inoffensive disposition but sometimes also classed with malignant spirits, and Rasetsu, Rakshasa.</e>
<cmt>夜叉→http://www.aisf.or.jp/~jaanus/deta/y/yasha.htm、羅刹→Webster&apos;s Online Dictionary</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, it subordinates devils such as Yasha (a class of semi-divinity that is usually considered to be of a benevolent and inoffensive disposition but is sometimes also classified with malignant spirits) and Rasetsu (Rakshasa).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, it subordinates devils such as Yasha (a class of semi-divinity that is usually considered to be of a benevolent and inoffensive disposition but is sometimes also classified with malignant spirits) and Rasetsu (Rakshasa).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="21">
<j>また、密教においては十二天の一尊で北方を守護するとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, in Mikkyo it is one of the Juniten (十二天) and is said to guard the north.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, in Mikkyo it is one of the juniten (十二天) and is said to guard the north.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, in Mikkyo it is one of the juniten (十二天) and is said to guard the north.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また日本独自の信仰として七福神の一尊とされ、特に勝負事に利益ありとして崇められる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan it is one of the seven deities of good luck as an unique faith and is revered because it seems to benefit games especially.</e>
<cmt>七福神→Webster&apos;s Online Dictionary</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan it is one of the seven deities of good luck as a unique faith and is revered because it seems to benefit games especially.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan it is one of the seven deities of good luck as a unique faith and is revered because it seems to benefit games especially.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="23">
<j>像容</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Figure of image</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Figure of image</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Figure of image</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>毘沙門天の姿にははっきりした規定は無く、様々な表現がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are no clear rule of Bisyamonten&apos;s figure so that there exist various expressions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no clear rule regarding Bisyamonten&apos;s figure, so that various expressions exist.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no clear rule regarding Bisyamonten&apos;s figure, so that various expressions exist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>前述のとおり日本では武将風の姿で表され、宝塔を持つ姿が一般的。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is expressed as a figure of warrior in Japan as mentioned above and generally has a pagoda.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is expressed as the figure of a warrior in Japan as mentioned above, and generally it has a pagoda.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is expressed as the figure of a warrior in Japan as mentioned above, and generally it has a pagoda.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>ほかに三叉戟を持つ造形例もあり、例えば京都・三室戸寺像などは宝塔を持たず片手を腰に当て片手に三叉戟を持つ姿である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is another work which has a trident; for example the statue at Miruroto-ji Temple in Kyoto does not have a pagoda but a trident in a hand with putting another hand on his hip.</e>
<cmt>三叉戟→Webster&apos;s Online Dictionary、三室戸寺→http://www.mimurotoji.com/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is another work that has a trident: for example the statue at Miruroto-ji Temple in Kyoto does not have a pagoda but a trident in one hand with putting another hand on his hip.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is another work that has a trident: for example, the statue at Mimuroto-ji Temple in Kyoto does not have a pagoda but a trident in one hand and places the other hand on his hip.</e>
<cmt>三室戸寺　Mimuroto-ji</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="27">
<j>また、中国の民間信仰に於いては緑色の顔で右手に傘、左手に銀のネズミを持った姿で表される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the folk faith in China it is expressed as a figure which has a green face with an umbrella in the right hand and a silver mouse in the left hand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the folk faith of China it is expressed as a figure that has a green face with an umbrella in the right hand and a silver mouse in the left hand.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the folk faith of China it is expressed as a figure that has a green face with an umbrella in the right hand and a silver mouse in the left hand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>チベット仏教では金銀宝石を吐くマングースを持つ姿で表され、インドでの財宝神としての性格を残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Tibetan Buddhism it is expressed as a figure which has a mongoose who disgorges gold, silver and jewels, which shows that it remains a character as a treasure god in India.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Tibetan Buddhism it is expressed as a figure that has a mongoose who disgorges gold, silver and jewels, thus maintaining the character of a treasure god in India.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Tibetan Buddhism it is expressed as a figure that has a mongoose who disgorges gold, silver and jewels, thus maintaining the character of a treasure god in India.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="29">
<j>独尊、また中心尊としても多くの造形例がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many works as an individual deity or the central deity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many works as an individual deity or the central deity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many works as an individual deity or the central deity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>安置形態としては、毘沙門天を中尊とし、吉祥天（毘沙門天の妃または妹とされる）と善膩師童子（ぜんにしどうじ。毘沙門天の息子の一人とされる）を脇侍とする三尊形式の像（京都・鞍馬寺、高知・雪蹊寺など）、毘沙門天と吉祥天を一対で安置するもの（奈良・法隆寺金堂像など）、毘沙門天と不動明王を一対として安置するもの（高野山金剛峯寺像など）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The styles of placement are as follows; a triad style in which Bishamonten is placed at the center with Kyoji (Attendant figures) of Kisshoten (Kichijoten, Sri-mahadevi, who is said to a wife of sister of Bishamonten) and Zennishi-doji (who is said to be a son of Bishamonten) (Kurama Temple in Kyoto, Sekkei-ji Temple in Kochi, and so on), a style to place a pair of Bishamonten with Kisshoten (the statue of Horyuji Temple Kondo (法隆寺金堂) in Nara), and a style to place a pair of Bishamonten with Fudo Myoo (the statue of Koyasan Kongobuji Temple and so on).</e>
<cmt>吉祥天→http://www.eudict.com/?lang=engjpk&amp;word=(Buddh)%20Vaisravana%20(Buddhist%20deity)脇侍→http://www.aisf.or.jp/%7Ejaanus/、雪蹊寺→http://88.portal2.jp/kochi/33/、法隆寺金堂→定訳不明、不動明王→http://www.aisf.or.jp/~jaanus/deta/g/godaimyouou.htm、高野山金剛峯寺→http://www.koyasan.or.jp/english/index.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The styles of placement are as follows: a triad style in which Bishamonten is placed at the center with Kyoji (attendant figures) of Kisshoten (Kichijoten, Sri-mahadevi, who is said to a wife of the sister of Bishamonten) and Zennishi-doji (who is said to be a son of Bishamonten) (Kurama Temple in Kyoto, Sekkei-ji Temple in Kochi, and so on); a style that places a pair of Bishamonten with Kisshoten (the statue of Horyuji Temple Kondo (法隆寺金堂) in Nara); and a style that places a pair of Bishamonten with Fudo Myoo (the statue of Koyasan Kongobuji Temple and so on).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The styles of placement are as follows: a triad style in which Bishamonten is placed at the center with Kyoji (attendant figures) of Kisshoten (Kichijoten, Sri-mahadevi, who is said to a wife of the sister of Bishamonten) and Zennishi-doji (who is said to be a son of Bishamonten) (Kurama Temple in Kyoto, Sekkei-ji Temple in Kochi, and so on); a style that places a pair of Bishamonten with Kisshoten (the statue of Horyuji Temple Kondo (法隆寺金堂) in Nara); and a style that places a pair of Bishamonten with Fudo Myoo (the statue of Koyasan Kongobuji Temple and so on).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="31">
<j>また、天台宗系の寺院では、千手観音を中尊として両脇に毘沙門天・不動明王を安置することも多い（滋賀・明王院像、京都・峰定寺像など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, in Tendai sect&apos;s temples it is often seen that Senju Kannon is placed at the center and Bishamonten and Fudo Myoo are placed at its both sides (Myoo-in Temple in Shiga, Bujo-ji Temple in Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>峰定寺→http://homepage1.nifty.com/hon/2/2-131/2-131.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, in the temples of the Tendai sect it is often seen that Senju Kannon is placed at the center and Bishamonten and Fudo Myoo are placed at its sides (Myoo-in Temple in Shiga, Bujo-ji Temple in Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, in the temples of the Tendai sect it is often seen that Senju Kannon is placed at the center and Bishamonten and Fudo Myoo are placed at its sides (Myoo-in Temple in Shiga, Bujo-ji Temple in Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="32">
<j>四天王の1体として北方（須弥壇上では向かって右奥）を護る多聞天像の作例も数多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many works of Tamonten statues which guard the north (the back of dais for a Buddhist image on the observers&apos; right) as one of the Shitenno.</e>
<cmt>須弥壇→Webster&apos;s Online Dictionary</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many works of Tamonten statues that guard the north (the back of the dais for a Buddhist image on the observers&apos; right) as being among the shitenno.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many works of Tamonten statues that guard the north (the back of the dais for a Buddhist image on the observer&apos;s right) as being among the Shitenno.</e>
<cmt>四天王を大文字に。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>その姿は独尊の毘沙門天像と特に変わるところはないが、左右いずれかの手に宝塔を捧げ持つ像が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The figure is almost same as individual Bishamonten statue but often has a pagoda in one hand or the other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The figure is nearly the same as an individual Bishamonten statue but often has a pagoda in one hand.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The figure is nearly the same as an individual Bishamonten statue but often has a pagoda in one hand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="34">
<j>国宝指定品としては東大寺戒壇堂、京都・浄瑠璃寺、奈良・興福寺などの四天王像中の多聞天像がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Designated works from nation are Tamonten statues among Shitenno statues at Todai-ji Temple Kaidan-do, Joruri-ji Temple in Kyoto, Kofuku-ji Temple in Nara.</e>
<cmt>興福寺→http://www.kohfukuji.com/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Designated works from the nation are Tamonten statues among the shitenno statues at Todai-ji Temple Kaidan-do, Joruri-ji Temple in Kyoto, Kofuku-ji Temple in Nara.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Designated works from the nation are Tamonten statues among the Shitenno statues at Todai-ji Temple Kaidan-do, Joruri-ji Temple in Kyoto, Kofuku-ji Temple in Nara.</e>
<cmt>四天王を大文字に。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="35">
<j>派生的な姿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Derived figures</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Derived figures</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Derived figures</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="36">
<j>托塔李天王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takutori-tenno</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takutori-tenno</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takutori-tenno</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>中国では、軍神と称えられた唐代初期の武将李靖と習合し、托塔李天王(たくとうりてんのう。単に托塔天王とも)という尊格が生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In China it was mixed with Risei, Li Jing, a warrior at the beginning of Tang who was respected as a war god, which led to a creation of a god, Takutori-tenno.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In China it was mixed with Risei (Li Jing), a warrior at the beginning of the Tang who was respected as a war god, which led to the creation of the god Takutori-tenno.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In China it was mixed with Risei (Li Jing), a warrior at the beginning of the Tang who was respected as a war god, which led to the creation of the god Takutori-tenno.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="38">
<j>この托塔李天王は、現在では四天王の多聞天とは別の神と考えられ、むしろ多聞天も含めた四天王を率いる神々の将軍とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This Takutori-tenno is thought as another god other than Tamonten among Shitenno at present and rather a Shogun of gods who lead Shitenno including Tamonten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Takutori-tenno is today thought of as a god other than Tamonten among the shitenno and as a kind of shogun of gods who lead the shitenno, including Tamonten.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Takutori-tenno is today thought of as a god other than Tamonten among the Shitenno and as a kind of shogun of gods who led the Shitenno, including Tamonten.</e>
<cmt>四天王を大文字に。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>後に道教でも崇められるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, it became to be revered in Dokyo as well.</e>
<cmt>道教→Webster Online Dictionary</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, it became to be revered in Dokyo as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, it became to be revered in Dokyo as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>ナタ太子の父として描かれる『西遊記』の托塔李天王、封神演義の李靖がこれである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is Takutori-tenno described as father of Nata-taishi in &quot;Journey to West&quot; and Risei in Feng-Shen-Yen-I.</e>
<cmt>封神演義→http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110000340044/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is Takutori-tenno, described as father of Nata-taishi in &quot;Journey to West&quot; and Risei in Feng-Shen-Yen-I.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is Takutori-tenno, described as father of Nata-taishi in &quot;Journey to West&quot; and Risei in Feng-Shen-Yen-I.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="41">
<j>前述の通り四天王の多聞天は傘などを持った姿で表されるが、托塔李天王は宝塔を持った武将の姿で表される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As mentioned above, while Tamonten of Shitenno is shown as a figure which has an umbrella, Takutori-tenno is shown as a figure of warrior which has a pagoda.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As mentioned above, while Tamonten of the shitenno is shown as a figure that has an umbrella, Takutori-tenno is shown as a warrior figure that has a pagoda.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As mentioned above, while Tamonten of the Shitenno is shown as a figure that has an umbrella, Takutori-tenno is shown as a warrior figure that has a pagoda.</e>
<cmt>四天王を大文字に。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>これは唐代に於いて造形された毘沙門天の古い姿を継承したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This succeeds the old figure of Bishamonten, which was shaped during Tang Dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This succeeds the old figure of Bishamonten, which was shaped during the Tang dynasty.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This succeeds the old figure of Bishamonten, which was shaped during the Tang dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="43">
<j>兜跋毘沙門天</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tobatsu Bishamonten</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tobatsu Bishamonten</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tobatsu Bishamonten</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>兜跋毘沙門天（とばつびしゃもんてん）と呼ばれる特殊な像容がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a particular figure of statue which is called Tobatsu Bishamonten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a particular figure of statue which is called Tobatsu Bishamonten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a particular figure of statue which is called Tobatsu Bishamonten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>金鎖甲（きんさこう）という鎖を編んで作った鎧を着し、腕には海老籠手（えびごて）と呼ぶ防具を着け筒状の宝冠を被る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It puts on an amour knitted by chains, Kinsako (金鎖甲), and protective gears which are called Ebigote (海老籠手) in arms and a coronet on the head.</e>
<cmt>金鎖甲、海老籠手→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It puts on an amour knitted from chains (kinsako (金鎖甲), and protective gear called ebigote (海老籠手) over the arms, as well as a coronet on the head.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It wears armor knitted from chains (Kinsako (金鎖甲), and protective gear called Ebigote (海老籠手) over the arms, as well as a coronet on the head.</e>
<cmt>金鎖甲（きんさこう）・海老籠手（えびごて）を大文字に。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>持物は左手に宝塔、右手に宝棒または戟で、見るからに異国風の像である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its belongings are a pagoda in the left hand, a treasure club or ji in the right hand, which is visibly-exotic.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its belongings are a pagoda in the left hand and a treasure club or ji in the right hand, which is clearly exotic.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its belongings are a pagoda in the left hand and a treasure club or ji in the right hand, which is clearly exotic.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>また、邪鬼ではなく地天女及び二鬼(尼藍婆、毘藍婆)の上に立つ姿である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it stands on Chitennyo and two devils (Niramba and Biramba) instead of Jaki.</e>
<cmt>地天女→http://www.eonet.ne.jp/~kotonara/sitennouzou.htm、尼藍婆→http://www.eonet.ne.jp/~kotonara/sitennouzou.htm、毘藍婆→http://www.eonet.ne.jp/~kotonara/sitennouzou.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, it stands on Chitennyo and two devils (Niramba and Biramba) instead of Jaki.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, it stands on Chitennyo and two devils (Niranba and Biranba) instead of Jaki.</e>
<cmt>Niramba →Niranba に変更しました。Biramba→Biranbaに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>東寺の兜跋毘沙門天像は、かつて羅城門の楼上に安置されていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Tobatsu Bishamonten in To-ji Temple (Kyoogokoku-ji Temple) was placed on Rajomon gate.</e>
<cmt>東寺→http://kaiwai.city.kyoto.jp/search/view_sight.php?ManageCode=1000042&amp;InforKindCode=1、羅城門→http://kaiwai.city.kyoto.jp/search/view_sight.php?ManageCode=6000058&amp;InforKindCode=1</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Tobatsu Bishamonten in To-ji Temple (Kyoogokoku-ji Temple) was placed on Rajomon gate.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Tobatsu Bishamonten in To-ji Temple (Kyoogokoku-ji Temple) was placed on Rajomon gate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="49">
<j>「兜跋」とは西域兜跋国、即ち現在のトゥルファンとする説が一般的で、ここに毘沙門天がこの姿で現れたという伝説に基づく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is generally said that &apos;Tobatsu (兜跋)&apos; means Western 兜跋 country, that is, Turfan at present, which is based on a legend that Bishamonten appeared in this place with this figure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is generally said that &apos;Tobatsu (兜跋)&apos; means Western 兜跋 country (Turfan at present), which is based on a legend that Bishamonten appeared in this place with this figure.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is generally said that &apos;Tobatsu (兜跋)&apos; means Western 兜跋 country (Turfan at present), which is based on a legend that Bishamonten appeared in this place with this figure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>また「刀抜」「屠半」などの字を宛てることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other characters of &apos;刀抜&apos; or &apos;屠半&apos; are used in some cases.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other characters of &apos;刀抜&apos; or &apos;屠半&apos; are used in some cases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other characters of &apos;刀抜&apos; or &apos;屠半&apos; are used in some cases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="51">
<j>像容は、東寺像を忠実に模刻したもの（奈良国立博物館像、京都・清凉寺像など）と、地天女の両手の上に立つ以外は通例の毘沙門天像と変わらないもの（岩手・成島毘沙門堂像など）とがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The figures of statue are clarified into two; the one which imitates the statue of To-ji Temple truly (the statue of Nara National Museum, the statue of Seiryo-ji Temple in Kyoto) and the other which is almost same as usual Bishamonten statue except standing on the both hands of Chitennyo (Narushima Bishamon-do in Iwate, and so on).</e>
<cmt>奈良国立博物館→http://www.narahaku.go.jp/、清凉寺→http://www.kyototsuu.jp/Temple/SeiryouJi.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The figures of statues are clarified into two: the one that faithfully emulates the statue of To-ji Temple (the statue of Nara National Museum, the statue of Seiryo-ji Temple in Kyoto) and the other, which is nearly the same as the usual Bishamonten statue except that it stands on both hands of Chitennyo (Narushima Bishamon-do in Iwate, etc.).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The figures of statues are clarified into two: the one that faithfully emulates the statue of To-ji Temple (the statue of Nara National Museum, the statue of Seiryo-ji Temple in Kyoto) and the other, which is nearly the same as the usual Bishamonten statue except that it stands on both hands of Chitennyo (Narushima Bishamon-do in Iwate, etc.).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), POPPE(id:36219), 月下薄氷(id:47743), Nnh(id:474), MIsogi(id:20599), Kstigarbha(id:13376), 0null0(id:582), Eskimbot(id:29676), Urania(id:7213), 寒漁夫(id:99134), 摩利支天(id:187890), Akiyoshi&apos;s Room(id:146283), Ko-ken(id:49348), くっちゃめ(id:86793), Chobot(id:20846), 無空(id:17049), ウィキ豊(id:82961), Izayohi(id:13095), Peehyoro Acala(id:170), Chi-Ham(id:143515), Σειρην(id:103233), 優曇華(id:6461), STBot(id:137943), Yanahan(id:2437), しまながし(id:90740), Sh(id:2707), Makotozushi(id:4545), SuisuiBot(id:10165), M-Falcon(id:1227), Boca samba(id:137526), 663highland(id:18755), Alexbot(id:157199), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>