<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>守敏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shubin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shubin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shubin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>守敏（しゅびん、生没年不詳）は、平安時代前期の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shubin (dates of his birth and death are unknown) was a monk in the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shubin (dates of birth and death unknown) was a monk in the early Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shubin (dates of birth and death unknown) was a monk in the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>出自については不詳である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His origin is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His birthplace is unknown.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His birthplace was unknown.</e>
<cmt>過去形にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>守敏僧都（しゅびんそうず）と称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was called Shubin Sozu (high-ranking priest).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was called Shubin Sozu (high-ranking priest).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was called Shubin Sozu (high-ranking priest).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>大和国石淵寺の勤操（ごんそう）らに三論・法相を学び、真言密教にも通じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He learned Sanlun (a school of Buddhism) and the Hosso (Dharma Characteristics school) from Gonso of Iwabuchi-dera Temple in Yamato Province and others, as well as had thorough knowledge of Shingon Esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He learned the tenets of the Sanlun (a school of Buddhism) and the Hosso (Dharma Characteristics school) from Gonso of Iwabuchi-dera Temple in Yamato Province among others, and had thorough knowledge of Shingon Esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He learned the Three Shastras (Three Treatises) and the Hosso (Dharma Characteristics school) from Gonso of Iwabuchi-dera Temple in Yamato Province among others, and had thorough knowledge of Shingon Esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>823年（弘仁14年）嵯峨天皇から空海に東寺が、守敏に西寺が与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Emperor Saga granted To-ji Temple to Kukai in 823, he simultaneously granted Sai-ji Temple to Shubin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Emperor Saga granted To-ji Temple to Kukai in 823, he simultaneously granted Sai-ji Temple to Shubin.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Emperor Saga granted To-ji Temple to Kukai and simultaneously granted Sai-ji Temple to Shubin in 823.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>東寺の僧空海とは何事にも対立していたとされ、824年（弘仁15年）の干ばつのときに神泉苑での雨乞いの儀式に於いて空海に敗れ、空海に矢を放ったが地蔵菩薩に阻まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having been in rivalry on everything with a monk of To-ji Temple Kukai, when he was defeated by Kukai in the competition for inducing rainfall by prayer in the draught hit in 824, he shot an arrow at Kukai, but it was interrupted by Jizo Bosatsu (Jizo Bodhisattva).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having been a rival in most matters with the monk Kukai, on being defeated by him in a competition for inducing rainfall by prayer when a draught hit in 824, he shot an arrow at Kukai, but its path was interrupted by a Jizo Bosatsu (Jizo Bodhisattva).</e>
<cmt>Grammar, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having been a rival in most matters with Kukai, the monk of To-ji Temple, on being defeated by him in a competition for inducing rainfall by prayer when a draught hit in 824, he shot an arrow at Kukai, but its path was interrupted by a Jizo Bosatsu (Jizo Bodhisattva).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>現在、羅城門跡の傍らに「矢取地蔵」か祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Yatori Jizo&quot; (Jizo Bosatsu which protected Kukai from arrow) is now enshrined beside the site of the demolished Rasho-mon Gate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Yatori Jizo&quot; (Jizo Bosatsu which protected Kukai from the arrow) is now enshrined beside the site of the demolished Rasho-mon Gate.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;Yatori Jizo&apos; (Jizo Bosatsu which protected Kukai from the arrow) is now enshrined beside the site of the demolished Rasho-mon Gate.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>同じくして西寺も寂れていったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that Sai-ji Temple gradually fell into ruin in those days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that Sai-ji Temple gradually fell into ruin in those days as a result.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that Sai-ji Temple gradually fell into ruin in those days as a result.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Bmeg(id:118515), 代言人(id:33675), R28Bot(id:177951), Nighthawks(id:36125), Ete(id:28565), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>