<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>綽如</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shakunyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shakunyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shakunyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>綽如（しゃくにょ）は、南北朝時代 (日本)の浄土真宗の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shakunyo was a monk of Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shakunyo was a monk of Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shakunyo was a monk of Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は善如。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Zennyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Zennyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Zennyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>権大納言日野時光の猶子となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was adopted by Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor), Tokimitsu HINO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was adopted by Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor), Tokimitsu HINO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was adopted by Gon Dainagon (provisional chief councilor of state), Tokimitsu HINO.</e>
<cmt>権大納言の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>本願寺第五世。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the fifth chief priest of Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the fifth chief priest of Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the fifth chief priest of Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>年齢は、数え年。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ages here are represented according to the traditional Japanese system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ages here are represented according to the traditional Japanese system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ages here are represented according to the traditional Japanese system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>日付は、文献との整合を保つ為、旧暦（宣明暦）表示（生歿年月日を除く）とし、南北朝時代の元号は、北朝 (日本)で表記する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to keep the correspondence with the documents, the dates are indicated according to the lunar calendar (the Senmyo Calendar), except the dates of birth and death, and the names of era from the period of the Northern and Southern Courts are expressed according to those designated by the Northern Court (Japan).</e>
<cmt>英訳においては、日付・年号はすべてグレゴリオ暦で表記されるため、この一文は、不要になるかと思われます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to store and maintain the correspondence with the documents, the dates are indicated according to the lunar calendar (the Senmyo Calendar), except for the dates of births and deaths, and the names of eras from the period of the Northern and Southern Courts are expressed according to those designated by the Northern Court (Japan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to store and maintain the correspondence with the documents, the dates are indicated according to the lunar calendar (the Senmyo Calendar), except for the dates of births and deaths, and the names of eras during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts are expressed according to those designated by the Northern Court (Japan).</e>
<cmt>Ｅ欄ご確認願います。From→during</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>観応元年3月15日（1350年4月30日）、誕生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shakunyo was born on April 30, 1350.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shakunyo was born on April 30, 1350.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shakunyo was born on April 30, 1350.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>得度した後、権大僧都に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After entering the priesthood, he was given a position as gon daisozu (junior prelate).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After entering the priesthood, he was given a position as gon daisozu (junior prelate).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After entering the priesthood, he was given a position as gon daisozu (the provisional highest grade that can be held by one who has reached the second highest rank in the hierarchy of Buddhist priests).</e>
<cmt>大僧都の訳を用語統一リストのもにし、「権」なので provisional を追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>康応2年/明徳元年（1390年）、「本願寺」を継承し第五世になるも、まもなく寺務を法嗣である第2子の巧如に委任し、越中国杉谷に草庵を結び居所とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he was appointed as the fifth chief priest of &quot;Hongan-ji Temple&quot; in 1390, soon after he entrusted the practical running of the temple to his second son Gyonyo who was his hoshi (a successor to an abbacy) in order to build and live in a soan (a hermitage built with a simple structure with a thatched roof) in Sugitani of Ecchu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon after he was appointed as the fifth chief priest of &quot;Hongan-ji Temple&quot; in 1390, he entrusted the practical running of the temple to his second son Gyonyo who was his hoshi (successor to an abbacy) in order to build and live in a soan (a hermitage built with a simple structure with a thatched roof) in Sugitani of Ecchu Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon after he was appointed as the fifth chief priest of &apos;Hongan-ji Temple&apos; in 1390, he entrusted the practical running of the temple to his second son Gyonyo who was his hoshi (successor to an abbacy) in order to build and live in a soan (a hermitage built with a simple structure with a thatched roof) in Sugitani of Ecchu Province.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>明から朝廷に送られてきた難解な国書を読むのに、青蓮院は綽如を推挙し、上洛する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shakunyo moved to Kyoto upon being recommended by Shoren-in Temple as a scholar who excelled at deciphering the difficult sovereign&apos;s messages sent from Ming to the Japanese imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shakunyo moved to Kyoto upon being recommended by Shoren-in Temple as a scholar who excelled at deciphering the difficult sovereign&apos;s messages sent from Ming to the Japanese imperial court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shakunyo moved to Kyoto upon being recommended by Shoren-in Temple as a scholar who excelled at deciphering the difficult sovereign&apos;s messages sent from Ming to the Japanese imperial court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>綽如によって、その国書の内容が分かり、また返書の草稿も書く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shakunyo translated the contents of the sovereign&apos;s messages, and also wrote the drafts of reply on behalf of the court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shakunyo translated the contents of the sovereign&apos;s messages, and also wrote the drafts of replies on behalf of the court.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shakunyo translated the contents of the sovereign&apos;s messages, and also wrote the drafts of replies on behalf of the court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その才と功績を認めた後小松天皇より、「周圓上人」の号を賜わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Gokomatsu praised his talent and achievements, and gave him the title of Shuen jonin (a circumferential holy priest).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Gokomatsu praised his talent and achievements, and gave him the title of Shuen jonin (a circumferential holy priest).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Gokomatsu praised his talent and achievements, and gave him the title of &apos;Shuen shonin&apos; (a circumferential holy priest).</e>
<cmt>jonin→shonin「」に &apos; &apos;circumferential が必要かご確認願います。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>また後小松天皇より、宮中で『無量寿経』を講ずることを依頼される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Gokomatsu also requested him to give lectures on &quot;Muryojukyo Sutra&quot; at the imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Gokomatsu also requested him to give lectures on &quot;Muryojukyo Sutra&quot; at the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Gokomatsu also requested him to give lectures on &quot;Muryojukyo Sutra&quot; at the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>その礼として、聖徳太子2歳の南無佛木像と「聖徳太子絵伝」8巻を賜わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a token of his gratitude, the emperor gave him Namubutukizo (a Buddhist wooden statue) and eight volumes of Shotokutaishi-eden (Illustrated Biography of Prince Shotoku).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a token of his gratitude, the emperor gave him Namubutukizo (a Buddhist wooden statue) and eight volumes of Shotokutaishi-eden (Illustrated Biography of Prince Shotoku).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a token of his gratitude, the emperor gave him Namubutukizo (a Buddhist wooden statue) and eight volumes of &apos;Shotokutaishi-eden&apos; (Illustrated Biography of Prince Shotoku).</e>
<cmt>「」に &apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>後小松天皇は、綽如に一寺建立の願いがある事を知ると、「勧進状」の作成を認め「料紙」を授ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Emperor Gokomatsu learned that Shakunyo had a dream of erecting a temple, he permitted him to make &quot;kanjinjo&quot; (a letter of temple solicitation) and gave him &quot;ryoshi&quot; (special paper for writing).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Emperor Gokomatsu learned that Shakunyo had a dream of erecting a temple, he permitted him to make &quot;kanjinjo&quot; (a letter of temple solicitation) and gave him &quot;ryoshi&quot; (special paper for writing).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Emperor Gokomatsu learned that Shakunyo had a dream of erecting a temple, he permitted him to make &apos;kanjinjo&apos; (a letter of temple solicitation) and gave him &apos;ryoshi&apos; (special paper for writing).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>越中国に戻ると「勧進状」（重要文化財）を作成し、加賀・能登・越中・越後・信濃・飛騨において勧化する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shakunyo returned to Ecchu Province and completed &quot;kanjinjo&quot; (now preserved as a National important cultural asset), and with it, he solicited donations in Kaga, Noto, Ecchu, Echigo, Shinano and Hida for erecting the temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shakunyo returned to Ecchu Province and completed &quot;kanjinjo&quot; (now preserved as a National important cultural asset), and with it, he solicited donations in Kaga, Noto, Ecchu, Echigo, Shinano and Hida for erecting the temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shakunyo returned to Ecchu Province and completed &apos;kanjinjo&apos; (now preserved as a National important cultural asset), and with it, he solicited donations in Kaga, Noto, Ecchu, Echigo, Shinano and Hida for erecting the temple.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>その浄財により井波の地に寺を建立し、「瑞泉寺」の勅号を賜わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thanks to the donations, he was able to erect a temple in Inami (in Ecchu Province), which received a temple name of &quot;Zuisen-ji&quot; from the emperor.</e>
<cmt>井波には（in Ecchu Province)と補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thanks to the donations, he was able to erect a temple in Inami (in Ecchu Province), which received the temple name of &quot;Zuisen-ji&quot; from the emperor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thanks to the donations, he was able to erect a temple in Inami (in Ecchu Province), which received the temple name of &apos;Zuisen-ji&apos; from the emperor.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これより後は、「瑞泉寺」を拠点に教化にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From then on, he pursued his enlightenment campaign which was based in the Zuisen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From then on, he pursued his enlightenment campaign which was based in the Zuisen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From then on, he pursued his enlightenment campaign which was based in &apos;the Zuisen-ji Temple.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「」に &apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="19">
<j>明徳4年4月24日（1393年6月12日）、44歳にて示寂。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 12, 1393, Shakunyo entered nirvana (passed away) at the age of forty-four.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 12, 1393, Shakunyo entered nirvana (passed away) at the age of forty-four.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 12, 1393, Shakunyo entered nirvana (passed away) at the age of 44.</e>
<cmt>数字表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="20">
<j>応永元年（1394年）、寺務を委任されていた巧如が「本願寺」を継承する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1394, Gyonyo, who had been appointed as a temple administrator, inherited &quot;Hongan-ji Temple.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1394, Gyonyo, who had been appointed as a temple administrator, inherited &quot;Hongan-ji Temple.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1394, Gyonyo, who had been appointed as a temple administrator, inherited &apos;Hongan-ji Temple.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Resto1578(id:168692), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), R28Bot(id:177951), 松茸(id:27535), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), Nighthawks(id:36125), Point136(id:211299), 調声人(id:126495), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), Nog(id:53565), Tiu(id:9523), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>