<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>蘭坡景し</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ranbakeishi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ranbakeishi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ranbakeishi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>蘭坡景茝（らんぱけいし、応永26年（1417年） － 文亀元年2月28日 (旧暦)（1501年3月17日））は、室町時代中期から戦国時代 (日本)にかけての臨済宗の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ranbakeishi (1417 – March 17, 1501) was a Buddhist priest of the Rinzai sect between the mid Muromachi and Sengoku periods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ranbakeishi (1417 – March 17, 1501) was a Buddhist priest of the Rinzai sect between the mid-Muromachi and Sengoku periods.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ranbakeishi (1417 – March 17, 1501) was a Buddhist priest of the Rinzai sect between the mid-Muromachi and Sengoku periods (Period of Warring States).</e>
<cmt>英語説明補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>別号は雪樵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His another name was Sessho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His other name was Sessho.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His other name was Sessho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>近江国の出身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ranbakeishi came from Omi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ranbakeishi came from Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ranbakeishi came from Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>南禅寺に入り大模梵軌（だいもぼんき）に師事してその法を継ぎ、希世霊彦（きせいれいげん）や瑞巌龍惺（ずいがんりゅうせい）らに漢詩文を学んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon entering to Nanzen-ji Temple, Ranbakeishi became a pupil of Daimobonki, Ranbakeishi, carrying over his master&apos;s dharma and studying Chinese poetry under various people including Kiseireigen and Zuiganryusei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon entering Nanzen-ji Temple, Ranbakeishi became a pupil of Daimobonki, carrying over his master&apos;s dharma and studying Chinese poetry under various people including Kiseireigen and Zuiganryusei.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon entering Nanzen-ji Temple, Ranbakeishi became a pupil of Daimobonki, carrying over his master&apos;s dharma and studying Chinese poetry under various people including Kiseireigen and Zuiganryusei.</e>
<cmt>全角削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>1475年（文明 (日本)7年）臨川寺の住持となり、その後は相国寺・等持院・常在光寺などの住持を歴任し、南禅寺内に仙館軒（のちに仙館院）を創建している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequent to becoming the chief priest of Rinsen-ji Temple in 1475, Ranbakeishi successively held the post of the chief priest of various temples such as Shokoku-ji Temple, Toji-in Temple and常在光寺 and created仙館軒 (later called仙館院) on the grounds of Nanzen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>仙館軒、仙館院－読み・定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequent to becoming the chief priest of Rinsen-ji Temple in 1475, Ranbakeishi successively held the post of chief priest of various temples such as Shokoku-ji Temple, Toji-in Temple and常在光寺 and created仙館軒 (later called仙館院) on the grounds of Nanzen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequent to becoming the chief priest of Rinsen-ji Temple in 1475, Ranbakeishi successively held the post of chief priest of various temples such as Shokoku-ji Temple, Toji-in Temple and 常在光寺 and created 仙館軒 (later called 仙館院) on the grounds of Nanzen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>仙館軒、仙館院－読み・定訳不明　スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>後土御門天皇に重用され、詩などを進講している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ranbakeishi was given important a post by Emperor Gotsuchimikado giving lectures on various subjects including poetry to that emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ranbakeishi was given an important post by Emperor Gotsuchimikado, and gave lectures on various subjects including poetry to the emperor.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ranbakeishi was given an important post by Emperor Gotsuchimikado, and gave lectures on various subjects including poetry to the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 พริกขี้หนู(id:131976), Oxhop(id:2551), Nevylax(id:38464), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), Charenji(id:7908), Nighthawks(id:36125), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>