<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>慈雲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jiun</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jiun</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jiun</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>慈雲（じうん　享保3年7月28日 (旧暦)(1718年8月24日) - 文化 (元号)元年12月22日 (旧暦)(1805年1月22日)）は江戸時代後期の真言宗の僧侶。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jiun is (August 24, 1718-January 22, 1805) was a Buddhist monk of Shingon Sect who was active in the late Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jiun (August 24, 1718-January 22, 1805) was a Buddhist monk of the Shingon Sect who was active in the late Edo period.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jiun (August 24, 1718 - January 22, 1805) was a Buddhist priest of the Shingon Sect in the late Edo period.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>戒律を重視し「正法律」（真言律）を提唱した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He emphasized Buddhist precepts and advocated &quot;Shoboritsu&quot; (Shingonritsu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He emphasized Buddhist precepts and advocated &quot;Shoboritsu&quot; (Shingonritsu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He emphasized Buddhist precepts and advocated &apos;Shoboritsu&apos; (Shingonritsu (literally, True Word Precepts)).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変え補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>雲伝神道の開祖。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is a founder of Unden Shinto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a founder of Unden Shinto.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a founder of Unden Shinto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>能書家としても知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is also known as a skilled calligrapher.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is also known as a skilled calligrapher.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also known as a skilled calligrapher.</e>
<cmt>過去形にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>俗姓、上月氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His secular surname was Ueduki clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His secular surname was Ueduki clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His secular surname was the Uezuki clan.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>諱は飲光（おんこう）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Imina was Onko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Imina was Onko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His imina (personal name) was Onko.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>号は百不知童子、葛城山人、雙龍叟など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Go (pen name) was Hyakufuchi Doji, Katsuragi Sanjin and Soryu no okina etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Go (pen name) was Hyakufuchi Doji, Katsuragi Sanjin and Soryu no okina etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His go (pen name) was Hyakufuchi Doji (literally, know-nothing child), Katsuragi Sanjin (literally, a man on Mt. Katsuragi) and Soryu no okina (literally, an old man of twin dragon), and so on.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>慈雲尊者と尊称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His title of honor was Jiunsonja.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His title of honor was Jiunsonja.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His title of honor was Jiun Sonja (Buddhist saint).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>大阪中之島 (大阪府)（現、大阪市北区 (大阪市)）の高松藩蔵屋敷で上月安範の子として生まれ、父の遺言により13歳の時に摂津国の法楽寺（大阪市東住吉区）で出家、同寺の住職・忍網貞紀に密教と梵語（サンスクリット）を学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born at Takamatsu Domain&apos;s Kurayashiki-warehouses located in Osaka Nakanoshima (Osaka Prefecture) (Kita Ward, Osaka City) as a son of Yasunori KODUKI, became a monk of Horaku-ji Temple, located in Settsu-no-Kuni (Higashisumiyoshi Ward, Osaka City), when he was 13 years old in accordance with his father&apos;s living will and studied Mikkyo (Esoteric Buddhism) and Sanskrit under the guidance of Sadanori SHINOBITSUNA, the chief priest of the temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born at Takamatsu Domain&apos;s Kurayashiki-warehouses located in Osaka Nakanoshima (Osaka Prefecture) (Kita Ward, Osaka City) as a son of Yasunori KODUKI, became a monk at Horaku-ji Temple, located in Settsu-no-Kuni (Higashi-Sumiyoshi Ward, Osaka City), when he was 13 years old, in accordance with his father&apos;s living will and studied Mikkyo (Esoteric Buddhism) and Sanskrit under the guidance of Sadanori SHINOBITSUNA, the chief priest of the temple.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born at Kurayashiki (Warehouse-residence) of Takamatsu clan&apos;s located in Osaka Nakanoshima (Osaka Prefecture) (present Kita-ku Ward, Osaka City) as a son of Yasunori KOZUKI, became a priest at Horaku-ji Temple in Settsu Province (Higashi-Sumiyoshi-ku Ward, Osaka City) at his age of 13 in accordance with his father&apos;s will and studied Esoteric Buddhism and Sanskrit under the guidance of Sadanori SHINOBITSUNA, the chief priest of the temple.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>18歳の時に、忍綱の命で京都に行き、伊藤東涯に古学の儒学を学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he was 18 years old, he went to Kyoto at the behest of Shinobitsuna and studied ancient Confucianism under the guidance of Togai ITO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he was 18 years old, he went to Kyoto at the behest of Shinobitsuna and studied ancient Confucianism under the guidance of Togai ITO.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he was 18 years old, he went to Kyoto at the order of Shinobitsuna and studied ancient Confucianism under the guidance of Togai ITO.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>翌年に奈良に遊学し、顕教、密教、神道と宗派を問わず学び、河内国の野中寺（羽曳野市）で秀厳の教えを受けて、戒律の研究を始め、1738年(元文3年)、具足戒を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following year, he travelled to Nara to study Exoteric Buddhism, Esoteric Buddhism and Shinto Religion and thereafter he started to study Buddhist precepts at Nonakadera Temple (Habikino City) in Kawachi-no-kuni under the guidance of Shugen and was bestowed Gusokukai in 1738.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following year, he travelled to Nara to study Exoteric Buddhism, Esoteric Buddhism and the Shinto Religion and thereafter he started to study Buddhist precepts at Nonakadera Temple (Habikino City) in Kawachi-no-kuni under the guidance of Shugen and was bestowed Gusokukai in 1738.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following year, he travelled to Nara to study Exoteric Buddhism, Esoteric Buddhism and the Shinto Religion and thereafter he started to study Buddhist precepts at Nonaka-dera Temple (Habikino City) in Kawachi Province under the guidance of Shugen and was bestowed Gusokukai (taking the full precepts) in 1738.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>翌年には忍網から灌頂を受け、法楽寺の住職となったが、2年後に住職を同門に譲った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following year, he received Kanjo from Shinobitsuna and became the chief priest of Horaku-ji Temple, but he handed over the position of the chead hief to a fellow monk 2 years later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following year, he received Kanjo from Shinobitsuna and became chief priest of Horaku-ji Temple, but he handed over the position to a fellow monk 2 years later.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following year, he received kanjo (a ceremony to be the successor) from Shinobitsuna and assumed the position of the chief priest of Horaku-ji Temple, but he handed over the position to a fellow priest two years later.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。ネイティブチェックをお願いします。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その後、信濃国に曹洞宗の僧侶の大梅を訪ね、禅も修行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, he visited Daibai, a Buddhist monk of Soto Sect who resided in Shinano-no- kuni, and studied Zen Sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, he visited Daibai, a Buddhist monk of Soto Sect who resided in Shinano-no-kuni, and studied the Zen Sect.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, he visited Daibai, a priest of Soto Sect in Shinano Province, and studied the Zen Sect as well.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。ネイティブチェックをお願いします。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>1744年(延享元年)、河内の長栄寺（東大阪市）を再興して住職となり、初めて戒律の講義を行なったのを皮切りに、高野山や近畿の各地で修行と講演を続ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1744, he restored Choei-ji Temple (Higashiosaka City) in Kawachi, became its chief priest and conducted his first lecture on Buddhist precepts, and thereafter he continued ascetic training and lecture at Koyasan and other places in Kinki region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1744, he restored Choei-ji Temple (Higashiosaka City) in Kawachi, became its chief priest and conducted his first lecture on Buddhist precepts, and thereafter he continued ascetic training and lectures at Koyasan and other places in the Kinki region.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1744, he restored Choei-ji Temple (Higashiosaka City) in Kawachi, assumed the position of the chief priest and conducted his first lecture on Buddhist precepts, and thereafter he continued ascetic training and lectures on Mt. Koya and other places in the Kinki region.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。ネイティブチェックをお願いします。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>1758年(宝暦8年)から生駒山中の雙龍庵という草庵に隠居して研究に専念し、千巻にも及ぶ梵語研究の大著『梵学津梁』を著す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From 1758, he stayed at a tea hut called Soryuan located on Mt. IKomayama, concentrated on studying and wrote 1,000 volumes of &quot;Bongakushinryo&quot;, a book of Sanskrit research.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 1758, he stayed at a tea hut called Soryuan located on Mt. Ikomayama, concentrated on studying and wrote 1,000 volumes of &quot;Bongakushinryo&quot;, a book of Sanskrit research.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 1758, he stayed at a tea hut called Soryuan on Mt. Ikomayama, concentrated on studying and wrote 1,000 volumes of &quot;Bongakushinryo&quot;, a book of Sanskrit research.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>その内容は、密教で行われてきた梵字の呪術的解釈を排し、梵語の文法を研究して、梵文で書かれた仏教教典の原典の内容を正しく読解しようとするものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this book, he rejected magical interpretation of Sanskrit which was prevalent in the world of Exoteric Buddhism and tried to understand correctly the content of original Buddhist scriptures that were written in Sanskrit by studying the grammar of Sanskrit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this book, he rejected the magical interpretation of Sanskrit which was prevalent in the world of Exoteric Buddhism and tried to correctly understand the contents of the original Buddhist scriptures that were written in Sanskrit, by studying Sanskrit grammar.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this book, he rejected the magical interpretation of Sanskrit which was prevalent in the world of Esoteric Buddhism and tried to correctly understand the contents of the original Buddhist scriptures written in Sanskrit, by studying Sanskrit grammar.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>この『梵学津梁』の内容は、明治時代に来日したフランス人のサンスクリット研究家シルヴェン・レヴィから高く評価されたほどであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The content of &quot;Bongakushinryo&quot; was highly valued by Silvain Revie, a French researcher of Sanskrit who came to Japan in Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>シルヴェン・レヴィ→フランス語の正確なスペル不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The contents of &quot;Bongakushinryo&quot; were highly valued by Silvain Revie, a French researcher of Sanskrit who came to Japan during the Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The contents of &quot;Bongakushinryo&quot; were highly valued by Silvain Revie, a French researcher of Sanskrit who came to Japan during the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>1775年(安永4年)、『十善法語』を著す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He wrote &quot;Juzen Hogo&quot; in 1775.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He wrote &quot;Juzen Hogo&quot; in 1775.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He wrote &quot;Juzen Hogo&quot; (Sermons on the Ten Good Precepts) in 1775.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>1776年(安永5年)に河内の高貴寺（南河内郡河南町）に入寺した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1776, he joined Koki-ji Temple (Anan-cho, MInamikawachi-gun) in Kawachi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1776, he joined Koki-ji Temple (Anan-cho, Minamikawachi-gun) in Kawachi.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1776, he joined Koki-ji Temple (Anan-cho, Minamikawachi-gun) in Kawachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="20">
<j>郡山藩主・柳沢保光の支援を受け、高貴寺の堂舎を整備し、この寺を正法律の本山と定めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the support of Yasumitsu YANAGISAWA, Koriyama feudal lord, he repaired temple buildings of Koki-ji Temple and decided this temple as the head temple of Shoboritsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the support of Yasumitsu YANAGISAWA, a Koriyama feudal lord, he repaired the temple buildings of Koki-ji Temple and selected this temple as the head temple of Shoboritsu.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the support of Yasumitsu YANAGISAWA, a feudal lord of the Koriyama clan, he repaired the temple buildings of Koki-ji Temple and selected this temple as the head temple of Shoboritsu.</e>
<cmt>用語表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="21">
<j>保光は慈雲に深く帰依し、慈雲の死後に保光が剃髪した際には毛髪を慈雲の墓のそばに埋めたほどであったと伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that as Yasumitsu was a devout believer in Jiun, he buried his hair beside Jiun&apos;s tomb when he took the tonsure after the death of Jiun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that as Yasumitsu was a devout believer in Jiun, he buried his hair beside Jiun&apos;s tomb when he took the tonsure after the death of Jiun.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that as Yasumitsu was a devout believer in Jiun, he buried his hair beside Jiun&apos;s tomb when he took the tonsure after the death of Jiun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="22">
<j>晩年に、独自の神道説を唱え、磐船神社 (河南町)を根本道場とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his last years, he advocated his own Shinto Thoughts and decided Iwafune-jinja shrine (Kanan-cho) as the konpondojo (fundamental training hall).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his last years, he advocated his own Shinto Thoughts and decided on Iwafune-jinja shrine (Kanan-cho) as the konpondojo (fundamental training hall).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his last years, he advocated his own Shinto thoughts and decided on Iwafune-jinja Shrine (Kanan-cho) as the konpondojo (fundamental training hall).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>慈雲の提唱した神道はのちに「雲神神道（うんでんしんとう）」と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinto Religion which Jiun advocated was called &quot;Unden Shinto&quot; in later years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shinto religion which Jiun advocated was called &quot;Unden Shinto&quot; in later years.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shinto religion which Jiun advocated was called &apos;Unden Shinto&apos; in later years.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="24">
<j>1804年、京都の阿弥陀寺でその生涯を終えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1804, he ended his life at Amida-ji temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1804, he ended his life at Amida-ji temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1804, he ended his life at Amida-ji temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nnh(id:474), Otraff(id:97860), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), Himazin(id:22034), Knua(id:66861), 岡部碩道(id:182846), 蔭人(id:80171), Ajax(id:11202), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>