<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>二箇相承</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nika Sojo Documents</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nika Sojo Documents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nika Sojo Documents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>二箇相承（にかそうじょう）は、1282年（弘安5年）、日蓮が、弟子の日興に宛てたとされる書。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nika Sojo are documents which are believed to be addressed from Nichiren to his disciple, Nikko, in 1282.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nika Sojo are documents which were believed to be addressed from Nichiren to his disciple, Nikko, in 1282.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nika Sojo are documents which were believed to be addressed from Nichiren to his disciple, Nikko, in 1282.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日蓮の一切の法の継承者であること（総付嘱書）と、身延山久遠寺の住職であると定めた（別付嘱書）とされる書状のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are regarded as documents that approved Nikko as the successor of each and every teachings by Nichiren (Sofuzokusho, or total document for entrustment) and decided Nikko as the chief priest of Minobusan Kuon-ji Temple (Betsufuzokusho).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are regarded as documents that approved Nikko as the successor of each and every teaching by Nichiren (Sofuzokusho, or total document for entrustment) and decided Nikko as the chief priest of Minobusan Kuon-ji Temple (Betsufuzokusho).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are regarded as documents that approved Nikko as the successor of each and every teaching by Nichiren (So-fuzokusho (total document for entrustment)) and decided Nikko as the chief priest of Kuon-ji Temple on Mt. Minobu (Betsu-fuzokusho).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>2通あることから二箇相承といい、書かれた場所から「身延相承」「池上相承」ともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are called Nika Sojo since there are 2 documents, and from the place it was written, they are also called &apos;Minobu Sojo&apos; and &apos;Ikegami Sojo.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are called Nika Sojo since there are 2 documents, and from the place it was written, they are also called &apos;Minobu Sojo&apos; and &apos;Ikegami Sojo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are called Nika Sojo since there are 2 (&apos;ni&apos;, in Japanese) documents, and from the place it was written, they are also called &apos;Minobu Sojo&apos; and &apos;Ikegami Sojo&apos; respectively.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>もともとは重須本門寺（北山本門寺）に伝えられたものであるが現在は日蓮の真筆は無く、写本のみが京要法寺、富士大石寺、西山本門寺等に伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, those were handed down to Omosu Honmon-ji Temple (Kitayama Honmon-ji Temple), but presently, there are no original copies by Nichiren, and only manuscripts are handed down to Yobo-ji Temple in Kyoto, Taiseki-ji Temple in Fuji, Nishiyama Honmon-ji Temple, and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, those were handed down to Omosu Honmon-ji Temple (Kitayama Honmon-ji Temple), but presently, there are no original copies by Nichiren, and only manuscripts are handed down to Yobo-ji Temple in Kyoto, Taiseki-ji Temple in Fuji, Nishiyama Honmon-ji Temple, and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, those were handed down to Omosu Honmon-ji Temple (Kitayama Honmon-ji Temple), but presently, there are no original copies by Nichiren, and only manuscripts are handed down to Yobo-ji Temple in Kyoto, Taiseki-ji Temple in Fuji, Nishiyama Honmon-ji Temple, and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>またさまざまな異本が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, many different manuscripts exist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, many different manuscripts exist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, many different manuscripts exist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史と経緯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History and circumstances</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History and circumstances</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History and Circumstances</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>身延相承は、その内容から日蓮一期弘法付属書とも総付嘱書とも称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minobu Sojo, from its contents, is also called Nichiren Ichigo Guho Fuzokusho (document of entrusting Nichiren&apos;s lifetime preaching) and Sofuzokusho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minobu Sojo, from its contents, is also called Nichiren Ichigo Guho Fuzokusho (document entrusting Nichiren&apos;s lifetime preachings) and Sofuzokusho.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minobu Sojo, from its contents, is also called Nichiren Ichigo Guho Fuzokusho (document entrusting Nichiren&apos;s lifetime preachings) and Sofuzokusho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>日蓮が身延を出発する直前に身延山中で書かれたと記述され身延相承と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is written that it was wrote in Minobu-san Mountain right before Nichiren depart from Minobu, and is called Minobu Sojo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is written that it was composed at Minobu-san Mountain right before Nichiren departed from Minobu, and is called Minobu Sojo.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is written that it was composed at Mt. Minobu right before Nichiren departed from Minobu, and is called Minobu Sojo.</e>
<cmt>用語表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>日蓮は湯治のため身延を出発し、途中、池上に寄って、その地で入滅した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nichiren departed from Minobu for hot spring cure, and on his way, he stopped at Ikegami, and died at the place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nichiren departed from Minobu for a hot spring cure, and on his way, he stopped at Ikegami, and died at there.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nichiren departed from Minobu for a hot spring cure, and on his way, he stopped at Ikegami, and died at there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>池上相承は、この入滅に際して池上（池上本門寺）で書かれたため、池上相承と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikegami Sojo is called like that since it was written at the time of his death at Ikegami (Ikegami Honmon-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ikegami Sojo is called that since it was written at the time of his death at Ikegami (Ikegami Honmon-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikegami Sojo is called that since it was written at the time of his death at Ikegami (Ikegami Honmon-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また身延久遠寺の別当（住職）であるとの記述から、身延山付属書とも別付嘱書とも称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also from the description as the betto (chief priest) of Minobu Kuon-ji Temple, it is also called Minobusan Fuzokusho (document for entrustment of Minobu-san Mountain) or Betsufuzokusho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also from the description as the betto (chief priest) of Minobu Kuon-ji Temple, it is also called Minobusan Fuzokusho (document for entrustment of Minobu-san Mountain) or Betsufuzokusho.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also from the description as the betto (chief priest) of Minobu Kuon-ji Temple, it is also called Minobusan Fuzokusho (document for entrustment of Mt. Minobu) and Betsu-fuzokusho.</e>
<cmt>前出に合わせ表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>身延相承は日付が9月13日になっているが、元祖化導記には、9月8日に身延沢を出発したとあり13日に身延山には居ないことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The date on Minobu Sojo is September 13, but in Ganso Kado Ki (biography of Nichiren), it is written that he had departed from Minobu stream in September 8, so that he can not be at Minobu-san Mountain on September 13.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The date on Minobu Sojo is September 13, but in Ganso Kado Ki (biography of Nichiren), it is written that he had departed from Minobu stream on September 8, so that he could not have been at Minobu-san Mountain on September 13.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The date on Minobu Sojo is September 13, but in Ganso Kado Ki (biography of Nichiren), it is written that he had departed from Minobu-sawa stream on September 8, so that he could not be at Mt. Minobu on September 13.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>この日付から二箇相承は偽書であるとの指摘がされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From this date, some people point out that Nika Sojo are forged documents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From this date, some people point out that Nika Sojo are forged documents.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From this date, some people point out that Nika Sojo are forged documents.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>さらに二箇相承は、上代には記録が無いため偽書であるとされているが、富士大石寺によると日蓮滅後27年目に六老僧の一人日頂の本尊抄得意抄添書があるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, Nika Sojo are regarded as fake documents since there are no records in ancient times, but according to Fuji Taiseki-ji Temple, there is a document by Niccho, who is one of 6 leading disciples of Nichiren, called Honzon Shotokuisho Soegaki, written in twenty-seventh year after Nichiren&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, Nika Sojo are regarded as fake documents since there are no records in ancient times, but according to Fuji Taiseki-ji Temple, there is a document by Niccho, who is one of 6 leading disciples of Nichiren, called Honzon Shotokuisho Soegaki, written in the twenty-seventh year after Nichiren&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, Nika Sojo are regarded as fake documents since there are no records in ancient times, but according to Fuji Taiseki-ji Temple, there is a document by Niccho, who was one of roku roso (the Six Senior Disciples of Nichiren), called Honzon Sho Tokui Sho Soegaki (The Covering Letter of &quot;Kanjin Honzon Sho&quot; (the Spiritual Contemplation and the Most Venerable One)), written in the twenty-seventh year after Nichiren&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>「本尊抄得意抄添書」は「観心本尊鈔得意鈔副書」と思われますが、そのまま訳出しています。過去形にし、補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>1308年（徳治3年）9月28日、本尊抄得意抄添書には次のように記述されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 28, 1308, it is described as follows in Honzon Shotokuisho Soegaki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 28, 1308, it is described as follows in Honzon Shotokuisho Soegaki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 19, 1308, it is described as follows in Honzon Sho Tokui Sho Soegaki.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ歴にし、用語表記を前出に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>興上一期弘法の付属をうけ日蓮日興と次第日興は無辺行の再来として末法本門の教主日蓮が本意之法門直受たり、熟脱を捨て下種を取るべき時節なり（日蓮宗宗学全書1）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By this entrustment of Nichiren&apos;s lifetime preaching, Nikko directly inherited the Buddhist teachings by the head of the sect Nichiren, and it is time that you should stop learning by yourself and spread the teachings to people as the second coming of Muhengyo Bosatsu in Mappo (latter days of Buddhism) (Nichiren Shu Shugaku Zensho, or the Complete Works of Nichiren sect, 1).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By this entrustment of Nichiren&apos;s lifetime preaching, Nikko directly inherited the Buddhist teachings by the head of the sect Nichiren, and it is time that you should stop learning by yourself and spread the teachings to people as the second coming of Muhengyo Bosatsu in Mappo (latter days of Buddhism) (Nichiren Shu Shugaku Zensho, or the Complete Works of Nichiren sect, 1).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By this entrustment of Nichiren&apos;s lifetime preaching, Nikko directly inherited the Buddhist teachings by the head of the sect Nichiren, and it is time that you should stop learning by yourself and spread the teachings to people as the second coming of Muhengyo Bosatsu (Boundless Practices) in Mappo (latter days of Buddhism) (Nichiren Shu Shugaku Zensho (the Complete Works of Nichiren Sect), volume 1).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>ただし日蓮の真筆とされる多くの遺文では、教主を釈尊としており、本尊抄得意抄添書には教主日蓮となっていることから、後世の作との指摘がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in many articles which are regarded to be written by Nichiren, the head of the sect is assumed as Shakyamuni, and since in Honzon Shotokuisho Soegaki it is written as the head of the sect Nichiren, it is pointed out that is was written in later years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in many articles which are regarded as having been written by Nichiren, the head of the sect is assumed as Shakyamuni, and since in Honzon Shotokuisho Soegaki it is written as the head of the sect Nichiren, it is pointed out that is was written in later years.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in many articles which are regarded as having been written by Nichiren, the head of the sect is assumed as Shakyamuni, and since in Honzon Shoto Tokui Sho Soegaki it is written as the head of the sect Nichiren, it is pointed out that it was written in later years.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="17">
<j>1350年（正平 (日本)5年）、摧邪立正抄には次のように記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1350, it is described as follows in Saijarisshosho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1350, it is described as follows in Saijarisshosho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1350, it is described as follows in Saijarissho Sho (Commentary written by Nichijun about the principle images of kuge (court nobles) and samurai families).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="18">
<j>抑大聖忝くも真筆に戴する本尊、日興に授くる遺札には白蓮阿闍梨と云々。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of edifying honzon written by Nichiren, there was Byakuren Ajari (a master in esoteric Buddhism) and so on written on the card granted to Nikko.</e>
<cmt>古文の為意訳です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of edifying honzon written by Nichiren, there was Byakuren Ajari (a master in esoteric Buddhism) and so on written on the card granted to Nikko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of edifying honzon written by Nichiren, there was Byakuren Ajari (a master in esoteric Buddhism) and so on written on the card granted to Nikko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>（宗全2）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Nichiren Shu Shugaku Zensho, 2)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Nichiren Shu Shugaku Zensho, 2)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Nichiren Shu Shugaku Zensho, volume 2)</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="20">
<j>これが二箇相承そのものとはいえないが、なんらかの相承書があったとみることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is not Nika Sojo itself, but it can be seen that there was some kind of a document of entrustment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is not Nika Sojo itself, but it can be seen that there was some kind of a document of entrustment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is not Nika Sojo itself, but it can be seen that there was some kind of a document of entrustment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="21">
<j>日蓮の弟子たちは、日蓮の教えを法 (仏教)と呼び、これを正しく伝えることを相承、付属、付法などと呼んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The disciples of Nichiren called his teachings ho (Buddhism), and called the proper inheritance of these teachings sojo, fuzoku, fuho, and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The disciples of Nichiren called his teachings ho (Buddhism), and called the proper inheritance of these teachings sojo, fuzoku, fuho, and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The disciples of Nichiren called his teachings ho (Buddhism), and called the proper inheritance of these teachings sojo, fuzoku, fuho, and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>唯受一人（ゆいじゅいちにん）血脈相承とも嫡々付法ともいい、日興が正統であるという主張の根拠としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Yuiju Ichinin Kechimyaku Sojo (only one person to inherit the blood) and Chaku Chaku Fufo (legitimate inheritance), and regard it as the basis for the assertion of Nikko as the legitimacy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called Yuiju Ichinin Kechimyaku Sojo (only one person to inherit the blood) and Chaku Chaku Fufo (legitimate inheritance), and regard it as the basis for the assertion of Nikko as the legitimacy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called Yuiju Ichinin Kechimyaku Sojo (only one person to inherit the blood) and Chaku Chaku Fufo (legitimate inheritance), and regard it as the basis for the assertion of Nikko as the legitimacy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>厳密には、二箇相承と血脈相承とは別ものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Strictly saying, Nika Sojo and Kechimyaku Sojo are different things.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Strictly speaking, Nika Sojo and Kechimyaku Sojo are different things.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Strictly speaking, Nika Sojo and Kechimyaku Sojo are different things.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>ただ日興のみ一人が相承したという日興門流の主張は、他の日蓮各派は認めていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the assertion of Nikko-monryu Lineage, which argues that only Nikko has inherited the teachings, is not accepted by other lineages of Nichiren sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the assertion of Nikko-monryu Lineage, which argues that only Nikko has inherited the teachings, is not accepted by other lineages of Nichiren sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the assertion of Nikkomon School, which argues that only Nikko has inherited the teachings, is not accepted by other schools of Nichiren Sect.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="25">
<j>日廣本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nikkobon (book by Nikko)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nikkobon (book by Nikko)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nikkobon (book by Nikko)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>1468年（応仁2年）10月13日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 13, 1468</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 13, 1468</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 6, 1468</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>住本寺十代、日廣、重須にて二箇相承全文を書写す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nikko, the tenth chief priest of Juhon-ji Temple, transcribed the whole Nika Sojo at Omosu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nikko, the tenth chief priest of Juhon-ji Temple, transcribed the whole Nika Sojo at Omosu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nikko, the tenth chief priest of Juhon-ji Temple, transcribed the whole Nika Sojo at Omosu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>京要法寺に在り。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is at Yobo-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is at Yobo-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is at Yobo-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>（夏季講習録2）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Record of Summer Seminar Vol.2)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Record of Summer Seminar Vol.2)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Kaki Koshuroku (Record of Summer Seminar), volume 2)</e>
<cmt>表記を合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="30">
<j>日廣本は未公開であるため、その内容は確認できないが、後に紹介する日教は、同じ住本寺の出身であるため日教本と同じ内容と考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The contents of Nikkobon can&apos;t be confirmed since it is not open to the public, but it is believed that since Nikkyo, who is introduced below, was also from Yobo-ji Temple, that Nikkobon has same contents as Nikkyobon (book by Nikkyo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The contents of Nikkobon can not be confirmed since it is not open to the public, but it is believed that since Nikkyo, who is introduced below, was also from Yobo-ji Temple, that Nikkobon has the same contents as Nikkyobon (book by Nikkyo).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The contents of Nikkobon can not be confirmed since it is not open to the public, but it is believed that since Nikkyo, who is introduced below, was also from Yobo-ji Temple, that Nikkobon has the same contents as Nikkyobon (book by Nikkyo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="31">
<j>日教本（日叶本）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nikkyobon (Nikkyobon)</e>
<cmt>発音が同じ為、スペルが重複しています</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nikkyobon (Nikkyobon)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nikkyobon</e>
<cmt>補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>住本寺の日叶が文明14年ころ大石寺に帰伏し名を日教と改めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1482, Nikkyo of Juhon-ji Temple submitted to Taiseki-ji Temple and changed his name to Nikkyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1482, Nikkyo of Juhon-ji Temple submitted to Taiseki-ji Temple and changed his name to Nikkyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1482, Nikkyo (日叶) of Juhon-ji Temple submitted to Taiseki-ji Temple and changed his name to Nikkyo (日教).</e>
<cmt>漢字を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>日教本と呼ばれているものは2種類あり、身延相承と池上相承の中身が入れ替わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are 2 books that are called Nikkyobon, and the contents of Minobu Sojo and Ikegami Sojo is replaced with each other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are 2 books that are called Nikkyobon, and the contents of Minobu Sojo and Ikegami Sojo is replaced by each other.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are 2 books that are called Nikkyobon, and the contents of Minobu Sojo and Ikegami Sojo is replaced by each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="34">
<j>百五十箇条</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hyakugojikkajo (Hundred and Fifty Articles)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hyakugojikkajo (Hundred and Fifty Articles)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hyakugojikkajo (Hundred and Fifty Articles)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>1480年（文明 (日本)12年）、住本寺の日叶は「百五十箇条」を著し、その中に二箇相承を引用している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1480, Nikkyo of Juhon-ji Temple wrote &apos;Hyakugojikkajo&apos; and quoted Nika Sojo in the book.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1480, Nikkyo of Juhon-ji Temple wrote &apos;Hyakugojikkajo&apos; and quoted Nika Sojo in the book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1480, Nikkyo of Juhon-ji Temple wrote &apos;Hyakugojikkajo&apos; and quoted Nika Sojo in the book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="36">
<j>身延相承</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minobu Sojo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minobu Sojo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minobu Sojo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>日蓮一期の弘法、白蓮阿闍梨日興に之を付属す、本門弘通の大導師為るべきなり、国主此の法を立てられば富士山に本門寺の戒壇を建立せらるべきなり、時を待つべきのみ・事の戒法と謂ふは是なり、中ん就く我門弟等此状を守るべきなり</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The lifetime preaching by Nichiren is entrusted to Byakuren Ajari Nikko, he should become a great preacher to spread honmon (second half of 28 chapters of Lotus Sutra), if the lord of province respects these teachings, Kaidan (Buddhist ordination platform) of Honmon-ji Temple should be constructed in Mt. Fuji, you should only wait, this is the Kaiho (religious precepts in Buddhism), and especially our disciples should obey this document.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lifetime preachings of Nichiren were entrusted to Byakuren Ajari Nikko, and he should become a great preacher to spread honmon (second half of 28 chapters of Lotus Sutra), if the lord of the province respects these teachings, Kaidan (Buddhist ordination platform) of Honmon-ji Temple should be constructed at Mt. Fuji, and you should only wait, this is the Kaiho (religious precepts in Buddhism), and especially our disciples should obey this document.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lifetime preachings of Nichiren were entrusted to Byakuren Ajari Nikko, and he should become a great preacher to spread honmon (second half of 28 chapters of Lotus Sutra), if the lord of the province respects these teachings, Kaidan (Buddhist ordination platform) of Honmon-ji Temple should be constructed at Mt. Fuji, and you should only wait, this is the Kaiho (religious precepts in Buddhism), and especially our disciples should obey this document.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>弘安五年壬午九月　日、血脈の次第・日蓮・日興、甲斐国波木井山中に於て之を写す</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The day of Mizunoeuma in September (blank), 1282, lineage of Nichiren ・Nikko, written in Hakii-san Mountain at Kai Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The day of Mizunoeuma in September (blank), 1282, lineage of Nichiren ・Nikko, written in Hakii-san Mountain at Kai Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October (blank), 1282, lineage of Nichiren and Nikko, written at Mt. Hakii in Kai Province.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>池上相承</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikegami Sojo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ikegami Sojo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikegami Sojo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>釈尊五十年の説法、白蓮阿闍梨日興に相承す、身延山久遠寺の別当為るべし、背く在家出家共の輩は非法の衆為るべきなり</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fifty years of preaching by Shakyamuni should be entrusted to Byakuren Ajari Nikko, he should become the betto of Kuon-ji Temple in Minobu-san Mountain, and all the lay believers and monks who are against this should be regarded as ones that are against the Buddhist teachings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fifty years of preaching by Shakyamuni should be entrusted to Byakuren Ajari Nikko, he should become the betto of Kuon-ji Temple in Minobu-san Mountain, and all the lay believers and monks who are against this should be regarded as ones that are against the Buddhist teachings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fifty years of preaching by Shakyamuni should be entrusted to Byakuren Ajari Nikko, he should become the betto of Kuon-ji Temple on Mt. Minobu, and all the lay believers and monks who are against this should be regarded as ones that are against the Buddhist teachings.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>弘安五年壬午十月十三日、日蓮御判、武州池上</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The day of Mizunoeuma October 13, 1282, honorable seal by Nichiren, Bushu (Musashi Province) Ikegami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The day of Mizunoeuma October 13, 1282, honorable seal by Nichiren, Bushu (Musashi Province) Ikegami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 21, 1282, honorable seal by Nichiren, Ikegami in Bushu (Musashi Province).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="42">
<j>類衆翰集私</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ruijukanshushi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ruijukanshushi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ruiju Kanshushi (&quot;My Personal Views&quot; written by Nikkyo)</e>
<cmt>正しくは「類聚翰集私」と思われ、補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>1488年（長享2年）、日教は「類衆翰集私」を著し、その中に二箇相承を引用している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1488, Nikkyo wrote &apos;Ruijukanshushi&apos; and quoted Nika Sojo in there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1488, Nikkyo wrote &apos;Ruijukanshushi&apos; and quoted Nika Sojo there.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1488, Nikkyo wrote &apos;Ruiju Kanshushi&apos; and quoted Nika Sojo there.</e>
<cmt>表記を合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="44">
<j>身延相承</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minobu Sojo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minobu Sojo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minobu Sojo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>釈尊五十年の説教、白蓮日興に之を付属す身延山久遠寺の別当たるべし、背く在家出家共の輩は非法の衆たるべきなり</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fifty years of preaching by Shakyamuni is entrusted to Byakuren Nikko, he should become the betto of Minobu-san Mountain Kuon-ji Temple, and lay believers and monks who are against this are regarded as people who are against the teachings of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fifty years of preaching by Shakyamuni is entrusted to Byakuren Nikko, he should become the betto of Minobu-san Mountain Kuon-ji Temple, and lay believers and monks who are against this are regarded as people who are against the teachings of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fifty years of preaching by Shakyamuni is entrusted to Byakuren Nikko, he should become the betto of Kuon-ji Temple on Mt. Minobu, and lay believers and monks who are against this are regarded as people who are against the teachings of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>弘安五年十月十三日、日蓮在御判、血脈次第日蓮日興、甲斐国波木井山中に於いて之を図す</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 13, 1282, honorable seal by Nichiren, lineage of Nichiren Nikko, written in Hakii-san Mountain in Kai Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 13, 1282, honorable seal by Nichiren, lineage of Nichiren Nikko, written in Hakii-san Mountain in Kai Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 21, 1282, honorable seal by Nichiren, lineage of Nichiren Nikko, written at Mt. Hakii in Kai Province.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>池上相承</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikegami Sojo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ikegami Sojo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikegami Sojo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>日蓮一期の弘法、白蓮阿闍梨日興に之を付属す本門弘通の大導師たるべきなり、国主此の法を立てらるれば富士山に本門寺の戒壇を建立すべきなり、時を待つべきのみ、事の戒法とは是なり、中んづく我門弟等此状を守るべきなり、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lifetime preaching of Nichiren is entrusted to Byakuren Ajari Nikko, he should become a great preacher to spread honmon, if the lord of the province respect this teachings, he should construct Kaidan of Honmon-ji Temple in Mt. Fuji, time should be waited, this is so called Kaiho, and especially our disciples should obey this document.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lifetime preachings of Nichiren are entrusted to Byakuren Ajari Nikko, he should become a great preacher to spread honmon, if the lord of the province respects these teachings, he should construct Kaidan of Honmon-ji Temple at Mt. Fuji, and he should wait, this is the so-called Kaiho, and especially our disciples should obey this document.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lifetime preachings of Nichiren are entrusted to Byakuren Ajari Nikko, he should become a great preacher to spread honmon, if the lord of the province respects these teachings, he should construct Kaidan of Honmon-ji Temple at Mt. Fuji, and he should wait, this is the so-called Kaiho, and especially our disciples should obey this document.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>弘安五年壬午九月　日、日蓮御判</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The day of Mizunoeuma in September 1282, honorable seal by Nichiren.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The day of Mizunoeuma in September 1282, honorable seal by Nichiren.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October (blank), 1282, honorable seal by Nichiren.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="50">
<j>六人立義破立抄私記</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rokunin Ryugi Haryu Shoshiki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rokunin Ryugi Haryu Shoshiki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rokunin Ryugi Haryu Shoshiki (literally, Commentary on proposition of six people)</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>1489年（延徳元年）、日教は「六人立義破立抄私記」を著し、その中に二箇相承を引用している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1489, Nikkyo wrote &apos;Rokunin Ryugi Haryu Shoshiki&apos; and quoted Nika Sojo in there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1489, Nikkyo wrote &apos;Rokunin Ryugi Haryu Shoshiki&apos; and quoted Nika Sojo there.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1489, Nikkyo wrote &apos;Rokunin Ryugi Haryu Shoshiki&apos; and quoted Nika Sojo there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="52">
<j>身延相承</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minobu Sojo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minobu Sojo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minobu Sojo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>釈尊五十余年之説教、白蓮日興に之れを付属す、身延山久遠寺の別当為る可し、背く在家出家共の輩は非法の衆為る可き者也</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fifty years of Shakayumi&apos;s preaching is entrusted to Byakuren Nikko, he should become the betto of Minobu-san Mountain Kuon-ji Temple, and lay believers and monks who are against this should be regarded as ones that are against Buddhist teachings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fifty years of Shakayumi&apos;s preaching is entrusted to Byakuren Nikko, he should become the betto of Minobu-san Mountain Kuon-ji Temple, and lay believers and monks who are against this should be regarded as those that are against Buddhist teachings.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fifty years of Shakyamuni&apos;s preaching is entrusted to Byakuren Nikko, he should become the betto of Kuon-ji Temple on Mt. Minobu, and lay believers and monks who are against this should be regarded as those that are against Buddhist teachings.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>弘安五年十月十三日、日蓮在御判　血脈の次第日蓮日興　甲斐国波木井郷の山中に於て之れを図す</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 13, 1282, honorable seal by Nichiren, lineage of Nichiren Nikko, this is written in mountain at Hakii-go Village of Kai Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 13, 1282, honorable seal by Nichiren, lineage of Nichiren Nikko, this is written in the mountain at Hakii-go Village of Kai Province.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 21, 1282, honorable seal by Nichiren, lineage of Nichiren Nikko, this is written in the mountain at Hakii-go Village of Kai Province.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>池上相承</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikegami Sojo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ikegami Sojo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikegami Sojo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>日蓮一期の弘法白蓮阿闍梨日興に之れを付属す、本門弘通之大導師為る可き也、国主此の法を立て被れば富士山に本門寺の戒壇を建立為す可き也、時を待つ可き於耳、事の戒法と謂ふは是れ也、中ん付く我か門弟等此の状を守る可き也</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The lifetime preaching by Nichiren is entrusted to Byakuren Ajari Nikko, he should become a great preacher to spread honmon, if the lord of the province respect this teachings he should construct Kaidan of Honmon-ji Temple in Mt. Fuji, time should be waited, this is so called Kaiho, and especially our disciples should obey this document.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lifetime preachings of Nichiren are entrusted to Byakuren Ajari Nikko, he should become a great preacher to spread honmon, if the lord of the province respects these teachings he should construct Kaidan of Honmon-ji Temple at Mt. Fuji, and he should wait, this is the so-called Kaiho, and especially our disciples should obey this document.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lifetime preachings of Nichiren are entrusted to Byakuren Ajari Nikko, he should become a great preacher to spread honmon, if the lord of the province respects these teachings he should construct Kaidan of Honmon-ji Temple at Mt. Fuji, and he should wait, this is the so-called Kaiho, and especially our disciples should obey this document.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>弘安五年九月　日　日蓮在御判</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September (blank), 1282, honorable seal by Nichiren</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September (blank), 1282, honorable seal by Nichiren</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October (blank), 1282, honorable seal by Nichiren</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="58">
<j>日現本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nichigenbon (book by Nichigen)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nichigenbon (book by Nichigen)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nichigenbon (book by Nichigen)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>1516年（永正11年）、越後本成寺の8代日現は「五人所破抄斥」の中に二箇相承を全文引用し、さらに次のように書いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1516, Nichigen, the 8th chief priest of Echigo Honjo-ji Temple, quoted the whole Nika Sojo in &apos;Gonin Shoha Shoshaku&apos; and further written as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1516, Nichigen, the 8th chief priest of Echigo Honjo-ji Temple, quoted the whole Nika Sojo in &apos;Gonin Shoha Shoshaku&apos; and further wrote as follows.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1516, Nichigen, the 8th chief priest of Echigo Honjo-ji Temple, quoted the whole Nika Sojo in &apos;Gonin Shoha Shoshaku&apos; and further wrote as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="60">
<j>日現申す、前の御相承（9月13日）は身延相承、後は（10月13日）池上相承と云云。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nichigen says, the first sojo (September 13) is Minobu Sojo, and the second one (October 13) is Ikegami Sojo and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nichigen says, the first sojo (September 13) is Minobu Sojo, and the second one (October 13) is Ikegami Sojo and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nichigen says, the first sojo (October 22) is Minobu Sojo, and the second one (November 21) is Ikegami Sojo and so on.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>御判形現形也。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The honorable seal is true one.</e>
<cmt>意訳です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The honorable seal is a true one.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The honorable seal is a original one.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>されども一向御正筆に非ず偽書謀判也。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the handwriting is not by Nichiren, and it seems to be forged.</e>
<cmt>意訳です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the handwriting is not by Nichiren, and it seems to be forged.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the handwriting is not by Nichiren, and it seems to be forged.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>又日興の手跡にもあらず、蔵人阿日代と云う人の筆に似たりと承り及也。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, it is not the handwriting of Nikko, either, and I hear that it is similar to the handwriting of a person called 蔵人阿 Nichidai.</e>
<cmt>蔵人阿→読み、定訳不明です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, it is not the handwriting of Nikko, either, and I hear that it is similar to the handwriting of a person called 蔵人阿 Nichidai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, it is not the handwriting of Nikko, either, and I hear that it is similar to the handwriting of a person called Kurodo Ajari Nichidai.</e>
<cmt>「蔵人阿」は「蔵人阿闍梨」（日代の別名）と思われるため、訳を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>（宗全7－182）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">((Nichiren Shu Shugaku Zensho 7-182)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">((Nichiren Shu Shugaku Zensho 7-182)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Nichiren Shu Shugaku Zensho, volume 7 - 182)</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="65">
<j>日興は身延山久遠寺を降りて、南条氏の寄進を受けて大石寺を建立したがこれを日目に譲り、2、3年後には重須談所（重須本門寺）を建立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nikko came down from Minobu-san Mountain Kuon-ji Temple, received donation from the Nanjo clan, constructed Taiseki-ji Temple but handed over this to Nichimoku, and after 2, 3 years, he constructed Omosu Dansho (Omosu Honmon-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nikko came down from Minobu-san Mountain Kuon-ji Temple, received donations from the Nanjo clan, constructed Taiseki-ji Temple but handed this over to Nichimoku, and after 2, 3 years, he constructed Omosu Dansho (Omosu Honmon-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nikko came down from Kuon-ji Temple on Mt. Minobu, received donations from the Nanjo clan, constructed Taiseki-ji Temple but handed this over to Nichimoku, and after 2, 3 years, he constructed Omosu Dansho (Omosu Honmon-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>重須の2代目が日代である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second chief priest of Omosu is Nichidai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second chief priest of Omosu was Nichidai.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second chief priest of Omosu was Nichidai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>日代は重須を追い出され、後に西山本門寺を開き、初代住職となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nichidai was thrown out from Omosu, later founded Nishiyama Honmon-ji Temple, and became the first chief priest there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nichidai was thrown out from Omosu, later founded Nishiyama Honmon-ji Temple, and became the first chief priest there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nichidai was thrown out from Omosu, later founded Nishiyama Honmon-ji Temple, and assumed the position of the first chief priest there.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>また西山本門寺の過去帳には越後本成寺の9代日覚の名が記されていることから、両寺には互いに交流があったものと推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, since there is name of Nichikaku recorded on the family register of deaths in Nishiyama Honmon-ji Temple, it is supposed that both temples had exchanges with each others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, since there is the name of Nichikaku recorded on the family register of deaths in Nishiyama Honmon-ji Temple, it is supposed that both temples had exchanges with each other.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, since there is the name of Nichikaku recorded on the family register of deaths in Nishiyama Honmon-ji Temple, it is supposed that both temples had exchanges with each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="69">
<j>日辰本（日耀本）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nisshinbon (book by Nisshin, also called Nichiyobon)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nisshinbon (book by Nisshin, also called Nichiyobon)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nisshinbon (book by Nisshin, also known as Nichiyobon)</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>1556年（弘治 (日本)2年）、京要法寺の日辰が弟子の日耀に重須の二箇相承を臨写させたと伝えられているもので、西山本門寺に現存する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said to be a transcription of Nika Sojo in Omosu which was ordered by Nisshin in Kyoto Yobo-ji Temple to his disciple Nichiyo to be transcribed, and does exist in Nishyama Honmon-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said to be a transcription of Nika Sojo in Omosu which was ordered to be transcribed by Nisshin in Kyoto Yobo-ji Temple to his disciple Nichiyo, and exists in Nishyama Honmon-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said to be a transcription of Nika Sojo in Omosu which was ordered to be transcribed by Nisshin in Kyoto Yobo-ji Temple to his disciple Nichiyo in 1556, and exists in Nishyama Honmon-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>年号を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>身延相承の日付は「九月　日」となっていて13日の日付が無く、身延山のところが身遠山と書かれているのが特徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The characteristics are that the date in Minobu Sojo is written as &apos;September (blank)&apos; and doesn&apos;t have the date 13, and Minobu-san Mountain is written as Mito-san Mountain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The characteristics are that the date in Minobu Sojo is written as &apos;September (blank)&apos; and does not have the date 13, and Minobu-san Mountain is written as Mito-san Mountain.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The characteristics are that the date in Minobu Sojo is written as &apos;October (blank)&apos; and does not have the date 22, and Mt. Minobu is written as Mt. Mito.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>日廣本は内容が確認できないが、おなじ住本寺の日教本には身延山となっており、身遠山は単なる写し間違いではないかといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The contents of Nikkobon can&apos;t be confirmed, but since it is written as Minobu-san Mountain in Nikkyobon which is located at the same temple, Juhon-ji Temple, it is said that Mito-san Mountain is simply a mistake in transcription.</e>
<cmt>発音が同じ為スペルが重複しています</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The contents of Nikkobon cannot be confirmed, but since it is written as Minobu-san Mountain in Nikkyobon which is located at the same temple, Juhon-ji Temple, it is said that Mito-san Mountain is simply a mistake in transcription.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The contents of Nikkobon cannot be confirmed, but since it is written as Mt. Minobu in Nikkyobon which is located at the same temple, Juhon-ji Temple, it is said that Mt. Mito is simply a mistake in transcription.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="73">
<j>ただし、大石寺に伝わる第14世日主（在位：1573年 - 1586年）の写本は「身遠山」となっており、大石寺側は、正本が「身遠山」であった可能性もあるとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the transcription by Nisshu, the 14th chief priest of Taiseki-ji Temple (the period as chief: 1573 - 1586), which is handed down in Taiseki-ji Temple, it is written as &apos;Mito-san Mountain,&apos; and the Taiseki-ji Temple side assumes that there is a possibility that the original document was written as &apos;Mito-san Mountain.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the transcription by Nisshu, the 14th chief priest of Taiseki-ji Temple (the period as chief: 1573 - 1586), which is handed down in Taiseki-ji Temple, it is written as &apos;Mito-san Mountain,&apos; and the Taiseki-ji Temple side assumes that there is a possibility that the original document was written as &apos;Mito-san Mountain.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the transcription by Nisshu, the 14th chief priest of Taiseki-ji Temple (the period as chief: 1573 - 1586), which is handed down in Taiseki-ji Temple, it is written as &apos;Mt. Mito,&apos; and the Taiseki-ji Temple side assumes that there is a possibility that the original document was written as &apos;Mt. Mito.&apos;</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>日主の写本は、日辰本とほぼ同じとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The transcription by Nisshu is regarded as almost same as Nisshinbon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The transcription by Nisshu is regarded as almost the same as Nisshinbon.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The transcription by Nisshu is regarded as almost the same as Nisshinbon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="75">
<j>二箇相承紛失</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The loss of Nika Sojo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The loss of Nika Sojo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Loss of Nika Sojo</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>1581年（天正9年）3月、聖滅300年、武田勝頼の臣重須を襲い二箇相承等を奪う（要9－17・20）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March 1581, 300 years after the death of Nichiren, subjects of Katsuyori TAKEDA raided Omosu, and robbed Nika Sojo. (要9-17・20)</e>
<cmt>要→読み、定訳不明です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March 1581, 300 years after the death of Nichiren, subjects of Katsuyori TAKEDA raided Omosu, and robbed Nika Sojo. (要9-17・20)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 14, 1581, 300 years after the death of Nichiren, vessels of Katsuyori TAKEDA raided Omosu, and robbed Nika Sojo (Fujishu Gaku Yoshu (Teachings of Nichiren sects), volume 9 - 17 and 20).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦にし、補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>二箇相承書は武田勝頼軍によって奪われ、武田の兵乱によって失われたと伝承され、保田妙本寺の日我等が二箇相承紛失の顛末を著しているが、その30年後に徳川家康が拝したとの記録がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nika Sojo documents were robbed by the army of Katsuyori TAKEDA and were transmitted as being lost in the disturbance by TAKEDA, and books were wrote about the story of Nika Sojo&apos;s loss by Nichiga and others in Hota Myohon-ji Temple, but there is a record stating that Ieyasu TOKUGAWA read the Nika Sojo after thirty years from the disturbance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nika Sojo documents were robbed by the army of Katsuyori TAKEDA and were transmitted as being lost in the disturbance by TAKEDA, and books were wrote about the story of Nika Sojo&apos;s loss by Nichiga and others in Hota Myohon-ji Temple, but there is a record stating that Ieyasu TOKUGAWA read the Nika Sojo thirty years after the disturbance.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nika Sojo documents were robbed by the army of Katsuyori TAKEDA and were transmitted as being lost in the disturbance by TAKEDA, and books were wrote about the story of Nika Sojo&apos;s loss by Nichiga and others in Hota Myohon-ji Temple, but there is a record stating that Ieyasu TOKUGAWA read the Nika Sojo thirty years after the disturbance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="78">
<j>1611年（慶長16年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the year 1611</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the year 1611</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Year 1611</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>家康、駿府城に於て重須より奉持の二箇相承を拝す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ieyasu, in Sunpu-jo Castle, read Nika Sojo brought from Omosu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ieyasu, in Sunpu-jo Castle, read Nika Sojo brought from Omosu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ieyasu, in Sunpu-jo Castle, read Nika Sojo brought from Omosu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>（駿府政事録・駿国雑誌31－中－74）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Record of Political Affairs in Sunpu 31 - middle - 74)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Record of Political Affairs in Sunpu 31 - middle - 74)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Sunpu Seijiroku (Records of Sunpu Government) and Sunkoku Zatsushi (Topography of Sunpu), volume 31 - second - 74)</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="81">
<j>1611年（慶長16年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the year 1611</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the year 1611</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Year 1611</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>本光国師、二箇相承を道春（林羅山）より得て日記中に記す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honko Kokushi received Nika Sojo from Doshun (Razan HAYASHI) and wrote it in his diary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honko Kokushi received Nika Sojo from Doshun (Razan HAYASHI) and wrote it in his diary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honko Kokushi received Nika Sojo from Doshun (Razan HAYASHI) and wrote it in his diary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>（仏教全書、本光国師日記1－165）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Compendium of Buddhism, Diary by Honko Kokushi 1- 165)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Compendium of Buddhism, Diary by Honko Kokushi 1- 165)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Bukkyo Zensho (Compendium of Buddhism), Honko Kokushi Nikki (the Honko Kokushi Journal), volume 1 - 165)</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="84">
<j>1617年（元和 (日本)3年）、要山24代日陽、重須に至り二箇相承を拝す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1617, Nichiyo, the 24th chief priest of Kaname-yama Mountain, went to Omosu and read Nika Sojo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1617, Nichiyo, the 24th chief priest of Kaname-yama Mountain, went to Omosu and read Nika Sojo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1617, Nichiyo, the 24th chief priest of Mt. Kanama, went to Omosu and read Nika Sojo.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>（要5－60）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(要 5 - 60)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(要 5 - 60)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Fujishu Gaku Yoshu, volume 5 - 60)</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="86">
<j>1877年（明治10年）6月13日、重須（北山本門寺）の御風入（虫干し）にて奉拝。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 13, 1877, read them at Okazeire (summer airing) at Omosu (Kitayama Honmon-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 13, 1877, read them at Okazeire (summer airing) at Omosu (Kitayama Honmon-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 13, 1877, read them at Okazeire (summer airing) at Omosu (Kitayama Honmon-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>（興門口決）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Komonkuketsu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Komonkuketsu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Komon Guketsu (Kegi (the way Buddha guides people) of Komon School)</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="88">
<j>その後の重須の二箇相承の記録は定かでは無いため、現在も重須で秘匿されているとも言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the record of Nika Sojo in Omosu after that is not certain, it is also said that they still are concealed in Omosu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the record of Nika Sojo in Omosu after that is not certain, it is also said that they still are concealed in Omosu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the record of Nika Sojo in Omosu after that is not certain, it is also said that they still are concealed in Omosu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="89">
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>二箇相承以外にも、両巻血脈といわれる「百六箇抄（血脈抄）」「本因妙抄（法華本門宗血脈相承事）」などがあるが、いずれも同門他派からは疑義の強い書として批判されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are documents other than Nika Sojo such as &apos;Hyaku Rokka Sho (One Hundred and Six Articles, also called Kechimyakusho)&apos; and &apos;Honinmyosho (Hokkehonmonshu Kechimyakusojonokoto, or document about the inheritance of blood lineage in Hokke Honmon Sect),&apos; which are also called Ryokan Kechimyaku (blood lineage of two books), but both of them are criticized by other sects in Nichiren sect that the they are strongly doubtful books.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are documents other than Nika Sojo such as &apos;Hyaku Rokka Sho (One Hundred and Six Articles, also called Kechimyakusho)&apos; and &apos;Honinmyosho (Hokkehonmonshu Kechimyakusojonokoto, or document about the inheritance of blood lineage in Hokke Honmon Sect),&apos; which are also called Ryokan Kechimyaku (blood lineage of two books), but both are criticized by other sects within Nichiren sect that they are fake books.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are documents other than Nika Sojo such as &apos;Hyaku Rokka Sho&apos; (One Hundred and Six Articles, also known as Kechimyakusho) and &apos;Honinmyosho&apos; (Honin-myo Sho (On the Mystic Principle of the Original Cause, also known as Hokkehonmonshu Kechimyakusojonokoto (document about the inheritance of blood lineage in Hokke Honmon Sect)), which are also called Ryokan Kechimyaku (blood lineage of two books), but both are criticized by other sects within Nichiren sects that they are fake books.</e>
<cmt>補足などを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 トヘドッジ(id:89868), Oxhop(id:2551), Naranja(id:30069), Tetralemma(id:11903), Leo masaaki(id:171687), Kstigarbha(id:13376), 水野白楓(id:22811), 大石寺信徒(id:59000), Mixtures(id:29234), Kogane(id:28186), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>