<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>龍渓性潜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryukeishosen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryukeishosen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryukei Shosen</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>龍渓性潜（りゅうけいしょうせん、慶長7年7月30日 (旧暦)（1602年9月15日） － 寛文10年8月23日 (旧暦)（1670年10月6日））は、江戸時代前期の黄檗宗の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryukeishosen (September 15, 1602 - October 6, 1670) was a priest of the Obaku-shu sect in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryukeishosen (September 15, 1602 - October 6, 1670) was a priest of the Obaku-shu sect in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryukei Shosen (September 15, 1602 - October 6, 1670) was a priest of the Obaku Sect in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>俗姓は奥村氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His secular surname was OKUMURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His secular surname was OKUMURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His secular surname was Okumura.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>号は如常老人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His pseudonym was &quot;Jojorojin&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His pseudonym was &quot;Jojorojin&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His pseudonym was Jojo Rojin.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>諡号は大宗正統禅師。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was given the posthumous title of &quot;Taisoseitozenshi&quot; (meaning &quot;high-ranking zen priest honored by the imperial court&quot;).</e>
<cmt>「諡号」は、死後におくられるものですが、後述からは、生前におくられているようですが、矛盾はありますが、一応、文章に忠実に訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was given the posthumous title of &quot;Taisoseitozenshi&quot; (meaning &quot;high-ranking zen priest honored by the imperial court&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His shigo (a posthumous name) was Taiso Seito Zenshi (meaning &quot;high-ranking zen priest honored by the imperial court&quot;).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>京都の出身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>8歳で東寺に入って真言密教を習う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He entered To-ji Temple at the age of eight and studied the esoteric Buddhism of the Shingon Sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He entered To-ji Temple at the age of eight and studied the esoteric Buddhism of the Shingon Sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He entered To-ji Temple at the age of eight and studied the Shingon Esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>初め16歳の時、摂津国普門寺（臨済宗）で出家して宗琢と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First, he became a priest at Fumon-ji Temple of the Rinzai sect when he was sixteen, and called himself &quot;Sotaku&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First, he became a priest at Fumon-ji Temple of the Rinzai sect when he was sixteen, and called himself &quot;Sotaku&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First, he became a priest at Fumon-ji Temple in Settsu Province (the Rinzai Sect) when he was 16, and called himself Sotaku.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>1620年（元和 (日本)6年）師の籌室玄勝が没したため普門寺の第9代の住持となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, he became the 9th juji (chief priest) of Fumon-ji Temple in 1620 when his mentor, Chushitsu-gensho, died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, he became the 9th juji (chief priest) of Fumon-ji Temple in 1620 when his mentor, Chushitsu-gensho, died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, he became the 9th juji (chief priest) of Fumon-ji Temple in 1620 when his mentor, Chushitsu Gensho (籌室玄勝), died.</e>
<cmt>読み不明の漢字を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>竜安寺の伯蒲慧稜に参禅して龍渓宗潜と名を改め、伯蒲から印可を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He practiced Zen meditation under Hakuho-eryo (a high-ranking Zen monk) at Ryoan-ji Temple, changed his name to &quot;Ryokei-sozen&quot;, and was eventually given inka (formal confirmation of a student&apos;s awakening) by his master.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He practiced Zen meditation under Hakuho-eryo (a high-ranking Zen monk) at Ryoan-ji Temple, changed his name to &quot;Ryokei-sozen&quot;, and was eventually given inka (formal confirmation of a student&apos;s awakening) by his master.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He practiced Zen meditation under Hakuho Eryo (a high-ranking Zen monk) at Ryoan-ji Temple, changed his name to Ryokei Sozen, and was eventually given inka (formal confirmation of a student&apos;s awakening) by Hakuho.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>諸国をめぐり、1627年（寛永4年）におきた紫衣事件では師の伯蒲にしたがって活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He traveled across the country, and in 1627 when the Shii-jiken incident took place (a conflict between the imperial court and Tokugawa shogunate, where the shogunate blamed the imperial court for having given purple canonical robes (&quot;shii&quot;) to priests without its permission), he played an important role in it under the guidance of Hakuho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He traveled across the country, and in 1627 when the Shii-jiken incident took place (a conflict between the imperial court and Tokugawa shogunate, where the shogunate blamed the imperial court for having given purple canonical robes (&quot;shii&quot;) to priests without its permission), he played an important role in it under the guidance of Hakuho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He traveled across the country, and in 1627 when the Shie Incident took place (a conflict between the imperial court and Tokugawa shogunate, where the shogunate blamed the imperial court for having given purple canonical robes (shie) to priests without its permission), he played an important role in it under the guidance of his master Hakuho.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>伯蒲の没後、竜安寺の塔頭である皐東庵を自坊とし、以後、京都妙心寺の首座となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his master, Hakuho, died, he lived in a tacchu (dormitory built near the master&apos;s tomb) called &quot;Koto-an&quot;, and served as the top-ranking priest of Myoshin-ji Temple (Kyoto) thereafter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his master, Hakuho, died, he lived in a tacchu (dormitory built near the master&apos;s tomb) called &quot;Koto-an&quot;, and served as the top-ranking priest of Myoshin-ji Temple (Kyoto) thereafter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Hakuho died, he lived in a tatchu (dormitory built near the master&apos;s tomb) called Koto-an of Ryoan-ji Temple and served as the top-ranking priest of Myoshin-ji Temple in Kyoto thereafter.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>一時、普門寺に帰住していたが、慶安年間（1648年－1651年）には妙心寺で講説していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he returned to Fumom-ji Temple and lived there temporarily, he gave kosetsu (lectures on Buddhist scriptures) at Myoshin-ji Temple during 1648 - 1651.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he returned to Fumom-ji Temple and lived there temporarily, he gave kosetsu (lectures on Buddhist scriptures) at Myoshin-ji Temple during 1648 - 1651.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he returned to Fumon-ji Temple and lived there temporarily, he gave kosetsu (lectures on Buddhist scriptures) at Myoshin-ji Temple during 1648 and 1651.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>1651年（慶安4年）9月には、50歳で妙心寺の住持に就任し、紫衣を賜った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September 1651, he assumed the post of the chief priest of Myoshin-ji Temple at the age of fifty, and was given a purple canonical robe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September 1651, he assumed the post of the chief priest of Myoshin-ji Temple at the age of fifty, and was given a purple canonical robe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September 1651, he assumed the position of chief priest of Myoshin-ji Temple at the age of 50, and was given a shie (purple canonical robe).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>その後退隠して再び普門寺に戻った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he returned to Fumon-ji Temple again after he retired from the post.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he returned to Fumon-ji Temple again after he retired from the post.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he returned to Fumon-ji Temple again after he retired from the position.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>1654年（承応3年）中国から隠元隆きが来日すると、その弟子となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1654 when a Chinese priest, Ingen-ryuki, came over to Japan from China, he became one of his pupils.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1654 when a Chinese priest, Ingen-ryuki, came over to Japan from China, he became one of his pupils.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1654 when a Chinese priest, Ingen Ryuki, came over to Japan from China, he became one of his pupils.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>1657年（明暦3年）には後水尾天皇に講説を行い、天皇の帰依を受け、大宗正統禅師の勅号を賜った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1657, he gave Emperor Gomizunoo kosetsu and was given the title of &quot;Taisoseitozenshi&quot; as the Emperor converted to Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1657, he gave Emperor Gomizunoo kosetsu and was given the title of &quot;Taisoseitozenshi&quot; as the Emperor converted to Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1657, he gave Emperor Gomizunoo kosetsu and was embraced by the Emperor to be given the title of Taiso Seito Zenshi.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせ、表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>隠元のもとで宇治黄檗山萬福寺の建立を助け、日本における黄檗宗の開宗に尽力した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He assisted Ingen in founding Uji Obaku-san Manpuku-ji Temple and was committed to the establishment of the Obaku-shu sect in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He assisted Ingen in founding Uji Obaku-san Manpuku-ji Temple and was committed to the establishment of the Obaku-shu sect in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He assisted Ingen in founding Manpuku-ji Temple on Mt. Obaku in Uji and was committed to the establishment of the Obaku Sect in Japan.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせ、表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>1663年（寛文3年）隠元から印可を受け諡号を性潜に改めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1663, he received inka from Ingen and changed his posthumous name to &quot;Shosen&quot;.</e>
<cmt>ここでも「諡号」となっていますが、諡号は通常、死後におくられる名前であるので、矛盾していますが、一応、辞書どおりの解釈にしておきます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1663, he received inka from Ingen and changed his posthumous name to &quot;Shosen&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1663, he received inka from Ingen and changed his posthumous name to Shosen.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>1664年（寛文4年）1月には、法皇となった後水尾帝の勅願寺であった日野町 (滋賀県)の正明寺の住持となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 1664, he was appointed as the juji of Shomo-ji Temple in Hino town (Shiga Prefecture), a chokugan-ji (a temple built at an imperial command, praying for the stability of the country and the prosperity of the imperial family) built by Cloistered Emperor Gomizunoo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January 1664, he was appointed as the juji of Shomo-ji Temple in Hino town (Shiga Prefecture), a chokugan-ji (a temple built at an imperial command, praying for the stability of the country and the prosperity of the imperial family) built by Cloistered Emperor Gomizunoo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January 1664, he was appointed as the juji of Shomo-ji Temple in Hino town (Shiga Prefecture), a chokugan-ji (a temple built at an imperial command, praying for the stability of the country and the prosperity of the imperial family) built by Cloistered Emperor Gomizunoo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>1668年（寛文8年）4月、後水尾法皇に招かれ、内院にて菩薩戒を授けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1668, he was invited by the Cloistered Emperor to Naiin (the innermost shrine of Shomo-ji Temple) and gave him bosatsu-kai (bosatsu (bodhisattva)&apos;s commandments) there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1668, he was invited by the Cloistered Emperor to Naiin (the innermost shrine of Shomo-ji Temple) and gave him bosatsu-kai (bosatsu (bodhisattva)&apos;s commandments) there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1668, he was invited by the Cloistered Emperor Gomizunoo to Naiin (the innermost shrine of Shomo-ji Temple) and gave him bosatsu-kai (bosatsu (bodhisattva)&apos;s commandments) there.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>1669年（寛文9年）4月には、正式に隠元の法を嗣ぎ、日本人初の隠元の嗣法者となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1669, he officially took over Ingen&apos;s teachings and became the first Japanese who mastered Ingen&apos;s esoteric techniques.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1669, he officially took over Ingen&apos;s teachings and became the first Japanese who mastered Ingen&apos;s esoteric techniques.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1669, he officially took over Ingen&apos;s teachings and became the first Japanese who mastered Ingen&apos;s esoteric techniques.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>法皇からは、大宗正統禅師の師号を賜った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was given the title of &quot;Taisoseitozenshi&quot; by the Cloistered Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was given the title of &quot;Taisoseitozenshi&quot; by the Cloistered Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was given the title of Taiso Seito Zenshi by the Cloistered Emperor.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="23">
<j>1670年（寛文10年）8月に大坂の九島院で催行された斎会に赴いたが、23日に暴風が襲った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August 1670, he went over to Osaka to attend a saie (a Buddhist mass where meals are served to priests) held at Kyuto-in Temple, but on August 23, a storm hit the area; despite danotsu&apos;s (the supporters of the temple) and his pupils&apos; urgent request to evacuate, he remained seated at a zen hall even while the hall was being inundated, and eventually, he was found dead, seated in a zen position after water receded.</e>
<cmt>「禅堂に坐したまま」とありますが、一応、座禅を組んだ状態でいたと思われますので、そのように訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August 1670, he went over to Osaka to attend a saie (a Buddhist mass where meals are served to priests) held at Kyuto-in Temple, but on August 23, a storm hit the area. Despite danotsu&apos;s (the supporters of the temple) and his pupils&apos; urgent request to evacuate, he remained seated at a zen hall even while the hall was being inundated, and eventually, he was found dead, seated in a zen position after the water receded.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August 1670, he went over to Osaka to attend a saie (a Buddhist mass where meals are served to priests) held at Kyuto-in Temple, but on August 23, a storm hit the area.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。原文、訳文を分けました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="24">
<j>檀越や門弟が避難することを求めたが、応じず、自ら洪水中に身を置き、水が引いた後も禅堂に坐したまま没していた、という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Despite danotsu&apos;s (the supporters of the temple) and his pupils&apos; urgent request to evacuate, he remained seated at a zen hall even while the hall was being inundated, and eventually, he was found dead, seated in a zen position after the water receded.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。原文、訳文を分けました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>享年69。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of sixty nine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of sixty nine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 69.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Carkuni(id:79281), Lobbyonce(id:195963), Chi-Ham(id:143515), 代言人(id:33675), Urania(id:7213), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), Charenji(id:7908), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>