<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>皇円</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>皇円（こうえん、承保元年（1074年）？ - 嘉応元年6月13日 (旧暦)（1169年7月9日）？）は、平安時代後期の天台宗の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koen (1074? - July 16, 1169) was a priest of Tendai sect in the latter period of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>暦変換ツールでは訳文のようになりました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koen (1074? - July 16, 1169) was a priest of the Tendai sect in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koen (1074? - July 16, 1169) was a priest of the Tendai sect in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>肥後国に生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Higo Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Higo Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Higo Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>藤原北家藤原道兼流（道兼の玄孫）で、父は三河国権守藤原重兼。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He belonged to line of FUJIWARA no Michikane of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan (great-great-grandson of Michikane), and his father was the Provisional Governor of Mikawa Province, FUJIWARA no Shigekane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He belonged to the line of FUJIWARA no Michikane, of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan (the great-great-grandson of Michikane), and his father was the provisional governor of Mikawa Province, FUJIWARA no Shigekane.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He belonged to the line of FUJIWARA no Michikane, of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan (the great-great-grandson of Michikane), and his father was the provisional governor of Mikawa Province, FUJIWARA no Shigekane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>兄に少納言藤原資隆がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had Shonagon (lesser councilor of state) FUJIWARA no Suketaka as his older brother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His older brother was Shonagon (lesser councilor of state) FUJIWARA no Suketaka.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His older brother was Shonagon (lesser councilor of state) FUJIWARA no Suketaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>肥後阿闍梨とも功徳院阿闍梨とも称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was called Higo Ajari or Kotokuin Ajari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was called Higo Ajari or Kotokuin Ajari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was called Higo Ajari or Kotokuin Ajari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>法然の師。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the master of Honen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the master of Honen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the master of Honen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>比叡山の椙生流皇覚に師事して出家し、成円について密教を学んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He studied under Kokaku of Sugyu school in Hiei-zan Mountain and became as a priest, and studied Esoteric Buddhism under Joen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He studied under Kokaku, of the Sugyu school in Mt. Hiei-zan, and became a priest, and studied Esoteric Buddhism under Joen.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He studied under Kokaku, of the Sugyu school in Mt. Hiei, and became a priest, and studied Esoteric Buddhism under Joen.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その後延暦寺東塔西谷の功徳院に住して、天台教学を講義し、日本浄土宗の祖法然もその教えを受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he lived in Toto (eastern section) Sekoku (西谷) of Enryaku-ji Temple and taught Tendai doctrine, and Honen, the founder of Nihon Jodo sect (Japanese Pure Land sect), studied there, too.</e>
<cmt>西谷→読み不明です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he lived in Toto (eastern section) Sekoku (西谷) of Enryaku-ji Temple and taught Tendai doctrine; Honen, the founder of the Nihon Jodo sect (Japanese Pure Land sect), studied there, too.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he lived in Toto (eastern section) Nishidani of Enryaku-ji Temple and taught Tendai doctrine; Honen, the founder of the Nihon Jodo sect (Japanese Pure Land sect), studied there, too.</e>
<cmt>読みを確認し直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また、神武天皇から堀河天皇までの記事を、漢字の編年体でまとめた仏教史書「扶桑略記」を編纂している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, he compiled &quot;Fuso ryakki,&quot;a Buddhist historical book consisted of articles from Emperor Jinmu through Emperor Horikawa, written in classical Chinese and in chronological order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, he compiled &quot;Fuso ryakki,&quot; a Buddhist historical book consisting of articles from Emperor Jinmu through Emperor Horikawa, written in classical Chinese and in chronological order.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, he compiled &apos;Fuso ryakki,&apos; a Buddhist historical book consisting of articles from Emperor Jinmu through Emperor Horikawa, written in classical Chinese and in chronological order.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>天台の止観という方法に基づき、様々な苦難苦行を積んだという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on the method called Tendai contemplation, he is said to have conducted various harsh ascetic practices.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on the method called Tendai contemplation, he is said to have conducted various harsh ascetic practices.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on the method called Tendai contemplation, he is said to have conducted various harsh ascetic practices.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>96歳の時、人々を救う霊能を得ようと1169年（嘉応元年）6月13日、静岡県の桜ヶ池 (御前崎市)で大蛇となって菩薩行に入ったという伝説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a legend stating that when he was ninety-six years old, on July 16, 1169, he became as a giant snake at Sakuraga-ike Pond (Omaezaki City) in Shizuoka Prefecture and went into Bosatsu-gyo practice, wanting to earn spiritual power to save people.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処置です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a legend stating that on July 16, 1169, at 96 years of age, he became a giant snake at Sakuraga-ike Pond (Omaezaki City) in Shizuoka Prefecture and went into Bosatsu-gyo practice, wanting to earn the spiritual power to save people.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a legend stating that on July 16, 1169, at the age of 96, he became a giant snake at Sakuraga-ike Pond (Omaezaki City) in Shizuoka Prefecture and went into Bosatsu-gyo practice, wanting to earn the spiritual power to save people.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>桜ヶ池の奥の院、応声教院にあじゃり堂の碑が立ち、これが墓所とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an epigraph of Ajari-do Hall standing in Oshokyo-in Temple, which is Oku no in (inner sanctuary) of Sakuraga-ike Pond, and that is regarded as his tomb.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an epigraph of Ajari-do Hall standing in Oshokyo-in Temple, which is Oku no in (the inner sanctuary) of Sakuraga-ike Pond, and that is regarded as his tomb.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an epigraph of Ajari-do Hall standing in Oshokyo-in Temple, which is Oku no in (the inner sanctuary) of Sakuraga-ike Pond, and that is regarded as his tomb.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>なお、皇円の生地、熊本県玉名市には、皇円を記念して「蓮華院誕生寺」が建立されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, in Tamana City, Kumamoto Prefecture, which is Koen&apos;s birthplace, there is &apos;Renge-in Tanjo-ji Temple&apos; constructed, commemorating Koen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, in Tamana City, Kumamoto Prefecture, which is Koen&apos;s birthplace, there is &apos;Renge-in Tanjo-ji Temple,&apos; which commemorates Koen.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, in Tamana City, Kumamoto Prefecture, which is Koen&apos;s birthplace, there is &apos;Renge-in Tanjo-ji Temple,&apos; which commemorates Koen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), YOSHI438(id:174755), Andee(id:20421), 与左衛門(id:159462), Pan-P(id:142104), 代言人(id:33675), R28Bot(id:177951), 机龍之介(id:61257), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>