<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>律宗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Risshu sect</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Risshu sect</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Risshu Sect</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>律宗（りっしゅう）は、戒律の研究と実践を行う仏教の一宗派である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Risshu sect is one sect of Buddhism which research and practice commandments.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Risshu sect is one the sects of Buddhism which research and practice commandments.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Risshu sect is one the sects of Buddhism which research and practice commandments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>中国の律宗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Risshu sect in China</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Risshu sect in China</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Risshu Sect in China</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>中国では、日本と異なり、正式な僧となるには戒律を修めなければならなかったため、古くから研究が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike in the case of Japan, learning commandments was necessary for becoming an official priest in China, so that commandments had been researched from ancient times.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike in Japan, learning commandments was necessary for becoming an official priest in China, so that commandments had been researched from ancient times.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike in Japan, learning commandments was necessary for becoming an official priest in China, so that commandments had been researched from ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>唐代には南山律宗を開いた道宣が出て戒律学を大成し、その孫弟子である鑑真は、留学僧の要請で日本に律を伝えたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that in the period of Tang Dynasty, Dosen, who founded Nanzan-risshu sect, completed the study of commandments and that Ganjin, who learned from Dosen&apos;s disciple, transmitted commandments to Japan, requested by Japanese priests who studied in China.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that in the period of the Tang Dynasty, Dosen, who founded the Nanzan-risshu sect, completed the study of the commandments and that Ganjin, who learned from Dosen&apos;s disciple, transmitted the commandments to Japan, as requested by Japanese priests who had studied in China.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that in the period of the Tang Dynasty, Dosen, who founded the Nanzan-risshu sect, completed the study of the commandments and that Ganjin, who learned from Dosen&apos;s disciple, transmitted the commandments to Japan, as requested by Japanese priests who had studied in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>日本の律宗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Risshu sect in Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Risshu sect in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Risshu Sect in Japan</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>日本においても比較的初期の段階で戒律が伝えられていたものの、不完全なものでその意義が十分されずに一部の寺院における研究に留まり、授戒の儀式も行われていなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan commandments were introduced at the comparatively early stage in an incomplete way, so that their significance was not understood fully and researched only in a part of temples without any rituals of Jukai, handing down the precepts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, commandments were introduced at a comparatively early stage in an incomplete way, so that their significance was not understood fully and they were researched in only a portion of the temples without any Jukai rituals, handing down the precepts.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, commandments were introduced at a comparatively early stage in an incomplete way, so that their significance was not understood fully and they were researched in only a portion of the temples without any Jukai (rituals handing down the precepts).</e>
<cmt>（）を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>天平勝宝5年（753年）、鑑真が6度の航海の末に、唐から招来し、東大寺に戒壇を開き、聖武天皇太上天皇、称徳天皇を初めとする人々に日本で初めて戒律を授けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 753 Ganjin came to Japan from Tang after 6 times voyages, established Kaidan (Buddhist ordination platform) at Todai-ji Temple and conferred commandments to people such as the retired Emperor Shomu and Emperor Shotoku for the first time in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 753, Ganjin came to Japan from Tang after six voyages and established Kaidan (Buddhist ordination platform) at Todai-ji Temple and conferred commandments to the people such as the retired Emperor Shomu and Emperor Shotoku for the first time in Japan.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 753, Ganjin came to Japan from Tang after six voyages and established Kaidan (Buddhist ordination platform) at Todai-ji Temple and conferred commandments to the people such as the retired Emperor Shomu and Emperor Shotoku for the first time in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>後に唐招提寺を本拠として戒律研究に専念し、南都六宗の一つとして今日まで続いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later he devoted to the research on commandments at the base of Toshodai-ji Temple, which has been one of the six sects of Buddhism brought to Japan during the Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later he devoted himself to research on the commandments at the base of Toshodai-ji Temple, which was one of the six Buddhist sects brought to Japan during the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He later devoted himself to research on the commandments at the base of Toshodai-ji Temple, and this sect still exists today as one of Nanto rokushu (the six sects of Buddhism which flourished in ancient Nara).</e>
<cmt>他の記事に合わせ、表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>鑑真が伝えたのは「四分律」によるものであったが、平安時代の最澄や空海はこれを支持せず、空海は「十誦律」を重んじた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Ganjin transmitted &apos;Shibun-ritsu,&apos; Saicho and Kukai in Heian Period did not support it and Kukai put high value on &apos;Juju-ritsu.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Ganjin transmitted &apos;Shibun-ritsu,&apos; Saicho and Kukai in theHeian Period did not support it and Kukai put high value on &apos;Juju-ritsu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Ganjin transmitted &apos;Shibun-ritsu&apos; (Four-Part Vinayapitaka, which explains about regulations and prohibited matters of the priests), Saicho and Kukai in the Heian period did not support it and Kukai put high value on &apos;Juju-ritsu&apos; (Ten-Reciting Vinayapitaka).</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>このため、戒律に関する考え方が分散化して律宗は衰微した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the concept on commandments was decentralized so that Risshu sect declined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the concept on commandments was decentralized so that Risshu sect declined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the concept on commandments was decentralized so that Risshu sect declined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、受戒そのものは東大寺・延暦寺を中心に盛んに行われたものの、官僧の資格をえるためのものとなり内容は形骸化していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, although vowing to follow the precepts was often implemented around Todai-ji Temple and Enryaku-ji Temple, it fell into only a way of getting certificate of official priest and lost substance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, although vowing to follow the precepts was often implemented around Todai-ji Temple and Enryaku-ji Temple, it became only a way to obtain a certificate as an official priest and lost substance.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, although vowing to follow the precepts was often implemented around Todai-ji Temple and Enryaku-ji Temple, it became only a way to obtain a certificate as an official priest and lost substance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>平安時代末期から鎌倉時代には実範・明恵が戒律復興を論じ、それを引き継いで嘉禎2年（1236年）覚盛・有厳・円晴・叡尊の4人が国家と結びついた戒壇によらない自誓受戒を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the end of Heian Period to Kamakura Period, Jippan and Myoe discussed the renaissance of commandments, and subsequently Kakujo, Ugon (Yugon), Ensei and Eison implemented vowing to follow the precepts without depending on Kaidan which related to the state in 1236.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the end of the Heian Period to the Kamakura Period, Jippan and Myoe discussed the renaissance of the commandments, and subsequently Kakujo, Ugon (Yugon), Ensei and Eison implemented vowing to follow the precepts without depending on Kaidan which related to the state in 1236.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the end of the Heian period to the Kamakura period, Shippan and Myoe discussed the renaissance of the commandments, and subsequently Kakujo, Ugon (Yugon), Ensei and Eison implemented vowing to follow the precepts without depending on Kaidan which related to the state in 1236.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>後に覚盛は「四分律」を重視して唐招提寺を復興して律宗再興の拠点としたのに対して、叡尊は西大寺_(奈良市)を拠点に真言宗の「十誦律」を中心とした真言律宗を開いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Kakujo emphasized &apos;Shibun-ritsu&apos; and revived Toshodai-ji Temple as the base of restoration of Risshu sect later, Enson founded Shingon Risshu sect around &apos;Juju-ritsu&apos; of Shingon sect at the base of Saidai-ji Temple (Nara City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Kakujo emphasized &apos;Shibun-ritsu&apos; and revived Toshodai-ji Temple as the base of restoration of the Risshu sect later, Enson founded the Shingon Risshu sect around &apos;Juju-ritsu&apos; of the Shingon sect at the base of Saidai-ji Temple (Nara City).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Kakujo emphasized &apos;Shibun-ritsu&apos; and revived Toshodai-ji Temple as the base of restoration of the Risshu sect later, Enson founded the Shingon Risshu sect around &apos;Juju-ritsu&apos; of the Shingon sect at the base of Saidai-ji Temple (Nara City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>更に京都泉涌寺の俊芿が南宋より新たな律宗を持ち帰った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, Shunjo at Senyu-ji Temple in Kyoto brought back new Risshu sect from the Southern Sungs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, Shunjo at Senyu-ji Temple in Kyoto brought back a new Risshu sect from the Southern Sungs.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, Shunjo at Senyu-ji Temple in Kyoto brought back a new Risshu sect from the Southern Sungs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>このため、俊芿の「北京律」と「南京律」と呼ばれた唐招提寺派・西大寺派（真言律宗）両派の3つの律宗が並立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, there were three kinds of Risshu sect of &apos;Hokkyo-ritsu&apos; by Shunjo, Toshodai-ji-ha and Saidai-ji-ha (Shingon Risshu sect) which were called &apos;Nankyo-ritsu.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, there were three kinds of Risshu sect for &apos;Hokkyo-ritsu&apos; by Shunjo, Toshodai-ji-ha and Saidai-ji-ha (Shingon Risshu sect) which were called &apos;Nankyo-ritsu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, there were three kinds of Risshu sect for &apos;Hokkyo-ritsu&apos; by Shunjo, Toshodaiji school and Saidaiji school (Shingon Risshu sect) which were called &apos;Nankyo-ritsu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>この3派の革新派を「新義律」と呼称して、それ以前の「古義律」と区別することがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some cases, these three reformist groups are called &apos;Shingi-ritsu,&apos; distinguished from the former &apos;Kogi-ritsu.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some cases, these three reformist groups are called &apos;Shingi-ritsu,&apos; and are distinguished from the former &apos;Kogi-ritsu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some cases, these three reformist groups are called &apos;Shingi-ritsu&apos; (new Risshu sect) and are distinguished from the former &apos;Kogi-ritsu&apos; (old Risshu sect)</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかし、結果的にこの新義律3派が議論と交流を重ねることで律宗の深化と再興が進み、中世には禅宗と律宗を合わせて「禅律」とも呼ばれて重んじられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as a result, discussions and intercommunion among the three groups of this Shingi-ritsu promoted to deepen and restore Risshu sect, so that it was put high value in the medieval times, called &apos;Zen-ritsu&apos; combining Zen sect and Risshu sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as a result, discussions and intercommunion among the three groups of this Shingi-ritsu promoted deepening and restored the Risshu sect, so that it was put to high value during medieval times, and called &apos;Zen-ritsu&apos; combining the Zen sect and the Risshu sect.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as a result, discussions and intercommunion among the three groups of this Shingi-ritsu promoted deepening and restored the Risshu sect, so that it was put to high value during medieval times, and called &apos;Zen-ritsu&apos; combining the Zen sect and the Risshu sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>室町時代には禅宗に押されて再び衰退するが、江戸時代には明忍・友尊・慧雲が出現して再度戒律復興が唱えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Muromachi Period it declined again pressed by Zen sect, but in Edo Period Myonin, Yuson and Eun appeared and insisted on the renaissance of commandments.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Muromachi Period it declined again pressed by the Zen sect, but in the Edo Period, Myonin, Yuson and Eun appeared and insisted on the renaissance of the commandments.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Muromachi period it declined again pressed by the Zen sect, but in the Edo period, Myonin, Yuson and Eun appeared and insisted on the renaissance of the commandments.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="19">
<j>なお、明治初期には、唐招提寺を例外として他の律宗寺院は全て真言宗に所轄されたが、1900年（明治33年）律宗として独立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, in the early Meiji Period all Risshu temples except Toshodai-ji Temple were belonged to Shingon sect, but they became independent as Risshu sect in1900.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, in the early Meiji Period all Risshu temples except Toshodai-ji Temple belonged to the Shingon sect, but they became independent as the Risshu sect in 1900.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides, in the early Meiji period all Risshu temples except Toshodai-ji Temple belonged to the Shingon sect, but they became independent as the Risshu sect in 1900.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>宗義</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dharma of the sect</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dharma of the sect</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dharma of the Sect</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>戒律の研究と実践を主とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main dharma is the research and practice of commandments.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main dharma is the research and practice of commandments.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main dharma is the research and practice of commandments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>本山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Head Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Head Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Head Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>唐招提寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshodai-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshodai-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshodai-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Vina-iwbot(id:56449), Mooko(id:36162), Wainda(id:178301), Kakashi(id:13135), Kstigarbha(id:13376), R28Bot(id:177951), 水野白楓(id:22811), Extrahitz(id:26245), Dignaaga(id:91287), Authority(id:10737), Avxz(id:123412), 無空(id:17049), サイユ(id:25887), KTX(id:15123), Amaki bo(id:13580), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>