<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>般若心経</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heart of Great Perfect Wisdom Sutra (Hannya Shingyo)</e>
<cmt>http://global.sotozen-net.or.jp/eng/what_are_sutras.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heart of Great Perfect Wisdom Sutra (Hannya Shingyo)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heart of Great Perfect Wisdom Sutra (Hannya Shingyo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>『般若心経』（はんにゃしんぎょう、サンスクリットPrajñā-pāramitā-hṛdaya）は大乗仏教の空 (仏教)・般若思想を説いた経典の1つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Heart of Great Perfect Wisdom Sutra (Hannya Shingyo, Prajñā-pāramitā-hṛdaya in Sanskrit)&quot; is one of the Buddist sutra which preaches Ku (Buddhism) of Mahayana Buddhism and Prajna Thought.</e>
<cmt>大乗仏教→Webster Online Dictionary、般若思想→http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110000252297/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Heart of Great Perfect Wisdom Sutra (Hannya Shingyo, Prajñā-pāramitā-hṛdaya in Sanskrit)&quot; is one of the Buddhist sutras that preaches the Ku (Buddhism) of Mahayana Buddhism and Prajna thought.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Heart of Great Perfect Wisdom Sutra (Hannya Shingyo, Prajñā-pāramitā-hṛdaya in Sanskrit)&quot; is one of the Buddhist sutras that preaches the Ku (Buddhism) of Mahayana Buddhism and Prajna thought.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>宗派によって呼び方は様々あり、この他に仏説摩訶般若波羅蜜多心経、摩訶般若波羅蜜多心経、般若波羅蜜多心経と言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are various names depending on sects and it is also called Bussetsu Maka Hannya Haramitashin-gyo Sutra, Maka Hannya Haramitashin-gyo Sutra and Hannya Haramitashin-gyo Sutra.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various names depending on the sect, so it is also called Bussetsu Maka Hannya Haramitashin-gyo Sutra, Maka Hannya Haramitashin-gyo Sutra and Hannya Haramitashin-gyo Sutra.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various names depending on the sect, so it is also called Bussetsu Maka Hannya Haramitashin-gyo Sutra, Maka Hannya Haramitashin-gyo Sutra and Hannya Haramitashin-gyo Sutra.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>略称として心経。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is abbreviated to Heart Sutra (心経).</e>
<cmt>心経→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is abbreviated as &quot;Heart Sutra (心経).&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is abbreviated as &quot;Heart Sutra (心経).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>なお、漢訳には題名に「経」が付されているが、サンスクリットテキストの題名には「経」に相当する「スートラ」の字句はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Chinese title accompanies the word &apos;経 (sutra)&apos;, but in the title of Sanskrit text there is no word of &apos;sutra&apos; which corresponds to &apos;経.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, a Chinese title accompanies the word &apos;経 (sutra),&apos; but in the title of Sanskrit text there is no word &apos;sutra&apos; that corresponds to &apos;経.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, a Chinese title accompanies the word &apos;経 (sutra),&apos; but in the title of Sanskrit text there is no word &apos;sutra&apos; that corresponds to &apos;経.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>僅か300字足らずの本文に大乗仏教の心髄が説かれているとされ、一部の宗派を除き僧侶・在家を問わず、読誦経典の1つとして、永く依用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that in the text of less than only 300 characters the essense of Mahayana Buddhism is preached and it has been used as one of the reciting sutras without regard to priests or lay people except some sects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that in the text of less than 300 characters the essence of Mahayana Buddhism is preached, and it has been used as one of the sutras for recitation without regard to whether one is a priest or a lay person (except for certain sects).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that in the text of less than 300 characters the essence of Mahayana Buddhism is preached, and it has been used as one of the sutras for recitation without regard to whether one is a priest or a lay person (except for certain sects).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>『般若心経』は一般には600巻に及ぶ『大般若波羅蜜多経』のエッセンス等といわれているが、『大般若波羅蜜多経』（『大般若経』）及び『摩訶般若波羅蜜経』（『大品般若経』）からの抜粋に『陀羅尼集経』に収録されている陀羅尼（Sktdhāranī）を末尾に付け加えたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hannya Shingyo&quot; is generally said to be an essence or something of the 600 volumes of &quot;Mahaprajnaparamita-sutra (Daihannyaharamitta-kyo Sutra)&quot;, but it consists of the abstract from &quot;the Mahaprajnaparamita-sutra&quot; (&quot;Dai-Hannya-kyo Sutra&quot;) and &quot;Maka Hannya Haramitsu-kyo Sutra&quot;(&quot;Mahaprajnaparamita-sutra&quot;) with adding litany (Sktdhāranī) which is included in &quot;Darani Jikkyo Sutra&quot; to tail end.</e>
<cmt>大般若波羅蜜多経→http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110002661106、大般若経→Yahoo辞書、大品般若経→http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110000372810/、陀羅尼集経→http://homepage3.nifty.com/koyasan/nenju2.html、陀羅尼→Webster Online Dictionary</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hannya Shingyo&quot; is generally said to be the essence or a representation of the 600 volumes of &quot;Mahaprajnaparamita-sutra (Daihannyaharamitta-kyo Sutra),&quot; but it consists of the abstract from &quot;the Mahaprajnaparamita-sutra&quot; (&quot;Dai-Hannya-kyo Sutra&quot;) and &quot;Maka Hannya Haramitsu-kyo Sutra&quot;(&quot;Mahaprajnaparamita-sutra&quot;) with the addition of a litany (Sktdhāranī), which is included in &quot;Darani Jikkyo Sutra&quot; at the end.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Hannya Shingyo&quot; is generally said to be the essence or a representation of the 600 volumes of &quot;Mahaprajnaparamita-sutra (Daihannyaharamitta-kyo Sutra),&quot; but it consists of the abstract from &quot;the Mahaprajnaparamita-sutra&quot; (&quot;Dai-Hannya-kyo Sutra&quot;) and &quot;Maka Hannya Haramitsu-kyo Sutra&quot;(&quot;Mahaprajnaparamita-sutra&quot;) with the addition of a litany (Sktdhāranī), which is included in &quot;Darani Jikkyo Sutra&quot; at the end.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>般若経典群のテーマを「空 (仏教)」の1字に集約して、その重要性を説いて悟りの成就を讃える体裁をとりながら、末尾に付加した陀羅尼によって仏教の持つ呪術的な側面が特に強調されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While it summarizes themes of the Prajnaparamita-sutras as &apos;Ku (Buddhism)&apos;, preaches its importance and glorifies the reach of enlightenment, it also emphasizes on the magical aspect of Buddhism especially by the litany added in the ending.</e>
<cmt>般若経典→http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110002662678/、</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While it summarizes the themes of the Prajnaparamita-sutras as &apos;Ku (Buddhism),&apos; it preaches its importance and glorifies the attainment of enlightenment; moreover, it emphasizes the magical aspect of Buddhism, especially with the litany added at the end.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While it summarizes the themes of the Prajnaparamita-sutras as &apos;Ku (Buddhism),&apos; it preaches its importance and glorifies the attainment of enlightenment; moreover, it emphasizes the magical aspect of Buddhism, especially with the litany added at the end.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>般若心経の「心」とは、サンスクリットで心臓＝重要な物を意味する「hṛdaya」（フリダヤ）の訳語であり、同時に呪（陀羅尼、真言）をも意味する語である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &apos;Heart&apos; of Hannya Shingyo is a translation of &apos;hṛdaya&apos; in Sanskrit which means heart, that is, important thing, and it also means magic (litany, mantra).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &apos;Heart&apos; of Hannya Shingyo is a translation of &apos;hṛdaya&apos; in Sanskrit (which means &apos;heart&apos;), or an important thing, but it also means magic (litany, mantra).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;Heart&apos; of Hannya Shingyo is a translation of &apos;hṛdaya&apos; in Sanskrit (which means &apos;heart&apos;), or an important thing, but it also means magic (litany, mantra).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>そのため、般若心経は空観を説く経典であるとされる一方、陀羅尼の経典であるともいわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, while Hannya Shingyo is said to be a Buddhist sutra which preaches the view of Ku, it is also said to be a Buddhist sutra of litany.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, while Hannya Shingyo is said to be a Buddhist sutra that preaches the view of Ku, it is also said to be a Buddhist sutra of litany.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, while Hannya Shingyo is said to be a Buddhist sutra that preaches the view of Ku, it is also said to be a Buddhist sutra of litany.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>一般に般若経典には、後期の密教化したものは別として、呪文などは含まれていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally speaking, the Prajnaparamita-sutras do not include magical words except what became Mikkyo, Esoteric Buddhism, in the latter stage.</e>
<cmt>密教→http://www.koyasan.or.jp/english/shingonshu/mikkyo.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally speaking, the Prajnaparamita sutras do not include magical words except for what became Mikkyo (Esoteric Buddhism) in the latter stage.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally speaking, the Prajnaparamita sutras do not include magical words except for what became Mikkyo (Esoteric Buddhism) in the latter stage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>それを考慮すると、『般若心経』は、般若経典としては極めて特異なものと言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Considering above, &quot;Hannya Shingyo&quot; is extremely peculiar as one of the Prajnaparamita-sutras.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Considering the above, &quot;Hannya Shingyo&quot; is extremely peculiar as one of the Prajnaparamita sutras.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Considering the above, &quot;Hannya Shingyo&quot; is extremely peculiar as one of the Prajnaparamita sutras.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>またサンスクリット・テキストの原題には経という語はないため、陀羅尼（総持）のために作られた唱文が、中国で経として扱われるようになったのではないかという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, there is a theory that since the original title of Sanskrit text does not include the word of sutra, an invocation text made for litany (soji, 総持) became to be considered as a sutra in China.</e>
<cmt>総持</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, there is a theory that since the original title of the Sanskrit text does not include the word &quot;sutra,&quot; an invocation text made for litany (soji, 総持) came to be considered as a sutra in China.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, there is a theory that since the original title of the Sanskrit text does not include the word &quot;sutra,&quot; an invocation text made for litany (soji, 総持) came to be considered as a sutra in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>なお、最古の経典目録（経録）である東晋の釈道安撰『綜理衆経目録』(梁 (南朝)の僧祐撰『出三蔵記集』にほぼ収録)には、『摩訶般若波羅蜜神咒一巻』及び『般若波羅蜜神咒一巻　異本』とあり、経としての般若心経成立以前から、呪文による儀礼が先に成立していたという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, in &quot;Shuri Shu-kyo Mokuroku&quot; (mostly included in &quot;Shutsu Sanzo Kishu, the Chu sanzang ji ji&quot; edited by Soyu, a priest of Liang (nanchao)) edited by Doan SHAKU in the eastern Jin, the oldest catalog of Buddhist sutra, there are titles of &quot;Maka Hannya Haramitsu Shinju vol.1&quot; and &quot;Hannya Haramitsu Shinju vol.1, alternative version&quot; so that there is a theory that magic ritual had been established former than Hannya Shingyo was established as a sutra.</e>
<cmt>東晋→http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110000125240/、釈道安→http://www.koyasan.or.jp/taiken/shakyo/buten_shakyo.html、綜理衆経目録→http://www.koyasan.or.jp/taiken/shakyo/buten_shakyo.html、梁 (南朝)→http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110000092148/、僧祐→kotobank、出三蔵記集→http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110002662174/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, in &quot;Shuri Shu-kyo Mokuroku&quot; (mostly included in &quot;Shutsu Sanzo Kishu, the Chu sanzang ji ji&quot; edited by Soyu, a priest of Liang (Nanchao)) edited by Doan SHAKU in eastern Jin, the oldest catalog of Buddhist sutra, there are titles of &quot;Maka Hannya Haramitsu Shinju Vol. 1&quot; and &quot;Hannya Haramitsu Shinju Vol. 1, alternative version,&quot; so that there is a theory that a magic ritual had been established as opposed to Hannya Shingyo, which was established as a sutra.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, in &quot;Shuri Shu-kyo Mokuroku&quot; (mostly included in &quot;Shutsu Sanzo Kishu, the Chu sanzang ji ji&quot; edited by Soyu, a priest of Liang (Nanchao)) edited by Doan SHAKU in eastern Jin, the oldest catalog of Buddhist sutra, there are titles of &quot;Maka Hannya Haramitsu Shinju Vol. 1&quot; and &quot;Hannya Haramitsu Shinju Vol. 1, alternative version&quot;; thus there is a theory that a magic ritual had been established before Hannya Shingyo was established as a sutra.</e>
<cmt>「経としての般若心経成立以前から、」の意味になるように直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>また『大般若波羅蜜多経』（大般若経）では、第二分功德品第三十二に「般若波羅蜜多」（という語句・概念自体）が大明呪（偉大な呪文）であると説かれているが、『般若心経』では、雑密の陀羅尼を付加するために「般若波羅蜜多咒」という語句が挿入されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, while in the dainibun-Kudokuhon (第二分功德品) No.32 of &quot;the Mahaprajnaparamita-sutra (Dai-Hannya-kyo Sutra)&quot;, &apos;Hannya Haramita&apos; (a word or an idea itself) is considered to be the great spell (大明呪), in &quot;Hannya Shingyo&quot; the word of &apos;Hannya Haramita Shu&apos; is set in to add litany of Zo-mitsu (the Mixed Esoteric Buddhism).</e>
<cmt>第二分功德品→定訳不明、大明呪→定訳不明、雑密→http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110000252311/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, while in the dainibun-Kudokuhon (第二分功德品) No. 32 of &quot;the Mahaprajnaparamita-sutra (Dai-Hannya-kyo Sutra),&quot; &apos;Hannya Haramita&apos; (a word or an idea itself) is considered to be the great spell (大明呪), in &quot;Hannya Shingyo,&quot; the phrase &apos;Hannya Haramita Shu&apos; is set in to add the litany of Zo-mitsu (Mixed Esoteric Buddhism).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, while in the dainibun-Kudokuhon (第二分功德品) No. 32 of &quot;the Mahaprajnaparamita-sutra (Dai-Hannya-kyo Sutra),&quot; &apos;Hannya Haramita&apos; (a word or an idea itself) is considered to be the great spell (大明呪), in &quot;Hannya Shingyo,&quot; the phrase &apos;Hannya Haramita Shu&apos; is set in to add the litany of Zo-mitsu (Mixed Esoteric Buddhism).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>陀羅尼の意味については渡辺照宏説、中村元 (哲学者)説など多いが、定訳はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various theories on the meaning of litany have been brought out by such as Shoko WATANABE and Hajime NAKAMURA (philosopher), but there is no authorized translation.</e>
<cmt>渡辺照宏→kotobank、中村元→kotobank</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various theories on the meaning of litany have been proposed by such people as Shoko WATANABE and the philosopher Hajime NAKAMURA, but there is no authorized translation.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various theories on the meaning of litany have been proposed by such people as Shoko WATANABE and the philosopher Hajime NAKAMURA, but there is no authorized translation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>原型</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Original</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Original</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Original</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>西暦2～3世紀にインドの龍樹が般若経典の注釈書である『大智度論』を著したとされ、般若心経もこの頃に成立したものと推定する説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Ryuju in India wrote &quot;Daichidoron&quot;, a commentary of the Prajnaparamita-sutras during the 2nd to 3rd centuries, and there is a theory which guesses that Hannya Shingo was established around this time.</e>
<cmt>大智度論→kotobank</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Ryuju in India wrote &quot;Daichidoron,&quot; a commentary on the Prajnaparamita-sutras during the second to third centuries, and there is a theory assuming that Hannya Shingo was established around this time.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Ryuju in India wrote &quot;Daichidoron,&quot; a commentary on the Prajnaparamita-sutras during the second to third centuries, and there is a theory assuming that Hannya Shingo was established around this time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>しかしながら、現存する最古のサンスクリット（梵字）本は、法隆寺所蔵の8世紀後半（伝承では609年請来）の写本とされる貝葉本であり、漢訳経典より時代を下る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the existing oldest Sanskrit book is Baiyo-bon Edition housed at Horyu-ji Temple, which is said to be a manuscript in the latter part of the 8th centuries (introduced in 609 according to a myth), and it was written in the later age than the time when Buddhist sutra was translated into Chinese.</e>
<cmt>法隆寺→http://www.horyuji.or.jp/、貝葉本→http://www.aa.tufs.ac.jp/i-moji/hiroba/qa2.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the oldest existing Sanskrit book is the Baiyo-bon edition housed at Horyu-ji Temple, which is said to be a manuscript from the latter part of the eighth century (introduced in 609 according to a legend), and it was written in a later age than the time when Buddhist sutras were translated into Chinese.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the oldest existing Sanskrit book is the Baiyo-bon edition housed at Horyu-ji Temple, which is said to be a manuscript from the latter part of the eighth century (introduced in 609 according to a legend), and it was written in a later age than the time when Buddhist sutras were translated into Chinese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>また、現在チベットやネパール等に伝わる写本も、それ以降の時代のものであり原形については不明であり、偽経説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, manuscripts left in Tibet and Nepal at present were also made in the later age after that and their original forms are not known, so that there is a doubt that it might be a fake sutra.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, manuscripts that remain in Tibet and Nepal were also made in a subsequent age and their original forms aren&apos;t known, so it is suspected that they might be fake sutras.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, manuscripts that remain in Tibet and Nepal were also made in a subsequent age and their original forms aren&apos;t known, so it is suspected that they might be fake sutras.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>漢訳</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Translation into Chinese</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Translation into Chinese</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Translation into Chinese</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>『摩訶般若波羅蜜神咒一巻』及び『般若波羅蜜神咒一巻　異本』は、後世の文献では前者は3世紀中央アジア出身の支謙、後者は鳩摩羅什の訳とされているが、『綜理衆経目録』には訳者不明（失訳）とされており、この二人に帰することは信憑性にとぼしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the documents of later age &quot;Maka Hannya Haramitsu Shinju vol.1&quot; was translated by Zhi Qian, who came from Central Asia in the 3rd centuries, and &quot;Hannya Haramitsu Shinju vol.1, alternative version&quot; was translated by Kumaraju, but &quot;Shuri Shu-kyo Mokuroku&quot; describes that their translators are unknown, so that it is dubious about the credibility to think they were translated by these people.</e>
<cmt>支謙→http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110006572538/、鳩摩羅什→Yahoo辞書</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the documents of a later age, &quot;Maka Hannya Haramitsu Shinju Vol. 1&quot; was translated by Zhi Qian, who came from Central Asia in the third century, and &quot;Hannya Haramitsu Shinju Vol. 1, alternative version&quot; was translated by Kumaraju; however, &quot;Shuri Shu-kyo Mokuroku&quot; states that their translators are unknown, so it is doubtful that they were translated by these people.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the documents of a later age, &quot;Maka Hannya Haramitsu Shinju Vol. 1&quot; was translated by Zhi Qian, who came from Central Asia in the third century, and &quot;Hannya Haramitsu Shinju Vol. 1, alternative version&quot; was translated by Kumaraju; however, &quot;Shuri Shu-kyo Mokuroku&quot; states that their translators are unknown, so it is doubtful that they were translated by these people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>前者は現存せず、後者は大蔵経収録の羅什訳『摩訶般若波羅蜜大明咒經』とされるが、羅什の訳経開始が402年であるため、釈道安の没年385年には未訳出である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former does not exists now and the latter is regarded as &quot;Maka Hannya Haramitsu Daimyo Jukyo&quot; translated by Raju included in Tripitaka, but since Raju began to translate in 402 it must not have been translated in 385, when Doan SHAKU died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former no longer exists, and the latter is regarded as &quot;Maka Hannya Haramitsu Daimyo Jukyo&quot; translated by Raju included in Tripitaka, but since Raju began to translate in 402 it could not have been translated in 385, when Doan SHAKU died.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former no longer exists, and the latter is regarded as &quot;Maka Hannya Haramitsu Daimyo Jukyo&quot; translated by Raju included in Tripitaka, but since Raju began to translate in 402 it could not have been translated in 385, when Doan SHAKU died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>またそのテキストの主要部は宋・元・明大蔵経版の鳩摩羅什訳『摩訶般若波羅蜜経』のテキストと一致するが、宋版大蔵経の刊行は12世紀後半であるため、このテキストが羅什訳であるということも疑われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the major part of the text corresponds to the text of &quot;Maka Hannya Haramitsu-kyo Sutra&quot; translated by Kumaraju of Tripitaka in Sung, Yuan and Ming editions, but since So-ban Daizo-kyo Sutra (Tripitaka in Song Edition) was published in the latter part of the 12th centuries there is a doubt that this text was translated by Raju.</e>
<cmt>宋版大蔵経→http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110000476519/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, the majority of the text corresponds to the text of &quot;Maka Hannya Haramitsu-kyo Sutra&quot; translated by Kumaraju of Tripitaka in the Sung, Yuan and Ming editions, but since So-ban Daizo-kyo Sutra (Tripitaka in the Sung edition) was published in the latter part of the twelfth century it is doubtful that this text was translated by Raju.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, the majority of the text corresponds to the text of &quot;Maka Hannya Haramitsu-kyo Sutra&quot; translated by Kumaraju of Tripitaka in the Sung, Yuan and Ming editions, but since So-ban Daizo-kyo Sutra (Tripitaka in the Sung edition) was published in the latter part of the twelfth century it is doubtful that this text was translated by Raju.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="24">
<j>649年、インドより帰還した玄奘もまた『般若心経』を翻訳したとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Genjo, who came back from India, also translated &quot;Hannya Shingyo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Genjo, who had returned from India, also translated &quot;Hannya Shingyo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Genjo, who had returned from India in 649, also translated &quot;Hannya Shingyo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>年号追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>訳経史の概念として鳩摩羅什までの漢訳経典を「古訳」鳩摩羅什以降、玄奘までを「旧訳（くやく）」玄奘以降を「新訳」と言う（訳経史区分）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As an idea of the history of translation of sutra, Buddhist sutras translated into Chinese before Kumaraju are called &apos;ancient translation,&apos; those after Kumaraju and before Genjo are called &apos;old translation &apos; and those after Genjo are called &apos;new translation&apos; (classification of sutra translation).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As an idea on the history of sutra translation, Buddhist sutras translated into Chinese before Kumaraju are called &apos;ancient translations,&apos; those after Kumaraju and before Genjo are called &apos;old translations&apos; and those after Genjo are called &apos;new translations&apos; (as per the classification of sutra translations).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As an idea on the history of sutra translation, Buddhist sutras translated into Chinese before Kumaraju are called &apos;ancient translations,&apos; those after Kumaraju and before Genjo are called &apos;old translations&apos; and those after Genjo are called &apos;new translations&apos; (as per the classification of sutra translations).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="26">
<j>しかし、文献学的にはテキストの主要部分が高麗大蔵経版（13世紀前半）の鳩摩羅什訳『摩訶般若波羅蜜経』からの抽出文そのものであり、玄奘が翻訳した『大般若波羅蜜多経』の該当部分とは異なるため、これも羅什訳と同様に玄奘訳であるということが疑われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the aspect of philology, major part of the text was the abstraction itself from &quot;Maka Hannya Haramitsu-kyo Sutra&quot; of Tripitaka in Korean edition (in the first part of the 13th centuries) translated by Kumaraju, and was different from the corresponding part of &quot;the Mahaprajnaparamita-sutra&quot; translated by Genjo so that this is also suspicious about being translated by Genjo, as well as the Buddist sutra which was said to be translated by Raju.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the aspect of philology the majority of the text was an abstraction from &quot;Maka Hannya Haramitsu-kyo Sutra&quot; of Tripitaka in the Korean edition (in the first part of the thirteenth century) translated by Kumaraju, and was different from the corresponding part of the &quot;Mahaprajnaparamita-sutra&quot; translated by Genjo, so that there is also suspicion about whether it was translated by Genjo, as well as the Buddhist sutra, which was said to be a translation by Raju.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the aspect of philology the majority of the text was an abstraction from &quot;Maka Hannya Haramitsu-kyo Sutra&quot; of Tripitaka in the Korean edition (in the first part of the thirteenth century) translated by Kumaraju, and was different from the corresponding part of the &quot;Mahaprajnaparamita-sutra&quot; translated by Genjo, so that there is also suspicion about whether it was translated by Genjo, as well as the Buddhist sutra, which was said to be a translation by Raju.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="27">
<j>現在、玄奘訳の最古のテキストとされるものは、672年に建てられた弘福寺（興福寺）の集王聖教序碑（集字聖教序碑）中の『聖教序』の後に付加されているテキストである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The oldest text which is considered to be translated by Genjo at present is the text which is added to the tail end of &quot;Shogyojo&quot; in Shuo Shogyojo (Ji wang shen jiao xu, Shuji Shogyojo) monument at Hongfusi Temple (Kofukuji Temple) built in 672.</e>
<cmt>弘福寺→http://www.chinaviki.com/china-travel/attrations/Guizhou/Guiyang/Hongfusi/、興福寺→http://www.kohfukuji.com/、集王聖教序→http://abc0120.net/words01/abc2009030807.html*興福寺は中国の寺と思われますが、定訳不明なので用語集どおりに訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The oldest text that is currently considered to be a translation by Genjo is the text that is added to the end of &quot;Shogyojo&quot; in the Shuo Shogyojo (Ji wang shen jiao xu, Shuji Shogyojo) monument at Hongfusi Temple (Kofukuji Temple), which was built in 672.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The oldest text that is currently considered to be a translation by Genjo is the text that is added to the end of &quot;Shogyojo&quot; in the Shuo Shogyojo (Ji wang shen jiao xu, Shuji Shogyojo) monument at Hongfusi Temple (Kofukuji Temple), which was built in 672.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>しかしながら太宗 (唐)が『聖教序』を下賜した648年から大幅に時間が経過している上、跋文に「勅を奉けて潤色せり」という記載があることから、この碑文は玄奘の没後にその偉業を讃えるために鳩摩羅什の訳文を元に玄奘訳としてまとめられたものではないかとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, because it had been long time since 648, when Taiso, Tang tai zong, gave &quot;Shogyojo&quot; and there is a description in afterword that &apos;embroidered by emperor&apos;s order&apos;, there is a theory that this epigraph became to be told as a translation by Genjo based on Kumaraju&apos;s translation in order to glorify Genjo&apos;s great work after his death.</e>
<cmt>太宗 (唐)→http://abc0120.net/words01/abc2008081501.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, because it had been a long time since 648 when Taiso (Tang tai zong) gave &quot;Shogyojo,&quot; and there is a description in the afterword that &apos;embroidered by order of the Emperor,&quot; there is a theory that this epigraph came to be assessed as a translation by Genjo based on Kumaraju&apos;s translation in order to glorify Genjo&apos;s great work after his death.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, because it had been a long time since 648 when Taiso (Tang tai zong) gave &quot;Shogyojo,&quot; and there is a description in the afterword that &apos;embroidered by order of the Emperor,&quot; there is a theory that this epigraph came to be assessed as a translation by Genjo based on Kumaraju&apos;s translation in order to glorify Genjo&apos;s great work after his death.</e>
<cmt>afterword→afterward</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>また、玄奘の弟子である慈恩大師基 (僧)の『般若波羅蜜多心経幽讃』にもその旨を示唆するような記述がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, in &quot;Hannya Haramitashin-gyo Sutra Yusan&quot; written by Jion Daishi Ki, a disciple of Genjo, there is a description to indicate that theory.</e>
<cmt>慈恩大師基→kotobank</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, in &quot;Hannya Haramitashin-gyo Sutra Yusan,&quot; written by Jion Daishi Ki, a disciple of Genjo, there is a description to indicate that theory.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, in &quot;Hannya Haramitashin-gyo Sutra Yusan,&quot; written by Jion Daishi Ki, a disciple of Genjo, there is a description to indicate that theory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="30">
<j>また玄奘訳とされている『般若心経』は読誦用として最も広く普及しているが、これは羅什訳と玄奘訳との双方がある経典は、古来前者が依用されていることを考慮すると異例のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, although &quot;Hannya Shingyo&quot; which is said to be translated by Genjo widespreads most broadly for reading and invocation, this is unusual, considering that the Buddhist sutra translated by Raju had been used more often than the Buddhist sutra translated by Genjo since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>「経典は」は「経典のうち」と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, although &quot;Hannya Shingyo,&quot; which is said to be a translation by Genjo, became the most widespread for reading and invocation, this is unusual considering that the Buddhist sutra translated by Raju had since ancient times been used more often than the Buddhist sutra translated by Genjo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, although &quot;Hannya Shingyo,&quot; which is said to be a translation by Genjo, became the most widespread for reading and invocation, this is unusual considering that the Buddhist sutra translated by Raju had since ancient times been used more often than the Buddhist sutra translated by Genjo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>なお『大般若波羅蜜多経』転読は頻繁に行われるが、経典のテキストそのものを読誦することは稀である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, sloppy reading of &quot;the Mahaprajnaparamita-sutra&quot; is often performed but the text of Buddhist sutra itself is rarely read and recited.</e>
<cmt>転読→略して読むと解釈しました。Goo辞書、英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, sloppy reading of &quot;the Mahaprajnaparamita-sutra&quot; is often performed but the text of the Buddhist sutra itself is rarely read and recited.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, sloppy reading of &quot;the Mahaprajnaparamita-sutra&quot; is often performed but the text of the Buddhist sutra itself is rarely read and recited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>代表的なテキスト</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Representative texts</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Representative texts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Representative texts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="32">
<j>以下は、代表的な流布テキストに句読点を施したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Representative widespreading texts added punctuation marks are as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Representative widespread texts that have additional punctuation marks are as follows:</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Representative widespread texts that have additional punctuation marks are as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="33">
<j>なお、羅什訳・玄奘訳とも、「般若波羅蜜（多）」「舍利弗（子）」「阿耨多羅三藐三菩提」「菩薩（菩提薩&amp;amp22517）」及び最後の「咒（しゅ）」の部分だけは漢訳せず、サンスクリットをそのまま音写している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, in both Raju&apos;s and Genjo&apos;s translations, &apos;Hannya Haramitsu (Hannya Haramita),&apos; &apos;Sariputra,&apos; &apos;阿耨多羅三藐三菩提,&apos; &apos;Bosatsu (菩提薩&amp;amp22517)&apos; and the last &apos;shu&apos; were not translated into Chinese and showed transcription of Sanskrit without change.</e>
<cmt>舍利弗（子)→http://www2.toyo.ac.jp/~morimori/mokuroku02-3.html、咒（しゅ）→定訳不明Webster Online Dictionary、阿耨多羅三藐三菩提、菩提薩&amp;amp22517→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, in both Raju&apos;s and Genjo&apos;s translations, &apos;Hannya Haramitsu (Hannya Haramita),&apos; &apos;Sariputra,&apos; &apos;阿耨多羅三藐三菩提,&apos; &apos;Bosatsu (菩提薩&amp;amp22517)&apos; and the last &apos;shu&apos; were not translated into Chinese and showed transcriptions of Sanskrit without changes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, in both Raju&apos;s and Genjo&apos;s translations, &apos;Hannya Haramitsu (Hannya Haramita),&apos; &apos;Sariputra,&apos; &apos;阿耨多羅三藐三菩提,&apos; &apos;Bosatsu (菩提薩&amp;amp22517)&apos; and the last &apos;shu&apos; were not translated into Chinese and showed transcriptions of Sanskrit without changes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="34">
<j>また、玄奘訳とされるテキストには版本によって、例えば下記の箇所のように、字句の異同が十数箇所存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, in the text which is said to be translated by Genjo there are more than ten differences in words depending on editions, of which examples are as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, in the text that is said to be a translation by Genjo there are more than 10 differences in words depending on the edition, examples of which are as follows:</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, in the text that is said to be a translation by Genjo there are more than 10 differences in words depending on the edition, examples of which are as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="35">
<j>空即是色受想行識亦復如是（大正蔵）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">空即是色受想行識亦復如是（大正蔵）</e>
<cmt>大正蔵→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">空即是色受想行識亦復如是（大正蔵）</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">空即是色受想行識亦復如是（大正蔵）</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>空即是色受想行識等亦復如是（法隆寺本等法相宗系）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">空即是色受想行識等亦復如是 (linage of Hosso-shu sect such as Horyu-ji Temple edition)</e>
<cmt>法相宗→kotobank</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">空即是色受想行識等亦復如是 (lineage of the Hosso-shu sect such as the Horyu-ji Temple edition)</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">空即是色受想行識等亦復如是 (lineage of the Hosso-shu sect such as the Horyu-ji Temple edition)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>日本における般若心経</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hannya Shingyo in Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hannya Shingyo in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hannya Shingyo in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>各宗派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In various sects</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In various sects</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In various sects</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="37">
<j>日本では仏教各派、特に法相宗・天台宗・真言宗・禅宗が般若心経を使用し、その宗派独特の解釈を行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, various sects, especially Hosso-shu sect, Tendai sect, Shingon sect and Zen sect, use Hannya Shingyo and interpret it individually in each sect.</e>
<cmt>真言宗→英辞郎 on the WEB、禅宗→英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan various sects, especially the Hosso-shu, Tendai, Shingon and Zen sects, use Hannya Shingyo and interpret it individually.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan various sects, especially the Hosso-shu, Tendai, Shingon and Zen sects, use Hannya Shingyo and interpret it individually.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>ただし、浄土真宗は『浄土三部経』を、日蓮宗・法華宗は『妙法蓮華経（法華経）』を根本経典としているため、般若心経を唱えることはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Jodo Shinshu sect regards &quot;Three Sutras of the Pure Land (Jodosanbu-kyo Sutra)&quot; as the foundamental Buddhist sutra, and Nichiren sect and Hokke sect regard &quot;Myohorenge-kyo&quot; as that, so that they do not recite Hannya Shingyo.</e>
<cmt>浄土三部経→http://www.jsri.jp/English/Terminology/eng-jap.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Jodo Shinshu sect regards &quot;Three Sutras of the Pure Land (Jodosanbu-kyo Sutra)&quot; as the fundamental Buddhist sutra, and the Nichiren and Hokke sects regard &quot;Myohorenge-kyo&quot; as that, so they don&apos;t recite the Hannya Shingyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Jodo Shinshu sect regards &quot;Three Sutras of the Pure Land (Jodosanbu-kyo Sutra)&quot; as the fundamental Buddhist sutra, and the Nichiren and Hokke sects regard &quot;Myohorenge-kyo&quot; as that, so they don&apos;t recite the Hannya Shingyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>これは当該宗派の教義上、用いる必要がないということであり、心経を否定しているのではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is because they do not need to use it from the viewpoint of their dharma, and not because they deny Heart Sutra.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because they don&apos;t need to use it from the viewpoint of their dharma, not because they deny the Heart Sutra.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because they don&apos;t need to use it from the viewpoint of their dharma, not because they deny the Heart Sutra.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>例えば、浄土真宗西本願寺の住職であった大谷光瑞は般若心経の注釈を表している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, Kozui OTANI, who was a chief priest of Jodo Shinshu sect Nishi Hongwan-ji Temple, wrote a commentary of Hannya Shingyo.</e>
<cmt>「表している」は「著している」の誤りと判断しました。大谷光瑞→kotobank</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, Kozui OTANI, who was a chief priest of the Jodo Shinshu sect at Nishi Hongwan-ji Temple, wrote a commentary on the Hannya Shingyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, Kozui OTANI, who was a chief priest of the Jodo Shinshu sect at Nishi Hongwan-ji Temple, wrote a commentary on the Hannya Shingyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="41">
<j>天台宗では、「根本法華」として重視している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tendai sect puts high value on it as &apos;fundamental Hokke (根本法華).&apos;</e>
<cmt>根本法華→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tendai sect values it highly as a &apos;fundamental Hokke (根本法華).&apos;</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tendai sect values it highly as a &apos;fundamental Hokke (根本法華).&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>また最澄作とされる般若心経の注釈がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, there is a commentary which is said to be written by Saicho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, there is a commentary that is said to have been written by Saicho.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, there is a commentary that is said to have been written by Saicho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="43">
<j>真言宗では、読誦・観誦の対象としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Shingon sect it is read and recited and is a subject of 観誦.</e>
<cmt>観誦→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Shingon sect it is read and recited, and is a subject of 観誦.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Shingon sect it is read and recited, and is a subject of 観誦.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>日用経典（日課等通常行事用の経典）の1つとしている（般若心経秘鍵を参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It uses it as one of the Buddhist sutra for daily use (see the article of Hannyashin-gyo Hiken).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It uses it as one of the Buddhist sutra for daily use (see the article of Hannyashin-gyo Hiken).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It uses it as one of the Buddhist sutra for daily use (see the article of Hannyashin-gyo Hiken).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>また、繰り返し読誦する場合は、一回目は、冒頭の「仏説」から読み始めるが、2回目以降の読誦では「仏説」を読まず、「摩訶」から読む慣わしとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case when one reads and recites it repeatedly, traditionally he begins to read from &apos;Bussetsu&apos; in the beginning for the first time, and begins to read from &apos;Maka&apos; for the second time without reading of &apos;Bussetsu.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case where one reads and recites it repeatedly, traditionally he starts reading from &apos;Bussetsu&apos; in the beginning for the first time but begins reading from &apos;Maka&apos; for the second time without reading &apos;Bussetsu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case where one reads and recites it repeatedly, traditionally he starts reading from &apos;Bussetsu&apos; in the beginning for the first time but begins reading from &apos;Maka&apos; for the second time without reading &apos;Bussetsu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>この宗派の僧侶には開祖空海が般若心経を重視したために注釈・解釈を著す僧が多く、著作が色々とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Kukai, the founder of the sect, emphasized Hannya Shingyo so that many priest of this sect have written various commentaries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Kukai, the founder of the sect, emphasized Hannya Shingyo, various priests of this sect have written commentaries.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Kukai, the founder of the sect, emphasized Hannya Shingyo, various priests of this sect have written commentaries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>このうち、特に戦後の日本における高神覚昇・宮坂宥洪などの著作が知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among those, the works by Kakusho TAKAGAMI, Yuko MIYASAKA and others in the postwar period in Japan are famous.</e>
<cmt>高神覚昇→kotobank、宮坂宥洪→http://www.shunjusha.co.jp/writer/27320/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among those, the works by Kakusho TAKAGAMI, Yuko MIYASAKA and others in the postwar period of Japan are well known.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among those, the works by Kakusho TAKAGAMI, Yuko MIYASAKA and others in the postwar period of Japan are well known.</e>
<cmt>スペース修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>高神の『般若心経講義』は戦前、NHKラジオ放送で行われたものであり、当時好評を博した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Lecture on Hannya Shingyo&quot; by TAKAGAMI, which was broadcasted via NHK radio in prewar days, was very popular at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Lecture on Hannya Shingyo&quot; by TAKAGAMI, which was broadcasted via NHK radio in the prewar days, was very popular at that time.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Lecture on Hannya Shingyo&quot; by TAKAGAMI, which was broadcasted via NHK radio in the prewar days, was very popular at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>現代日本語で書かれた解釈書としては非常に評価の高いものであり、異なる宗派の僧侶や仏教学者からも評価されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It receives a high evaluation among the commentaries written in modern Japanese, and receives a high evaluation from priests of other sects and scholars as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered very highly among the commentaries written in modern Japanese, and it receives high praise from scholars and priests of other sects.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered very highly among the commentaries written in modern Japanese, and it receives high praise from scholars and priests of other sects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="50">
<j>浄土宗では、食事等の際に唱える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Jodo Shu sect it is recited at the time of having meals and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Jodo Shu sect it is recited at mealtime and so on.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Jodo Shu sect it is recited at mealtime and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="51">
<j>時宗では、神社参拝及び本山での朝の勤行の後に熊野大社の御霊を祀る神棚に向かい三唱することが必須となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Jishu sect it is necessary to recite it three times in front of shelf of gods which enshrines the soul of Kumano Taisha Shrine after a worship to shrine and morning devotions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Jishu sect it is necessary to recite it three times in front of the shelf of gods that enshrines the soul of Kumano Taisha Shrine after worship of the shrine and morning devotions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Jishu sect it is necessary to recite it three times in front of the shelf of gods that enshrines the soul of Kumano Taisha Shrine after worship of the shrine and morning devotions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>日用に用いる場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also used daily in some cases.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also used daily in some cases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also used daily in some cases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="53">
<j>臨済宗では、日用経典の1つとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rinzai sect regareds it as one of the daily Buddhist sutras.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Rinzai sect regards it as one of the daily Buddhist sutras.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Rinzai sect regards it as one of the daily Buddhist sutras.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>また、一休・盤珪・白隠が解釈を行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Ikkyu, Bankei and Hakuin made interpretations.</e>
<cmt>盤珪→kotobank、白隠→kotobank</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, Ikkyu, Bankei and Hakuin have made interpretations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, Ikkyu, Bankei and Hakuin have made interpretations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>般若心経とは自分の心の本来の姿を現した経典であるという主張を行うことが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is often insisted that Hannya Shingyo is a Buddhist sutra which reveals the primary figure of one&apos;s heart.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is often asserted that Hannya Shingyo is a Buddhist sutra that reveals the primary figure of one&apos;s heart.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is often asserted that Hannya Shingyo is a Buddhist sutra that reveals the primary figure of one&apos;s heart.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="56">
<j>曹洞宗では、日用経典の1つとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soto sect regards it as one of the daily Buddhist sutras.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Soto sect regards it as one of the daily Buddhist sutras.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Soto sect regards it as one of the daily Buddhist sutras.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>開祖道元が解釈しているほか、天桂の「観自在菩薩とは汝自身である」という解釈が有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the founder Dogen interpreted it, Tenkei&apos;s interpretation &apos;Kanjizai Bosatsu is yourself&apos; is famous.</e>
<cmt>道元→Yahoo辞書、天桂→kotobank</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the founder Dogen interpreted it, Tenkei&apos;s interpretation &apos;Kanjizai Bosatsu is yourself&apos; is famous.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the founder Dogen interpreted it, Tenkei&apos;s interpretation &apos;Kanjizai Bosatsu is yourself&apos; is famous.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>また、良寛・種田山頭火など般若心経の実践に取り組んだ僧も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition many priests such as Ryokan and Santoka TANEDA tried to implement Hannya Shingyo.</e>
<cmt>種田山頭火→kotobank</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, many priests such as Ryokan and Santoka TANEDA have tried to implement Hannya Shingyo.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, many priests such as Ryokan and Santoka TANEDA have tried to implement Hannya Shingyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>良寛は般若心経の大量の写経を残しており、種田は般若心経を俳句に読み込んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryokan left a large amount of manuscripts of Hannya Shingyo and TANEDA made haiku from Hannya Shingyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryokan left numerous manuscripts of the Hannya Shingyo, and TANEDA made haiku from the Hannya Shingyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryokan left numerous manuscripts of the Hannya Shingyo, and TANEDA made haiku from the Hannya Shingyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="60">
<j>修験道では、修験者（山伏などの行者）が「行」を行う際に唱える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Shugen-do mountaineering ascetic (practitioners such as itinerant Buddhist monk) recites when they practice.</e>
<cmt>修験者→Webster&apos;s Online Dictionary、山伏→Webster&apos;s Online Dictionary、行者→英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Shugen-do mountaineering ascetic, practitioners (such as itinerant Buddhist monks) recite it when they practice.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Shugen-do mountaineering ascetic, practitioners (such as itinerant Buddhist monks) recite it when they practice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="61">
<j>神道でも唱えるところがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Shinto some sects recite it.</e>
<cmt>神道→Webster&apos;s Online Dictionary</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Shinto religion, some sects recite it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Shinto religion, some sects recite it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>神社（神前）で読誦の際は、冒頭の「仏説」を読まずに、「摩訶」から読む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When it is read and recited in shrine (in front of gods), it is read from &apos;Maka&apos; without reading &apos;Bussetsu&apos; of the beginning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When it is read and recited in the shrine (in front of the gods), it is read from &apos;Maka&apos; without reading &apos;Bussetsu&apos; at the beginning.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When it is read and recited in the shrine (in front of the gods), it is read from &apos;Maka&apos; without reading &apos;Bussetsu&apos; at the beginning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>在家信者</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lay people</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lay people</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lay people</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="63">
<j>一般の人々にとっては、「空」を説く経典と言うより、むしろ、「霊験あらたかな真言」の経典として受け止められており、一部には悪霊の力を「空ずる」という解釈もされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For ordinary people it is regarded as a Buddhist sutra of &apos;miracle-working mantra&apos; rather than a Buddhist sutra which preaches &apos;Ku,&apos; and some people interpret that it &apos;vanishes (空ずる)&apos; the power of evil spirit.</e>
<cmt>真言→英辞郎 on the WEB、空ずる→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For ordinary people it is regarded as a Buddhist sutra of &apos;miracle-working mantra&apos; instead of a Buddhist sutra that preaches &apos;Ku,&apos; and some people interpret that it &apos;erases (空ずる),&apos; the power of evil spirits.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For ordinary people it is regarded as a Buddhist sutra of &apos;miracle-working mantra&apos; instead of a Buddhist sutra that preaches &apos;Ku,&apos; and some people interpret that it &apos;erases (空ずる)&apos; the power of evil spirits.</e>
<cmt>不要なコンマを取りました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>古くから般若心経の利益で病気が治るという信仰があり、既に日本霊異記にその説話が残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an old faith that Hannya Shingyo benefits for recovery from illness, which is seen in Nihon Ryoiki.</e>
<cmt>日本霊異記→kotobank</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an old belief that Hannya Shingyo benefits the recovery from illness, which is seen in &quot;Nihon Ryoiki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an old belief that Hannya Shingyo benefits the recovery from illness, which is seen in &quot;Nihon Ryoiki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>お守りとして所持したり、病気になったときに写経して平癒を祈願したりした人が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many people carried it as a charm or hand-copied it in order to pray a recovery from illness.</e>
<cmt>写経→Webster&apos;s Online Dictionary</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many people carried it as a charm or hand-copied it in order to pray for recovery from illness.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many people carried it as a charm or hand-copied it in order to pray for recovery from illness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="66">
<j>また、神社で読誦された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it was recited in shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, it was recited at shrines.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, it was recited at shrines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>亀戸天満宮で塙保己一が般若心経を読んで『群書類従』の成功を祈願したことは有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is famous that Hokiichi HANIWA read Hannya Shingyo at Kameido Temmangu Shrine and prayed for the success of &quot;Gunsho Riju.&quot;</e>
<cmt>亀戸天満宮→http://kameidotenjin.or.jp/、塙保己一→kotobank、群書類従→kotobank</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is well known that Hokiichi HANIWA read Hannya Shingyo at Kameido Temmangu Shrine and prayed for the success of &quot;Gunsho Riju.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is well known that Hokiichi HANIWA read Hannya Shingyo at Kameido Temmangu Shrine and prayed for the success of &quot;Gunsho Ruiju.&quot;</e>
<cmt>riju→ruiju</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="68">
<j>江戸時代には、文字を読めない層のために、内容を絵に表した絵心経も製作された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Edo Period, E-shin-gyo, Heart Sutra in Picture Version, was produced for illiteracy.</e>
<cmt>江戸時代→英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo period, E-shin-gyo (Heart Sutra in Picture Version), was produced for illiterates.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period, E-shin-gyo (Heart Sutra in Picture Version), was produced for illiterates.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>百瀬明治『般若心経の謎』によれば、これは元禄年間に現在の岩手県二戸郡の八幡源右衛門という人が文字の読めない人向けに創作した後、随筆によって諸国に伝播されブームとなったものであり、文字か読める人たちの間でも判じ物的に楽しまれたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Hannyashin-gyo no Nazo&quot; written by Meiji MOMOSE, this was created by Genemon YAWATA in Ninohe-gun Iwate Prefecture from 1688 to 1703 for illiteracy and became popular in various provinces through essay, and even literacy people enjoyed it as a kind of rebus.</e>
<cmt>百瀬明治→http://www.honganjifoundation.org/jouen/kangaku/sinsingaku/kousi.html、元禄年間→http://homepage2.nifty.com/mitamond/nenpyo/nenpyo_genroku.htm、岩手県二戸郡→http://www.post.japanpost.jp/cgi-zip/zipcode.php?pref=3&amp;city=1035240</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Hannyashin-gyo no Nazo,&quot; written by Meiji MOMOSE, this was created by Genemon YAWATA in Ninohe-gun, Iwate Prefecture from 1688 to 1703 for the sake of illiterates and became popular in various provinces through essays, and even literate people enjoyed it as a kind of rebus.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Hannyashin-gyo no Nazo,&quot; written by Meiji MOMOSE, this was created by Genemon YAWATA in Ninohe-gun, Iwate Prefecture from 1688 to 1703 for the sake of illiterates and became popular in various provinces through essays, and even literate people enjoyed it as a kind of rebus.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="70">
<j>現在では写経の際によく筆写される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is often hand-copied at the same time of the practice of manuscripts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is often hand-copied concurrently with the practice of manuscripts.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is often hand-copied concurrently with the practice of manuscripts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>また手拭いなどにも印刷され、極めて普及している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also printed on towels and is very common.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also printed on towels and is very common.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also printed on towels and is very common.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="72">
<j>解釈書も大量に出版されており、中には般若心経の原意を取り違えたものさえあり、仏教学者が警鐘を鳴らしているような状態である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although a large amount of commentaries have been published, some of them make a mistake to interpret the original intension of Hannya Shingyo, so that Buddhism scholars sound the alarm.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although numerous commentaries have been published, some of them make the mistake of interpreting the original intension of Hannya Shingyo, so that Buddhist scholars sound the alarm.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although numerous commentaries have been published, some of them make the mistake of interpreting the original intension of Hannya Shingyo, so that Buddhist scholars sound the alarm.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>現代の主な翻訳及び解説としては、サンスクリット原文からの翻訳である中村元・紀野一義訳の岩波文庫本、高神覚昇の『般若心経講義』、また臨済宗の僧侶の立場から解釈した松原泰道の『般若心経入門』などがあり、それぞれ版を重ねて何れも文庫本として手軽に入手できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the major translation and commentary in modern times, a book of Iwanami-bunko, a translation from original Sanskrit by Hajime NAKAMURA and Kazuyoshi KINO, &quot;Lecture on Hannya Shingyo&quot; written by Kakusho TAKAGAMI and &quot;Hannyashin-gyo Nyumon&quot; written by Taido MATSUBARA, which interprets from the viewpoint of priest of Rinzai sect are published and reprinted many times so that their paperback editions are easily obtainable.</e>
<cmt>紀野一義→http://www.jmca.jp/prod/teacher/1236.html、松原泰道→kotobank</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the major translation and commentary in modern times, a book of Iwanami-bunko, a translation from the original Sanskrit by Hajime NAKAMURA and Kazuyoshi KINO, &quot;Lecture on Hannya Shingyo,&quot; written by Kakusho TAKAGAMI and &quot;Hannyashin-gyo Nyumon,&quot; written by Taido MATSUBARA, which interprets from the viewpoint of a priest of the Rinzai sect, have been published and reprinted many times so that their paperback editions are easily obtainable.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the major translation and commentary in modern times, a book of Iwanami-bunko, a translation from the original Sanskrit by Hajime NAKAMURA and Kazuyoshi KINO, &quot;Lecture on Hannya Shingyo,&quot; written by Kakusho TAKAGAMI and &quot;Hannyashin-gyo Nyumon,&quot; written by Taido MATSUBARA, which interprets from the viewpoint of a priest of the Rinzai sect, have been published and reprinted many times so that their paperback editions are easily obtainable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="74">
<j>また遊びに近いものとしてみうらじゅんがアウトドア般若心経を提唱している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, Jun MIURA proposed outdoor Hannya Shingyo, which is near to a pleasure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, Jun MIURA proposed outdoor Hannya Shingyo, which is near to pleasure.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, Jun MIURA proposed outdoor Hannya Shingyo, which is near to pleasure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 PrajnaParamita(id:115669), JAnDbot(id:66507), Lobbyonce(id:195963), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Eskimbot(id:29676), 翰林学士(id:79905), Uraios(id:72687), Johncapistrano(id:969), Kurz(id:1601), 麓(id:77268), Yamakazudd51(id:34319), Goki(id:7107), Rei-bot(id:94097), くっちゃめ(id:86793), &quot;Ｄ&quot;(id:30901), T. Nakamura(id:696), 無空(id:17049), 赤鉛筆(id:2434), 白糸(id:47025), ウィキ豊(id:82961), Anonymouss(id:3225), デーモン博士(id:99293), Soten(id:27409), Izayohi(id:13095), 羊3(id:192108), Youtetsu(id:7844), たね(id:10372), 優曇華(id:6461), Kahusi(id:1523), Tomos(id:10), Authority(id:10737), 彩華1226(id:64711), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), Baudda(id:3312), SuisuiBot(id:10165), NShunsuke(id:79004), Miya(id:1881), Ash(id:15625), Baffclan(id:499), 羊鶴(id:7557), ドットコム(id:3360), LeonardoRob0t(id:25875), SieBot(id:126695), 空(id:3256), Ziksy(id:84091), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>