<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>灌頂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanjo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanjo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanjo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>灌頂（かんじょう）とは、主に密教で行う、頭頂に水を灌ぎ、正統な継承者とする為の儀式。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanjo is a ceremony mainly celebrated in esoteric Buddhism, in which a legitimate successor is declared by pouring water over top of head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanjo is a ceremony mainly celebrated in esoteric Buddhism, in which a legitimate successor is declared by pouring water over the top of the head.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanjo is a ceremony mainly celebrated in Esoteric Buddhism, in which a legitimate successor is declared by pouring water over the top of the head.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>元々は天竺といわれたインドで王の即位や立太子での風習である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It originated as a ceremony that celebrated enthronement of the kind or investiture of the Crown Prince in India, which used to be called Tenjiku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It originated as a ceremony that celebrated enthronement of the kind or investiture of the Crown Prince in India, which used to be called Tenjiku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It originated as a ceremony that celebrated enthronement of the kind or investiture of the Crown Prince in India, which used to be called Tenjiku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>釈迦の誕生日を祝う祭りである灌仏会もこれの一例であったが、密教において複雑化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Example includes Kanbutsu-e, which is a ceremony that commemorates Buddha&apos;s birthday; esoteric Buddhism complicated the ceremony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Examples includes Kanbutsu-e, which is a ceremony that commemorates Buddha&apos;s birthday; esoteric Buddhism complicated the ceremony.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Examples includes Kanbutsu-e, which is a ceremony that commemorates Buddha&apos;s birthday; Esoteric Buddhism complicated the ceremony.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>数種類あり、場合によって使い分ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are a variety of ceremonies that are used on different occasions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are a variety of ceremonies that are used on different occasions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are a variety of ceremonies that are used on different occasions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>日本では、805年に最澄が高雄山の神護寺で初めて灌頂を行ったといわれる（最澄は渡唐の際に龍興寺の順暁から秘密灌頂を受け、後年、空海の将来した金剛界・胎蔵界の灌頂も受けた）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, it is believed that Saicho conducted the first Kanjo at Jingo-ji Temple at Mt Takao in 805 (Saicho received the teachings of Himitsu-kanjo from Jungyo at Ryuko-ji Temple when he visited Tang, and later received Kanjo in Kongokai (Diamond Realm) and Taizokai (Womb Realm) that were brought from Kukai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, it is believed that Saicho conducted the first Kanjo at Jingo-ji Temple at Mt Takao in 805 (Saicho received the teachings of Himitsu-kanjo from Jungyo at Ryuko-ji Temple when he visited Tang, and later received Kanjo in Kongokai (Diamond Realm) and Taizokai (Womb Realm) that were brought from Kukai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, it is believed that Saicho conducted the first Kanjo at Jingo-ji Temple at Mt. Takao in 805 (Saicho received the teachings of Himitsu (secret) kanjo from Jungyo at Ryuko-ji Temple when he visited Tang, and later received Kanjo in Kongokai (Diamond Realm) and Taizokai (Womb Realm) that were brought from Kukai.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>灌頂の種類は以下の通り。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The types of Kanjo are described below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The types of Kanjo are described below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The types of Kanjo are described below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>結縁灌頂（けちえんかんじょう）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kechien-kanjo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kechien-kanjo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kechien-kanjo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>出家して、どの仏に守り本尊となってもらうかを決める儀式。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this type of Kanjo, a person who enters priesthood chooses his/her guardian deity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this type of Kanjo, a person who enters priesthood chooses his/her guardian deity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this type of Kanjo, a person who enters priesthood chooses his or her guardian deity.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>投華得仏（とうけとくぶつ）といい、目隠しをして曼荼羅の上に華を投げ、華の落ちた所の仏と結縁する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It features Toke Tokubutsu, in which a blindfolded new initiate throws a flower onto mandala to choose his/her tutelary deity depending on where the flower lands; the new initiate connects with the deity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It features Toke Tokubutsu, in which a blindfolded new initiate throws a flower onto mandala to choose his/her tutelary deity depending on where the flower lands; the new initiate connects with the deity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It features Toke Tokubutsu, in which a blindfolded new initiate throws a flower onto mandala to choose his or her tutelary god depending on where the flower lands; the new initiate connects with the god.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>曼荼羅には鬼神や羅刹などもあるが、その場合でも、祀り方などや儀式を伝授される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The mandala includes Kijin (fierce god) and rakshasa (type of evil spirit); new initiates learn how to worship and celebrate those deities in case they select them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The mandala includes Kijin (fierce god) and rakshasa (type of evil spirit). New initiates learn how to worship and celebrate those deities in case they select them.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The mandala includes Kijin (fierce god) and rakshasa (type of evil spirit) but new initiates learn how to worship and celebrate those gods in case they select them.</e>
<cmt>1文にし表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>空海は3度これを行い3度とも大日如来の上に落ちた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kukai conducted the ceremony three times; his flowers always fell on Dainichi Nyorai (Mahavairocana).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kukai conducted the ceremony three times; his flowers always fell on Dainichi Nyorai (Mahavairocana).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kukai conducted the ceremony three times; his flowers always fell on Dainichi Nyorai (Mahavairocana).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>受明灌頂（じゅみょうかんじょう）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jumyo-kanjo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jumyo-kanjo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jumyo-kanjo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>修行して密教を深く学ぼうとする人に対して行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is conducted for people who are determined to practice and learn profound esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is conducted for people who are determined to practice and learn profound esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is conducted for people who are determined to practice and learn profound Esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>仏と縁を結ぶ入門的な結縁灌頂と違い、弟子としての資格を得る灌頂なので、弟子灌頂とも言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike Kechien-kanjo, which is an introductory ceremony that connects people with deities, Jumyo-kanjo is a ceremony that certifies disciples; it is also known as Deshi-kanjo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike Kechien-kanjo, which is an introductory ceremony that connects people with deities, Jumyo-kanjo is a ceremony that certifies disciples; it is also known as Deshi-kanjo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike Kechien-kanjo, which is an introductory ceremony that connects people with gods, Jumyo-kanjo is a ceremony that certifies disciples; it is also known as Deshi (disciple) kanjo.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>伝法灌頂（でんぼうかんじょう）、金胎両部伝法灌頂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Denpo-kanjo, Kintai-ryobu denpo-kanjo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Denpo-kanjo, Kintai-ryobu denpo-kanjo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Denpo-kanjo, Kintai-ryobu denpo-kanjo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>阿闍梨という指導者の位を授ける灌頂。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this type of Kanjo, the title of Ajari (a master in esoteric Buddhism; a high priest) is given.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this type of Kanjo, the title of Ajari (a master in esoteric Buddhism; a high priest) is given.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this type of Kanjo, the title of Ajari (a master in Esoteric Buddhism; a high priest) is given.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>四度加行（しどけぎょう）という密教の修行を終えた人のみが受けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only the priests who completed an esoteric Buddhism practice called shidokegyo (four trainings) are entitled to the ceremony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only the priests who have completed an esoteric Buddhism practice called shidokegyo (four trainings) are entitled to the ceremony.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only the priests who have completed an Esoteric Buddhism practice called shidokegyo (four trainings) are entitled to the ceremony.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>ここで密教の奥義が伝授され、弟子を持つことを許される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the ceremony, priests receive esoteric points of esoteric Buddhism and are permitted to have disciples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the ceremony, priests receive esoteric points of esoteric Buddhism and are permitted to have disciples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the ceremony, priests receive esoteric points of Esoteric Buddhism and are permitted to have disciples.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>また仏典だけに捉われず、口伝や仏意などを以って弟子を指導することができ、またさらには正式に一宗一派を開くことが出来るともされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Priests are allowed to teach their disciples by using Buddhist scriptures as well as oral instruction and bucchi; they are also allowed to officially begin a new school and a new sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Priests are allowed to teach their disciples by using Buddhist scriptures as well as oral instruction and bucchi. They are also allowed to officially begin a new school and a new sect.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Priests are allowed to teach their disciples by using Buddhist scriptures as well as oral instruction and the Buddha&apos;s intention and they are also allowed to officially begin a new school and a new sect.</e>
<cmt>1文にし、用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>阿闍梨灌頂、または受職灌頂ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also known as Ajari-kanjo or Jushoku-kanjo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also known as Ajari-kanjo or Jushoku-kanjo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also known as Ajari-kanjo or Jushoku-kanjo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>また、日本では鎌倉時代から幕末にかけて天皇の即位式には「即位灌頂」という行事が行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan used to conduct &apos;Sokui-Kanjo&apos; to celebrate enthronement of the emperor between the Kamakura Period and the end of Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan used to conduct &apos;Sokui-Kanjo&apos; to celebrate enthronement of the emperor between the Kamakura Period and the end of Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan used to conduct &apos;Sokui-Kanjo&apos; to celebrate enthronement of the emperor between the Kamakura period and the end of Edo period.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>ちなみに灌頂を受けたのは、後鳥羽院・後深草院の名が記録されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the record, Gotoba-in and Gofukakusa-in also received Kanjo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the record, Gotoba-in and Gofukakusa-in also received Kanjo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the record, Gotobain and Gofukakusain also received Kanjo.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), พริกขี้หนู(id:131976), Okt(id:18107), Boca samba(id:137526), Chi-Ham(id:143515), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Vanvan(id:18481), R28Bot(id:177951), Charenji(id:7908), 水野白楓(id:22811), FlaBot(id:30804), ウィキ豊(id:82961), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>