<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>心敬</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinkei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinkei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinkei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>心敬（しんけい、1406年（応永3年） - 1475年5月20日（文明 (日本)7年4月16日 (旧暦)））は、室町時代中期の天台宗の僧、連歌師である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinkei (born in 1406, birth date unknown - May 20, 1475) was a Buddhist monk of the Tendai sect and also a renga poet (linked-verse poet) who lived in the middle of the Muromachi era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinkei (born in 1406, birth date unknown - May 20, 1475) was a Buddhist monk of the Tendai sect and also a renga poet (linked-verse poet) who lived in the middle of the Muromachi era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinkei (1406 - May 29, 1475) was a Buddhist priest of the Tendai Sect and also a renga poet (linked-verse poet) in the middle of the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>表記を他と合わせ、用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>連海、心恵、心教ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also called Renkai, Shinkei (using a different set of Chinese characters), or Shinkyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also called Renkai, Shinkei (using a different set of Chinese characters), or Shinkyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also called Renkai, Shinkei (using a different set of Chinese characters, 心恵), or Shinkyo.</e>
<cmt>漢字を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>紀伊国に生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Kii Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Kii Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Kii Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>幼いときに出家し、比叡山で修行。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He entered the priesthood when he was still young and trained himself at Hiei-zan Mountain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He entered the priesthood when he was still young and trained himself at Hiei-zan Mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He entered the priesthood when he was still young and trained himself on Mt. Hiei.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>44あるいは45歳のころ園城寺仏地院に住し、のち京都清水寺付近の十住心院の住持となり、権大僧都、法印に叙せられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He lived at the Onjo-ji Bucchi-in Temple when he was 44 or 45 years old, became the chief priest of Jujushin-in near Kiyomizu-dera Temple in Kyoto, became gon daisozu (junior prelate), and then he was finally appointed to hoin, which was the highest-ranked priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He lived at the Onjo-ji Bucchi-in Temple when he was 44 or 45 years old, became the chief priest of Jujushin-in near Kiyomizu-dera Temple in Kyoto, became gon daisozu (junior prelate), and then he was finally appointed to hoin, which was the highest-ranked priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He lived at the Butchiin of Onjo-ji Temple when he was 44 or 45 years old, assumed the position of the chief priest of Jujushinin Temple near Kiyomizu-dera Temple in Kyoto, became Gon Daisozu (Associate grade of Daisojo (the highest grade that can be held by one who has reached the second highest rank in the hierarchy of Buddhist priests)), and then he was finally appointed to Hoin (the highest rank in the hierarchy of Buddhist priests).</e>
<cmt>用語を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>正徹に師事して冷泉派の歌人として知られる一方、1433年（永享5年）、「北野社万句」の座に列するなど、連歌作者として次第に時代を代表する存在となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While he studied under another Buddhist monk called Shotetsu and was known as a poet of the Reizei school, he gradually became a renga poet of the time by for example attending the &apos;Kitano-sha (shrine) manku (10,000 linked verses)&apos; event in 1433.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While he studied under another Buddhist monk called Shotetsu and was known as a poet of the Reizei school, he gradually became a renga poet of the time by for example attending the &apos;Kitano-sha (shrine) manku (10,000 linked verses)&apos; event in 1433.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While he studied under another Buddhist priest called Shotetsu and was known as a poet of the Reizei School, he gradually became a renga poet of the time by for example attending the &apos;Kitano-sha manku&apos; (10,000 linked verses event at Kitano-jinja Shrine) in 1433.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>作風は、正徹から受け継いだ新古今風を基礎に、表現対象の凝視と表現主体の沈潜とを重視する独特のもので、「ひえやせたる」風趣のうちに得意な感覚の冴え方を示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on the shin-kokin (traditional, picturesque, and narrative) taste learned from Shotetsu, Shinkei&apos;s work was unique in the way that he placed the importance on close examination of poem subjects and self-preoccupation in poem themes, exhibiting his refined senses in his &apos;hieyasetaru (simple and natural)&quot; poem style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on the shin-kokin (traditional, picturesque, and narrative) taste learned from Shotetsu, Shinkei&apos;s work was unique in the way that he placed the importance on close examination of poem subjects and self-preoccupation in poem themes, exhibiting his refined senses in his &apos;hieyasetaru (simple and natural)&quot; poem style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on the Shinkon style (tone of poems seen in &quot;New Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese poetry&quot;) learned from Shotetsu, Shinkei&apos;s work was unique in the way that he placed the importance on close examination of poem subjects and self-preoccupation in poem themes, exhibiting his refined senses in his &apos;hieyasetaru&apos; (simple and natural) poem style.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>和歌及び連歌の修行を仏道の修行と究極的に同一視する連歌論は、主著である『ささめごと』のほか『老のくり言』『ひとり言』(1468年)などに強調され、次代の宗祇、猪苗代兼載、侘び茶の村田珠光ら茶人にも影響を与える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to his renga theory, waka (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables) and renga training, and Buddhism training were ultimately the same thing, and this theory was emphasized in his important work called &quot;Sasamegoto&quot; as well as other works such as &quot;Oi-no-kurigoto,&quot; and &quot;Hitorigoto&quot; (1468), and also influenced next-generation renga poets such as Sogi and Kensai INAWASHIRO and a master of tea ceremony Juko MURATA who practiced wabicha (literally, &quot;poverty tea style&quot;; known as the tea ceremony).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to his renga theory, waka (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables) and renga training, and Buddhism training were ultimately the same thing, and this theory was emphasized in his important work called &quot;Sasamegoto&quot; as well as other works such as &quot;Oi-no-kurigoto,&quot; and &quot;Hitorigoto&quot; (1468), and also influenced next-generation renga poets such as Sogi and Kensai INAWASHIRO and a master of tea ceremony Juko MURATA who practiced wabicha (literally, &quot;poverty tea style&quot;; known as the tea ceremony).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to his renga theory, waka (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables) and renga training, and Buddhism training were ultimately the same thing, and this theory was emphasized in his important work called &quot;Sasamegoto&quot; (Murmurings) as well as other works such as &quot;Oinokurigoto&quot; (Old man&apos;s prattle), and &quot;Hitorigoto&quot; (Solitary ramblings) (1468), and also influenced next-generation renga poets such as Sogi and Kensai INAWASHIRO and a master of tea ceremony Juko MURATA who practiced wabicha (literally, &quot;poverty tea style&quot;; known as the tea ceremony).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>戦乱を避けて晩年を関東で過ごし、70歳で死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Avoiding wars, he spent later stages of his life in Kanto and died at the age of 70.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Avoiding wars, he spent the later stages of his life in Kanto and died at the age of 70.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Avoiding wars, he spent the later stages of his life in Kanto and died at the age of 70.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>連歌集・歌集として『心玉集』、『心敬僧都十体和歌』などがあるほか、宗祇編『竹林抄』に入集する連歌七賢の一人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While he compiled rengashu (renga collections) and kashu (poem collections) such as &quot;Shingyoku-shu&quot; and &quot;Shinkei-sozu Jittai-waka,&quot; he was also one of the renga shichiken (seven sages of renga) whose poems were included in &quot;Chikurinsho (Bamboo Grove Notes) compiled by Sogi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While he compiled rengashu (renga collections) and kashu (poem collections) such as &quot;Shingyoku-shu&quot; and &quot;Shinkei-sozu Jittai-waka,&quot; he was also one of the renga shichiken (seven sages of renga) whose poems were included in &quot;Chikurinsho (Bamboo Grove Notes) compiled by Sogi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While he compiled rengashu (renga collections) and kashu (poem collections) such as &quot;Shingyokushu&quot; (New gems collection) and &quot;Shinkei Sozu Juttai Waka&quot; (Priest Shinkei&apos;s Waka in Ten Style), he was also one of the renga shichiken (seven sages of renga) whose poems were included in &quot;Chikurinsho&quot; (Bamboo Grove Notes) compiled by Sogi.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>『新撰菟玖波集』に最多数の入集を見る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shinsen Tsukubashu (the newly-selected Tsukubashu)&quot; included the largest number of his poems.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shinsen Tsukubashu (the newly-selected Tsukubashu)&quot; included the largest number of his poems.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shinsen Tsukubashu&quot; (the newly-selected Tsukubashu) included the largest number of his poems.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), Oxhop(id:2551), たね(id:10372), 代言人(id:33675), Kstigarbha(id:13376), R28Bot(id:177951), Urania(id:7213), Cprobot(id:97843), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>