<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>真盛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinsei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinsei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinsei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>真盛（しんせい、嘉吉3年1月28日 (旧暦)（1443年2月27日） - 明応4年2月30日 (旧暦)（1495年3月26日））は、戦国時代の天台宗の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinsei (January 28, 1443 (old lunar calendar) (March 8, 1443) - February 30, 1495 (old lunar calendar) (April 4, 1495)) was a priest of the Tendai sect in the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinsei (January 28, 1443 - old lunar calendar) (March 8, 1443 - February 30, 1495 - old lunar calendar (April 4, 1495) was a priest of the Tendai sect during the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinsei (March 8, 1443 - - April 4, 1495) was a priest of the Tendai sect during the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦のみの記載としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>諡号は円戒国師・慈摂大師。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His shigo (posthumous title) was Enkai Kokushi (the Most Reverend Priest, Enkai) and Jisetsu Daishi (the Great Teacher, Jisetsu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His shigo (posthumous title) was Enkai Kokushi (the Most Reverend Priest, Enkai) and Jisetsu Daishi (the Great Teacher, Jisetsu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His shigo (posthumous title) was Enkai Kokushi (the Most Reverend Priest, Enkai) and Jisetsu Daishi (the Great Teacher, Jisetsu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>伊勢国の出身で、父は小泉左近尉藤能。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He came from Ise Province and his father was KOIZUMI Sakon no jo Fujiyoshi (Lieutenant of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards, Fujiyoshi KOIZUMI).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He came from Ise Province and his father was KOIZUMI Sakon no jo Fujiyoshi (Lieutenant of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards, Fujiyoshi KOIZUMI).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He came from Ise Province and his father was KOIZUMI Sakon no jo Fujiyoshi (Lieutenant of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards, Fujiyoshi KOIZUMI).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>天台宗真盛派（現在の天台真盛宗）の祖。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinsei is the founder of the Shinsei School of Tendai Sect (present-day Tendai Shinsei sect).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinsei is the founder of the Shinsei School of the Tendai Sect (present-day Tendai Shinsei sect).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinsei is the founder of the Shinsei School of the Tendai Sect (present-day Tendai Shinsei sect).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>比叡山西塔の慶秀に師事し、天台宗の教学を学んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He studied learning of religious doctrines under Keishu at the Saito (Western section) of Mt. Hiei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He studied learning of religious doctrines under Keishu at the Saito (Western section) of Mt. Hiei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He studied learning of religious doctrines under Keishu at the Saito (Western section) of Mt. Hiei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その後、同所にある黒谷青龍寺に隠遁し、「往生要集」に拠り称名念仏を唱えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later he retired in Kurotani Seiryu-ji Temple at the Saito (Western section) of Mt. Hiei where he chanted the Invocation of the Buddha&apos;s Name based on &quot;Ojoyoshu (The Essentials of Salvation).&quot;</e>
<cmt>原文は「青龍寺 (大津市坂本)」でしたがWeb上では「黒谷青龍寺」でしたので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later he retired in Kurotani Seiryu-ji Temple at the Saito (Western section) of Mt. Hiei where he chanted the Invocation of Buddha&apos;s Name based on &quot;Ojoyoshu (The Essentials of Salvation).&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later he retired in Kurotani Seiryu-ji Temple at the Saito of Mt. Hiei where he chanted the Invocation of Buddha&apos;s Name based on &apos;Ojoyoshu&apos; (The Essentials of Salvation).</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。西塔　既出単語のため、補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>戒律と称名念仏の一致を唱え、宮中や公家・女官・守護などに無欲と慈悲を説いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He preached the agreement between the precepts of Buddhism and the Invocation of the Buddha&apos;s Name, and lectured on unselfishness and mercy at the Imperial court and for court nobles and ladies, and provincial constables.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He preached the agreement between the precepts of Buddhism and the Invocation of Buddha&apos;s Name, and lectured on unselfishness and mercy at the Imperial court and for court nobles and ladies, and provincial constables.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He preached the agreement between the precepts of Buddhism and the Invocation of Buddha&apos;s Name, and lectured on unselfishness and mercy at the Imperial Court and for court nobles and ladies, and provincial constables.</e>
<cmt>Imperial Court としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>かつて良源や源信などが住み、円観が円頓戒の本寺としたこともある近江国坂本の西教寺を再興して、天台宗真盛派の本寺とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He restored Saikyo-ji Temple in Sakamoto, Omi Province where Ryogen and Genshin once lived and Enkan designated as the main temple for Endonkai (Perfect and Sudden Precepts), and made the Saikyo-ji as the main temple of the Shinsei School of Tendai Sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He restored Saikyo-ji Temple in Sakamoto, Omi Province where Ryogen and Genshin once lived and Enkan designated as the main temple for Endonkai (Perfect and Sudden Precepts), and made the Saikyo-ji as the main temple of the Shinsei School of Tendai Sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He restored Saikyo-ji Temple in Sakamoto, Omi Province where Ryogen and Genshin once lived and which Enkan once designated as the main temple for Endonkai (Perfect and Sudden Precepts), and made it as the main temple of the Shinsei School of Tendai Sect.</e>
<cmt>Saikyo-ji Temple としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mnd(id:15140), Soudyui(id:213462), Ko-ken(id:49348), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), 663highland(id:18755), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>