<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>尊長</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soncho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soncho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soncho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>尊長（そんちょう、生年未詳 - 安貞元年（1227年））は鎌倉時代初期の僧侶。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soncho (year of birth unknown-1227) is a Buddhist monk in the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soncho (year of birth unknown-1227) is a Buddhist monk in the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soncho (year of birth unknown - 1227) is a Buddhist monk in the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>中納言一条能保の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the child of Yoshiyasu ICHIJO, Chunagon (Middle Counselor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the child of Yoshiyasu ICHIJO, Chunagon (Middle Counselor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the child of Yoshiyasu ICHIJO, Chunagon (vice-councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>(vice-councilor of state)　用語統一リストより訂正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>異母兄弟に一条高能、一条信能、一条実雅らがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takayoshi ICHIJO, Nobuyoshi ICHIJO, and Sanemasa ICHIJO numbered among his paternal half-brothers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takayoshi ICHIJO, Nobuyoshi ICHIJO, and Sanemasa ICHIJO numbered among his paternal half-brothers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takayoshi ICHIJO, Nobuyoshi ICHIJO, and Sanemasa ICHIJO numbered among his paternal half-brothers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>法印、法勝寺執行、また出羽国出羽三山総長吏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soncho was hoin (a priest of the highest rank in the highest managerial position), the shigyo (executor) of Hosho-ji Temple, and Dewa no kuni Dewasanzan sochori (chief priest of the Three Sacred Mountains in Dewa Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soncho was hoin (a priest of the highest rank in the highest managerial position), the shigyo (executor) of Hosho-ji Temple, and Dewa no kuni Dewasanzan sochori (chief priest of the Three Sacred Mountains in Dewa Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soncho was hoin (a priest of the highest rank in the highest managerial position), the shigyo (executor) of Hosho-ji Temple, and Dewa no kuni Dewasanzan sochori (chief priest of the Three Sacred Mountains in Dewa Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>通称は二位法印。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was commonly known as &apos;Nii no Hoin.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was commonly known as &apos;Nii no Hoin.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was commonly known as &apos;Nii no Hoin.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>延暦寺の僧であったが、その智謀と武芸を認められ、後鳥羽上皇の側近となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thanks to his intelligence and martial competency, he was promoted from a monk at Enryaku-ji Temple to an aide of the retired Emperor Gotoba.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thanks to his intelligence and martial competency, he was promoted from a monk at Enryaku-ji Temple to an aide of the retired Emperor Gotoba.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thanks to his intelligence and martial competency, he was promoted from a monk at Enryaku-ji Temple to an aide of the Retired Emperor Gotoba.</e>
<cmt>Retired大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>上皇の鎌倉幕府打倒計画には首謀者の一人として参加。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was one of masterminds behind Retired Emperor Gotaba&apos;s plot to overthrow the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was one of the masterminds behind Retired Emperor Gotaba&apos;s plot to overthrow the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was one of the masterminds behind Retired Emperor Gotaba&apos;s plot to overthrow the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>承久3年（1221年）の承久の乱に当たっては、義兄弟ながら親幕府派の筆頭と目されていた西園寺公経父子の逮捕・監禁に当たるなど、上皇の片腕として行動する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Jokyu War (1221), Soncho played an important role as Retired Emperor Gotoba&apos;s man and took charge of capture and detention of Kintsune SAIONJI and his son, who were considered leaders of the pro-Kamakura bakufu group, although Kintsune was Soncho&apos;s brother-in-law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Jokyu War (1221), Soncho played an important role as Retired Emperor Gotoba&apos;s man and took charge of capture and detention of Kintsune SAIONJI and his son, who were considered leaders of the pro-Kamakura bakufu group, although Kintsune was Soncho&apos;s brother-in-law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Jokyu War (1221), Soncho played an important role as Retired Emperor Gotoba&apos;s man and took charge of capture and detention of Kintsune SAIONJI and his son, who were considered leaders of the pro-Kamakura bakufu group, although Kintsune was Soncho&apos;s brother-in-law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>幕府軍との戦闘においては、兄弟の信能とともに芋洗方面の守備に就くが、敗戦が明らかになると乱軍の中を脱出し行方不明となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When fighting with the army of bakufu, Soncho and his brother Nobuyoshi defended the Imoarai district, but upon the realization of their defeat, he cut himself loose from the battalion and was on the run.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When fighting with the army of bakufu, Soncho and his brother Nobuyoshi defended the Imoarai district, but upon the realization of their defeat, he cut himself loose from the battalion and was on the run.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When fighting with the army of bakufu, Soncho and his brother Nobuyoshi defended the Imoarai district, but upon the realization of their defeat, he cut himself loose from the battalion and was on the run.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>6年の潜伏の後、安貞元年（1227年）京において謀反を計画しているところを発見され、六波羅探題北条時氏の近習・菅十郎左衛門周則によって逮捕され、誅殺された（一説に自害したとも）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After six-year running away, Soncho was discovered to plot a coup in Kyoto in 1227 and arrested and murdered (it is also said that he committed suicide) by Sugajuro Saemon Chikanori, a kinju (attendant) of Tokiuji HOJO, Rokuhara Tandai (the high-rank intelligent officer at the administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After six-years of running away, Soncho was discovered to plot a coup in Kyoto in 1227 and arrested and murdered (it is also said that he committed suicide) by Sugajuro Saemon Chikanori, a kinju (attendant) of Tokiuji HOJO, Rokuhara Tandai (the high-rank intelligent officer at the administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After 6 years of running away, Soncho was discovered to plot a coup in Kyoto in 1227 and arrested and murdered (it is also said that he committed suicide) by Sugajurozaemon Chikanori, a kinju (attendant) of Tokiuji HOJO, Rokuhara Tandai (the high-rank intelligent officer at the administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>6 yearsに訂正しました。Sugajurozaemonとしました。不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>捕縛された際に自殺し損なった尊長は、「早く首を切れ。さもなければ義時の妻が義時に飲ませた薬で早く自分を殺せ」と叫び、その3年前における前執権北条義時の死去がその室伊賀の方による毒殺であったことを示唆したとされる（藤原定家の日記の記述による）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that when Soncho was captured and failed to commit suicide, he shouted, &quot;Cut my head off now! Or, kill me with the poison that Yoshitoki&apos;s wife used!,&quot; suggesting that Yoshitoki HOJO, then regent to the shognate, who had died three years before, was killed with poison by Iga no kata, the wife of Yoshitoki (based on the episode described in a diary of Teika FUJIWARA).</e>
<cmt>前文とつながっているので、こちらに翻訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that when Soncho was captured and failed to commit suicide, he shouted, &quot;Cut my head off now! Or, kill me with the poison that Yoshitoki&apos;s wife used!,&quot; suggesting that Yoshitoki HOJO, then regent to the shognate, who had died three years before, was killed with poison by Iga no kata, the wife of Yoshitoki (based on the episode described in a diary of Teika FUJIWARA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that when Soncho was captured and failed to commit suicide, he shouted, &apos;Cut my head off now! Or, kill me with the poison that Yoshitoki&apos;s wife used!,&apos; suggesting that Yoshitoki HOJO, then regent to the shognate, who had died three years before, was killed with poison by Iga no kata, the wife of Yoshitoki (based on the episode described in a diary of Teika FUJIWARA).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また尊長は問いつめる武士たちに「今から死ぬ身であるのに、嘘など言わん」とも述べたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that when grilled by warriors, Soncho snapped, &quot;I am not lying because I am dying.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that when grilled by warriors, Soncho snapped, &quot;I am not lying because I am dying.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that when grilled by warriors, Soncho snapped, &apos;I am not lying because I am dying.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>このことは現在、義時死後に起こった伊賀氏の変において尊長の兄弟である一条実雅が将軍候補とされていたことと、関連つけて語られることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Presently, it has become often the case that this episode is cited in conjunction with the fact that Sanemasa ICHIJO, Soncho&apos;s brother, was selected as a candidate for the shognate during the coup attempt of the Iga clan, which took place after the death of Yoshitoki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Presently, it has often become the case that this episode is cited in conjunction with the fact that Sanemasa ICHIJO, Soncho&apos;s brother, was selected as a candidate for the shognate during the coup attempt of the Iga clan, which took place after the death of Yoshitoki.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Presently, it has often become the case that this episode is cited in conjunction with the fact that Sanemasa ICHIJO, Soncho&apos;s brother, was selected as a candidate for the shognate during the coup attempt of the Iga clan, which took place after the death of Yoshitoki.</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ちちぶ(id:184715), Andee(id:20421), 小者(id:172526), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>