<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>空海</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kukai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kukai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kukai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>空海（くうかい）は、平安時代初期の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kukai was a priest who lived in the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kukai was a priest who lived in the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kukai was a priest who lived in the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「弘法大師（こうぼうだいし）」の名（諡号〈醍醐天皇、921年贈〉）で知られる、真言宗の開祖。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was known as &apos;Kobo Daishi&apos; (the shigo (posthumous name) awarded by Emperor Daigo in 921) and was the founder of the Shingon sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was known as &apos;Kobo Daishi&apos; (the shigo (posthumous name) awarded by Emperor Daigo in 921) and was the founder of the Shingon sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was known as &apos;Kobo Daishi&apos; (the shigo (posthumous name) awarded by Emperor Daigo in 921) and was the founder of the Shingon sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>俗名は佐伯 眞魚（さえき の まお、〈まなとも〉）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His secular name was SAEKI no Mao (or Mana).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His secular name was SAEKI no Mao (or Mana).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His secular name was SAEKI no Mao (or Mana).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>天台宗の開祖最澄（伝教大師）とともに、旧来のいわゆる奈良仏教から新しい平安仏教へと日本仏教が転換していく流れの劈頭に位置し、中国から真言密教をもたらした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Together with Saicho (Dengyo Daishi), he was positioned at the head of the trend in which Buddhism in Japan had been transformed from the older so-called Nara Buddhism into the new Heian Buddhism, and brought Shingon Esoteric Buddhism to Japan from China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Together with Saicho (Dengyo Daishi), he was positioned at the head of the trend in which Buddhism in Japan had been transformed from the older so-called Nara Buddhism into the new Heian Buddhism, and brought Shingon Esoteric Buddhism to Japan from China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Together with Saicho (Dengyo Daishi) of Tendai sect, he was positioned at the head of the trend in which Buddhism in Japan had been transformed from the older so-called Nara Buddhism into the new Heian Buddhism, and brought Shingon Esoteric Buddhism to Japan from China.</e>
<cmt>天台宗　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>能書家としても知られ、嵯峨天皇・橘逸勢と共に三筆のひとりに数えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Known also as noshoka (master of calligraphy), he is listed one of three famous ancient calligraphers, together with Emperor Saga and TACHIBANA no Hayanari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Known also as noshoka (master of calligraphy), he is listed one of three famous ancient calligraphers, together with Emperor Saga and TACHIBANA no Hayanari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Known also as noshoka (master of calligraphy), he is listed one of three famous ancient calligraphers, together with Emperor Saga and TACHIBANA no Hayanari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>佐伯真魚</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SAEKI no Mao (or Mana)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SAEKI no Mao (or Mana)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SAEKI no Mao (or Mana)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>宝亀5年（774年）、讃岐国多度郡屏風浦（現：香川県善通寺市）で生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 774, he was born in Byobugaura Tado county, Sanuki Province (present Zentsuji City, Kagawa Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 774, he was born in Byobugaura Tado county, Sanuki Province (present Zentsuji City, Kagawa Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 774, he was born in Byobugaura Tado County, Sanuki Province (present Zentsuji City, Kagawa Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>County を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>父は郡司・佐伯直田公（さえきのあたいたぎみ）、母は阿刀氏、幼名は真魚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was SAEKI no Atai Tagimi, a gunji (an officer in charge of a gun (county), his mother was from the Ato clan, and his childhood name Mao (or Mana).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was SAEKI no Atai Tagimi, a gunji (an officer in charge of gunnery (county), his mother was from the Ato clan, and his childhood name was Mao (or Mana).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was SAEKI no Atai Tagimi, a Gunji (local magistrates), his mother was from the Ato clan, and his childhood name was Mao (or Mana).</e>
<cmt>郡司　の補足を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>真言宗の伝承では空海の誕生日を6月15日とするが、これは中国密教の大成者である不空金剛三蔵の入滅の日である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a tradition in the Shingon sect, his birth date is June 16, but it corresponds to the day when Huku Kongo Sanzo, who established Esoteric Buddhism in China, died.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a tradition in the Shingon sect, his birth date is June 16, but it corresponds to the day when Huku Kongo Sanzo, who established Esoteric Buddhism in China, died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a tradition in the Shingon sect, his birth date is June 15, but it corresponds to the day when Fuku Kongo Sanzo, who established Esoteric Buddhism in China, died.</e>
<cmt>数字を修正しました。Huku→Fuku としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>そのため、空海が不空の生まれ変わりとする伝承によるもので、正確な誕生日は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it is considered that the date was used based on the tradition in which Kukai was considered a reincarnation of Huku.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it is considered that the date was used based upon the tradition that Kukai was considered a reincarnation of Huku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, his accurate date of birth is unknown since it is considered that the date was used based upon the tradition that Kukai was considered a reincarnation of Fuku.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を追加しました。Huku→Fuku としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>延暦8年（789年）、15歳で桓武天皇の皇子伊予親王の家庭教師であった母方の舅である阿刀大足について論語、孝経、史伝、文章等を学んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 789 when he was 15 years old, he leaned from ATO no Otari, who was a tutor of Imperial Prince Iyo, a prince of Emperor Kanmu and the father-in-law of his mother, Rongo Analects, Kokyo (the book of filial piety), shiden (history and related items) and monjo (literature).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 789 when he was 15 years old, he learned from ATO no Otari, who was a tutor of Imperial Prince Iyo, a prince of Emperor Kanmu and the father-in-law of his mother, Rongo Analects, Kokyo (the book of filial piety), shiden (history and related items) and monjo (literature).</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 789 when he was 15 years old, he learned from ATO no Otari, who was a tutor of Imperial Prince Iyo, a prince of Emperor Kanmu and the father-in-law of his mother, Rongo Analects, Kokyo (the book of filial piety), shiden (history and related items) and monjo (literature).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>延暦11年（792年）、18歳で京の大学寮に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 792, he entered Daigaku-ryo (Bureau of Education under the ritsuryo system) at the age of 18.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 792, he entered the Daigaku-ryo (the Bureau of Education under the ritsuryo system) at the age of 18.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 792, he entered the Daigaku-ryo (the Bureau of Education under the ritsuryo system) at the age of 18.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>大学での専攻は明経道で、春秋左氏伝、毛詩、尚書等を学んだと伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that at the Bureau of Education, he majored in Myogyo-do (the study of Confucian classics), and learned Chunqiu Zuoshi Zhuan (Master Zuo&apos;s Commentary to the Spring and Autumns), Moshi (the book of poetry in ancient china), and Shosho (classics of history).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that at the Bureau of Education, he majored in Myogyo-do (the study of Confucian classics), and learned Chunqiu Zuoshi Zhuan (Master Zuo&apos;s Commentary about the Spring and Autumns), Moshi (the book of poetry in ancient china), and Shosho (classics of history).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that at the Bureau of Education, he majored in Myogyo-do (the study of Confucian classics), and learned Chunqiu Zuoshi Zhuan (Master Zuo&apos;s Commentary about the Spring and Autumns), Moshi (the book of poetry in ancient china), and Shosho (classics of history).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>仏道修行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ascetic Buddhist practice</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ascetic Buddhist practice</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ascetic Buddhist practice</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>延暦12年（793年）、大学での勉学に飽き足らず、19歳を過ぎた頃から山林での修行に入ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that, not satisfied by the learning at Bureau of Education, he performed ascetic practices in forests starting around the age of 20.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that, not satisfied with learning at the Bureau of Education, he performed ascetic practices in the forests starting around the age of 20.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that, not satisfied with learning at the Bureau of Education, he performed ascetic practices in the forests starting around the age of 20.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>御蔵洞（高知県室戸市）で修行をしている時、口に明星が飛び込んできて悟りを開いたといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that, when he was performing ascetic practices in Mikurodo (located in present Muroto city, Kochi Prefecture), myojo (the morning star; Venus) plunged into his mouth, making him awaken spiritually.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that, when he was performing ascetic practices in Mikurodo (located in present Muroto city, Kochi Prefecture), myojo (the morning star; Venus) plunged into his mouth, causing him to awaken spiritually.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that, when he was performing ascetic practices in Mikurodo (located in present Muroto city, Kochi Prefecture), myojo (the morning star; Venus) plunged into his mouth, causing him to awaken spiritually.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>その間、空海が目にしていたのは空と海だけであったため、空海と名乗ったと伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been said that he called himself Kukai (literally, sky and sea), because what was in his sight at that time was only the sky and sea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been said that he called himself Kukai (literally, sky and sea), because what was in his sight at that time was only the sky and the sea.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been said that he called himself Kukai (literally, sky and sea), because what was in his sight at that time was only the sky and the sea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>24歳で儒教・道教・仏教の比較思想論でもある『聾瞽指帰（ろうごしいき）』を著して俗世の教えが真実でないことを示した（「聾瞽指帰」は、後に序文と巻末の十韻詩を改定、『三教指帰』（さんごうしいき）と改題されている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the age of 24, he wrote &quot;Rogoshiki,&quot; where the thought of Confucianism, that of Taoism, and that of Buddhism were comparatively discussed, showing that what was taught popularly was not true (the title of &quot;Rogoshiki&quot; was later changed into Sango ishiki, with the ten rhyme-based poems in the preface and at the end of the book revised).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the age of 24, he wrote &quot;Rogoshiki,&quot; where the thought of Confucianism, that of Taoism, and that of Buddhism were comparatively discussed, showing that what was taught popularly was not true (the title of &quot;Rogoshiki&quot; was later changed into Sango ishiki, with the ten rhyme-based poems in the preface and at the end of the book revised).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the age of 24, he wrote &quot;Rogoshiki,&quot; where the thought of Confucianism, that of Taoism, and that of Buddhism were comparatively discussed, showing that what was taught popularly was not true (the title of &quot;Rogoshiki&quot; was later changed into &quot;Sango shiiki,&quot; with the ten rhyme-based poems in the preface and at the end of the book revised).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;　を追加しました。Sango shiiki と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>この時期より入唐までの空海の足取りは資料が少なく断片的で不明な点が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concerning where he was and what he was doing during the period after this until he entered Tang, only few fragmentary materials are available, with many points still remaining unclear</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concerning where he was and what he was doing during the period after this until he entered Tang, only a few fragmentary materials are available, with many points still remaining unclear.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concerning where he was and what he was doing during the period after this until he entered Tang, only a few fragmentary materials are available, with many points still remaining unclear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>しかし吉野の金峰山や四国の石鎚山などで山林修行を重ねると共に、幅広く仏教思想を学んだことは想像に難くない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it can be easily imagined that he performed ascetic performances repeatedly in the forests of Mt. Kinpu in Yoshino and of Mt. Ishizuchi in Shikoku and that he learnt Buddhist thoughts widely.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it can be easily imagined that he performed ascetic performances repeatedly in the forests of Mt. Kinpu in Yoshino and on Mt. Ishizuchi in Shikoku and that he learnt Buddhist thoughts widely.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it can be easily imagined that he performed ascetic performances repeatedly in the forests of Mt. Kinpu in Yoshino and on Mt. Ishizuchi in Shikoku and that he learnt Buddhist thoughts widely.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>『大日経』を初めとする密教経典に出会ったのもこの頃と考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that, around this time, he found the existence of Buddhist scriptures about Esoteric Buddhism, including Dainichi-kyo (Mahavairocana Sutra).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that, around this time, he found the existence of Buddhist scriptures about Esoteric Buddhism, including Dainichi-kyo (Mahavairocana Sutra).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that, around this time, he found the existence of Buddhist scriptures about Esoteric Buddhism, including &quot;Dainichi-kyo&quot; (Mahavairocana Sutra).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>さらに中国語や梵字などにも手を伸ばした形跡もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, some evidences show that he also tried to learn the Chinese language and Sanskrit characters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, some evidences show that he also tried to learn the Chinese language and Sanskrit characters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, some evidences show that he also tried to learn the Chinese language and Sanskrit characters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="21">
<j>ところでこの時期、一沙門より「虚空蔵菩薩求聞持法」を授かったことはよく知られるところである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is well known that, during this period, he learnt &apos;Kokudo Bosatsu Gumonjiho (ascetic practices for good memory in esoteric Buddhism)&apos; from a shamon (priest).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is well known that, during this period, he learnt &apos;Kokudo Bosatsu Gumonjiho (ascetic practices for having a good memory in esoteric Buddhism)&apos; from a shamon (priest).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is well known that, during this period, he learnt &apos;Kokudo Bosatsu Gumonjiho (ascetic practices for having a good memory in esoteric Buddhism)&apos; from a shamon (priest).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>『三教指帰』の序文には、空海が阿波国の大瀧岳や土佐国の室戸岬などで求聞持法を修ましたこと、明けの明星が来影するという形で行が成就したこと、が記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the preface of Sango ishiki, it is written that Kukai practiced Gumonji-ho in Dairyo-dake Mountain in the Awa province and at Muroto-misaki Cape in the Tosa province, and that light from the morning bright star hit him showing that the practice was completed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the preface of Sango ishiki, it is written that Kukai practiced Gumonji-ho in Dairyo-dake Mountain in Awa province and at Muroto-misaki Cape in the Tosa province, and that light from the morning bright star hit him showing that the practice was completed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the preface of &quot;Sango shiiki,&quot; it is written that Kukai practiced Gumonji-ho in Mt. Dairyo-dake in Awa Province and at Muroto-misaki Cape in the Tosa Province, and that light from the morning bright star hit him showing that the practice was completed.</e>
<cmt>Sango shiiki と修正しました。Province と大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>求聞持法を空海に伝えた一沙門とは、旧来の通説では勤操とされていたが、現在では大安寺の戒明ではないかと云われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was said that the priest who taught Gumonji-ho to Kuaki was Gonso, but today it is said that Kaimyo at Daian-ji Temple might have been the priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was said that the priest who taught Gumonji-ho to Kuaki was Gonso, but today it is said that Kaimyo at Daian-ji Temple might have been the priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was said that the priest who taught Gumonji-ho to Kuaki was Gonso, but today it is said that Kaimyo at Daian-ji Temple might have been the priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>戒明は空海と同じ讃岐の出身で、その後空海が重要視した『釈摩訶衍論』の請来者である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaimyo came from the same Sanuki province as Kukai, and brought to Japan scriptures &quot;Shakumakaenron&quot; that Kukai put importance on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaimyo came from the same Sanuki province as Kukai, and brought to Japan scriptures &quot;Shakumakaenron&quot; that Kukai placed importance on.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaimyo came from the same Sanuki Province as Kukai, and brought to Japan scriptures &quot;Shakumakaenron&quot; that Kukai placed importance on.</e>
<cmt>Province と大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="25">
<j>空海の得度に関しては、延暦12年（793年）に20歳にして勤操を師とし槇尾山寺で出家した、という説、あるいは25歳出家説が古くからとなえられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concerning when Kukai entered the Buddhist priesthood, there were the following two views in the past: One was that he became a priest under priest Gonso at Makionosan-ji Temple in 793 at the age of 20, and the other was that he became a priest at the age of 25.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concerning when Kukai actually entered the Buddhist priesthood, there were the following two views: One was that he became a priest under priest Gonso at Makionosan-ji Temple in 793 at the age of 20, and the other was that he became a priest at the age of 25.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concerning when Kukai actually entered the Buddhist priesthood, there were the following two views: One was that he became a priest under priest Gonso at Makionosan-ji Temple in 793 at the age of 20, and the other was that he became a priest at the age of 25.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>しかしながら、現在では、延暦23年（804年）、入唐直前31歳の年に東大寺戒壇院で得度受戒したという説が有力視されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, nowadays, the view became promising that he entered the Buddhist priesthood and received religious precepts at Todai-ji Kaidan-in in 804 at the age of 30 just before he went to Tang.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, nowadays, the view is that he entered the Buddhist priesthood and received religious precepts at Todai-ji Kaidan-in in 804 at the age of 30 just before he went to Tang.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, nowadays, the view is that he entered the Buddhist priesthood and received religious precepts at Todai-ji Kaidan-in in 804 at the age of 31 just before he went to Tang.</e>
<cmt>30→31 としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>また空海という名をいつから名乗っていたのかは定かではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is not clear when he started using the name of Kukai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not clear when he started using the name of Kukai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not clear when he started using the name of Kukai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>無空や教海と名乗った時期があるとする文献もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some historical documents include the description that he called Muku or Kyoka during a certain period of time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some historical documents include descriptions of him being called Muku or Kyoka during a certain period of time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some historical documents include descriptions of him being called Muku or Kyoka during a certain period of time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>入唐求法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nitto Guho (entering Tang and seeking after Buddhism)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nitto Guho (entering Tang and seeking after Buddhism)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nitto Guho (entering Tang and seeking after Buddhism)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>延暦23年（804年）、正規の遣唐使の留学僧（留学期間20年の予定）として唐に渡る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 804, he went to Tang as formal ryugakuso (foreign priest studying Buddhism) (who were scheduled to stay in Tang for study for 20 years) included in a Japanese envoy to Tang Dynasty China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 804, he went to Tang as formal ryugakuso (foreign priest studying Buddhism) (who were scheduled to stay in Tang for study for 20 years) included in a Japanese envoy to Tang Dynasty China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 804, he went to Tang as formal ryugakuso (foreign priest studying Buddhism) (who were scheduled to stay in Tang for study for 20 years) included in a Japanese envoy to Tang Dynasty China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>入唐直前まで一私度僧であった空海が突然留学僧として浮上する過程は、今日なお謎を残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was only a shidoso (priest having entered Buddhist priesthood without permission) until immediately before going to Tang, and it still remains a riddle how such a priest suddenly emerged as a ryugakuso.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was only a shidoso (priest having entered Buddhist priesthood without permission) until immediately before going to Tang, and it still remains a riddle about how such a priest coulc suddenly emerge as a ryugakuso.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was only a shidoso (priest having entered Buddhist priesthood without permission) until immediately before going to Tang, and it still remains a riddle about how such a priest could suddenly emerge as a ryugakuso.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>伊予親王や奈良仏教界との関係を指摘するむきもあるが定説はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some pointed out his relations with Imperial Prince Iyo or with the Nara Buddhist society, but no established view exists.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some pointed out his relationship with Imperial Prince Iyo or with the the Nara Buddhist society, but no established view exists.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some pointed out his relationship with Imperial Prince Iyo or with the Nara Buddhist society, but no established view exists.</e>
<cmt>the ダブりを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="32">
<j>また、第16次（20回説では18次）遣唐使一行には、最澄や後に中国で三蔵法師の称号を贈られる霊仙がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 16th envoy to Tang Dynasty China (18th, when the total number of such envoys was considered 20) included Saicho and Ryosen who was awarded the title of Sanzohoshi later in China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 16th envoy to Tang Dynasty China (18th, when the total number of such envoys was considered 20) included Saicho and Ryosen who was awarded the title of Sanzohoshi later in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 16th envoy to Tang Dynasty China (18th, when the total number of such envoys was considered 20) included Saicho and Ryosen who was awarded the title of Sanzohoshi later in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>最澄はこの時期すでに天皇の護持僧である内供奉十禅師の一人に任命されており、当時の仏教界に確固たる地位を築いていたが、空海はまったく無名の一沙門だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, Saicho had been appointed to one of naikubu-juzenshi (the ten selected excellent priests for a Buddhist service in the Imperial Court) who were gojiso (a priest who prayed to guard the emperor), but Kukai was only an obscure priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, Saicho had been appointed to one of the naikubu-juzenshi (the ten selected excellent priests for conducting Buddhist services in the Imperial Court) who were gojiso (a priest who prayed to guard the emperor), but Kukai was only an obscure priest.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, Saicho had been appointed to one of the naikubu-juzenshi (the ten selected excellent priests for conducting Buddhist services in the Imperial Court) who were gojiso (a priest who prayed to guard the emperor), but Kukai was only an obscure priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="34">
<j>同年5月12日、難波津を出航、博多を経由し7月6日、肥前国松浦郡田浦から入唐の途についた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The envoy set sail from Naniwazu on June 16, the same year, and departed for Tang on August 18 from Taura, Matsuura County, Hizen Province, via Hakata.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The envoy set sail from Naniwazu on June 16, the same year, and departed for Tang on August 18 from Taura, Matsuura County, Hizen Province, via Hakata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The envoy set sail from Naniwa no tsu (Naniwa Port) on June 26, the same year, and departed for Tang on August 18 from Taura, Matsuura County, Hizen Province, via Hakata.</e>
<cmt>難波津 読みと補足を変更しました。グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>空海が乗船したのは遣唐大使の乗る第1船、最澄は第2船である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kukai was on board the first ship that was for chief of the Japanese envoy to Tang Dynasty China, and Saicho on board the second ship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kukai was on board the first ship that carried the chief of the Japanese envoy to the Tang Dynasty China, and Saicho was on board the second ship.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kukai was on board the first ship that carried the chief of the Japanese envoy to the Tang Dynasty China, and Saicho was on board the second ship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>この入唐船団の第3船、第4船は遭難し、唐にたどり着いたのは第1船と第2船のみであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The third and fourth ships of this envoy to Tang were wrecked, and only the first and second ships arrived at Tang.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The third and fourth ships of this envoy to Tang were wrecked, and only the first and second ships arrived at Tang.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The third and fourth ships of this envoy to Tang were wrecked, and only the first and second ships arrived at Tang.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="37">
<j>空海の乗った船は、途中で嵐にあい大きく航路を逸れて貞元 (唐)20年（延暦23年、804年）8月10日、福州長渓県赤岸鎮に漂着。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ship Kukai was on board was caught in a storm, significantly deviated from its scheduled route and drifted ashore Sekiganchin, Chokei-ken, Fuku-shu on September 21, 804.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ship Kukai was on was caught in a storm and significantly deviated from its scheduled route and finally drifted ashore at Sekiganchin, Chokei-ken, Fuku-shu on September 21, 804.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ship Kukai was on was caught in a storm and significantly deviated from its scheduled route and finally drifted ashore at Sekiganchin, Chokei-ken, Fuku-shu on September 21, 804.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>海賊の嫌疑をかけられ、疑いが晴れるまで約50日間待機させられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were suspected of pirates, and were forced to wait for about 50 days until the suspicion was cleared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were suspected as pirates, and were forced to wait for about 50 days until the suspicion was cleared up.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were suspected as pirates, and were forced to wait for about 50 days until the suspicion was cleared up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>このとき遣唐大使に代わり、空海が福州の長官へ嘆願書を代筆している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this occasion, Kukai wrote a petition to the governor of Fuku-shu for the chief of the envoy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this occasion, Kukai wrote a petition to the governor of Fuku-shu for the chief of the envoy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this occasion, Kukai wrote a petition to the governor of Fuku-shu for the chief of the envoy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>同年11月3日に長安入りを許され、12月23日に長安に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was permitted for him to enter Changan in December 12, 805, and he actually entered Changan on January 31, 805.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was permitted to enter Changan in December 12, 805, but he actually entered Changan on January 31, 805.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was permitted to enter Changan in December 12, 805, but he actually entered Changan on January 31, 805.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="41">
<j>永貞 (唐)元年（延暦24年、805年）2月、西明寺 (西安市)に入り滞在し、空海の長安での住居となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March or April of 805, he entered Saimyo-ji Temple (located in Xian City) and stayed at the temple where became his dwelling in Changan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March or April of 805, he entered Saimyo-ji Temple (located in Xian City) and stayed at the temple that became his dwelling in Changan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March of 805, he entered Saimyo-ji Temple (located in Xian City) and stayed at the temple that became his dwelling in Changan.</e>
<cmt>延暦24年2月(1日)はグレゴリオ暦ですと3月9日のようですので、 ここは単に3月としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="42">
<j>長安で空海が師事したのは、まず醴泉寺の印度僧般若三蔵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Changan, Kukai studied first under Hannya Sanzo, an Indian priest at Reisen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Changan, Kukai studied first under Hannya Sanzo, an Indian priest at the Reisen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Changan, Kukai studied first under Hannya Sanzo, an Indian priest at the Reisen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>密教を学ぶために必須の梵語に磨きをかけたものと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that he brushed up on Sanskrit essential for learning Esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that he brushed up on Sanskrit essential for learning Esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that he brushed up on Sanskrit essential for learning Esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>空海はこの般若三蔵から梵語の経本や新訳経典を与えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kukai was given by this Hannya Sanzo sutras in Sanskrit and Buddhist scriptures newly translated into Chinese.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hannya Sanzo gave Kukai sutras in Sanskrit and Buddhist scriptures newly translated into Chinese.</e>
<cmt>grammar, word spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hannya Sanzo gave Kukai sutras in Sanskrit and Buddhist scriptures newly translated into Chinese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="45">
<j>5月になると空海は、密教の第七祖である唐長安青龍寺 (西安市)の恵果和尚を訪ね、以降約半年にわたって師事することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Entering June or July, Kukai visited priest Keika, who was the seventh founder of Esoteric Buddhism, at Shoryu-ji Temple (located in Xian City), in Changan, Tang, and studied under him about half a year after that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Entering June or July, Kukai visited priest Keika, who was the seventh founder of Esoteric Buddhism, at Shoryu-ji Temple (located in Xian City), in Changan, Tang, and studied under him for about 6 months after that.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Entering June, Kukai visited priest Keika, who was the seventh founder of Esoteric Buddhism, at Shoryu-ji Temple (located in Xian City), in Changan, Tang, and studied under him for about 6 months after that.</e>
<cmt>July を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>6月13日に大悲胎蔵の学法灌頂、7月に金剛界の灌頂を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A gakujokanjo ceremony in Daihitaizo was held for him on July 16, and a kanjo ceremony in Vajradhatu in August or September.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A gakujokanjo ceremony in Daihitaizo was held for him on July 16, and a kanjo ceremony in Vajradhatu in August or September.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A gakujokanjo ceremony in Daihitaizo was held for him on July 16, and a kanjo ceremony in Vajradhatu in August.</e>
<cmt>September を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>ちなみに胎蔵界・金剛界のいずれの灌頂においても彼の投じた花は敷き曼荼羅の大日如来の上へ落ち、両部（両界）の大日如来と結縁した、と伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been said that, in either of the kanjo ceremony in Taizokai (Womb Realm) and that in Vajradhatu, the flower Kukai threw dropped on the laid Mandala (a diagram that depicts Buddhist deities according to certain geometric formats and illustrates the Buddhist world view), making him connected with Dainichi Nyorai (Mahavairocana) in the two areas (or two realms).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been said that, in either of the kanjo ceremony in Taizokai (Realm of the Womb) and that in Vajradhatu, the flower Kukai threw dropped on the laid Mandala (a diagram that depicts Buddhist deities according to certain geometric formats and illustrates the Buddhist world view), connecting him with Dainichi Nyorai (Mahavairocana) in the two areas (or two realms).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been said that, in either of the kanjo ceremony in Taizokai (Realm of the Womb) and that in Vajradhatu, the flower Kukai threw dropped on the laid Mandala (a diagram that depicts Buddhist deities according to certain geometric formats and illustrates the Buddhist world view), connecting him with Dainichi Nyorai (Mahavairocana) in the two areas (or two realms).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="48">
<j>8月10日には伝法阿闍梨位の灌頂を受け、「この世の一切を遍く照らす最上の者」を意味する遍照金剛（へんじょうこんごう）の灌頂名を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A knjo ceremony for the Denpo Ajari rank was held for him on September 10, 805, awarded a kanjo name of Henjokongo meaning &quot;the best person who will enlighten everything in this world.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A kanjo ceremony for the Denpo Ajari rank was held for him on September 10, 805, awarded a kanjo name of Henjokongo meaning &quot;the best person who will enlighten everything in this world.&quot;</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A kanjo ceremony for the Denpo Ajari rank was held for him on September 10, 805, awarded a kanjo name of Henjokongo meaning &quot;the best person who will enlighten everything in this world.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>この名は後世、空海を尊崇する真言として唱えられるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This name has become to be chanted as a mantra for worshiping Kukai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This name has become a chant as a mantra for worshiping Kukai.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This name has become a chant as a mantra for worshiping Kukai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>このとき空海は、青龍寺や不空三蔵ゆかりの大興善寺から500人にものぼる人々を招いて食事の接待をし、感謝の気持ちを表している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this occasion, Kukai invited as many as 500 persons from Seiryu-ji Temple and from the Da Xing Shan Temple that was deeply associated with Fukusanzo, and held a banquet for them for expressing his gratitude.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this occasion, Kukai invited as many as 500 persons from the Seiryu-ji Temple and from the Da Xing Shan Temple that were deeply associated with Fukusanzo, and held a banquet for them to express his gratitude.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this occasion, Kukai invited as many as 500 persons from the Seiryu-ji Temple and from the Da Xing Shan Temple that were deeply associated with Fukusanzo, and held a banquet for them to express his gratitude.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="51">
<j>8月中旬以降になると、大勢の人たちが関わって曼荼羅や密教法具の製作、経典の書写が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the middle of September, together with many others, he was engaged in making mandalas and mikkyo hogu (Buddhist instruments of esoteric Buddhism), and in copying Buddhist scriptures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the middle of September, together with many others, he was engaged in making mandalas and mikkyo hogu (Buddhist instruments of esoteric Buddhism), and in copying Buddhist scriptures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the middle of September, together with many others, he was engaged in making mandalas and mikkyo hogu (Buddhist instruments of esoteric Buddhism), and in copying Buddhist scriptures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>また恵果和尚からは阿闍梨付嘱物を授けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also awarded Ajari fushokubutsu (see below) by priest Keika.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also awarded Ajari fushokubutsu (see below) by priest Keika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also awarded Ajari fushokubutsu (see below) by priest Keika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>伝法の印信である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was Injin (the mystagogy certificate a Buddhist priest awards his follower) for denpo (the teachings of Buddhism).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was Injin (the mystagogy certificate a Buddhist priest awards his follower) for denpo (the teachings of Buddhism).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was Injin (the mystagogy certificate a Buddhist priest awards his follower) for denpo (the teachings of Buddhism).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>阿闍梨付嘱物とは、金剛智－不空金剛－恵果と伝えられてきた仏舎利、刻白檀仏菩薩金剛尊像(高野山に現存)など8点、恵果和尚から与えられた健陀穀糸袈裟（東寺に現存）や供養具など5点の計13点である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ajari fushokubutsu consisted of the following 15 items: eight items, which included the Buddha&apos;s ashes said to have been handed down from Kongochi to Huku Kongo and to Keika, and a noble image of Kongo-bosatsu sculpted in byakudan wood (now located in Koya-san Mountain), and five items, including the Kendagokushi kesa (a Buddhist stole) (now located in Ko-ji Temple) and Kuyogu (tools for memorial service) given by Keika.</e>
<cmt>刻白檀仏菩薩金剛尊像：　この訳で良いか、自信はありません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ajari fushokubutsu consisted of the following 15 items: eight items, which included the Buddha&apos;s ashes said to have been handed down from Kongochi to Huku Kongo and to Keika, and a noble image of Kongo-bosatsu sculpted in byakudan wood (now located in Koya-san Mountain), and five items, including the Kendagokushi kesa (a Buddhist stole) (now located in Ko-ji Temple) and Kuyogu (tools for memorial service) given by Keika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ajari fushokubutsu consisted of the following 13 items: eight items, which included the Buddha&apos;s ashes said to have been handed down from Kongochi to Fuku Kongo and to Keika, and a noble image of Kongo-bosatsu sculpted in byakudan wood (now located in Mt. Koya), and five items, including the Kendagokushi kesa (a Buddhist stole) (now located in To-ji Temple) and Kuyogu (tools for memorial service) given by Keika.</e>
<cmt>数字を修正しました。スペルなどを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>対して空海は伝法への感謝を込め、恵果和尚に袈裟と柄香炉を献上している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this, Kukai presented, for expressing gratitude for denpo, a kesa and egoro (an incense burner) to priest Keika.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this, Kukai presented, for expressing gratitude for denpo, a kesa and egoro (an incense burner) to priest Keika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this, Kukai presented, for expressing gratitude for denpo, a kesa and egoro (an incense burner) to priest Keika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="56">
<j>同年12月15日、恵果和尚が60歳で入滅。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 12, 806, priest Keika died at the age of 60.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 12, 806, priest Keika died at the age of 60.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 12, 806, priest Keika died at the age of 60.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>元和 (唐)元年（延暦25年、806年）1月17日、空海は全弟子を代表して和尚を顕彰する碑文を起草した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 13, 806, Kukai, representing the followers of Keika, wrote an inscription for praising the priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 13, 806, Kukai, representing the followers of Keika, wrote an inscription praising the priest.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 13, 806, Kukai, representing the followers of Keika, wrote an inscription praising the priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="58">
<j>そして、3月に長安を出発し、4月には越州に到り4か月滞在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then he departed Changan in March or April, arriving at Esshu in April or May, and stayed there for four months.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then he departed Changan in March or April, arriving at Esshu in April or May, and stayed there for four months.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then he departed Changan in March, arriving at Esshu in April, and stayed there for four months.</e>
<cmt>April, Mayを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>ここでも土木技術や薬学をはじめ多分野を学び、経典等を収集した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here as well, he learnt lots of things in many areas, including civil engineering technology and pharmacology, and collected Buddhist scriptures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Here as well, he learnt lots of things in many areas, including civil engineering technology and pharmacology, and collected Buddhist scriptures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Here as well, he learnt lots of things in many areas, including civil engineering technology and pharmacology, and collected Buddhist scriptures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>8月に明州を出航して、帰国の途についた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He set sail from Meishu in September or October for returning to Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He set sail from Meishu in September or October to returning to Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He set sail from Meishu in September to return to Japan.</e>
<cmt>October を削除しました。Returning →return としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="61">
<j>途中暴風雨に遭遇し、五島列島福江島玉之浦の大宝港に寄港した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Encountering a storm, the ship stopped at the Daihou-ko harbor in Tamanoura, Fukue Island, the Goto Islands.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Encountering a storm, the ship stopped at the Daihou-ko harbor in Tamanoura, Fukue Island, the Goto Islands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Encountering a storm, the ship stopped at the Daiho-ko harbor in Tamanoura, Fukue-jima Island, the Goto Islands.</e>
<cmt>Fukue-jima としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>そこで真言密教を開宗し、以来、大宝寺 (五島市)を西の高野山というようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There, he founded Shingon Esoteric Buddhism, and thereafter, Daiho-ji Temple (located in Goto City) became to be called western Koyasan</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There, he founded Shingon Esoteric Buddhism, and thereafter, the Daiho-ji Temple (located in Goto City) came to be called western Koyasan</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There, he founded Shingon Esoteric Buddhism, and thereafter, the Daiho-ji Temple (located in Goto City) came to be called western Koyasan (Mt. Koya).</e>
<cmt>Koyasan (Mt. Koyasan) としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>なお、福江に本尊虚空菩薩を安置してあると知った空海は参籠した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Knowing that a sculpture of Koku Bosatsu, a principal in Esoteric Buddhism, was enshrined in a temple in Fukue, he confined himself in the temple to pray.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Knowing that a sculpture of Koku Bosatsu, a principal in Esoteric Buddhism, was enshrined in a temple in Fukue, he confined himself in the temple to pray.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Knowing that a sculpture of Koku Bosatsu, a principal in Esoteric Buddhism, was enshrined in a temple in Fukue, he confined himself in the temple to pray.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>満願の朝に明星の奇光と瑞兆を拝されて、異国で修業された真言密教が日本の鎮護に効果をもらたす証しであると信じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the morning of the day when his vow was to be fulfilled, he sighted Kiko (strange light) from the morning star (Venus) and zuicho (good omens), and believed that this was an evidence of showing that Shingon Esoteric Buddhism, which he learnt with efforts in the foreign country, would be effective for protecting Japan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the morning of the day when his vow was to be fulfilled, he sighted Kiko (strange light) from the morning star (Venus) and zuicho (good omens), and believed that this was an evidence of showing that Shingon Esoteric Buddhism, which he learnt with efforts in a foreign country, would be effective for protecting Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the morning of the day when his vow was to be fulfilled, he sighted Kiko (strange light) from the morning star (Venus) and zuicho (good omens), and believed that this was an evidence of showing that Shingon Esoteric Buddhism, which he learnt with efforts in a foreign country, would be effective for protecting Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>そこで、寺の名を明星院と名づけられたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that then he named the temple Myojo-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that then he gave the name Myojo-in to the Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that then he gave the name Myojo-in to the Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>虚しく往きて実ちて帰る</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Going with nothing, I came back fully enriched.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Going with nothing, I came back fully enriched.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Going with nothing, I came back fully enriched.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="66">
<j>「虚しく往きて実ちて帰る」という空海の言葉は、わずか2年前無名の一留学僧として入唐した空海の成果がいかに大きなものであったかを如実に示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kukai&apos;s sentence of &apos;Going with nothing, I came back fully enriched&apos; vividly shows how great was the achievements of Kukai, who entered Tang as a mere obscure foreign priest, in his two-year stay in Tang.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kukai&apos;s expression &apos;Going with nothing, I came back fully enriched&apos; vividly shows how great were the achievements of Kukai, who entered Tang as a mere obscure foreign priest, during his two-year stay in Tang.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kukai&apos;s expression &apos;Going with nothing, I came back fully enriched&apos; vividly shows how great were the achievements of Kukai, who entered Tang as a mere obscure foreign priest, during his two-year stay in Tang.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="67">
<j>大同 (日本)元年（806年）10月、空海は無事帰国し、大宰府に滞在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November or December of 806, Kukai safely returned to Japan, and stayed in Dazai-fu (local government office in Kyushu region).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November or December of 806, Kukai safely returned to Japan, and stayed in Dazai-fu (local government office in the Kyushu region).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November of 806, Kukai safely returned to Japan, and stayed in Dazai-fu (local government office in the Kyushu region).</e>
<cmt>December を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>日本では、この年の3月に桓武天皇が崩御し、平城天皇が即位していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, Emperor Kanmu died in March or April of this year, and Emperor Heizei had reigned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, Emperor Kanmu died in March or April of that year, and Emperor Heizei reigned.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, Emperor Kanmu had died in March of that year, and Emperor Heizei had reigned.</e>
<cmt>April を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="69">
<j>空海は、10月22日付で朝廷に『請来目録』を提出。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kukai submitted to the imperial court &quot;Shorai Mokuroku&quot; (a list of what was brought back from China) dated December 9.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kukai submitted to the imperial court &quot;Shorai Mokuroku&quot; (a list of what was brought back from China) dated December 9.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kukai submitted to the imperial court &quot;Shorai Mokuroku&quot; (a list of what was brought back from China) dated December 9.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>唐から空海が持ち帰ったものは『請来目録』によれば、多数の経典類（新訳の経論等216部461巻）、両部大曼荼羅、祖師図、密教法具、阿闍梨付属物等々膨大なものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Shorai Mokuroku,&quot; what Kukai brought back from Tang was huge, including various Buddhist scriptures (216 bu (parts), 461 volumes, including newly translated Kyo-Ron), Ryobu-dai-Mandala, Soshi-zu painting (paintings of the founders of Esoteric Buddhism), mikkyo hogu, and Ajari fushokubutsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Shorai Mokuroku,&quot; what Kukai brought back from Tang was huge, including various Buddhist scriptures (216 bu (parts), 461 volumes, including newly translated Kyo-Ron), Ryobu-dai-Mandala, Soshi-zu painting (paintings of the founders of Esoteric Buddhism), mikkyo hogu, and Ajari fushokubutsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Shorai Mokuroku,&quot; what Kukai brought back from Tang was huge, including various Buddhist scriptures (216 bu (parts), 461 volumes, including newly translated Kyo-Ron), Ryobu-dai-Mandala, Soshi-zu painting (paintings of the founders of Esoteric Buddhism), mikkyo hogu, and Ajari fushokubutsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>当然、この目録に載っていない私的なものも別に数多くあったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naturally, it is considered that he also brought back many private things not included in this list.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naturally, it is considered that he also brought back many private things not included in this list.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naturally, it is considered that he also brought back many private things not included in this list.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>「未だ学ばざるを学び、～聞かざるを聞く」（『請来目録』）、空海が請来したのは密教を含めた最新の文化体系であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I learnt that many things remained to be studied further, and I heard that many things still remain to be listened to&apos; (included in &quot;Shorai Mokuroku&quot;): What Kukai brought back was the latest culture system including Esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I learnt that many things remained to be studied further, and I heard that many things still remain to be listened to&apos; (included in &quot;Shorai Mokuroku&quot;): What Kukai brought back was the latest cultural system including Esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I learnt that many things remained to be studied further, and I heard that many things still remain to be listened to&apos; (included in &quot;Shorai Mokuroku&quot;): What Kukai brought back was the latest cultural system including Esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="73">
<j>空海は、20年の留学期間を2年で切り上げ帰国した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kukai should have stayed in Tang for 20 years for learning but returned after staying only for two years.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kukai should have stayed in Tang for 20 years for study, but returned after staying for only two years.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kukai should have stayed in Tang for 20 years for study, but returned after staying for only two years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>そのため、当時の規定ではそれは闕期の罪にあたるとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it was decided that this constituted a Kekki no Tsumi (the crime violating the specification of the period of staying in Tang) based on a specification at that time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it was decided that this constituted a Kekki no Tsumi (the crime violating the required period to stay in Tang) based on the requirements at that time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it was decided that this constituted a Kekki no Tsumi (the crime violating the required period to stay in Tang) based on the requirements at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>そのためかどうかは定かではないが、大同元年（806年）10月の帰国後は、入京の許しを待って数年間太宰府に滞在することを余儀なくされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to this crime or other reason, he was forced to stay, after returning to Japan in November or December of 806, in Dazaifu for several years waiting for a permission of entering Heian Kyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to this crime or for other reasons, he was forced to stay, after returning to Japan in November or December of 806, in Dazaifu for several years waiting for permission to enter Heian Kyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to this crime or for other reasons, he was forced to stay, after returning to Japan in November of 806, in Dazaifu for several years waiting for permission to enter Heian-kyo.</e>
<cmt>Heian-kyo としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>大同2年より2年ほどは大宰府・観世音寺に止住している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He stayed in Kanzeon-ji Temple in Dazaifu for about two year from 807.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He stayed in Kanzeon-ji Temple at Dazaifu for about two years from 807.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He stayed in Kanzeon-ji Temple at Dazaifu for about two years from 807.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>この時期空海は、個人の法要を引き受け、その法要のために密教図像を制作するなどしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this period of time, Kukai undertook personal Buddhist memorial services, and made paintings related to Esoteric Buddhism for the services.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this period of time, Kukai undertook personal Buddhist memorial services, and made paintings related to Esoteric Buddhism for services.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this period of time, Kukai undertook personal Buddhist memorial services, and made paintings related to Esoteric Buddhism for services.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>真言密教の確立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Establishment of Shingon Esoteric Buddhism</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Establishment of Shingon Esoteric Buddhism</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Establishment of Shingon Esoteric Buddhism</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="78">
<j>大同4年（809年）、平城天皇が退位し、嵯峨天皇が即位した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 809, Emperor Heizei abdicated and Emperor Saga was enthroned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 809, Emperor Heizei abdicated and Emperor Saga was enthroned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 809, Emperor Heizei abdicated and Emperor Saga was enthroned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>空海は、まず和泉国槇尾山寺に滞在し、7月の太政官符を待って入京、和気氏の私寺であった高雄山寺（後の神護寺）に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kukai stayed first in Makionosan-ji Temple in Izumi Province, entered Heian Kyo in August or September of 809 with Daijokanpu (official documents issued by Daijokan, Grand Council of State), and entered Takaosan-ji Temple (later Jingo-ji Temple), which was a private temple of the Wake clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kukai stayed first in Makionosan-ji Temple in Izumi Province, entered Heian Kyo in August or September of 809 with Daijokanpu (official documents issued by Daijokan, Grand Council of State), and entered Takaosan-ji Temple (later Jingo-ji Temple), which was a private temple of the Wake clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kukai stayed first in Makiono-dera Temple in Izumi Province, entered Heian-kyo in August of 809 with Daijokanpu (official documents issued by Daijokan, Grand Council of State), and entered Takaosan-ji Temple (later Jingo-ji Temple), which was a private temple of the Wake clan.</e>
<cmt>Makiono-dera としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="80">
<j>この空海の入京には、最澄の尽力や支援があった、といわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Saicho gave support for Kukai to enter Heian Kyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Saicho supported Kukai entering Heian Kyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Saicho supported Kukai entering Heian-kyo.</e>
<cmt>Heian-kyo としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>最澄は『請来目録』を見て空海が持ち帰った密教の重要さを評価したためといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that this was because, viewing the &quot;Shorai Mokuroku,&quot; Saicho recognized the importance of Esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that this was because, viewing the &quot;Shorai Mokuroku,&quot; Saicho recognized the importance of Esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that this was because, viewing the &quot;Shorai Mokuroku,&quot; Saicho recognized the importance of Esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>その後、二人は10年程交流関係を持った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For around ten years after this, they kept relationships.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For around ten years after this, they kept up a relationship.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For around ten years after this, they kept up a relationship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>密教の分野に限っては、最澄が空海に対して弟子としての礼を取っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concerning the area of Esoteric Buddhism, Saicho took the stance of a disciple for Kukai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concerning the area of Esoteric Buddhism, Saicho took the stance of a disciple for Kukai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concerning the area of Esoteric Buddhism, Saicho took the stance of a disciple for Kukai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>しかし、法華一乗を掲げる最澄と密厳一乗を標榜する空海とは徐々に対立するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Saicho, who advocated hokke-ichijo (Hokke scripture-based philosophy) and Kukai, who advocated mitsugon-ichijo (Esoteric Buddhism-based philosophy), became confronted with each other gradually.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Saicho, who advocated hokke-ichijo (Hokke scripture-based philosophy) and Kukai, who advocated mitsugon-ichijo (Esoteric Buddhism-based philosophy), eventually confronted each other.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Saicho, who advocated hokke-ichijo (Hokke scripture-based philosophy) and Kukai, who advocated mitsugon-ichijo (Esoteric Buddhism-based philosophy), eventually confronted each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>弘仁7年（816年）初頭頃には訣別するに至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, they finally broke their relationships in around early 816.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, they finally broke up their relationship around early 816.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, they finally broke up their relationship around early 816.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>なお二人の訣別に関しては、古くから最澄からの理趣釈経（「理趣経」の注釈書）の借覧要請を空海が拒絶したことや、最澄の弟子泰範が空海の下へ走った問題があげられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concerning the breaking of their relationships, the following have been said from old times: Kukai refused Saicho a request of borrowing Rishishakukyo (commentaries of Rishu-kyo (Principle of Wisdom Sutra)) and Taihan, who had been a discipline of Saicho, became a discipline of Kukai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding the breaking of their relationship, its been said from olden times: Kukai refused Saicho&apos;s request to borrow Rishishakukyo (commentaries of Rishu-kyo - Principle of Wisdom Sutra) and Taihan, who had been a discipline of Saicho, became a discipline of Kukai.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding the breaking of their relationship, it has been said from olden times: Kukai refused Saicho&apos;s request to borrow Rishishakukyo (commentaries of &apos;Rishu-kyo&apos; [Principle of Wisdom Sutra]) and Taihan, who had been a discipline of Saicho, became a discipline of Kukai.</e>
<cmt>&apos; &apos; を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>だが、近年その通説には疑義が提出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, these popular views have become doubted recently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, these popular views have recently become doubted.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, these popular views have recently become doubted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="88">
<j>大同5年（810年）、薬子の変が起こったため、嵯峨天皇側につき鎮護国家のための大祈祷を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Kusuko Incident occurred in 810, Kukai offered a big prayer for protecting the nation, standing on Emperor Saga&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Kusuko Incident occurred in 810, Kukai offered a big prayer for protecting the nation, standing on Emperor Saga&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Kusuko Incident occurred in 810, Kukai offered a big prayer for protecting the nation, standing on Emperor Saga&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="89">
<j>弘仁2年（811年）から弘仁3年（812年）にかけて乙訓寺の別当を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the period from 811 to 812, he assumed the post of betto (chief officer) of Otokuni-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the period from 811 to 812, he assumed the post of betto (chief officer) of Otokuni-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the period from 811 to 812, he assumed the post of betto (chief officer) of Otokuni-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="90">
<j>弘仁3年（812年）11月15日、高雄山寺にて金剛界結縁灌頂を開壇した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 26, 812, he opened a stage for carrying out kanjo ceremonies in Vajradhatu at Takaosan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 26, 812, he opened a stage for carrying out kanjo ceremonies in Vajradhatu at Takaosan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 26, 812, he held kechien-kanjo (ceremony to make a good relationship with Buddha) for Vajradhatu at Takaosan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>結縁灌頂、開壇　の表現を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>入壇者には、最澄も含まれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those for whom a kanjo ceremony was held using the stage included Saicho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those for whom the kanjo ceremony was held using the stage included Saicho.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those for whom the kanjo ceremony was held included Saicho.</e>
<cmt>stage 削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>さらに12月14日には胎蔵灌頂を開壇。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, on January 13, 813, a stage for carrying out kanjo ceremonies in Taizo was opened as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, on January 13, 813, a stage for carrying out kanjo ceremonies in Taizo was opened as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, on January 13, 813, he held a taizo-kanjo (kanjo ceremony in Taizokai).</e>
<cmt>stage 削除しました。胎蔵灌頂→taizo-kanjo (kanjo ceremony in Taizokai)　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>入壇者は最澄やその弟子円澄、光定、泰範の他190名にのぼった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For up to 190 persons, including Saicho and his three disciplines, Encho, Kojo and Taihan, a kanjo ceremony using the stage was held.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For up to 190 persons, including Saicho and his three disciplines, Encho, Kojo and Taihan, a kanjo ceremony was held using the stage.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For up to 190 persons, including Saicho and his three disciplines, Encho, Kojo and Taihan, a kanjo ceremony was held.</e>
<cmt>stage 削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="94">
<j>弘仁6年（815年）春、会津の徳一菩薩、下野の広智禅師、萬徳菩薩（基徳の誤記か?）などの東国有力僧侶の元へ弟子康守らを派遣し密教経典の書写を依頼した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the spring of 815, he sent Koshu, his discipline, to powerful priests in the easter region, such as Tokuichi Bosatsu in Aizu Province, and Kochi zenji and Mantoku (萬徳) Bosatsu (correctly 基徳?) to ask for copying scriptured of Esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>広智禅師、萬徳菩薩、康守：　これらの正しい読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the spring of 815, he sent Koshu, his discipline, to powerful priests in the easter region, such as Tokuichi Bosatsu in Aizu Province, and Kochi zenji and Mantoku (萬徳) Bosatsu (correctly 基徳?) to request copying the scriptures of Esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the spring of 815, he sent Koshu, his discipline, to powerful priests in the eastern region, such as Tokuichi Bosatsu in Aizu Province, and Kochi zenji and Mantoku (萬徳) Bosatsu (it may have been Kitoku) to request copying the scriptures of Esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>また時を同じくして西国筑紫へも勧進をおこなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same period of time, he also made efforts to promote Esoteric Buddhism in Tsukushi in the western region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same period of time, he also made an effort to promote Esoteric Buddhism in Tsukushi in the western region.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same period of time, he also made an effort to promote Esoteric Buddhism in Tsukushi in the western region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>この頃『弁顕密二教論』を著している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around this time, he wrote &quot;Ben Kenmitsu Nikyo Ron.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around this time, he wrote &quot;Ben Kenmitsu Nikyo Ron.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around this time, he wrote &quot;Ben Kenmitsu Nikyo Ron.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="97">
<j>弘仁7年（816年）6月19日、修禅の道場として高野山の下賜を請い、7月8日には、高野山を下賜する旨勅許を賜る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 21, 816, he requested Koya-san Mountain to be granted as a place for Zen training, and gained the imperial sanction that the mountain should be granted to him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 21, 816, he requested Koya-san Mountain to be granted as a place for Zen training, and gained the imperial sanction that the mountain should be granted to him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 21, 816, he requested Mt. Koya to be granted as a place for Zen training, and on August 8, he gained the imperial sanction that the mountain should be granted to him.</e>
<cmt>日付を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>翌弘仁8年（817年）、泰範や実恵ら弟子を派遣して高野山の開創に着手した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 817, he sent his disciplines, including Taihan and Jichie, to Koya-san Mountain to start developing and founding a base place for his religion.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 817, he sent his disciplines, including Taihan and Jichie, to Koya-san Mountain to start developing and founding a base for his religion.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 817, he sent his disciplines, including Taihan and Jichie, to Mt. Koya to start developing and founding a base for his religion.</e>
<cmt>Mt.Koya としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>弘仁9年（818年）11月には、空海自身が勅許後はじめて高野山に登り翌年まで滞在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December of 818 or January of 819, Kukai himself climbed up the mountain for the first time after the sanction was granted, and stayed there until February or March of 819.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December of 818 or January of 819, Kukai himself climbed up the mountain for the first time after the sanction was granted, and stayed there until February or March of 819.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December of 818, Kukai himself climbed up the mountain for the first time after the sanction was granted, and stayed there until the next year.</e>
<cmt>一部表現を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>弘仁10年（819年）春には七里四方に結界を結び、伽藍建立に着手した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the spring of 819, a boundary was set around an approx. 27.3 km square area, and the work to build Buddhist temples there started.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the spring of 819, a boundary was set around an approx. 27.3 km square area, and the work to build Buddhist temples there started.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the spring of 819, a boundary was set around an approx. 27.3 km square area, and the work to build Buddhist temples there started.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="101">
<j>この頃、『即身成仏義』『声字実相義』『吽字義』『文鏡秘府論』『篆隷万象名義』等を立て続けに執筆した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around this time, he wrote &quot;Sokushin Jobutsu gi,&quot; &quot;Shojijissogi,&quot; &quot;Unjigi,&quot; &quot;Bunkyo-hifuron,&quot; and &quot;Tenrei-Bansho-Meigi&quot; one after another.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around this time, he wrote &quot;Sokushin Jobutsu gi,&quot; &quot;Shojijissogi,&quot; &quot;Unjigi,&quot; &quot;Bunkyo-hifuron,&quot; and &quot;Tenrei-Bansho-Meigi&quot; one after another.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around this time, he wrote &quot;Sokushin Jobutsu gi,&quot; &quot;Shojijissogi,&quot; &quot;Unjigi,&quot; &quot;Bunkyo-hifuron,&quot; and &quot;Tenrei-Bansho-Meigi&quot; one after another.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="102">
<j>弘仁12年（821年）、満濃池（まんのういけ、現在の香川県にある日本最大の農業用ため池）の改修を指揮して、アーチ型堤防など当時の最新工法を駆使し工事を成功に導いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 821, he led the work to repair Manno-ike Pond (the largest-in-Japan irrigation pond for farming, located in present Kagawa Prefecture) and led to a successful accomplishment of the work using the latest technology at that time, for example, using arched banks</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 821, he led the work to repair Manno-ike Pond (the largest-in-Japan irrigation pond for farming, located in present Kagawa Prefecture) and led to a successful accomplishment of the work using the latest technology at that time, for example, using arched banks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 821, he led the work to repair Manno-ike Pond (the largest-in-Japan irrigation pond for farming, located in present Kagawa Prefecture) and led to a successful accomplishment of the work using the latest technology at that time, for example, using arched banks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="103">
<j>弘仁13年（822年）、太政官符により東大寺に灌頂道場真言院建立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 822, based on a Daijokanpu (official document issued by Daijokan, Grand Council of State), he built Shingon-in, for offering prayer for the safety of Emperor and the imperial court, in Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 822, based on a Daijokanpu (official document issued by Daijokan, Grand Council of State), he built Shingon-in, for offering prayer for the safety of Emperor and the imperial court, in Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 822, based on a Daijokanpu, he built Shingon-in, for offering prayer for the safety of Emperor and the Imperial Court, in Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>太政官符　既出により補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>この年平城上皇に潅頂を授けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this year, he held a kanjo ceremony for the retired Emperor Heizei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In that year, he held a kanjo ceremony for the retired Emperor Heizei.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In that year, he held a kanjo ceremony for the retired Emperor Heizei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="105">
<j>弘仁14年（823年）正月、太政官符により東寺を賜り、真言密教の道場とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January or February of 823, he was granted To-ji Temple based on a Daijokanpu and used the temple as a training place for Shingon Esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January or February of 823, he was granted To-ji Temple based on a Daijokanpu and used the temple as a training place for Shingon Esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February of 823, he was granted To-ji Temple based on a Daijokanpu and used the temple as a training place for Shingon Esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>2月　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>後に天台宗の密教を台密、対して東寺の密教を東密と呼ぶようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, it became customary to call the Tendai-shu sect-related Esoteric Buddhism Taimitsu, and Esoteric Buddhism at To-ji Temple as Tomitsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, it became customary to call the Tendai-shu sect-related Esoteric Buddhism Taimitsu, and Esoteric Buddhism at To-ji Temple as Tomitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, it became customary to call the Tendai sect-related Esoteric Buddhism Taimitsu, and Esoteric Buddhism at To-ji Temple as Tomitsu.</e>
<cmt>Tendai sect としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>東寺は教王護国寺の名を合わせ持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To-ji Temple is provided with the name of Kyoogokoku-ji Temple as well.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To-ji Temple was also provided with the name of Kyoogokoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To-ji Temple was also provided with the name of Kyoogokoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>しかしながら、この名称が用いられるようになるのは鎌倉時代になってからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is from the Kamakura period that this name became to be used.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this name came to be used from the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this name came to be used from the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="109">
<j>天長元年（824年）2月、勅により神泉苑で祈雨法を修した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March of 824, he offered a kiuho service (service to pray for rain) based on an Imperial order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March of 824, he offered a kiuho service (service to pray for rain) based on an Imperial order.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March of 824, he offered a kiuho service (service to pray for rain) based on an Imperial order.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>3月には少僧都に任命され、僧綱入り（天長4年には大僧都）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April, he was appointed to Shosozu (a junior prelate), entering Sogo (Office of Monastic Affairs) (was appointed to Daisozu (the upper Buddhist priests in the second highest position) in 827).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April, he was appointed to Shosozu (a junior prelate), entering Sogo (Office of Monastic Affairs) (was appointed to Daisozu (the upper Buddhist priests in the second highest position) in 827).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April, he was appointed to Shosozu (a junior prelate), entering Sogo (Office of Monastic Affairs) (was appointed to Daisozu (the upper Buddhist priests in the second highest position) in 827).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>6月に造東寺別当。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July or August, he was appointed to Zo Toji Betto (the chief of the constructing department of To-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July or August, he was appointed to Zo Toji Betto (the chief of the constructing department of To-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July, he was appointed to Zo Toji Betto (the chief of the constructing department of To-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>Augustを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>9月には高雄山寺が定額寺となり、真言僧14名を置き、毎年年分度者一名が許可となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September or October, Takaosan-ji Temple became a Jogaku-ji temple (one of the temples next to national temples in rank), where 14 Shingon priests resided, and became entitled to accept a nenbundo-sha (approved people who enter the Buddhist priesthood) every year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September or October, Takaosan-ji Temple became a Jogaku-ji temple (one of the temples next to national temples in rank), where 14 Shingon priests resided, and became entitled to accept a nenbundo-sha (approved people who enter the Buddhist priesthood) every year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September, Takaosan-ji Temple became a Jogaku-ji temple (one of the temples next to national temples in rank), where 14 Shingon priests resided, and became entitled to accept a nenbundo-sha (approved people who enter the Buddhist priesthood) every year.</e>
<cmt>Octoberを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="113">
<j>天長5年（828年）には『綜藝種智院式并序』を著すとともに、東寺の東にあった藤原三守の私邸を譲り受けて私立の教育施設「綜芸種智院（しゅげいしゅちいん）」を開設。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 828, he wrote &quot;Shugeishuchiin shiki-narabini-jo,&quot; and taking over the private residence of FUJIWARA no Mimori, located adjacent to To-ji Temple, opened &apos;Shugeishuchiin,&apos; a private educational facility.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 828, he wrote &quot;Shugeishuchiin shiki-narabini-jo,&quot; and took over the private residence of FUJIWARA no Mimori, located adjacent to To-ji Temple, and opened &apos;Shugeishuchiin,&apos; a private educational facility.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 828, he wrote &quot;Shugeishuchiin shiki-narabini-jo,&quot; and took over the private residence of FUJIWARA no Mimori, located east of To-ji Temple, and opened &apos;Shugeishuchiin,&apos; a private educational facility.</e>
<cmt>東　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>当時の教育は、貴族や郡司の子弟を対象にするなど、一部の人々にしか門戸を開いていなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Targeted only at children of nobles or gunji, education at that time was only for limited persons.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Targeting only the children of nobles or gunji, education at that time was only for a limited number people.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Targeting only the children of nobles or gunji, education at that time was only for a limited number people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>しかし、綜芸種智院は庶民にも教育の門戸を開いた画期的な学校であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Shugeishuchiin was an epoch-making school that was open to the general public.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Shugeishuchiin was an epoch-making school that was open to the general public.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Shugeishuchiin was an epoch-making school that was open to the general public.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>綜芸種智院の名に表されるように、儒教・仏教・道教などあらゆる思想・学芸を網羅する総合的教育機関でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As known from the name of Shugeishuchiin, it was also a comprehensive educational facility where every philosophy, science and art, including Confucianism, Buddhism and Taoism, were taught.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As known from the name of Shugeishuchiin, it was also a comprehensive educational facility where every philosophy, science and art, including Confucianism, Buddhism and Taoism, were taught.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As known from the name of Shugeishuchiin, it was also a comprehensive educational facility where every philosophy, science and art, including Confucianism, Buddhism and Taoism, were taught.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>また、『綜藝種智院式并序』において「物の興廃は必ず人に由る, 人の昇沈は定んで道にあり」と、学校の存続が運営に携わる人の命運に左右される不安定なものであることを認めたうえで、「一人恩を降し、三公力をあわせ、諸氏の英貴諸宗の大徳、我と志を同じうせば、百世継ぐを成さん」と、天皇、大臣諸侯や仏教諸宗の支持・協力のもとに運営することで恒久的な存続を図る方針を示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Shugeishuchiin shiki-narabini-jo,&quot; he wrote his policy of maintaining the facility permanently through operations under the support and cooperation of Emperor, ministers, lords and all Buddhist sects, as described in the following: First, he admitted that the existence of the school was unstable, depending on the destiny of the persons operating it, saying &apos;The prosperity and demise always depends on the persons concerned, and the ups and downs of a person always depends on whether the person conducts himself or herself rightly or not, and then he described &apos;This school will exist for 100 generations, if a person shows favors, three high level bureaucrats (sanko) cooperate, and with the noble and prosperous clans and the big virtues of various sects, their aspirations are the same those of mine.&apos;</e>
<cmt>2文章を合体しました。一人恩を降し、三公力をあわせ、諸氏の英貴諸宗の大徳、：　意味が十分理解できないままの訳となっております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Shugeishuchiin shiki-narabini-jo,&quot; he wrote his policy of maintaining the facility permanently through operations under the support and cooperation of Emperor, ministers, lords and all Buddhist sects, as described in the following: First, he admitted that the existence of the school was unstable, depending on the destiny of the persons operating it, saying &apos;The prosperity and demise always depends on the persons concerned, and the ups and downs of a person always depends on whether the person conducts himself or herself correctly or not, and then he described &apos;This school will exist for 100 generations, if a person shows favors, three high level bureaucrats (sanko) cooperate, and with the noble and prosperous clans and the big virtues of various sects, their aspirations are the same those of mine.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Shugeishuchiin shiki-narabini-jo,&quot; he wrote his policy of maintaining the facility permanently through operations under the support and cooperation of Emperor, ministers, lords and all Buddhist sects, as described in the following: First, he admitted that the existence of the school was unstable, depending on the destiny of the persons operating it, saying &apos;The prosperity and demise always depends on the persons concerned, and the ups and downs of a person always depends on whether the person conducts himself or herself correctly or not, and then he described &apos;This school will exist for 100 generations, if a person shows favors, three high level bureaucrats (sanko) cooperate, and with the noble and prosperous clans and the big virtues of various sects, their aspirations are the same as those of mine.&apos;</e>
<cmt>same as those としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>ただし、これは実現しなかったらしく、綜芸種智院は空海入滅後10年ほどで廃絶した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is likely that his desire was not achieved, and Shugeishuchiin became extinct in about ten years after Kukai died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is likely that his desire was not achieved, and Shugeishuchiin became extinct about ten years after Kukai died.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is likely that his desire was not achieved, and Shugeishuchiin became extinct about ten years after Kukai died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>現在は種智院大学がその流れを受け継いでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, Shuchiin University inherits its spirit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, Shuchiin University inherits its spirit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, Shuchiin University inherits its spirit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="120">
<j>天長7年（830年）、淳和天皇の勅に答え『秘密曼荼羅十住心論』十巻、『秘蔵宝鑰』三巻を著した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 830, he wrote Himitsu Mandala Jujushinron (Ten Abiding Stages on the Secret Mandalas) of ten volumes and Hizohoyaku of three volumes, corresponding to an imperial order from Emperor Junna.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 830, he wrote Himitsu Mandala Jujushinron (Ten Abiding Stages on the Secret Mandalas) of ten volumes and Hizohoyaku of three volumes, corresponding to an imperial order from Emperor Junna.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 830, he wrote &quot;Himitsu Mandala Jujushinron&quot; (Ten Abiding Stages on the Secret Mandalas) of ten volumes and &quot;Hizohoyaku&quot; of three volumes, corresponding to an Imperial order from Emperor Junna.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="121">
<j>天長8年（831年）5月末、病（悪瘡といわれている）を得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In around middle of June of 832, he suffered from a disease (said bad swelling).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In around the middle of June of 832, he suffered from a disease (said bad swelling).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In around the middle of June of 832, he suffered from a disease (said bad swelling).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>そのため、6月大僧都を辞する旨上表するが、天皇に慰留された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this, he asked for resigning from the post of daisozu in July or August, but was dissuaded by the emperor.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this, he asked to resign from the post of daisozu in July or August, but was dissuaded by the emperor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this, he asked to resign from the post of daisozu in July, but was dissuaded by the emperor.</e>
<cmt>August を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="123">
<j>天長9年（832年）8月22日、高野山において最初の万燈万華会が修された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 23, 832, the first Manto Mange E (a Buddhist mass) in Koya-san Mountain was held.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 23, 832, the first Manto Mange E (a Buddhist mass) in Koya-san Mountain was held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 23, 832, the first Manto Mange E (a Buddhist mass) in Mt. Koya was held.</e>
<cmt>Mt. Koya としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>空海は、願文に「虚空盡き、衆生盡き、涅槃盡きなば、我が願いも盡きなん」と想いを表している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the ganmon (Shinto or Buddhist prayer (read)) at that time, Kukai expressed his thought that &quot;My wishes would be extinct if empty space were extinct, the general public were extinct and Nirvarna were extinct.</e>
<cmt>「虚空盡き、衆生盡き、涅槃盡きなば、我が願いも盡きなん」：　とりあえず、字面らを訳してみた、というレベルと思います。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the ganmon (Shinto or Buddhist prayer - read) at that time, Kukai expressed his thought that &quot;My wishes would be extinct if empty space were extinct, the general public were extinct and Nirvarna were extinct.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the ganmon (written prayers) at that time, Kukai expressed his thought that &apos;My wishes would be extinct if empty space were extinct, the general public were extinct and Nirvana were extinct.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>その後、秋より高野山に隠棲し、穀物を断ち禅定を好む日々であったと伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that, after that, he lived in Koya-san Mountain in seclusion after the autumn, and ate no grain and liked to do zenjo (meditation, and mental concentration) practice every day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that, after that, he lived on Koya-san Mountain in seclusion after the autumn, and ate no grain and liked to do zenjo (meditation, and mental concentration) practice every day.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that, after that, he lived on Mt. Koya in seclusion after the autumn, and ate no grain and liked to do zenjo (meditation, and mental concentration) practice every day.</e>
<cmt>Mt. Koya としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="126">
<j>承和 (日本)元年（834年）2月、東大寺真言院で『法華経』、『般若心経秘鍵』を講じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March or April of 834, he lectured &quot;Hoke-kyo Sutra (the Lotus Sutra)&quot; and &quot;Hannyashin-gyo Hiken&quot; at Shingon-in of Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March or April of 834, he lectured &quot;Hoke-kyo Sutra (the Lotus Sutra)&quot; and &quot;Hannyashin-gyo Hiken&quot; at Shingon-in of Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March of 834, he lectured on the &quot;Hoke-kyo&quot; (the Lotus Sutra) and &quot;Hannyashin-gyo Hiken&quot; at Shingon-in of Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>April を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>12月19日、毎年正月宮中において真言の修法（後七日御修法）を行いたい旨を奏上。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 25, 835, he reported to the Empress his wish of holding Shuho (an esoteric ritual) of the Shingon sect (Goshichinichi no mishiho (seven days New Year ritual)) in the imperial court in every new year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 25, 835, he reported to the Empress his wish of holding Shuho (an esoteric ritual) of the Shingon sect (Goshichinichi no mishiho - seven day New Year ritual) in the imperial court every new year.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 25, 835, he reported to the Emperor his wish of holding Shuho (an esoteric ritual) of the Shingon sect (Goshichinichi no mishiho - seven day New Year ritual) in the Imperial Court every new year.</e>
<cmt>emperor としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>同29日に太政官符で許可され、同24日の太政官符では東寺に三綱を置くことが許されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His wish was accepted with a Daijokanpu issued on February 4, 835, and based on a Daijokanpu issued on January 30, 835, it was permitted to place Sango (three priests with management roles) at To-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His wish was accepted with a Daijokanpu issued on February 4, 835, and based upon a Daijokanpu issued on January 30, 835, it was permitted to place Sango (three priests with management roles) at To-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His wish was accepted with a Daijokanpu issued on February 4, 835, and based upon a Daijokanpu issued on January 30, 835, it was permitted to place Sango (three priests with management roles) at To-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="129">
<j>承和2年（835年）、1月8日より宮中で後七日御修法を修す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Starting on February 13, 835, he held Goshichinichi no mishiho in the imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Starting on February 13, 835, he held Goshichinichi no mishiho in the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Starting on February 13, 835, he held Goshichinichi no mishiho in the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>Imperial Court としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>宮中での御修法はこれより明治になるまで続き、明治以後は東寺に場所を移して今も行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The esoteric ritual held in the imperial court in every year until the Meiji Restoration, and in the Meiji period and later, has been held in To-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The esoteric ritual held in the imperial court in every year until the Meiji Restoration, and in the Meiji period and later, has been held at To-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The esoteric ritual held in the Imperial Court in every year until the Meiji Restoration, and in the Meiji period and later, has been held at To-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Imperial Court としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>1月22日には、真言宗の年分度者3人を申請して許可されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 27, he applied for three nenbundo-sha persons (approved person who enter the Buddhist priesthood), and the application was approved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 27, he applied for three nenbundo-sha persons (approved person who enter the Buddhist priesthood), and the application was approved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 27, he applied for three nenbundo-sha persons, and the application was approved.</e>
<cmt>年分度者　既出のため、補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>2月30日、金剛峯寺が定額寺となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 5, Kongobu-ji Temple became a Jogaku-ji temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 5, Kongobu-ji Temple became a Jogaku-ji temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 5, Kongobu-ji Temple became a Jogaku-ji temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>3月15日、高野山で弟子達に遺告を与え、3月21日に死亡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 20, he gave his will to his disciplines at Koya-san Mountain, and died on April 26.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 20, he gave his will to his disciplines at Koya-san Mountain, and died on April 26.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 20, he gave his will to his disciplines at Mt. Koya and died on April 26.</e>
<cmt>Mt. Koya としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>享年62（満60歳没）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died in the 62nd year after his birth (in 60 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died in the 62nd year after his birth (at 60 years old)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died in the 62nd year after his birth (at 60 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="135">
<j>真済による『空海僧都伝』によると死因は病死で、『続日本後紀』によると遺体は荼毘に付された（火葬された）ようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Kukai-sozu-den&quot; (a biography of Kukai) written by Shinzei, he died of a disease, and it is likely that his body was cremated, according to &quot;Shoku Nihon Koki (Later Chronicle of Japan Continued).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Kukai-sozu-den&quot; (a biography of Kukai) written by Shinzei, he died of a disease, and it is likely that his body was cremated, according to &quot;Shoku Nihon Koki (Later Chronicle of Japan Continued).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Kukai-sozu-den&quot; (a biography of Kukai) written by Shinzei, he died of a disease, and it is likely that his body was cremated, according to &quot;Shoku Nihon Koki&quot; (Later Chronicle of Japan Continued).</e>
<cmt>&quot; の位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>しかし後代には、入定した（即身仏となった）とする文献が現れる（詳しくは後述）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, a document describing that he died through the practice of Nyujo (Sokushinbutsu (Buddhist monks or priests who allegedly caused their own deaths in a way that resulted in their being mummified)) appeared later (described later in details).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, a document describing that he died through the practice of Nyujo (Sokushinbutsu - Buddhist monks or priests who allegedly caused their own deaths in a way that resulted in their being mummified) appeared later (described later in details).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, a document describing that he died through the practice of Nyujo (Sokushinbutsu - Buddhist monks or priests who allegedly caused their own deaths in a way that resulted in their being mummified) appeared later (described later in details).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="137">
<j>天長8年（831年）に病を得た以降の空海は、文字通りみずからの命をかけて真言密教の基盤を磐石化するとともに、その存続のために尽力した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he suffered form a disease in 831, Kukai made every effort, even risking his life, to make the foundation of Shingon Esoteric Buddhism solid enough and to enable the religion to exist for ever.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he suffered form a disease in 831, Kukai made every effort, even risking his life, to make the foundation of Shingon Esoteric Buddhism solid enough and to enable the religion to exist forever.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he suffered form a disease in 831, Kukai made every effort, even risking his life, to make the foundation of Shingon Esoteric Buddhism solid enough and to enable the religion to exist forever.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>とくに承和元年（834年）12月から入滅までの3ヶ月間は、後七日御修法が申請から10日間で許可されその10日後には修法、また年分度者を獲得し金剛峯寺を定額寺とするなど、密度の濃い活動を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular, in the three months between January of 835 to his death, his activities were very aggressive as in the following: Practicing the Goshichinichi-mishiho was permitted only 10 days after the application, in ten day after it, Shuho was actually practiced, acquired nenbundo-sha, and got the status of a Jogaku-ji temple for Kongobu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, in the three months between January of 835 until his death, his activities were very aggressive as in the following: Practicing the Goshichinichi-mishiho was permitted only 10 days after the application, in ten day after it, Shuho was actually practiced, acquired nenbundo-sha, and obtained the status of a Jogaku-ji temple for Kongobu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, in the three months between January of 835 until his death, his activities were very aggressive as in the following: Practicing the Goshichinichi-mishiho was permitted only 10 days after the application, in 10 day after it, Shuho was actually practiced, acquired nenbundo-sha, and obtained the status of a Jogaku-ji temple for Kongobu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>10　数字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>すべてをやり終えた後に入定、即ち永遠の禅定に入ったとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that after all was done, he started the practice of Nyujo (or Sokushinbutsu), the ultimate zen practice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that after all was done, he started the practice of Nyujo (or Sokushinbutsu), the ultimate zen practice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that after all was done, he started the practice of Nyujo (or Sokushinbutsu), the ultimate zen practice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>弘法大師</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kobo Daishi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kobo Daishi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kobo Daishi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="140">
<j>延喜21年（921年）10月27日、東寺長者観賢の奏上により、醍醐天皇から「弘法大師」の諡号が贈られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 4, 921, shigo (a posthumous name) of Kobo Daishi was granted by Emperor Daigo, corresponding to a report to the emperor from Kangen, To-ji choja (the chief abbot of To-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 4, 921, shigo (posthumous name) of Kobo Daishi was granted by Emperor Daigo, corresponding to a report to the emperor from Kangen, To-ji choja (the chief abbot of To-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 4, 921, shigo (posthumous name) of Kobo Daishi was granted by Emperor Daigo, corresponding to a report to the emperor from Kangen, To-ji choja (the chief abbot of To-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="141">
<j>最初は「本覚大師」の諡号が贈られることになっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Initially, it was decided that the shigo was Hongaku Daishi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially, it was decided that the shigo was Hongaku Daishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially, it was decided that the shigo was Hongaku Daishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>しかしながら、「弘法利生（こうぼうりしょう）」の業績から、「弘法大師」の諡号が贈られることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the shigo of Kobo Daishi became to be granted actually due to his accomplishments concerning &quot;Kobo-risho&quot; (meaning &quot;making the religion known widely and benefiting living things&quot;).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the shigo of Kobo Daishi was granted actually due to his accomplishments concerning &quot;Kobo-risho&quot; (meaning &quot;making the religion known widely and benefiting living things&quot;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the shigo of Kobo Daishi was granted actually due to his accomplishments concerning &apos;Kobo-risho&apos; (meaning &quot;making the religion known widely and benefiting living things&quot;).</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="143">
<j>弘法大師は「空海」を越え、千年の時を越え、普遍化したイメージでもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Transcending &quot;Kukai&quot; and in more than thousand years, Kobo Daishi is a popularized image as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Transcending &quot;Kukai&quot; and in more than thousand years, Kobo Daishi is a popularized image as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Transcending &apos;Kukai&apos; and in more than thousand years, Kobo Daishi is a popularized image as well.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>歴史上、天皇から下賜された大師号は全27名におよぶが、一般的に大師 (僧)と言えばほとんどの場合弘法大師を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the history, a Daishi-go title was granted by emperors up to 27 persons, but it almost always indicates Kobo Daishi when the term of Daishi is used generally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In history, a Daishi-go title was granted by emperors up to 27 year olds, but it almost always indicates Kobo Daishi when the term of Daishi is used generally.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In history, a Daishi-go title was granted by emperors up to 27 persons, but it almost always indicates Kobo Daishi when the term of Daishi is used generally.</e>
<cmt>persons としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>空海を知らなくても「弘法さん」「お大師さん」を知る人は多いと言えるだろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be said that even many of those who do not know Kukai would know &quot;Kobo-san&quot; (Mr. Kobo) or &quot;o-Daishi-san&quot; (Mr, Daishi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be said that even many of those who do not know Kukai would know &quot;Kobo-san&quot; (Mr. Kobo) or &quot;o-Daishi-san&quot; (Mr. Daishi).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be said that even many of those who do not know Kukai would know &apos;Kobo-san&apos; (Mr. Kobo) or &apos;o-Daishi-san&apos; (Mr. Daishi).</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="146">
<j>真言宗では、宗祖空海を「大師」と崇敬し、その入定を死ではなく禅定に入っているものとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Shingon sect, Kukai, its founder, was worshiped as &quot;Daishi,&quot; and his Nyujo was not death but he still continues his Zenjo practice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Shingon sect, Kukai, its founder, was worshiped as &quot;Daishi,&quot; and his Nyujo was not death but he still continues his Zenjo practice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Shingon sect, Kukai, its founder, was worshiped as &apos;Daishi,&apos; and his Nyujo was not death but he still continues his Zenjo practice.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="147">
<j>高野山奥の院御廟で空海は今も生き続けていると信じ、「南無大師遍照金剛」の称呼によって宗祖への崇敬を確認するのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that Kukai is still alive in the mausoleum of Oku-no-in (inner sanctuary) in Koya-san Mountain, and worship to the founder of the sect was confirmed by chanting the phrase of &quot;Namu Daishi Henjo Kongo.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that Kukai is still alive in the mausoleum of Oku-no-in (inner sanctuary) on Koya-san Mountain, and worship to the founder of the sect was confirmed by chanting the phrase of &quot;Namu Daishi Henjo Kongo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that Kukai is still alive in the mausoleum of Oku-no-in (inner sanctuary) on Mt. Koya, and worship to the founder of the sect was confirmed by chanting the phrase of &apos;Namu Daishi Henjo Kongo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="148">
<j>故郷である四国において彼が山岳修行時代に遍歴した霊跡は、江戸初期の真念によって札番号を付けてまとめられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sites in Shikoku, his birth place, where he wandered while doing ascetic practices in mountains became to be called sacred sites, and a number (called fuda number) was given to each of them by Shinen who lived in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sites in Shikoku, his birth place, where he wandered while doing ascetic practices in the mountains came to be called sacred sites, and a number (called fuda number) was given to each of them by Shinen who lived in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sites in Shikoku, his birth place, where he wandered while doing ascetic practices in the mountains came to be called sacred sites, and a number (called fuda number) was given to each of them by Shinen who lived in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>これらは、俗に言う四国八十八箇所の寺々他多くの霊跡として残り、それ以降霊場巡りは幅広く大衆の信仰を集めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With many sacred sites remaining in addition to so-called 88 Shikoku temples, these sacred sites have thereafter been visited and worshipped by the general public</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With many sacred sites remaining in addition to so-called 88 Shikoku temples, these sacred sites have thereafter been visited and worshipped by the general public</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With many sacred sites remaining in addition to so-called 88 Shikoku temples, these sacred sites have thereafter been visited and worshipped by the general public</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>入定に関する諸説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various theories about Nyujo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various theories about Nyujo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various theories about Nyujo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="150">
<j>高野山奥の院の霊廟には現在も空海が禅定を続けているとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Kukai still continues his zenjo practice in the mausoleum of Oku-no-in in Koya-san Mountain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Kukai still continues his zenjo practice in the mausoleum of Oku-no-in in Koya-san Mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Kukai still continues his zenjo practice in the mausoleum of Oku-no-in in Mt. Koya.</e>
<cmt>Mt. Koya としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="151">
<j>奥の院の維那（ゆいな）と呼ばれる仕侍僧が衣服と二時の食事を給仕している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A siji-so (attendant priest) called Yuina at the Oku-no-in changes his clothes and serves meals two times a day.</e>
<cmt>二時の食事：　”一日2回の食事”の意味に解釈して訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A siji-so (attendant priest) called Yuina at the Oku-no-in changes his clothes and serves meals two times a day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A shiji-so (attendant priest) called Yuina at the Oku-no-in changes his clothes and serves meals two times a day.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>霊廟内の模様は維那以外が窺う事はできず、維那を務めた者も他言しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobody other than Yuina can look the inside of the mausoleum, and Yuina does not say anything about what he saw there.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobody other than Yuina can look the inside of the mausoleum, and Yuina does not say anything about what he saw there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobody other than Yuina can look the inside of the mausoleum, and Yuina does not say anything about what he saw there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>そのため一般には不明のままである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, what is there still remains unknown generally.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, what is there still remains unknown generally.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, what is there still remains unknown generally.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="154">
<j>現存する資料で空海の入定に関する初出のものは、入寂後100年以上を経た康保5年（968年）に仁海が著した『金剛峰寺建立修行縁起』で、入定した空海は四十九日を過ぎても容色に変化がなく髪や髭が伸び続けていたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first existing document about his Nyujo was &quot;Kongobuji Konryu Shugyo Engi&quot; written by Ningai in 968, in more than 100 years after his death, in which he described that, even in 49 days after his Nyujo, his body color remained unchanged and his hair and beard continued growing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first existing document about his Nyujo was &quot;Kongobuji Konryu Shugyo Engi&quot; written by Ningai in 968, in more than 100 years after his death, in which he described that, even 49 days after his Nyujo, his body color remained unchanged and his hair and beard continued growing.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first existing document about his Nyujo was &quot;Kongobuji Konryu Shugyo Engi&quot; written by Ningai in 968, in more than 100 years after his death, in which he described that, even 49 days after his Nyujo, his body color remained unchanged and his hair and beard continued growing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>また、『今昔物語』には高野山が東寺との争いで一時荒廃していた時期、東寺長者であった観賢が霊廟を開いたという記述がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Konjaku Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Times Now Past), it is described that, in the period when the religious site in Koya-san Mountain was dilapidated due to a dispute with the To-ji Temple side, Kangen, the To-ji choja at that time, opened the mausoleum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Konjaku Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Times Now Past), it is described that, in the period when the religious site in Koya-san Mountain was dilapidated due to a dispute with the To-ji Temple side, Kangen, the To-ji choja at that time, opened the mausoleum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Konjaku Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Times Now Past), it is described that, in the period when the religious site in Mt. Koya was dilapidated due to a dispute with the To-ji Temple side, Kangen, the To-ji choja at that time, opened the mausoleum.</e>
<cmt>Mt. Koya としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>これによると霊廟の空海は石室と厨子で二重に守られ坐っていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to this, Kukai in the mausoleum sat protected doubly by a stone chamber and a zushi (a cupboard-like case with double doors in which an image of (the) Buddha, a sutra, or some other revered object is kept at a temple).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to this, Kukai in the mausoleum sat protected doubly by a stone chamber and a zushi (a cupboard-like case with double doors in which an image of (the) Buddha, a sutra, or some other revered object is kept at a temple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to this, Kukai in the mausoleum sat protected doubly by a stone chamber and a zushi (a cupboard-like case with double doors in which an image of (the) Buddha, a sutra, or some other revered object is kept at a temple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>観賢は、一尺あまり伸びていた空海の蓬髪を剃り衣服や数珠の綻びを繕い整えた後、再び封印した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kangen shaved approx. 30-cm long disheveled hair, repaired his clothes and juzu (beadroll), and then sealed the place again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kangen shaved approx. 30-cm long disheveled hair, repaired his clothes and juzu (beadroll), and then sealed the place again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kangen shaved approx. 30-cm long disheveled hair, repaired his clothes and juzu (beadroll), and then sealed the place again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="158">
<j>このように一般には空海は肉身を留めて入定していると信じられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this way, it is generally believed that Kuaki is in a Nyujo state with his body still remaining.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this way, it is generally believed that Kuaki is in a Nyujo state with his body still remaining.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this way, it is generally believed that Kukai is in a Nyujo state with his body still remaining.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>しかしながら、『続日本後紀』に記された淳和天皇が高野山に下した院宣に空海の荼毘に関する件が見えること、空海入定直後に東寺長者の実慧が青竜寺へ送った手紙の中に空海を荼毘に付したと取れる記述があることなど、いくつかの根拠を示して火葬されたとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there is a view of considering that his body was cremated, based on the following descriptions: The inzen (a decree from the retired Emperor) that Emperor Junna sent to the Koya-san side included an item related the cremation of Kukai&apos;s body, and a letter Jichie, To-ji choja at that time, sent to Qinglong Temple included a description that could be considered that Kukai&apos;s body had been cremated.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there is a view of considering that his body was cremated, based on the following descriptions: The inzen (a decree from the retired Emperor) that Emperor Junna sent to the Koya-san side included an item related the cremation of Kukai&apos;s body, and a letter Jichie, To-ji choja at that time, sent to Qinglong Temple included a description that could be considered that Kukai&apos;s body had been cremated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there is a view of considering that his body was cremated, based on the following descriptions: &quot;Shoku Nihon Koki&quot; describes that an Inzen (a decree from the retired Emperor) that Emperor Junna sent to the Mt. Koya included an item related the cremation of Kukai&apos;s body, and a letter Jichie, To-ji choja at that time, sent to Qinglong Temple included a description that could be considered that Kukai&apos;s body had been cremated.</e>
<cmt>Mt. Koya としました。『続日本後記』　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="160">
<j>このように空海に関しては、史実よりも伝承のほうが多く、この方面での研究が待たれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this way, oral traditions more than historical facts exist concerning Kukai, and further research remains to be conduced in this sphere.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this way, oral traditions more so than historical facts exist concerning Kukai, and further research remains to be conduced in this sphere.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this way, oral traditions more so than historical facts exist concerning Kukai, and further research remains to be conduced in this sphere.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>年譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A chronological list of the main events</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A chronological list of the main events</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A chronological list of the main events</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>評価</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Evaluations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Evaluations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Evaluations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>真言宗の開祖として</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the founder of the Shingon sect</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the founder of the Shingon sect</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the founder of the Shingon sect</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="161">
<j>空海は、江戸時代を通して、お大師さんとして人々に親しまれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kukai was familiar with people as o-Daishi-san throughout the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kukai was familiar with people such as o-Daishi-san throughout the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kukai was familiar with people such as o-Daishi-san throughout the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>しかし、純正の日本に仏教という外来の不純な思想を持ち込んだとして、本居宣長などによって批判された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he was criticized by Norinaga MOTOORI and others saying that Kukai brought to pure Japan a foreign impure philosophy called Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he was criticized by Norinaga MOTOORI and others saying that Kukai brought to pure Japan a foreign impure philosophy called Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he was criticized by Norinaga MOTOORI and others saying that Kukai brought to pure Japan a foreign impure philosophy called Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="163">
<j>明治時代に入ると廃仏毀釈運動によって一時的にその評価が落ちることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Entering the Meiji period, he became lowly evaluated due to Haibutsu-kishaku undo (anti-Buddhism movement).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Entering the Meiji period, he became lowly evaluated due to Haibutsu-kishaku undo (anti-Buddhism movement).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Entering the Meiji period, he became lowly evaluated due to Haibutsu-kishaku undo (anti-Buddhism movement).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="164">
<j>空海は、今もなお高野山に隠れているということから、空海が高野山に隠れてから50年ごとに「御遠忌」法要が営まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because it is said that Kukai still hides in Koya-san Mountain, a goenki memorial service was held every 50 years after he hid in the mountain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because it is said that Kukai still hides on Koya-san Mountain, a goenki memorial service has been held every 50 years after he hid on the mountain.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because it is said that Kukai still hides on Koya-san Mountain, a goenki memorial service has been held every 50 years after he hid on the mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>しかしながら、1884年のそれは明治時代初頭であったため、上の理由から低調だったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is said that the one in 1884 was dull because the timing was in early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is said that the one in 1884 was dull because the timing was during the early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is said that the one in 1884 was dull because the timing was during the early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="166">
<j>そのためか、1934年の御遠忌は単なる宗教行事にとどまらず、大阪朝日新聞や東京日日新聞などの新聞社を巻き込んだ一大キャンペーンとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason?, the goenki held in 1934 became rather like a big campaign than a mere religious event, with The Asahi Shinbun in Osaka and Tokyo Nichinichi Newspaper involved as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason?, the goenki held in 1934 became rather like a big campaign than a mere religious event, with The Asahi Shinbun in Osaka and Tokyo Nichinichi Newspaper involved as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It may have been for this reason that the goenki held in 1934 became rather like a big campaign than a mere religious event, with The Asahi Shinbun in Osaka and Tokyo Nichinichi Newspaper involved as well.</e>
<cmt>？ →It may have been としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="167">
<j>このキャンペーンのなかで、かつて不純な思想を持ち込んだと批判された空海は、外来の思想を日本流に換骨奪胎して紹介し、日本文化の形成に一役買った人物として評価されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this campaign, Kukai, who was once criticized saying that he brought to Japan an impure philosophy, became to be evaluated as a person who introduced foreign philosophy after totally altering the contents so as to conform to Japanese ways and contributed to the formation of Japanese culture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this campaign, Kukai, who was once criticized for bringing an impure philosophy to Japan, came to be evaluated as a person who introduced foreign philosophy after totally altering the contents to conform to Japanese ways and contributed to the formation of Japanese culture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this campaign, Kukai, who was once criticized for bringing an impure philosophy to Japan, came to be evaluated as a person who introduced foreign philosophy after totally altering the contents to conform to Japanese ways and contributed to the formation of Japanese culture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="168">
<j>これは1934年という時代と関係している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This situation is related to the year of 1934.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This situation is related to the year 1934.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This situation is related to the year 1934.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="169">
<j>日本と中国の戦争すなわち日華事変がすでにこのとき開始しており、国民が団結して戦争に臨む必要があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">War between Japan and China, or Nikkajihen, had already broken out, and it was necessary for the national to be united for the war.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">War between Japan and China, or Nikkajihen, had already broken out, and it was necessary for the nation to be united for the war.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">War between Japan and China, or Nikkajihen, had already broken out, and it was necessary for the nation to be united for the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>そのために国民の英雄として空海が再評価されたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was this reason that Kukai was re-evaluated as a national hero.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was this reason Kukai was re-evaluated as a national hero.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was this reason Kukai was re-evaluated as a national hero.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="171">
<j>日本統治時代の影響を受けてか、台湾には空海を祀る廟が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to influence in the period of Japan&apos;s rule?, there are many mausoleums enshrining Kukai in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to influence during the period of Japan&apos;s rule?, there are many mausoleums enshrining Kukai in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Perhaps due to influence during the period of Japan&apos;s rule, there are many mausoleums enshrining Kukai in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>? →perhaps　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>書家として</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a calligrapher</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a calligrapher</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a calligrapher</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="172">
<j>書道は在唐中、韓方明に学んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He learned calligraphy from Homei KAN while he stayed in Tang.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He learned calligraphy from Homei KAN while he stayed in Tang.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He learned calligraphy from Homei KAN while he stayed in Tang.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="173">
<j>唐の地ですでに書家として知られ、殊に王羲之や顔真卿の書風の影響を受け、また篆書体、隷書体、楷書体、行書体、草書体、飛白体文字すべてよくした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was known as a calligrapher already in Tang, was affected, in particular, by the Tang style of Wang Xizhi and Gan Shinkei, and was good at all of tensho-tai (seal-engraving style of writing Chinese characters), tensho-tai (seal-engraving style of writing Chinese characters), kaisho-tai (square (block) style of writing), gyosho-tai (semi-cursive style of writing), sosho-tai (cursive style writing), and hihaku-tai (splash pattern of writing) characters.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was known as a calligrapher already in Tang, and was affected, in particular, by the Tang style of Wang Xizhi and Gan Shinkei, and was good at all of tensho-tai (seal-engraving style of writing Chinese characters), tensho-tai (seal-engraving style of writing Chinese characters), kaisho-tai (square block style of writing), gyosho-tai (semi-cursive style of writing), sosho-tai (cursive style writing), and hihaku-tai (splash pattern of writing) characters.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was known as a calligrapher already in Tang, and was affected, in particular, by the Tang style of Wang Xizhi and Gan Shinkei, and was good at all of tensho-tai (seal-engraving style of writing Chinese characters), reisho-tai (clerical script), kaisho-tai (square block style of writing), gyosho-tai (semi-cursive style of writing), sosho-tai (cursive style writing), and hihaku-tai (splash pattern of writing) characters.</e>
<cmt>隷書体　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="174">
<j>中国では風信帖五筆和尚といわれ、日本では入木道の祖と仰がれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was called Fushinjo Gohitsu Osho (priest) in China, and was worshipped as the founder of Jubokudo (calligraphy) in Japan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was called Fushinjo Gohitsu Osho (priest) in China, and was worshipped as the founder of Jubokudo (calligraphy) in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was called Gohitsu Osho (the priest who writes with five brushes) in China, and was worshipped as the founder of Jubokudo (calligraphy) in Japan.</e>
<cmt>原文wikiでは「風信帖」はなく、「五筆和尚」のみです。従ってここでも「風信帖」は削除し、左記のようにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="175">
<j>日本の書流は大師流と称された不出世の能書家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a peerless expert calligrapher, as it is said that the Japanese calligraphic style is that of Daishi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a peerless expert calligrapher, as it is said that the Japanese calligraphic style is that of Daishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a peerless expert calligrapher, as it is said that the Japanese calligraphic style is that of Daishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="176">
<j>真跡としては次のようなものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Shinseki (original handwritings) include the following:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Shinseki (original handwritings) include the following:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Shinseki (original handwritings) include the following:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="177">
<j>聾瞽指帰（ろうこしいき）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rokoshiki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rokoshiki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rokoshiki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="178">
<j>『三教指帰』の初稿本に当る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was the first edition of &quot;Sango ishiki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the first edition of &quot;Sango ishiki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the first edition of &quot;Sango shiiki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>shiiki と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="179">
<j>2巻存し、入唐前、延暦16年（797年）24歳頃の書といわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two volumes remain, and it is said that they were written in around 797, around the age of 24, before going to Tang.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two volumes remain, and it is said that they were written around 797, at the age of about 24, before going to Tang.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two volumes remain, and it is said that they were written around 797, at the age of about 24, before going to Tang.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="180">
<j>書はやや硬いが筆力があり、後の風信帖に見られる書風とは異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The calligraphic style is rather rigid and is slightly different from the style seen in Fushinjo (the letters Kukai wrote to Saicho) written later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The calligraphic style is rather rigid and is slightly different from the style seen in Fushinjo (the letters Kukai wrote to Saicho) written later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The calligraphic style is rather rigid and is slightly different from the style seen in Fushinjo (the letters Kukai wrote to Saicho) written later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="181">
<j>金剛峯寺蔵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Owned by Kongobu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Owned by Kongobu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Owned by Kongobu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="182">
<j>国宝。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A national treasure</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A national treasure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A national treasure.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="183">
<j>灌頂歴名（かんじょうれきめい、『灌頂記』とも）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanjo rekimei (a record list of the Ganjo (an important ceremony in the esoteric Buddhism)) (written as 灌頂歴名 or 灌頂記)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanjo rekimei (a record list of the Ganjo - an important ceremony in the esoteric Buddhism) (written as 灌頂歴名 or 灌頂記)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanjo rekimei (a record list of the Ganjo - an important ceremony in the esoteric Buddhism) (written as 灌頂歴名 or 灌頂記)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="184">
<j>弘仁3年（812年）から弘仁4年（813年）にかけて、空海が高雄山寺で金剛・胎蔵両界の灌頂を授けた時の人名を記録した手記である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the private note in which he wrote the names of the persons for whom he held a kanjo ceremony in Vajradhatu or Taizokai in the period from 812 to 813</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a private note in which he wrote the names of the persons for whom he held a kanjo ceremony in Vajradhatu or Taizokai during the period from 812 to 813.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a private note in which he wrote the names of the persons for whom he held a kanjo ceremony in Vajradhatu or Taizokai during the period from 812 to 813.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="185">
<j>処々書き直しているが、筆力、結構ともに流露している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although rewritten in several portions, the calligraphy is powerful and the configurations are clearly visible.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although rewritten in several portions, the calligraphy is powerful and the configurations are clearly visible.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although rewritten in several portions, the calligraphy is powerful and the configurations are clearly visible.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="186">
<j>神護寺蔵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Owned by Jingo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Owned by Jingo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Owned by Jingo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="187">
<j>国宝。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A national treasure</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A national treasure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A national treasure.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="188">
<j>風信帖（ふうしんじょう）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fushinjo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fushinjo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fushinjo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="189">
<j>国宝指定名称は「弘法大師筆尺牘（せきとく）」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was designated as a national treasure in the title of &apos;Kobo Daishi hitsu sekitoku.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was designated as a national treasure in the title of &apos;Kobo Daishi hitsu sekitoku.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was designated as a national treasure in the title of &apos;Kobo Daishi hitsu sekitoku.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="190">
<j>空海が最澄に送った書状3通を1巻にまとめたもので、1通目の書き出しの句に因んで風信帖と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a volume of the three letters sent to Saicho, and is called after the initial phrase on the first letter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a volume of the three letters sent to Saicho, and is called after the initial phrase on the first letter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a volume of the three letters sent to Saicho, and is called after the initial phrase on the first letter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="191">
<j>もとは5通あったが、1通は盗まれ、1通は豊臣秀次の所望により、天正20年（1592年）献上したことが巻末の奥付に記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following is written on the okuzuke (ordinarily the last page of a book where the author name, publisher&apos;s name, etc. are written): Originally, there were five letters, but one of them was stolen and another one was requested by Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI and was presented to him in 1592.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following is written on the okuzuke (ordinarily the last page of a book where the author name, publisher&apos;s name, etc. are written): Originally, there were five letters, but one of them was stolen and another one was requested by Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI and was presented to him in 1592.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following is written on the okuzuke (ordinarily the last page of a book where the author name, publisher&apos;s name, etc. are written): Originally, there were five letters, but one of them was stolen and another one was requested by Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI and was presented to him in 1592.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="192">
<j>現存の3通は、いずれも行草体の率意の書で、空海の書として灌頂歴名とともに絶品とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Any of the three remaining letters are written freely in the gyosho-tai style and are said to be superb as Kukai&apos;s calligraphy, together with the Kanjo rekimei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All of the three remaining letters were written freely in the gyosho-tai style and are said to be superb as Kukai&apos;s calligraphy, together with the Kanjo rekimei.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All of the three remaining letters were written freely in the gyosho-tai style and are said to be superb as Kukai&apos;s calligraphy, together with the Kanjo rekimei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="193">
<j>年号は不明であるが、弘仁3年（812年）頃とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The year when they were written is not known, but is said being likely to be around 812.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year when they were written is not known, but is said being likely to be around 812.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year when they were written is not known, but is said being likely to be around 812.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="194">
<j>第1通目は、9月11日付で「風信雲書」の書き出し。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dated on September 11 (in the old calendar), the first letter is started with &apos;Fushinunsho.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dated on September 11 (in the old calendar), the first letter starts with &apos;Fushinunsho.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dated on September 11 (in the old calendar), the first letter starts with &apos;Fushinunsho.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="195">
<j>書風は謹厳である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The calligraphic style is solemn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The calligraphic style is solemn.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The calligraphic style is solemn.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="196">
<j>第2通目は、9月13日付で「忽披枉書」の書き出し。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dated on September 13 (in the old calendar), the second letter is started with &quot;Kotsuhi Osho.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dated on September 13 (in the old calendar), the second letter starts with &quot;Kotsuhi Osho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dated on September 13 (in the old calendar), the second letter starts with &quot;Kotsuhi Osho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="197">
<j>書風は精気があり、また情緒もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The calligraphic style is vigorous and affectionate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The calligraphic style is vigorous and affectionate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The calligraphic style is vigorous and affectionate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="198">
<j>第3通目は、9月5日付で「忽恵書礼」の書き出し。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dated on September 5 (in the old calendar), the third letter is started with &quot;Kotsukei Shorei.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dated September 5 (in the old calendar), the third letter starts with &quot;Kotsukei Shorei.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dated September 5 (in the old calendar), the third letter starts with &quot;Kotsukei Shorei.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="199">
<j>流麗な草書体である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This letter is written in a flowing sosho-tai style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This letter is written in the flowing sosho-tai style.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This letter is written in the flowing sosho-tai style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="200">
<j>全体は王羲之の体である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a whole, Wang Xizhi&apos;s style is employed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a whole, the Wang Xizhi&apos;s style is employed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a whole, the Wang Xizhi&apos;s style is employed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="201">
<j>東寺蔵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Owned by To-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Owned by To-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Owned by To-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="202">
<j>国宝。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A national treasure</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A national treasure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A national treasure.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="203">
<j>崔子玉座右銘（さいしぎょく ざゆうのめい）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saishigyoku-zayunomei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saishigyoku-zayunomei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saishigyoku-zayunomei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="204">
<j>後漢の中国の書家一覧崔瑗の『座右銘』100字（五言二十句）を草書で2、3字ずつ、数十行に書かれたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this, the 100 characters (five characters/phrase x 20 phrases) of &quot;Zayumei&quot; in the calligrapher list in the Later Han Dynasty in China were written in the sosho-tai style, with two ro three characters on each line of several tens of lines in total.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this, the 100 characters (five characters/phrase x 20 phrases) of &quot;Zayumei&quot; in the calligrapher list in the Later Han Dynasty in China were written in the sosho-tai style, with two ro three characters on each line of several tens of lines in total.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this, the 100 characters (five characters/phrase x 20 phrases) of &quot;Zayumei&quot; in the calligrapher list in the Later Han Dynasty in China were written in the sosho-tai style, with two ro three characters on each line of several tens of lines in total.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="205">
<j>もとは白麻紙の横巻で高野山宝亀院の蔵であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, this calligraphic product was written on white asa (hemp) paper that could be scrolled laterally, and was owned by Hoki-in in Koya-san Mountain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, this calligraphic product was written on white asa (hemp) paper that could be scrolled laterally, and was owned by Hoki-in in Koya-san Mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, this calligraphic product was written on white asa (hemp) paper that could be scrolled laterally, and was owned by Hoki-in Temple in Mt. Koya.</e>
<cmt>Hoki-in Temple としました。Mt. Koya としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="206">
<j>しかしながら、今は同院に冒頭10字が残るだけで、他は諸家に分蔵され、100字中42字が現存する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, now, the calligraphy of only initial ten characters remain in the temple, and the others are owned by various families separately, with those of 42 characters of the 100 characters still remaining.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, now, the calligraphy of only initial ten characters remain in the temple, and the others are owned by various families separately, with those of 42 characters of the 100 characters still remaining.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, now, the calligraphy of only initial ten characters remain in the temple, and the others are owned by various families separately, with those of 42 characters of the 100 characters still remaining.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="207">
<j>字径が12cm〜16cmもあるので古筆は『大字切』（だいじぎれ）と称している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because the character sizes are as large as 12 cm to 16 cm, this ancient calligraphic product is called &quot;Daiji (big character)-gire.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the character sizes are as large as 12 cm to 16 cm, this ancient calligraphic product is called &quot;Daiji (big character)-gire.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the character sizes are as large as 12 cm to 16 cm, this ancient calligraphic product is called &quot;Daiji (big character)-gire.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="208">
<j>なお、空海の門人で同じ佐伯氏の出身である実慧は若い頃に同じ一族と思われる讃岐国多度郡出身の佐伯酒麻呂らに儒学を学んだとされている（『弘法大師弟子伝』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Jichie, who was a follower of Kukai and came from the same Saeki clan as that of Kukai, leant Confucianism from SAEKI no Sakemaro, who came from Tado no Gori, Sanuki Province and is considered also coming from the same clan (according to &quot;Disciplines of Kobo Daishi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Jichie, who was a follower of Kukai and came from the same Saeki clan as that of Kukai, learnt Confucianism from SAEKI no Sakemaro, who came from Tado no Gori, Sanuki Province and is considered also to come from the same clan (according to &quot;Disciplines of Kobo Daishi.&quot;)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Jichie, who was a follower of Kukai and came from the same Saeki clan as that of Kukai, learnt Confucianism from SAEKI no Sakemaro, who came from Tado no Gori, Sanuki Province and is considered also to come from the same clan (according to &quot;Disciplines of Kobo Daishi.&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="209">
<j>しかしながら、酒麻呂とその一族が平安時代前期において、長期に渡って書博士の地位を占めていた事が『日本三代実録』に記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is described in &quot;Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku&quot; (sixth of the six classical Japanese history texts) that Sakemaro and his clan occupied the post of Sho hakase (professor of calligraphy) for a long period of time in the first half of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is described in the &quot;Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku&quot; (sixth of the six classical Japanese history texts) that Sakemaro and his clan occupied the post of Sho hakase (professor of calligraphy) for a long period of time in the first half of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is described in the &quot;Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku&quot; (sixth of the six classical Japanese history texts) that Sakemaro and his clan occupied the post of Sho hakase (professor of calligraphy) for a long period of time in the first half of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="210">
<j>空海を含む讃岐の佐伯氏は、書と深く関わりを持っていた一族であったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that the Saeki clan in Sanuki, including Kukai, was deeply related to calligraphy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that the Saeki clan in Sanuki, including Kukai, was deeply related to calligraphy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that the Saeki clan in Sanuki, including Kukai, was deeply related to calligraphy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>弘法大師の伝説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Legends about Kobo Daishi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Legends about Kobo Daishi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Legends about Kobo Daishi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="211">
<j>「弘法大師」は空海の諡号であるが、「弘法大師」と「空海」とは必ずしも同じではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although &quot;Kobo Daishi&quot; is the posthumous name of Kukai, &quot;Kobo Daishi&quot; and &quot;Kukai are not always the same.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although &quot;Kobo Daishi&quot; is the posthumous name of Kukai, &quot;Kobo Daishi&quot; and &quot;Kukai are not always the same.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although &apos;Kobo Daishi&apos; is the posthumous name of Kukai, &apos;Kobo Daishi&apos; and &apos;Kukai&apos; are not always the same.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="212">
<j>弘法大師に関する伝説は、北海道を除く日本各地に5,000以上あるといわれ、歴史上の空海の足跡をはるかに越えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that more than 5,000 legends about Kobo Daishi exist throughout Japan, by far exceeding the number of sites where Kukai actually visited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that more than 5,000 legends about Kobo Daishi exist throughout Japan, by far exceeding the number of sites where Kukai actually visited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that more than 5,000 legends about Kobo Daishi exist throughout Japan, by far exceeding the number of sites where Kukai actually visited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="213">
<j>柳田国男は大子（オオゴ、神の長男を意味）伝説が大師伝説に転化したという説を提出している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kunio YANAGITA presented the theory that legends about Ogo (meaning the oldest son of god) were transformed into those about Daishi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kunio YANAGITA presented the theory that legends about Ogo (meaning the oldest son of god) were transformed into those about Daishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kunio YANAGITA presented the theory that legends about Ogo (meaning the oldest son of god) were transformed into those about Daishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="214">
<j>しかしながら、他に中世、日本全国を勧進して廻った遊行僧である高野聖の存在もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the medieval period, Koya-hijiri, who were Yugyo-so (traveling monks) from starting from Koya-Mountain, traveled while requesting donations around Japan, and therefore, the existence of such monks should also be taken into account.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the medieval period, Koya-hijiri, who were Yugyo-so (traveling monks) from starting from Koya-Mountain, traveled while requesting donations around Japan, and therefore, the existence of such monks should also be taken into account.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the medieval period, Koya-hijiri, who were Yugyo-so (traveling monks) starting from Koya-Mountain, traveled while requesting donations around Japan, and therefore, the existence of such monks should also be taken into account.</e>
<cmt>from を一箇所削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="215">
<j>ただ、闇雲に多くの事象と弘法大師が結び付けられたわけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it would not be true that many phenomena were connected to Kobo Daishi blindly.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it would not be true that many phenomena were blindly connected to Kobo Daishi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it would not be true that many phenomena were blindly connected to Kobo Daishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="216">
<j>やはり空海の幅広い分野での活躍、そして空海への尊崇がその伝説形成の底辺にあると考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It should be considered that worships of Kukai as well as the fact that Kukai actually played important roles in various fields constituted a basis for forming such legends.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It should be considered that worshipers of Kukai as well as the fact that Kukai actually played important roles in various fields constituting a basis for forming such legends.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It should be considered that worshipers of Kukai as well as the fact that Kukai actually played important roles in various fields constitute a basis for forming such legends.</e>
<cmt>constituting →constitute　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="217">
<j>弘法大師にまつわる伝説は寺院の建立や仏像などの彫刻、あるいは聖水、岩石、動植物等々多岐にわたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Legends related to Kobo Daishi cover a variety of areas, including the building of temples, Buddhist sculptures, sacred water, rocks, animals and plants.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Legends related to Kobo Daishi cover a variety of areas, including the building of temples, Buddhist sculptures, sacred water, rocks, plants, and animals.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Legends related to Kobo Daishi cover a variety of areas, including the building of temples, Buddhist sculptures, sacred water, rocks, plants, and animals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="218">
<j>特に弘法水に関する伝説は日本各地に残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular, legends about Kobo-water remain throughout Japan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, legends about Kobo-water remain throughout Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, legends about Kobo-water remain throughout Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="219">
<j>弘法大師が杖をつくと泉が湧き井戸や池となった、といった弘法水の伝承をもつ場所は日本全国で千数百件にのぼるといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the number of sites provided with a legend of Kobo-water, for example, &quot;when Kobo Daishi hit ground with his stick, a spring appeared, forming a well or pond,&quot; reaches a thousand and several hundreds.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the number of sites provided with a legend of Kobo-water, for example, &quot;when Kobo Daishi hit the ground with his stick, a spring appeared, forming a well or pond,&quot; reaches a thousand and several hundreds.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the number of sites provided with a legend of Kobo-water, for example, &quot;when Kobo Daishi hit the ground with his stick, a spring appeared, forming a well or pond,&quot; reaches a thousand and several hundreds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="220">
<j>弘法大師の伝説や弘法水については以下のサイトが参考になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For legends about Kobo Daixhi or Kobo-water, refer to the following web sites if necessary:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For legends about Kobo Daixhi or Kobo-water, refer to the following web sites if necessary:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For legends about Kobo Daishi or Kobo-water, refer to the following web sites if necessary:</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="221">
<j>鎌倉～江戸時代の学者等により、空海は本朝における男色の開祖とされることもある</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kukai was sometimes said to be the originator of gays in Japan by scholars and others in the Kamakura to Edo periods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kukai was sometimes said to be the originator of gays in Japan by scholars and others in the Kamakura to Edo periods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kukai was sometimes said to be the originator of gays in Japan by scholars and others in the Kamakura to Edo periods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="222">
<j>徳川時代の川柳や笑話などにも、しばしば衆道を唐土から導入した人物として登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In senryu (satiric haiku) or comical stories in the Tokugawa period, Kukai often appears as a person who introduced homosexual from China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In senryu (satiric haiku) or comical stories in the Tokugawa period, Kukai often appears as a person who introduced homosexuality from China.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In senryu (satiric haiku) or comical stories in the Tokugawa period, Kukai often appears as a person who introduced homosexuality from China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>発見したとされる温泉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hot springs said to have been found by Kobo Daishi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hot springs said to have been found by Kobo Daishi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hot springs said to have been found by Kobo Daishi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="223">
<j>弘法大師が発見したとされる温泉は、日本各地に存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hot springs said to have been found by Kobo Daishi exist throughout Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hot springs said to have been found by Kobo Daishi exist throughout Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hot springs said to have been found by Kobo Daishi exist throughout Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="224">
<j>ただし、これらのなかには、後年、開湯伝説を作った際に名前が使われただけの場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in some of them, the name of Kobo Daishi was simply used when legends about their origins became necessary later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in some of them, the name of Kobo Daishi was simply used when legends about their origins became necessary later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in some of them, the name of Kobo Daishi was simply used when legends about their origins became necessary later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="225">
<j>高野聖のうちには、その離農的な性格から、いわゆる山師的なものもおり、それらが温泉を探り当てた際に宗祖たる空海の名を借用したともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of the Koya-hijiri, being not farmer-like originality, were provided with a yamashi (person engaged in work in mountains, such as woodcutters, etc.)-like character, and it is also said that, when finding a hot spring, they borrowed the name of Kukai, the founder of their sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of the Koya-hijiri, being not farmer-like originality, were provided with a yamashi (person engaged in work in mountains, such as woodcutters, etc.)-like character, and it is also said that, when finding a hot spring, they borrowed the name of Kukai, the founder of their sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of the Koya-hijiri, being not farmer-like originality, were provided with a yamashi (person engaged in work in mountains, such as woodcutters, etc.)-like character, and it is also said that, when finding a hot spring, they borrowed the name of Kukai, the founder of their sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>伝説・伝承</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Legends and oral traditions</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Legends and oral traditions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Legends and oral traditions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="226">
<j>弘法大師が由来とされる伝説や伝承があるもの、以下にそれを記す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to legends or oral traditions, the following items originated in Kobo Daishi:</e>
<cmt>2行の文章を1行の文章に合体しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to legends or oral traditions, the following items originated in Kobo Daishi:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to legends or oral traditions, the following items originated in Kobo Daishi:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="227">
<j>平仮名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiragana</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiragana</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiragana</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="228">
<j>いろは歌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iroha-uta (a poem in Japanese)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iroha-uta (a poem in Japanese)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iroha-uta (a poem in Japanese)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="229">
<j>灸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moxibustion</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moxibustion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moxibustion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="230">
<j>讃岐うどん</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanuki Udon (udon noodles from Kagawa Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanuki Udon (udon noodles from Kagawa Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanuki Udon (udon noodles from Kagawa Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="231">
<j>手こね寿司</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tekone-zushi (a type of sushi: raw fish placed on top of a bowl of cooked rice)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tekone-zushi (a type of sushi: raw fish placed on top of a bowl of cooked rice)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tekone-zushi (a type of sushi: raw fish placed on top of a bowl of cooked rice)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="232">
<j>九条葱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">kujo-negi (leek from Kujo)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">kujo-negi (leek from Kujo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">kujo-negi (leek from Kujo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>エツ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Etsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Etsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Etsu:</e>
<cmt>コロンを追加しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="233">
<j>- 日本では筑後川のみに生息する魚、絶滅危惧種</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- A fish that lives only in the Chikugo river in Japan: endangered species</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">- A fish that lives only in the Chikugo river in Japan: endangered species</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A fish that lives only in the Chikugo-gawa River in Japan; endangered species</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="234">
<j>曜日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of each day of a week</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of each day of a week</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of each day of a week</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>ことわざ・慣用句</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Proverbs and idiomatic expressions</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Proverbs and idiomatic expressions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Proverbs and idiomatic expressions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>「弘法にも筆の誤り」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kobo mo fude no ayamari&quot; (read the following for the meaning)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kobo mo fude no ayamari&quot; (read the following for the meaning)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kobo mo fude no ayamari&quot; (read the following for the meaning):</e>
<cmt>コロンを追加しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="235">
<j>- 空海は天皇からの勅命を得,大内裏応天門の額を書くことになったが,「応」の一番上の点を書き忘れてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- Ordered by the emperor, Kukai wrote the characters of 応天門 (Oten-mon Gate) on a board to be hanged on Oten-mon Gate of Dai-dairi (place of the Imperial Palace and government offices), but forgot writing the dot at the top of the character 応.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">- Ordered by the emperor, Kukai wrote the characters of 応天門 (Oten-mon Gate) on a board to be hung on the Oten-mon Gate of Dai-dairi (place of the Imperial Palace and government offices), but forgot to write the dot at the top of the character 応.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ordered by the emperor, Kukai wrote the characters of 応天門 (Oten-mon Gate) on a board to be hung on the Oten-mon Gate of Dai-dairi (place of the Imperial Palace and government offices), but forgot to write the dot at the top of the character 応.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="236">
<j>空海は掲げられた額を降ろさずに筆を投げつけて書き直したといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Kukai did not bring down the board to correct the writing, but instead, threw a brush for calligraphy, successfully adding the dot.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Kukai did not bring down the board to correct the writing, but instead, threw a brush for calligraphy, successfully adding the dot.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Kukai did not bring down the board to correct the writing, but instead, threw a brush for calligraphy, successfully adding the dot.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="237">
<j>現在残っているこのことわざの意味は「たとえ大人物であっても、誰にでも間違いはあるもの」ということだけである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, this proverb is understood only meaning that anyone, even a great man, could make a mistake.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, this proverb is understood only meaning that anyone, even a great man, could make a mistake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, this proverb is understood only meaning that anyone, even a great man, could make a mistake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="238">
<j>しかしながら、本来は「さすが大師、書き直し方さえも常人とは違う」というほめ言葉の意味も含まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, originally, this proverb also included the meaning of praising him, or that &quot;Expectedly, Daishi made even such correction in a way unexpected by ordinary men.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, originally, this proverb also included the meaning of praising him, or that &quot;Expectedly, Daishi made even such correction in ways unexpected by ordinary men.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, originally, this proverb also included the meaning of praising him, or that &apos;Expectedly, Daishi made even such correction in ways unexpected by ordinary men.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>「弘法筆を選ばず」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kobo fude wo erabazu&quot; (Literally, Kobo does not select a brush for writing.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kobo fude wo erabazu&quot; (Literally, Kobo does not select a brush for writing.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kobo fude wo erabazu&quot; (Literally, Kobo does not select a brush for writing.):</e>
<cmt>コロンを追加しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="239">
<j>- 文字を書くのが上手な人間は、筆の良し悪しを問わないということ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- This phrase means that a person good at writing characters does not select a brush for writing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">- This phrase means that a person good at writing characters does not select a brush for writing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This phrase means that a person good at writing characters does not select a brush for writing.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="240">
<j>ただし、性霊集には、よい筆を使うことができなかったので、うまく書けなかった、という、全く逆の意味の言及がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Shoryoshu (collected works of prose and poetry of Kukai) includes a description of meaning that he could not write characters in a good shape because the brush used was not good.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Shoryoshu (collected works of prose and poetry of Kukai) includes a description of meaning that he could not write characters in good shapes because the brush used was not good.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Shoryoshu (collected works of prose and poetry of Kukai) includes a description of meaning that he could not write characters in good shapes because the brush used was not good.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="241">
<j>「弘法筆を選ぶ」として、逆の意味のことわざとして用いられることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The phrase of &quot;Kobo fude wo erabu&quot; (literally, Kobo selects a brush for writing) is also sometimes used as a proverb for a totally opposite meaning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The phrase of &quot;Kobo fude wo erabu&quot; (literally, Kobo selects a brush for writing) is also sometimes used as a proverb for the totally opposite meaning.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The phrase of &apos;Kobo fude wo erabu&apos; (literally, Kobo selects a brush for writing) is also sometimes used as a proverb for the totally opposite meaning.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="20">
<tit>
<j>「護摩の灰」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Goma no hai&quot; (literally, ash of Goma (burning small pieces of wood on the alter to invoke divine help))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Goma no hai&quot; (literally, ash of Goma - burning small pieces of wood on the alter to invoke divine help)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Goma no hai&quot; (literally, ash of Goma - burning small pieces of wood on the alter to invoke divine help):</e>
<cmt>コロンを追加しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="242">
<j>- 弘法大師が焚いた護摩の灰と称する灰を,ご利益があるといって売りつける,旅の詐欺師をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- This phrase means a wandering swindler who sells ash called &quot;goma no hai,&quot; said to have been generated from Kobo Daishi&apos;s goma practice, as being beneficial.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">- This phrase means a wandering swindler who sells ash called &quot;goma no hai,&quot; said to have been generated from Kobo Daishi&apos;s goma practice, as being beneficial.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This phrase means a wandering swindler who sells ash called &quot;goma no hai,&quot; said to have been generated from Kobo Daishi&apos;s goma practice, as being beneficial.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="243">
<j>後に転じて旅人の懐を狙う盗人全般を指すようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, this phrase became to mean the thieves who attempt to steal wallets of travelers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, this phrase came to mean the thieves who attempt to steal the purses of travelers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, this phrase came to mean the thieves who attempt to steal the purses of travelers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="21">
<tit>
<j>「生麦大豆二升五合（なまむぎだいずにしょうごんごう）」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Namamugi daizu nisho-gongo&quot; (literally, raw barley and soybeans of 450 ml)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Namamugi daizu nisho-gongo&quot; (literally, raw barley and soybeans of 450 ml)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Namamugi daizu nisho-gongo&quot; (literally, raw barley and soybeans of 450 ml):</e>
<cmt>コロンを追加しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="244">
<j>- 民間に伝わる呪文で,これを唱えれば難事を避けることができると言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- This is magic words handed down for generations among people, and it is said that when chanting these words, you can avoid difficult things.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">- These are magic words handed down for generations among people, and it is said that when chanting these words, you can avoid difficult things.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These are magic words handed down for generations among people, and it is said that when chanting these words, you can avoid difficult things.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="245">
<j>本来の字義からは離れてしまっているが、空海の御宝号「南無大師遍照金剛（なむだいしへんじょうこんごう）」が転訛したもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This phrase is a transformed version of &quot;Namu Daishi henjo kongo,&quot; a gohogo for Kukai (a phrase praising Kukai), although the content of the phrase has become different from what was meant by the original one.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This phrase is a transformed version of &quot;Namu Daishi henjo kongo,&quot; a gohogo for Kukai (a phrase praising Kukai), although the content of the phrase has become different from what was meant by the original one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This phrase is a transformed version of &apos;Namu Daishi henjo kongo,&apos; a gohogo for Kukai (a phrase praising Kukai), although the content of the phrase has become different from what was meant by the original one.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 松本ゆきお(仮)(id:117128), Nnh(id:474), 0null0(id:582), 紀州太政大臣(id:42479), 摩訶離垢摩訶利他(id:219819), Cprobot(id:97843), Eskimbot(id:29676), Wei Yuan(id:13342), Lupinoid(id:68), Kane(id:6812), Greenland4(id:114494), Enoch(id:93257), ＋－(id:17104), らりた(id:1327), Northface(id:70750), 代言人(id:33675), Kimura.shinichi(id:91002), Dignaaga(id:91287), Hotmocha(id:31395), Yas(id:739), 無空(id:17049), Ｋｓ(id:15319), Kouko0515(id:100370), Sumaru(id:20609), ウィキ豊(id:82961), ロリ(id:613), たね(id:10372), Youtetsu(id:7844), PixelBot(id:166734), Ginz(id:31584), Authority(id:10737), Himazin(id:22034), Seibuabina(id:37532), Hisayama(id:208298), Martin(id:6394), Trisahasra(id:160332), Rusk(id:9895), Fryed-peach(id:63402), Tropicanna(id:9972), 唯(id:15499), Boca samba(id:137526), Nnn(id:26535), R28Bot(id:177951), 蔭人(id:80171), Ha～Ha(id:36403), Riden(id:27573), 机龍之介(id:61257), MD242(id:11277), Resto1578(id:168692), Tomzo(id:16777), Bakkai(id:7233), Straysheep(id:42448), Modeha(id:1276), クモハモハ大王(id:185685), Wiki0825(id:34646), Uaa(id:136371), ノトス(id:42992), Reggaeman(id:6214), Ibokorori(id:195769), Urania(id:7213), Charenji(id:7908), 陽一(id:92099), ハノト(id:39008), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Mintleaf(id:2216), Sutou(id:32), 胡亂堂(id:263343), 原口せつはる(id:158652), Toto-tarou(id:16648), 嫦娥(id:81469), Ko-ken(id:49348), Chobot(id:20846), Kurihaya(id:132524), Qurren(id:20140), Izayohi(id:13095), Chi-Ham(id:143515), 水野白楓(id:22811), Taisyo(id:6896), Setu(id:88), Aphaia(id:3132), 黒砂糖(id:38164), 伊集院聖(id:53199), Makotozushi(id:4545), Terrykyo(id:92403), 松岡徳次郎(id:218163), Etsuk(id:878), L26(id:119681), Carkuni(id:79281), Mooko(id:36162), VolkovBot(id:105371), TottyBot(id:101680), 矢吹城(id:126243), 岡部碩道(id:182846), Ponsaku(id:31417), Louperibot(id:128971), 中二病の端くれ(id:137185), SieBot(id:126695), Saaki(id:43602), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>