<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>公海 (僧)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokai (Buddhist priest)</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>公海（こうかい、慶長12年12月12日 (旧暦)（1608年1月29日） - 元禄8年10月16日 (旧暦)（1695年11月22日））は、江戸時代前期の天台宗の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokai (January 29, 1608 – November 22, 1695) was a Buddhist priest of the Tendai sect in the early part of the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokai (January 29, 1608 – November 22, 1695) was a Buddhist priest of the Tendai sect in the early part of the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokai (January 29, 1608 – November 22, 1695) was a Buddhist priest of the Tendai Sect in the early part of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は花山院忠長。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokai&apos;s father was Tadanaga KAZANIN.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokai&apos;s father was Tadanaga KAZANIN.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Tadanaga KAZANIN.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>師の天海の没後に日光山貫主を継承する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequent to the passing of his teacher Tenkai, Kokai succeeded him as the chief priest of Nikko-zan Mountain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequent to the passing of his teacher Tenkai, Kokai succeeded him as the chief priest of Nikko-zan Mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequent to the passing of his teacher Tenkai, Kokai succeeded him as the chief priest of Mt. Nikko.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>1620年（元和 (日本)6年）黒衣の宰相と称された天海僧正の門に入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1620, Kokai became a pupil of Tenkai Sojo (high-ranking Buddhist priest) who was referred to as Kokui no saisho (a priest who has influence in politics).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1620, Kokai became a pupil of Tenkai Sojo (a high-ranking Buddhist priest) who was referred to as Kokui no Saisho (a priest who has influence in politics).</e>
<cmt>Grammar, capitalization.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1620, Kokai became a pupil of Tenkai Sojo (a high-ranking Buddhist priest) who was referred to as Kokui no Saisho (a priest who has influence in politics).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>1643年（寛永20年）に天海が没するとその法をついで東叡山寛永寺に住し、天台宗の総本山である比叡山・徳川家康を祀る日光東照宮のある日光山を管理下に置いて天台宗一宗を管領するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1643, upon the passing of Tenkai, Kokai, residing at Toeizan Kanei-ji Temple, carried on Tenkai&apos;s dharma and, by placing Hidei-zan Mountain, the Grand Head Temple of the Tendai sect as well as Nikko-zan Mountain where Nikko Toshogu Shrine dedicated to Ieyasu TOKUGAWA was located under his control, took the helm of the entire Tendai sect</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon the passing of Tenkai in 1643, Kokai, residing at Toeizan Kanei-ji Temple, carried on Tenkai&apos;s dharma and by placing under his control Hidei-zan Mountain the Grand Head Temple of the Tendai sect as well as Nikko-zan Mountain where the Nikko Toshogu Shrine dedicated to Ieyasu TOKUGAWA was located, took the helm of the entire Tendai sect</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon the passing of Tenkai in 1643, Kokai, residing at Kanei-ji Temple on Mt. Toei, carried on Tenkai&apos;s dharma and by placing under his control Mt. Hiei the Grand Head Temple of the Tendai Sect as well as Mt. Nikko where the Nikko Toshogu Shrine dedicated to Ieyasu TOKUGAWA was located, took the helm of the entire Tendai Sect.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>1647年（正保4年）に僧正に任じられ、翌1648年（正保5年）には大僧正に就任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1647, Kokai was appointed as Sojo and, in 1648, the following year, assumed the post of Daisojo (a Buddhist priest of the highest order).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1647, Kokai was appointed as Sojo and in the following year assumed the post of Daisojo (a Buddhist priest of the highest order).</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1647, Kokai was appointed as Sojo and in 1648, the following year, assumed the position of daisojo (a Buddhist priest of the highest order).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>後に守澄法親王に三山の管理者の地位を譲った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later on, Kokai turned the position of administrator of the three major shrines and temples over to Shucho Hosshinno (Cloistered Imperial Prince Shucho).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later on, Kokai turned the position of administrator of the three major shrines and temples over to Shucho Hosshinno (Cloistered Imperial Prince Shucho).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later on, Kokai turned the position of administrator of the three major shrines and temples over to Cloistered Imperial Prince Shucho.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>天海の遺志をつぎ山科出雲寺を復興している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Carrying out the wishes of Tenkai, Kokai restored Yamashina Izumo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Carrying out the wishes of Tenkai, Kokai restored Yamashina Izumo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Carrying out the wishes of Tenkai, Kokai restored Yamashina Izumo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Carkuni(id:79281), Andee(id:20421), Yonoemon(id:55450), Nnh(id:474), R28Bot(id:177951), くっちゃめ(id:86793), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>