<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>天台座主</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tendai-zasu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tendai-zasu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tendai-zasu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>天台座主（てんだいざす）は、日本の天台宗の本山である比叡山延暦寺の貫主（住職）で、天台宗の諸末寺を総監する役職。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tendai-zasu (head priest of the Tendai sect) is a post that serves as the resident priest of Hieizan Enryaku-ji Temple, the head temple of the Tendai sect, exercising general supervision over all of its sub-temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tendai-zasu (head priest of the Tendai sect) is a post that serves as the resident priest of Hieizan Enryaku-ji Temple, the head temple of the Tendai sect, exercising general supervision over all of its sub-temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tendai-zasu (head priest of the Tendai sect) is a post that serves as the resident priest of Enryaku-ji Temple on Mt. Hiei, the head temple of the Tendai sect, exercising general supervision over all of its sub-temples.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「山の座主」とも呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tendai-zasu was also referred to as the &apos;Head Priest of the Mountain.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tendai-zasu was also referred to as the &apos;Head Priest of the Mountain.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tendai-zasu was also referred to as the &apos;Head Priest of the Mountain.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>ただし、比叡山に居住することは少なく、重要な修法、儀式の時のみ入山する座主が多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tendai-zasu, however, rarely lived at Hiei-zan Mountain and many of them came to that mountain only on occasions when important services and ceremonies were held.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tendai-zasu, however, rarely lived at Hiei-zan Mountain and many of them went to that mountain only on occasions when important services and ceremonies were held.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tendai-zasu, however, rarely lived at Mt. Hiei and many of them went to that mountain only on occasions when important services and ceremonies were held.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>天長元年（824年）に義真が初めて天台座主を称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 824, Gishin was referred to as Tendai-zasu for the first time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 824, Gishin was referred to as Tendai-zasu for the first time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 824, Gishin was referred to as Tendai-zasu for the first time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>2世円澄までは延暦寺内の私称であったが、3世の円仁からは太政官が官符をもって任命する公的な役職となり、明治4年（1871年）まで続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Up to the times of the second head priest Encho, the term Tendai-zasu was a private title used within a compound of Enryaku-ji Temple but, starting with the third head priest Ennin, it became an official post appointed by way of kanpu (official documents from Dajokan or Grand Council of State) issued by Dajokan (Grand Council of State) which continued until 1871.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Up to the time of the second head priest Encho, the term Tendai-zasu was a private title used within the compound of Enryaku-ji Temple but, starting with the third head priest Ennin, it became an official post appointed by way of kanpu (official documents from the Dajokan or Grand Council of State) issued by the Dajokan, and which continued until 1871.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Up to the time of the second head priest Encho, the term Tendai-zasu was a private title used within the compound of Enryaku-ji Temple but, starting with the third head priest Ennin, it became an official post appointed by way of kanpu (official documents from the Dajokan or Grand Council of State) issued by the Dajokan, and which continued until 1871.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>1人で複数回任命されることも多く、慈円などは3度、尊円法親王などは4度、天台座主に就いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There have been numerous occasions when the same person received the appointment more than once with, for example, Jien and Cloistered Imperial Prince Sonen assuming the post of Tendai-zasu 3 and 4 times, respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There have been numerous occasions when the same person received the appointment more than once, with, for example, Jien and Cloistered Imperial Prince Sonen assuming the post of Tendai-zasu 3 and 4 times respectively.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There have been numerous occasions when the same person received the appointment more than once, with, for example, Jien and Cloistered Imperial Prince Sonen assuming the post of Tendai-zasu 3 and 4 times respectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>中世になると、摂家門跡、宮門跡の制度が整えられ、とりわけ妙法院・青蓮院・三千院（天台三門跡）から法親王が、天台座主として就任することが多くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early Middle Ages, with the Sekke-monzeki (the priest clan eligible for regents) and miya-monzeki (temples headed by imperial princes) systems being in place, cloistered imperial princes from Myoho-in Temple, Joren-in Temple and Sanzen-in Temple (the Tendai Three Monzeki) in particular began to assume the position of Tendai-zasu frequently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early Middle Ages, with the Sekke-monzeki (the priest clan eligible to serve regents) and miya-monzeki (temples headed by imperial princes) systems being in place, cloistered imperial princes from Myoho-in Temple, Joren-in Temple and Sanzen-in Temple (the Tendai Three Monzeki) in particular began to assume the position of Tendai-zasu frequently.</e>
<cmt>The phrase &apos;the priest clan eligible for regents&apos; is unclear. Does this mean they are eligible to become regent, or to perform ceremonies to regents?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early Middle Ages, with the Sekke-monzeki (temples headed by regents) and miya-monzeki (temples headed by imperial princes) systems being in place, cloistered imperial princes from Myoho-in Temple, Joren-in Temple and Sanzen-in Temple (the Tendai Three Monzeki) in particular began to assume the position of Tendai-zasu frequently.</e>
<cmt>trans 2 のコメントを受け修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、室町時代には足利将軍家からも出ている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, during the Muromachi Period, the post of Tendai-zasu was filled by members of the Ashikaga Shogun family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, during the Muromachi Period, the post of Tendai-zasu was filled by members of the Ashikaga Shogun family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, during the Muromachi period, the post of Tendai-zasu was filled by members of the Ashikaga Shogun family.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>天台座主となった後に還俗し、征夷大将軍となった例として、護良親王（還俗して護良親王）や、足利義教（還俗して足利義教）などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some examples of Tendai-zasu who subsequently returned to secular life to become Seii taishogun (literally, the great general who subdues barbarians) including Imperial Prince Morinaga (which is his secular name after leaving the priesthood) and Yoshinori ASHIKAGA (which is his secular name after leaving the priesthood).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are some examples of Tendai-zasu who subsequently returned to secular life to become Seii taishogun (literally, the great general who subdues barbarians) including Imperial Prince Morinaga (his secular name after leaving the priesthood) and Yoshinori ASHIKAGA (also his secular name after leaving the priesthood).</e>
<cmt>Changed to improve flow.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are some examples of Tendai-zasu who subsequently returned to secular life to become Seii taishogun (literally, the great general who subdues barbarians) including Imperial Prince Morinaga (his secular name after leaving the priesthood) and Yoshinori ASHIKAGA (also his secular name after leaving the priesthood).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>江戸時代になると、江戸幕府によって東国の天台宗の大寺院として日光の日光山輪王寺と上野の東叡山寛永寺（開山は天海）が建立されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo Period, as the grand temples of the Tendai sect in Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region), Nikko-zan Rinno-ji Temple in Nikko and Toeizan Kanei-ji Temple (Tenkai was the founder and the first chief priest) in Ueno were built by the Edo shogunate with Rinno-ji Temple being designated as a temple headed by imperial princes (referred to as Rinnojinomiya or Nikko-monzeki), whereby, since 1656, it was decided that Rinnojinomiya had double assignments as the resident priest of Toeizan and Tendai-zasu being responsible for general supervision of the three temples of the Tendai sect in the foregoing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo Period, the grand temples of the Tendai sect in Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region), Nikko-zan Rinno-ji Temple in Nikko and Toeizan Kanei-ji Temple (Tenkai was the founder and the first chief priest) in Ueno were built by the Edo shogunate.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処Sentence split to make the meaning clear.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period, the grand temples of the Tendai sect in Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region), Rinno-ji Temple on Mt. Nikko in Nikko and Kanei-ji Temple on Mt. Toei (Tenkai was the founder and the first chief priest) in Ueno were built by the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>用語統一英語説明補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>輪王寺は宮門跡とされ（輪王寺宮、日光門跡）、明暦2年（1656年）以降は、輪王寺宮が東叡山の門跡と天台座主を兼務し、以上の天台三山を総監することが定められた（三山管領宮）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rinno-ji Temple was designated as a temple headed by imperial princes (referred to as Rinnojinomiya or Nikko-monzeki), and it was settled that after 1656 Rinnojinomiya had responsibilities both as the resident priest of Toeizan and Tendai-zasu, being responsible for general supervision of the three temples of the Tendai sect above.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処Grammar, word choice. Sentence split to make the meaning clear.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rinno-ji Temple was designated as a temple headed by imperial princes (referred to as Rinnojinomiya or Nikko-monzeki), and it was settled that after 1656 Rinnojinomiya had responsibilities both as the resident priest of Toeizan and Tendai-zasu, being responsible for general supervision of the three temples of the Tendai sect above (.Sanzan Kanryo no miya).</e>
<cmt>Sanzan Kanryo no miya補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>明治4年（1871年）をもって、太政官による任命は廃止され、天台座主そのものも無くなったが、天台宗内外に復活を望む声は多く、明治17年（1885年）より、再び私称として復活した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1871 the designation of the Tendai-zasu was repealed by the Dajokan (Grand Council of State) and the position of Tendai-zasu disappeared, but following the many calls for its restoration both from within the Tendai sect and without, in 1885 it was revived in the form of a private title.</e>
<cmt>Translated</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1871 the designation of the Tendai-zasu was repealed by the Dajokan (Grand Council of State) and the position of Tendai-zasu disappeared, but following the many calls for its restoration both from within the Tendai sect and without, in 1885 it was revived in the form of a private title.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>現在の天台座主は、256世の半田孝淳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kojun HANDA is the current and the 256th Tendai-zasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kojun HANDA is the current and the 256th Tendai-zasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kojun HANDA is the current and the 256th Tendai-zasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>歴代の座主の補任記録、修法、行事、事件の記録などは「天台座主記」に残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various records including the appointment log of the successive zasu, services, events and incidents are documented in Tendai-zasu ki (Archives of Tendai-zasu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various records including the appointment log of the successive zasu, services, events and incidents are documented in Tendai-zasu ki (Archives of Tendai-zasu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various records including the appointment log of the successive zasu, services, events and incidents are documented in &apos;Tendai-zasu ki&apos; (Archives of Tendai-zasu).</e>
<cmt>補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 中右(id:50196), Kstigarbha(id:13376), 松茸(id:27535), Law soma(id:45202), トホホ川(id:50502), YOSHI438(id:174755), 岡部碩道(id:182846), Broad-Sky(id:68334), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>