<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>四箇格言</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shika Kakugen (Nichiren&apos;s Four Criticisms)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shika Kakugen (Nichiren&apos;s Four Criticisms)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shika Kakugen (Nichiren&apos;s Four Criticisms)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>四箇格言（しか、しこ・かくげん、しかのかくげん）とは、日蓮宗の宗祖日蓮が他の仏教宗派を批判したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shika (or Shiko) Kakugen (or Shika no Kakugen) (Four Criticisms) refers to the criticisms expressed by Nichiren, the founder of Nichiren Buddhism, against other Buddhist sects that existed in his time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shika (or Shiko) Kakugen (or Shika no Kakugen) (Four Criticisms) refers to the criticisms expressed by Nichiren, the founder of Nichiren Buddhism, against other Buddhist sects that existed in his time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shika (or Shiko) Kakugen (or Shika no Kakugen) (Four Criticisms) refers to the criticisms expressed by Nichiren, the founder of Nichiren Buddhism, against other Buddhist sects that existed in his time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>いわゆる真言亡国、禅天魔、念仏無間、律国賊（しんごんぼうこく、ぜんてんま、ねんぶつむけん、りつこくぞく）の四つをいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His four criticisms (directed at Shingon Buddhism as a threat to the nation, Zen Buddhism as the work of the devil, Nenbutsu Buddhism as infernal doctrine and Ritsu Buddhism as an act of treason) are known, respectively, as &quot;Shingon Bokoku,&quot; &quot;Zen Tenma,&quot; &quot;Nenbutsu Muken&quot; and &quot;Ritsu Kokuzoku.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His four criticisms (directed at Shingon Buddhism as a threat to the nation, Zen Buddhism as the work of the devil, Nenbutsu Buddhism as infernal doctrine and Ritsu Buddhism as an act of treason) are known, respectively, as &quot;Shingon Bokoku,&quot; &quot;Zen Tenma,&quot; &quot;Nenbutsu Muken&quot; and &quot;Ritsu Kokuzoku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His four criticisms (directed at Shingon Buddhism as a threat to the nation, Zen Buddhism as the work of the devil, Nenbutsu Buddhism as infernal doctrine and Ritsu Buddhism as an act of treason) are known, respectively, as &quot;Shingon Bokoku,&quot; &quot;Zen Tenma,&quot; &quot;Nenbutsu Muken&quot; and &quot;Ritsu Kokuzoku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>諌暁八幡抄、御義口伝上などに書かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These criticisms are found in his writings such as &quot;Kangyo Hachiman Sho&quot; (Buddhist Teachings) and &quot;Ongi Kuden Jo&quot; (Collection of Sermons).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These criticisms are found in his writings such as &quot;Kangyo Hachiman Sho (Buddhist Teachings)&quot; and &quot;Ongi Kuden Jo (Collection of Sermons).&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These criticisms are found in his writings such as Kangyo Hachiman Sho (Buddhist Teachings) and Ongi Kuden Jo (Collection of Sermons).</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>日蓮は、法華経を一乗とする立場から、法華経に依らない仏教宗派を謗法（誹謗正法の略）だとして批判した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nichiren, who believed in the Lotus Sutra as the single most important sutra of Buddhism, criticized Buddhist sects that were not founded on the faith in the Lotus Sutra as denigrating the true teachings of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nichiren, who believed in the Lotus Sutra as the single most important sutra of Buddhism, criticized Buddhist sects that were not founded on the faith in the Lotus Sutra as denigrating the true teachings of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nichiren, who believed in the Lotus Sutra as the single most important sutra of Buddhism, criticized Buddhist sects that were not founded on the faith in the Lotus Sutra as denigrating the true teachings of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>これは法華経以前の釈迦が説いた教えは、すべて方便で説かれたものであるから成仏する道ではない、という爾前無得道論（にぜんむとくどうろん）に基づく主張である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His criticisms are based on the argument that teachings of Buddha before the Lotus Sutra do not show the true way of attaining nirvana because they were given as provisional teachings.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His criticisms are based on the argument that the teachings of Buddha prior to the Lotus Sutra do not show the true way to attain nirvana because they were given as provisional teachings.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His criticisms are based on the argument that the teachings of Buddha prior to the Lotus Sutra do not show the true way to attain nirvana because they were given as provisional teachings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>それを各宗派の教えの特徴にあわせて批判したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nichiren used this argument to criticize the unique teachings of Buddhist sects that existed at his time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nichiren used this argument to criticize the unique teachings of Buddhist sects that existed during his time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nichiren used this argument to criticize the unique teachings of Buddhist sects that existed during his time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>真言亡国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shingon Bokoku (criticism of Shingon Buddhism as a threat to the nation)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shingon Bokoku (criticism of Shingon Buddhism as a threat to the nation)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shingon Bokoku (criticism of Shingon Buddhism as a threat to the nation)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>真言宗では、法華経などの経典は応身の釈迦が説法したもので、大日経は法身の大日如来が説法したものであるとし「大日如来に比べれば釈迦は無明の辺域であり、草履取りにも及ばない」といっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shingon Buddhism maintains that all Buddhist sutras, including the Lotus Sutra, are teachings of Buddha as a mortal being except for the Great Sun Buddha Sutra (Dainichi kyo), which was preached by Mahavairocana Buddha (Great Sun Buddha, or Dainichi Nyorai in Japanese), the Buddha enlightened by eternal truth, and that the Buddha as a mortal being, who belongs to the realm of unenlightened existence, is inferior even to the servant of Mahavairocana Buddha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shingon Buddhism maintains that all Buddhist sutras, including the Lotus Sutra, are teachings of Buddha as a mortal being except for the Great Sun Buddha Sutra (Dainichi kyo), which was preached by Mahavairocana Buddha (Great Sun Buddha, or Dainichi Nyorai in Japanese), the Buddha enlightened by eternal truth, and that the Buddha as a mortal being, who belongs to the realm of unenlightened existence, is inferior even to the servant of Mahavairocana Buddha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shingon Buddhism maintains that all Buddhist sutras, including the Lotus Sutra, are teachings of Buddha as a mortal being except for the Great Sun Buddha Sutra (Dainichi kyo), which was preached by Mahavairocana Buddha (Great Sun Buddha, or Dainichi Nyorai in Japanese), the Buddha enlightened by eternal truth, and that the Buddha as a mortal being, who belongs to the realm of unenlightened existence, is inferior even to the servant of Mahavairocana Buddha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>法華経にも一念三千の「理」はあるが、印と真言という「事」が無いから、大日経の方が優れている（理同事勝、りどうじしょう）などと主張している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shingon Buddhism further insists that although the Lotus Sutra knows theories about the three thousand realms of existence, it does not know rituals, including symbols and words of truth (&quot;shingon&quot; in Japanese), and that the Great Sun Buddha Sutra, which teaches rituals along with theories, is therefore superior to the Lotus Sutra.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shingon Buddhism further insists that although the Lotus Sutra knows theories about the 3,000 realms of existence, it doesn&apos;t know rituals, including symbols and words of truth (&quot;shingon&quot; in Japanese), and that the Great Sun Buddha Sutra, which teaches rituals along with theories, is therefore superior to the Lotus Sutra.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shingon Buddhism further insists that although the Lotus Sutra knows theories about the 3,000 realms of existence, it doesn&apos;t know rituals, including symbols and words of truth (&quot;shingon&quot; in Japanese), and that the Great Sun Buddha Sutra, which teaches rituals along with theories, is therefore superior to the Lotus Sutra.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>そして真言宗は天台宗の一念三千をひそかに盗み取り、自宗の極理としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Nichiren, Shingon Buddhism stole the teaching about the three thousand realms of existence from the Tendai School of Buddhism and adopted it as its own religious doctrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Nichiren, Shingon Buddhism stole the teaching about the 3,000 realms of existence from the Tendai school of Buddhism and adopted it as its own religious doctrine.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Nichiren, Shingon Buddhism stole the teaching about the 3,000 realms of existence from the Tendai school of Buddhism and adopted it as its own religious doctrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>したがって本来の主人である釈迦や法華経を卑下し、生国不明の架空の仏で無縁の主である大日如来を立てる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nichiren further argues that Shingon Buddhism worships the Great Sun Buddha, a fictional Buddha of doubtful origin unrelated to the Buddhist teaching, thereby denigrating Buddha and the Lotus Sutra, which provides the true source of enlightenment.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nichiren also asserted that Shingon Buddhism worshiped the Great Sun Buddha, a fictional Buddha of doubtful origin unrelated to the Buddhist teaching, thereby denigrating Buddha and the Lotus Sutra, which provided the true source of enlightenment.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nichiren also asserted that Shingon Buddhism worshiped the Great Sun Buddha, a fictional Buddha of doubtful origin unrelated to the Buddhist teaching, thereby denigrating Buddha and the Lotus Sutra, which provided the true source of enlightenment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>こうした理由から、真言は亡国、亡家、亡人の法で男子が成長しない、という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From this, Nichiren concludes that Shingon Buddhism is a threat to the existence of the nation, families and individuals, which prevents the growth of healthy young boys.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From this, Nichiren concluded that Shingon Buddhism was a threat to the existence of the nation, families and individuals, since it prevented the growth of healthy young boys.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From this, Nichiren concluded that Shingon Buddhism was a threat to the existence of the nation, families and individuals, since it prevented the growth of healthy young boys.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>禅天魔</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zen Tenma (criticism of Zen Buddhism as the work of the devil)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zen Tenma (criticism of Zen Buddhism as the work of the devil)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zen Tenma (criticism of Zen Buddhism as the work of the devil)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>禅宗は、釈迦が華を拈（ひね）り、大衆の中で大迦葉だけがその意味を悟って破顔微笑（はがんびしょう）した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a Zen Buddhist legend, Buddha twirled a flower in one of his sermons but no one understood the meaning of his gesture except for Mahakasyapa (one of the disciples of Buddha), who grasped the meaning of Buddha&apos;s wordless sermon and broke into a smile.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a Zen Buddhist legend, Buddha twirled a flower in one of his sermons but no one understood the meaning of his gesture except for Mahakasyapa (one of the disciples of Buddha), who grasped the meaning of Buddha&apos;s wordless sermon and broke into a smile.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a Zen Buddhist legend, Buddha twirled a flower in one of his sermons but no one understood the meaning of his gesture except for Mahakasyapa (one of the disciples of Buddha), who grasped the meaning of Buddha&apos;s wordless sermon and broke into a smile.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>これを拈華微笑（ねんげみしょう）、以心伝心（いしんでんしん）といい、それを以って仏法の未来への附属を大迦葉に与えたといっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mahakasyapa&apos;s smile symbolizes the preaching of Zen Buddhism that the truth is beyond all verbal explanation, and Zen Buddhism maintains that through this wordless sermon, Buddha entrusted the eternal truth of Buddhism to Mahakasyapa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mahakasyapa&apos;s smile symbolizes the preaching of Zen Buddhism that the truth is beyond all verbal explanation, and Zen Buddhism maintains that through this wordless sermon Buddha entrusted the eternal truth of Buddhism to Mahakasyapa.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mahakasyapa&apos;s smile symbolizes the preaching of Zen Buddhism that the truth is beyond all verbal explanation, and Zen Buddhism maintains that through this wordless sermon Buddha entrusted the eternal truth of Buddhism to Mahakasyapa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>大梵天王問仏決疑経の中に「正法眼蔵・涅槃妙心・実相無相の法門があり、文字を立てず教外に別伝して迦葉に付属する」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the &quot;Daibontenno Monbutsu Ketsugikyo&quot; (Sutra on King Mahabrahma&apos;s Questions to the Buddha and Clarification of Doubts), it is written that there are Buddhist teachings known as Shobogenzo (literally, True Dharma-eye Treasury), Nehanmyoshin (Fine Mind of Nirvana) and Jissomuso (Undisclosed Subtle Dharma Gate), which were transmitted to Mahakasyapa outside the teachings without using written words.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処以下のサイトを参照しました。http://dogenandtheshobogenzo.blogspot.com/2008/06/some-implications-of-title-shobogenzo.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the &quot;Daibontenno Monbutsu Ketsugikyo (Sutra on King Mahabrahma&apos;s Questions to the Buddha and Clarification of Doubts),&quot; it is written that there are Buddhist teachings known as Shobogenzo (literally, True Dharma-eye Treasury), Nehanmyoshin (Fine Mind of Nirvana) and Jissomuso (Undisclosed Subtle Dharma Gate), which were transmitted to Mahakasyapa outside the teachings without the use of written words.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Daibontenno Monbutsu Ketsugikyo (Sutra on King Mahabrahma&apos;s Questions to the Buddha and Clarification of Doubts), it is written that there are Buddhist teachings known as Shobogenzo (literally, True Dharma-eye Treasury), Nehanmyoshin (Fine Mind of Nirvana) and Jissomuso (Undisclosed Subtle Dharma Gate), which were transmitted to Mahakasyapa outside the teachings without the use of written words.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>禅宗は、この経文通りに承伝してきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zen Buddhism has handed down its tradition based on this sutra.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zen Buddhism has handed down its tradition based on this sutra.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zen Buddhism has handed down its tradition based on this sutra.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし不立文字・教外別伝（ふりゅうもんじ・きょうげべつでん）などと説き、経文を否定している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Zen Buddhism denies the significance of sutras, insisting on the importance of nonverbal truths transmitted outside the teachings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Zen Buddhism denies the significance of sutras, insisting on the importance of nonverbal truths transmitted outside the teachings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Zen Buddhism denies the significance of sutras, insisting on the importance of nonverbal truths transmitted outside the teachings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これは凡夫である自己を過信した仏法を破壊する業（わざ）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nichiren criticizes this aspect of Zen Buddhism, arguing that Zen Buddhism is based on excessive confidence in one&apos;s mediocre self and will eventually lead to the destruction of Buddhism itself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nichiren criticizes this aspect of Zen Buddhism, arguing that Zen Buddhism is based on excessive confidence in one&apos;s mediocre self and will eventually lead to the destruction of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nichiren criticizes this aspect of Zen Buddhism, arguing that Zen Buddhism is based on excessive confidence in one&apos;s mediocre self and will eventually lead to the destruction of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>涅槃経では「仏の所説に順ぜざる（したがわない）者あれば、まさに知るべし、これ魔の眷属なり」と説いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Nirvana Sutra, it is written that anyone who disobeys the teachings of Buddha is a devil&apos;s advocate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Nirvana Sutra, it is written that anyone who disobeys the teachings of Buddha is a devil&apos;s advocate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Nirvana Sutra, it is written that anyone who disobeys the teachings of Buddha is a devil&apos;s advocate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>また偽経である大梵天王問仏決疑経などの経典を引用するのは「不立文字」と矛盾相違する行為である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zen Buddhists themselves cite passages from sutras like Daibontenno Monbutsu Ketsugikyo, which contradicts their doctrine about nonverbal truths.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zen Buddhists did, in fact, cite passages from sutras like Daibontenno Monbutsu Ketsugikyo, which contradicts their doctrine about nonverbal truths.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zen Buddhists did, in fact, cite passages from sutras like Daibontenno Monbutsu Ketsugikyo, which contradicts their doctrine about nonverbal truths.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>したがって禅は天魔の所業である、という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On these grounds, Nichiren denounces Zen Buddhism as the work of the devil.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, Nichiren denounced Zen Buddhism as the work of the devil.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, Nichiren denounced Zen Buddhism as the work of the devil.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>念仏無間</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nenbutsu Muken (criticism of Nenbutsu Buddhism as infernal doctrine)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nenbutsu Muken (criticism of Nenbutsu Buddhism as infernal doctrine)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nenbutsu Muken (criticism of Nenbutsu Buddhism as infernal doctrine)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>念仏宗（浄土宗や浄土真宗など）は、浄土三部経を所依とし、釈迦ではなく阿弥陀如来を立てる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nenbutsu Buddhism (including Jodoshu (Pure Land Buddhism) and Jodoshinshu (True Pure Land Buddhism)) is based on the Three Sutras of Pure Land (the Sutra of Immeasurable Life, the Meditation Sutra and the Amida Sutra) and worships Amida Buddha instead of Buddha himself.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nenbutsu Buddhism (including Jodoshu (Pure Land Buddhism) and Jodoshinshu (True Pure Land Buddhism)) is based on the Three Sutras of Pure Land (the Sutra of Immeasurable Life, the Meditation Sutra and the Amida Sutra) and worships Amida Buddha instead of Buddha himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nenbutsu Buddhism (including Jodoshu (Pure Land Buddhism) and Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism)) is based on the Three Sutras of Pure Land (the Sutra of Immeasurable Life, the Meditation Sutra and the Amida Sutra) and worships Amida Buddha instead of Buddha himself.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>浄土宗の宗祖である法然などは『選択本願念仏集』（せんちゃくしゅう）において、浄土三部経以外を雑修・雑行であるから「捨てよ、閉じよ、閣（さしお）け抛（なげう）て」（捨閉閣抛、しゃへいかくほう）と言って法華経を誹謗している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his &quot;Senchaku Hongan Nenbutsushu&quot; (Selection of Genuine Nenbutsu), Honen, the founding father of the Jodoshu Buddhism, even denounces sutras other than the Three Sutras of Pure Land, urging his disciples to throw away, close, ignore and discard unnecessary sutras, thereby denigrating the Lotus Sutra as well.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his &quot;Senchaku Hongan Nenbutsushu (Selection of Genuine Nenbutsu),&quot; Honen, the founding father of the Jodoshu Buddhism, even denounces sutras other than the Three Sutras of Pure Land, urging his disciples to throw away, close, ignore and discard unnecessary sutras, thereby denigrating the Lotus Sutra as well.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his &quot;Senchaku Hongan Nenbutsushu&quot; (Selection of Genuine Nenbutsu), Honen, the founding father of the Jodoshu Buddhism, even denounces sutras other than the Three Sutras of Pure Land, urging his disciples to throw away, close, ignore and discard unnecessary sutras, thereby denigrating the Lotus Sutra as well.</e>
<cmt>&quot;位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>しかし浄土経典は釈迦説法の中で方便権教の部類である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Pure Land Sutras are provisional teachings of Buddha, as shown in his own words in Muryogikyo (Sutra of Infinite Meaning).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Pure Land sutras are provisional teachings of Buddha, as shown in his own words in Muryogikyo (Sutra of Infinite Meaning).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Pure Land sutras are provisional teachings of Buddha, as shown in his own words in Muryogikyo (Sutra of Infinite Meaning).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>法華経の開経である無量義経で「四十余年未顕真実」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Muryogikyo, which is the &quot;opening&quot; sutra to the Lotus Sutra, Buddha states that he has been searching for the truth for more than forty years and has as yet found none.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Muryogikyo, which is the &quot;opening&quot; sutra to the Lotus Sutra, Buddha states that he has been searching for the truth for more than 40 years but has not yet found it.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Muryogikyo, which is the &quot;opening&quot; sutra to the Lotus Sutra, Buddha states that he has been searching for the truth for more than 40 years but has not yet found it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>また阿弥陀如来の前世である法蔵菩薩が立願した48願のうち、第18願の「いかなる罪人・悪人でも阿弥陀を念ずれば西方十万億土の極楽浄土へ往生することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Dharmakara Bodhisattva (Hozo Bosatsu in Japanese), who is believed to be the incarnation of Amida Buddha, takes 48 oaths, and in his 18th oath, he promises that he will lead any sinner or criminal to be reborn in the Pure Land, which is tens of millions of miles away from this world, if only the sinner sincerely believes in Amida Buddha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, Dharmakara Bodhisattva (Hozo Bosatsu in Japanese), who is believed to be the incarnation of Amida Buddha, takes 48 oaths, and in his eighteenth oath he promises to lead any sinner or criminal to be reborn in the Pure Land, which is tens of millions of miles away from this world, if only the sinner sincerely believes in Amida Buddha.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, Dharmakara Bodhisattva (Hozo Bosatsu in Japanese), who is believed to be the incarnation of Amida Buddha, takes 48 oaths, and in his eighteenth oath he promises to lead any sinner or criminal to be reborn in the Pure Land, which is tens of millions of miles away from this world, if only the sinner sincerely believes in Amida Buddha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>ただし五逆罪と誹謗正法を者をば除く」という誓文に背き、法華経を誹謗している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, from the list of sinners worthy of salvation, Hozo Bosatsu excludes those who have committed the five mortal sins along with those who have denounced Buddhist teachings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, from the list of sinners worthy of salvation, Hozo Bosatsu excludes those who have committed the five mortal sins along with those who have denounced Buddhist teachings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, from the list of sinners worthy of salvation, Hozo Bosatsu excludes those who have committed the five mortal sins along with those who have denounced Buddhist teachings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>したがって、極楽浄土に往生できるわけがない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And yet, Hozo Bosatsu denounces the Lotus Sutra, thereby preventing himself from being reborn in the Pure Land.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Hozo Bosatsu denounces the Lotus Sutra, thus preventing himself from being reborn in the Pure Land.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Hozo Bosatsu denounces the Lotus Sutra, thus preventing himself from being reborn in the Pure Land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>このことは法華経譬喩品に「この経を毀謗する者は無間地獄に堕す」と説かれている通りであるから、念仏は無間地獄への法である、という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Fundamental Rules of the Lotus Sutra, it is written that anyone who criticizes this sutra will be sent to hell, and based on this, Nichiren argues that Nenbutsu Buddhism is the teaching of hell.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Fundamental Rules of the Lotus Sutra, it is written that anyone who criticizes this sutra will be sent to Hell; thus Nichiren argued that Nenbutsu Buddhism was the teaching of Hell.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Fundamental Rules of the Lotus Sutra, it is written that anyone who criticizes this sutra will be sent to Hell; thus Nichiren argued that Nenbutsu Buddhism was the teaching of Hell.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>律国賊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ritsu Kokuzoku (criticism of Ritsu Buddhism as an act of treason)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ritsu Kokuzoku (criticism of Ritsu Buddhism as an act of treason)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ritsu Kokuzoku (criticism of Ritsu Buddhism as an act of treason)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>律宗の教えは、釈迦在世の正法時代の法であり、小乗教の250戒などの戒律を根本の教義としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ritsu Buddhism is based on religious precepts that were practiced during the time when Buddha was still alive and it adopts these precepts, including the 250 precepts of Hinayana Buddhism, as its fundamental religious doctrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ritsu Buddhism is based on religious precepts that were practiced during the time when Buddha was still alive; it adopts these precepts, including the 250 precepts of Hinayana Buddhism, as its fundamental religious doctrine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ritsu Buddhism is based on religious precepts that were practiced during the time when Buddha was still alive; it adopts these precepts, including the 250 precepts of Hinayana Buddhism, as its fundamental religious doctrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>日本では像法時代の中ごろに、衆生の機根を調理するために広まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, Ritsu Buddhism was spread during the middle of the second millennium after the death of Buddha in order to bring about a religious awakening among the masses.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, Ritsu Buddhism was spread during the middle of the second millennium after the death of Buddha in order to bring about a religious awakening among the masses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, Ritsu Buddhism was spread during the middle of the second millennium after the death of Buddha in order to bring about a religious awakening among the masses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>個人主義的色彩が強くこれらの戒律は末法の衆生の機根には合わないものであり、現実から遠離した世間を誑惑させる教えである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ritsu Buddhism, which is highly individualistic, practices religious precepts that are inappropriate for the masses living in the age when Buddhism is in decline, and its teaching takes them away from the reality by its deceptive practices.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ritsu Buddhism, which is highly individualistic, incorporates religious precepts that were inappropriate for the masses living in the age when Buddhism is in decline, and its teaching would take them away from the reality due to its deceptive practices.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ritsu Buddhism, which is highly individualistic, incorporates religious precepts that were inappropriate for the masses living in the age when Buddhism is in decline, and its teaching would take them away from the reality due to its deceptive practices.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>このような戒律を説いて清浄を装う律僧は人を惑わし、国を亡ぼす国賊である、という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On these grounds, Nichiren argues that Ritsu Buddhist monks, who preach these precepts and purport themselves to be religiously pure, are traitors that deceive people and bring ruin to the nation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on such grounds, Nichiren argued that Ritsu Buddhist monks, who preached these precepts and purported themselves to be religiously pure, were traitors who deceived people and would bring the nation to the point of ruin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on such grounds, Nichiren argued that Ritsu Buddhist monks, who preached these precepts and purported themselves to be religiously pure, were traitors who deceived people and would bring the nation to the point of ruin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>考証</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Critical considerations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Critical considerations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Critical considerations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="33">
<j>日蓮が四箇格言を行ったのは、時代における様々な背景なども考証し検討する必要があるという指摘がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some critics point out that there is a need to consider various historical backgrounds in order to study the meaning of Nichiren&apos;s Four Criticisms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some critics point out the need to consider various historical aspects in order to study the meaning of Nichiren&apos;s Four Criticisms.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some critics point out the need to consider various historical aspects in order to study the meaning of Nichiren&apos;s Four Criticisms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>たとえば、浄土宗や臨済宗などの鎌倉新仏教が新しく成立した時に、奈良や平安などの既存仏教から論難排撃された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, we need to consider the fact that the new Buddhist sects that came into being during the Kamakura period, such as the Pure Land sect and Rinzai sect, were severely criticized by the existing Buddhist schools, including Nara and Heian Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, one must consider the fact that the new Buddhist sects that came into existence during the Kamakura period, such as the Pure Land sect and Rinzai sect, were severely criticized by the existing Buddhist schools, including those of Nara and Heian Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, one must consider the fact that the new Buddhist sects that came into existence during the Kamakura period, such as the Pure Land sect and Rinzai sect, were severely criticized by the existing Buddhist schools, including those of Nara and Heian Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>またそれらが当時の政治権力と結託していた背景もあり、したがって日蓮の法華宗もその中にあった、といわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And under the circumstances where these old Buddhist schools had connections with those in power at the time, Nichiren&apos;s Lotus Sutra Buddhism of Nichiren is also likely to have been subjected to the attack of these schools.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the circumstances in which these old Buddhist schools had connections with those in power, Nichiren&apos;s Lotus Sutra Buddhism is also likely to have been subjected to the attacks by those schools.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the circumstances in which these old Buddhist schools had connections with those in power, Nichiren&apos;s Lotus Sutra Buddhism is also likely to have been subjected to the attacks by those schools.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="36">
<j>これは創価学会も、近年になってこの点を主張し「創価学会も似たような事情から他宗派を反撃した過去があるが、今後は攻撃されない限り協調していきたい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soka Gakkai has made the same claim in recent years, insisting that it has attacked other Buddhist sects in the past under similar circumstances and that it will make efforts to cooperate with these sects in the future unless it is subjected to criticism by other sects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soka Gakkai has made the same claim in recent years, insisting that it has attacked other Buddhist sects in the past under similar circumstances and that it will make efforts to cooperate with these sects in the future unless it is subjected to criticism by other sects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soka Gakkai has made the same claim in recent years, insisting that it has attacked other Buddhist sects in the past under similar circumstances and that it will make efforts to cooperate with these sects in the future unless it is subjected to criticism by other sects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>時代の変化を無視して今の世に『四箇格言』をそのままにしておくことは、かえってこちらが独善的と批判されかねない」などとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soka Gakkai also recognizes that adopting the Four Criticisms in contemporary world as they were preached by Nichiren in his time, ignoring the change of the times, would attract criticism for being self-righteous.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soka Gakkai also recognizes that adopting the Four Criticisms in the contemporary world as they were preached by Nichiren in his time, thereby ignoring the change of the times, would be criticized as self-righteous.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soka Gakkai also recognizes that adopting the Four Criticisms in the contemporary world as they were preached by Nichiren in his time, thereby ignoring the change of the times, would be criticized as self-righteous.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>上記のような四箇格言の解釈を捨てて、念仏や真言、禅などの宗派に対してこれまで厳しく破折してきたのを一転、それぞれの宗派を認めて極めて肯定的な見方を行っている（ただし、これは政治的なポーズであるという指摘もまたあり、創価学会を破門した日蓮正宗も、宗祖日蓮大聖人に背くものだと批判している）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, Soka Gakkai has abandoned its past interpretation of the Four Criticisms and adopted a positive attitude toward other Buddhist sects instead of directing severe criticism against Nenbutsu, Shingon, Zen and other schools of Buddhism (however, some critics point out that this is merely a political posture and the Nichiren orthodox Buddhism also criticizes Soka Gakkai for its betrayal against Nichiren.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, Soka Gakkai has abandoned its past interpretation of the Four Criticisms and adopted a positive attitude toward other Buddhist sects instead of directing severe criticism against Nenbutsu, Shingon, Zen and other schools of Buddhism (however, some critics point out that this is merely a political posture and the Nichiren orthodox Buddhism also criticizes Soka Gakkai for its betrayal against Nichiren).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, Soka Gakkai has abandoned its past interpretation of the Four Criticisms and adopted a positive attitude toward other Buddhist sects instead of directing severe criticism against Nenbutsu, Shingon, Zen and other schools of Buddhism (however, some critics point out that this is merely a political posture and the Nichiren orthodox Buddhism also criticizes Soka Gakkai for its betrayal against Nichiren).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>以上、朝日新聞夕刊 平成14年8月12日の記事より。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above comments are quoted from an article in the Asahi Shinbun Newspaper dated August 12, 2002.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above comments are quoted from an article in the Asahi Shinbun Newspaper dated August 12, 2002.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The above comments are quoted from an article in the Asahi Shinbun Newspaper dated August 12, 2002.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="40">
<j>また仏教では、新しく宗派を開く時に教相判釈（略して、教判）といい、釈迦の説法をその性質によって分類し、その中からどれが一番優れているかを選定し、自宗の教えの基礎とするかが常套である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a new Buddhist sect is created, it usually evaluates various teachings of Buddha, classifies them according to their nature, and chooses teachings best suited to itself and adopts them as its doctrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a new Buddhist sect is created, it usually evaluates various teachings of Buddha, classifies them according to their nature, chooses the teachings that are best suited to its needs, and adopts them as its doctrine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a new Buddhist sect is created, it usually evaluates various teachings of Buddha, classifies them according to their nature, chooses the teachings that are best suited to its needs, and adopts them as its doctrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>これが成されないと宗派として成立しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Buddhist sect cannot be established without this process.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Buddhist sect cannot be established without this process.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Buddhist sect cannot be established without this process.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>したがって、どの宗派の宗祖も他の教えや宗派を多少なりとも批判している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, no founder of a Buddhist sect can avoid criticizing the teachings of other sects, at least to a certain extent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, no founder of a Buddhist sect can avoid criticizing the teachings of other sects, at least to a certain extent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, no founder of a Buddhist sect can avoid criticizing the teachings of other sects, at least to a certain extent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>日蓮はその中でも「地獄に堕す」などと激しく他宗を論難した人であるが、これは日蓮だけに限ったことではない、という指摘がなされており、近代に至っても様々な角度から論考される問題を含んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nichiren is known to have directed particularly harsh criticisms at other sects, but as some people point out, such criticisms are not necessarily limited to Nichiren, and his religious criticisms raise issues worth studying from various angles even in contemporary society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nichiren is known to have directed particularly harsh criticisms at other sects, but as some people have pointed out, such criticisms aren&apos;t necessarily limited to Nichiren, and that even in contemporary society his religious criticisms raise issues worth studying from various perspectives.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nichiren is known to have directed particularly harsh criticisms at other sects, but as some people have pointed out, such criticisms aren&apos;t necessarily limited to Nichiren, and that even in contemporary society his religious criticisms raise issues worth studying from various perspectives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mobnoboka(id:35218), Boca samba(id:137526), 大石寺信徒(id:59000), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>