<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>明全</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myozen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myozen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myozen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>明全（みょうぜん、元暦元年（1184年）- 嘉禄元年5月27日 (旧暦)（1225年7月4日））は、鎌倉時代前期の臨済宗の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myozen (1184-July 4, 1225) was a Buddhist priest of the Rinzai sect who lived in the beginning of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myozen (1184 - July 4, 1225) was a Buddhist priest of the Rinzai sect who lived in the beginning of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myozen (1184 - July 11, 1225) was a Buddhist priest of the Rinzai sect who lived in the beginning of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>号は仏樹房。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also used alias name of &quot;Butsujubo.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also used the alias &quot;Butsujubo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also used the alias &quot;Butsujubo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>初め延暦寺の杉井房明融に師事し、その後栄西に師事して法を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first Myozen learned under Sugiibo Myoyu of Enryaku-ji Temple, and then under Eisai and succeed to the teachings of Eisai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myozen first studied under Sugiibo Myoyu of Enryaku-ji Temple and then under Eisai; eventually, he succeeded to the teachings of Eisai.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myozen first studied under Sugiibo Myoyu of Enryaku-ji Temple and then under Eisai; eventually, he succeeded to the teachings of Eisai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>1223年（貞応2年）道元・高照・廓然らを伴って中国の宋 (王朝)に渡った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went to China in the Sung dynasty in 1223 along with Dogen, Kosho, Kakunen and others.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He went to China in the Sung Dynasty in 1223 along with Dogen, Kosho, Kakunen and others.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He went to China in the Sung Dynasty in 1223 along with Dogen, Kosho, Kakunen and others.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>景福寺の妙雲、ついで栄西の師でもある太白山景徳寺の無際了派のもとで学んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He learned under Myoun of Keifuku-ji Temple and then Musai Ryoha of Keitoku-ji Temple on Mt. Taihaku who was the master of Eisai.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He studied under Myoun of Keifuku-ji Temple and then Musai Ryoha of Keitoku-ji Temple on Mt. Taihaku, the latter of whom was the master of Eisai.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He studied under Myoun of Keifuku-ji Temple and then Musai Ryoha of Keitoku-ji Temple on Mt. Taihaku, the latter of whom was the master of Eisai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>太白山にいること3年で明全は病に倒れ了然院でなくなってしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After having been in Mt. Taihaku for three years, he got illness and died at the Ryonen-in Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After having been in Mt. Taihaku for three years, he fell ill and died at Ryonen-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After having been in Mt. Taihaku for three years, he fell ill and died at Ryonen-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>道元は師弟関係9年の間に天台教学・黄竜派の禅・戒律などを学んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dogen had learnt the Zen and precepts of the Oryuha lineage of the Tendai doctrine from Myozen through nine years of their relationship of master and apprentice.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dogen had studied Zen and the precepts of the Oryuha lineage of the Tendai doctrine from Myozen over the nine years of their relationship as master and apprentice.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dogen had studied Zen and the precepts of the Oryuha lineage of the Tendai doctrine from Myozen over the nine years of their relationship as master and apprentice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>道元は明全の遺骨を持ち帰り「舎利相伝記」を表し、明全の戒牒に奥書を記して永平寺に納めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dogen brought back the cremains of Myozen, wrote &apos;&apos;Shari sodenki&quot; (Record of the Transmission of Sarira), and wrote an Okugaki (postscript) on the Myozen&apos;s kaicho (Certificates of Reception of Buddhist Commandments) then placed it in the Eihei-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dogen brought back the remains of Myozen, wrote &apos;&apos;Shari sodenki (Record of the Transmission of Sarira),&quot; and wrote an Okugaki (postscript) on Myozen&apos;s kaicho (certificates of reception of Buddhist commandments) and placed it in Eihei-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dogen brought back the remains of Myozen, wrote &apos;&apos;Shari sodenki&quot; (Record of the Transmission of Sarira), and wrote an Okugaki (postscript) on Myozen&apos;s kaicho (certificates of reception of Buddhist commandments) and placed it in Eihei-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>説明括弧の位置を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 浩(id:70121), Okapia2(id:98589), 果心居士(id:248111), 水野白楓(id:22811), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), Nighthawks(id:36125), Point136(id:211299), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>