<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>教相判釈</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoso Hanjaku (evaluation of sutras)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoso Hanjaku (evaluation of sutras)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoso Hanjaku (evaluation of sutras)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>教相判釈（きょうそう はんじゃく）とは、中国をはじめとする漢訳仏典圏において、仏教の経典を、その相（内容）によって、高低、浅深を判定し解釈したもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoso Hanjaku means evaluation of Buddhist scriptures that was practiced in the regions where Buddhist scriptures of Chinese character were used, including China, for the purpose of evaluating and interpreting Buddhist scriptures based on the height and depth of their contents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoso Hanjaku means evaluation of Buddhist scriptures, and was practiced in regions where Buddhist scriptures using Chinese characters were used, including China, for the purpose of evaluating and interpreting Buddhist scriptures based on the height and depth of their contents.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoso Hanjaku means evaluation of Buddhist scriptures, and was practiced in regions where Buddhist scriptures using Chinese characters were used, including China, for the purpose of evaluating and interpreting Buddhist scriptures based on the height and depth of their contents.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>略して教判ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Kyohan for short.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called Kyohan for short.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called Kyohan for short.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>釈迦は成道して、涅槃に入るまでの45年前後の間に、多くの教えを説いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shaka preached a lot of teachings during the period of 45 years after he attained enlightenment until he entered nirvana.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shaka preached many teachings during the 45 year period after he attained enlightenment and until he entered nirvana.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shaka preached many teachings during around 45 year period after he attained enlightenment and until he entered nirvana.</e>
<cmt>前後、を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>後々にそれが発展して経典として形成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These teachings were compiled into scriptures in later years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These teachings were compiled into scriptures in later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These teachings were compiled into scriptures in later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>しかしてそれらの多くの経典が、中国へ伝えられ、漢訳仏典として集成されると、中国的な仏伝の解釈に基づき、これらの諸経典の教えの相や時期を分けて判別して、それらから仏道修行の完全なる悟りを得ようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After these many scriptures had been introduced into China and compiled into Buddhist scriptures of Chinese character, they were distinguished, according to Chinese-style interpretation of Shaka&apos;s teaching, based on their contents and the era of original teachings and monks sought perfect Satori (enlightenment) in unobstructed cultivation of Buddhism from such scriptures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After many scriptures had been introduced into China and compiled into Buddhist scriptures using Chinese characters, they were distinguished, according to Chinese-style interpretation of Shaka&apos;s teaching, based on their contents and the era of original teachings and monks sought perfect Satori (enlightenment) in unobstructed cultivation of Buddhism from such scriptures.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After many scriptures had been introduced into China and compiled into Buddhist scriptures using Chinese characters, they were distinguished, according to Chinese-style interpretation of Shaka&apos;s teaching, based on their contents and the era of original teachings and monks sought perfect Satori (enlightenment) in unobstructed cultivation of Buddhism from such scriptures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>これが教相判釈の始まりであり、北伝の仏教として日本や朝鮮、ベトナムなどに伝えられていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the origin of Kyoso Hanjaku and it was introduced into Japan, Korea and Vietnam as north-route Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the origin of Kyoso Hanjaku and it was introduced into Japan, Korea and Vietnam as northern-route Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the origin of Kyoso Hanjaku and it was introduced into Japan, Korea and Vietnam as northern-route Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし、今日では、経典の成立した年代がある程度特定され、大乗経典などは、釈迦の直説ではなく後代によって成立したことが周知の事実であることから、大乗非仏説の根拠として批判されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Currently, however, it is widely criticized and cited as the proof of thesis that the Mahayana teachings do not stem from the historical Buddha&apos;s teachings because the era of creation of each scripture is specified to a certain extent and the fact that Mahayana Sutra is not Shaka&apos;s direct teachings but the one created in later years is well known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently, however, it is widely criticized and cited as proof of the thesis that the Mahayana teachings do not stem from the historical Buddha&apos;s teachings because the era of creation of each scripture is specified to a certain extent and the fact that the Mahayana Sutra is not Shaka&apos;s direct teaching but one created in later years is well known.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Currently, however, it is widely criticized and cited as proof of the thesis that the Mahayana teachings do not stem from the historical Buddha&apos;s teachings because the era of creation of each scripture is specified to a certain extent and the fact that the Mahayana Sutra is not Shaka&apos;s direct teaching but one created in later years is well known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>したがって五時八教説（後述）は完全なものではない、あるいは正しくないと一般的に否定されつつある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, classification of Buddhist Doctrines known as &quot;Fivefold Periods and Eight Teachings&quot;(to be mentioned later) is generally denied as being imperfect or incorrect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, classification of the Buddhist Doctrines known as &quot;Fivefold Periods and Eight Teachings&quot;(to be mentioned later) is generally rejected as being imperfect or incorrect.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, classification of the Buddhist Doctrines known as &quot;Fivefold Periods and Eight Teachings&quot; (to be mentioned later) is generally rejected as being imperfect or incorrect.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>ただし上座部仏教の三蔵も、最古の部分でも釈迦の死後100年内に編纂されたと推測されている程度で、実際に釈迦の直接の教説の記述を伝えるものとし確定されている経典は存在しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, even the oldest portion of Theravada Buddhism&apos;s tripitaka is only assumed to have been compiled 100 years after Shaka&apos;s demise and there exist no scriptures that were confirmed as the ones that hand down Shaka&apos;s direct teachings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, even the oldest portion of Theravada Buddhism&apos;s tripitaka is assumed to have been compiled only 100 years after Shaka&apos;s demise and there exist no scriptures that have been confirmed as those handed down from Shaka&apos;s direct teachings.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, even the oldest portion of Theravada Buddhism&apos;s tripitaka is assumed to have been compiled only 100 years after Shaka&apos;s demise and there exist no scriptures that have been confirmed as those handed down from Shaka&apos;s direct teachings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>だが、当時は南伝も北伝も、経典はすべて釈迦の説いた教えであると信じられていたため、教相判釈による以外に判別する方法が無かったともいえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, however, there were no methods other than Kyoso Hanjaku to distinguish many scriptures because all Buddhist scriptures, regardless of south route or north route, were believed to be the direct teachings of Shaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, however, there were no methods other than Kyoso Hanjaku to distinguish the many scriptures because all Buddhist scriptures, regardless of south route or north route, were believed to be the direct teachings of Shaka.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, however, there were no methods other than Kyoso Hanjaku to distinguish the many scriptures because all Buddhist scriptures, regardless of south route or north route, were believed to be the direct teachings of Shaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>またちなみに、多くの経典が釈迦の直説ではないといっても、そのおおもととなる教説により各経典が発展して成立し、まったくのデタラメとも言えないという観点から、大乗非仏説ではなく経典成立史と呼称して新しく教相の判釈を試みる傾向もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this connection, some monks still try to conduct Kyoso Hanjaku under the pretext of the history of creation of scriptures, apart from the thesis that the Mahayana teachings do not stem from the historical Buddha, from a standpoint that even though many of scriptures don&apos;t directly derive from Shaka&apos;s teachings, they cannot be completely bogus since each scripture should have been created and developed based on the original Shaka&apos;s teaching.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this connection, some monks still try to conduct Kyoso Hanjaku under the pretext of the history of creation of scriptures, independent of the thesis that the Mahayana teachings do not stem from the historical Buddha, from the standpoint that even though many of scriptures do not directly derive from Shaka&apos;s teachings, they cannot be completely bogus since each scripture should have been created and developed based on the original Shaka&apos;s teachings.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this connection, some monks still try to conduct Kyoso Hanjaku under the pretext of the history of creation of scriptures, independent of the thesis that the Mahayana teachings do not stem from the historical Buddha, from the standpoint that even though many of scriptures do not directly derive from Shaka&apos;s teachings, they cannot be completely bogus since each scripture should have been created and developed based on the original Shaka&apos;s teachings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>チベット語仏典圏（チベット、モンゴル、清朝）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Block of Tibetan Buddhist scripturs (Tibet, Mongolia, Chin)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Block of Tibetan Buddhist scriptures (Tibet, Mongolia, China)</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Block of Tibetan Buddhist Scriptures (Tibet, Mongolia, Ching)</e>
<cmt>清朝の用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>チベットでは、八世紀末から九世紀にかけ、国家事業として仏教の導入に取り組み、この時期にインドで行われた仏教の諸潮流のすべてを、短期間で一挙に導入した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Tibet, the introduction of Buddhism was carried out as a national project during the period from the end of 8th century to 9th century and various traditions of Buddhism then existed in India were introduced at one swoop in a short period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Tibet, the introduction of Buddhism was carried out as a national project during the period from the end of the 8th century to the 9th century and various Buddhist traditions that then existed in India were introduced in one swoop in a short period.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Tibet, the introduction of Buddhism was carried out as a national project during the period from the end of the 8th century to the 9th century and various Buddhist traditions that then existed in India were introduced in one swoop in a short period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>仏典の翻訳にあたっても、サンスクリット語を正確に対訳するためのチベット語の語彙や文法の整備を行った上でとりくまれたため、ある経典に対する単一の翻訳、諸経典を通じての、同一概念に対する同一の訳語など、チベットの仏教界は、漢訳仏典と比してきわめて整然とした大蔵経を有することができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In translating Buddhist scriptures, preparation of proper vocabularies and grammar of Tibetan required for correct translation from Sanskrit was conducted beforehand and as a result, Daizo-kyo Sutra of Tibetan Buddhism is much more streamlined, such as the existence of single translation of a particular scripture and the unified word selection of the same notion used in various scriptures, compared with Buddhist scriptures of Chinese character.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In translating Buddhist scriptures, preparation of the proper Tibetan vocabulary and grammar required for correct translation from Sanskrit was conducted beforehand and as a result, Daizo-kyo Sutra of Tibetan Buddhism are much more streamlined, such as the existence of a single translation of a particular scripture and unified word selection of the same notion used in various scriptures, compared with Buddhist scriptures using Chinese characters.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In translating Buddhist scriptures, preparation of the proper Tibetan vocabulary and grammar required for correct translation from Sanskrit was conducted beforehand and as a result, Daizo-kyo Sutra (the Tripitaka) of Tibetan Buddhism are much more streamlined, such as the existence of a single translation of a particular scripture and unified word selection of the same notion used in various scriptures, compared with Buddhist scriptures using Chinese characters.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>そのため、チベット仏教においては、部分的に矛盾する言説を有する経典群を、いかに合理的に、一つの体系とするか、という観点から仏典研究が取り組まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under such circumstances, a study of Buddhist scriptures in Tibetan Buddhism was conducted from the viewpoint that how to rationally systematize a group of scriptures which include partially contradictory wordings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under such circumstances, a study of Buddhist scriptures in Tibetan Buddhism was conducted from the viewpoint of how to rationally systematize a group of scriptures which also includes partially contradictory wordings.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under such circumstances, a study of Buddhist scriptures in Tibetan Buddhism was conducted from the viewpoint of how to rationally systematize a group of scriptures which also includes partially contradictory wordings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>歴史（漢訳仏典圏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History (block of Buddhist scriptures of Chinese character)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History (block of Buddhist scriptures of Chinese characters)</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History (Block of Buddhist Scriptures of Chinese Characters)</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>中国においては、伝えられた経典の多さから仏教の教えがあまりにも多様化し、どれが釈迦の真実の教えかということが問題になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In China, the problem concerning the real teachings of Shaka arose because the Buddhist teachings had been highly diversified many due to too many scriptures introduced into there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In China, the problem concerning the real teachings of Shaka arose because Buddhist teachings were highly diversified due to too many scriptures being introduced.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In China, the problem concerning which are the real teachings of Shaka arose because Buddhist teachings were highly diversified due to too many scriptures being introduced.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>そこで、経典の内容が種々異なるのは、釈迦が教えを説いた時期や内容が異なるためと考え、教えを説いた時期を分類し、その中でどれが最高の教えであるかという、ひとつの判定方法として、各宗派によってさまざまな教相判釈が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under such circumstances, it was widely thought that the root of such differences in the contents of scriptures was the difference of the era and contents of Shaka&apos;s original teachings and a variety of Kyoso Hanjaku, a method for distinguishing the era of Shaka&apos;s preaching as well as judging the supreme teachings among them, were practiced by various sects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under such circumstances, it was widely thought that the root of such differences in the contents of scriptures was the difference of the era and contents of Shaka&apos;s original teachings and a variety of Kyoso Hanjaku, a method for distinguishing the era of Shaka&apos;s preachings as well as judging the supreme teachings among them, were practiced by various sects.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under such circumstances, it was widely thought that the root of such differences in the contents of scriptures was the difference of the era and contents of Shaka&apos;s original teachings and a variety of Kyoso Hanjaku, a method for distinguishing the era of Shaka&apos;s preachings as well as judging the supreme teachings among them, were practiced by various sects.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>最古の教判は、道生によるといわれるもので、以下の4種に分けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The oldest Kyohan is believed to be the one practiced by Dosho and it is categorized into 4 kinds as shown below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The oldest Kyohan is believed to be the one practiced by Dosho and it is categorized into 4 kinds as shown below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The oldest Kyohan is believed to be the one practiced by Dosho and it is categorized into four kinds as shown below.</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>善浄法輪（ぜんじょうほうりん） - 在家信者のために説いた</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zenjo-horin - Shaka preached to lay believers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zenjo-horin - Shaka preached to lay believers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zenjo-horin - Shaka preached to lay believers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>方便法輪（ほうべんほうりん） - 声聞・縁覚・菩薩のために説いた</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoben-horin - Shaka preached to Zraavaka, Pratyekabuddha and Bodhisattva.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoben-horin - Shaka preached to Zraavaka, Pratyekabuddha and Bodhisattva.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoben-horin - Shaka preached to Zraavaka, Pratyekabuddha and Bodhisattva.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>真実法輪（しんじつほうりん） - 法華経を説いた</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinjitsu-horin - Shaka preached Hoke-kyo Sutra.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinjitsu-horin - Shaka preached Hoke-kyo Sutra.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinjitsu-horin - Shaka preached Hoke-kyo Sutra (the Lotus Sutra).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>無余法輪（むよほうりん） - 大般泥洹経（だいはつないおんきょう、法顕訳の涅槃経前半部のみ）を説いた</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Muyo-horin - Shaka preached Daihatusnaion-kyo Sutra (only first half of Nehan-gyo Sutra translated by Hokken).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Muyo-horin - Shaka preached Daihatusnaion-kyo Sutra (only first half of Nehan-gyo Sutra translated by Hokken).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Muyo-horin - Shaka preached Daihatusnaion-kyo Sutra (only first half of Nehan-gyo Sutra (the Nirvana Sutra) translated by Hokken).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="23">
<j>次いで、慧観（えかん）の五時の教判が提唱される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Next, Ekan exhorted Kyohan called Fivefold Periods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Next, Ekan exhorted Kyohan, called the Fivefold Periods.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Next, Ekan exhorted Kyohan, called the Fivefold Periods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="24">
<j>サルナートで四諦転法輪（したいてんぽうりん）を説いた</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shaka preached Shitaitem-porin at Sarnath.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shaka preached Shitaitem-porin at Sarnath.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shaka preached Shitai Tenporin (literally, spinning the dharma wheel and metaphorically to &apos;expounding the truth&apos; of Four Noble Truths) at Sarnath.</e>
<cmt>用語表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>各所で大品般若経（だいぼんはんにゃきょう）を説いた</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shaka preached Mahaprajnaparamita-sutra at various place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shaka preached Mahaprajnaparamita-sutra at various places.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shaka preached Mahaprajnaparamita-sutra at various places.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>各所で維摩経（ゆいまきょう）・梵天思益経（ぼんてんしやくきょう）を説いた</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shaka preached Yuima-kyo Sutra and Bontenyakushi-kyo Sutra at various place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shaka preached Yuima-kyo Sutra and Bontenyakushi-kyo Sutra at various places.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shaka preached Yuima-gyo (Vimalakirti Sutra) and Bontenyakushi-kyo (Brahmapariprccha Sutra) at various places.</e>
<cmt>共有サイトなどに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>霊鷲山で法華経を説いた</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shaka preached Hoke-kyo sutra at RyojusenMountain (Griddhakuta).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shaka preached Hoke-kyo sutra at Ryojusen Mountain (Griddhakuta).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shaka preached Hoke-kyo sutra at Ryojusen Mountain (Griddhakuta).</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>娑羅双樹（しゃらそうじゅ）林で大般涅槃経を説いた</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shaka preached the Nirvana Sutra at the grove of sal tree.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shaka preached the Nirvana Sutra at a grove of sal trees.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shaka preached Daihatsu Nehan-gyo (the Nirvana Sutra) at a grove of sal trees.</e>
<cmt>大般涅槃経=涅槃経として修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>慧観は、この五時を定めて、五時の教判の源流を創始したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ekan is believed to have established Fivefold Periods and founded the origin of Fivefold Periods Kyohan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ekan is believed to have established Fivefold Periods and founded the origin of the Fivefold Periods Kyohan.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ekan was believed to have established Fivefold Periods and founded the origin of the Fivefold Periods Kyohan.</e>
<cmt>過去形にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="30">
<j>道生・慧観ともに、法華経を訳した鳩摩羅什の筆頭の弟子である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both Dosho and Ekan are the principal disciples of Kumaraju, who translated Hoke-kyo Sutra.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both Dosho and Ekan are the principal disciples of Kumaraju, who translated Hoke-kyo Sutra.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both Dosho and Ekan were the principal disciples of Kumaraju, who translated Hoke-kyo Sutra.</e>
<cmt>過去形にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>また両者は涅槃経の解釈に差異があり、慧観が道生を批判したりするが、両者ともに教判上では最高の経典は涅槃経であると位置付けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there is a difference between them in the interpretation of Nehan-gyo Sutra and Ekan once criticized Dosho, both of them judged Nehan-gyo Sutra as the supreme scripture in their Kyohan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there is a difference between them in thier interpretation of Nehan-gyo Sutra, and Ekan once criticized Dosho, both judged Nehan-gyo Sutra to be the supreme scripture in their Kyohan.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there is a difference between them in their interpretation of Nehan-gyo, and Ekan once criticized Dosho, both judged the Nirvana Sutra to be the supreme scripture in their Kyohan.</e>
<cmt>用語表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="32">
<j>今日、五時の教判といえば、天台宗のものが有名だが、もともとは慧観の提唱した五時がその始めである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As far as Fivefold Periods Kyohan is concerned, that of Tendai sect is famous today but its origin is Fivefold Periods which was exhorted by Ekan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As far as the Fivefold Periods Kyohan is concerned, that of the Tendai sect is famous today but its origin is the Fivefold Periods as exhorted by Ekan.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As far as the Fivefold Periods Kyohan is concerned, that of the Tendai sect is famous today but its origin is the Fivefold Periods as exhorted by Ekan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>これにより、さまざまな教相判釈が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on this, a variety of Kyoso-hanjaku were practiced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on this, a variety of Kyoso-hanjaku were practiced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on this, a variety of Kyoso-hanjaku were practiced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>したがって天台宗の「五時八教の教判」は、道生・慧観にそのルーツを見ることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the origin of &quot;Fivefold Periods Kyohan and Eight Teachings&quot; of Tendai sect can be traced back to Dosho and Ekan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the origin of &quot;Fivefold Periods Kyohan and Eight Teachings&quot; of the Tendai sect can be traced back to Dosho and Ekan.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the origin of &apos;Fivefold Periods Kyohan and Eight Teachings&apos; of the Tendai sect can be traced back to Dosho and Ekan.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="35">
<j>五時八教説（天台）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thesis of &quot;Fivefold Periods and Eight Teachings&quot; (Tendai)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thesis of &quot;Fivefold Periods and Eight Teachings&quot; (Tendai)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thesis of Fivefold Periods and Eight Teachings (Tendai)</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>五時八教の教判、あるいは五時八教説(ごじはっきょうせつ)とは、天台山智ギ（ちぎ、538年 - 597年）が、一切経を五時八教に分けたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyohan based on &quot;Fivefold Periods and Eight Teachings&quot;, or the thesis of &quot;Fivefold Periods and Eight Teachings&quot;, is what Chigi of Tendai-san Mountain divided Issai-kyo Sutra (complete Buddhist scriptures) into &quot;Fivefold Periods and Eight Teachings&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyohan based on &quot;Fivefold Periods and Eight Teachings&quot;, or the thesis of &quot;Fivefold Periods and Eight Teachings&quot;, is what Chigi of Tendai-san Mountain divided Issai-kyo Sutra (complete Buddhist scriptures) into &quot;Fivefold Periods and Eight Teachings&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyohan based on Fivefold Periods and Eight Teachings, or the thesis of Fivefold Periods and Eight Teachings, is what Chigi (538 - 597) of Mt. Tendai divided Issai-kyo Sutra (complete Buddhist scriptures) into Fivefold Periods and Eight Teachings.</e>
<cmt>年号補足、用語変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>日本へは最澄が紹介した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saicho introduced it into Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saicho introduced it into Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saicho introduced it into Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>これを日蓮が採用し、法華経が最高の教えであるという根拠とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nichiren adopted it as the basis of his advocacy that Hoke-kyo Sutra is the supreme scripture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nichiren adopted it as the basis of his advocacy that Hoke-kyo Sutra is the supreme scripture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nichiren adopted it as the basis of his advocacy that Hoke-kyo Sutra is the supreme scripture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="39">
<j>五時</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fivefold Periods</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fivefold Periods</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fivefold Periods</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>最初に華厳経を説き、その教えが難しいため人々が理解できなかったとして、次に平易な阿含経を説いたとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to this thesis, Shaka preached Kegon-kyo Sutra first but as it was too difficult for people to understand, he preached Agon-kyo Sutra next.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to this thesis, Shaka preached Kegon-kyo Sutra first but as it was too difficult for people to understand, he preached Agon-kyo Sutra next.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to this thesis, Shaka preached Kegon-kyo Sutra (Avatamska Sutra) first but as it was too difficult for people to understand, he preached Agon-kyo Sutra (Agama Sutra) next which was easier.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>人々の理解の割合に応じて、方等経、般若経を説き、最後の8年間で法華経と涅槃経を説いたとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shaka, then, preached Hodo-kyo Sutra and Hannya-kyo Sutra depending on peoples&apos; level of understanding and during final 8 years, he preached Hoke-kyo Sutra and Nehan-gyo Sutra.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shaka, then preached Hodo-kyo Sutra and Hannya-kyo Sutra depending on peoples&apos; level of understanding and during the final 8 years, he preached Hoke-kyo Sutra and Nehan-gyo Sutra.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shaka, then preached Hodo-kyo Sutra (Vaipulya Sutra) and Hannya-kyo Sutra (Great Perfection of Wisdom Sutra) depending on peoples&apos; level of understanding and during the final 8 years, he preached Hoke-kyo Sutra and Nehan-gyo.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>そして最後に説いた法華経が釈迦のもっとも重要な教えであるとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a conclusion, this thesis asserts that Hoke-kyo Sutra, which Shaka finally preached, is the most important teachings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a conclusion, this thesis asserts that Hoke-kyo Sutra, which Shaka finally preached, is the most important teaching.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a conclusion, this thesis asserted that Hoke-kyo Sutra, which Shaka finally preached, was the most important teaching.</e>
<cmt>過去形にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="43">
<j>五時を、説法した期間・会座（えざ＝説法の場所）・経典などを分類すると次の通り。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Base on periods, Eza (place where Shaka preached) and scriptures, Fivefold Periods are sorted out as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on periods, Eza (place where Shaka preached) and scriptures, Fivefold Periods are sorted out as follows.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on duration, Eza (place where Shaka preached) and scripture, D are sorted out as follows.</e>
<cmt>用語を合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="44">
<j>華厳時</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kegon period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kegon period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Period of Kegon-kyo (Avatamsaka)</e>
<cmt>以下サイトなどに合わせて表現を変えました。http://www.buddhistdoor.com/OldWeb/bdoor/archive/nutshell/teach70.htm</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>期間 - 21日間（一説に31日間とも）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Duration - 21 days (somme asserts 31 days)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Duration - 21 days (some assert is was 31 days)</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Duration - 21 days (some assert it was 31 days)</e>
<cmt>不要な語をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>会座 - ガヤー城近郊、ナイランジャナー河の菩提樹の下など、7処8会</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eza - 8 meetings at 7 places including nearby Gaya Castle and under a lime tree along the Niranjana River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eza - 8 meetings at 7 places including nearby Gaya Castle and under a lime tree along the Niranjana River.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eza - 8 meetings at 7 places including nearby Gaya Castle and under a lime tree along the Niranjana River.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>経典 - 華厳経（大方廣仏華厳経）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Scripture - Kegon kyo Sutra (Daihokobutsu Kegon-kyo Sutra)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Scripture - Kegon kyo Sutra (Daihokobutsu Kegon-kyo Sutra)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Scripture - Kegon-kyo Sutra (Daihokobutsu Kegon-kyo Sutra)</e>
<cmt>用語を合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>位 - 乳酥、別・円を説く頓教、擬宜の教え</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Contents - Fresh milk, Subitism that advocates Betsu-kyo (Shakamuni&apos;s differentiated,or separated, bodhisattva teaching) and En-kyo (Shakamuni&apos;s final, perfect, bodhisattva) and the teaching of gisen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Contents - Fresh milk, Subitism that advocates Betsu-kyo (Shakamuni&apos;s differentiated, or separated, bodhisattva teaching) and En-kyo (Shakamuni&apos;s final, perfect, bodhisattva) and the teaching of gisen.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Contents - Nyuso (Fresh milk), Sudden Teaching that advocates Betsu-kyo (Distinctive Teaching) and En-kyo (Complete Teaching) and the teaching of gigi (to gauge good things).</e>
<cmt>乳酥など（以降同じ）は、以下サイトを参考にしました。http://www.buddhistdoor.com/OldWeb/bdoor/archive/nutshell/teach70.htm</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>阿含時</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Agan period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Agan period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Period of Agon-kyo (Agamas)</e>
<cmt>以下サイトなどに合わせて表現を変えました。http://www.buddhistdoor.com/OldWeb/bdoor/archive/nutshell/teach70.htm</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>期間 - 12年間</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Duration - 12 years</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Duration - 12 years</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Duration - 12 years</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>会座 - バラナシー国の鹿野苑</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eza - Sarnath in Varanasi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eza - Sarnath in Varanasi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eza - Sarnath in Varanasi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>経典 - 増一、長、中、雑、小の阿含経、法句経などの南伝大蔵経</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Scripture- Agan-kyo Sutra of zoichi, cho, chu, zatsu, and sho and Nanden Daizo-kyo Sutra such as Hokku-kyo Sutra.</e>
<cmt>増一、長、中、雑、小の意味が理解できませんので、そのままローマ字表記しております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Scripture- Agan-kyo Sutra of zoichi, cho, chu, zatsu, and sho and Nanden Daizo-kyo Sutra such as Hokku-kyo Sutra.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Scripture - Agon-kyo Sutra of zoitsu (or Ekottara Agama, Additional Discourses), Jo (or diigha-nikaaya, Collection of Long Discourses), chu (or majjhima-nikaaya, Collection of Middle-length Discourses), zo (or saMyutta-nikaaya, Connected Discourses or Kindred Sayings), and sho (or khuddaka-nikaaya, Collection of Little Texts) and Nanden Daizo-kyo Sutra (the Tripitaka coming from the south) such as Hokku-kyo Sutra (Dhammapada).</e>
<cmt>Agonとし、他用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>位 - 酪酥、蔵のみを説く漸教（秘密・不定教もあり）、誘引の教え</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Contents - Coagulated milk, Zen-kyo (gradual teaching) that advocates only Zo-kyo (including Himitsu-kyo (esoteric teaching, only understood by special members of the assembly) and Fujo-kyo (general or indeterminate teaching, from which each hearer would derive benefit according to his interpretation) and the teaching of yuin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Contents - Coagulated milk, Zen-kyo (gradual teaching) that advocates only Zo-kyo (including Himitsu-kyo (esoteric teaching, only understood by special members of the assembly) and Fujo-kyo (general or indeterminate teaching, from which each hearer would derive benefit according to his interpretation) and the teaching of yuin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Contents - Rakuso (Cream), Zen-kyo (gradual teaching) that advocates only Daizo-kyo (including Himitsu-kyo (Secret Teaching) and Fujo-kyo (Variable Teaching)) and the teaching of yuin (to lead).</e>
<cmt>蔵（蔵経）＝大蔵経として訳を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>方等時</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hodo period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hodo period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Period of Hodo-kyo (Vaipulya)</e>
<cmt>以下サイトなどに合わせて表現を変えました。http://www.buddhistdoor.com/OldWeb/bdoor/archive/nutshell/teach70.htm</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>期間 - 16年間（一説に8年間）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Duration - 16 years (some asserts 8 years)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Duration - 16 years (some assert it was 8 years)</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Duration - 16 years (some assert it was 8 years)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>会座 - 舎衛城の祇園精舎、マガダ国の竹林精舎、ヴェーサリー国のアンバーパリー園など</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eza - Gion-shoja (the Jetavana monastery) at Sravasti, Venuvana Monastery in Magadh and Amrapali in Vaisali</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eza - Gion-shoja (the Jetavana monastery) at Sravasti, Venuvana Monastery in Magadh and Amrapali in Vaisali</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eza - Gion-shoja (the Jetavana monastery) at Sravasti, Venuvana Monastery in Magadh and Amrapali in Vaisali</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>経典 - 阿弥陀経、大日経、金光明経、維摩経、勝鬘経、解深密経など権大乗経</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Scripture - Gondaijo-kyo Sutra including Amida-kyo Sutra, Dainichi-kyo Sutra, Konkomyo-kyo Sutra, Yuima-kyo Sutra, Shoman-kyo Sutra and Gejinmitsu-kyo Sutra.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Scripture - Gondaijo-kyo Sutra including Amida-kyo Sutra, Dainichi-kyo Sutra, Konkomyo-kyo Sutra, Yuima-kyo Sutra, Shoman-kyo Sutra and Gejinmitsu-kyo Sutra.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Scripture - Gon-daijo-kyo (sutras to explain Mahayana Buddhism) including Amida-kyo Sutra, Dainichi-kyo Sutra (Mahavairocana Sutra), Konkomyo-kyo Sutra Konkomyo-kyo Sutra (Golden Light Sutra), Yuima-kyo Sutra (Vimalakirti Sutra), Shoman-kyo Sutra (Srimala Sutra) and Gejinmitsu-kyo Sutra (Samdhinirmocana-sutra).</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>位 - 生酥、蔵通別円の4教を対比して説く漸教（秘密・不定教もあり）、弾訶の教え</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Contents - Curdled milk, Zen-kyo (including Himitsu-kyo and Fujo-kyo) that advocates the comparison of 4 teachings of Zo-kyo, Tsu-kyo, En- kyo and Betsu-kyo and the teaching of danka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Contents - Curdled milk, Zen-kyo (including Himitsu-kyo and Fujo-kyo) that advocates the comparison of 4 teachings of Zo-kyo, Tsu-kyo, En- kyo and Betsu-kyo and the teaching of danka.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Contents - Shoso (Curds), Zen-kyo (including Himitsu-kyo and Fujo-kyo) that advocates the comparison of 4 teachings of Daizo-kyo, Tsu-kyo (Shared Teaching), Betsu-kyo and En-kyo and the teaching of danka (to scold).</e>
<cmt>蔵（蔵経）＝大蔵経とし、他用語を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>般若時</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanya period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanya period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Period of Hannya-kyo (Prajna)</e>
<cmt>以下サイトなどに合わせて表現を変えました。http://www.buddhistdoor.com/OldWeb/bdoor/archive/nutshell/teach70.htm</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>期間 - 14年間（一説に22年間）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Duration - 14 years (some assert 22 years)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Duration - 14 years (some assert it was 22 years)</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Duration - 14 years (some assert it was 22 years)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>会座 - マガダ国のラージャガハ附近の霊鷲山など、4処16会</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eza - 16 meetings at 4 places including nearby Rajagrha in Magadh.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eza - 16 meetings at 4 places including nearby Rajagrha in Magadh.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eza - 16 meetings at 4 places including Ryojusen Mountain nearby Rajagrha in Magadh.</e>
<cmt>Ryojusen Mountainを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>経典 - 大般若経、金剛般若経、般若心経など</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Scripture - Dai-Hannya-kyo Sutra, Kongo Hannya-kyo Sutra and Hannya-shingyo Sutra etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Scripture - Dai-Hannya-kyo Sutra, Kongo Hannya-kyo Sutra and Hannya-shingyo Sutra etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Scripture - Daihannya-kyo (Great Perfection of Wisdom Sutra), Kongohannya-kyo Sutra (Diamond Sutra) and Hannya Shin-gyo (Heart Sutra), and so on.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>位 - 熟酥、円教に通別を帯ばしめて説く漸教（秘密・不定教もあり）、淘汰の教え</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Contents - Butter, Zen-kyo that advocates En-kyo with Tsu-kyo and Betsu-kyo mixing ((including Himitsu-kyo and Fujo-kyo) and the teaching of tota.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Contents - Butter, Zen-kyo that advocates En-kyo with Tsu-kyo and Betsu-kyo mixing ((including Himitsu-kyo and Fujo-kyo) and the teaching of tota.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Contents - Jukuso (Butter), Zen-kyo that advocates En-kyo with Tsu-kyo and Betsu-kyo mixing (including Himitsu-kyo and Fujo-kyo) and the teaching of tota (to select).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>法華涅槃時</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoke-Nehan Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoke-Nehan Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Period of Hokke Nehan-gyo (Lotus Nirvana)</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>期間 - 8年間（うち涅槃経は一日一夜）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Duration - 8 years (1 day 1 night as for Nehan-kyo Sutra)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Duration - 8 years (1 day 1 night as for Nehan-kyo Sutra)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Duration - 8 years (1 day 1 night as for Nehan-gyo Sutra)</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>会座 - マガダ国のラージャガハ附近の霊鷲山など、2処3会（法華経）、クシナガラのアジタパティー河辺の沙羅双樹の下（涅槃経）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eza - 3 meetings at 2 palces including RyojusenMountain nearby Rajagrha in Magadh (Hoke-kyo Sutra) and under a sal tree along the Ajitavati River in Kushinagar (Nehan -gyo Sutra).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eza - 3 meetings at 2 places including Ryojusen Mountain near to Rajagrha in Magadh (Hoke-kyo Sutra) and under a sal tree along the Ajitavati River in Kushinagar (Nehan -gyo Sutra).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eza - 3 meetings at 2 places including Ryojusen Mountain nearby Rajagrha in Magadh (Hoke-kyo Sutra) and under a sal tree along the Ajitavati River in Kushinagar (Nehan -gyo Sutra).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>経典 - 法華経28品を中心とする法華三部経、涅槃経</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Scripture - Hokke Sambu-kyo Sutra (The Threefold Lotus Sutra) centered on Hoke-kyo Sutra 28 pon and Nehan-gyo Sutra.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Scripture - Hokke Sambu-kyo Sutra (The Threefold Lotus Sutra) centered on Hoke-kyo Sutra 28 pon and Nehan-gyo Sutra.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Scripture - Hokke Sanbu-kyo Sutra (The Threefold Lotus Sutra) centered on Hoke-kyo Sutra 28 chapters and Nehan-gyo Sutra.</e>
<cmt>chapterを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>位 - 醍醐、円教を説く頓教（秘密・不定教なし）、開会の教え</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Contents - Clarified butter, Ton-kyo that advocates En-kyo (no Himitsu-kyo and Fujo-kyo) and the teaching of kaikai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Contents - Clarified butter, Ton-kyo that advocates En-kyo (no Himitsu-kyo and Fujo-kyo) and the teaching of kaikai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Contents - Daigo (Ghee), Ton-kyo that advocates En-kyo (no Himitsu-kyo and Fujo-kyo) and the teaching of kaie (to reveal).</e>
<cmt>用語を変え、補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="69">
<j>ただしこれは、経典に書かれている時間・時期的な記述や場所、またその内容から、あくまでも順序だてて分けただけで、必ずしも釈迦が絶対的に必ずその順番で説いたわけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the above time-series classification was made simply base on the time ・ descriptions relevant to time and places that are described in scriptures together with their contents, it doesn&apos;t necessarily mean that Shaka actually preached in this order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the above time-series classification was made simply based on the time descriptions relevant to time and places that are described in scriptures together with their contents, it does not necessarily mean that Shaka actually preached in this order.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the above time-series classification was made simply based on the time, descriptions relevant to time and places that are described in scriptures together with their contents, it does not necessarily mean that Shaka actually preached in this order.</e>
<cmt>カンマを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="70">
<j>そのことは、日蓮も守護国家論で、「大部の経、大概（おおむね）是の如し。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this connection, Nichiren said in his Shugo Kokka-ron; &quot; The above is the summary of voluminous sutra.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this connection, Nichiren said in his Shugo Kokka-ron; &quot; The above is a summary of voluminous sutra.&quot;</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this connection, Nichiren said in his Shugo Kokka-ron (Treatise on protection of the nation); &apos;The above is a summary of voluminous sutra.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>此れより已外（いげ）諸の大小乗経は次第不定（しだいふじょう）なり、或は阿含経より已後に華厳経を説き、法華経より已後に方等般若を説く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concerning various sutras of Mahayana and Hinayana other than this, their histories are not definitely confirmed and there is a possibility that Shaka preached Kegon-kyo Sutra after Agan-kyo Sutra or he preached Hodo-kyo Sutra and Hanya-kyo Sutra after Hoke-kyo Sutra.</e>
<cmt>日蓮の原文を正確に理解することができませんでした (たとえば「義類」等）。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concerning various sutras of Mahayana and Hinayana other than this, their histories are definitely confirmed and there is a possibility that Shaka preached Kegon-kyo Sutra after Agan-kyo Sutra or he preached Hodo-kyo Sutra and Hanya-kyo Sutra after Hoke-kyo Sutra.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concerning various sutras of Mahayana and Hinayana other than this, their histories are definitely confirmed and there is a possibility that Shaka preached Kegon-kyo Sutra after Agon-kyo Sutra or he preached Hodo-kyo Sutra and Hannya-kyo Sutra after Hoke-kyo Sutra.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>みな義類（ぎるい）を以て之を収めて一処に置くべし」と述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the meanings of them are analogous, they should be treated together&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the meanings of them are analogous, they should be treated together&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the meanings of them are analogous, they should be treated together.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>したがって、対機説法（たいきせっぽう）、臨機応変という言葉が示すように釈迦仏が衆生の機根（教えを聞ける器、度合い）に応じて、教法を前後して説いたことを留意しなくてはならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, attention should be paid to the fact that Shaka preached his teachings taking into account people&apos;s patience (ability to listen to or understand his teachings) and as the term taiki-seppo (the best suitable expression of the teaching for the target audience) and &quot;rinkiohen (the best suitable action according to circumstances)&quot; indicate, he preached not necessarily in sequence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, attention should be paid to the fact that Shaka preached his teachings taking into account people&apos;s patience (ability to listen to or understand his teachings) and as the term taiki-seppo (the best suitable expression of the teaching for the target audience) and &quot;rinkiohen (the best suitable action according to circumstances)&quot; indicate, he preached not necessarily in sequence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, attention should be paid to the fact that Shaka preached his teachings taking into account people&apos;s patience (ability to listen to or understand his teachings) and as the term taiki-seppo (the best suitable expression of the teaching for the target audience) and Rinki Ohen (the best suitable action according to circumstances) indicate, he preached not necessarily in sequence.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>また智顗が分類した五時説を日蓮が採用しつつも、次第不定で前後していることを既に認知していたという事実があることを、大乗非仏説及び経典成立史の観点から留意しなくてはならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the viewpoint of thesis that the Mahayana teachings do not stem from the historical Buddha as well as the history of scriptures, attention also should be paid to the fact that even Nitiren admitted the history of sutras were not confimed while he adopted Fivefold Periods thesis which Chigi had sort out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the viewpoint of the thesis that the Mahayana teachings do not stem from the historical Buddha as well as the history of scriptures, attention also should be paid to the fact that even Nichiren admitted the history of sutras was not confimed while he adopted the Fivefold Periods thesis which Chigi had determined.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the viewpoint of the thesis that the Mahayana teachings do not stem from the historical Buddha as well as the history of scriptures, attention also should be paid to the fact that even Nichiren admitted the history of sutras was not confirmed while he adopted the Fivefold Periods thesis which Chigi had determined.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>したがって今日の仏教学では五時説は間違いであるとして否定する向きもあるが、完全に否定されるものともいえない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therfore, although some members of current Buddhism community deny Fivefold Periods thesis as it is wrong, it cannot be denied completely.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, although some members of the current Buddhist community reject the Fivefold Periods thesis as wrong, it cannot be denied completely.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, although some members of the current Buddhist community reject the Fivefold Periods thesis as wrong, it cannot be denied completely.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="76">
<j>なお、智顗は、涅槃経に対しては、法華経とほぼ同内容で、その真理は既に法華経で明かしており、法華の救いに漏れた者達のために説かれた教えにすぎないと位置づける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this connection, Chigi asserts that the contents of Nehan-gyo Sutra is almost same with that of Hoke-kyo Sutra, its truth had already been clarified in Hoke-kyo Sutra and therefore, it was preached only for the purpose of rescuing people who had been left out from Hoke&apos;s rescue.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this connection, Chigi asserts that the content of Nehan-gyo Sutra is almost same as that of Hoke-kyo Sutra, and its truth had already been clarified in Hoke-kyo Sutra and therefore, it was preached only for the purpose of rescuing people who had been left out from Hoke&apos;s rescue.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this connection, Chigi asserted that the content of Nehan-gyo Sutra was almost the same as that of Hoke-kyo Sutra, and its truth had already been clarified in Hoke-kyo Sutra and therefore, it was preached only for the purpose of rescuing people who had been left out from Hoke&apos;s rescue.</e>
<cmt>過去形にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>そうした位置づけのうえで、涅槃は一日一夜の説法なので法華の八年間に摂したため、法華と涅槃とを分けず「法華涅槃時」としたが、華厳経から法華経までは次第不定に説かれたのに対して、涅槃経は経典の内容や場所から判断して唯一、釈迦が入滅の時に至って説いた教法である、としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on the above standpoint, Chigi further asserts that he didn&apos;t separate Nehan and Hoke and classified them together into &quot;Hoke-Nehan period&quot; because Nehan was preached only for one day one night while Hoke was preached for 8 years, but judging from contents and the place of preaching, only Nehan-gyo Sutra is the teachings that Shaka preached when he was dying.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on the above standpoint, Chigi further asserts that he did not separate Nehan and Hoke and classified them together into &quot;Hoke-Nehan period&quot; because Nehan was preached only for one day and one night while Hoke was preached for 8 years, but judging from the content and the place of preaching, only Nehan-gyo Sutra are the teachings that Shaka preached when he was dying.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on this standpoint, Chigi further asserted that, rather than separating Nehan (nirvana) and Hoke, he classified them together in the &apos;Hoke-Nehan period&apos; because Nehan was preached only for one day and one night, while Hoke was preached for 8 years; judging from the content and the place of preaching while the period of preaching from the Kegon-kyo and Hoke-kyo sutras were unknown, however, the Nehan-gyo Sutra are the only teachings that Shaka preached when he was dying.</e>
<cmt>過去形にし、「華厳経から法華経までは次第不定に解かれたのに対して」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="78">
<j>五味相生の譬</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gomisosho-no-tatoe (The five flavours, or stages of making ghee, which is said to be a cure for all ailments; it is a Tiantai illustration of the five periods of the Buddha&apos;s teaching)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gomisosho-no-tatoe (The five flavours, or stages of making ghee, which is said to be a cure for all ailments; it is a Tiantai illustration of the five periods of the Buddha&apos;s teaching)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gomisosho-no-tatoe (The five flavors, or stages of making ghee, which is said to be a cure for all ailments; it is a Tiantai illustration of the five periods of the Buddha&apos;s teaching)</e>
<cmt>スペルおよび全角括弧を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>また智顗は、華厳・阿含・方等・般若・法華涅槃の五時を涅槃経に説かれる、乳酥・酪酥・生酥・熟酥・醍醐の五味である五味相生の譬（ごみそうしょうのたとえ）に配釈した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chigi also linked Fivefold Periods, Kegon, Agan, Hodo, Hannya and Hoke-Nehan, to Five Flavors, fresh milk, coagulated milk, curdled milk, butter and clarified butter, that are advocated by Nehan-gyo Sutra as Gomisosho-no-tatoe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chigi also linked Fivefold Periods, Kegon, Agan, Hodo, Hannya and Hoke-Nehan, to Five Flavors, fresh milk, coagulated milk, curdled milk, butter and clarified butter, that are advocated by Nehan-gyo Sutra as Gomisosho-no-tatoe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chigi also linked Fivefold Periods, Kegon, Agon, Hodo, Hannya and Hoke-Nehan, to Five Flavors, fresh milk, cream, curds, butter and ghee, that are advocated by Nehan-gyo Sutra as Gomisosho-no-tatoe.</e>
<cmt>訳語を前出に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="80">
<j>乳酥＝華厳</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fresh milk = Kegon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fresh milk = Kegon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nyuso = Kegon</e>
<cmt>用語を前出に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>酪酥＝阿含</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Coagulated milk = Agan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Coagulated milk = Agan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rakuso = Agon</e>
<cmt>Agonとし、用語を前出に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>生酥＝方等</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Curdled milk = Hodo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Curdled milk = Hodo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoso = Hodo</e>
<cmt>用語を前出に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>熟酥＝般若</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Butter = Hannya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Butter = Hannya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jukuso = Hannya</e>
<cmt>用語を前出に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>醍醐＝法華涅槃</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Clarified butter = Hoke-Nehan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Clarified butter = Hoke-Nehan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daigo = Hoke-Nehan</e>
<cmt>用語を前出に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="85">
<j>これは醍醐のたとえとしても有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is well-known as Daigo-no-tatoe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is well-known as Daigo-no-tatoe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is well-known as Daigo-no-tatoe (analogy of Daigo).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>しかし、この涅槃経の記述は、あくまでも、あらゆる経典の中で涅槃経が最も最後であり優れたものである、ということを説いたもので、厳密にいえば、そこに法華経の名称は見当たらない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the above description of Nehan-gyo Sutra solely advocates that Nehan-gyo Sutra is the ultimate and supreme sutra among all sutras and strictly speaking, Hoke-kyo Sutra doesn&apos;t appear in this description.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the above description of Nehan-gyo Sutra solely advocates that Nehan-gyo Sutra is the ultimate and supreme sutra among all sutras and strictly speaking, Hoke-kyo Sutra does not appear in this description.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the above description of Nehan-gyo Sutra solely advocates that Nehan-gyo Sutra is the ultimate and supreme sutra among all sutras and strictly speaking, Hoke-kyo Sutra does not appear in this description.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="87">
<j>実際に涅槃経を読めば「牛より乳を出し、乳より酪酥（らくそ）を出し、酪酥より熟酥（じゅくそ　salpis　サルピス：カルピスの語源）を出し、熟酥より醍醐を出す、仏の教えもまた同じく、仏より十二部経を出し、十二部経より修多羅（しゅたら）を出し、修多羅より方等経を出し、方等経より般若波羅密を出し、般若波羅密より大涅槃経を出す」（「譬如從牛出乳 從乳出酪 從酪出生蘇 從生蘇出熟蘇 從熟蘇出醍醐 醍醐最上 若有服者 衆病皆除 所有諸藥、悉入其中 善男子 佛亦如是 從佛出生十二部經 從十二部経出修多羅 從修多羅出方等経 從方等経出般若波羅蜜 從般若波羅蜜出大涅槃 猶如醍醐 言醍醐者 喩于佛性」）とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Precisely, the description of Nehan-gyo Sutra says &quot;a cow creates fresh milk, fresh milk creates coagulated milk, coagulated milk creates butter (salpis, which is the word origin of Karupisu) and butter creates clarified butter and similarly in the teaching of Buddhism, Buddha creates Junibu-kyo Sutra, Junibu-kyo Sutra creates Shutara, Shutara creates Hodo-kyo Sutra, Hodo-kyo sutra creates Hannya Haramitsu and Hannya Haramitsu creates Dainehan-kyo Sutra&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Precisely, the description of Nehan-gyo Sutra says &quot;a cow creates fresh milk, fresh milk creates coagulated milk, coagulated milk creates butter (salpis, which is the word origin of Karupisu) and butter creates clarified butter and similarly in the teaching of Buddhism, Buddha creates Junibu-kyo Sutra, Junibu-kyo Sutra creates Shutara, Shutara creates Hodo-kyo Sutra, Hodo-kyo sutra creates Hannya Haramitsu and Hannya Haramitsu creates Dainehan-kyo Sutra&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Precisely, the description of Nehan-gyo Sutra says &apos;a cow creates nyu (fresh milk), nyu creates rakuso, rakuso creates jukuso (salpis, which is the word origin of Calpis (Japanese milk-based soft drink) and jukuso creates ghee and similarly in the teaching of Buddhism, Buddha creates Junibu-kyo Sutra (the Twelve Divisions of Scriptures), Junibu-kyo Sutra creates Shutara (sutra), Shutara creates Hodo-kyo Sutra, Hodo-kyo sutra creates Hannya Haramitsu (prajnaparamita) and Hannya Haramitsu creates Dainehan-kyo Sutra&apos; (the Nirvana Sutra).</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションにし補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="88">
<j>したがって厳密には、以下のように配釈される（と想定される）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Strictly speaking, therefore, linkage is (presumed to be) as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Strictly speaking, therefore, linkage is (presumed to be) as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Strictly speaking, therefore, linkage is (presumed to be) as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="89">
<j>乳＝十二部経</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fresh milk = Junibu-kyo Sutra</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fresh milk = Junibu-kyo Sutra</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nyu = Junibu-kyo Sutra</e>
<cmt>表記を前出に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>酪酥＝修多羅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Coagulated milk = Shutara</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Coagulated milk = Shutara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rakuso = Shutara</e>
<cmt>表記を前出に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>生酥＝方等経</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Curdled milk = Hodo-kyo Sutra</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Curdled milk = Hodo-kyo Sutra</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoso = Hodo-kyo Sutra</e>
<cmt>表記を前出に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>熟酥＝般若波羅密</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Butter = Hannya Haramitsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Butter = Hannya Haramitsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jukuso = Hannya Haramitsu</e>
<cmt>表記を前出に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>醍醐＝大涅槃経</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Clarified butter = Dainehan-kyo Sutra</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Clarified butter = Dainehan-kyo Sutra</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daigo = Dainehan-kyo Sutra</e>
<cmt>表記を前出に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="94">
<j>智顗は、聡明なる閃きにより五時と五味を配釈した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chigi linked Fivefold Periods and Five Flavors by his intelligent inspiration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chigi linked Fivefold Periods and Five Flavors by his intelligent inspiration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chigi linked Fivefold Periods and Five Flavors by his intelligent inspiration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>しかし法華優位の立場から涅槃経を劣ると判じるその解釈については、やや牽強付会（けんきょうふかい）であった、という指摘が仏教学において多く提示されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the people belonging to Buddhism academy, however, a lot of criticism have been raised against his interpretation which judges Nehan-gyo Sutra is inferior to Hoke-kyo Sutra, asserting that he twisted the argument too much in favor of Hoke-kyo Sutra from his standpoint of Hoke-kyo Sutra&apos;s superiority.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By people belonging to the Buddhist academy, however, much criticism has been raised against his interpretation which judges that Nehan-gyo Sutra is inferior to Hoke-kyo Sutra, asserting that he twisted the argument too much in favor of Hoke-kyo Sutra from his standpoint regarding Hoke-kyo Sutra&apos;s superiority.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By people belonging to the Buddhist academy, however, much criticism has been raised against his interpretation which judges that Nehan-gyo Sutra is inferior to Hoke-kyo Sutra, asserting that he twisted the argument too much in favor of Hoke-kyo Sutra from his standpoint regarding Hoke-kyo Sutra&apos;s superiority.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="96">
<j>八教</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eight teachings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eight teachings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eight Teachings</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>八教（はちきょう）は、化義(けぎ)の四教と、化法(けほう)の四教に分けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eight teachings are divided into Kegi-no-shikyo (Shakamuni&apos;s four modes of instruction) and Keho-no-shikyo (Shakamuni&apos;s four kinds of teaching of the content of the Truth accommodated to the capacity of his disciples).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eight teachings are divided into Kegi-no-shikyo (Shakamuni&apos;s four modes of instruction) and Keho-no-shikyo (Shakamuni&apos;s four kinds of teaching the content of the Truth, accommodated to the capacity of his disciples).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eight teachings are divided into Kegi-no-shikyo (Shakamuni&apos;s four modes of instruction) and Keho-no-shikyo (Shakamuni&apos;s four kinds of teaching the content of the Truth, accommodated to the capacity of his disciples).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="98">
<j>化義の四教</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kegi-no-shikyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kegi-no-shikyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kegi-no-shikyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>化義の四教とは、人々を導くための形式（儀式など)を義と呼び、釈迦の教えを形式の上から分類したもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kegi-no-shikyo is the categorization of Shaka&apos;s teachings based on the form of teaching to guide people (such as rite) with calling such form as &quot;gi&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kegi-no-shikyo is the categorization of Shaka&apos;s teachings based on the form of teaching to guide people (such as rites) with the calling of such form as &quot;gi&quot;.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kegi-no-shikyo is the categorization of Shaka&apos;s teachings based on the form of teaching to guide people (such as rites) with the calling of such form as Gi.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="100">
<j>頓教（とん、頓とは速やかの意で、仏が悟りを開いた直後、衆生の機根に関係なくすぐに説いた教え）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ton-kyo (&quot;ton&quot; means immediately and Ton-kyo is the teachings which Buddha preached immediately after he attained Satori regardless of people&apos;s patience)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ton-kyo (&quot;ton&quot; means immediately and Ton-kyo are the teachings which Buddha preached immediately after he attained Satori regardless of people&apos;s patience)</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ton-kyo (ton means immediately and Ton-kyo are the teachings which Buddha preached immediately after he attained Satori regardless of people&apos;s patience)</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>漸教（ぜん、漸とは次第にの意で、浅い教えから深い教えと次第し順序を追って衆生の機根に応じて説いた教え）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zen-kyo (gradual teaching) (&quot;zen&quot; means gradually and Zen-kyo is the teaching which Buddha preached stepwise from shallow teachings to deep teachings depending on people&apos;s patience)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zen-kyo (gradual teaching) (&quot;zen&quot; means gradually and Zen-kyo is the teaching which Buddha preached stepwise from shallow teachings to deep teachings depending on people&apos;s patience)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zen-kyo (zen means gradually and Zen-kyo is the teaching which Buddha preached stepwise from shallow teachings to deep teachings depending on people&apos;s patience)</e>
<cmt>前出用語の英訳補足、クォーテーション、不要なスペースなどをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>秘密教（ひみつ、正しくは秘密不定教といい、機根の違う衆生同士に説法の違いを知られず（秘密）に、各々別々（各別）に応じた不定の得益がある法を説いた教え）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Himitsu-kyo (Esoteric teaching, only understood by special members of the assembly) (Its correct name is Himitsu Fujo-kyo and it is the teaching which Shaka preached in order to give indefinite benefits separately (individually) to people whose patience are different while keeping the difference of teachings in secret (confidentially))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Himitsu-kyo (Esoteric teaching, only understood by special members of the assembly) (Its correct name is Himitsu Fujo-kyo and it is the teaching which Shaka preached in order to give indefinite benefits separately (individually) to people whose patience is different while keeping the difference in teachings a secret (confidentially))</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Himitsu-kyo (Its correct name is Himitsu Fujo-kyo and it is the teaching which Shaka preached in order to give indefinite benefits separately (individually) to people whose patience is different while keeping the difference in teachings a secret (confidentially))</e>
<cmt>前出用語の英訳補足のぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>不定教（ふじょう、正しくは顕露（けんろ）不定教といい、機根の違う衆生同士でも説法の違いを知り（顕露）ながらも、各々別々（各別）に応じた不定の得益がある法を説いた教え）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fujo-kyo (Its correct name is Kenro Fujo-kyo and it is the teachings which Shaka preached in order to give indefinite benefits separately (individually) to people whose patience are different while revealing the difference of teachings)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fujo-kyo (correct name is Kenro Fujo-kyo and it is the teachings which Shaka preached in order to give indefinite benefits separately (individually) to people whose patience is different while revealing the difference of the teachings)</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fujo-kyo (correct name is Kenro Fujo-kyo and it is the teachings which Shaka preached in order to give indefinite benefits separately (individually) to people whose patience is different while revealing the difference of the teachings)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="104">
<j>これを五時と配釈すると、頓教は華厳時、漸教は阿含・方等・般若の三時、秘密教と不定教は華厳の一部と阿含・方等・般若となり、非頓非漸・非秘密非不定が法華涅槃時とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These 4 correspond to Fivefold Periods as Ton-kyo to Kegon Period, Zen-kyo to 3 periods of Agan ・ Hodo ・ Hannya, Himitsu-kyo and Fujo-kyo to a part of Kegon and Agan ・ Hodo ・ Hannya and neither Ton-kyo, Zen-kyo, Himitsu-kyo nor Fujo-kyo correspond to Hoke-Nehan period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These 4 correspond to Fivefold Periods as Ton-kyo to the Kegon Period, Zen-kyo to 3 periods of Agan ・ Hodo ・ Hannya, Himitsu-kyo and Fujo-kyo to a part of Kegon and Agan ・ Hodo ・ Hannya and neither Ton-kyo, Zen-kyo, Himitsu-kyo nor Fujo-kyo correspond to the Hoke-Nehan period.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These four correspond to Fivefold Periods as Ton-kyo to the Period of Kegon-kyo, Zen-kyo to three periods of Agon-kyo, Hodo-kyo and Hannya-kyo, Himitsu-kyo and Fujo-kyo to a part of Kegon and Agon, Hodo and Hannya and neither Ton-kyo, Zen-kyo, Himitsu-kyo nor Fujo-kyo correspond to the Period of Hoke-Nehan-kyo.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="105">
<j>化法の四教</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keho-no-shikyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keho-no-shikyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keho-no-shikyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>化法の四教とは、教えそのもの(四諦など)を法と呼び、釈迦の教えを内容から分類したもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keho-no-shikyo is the categorization of Shaka&apos;s teachings based on their contents with calling such teachings (such as the Four Axioms etc) &quot;ho&quot; (teaching).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keho-no-shikyo is the categorization of Shaka&apos;s teachings based on their contents and the calling of such teachings (such as the Four Axioms etc) &quot;ho&quot; (teaching).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keho-no-shikyo is the categorization of Shaka&apos;s teachings based on their contents and such teachings (such as the Four Axioms, and so on) are called ho (teaching).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションをのぞき、表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="107">
<j>蔵教（ぞう、経・論・律の三蔵教（さんぞう）の略。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zo-kyo (the abbreviated name of Tripitaka Teaching that consists of kei ・ ron ・ ritsu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zo-kyo (the abbreviated name of Tripitaka Teaching that consists of kei ・ ron ・ ritsu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zo-kyo (the abbreviated name of Sanzo-kyo (Tripitaka Teaching) that consists of kei (Sutta-pitaka), ron (Abhidhamma-pitaka) and ritsu (Vinaya-pitaka)).</e>
<cmt>・をカンマに変え、用語、ピリオドを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>小乗教ともいい煩悩を断ずるために、空理を悟るべきことを説くが、すべての実体をただ空の一辺のみと見るので「但空（たんくう）の理」といい、また偏った真理なので「偏真の空理」ともいう）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Hinayana and it advocates the necessity of attaining Satori of Kuri in order to renounce worldly desires but as it regards every substance as a part of &quot;Ku&quot; (mind that is not bound by anything), it is called &quot;Tanku-no ri&quot; or &quot;Henshin no Kuri&quot; because it is a prejudiced truth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called Hinayana and it advocates the necessity of attaining Satori of Kuri in order to renounce worldly desires but as it regards every substance as a part of &quot;Ku&quot; (mind that is not bound by anything), it is called &quot;Tanku-no ri&quot; or &quot;Henshin no Kuri&quot; because it is a prejudiced truth.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called Hinayana and it advocates the necessity of attaining enlightenment of Kuri (abstract or impracticable theory) in order to renounce worldly desires but as it regards every substance as a part of Ku (mind that is not bound by anything), it is called &apos;Tanku-no ri&apos; (the theory of only Ku) or &apos;Henshin no Kuri&apos; (the abstract or impracticable theory of prejudicial truth) because it is a prejudiced truth.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="109">
<j>通教（つう、蔵教と別教に通じる教え。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsu-kyo (teachings that are similar to Zo-kyo and Betsu-kyo)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsu-kyo (teachings that are similar to Zo-kyo and Betsu-kyo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsu-kyo (teachings that are similar to Zo-kyo and Betsu-kyo.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足し、)をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>大乗の初門。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a primer of Mahayana</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a primer of Mahayana</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a primer of Mahayana</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>諸法の本体に即しそのまま空とする体空観（たいくうかん）を説くが、利根な菩薩は、ただ単なる空ではないという中道の妙理を含む「不但空の理」を悟るも、鈍根な菩薩や声聞・縁覚は蔵教と同じく「但空」を悟るに止まった）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It advocates &quot;Taikukan&quot; which regards the substances of various &quot;Ho&quot; as &quot;Ku&quot;, but while clever Bodhisattva attained &quot;Hutanku-no-ri&quot;which contains Chudo-no-myori that is not mere &quot;Ku&quot; from it, stupid Bodhisattva, Zraavaka and Pratyekabuddha attained only &quot;Tanku&quot; which could be attained from Zo-kyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It advocates &quot;Taikukan&quot; which regards the substances of various &quot;Ho&quot; as &quot;Ku&quot;, but while clever Bodhisattva attained &quot;Hutanku-no-ri&quot;which contains Chudo-no-myori that is not mere &quot;Ku&quot; from it, stupid Bodhisattva, Zraavaka and Pratyekabuddha attained only &quot;Tanku&quot; which could be attained from Zo-kyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It advocates Taikukan which regards the substances of various Ho as Ku, but while clever Bodhisattva attained &apos;Futanku-no-ri&apos; which contains Chudo-no-myori (profound reasons of moderation) that is not mere Ku from it, stupid Bodhisattva, shomon (Sharavakia) and Engaku (or paccekabuddha, who has come to Bodhi independent of any other person) attained only &apos;Tanku&apos; which could be attained from Zo-kyo).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを修正し、用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="112">
<j>別教（べつ、前の蔵・通二教や後の円教と違い、菩薩のみに別に説かれた教え。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Betsu-kyo (Unlike Zo-kyo and Tsu-kyo above or En-kyo below, it is the teachings which Shaka separately preached to Bodhisattva only)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Betsu-kyo (unlike Zo-kyo and Tsu-kyo above or En-kyo below, it is the teachings which Shaka separately preached to Bodhisattva only)</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Betsu-kyo (unlike Zo-kyo and Tsu-kyo above or En-kyo below, it is the teachings which Shaka separately preached to Bodhisattva only.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足し、)をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>前の二教が空理のみを説くのに対し、空・仮・中の三諦を説くが、三諦は互いに融合せず、各々が隔たるので「隔歴の三諦」といい、一切の事物について差別のみが説かれて、融和を説いていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the above 2 teachings advocate only Kuri, it advocates the three dogmas of Ku ・ Ka ・ Chu but as the three dogmas are not united and separated, it is called &quot;Kakureki- no- sandai&quot; (separate three dogmas) and it advocates only discrimination, rather than harmonization, concerning all things.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the above 2 teachings advocate only Kuri, it advocates the three dogmas of Ku ・ Ka ・ Chu but as the three dogmas are not united and separated, it is called &quot;Kakureki- no- sandai&quot; (three separate dogmas) and it advocates only discrimination, rather than harmonization, concerning all things.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the above two teachings advocate only Kuri, it advocates the three axioms of Ku, Ke (or difference, a though that things exits temporally) and Chu (or totality) but as the three axioms are not united and separated, it is called &apos;Kakureki-no-sandai&apos; (three separate axioms) and it advocates only discrimination, rather than harmonization, concerning all things.</e>
<cmt>用語を前出と合わせ、他補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>また中道諦も説くが、空・仮二諦を離れた単なる中道なので「但中の理」という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it also advocates &quot;Chuudo-dai&quot;, it is called &quot;Tanchu-no-ri&quot; because what it advocates is mere Chudo that is separated from Ku-dai and Kari-dai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it also advocates &quot;Chuudo-dai&quot;, it is called &quot;Tanchu-no-ri&quot; because what it advocates is mere Chudo that is separated from Ku-dai and Kari-dai.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it also advocates the axiom of Chudo (moderation), it is called &apos;Tanchu-no-ri&apos; (the theory of only Chudo) because what it advocates is mere Chudo that is separated from two axioms of Ku and Ke.</e>
<cmt>用語を前出と合わせ、他補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>また三惑（見思惑・塵沙惑・無明惑）を説き、これを断ずるために、菩薩の五十二位の修行の段階を説く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, it advocates the three delusions (illusions from imperfect perception ・ illusion and temptation through the immense variety of duties in saving men ・ illusions and temptations that arise from failure philosophically to understand things in their reality) as well as the 52 steps of unobstructed cultivation required for Bodhisattva to practice in order to renounce them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, it advocates the three delusions (illusions from imperfect perception ・ illusion and temptation through the immense variety of duties in saving men ・ illusions and temptations that arise from failure philosophically to understand things in their reality) as well as the 52 steps of unobstructed cultivation required for Bodhisattva to practice in order to renounce them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, it advocates the three delusions (illusions from imperfect perception, illusion and temptation through the immense variety of duties in saving men, illusions and temptations that arise from failure philosophically to understand things in their reality) and, to renounce them, it advocates the 52 steps of ascetic practices for Bodhisattva.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>さらに十界の因果を説くも、各々の境界を別個に説くだけである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It further advocates karma of Jikkai (the Ten Realms) but only advocates the border of each realm separately.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It further advocates karma of Jikkai (the Ten Realms) but only advocates the border of each realm separately.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It further advocates karma of Jikkai (the Ten Realms) but only advocates the border of each realm separately.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>したがって別教は三諦円融や十界互具（じゅっかいごぐ）の義もない不完全な教えとされる）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In view of the above, Betsu-kyo is deemed as imperfect teachings since it lacks Sandai Enyu (The Perfectly Integrated Three Truths) and Jikkaigogu (Mutual Containment of the Ten Realms).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In view of the above, Betsu-kyo is deemed an imperfect teaching since it lacks Sandai Enyu (The Perfectly Integrated Three Truths) and Jikkaigogu (Mutual Containment of the Ten Realms).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In view of the above, Betsu-kyo is deemed an imperfect teaching since it lacks Sandai Enyu (The Perfectly Integrated Three Truths) and Jikkaigogu (Mutual Containment of the Ten Realms)).</e>
<cmt>)を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="118">
<j>円教（えん、円満融和の教え。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">En-kyo (the teachings of peace and harmonization)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">En-kyo (the teachings of peace and harmonization)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">En-kyo (the teachings of peace and harmonization.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足し、)をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>空仮中の三諦の融和、十界互具を説く、最も優れた完全なる教え）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the supreme teschings that advocates the harmonization of Sandai (three dogmas), i.e. Ku, Kari and Chu as well as Jikkaigogu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the supreme teachings that advocate the harmonization of Sandai (three dogmas), i.e. Ku, Kari and Chu as well as Jikkaigogu.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the supreme teachings that advocate the harmonization of three axioms of Ku, Ke and Chu as well as Jikkaigogu).</e>
<cmt>axioms, Keとし、)を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="120">
<j>これを五時と配釈すると、蔵教は阿含・方等、通教は方等・般若、別教は華厳・方等・般若、円教は華厳・方等・般若・法華涅槃となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These 4 teachings correspond to Fivefold Periods as Zo-kyo to Agan ・ Hodo, Tsu-kyo to Hodo ・ Hannya, Betsu-kyo to Kegon ・ Hodo ・ Hannya and En-kyo to Kegon ・ Hodo ・ Hannya ・ Hoke-Nehan respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These 4 teachings correspond to Fivefold Periods as Zo-kyo to Agan ・ Hodo, Tsu-kyo to Hodo ・ Hannya, Betsu-kyo to Kegon ・ Hodo ・ Hannya and En-kyo to Kegon ・ Hodo ・ Hannya ・ Hoke-Nehan respectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These four teachings correspond to Fivefold Periods as Zo-kyo to Agon and Hodo, Tsu-kyo to Hodo and Hannya, Betsu-kyo to Kegon, Hodo and Hannya and En-kyo to Kegon, Hodo, Hannya and Hoke-Nehan respectively.</e>
<cmt>・をカンマなどに変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>しかし華厳・方等・般若と涅槃経は蔵・通・別の方便教が混じる雑円の教えであり、純粋な円教ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Kegon, Hodo, Hannya and Nehan-kyo are Zatsu-En (En-kyo that is mixed with other teachings) that is mixed with Hoben-kyo (tentative teachings that aim to induce people into real teachings) of Zo-kyo, Tsu-kyo and Betsu-kyo and therefore, they are not pure Enkyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Kegon, Hodo, Hannya and Nehan-kyo are Zatsu-En (En-kyo that is mixed with other teachings) that is mixed with Hoben-kyo (tentative teachings that aim to induce people into real teachings) of Zo-kyo, Tsu-kyo and Betsu-kyo and therefore, they are not pure Enkyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Kegon, Hodo, Hannya and Nehan-kyo are Zatsu-En (En-kyo that is mixed with other teachings) that is mixed with Hoben-kyo (tentative teachings that aim to induce people into real teachings) of Zo-kyo, Tsu-kyo and Betsu-kyo and therefore, they are not pure Enkyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>ただ法華経のみが独立して純粋な妙なる円教を説くとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only Hoke-kyo is deemed as the one that advocates excellent En-kyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only Hoke-kyo is deemed as the one that advocates excellent En-kyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only Hoke-kyo is deemed as the one that advocates purely excellent En-kyo independently.</e>
<cmt>純粋な、独立して、を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="32">
<sen id="123">
<j>したがって、法華は化儀と化法の八教を超越しているので「超八･醍醐」の教えという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Hoke-kyo is called the teachings of &quot;transcending eight / clarified butter&quot; because it transcends 8 teachings of Kagi-no shiho and Keho-no-shikyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Hoke-kyo is called the teachings of &quot;transcending eight-clarified butter&quot; because it transcends the 8 teachings of Kagi-no shiho and Keho-no-shikyo.</e>
<cmt>slight modification. Are the red words OK? They seem very strange, but I don’t know the expression.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Hoke-kyo is called the teachings of &apos;transcending eight - Daigo&apos; because it transcends the eight teachings of Kegi (Shakamuni&apos;s four modes of instruction) and Keho (Shakamuni&apos;s four kinds of teaching the content of the Truth, accommodated to the capacity of his disciples).</e>
<cmt>補足し、表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 78(id:10935), Vapour(id:36031), 名称未設定(id:19263), Tetralemma(id:11903), Boca samba(id:137526), Chi-Ham(id:143515), Dalaibaatur(id:16203), R28Bot(id:177951), 机龍之介(id:61257), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>