<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>顕本法華宗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenpon Hokke Sect</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenpon Hokke Sect</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenpon Hokke Sect</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>顕本法華宗（けんぽんほっけしゅう）は、日蓮を宗祖とし、日什を派祖とする、日蓮門下の一派である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenpon Hokke Sect, whose sect founder is Nichiren and school founder is Nichiju, is a school of Nichiren Sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenpon Hokke Sect, whose sect founder was Nichiren and school founder was Nichiju, is a school of the Nichiren Sect.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenpon Hokke Sect, whose sect founder was Nichiren and school founder was Nichiju, is a school of the Nichiren Sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>宗祖</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sect founder</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sect founder</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sect Founder</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>日蓮</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nichiren</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nichiren</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nichiren</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>派祖</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">School founder</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">School founder</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">School Founder</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>日什</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nichiju</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nichiju</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nichiju</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>総本山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main temple of the school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main temple of the school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Main Temple of the School</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>妙満寺（京都府京都市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myoman-ji Temple (Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myoman-ji Temple (Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myoman-ji Temple (Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>京都妙満寺を総本山とする日蓮系の宗派である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenpon Hokke Sect is a school of Nichiren Sect whose main temple is Myoman-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenpon Hokke Sect is a school of the Nichiren Sect whose main temple is Myoman-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenpon Hokke Sect is a school of the Nichiren Sect whose head temple is Myoman-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>古くは日蓮宗妙満寺派、日什門流とも称す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the past, it was also called Myoman-ji Temple school of Nichiren Sect or Nichijumon school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the past, it was also called the Myoman-ji Temple school of the Nichiren Sect or Nichijumon school.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the past, it was also called the Myoman-ji School of the Nichiren Sect or Nichijumon School.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="11">
<j>本多日生上人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honda Nissho Shonin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honda Nissho Shonin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honda Nissho Shonin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>慶応3年、姫路藩国友堅次郎の二男として生まれ、菩提寺の本多日鏡の嗣子となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in 1867 as a 2nd son of Kenjiro KUNITOMO of Himeji Domain and became the heir of Nikkyo HONDA, who was a monk of his family temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in 1867 as the 2nd son of Kenjiro KUNITOMO of Himeji Domain and became the heir of Nikkyo HONDA, who was a monk at his family temple.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in 1867 as the 2nd son of Kenjiro KUNITOMO of the Himeji clan and became the heir of Nikkyo HONDA, who was a priest at his family temple.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>哲学館（後の東洋大学）に学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He studied at Tetsugakukan (Toyo University).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He studied at Tetsugakukan (Toyo University).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He studied at Tetsugakukan (later Toyo University).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>宗門の積弊不振を概き、24歳教務部長となり教学布教に振るうも、宗門内の怨恨をかって、突如剥牒処分となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became the head of religious affairs division at the age of 24 and strived for the education and propagation since he was so disappointed with the shool&apos;s deep-rooted evil and slump, but his activities caused other monks&apos; resentment against him and he was suddenly divested of his priesthood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became the head of the religious affairs division at the age of 24 and strived for education and propagation since he was so disappointed with the shool&apos;s deep-rooted evil and slump, but his activities caused other monks&apos; resentment against him and he was suddenly divested of his priesthood.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He assumed the position of the head of the religious affairs division at the age of 24 and strived for education and propagation since he was so disappointed with the school&apos;s deep-rooted evil and slump, but his activities caused other priests&apos; resentment against him and he was suddenly divested of his priesthood.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>正義貫徹のため、顕本法華宗義布教所を各地に開設し東奔西走す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to realize justice, he established propagation facilities of Kenpon Hokke Sect at many places and was constantly on the move.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to realize justice, he established propagation facilities of the Kenpon Hokke Sect at many places and was constantly on the move.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to realize justice, he established propagation facilities of the Kenpon Hokke Sect at many places and was constantly on the move.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>各宗協会から師を宗門に復帰させよの声起こり、僧籍に復し妙満寺派綱要を編す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the back of many religious associations&apos; voice that requested his comeback to Buddhism society, he returned to the priesthood and compiled the elements of Myoman-ji Temple school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the back of many religious associations&apos; voice that requested his return to Buddhist society, he returned to the priesthood and compiled the elements of the Myoman-ji Temple school.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the back of many religious associations&apos; voice that requested his return to Buddhist society, he returned to the priesthood and compiled the elements of the Myoman-ji School.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>顕本法華宗と宗名を改す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He renamed the school Kenpon Hokke Sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He renamed the school Kenpon Hokke Sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He renamed the school Kenpon Hokke Sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>仏教界の退廃と日蓮門下の分裂を憂い、各教団有志を募って統一団を結成。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As he was worried about the decadence in Buddhism society as well as fragmented Nichiren Sect, he organized toitsudan (unification groups) in cooperation with interested people of other religious orders.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As he was worried about the decadence in Buddhist society, as well as the fragmented Nichiren Sect, he organized toitsudan (unification groups) in cooperation with interested people from other religious orders.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As he was worried about the decadence in Buddhist society, as well as the fragmented Nichiren Sect, he organized toitsudan (unification groups) in cooperation with interested people from other religious orders.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>後、各界の名士からなる天晴会、その他講妙会、婦人のための地明会、労務者のための自慶会等を創す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, he organized Tensei-kai, which consisted of prominent persons of various society, Komyo-kai, Chimei-kai, which was for female, and Jikei-kai, which was for laborers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, he organized Tensei-kai, which consisted of prominent persons from various societies such as Komyo-kai and Chimei-kai, which were for females, and Jikei-kai, which was for laborers.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, he organized Tensei-kai, which consisted of prominent persons from various societies, Komyo-kai, Chimei-kai, which were for females, and Jikei-kai, which was for laborers.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>日蓮聖人の唱える本仏・釈尊中心の仏教と、人生に勇気と慈悲を持って歩む信仰の感激を全国に展開し活躍す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was active throughout the nation in spreading Buddhism centered on Buddha・Shakyamuni, which was advocated by Nichiren Shonin, as well as the joy of belief that gives courage and mercy in life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was active throughout the nation, spreading Buddhism centered on Buddha・Shakyamuni, which was advocated by Nichiren Shonin, as well as the joy of belief that gives courage and mercy in life.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was active throughout the nation, spreading Buddhism centered on Buddha and Shakyamuni, which was advocated by Nichiren Shonin, as well as the joy of belief that gives courage and mercy in life.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>昭和6年、65歳寂。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died in 1931 at the age of 65.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died in 1931 at the age of 65.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died in 1931 at the age of 65.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="22">
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>1389年（嘉慶 (日本)3年）に日什は妙満寺（京都府）を建立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nichiju established Myoman-ji Temple (Kyoto Prefecture) in 1389.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nichiju established Myoman-ji Temple (Kyoto Prefecture) in 1389.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nichiju established Myoman-ji Temple (Kyoto Prefecture) in 1389.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="24">
<j>1608年（慶長13年）に徳川家康は妙満寺（京都府）日経と浄土宗の廓山を江戸城にて宗論（慶長宗論）させ、日経は耳と鼻を削がれ酷刑となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1608, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA ordered Nikkei of Myoman-ji Temple (Kyoto Prefecture) and Kakuzan of Jodo Sect to hold a doctrinal debate (Keicho shuron) at Edo-jo castle and Nikkei was punished with his ears and a nose being cut off.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1608, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA ordered Nikkei of Myoman-ji Temple (Kyoto Prefecture) and Kakuzan of Jodo Sect to hold a doctrinal debate (Keicho shuron) at Edo-jo castle and Nikkei was punished by having his ears and nose cut off.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1608, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA ordered Nikkei of Myoman-ji Temple (Kyoto Prefecture) and Kakuzan of Jodo Sect to hold a doctrinal debate (Keicho shuron) at Edo-jo Castle and Nikkei was punished by having his ears and nose cut off.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="25">
<j>1872年（明治5年）に一宗一管長制により、日什門流は日蓮門下の諸門流と連合する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1872, Nichijumon school became associated with other schools in Nichiren Sect according to the system of one superintendent priest for one sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1872, the Nichijumon school became associated with other schools in the Nichiren Sect according to the system of one superintendent priest for one sect.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1872, the Nichijumon School became associated with other schools in the Nichiren Sect according to the system of one superintendent priest for one sect.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="26">
<j>1874年（明治7年）に日什門流は日蓮宗勝劣派に属する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1874, Nichijumon school became affiliated with Shoretsu school of Nichiren Sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1874, the Nichijumon school became affiliated with the Shoretsu school of the Nichiren Sect.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1874, the Nichijumon School became affiliated with the Shoretsu School of the Nichiren Sect.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="27">
<j>1876年（明治9年）に管長設置により、日什門流は妙満寺派と公称し、日蓮宗勝劣派は解体する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1876, Nichijumon school officially named itself Myoman-ji Temple school with nominating its own superintendent priest and Shoretsu school of Nichiren Sect was dissolved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1876, Nichijumon school officially named itself Myoman-ji Temple school while nominating its own superintendent priest and the Shoretsu school of the Nichiren Sect was dissolved.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1876, Nichijumon School officially named itself Myoman-ji School while nominating its own superintendent priest and the Shoretsu School of the Nichiren Sect was dissolved.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="28">
<j>1898年（明治31年）に妙満寺派は顕本法華宗と公称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1898, Myoman-ji Temple school officially renamed itself Kenpon Hokke Sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1898, Myoman-ji Temple school officially renamed itself Kenpon Hokke Sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1898, Myoman-ji School officially renamed itself Kenpon Hokke Sect.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="29">
<j>1941年（昭和16年）に宗教団体法により、顕本法華宗と本門宗と日蓮宗が合同し、日蓮宗と公称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1941, Kenpon Hokke Sect, Honmon Sect and Nichiren Sect consolidated in accordance with the Religious Corporation Act and the new sect officially named itself Nichiren Sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1941, Kenpon Hokke Sect, Honmon Sect and Nichiren Sect consolidated in accordance with the Religious Corporation Act and the new sect officially named itself Nichiren Sect.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1941, Kenpon Hokke Sect, Honmon Sect and Nichiren Sect consolidated in accordance with the Religious Corporation Act and the new sect officially named itself Nichiren Sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="30">
<j>1947年（昭和22年)、日什門流の約380ヶ寺のうち、妙満寺（京都府）をはじめとする約200ヶ寺が日蓮宗から再独立、顕本法華宗と公称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1947, out of about 380 temples belonging to Nichijumon school, about 200 temples including Myoman-ji Temple (Kyoto Prefecture) became independent from Nichiren Sect again and officially named themselves Kenpon Hokke Sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1947, out of about 380 temples belonging to the Nichijumon school, about 200 temples including Myoman-ji Temple (Kyoto Prefecture) became independent from the Nichiren Sect again and officially named themselves Kenpon Hokke Sect.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1947, out of about 380 temples belonging to the Nichijumon School, about 200 temples including Myoman-ji Temple (Kyoto Prefecture) became independent from the Nichiren Sect again and officially named themselves Kenpon Hokke Sect.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>日什門流の180ヶ寺は日蓮宗に残留。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other 180 temples of Nichijumon school remained in Nichiren Sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another 180 temples of the Nichijumon school remained in the Nichiren Sect.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another 180 temples of the Nichijumon School remained in the Nichiren Sect.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="32">
<j>現在の本山、上総十ヶ寺（七里法華）の所属状況は以下の通り。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Head temples and Kazusa ten temples belong to each sect as shown below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Head temples and Kazusa ten temples belong to each sect as shown below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Head temples and Kazusa ten temples belong to each sect as shown below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="33">
<j>顕本法華宗：大本山妙満寺、本山会津妙法寺、本山品川天妙國寺、本山京都寂光寺、上総十ヶ寺＝土気善勝寺、土気本壽寺、本納蓮福寺、東金本漸寺、北之幸谷妙徳寺、松之郷本松寺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenpon Hokke Sect : The main temple of the sect Myoman-ji Temple, the head temple of the sect Aizu Myoho-ji Temple, the head temple of the sect Shinagawa Tenmyokoku-ji Temple, the head temple of the sect Kyoto Jakko-ji Temple, Kazusa ten temples=Toke Zensho-ji Temple, Toke Honju-ji Temple, Honno Renpuku-ji Temple, Togane Honzen-ji Temple, Kitanokoya Myotoku-ji Temple and Matsunogo Honsho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenpon Hokke Sect : The main temple of the sect Myoman-ji Temple, the head temple of the sect Aizu Myoho-ji Temple, the head temple of the sect Shinagawa Tenmyokoku-ji Temple, the head temple of the sect Kyoto Jakko-ji Temple, Kazusa ten temples=Toke Zensho-ji Temple, Toke Honju-ji Temple, Honno Renpuku-ji Temple, Togane Honzen-ji Temple, Kitanokoya Myotoku-ji Temple and Matsunogo Honsho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenpon Hokke Sect : The main temple Myoman-ji Temple, the head temple Aizu Myoho-ji Temple, the head temple Shinagawa Tenmyokoku-ji Temple, the head temple Kyoto Jakko-ji Temple, Kazusa ten temples including Toke Zensho-ji Temple, Toke Honju-ji Temple, Honno Renpuku-ji Temple, Togane Honzen-ji Temple, Kitanokoya Myotoku-ji Temple and Matsunogo Honsho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="34">
<j>日蓮宗：本山会津妙國寺、本山飯田本興寺、本山見附玄妙寺、本山吉美妙立寺、上総十ヶ寺＝大網蓮照寺、宮谷壇林本國寺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nichiren Sect : The main temple of the sect Aizu Tenmyokoku-ji Temple, the main temple of the sect Iida Honko-ji Temple, the main temple of the sect Mitsuke Genmyo-ji Temple, the main temple of the sect Yoshimi Myoritsu-ji Temple, Kazusa ten temples=Oami Rensho-ji Temple and Miyatanidanrin Honkoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nichiren Sect : The main temple of the sect Aizu Tenmyokoku-ji Temple, the main temple of the sect Iida Honko-ji Temple, the main temple of the sect Mitsuke Genmyo-ji Temple, the main temple of the sect Yoshimi Myoritsu-ji Temple, Kazusa ten temples=Oami Rensho-ji Temple and Miyatanidanrin Honkoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nichiren Sect : The main temple Aizu Tenmyokoku-ji Temple, the main temple Iida Honko-ji Temple, the main temple Mitsuke Genmyo-ji Temple, the main temple Yoshimi Myoritsu-ji Temple, Kazusa ten temples including Oami Rensho-ji Temple and Miyatanidanrin Honkoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="35">
<j>単立：本山品川本光寺、上総十ヶ寺＝東金最福寺、田中法光寺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Independent : The head temple of the sect Shinagawa Honko-ji Temple, Kazusa ten temples=Togane Saifuku-ji Temple and Tanaka Hoko-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Independent : The head temple of the sect Shinagawa Honko-ji Temple, Kazusa ten temples=Togane Saifuku-ji Temple and Tanaka Hoko-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Independent : The head temple Shinagawa Honko-ji Temple, Kazusa ten temples including Togane Saifuku-ji Temple and Tanaka Hoko-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="36">
<j>妙満寺貫首は305世中村日玄貫首。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Currently, Nichigen NAKAMURA is the three hundreds-fifth chief abbot of Myoman-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently, Nichigen NAKAMURA is the three hundred and fifth chief abbot of Myoman-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Currently, Nichigen NAKAMURA is the three hundred and fifth chief abbot of Myoman-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 長栄山出入職方(id:38334), 水野白楓(id:22811), ウィキ豊(id:82961), Ons(id:21830), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>