<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>満済</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mansai (Manzei)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mansai (Manzei)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mansai (Manzei)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>満済（まんさい・まんぜい、天授 (日本)4年 / 永和 (日本)4年（1378年） － 永享7年6月13日 (旧暦)（1435年7月8日））は、南北朝時代 (日本)から室町時代中期にかけての醍醐寺（真言宗）の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mansai (or Manzei) (1378 – July 8, 1435) was a Buddhist monk of a Daigo-ji Temple (Shingon Sect) who had lived from the (Japanese) Southern and Northern Dynasties period through the middle of the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mansai (or Manzei) (1378 – July 8, 1435) was a Buddhist monk of Daigo-ji Temple (Shingon Sect) who lived from the (Japanese) Southern and Northern Dynasties period through the middle of the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mansai (Also known as Manzei) (1378 – July 17, 1435) was a Buddhist monk of Daigo-ji Temple (Shingon Sect) from the period of the Northern and Southern Courts through the middle of the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変え、用語を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>法身院（ほっしんいん）准后とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mansai also went by the title of Hosshinin Jugo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mansai also went by the title of Hosshinin Jugo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mansai also went by the title of Hosshinin Jugo (honorary rank next to the three Empresses: Great Empress Dowager, Empress Dowager, and Empress).</e>
<cmt>用語を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>醍醐寺中興の祖として、桃山時代の義演准后と並ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a restorer of the Daigo-ji Temple, Mansai is compared with later Gien Jugo who had lived in the Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a restorer of Daigo-ji Temple, Mansai is compared with the later Gien Jugo who lived in the Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a restorer of Daigo-ji Temple, Mansai was compared with the later Gien Jugo in the Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>父は従一位大納言今小路師冬、母は聖護院房官法印源意の娘で室町幕府3代将軍足利義満の室日野業子に仕えた白川殿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mansai&apos;s father was Junior First Rank Dainagon (grand councillor) Morofuyu IMAKOJI, and Mansai&apos;s mother was Shirakawadono who was a daughter of Geni, Bokan Hoin of the Seigoin Temple, and served Nariko HINO, the legal wife of Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, the third Shogun of the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mansai&apos;s father was Junior First Rank Dainagon (grand councillor) Morofuyu IMAKOJI, and Mansai&apos;s mother was Shirakawadono who was a daughter of Geni, Bokan Hoin of the Seigoin Temple, and served Nariko HINO, the legal wife of Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, the third Shogun of the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mansai&apos;s father was Juichii (Junior First Rank) Dainagon (grand councilor) Morofuyu IMAKOJI, and Mansai&apos;s mother was Shirakawadono who was a daughter of Geni, Bokan (a priest who served for the families of Monzeki (temple formerly led by founder of sect, temple in which resided a member of nobility or imperial family)) Hoin (the highest rank among Buddhist priests) of the Seigoin Temple, and served Nariko HINO, the legal wife of Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, the third Shogun of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>生家の今小路家は関白二条兼基の子二条良冬を始祖とし、満済は兼基の四世孫にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The IMAKOJI family, the house where Mansai was born, descended from Yoshifuyu NIJO (a son of Kanpaku Kanemoto NIJO (chief advisor to the Emperor)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The IMAKOJI family, the house where Mansai was born, descended from Yoshifuyu NIJO (a son of Kanpaku Kanemoto NIJO (chief advisor to the Emperor)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imakoji family, the house where Mansai was born, descended from Yoshifuyu NIJO (a son of Kanpaku Kanemoto NIJO (chief advisor to the Emperor)) and Mansai was the 4th generation grandchild of Kanemoto.</e>
<cmt>満済は兼基の四世孫にあたる、を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>足利義満の猶子となり、三宝院賢俊に入室し、報恩院隆源の下で得度した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mansai was adopted to Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, and studied Buddhism under Sambo-in Kenshun to come to enter the Buddhist priesthood under Hoo&apos;in Ryugen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mansai was adopted by Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, and studied Buddhism under Sambo-in Kenshun to come to enter the Buddhist priesthood under Hoo&apos;in Ryugen.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mansai was adopted by Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, and studied Buddhism under Sanboin Kenshun to come to enter the Buddhist priesthood under Hooin Ryugen.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>三宝院25世門跡となり、応永2年（1395年）から永享6年（1434年）の間醍醐寺第74代座主を務め、以後、三宝院門跡が醍醐寺座主を兼ねる例となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mansai served as the twenty-fifth monzeki (head priest of temple formerly led by founder of sect) of the Sambo-in Temple, and also held the a post of the seventy-fourth zasu (temple&apos;s head priest) of the Daigo-ji Temple from 1395 to 1434, creating a precedent for the monzeki of the Sambo-in Temple concurrently holding the post of the zasu of the Daigo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mansai served as the twenty-fifth monzeki (head priest of the temple, formerly led by the sect founder) of the Sambo-in Temple, and also held the post of seventy-fourth zasu (temple head priest) of Daigo-ji Temple from 1395 to 1434, creating a precedent for the monzeki of Sambo-in Temple concurrently holding the post of zasu of Daigo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mansai served as the twenty-fifth monzeki (head priest of the temple, formerly led by the sect founder) of the Sanboin Temple, and also held the post of seventy-fourth zasu (temple head priest) of Daigo-ji Temple from 1395 to 1434, creating a precedent for the monzeki of Sanboin Temple concurrently holding the post of zasu of Daigo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その間東寺長者・四天王寺別当などをも兼任し、応永16年（1409年）大僧正の位に上る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While concurrently holding the two posts, Mansai also served as chosha (man of high position) in the To-ji Temple (Kyoogokoku-ji Temple) and the head priest of the Shitenno-ji Temple, and finally rose to Daisojo (the head priest of the Buddhist sect) in 1409.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While concurrently holding the two posts, Mansai also served as chosha (man of high position) in the To-ji Temple (Kyoogokoku-ji Temple) and head priest of Shitenno-ji Temple, and finally rose to Daisojo (head priest of the Buddhist sect) in 1409.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While concurrently holding the two posts, Mansai also served as To-ji choja (the chief abbot of To-ji Temple) and the head priest of Shitenno-ji Temple, and finally rose to Daisojo (head priest of the Buddhist sect) in 1409.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>正長元年（1428年）には三宝院門跡では初めて准三后（准三宮とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1428, Mansai was titled Jusango (or Jusangu) which was the first time the monzeki of the Sambo-in Temple got the title.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1428, Mansai was titled Jusango (or Jusangu) which was the first time the monzeki of Sambo-in Temple received the title.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1428, Mansai was titled Jusango (Also known as Jusangu) which was the first time the monzeki of Sanboin Temple received the title.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>太皇太后・皇太后・皇后に準じる位＝准后（じゅごう））の宣旨を蒙った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mansai was proclaimed Jugo, the title equivalent to the Grand Empress Dowager, the Empress Dowager, and the Empress.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mansai was proclaimed Jugo, the title equivalent to the Grand Empress Dowager, the Empress Dowager, and the Empress.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mansai was proclaimed Jugo, the title equivalent to the Grand Empress Dowager, the Empress Dowager, and the Empress.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>義満とその子である4代将軍足利義持・6代将軍足利義教の信任が厚く、内政･外交などの幕政に深く関与し、黒衣の宰相と称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having much confidence of Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA and his sons the fourth shogun Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA and the sixth shogun Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, Mansai deeply involved in internal politics and diplomacy of the shogunate government and nicknamed Government minister in black priestly vestments (Buddhist priest who is a government minister).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having the confidence of Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA and his sons, the fourth shogun Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA and the sixth shogun Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, Mansai was deeply involved in the internal politics and diplomacy of the shogunate government and was nicknamed Government minister in black priestly vestments (Buddhist priest who is a government minister).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having the confidence of Yoshimitsu and his sons, the fourth shogun Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA and the sixth shogun Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, Mansai was deeply involved in the internal politics and diplomacy of the shogunate government and was nicknamed Kokui no saisho (a priest who has influence in politics).</e>
<cmt>他の記事の表現をもとに表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>くじ引き将軍義教を登場させたのは満済の功によるところが大きく、恐怖政治を行った義教も、満済の建言には多く従ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mansai contributed so much to the appointment of Shogun Yoshinori by lot (creating Lottery Shogun) that even Shogun Yoshinori who was a tyrant did as Mansai suggested on most occasions, feeling his obligation to Mansai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mansai contributed so much to the appointment of Shogun Yoshinori by lot (creating Lottery Shogun) that even Shogun Yoshinori, who was a tyrant, did as Mansai suggested on most occasions, feeling his obligation to Mansai.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mansai contributed so much to the appointment of Shogun Yoshinori by lot (creating Lottery Shogun) that even Shogun Yoshinori, who was a tyrant, did as Mansai suggested on most occasions, feeling his obligation to Mansai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>幕政の中枢にありながら情勢を冷静に判断し、人情に厚い満済の態度は、同時代人から「天下の義者」（伏見宮貞成親王『看聞日記』）と賞賛された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Got involved in corridors of power in the shogunate government, Mansai was cool in assessing the situation and warm in getting on with people, which was appreciated by his contemporaries as &quot;a loyal retainer of the whole country&quot; (&quot;Kanmon Nikki&quot; by Imperial Prince Fishimi no miya Sadafusa).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Getting involved in the corridors of power in the shogunate government, Mansai was cool in assessing the situation and warm in getting on with people, which was appreciated by his contemporaries as &quot;a loyal retainer of the whole country&quot; (&quot;Kanmon Nikki&quot; by Imperial Prince Fishimi no miya Sadafusa).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Getting involved in the corridors of power in the shogunate government, Mansai was cool in assessing the situation and warm in getting on with people, which was appreciated by his contemporaries as &apos;a loyal retainer of the whole country&apos; (&quot;Kanmon Nikki&quot; (Diary of Imperial Prince Fushiminomiya Sadafusa) by Imperial Prince Fushiminomiya Sadafusa).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変え、表記を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>満済が具注暦の裏にその日の出来事を記録しておいたものが『満済准后日記』（『法身院准后記』）と呼ばれ、応永18年（1411年）から死去の年までの記事があり、自筆本も伝存する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Extant Mansai&apos;s diary is called &quot;Mansai Jugo Nikki&quot; (&quot;Hosshinin Jugo-ki&quot;) which was recorded on the back of the guchureki (Japanese Lunisolar calendar) from 1411 through the year Mansai died, with some copies written by Mansai himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Extant Mansai&apos;s diary is called &quot;Mansai Jugo Nikki&quot; (&quot;Hosshinin Jugo-ki&quot;) which was recorded on the back of the guchureki (Japanese Lunisolar calendar) from 1411 through the year Mansai died, with some copies written by Mansai himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Extant Mansai&apos;s diary is called &quot;Mansai Jugo Nikki&quot; (Also known as &quot;Hosshinin Jugo-ki,&quot; Diary of Mansai) which was recorded on the back of the guchureki (Japanese Lunisolar calendar) from 1411 through the year Mansai died, and the copies written by Mansai are existent.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>室町殿護持僧として祈祷だけでなく、当時の政治情勢が克明に記録してあり、室町中期の極めて重要な史料となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The diary is now considered as quite important historical sources on the middle of the Muromachi period because Mansai recorded there not only prayers as a gojiso of the Muromachi-dono (a priest who protects the public residence of the Shogun) but also the contemporary political circumstances in detail.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The diary is now considered as a quite important historical source on the middle of the Muromachi period because Mansai recorded not only prayers as a gojiso of the Muromachi-dono (a priest who protects the public residence of the Shogun) but also the contemporary political circumstances in detail.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The diary is now considered as a quite important historical source on the middle of the Muromachi period because Mansai recorded not only prayers as a gojiso of the Muromachi-dono (a priest who protects the public residence of the Shogun) but also the contemporary political circumstances in detail.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Novo(id:87875), 玄史生(id:43670), Kstigarbha(id:13376), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), Yume149(id:17504), トホホ川(id:50502), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>