<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>宝塔</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoto (a treasure tower)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoto (a treasure tower)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoto (a treasure tower)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>宝塔（ほうとう）は、円筒や八角などの塔身に方形などの屋根を被せ、さらに相輪を載せた仏塔。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hoto&quot; is a Buddhist pagoda composed of a cylindrical or octagonal toshin (a body of pagoda,) with a square-shaped roof on it, and sorin (a metal pinnacle placed on the top of pagoda.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hoto&quot; is a Buddhist pagoda composed of a cylindrical or octagonal toshin (the body of a pagoda,) with a square-shaped roof on it, and sorin (a metal pinnacle placed on the top of a pagoda.)</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Hoto&quot; is a Buddhist pagoda composed of a cylindrical or octagonal toshin (the body of a pagoda,) with a square-shaped roof on it, and sorin (a metal pinnacle placed on the top of a pagoda).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドをかっこの外に移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>法華宗では、「妙法蓮華経」見宝塔品第十一に基づき釈迦如来・多宝如来を脇士として本尊とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Hokke-shu (Hokke school of Buddhism,) Shaka Nyorai (Buddha Shakamuni) and Taho Nyorai (Buddha of Many Treasures) are worshipped as the principal images who are flanking each other, in accordance with the story of Ken Hotohon Dai-juichi of &quot;Myo Horengekyo&quot; (the &quot;Lotus Sutra&quot; Chapter Eleven: the Emergence of the Treasure Tower.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Hokke-shu (the Hokke school of Buddhism), Shaka Nyorai (Buddha Shakamuni) and Taho Nyorai (Buddha of Many Treasures) are worshipped as the principal images who flank each other, in accordance with the story of Ken Hotohon Dai-juichi of &quot;Myo Horengekyo&quot; (the &quot;Lotus Sutra&quot; Chapter Eleven: the Emergence of the Treasure Tower).</e>
<cmt>articles, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Hokke-shu (the Hokke school of Buddhism), Shaka Nyorai (Buddha Shakamuni) and Taho Nyorai (Buddha of Many Treasures) are worshipped as the principal images who flank each other, in accordance with the story of Ken Hotohon Dai-juichi of &quot;Myo Horengekyo&quot; (the &apos;Lotus Sutra&apos; Chapter Eleven: the Emergence of the Treasure Tower).</e>
<cmt>&quot;を &apos; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>その他の用法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other meanings:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other meanings:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other meanings:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>多宝塔などの仏塔を美称して用いられることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;Hoto&quot; is also used as an eulogistic name for other Buddhist pagodas including Tahoto pagoda (a multi-treasure pagoda.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;Hoto&quot; is also used as an eulogistic name for other Buddhist pagodas, including Tahoto pagoda (a multi-treasure pagoda.)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;Hoto&quot; is also used as an eulogistic name for other Buddhist pagodas, including Tahoto pagoda (a multi-treasure pagoda).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドをかっこの外に移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>金銀玉などで飾り立てた装飾仏塔のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tahoto pagoda is a decorative Buddhist pagoda adorned with gold, silver, jewels and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tahoto pagoda is a decorative Buddhist pagoda adorned with gold, silver, jewels, and so on.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tahoto pagoda is a decorative Buddhist pagoda adorned with gold, silver, jewels, and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>各地の宝塔</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Local Hoto pagodas:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Local Hoto pagodas:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Local Hoto pagodas:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 浩(id:70121), 新茶(id:157775), ウィキ豊(id:82961), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>