<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>安国寺恵瓊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ekei in Ankoku-ji Temple (&quot;Temple for National Pacification“) (安国寺)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ekei in Ankoku-ji Temple (&quot;Temple for National Pacification&quot;) (安国寺)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ekei in Ankoku-ji Temple (&quot;Temple for National Pacification&quot;) (安国寺)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>安国寺 恵瓊（あんこくじ えけい）は、戦国時代 (日本)から安土桃山時代にかけての禅僧・大名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ekei in Ankoku-ji Temple was a Zen priest and a Japanese feudal lord from the age of civil war (Japan) to Azuchi Momoyama Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ekei, of Ankoku-ji Temple, was a Zen priest and a Japanese feudal lord from the Age of Civil War (Japan) to the Azuchi Momoyama Period.</e>
<cmt>I&apos;ve often seen it as the Warring States period.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ekei, of Ankoku-ji Temple, was a Zen priest and a Japanese feudal lord from the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) (Japan) to the Azuchi Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>戦国時代→Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) (Japan)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「安国寺」は住持した寺（安芸国安国寺利生塔（不動院））の名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ankoku-ji&apos; is the name of temple (Aki Province Ankoku-ji Temple Rishoto (Fudo-in)) of which he was the chief priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ankoku-ji&apos; is the name of the temple (Aki Province Ankoku-ji Temple Rishoto (Fudo-in)) of which he was the chief priest.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ankoku-ji&apos; is the name of the temple (Aki Province Ankoku-ji Temple Rishoto (Fudo-in)) of which he was the chief priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>毛利氏の外交僧（武家の対外交渉の任を務めた禅僧）から、最終的には僧侶の身分のまま大名となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a diplomat priest of Mori clan (a Zen priest who was in charge of negotiation for warrior cast) and finally became a Japanese feudal lord, staying at priest&apos;s status.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a diplomat priest of the Mori clan (a Zen priest who was in charge of negotiations for the warrior caste) and finally became a Japanese feudal lord while retaining his status as a priest.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a diplomat priest of the Mori clan (a Zen priest who was in charge of negotiations for the warrior caste) and finally became a Japanese feudal lord while retaining his status as a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>Life→Biographyに変更</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>生年には諸説があり、天文8年（1539年）とも天文6年（1537年）ともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are various views on the year of his birth, such as in 1539 and in 1537.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various views on the year of his birth, so that some believe it was 1539 and others believe it was 1537.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various views on the year of his birth, so that some believe it was 1539 and others believe it was 1537.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>父親に関しても安芸武田氏の一族である武田信重の子とも、同じく安芸武田氏である武田元繁の娘婿・伴繁清の息子とも伝わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are also various views on his father, such as Nobushige TAKEDA of Aki Takeda clan and Shigekiyo BAN, husband of Motoshige TAKEDA&apos;s daughter of the same clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are also various views on his father, such as Nobushige TAKEDA of the Aki Takeda clan and Shigekiyo BAN, the husband of Motoshige TAKEDA&apos;s daughter of the same clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are also various views on his father, such as Nobushige TAKEDA of the Aki Takeda clan and Shigekiyo BAN, the husband of Motoshige TAKEDA&apos;s daughter of the same clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>天文10年（1541年）、毛利元就の攻撃で安芸武田氏が滅亡すると、家臣に連れられて脱出し、安芸の安国寺（不動院）に入って出家した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1541 when Aki Takeda clan was subverted by the attack of Motonari MORI, he got out led by his followers and became a priest at the Ankoku-ji Temple (Fudo-in) in Aki Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1541, when the Aki Takeda clan was subverted by the attack of Motonari MORI, he was led to safety by his followers and became a priest at the Ankoku-ji Temple (Fudo-in) in Aki Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1541, when the Aki Takeda clan was subverted by the attack of Motonari MORI, he was led to safety by his followers and became a priest at the Ankoku-ji Temple (Fudo-in) in Aki Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その後、京都の東福寺に入り、竺雲恵心の弟子となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he entered in Tofuku-ji Temple in Kyoto and became a disciple of Jikuun Eshin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, he entered Tofuku-ji Temple in Kyoto and became a disciple of Jikuun Eshin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, he entered Tofuku-ji Temple in Kyoto and became a disciple of Jikuun Eshin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>僧侶としては天正2年（1574年）に安芸安国寺の住持となり、後に東福寺、南禅寺の住持にもなり、中央禅林最高の位にもついた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a priest, he became the chief priest of Ankoku-ji Temple in Aki Province in 1574, and also became the chief priests of Tofuku-ji Temple and Nanzen-ji Zen Temple, and assumed the highest status among the central Zen temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a priest he became the chief priest of Ankoku-ji Temple in Aki Province in 1574, and he also became the chief priest of Tofuku-ji Temple and Nanzen-ji Zen Temple, assuming the highest status among the central Zen temples.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a priest he became the chief priest of Ankoku-ji Temple in Aki Province in 1574, and he also became the chief priest of Tofuku-ji Temple and Nanzen-ji Zen Temple, assuming the highest status among the central Zen temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>慶長4年(1599年）には建仁寺の再興にも尽力している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1599 he made exertions to rebuild Kennin-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1599 he made efforts to rebuild Kennin-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1599 he made efforts to rebuild Kennin-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>一方、毛利氏が恵心に帰依していた関係から、早くに毛利家に仕える外交僧となり、元亀元年（1570年）には豊後国の大友氏との和睦を取りまとめることに成功する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, he became a diplomat priest of Mori clan in his early life because Mori clan embraced Eshin, and succeeded to make a peace with Otomo clan in Bungo Province in 1570.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, he became a diplomat priest of the Mori clan relatively early in life because the Mori clan had embraced Eshin, and succeeded in making peace with the Otomo clan in Bungo Province in 1570.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, he became a diplomat priest of the Mori clan relatively early in life because the Mori clan had embraced Eshin, and succeeded in making peace with the Otomo clan in Bungo Province in 1570.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>天正10年（1582年）、毛利氏が羽柴秀吉（豊臣秀吉）と高松城 (備中国)で対陣していた（備中高松城の戦い）最中に本能寺の変が起き、織田信長が本能寺にて横死した（本能寺の変）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1582, while Mori clan was encamped facing each other with Hideyoshi HASHIBA (Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) at Takamatsu-jo Castle in Bichu Province (the Battle of Bichu Takamatsu-jo Castle), Honno-ji Incident occurred and Nobunaga ODA was killed at Honno-ji Temple (Honno-ji Incident).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1582, while the Mori clan was encamped opposite Hideyoshi HASHIBA (Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) at Takamatsu-jo Castle in Bichu Province (the Battle of Bichu Takamatsu-jo Castle), the Honno-ji Incident occurred and Nobunaga ODA was killed at Honno-ji Temple (the Honno-ji Incident).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1582, while the Mori clan was encamped opposite Hideyoshi HASHIBA (Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) at Takamatsu-jo Castle in Bichu Province (the Battle of Bichu Takamatsu-jo Castle), the Honno-ji Incident occurred and Nobunaga ODA was killed at Honno-ji Temple (the Honno-ji Incident).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>このとき羽柴秀吉はその事実を隠して毛利氏に和睦案を提示し、外交僧である恵瓊はその和睦を取りまとめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, Hideyoshi HASHIBA brought up the peace plan against Mori clan, hiding that fact, and Ekei, a diplomat priest made up that peace plan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, Hideyoshi HASHIBA brought up the peace plan with respect to the Mori clan, but hid the fact, and Ekei, a diplomat priest, made up the peace plan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, Hideyoshi HASHIBA brought up the peace plan with respect to the Mori clan, but hid the fact, and Ekei, a diplomat priest, made up the peace plan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>彼は秀吉がこれから躍進することを予測して進んで和睦を取りまとめたとされ、秀吉の信任を得る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was regarded to forecast Hideyoshi&apos;s future success and make up the peace plan willingly, so that he gained the confidence of Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was regarded as having forecast Hideyoshi&apos;s future success and having willingly devised the peace plan, so that he gained the confidence of Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was regarded as having forecast Hideyoshi&apos;s future success and having willingly devised the peace plan, so that he gained the confidence of Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>天正13年（1585年）1月、毛利氏が秀吉に正式に臣従する際の交渉を務めて、秀吉から賞賛された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was praised by Hideyoshi because he was in charge of negotiation when Mori clan became to serve as a vassal of Hideyoshi formally in January, 1585.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was praised by Hideyoshi because he was in charge of negotiations when the Mori clan formally entered service as a vassal of the Hideyoshi in January 1585.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was praised by Hideyoshi because he was in charge of negotiations when the Mori clan formally entered service as a vassal of the Hideyoshi in January 1585.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>そのため、四国征伐後は伊予に2万3000石を与えられ、天正14年（1586年）の秀吉の九州征伐後は伊予国6万石に加増され、僧侶でありながら豊臣大名という異例の位置付けの大名となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, he was given a land of 23,000 goku in Iyo Province after the conquest of Shikoku, and was given a land of 60,000 goku in Iyo Province after the conquest of Kyushu in 1586, so that he became an unusual Japanese feudal lord of Toyotomi clan, staying at priest&apos;s status.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason he was given land of 23,000 goku in Iyo Province after the conquest of Shikoku, and was given land of 60,000 goku in Iyo Province after the conquest of Kyushu in 1586, so that he became an unusual Japanese feudal lord of the Toyotomi clan, retaining his status as a priest.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason he was given land of 23,000 goku in Iyo Province after the conquest of Shikoku, and was given land of 60,000 goku in Iyo Province after the conquest of Kyushu in 1586, so that he became an unusual Japanese feudal lord of the Toyotomi clan, retaining his status as a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また同時に秀吉の側近も兼ねることとなり、秀吉の命令で行なわれた検地などの奉行を務めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, he served Hideyoshi as aide at the same time so that he was in charge of Bugyo, administrator, of land survey which was implemented by Hideyoshi&apos;s order and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, he served Hideyoshi as an aide at the same time so that he was in charge as the bugyo (administrator) of land surveys, as implemented at the order of Hideyoshi, etc.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, he served Hideyoshi as an aide at the same time so that he was in charge as the bugyo (administrator) of land surveys and so on, as implemented at the order of Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>and so onをland surveysの後に移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>文禄・慶長の役においても検使として渡海した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time of the Bunroku-Keicho War, he crossed the sea as Kenshi, inspector.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time of the Bunroku-Keicho War, he crossed the sea as a kenshi (inspector).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time of the Bunroku-Keicho War, he crossed the sea as a kenshi (inspector).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>恵瓊は毛利一族の中では親秀吉派の中心であった小早川隆景に近かったが、隆景が死去すると小早川氏と並ぶ毛利氏の支柱であった吉川広家と対立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among Mori clan, Ekei was familiar to Takakage KOBAYAKAWA, who was the key figure of pro-Hideyoshi group, but he was opposed to Hiroie KIKKAWA, a central figure in Mori clan as well as Kobayakawa clan, after Takakage&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the Mori clan, Ekei was familiar to Takakage KOBAYAKAWA, who was the key figure in the pro-Hideyoshi group, but he was opposed to Hiroie KIKKAWA, a central figure in the Mori clan as well as the Kobayakawa clan, after Takakage&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the Mori clan, Ekei was familiar to Takakage KOBAYAKAWA, who was the key figure in the pro-Hideyoshi group; however, after Takakage&apos;s death he was opposed to Hiroie KIKKAWA, a central figure in the Mori clan, just as the Kobayakawa clan was.</e>
<cmt>「吉川広家が、小早川氏と並ぶ毛利氏の支柱であった」という意味合いが出るように訳出し直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>慶長5年（1600年）の関ケ原の戦いでは懇意であった石田三成と通じて西軍に与し、毛利一族の当主・毛利輝元を西軍の総大将として担ぎ出すことに成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, he took sides with West squad through Mitsunari ISHIDA, who was familiar to him, and succeeded to make Terumoto MORI the commander in chief of West squad.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, he sided with the Western army through Mitsunari ISHIDA, who was familiar to him, and succeeded in making Terumoto MORI the commander in chief of the Western army.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, he sided with the Western army through Mitsunari ISHIDA, who was familiar to him, and succeeded in making Terumoto MORI the commander in chief of the Western army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="20">
<j>9月15日 (旧暦)の関ヶ原における合戦では、毛利秀元・吉川広家とともに徳川家康軍の後方に陣取ったが、前に布陣する広家が家康にひそかに通じて毛利軍の参戦を阻んだため、戦闘に参加することなく終わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the Battle of Sekigahara on September 15 (old lunar calendar), he took up line on the back of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA&apos;s force with Hidemoto MORI and Hiroie KIKKAWA, but he could not join the fight because Hiroie in the front line communicated with Ieyasu secretly and prevented Mori force&apos;s participation in war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the Battle of Sekigahara on September 15 (old lunar calendar), he took up a line at the rear of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA&apos;s force with Hidemoto MORI and Hiroie KIKKAWA, but he could not join the fight because Hiroie at the front line communicated with Ieyasu secretly and prevented Mori force&apos;s from participating in the battle.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the Battle of Sekigahara on September 15 (old lunar calendar), he took up a line at the rear of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA&apos;s force with Hidemoto MORI and Hiroie KIKKAWA, but he could not join the fight because Hiroie at the front line communicated with Ieyasu secretly and prevented Mori force&apos;s from participating in the battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="21">
<j>西軍の敗北後、恵瓊は逃亡したが京都で奥平信昌隊に捕縛され、西軍首脳の1人として、六条河原にて斬首された（彼が処刑されたのは、もともと反徳川の旗幟を鮮明にしていなかった毛利氏を西軍に引き込んだことが原因と推測する見解もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the defeat of West squad, Ekei escaped but was captured by Nobumasa OKUDAIRA&apos;s military unit in Kyoto, and went to the guillotine as one of the leaders of West squad at Rokujokawara (There is a view that the reason for his execution was that he brought Mori clan into West squad, though Mori clan did not make its position of anti-Tokugawa clearly at first).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the defeat of the Western army, Ekei escaped but was captured by Nobumasa OKUDAIRA&apos;s military unit in Kyoto, and went to the guillotine as one of the leaders of the Western army at Rokujokawara (there is a view that the reason for his execution was that he brought the Mori clan into the Western army, though the Mori clan had not initially made clear its position as anti-Tokugawa).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the defeat of the Western army, Ekei escaped but was captured by Nobumasa OKUDAIRA&apos;s military unit in Kyoto, and went to the guillotine as one of the leaders of the Western army at Rokujokawara (there is a view that the reason for his execution was that he brought the Mori clan into the Western army, though the Mori clan had not initially made clear its position as anti-Tokugawa).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>享年62。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of 62.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 62.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 62.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>または享年64。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Or at the age of 64.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He might also have been 64.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He might also have been 64.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="24">
<j>墓所は建仁寺本坊内の庭に首塚があり、広島の不動院にも墓がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Kubizuka, a grave of his head, (首塚) lies in the garden of Kennin-ji Temple and his grave also lies at Fudo-in in Hiroshima.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His kubizuka (a grave of his head) (首塚) lies in the garden of Kennin-ji Temple, and there is also a grave at Fudo-in, in Hiroshima.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His kubizuka (a grave of his head) (首塚) lies in the garden of Kennin-ji Temple, and there is also a grave at Fudo-in Temple, in Hiroshima.</e>
<cmt>Fudo-in Temple　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Character</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Character</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>Character→Personal Profileに変更</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>天正元年（1573年）12月12日付山県越前守・井上春忠宛書状で、｢信長之代、五年、三年は持たるべく候。明年辺は公家などに成さるべく候かと見及び申候。左候て後、高ころびに、あおのけに転ばれ候ずると見え申候。藤吉郎さりとてはの者にて候｣と書いてある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the letter to Yamagata Echizen-no-kami Harutada INOUE as of December 12, 1573, he wrote that &apos;Nobunaga&apos;s government will not continue for five or three years. He seems to become a court noble around next year. I think he will be subverted after that. Tokichiro is really something.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the letter to Yamagata Echizen-no-kami Harutada INOUE as of December 12, 1573, he wrote that &apos;Nobunaga&apos;s government will not continue for five or three years. He seems to become a court noble around next year. I think he will be subverted after that. Tokichiro is really something.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the letter to Yamagata Echizen-no-kami (Lord of Echizen province) Harutada INOUE as of December 12, 1573, he wrote that &apos;Nobunaga&apos;s government will not continue for five or three years. He seems to become a court noble around next year. I think he will be subverted after that. Tokichiro (Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) is really something.&apos;</e>
<cmt>越前守の説明としてLord of Echizen province　と追加しました。藤吉郎が誰を指すのか分かるように、Tokichiro (Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI)と補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>織田信長の転落と、その家臣の豊臣秀吉の躍進を予想し、結果的にそれが的中したことで恵瓊の慧眼を示す逸話としてよく引き合いに出される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This letter has been often quoted as an anecdote to show Ekei&apos;s insight because he forecasted the downfall of Nobunaga ODA and the strong showing of his follower, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and his expectations proved right as a result.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This letter has often been quoted as an anecdote to show Ekei&apos;s insight because he forecasted the downfall of Nobunaga ODA and the strong showing of his follower, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and as a result his expectations were proved to be correct.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This letter has often been quoted as an anecdote to show Ekei&apos;s insight because he forecasted the downfall of Nobunaga ODA and the strong showing of his follower, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and as a result his expectations were proved to be correct.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kdo84221(id:6188), JAnDbot(id:66507), Straysheep(id:42448), ドルチェット(id:46458), Nnh(id:474), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Cprobot(id:97843), Kamakura(id:472), ベルゼブブ(id:184141), 厭離穢土欣求浄土(id:175954), Mekadebiru(id:137893), Kamitani(id:30757), ＋－(id:17104), Cross-j(id:44270), Boca samba(id:137526), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 代言人(id:33675), R28Bot(id:177951), Frei(id:12101), 663highland(id:18755), こぶまき(id:38278), Yas(id:739), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), けんち(id:5147), NDR(id:5500), Kuma83(id:31177), Safkan(id:423), 青心(id:173433), KASAGI(id:24405), Jmho(id:10472), 立志堂(id:132177), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>