<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>智光曼荼羅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chiko Mandala</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chiko Mandala</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chiko Mandala</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>智光曼荼羅（ちこうまんだら）とは、奈良市の元興寺に伝わる智光が感得したという曼荼羅の図像に基づいて作られた浄土曼荼羅の総称である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Chiko mandala is a collective name for the Jodo (Pure Land) mandalas, based on the pictures and figures of mandala which is said to have been envisioned by Chiko that has been preserved at Gango-ji Temple in Nara City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chiko Mandala is the generic name for Jodo Mandalas made after the style of the Mandala which is said to have been envisioned by Chiko and has been preserved in Gango-ji Temple of Nara City</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chiko Mandala is the generic name for Jodo Mandalas made after the style of the Mandala which is said to have been envisioned by Chiko and has been preserved in Gango-ji Temple of Nara City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>浄土三曼荼羅の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of the Three Jodo Mandalas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is one of the Three Jodo Mandalas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is one of the Three Jodo Mandalas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>当麻曼荼羅が、観無量寿経に基づいて画面を４分割する複雑な画面構成をとるのに対して、智光曼荼羅は極めてシンプルな浄土図のみの図様をとっているのが特徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the Taima mandara has the complex composition, divided into four sections based on the Kanmuryojukyo (one of the scriptures of Mahayana Buddhism), Chiko mandala has the extremly simple design representing only Pure Land.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the Taima Mandara has the complex composition formed of four sections based on Kanmuryoju-kyo (one of the scriptures of Mahayana Buddhism), Chiko Mandala has the extremly simple design representing only Jodo (Pure Land).</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the Taima Mandara has the complex composition formed of four sections based on Kanmuryoju-kyo (one of the scriptures of Mahayana Buddhism), Chiko Mandala has the extremly simple design representing only Jodo (Pure Land).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また、図の下方に智光と頼光の二僧が描かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also includes two priests, Chiko and Raiko at the bottom of the mandala.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also includes two priests, Chiko and Raiko at the bottom of the mandala.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also includes two priests, Chiko and Raiko at the bottom of the mandala.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>また、智光が自らの僧房に、画工に描かせた浄土変相図（浄土曼荼羅）を掛けて極楽往生を念じた縁由により、元興寺 という呼称が用いられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, Chiko&apos;s own sobo (the priests&apos; living quarters in a Buddhist temple) was called Gango-ji Temple, because he prayed for rebirth in the Buddha Amida&apos;s Pure Land in his sobo, hanging the jodo henso-zu (Jodo mandala) which he had painters paint.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, Chiko&apos;s own sobo (the priests&apos; living quarters in a Buddhist temple) was called Gango-ji Temple, because he had hung Jodo Henso-zu (Jodo Mandala) which he had painters paint and prayed for the rebirth in Gokuraku-Jodo.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, Chiko&apos;s own sobo (the priests&apos; living quarters in a Buddhist temple) was called Gango-ji Temple, because he had hung Jodo Henso-zu (Jodo Mandala) which he had painters paint and prayed for the rebirth in Gokuraku-Jodo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また、長方形の僧房は、智光曼荼羅を安置する極楽堂と道場としての禅室とに二分されて今日に至っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His rectangular sobo divided between two has existed up until today; one for Gokuraku-do Hall where the Chiko mandala was enshrined and the other for Zenshitsu (Zen room) used as dojo (place of Buddhist practice or Zen sitting meditation).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His rectangular sobo was divided in two &apos;Gokuraku-do&apos; where Chiko Mandala was enshrined and &apos;zenshitsu&apos; (Zen room) for dojo (place of Buddhist practice or Zen sitting meditation), and has been preserved until today.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His rectangular sobo was divided in two &apos;Gokuraku-do&apos; where Chiko Mandala was enshrined and &apos;zenshitsu&apos; (Zen room) for dojo (place of Buddhist practice or Zen sitting meditation), and has been preserved until today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Wei Yuan(id:13342), Point136(id:211299), Izayohi(id:13095), 無空(id:17049), Mooko(id:36162), Reggaeman(id:6214), にゃ(id:89329), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>