<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>阿修羅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ashura</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ashura</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ashura</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>阿修羅（あしゅら、あすら、サンスクリット語：asuraの音写、意訳：非天）は八部衆に属する仏教の守護神。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ashura (the transcription of asura in Sanskrit with the meaning of non-heaven) is a guardian god of Hachi Bushu (or Eight Legions, Protectors of Buddhist Teachings) in Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ashura (the transcription of asura in Sanskrit with the meaning of non-heaven) is a guardian god of Hachi Bushu (or Eight Legions, Protectors of Buddhist Teachings) in Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ashura (the transcription of asura in Sanskrit with the meaning of non-heaven) is a guardian god of Hachi Bushu (or Eight Legions, Protectors of Buddhist Teachings) in Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>修羅（しゅら）とも言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Shura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called Shura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called Shura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>大乗仏教時代に、その闘争的な性格から五趣の人と畜生の間に追加され、六道の一つである阿修羅道（修羅道）の主となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the combative character, it was added between human and chikusho (Buddhist realm of beasts) of Goshu in the Mahayana Buddhism period and became the master of Ashura-do, Asura realm (path of bellicose demons) which was one of Rokudo (six posthumous worlds).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With a combative character, it was added between human and chikusho (Buddhist realm of beasts) of Goshu in the Mahayana Buddhism period and became the master of Ashura-do, Asura realm (path of bellicose demons) which was one of Rokudo (six posthumous worlds).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With a combative character, it was added between human and chikusho (Buddhist realm of beasts) of Goshu in the Mahayana Buddhism period and became the master of Ashura-do, Asura realm (path of bellicose demons) which was one of Rokudo (six posthumous worlds).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>古代ペルシャの聖典『アヴェスター』に出る最高神アフラ・マズダーに対応するといわれる（以下、歴史的背景の項を参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ashura is said to correspond to Ahura Mazda which is the highest-ranking deity appeared in the ancient Persian scripture &quot;Avesta&quot; (see the article of historical background).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ashura is said to correspond to Ahura Mazda, which is the highest-ranking deity appearing in the ancient Persian scripture &quot;Avesta&quot; (see the article of historical background).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ashura is said to correspond to Ahura Mazda, which is the highest-ranking deity appearing in the ancient Persian scripture &quot;Avesta&quot; (see the article of historical background).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>それが古代インドの魔神アスラとなり、のちに仏教に取り入れられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It became the demon of ancient India, Asura and was taken into Buddhism later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It became the demon Asura of ancient India, and was taken into Buddhism later.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It became the demon Asura of ancient India, and was taken into Buddhism later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>古くインドでは生命生気の善神であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the good deity for spark of life in ancient India.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the good deity for spark of life in ancient India.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was the good deity for spark of life in ancient India.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>天の隣国だが天ではなく、男の顔立ちは端正ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is located next to heaven, but it is not heaven and the man is not handsome.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is located next to heaven, but it is not heaven and the man is not handsome.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is located next to heaven, but it is not heaven and the man is not handsome.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>醸酒にも失敗し、果報が尽きて忉利天にも住めないといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After failure in brewing alcohol, it run out of lucks and is said that it can not live even in the Touriten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After failure in brewing alcohol, it ran out of luck and is said that it could not live even in the Touriten.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After failure in brewing alcohol, it ran out of luck and is said that it could not live even in the Toriten (Trayastrimsa Heaven).</e>
<cmt>Touriten→Toriten (Trayastrimsa Heaven)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>本来サンスクリットで「asu」が「命」、「ra」が「与える」という意味で善神だったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ashura was said to be a good deity because originally &apos;asu&apos; meant &apos;life&apos; and &apos;ra&apos; meant &apos;give&apos; in Sanskrit.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ashura was said to be a good deity, because originally &apos;asu&apos; meant &apos;life&apos; and &apos;ra&apos; meant &apos;give&apos; in Sanskrit.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ashura was said to be a good deity, because originally &apos;asu&apos; meant &apos;life&apos; and &apos;ra&apos; meant &apos;give&apos; in Sanskrit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし、「a」が否定の接頭語となり、「sura」が「天」を意味することから、非天、非類などと訳された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the negative prefix &apos;a&apos; and &apos;sura&apos; meaning &apos;heaven&apos;, however, Ashura was translated to non-heaven, non-human and others.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the negative prefix &apos;a&apos; and &apos;sura&apos; meaning &apos;heaven&apos;, however, Ashura was translated to non-heaven, non-human, and others.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the negative prefix &apos;a&apos; and &apos;sura&apos; meaning &apos;heaven,&apos; however, Ashura was translated to non-heaven, non-human, and others.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>そのため、帝釈天の台頭に伴いヒンドゥー教で悪者としてのイメージが定着し、地位を格下げされたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it was thought to be demoted due to the fixed image as a villain in Hindooism with the rise of Taishakuten.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it was thought to be demoted due to the fixed image as a villain in Hinduism with the rise of Taishakuten.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it was thought to be demoted due to the fixed image as a villain in Hinduism with the rise of Taishakuten (Sakra devanam Indra).</e>
<cmt>Taishakuten (Sakra devanam Indra)としました。(参照: http://tangorin.com/words/taishakuten)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>帝釈天とよく戦闘した神である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ashura often battled with Taishakuten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ashura often battled with Taishakuten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ashura often battled with Taishakuten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>リグ・ヴェーダでは最勝なる性愛の義に使用されたが、中古以来、恐るべき鬼神として認められるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though Ashura was used for the strongest sexual justice in The Rig-Veda, it has been recognized as an awful Kijin (fierce god) since the Middle Ages (the times around the Heian period).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though Ashura was used for the strongest sexual justice in The Rig-Veda, it has been recognized as an awful Kijin (fierce god) since the Middle Ages (the times around the Heian period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though Ashura was used for the strongest sexual justice in The Rig-Veda, it has been recognized as an awful Kijin (fierce god) since the Middle Ages (the times around the Heian period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>仏教に取り込まれた際には仏法の守護者として八部衆に入れられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taken in Buddhism, Ashura was added in Hachi Bushu as a Buddhist guardian.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taken into Buddhism, Ashura was added in Hachi Bushu as a Buddhist guardian.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taken into Buddhism, Ashura was added in Hachi Bushu as a Buddhist guardian.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>なお五趣説では認めないが、六道説では、常に闘う心を持ち、その精神的な境涯・状態の者が住む世界、あるいはその精神境涯とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though it is not recognized in the theory of Goshu (Five Realms), it refers to the world in which people with fighting spirit at any time live in such mental condition or refers to such mental condition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though it is not recognized in the theory of Goshu (Five Realms), it refers to the world in which people with fighting spirit at any time live in such mental condition, or refers to such a mental condition.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though it is not recognized in the theory of Goshu (Five Realms), in the theory of Rokudo it refers to the world in which people with fighting spirit at any time live in such mental condition, or refers to such a mental condition.</e>
<cmt>「六道説では」→訳漏れのため訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>興福寺宝物殿の解説では、「阿修羅」はインドヒンドゥーの『太陽神』もしくは『火の神』と表記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The interpretation of a treasure hall of Kofuku-ji Temple describes &apos;Ashura&apos; as &quot;Taiyoshin&quot; (the sun god) or &quot;Hinokami&quot; (the god of fire) in Indian Hindooism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The interpretation of a treasure hall of Kofuku-ji Temple describes &apos;Ashura&apos; as &quot;Taiyoshin&quot; (the sun god) or &quot;Hinokami&quot; (the god of fire) in Indian Hinduism.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The interpretation of a treasure hall of Kofuku-ji Temple describes &apos;Ashura&apos; as &quot;Taiyoshin&quot; (the sun god) or &quot;Hinokami&quot; (the god of fire) in Indian Hinduism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>帝釈天と戦争をするが、常に負ける存在。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ashura always loses in the battle with Taishakuten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ashura always loses in the battle with Taishakuten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ashura always loses in the battle with Taishakuten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>この戦いの場を修羅場（しゅらば）と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The situation of this battle is called Shuraba (dreadful scene).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The situation of this battle is called Shuraba (dreadful scene).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The situation of this battle is called Shuraba (dreadful scene).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>姿は、三面六臂（三つの顔に六つの腕）で描かれることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The figure of Ashura is often represented in Buddhist statue with three faces and six arms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The figure of Ashura is often represented in Buddhist statuary with three faces and six arms.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The figure of Ashura is often represented in Buddhist statuary with three faces and six arms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="20">
<j>奈良県・興福寺の八部衆像・阿修羅像（国宝）や、京都府・三十三間堂の二十八部衆像・阿修羅像（国宝）が有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The famous statues include standing statues of eight legions and the statue of Asura (fighting demon) (National Treasure) of Kofuku-ji Temple in Nara Prefecture as well as standing statues of twenty-eight legions and the statue of Asura (fighting demon) (National Treasure) of Sanjusangendo Temple in Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Famous statues include standing statues of eight legions and the statue of Asura (fighting demon) (National Treasure) of Kofuku-ji Temple in Nara Prefecture as well as standing statues of twenty-eight legions and the statue of Asura (fighting demon) (National Treasure) of Sanjusangendo Temple in Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Famous statues include the statues of eight legions and the statue of Asura (fighting demon) (National Treasure) of Kofuku-ji Temple in Nara Prefecture as well as the statues of twenty-eight legions and the statue of Asura (fighting demon) (National Treasure) of Sanjusangendo Temple in Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>standing statues of eight legions→the statues of eight legions、standing statues of twenty-eight legions→the statues of twenty-eight legionsとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="21">
<j>日本語では、争いの耐えない状況を修羅道に例えて修羅場（しゅらば）と呼ぶ場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japanese, the situation with constant conflicts is sometimes called shuraba, using an analogy from Ashura precept (pandemonium).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japanese, the situation with constant conflicts is sometimes called shuraba, using an analogy from Ashura precept (pandemonium).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japanese, the situation with constant conflicts is sometimes called shuraba, using an analogy from Ashura precept (pandemonium).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>激しい闘争の行われている場所、あるいはそのような場所を連想させる状況を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It refers to the place where fierce fight is going or the situation associating such place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It refers to the place where fierce fighting is going on or the situation associated with such a place.</e>
<cmt>rwording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It refers to the place where fierce fighting is going on or the situation associated with such a place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>歴史的背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Historical background</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historical background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historical background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>一般的には、サンスクリットのアスラ(asura)は歴史言語学的に正確にアヴェスター語のアフラ(ahura)に対応し、おそらくインド-イラン時代にまでさかのぼる古い神格であると考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally, asura in Sanskrit exactly corresponds to ahura in Avesta in historical linguistics and is considered to be old divinity that probably goes back to India-Iran period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, asura in Sanskrit exactly corresponds to ahura in Avesta in historical linguistics and is considered to be old divinity that probably goes back to the India-Iran period.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, asura in Sanskrit exactly corresponds to ahura in Avesta in historical linguistics and is considered to be old divinity that probably goes back to the India-Iran period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>宗教学的にも、ヴェーダ文献においてアスラの長であるとされたヴァルナ (神)とミトラは諸側面においてゾロアスター教のアフラ・マズダーとミスラに対応し、インド・ヨーロッパ比較神話学的な観点では第一機能（司法的・宗教的主権）に対応すると考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In view of religious studies, Varuna (deity) which was considered to be the master of Asura in Veda materials and Mithra correspond to Ahura Mazda and Mithra of Zoroastrianism in various aspects and are considered to correspond to the principal function (judicial and religious sovereignty) in Indian and European comparative mythological view.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In view of religious studies, Varuna (deity), which was considered to be the master of Asura in Veda materials, and Mithra correspond to Ahura Mazda and Mithra of Zoroastrianism in various aspects and are considered to correspond to the principal function (judicial and religious sovereignty) in Indian and European comparative mythological views.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In view of religious studies, Varuna (deity), which was considered to be the master of Asura in Veda materials, and Mithra correspond to Ahura Mazda and Mithra of Zoroastrianism in various aspects and are considered to correspond to the principal function (judicial and religious sovereignty) in Indian and European comparative mythological views.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>アスラは今でこそ悪魔や魔神であるという位置づけだが、より古いヴェーダ時代においては、インドラらと対立する悪魔であるとされるよりは最高神的な位置づけであることのほうが多かったことに注意する必要がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though Asura is currently positioned as evil or demon, it should be noted that it was often positioned as the highest-ranking deity rather than the evil conflicting with Indra and others in older Veda period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though Asura is currently positioned as evil or a demon, it should be noted that it was often positioned as the highest-ranking deity rather than the evil conflicting with Indra and others in the older Veda period.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though Asura is currently positioned as evil or a demon, it should be noted that it was often positioned as the highest-ranking deity rather than the evil conflicting with Indra and others in the older Veda period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="26">
<j>ただし、阿修羅の起源は古代メソポタミア文明のシュメール、アッシリア、ペルシア文明とする説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, one of theories shows that the origin of Ashura is Sumerian, Assyrian and Persian civilizations of the ancient Mesopotamia civilization.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, one theory shows that the origin of Ashura is Sumerian, Assyrian, and Persian civilizations of the ancient Mesopotamia civilization.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, one theory shows that the origin of Ashura is Sumerian, Assyrian, and Persian civilizations of the ancient Mesopotamia civilization.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="27">
<j>シュメールやアッカドのパンテオンに祀られていた神アンシャル。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The deity Anshar enshrined in pantheons in Sumer and Akkad.</e>
<cmt>文の形にはなっていませんが、ウィキペディアのサイト内原文ではこの通り。（句点）で終わっていましたので、その通りにしております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The deity Anshar enshrined in pantheons in Sumer and Akkad.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The deity Anshar enshrined in pantheons in Sumer and Akkad.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>アッシリアの最高神アッシュル。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The highest-ranking deity of Assyria, Ashur.</e>
<cmt>文の形にはなっていませんが、ウィキペディアのサイト内原文ではこの通り。（句点）で終わっていましたので、その通りにしております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The highest-ranking deity of Assyria, Ashur.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The highest-ranking deity of Assyria, Ashur.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>ペルシアのゾロアスター教の最高神アフラ・マズダー。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The highest-ranking deity of Zoroastrianism in Persia, Ahura Mazda.</e>
<cmt>文の形にはなっていませんが、ウィキペディアのサイト内原文ではこの通り。（句点）で終わっていましたので、その通りにしております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The highest-ranking deity of Zoroastrianism in Persia, Ahura Mazda.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The highest-ranking deity of Zoroastrianism in Persia, Ahura Mazda.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>それらの神がインドに伝来してアスラとなり、中国で阿修羅の音訳を当てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These deities were introduced into India and became Asura, which was transliterated into 阿修羅 in China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These deities were introduced into India and became Asura, which was transliterated into 阿修羅 in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These deities were introduced into India and became Asura, which was transliterated into 阿修羅 in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>阿素羅、阿蘇羅、阿須羅、阿素洛、阿須倫、阿須輪などとも音写する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also transliterated into 阿素羅, 阿蘇羅, 阿須羅, 阿素洛, 阿須倫, 阿須輪 and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also transliterated into 阿素羅, 阿蘇羅, 阿須羅, 阿素洛, 阿須倫, 阿須輪 and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also transliterated into 阿素羅, 阿蘇羅, 阿須羅, 阿素洛, 阿須倫, 阿須輪 and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="32">
<j>シュメール、アッシリアの古代史と仏教の阿修羅にまつわる伝承との類似性も高く、信憑性のある事実として指摘される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The transmissions about Ashura of Buddhism have great similarities to the ancient histories of Sumer and Assyria and are noted as credible facts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The transmissions about Ashura of Buddhism have great similarities to the ancient histories of Sumer and Assyria and are noted as credible facts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The transmissions about Ashura of Buddhism have great similarities to the ancient histories of Sumer and Assyria and are noted as credible facts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="33">
<j>仏教伝承では、阿修羅は須弥山の北に住み、帝釈天と戦い続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the transmissions of Buddhism, Ashura lived in the north of Mt. Sumeru (in Buddhism - said to be the highest mountain rising in the center of the world) and continued to fight with Taishakuten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the transmissions of Buddhism, Ashura lived in the north of Mt. Sumeru (in Buddhism - said to be the highest mountain rising in the center of the world) and continued to fight with Taishakuten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the transmissions of Buddhism, Ashura lived in the north of Mt. Sumeru (in Buddhism - said to be the highest mountain rising in the center of the world) and continued to fight with Taishakuten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>阿修羅は帝釈天に斃されて滅ぶが、何度でも蘇り永遠に帝釈天と戦い続ける、との記述がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is the description that Ashura came to life many times after being killed and destroyed by Taishakuten and then continued to fight with it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a description that Ashura came to life many times after being killed and destroyed by Taishakuten and then continued to fight with it.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a description that Ashura came to life many times after being killed and destroyed by Taishakuten and then continued to fight with it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>これらの伝承を古代史になぞらえると、以下のようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The followings are the events likened these transmissions to the ancient history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following are the events that likened these transmissions to ancient history.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following are the events that likened these transmissions to ancient history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="36">
<j>アッシュルを最高神と崇めたアッシリア帝国は、シュメール（現在のイラク周辺）の北部に一大帝国を築き、シュメール・アッカドの後に勃興したバビロニアに侵略戦争を繰り返した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Assyrian Empire revering Ashur as the highest-ranking deity built a huge empire in the northern part of Sumer (currently, around Iraq) and continued wars of invasions into Babylonia which emerged after Sumer and Akkad.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Assyrian Empire, revering Ashur as the highest-ranking deity, built a huge empire in the northern part of Sumer (currently, around Iraq) and continued wars of invasions into Babylonia, which had emerged after Sumer and Akkad.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Assyrian Empire, revering Ashur as the highest-ranking deity, built a huge empire in the northern part of Sumer (currently, around Iraq) and continued wars of invasions into Babylonia, which had emerged after Sumer and Akkad.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="37">
<j>バビロニア人はメディア人と手を結びアッシリアを滅ぼしたが、国を再興したアッシリア人達にバビロニアは滅ぼされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though Babylonian destroyed Assyria in alignment with Median, Babylonia was destroyed by Assyrian who rebuilt their country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though Babylonian destroyed Assyria in alignment with Median, Babylonia was destroyed by Assyrians, who rebuilt their country.</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though Babylonian destroyed Assyria in alignment with Median, Babylonia was destroyed by Assyrians, who rebuilt their country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>後にてバビロニアの地にカルデアが勃興して、再びアッシリアを滅ぼした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Chaldea was built on the site of Babylonia and destroyed Assyria again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Chaldea was built on the site of Babylonia and destroyed Assyria again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Chaldea was built on the site of Babylonia and destroyed Assyria again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>その後、アフラ・マズダーを崇めるペルシアが勃興して、カルデアを占領下におさめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Persia revering Ahura Mazda was built and occupied Chaldea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Persia, revering Ahura Mazda, was built and occupied Chaldea.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Persia, revering Ahura Mazda, was built and occupied Chaldea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>その後、古代マケドニアがペルシアを滅ぼした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later again, the ancient Makedonia destroyed Persia.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later again, ancient Makedonia destroyed Persia.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later again, ancient Makedonia destroyed Persia.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="41">
<j>また、シュメールと須弥山（サンスクリットでは「スメール」と発音する）の類似性。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, there is the similarity between Sumer and Mt. Sumeru (pronounciated &apos;Sumer&apos; in Sanskrit.)</e>
<cmt>文の形にはなっていませんが、ウィキペディアのサイト内原文ではこの通り。（句点）で終わっていましたので、その通りにしております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, there is similarity between Sumer and Mt. Sumeru (pronounciated &apos;Sumer&apos; in Sanskrit.)</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, there is similarity between Sumer and Mt. Sumeru (pronounciated &apos;Sumer&apos; in Sanskrit).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>シュメールの最高神マルドゥークと帝釈天インドラの類似性を指摘する説もあり、阿修羅と帝釈天の構図はアッシュルとマルドゥークの構図と全く同じである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One theory points out the similarity between the highest-ranking deity of Sumer, Marduk and Taishakuten Indra, and the pattern of Ashura and Taishakuten is exactly the same as the one of Ashur and Marduk.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One theory points out the similarity between the highest-ranking deity of Sumer, Marduk, and Taishakuten Indra, and the pattern of Ashura and Taishakuten is exactly the same as the one of Ashur and Marduk.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One theory points out the similarity between the highest-ranking deity of Sumer, Marduk, and Taishakuten Indra, and the pattern of Ashura and Taishakuten is exactly the same as the one of Ashur and Marduk.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>これらの古代史を仏教の伝承として取り込んだ可能性が高いと主張する神学者もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some divines argue that these ancient histories were probably introduced for the transmission of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some divines argue that these ancient histories were probably introduced for the transmission of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some divines argue that these ancient histories were probably introduced for the transmission of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>戦闘神になった背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Background of becoming the fighting deity</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background of becoming the fighting deity</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background of becoming the fighting deity</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="44">
<j>阿修羅は帝釈天に歯向かった悪鬼神と一般的に認識されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ashura is generally recognized as a devil deity who kicked against Taishakuten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ashura is generally recognized as a devil deity who kicked against Taishakuten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ashura is generally recognized as a devil deity who kicked against Taishakuten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>しかし事実は少し違うといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eventually, however, the fact is said to be a little different.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eventually, however, the facts are said to be a little different.</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eventually, however, the facts are said to be a little different.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>阿修羅はもともと天部の神であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ashura was originally Tembu-shin (deity who resides in a heavenly realm, one of six realms in which the souls of living beings transmigrate from one to another).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ashura was originally Tembu-shin (deity who resides in a heavenly realm, one of six realms in which the souls of living beings transmigrate from one to another).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ashura was originally Tenbu-shin (deity who resides in a heavenly realm, one of six realms in which the souls of living beings transmigrate from one to another).</e>
<cmt>Tembu-shin→Tenbu-shinに修正しんました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>阿修羅が天部から追われて修羅界を形成したのには次のような逸話がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is the following story about the reason because Ashura was exiled from Tenbu and formed the world of Ashura (fighting demon).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is the following story about the reason why Ashura was exiled from Tenbu and formed the world of Ashura (fighting demon).</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is the following story about the reason why Ashura was exiled from Tenbu and formed the world of Ashura (fighting demon).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="48">
<j>阿修羅は正義を司る神といわれ、帝釈天は力を司る神といわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ashura is said to be the deity controlling the justice while Taishakuten is said to be the deity controlling the power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ashura is said to be the deity controlling justice, while Taishakuten is said to be the deity controlling power.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ashura is said to be the deity controlling justice, while Taishakuten is said to be the deity controlling power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="49">
<j>阿修羅の一族は、帝釈天が主である忉利天（とうりてん、三十三天ともいう）に住んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family of Ashura lived in Touriten (called Sanjusanten as well) with Taishakuten as its master.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family of Ashura lived in Touriten (called Sanjusanten as well) with Taishakuten as its master.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family of Ashura lived in the Toriten (called Sanjusanten [Heaven of the Thirty-three Gods] as well) with Taishakuten as its master.</e>
<cmt>in Touriten→in the Toritenとし、Sanjusantenの補足追加 (参照: http://www.aisf.or.jp/~jaanus/deta/s/sanjuusanten.htm)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>また阿修羅にはシャチーという娘がおり、いずれ帝釈天に嫁がせたいと思っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, Ashura had the daughter named Sachi and wanted her off to marry Taishakuten some day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Ashura had a daughter named Sachi and wanted her to marry Taishakuten some day.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Ashura had a daughter named Sachi and wanted her to marry Taishakuten some day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>しかし、その帝釈天は舎脂を力ずくで奪った（誘拐して凌辱したともいわれる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Taishakuten deprived of Sachi by force (he is also said to abduct her and did indecent conduct).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Taishakuten took Sachi by force (he is also said to have abducted her and committed indecent conduct).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Taishakuten took Sachi by force (he is also said to have abducted her and committed indecent conduct).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>それを怒った阿修羅が帝釈天に戦いを挑むことになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ashura got angry with it and challenged the fight against Taishakuten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ashura got angry with it and challenged Taishakuten to a fight.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ashura got angry with it and challenged Taishakuten to a fight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>帝釈天は配下の四天王などや三十三天の軍勢も遣わせて応戦した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taishakuten fought back sending Shitenno (four guardian kings) and others under his command and the army of Sanjusanten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taishakuten fought back, sending Shitenno (four guardian kings) and others under his command and the army of Sanjusanten.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taishakuten fought back, sending Shitenno (four guardian kings) and others under his command and the army of Sanjusanten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>戦いは常に帝釈天側が優勢であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taishakuten had prevailed in the battle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taishakuten had prevailed in the battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taishakuten had prevailed in the battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>しかし、ある時、阿修羅の軍が優勢となり、帝釈天が後退していたところへ蟻の行列にさしかかり、蟻を踏み殺してしまわないようにという帝釈天の慈悲心から軍を止めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, they came across the row of ants and Taishakuten with mercy stopped his army not to stump them to death when the army of Ashura changed to prevail once and Taishakuten backed off.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, they came across a row of ants and Taishakuten mercifully stopped his army from stomping them to death when the army of Ashura changed to prevail once and Taishakuten backed off.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, they came across a row of ants and Taishakuten mercifully stopped his army from stomping them to death when the army of Ashura changed to prevail once and Taishakuten backed off.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>それを見た阿修羅は驚いて、帝釈天の計略があるかもしれないという疑念を抱き、撤退したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ashura was surprised to see Taishakuten&apos;s behavior and drew off doubting if he had some plots.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ashura was surprised to see Taishakuten&apos;s behavior and drew off doubting if he had some plots.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ashura was surprised to see Taishakuten&apos;s behavior and drew off doubting if he had some plots.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="57">
<j>一説では、この話が天部で広まって阿修羅が追われることになったといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One theory shows that Ashura was exiled because this story spreaded in Tenbu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One theory shows that Ashura was exiled because this story spreaded in Tenbu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One theory shows that Ashura was exiled because this story spreaded in Tenbu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>また一説では、阿修羅は正義ではあるが、舎脂が帝釈天の正式な夫人となっていたのに、戦いを挑むうちに赦す心を失ってしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another theory shows that Ashura&apos;s challenges to fight lost the mind to permit Taishakuten in spite of justice though Sashi had already became the lawful wife of Taishakuten</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another theory shows that Ashura&apos;s challenges to fight deprived him of the mind to permit Taishakuten in spite of justice though Sashi had already became the lawful wife of Taishakuten</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another theory shows that Ashura&apos;s challenges to fight deprived him of the mind to permit Taishakuten in spite of justice though Sashi had already became the lawful wife of Taishakuten.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>つまり、たとえ正義であっても、それに固執し続けると善心を見失い妄執の悪となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, sticking around even a justice too much loses the right mind and brings evil caused by obsession.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, sticking around even justice too much deprives one of the right mind and brings evil caused by obsession.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, sticking around even justice too much deprives one of the right mind and brings evil caused by obsession.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>このことから仏教では天界を追われ人間界と餓鬼界の間に修羅界が加えられたともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on this, it is said that Ashura was exiled from Tenkai in Buddhism and the world of Asura (fighting demon) was added between Ningenkai (Human world) and the world of hungry spirits.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on this, it is said that Ashura was exiled from Tenkai in Buddhism and the world of Asura (fighting demon) was added between Ningenkai (Human world) and the world of hungry spirits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on this, it is said that Ashura was exiled from Tenkai in Buddhism and the world of Asura (fighting demon) was added between Ningenkai (Human world) and the world of hungry spirits.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="61">
<j>阿修羅を意訳すると「非天」というが、これは阿修羅の果報が優れて天部の神にも似ているが天には非ざるという意義から名づけられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The free translation of Ashura is &apos;non-heaven&apos;, which was named in the meaning that Ashura is not heaven though the luck of Ashura is remarkable and is similar to Tembu-shin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The free translation of Ashura is &apos;non-heaven&apos;, which was named in the meaning that Ashura is not heaven though the luck of Ashura is remarkable and is similar to Tembu-shin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The free translation of Ashura is &apos;non-heaven,&apos; which was named in the meaning that Ashura is not heaven though the luck of Ashura is remarkable and is similar to Tenbu-shin.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を移動、Tembu-shin→Tenbu-shinに修正しんました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>阿修羅王と住処</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ashura-o (Ashura King) and his home</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ashura-o (Ashura King) and his home</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ashura-o (Ashura King) and his home</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="62">
<j>阿修羅王の名前や住処、業因などは経論によって差異がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are differences depending on Buddhist theories in the name, home, behaviors and others of Ashura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are differences depending on Buddhist theories in the name, home, behaviors and other aspects of Ashura.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;aspects&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are differences depending on Buddhist theories in the name, home, behaviors and other aspects of Ashura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>パーリ語（Pl)では、阿修羅王にRāhu、Vepacitti、Sambara、Pahārāda、Verocana、Baliの5つの名が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Pali, Ashura-o has 5 names, Rāhu, Vepacitti, Sambara, Pahārāda, Verocana, Bali.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Pali, Ashura-o has 5 names, Rāhu, Vepacitti, Sambara, Pahārāda, Verocana, Bali.</e>
<cmt>6 names are given, although the sentence states that there are 5.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Pali, Ashura-o has five names, Rāhu, Vepacitti, Sambara, Pahārāda, Verocana, Bali.</e>
<cmt>5をスペルアウト* NCコメントの通り、5つではなく実際には6つの名が記載されておりますが、仕様書に基づきあえてそのままの訳「5つ」にしております。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>ただし大乗仏典では、一般的に阿修羅王は4人の王とされることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Ashura-o is generally considered to be the four kings in Mahayana Buddhist scriptures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Ashura-o is generally considered to be the four kings in Mahayana Buddhist scriptures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Ashura-o is generally considered to be the four kings in Mahayana Buddhist scriptures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="65">
<j>『法華経』序品には、4人の王の名を挙げ、各百千の眷属を有しているとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Johon of &quot;Hokke-kyo Sutra&quot; (the Lotus Sutra) lists the names of four kings and shows that each of them have a thousand of kenzoku (disciples or followers of Buddha).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Johon of &quot;Hokke-kyo Sutra&quot; (the Lotus Sutra) lists the names of four kings and shows that each of them have a thousand of kenzoku (disciples or followers of Buddha).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Johon (Introduction) of &quot;Hokke-kyo Sutra&quot; (the Lotus Sutra) lists the names of four kings and shows that each of them have a thousand of kenzoku (disciples or followers of Buddha).</e>
<cmt>The Johonとし、補足追加しました。 (参照: http://artsci.wustl.edu/~robertmo/pdf/hokke6.pdf)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>また『十地経』や『正法念処経』巻18～21には、これら4人の住処・業因・寿命などを説明しており、其の住処は妙高山（須弥山）の北側の海底地下8万4千由旬の間に4層地に分けて住していると説く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, &quot;Jyuji-kyo Sutra&quot; and the volume eighteenth to twenty-first of &quot;Shobonenjo-kyo Sutra&quot; (Meditation on the Correct Teaching Sutra) explains the homes, behaviors and life durations of these four kings and suggests that their homes are located separately in the four-layered grounds between 84000 yojana (an ancient Indian scale: seven miles or nine miles) under the bottom of the sea in the north of Mt. Myoko (Mt. Sumeru).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, &quot;Jyuji-kyo Sutra&quot; and the eighteenth to twenty-first volumes of &quot;Shobonenjo-kyo Sutra&quot; (Meditation on the Correct Teaching Sutra) explain the homes, behaviors, and life durations of these four kings and suggests that their homes are located separately in the four-layered grounds between 84000 yojana (an ancient Indian scale: seven miles or nine miles) under the bottom of the sea to the north of Mt. Myoko (Mt. Sumeru).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, &quot;Juji-kyo Sutra&quot; and the eighteenth to twenty-first volumes of &quot;Shobonenjo-kyo Sutra&quot; (Meditation on the Correct Teaching Sutra) explain the homes, behaviors, and life durations of these four kings and suggests that their homes are located separately in the four-layered grounds between 84000 yojana (an ancient Indian scale: seven miles or nine miles) under the bottom of the sea to the north of Mt. Myoko (Mt. Sumeru).</e>
<cmt>Jyuji-kyo→Juji-kyoに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>以下説明は主に正法念処経による。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following explanations are based mainly on Shobonenjo-kyo Sutra.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following explanations are based mainly on Shobonenjo-kyo Sutra.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following explanations are based mainly on Shobonenjo-kyo Sutra.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="68">
<j>羅喉阿修羅王（らご）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rago-Ashura-o (Rago)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rago-Ashura-o (Rago)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rago-Ashura-o (Rago)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>Skt及びPl：Rāhu、ラーフ、パーリ語：訳：障月、執月、月食など、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Sanskrit and Pali :Rāhu, Rafu, in Pali: translation : 障月,執月, lunar eclipse and others.</e>
<cmt>「パーリ語：」部分は不要ではないかと思いましたが、そのまま訳出しております。「障月、執月」については訳語不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Sanskrit and Pali :Rāhu, Rafu, in Pali: translation : 障月,執月, lunar eclipse and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Sanskrit and Pali: Rāhu, Rafu, in Pali: translation: 障月,執月, lunar eclipse and others.</e>
<cmt>スペース修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>その手でよく日月を執て、その光を遮るので、この名がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its name is based on the fact that it keeps out the sunlight by its hands shading the sun and moon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its name is based on the fact that it keeps out the sunlight by its hands shading the sun and moon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its name is based on the fact that it keeps out the sunlight by its hands shading the sun and moon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="71">
<j>（住処）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Home)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Home)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Home)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>- 第1層、海底地下21000由旬を住処とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- It lives in the first-layer which is located 21000 yojana under the bottom of the sea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">- It lives in the first-layer which is located 21000 yojana under the bottom of the sea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">- It lives in the first-layer which is located 21000 yojana under the bottom of the sea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>身量広大にして須弥山のようで、光明城に住み、縦横8000由旬。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is so big like Mt. Sumeru and lives in Komyo Castle in the size of 8000 yojana in height and width.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is big like Mt. Sumeru and lives in Komyo Castle in the size of 8000 yojana in height and width.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;so&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is big like Mt. Sumeru and lives in Komyo Castle in the size of 8000 yojana in height and width.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="74">
<j>（業因）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Behavior)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Behavior)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Behavior)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>- 前世にバラモンであった時、1つの仏塔が焼き払われるのを防ぎ、その福徳により後身に大身相を願った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- When it was Brahman in the previous life, it prevented a Buddhist pagoda from burning down and wished a later self to be 大身相 due to its fortune and luck.</e>
<cmt>「大身相」については意味不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">- When it was Brahman in the previous life, it prevented a Buddhist pagoda from burning down and wished a later self to be 大身相 due to its fortune and luck.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">- When it was Brahman in the previous life, it prevented a Buddhist pagoda from burning down and wished a later self to be 大身相 due to its fortune and luck.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>不殺生の実践したが、諸善業を行わなかったので、その身が破壊（はえ）し、命終して阿修羅道へ堕ちてその身を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It did not conduct various good deeds after ahimsa, so its body destroyed into death, resulting in falling into Ashura-do, Asura realm.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It did not conduct various good deeds after ahimsa, so its body dwas estroyed into death, resulting in a fall into Ashura-do, Asura realm.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It did not conduct various good deeds after ahimsa, so its body dwas estroyed into death, resulting in a fall into Ashura-do, Asura realm.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="77">
<j>（寿命）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Life duration)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Life duration)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Life duration)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>- 人の500歳を1日1夜として、その寿命は5000歳</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- Its life duration is 5000 years old in the basis on a day and night per 500 years old for human.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">- Its life duration is 5000 years old on the basis of a day and night being equal to 500 years for a human.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">- Its life duration is 5000 years old on the basis of a day and night being equal to 500 years for a human.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>婆稚阿修羅王（ばち、婆稚とも）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bachi-Ashura-o (Bachi)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bachi-Ashura-o (Bachi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bachi-Ashura-o (Bachi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>Skt及びPl：Bali、バリ、訳：被縛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Sanskrit and Pali :Bali, translation : being fastened</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Sanskrit and Pali :Bali, translation : being fastened</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Sanskrit and Pali: Bali, translation: being fastened</e>
<cmt>スペース修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>帝釈天と戦って破れ、縛せられたためにこの名がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This name came from the fact that it lost in the battle with Taishakuten and was fastened up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This name came from the fact that it lost in the battle with Taishakuten and was fastened up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This name came from the fact that it lost in the battle with Taishakuten and was fastened up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>正法念処経では勇犍（ゆうごん）阿修羅王。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Shobonenjo-kyo Sutra, it is called Yugon-Ashura-o.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Shobonenjo-kyo Sutra, it is called Yugon-Ashura-o.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Shobonenjo-kyo Sutra, it is called Yugon-Ashura-o.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>ラーフの兄弟で、彼の子らはみなVerocaと名づく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the brother of Rafu and his children have the name, Veroca.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the brother of Rafu and his children have the name, Veroca.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the brother of Rafu and his children have the name, Veroca.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="84">
<j>（住処）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Home)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Home)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Home)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>- 第1層の下の第2層、さらに21000由旬の月鬘（げつまん）という地で、双遊城に住み、縦横8000由旬。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- It lives in Soyu Castle in the size of 8000 yojana in height and width in Getsuman located 21000 yojana in the second-layer below the first-layer.</e>
<cmt>「双遊城」については読みが確認できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">- It lives in Soyu Castle in the size of 8000 yojana in height and width in Getsuman located 21000 yojana in the second-layer below the first-layer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">- It lives in Soyu Castle in the size of 8000 yojana in height and width in Getsuman located 21000 yojana in the second-layer below the first-layer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="86">
<j>（業因）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Behavior)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Behavior)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Behavior)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>- 前世に他人の所有物を盗み、不正の思いをなして離欲の外道に施して、飲食（読み：おんじき）を充足させたので、命終して阿修羅道へ堕ちてその身を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- In the previous life, it stole other&apos;s belongings, run the heretical doctrine of selflessness without a sense of injustice and was satisfied with eating and drinking, so it died, resulting in falling into Ashura-do, Asura realm.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">- In the previous life, it stole others&apos; belongings, followed the heretical doctrine of selflessness without a sense of injustice and was satisfied with eating and drinking, so it died, resulting in a fall into Ashura-do, Asura realm.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">- In the previous life, it stole others&apos; belongings, followed the heretical doctrine of selflessness without a sense of injustice and was satisfied with eating and drinking, so it died, resulting in a fall into Ashura-do, Asura realm.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="88">
<j>（寿命）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Life duration)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Life duration)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Life duration)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>- 人の600歳を1日1夜として、その寿命は6000歳</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- Its life duration is 6000 years old in the basis on a day and night per 600 years old for human.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">- Its life duration is 6000 years on the basis of a day and night being equal to 600 years for a human.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">- Its life duration is 6000 years on the basis of a day and night being equal to 600 years for a human.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>佉羅騫駄阿修羅王（きゃらけんだ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyarakenda-Ashura-o (Kyarakenda)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyarakenda-Ashura-o (Kyarakenda)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyarakenda-Ashura-o (Kyarakenda)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>SktŚambara、PlSambara、サンバラ、訳：勝楽、詐譌、木綿など</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Śambara in Sanskrit and Śambara in Pali, translation : easy win, fraud, cotton and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Śambara in Sanskrit and Śambara in Pali, translation : easy win, fraud, cotton, and others.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Śambara in Sanskrit and Śambara in Pali, translation: easy win, fraud, cotton, and others</e>
<cmt>スペース、ピリオド削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>正法念処経では華鬘（けまん）阿修羅王と訳される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Shobonenjo-kyo Sutra, it is translated into Keman-Ashura-o.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Shobonenjo-kyo Sutra, it is translated into Keman-Ashura-o.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Shobonenjo-kyo Sutra, it is translated into Keman-Ashura-o.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="93">
<j>（住処）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Home)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Home)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Home)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>- 第2層の下の第3層、さらに21000由旬の修那婆（しゅなば）という地で、頷（正字は金＋含）毘羅城（かんびら）に住み、縦横8000由旬。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- It lives in Kanbira Castle in the size of 8000 yojana in height and width in Shunaba located 21000 yojana in the third-layer below the second-layer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">- It lives in Kanbira Castle in the size of 8000 yojana in height and width in Shunaba located 21000 yojana in the third-layer below the second-layer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">- It lives in Kanbira Castle in the size of 8000 yojana in height and width in Shunaba located 21000 yojana in the third-layer below the second-layer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="95">
<j>（業因）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Behavior)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Behavior)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Behavior)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>- 前世に食を破戒の病人に施して,余の衆は節会の日により相撲や射的など種々の遊戯をなし,また不浄施を行じたので,命終して阿修羅道へ堕ちてその身を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- In the previous life, it fed to the depraved ill person and enjoyed various games including as sumo and target practicing on the day of Sechi-e (seasonal court banquets) as well as making improper offering, so it died, resulting in falling into Ashura-do, Asura realm.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the previous life, it fed a depraved ill person and enjoyed various games including sumo and target practice on the day of Sechi-e (seasonal court banquets) and made an improper offering, so it died, resulting In a fall into Ashura-do, Asura realm.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the previous life, it fed a depraved ill person and enjoyed various games including sumo and target practice on the day of Sechi-e (seasonal court banquets) and made an improper offering, so it died, resulting in a fall into Ashura-do, Asura realm.</e>
<cmt>In→inに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="97">
<j>（寿命）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Life duration)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Life duration)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Life duration)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>- 人の700歳を1日1夜として、その寿命は7000歳</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- Its life duration is 7000 years old in the basis on a day and night per 700 years old for human.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">- Its life duration is 7000 years on the basis of a day and night being equal to 700 years for a human.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">- Its life duration is 7000 years on the basis of a day and night being equal to 700 years for a human.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>毘摩質多羅阿修羅王（びましったら）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bimashittara-Ashura-o (Bimashittara)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bimashittara-Ashura-o (Bimashittara)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bimashittara-Ashura-o (Bimashittara)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>Skt：Vemacitra、Vimalacitra、Pl：Vepacitti、訳：浄心、絲種種、綺書、宝飾、紋身など</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Vemacitra, Vimalacitra in Sanskrit and Vepacitti in Pali, translation : purification, 絲種種, 綺書, jewelry, tatoo and others</e>
<cmt>「絲種種」 「綺書」については読み、意味とも不明でした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Vemacitra, Vimalacitra in Sanskrit and Vepacitti in Pali, translation : purification, 絲種種, 綺書, jewelry, tattoo, and others</e>
<cmt>punctuation, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Vemacitra, Vimalacitra in Sanskrit and Vepacitti in Pali, translation: purification, 絲種種, 綺書, jewelry, tattoo, and others</e>
<cmt>スペース消去しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>乾闥婆の娘を娶り、娘の舎脂を産んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It married the daughter of Kendatsuba, Gandharva and had a daughter, Sachi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It married the daughter of Kendatsuba, Gandharva, and had a daughter, Sachi.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It married the daughter of Kendatsuba, Gandharva, and had a daughter, Sachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>前出のように舎脂は帝釈天に嫁いだため、帝釈天の舅にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As described above, Sachi married Taishakuten and it is the father-in-law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As described above, Sachi married Taishakuten and it is the father-in-law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As described above, Sachi married Taishakuten and it is the father-in-law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="103">
<j>（住処）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Home)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Home)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Home)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>- 第3層の下の第4層、さらに21000由旬の不動という地で、頷（正字は金＋含）毘羅城（かんびら）に住み、縦横13000由旬。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- It lives in Kanbira-castle in the size of 13000 yojana in height and width in Fudo located 21000 yojana in the fourth-layer below the third-layer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">- It lives in Kanbira-castle in the size of 13000 yojana in height and width in Fudo located 21000 yojana in the fourth-layer below the third-layer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">- It lives in Kanbira Castle in the size of 13000 yojana in height and width in Fudo located 21000 yojana in the fourth-layer below the third-layer.</e>
<cmt>表記統一のため、Kanbira-castle→Kanbira Castleに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="105">
<j>（業因）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Behavior)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Behavior)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Behavior)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>- 前世に邪見の心を以って持戒する者に施して,余の衆は自身のために万樹を護ったので,命終して阿修羅道へ堕ちてその身を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">-In the previous life, it offered to people keeping precepts with the unreasonable mind and preserved trees for its own benefit, so it died, resulting in falling into Ashura-do, Asura realm.</e>
<cmt>「万樹」については意味が確認できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">-In the previous life, it made offers to people keeping precepts with the unreasonable mind and preserved trees for its own benefit, so it died, resulting in a fall into Ashura-do, Asura realm.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">- In the previous life, it made offers to people keeping precepts with the unreasonable mind and preserved trees for its own benefit, so it died, resulting in a fall into Ashura-do, Asura realm.</e>
<cmt>スペース追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="107">
<j>その他『起世経』では、須弥山の東西の面を去ること1000由旬の外に毘摩質多羅王の宮があり、縦横8万由旬であるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, &quot;Kisekyo&quot; (literally, &quot;Sutra of the World Arising&quot;) shows that there is the palace of Bimashittara-o 1000 yojana away from east and west sides of Mt. Sumeru, in the size of 80000 yojana in height and width.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, &quot;Kisekyo&quot; (literally, &quot;Sutra of the World Arising&quot;) shows that there is the palace of Bimashittara-o 1000 yojana away from the east and west sides of Mt. Sumeru, in the size of 80000 yojana in height and width.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, &quot;Kisekyo&quot; (literally, &quot;Sutra of the World Arising&quot;) shows that there is the palace of Bimashittara-o 1000 yojana away from the east and west sides of Mt. Sumeru, in the size of 80000 yojana in height and width.</e>
<cmt>スペース消去しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>また修羅の中に極めて弱き者は人間山地の中に在りて住す、すなわち今、西方の山中に大きくて深い窟があり、多く非天＝阿修羅の宮があるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the extremely weak shura (timber chute) lives in the human-living mountain, and therefore, it is said that now there is the big and deep cave in the western mountain in which many non-heavens i.e. the palace of Ashura are located.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the extremely weak shura (timber chute) lives in the human-living mountain, and therefore, it is said that now there is a big and deep cave in the western mountain in which many non-heavens; i.e. the palace of Ashura, are located.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the extremely weak shura (timber chute) lives in the human-living mountain, and therefore, it is said that now there is a big and deep cave in the western mountain in which many non-heavens; i.e. the palace of Ashura, are located.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Evan1975(id:30510), 五代雄介(id:67888), Mnd(id:15140), Takobou(id:10633), Toroia(id:31889), Drblack(id:116617), Hvn0413(id:38818), Authority(id:10737), Seibuabina(id:37532), Robbot(id:3063), Cc1301(id:143409), Qazzx(id:8772), Sh(id:2707), どりんく(id:108137), Hatsune(id:26654), MDR-SK(id:192066), 摩利支天(id:187890), WSWatcher(id:100280), Fxcxt(id:21803), VolkovBot(id:105371), Boca samba(id:137526), SuisuiBot(id:10165), らんたん(id:131466), Sionnach(id:21673), R28Bot(id:177951), Iokseng(id:92490), うぃき野郎(id:53567), Korokoro(id:42329), はぜ(id:24807), 無空(id:17049), Peccafly(id:54812), Suisui(id:69), Cpro(id:28341), っ(id:4481), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>