<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大典顕常</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenjo DAITEN</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenjo DAITEN</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenjo DAITEN</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>大典顕常（だいてん けんじょう、享保4年（1719年） - 享和元年2月8日 (旧暦)（1801年3月22日））は江戸時代中期 - 後期の禅僧、漢詩人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenjo DAITEN (1719-March 22, 1801) was the Zen Buddhist monk, who practiced Chinese-style poetry, between the mid to end of the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenjo DAITEN (1719-March 22, 1801), a Zen Buddhist monk who practiced Chinese-style poetry, lived from the middle to late Edo period.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenjo DAITEN (1719 - March 22, 1801), a Zen Buddhist monk and a Chinese-style poet, lived from the middle to late Edo period.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>大典と高遊外との交遊は有名であり『売茶翁伝』を著している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The friendly relation between Daiten and Baisao was famous, and he wrote &quot;Baisaoden&quot; (The Story of Baisao).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The friendly relationship between Daiten and Baisao was famous, and he wrote &quot;Baisaoden (The Story of Baisao).&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The friendly relationship between Daiten and Koyugai (also known as Baisao) was famous, and he wrote &quot;Baisaoden&quot; (The Story of Baisao).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>また伊藤若冲の支援者としても知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also known as the supporter of Jakuchu ITO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also known as the supporter of Jakuchu ITO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also known as the supporter of Jakuchu ITO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>漢詩をよくし京都禅林中最高の詩僧と称されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He improved Chinese-style poem and praised as the best priest poet in Kyoto Zenrin (zen temples).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He elevated Chinese-style poetry and was praised as the best priest poet in Kyoto Zenrin (Zen temples).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He elevated Chinese-style poetry and was praised as the best priest poet in Kyoto Zenrin (Zen temples).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>生涯に70冊以上もの浩瀚な書を著した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He wrote a vast amount of writings of over seventy books during his lifetime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During his lifetime he wrote a vast amount of writings, comprising more than 70 books.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During his lifetime he wrote a vast amount of writings, comprising more than 70 books.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>禅の高僧でもあり相国寺第113世となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the highest monk of Zen Sect and was the hundred and thirteenth head of the Shokoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the highest monk of the Zen sect and was the 113th head of Shokoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the highest monk of the Zen sect and was the 113th head priest of Shokoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>顕常は諱である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenjo is his imina (personal name referred to after his or her death).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His imina (a personal name referred to after death) was Kenjo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His imina (personal name) was Kenjo.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>大典は号 (称号)で大典禅師と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daiten was his go (title), and he was called as Daiten Zenshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daiten was his go (title), and he was called Daiten Zenshi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daiten was his go (title), and he was called Daiten Zenshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>宗派内は梅荘と号していたが、のちに焦中と改号した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His go was Baisho within the religious sect, but was replaced with the go of Shochu eventually.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His go was Baisho within the religious sect, but was eventually it was replaced with the go of Shochu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He called himself Baisho within the religious sect, but was eventually changed to call himself Shochu.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その他に近江国出身であることから淡海、居処の名に因んで小雲棲、北禅書院、ほか東湖山人、不生主人、太真などと号している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also had other go of Atami since he originated from Omi and Shounsei, Hokuzenshoin, Tokosanjin, Fushoshujin, and Taishin from the name of his residential area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also had other go of Atami (since he originated from Omi) and Shounsei, Hokuzenshoin, Tokosanjin, Fushoshujin and Taishin (from the name of his residential area).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also had other go of Atami (since he originated from Omi) and Shounsei, Hokuzen Shoin, Toko Sanjin, Fusho Shujin and Taishin, from the name of his residential area.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>竺常（じくじょう）と名乗るがこれは「釈（顕）常」のことであり、諱が二つあるわけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also referred as Jikujo but was &quot;Shaku (Ken)jo&quot; and not that he had two imina.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, he was referred to as Jikujo but was &quot;Shaku (Ken)jo,&quot; so it wasn&apos;t that he had two imina.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, he was referred to as Jikujo but was &apos;Shaku (Ken) jo,&apos; so it wasn&apos;t that he had two imina.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>本姓は今堀、通称 太一郎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His original surname was Imahori and first name was Taichiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His original surname was Imahori, and his first name was Taichiro.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His original surname was Imahori, and his first name was Taichiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>近江国神崎郡 (滋賀県)伊庭郷（現 滋賀県東近江市）の儒医 今堀東安の子として生まれたとされるが、権大納言園基勝（その もとかつ）の私生児でその後里子に出されたとの説が有力である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as the child of Toan IMAHORI, who practiced Confucianism and medicine, in Iba go(current Omi City, Shiga Prefecture), Kanzaki District (Shiga Prefecture), Omi Province, but was mostly likely that he was the illegitimate child of Motokatsu SONO, who had the title of Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor), and later sent for adoption.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born as the child of Toan IMAHORI, who practiced Confucianism and medicine, in Iba go (the present-day Omi City, Shiga Prefecture), Kanzaki District (Shiga Prefecture), Omi Province, but he was mostly likely the illegitimate child of Motokatsu SONO, who had the title of Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor) and was later sent for adoption.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born as the child of Toan IMAHORI, who practiced Confucianism and medicine, in Iba-go, Kanzaki District, Omi Province, (the present-day Higashiomi City, Shiga Prefecture) but he was mostly likely the illegitimate child of Motokatsu SONO of Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor) and was later sent for adoption.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>8歳のとき父と上京し、はじめ黄檗山の華蔵院に入ったが臨済宗に転じて11歳で相国寺慈雲庵にて得度する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He arrived to Kyoto with his father when he was 8 years old and entered Kezo-in Temple of Obaku Mountain first but switched to Rinzai Sect to begin his training as a monk in Jiun-an in Sokoku-ji Temple when he was eleven years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was assigned the Juji (chief priest) position when he was 32 years old, but with illness as an excuse he asked to refrain from the top position when his master Doppo passed away.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He arrived to Kyoto with his father when he was eight years old and entered Kezo-in Temple on Mt. Obaku first but switched to Rinzai Sect to begin his training as a monk in Jiun-an in Sokoku-ji Temple when he was 11 years old.</e>
<cmt>trans2は別の文の訳文のようなので、trans1に対して補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>独峰慈秀の下で禅の修行に勤しみながらも、20代後半まで宇野明霞や大潮元皓に儒学の一派である古文辞学を学んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He studied one type of Confucianism, Kobunjigaku, trained for Zen Buddhism under Meika UNO and Genko GENKO up to the end of his twenties while he trained for Zen under Dokusho Jishu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He studied a type of Confucianism called Kobunjigaku, and he trained in Zen Buddhism under Meika UNO and Genko GENKO up to the end of his twenties while training for Zen under Dokusho Jishu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He studied a type of Confucianism called kobunjigaku, (study of ancient rhetoric school), and he trained in Zen Buddhism under Meika UNO and Daicho Genko up to the end of his twenties while training for Zen under Dokusho Jishu.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>儒学の師 明霞が歿した3年後に、大典は師の遺稿を編集して『明霞先生遺稿集』として刊行しているが、師の信任が篤かったことが伺える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He edited and published the posthumous manuscripts of his master as &quot;Meika Sensei Ikoshu&quot; (Collection of posthumous manuscripts of Teacher Meika) three years after his Confucius master, Meika, passed away and this showed how deeply he was trusted by his master.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He edited and published the posthumous manuscripts of his master as &quot;Meika Sensei Ikoshu (Collection of Posthumous Manuscripts of Teacher Meika)&quot; three years after his Confucian master, Meika, passed away, and this showed how deeply he was trusted by his master.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He edited and published the posthumous manuscripts of his Confucian master Meika, as &quot;Meika Sensei Ikoshu&quot; (Collection of Posthumous Manuscripts of Teacher Meika) three years after his master passed away, and this showed how deeply he was trusted by his master.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>明霞門の盟友に片山北海がいるが、彼の主催する混沌詩社にも参加して詩文を磨いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was Hokkai KATAYAMA among sworn friends of the disciples of Meika, and he participated in Konton-shisha (Chinese poetry club) arranged by him and showed off his poetic skills.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was Hokkai KATAYAMA among the sworn friends of the disciples of Meika, and he participated in Konton-shisha (Chinese poetry club) arranged by him and demonstrated his profound skills as a poet.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was Hokkai KATAYAMA among the sworn friends of the disciples of Meika, and he participated in Konton-shisha (Chinese poetry club) arranged by him and demonstrated his profound skills as a poet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="18">
<j>32歳で住持になるが師独峰が示寂すると病気を理由に致仕を願い出て許される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was assigned with Juji (chief priest) position when he was thirty-two years old, but asked to refrain from the top position when his master Doppo passed away with an excuse of having illness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was assigned the Juji (chief priest) position when he was 32 years old, but with the excuse of illness he asked to refrain from the top position when his master Doppo passed away.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was assigned the Juji (chief priest) position when he was 32 years old, but with the excuse of illness he asked to refrain from the top position when his master Doppo passed away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>公務に縛られることなく文芸に身を投じたいという文人的な隠逸を望んだものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that he sought a literary recluses in his wish to pursue culture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that he sought literary reclusion in his wish to pursue culture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that he sought literary reclusion in his wish to pursue culture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>43歳のとき代表作『昨非集』を刊行した後、旺盛に詩作と著述に励んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he published his representative work, &quot;Sakuhishu&quot; (Collection of the Mistakes of Yesterday) when he was forty-three years old, he pursued poetry making and writing intensively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he published his representative work, &quot;Sakuhishu (Collection of the Mistakes of Yesterday)&quot; when he was 43 years old, he engaged himself fully in the creation and writing of poetry.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he published his representative work, &quot;Sakuhishu&quot; (Collection of the Mistakes of Yesterday) when he was 43 years old, he engaged himself fully in the creation and writing of poetry.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="21">
<j>多くの文人墨客と積極的に交わり、特に慈周とは終生の親交をもった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He associated with many writers and artists and had a life long friendship, especially with Jishu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He associated with many writers and artists, and among them he built lifelong friendships, particularly with Jishu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He associated with many writers and artists, and among them he built lifelong friendships, particularly with Jishu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>中国において貴重な経典が失われる事件があったとき、大典は慈周とともにこの寄贈を果たしたというエピソードがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was an episode where when a highly valued Buddhist scriptures disappeared in China, Daiten and Jishu donated this gift.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was an episode in which, when a highly valued Buddhist scripture disappeared in China, Daiten and Jishu donated this gift.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was an episode in which, when a highly valued Buddhist scripture disappeared in China, Daiten and Jishu donated this gift.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="23">
<j>ほかにも異才の画家 伊藤若冲に支援を続け、相国寺の襖絵などを画かせている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also supported Jakuchu ITO, who was an artist with an unique talent, and made him paint on Fusumae (images drawn on fusuma sliding door) of Shokoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also supported Jakuchu ITO, who was a uniquely talented artist, and had him paint Fusumae (images drawn on fusuma sliding doors) for Shokoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also supported Jakuchu ITO, who was a uniquely talented artist, and had him paint Fusuma-e (images drawn on fusuma sliding doors) for Shokoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>また売茶翁のよき理解者として煎茶道を広めることに尽力し『茶経評説』などを著している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also aimed to spread Senchado (Sencha Tea Service) as an understanding person of Baisao and wrote &quot;Chakyo Hyosetsu&quot; (comment on Chakyo, Chinese book written about tea).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also worked to spread Senchado (Sencha Tea Service) as one who understood Baisao, and wrote &quot;Chakyo Hyosetsu&quot; (comment on Chakyo, a Chinese book about tea).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also worked to spread Senchado (green tea ceremony) as one who understood Baisao, and wrote &quot;Chakyo Hyosetsu&quot; (comment on Chakyo, a Chinese book about tea).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>さらに木村蒹葭堂と協力して清国の『煎茶訣』を刊行し本邦に紹介している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, he collaborated with Kenkado KIMURA and published &quot;Senchaketsu&quot; of Kiyokuni and introduced it to Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, he collaborated with Kenkado KIMURA and published &quot;Senchaketsu&quot; of Kiyokuni, whereupon he introduced it to Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, he collaborated with Kenkado KIMURA and published &quot;Sencha ketsu&quot; (secrets of steeped tea) in Qing, whereupon he introduced it to Japan.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>売茶翁の生涯を綴った唯一の伝記「売茶翁伝」（『売茶翁偈語』巻頭）を著し後世に伝えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He composed &quot;Baisaoden&quot; (Forward of &quot;Baisaogo&quot;), which was the only biography that wrote about the life of Baisao and told in future generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He composed &quot;Baisaoden&quot; (the forward of &quot;Baisaogo&quot;), which was the only biography concerning the life of Baisao; the story was thus handed down to succeeding generations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He composed &apos;Baisaoden&apos; (the preface of &quot;Baisao Gego&quot; (Verses and Prose by the Old Tea Seller)), which was the only biography concerning the life of Baisao; the story was thus handed down to succeeding generations.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>そのほかにも池大雅の詩文の師であり、菅茶山、高芙蓉、葛子琴、篠崎三島らとの交流が伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also the master of the poetry for Taiga IKENO and had association with Chazan KAN, Fuyo KO, Shikin KATSU, and Santo SHINOZAKI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also the master of poetry for Taiga IKENO and had an association with Chazan KAN, Fuyo KO, Shikin KATSU and Santo SHINOZAKI.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also the master of poetry for Taiga IKENO and had an association with Chazan KAN, Fuyo KO, Shikin KATSU and Santo SHINOZAKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="28">
<j>53歳になり帰山すると相国寺住持に推され、続いて京都五山碩学と朝鮮修文職を任じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he returned to his own temple when he was fifty-three years old, he was given the Juji (chief priest) position in Shokokuji and was additionally assigned with Kyoto Gozan Scholar and position of negotiating with Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he returned to his own temple at 53 years of age, he was given the Juji (chief priest) position in Shokokuji and was additionally assigned to be a Kyoto Gozan scholar and negotiator with Korea.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he returned to his own temple at 53 years of age, he was given the Juji position in Shokoku-ji Temple and was additionally assigned to be a great scholar of Kyoto Gozan (Five Great zen Temples of Kyoto) and negotiator with Korea.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>62歳のとき、対馬の以酊庵に住持として2年間赴任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He left for the new post of Juji of Iteian, Tsushima (province) for two years when he was sixty-two years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the age of 62, he left for the new post of Juji of Iteian, Tsushima (province) for a period of two years.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the age of 62, he left for the new position of Juji of Itei-an Temple, Tsushima (province) for a period of two years.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>帰山後は南禅寺住持になり、江戸幕府の辞令を受けたことへの拝礼のため江戸に下る（1785年）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he returned to his own temple, he became the Juji of Nanzen-ji Temple and traveled to Edo to appreciate and worship the leader for being ordered by Edo Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) (1785).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he returned to his own temple, he became the Juji of Nanzen-ji Temple and traveled to Edo in order to appreciate and worship the leader, as ordered by the Edo Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) (1785).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he returned to his own temple, he became the Juji of Nanzen-ji Temple and traveled to Edo in order to appreciate and worship the leader, as ordered by the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) (in 1785).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>松平定信に優遇され、再度江戸に招かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was favored by Sadanobu MATSUDAIRA and was invited again to Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was favored by Sadanobu MATSUDAIRA and was again invited to Edo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was favored by Sadanobu MATSUDAIRA and was again invited to Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>このころに朝鮮通信使に関する国書の起草に関与しているが、以降朝鮮外交に関して幕府顧問となって活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He drafted a manuscript for the diplomatic document concerning the Buddhist missionary to Korea at this time, but he later participated as the advisor to bakufu concerning its diplomatic relation with Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time he drafted a manuscript for a diplomatic document concerning the Buddhist missionary to Korea, and later he participated as the advisor to the bakufu concerning diplomatic relations with Korea.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time he drafted a manuscript for a diplomatic document concerning the Buddhist missionary to Korea, and later he participated as the advisor to the bakufu concerning diplomatic relations with Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="33">
<j>天明の大火（1789年）で相国寺も全焼し貴重な典籍の再収集や再建に尽力している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shokoku-ji Temple was also completely burnt in the Temmei no Taika (The Great Fire of the Temmei period) (1789), and he tried to actively re-collect and reconstruct valuable books.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shokoku-ji Temple was also completely destroyed in the Temmei no Taika (the great fire of the Temmei period) (1789), and energetically he worked to re-collect and reconstruct valuable books.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shokoku-ji Temple was also completely destroyed in Great Fire of Tenmei (in 1789), and energetically he worked to re-collect and reconstruct valuable books.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="34">
<j>享和元年（1801年）歿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He passed away in 1801.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He passed away in 1801.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He passed away in 1801.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>享年83。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His dying age was eighty-three.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was 83 at the time of his death.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was 83 at the time of his death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="36">
<j>詩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Poetry</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Poetry</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Poetry</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="37">
<j>古文辞派の詩風ではあったが、和歌の教養も深くその要素を漢詩に取り込もうと試みている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His poetic style followed the Kobunji school, but his education in waka (Japanese poem) was vast and tried to incorporate its elements into Chinese-style poems.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His poetic style followed the Kobunji school, but his education in waka (Japanese poetry) was vast and he attempted to incorporate its elements into Chinese-style poems.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His poetic style followed the Kobunji School, but his education in waka (Japanese poetry) was vast and he attempted to incorporate its elements into Chinese-style poems.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>仏教的な枠に囚われることなく自由で大胆な作風である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His poetic style was not restricted to Buddhistic boundary and was daring.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His poetic style was daring in that it transcended the boundaries of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His poetic style was daring in that it transcended the boundaries of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>多くの詩集を刊行し多作であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He published many poetry collections and was a prolific writer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A prolific writer, he published numerous collections of poetry.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A prolific writer, he published numerous collections of poetry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kaznov17(id:68122), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), 樒(id:35770), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>