<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>五大菩薩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Godai Bosatsu</e>
<cmt>五大菩薩（ごだいぼさつ）→Godai Bosatsu, Five Great Bosatsu[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Godai Bosatsu</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Godai Bosatsu (Five Great Bodhisattava)</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>五大菩薩（ごだいぼさつ）は、仏教の信仰・造像の対象である菩薩（真理を探求し、悟りを開くために修行中の者）の組み合わせの1つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Godai Bosatsu is a kind of the combination of Bosatsu (those who are engaged in ascetic training in pursuit of the truth and enlightment) that are the target of worsiping and making statues in Buddhism society.</e>
<cmt>菩薩→Bosatsu, Bodhisattva</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Godai Bosatsu are a kind of combination of Bosatsu (those who are engaged in ascetic training in pursuit of the truth and enlightment) that are objects of worship and construction of statues in Buddhist society.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Godai Bosatsu are a kind of combination of Bosatsu (those who are engaged in ascetic training in pursuit of the truth and enlightment) that are objects of worship and construction of statues in Buddhist society.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>密教において重視される両界曼荼羅（こんごうかいまんだら）に登場する数多い菩薩のうち主要なものを組み合わせたものであるが、以下に述べる京都市・東寺の像以外には顕著な作例を見ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the combination of principal Bosatsu picked up from a lot of Bosatsu depicted in Ryokai-mandara (Vajradhatumandala), which is valued by Esoteric Buddhism, but there is no prominent work other than the statues at To-ji Temple (Kyoogokoku-ji Temple) in Kyoto City mentioned below.</e>
<cmt>密教→Mikkyo, Esoteric Buddhism[http://www.koyasan.or.jp/english/shingonshu/mikkyo.html]両界曼荼羅→Ryokai-mandara, mandala of the two realmsこんごうかいまんだら→Kongokai-mandara, Vajradhatumandala京都市→Kyoto City東寺（教王護国寺）→To-ji Temple (Kyoogokoku-ji Temple) [http://kaiwai.city.kyoto.jp/search/view_sight.php?ManageCode=1000042&amp;InforKindCode=1]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the combination of principal Bosatsu, picked up from many Bosatsu depicted in Ryokai-mandara (Vajradhatumandala), which is valued by Esoteric Buddhism, but there is no prominent work other than the statues at To-ji Temple (Kyoogokoku-ji Temple) in Kyoto City, as mentioned below.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the combination of principal Bosatsu, picked up from many Bosatsu depicted in Ryokai-mandala (Vajradhatumandala), which is valued by Esoteric Buddhism, but there is no prominent work other than the statues at To-ji Temple in Kyoto City, as mentioned below.</e>
<cmt>(Kyoogokoku-ji Temple)をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>京都・東寺（教王護国寺）の講堂には、空海の構想によって造立された、21体の尊像から成る立体曼荼羅がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Lecture Hall of To-ji Temple (Kyoogokoku-ji Temple) in Kyoto, there is a three dimensional Mandara, which consists of 21 statues, that was made by the initiative of Kukai.</e>
<cmt>講堂→Kodo, Lecture Hall</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Lecture Hall of To-ji Temple (Kyoogokoku-ji Temple) in Kyoto, there is a three dimensional Mandara, which consists of 21 statues, that was made by the initiative of Kukai.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Lecture Hall of To-ji Temple (Kyoogokoku-ji Temple) in Kyoto, there is a three dimensional Mandala, which consists of 21 statues, that was made by the initiative of Kukai.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>講堂に安置される仏像群は、如来グループ、明王グループ、菩薩グループに分かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those statues enshrined at the Lecture Hall are categorized into Nyorai group, Myoo group and Basatsu group respectively.</e>
<cmt>如来→Nyorai明王→Myoo</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those statues enshrined at the Lecture Hall are categorized into the Nyorai group, the Myoo group and the Bosatsu group respectively.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those statues enshrined at the Lecture Hall are categorized into the Nyorai (Tathagata) group, the Myoo (vidya-raja) group and the Bosatsu (Bodhisattva) group respectively.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>すなわち、堂の中央には大日如来を中心とする金剛界五仏（五智如来）、向かって左（西）には不動明王を中心とする五大明王、そして堂内の向かって右には五大菩薩像をそれぞれ安置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kongokai-gobutsu (Gochi-nyorai), of which principal statue is Dainichinyorai, is enshrined at the center of the Hall, Godai Myoo, of which principal statue is Fudo Myoo, is enshrined on the observers&apos; left (west) and Godai Bosatsu is enshrined on the observers&apos; right respectively.</e>
<cmt>大日如来→Dainichinyorai金剛界五仏→Kongokai-gobutsu, Five Buddhas of the Diamond world五智如来→Gochi-nyorai, Five Wisdom nyorai, Tathagatas[http://www.aisf.or.jp/%7Ejaanus/]不動明王→Fudo Myoo[http://www.aisf.or.jp/~jaanus/deta/g/godaimyouou.htm]五大明王→Godai Myoo, Five Great Myoo[http://www.aisf.or.jp/~jaanus/deta/g/godaimyouou.htm]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kongokai-gobutsu (Gochi-nyorai), of which the principal statue is Dainichinyorai, is enshrined at the center of the Hall, Godai Myoo, of which the principal statue is Fudo Myoo, is enshrined on the observers&apos; left (west) and Godai Bosatsu is enshrined on the observers&apos; right respectively.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kongokai-gobutsu (Gochi Nyorai (Five Wisdom Nyorai, Tathagatas)), of which the principal statue is Dainichi Nyorai (Mahavairocana), is enshrined at the center of the Hall, Godai Myoo (Five Great Myoo), of which the principal statue is Fudo Myoo (Acala, one of the Five Wisdom Kings), is enshrined on the observers&apos; left (west) and Godai Bosatsu is enshrined on the observers&apos; right respectively.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>東寺講堂の五大菩薩は金剛波羅蜜、金剛薩た（さった）、金剛宝菩薩、金剛法菩薩、金剛業（ごう）菩薩の5体である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Godai Bosatsu enshrined at the Lecture Hall of To-ji Temple consists of 5 Bosatsu statues, namely Kongouharamitsu, Kongosatta, Kongoho Bosatsu, Kongoho Bosatsu and Kongogo Bosatsu.</e>
<cmt>金剛波羅蜜→Kongouharamitsu, Vajraparamita金剛薩た（さった）→Kongosatta金剛宝菩薩→Kongoho Bosatsu金剛法菩薩→Kongoho Bosatsu金剛業（ごう）菩薩→Kongogo Bosatsu</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Godai Bosatsu enshrined at the Lecture Hall of To-ji Temple consist of 5 Bosatsu statues, namely Kongouharamitsu, Kongosatta, Kongoho Bosatsu, Kongoho Bosatsu and Kongogo Bosatsu.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Godai Bosatsu enshrined at the Lecture Hall of To-ji Temple consist of 5 Bosatsu statues, namely Kongouharamitsu (Vajraparamita), Kongosatta (Vajrapani, the Diamond Being), Kongoho Bosatsu (Vajraratna Bodhisattava), Kongoho Bosatsu (Vajragarbha Bodhisattava) and Kongogo Bosatsu (Vajrakarma Bodhisattava).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>五仏（五智如来）と五大明王については日本国内に他にも造像例が多数あるが、金剛波羅蜜、金剛薩埵、金剛宝菩薩、金剛法菩薩、金剛業菩薩の組み合わせを五大菩薩として安置した例は他にほとんど知られず、その典拠は明らかでない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A lot of Gobutsu (Gochi-nyorai) and Godai Myoo are seen throughout Japan but Godai Bosatsu that combines Kongouharamitsu, Kongosatta, Kongoho Bosatsu, Kongoho Bosatsu and Kongogo Bosatsu is rarely enshrined at other temples than To-ji Temple and its authority is also unknown.</e>
<cmt>五仏→the Five Buddhas, Gobutsu[http://www.aisf.or.jp/%7Ejaanus/]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many Gobutsu (Gochi-nyorai) and Godai Myoo are seen throughout Japan but Godai Bosatsu which combine Kongouharamitsu, Kongosatta, Kongoho Bosatsu, Kongoho Bosatsu and Kongogo Bosatsu are only rarely enshrined at temples other than To-ji Temple and its authority is also unknown.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many Gobutsu (Gochi-nyorai) and Godai Myoo are seen throughout Japan but Godai Bosatsu which combine Kongouharamitsu, Kongosatta, Kongoho Bosatsu, Kongoho Bosatsu and Kongogo Bosatsu are only rarely enshrined at temples other than To-ji Temple and its authority is also unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>金剛頂経（密教の根本経典の1つ）、仁王経（仏教による国家鎮護を説いた経）などをもとに空海が独自に発案したものとも言われ、中国の唐時代の密教美術にその源を求める説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is commonly believed that Kukai created Godai Bosatsu by himself based on Kongocho-kyo Sutra (one of basic sutra of Esoteric Buddhism) and Nio-kyo Sutra (a sutra that advocates guarding the nation by Buddhism), but there is also a view that it is traceable to Esoteric Buddhism art during the era of Tang Dynasty, China.</e>
<cmt>金剛頂経→Kongocho-kyo Sutra仁王経→Nio-kyo Sutra唐時代→Tang Dynasty</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is commonly believed that Kukai created Godai Bosatsu by himself based on Kongocho-kyo Sutra (one of the basic sutra of Esoteric Buddhism) and Nio-kyo Sutra (a sutra that advocates guarding the nation by Buddhism), but there is also a view that it is traceable to Esoteric Buddhist art during the era of the Tang Dynasty in China.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is commonly believed that Kukai created Godai Bosatsu by himself based on Kongocho-kyo Sutra (or Vajrasekhara Sutra, one of the basic sutra of Esoteric Buddhism) and Nio-kyo Sutra (or the Sutra of Benevolent Kings, a sutra that advocates guarding the nation by Buddhism), but there is also a view that it is traceable to Esoteric Buddhist art during the period of the Tang Dynasty in China.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>東寺の五大菩薩のうち、金剛波羅蜜は、金剛界曼荼羅において大日如来の東西南北を囲む「四波羅蜜」のうちの筆頭とされる菩薩である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among five Bosatsu that make up Godai Bosatsu of To-ji Temple, Kongoharamitsu is the head Bosatsu of &quot;Shiharamitsu&quot; placed at at east, west, south and north of Dainichinyorai in Vajradhatumandala.</e>
<cmt>金剛界曼荼羅→Vajradhatumandala[http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110002662145/]四波羅蜜→Shiharamitsu, four paramita</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the five Bosatsu that make up Godai Bosatsu at To-ji Temple, Kongoharamitsu is the head Bosatsu &quot;Shiharamitsu&quot; placed at the east, west, south and north of Dainichinyorai in Vajradhatumandala.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among Godai Bosatsu at To-ji Temple, Kongoharamitsu is the head Bosatsu of &apos;Shiharamitsu&apos; (four paramita) placed at the east, west, south and north of Dainichinyorai in Vajradhatu Mandala.</e>
<cmt>用語を他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>金剛薩埵は、金剛界曼荼羅において、東方の・阿閦（あしゅく）如来の周囲に配される四親近菩薩（ししんごんぼさつ）の筆頭であり、同様に金剛宝菩薩、金剛法菩薩、金剛業菩薩はそれぞれ、南方・宝生如来、西方・阿弥陀如来、北方・不空成就如来の四親近菩薩の筆頭である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Vajradhatumandala, Kongosatta is the head of Shishingon Bosatsu placed around Ashuku-nyorai of east and similarly Kongoho Bosatsu, Kongoho Bosatsu and Kongogo Bosatsu are the heads of Shishingon Bosatsu placed around Hoshonyarai of south, Amidanyorai of west and Fukujoju-nyorai of north respectively.</e>
<cmt>阿?（あしゅく）如来→Ashuku-nyorai四親近菩薩（ししんごんぼさつ）→Shishingon Bosatsu宝生如来→Hoshonyarai[kotobank]阿弥陀如来→Amidanyorai不空成就如来→Fukujoju-nyorai</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Vajradhatumandala, Kongosatta is the head of the Shishingon Bosatsu placed around Ashuku-nyorai at the east and similarly Kongoho Bosatsu, Kongoho Bosatsu and Kongogyo Bosatsu are the heads of Shishingon Bosatsu placed around Hoshonyarai at the south, Amidanyorai at the west and Fukujoju-nyorai at the north, respectively.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Vajradhatu Mandala, Kongosatta is the head of the Shishingon Bosatsu placed around Ashuku-nyorai at the east and similarly Kongoho Bosatsu, Kongoho Bosatsu and Kongogyo Bosatsu are the heads of Shishingon Bosatsu (Four Attendant Bodhisattva) placed around Hosho Nyorai (Ratnasambhava) at the south, Amida Nyorai (Amitabha Tathagata) at the west and Fukujoju N-nyorai (Amoghasiddhi) at the north, respectively.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>こうして見ると、五大菩薩のそれぞれが五仏のうちの1体と対応していることが明らかである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the above, it is obvious that each of Godai Bosatsu corresponds to one of Gobutsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the above, it is obvious that each of the Godai Bosatsu corresponds to one of the Gobutsu.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the above, it is obvious that each of the Godai Bosatsu corresponds to one of the Gobutsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>密教では三輪身（さんりんじん）説といって、1つの「ほとけ」が自性輪身（じしょうりんじん）、正法輪身（しょうぼうりんじん）、教令輪身（きょうりょうりんじん）という3つの姿をとることが説かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanrinshin theory of Esoteric Buddhism advocates that &quot;Buddha&quot; has three figures called jishorinjin, shoborinjin and Kyoryorinjin.</e>
<cmt>三輪身（さんりんじん）→Sanrinshin, the three wheel-embodiments[http://www.aisf.or.jp/%7Ejaanus/]自性輪身（じしょうりんじん）→Jishorinjin, the &quot;embodiment of the wheel of own-nature&quot;[http://www.aisf.or.jp/%7Ejaanus/]正法輪身（しょうぼうりんじん）→Shoborinjin, shohorinjin, the &quot;embodiment of the wheel of the true Dhara&quot;[http://www.aisf.or.jp/%7Ejaanus/]教令輪身（きょうりょうりんじん）→Kyoryorinjin, embodiment of the wheel of injunction</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sanrinshin theory of Esoteric Buddhism advocates that &quot;Buddha&quot; has three figures called Jishorinjin, Shoborinjin and Kyoryorinjin.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sanrinshin (the three wheel-embodiments) theory of Esoteric Buddhism advocates that &apos;Buddha&apos; has three figures called Jishorinjin (embodiment of the wheel of own-nature), Shoborinjin (embodiment of the wheel of the true Dhara) and Kyoryorinjin (embodiment of the wheel of injunction).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>自性輪身とは真理や悟りの境地そのものであって五仏に相当し、正法輪身は真理を説く者、すなわち五大菩薩に相当し、教令輪身は説法によって教化されない者を力づくで導こうとする者で五大明王に相当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to this theory, Jishorinjin represents the truth and the state of enlightment itself and corresponds to Gobutsu, Shoborinjin represents the one preaching the truth and corresponds to Godai Bosatsu and Kyoryorinjin represents the one forcibly guiding people who cannot be educated by preaching and corresponds to Godai Myoo respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to this theory, Jishorinjin represents the truth and the state of enlightment itself and corresponds to Gobutsu, Shoborinjin represents the one preaching the truth and corresponds to Godai Bosatsu and Kyoryorinjin represents the one forcibly guiding people who cannot be educated by preaching and corresponds to Godai Myoo, respectively.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to this theory, Jishorinjin represents the truth and the state of enlightment itself and corresponds to Gobutsu, Shoborinjin represents the one preaching the truth and corresponds to Godai Bosatsu and Kyoryorinjin represents the one forcibly guiding people who cannot be educated by preaching and corresponds to Godai Myoo, respectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>東寺講堂の諸仏は、こうした密教の思想を立体的な彫像で表わした立体曼荼羅にほかならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Statues enshrined at the Lecture Hall of To-ji Temple make up a three dimensional mandara that represents such philosophy of Esoteric Buddhism in the form of three dimensional sculptures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Statues enshrined at the Lecture Hall of To-ji Temple make up a three dimensional mandara that represents such Esoteric Buddhist philosophy in the form of three dimensional sculptures.</e>
<cmt>Slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Statues enshrined at the Lecture Hall of To-ji Temple make up a three dimensional mandala that represents such Esoteric Buddhist philosophy in the form of three dimensional sculptures.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Authority(id:10737), PP-22(id:84562), 無空(id:17049), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Boca samba(id:137526), Chi-Ham(id:143515), Charenji(id:7908), Urania(id:7213), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>