<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>明恵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myoe</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myoe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myoe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>明恵（みょうえ、承安 (日本)3年1月8日 (旧暦)（1173年2月21日） - 寛喜4年1月19日 (旧暦)（1232年2月11日））は、鎌倉時代前期の華厳宗の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myoe (February 21, 1173 - February 11, 1232) was a Buddhist monk of Kegon Sect who was active in the early Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myoe (February 21, 1173 - February 11, 1232) was a Buddhist monk of Kegon Sect who was active in the early Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myoe (February 28, 1173 - February 18, 1232) was a Buddhist monk of Kegon Sect in the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し、表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>法諱は高弁（こうべん）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His dharma Imina was Koben.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His dharma Imina was Koben.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His hoi (imina (personal name) used by Buddhist priests) was Koben.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>明恵上人・栂尾上人とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also called Myoe Shonin or Toganoo Shonin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also called Myoe Shonin or Toganoo Shonin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also called Myoe Shonin or Toganoo Shonin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>平重国。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Shigekuni</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Shigekuni</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Shigekuni.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>母は湯浅宗重の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a daugter of Muneshige YUASA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was a daugter of Muneshige YUASA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of Muneshige YUASA.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>現在の和歌山県有田川町生まれ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in current Aritagawa-cho, Wakayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in the current Aritagawa-cho, Wakayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in the present Aritagawa-cho, Wakayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>4歳にして両親を失い、高雄山神護寺に文覚の弟子上覚を師として出家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He lost his parents when he was 4 years old and became the priest of Takaosan Jingo-ji Temple with Jokaku, a disciple of Bunkaku, being his mentor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He lost his parents when he was 4 years old and became the priest of Takaosan Jingo-ji Temple with Jokaku, a disciple of Bunkaku, being his mentor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He lost his parents when he was 4 years old and became the priest of Jingo-ji Temple on Mt. Takao with Jokaku, a disciple of Bunkaku, being his mentor.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>仁和寺‧東大寺で真言密教や華厳を学び、将来を嘱望されたが俗縁を絶ち紀伊国有田郡白上や同国筏立に遁世した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He studied Shingon Esoteric Buddhism and Kegon Sect at Ninna-ji Temple‧Toda-ji Temple and showed great promise as a priest, but he abandoned the connection with a secular society and lived in seclusion at Shirakami, Arita-gun in Kii-no-Kuni and Ikadachi in Kii-no-Kuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He studied Shingon Esoteric Buddhism and Kegon Sect at Ninna-ji Temple‧Toda-ji Temple and showed great promise as a priest, but he abandoned the connection with secular society and lived in seclusion at Shirakami, Arita-gun in Kii-no-Kuni and Ikadachi in Kii-no-Kuni.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He studied Shingon Esoteric Buddhism and Kegon Sect at Ninna-ji Temple and Toda-ji Temple and showed great promise as a priest, but he abandoned the connection with secular society and lived in seclusion at Shirakami, Arita-gun in Kii Province and Ikadachi in the same Province.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>釈迦への思慕の念が深く2度天竺（インド）へ渡ることを企画したが、春日明神の神託が在り断念した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As he yearned for Shaka very much, he planned to travel to India twice but finally gave up because of the oracle of Kasuga Myojin (the deity of Kasuga Shrine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As he yearned for Shaka very much, he twice planned to travel to India but finally gave up because of the oracle of Kasuga Myojin (the deity of Kasuga Shrine).</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As he yearned for Shakyamuni very much, he twice planned to travel to India but finally gave up because of the oracle of Kasuga Myojin (the deity of Kasuga Shrine).</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>1206年（建永元年）後鳥羽上皇から山城国栂尾（とがのお）を下賜されて高山寺を開山し、観行と学問にはげんだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1206, he founded Kozan-ji Temple when Toganoo of Yamashiro-no-Kuni was given to him by the retired Emperor Gotoba and strove for kangyo and study.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1206, he founded Kozan-ji Temple when Toganoo of Yamashiro-no-Kuni was given to him by the retired Emperor Gotoba and strove for kangyo and study.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1206, he founded Kozan-ji Temple when Toganoo of Yamashiro Province was given to him by the retired Emperor Gotoba and strove for kangyo (practice of observation and contemplation) and study.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>戒律を重んじ、念仏の信徒の進出に対抗し、顕密諸宗の復興に尽力した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He highly valued Buddhist precepts and endeavored for the restoration of Kenmitsu Buddhism against the increase of Buddhist invocation supporters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He highly valued Buddhist precepts and endeavored for the restoration of Kenmitsu Buddhism against the increase of Buddhist invocation supporters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He highly valued Buddhist precepts and endeavored for the restoration of kenmitsu (exoteric and Esoteric Buddhism) against the increase of nenbutsu (Buddhist invocation) supporters.</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>法然の浄土宗を批判した『摧邪輪（ざいじゃりん）』『四座講式』の著作や、40年にも及ぶ観行での夢想を記録した『夢記』などがあり、弟子の筆記による『却廃忘記』など数多くの著書がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He left many writings including &quot;Zaijarin&quot; and &quot;Shizakoshiki&quot;, both of which criticized Honen&apos;s Jodo Sect, &quot;Yumeki&quot;, which recorded dreams which he had during his 40 years&apos; kangyo, and &quot;Kyakuhaiboki&quot;, which was taken notes by his disciples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He left many writings including &quot;Zaijarin&quot; and &quot;Shizakoshiki&quot;, both of which criticized Honen&apos;s Jodo Sect, &quot;Yumeki&quot;, which recorded dreams which he had during his 40 years&apos; kangyo, and &quot;Kyakuhaiboki&quot;, which was taken in notes by his disciples.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He left many writings including &quot;Zaijarin&quot; (A Wheel for Pulverizing Heresy) and &quot;Shizakoshiki&quot; (a chant composed of four formulas), both of which criticized Honen&apos;s Jodo Sect, &quot;Yumeki,&quot; which recorded dreams which he had during his 40 years&apos; kangyo, and &quot;Kyakuhaiboki,&quot; which was taken in notes by his disciples.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>和歌もよくし家集『明恵上人和歌集』がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also excelled in waka(a 31-syllable Japanese poem) and &quot;Myoe Shonin Waka-shu&quot; is the collection of his waka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also excelled in waka(a 31-syllable Japanese poem) and &quot;Myoe Shonin Waka-shu&quot; is a collection of his waka.</e>
<cmt>slight modifcation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also excelled in waka (a 31-syllable Japanese poem) and &quot;Myoe Shonin Waka-shu&quot; is a collection of his waka.</e>
<cmt>半角カッコにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Ju214587(id:86742), Mooko(id:36162), 深志(id:34508), Ks8823(id:130146), Kstigarbha(id:13376), 代言人(id:33675), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), Hannah(id:15935), BitBucket(id:30999), Dignaaga(id:91287), Point136(id:211299), BAKU(id:55205), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>