<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>千観</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senkan (Dento Daihosshi)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senkan (Dento Daihosshi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senkan</e>
<cmt>(Dento Daihosshi) を削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>千観（せんかん、延喜18年（918年）- 永観元年12月13日 (旧暦)（984年1月18日））は、平安時代中期の天台宗の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senkan (918-January 23, 984) was a priest of Tendai Sect in the mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt>「永観元年12月13日 (旧暦)」＝グレゴリオ暦「西暦984年1月23日」、出典：http://maechan.net/kanreki</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senkan (918-January 23, 984) was a priest of the Tendai Sect in the mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Tendai&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senkan (918-January 23, 984) was a priest of the Tendai Sect in the mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>橘公頼の子・相模守橘敏貞を父とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Sagami no kami (governor of Sagami Province) TACHIBANA no Toshisada, a child of TACHIBANA no Kimiyori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was TACHIBANA no Toshisada who was the Sagami no Kami (governor of Sagami Province) and child of TACHIBANA no Kimiyori.</e>
<cmt>rearranged sentence to read more smoothly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was TACHIBANA no Toshisada who was the Sagami no Kami (governor of Sagami Province) and child of TACHIBANA no Kimiyori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>園城寺に入って出家、受戒。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became a priest at Onjo-ji Temple and received religious precepts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senkan entered the priesthood at Onjo-ji Temple and vowed to follow the precepts..</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senkan entered the priesthood at Onjo-ji Temple and received the religious precepts.</e>
<cmt>受戒用語集の表記に従い、vowed to follow the precepts.. をreceived the religious precepts. に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>行誉（一説によれば運昭）に師事して天台教学を学んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He learned about the Tendai Sect under Gyoyo (Unsho according to another account).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He learned about the Tendai Sect under Gyoyo (Unsho according to another account).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He learned about the Tendai Sect under Gyoyo (Unsho according to another account).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>後に空也の影響を受けて浄土教へ傾倒し、民衆教化のための和讃としてはじめての阿弥陀和讃をつくった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward, he was influenced by Kuya to be devoted to Jodo (Pure Land) sect and prepared Praise of Amida as the first Wasan (Japanese hymns) for popular edification.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later on he was influenced by Kuya and devoted himself to the Jodo (Pure Land) sect and prepared the &quot;Praise of Amida&quot; as the first Wasan (Japanese hymn) to educate the masses.</e>
<cmt>&quot;popular edification&quot; was not easy for me to understand, so I changed &quot;民衆教化&quot; to &quot;educate the masses&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later on he was influenced by Kuya and devoted himself to the Jodo (Pure Land) sect and prepared the &quot;Praise of Amida&quot; as the first Wasan (Japanese hymn) to educate the masses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>962年（応和2年）に摂津国箕面山に隠遁して浄土行の生活を送った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He started to live in Mt. Mino, Settsu Province in retirement in 962 and trained himself in Jodo practices.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 962, he secluded himself on Mt. Mino in the Settsu Province and trained in Jodo practices.</e>
<cmt>For &quot;隠遁&quot; I changed from &quot;retirement&quot; to &quot;secluded himself&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 962, he secluded himself on Mt. Mino in the Settsu Province and trained in Jodo practices.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>963年（応和3年）勅命により祈雨を祈願し奇瑞を現したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 963, he prayed for rain by an Imperial order and reportedly made Kizui (auspicious omen) happen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By imperial command in 963, he prayed for rain and allegedly made a Kizui (auspicious omen) occur.</e>
<cmt>reportedly→allegedly; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By imperial command in 963, he prayed for rain and allegedly made a Kizui (auspicious omen) occur.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>応和宗論の論者として選ばれたが辞退し、摂津国金龍寺 (高槻市)（安満寺）を再興してそこに住した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he was selected as a debater for Owa shuron debate, he refused to accept it, and he revived Konryu-ji Temple in Settsu Province (Takatsuki City) (Ama-dera Temple), where he lived in.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senkan was selected to debate for discourses on Owa Shuron, but declined the offer and went to revive the Konryu-ji Temple in the Settsu Province (Takatsuki City) (Ama-dera Temple) where he lived.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senkan was selected to debate for discourses on Owa Shuron, but declined the offer and went to revive the Konryu-ji Temple in the Settsu Province (Takatsuki City) (Ama-dera Temple) where he lived.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>970年（天禄元年）行誉から三部大法を伝授されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was instructed on three divisions of the great pantheon from Gyoyo in 970.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 970 he was initiated by Gyoyo on the three divisions of the great pantheon.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 970 he was initiated by Gyoyo on the three divisions of the great pantheon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>常に念仏者の規範である八誓十願の教えを広め、浄土教の信者集団を作った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He always tried to spread Hassei Jugan teachings which was the standard for Nenbutsu (Buddhist invocation) devotees and formed Jodo-sect-believer groups.</e>
<cmt>「八誓十願」は、読み方が不明で、常識的と思われる読み方をローマ字化しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was always spreading the Hassei Jugan teachings, which were the standard for Nenbutsu (Buddhist invocation) devotees, and formed Jodo-sect-believer groups.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was always spreading the Hassei Jugan teachings, which were the standard for Nenbutsu (Buddhist invocation) devotees, and formed Jodo-sect-believer groups.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), 浩(id:70121), Y.Sanada(id:36926), Andee(id:20421), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), 流れ星(id:124374), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>