<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>常行三昧堂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jogyo Zanmai-do Hall</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jogyo Zanmai-do Hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jogyo Zanmai-do Hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>常行三昧堂（じょうぎょうざんまいどう）とは、天台宗において四種三昧のうち常行三昧の行を修するために建てられた仏堂である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jogyo zanmai-do hall is a type of Buddhist hall built to perform the jogyo zanmai which is one of the Shishuzanmai (the four kinds of samadhi) of the Tendai sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jogyo zanmai-do hall is a type of Buddhist hall built to perform the jogyo zanmai which is one of the Shishuzanmai (the four kinds of samadhi) of the Tendai sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jogyo zanmai-do hall is a type of Buddhist hall built to perform the jogyo zanmai which is one of the Shishuzanmai (the four kinds of samadhi) of the Tendai sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>常行堂とも称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called jogyo-do hall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called jogyo-do hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called Jogyo-do hall.</e>
<cmt>Jogyo大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>阿弥陀如来を本尊とするが、信仰の対象として建てられた阿弥陀堂と異なり常行三昧行を修するための仏堂である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the Amida Nyorai (Amitabha Tathagata) is placed as the honzon (principal object of worship at a temple), this hall is not an Amida-do hall for the Amida worship, but an hall for the purpose of exercise of the jogyo zanmai-gyo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the Amida Nyorai (Amitabha Tathagata) is placed as the honzon (principal object of worship at a temple), this hall is not an Amida-do hall for the Amida worship, but an hall for the purpose of exercise of the jogyo zanmai-gyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the Amida Nyorai (Amitabha Tathagata) is placed as the honzon (principal object of worship at a temple), this hall is not an Amida-do hall for the Amida worship, but an hall for the purpose of exercise of the Jogyo zanmai-gyo.</e>
<cmt>Jogyo大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>このことから、比叡山延暦寺をはじめとする天台宗の修行道場をおく寺院に建てられることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore this type of hall was often built in the Tendai sect temple having ascetic exercise halls such as the Enryaku-ji Temple on Mt. Hiei.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore this type of hall was often built in the Tendai sect temple having ascetic exercise halls such as the Enryaku-ji Temple on Mt. Hiei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore this type of hall was often built in the Tendai sect temple having ascetic exercise halls such as the Enryaku-ji Temple on Mt. Hiei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>日本における常行三昧堂については、851年（仁寿元年）円仁が比叡山に建立したものが始まりとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that the first jogyo zanmai-do hall in Japan was built by Ennin in 851 at the Mt. Hiei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that the first jogyo zanmai-do hall in Japan was built by Ennin in 851 at the Mt. Hiei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that the first Jogyo zanmai-do hall in Japan was built by Ennin in 851 at the Mt. Hiei.</e>
<cmt>Jogyo大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>構造</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Construction</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Construction</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Construction</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>常行三昧堂では、90日間阿弥陀如来の周囲を念仏を唱えつつ、また心に阿弥陀如来を念じながら歩く常行三昧の行を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the jogyo zanmai-do hall, the jogyo zanmai exercise is performed which is to walk around the Amida Nyorai during 90 days with praying to Amida Buddha and revering the Amida Nyorai in mind.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the jogyo zanmai-do hall, the jogyo zanmai exercise is performed which involves walking around the Amida Nyorai for 90 days while praying to Amida Buddha and revering the Amida Nyorai in mind.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Jogyo zanmai-do hall, the Jogyo zanmai exercise is performed which involves walking around the Amida Nyorai for 90 days while praying to Amida Buddha and revering the Amida Nyorai in mind.</e>
<cmt>Jogyo大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>このことから、常行三昧堂は堂の中心に阿弥陀如来を安置した方形の堂であり、屋根は宝形造が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For that reason, most of the halls are in a square shape, the Amida Nyorai is placed at the center of the hall and the roof is hogyo-zukuri style (all the roof ridges gathering at the center).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For that reason, most of the halls are square shaped, the Amida Nyorai is placed at the center of the hall and the roof is hogyo-zukuri style (all the roof ridges gathering at the center).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For that reason, most of the halls are square shaped, the Amida Nyorai is placed at the center of the hall and the roof is hogyo-zukuri style (all the roof ridges gathering at the center).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>常行三昧とともに天台宗の重要な行とされる法華三昧を修するための堂である法華堂とともに建てられることある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It may built along with a hokke-do hall which is a type of Buddhist hall built to perform the Hokke-zanmai (Dharma-Lotus Samadhi) exercise which is an important exercise of the Tendai sect along with the jogyo zanmai.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It may built along with a hokke-do hall which is a type of Buddhist hall built to perform the Hokke-zanmai (Dharma-Lotus Samadhi) exercise which is an important exercise of the Tendai sect along with the jogyo zanmai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It may built along with a hokke-do hall which is a type of Buddhist hall built to perform the Hokke-zanmai (Dharma-Lotus Samadhi) exercise which is an important exercise of the Tendai sect along with the Jogyo zanmai.</e>
<cmt>Jogyo大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>両堂を廊下で結んで「荷い堂」（にないどう）とも称されることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These halls connected together with a corridor are often called &quot;Ninai-do hall.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These halls connected together with a corridor are often called &quot;Ninai-do hall.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These halls connected together with a corridor are often called &quot;Ninai-do hall.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 与左衛門(id:159462), Volfgang(id:98768), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>