<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>蓮淳</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Renjun</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Renjun</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Renjun</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>蓮淳（れんじゅん、寛正5年（1464年） - 天文 (元号)19年8月18日 (旧暦)（1550年9月28日））、は室町時代・戦国時代 (日本)の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Renjun (1464 - September 28, 1550) was a monk in the Muromachi period and the Sengoku period (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Renjun (1464 - October 8, 1550) was a priest in the Muromachi period and the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し、統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Renjun (1464 - October 8, 1550) was a priest in the Muromachi period and the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>浄土真宗の第8世蓮如の6男として、蓮祐を母として産まれ、幼名を光徳といい、諱を兼誉と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the sixth son of the eighth Rennyo of the Jodo Shinshu Sect (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) and Renyu, mother, and had the childhood name of Kotoku and the real personal name of Kanetaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the sixth son of the eighth Rennyo of Jodo Shinshu sect (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) and Renyu, mother, and had the childhood name of Kotoku and the real personal name of Kanetaka.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the sixth son of the eighth Rennyo of Jodo Shinshu sect (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) and Renyu, mother, and had the childhood name of Kotoku and the real personal name of Kanetaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>兄実如の命により、大津近松の顕証寺に入り、伊勢国長島（三重県桑名市長島）の願証寺を創建する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At his elder brother Jitsunyo&apos;s command, Renjun entered Kensho-ji Temple in Otsu Chikamatsu and established Gansho-ji Temple in Nagashima, Ise Province (Nagashima, Kuwana City, Mie Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At his older brother Jitsunyo&apos;s command, Renjun entered Kensho-ji Temple in Otsu Chikamatsu and established Gansho-ji Temple in Nagashima, Ise Province (Nagashima, Kuwana City, Mie Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At his older brother Jitsunyo&apos;s command, Renjun entered Kensho-ji Temple in Otsu Chikamatsu and established Gansho-ji Temple in Nagashima, Ise Province (Nagashima, Kuwana City, Mie Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>後に河内国の顕証寺_(八尾市)・光応寺に住まいした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later he lived in Kensho-ji Temple (Yao City) and Koo-ji Temple in Kawachi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later he lived in Kensho-ji Temple (Yao City) and Koo-ji Temple in Kawachi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later he lived in Kensho-ji Temple (Yao City) and Koo-ji Temple in Kawachi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>北陸地方に拠点があった他の兄弟と違って畿内を拠点にしていたこと、実如の同母弟であったことから自然と実如の相談役となり、その後継者として予定されていた円如を娘婿とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Renjun based in Kinai region unlike others of his brothers who had their footholds in Hokuriku region and he was a younger maternal half-brother of Jitsunyo, so Renjun naturally became Jitsunyo&apos;s adviser and accepted Ennyo, who had been intended to be Jitsunyo&apos;s successor, as a son-in-law married to his daughter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Renjun based in Kinai region unlike others of his brothers who had their footholds in Hokuriku region and he was a younger maternal half-brother of Jitsunyo, so Renjun naturally became Jitsunyo&apos;s adviser and accepted Ennyo, who had been intended to be Jitsunyo&apos;s successor, as a son-in-law married to his daughter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Renjun based in Kinai region unlike others of his brothers who had their footholds in Hokuriku region and he was a younger maternal half-brother of Jitsunyo, so Renjun naturally became Jitsunyo&apos;s adviser and accepted Ennyo, who had been intended to be Jitsunyo&apos;s successor, as a son-in-law married to his daughter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>円如は若くして没したものの、娘は後の本願寺10世証如を生んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Ennyo died young, Renjun&apos;s daughter gave birth to a baby who later became Shonyo, the 10th chief priest of Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Ennyo died young, Renjun&apos;s daughter gave birth to a baby who later became Shonyo, the 10th chief priest of Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Ennyo died young, Renjun&apos;s daughter gave birth to a baby who later became Shonyo, the 10th chief priest of Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>主に、近江国・伊勢国・河内の教団発展に努力し、実如の死の際には共通の孫にあたる証如を託され、幼少の法主の後見人として本願寺内部で大きな発言権を持ち、指導的な役割を果した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Renjun worked hard for the development of the religious community in Omi Province, Ise Province and Kawachi Province, and when Jitsunyo died, Renjun was entrusted with the care of Shonyo, the grandson of both these brothers, and exerted leadership with his powerful voice within Hongan-ji Temple as the guardian of the future head of the sect in his childhood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Renjun worked hard for the development of the religious community in Omi, Ise, and Kawachi Provinces, and when Jitsunyo died, Renjun was entrusted with the care of Shonyo, the grandson of both these brothers, and exerted leadership with his powerful voice within Hongan-ji Temple as the guardian of the future head of the sect in his childhood.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Renjun worked hard for the development of the religious community in Omi, Ise, and Kawachi Provinces, and when Jitsunyo died, Renjun was entrusted with the care of Shonyo, the grandson of both these brothers, and exerted leadership with his powerful voice within Hongan-ji Temple as the guardian of the future head of the sect in his childhood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>各地の戦国大名に対抗して教団の統率力を高めた事は評価されるものの、後に驕りから顕証寺と布教地域が重複していた教団内の有力寺院である堅田本福寺_(大津市)に3度（1518年・1527年・1532年）も無実の罪を着せて破門するなどの専横を見せるようになった（破門は本来法主にしか許されていなかったが、蓮淳は証如の後見人としての職務代行を利用して破門を行った）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While his efforts in enhancing the religious community&apos;s leadership against Sengoku feudal lords in various places were appreciated, Renjun later turned tyrannical out of arrogance, falsely charging and excommunicating three times (in 1518, 1527 and 1532) Katada Honpuku-ji Temple (Otsu City), which was an influential temple within the religious community and had fields of propagation overlapping those of Kensho-ji Temple (originally only the head of the sect was allowed to pronounce excommunication, but Renjun took advantage of the vicarious execution of duties as the guardian of Shonyo and thus pronounced excommunication).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While his efforts in enhancing the religious community&apos;s leadership against Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period) in various places were appreciated, Renjun later turned tyrannical out of arrogance, falsely charging and excommunicating three times (in 1518, 1527 and 1532) Katada Honpuku-ji Temple (Otsu City), which was an influential temple within the religious community and had fields of propagation overlapping those of Kensho-ji Temple (originally only the head of the sect was allowed to pronounce excommunication, but Renjun took advantage of the vicarious execution of duties as the guardian of Shonyo and thus pronounced excommunication).</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While his efforts in enhancing the religious community&apos;s leadership against Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period) in various places were appreciated, Renjun later turned tyrannical out of arrogance, falsely charging and excommunicating three times (in 1518, 1527 and 1532) Katada Honpuku-ji Temple (Otsu City), which was an influential temple within the religious community and had fields of propagation overlapping those of Kensho-ji Temple (originally only the head of the sect was allowed to pronounce excommunication, but Renjun took advantage of the vicarious execution of duties as the guardian of Shonyo and thus pronounced excommunication).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>この横暴ぶりに対して一族や地方の門徒が激しく反発するようになり、やがて享禄・天文の乱と呼ばれる内紛のきっかけを作ったのみならず、この内紛で対立した実の兄弟（蓮如の諸子息）やその家族の処刑・追放を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Renjun&apos;s oppression incurred rebellions by his family and relatives and followers in the provinces, and this not only triggered an internal conflict called the Kyoroku-Tenbun War, but also led to the execution and banishment of his own brothers (Rennyo&apos;s sons) and their families who confronted against Renjun in the internal conflict.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Renjun&apos;s oppression incurred rebellions by his family and followers in the provinces, and this not only triggered an internal conflict called the Kyoroku-Tenbun War, but also led to the execution and banishment of his own brothers (Rennyo&apos;s children) and their families who confronted against Renjun in the internal conflict.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Renjun&apos;s oppression incurred rebellions by his family and followers in the provinces, and this not only triggered an internal conflict called the Kyoroku-Tenbun War, but also led to the execution and banishment of his own brothers (Rennyo&apos;s children) and their families who confronted against Renjun in the internal conflict.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また、この乱に関連して細川晴元によって山科本願寺を焼き討ちにされた際に孫である証如を置き去りにして、息子実恵 (浄土真宗)がいる願証寺に戻った事も非難の的になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In connection with this war, Renjun was also condemned for having left his grandson Shonyo behind when Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple was burned down by Harumoto HOSOKAWA and having then returned to Gansho-ji Temple where his son Jichie (or Jitsue) (Jodo Shinshu Sect) was there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In connection with this war, Renjun was also condemned for having left his grandson Shonyo behind when Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple was burned down by Harumoto HOSOKAWA and having then returned to Gansho-ji Temple where his son Jichie (also known as Jitsue) (Jodo Shinshu sect) was.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In connection with this war, Renjun was also condemned for having left his grandson Shonyo behind when Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple was burned down by Harumoto HOSOKAWA and having then returned to Gansho-ji Temple where his son Jichie (also known as Jitsue) (Jodo Shinshu sect) was.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>それでも証如の祖父・蓮淳に対する信頼は絶対的であり、蓮淳も証如が没する4年前まで長寿を保った事から証如の法主時代の本願寺は事実上蓮淳によって統治されていたとまで言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Despite that, Shonyo had complete trust in his grandfather Renjun and Renjun secured longevity until four years before Shonyo&apos;s death, so it is even said that Hongan-ji Temple was virtually controlled by Renjun while Shonyo was the head of the sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Despite that, Shonyo had complete trust in his grandfather Renjun who secured longevity until four years before Shonyo&apos;s death, so it is even said that Hongan-ji Temple was virtually controlled by Renjun while Shonyo was the head of the sect.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Despite that, Shonyo had complete trust in his grandfather Renjun who secured longevity until four years before Shonyo&apos;s death, so it is even said that Hongan-ji Temple was virtually controlled by Renjun while Shonyo was the head of the sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 マイコン坊主(id:338), Asura2007(id:78364), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>