<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>百万遍念仏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hyakumanben Nenbutsu (One Million Prayers to the Buddha)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hyakumanben Nenbutsu (One Million Prayers to the Buddha)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hyakumanben Nenbutsu</e>
<cmt>タイトルですので、補足を削除して統一しています。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>百万遍念仏（ひゃくまんべんねんぶつ）とは、自身の往生、故人への追善、各種の祈祷を目的として念仏を百万回唱えること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hyakumanben Nenbutsu is to repeat nenbutsu (Buddhist invocation) for a million times for the purposes of one&apos;s own birth in the Pure Land, ceremony as a memorial, and other variety of prayer.</e>
<cmt>念仏は、定訳のほかにローマ字読みnenbutsuを訳出し、以後文中ではローマ字読みとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hyakumanben Nenbutsu is to repeat nenbutsu (Buddhist invocation) for a million times for the purposes of one&apos;s own birth in the Pure Land, ceremony as a memorial, and other variety of prayer.</e>
<cmt>&quot;ceremony as a memorial&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hyakumanben Nenbutsu is to repeat nenbutsu (Buddhist invocation) for a million times for the purposes of one&apos;s own birth in the Pure Land, ceremony as a memorial, and other variety of prayer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>本来は、個人が念仏を7日間（もしくは10日間）のうちに100万回唱えることで目的が成就されるとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally it is said that an objective may be achieved if one repeats nenbutsu for a million times in seven (or ten) days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally it is said that an objective may be achieved if one repeats nenbutsu for a million times in seven (or ten) days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally it is said that an objective may be achieved if one repeats nenbutsu for a million times in seven (or ten) days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>ただし、複数の人間が同時同音で念仏を唱えることによって互いの念仏の功徳を融通することが出来るとする考え方もある（例えば、10人が10万回の念仏を同時に唱えることが出来れば、10×10万＝100万となり100万回念仏を唱えたのと同じ効果があるとするものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also an idea that kudoku (merit) of nenbutsu of other people can be interchanged among several people when they pray nenbutsu simultaneously in the same words (for example, if ten people repeat nenbutsu for a hundred thousands times it will have the equal effect as a million times of nenbutsu of one person (10 x 100,000 =1,000,000).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also an idea that kudoku (merit) of nenbutsu of other people can be interchanged among several people when they pray nenbutsu simultaneously in the same words (for example, if ten people repeat nenbutsu for a hundred thousands times it will have the equal effect as a million times of nenbutsu by one person (10 x 100,000 =1,000,000)).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also an idea that kudoku (merit) of nenbutsu of other people can be interchanged among several people when they pray nenbutsu simultaneously in the same words (for example, if ten people repeat nenbutsu for a hundred thousands times it will have the equal effect as a million times of nenbutsu by one person (10 x 100,000 =1,000,000)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>→融通念仏）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">See Yuzu Nenbutsu.</e>
<cmt>用語集訳のカッコ内はnenbutsuが初出の場合の説明書きとみなし、ここでは省きました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">See Yuzu Nenbutsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">See Yuzu Nenbutsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また、念仏の際に数取りのために大型の数珠をこすり合わせながら行う場合もある（複数で行う場合には数珠も揃える必要がある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some cases this is done rubbing big juzu (beadroll) together to count number while repeating nenbutsu (when done by several people they need to have the same juzu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some cases this is done by rubbing big juzu (beadroll) together to count the number while repeating nenbutsu (when done by several people they need to have the same juzu).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some cases this is done by rubbing big juzu (beadroll) together to count the number while repeating nenbutsu (when done by several people they need to have the same juzu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>この際に用いられる数珠を百万遍数珠と呼ぶ場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The juzu which is used in such a case is sometimes called Hyakumanben Juzu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The juzu which is used in such a case is sometimes called Hyakumanben Juzu.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The juzu which is used in such a case is sometimes called Hyakumanben Juzu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>百万遍念仏と極楽往生を結びつけた最初の人物は唐の迦才であると言われている（『浄土論』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first person who related Hyakumanben Nenbutsu and gokuraku ojo (peaceful death) is said to be Kasai of Tang (&quot;Jodo-ron&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first person who related Hyakumanben Nenbutsu and gokuraku ojo (peaceful death) is said to be Kasai of Tang (&quot;Jodo-ron&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first person who related Hyakumanben Nenbutsu and gokuraku ojo (peaceful death) is said to be Kasai of Tang (according to &quot;Jodo-ron&quot; (the Pure Land Treatise written by Kasai)).</e>
<cmt>浄土論　の補足を追加しｈました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>日本にも平安時代に伝来され、浄土教の流行とともに盛んになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was introduced into Japan in the Heian period, and became widespread along with popularization of Jodo (Pure Land) sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was introduced into Japan in the Heian period, and became widespread along with popularization of the Jodo (Pure Land) sect.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was introduced into Japan in the Heian period, and became widespread along with popularization of the Jodo (Pure Land) sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>元弘元年（1331年）、後醍醐天皇の命を受けた善阿 (浄土宗)が7日間にわたって百万遍念仏を行って達成させ、疫病を鎮めたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1331, Zen&apos;a completed Hyakumanben Nenbutsu in seven days with by command of Emperor Godaigo to control an epidemic.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1331, Zen&apos;a completed Hyakumanben Nenbutsu in seven days with by command of Emperor Godaigo to control an epidemic.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1331, a priest called Zena (Jodo sect) completed Hyakumanben Nenbutsu in seven days by command of Emperor Godaigo to control an epidemic and succeeded in ending it.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>彼が居住した知恩寺の別名「百万遍」はその時の褒賞として授けられた寺号である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hyakumanben&quot;, a byname of Chion-ji Temple where he lived, is jigo (literally, &quot;temple name&quot;), which is the title given to a Buddhist temple, as an award at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hyakumanben&quot;, a byname of Chion-ji Temple where he lived, is jigo (literally, &quot;temple name&quot;), which is the title given to a Buddhist temple, as an award at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The jigo (temple name) called &apos;Hyakumanben,&apos; which is a byname of Chion-ji Temple where he lived, is the title given to a Buddhist temple, as an award at that time.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>室町時代から戦国時代 (日本)にかけて宮中から地方の村々の間にまで百万遍念仏が広まり、宮中では1・5・9月の16日に行われることになっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Muromachi period to Sengoku period, Hyakumanben Nenbutsu spread from imperial court to rural villages, and it was a rule in imperial court to do Hyakumanben Nenbutsu on 16th of January, May, and September.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Muromachi period to Sengoku period, Hyakumanben Nenbutsu spread from imperial court to rural villages, and it was a rule in the Imperial court to do Hyakumanben Nenbutsu on 16th of January, May, and September.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Muromachi period to Sengoku period (period of warring states) (Japan), Hyakumanben Nenbutsu spread from Imperial Court to rural villages, and it was a rule in the Imperial Court to do Hyakumanben Nenbutsu on 16th of January, May, and September.</e>
<cmt>戦国時代　の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>伏見宮貞成親王は日記『看聞日記』の中で百万遍念仏の目的を「過去追善 現在祈祷」と端的に記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Fushiminomiya Sadafusa in his diary &quot;Kanmon Nikki&quot; wrote the purpose of Hyakumanben Nenbutsu plainly as &quot;ceremony for the past and prayer for the present&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Fushiminomiya Sadafusa in his diary &quot;Kanmon Nikki&quot; wrote the purpose of Hyakumanben Nenbutsu to be plainly as &quot;ceremony for the past and prayer for the present&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Fushiminomiya Sadafusa in his diary &quot;Kanmon Nikki&quot; wrote the purpose of Hyakumanben Nenbutsu to be plainly as &apos;ceremony for the past and prayer for the present.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>今日でも日本の寺院や地域の間において、鎮魂・追善・豊穣・除災などを目的として百万遍念仏を行われる事例がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today there are cases of Hyakumanben Nenbutsu in the temples and some regions in Japan for the purposes of repose of souls, ceremony as a memorial, fertility, and prevention of disasters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today there are cases of Hyakumanben Nenbutsu in the temples and some regions in Japan for the purpose of reposing souls, ceremony as a memorial, fertility, and prevention of disasters.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today there are cases of Hyakumanben Nenbutsu in the temples and some regions in Japan for the purpose of reposing souls, ceremony as a memorial, fertility, and prevention of disasters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mooko(id:36162), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>