<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>生長の家宇治別格本山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seicho no Ie Ujibekkakuhonzan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seicho no Ie Ujibekkakuhonzan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seicho no Ie Uji Bekkaku Honzan</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>生長の家宇治別格本山（せいちょうのいえうじべっかくほんざん）は京都府宇治市にある宝蔵神社を中心とする生長の家の別格本山。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seicho no Ie Ujibekkakuhonzan is the bekkaku honzan (special head temple) of Seicho no Ie that centered around Hozo Shrine in Uji City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seicho no Ie Ujibekkakuhonzan is the bekkaku honzan (special head temple) of Seicho no Ie, which is centered around Hozo Shrine in Uji City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seicho no Ie Uji Bekkaku Honzan is the bekkaku honzan (special head temple) of Seicho no Ie, which is centered around Hozo-jinja Shrine in Uji City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>昭和35年に落慶。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The temple was built in 1960.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The temple was built in 1960.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The temple was built in 1960.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>宝蔵神社の本尊神霊（祭神）は生長の家大神・大国主大神・観世音菩薩・地蔵大菩薩・阿弥陀如来である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The enshrined deity of Hozo Shrine are the Great God of Seicho no Ie, Okuni nushi no okami (the great god of Earth), Kanzeon Bosatsu (the Buddhist Goddess of Mercy), Jizo Daibosatsu, and Amidanyora (Amitabha Tathagata).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The enshrined deities of Hozo Shrine are the Great God of Seicho no Ie, Okuni nushi no okami (Great God of the earth), Kanzeon Bosatsu (the Buddhist Goddess of Mercy), Jizo Daibosatsu and Amidanyora (Amitabha Tathagata).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The enshrined deities of Hozo-jinja Shrine are the Great God of Seicho no Ie, Okuni nushi no okami (Great God of the earth), Kanzeon Bosatsu (the Buddhist Goddess of Mercy), Jizo Dai Bosatsu (Great Jizo Bodhisattva; Guardian Deity of Children) and Amida Nyorai (Amitabha Tathagata).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>先祖供養・永代供養・流産児供養など、教団内では霊供養の場所として知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is known within the religious group as the place to hold memorial services for spirits, such as the ancestor, eitaikuyo (services held on the anniversaries of the dead and other special occasions for a long period in charge of a temple), and unborn babies due to miscarriage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is known within the religious group as the place in which to hold memorial services for spirits such as ancestors, eitaikuyo (services held on the anniversaries of the dead who were for long periods in charge of a temple, and other occasions), and unborn babies due to miscarriage.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is known within the religious group as the place in which to hold memorial services for spirits such as ancestors, eitaikuyo (services held on the anniversaries of the dead who were for long periods in charge of a temple, and other occasions), and unborn babies due to miscarriage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>永代祭祀されると霊宮聖使命菩薩としてまつられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once the perpetual religious service was held, he or she was worshipped as Reiguseishimei Bosatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once the perpetual religious service was held, he or she was worshipped as Reiguseishimei Bosatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once the perpetual religious service was held, he or she was worshipped as Reigu Seishimei Bosatsu.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>神癒祈願が行われる施設の一つでもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of the facilities where Shinyu Kigan (praying to God for healing) was held.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s one of the facilities in which Shinyu Kigan (prayer to God for healing) was held.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s one of the facilities in which Shinyu Kigan (prayer to God for healing) was held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>毎月、十数人の体験談を載せた体験談集「宝蔵」を発行している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The monthly &apos;Hozo&apos; (Treasure House) is published with the life experience stories of several dozen people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The monthly &apos;Hozo (Treasure House)&apos; is published with the life-experience stories of several dozen people.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The monthly &apos;Hozo (Treasure House)&apos; is published with the life-experience stories of several dozen people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>毎日聖経「甘露の法雨」が読誦される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Saint Sutra of &quot;Kanro no Hou&quot; is read out everyday.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Saint Sutra of &quot;Kanro no Hou&quot; is read aloud each day.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Saint Sutra of &apos;Kanro no Hou&apos; is read aloud each day.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="9">
<j>宇治川を挟んで向かいには宇治神社、宇治上神社、興聖寺がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uji Shrine, Ujikami Shrine, and Kosho-ji Temple are located opposite of Uji River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uji Shrine, Ujikami Shrine and Kosho-ji Temple are located opposite the Uji River.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uji-jinja Shrine, Uji kami-jinja Shrine and Kosho-ji Temple are located opposite the Uji-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>かつてこの一帯は南泉坊といわれ平等院の宝物を納めるところが幾つもあった「安養集」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The region here was once called as Nansebo and where &quot;Anyoshu&quot; that stored treasures of Byodo-in Temple was present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The region here was once called Nansebo and is where &quot;Anyoshu,&quot; which stored the treasures of Byodo-in Temple, was present.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The region here was once called Nansebo and is where &apos;Anyoshu,&apos; which stored the treasures of Byodo-in Temple, was present.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、別格本山とは別に総本山として長崎県西海市に「生長の家総本山」龍宮住吉本宮がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is &quot;Seicho no Iesohonzan&quot; Ryugusumiyoshihongu in Saikai City, Nagasaki Prefecture as the grand head temple different from bekkaku honzan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Seicho no Iesohonzan&quot; Ryugusumiyoshihongu in Saikai City, Nagasaki Prefecture, is the grand head temple, as distinguished from bekkaku honzan.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seicho no Ie Sohonzan&apos; Ryugu Sumiyoshi Hongu Shrine in Saikai City, Nagasaki Prefecture, is the grand head temple, as distinguished from bekkaku honzan.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>尚、ブラジルにも宝蔵神社（1957年落慶）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also Hozo Shrine in Brazil (completed in 1957).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also the Hozo Shrine in Brazil (completed in 1957).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also the Hozo-jinja Shrine in Brazil (completed in 1957).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="13">
<j>主な祭事</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main Festivals</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Main Festivals</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Main Festivals</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>霊宮聖使命菩薩・霊宮聖使命会員祥月命日供養祭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reiguseishimei Bosatsu and Reiguseishimei kaiin shotsuki meinichi kuyosai.</e>
<cmt>霊宮聖使命菩薩・霊宮聖使命会員祥月命日供養祭→Reiguseishimei Bosatsu and Reiguseishimei kaiin shotsuki meinichi kuyosai[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reiguseishimei Bosatsu and Reiguseishimei kaiin shotsuki meinichi kuyosai</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reigu Seishimei Bosatsu and Reigu Seishimei Kaiin Shotsuki Meinichi Kuyosai (the anniversaries of one&apos;s death after the first anniversary of members of Reigu Seishimei)</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>宝蔵神社月次祭・全国流産児無縁霊供養塔供養月次祭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hozo-jinja Getsujisai (monthly mass) and Zenkoku ryuzanji muenrei kuyotokuyo Getsujisai (monthly mass for aborted fetus).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hozo-jinja Getsujisai (monthly mass) and Zenkoku ryuzanji muenrei kuyotokuyo Getsujisai (monthly mass for aborted fetuses)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hozo-jinja Getsujisai (monthly mass) and Zenkoku ryuzanji muenrei kuyotokuyo Getsujisai (monthly mass for aborted fetuses)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>末一稲荷神社月次祭・精霊招魂神社月次祭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suekazu-inarijinja Shrine Getsujisai (monthly mass of Suekazu-inarijinja Shrine) and Seirei Shokon-jinja Shrine Getsujisai (monthly mass of Seirei Shokon-jinja Shrine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suekazu-inarijinja Shrine Getsujisai (monthly mass of Suekazu-inarijinja Shrine) and Seirei Shokon-jinja Shrine Getsujisai (monthly mass of Seirei Shokon-jinja Shrine)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suekazu Inari-jinja Shrine Getsujisai (monthly mass of Suekazu Inari-jinja Shrine) and Seirei Shokon-jinja Shrine Getsujisai (monthly mass of Seirei Shokon-jinja Shrine)</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nanashi-seicho(id:78183), Nnh(id:474), Qazzx(id:8772), Kstigarbha(id:13376), 16toki(id:60127), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>