<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>慈雲妙意</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jiun-Myoi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jiun-Myoi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jiun-Myoi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>慈雲妙意（じうんみょうい、文永11年（1274年） － 貞和元年/興国6年6月3日 (旧暦)（1345年7月2日））は、鎌倉時代後期から南北朝時代 (日本)にかけての臨済宗の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jiun-Myoi (born 1274, died June 3, 1345 (old lunar calender) July 2, 1345) was a priest in the Rinzai Sect from the latter part of the Kamakura Era to the Nanboku-cho Era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jiun-Myoi (born 1274, died June 3, 1345 (old lunar calender) July 2, 1345) was a priest in the Rinzai Sect from the latter part of the Kamakura Era to the Nanboku-cho Era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jiun-Myoi (1274 - July 10, 1345) was a priest of the Rinzai Sect from the latter part of the Kamakura period to the period of the Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>俗姓は平氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His original family name was TAIRA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His original family name was TAIRA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His original family name was Taira.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>諱は妙意。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His imina or posthumous name was Myoi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His imina or posthumous name was Myoi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His imina (posthumous name) was Myoi.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>道号は慈雲。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His pseudonym as a priest was Jiun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His pseudonym as a priest was Jiun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His dogo (a pseudonym as a priest) was Jiun.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>諡号は恵日聖光国師。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His shigo or posthumous title dedicated based on noble behaviors was Keijitsuseiko-kokushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His shigo or posthumous title, dedicated based on noble behavior, was Keijitsuseiko-kokushi.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His shigo (a posthumous name) was Keijitsu Seiko Kokushi.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>信濃国の出身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Shinano Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Shinano Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Shinano Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>15歳で越後国五智山で出家・得度し、その後下野国日光山、鎌倉建長寺・円覚寺を経た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After becoming a priest and entering the Buddhist priesthood at Gochi-san Mountain in Echigo Province at age 15, he gained experience at Nikko-zan Mountain in Shimotsuke Province as well as Kencho-ji Temple and Engaku-ji Temple in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対応</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After becoming a priest and entering the Buddhist priesthood at Gochi-san Mountain in Echigo Province at age 15, he gained experience at Nikko-zan Mountain in Shimotsuke Province as well as Kencho-ji Temple and Engaku-ji Temple in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After becoming a priest and entering the Buddhist priesthood at Mt. Gochi in Echigo Province at age 15, he gained experience at Mt. Nikko in Shimotsuke Province as well as Kencho-ji Temple and Engaku-ji Temple in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>能登国永光寺の瑩山紹瑾に参禅したのち、越中国二上山に草庵を結んでそこに住した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He practiced Zen meditation under Jokin KEIZEN at Eiko-ji Temple in Noto Province, and later made a thatched hut at Futakami-yama Mountain in Ecchu Province</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対応</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He practiced Zen meditation under Jokin KEIZEN at Eiko-ji Temple in Noto Province, and later made a thatched hut at Futakami-yama Mountain in Ecchu Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He practiced Zen meditation under Jokin KEIZEN at Eiko-ji Temple in Noto Province, and later made a thatched hut at Mt. Futakami in Etchu Province</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>孤峰覚明に師事してそれに従い、紀伊国無本覚心に参禅した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He studied under Kakumyo KOHO and accompanied his visit to Kakushin MUHON in Kii Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He studied under Kakumyo KOHO and accompanied his visit to Kakushin MUHON in Kii Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He studied under Kakumyo KOHO and accompanied his visit to Kakushin MUHON in Kii Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>1298（永仁6）年に覚心が没した後は、孤峰に従い出雲国雲樹寺でその印可を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Kakushin died in 1298, he accompanied Koho&apos;s visit to Unju-ji Temple in Izumo Province, where he was certified for enlightenment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Kakushin died in 1298, he accompanied Koho&apos;s visit to Unju-ji Temple in Izumo Province, where he was certified for enlightenment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Kakushin died in 1298, he accompanied Koho&apos;s visit to Unju-ji Temple in Izumo Province, where he was certified for enlightenment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>1327年（嘉暦2年）二上山に東松寺（現・国泰寺 (高岡市)）に住していたとき、後醍醐天皇からの諮問にこたえた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he was residing at Tosho-ji Temple (present-day Kokutai-ji Temple (Takaoka City)) in Nijo-zan Mountain in 1327, he responded the Emperor Godaigo&apos;s request for advice.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対応</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he was residing at Tosho-ji Temple (present-day Kokutai-ji Temple (Takaoka City)) in Nijo-zan Mountain in 1327, he responded to Emperor Godaigo&apos;s request for advice.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he was residing at Tosho-ji Temple (present-day Kokutai-ji Temple (Takaoka City)) on Mt. Nijo in 1327, he responded to Emperor Godaigo&apos;s request for advice.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その功により紫衣と清泉禅師の号を賜るとともに、国泰寺には官寺としての勅額を賜った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To honor his achievement, the Emperor gave sie or canonical purple robe and the pseudonym of Seisen-zenji to Jiun-Myoi, and designated Kokutai-ji Temple as a temple under government by the Emperor&apos;s own handwriting.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対応</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To honor his achievement, the Emperor gave sie, or a canonical purple robe, and the pseudonym of Seisen-zenji to Jiun-Myoi, and designated Kokutai-ji Temple as a temple under government by the Emperor&apos;s own handwriting.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To honor his achievement, the Emperor gave sie purple Buddhist priest stole), and the pseudonym of Seisen Zenji to Jiun-Myoi, and designated Kokutai-ji Temple as a temple under government by the Emperor&apos;s own handwriting.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>晩年に、光明天皇にも禅に関する諮問に答え、紫衣を授けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his later years, the Emperor Komyo gave him another sie to honor his advise concerning Zen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his later years, Emperor Komyo gave him another sie to honor his advice concerning Zen.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his later years, Emperor Komyo also gave him another sie to honor his advice concerning Zen.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>没後、光明天皇から「恵日聖光禅師」の号を贈られたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor Komyo gave the pseudonym of &apos;Keijitsuseiko-zenji&apos; after his death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor Komyo gave the pseudonym of &apos;Keijitsuseiko-zenji&apos; after his death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor Komyo gave the pseudonym of &apos;Keijitsuseiko Zenji&apos; after his death.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), 与左衛門(id:159462), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), Nighthawks(id:36125), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>