<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>天部</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tembu</e>
<cmt>天部（てんぶ、サンスクリット）→Tembu, Deities who reside in a heavenly realm, one of six realms in which the souls of living beings transmigrate from one to another[http://www.kcn-net.org/e_kama_history/glossary/glossary.htm]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tembu</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenbu (Celestial Beings)</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました（以下同様）。</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>天部（てんぶ、サンスクリット(deva））は、仏教における神々。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tembu (Sanskrit) means deities of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tembu (Sanskrit) means deities of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenbu (deva in Sanskrit) means deities of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変え、devaを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>ほとんどは、古代インドのバラモン教の神々が仏教に取り入れられ、仏教の守護神である護法善神となったものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of most of them are deities of Brahmanism in ancient India and lator on, they were introduced in Buddhism and became Goho Zenshin (good deities protecting dharma), guardian deities of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>護法善神→Goho Zenshin, good dieties protecting dharma[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of most of them are deities of Brahmanism in ancient India and lator on, they were introduced in Buddhism and became Goho Zenshin (good deities protecting dharma), guardian deities of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of most of them are deities of Brahmanism in ancient India and later on, they were introduced in Buddhism and became Goho Zenshin (good deities protecting dharma), guardian deities of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>天、天部神。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ten, Tembu-shin</e>
<cmt>天→Ten天部神→Tembu-shin</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ten, Tembu-shin</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ten (deity of heavenly realm), Tenbu-shin (Tenbu deity).</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>「天部」の語義</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Word meaning of &quot;Tembu&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Word meaning of &quot;Tembu&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Word Meaning of &apos;Tenbu&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション、用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>天部を単に天ともいうが、天部が住む世界も天 (仏教)（devaloka）と訳されるため、漢字圏ではしばしば混同される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Tembu is sometimes simply referred to as Ten, the world where Tembu resides in is also translated as Ten (Buddhism) (devaloka) and these two are often confused in Chinese character using regions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Tembu is sometimes simply referred to as Ten, the world where Tembu resides in is also translated as Ten (Buddhism) (devaloka) and these two are often confused in Chinese character using regions.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Tenbu is sometimes simply referred to as Ten, the world where Tenbu resides in is also translated as Ten (Buddhism) (devaloka) and these two are often confused in Chinese character using regions.</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>原語のデーヴァ (deva) は「神」に相当する語であるが、中国において「天」と訳され、日本語においてもそれが踏襲されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the term of deva in Sanskrit means &quot;deity&quot;, it was translated as &quot;Ten&quot; in China and Japanese language followed such translation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the term of deva in Sanskrit means &quot;deity&quot;, it was translated as &quot;Ten&quot; in China and the Japanese language followed such translation.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the term of deva in Sanskrit means &apos;deity,&apos; it was translated as &apos;Ten&apos; in China and the Japanese language followed such translation.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>「天部」の「部」は「部門」「グループ」というほどの意味である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Chinese character of &quot;Bu&quot;, which makes up the term of &quot;Tembu&quot; together with the Chinese character of &quot;Ten&quot;, doesn&apos;t have significant meaning other than &quot;division&quot; or &quot;group&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Chinese character of &quot;Bu&quot;, which makes up the term of &quot;Tembu&quot; together with the Chinese character of &quot;Ten&quot;, doesn&apos;t have a significant meaning other than &quot;division&quot; or &quot;group&quot;.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Chinese character of &apos;Bu,&apos; which makes up the term of &apos;Tenbu&apos; together with the Chinese character of &apos;Ten,&apos; doesn&apos;t have a significant meaning other than &apos;division&apos; or &apos;group.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>したがって、「天」だけで意味が通じるはずだが、日本語では「天像」とは言わず「天部像」と言いならわしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, simply referring to as &quot;Ten&quot; ought to be enough for understanding but in Japanese, the term of &quot;Tembu image&quot; has been traditionally used instead of &quot;Ten image&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, simply referring to as &quot;Ten&quot; ought to be enough for understanding but in Japanese, the term &quot;Tembu image&quot; has been traditionally used instead of &quot;Ten image&quot;.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, simply referring to as &apos;Ten&apos; ought to be enough for understanding but in Japanese, the term &apos;Tenbu zo&apos; (image of Tenbu) has been traditionally used instead of &apos;Ten zo&apos; (image of Ten).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>なおdevaは天神、天人とも訳すが、その場合は多少ニュアンスが異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term of deva is also translated as Tenjin or Tennin, but in this case, the shades of meaning are different to a certain extent.</e>
<cmt>天神→Tenjin, heaven people天人→tennin, heavenly beings</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term of deva is also translated as Tenjin or Tennin, but in this case, the shades of meaning are different to a certain extent.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term of deva is also translated as Tenjin (heavenly deities) or Tennin (heavenly beings), but in this case, the shades of meaning are different to a certain extent.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>天部のルーツ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The roots of Tembu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The roots of Tembu</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Roots of Tenbu</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>天部諸尊のルーツである古代インドのバラモン教の神々は、宇宙の創造神から、悪霊鬼神の類に至るまでさまざまである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brahmanism deities in ancient India, the roots of deities of Tembu, include a wide variety of deities ranging from the deity of universe creation to those of evil spirit or demon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brahmanism deities in ancient India, the roots of deities of Tembu, include a wide variety of deities ranging from the deity of universe creation to those of evil spirits or demons.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brahmanism deities in ancient India, the roots of deities of Tenbu, include a wide variety of deities ranging from the deity of universe creation to those of evil spirits or demons.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>そのうちには、男性神（毘沙門天、大黒天など）、女性神（吉祥天、弁才天など）、貴紳形（梵天）、天女形（吉祥天）、力士形（金剛力士）、武将形（十二神将）など、さまざまな形態や性格のものを含む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These deities have various appearance and nature including Male deities (Bishamonten, Daikokuten etc.), female deities (Kisshoten, Benzaiten etc.), kishin-kei (Bonten), tennyo-kei (Kisshoten), rikishi-kei (Kongo-rikishi) and busho-kei (Juni Shinsho) etc.</e>
<cmt>毘沙門天→Bishamonten, Vaisravana[http://www.eudict.com/?lang=engjpk&amp;word=(Buddh)%20Vaisravana%20(Buddhist%20deity)]大黒天→Daikokuten吉祥天→Kisshoten, Kichijoten, Sri-mahadevi[http://www.eudict.com/?lang=engjpk&amp;word=(Buddh)%20Vaisravana%20(Buddhist%20deity)]弁才天→Benzaiten, Sarasvati. A Buddhist goddess of music, learning, eloquence, wealth, longevity, and protection from natural disasters梵天→Bonten, Brahma, A major Hindu deity thought to be responsible for creating the world[http://www.aisf.or.jp/~jaanus/deta/b/bonten.htm]金剛力士→Kongo-rikishi十二神将→Juni Shinsho, the twelve protective deities[http://www.aisf.or.jp/%7Ejaanus/]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These deities have various appearances and nature including male deities (Bishamonten, Daikokuten etc.), female deities (Kisshoten, Benzaiten etc.), kishin-kei (Bonten), tennyo-kei (Kisshoten), rikishi-kei (Kongo-rikishi) and busho-kei (Juni Shinsho) etc.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These deities have various appearances and nature including male deities (Bishamonten (Vaisravana), Daikokuten (Mahakala), and so on), female deities (Kisshoten (Laksmi), Benzaiten (Sarasvati, Buddhist goddess of music, learning, eloquence, wealth, longevity, and protection from natural disasters), and so on), type of kishin (nobles) (Bonten (Brahma, a major Hindu deity thought to be responsible for creating the world)), type of tennyo (a heavenly maiden) (Kisshoten), type of rikishi (strong men) Kongo Rikishi (protector deities) and type of busho (Japanese military commander) (Juni Shinsho (the twelve protective deities)), and so on.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>仏教の信仰・造像の対象となっている、広い意味での「仏」は、その由来や性格に応じ、「如来部」「菩薩部」「明王部」「天部」の4つのグループに分けるのが普通である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Buddha&quot; in broad terms that are the target of worshiping and making sculptures in Buddhism are generally categorized into four groups, namely &quot;Nyoraibu&quot;, &quot;Bosatsubu&quot;, myoobu&quot; and &quot;Tembu&quot;.</e>
<cmt>如来→Nyorai菩薩→Bosatsu, Bodhisattva明王→Myoo</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Buddha&quot; in broad terms that are the target of worshipping and making sculptures in Buddhism are generally categorized into four groups, namely &quot;Nyoraibu&quot;, &quot;Bosatsubu&quot;, &quot;Myoobu&quot; and &quot;Tembu&quot;.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddha&apos; in broad terms that are the target of worshipping and making sculptures in Buddhism are generally categorized into four groups, namely &apos;Nyorai-bu&apos; (group of Tathagata), &apos;Bosatsu-bu&apos; (group of Bodhisattva), &apos;Myoo-bu&apos; (group of Acala, one of the Five Wisdom Kings) and &apos;Tenbu&apos; (group of protesters of Buddhist laws).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変え、用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>「如来」とは「仏陀」と同義で「悟りを開いた者」の意、「菩薩」とは悟りを開くために修行中の者の意、なお、なお顕教では、十界を立てて本来は明王部を含まない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nyorai&quot; is equivalent to &quot;Buddha&quot; and means &quot;those who have attained enlightment&quot;, &quot;Bosatsu&quot; means those who are engaged in ascetic training in pursut of attaining enlightment and under exoteric Buddhism, Myoobu is not included basically because it holds Jikkai theory.</e>
<cmt>仏陀→Buddha顕教→exoteric Buddhism[英辞郎 on the WEB]十界→Jikkai, the Ten Realms</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nyorai&quot; is equivalent to &quot;Buddha&quot; and means &quot;those who have attained enlightment&quot;, &quot;Bosatsu&quot; means those who are engaged in ascetic training in pursut of attaining enlightment and under exoteric Buddhism, Myoobu is not included basically because it holds Jikkai theory.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nyorai&apos; is equivalent to &apos;Buddha&apos; and means &apos;those who have attained enlightment,&apos; &apos;Bosatsu&apos; means those who are engaged in ascetic training in pursuit of attaining enlightment and under Exoteric Buddhism, Myoo-bu is not included basically because it holds Jikkai (the Ten Realms) theory.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変え、補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>これに対し密教では、自性輪身・正法輪身・教令輪身の三輪身説を立てて、その中の「明王」は教令輪身で、如来の化身とされ、説法だけでは教化しがたい民衆を力づくで教化するとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Esoteric Buddhism holds Sanrinshin theory which asserts that Buddha has three figures of Jishorinjin, Shoborinjin and Kyoryorinjin and according to this theory, &quot;Myoo&quot; is considered as Kyoryorinjin, the incarnation of Nyorai, that forcibly guides people who cannot be educated by preaching only.</e>
<cmt>密教→Mikkyo, Esoteric Buddhism[http://www.koyasan.or.jp/english/shingonshu/mikkyo.html]自性輪身→jishorinjin, the &quot;embodiment of the wheel of own-nature&quot;[http://www.aisf.or.jp/%7Ejaanus/]正法輪身→shoborinjin, shohorinjin, the &quot;embodiment of the wheel of the true Dhara&quot;[http://www.aisf.or.jp/%7Ejaanus/]教令輪身→Kyoryorinjin, embodiment of the wheel of injunction三輪身→Sanrinshin, the three wheel-embodiments</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Esoteric Buddhism holds Sanrinshin theory which asserts that Buddha has three figures of Jishorinjin, Shoborinjin and Kyoryorinjin and according to this theory, &quot;Myoo&quot; is considered as Kyoryorinjin, the incarnation of Nyorai, that forcibly guides people who cannot be educated by preaching only.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Esoteric Buddhism holds Sanrinshin (the three wheel-embodiments) theory which asserts that Buddha has three figures of Jishorinjin (the embodiment of the wheel of own-nature), Shoborinjin (the embodiment of the wheel of the true Dhara) and Kyoryorinjin (the embodiment of the wheel of injunction) and according to this theory, &apos;Myoo&apos; is considered as Kyoryorinjin, the incarnation of Nyorai, that forcibly guides people who cannot be educated by preaching only.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変え、補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>そのため忿怒（ふんぬ）といって恐ろしい形相をしているものが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, many of Myoo sculptures have fierce facial expression called hunnu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, many Myoo sculptures have fierce facial expressions called hunnu.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, many Myoo sculptures have fierce facial expressions called hunnu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>以上3つのグループの諸尊に対して、「天部」に属する諸尊は、仏法の守護神・福徳神という意味合いが濃く、現世利益的な信仰を集めるものも多数存在している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrst with deities belonging to the above three groups, those belonging to &quot;Tembu&quot; carry the connotation of a guardian deity of Buddhism or a deity of fortune and many of them are the target of worship seeking worldly divine help.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast with deities belonging to the above three groups, those belonging to &quot;Tembu&quot; carry the connotation of a guardian deity of Buddhism or a deity of fortune and many of them are the target of worship seeking worldly divine help.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast with deities belonging to the above three groups, those belonging to &apos;Tenbu&apos; carry the connotation of a guardian deity of Buddhism or a deity of fortune and many of them are the target of worship seeking worldly divine help.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変え、表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>天部の諸尊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Deities belonging to Tembu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Deities belonging to Tembu</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Deities Belonging to Tenbu</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>天部の神を代表するものに、梵天、帝釈天、持国天・増長天・広目天・多聞天（毘沙門天）の四天王、弁才天（弁財天）、大黒天、吉祥天、韋駄天、摩利支天、歓喜天、金剛力士、鬼子母神（訶梨帝母）、十二神将、十二天、八部衆、二十八部衆などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Principal deities belonging to Tembu are Bonten, Taishakuten, Shitenno that consists of Jikokuten, Zochoten, Komokuten and Tamonten(Bishamonten), Benzaiten (Benzaiten), Daikokuten, Kisshoten, Idaten, Marishiten, Kangiten, kongorikishi, Kishimo-jin (Kariteimo), Junishinsho, Juniten (twelve deities), Hachibushu and Nijuhachibushu etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Principal deities belonging to Tembu are Bonten, Taishakuten, Shitenno that consists of Jikokuten, Zochoten, Komokuten and Tamonten(Bishamonten), Benzaiten (Benzaiten), Daikokuten, Kisshoten, Idaten, Marishiten, Kangiten, kongorikishi, Kishimo-jin (Kariteimo), Junishinsho, Juniten, Hachibushu and Nijuhachibushu etc.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Principal deities belonging to Tenbu are Bonten, Taishakuten (Sakra devanam Indra), Shitenno (four guardian kings) that consists of Jikokuten (Dhrtarastra), Zochoten (Virudhaka), Komokuten (Virupaksa) and Tamonten (Vaisravana) (Bishamonten (Vaisravana)), Benzaiten, Daikokuten (Mahakala), Kisshoten, Idaten (Kitchen God, Protector of Monasteries &amp; Monks) Marishiten (Goddess of Wealth &amp; Warrior Class), Kangiten (Nandikesvara, Ganesh in the Buddhist pantheon), Kongorikishi, Kishimo-jin (Goddess of Children) (Kariteimo), Junishinsho, Juniten (twelve deities), Hachi Bushu (or Eight Legions, Protectors of Buddhist Teachings) and Nijuhachi Bushu (The twenty-eight attendants of Senju Kannon), and so on.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>数尊を集めて護法や守護神的な威力を高めたものとして、四天王・八部衆・十二天・十二神将・二十八部衆などが挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shitenno, Hachibushu, Juniten, Junushinsho and Nijuhachibushu are known as the group of deities that aim to enhance the power of protecting Buddhism as guardian deities by gathering several deities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shitenno, Hachibushu, Juniten, Junushinsho and Nijuhachibushu are known as the group of deities that aim to enhance the power of protecting Buddhism as guardian deities by gathering several deities.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shitenno, Hachi Bushu, Juniten, Junishinsho and Nijuhachi Bushu are known as the group of deities that aim to enhance the power of protecting Buddhism as guardian deities by gathering several deities.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>安置形態としては、寺院の入口の門の両脇に安置される場合、本尊の周辺や仏壇の周囲に安置される場合などさまざまであり、毘沙門天、弁才天などは堂の本尊として安置され、崇敬の対象となっている場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These deities are enshrined in various places like at both sides of temple&apos;s entrance gate, nearby Honzon (principal image of Buddha) or or around Butsudan (Buddhist altar) but in the case of Bishamonten and Benzaiten, they are often enshrined as Honzon and are the target of worship.</e>
<cmt>本尊→Honzon, principal image of Buddha[Webster&apos;s Online Dictionary]仏壇→Butsudan, Buddhist alta</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These deities are enshrined in various places, for example at both sides of a temple&apos;s entrance gate, nearby Honzon (principal image of Buddha) or or around Butsudan (Buddhist altar) but in the case of Bishamonten and Benzaiten, they are often enshrined as Honzon and are the target of worship.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These deities are enshrined in various places, for example at both sides of a temple&apos;s entrance gate, nearby Honzon (principal image of Buddha) or around Butsudan (Buddhist altar) but in the case of Bishamonten and Benzaiten, they are often enshrined as Honzon and are the target of worship.</e>
<cmt>不要なor、スペースをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Vina-iwbot(id:56449), Boca samba(id:137526), M-Falcon(id:1227), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Urania(id:7213), McBot(id:159617), くっちゃめ(id:86793), あお。(id:39226), 無空(id:17049), Misakawa(id:208485), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>