<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>中書島</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chushojima</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chushojima (a place name in Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City)</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chushojima (a place name in Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>中書島（ちゅうしょじま）は京都市伏見区の地名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chushojima is a name of a place in Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chushojima is a name of a place in Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chushojima is a name of a place in Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>地名は官職の唐名である『中書省』に由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name was derived from &quot;Chushojo,&quot; the Chinese name for an official rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name was derived from &quot;Chushojo,&quot; the Chinese name for an official rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name was derived from &quot;Chushojo,&quot; the Chinese name for an official rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>桃山時代まで伏見港一帯は湿地であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until the Momoyama Period, the whole area of Fushimi Port had been a wetland.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until the Momoyama period, the whole area of Fushimi Port had been a wetland.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until the Momoyama period, the whole area of Fushimi Port had been a wetland.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>豊臣秀吉によって開発され武家屋敷が立ち並ぶようになったが江戸時代前期に荒廃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The area was developed by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and samurai residences had been built around, but it fell into ruin in the early Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The area was developed by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and samurai residences had been built around, but it fell into ruin in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The area was developed by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and samurai residences had been built around, but it fell into ruin in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その後、伏見城下にあった遊廓が移転され、繁栄するようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, the yukaku (a red-light district) which was located in the Fushimi castle was transferred in, and began to prosper.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, the yukaku (a red-light district) which was located in the Fushimi-jo Castle was transferred in, and began to prosper.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, the yukaku (a red-light district) which was located in the Fushimi-jo Castle was transferred in, and began to prosper.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>酒の名所である為に利用し遊びに来る人が多く、また、宇治川に近く、交通便の良い中書島は遊廓であると同時に花街でもあり、祇園甲部に凌ぐほどの名妓を輩出してきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Chushojo was a place famous for sake, there were many people who visited and made use of the yukaku, and because Chushojima was close to the Ujigawa River with good transportation facilities, it was both a yukaku and Hanamachi (geisha districts in Kyoto), and produced many famous geishas, almost exceeding Gion Kobu district.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since it was famous for sake, many people visited and made use of the yukaku there, and being close to the Uji-gawa River with good transportation facilities, Chushojima was both a yukaku and Hanamachi (geisha districts in Kyoto) and produced many famous geishas, almost exceeding Gion Kobu district.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since it was famous for sake, many people visited and made use of the yukaku there, and being close to the Uji-gawa River with good transportation facilities, Chushojima was both a yukaku and Hanamachi (geisha districts in Kyoto) and produced many famous geishas, almost exceeding Gion Kobu district.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>明治末期に京阪電気鉄道が開通し益々栄えてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The yukaku flourished even more when the Keihan Electric Railway opened in the end of Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The yukaku flourished even more when the Keihan Electric Railway opened in the end of Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The yukaku flourished even more when the Keihan Electric Railway opened in the end of Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>昭和初期では第16師団の将校、兵士にも利用され、1958年（昭和33年）3月15日、売春防止法によって遊廓としての役割を閉じ、花街のみとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early Showa era, Chushojima was utilized by the officers and soldiers of the 16th division of the Imperial Army, and in March 15, 1958, it finished its role as a yukaku due to the Anti-Prostitution Law, and only its role as Hanamachi remained.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early Showa period, Chushojima was utilized by the officers and soldiers of the 16th division of the Imperial Army, and in March 15, 1958, it finished its role as a yukaku due to the Anti-Prostitution Law, and only its role as Hanamachi remained.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early Showa period, Chushojima was utilized by the officers and soldiers of the 16th division of the Imperial Army, and in March 15, 1958, it finished its role as a yukaku due to the Anti-Prostitution Law, and only its role as Hanamachi remained.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>当初、転業にめぐってお茶屋派と学生相手の下宿派に別れ対立してきたが沈静化し、その後、徐々に衰退してくるようになり、1970年にその長い歴史に終止符を打った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, there were two groups, those that wanted to start a tea house and those that wanted to open an inn for students, that split and stood in conflict over the dispute in the change of trade, but it calmed down, and afterwards Chushojima gradually fell into decline and put an end to its long history in 1970.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To decide their next business, those who wanted to open ochaya (literally &quot;teahouse&quot; which refers to places where geisha entertain their guests) conflicted with those who wanted to rent rooms for students at first but it was settled, then Chushojima gradually fell into decline and put an end to its long history in 1970.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To decide their next business, those who wanted to open ochaya (literally &quot;teahouse&quot; which refers to places where geisha entertain their guests) conflicted with those who wanted to rent rooms for students at first but it was settled, then Chushojima gradually fell into decline and put an end to its long history in 1970.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>現在は普通の住宅地であり、僅かながら花街、遊廓時代の建物が残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the present-day, it is a normal residential area and although small in number, buildings from the days of Hanamachi and Yukaku are being kept.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the present-day, it is a normal residential area and although small in number, buildings from the days of Hanamachi and Yukaku are being kept.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the present-day, it is a normal residential area and although small in number, buildings from the days of Hanamachi and Yukaku are being kept.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>地理</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Geography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Geography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Geography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="13">
<j>現在の京阪中書島駅を中心とした地域であり、南北に竹田街道が通っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was an area around the present-day Keihan Chushojima Station, and the Takeda-kaido Road passes through north to south.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was an area centered in present-day Keihan Chushojima Station, and the Takeda-kaido Road passes through north to south.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was an area centered in present-day Keihan Chushojima Station, and the Takeda-kaido Road passes through north to south.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>四方を川（南は淀川、三方は濠川）に囲まれており、かつて島であった名残をとどめている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is circled all around in rivers (Yodo-gawa river in the south, and the Hori-kawa River in the remaining directions), leaving traces of which was once an island.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is circled all around in rivers (the Yodo-gawa river in the south, and the Hori-kawa River in the remaining directions), leaving traces of which was once an island.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is circled all around in rivers (the Yodo-gawa River in the south, and the Hori-kawa River in the remaining directions), leaving traces of which was once an island.</e>
<cmt>the Yodo-gawa river→the Yodo-gawa River</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Extrahitz(id:26245), Kansai explorer(id:48975), TTTNIS(id:169490), 今紫(id:9521), Tenori-on(id:296680), 樒(id:35770), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>