<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>住吉津</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suminoenotsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suminoenotsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suminoenotsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>住吉津（すみのえのつ）は、古代日本に存在した港である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suminoenotsu is the port which existed in ancient times in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suminoenotsu is a port which existed in ancient times in Japan.</e>
<cmt>the --&gt; a</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suminoenotsu is a port which existed in ancient times in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>この港を建設したのは仁徳天皇であるといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that this port was constructed by Emperor Nintoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that this port was constructed by Emperor Nintoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that this port was constructed by Emperor Nintoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>海の神である住吉大神を祀る住吉大社（大阪市住吉区）の南の住吉の細江と呼ばれた入り江にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suminoenotsu was located in the cove called Sumiyoshi no hosoe, the south of Sumiyoshi Taisha Shrine (Sumiyoshi Ward, Osaka City), which enshrines the sea god, Sumiyoshi Okami (the great gods of Sumiyoshi). (Currently, Sumiyoshi no hosoe becomes Hosoe River (alias), Hosoigawa station)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suminoenotsu was located in the cove called Sumiyoshi no hosoe, the south of Sumiyoshi Taisha Shrine (Sumiyoshi Ward, Osaka City), which enshrines the sea gods, Sumiyoshi Okami (the great gods of Sumiyoshi). (Currently, Sumiyoshi no hosoe is Hosoe River (alias), Hosoigawa station)</e>
<cmt>the sea god --&gt; the sea gods, becomes --&gt; is</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suminoenotsu was located in the cove called Sumiyoshi no hosoe, the south of Sumiyoshi Taisha Shrine (Sumiyoshi Ward, Osaka City), which enshrines the sea gods, Sumiyoshi Okami (the great gods of Sumiyoshi).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>（住吉の細江は、現在は細江川通称・細井川駅）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Currently, Sumiyoshi no hosoe is Hosoe River (alias), Hosoigawa station)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>住吉津から東へ向かうと、奈良盆地の飛鳥に至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If you go toward east from Suminoenotsu, you will get to Asuka in Nara Basin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If you go toward east from Suminoenotsu, you will get to Asuka in Nara Basin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If you go toward east from Suminoenotsu, you will get to Asuka in Nara Basin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>遣隋使や遣唐使は、住吉大社で住吉大神に祈りを捧げた後、住吉津から出発し、難波津を経由して現在で言うところの瀬戸内海（瀬戸内海の概念が生まれたのは明治期である）を九州へ向かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before Japanese envoys to Sui and Tong Dynasties China left from Suminoenotsu, they gave a prayer to Sumiyoshi Okami at Sumiyoshi Taisha Shrine, and went toward Kyushu through now called Seto Inland Sea (It was the Meiji Period when the idea of Seto Inland Sea came out.) via Naniwa no tsu (Naniwa Port).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before Japanese envoys to Sui and Tong Dynasties China left from Suminoenotsu, they gave a prayer to Sumiyoshi Okami at Sumiyoshi Taisha Shrine, and went toward Kyushu through currently called Seto Inland Sea (it was in the Meiji Period when the idea of Seto Inland Sea came out) via Naniwa no tsu (Naniwa Port).</e>
<cmt>It was the Meiji Period --&gt; it was in the Meiji Period</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before Japanese envoys to Sui and Tong Dynasties China left from Suminoenotsu, they gave a prayer to Sumiyoshi Okami at Sumiyoshi Taisha Shrine, and went toward Kyushu through currently called Seto Inland Sea (it was in the Meiji Period when the idea of Seto Inland Sea came out) via Naniwa no tsu (Naniwa Port).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>おとぎ話の「一寸法師」は、住吉の細江から出発し、住之江の海（現在で言うところの大阪湾）に出た後、淀川を上り、京都へ向かう話である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the fairy tale &quot;Issunboshi (The Inch-High Samurai)&quot;, after setting off from Suminoe no hosoe and got to sea of Suminoe, went up Yodo-gawa River toward Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fairy tale &quot;Issunboshi&quot; (The Inch-High Samurai) is a story in which Issunboshi sets off from Suminoe no hosoe, gets to the sea of Suminoe (present-day Oosaka bay), and then goes up the Yodo-gawa River toward Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fairy tale &quot;Issunboshi&quot; (The Inch-High Samurai) is a story in which Issunboshi sets off from Suminoe no hosoe, gets to the sea of Suminoe (present-day Oosaka bay), and then goes up the Yodo-gawa River toward Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Straysheep(id:42448), Reggaeman(id:6214), Hangbak(id:120071), Shimoxx(id:9332), Junger(id:10282), 沢田(id:40580), BAKU(id:55205), Peachkiller(id:99202), Suisui(id:69), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>