<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>舞鶴都市圏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maizuru urban area</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maizuru urban area</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maizuru urban area</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>舞鶴都市圏（まいづるとしけん）とは、舞鶴市を中心とした経済地域の総称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maizuru urban area collectively means an economic zone surrounding Maizuru City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maizuru urban area collectively means an economic zone surrounding Maizuru City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maizuru urban area collectively means an economic zone surrounding Maizuru City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>舞鶴経済圏とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Maizuru economic area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called Maizuru economic area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called Maizuru economic area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>北近畿の中心都市である舞鶴市を中核に、福井県（嶺南）大飯郡全域と綾部市、宮津市の一部などを含む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It embraces Maizuru City, which is the core city of Kita Kinki (Northern Kinki) region in center, whole area of Oi-gun (Reinan) in Fukui Prefecture, a part of Ayabe City, a part of Miyazu City and so forth.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It embraces Maizuru City, which is the core city of Kita Kinki (Northern Kinki) region in center, whole area of Oi-gun County (also referred as Reinan) in Fukui Prefecture, a part of Ayabe City, a part of Miyazu City and so on.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It embraces Maizuru City, which is the core city of Kita Kinki (Northern Kinki) region in center, whole area of Oi County (also referred as Reinan) in Fukui Prefecture, a part of Ayabe City, a part of Miyazu City and so on.</e>
<cmt>Oi-gun County→Oi County</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>その都市圏人口は約12万人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The population is about 120 thousand.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The urban area has a population of about 120,000.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The urban area has a population of about 120,000.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>人口集中地区人口は約7万人の経済都市圏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the economic urban area with a population of 70 thousand where the population is dense.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the economic urban area with a population of 70,000 in the densely-inhabited district.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the economic urban area with a population of 70,000 in the densely-inhabited district.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>特徴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Characteristics</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Characteristics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Characteristics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>都市圏の中心となるべき舞鶴市は高等学校等の教育機関が国立1校（舞鶴工業高等専門学校）、公立2校、私立1校と少ないため、統計上、昼間人口の吸収率は必ずしも高くない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maizuru City, the center of the urban area, has a few educational institutes including high schools, that is only one national high school (Maizuru National College of Technology), two public schools, and one private school, and consequently the daytime population is not necessarily large in statistics.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maizuru City, the center of the urban area, has a few educational institutes including high schools, that is only one national high school (Maizuru National College of Technology), two public schools, and one private school, and consequently the daytime population is not necessarily large in statistics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maizuru City, the center of the urban area, has a few educational institutes including high schools, that is only one national high school (Maizuru National College of Technology), two public schools, and one private school, and consequently the daytime population is not necessarily large in statistics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>それでも京都府中丹地方を統括する京都府中丹広域振興局や府北部唯一の社会保険事務所や近畿財務局、検察審査会等が立地、また京都地方裁判所舞鶴支部は北部４支部のなかで唯一、地裁の合議事件、実裁の少年事件を受け持つなど行政・司法の中心地である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Still it is the center of administration and judicature since it holds Kyoto Prefecture Chutan wide area Promotion Bureau which controls Chutan region, Kyoto Prefecture, the only social insurance office in the north of Kyoto prefecture, Kinki Finance Bureau, prosecution review commissions, and Kyoto District Court Maizuru Branch which is in charge of collegial affair of district court and juvenile delinquencies of family court.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Still it is the center of administration and judicature since it holds Kyoto Prefecture Chutan wide area Promotion Bureau which controls Chutan region, Kyoto Prefecture, the only social insurance office in the north of Kyoto Prefecture, Kinki Finance Bureau, prosecution review commissions, and Kyoto District Court Maizuru Branch is the only court among four branches in north which handles cases judging by collegiate court system in the district court and juvenile delinquencies of family court.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。補足し、表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Still it is the center of administration and judicature since it holds Kyoto Prefecture Chutan wide area Promotion Bureau which controls Chutan region, Kyoto Prefecture, the only social insurance office in the north of Kyoto Prefecture, Kinki Finance Bureau, prosecution review commissions, and Kyoto District Court Maizuru Branch is the only court among four branches in north which handles cases judging by collegiate court system in the district court and juvenile delinquencies of family court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>また造船・硝子といった日本でも有数の重厚長大産業の大規模工場も立地しており、雇用都市圏を形成している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, there locates large scale plants of Japan&apos;s leading heavy, thick, long and large industries such as shipbuilding and glass production, to make up Urban Employment Area (UEA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, there locates one of the large scale plants of Japan&apos;s leading heavy, thick, long and large industries such as shipbuilding and glass production, to make up Urban Employment Area (UEA).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, there locates one of the large scale plants of Japan&apos;s leading heavy, thick, long and large industries such as shipbuilding and glass production, to make up Urban Employment Area (UEA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>同時に、医療先進地として舞鶴医療センター（旧国立舞鶴病院）・舞鶴共済病院・舞鶴赤十字病院・市立舞鶴市民病院・自衛隊病院などの大規模病院があり、日常的に近隣市町村のみならず広域からの人口流入が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, as a medically advanced region, large hospitals, such as Maizuru Medical Center (former national Maizuru Hospital), Maizuru Kyosai Hospital, Maizuru Red Cross Hospital, Maizuru Municipal Hospital, and self-Defense Forces Maizuru Hospital attracting many people not only from the vicinity towns and villages but from a wide range of area on the routine basis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, as a medically advanced region, it has large hospitals, such as Maizuru Medical Center (former national Maizuru Hospital), Maizuru Kyosai Hospital, Maizuru Red Cross Hospital, Maizuru Municipal Hospital, and Self-Defense Forces Maizuru Hospital that result in a big population flow not only from the vicinity towns and villages but from a wide range of area on the routine basis.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, as a medically advanced region, it has large hospitals, such as Maizuru Medical Center (former national Maizuru Hospital), Maizuru Kyosai Hospital, Maizuru Red Cross Hospital, Maizuru Municipal Hospital, and Self-Defense Forces Maizuru Hospital that result in a big population flow not only from the vicinity towns and villages but from a wide range of area on the routine basis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="11">
<j>なお、軍港及び国際貿易港たる舞鶴港を有し、海上自衛隊舞鶴地方総監部や第八管区海上保安本部、国土交通省舞鶴港湾事務所など日本海広域を指揮監督する海事機関があるのも特徴の1つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another characteristic is that it has Maizuru Port, which is a naval port as well as an international trade port, therefore there exist maritime organizations to control and supervise a wide area of the Sea of Japan such as Maritime Self-Defense Force Maizuru District Headquarters, Maizuru Ports Office of the 8th Regional Coast Guard Headquarters, and Kinki Regional Development Bureau, Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Characteristically, it also has Maizuru Port which is a naval as well as international trade port, and maritime organizations to control and supervise a wide area of the Sea of Japan such as Maritime Self-Defense Force Maizuru District Headquarters, Maizuru Ports Office of the Eighth Regional Coast Guard Headquarters, and Kinki Regional Development Bureau, Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Characteristically, it also has Maizuru Port which is a naval as well as international trade port, and maritime organizations to control and supervise a wide area of the Sea of Japan such as Maritime Self-Defense Force Maizuru District Headquarters, Maizuru Ports Office of the Eighth Regional Coast Guard Headquarters, and Kinki Regional Development Bureau, Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="12">
<j>近年の動向</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Current Trend</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Current Trend</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Current Trend</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>都市圏の中心地となる舞鶴市は長らく軍事・行政の中心都市としての位置づけられてきたが、近年においては商業都市としても発展しつつある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maizuru City which is the center of the urban area has long been positioned as the central city for military and administration, and recently has been developing as a commercial city.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maizuru City which is the center of the urban area has long been positioned as the central city for military and administration, and recently has been developing as a commercial city.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maizuru City which is the center of the urban area has long been positioned as the central city for military and administration, and recently has been developing as a commercial city.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>2008年現在、北近畿では最大規模（売場面積：15,932㎡）の総合ショッピングセンター「らぽーる」（平成7年開業）や「バザールタウン舞鶴」（同11,874㎡、平成12年開業）、さとう舞鶴店（同7,703㎡）などが大型商業施設が立地。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 2008, large commercial centers have been built, for example, &quot;La Port&quot; (open in 1995) which is the largest scale of general shopping center in Northern Kinki (floor space:15,932 m2), &quot;Bazaar Town Maizuru&quot; (floor space: 11,874m2, open in 2000), and Sato, Maizuru (floor space: 7,703 m2).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As of 2008, large commercial centers have been built, including &apos;La Port&apos; (open in 1995) which is the largest scale of general shopping center in Kita Kinki (floor space: 15,932 square meters), &apos;Bazaar Town Maizuru&apos; (floor space: 11,874 square meters, open in 2000), and Sato, Maizuru (floor space: 7,703 square meters).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As of 2008, large commercial centers have been built, including &apos;La Port&apos; (open in 1995) which is the largest scale of general shopping center in Kita Kinki (floor space: 15,932 square meters), &apos;Bazaar Town Maizuru&apos; (floor space: 11,874 square meters, open in 2000), and Sato, Maizuru (floor space: 7,703 square meters).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また通称「京都府道28号小倉西舞鶴線」や国道27号を中心にベストワン舞鶴店（同2,396㎡、平成8年開業）や100満ボルト舞鶴店（同1,589㎡、平成8年開業）など郊外型大型店や洋服の青山やオートバックス、スシローなどロードサイド型店舗などが多数立地し、福井県や丹後地方からの近隣からの流入も増加している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also large suburban shopping centers have been built, for example, Best one Maizuru branch (floor space: 2,396㎡, open in 1996), and 100mv (2008 3Q Group) Maizuru branch (floor space:1,589㎡, open in 1996), as well as road-side stores such as Yofuku no Aoyama (Aoyama Trading Co., Ltd.), Autobacs Seven co., ltd., and AKINDO SUSHIRO CO.,LTD., mainly along the so-called &quot;Kyoto Prefectural Road 28 Kokura Nishi Maizuru Route&quot; and National Route 27, attracting more peaple from Fukui prefecture and Tango region.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also around the road commonly called &apos;Kyoto Prefectural Road 28 Kokura Nishi Maizuru Line&apos; and National Route 27, numerous shops have been built, such as large suburban shopping centers including Best one (an appliance store) Maizuru store (floor space: 2,396 square meters, open in 1996), and 100 man volt (an appliance store in 3Q Group) Maizuru store (floor space: 1,589 square meters, open in 1996), and road-side stores including Yofuku no Aoyama (a men&apos;s clothing store, Aoyama Trading Co., Ltd.), Autobacs Seven Co., Ltd. (an auto-supply shop), and AKINDO SUSHIRO CO., LTD. (a sushi restaurant), and they also lead to an increase in a population flow from nearby including Fukui Prefecture and Tango region.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also around the road commonly called &apos;Kyoto Prefectural Road 28 Kokura Nishi Maizuru Line&apos; and National Route 27, numerous shops have been built, such as large suburban shopping centers including Best one (an appliance store) Maizuru store (floor space: 2,396 square meters, open in 1996), and 100 man volt (an appliance store in 3Q Group) Maizuru store (floor space: 1,589 square meters, open in 1996), and road-side stores including Yofuku no Aoyama (a men&apos;s clothing store, Aoyama Trading Co., Ltd.), Autobacs Seven Co., Ltd. (an auto-supply shop), and AKINDO SUSHIRO CO., LTD. (a sushi restaurant), and they also lead to an increase in a population flow from nearby including Fukui Prefecture and Tango region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="16">
<j>商業統計に見る小売業の年間商品販売額は府北部では最大であり、京都府下でも京都市、宇治市に次いで第3位である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From a viewpoint of commercial statistics, its annual sales of the retailers is the largest in the northern prefecture and the third in Kyoto area following to Kyoto City and Uji City.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From a viewpoint of commercial statistics, its annual sales of the retailers is the largest in the northern prefecture and the third in Kyoto Prefecture following to Kyoto City and Uji City.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From a viewpoint of commercial statistics, its annual sales of the retailers is the largest in the northern prefecture and the third in Kyoto Prefecture following to Kyoto City and Uji City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>行政都市圏としてだけではなく、商業都市圏としての一面も垣間見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus we can see it has an aspect of not only administrative urban area but also commercial urban area.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus we can see it has an aspect of not only administrative urban area but also commercial urban area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus we can see it has an aspect of not only administrative urban area but also commercial urban area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="18">
<j>なお工業に関しては倉谷工業団地にケンコーマヨネーズ西日本工場が進出するなど明るい話題がある一方、大和紡績舞鶴工場が生産を中止するなどある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for manufacturing industry, the bright topic is that Kenko Mayonnaise Co., Ltd. branches out the western Japan factory in Kuratani Industrial Park, while the dark one is that DAIWABO CO.,LTD. discontinues its production at Maizuru factory.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for manufacturing industry, the bright topic is that Kenko Mayonnaise Co., Ltd. branches out the western Japan factory in Kuratani Industrial Park, while DAIWABO CO.,LTD. discontinues its production at Maizuru factory.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for manufacturing industry, the bright topic is that Kenko Mayonnaise Co., Ltd. branches out the western Japan factory in Kuratani Industrial Park, while DAIWABO CO.,LTD. discontinues its production at Maizuru factory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>工業統計における生産高も一進一退である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus industrial output in the industrial statistics is ever-changing.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus industrial output in the industrial statistics is ever-changing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus industrial output in the industrial statistics is ever-changing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>今後は国際貿易港たる舞鶴港を中心とした産業育成を急がれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the future industrial development should be hurried with Maizuru Port as an international trade port in center.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the future industrial development should be hurried with Maizuru Port as an international trade port in center.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the future industrial development should be hurried with Maizuru Port as an international trade port in center.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="21">
<j>産業</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Industry</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Industry</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Industry</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>日本海側でも有数の国際貿易港の舞鶴港を中心に重厚長大産業から成る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The industry of the Maizuru urban area is thick, long and large industries surrounding Maizuru port, which is Japan&apos;s leading international trade port.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The industry of the Maizuru urban area is heavy, thick, long and large industries surrounding Maizuru Port, which is one of the Japan&apos;s leading international trade ports on the Sea of Japan side.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is an area of heavy industries centering around Maizuru Port, which is one of the Japan&apos;s leading international trade ports on the Japan Sea side.</e>
<cmt>heavy, thick, long and large industries→heavy industries</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>工業製品出荷高は舞鶴市が約2,200億円となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The total industrial products of the Maizuru City amount to approximately 220 billion yen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The total industrial products of the Maizuru City amount to approximately 220 billion yen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The total industrial products of the Maizuru City amount to approximately 220 billion yen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="24">
<j>都市雇用圏（10%通勤圏）の変遷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Change in the Urban Employment Area (UEA) (10% commuting area)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Change in the Urban Employment Area (UEA) (10 percent commuting area)</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Change in the Urban Employment Area (UEA) (10 percent commuting area)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>金本良嗣・徳岡一幸によって提案された都市圏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">10% commuting area is the urban area proposed by Yoshitsugu KANEMOTO and Kazuyuki TOKUOKA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the urban area proposed by Yoshitsugu KANEMOTO and Kazuyuki TOKUOKA.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the urban area proposed by Yoshitsugu KANEMOTO and Kazuyuki TOKUOKA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>細かい定義等は都市雇用圏に則する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The full detail is in accordance with the Urban Employment Area (UEA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The full detail is in accordance with the Urban Employment Area (UEA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The full detail is in accordance with the Urban Employment Area (UEA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="27">
<j>一般的な都市圏の定義については都市圏を参照のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The general definition for the Urban Area, see the section of the Urban area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The general definition for urban area, see the section of the Urban area.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The general definition for urban area, see the section of the Urban area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="28">
<j>その他の北近畿の都市圏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other Urban Area of Kitakinki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other Urban Area of Kita Kinki</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other Urban Area of Kita Kinki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>北近畿地方は兵庫県、京都府の日本海側及び福井県嶺南地方の3県にまたがる事から横の繋がりは極めて希薄である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kitakinki region extends over three prefectures, namely Hyogo Prefecture, Kyoto Prefecture (the Sea of Japan side), and Reinan region, Fukui Prefecture, thus transverse communication across the prefectual border is quite poor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kita Kinki region extends over three prefectures, namely Hyogo Prefecture, the Sea of Japan side in Kyoto Prefecture, and Reinan region in Fukui Prefecture, thus transverse communication across the prefectural border is quite poor.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kita Kinki region extends over three prefectures, namely Hyogo Prefecture, the Sea of Japan side in Kyoto Prefecture, and Reinan region in Fukui Prefecture, thus transverse communication across the prefectural border is quite poor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>そのため舞鶴都市圏の他にも福知山市を商圏とする福知山都市圏、兵庫県但馬地方の中心都市である豊岡市を中核とする豊岡都市圏などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this, other than the Maizuru Urban area, there are Fukuchiyama urban area, trade area of which is Fukuchiyama city, and Toyooka urban area, which surrounds Toyooka City, the central city of Tajima district, Hyogo Prefecture in center.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this, other than the Maizuru urban area, there are some urban areas including Fukuchiyama urban area trading in Fukuchiyama City, and Toyoka urban area trading in Toyoka City, which is the center city of Tajima region in Hyogo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this, other than the Maizuru urban area, there are some urban areas including Fukuchiyama urban area trading in Fukuchiyama City, and Toyoka urban area trading in Toyoka City, which is the center city of Tajima region in Hyogo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>これらはそれぞれ独立して商圏を維持している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These two urban areas maintain their trade areas independently each other.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These two urban areas maintain their trade areas independently each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These two urban areas maintain their trade areas independently each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Yasu2006(id:93004), Dr jimmy(id:111486), DDR(id:27381), ぱむ(id:24323), 江口磐世☆(id:168037), Sea of Japan(id:3230), 樒(id:35770), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>