<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>六条河原</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rokujo-gawara</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rokujo-gawara</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rokujo-gawara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>六条河原（ろくじょうがわら）は、京都市内を流れる鴨川 (淀川水系)の河原に存在した刑場。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rokujo-gawara was an execution ground existing at the riverside of Kamogwa river (Yodogawa river system) running in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rokujo-gawara was used as an execution ground and located on the riverside of Kamogwa river (Yodogawa river system) running in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rokujo-gawara was used as an execution ground and located on the riverside of Kamogawa river (Yodogawa river system) running in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>古戦場。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a historic battlefield.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a historic battlefield.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a historic battlefield.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>古より時の権力者に反抗した政治犯たちが数多く処刑されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many political offenders protesting against then powerful persons were executed here from old times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Long ago, many political offenders were executed here who protested against those in power.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Long ago, many political offenders were executed here who protested against those in power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>保元の乱における源為義・平忠正、平治の乱における源義平・藤原信頼、源平合戦では平能宗、本能寺の変における斎藤利三、関ヶ原の戦いにおける石田三成・小西行長・安国寺恵瓊、大坂の役における長宗我部盛親・仙石秀範・豊臣国松らをはじめとする大阪方の残党など、著名な武将や政治家がここで最期の時を迎えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Famous busho (Japanese military commanders) and politicians who went to their fate included MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi and TAIRA no Tadamasa in the Hogen War, MINAMOTO no Yoshihira and FUJIWARA no Nobuyori in the Heiji War, TAIRA no Yoshimune in the Genpei War, Toshimitsu SAITO in the Honnoji Incident, Mitsunari ISHIDA, Yukinaga KONISHI and Ekei ANKOKUJI in the Battle of Sekigahra, and the remnants on the Osaka (Toyotomi) side including Morichika CHOSOKABE, Hidenori SENGOKU and Kunimatsu TOYOTOMI in the Siege of Osaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Famous busho (Japanese military commanders) and politicians who met their end here included MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi and TAIRA no Tadamasa in the Hogen War, MINAMOTO no Yoshihira and FUJIWARA no Nobuyori in the Heiji War, TAIRA no Yoshimune in the Genpei War, Toshimitsu SAITO in the Honnoji Incident, Mitsunari ISHIDA, Yukinaga KONISHI and Ekei ANKOKUJI in the Battle of Sekigahra, and the remnants from the Osaka (Toyotomi) side including Morichika CHOSOKABE, Hidenori SENGOKU and Kunimatsu TOYOTOMI in the Siege of Osaka.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Famous busho (Japanese military commanders) and politicians who met their end here included MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi and TAIRA no Tadamasa in the Hogen War, MINAMOTO no Yoshihira and FUJIWARA no Nobuyori in the Heiji War, TAIRA no Yoshimune in the Genpei War, Toshimitsu SAITO in the Honnoji Incident, Mitsunari ISHIDA, Yukinaga KONISHI and Ekei ANKOKUJI in the Battle of Sekigahara, and the remnants from the Osaka (Toyotomi) side including Morichika CHOSOKABE, Hidenori SENGOKU and Kunimatsu TOYOTOMI in the Siege of Osaka.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>いずれも処刑後、彼らの首級は三条大橋のたもとに晒されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the execution, all of their severed heads were exposed to the public display at the foot of Sanjo Ohashi Bridge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the execution, the severed heads were exposed for public display at the foot of Sanjo Ohashi Bridge.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the execution, the severed heads were exposed for public display at the foot of Sanjo Ohashi Bridge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>なお、平宗盛・平清宗親子は近江国で処刑された後、六条河原で首を晒されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After TAIRA no Munemori, and his son, TAIRA no Kiyomune, were executed in Omi Province, their severed heads were exposed to the public display at Rokujo-gawara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After TAIRA no Munemori, and his son, TAIRA no Kiyomune, were executed in Omi Province, the severed heads were exposed for public display at Rokujo-gawara.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After TAIRA no Munemori, and his son, TAIRA no Kiyomune, were executed in Omi Province, the severed heads were exposed for public display at Rokujo-gawara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 赤井彗星(id:18381), Blowback(id:173308), 歴史マニア(id:150945), 月夜野ほたる(id:7183), BitBucket(id:30999), Andee(id:20421), 小川尚明(id:93076), 立志堂(id:132177), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>