<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>長等山トンネル</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagarayama Tunnel</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagarayama Tunnel</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagarayama Tunnel</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>長等山トンネル（ながらやまトンネル）、長等トンネル（ながらトンネル）は、いずれも滋賀県大津市と京都府京都市山科区の間にある長等山（標高354メートル）に掘削されたトンネルである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both of Nagarayama Tunnel (長等山トンネル) and Nagara Tunnel (長等トンネル) are tunnels dug through Mount Nagara-yama (354m in height) between Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture and Yamashina Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both of Nagarayama Tunnel (長等山トンネル) and Nagara Tunnel (長等トンネル) are tunnels dug through Mount Nagara-yama (354m in height) between Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture and Yamashina Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both Nagarayama Tunnel and Nagara Tunnel are tunnels dug through Mt. Nagara (354 m in height) between Otsu City in Shiga Prefecture and Yamashina Ward in Kyoto City of Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>以下の2つがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are two tunnels as follows:</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処（前半の文章との続き具合からこの部分のみ切り離しました。）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are two tunnels as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The two tunnels are:</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>湖西線の長等山トンネル（湖西線の長等トンネルを参照）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagarayama Tunnel on the Kosei Line (See &apos;Nagara Tunnel on the Kosei Line&apos;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagarayama Tunnel on the Kosei Line (See &apos;Nagara Tunnel on the Kosei Line&apos;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagarayama Tunnel on the Kosei Line (See &apos;Nagara Tunnel on the Kosei Line&apos;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>琵琶湖西縦貫道路（国道161号）の長等トンネル（西大津バイパスの長等トンネルを参照）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagara Tunnel on Biwako nishi jukan road (Northern lake side bypass of National Route 161) (See &apos;Nagara Tunnel on Nishi-Otsu Bypass&apos;).</e>
<cmt>琵琶湖西縦貫道路（国道161号）→定訳不明：Biwako nishi jukan doro (Northern lake side bypass of National Route 161)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagara Tunnel on Biwako nishi jukan road (Northern lake side bypass of National Route 161) (See &apos;Nagara Tunnel on Nishi-Otsu Bypass&apos;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagara Tunnel on Biwako Nishi Jukan road (Northern lakeside bypass of National Route 161) (See &apos;Nagara Tunnel on Nishi-Otsu Bypass&apos;).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="5">
<j>なお、琵琶湖疏水（第1疏水）の第1トンネル（別名：長等山トンネル）についても、本項で記述する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The First Tunnel (also called Nagarayama Tunnel) of the Lake Biwa Canal (First Canal) is also touched on in this section.</e>
<cmt>琵琶湖疏水→the Lake Biwa Canal [http://www.a-rr.net/jp/observe/docs/09-0091.pdf]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The First Tunnel (also called Nagarayama Tunnel) of the Lake Biwa Canal (First Canal) is also touched on in this section.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The First Tunnel (also called Nagarayama Tunnel) of the Lake Biwa Canal (the Canal No. 1) is also described in this section.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>（琵琶湖疏水の第1トンネルを参照）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(See &apos;The First Tunnel of the Lake Biwa Canal&apos;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(See &apos;The First Tunnel of the Lake Biwa Canal&apos;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(See &apos;The First Tunnel of the Lake Biwa Canal&apos;.)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>湖西線の長等山トンネル</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagarayama Tunnel on the Kosei Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagarayama Tunnel on the Kosei Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagarayama Tunnel on the Kosei Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>西日本旅客鉄道湖西線の山科駅と大津京駅の間にある全長3,032mの鉄道トンネルで、山科側には3つの出口があるのに対し、途中で合流し大津京側の出口は1つとなる変形トンネルである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a 3,032 meters&apos; railway tunnel constructed between Yamashina Station and Otsukyo Station on the JR West Kosei Line, and while it has three exits on the Yamashina side, in the middle of the way, the tracks from each of these exits join together into one exit on the Otsukyo side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a 3,032 meters&apos; railway tunnel constructed between Yamashina Station and Otsukyo Station on the JR West Kosei Line, and while it has three exits on the Yamashina side, in the middle of the way, the tracks from each of these exits join together into one exit on the Otsukyo side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the railway tunnel constructed between Yamashina Station and Otsukyo Station on the JR West Kosei Line with the total length of 3,032 meters, having a special structure with three portals on the Yamashina side and one portal on the Otsukyo side and the tracks from the Yamashina side converged into one toward the Otsuryo side.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>1967年9月10日に着工、1971年4月16日に貫通し、湖西線開業の1974年から使用開始された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tunnel, whose construction started on September 10, 1967, passed completely through to the other side on April 16, 1971, and it started to be used in 1974, when the Kosei Line was inaugurated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tunnel construction started on September 10, 1967, passed completely through to the other side on April 16, 1971, and it started to be used in 1974, when the Kosei Line was inaugurated.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Construction started on September 10, 1967, completed on April 16, 1971, and the tunnel opened in 1974, when the Kosei Line was inaugurated.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>トンネルの出入口の両側はバラスト軌道であるが、トンネル内はスラブ軌道となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The both sides of the entry and exit points of the tunnel are equipped with the ballast track, while inside the tunnel the slab tracks are laid.</e>
<cmt>バラスト軌道→ballast track[英辞郎 on the WEB]　スラブ軌道→slab track [英辞郎 on the WEB]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both the entry and exit points of the tunnel are equipped with the ballast track, while inside the tunnel slab tracks are laid.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both the entry and exit points of the tunnel are ballast-tracked, while inside of the tunnel is slab-tracked.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>なお、トンネル自体は東海道本線（琵琶湖線）の逢坂山トンネルと同様に全区間が大津市内にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whole the section of the tunnel itself belongs to Otsu City, as well as Osakayama Tunnel (Biwako Line).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tunnel, and also the Osakayama Tunnel (Biwako Line), belong to Otsu City.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tunnel, and also the Osakayama Tunnel (Biwako Line), belong to Otsu City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>構造・線路配置</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structure and track allocation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structure and track allocation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structure and track allocation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>山科側の出口は3つであり、さらに新逢坂山トンネルの4つの出口と絡み合っていて複雑になっているため、ここでは山科駅からの線路配置についても説明する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As on the Yamashina side the tunnel has three exits, and these three exits together with the other four of Shin-osakayama Tunnel make the structure very complicated, the allocation of the tracks is explained, following the trajectory starting from Yamashina Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Yamashina side the tunnel has three exits, and these three exits together with the other four of the Shin-osakayama Tunnel make the structure very complicated, the allocation of the tracks is explained, following a trajectory starting from Yamashina Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These three portals of the Nagarayama tunnel on the Yamashina side and the four portals of the Shin-osakayama Tunnel make the structure very complicated; therefore, the allocation of the tracks from Yamashina Station is also explained here.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>山科駅〜山科側トンネル入口</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Yamashina Station to the tunnel entrance on the Yamashina Side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Yamashina Station to the tunnel entrance on the Yamashina Side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamashina Station and the tunnel entrance on the Yamashina Side</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>山科駅には線路が6線あり、北から順に琵琶湖線上り外側線、湖西線下り線、琵琶湖線上り内側線、琵琶湖線下り内側線、湖西線上り線、琵琶湖線下り外側線となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Yamashina Station, there are six lines as follows: from the north, the outer up line of the Biwako Line, down line of the Kosei Line, inner up line of the Biwako Line, Inner down line of the Biwako Line, the up line of the Kosei Line, outer down line of the Biwako Line.</e>
<cmt>上り線→up line[英辞郎 on the WEB] 下り線→down line[英辞郎 on the WEB] 外側線→定訳不明：outer line としました。内側線→定訳不明：inner lineとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At Yamashina Station, there are six lines as follows: from the north, the outer up line of the Biwako Line, down line of the Kosei Line, inner up line of the Biwako Line, Inner down line of the Biwako Line, the up line of the Kosei Line, outer down line of the Biwako Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At Yamashina Station, there are six tracks as follows: From north to south, Biwako Line (Outer track, westbound), Kosei Line (eastbound), Biwako Line (Inner track, westbound), Biwako Line (Inner track, eastbound), Kosei Line (westbound), and Biwako Line (Outer track, eastbound).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>同駅から（以下同じ）約500メートル離れた位置からは、湖西線下り線が上り18パーミル、湖西線上り線が上り16、琵琶湖線の4線が上り10の線形 (路線)勾配となり、湖西線が上層へ上がり高架線になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Starting from the position about 500m apart from the station (ditto with the explanations bellow), the gradient of the straight line (railway) becomes 18 per mil on the down line (track) of the Kosei Line, 16 per mil on the up line(of the Kosei Line, and 10 per mil on the four lines (tracks) of the Biwako Line, respectively, and thus the Kosei Line runs on the upper layer with elevated tracks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Starting from the position about 500m apart from the station (ditto with the explanations bellow), the gradient of the straight line (railway) becomes 18 per mil on the down line (track) of the Kosei Line, 16 per mil on the up line (of the Kosei Line, and 10 per mil on the four lines (tracks) of the Biwako Line, respectively, and thus the Kosei Line runs on the upper layer with elevated tracks.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Starting from a position about 500 m off the station (the same shall apply hereinafter) with a gradient of the straight line (railway) becomes 18 (in per mille) on the eastbound track of Kosei Line, 16 on the westbound track of Kosei Line, and 10 on the four tracks of Biwako Line, and thus the Kosei Line runs on elevated tracks.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>その後、約1,300m離れた位置で、湖西線下りの緩勾配の側線が琵琶湖線上り外側線から北側へ分岐する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, from the position about 1,300m, the slow grade side track of the down line of the Kosei Line diverges to the north of the outer up line of the Biwako Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterwards, from a position of about 1,300m, the slow grade side track of the down line of the Kosei Line diverges to the north of the outer up line of the Biwako Line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterwards, from a position of about 1,300 m, a gentle gradient sidetrack of the eastbound Kosei Line diverges to the north of the Outer eastbound Biwako Line.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>約1,600m離れた位置からは、湖西線と琵琶湖線の線路が交差し、湖西線下り線は下り11、湖西線上り線は上り1となり、約1,750m離れた位置に湖西線下り線・上り線のトンネル入口がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the point about 1,600m, the tracks of the Kosei Line start to intersect with those of the Biwako Line, and the upper and down lines of the Kosei Line proceed toward the respective exit located about 1,750m from the point, taking 11 downward gradient in case of the down line, and 1upward gradient in case of the up line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From a point of about 1,600m, the tracks of the Kosei Line start to intersect with those of the Biwako Line, and the up and down lines of the Kosei Line proceed toward the respective exit located about 1,750m from this point, with a 11 downward gradient for the down line, and 1upward gradient for the upper line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From a point of about 1,600 m, the tracks of the Kosei Line intersects the tracks of the Biwako Line, and Kosei Line tracks (westbound and eastbound) proceed toward portals for westbound and eastbound located about 1,750 m from this point, with a gradient of -11 for eastbound, and a gradient of 1 for westbound.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。数字の一部を全角から半角に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>なお、一番北側にある湖西線下りの緩勾配の側線は、1,640m離れた位置にトンネル入口がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The side track of the down line of the Kosei Line, which is running on the utmost north side, has its tunnel exit at the point of 1,640m away from the station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The side track of the Kosei down line, running on the utmost north side, has a tunnel exit at a point 1,640m from the station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The gentle gradient sidetrack of the Kosei eastbound track, running on the northmost track, encounters a tunnel portal 1,640 m off the station.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>湖西線下り線から分岐する緩勾配の側線は、勾配を緩和することで牽引定数を確保することで、重量のある列車が通過できるように設けられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The slow-grade side track diverging from the down line of the Kosei Line secures a certain nominal tractive capacity by lowering the gradient in order to enable the heavy-weighted trains pass through.</e>
<cmt>牽引定数→nominal tractive capacity[http://www.isok.jp/cgi-bin/rl_termn.cgi?_ke]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The slow-grade side track diverging from the Kosei down line secures a certain nominal tractive capacity by lowering the gradient in order to enable the heavy-weighted trains to pass through.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The gentle gradient sidetrack diverging from the westbound Kosei track secures a certain nominal hauling capacity by decreasing the gradient in order to enable heavy trains to pass through.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>湖西線下り列車は、普通列車・新快速などは下り線を通るが、特別急行列車・貨物列車などは側線を通る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the down trains running on the Kosei Line, local trains and Special Rapid trains go on the down line, but Limited Express trains and freight trains go through the side track.</e>
<cmt>新快速→Special Rapid (train)[http://www.rokko1go.jpn.org/main/photo/english/eng_jpnkind.htm] 貨物列車→freight trains[プログレッシブ和英辞典]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the down trains running on the Kosei Line, local trains and Special Rapid trains run on the down line, but Limited Express trains and freight trains run through the side track.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the eastbound tracks running on the Kosei Line, local trains and Special Rapid trains run on the eastbound tracks, and Limited Express trains and freight trains run through the sidetrack.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>なお、緩勾配の側線への分岐は制限速度60km/hとなっている（トンネル内の合流部（後述）も同様）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The limiting speed at the point of divergence to the slow-grade side track is 60km/h (the same limiting speed is applied at the joining point of the tracks inside the tunnel (described later)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The limiting speed at the point of divergence to the slow-grade side track is 60km/h (the same limiting speed is applied at the joining point of the tracks inside the tunnel (described later).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The speed limit at the point of divergence to the gentle gradient sidetrack is 60 km/h (the same speed limit is applied at the joining point of the tracks inside the tunnel (described later)).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>山科側トンネル入口〜大津京駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the entrance of the tunnel on the Yamashina side to Otsukyo Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the entrance of the tunnel on the Yamashina side to Otsukyo Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tunnel entrance on the Yamashina side and Otsukyo Station</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>下り線は、トンネル入口から（以下同じ）約300m進むと上り8となり、すぐに緩勾配の側線と合流する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The down line starts to have 8 permil gradient after going some 300m from the entrance of the tunnel (ditto with the explanations bellow), and soon joins the slow-grade side track.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The down line starts to have an 8 permil gradient after going some 300m from the entrance of the tunnel (ditto with the explanations bellow), and soon joins the slow-grade side track.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The eastbound track starts to have a gradient of 8 at about 300 m from the entrance of the tunnel (the same shall apply bellow), and immediately joins the gentle gradient sidetrack.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>その後、左線形 (路線)平面線形があり、約950mの位置から直線になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, there is a section formed of a left linear (railway) horizontal alignment, and at about 950m the trajectory becomes straight.</e>
<cmt>平面線形→horizontal alignment [英辞郎 on the WEB]　左線形 (路線)平面線形→定訳不明：left linear (railway) horizontal alignmentとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterwards, there is a section formed of a left linear (railway) horizontal alignment, and at about 950m the trajectory becomes straight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, there is a section formed with left (rail) alignment, and at about 950 m from there, the track becomes straight.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。ピリオドを打ちました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>約1,100mの位置で上り線のトンネルが右側から合流し、複線のトンネルになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At about 1,100m, the tunnel of the up line joins the down line coming from the right side, to make the tunnel double-tracked.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At about 1,100m, the tunnel of the up line joins the down line coming from the right side, to make a double-tracked tunnel.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At about 1,100 m, the tunnel of the westbound track joins the eastbound track coming from the right, to make a double-track tunnel.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>その後はしばらく直線が続いたあと、約1,900mの位置から上り2となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After a while, it goes on a straight line, and starts to have 2 per mil upward gradient from the point of about 1,900m.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After a while, it runs on a straight line, and starts to have a 2 per mil upward gradient from the point of about 1,900m.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, the tracks run on straight lines for a while, and starts running upward with a gradient of 2 from the point of some 1,900 m.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>約2,600mの位置から右カーブになり、山科駅から4,800mの位置に出口がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the point of about 2,600m it curves to the right hand until reaching the exit, which is 4,800m away from Yamashina Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the point of about 2,600m it curves to the right hand until reaching the exit, which is 4,800m away from Yamashina Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the point of some 2,600 m the tracks curve to the right hand until the portal which is 4,800 m off the Yamashina Station.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>出口を通過後に分岐器（両渡り線）があり、大津京駅に到達する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After passing the exit, there is a tounout (double crossing) and after crossing it, the line reaches Otsukyo</e>
<cmt>分岐器[http://www.isok.jp/cgi-bin/rl_term.cgi?%60tounout] 両渡り線double crossing [http://www.he.dion.ne.jo/ railfan/words/ta/words-ta.htm#w-cross]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After passing the exit, there is a tounout (double crossing) and after the crossing, the line reaches Otsukyo</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After passing the exit, there is a crossover turnout, then the tracks reach the Otsukyo Station.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="26">
<j>上り線は、下り線と分岐するまでは同じ複線のトンネルで、途中で下り8となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The upper line goes through the same double track tunnel until it diverged from the down line, and it starts to have 8 per mil downward gradient in the middle of the way.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The up line goes through the same double track tunnel until it diverges from the down line, and it starts to have an 8 per mil downward gradient midway.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The westbound track goes through the same double track tunnel until it diverges from the eastbound track, and it runs downward at a gradient of 8 midway.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>そして、トンネル入口から約1,800mの位置で、左カーブ（半径1,000m、反対側の下り線は直線）となり下り線と分岐する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, the line curves to the left-hand at the point of about 1,800m from the entrance of the tunnel (with radius 1,000m, while the down line on the opposite side maintains a straight line).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, the line curves to the left at a point about 1,800m from the entrance of the tunnel (with radius 1,000m, while the down line on the opposite side maintains a straight line).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The track curves to the left at a point about 1,800 m from the entrance of the tunnel with the radius 1,000 m, while the eastbound track on the opposite side maintains a straight line.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>その先に右カーブ（半径800m）があり、カーブの途中で下り18になったあとは直線のまま出口に至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Going ahead, there is a right-hand curve (800m in radius) and in the middle of the curve, the line comes to have 18 per mil downward gradient, and after the curve it proceeds straightforwardly to the exist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Going ahead, there is a right-hand curve (800m in radius) and in the middle of the curve, the line has an 18 per mil downward gradient, and beyond the curve it proceeds straightforwardly to the exit.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ahead, there is a right-hand curve with the radius 800 m, in the middle of which, the track runs downward at a gradient of 18, then beyond the curve, the track proceeds straight to the exit.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="29">
<j>上下線とも、大津京側の出口付近にあるカーブ（半径1,400m）の一部区間の制限速度は125km/h、上り線の山科側にあるカーブ（半径800m）の制限速度は115km/hである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the both of up and down lines, the limiting speed in a section within the curve (1,400m in radius) near the exit on the Otsukyo side is 125km/h, and that in the curve (800m in radius) on the up line on the Yamashiro side is 115km/h.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the both the up and down lines, the speed limit in the section within the curve (1,400m in radius) near the exit on the Otsukyo side is 125km/h, and in the curve (800m in radius) on the up line on the Yamashiro side, it is 115km/h.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On both of the westbound and eastbound tracks, the speed limit in the section within the curve with the radius 1,400 m near the exit on the Otsukyo side is 125 km/h, and the speed limit in the section within the curve with the radius 800 m of the westbound track on the Yamashiro side is 115 km/h.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="30">
<j>湖西線下り線と緩勾配の側線の合流部付近に信号機（第3日本の鉄道信号機閉塞信号機）があるが、どちらの線からも確認しやすい位置に設置されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Near the joining point of the down line and the slow-grade side track of the Kosei Line, there is a railroad signal (the 3rd Japanese railroad signal, block signal), which is located in a clearly visible place from the both line.</e>
<cmt>閉塞信号機→block signal [http://www.isok.jp/cgi-bin/rl_trem.cgi?%60blocksig] 第3日本の鉄道信号機閉塞信号機→定訳不明：the 3rd Japanese railroad signal, block signalとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Near the junction of the down line and the slow-grade side track of the Kosei Line, there is a railroad signal (the 3rd Japanese railroad signal, block signal), which is located in a clearly visible place seen from the both lines.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Near the junction of the eastbound track and the gentle gradient sidetrack of the Kosei Line, there is a railroad signal (the 3rd block signal) which is located in a clearly visible place seen from both of the tracks.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="31">
<j>湖西線上り線について、山科側の出口を出たすぐの位置に信号機（第1閉塞信号機、5灯式）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the up line of the Kosei Line, soon after getting out of the exit on the Yamashina side, there is a railroad signal (1st block signal, with 5 lights)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（第1日本の鉄道信号機場内信号機）→定訳不明：1st Japanese railroad signal, home signal [鉄道技術用語辞典 online：http://yougo.rtri.or.jp/dic/ の「第２場内信号機 (second home signal)」の項を参照にしました。]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the Kosei up line, soon after leaving the exit on the Yamashina side, there is a railroad signal (1st block signal, with 5 lights)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the Kosei up line, soon after leaving the exit on the Yamashina side, there is a railroad signal (1st block signal, with 5 lights).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>その先にある山科駅の信号機（第1日本の鉄道信号機場内信号機）が停止を現示（赤を点灯）しているとき、この第1閉塞信号機は警戒を現示（橙黄+橙黄を点灯）している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The aspect of this first block signal indicates &apos;speed restriction&apos; (the lights (orange-yellow + orange-yellow) are lit), when the aspect of the signal (1st Japanese railroad signal, home signal) in Yamashina Station, which is located a little ahead, is &apos;stopping&apos; (the red light is on).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処場内信号機→home signal　[英辞郎 on the WEB] 現示→aspect [鉄道技術用語辞典 online] 警戒→&apos;speed restriction&apos; [鉄道技術用語辞典 online]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The aspect of this first block signal indicates &apos;speed restriction&apos; (the lights - orange-yellow + orange-yellow) are lit), when the aspect of the signal (1st Japanese railroad signal, home signal) in Yamashina Station, which is located a little ahead, is &apos;stop&apos; (the red light is on).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the aspect of the signal (the 1st home signal) in the Yamashina Station, which is located ahead the first block signal, is &apos;stop&apos; (the red light is on), the aspect of the first block signal indicates &apos;speed restriction&apos; (yellow + yellow) are lit).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>この場合、湖西線上り線の列車は、トンネルの出口付近ではかなり減速して走行する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this case, the train running on the up line of the Kosei Line considerably lowers the speed near the exit of the tunnel.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this case, the train running on the Kosei up line considerably lowers the speed near the exit of the tunnel.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, the train running on the Kosei westbound track obviously slows down near the exit of the tunnel.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>西大津バイパスの長等トンネル</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagara Tunnel on Nishi-Otsu Bypass</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagara Tunnel on Nishi-Otsu Bypass</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagara Tunnel on Nishi-Otsu Bypass (National Route 161)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>琵琶湖西縦貫道路の藤尾奥町ランプと皇子山ランプの間にある全長1,305mの道路トンネル。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a 1,305m-long road tunnel constructed on Biwako nishi jukan road between Fujio Okumachi ramp and Ojiyama ramp.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a 1,305m-long road tunnel constructed along the Biwako nishi jukan road between Fujio Okumachi and Ojiyama ramps.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nagara Tunnel is a 1,305 m-long road tunnel constructed along the Biwako nishi jukan road between Fujio Okumachi and Ojiyama ramps.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>1980年から暫定2車線で供用開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It provisionally started to its service in 1980 with two lanes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It provisionally started service in 1980 with two lanes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It provisionally started service in 1980 with two lanes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>このトンネル自体も（鉄道の）長等山トンネルと同様に全区間が大津市内にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The whole section of this tunnel itself, like that of Nagarayama (railroad) tunnel, is in Otsu City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The whole section of this tunnel itself, like that of Nagarayama (railroad) tunnel, is in Otsu City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The whole length of this tunnel, like that of Nagarayama (railroad) tunnel, is in Otsu City.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>また、西大津側の出口の隣には山上トンネル（全長131m）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is another tunnel, Yamagami Tunnel (131 meters long) next to the exit of Nishi-Otsu side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is another tunnel, the Yamagami Tunnel (131 meters long) next to the exit of Nishi-Otsu side.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Next to the exit of the Nagara Tunnel on the Nishi-Otsu side, there is another tunnel, the Yamagami Tunnel (131meters long).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="38">
<j>同バイパスの4車線化工事の一環として現在、供用中のトンネルの北西（山側）に別のトンネルが建設されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a part of the bypass&apos;s expansion project to four lanes, at present another tunnel is under construction to the northwest (the mountain side) of the tunnels in service.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a part of the bypass&apos;s expansion project to four lanes, at present another tunnel is under construction to the northwest (the mountain side) of the tunnels in service.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a part of the bypass&apos;s expansion project to four lanes, another tunnel has been under construction to the northwest (the mountain side) of the tunnels in service.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>2008年2月末に貫通し、その後は舗装工事などが行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This tunnel passed completely through to the other side at the end of February, 2008, and since then the pavement work among others has been going on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This tunnel passed completely through to the other side as of the end of February, 2008, and since then the pavement work, among others, has been on going.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This tunnel passed completely through to the other side as of the end of February 2008, and afterwards, operations including the pavement work have been on going.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>琵琶湖疏水の第1トンネル</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The First Tunnel of the Lake Biwa Canal</e>
<cmt>第1トンネル→定訳不明：The First Tunnelとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The First Tunnel for the Lake Biwa Canal</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The First Tunnel for the Lake Biwa Canal</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="40">
<j>琵琶湖疏水の第1トンネル（長等山トンネル）は、大津市と京都市山科区の間にある全長2,436mのトンネルであり、長等山を貫いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The First Tunnel (Nagarayama Tunnel) of the Lake Biwa Cannel is a tunnel constructed between Otsu City and Yamashina Ward, Kyoto City, and it is 2,436 meters long in total and passing through Mt. Nagara-yama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The First Tunnel (Nagarayama Tunnel) for the Lake Biwa Canal is a tunnel constructed between Otsu City and Yamashina Ward, Kyoto City, and it is 2,436 meters long in tota, passing through Mt. Nagara-yama.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The First Tunnel (Nagarayama Tunnel) for the Lake Biwa Canal, a tunnel constructed between Otsu City and Yamashina Ward in Kyoto City, has the total length of 2,436 meters, passing through Mt. Nagara.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="41">
<j>竪坑（ダクトスペース）が2か所にあり、大津側の坑口（トンネル入口）から1,695mの位置に第1シャフト（深さ47m）、2,136mの位置に第2シャフト（深さ20m）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shaft (duct space) is opened in two points, the first shaft (47 meters deep) is found at the point of 1,695m from the tunnel entrance and the second shaft (20 meters deep) is located at the point of 2,136m from the entrance.</e>
<cmt>竪坑→ shaft [プログレッシブ中和英辞典] 抗口（トンネル入口）→定訳不明：tunnel entranceとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shaft (duct space) is opened at two points, the first shaft (47 meters deep) is found at the point of 1,695m from the tunnel entrance and the second shaft (20 meters deep) is located at the point of 2,136m from the entrance.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shaft (duct) is opened at two points, the first shaft (47 meters deep) is found at 1,695 m from the tunnel entrance on the Otsu side and the second shaft (20 meters deep) is located at 2,136 m from the entrance.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>また、京都方向へ1/3,000の下り勾配となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tunnel has 1/3,000 downward gradient toward the direction of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tunnel has a 1/3,000 downward gradient toward the direction of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tunnel has a 1/3,000 downward gradient toward the direction of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="43">
<j>湖西線の長等山トンネル（前述）の建設にともない、一部区間の改修や経路変更が行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the construction of Nagarayama Tunnel (railway) on the Kosei Line (previously mentioned), some parts of the section went under the renovation or changed the route.</e>
<cmt>「湖西線の長等山トンネル」→琵琶湖疏水の第1トンネルも「長等山トンネル」と呼ばれることがあるようなので、区別するためにNagarayama Tunnel (railway) on the Kosei Lineとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the construction of Nagarayama Tunnel (railway) on the Kosei Line (previously mentioned), some parts of the section were renovated or the route changed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the construction of Nagarayama Tunnel (railway) on the Kosei Line (previously mentioned), some parts of the section were renovated and rerouted.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>※詳しくは、琵琶湖疏水湖西線建設による改築を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For details, see &apos;Renovation of the Lake Biwa Cannel accompanied with the construction of the Kosei Line&apos;</e>
<cmt>琵琶湖疏水湖西線建設→英文名不明：&apos;Renovation of the Lake Biwa Cannel accompanied with the construction of the Kosei Line&apos;としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For details, see &apos;Renovation of the Lake Biwa Cannel accompanied with the construction of the Kosei Line&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For further details, see &apos;Renovation of the Lake Biwa Cannel accompanied with the construction of the Kosei Line&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>周辺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nearby spots</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nearby sightseeing spots</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nearby sightseeing spots</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="45">
<j>園城寺（三井寺、山号は「長等山」（ながらさん））</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onjo-ji Temple (Mii-dera Temple, Sango (temple&apos;s title) is &apos;Nagarasan&apos;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onjo-ji Temple (Mii-dera Temple, Sango (temple&apos;s title) is &apos;Nagarasan&apos;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onjo-ji Temple (commonly known as Mii-dera Temple, Sango (temple&apos;s title) is &apos;Nagara-san&apos;).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Carkuni(id:79281), Rusk(id:9895), Si-take.(id:91094), Dr jimmy(id:111486), Tam0031(id:165560), YOSHI0505(id:107383), 金山銀山銅山(id:163855), Seibuabina(id:37532), Fievarsty(id:201483), うら(id:40695), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>