<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>村</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Village</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Village</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Village</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>村（むら、そん）とは、集落や基礎自治体の一種である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A village (mura or son) refers to a sort of community, a municipality. It means an area whose number of houses is small and density is low. In the area, many of the population engage in the primary sector of the economy (agriculture, forestry and fishery).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A village (mura or son) refers to a sort of community, a municipality. It means an area where the number of houses is small and density is low. In the area, many of the population engage in the primary sector of the economy (agriculture, forestry and fishery).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A village (mura or son) refers to a sort of community, a municipality.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>第一次産業（農林漁業）に従事する者が多く、家屋の数と密集度が少ない地域を指す名称である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It indicates an area where a small number of houses are sparsely scattered.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>村（むら、そん）とは、集落や基礎自治体の一種で、第一次産業（農林漁業）に従事する者が多く、家屋の数と密集度が少ない地域を指す名称である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many residents of 村 engage in primary industry (agriculture, forestry and fishery).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>邑や邨とも書く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also written 邑 or 邨.</e>
<cmt>邑,邨は漢字表記しかできません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also written 邑 or 邨.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">村 is also written as 邑 or 邨.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>社会学や地理学では村落。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is called a rural community in sociology or geography.</e>
<cmt>村落の英語表記がrural communictyでよいのかどうか確認できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is called a rural community in sociology or geography.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">村 is called 村落 (read as sonraku, a rural community) in sociology and geography.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>対義語は市（都市）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its antonym is a city (town).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its antonym is city (town).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Antonym of 村--village is city (urban area).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>後述の自然村は、複数の集落の統合体であることが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A spontaneous village mentioned later often meant a unity of several comminities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A spontaneous village mentioned later often meant the unity of several communities.</e>
<cmt>spelling, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A &apos;spontaneous village&apos; to be mentioned often indicated a unity of several rural communities.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>行政区画（基礎自治体）の単位として村という語を用いることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term, village is used as a unit of an administrative district (a municipality). In this sense, a village is much spacious than a community.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term, village is used as a unit of an administrative district (a municipality). In this sense, a village is much more spacious than a community.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word 村--village is used as a unit of an administrative district (a municipality), too.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>この場合の村は、集落よりずっと広い範囲である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A &apos;village&apos; used in this sense indicates an area much more spacious than a rural community.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>なお、小さな世界･共同体を称して村ともいう（例：国会村、テント村）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A village also describes a specific small world or commnity (for example, a parliament village or a tent village).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A village also describes a specified small world or commnity (for example, a parliament village, or a tent village).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A village also describes a specified small world or community (for example, a parliament village, or a tent village).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>日本の「村」の歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The history of Japanese &apos;village&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History of the Japanese &apos;village&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History of the Japanese &apos;village&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>近代化以前の「村」は自然村（しぜんそん）ともいわれ、生活の場となる共同体の単位であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A &apos;village&apos; before modernization was also called a spontaneous village and it was a unit of community for living.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A &apos;village&apos; before modernization was also called a spontaneous village and it was a community unit for living.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A premodern &apos;village&apos;, also called a spontaneous village, was a unit of community where a group of people share a living space.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>江戸時代には百姓身分の自治結集の単位であり、中世の惣村を継承していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A village in the Edo period was a spontaneous unit of farming ranks and developed from medieval soson (a community consisting of peasants&apos; self-governing association).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A village in the Edo period was a spontaneous unit of farming ranks that developed from medieval soson (a community consisting of peasants&apos; self-governing association).</e>
<cmt>word spacing, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A &apos;village&apos; in the Edo period (1615-1868) was a unit of autonomous community of farming ranks that developed from medieval 惣村 (soson, a self-governing rural community).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>江戸時代にはこのような自然村が、約6万以上存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period, there were more than 60,000 spontaneous villages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period, there were more than 60,000 spontaneous villages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period, there were more than 60,000 spontaneous villages.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また、中世初期の領主が荘園公領とその下部単位である名田を領地の単位としていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early Medieval Ages, a unit of a landlord&apos;s teritorial land was shoen koryo (Public Lands and Private Estates) and its underlying unit myoden (rice field lots under charge of a nominal holder). On the other hand, in the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States)(Japan) and the Edo period, a unit of a landlord&apos;s teritorial land was a village or a town.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early Medieval Ages, a unit of a landlord&apos;s teritorial land was shoen koryo (Public Lands and Private Estates) and the underlying unit myoden (rice field lots under the charge of a nominal holder). On the other hand, in the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States - Japan) and during the Edo period, a unit of a landlord&apos;s teritorial land was a village or a town.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early Medieval Ages, a unit of a landlord&apos;s territorial land was &apos;shoen koryo&apos; (a private estate and a public land) and the underlying unit of &apos;myoden&apos; (a rice field lot under the charge of a nominal holder).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>それに対し、戦国時代 (日本)や江戸時代の領主の領地は村や町を単位としていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast, during the Sengoku period (Warring States period, 1482-1558) or the Edo period, a unit of a landlord&apos;s territorial land was a village or a town.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>江戸時代の百姓身分とは、主たる生業が農業・手工業・商業のいずれかであるかを問わず、村に石高を持ち、領主に年貢を納める形で権利義務を承認された身分階層を指した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period, a farming rank meant a status hierarchy in which a farmer had kokudaka (crop yield) in his village and his duty and right were approved by paying his nengu (land tax) to the landlord, regardless of his regular vocation being agriculture, manual industry or commerce.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo period, a farming rank meant a status hierarchy in which a farmer had kokudaka (crop yield) in his village and his duties and rights were approved by paying his nengu (land tax) to the landlord, regardless of his regular vocation being agriculture, labor industry, or commerce.</e>
<cmt>grammar, revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period, a farming rank was one of social status in which a farmer had &apos;kokudaka&apos; (crop yield) in his village and his duties and rights were approved by paying his nengu&apos; (land tax) to the landlord, whichever his regular vocation was agriculture, labor industry, or commerce.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>都市部の自治的共同体の単位である町（ちょう）に相当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The village corresponded to a town (cho), which was a unit of autonomous community in urban sites. It was quite arbitrarily decided by landlords whether each of their territories was a village or a town. Quite a few communities in urban sites in effect were regarded as &apos;villages.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The village corresponded to a town (cho), which was a unit of autonomous community in urban areas. It was quite arbitrarily decided by landlords whether each of their territories was a village or a town. Quite a few communities in urban sites were regarded as &apos;villages.&apos;</e>
<cmt>wordy, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The village corresponded to a town (cho), which was a unit of autonomous community in urban areas.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>しかし村か町かの認定はしばしば領主層の恣意によった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was mostly dependent on landlords whether each of their territories was a village or a town.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>実質的に都市的な共同体でも、「村」とされている箇所も多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many communities in urban sites were regarded as &apos;villages&apos;.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="20">
<j>近現代の大字（おおあざ）といわれる行政区域は、ほぼかつての自然村を継承している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Almost all the administrative districts called Oaza in modern times and the present day have developed from the former spontenuous villages. They have an aspect of keeping traditions of the smallest unit of the regional autonomy as an organization unit of residents&apos; association (a regional association, a neighborhood association) or a regional squad of a fire company.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Almost all the administrative districts called Oaza in modern times and the present day have developed from the former spontenuous villages. They have an aspect of keeping traditions of the smallest unit of regional autonomy as an organization unit of residents&apos; association (a regional association, a neighborhood association) or a regional squad of a fire company.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Almost all the modern and postmodern administrative districts called Oaza have developed from those once existed spontaneous villages.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>自治会（地区会・町内会）や消防団の地域分団の編成単位として、地域自治の最小単位としての命脈を保っている面がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They have survived as the smallest unit of regional autonomy and as an organization unit of residents&apos; association (for example, a regional association, a neighborhood association) or a local fire brigade of a fire company.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="22">
<j>明治に入ると、中央集権化のため、自然村の合併が推進された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Meiji period, it was promoted to unite spontenuous villages because of the centralization of power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Meiji period, uniting spontenuous villages was promoted because of the centralization of power.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Meiji period, uniting spontenuous villages was promoted because of the centralization of power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>こうして、かつての村がいくつか集まって新たな「村」ができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this way, a new &apos;village&apos; was formed by uniting several former villages. A newly-established village is also called an administrative village compared with a &apos;spontenuous village.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this way, a new &apos;village&apos; was formed by uniting several former villages. A newly-established village is also called an administrative village compared with a &apos;spontaneous village.&apos;</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, a new &apos;village&apos; was formed by uniting several once existed villages.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>これを「自然村」と対比して行政村（ぎょうせいそん）ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The newly-established village is called also an administrative village, in contrast to a &apos;spontaneous village&apos;.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>日本の行政村</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese administrative villages</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese administrative villages</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese administrative villages</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>日本国憲法第92条に基づく地方自治法では、村（そん、むら）は地方公共団体の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Local Autonomy Act based on the Constitution of Japan Article 92 defines a village (son, mura) as one of local public authorities. A village should be treated equal to each prefecture, city or town.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Local Autonomy Act, based on the Constitution of Japan Article 92, defines a village (son, mura) as one of local public authorities. A village should be treated equally to each prefecture, city, or town.</e>
<cmt>grammar,. Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Local Autonomy Act, based on the Constitution of Japan Article 92, defines a village (son, mura) as one of local public authorities.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>都道府県と対等の関係にあり、市・町と並立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A village is treated equally to a prefecture, city, and town.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="27">
<j>読み方を「そん」「むら」のどちらになるのかは各自治体で規定している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each municipality decides how to read its village(s); &apos;son&apos; or &apos;mura.&apos; While some prefectures decide to read all their villages &apos;son,&apos; other precture read their villages &apos;mura.&apos; In the other prefectures, their villages are read either &apos;son&apos; or &apos;mura.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each municipality decides how to read its village(s); &apos;son&apos; or &apos;mura.&apos; While some prefectures decide to read all their villages as &apos;son,&apos; other prefectures read their villages &apos;mura.&apos; In the other prefectures, their villages are read either &apos;son&apos; or &apos;mura.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each municipality defines whether to read its village(s) &apos;son&apos; or &apos;mura&apos;.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>「そん」で統一されている県、「むら」で統一されている県がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While some prefectures decide to read all their villages as &apos;son,&apos; others decide to read their villages as &apos;mura&apos;.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>「そん」「むら」が混在する県がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some other prefectures decide to mixedly read some of their villages as &apos;son&apos; and the others as &apos;mura&apos;.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>なお、「そん」で統一されている県は少なく、鳥取県・岡山県・徳島県・宮崎県・沖縄県のみである（かつては山口県も「そん」で統一されていたが、合併により村が消滅した）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Few prefectures decide to read their villages &apos;son&apos;: only in Tottori, Okayama, Tokkushima and Okinawa. (In Yamaguchi Prefecture, the villages used to be read &apos;son.&apos; But theser villages were united into one town and there is no village.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Few prefectures read their their villages as &apos;son&apos;: only in Tottori, Okayama, Tokkushima, and Okinawa. (In Yamaguchi Prefecture, villages used to be read &apos;son.&apos; But these villages were united into one town and now there is no village.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Few prefectures read their villages as &apos;son&apos;: only Tottori prefecture, Okayama prefecture, Tokushima prefecture, Miyazaki prefecture and Okinawa prefecture (In Yamaguchi prefecture, villages used to be read as &apos;son&apos; but these villages were united into one town and now there disappeared a village).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="31">
<j>かつては東京都にも「そん」と読む新島本村（にいじまほんそん）があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokyo Prefecture used to have Niijima Honson, (the village was read &apos;son&apos;). However, the name disappeared since it was changed into Niijimamura on April 1, 1992.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokyo Prefecture used to be Niijima Honson, (the village was read &apos;son&apos;). However, the name disappeared since it was changed into Niijimamura on April 1, 1992.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokyo Prefecture used to read its 新島本村 as &apos;Niijima Honson&apos; (村 was read as &apos;son&apos;).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>しかしながら、1992年4月1日、新島村（にいじまむら）に改称され、消滅した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name was replaced by &apos;新島村&apos; (Niijima-mura) on April 1, 1992.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>ただしこれは、本村（ほんそん）という地名に由来するため、例外的といえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This can be regarded as exceptional because it was from the toponym, Honson.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This can be regarded as exceptional because it was from the toponym, Honson.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This can be regarded as &apos;exceptional&apos; because it was from the toponym, &apos;本村&apos; (Honson).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 G25(id:82678), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Asakaze7000(id:180280), Nnh(id:474), March(id:9468), Michey.M(id:906), Knua(id:66861), Point136(id:211299), Sprinkler(id:14399), 吉田勝男(id:19081), Calvero(id:38360), Mizusumashi(id:360), Purodha(id:124727), ArthurBot(id:265089), DDR(id:27381), MizusumashiBot(id:180225), 乱次郎(id:213578), 樒(id:35770), Xqbot(id:273540), Gussan01-cat(id:182813), Kouchiumi(id:19253), Sionnach(id:21673), NOWOW(id:62041), SVS(id:18615), けんち(id:5147), ウミユスリカ(id:9504), Lunarjade(id:2797), MD242(id:11277), JAnDbot(id:66507), Idioma-bot(id:129667), Ziman-JAPAN(id:40303), Charenji(id:7908), D.h(id:79056), Tjan(id:17305), Wikiwikicompany(id:14588), KTM(id:18085), Kinori(id:443), Goki(id:7107), Mzaki(id:61977), マルケ(id:13532), Mark-zero(id:48822), Mamasaid(id:2903), LERK(id:4460), Shift(id:16394), Raff(id:14006), Nighthawks(id:36125), DX0(id:6198), Yanahan(id:2437), JunK(id:14563), Ro-(id:36890), NKEISK(id:17523), 1788910com(id:16251), BehBeh(id:55215), Zlan(id:11942), Eroro(id:18146), 住めら尊(id:173954), VolkovBot(id:105371), 地吹雪(id:38741), Fromm(id:71291), CarsracBot(id:217884), Muyo(id:14948), 編集仁王(id:208160), 友吾(id:42476), 深安(id:32266), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>