<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>京都市右京区の町名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Town names of the Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Town names of the Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Town names of the Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>本項京都市右京区の町名（きょうとしうきょうくのちょうめい）では、同区内に存在する公称町名を一覧化するとともに、その成立時期・成立過程等について概説する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This section, the Town&apos;s name of the Ukyu Ward, Kyoto City, shows the list of the official town&apos;s names in the Ukyo Ward and summarizes the period and process of their establishment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This section, the Town&apos;s name of the Ukyu Ward, Kyoto City, shows the list of the official town&apos;s names in the Ukyo Ward and summarizes the period and process of their establishment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This section shows the list of the official town names in the Ukyo Ward and summarizes the period and process of their establishment.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正, the Town&apos;s name of the Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City, 他の記事に合わせて削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>区の概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The summary of the Ukyo Ward</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The summary of the Ukyo Ward</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary of the Ukyo Ward</e>
<cmt>他の記事に合わせる</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>区役所のある太秦（うずまさ）地区は京都市街地の西方に位置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Uzumasa district where the Ukyo Ward Office is located, is in the western urban area of Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Uzumasa district where the Ukyo Ward Office is located, is in the western urban area of Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Uzumasa district where the Ukyo Ward Office is located, is in the western urban area of Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>区の領域はその北方、高雄山、愛宕山 (京都市)などの山間部、さらに北の旧・京北町の区域も含む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The area of the ward includes the mountain areas such as Mt.Takao and Mt.Atago (Kyoto City), which is located north of the Uzumasa district, and also includes the area of the former Keihoku Town, which is located north of them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The area of the ward includes the mountain areas such as Mt.Takao and Mt.Atago (Kyoto City), which is located north of the Uzumasa district, and also includes the area of the former Keihoku Town, which is located north of them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ward includes the mountainous areas such as Mt. Takao and Mt. Atago (Kyoto City), which is located north of the Uzumasa district, and also includes the area of the former Keihoku Town, which is located to the north.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>東から南は京都市左京区、北区 (京都市)、中京区、下京区、南区 (京都市)、西京区に接し、西から北は京都府亀岡市、南丹市に接する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has a border with the Sakyo Ward, Kita Ward (Kyoto City), Nakagyo Ward, Shimogyo Ward, Minami Ward (Kyoto City) and Nishikyo Ward from the east to the south, and with the Kameoka city and the Nantan City from the west to the north.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It shares a border with Sakyo Ward, Kita Ward (Kyoto City), Nakagyo Ward, Shimogyo Ward, Minami Ward (Kyoto City) and Nishikyo Ward from the east to the south, and with the Kameoka city and the Nantan City from the west to the north.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It shares a border with the wards of Sakyo, Kita (Kyoto City), Nakagyo, Shimogyo, Minami (Kyoto City) and Nishikyo from the east to the south, and with the cities of Kameoka and Nantan from the west to the north.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>面積291.95平方キロメートル。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is 291.95 square km in area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is 291.95 square km in area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is 291.95 square km in area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>2009年3月現在の推計人口は約204,000人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its population is estimated about 204,000 as of March 2009.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its population is estimated to be about 204,000 as of March 2009.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its population is estimated to be about 204,000 as of March 2009.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>京都市11区の中で面積は最大である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its area is the largest among the eleven wards in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its area is the largest among the eleven wards in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its area is the largest among the eleven wards in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>観光地として名高い嵯峨野、「三尾」（さんび）と称される高雄、槇尾（まきのお）、栂尾（とがのお）地区は当区に属し、区内には妙心寺、仁和寺、龍安寺、広隆寺、天龍寺、大覚寺、神護寺、高山寺、愛宕神社などの著名社寺が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It includes the Sagano district which is a famous sightseeing spot, and the Takao, Makinoo and Toganoo districts which are called &apos;Sanbi&apos; (literary, &quot;three bi (named after their Chinese characters)&quot;), and there are many famous temples and shrines such as Myoshin-ji Temple, Ninna-ji Temple, Ryoan-ji Temple, Koryu-ji Temple, Tenryu-ji Temple, Daikaku-ji Temple, Zingo-ji Temple, Kozan-ji Temple and Atago-jinja shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It includes the Sagano district which is a famous sightseeing spot, and the Takao, Makinoo and Toganoo districts which are called &apos;Sanbi&apos; (literary, &quot;three bi (named after their Chinese characters)&quot;), and there are many famous temples and shrines such as Myoshin-ji Temple, Ninna-ji Temple, Ryoan-ji Temple, Koryu-ji Temple, Tenryu-ji Temple, Daikaku-ji Temple, Zingo-ji Temple, Kozan-ji Temple and Atago-jinja shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ward includes the Sagano which is a famous sightseeing area as well as the districts of Takao, Makinoo and Toganoo which are titled &apos;Sanbi&apos; (all of the districts are famous for their finest views of Autumn leaves), with many famous temples and shrines including the temples of Myoshin-ji, Ninna-ji, Ryoan-ji, Koryu-ji, Tenryu-ji, Daikaku-ji, Zingo-ji, Kozan-ji, and Atago-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。Shrineのsを大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>区の成立は昭和6年（1931年）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ward was established in 1931.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ward was established in 1931.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ward was established in 1931.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>同年京都市は周辺の多くの町村を編入し、市域を拡大したが、うち葛野郡（かどのぐん）の嵯峨町、京極村、西院村、太秦村、梅津村、花園村、梅ケ畑村、松尾村、桂村、川岡村の旧1町9村の地域をもって右京区が新設された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, the Kyoto City spread its area by integrating many neighboring towns and villages, and the Ukyo Ward was newly created which consisted of the former one town and nine villages of the Kadono County, that is, Saga Town and Kyogoku, Sanin, Uzumasa, Umezu, Hanazono, Umegahata, Matsuo, Katsura and Kawaoka villages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, Kyoto City spread by integrating many neighboring towns and villages, and the Ukyo Ward was newly created which consisted of the former town and nine villages of the Kadono County, that is, Saga Town and Kyogoku, Sanin, Uzumasa, Umezu, Hanazono, Umegahata, Matsuo, Katsura and Kawaoka villages.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, Kyoto City spread by integrating many neighboring towns and villages, and the Ukyo Ward was newly created which consisted of the former town and nine villages of the Kadono County, that is, Saga Town and Kyogoku, Sanin, Uzumasa, Umezu, Hanazono, Umegahata, Matsuo, Katsura and Kawaoka villages.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>この時の区の領域は、現・右京区のうち旧・京北町域を除いた地域と、現・西京区の一部に相当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The area at this time corresponds to the area excluded the former Keihoku Town from the present Ukyo Ward and a part of the present Nishikyo Ward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The area at this time corresponds to the area exluding the former Keihoku Town from the present Ukyo Ward and a part of the present Nishikyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The area at this time corresponded to a part which excludes the former Keihoku Town from the present Ukyo Ward and a part of the present Nishikyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>昭和51年（1976年）に桂川右岸の地域（旧松尾村、桂村、川岡村を含む）が分区して西京区となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1976 the area of the right bank of the Katsura-gawa River (including former Matsuo, Katsura and Kawaoka villages) was split, forming the Nishikyo Ward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1976 the area of the right bank of the Katsura-gawa River (including former Matsuo, Katsura and Kawaoka villages) was split, forming the Nishikyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1976 the area of the right bank of the Katsura-gawa River (including former Matsuo, Katsura and Kawaoka villages) was split off to form the Nishikyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>平成17年（2005年）、いわゆる「平成の大合併」で、北桑田郡京北町を合併した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 2005 it integrated the Keihoku Town, Kitakuwada County, in what you call &apos;the great merger of municipalities in the Heisei era,&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 2005 it integrated the Keihoku Town, Kitakuwada County, in what was called &apos;the great merger of municipalities in the Heisei era,&apos;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 2005 it integrated the Keihoku Town, Kitakuwada County, in what was called &apos;the great merger of municipalities in the Heisei era.&apos;</e>
<cmt>最後の,をピリオドに</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>町名の概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The summary of towns</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary of towns</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary of towns</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>京都市内の町名には「大原来迎院町」のように旧村名、旧大字名に由来する地名（上記例の場合は「大原」）を冠称するものと、「亀屋町」「菊屋町」のような単独町名とがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The town&apos;s names in the Kyoto City are categorized into the one which uses the former village name or former Oaza (larger section of village) such as &apos;Ohara Raikoin-cho&apos; (in this case, &apos;Ohara&apos;) and the one which uses an independent name of town such as &apos;Kameya-cho&apos; and &apos;Kikuya-chi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The town&apos;s names in Kyoto City are categorized into the ones which use the former village name or former Oaza (larger section of village) such as &apos;Ohara Raikoin-cho&apos; (in this case, &apos;Ohara&apos;) and ones which uses an independent name such as &apos;Kameya-cho&apos; and &apos;Kikuya-chi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The town&apos;s names in Kyoto City are categorized into ones which use the former village name or former Oaza (larger section of village) such as &apos;Ohara Raikoin-cho&apos; (in this case, &apos;Ohara&apos;) and ones which uses an independent name such as &apos;Kameya-cho&apos; and &apos;Kikuya-cho.&apos;</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>右京区内の町名は例外なく、旧大字名などの地区名を冠した複合町名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The town&apos;s names in the Ukyo Ward all includes district&apos;s names such as former Oaza on the head with no exceptions.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The town&apos;s names in the Ukyo Ward all include district names such as former Oaza ath the beginning of the name with no exceptions.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The names of the towns in the Ukyo Ward is all include district names as a prefix, such as the former Oaza.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。ピリオドを打ちました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>区内の公称町名の数は、『角川日本地名大辞典 26 京都府』下巻によれば1980年現在608町であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the second volume of &quot;the Kadokawa dictionary of the place-name of Japan, No.26 Kyoto Prefecture,&quot; there were officially six-hundred and eight towns in 1980.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the second volume of &quot;the Kadokawa dictionary of the place-name of Japan, No.26 Kyoto Prefecture,&quot; there were officially six-hundred and eight towns in 1980.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the second volume of &quot;Kadokawa Nihon Chimei Daijiten No. 26 Kyoto-Fu&quot; (Kadokawa dictionary of place-names of Japan, No.26 Kyoto Prefecture), there were officially 608 declared towns in 1980.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これらの町は2009年現在も存続している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These towns have existed as of 2009.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These towns have existed as of 2009.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These towns have been there (2009-present).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>なお、2005年に京北町が編入され、その区域に1,232町が新設されているため、2009年現在の町数は1,840町である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Keihoku Town was integrated in 2005 and 1,232 towns were newly created, there are 1,840 towns as of 2009.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Keihoku Town was integrated in 2005 and 1,232 towns were newly created, there are 1,840 towns as of 2009.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Keihoku Town was integrated in 2005 and 1,232 towns were newly created, there have been 1,840 towns (2009-present).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>区内には「鳴滝宇多野谷」「梅ケ畑向井山」のように、末尾に「町」字を付さない町名が一部に存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some towns which have no letters of &apos;cho&apos; (which means town) on the end such as &apos;Narutaki Uda no tani&apos; and &apos;Umegahata Mukoyama.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「向井山」の読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are some towns which do not have the letters &apos;cho&apos; (which means town) as a suffix such as &apos;Narutaki Uda no tani&apos; and &apos;Umegahata Mukoyama.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are some towns which do not have the letters &apos;cho&apos; (which means town) as a suffix such as &apos;Narutaki Uda no tani&apos; and &apos;Umegahata Mukoyama.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>これらは、山間部などで、昭和6年の町名成立時において当該区域内に人家が存在しなかったものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These were the mountain area where no one lived when the Ukyo town was established in 1931.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These were mountainous regions where no one lived when the Ukyo town was established in 1931.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These were mountainous regions where is uninhabited when the Ukyo town was established in 1931.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="21">
<j>公称町名の一覧</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The list of the official town&apos;s names</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The list of the official town&apos;s names</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The List of Official Town Names</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>旧京極村</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former Kyogoku village</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Kyogoku village</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Kyogoku village</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>旧葛野郡京極村は、昭和6年京都市に編入され、右京区の一部となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former Kyogoku village, Kadono County, was integrated into the Kyoto City in 1931, and became a part of the Ukyo Ward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Kyogoku village, Kadono County, was integrated into Kyoto City in 1931, and became a part of the Ukyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Kyogoku village, Kadono County, was integrated into Kyoto City in 1931, and became a part of the Ukyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>京極村には川勝寺（せんしょうじ）、郡（こおり）、徳大寺の3つの大字があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were the three Oaza of Senshoji, Kori and Tokudaiji in the Kyogoku village.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were three Oaza of Senshoji, Kori and Tokudaiji in the Kyogoku village.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were three Oaza in the Kyogoku village: Senshoji, Kori and Tokudaiji.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。ピリオドを打ちました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>これらはそれぞれ「西京極」を冠称する46町、「西京極郡」を冠称する34町、「西京極徳大寺」を冠称する2町、計82町に編成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These were reorganized into eighty-two towns in total, that is, the forty-six towns which had the name of &apos;Nishikyogoku&apos; on the head, the thirty-four towns which had the name of &apos;Nishikyogoku Kori&apos; on the head and the two towns which had the name of &apos;Nishikyogoku Tokudaiji,&apos; respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These were reorganized into eighty-two towns in total, that is, forty-six towns which were headed by the name &apos;Nishikyogoku&apos;, thirty-four towns which were headed by the name &apos;Nishikyogoku Kori&apos; and two towns which were headed by the name &apos;Nishikyogoku Tokudaiji,&apos; respectively.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These were reorganized into eighty-two towns in total, that is, forty-six towns which were prefixed by the name of &apos;Nishikyogoku,&apos; thirty-four towns which were prefixed by the name &apos;Nishikyogoku Kori&apos; and two towns which were prefixed by the name &apos;Nishikyogoku Tokudaiji,&apos; respectively.</e>
<cmt>コンマを移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>これら82町は、以下のような変遷を経て、現在は64町となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These eighty-two towns have been reorganized into sixty-four towns through the following process.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These eighty-two towns have been reorganized into sixty-four towns through the following process.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These eighty-two towns have been reorganized into sixty-four towns through the following history.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="26">
<j>（昭和41年成立）橋詰町</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(established in 1966) Hashizume-cho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(established in 1966) Hashizume-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(established in 1966) Hashizume-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>（昭和41年廃止）下河原町、四ツ池町</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(abolished in 1966) Shimokawara-cho, Yotsuike-cho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(abolished in 1966) Shimokawara-cho, Yotsuike-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(abolished in 1966) Shimokawara-cho, Yotsuike-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>（昭和44年成立）東・西・南・北衣手町、新明町、東・西大丸町、葛野町、郡町、東・西池田町、浜ノ本町、北・南庄境町、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(established in 1969) Higashi, Nishi, Minami and Kitakoromode-cho, Shinmei-cho, Higashi and Nishiomaru-cho, Kadono-cho, Kori-cho, Higashi and Nishiikeda-cho, Hamanomoto-cho and Kita and Minamishozakai-cho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(established in 1969) Higashi, Nishi, Minami and Kitakoromode-cho, Shinmei-cho, Higashi and Nishiomaru-cho, Kadono-cho, Kori-cho, Higashi and Nishiikeda-cho, Hamanomoto-cho and Kita and Minamishozakai-cho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(established in 1969) Higashi, Nishi, Minami and Kitakoromodecho, Shinmeicho, Higashi and Nishiomarucho, Kadonocho, Koricho, Higashi and Nishiikedacho, Hamanomotocho, and Kita and Minamishozakai-cho.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>（昭和44年、冠称を「西京極郡」から「西京極」に変更）北・南大入町、午塚町、新田町、野田町</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(changed the prefix from &apos;Nishikyogoku Kori&apos; to &apos;Nishikyogoku&apos; in 1969) Kita and Minamioiri-cho, Umazuka-cho, Shinden-cho and Noda-cho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(changed the prefix from &apos;Nishikyogoku Kori&apos; to &apos;Nishikyogoku&apos; in 1969) Kita and Minamioiri-cho, Umazuka-cho, Shinden-cho and Noda-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(changed the prefix from &apos;Nishikyogoku Kori&apos; to &apos;Nishikyogoku&apos; in 1969) Kita and Minamioiri-cho, Umazukacho, Shindencho and Noda-cho</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>（昭和44年廃止）池田町、掛落町、庄境町、溝端町、六条町、郡浅代町、郡大宮田町、郡構エ町、郡北裏町、郡北堂ノ後町、郡南堂ノ後町、郡五反田町、郡衣手町、郡三反田町、郡四条縄手町、郡七反田町、郡芝土井町、郡下河原町、郡新上坊町、郡隅明町（こおりすみあけちょう）、郡大波町（こおりだいはちょう）、郡附洲町、郡佃町、郡辻堂町、郡鍋淵町、郡二反田町、郡浜ノ本町、郡樋渡町、郡平尻町（こおりへいじりちょう）、郡宮ノ後町、郡六条町</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(abolished in 1969) Ikeda-cho, Kakeochi-cho, Shozakai-cho, Mizobata-cho, Rokujo-cho, Kori Asashiro-cho, Kori Omiyata-cho, Kori Kitadonoato-cho, Kori Minamidonoato-cho, Kori Gotanda-cho, Kori Koromode-cho, Kori Mitanda-cho, Kori Shijonawate-cho, Kori Shichitanda-cho, Kori Shibadoi-cho, Kori Shimokawara-cho, Kori Sinjobo-cho, Kori Sumiake-cho, Kori Daiha-cho, Kori Fuzu-cho, Kori Tsukuda-cho, Kori Tsujido-cho, Kori Nabefuchi cho, Kori Nitanda-cho, Kori Hamanomoto-cho, Kori Hiwatari-cho, Kori Heijiri-cho, Kori Miyanoato-cho and Kori Rokujo-cho</e>
<cmt>掛落町、溝端町、郡浅代町、郡大宮田町、郡構エ町、郡北裏町、郡北堂ノ後町、郡南堂ノ後町、郡五反田町、郡衣手町、郡三反田町、郡四条縄手町、郡七反田町、郡芝土井町、郡下河原町、郡新上坊町、郡附洲町、郡佃町、郡辻堂町、郡鍋淵町、郡二反田町、郡浜ノ本町、郡樋渡町、郡宮ノ後町、郡六条町の読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(abolished in 1969) Ikeda-cho, Kakeochi-cho, Shozakai-cho, Mizobata-cho, Rokujo-cho, Kori Asashiro-cho, Kori Omiyata-cho, Kori Kitadonoato-cho, Kori Minamidonoato-cho, Kori Gotanda-cho, Kori Koromode-cho, Kori Mitanda-cho, Kori Shijonawate-cho, Kori Shichitanda-cho, Kori Shibadoi-cho, Kori Shimokawara-cho, Kori Sinjobo-cho, Kori Sumiake-cho, Kori Daiha-cho, Kori Fuzu-cho, Kori Tsukuda-cho, Kori Tsujido-cho, Kori Nabefuchi cho, Kori Nitanda-cho, Kori Hamanomoto-cho, Kori Hiwatari-cho, Kori Heijiri-cho, Kori Miyanoato-cho and Kori Rokujo-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(abolished in 1969) Ikedacho, Kakeochicho, Shozakaicho, Mizobatacho, Rokujocho, Kori Asashirocho, Kori Omiyatacho, Kori Kokocho, Kori Kitauracho, Kori Kitadonoatocho, Kori Minamidonoatocho, Kori Gotandacho, Kori Koromodecho, Kori Mitandacho, Kori Shijonawatecho, Kori Shichitandacho, Kori Shibadoicho, Kori Shimokawaracho, Kori Sinjobocho, Kori Sumiakecho, Kori Daihacho, Kori Fuzucho, Kori Tsukudacho, Kori Tsujidocho, Kori Nabefuchicho, Kori Nitandacho, Kori Hamanomotocho, Kori Hiwataricho, Kori Heijiricho, Kori Miyanoatocho and Kori Rokujo-cho</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>旧西院村</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former Sanin village</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Sanin village</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Sanin village</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="31">
<j>旧葛野郡西院村には山ノ内、西院の2つの大字があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were the two Oaza of Yamanouchi and Sanin in the former Sanin village, Kadono County.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were two Oaza, Yamanouchi and Sanin in the former Sanin village, Kadono County.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were two Oaza, Yamanouchi and Sanin in the former Sanin village, Kadono County.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>このうち、大字山ノ内の区域は「山ノ内」を冠称する15町と、西院を冠称する2町（金槌町、四条畑町）となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among them, the area of Oaza Yamanouchi led to the fifteen towns which had the name of &apos;Yamanouchi&apos; on the head and the two towns (Kanazuchi-cho and Shijobata-cho) which had the name of Sanin on the head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them, the area of Oaza Yamanouchi led to fifteen towns which here prefixed by the name of &apos;Yamanouchi&apos; and two towns (Kanazuchi-cho and Shijobata-cho) which here headed by the name of Sanin.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them, the area of Oaza Yamanouchi became fifteen towns which here prefixed by the name of &apos;Yamanouchi&apos; and two towns (Kanazuchicho and Shijobata-cho) which here prefixed by the name of Sanin.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="33">
<j>大字西院は一部が大正7年（1918年）に当時の下京区に編入された（当該区域は現在の中京区）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A part of the Oaza Sanin was integrated into the Shimogyo Ward in 1918 (which corresponds to the present Nakagyo Ward).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A part of Oaza Sanin was integrated into the Shimogyo Ward in 1918 (which corresponds to the present Nakagyo Ward).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A part of Oaza Sanin was integrated into the Shimogyo Ward in 1918 (which corresponds to the present Nakagyo Ward).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>大字西院の残余は昭和6年京都市に編入されて右京区の一部となり、「西院」を冠称する38町、及び山ノ内苗町となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The rest of Oaza Sanin was integrated into the Kyoto City in 1931 and became a part of the Ukyo Ward which consisted of the thirty-eight towns which had the name of &apos;Sanin&apos; on the head and the Yamanouchi naemachi town.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rest of Oaza Sanin was integrated into Kyoto City in 1931 and became a part of the Ukyo Ward which consisted of thirty-eight towns which were prefixed by the name &apos;Sanin&apos; and the Yamanouchi naemachi town.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The other part of Oaza Sanin was integrated into Kyoto City in 1931 and became a part of the Ukyo Ward which consisted of thirty-eight towns which were prefixed by the name &apos;Sanin&apos; and the Yamanouchi Naemachi town.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="35">
<j>「山ノ内」を冠称する計16町は現在も存続している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sixteen towns which have the name of &apos;Yamanouchi&apos; on the head have existed now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sixteen towns which were prefixed by the name &apos;Yamanouchi&apos; still exist today.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sixteen towns which were prefixed by the name &apos;Yamanouchi&apos; still exist today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>「西院」を冠称する計40町は、以下のような変遷を経て現在は50町となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The forty towns which have the name of &apos;Sanin&apos; on the head was reorganized into the present fifty towns through the following process.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The forty towns which were prefixed by the name &apos;Sanin&apos; were reorganized into the current fifty towns through the following process.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The forty towns which were prefixed by the name &apos;Sanin&apos; were reorganized into the current fifty towns through the following process.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="37">
<j>（昭和14年成立）高山寺町、松井町、西三蔵町、西平町、北・西矢掛町、西・南高田町、寿町、西・南寿町、中水町、東・西中水町、西溝崎町</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(established in 1939) Kozanji-cho, Matsui-cho, Nishisanzo-cho, Nishihiramachi, Kita and Nishi Yakage-cho, Nishi and Minami Takada-cho, Kotobuki-cho, Nishi and Minami Kotobuki-cho, Nakamizu-cho, Higashi and Nishi Nakamizu-cho and Nishi Mizosaki-cho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(established in 1939) Kozanji-cho, Matsui-cho, Nishisanzo-cho, Nishihiramachi, Kita and Nishi Yakage-cho, Nishi and Minami Takada-cho, Kotobuki-cho, Nishi and Minami Kotobuki-cho, Nakamizu-cho, Higashi and Nishi Nakamizu-cho and Nishi Mizosaki-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(established in 1939) Kozanjicho, Matsuicho, Nishisanzocho, Nishihiramachi, Kita and Nishi Yakagecho, Nishi and Minami Takadacho, Kotobukicho, Nishi and Minami Kotobukicho, Nakamizucho, Higashi and Nishi Nakamizucho and Nishi Mizosaki-cho</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>（昭和14年廃止）五条町、中溝町</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(abolished in 1939) Gojo-cho and Nakamizo-cho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(abolished in 1939) Gojo-cho and Nakamizo-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(abolished in 1939) Gojo-cho and Nakamizo-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>（昭和29年成立）上・東・西今田町、上・下花田町、東・西淳和院町、春日町</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(established in 1954) Kami, Higashi and Nishi Imada-cho, Kami and Shimo Hanada-cho, Higashi and Nishi Junnain-cho and Kasuga-cho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(established in 1954) Kami, Higashi and Nishi Imada-cho, Kami and Shimo Hanada-cho, Higashi and Nishi Junnain-cho and Kasuga-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(established in 1954) Kami, Higashi and Nishi Imadacho, Kami and Shimo Hanadacho, Higashi and Nishi Junnaincho and Kasuga-cho</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>（昭和29年廃止）今田町、艮町、花田町、淳和院町</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(abolished in 1954) Imada-cho, Ushitora-cho, Hanada-cho and Junnain-cho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(abolished in 1954) Imada-cho, Ushitora-cho, Hanada-cho and Junnain-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(abolished in 1954) Imadacho, Ushitoracho, Hanadacho and Junnain-cho</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>（昭和44年成立）北・南井御料町</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(established in 1969) Kita and Minami Igoryo-cho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(established in 1969) Kita and Minami Igoryo-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(established in 1969) Kita and Minami Igoryo-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>（昭和44年廃止）井御料町、馬塚町、桂町、東・西・中大丸町、羽根田町、馬場町、東田町</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(abolished in 1969) Igoryo-cho, Umatsuka-cho, Higashi, Nishi and Naka Omaru-cho, Haneda-cho, Baba-cho and Higashida-cho</e>
<cmt>馬塚町、馬場町の読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(abolished in 1969) Igoryo-cho, Umatsuka-cho, Higashi, Nishi and Naka Omaru-cho, Haneda-cho, Baba-cho and Higashida-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(abolished in 1969) Igoryocho, Umatsukacho, Katsuracho, Higashi, Nishi and Naka Omarucho, Hanedacho, Babacho and Higashida-cho</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>旧太秦村</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former Uzumasa village</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Uzumasa village</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Uzumasa village</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="43">
<j>旧葛野郡太秦村は、昭和6年京都市に編入され、右京区の一部となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former Uzumasa village, Kadono County, was integrated into the Kyoto City in 1931, and became a part of the Ukyo Ward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Uzumasa village, Kadono County, was integrated into Kyoto City in 1931, and became a part of the Ukyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Uzumasa village, Kadono County, was integrated into Kyoto City in 1931, and became a part of the Ukyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>太秦村には太秦、安井、中野、常盤谷、嵯峨野の5つの大字があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Uzumasa village, there were the five Oaza of Uzumasa, Yasui, Nakano, Tokiwadani and Sagano.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Uzumasa village, there were five Oaza: Uzumasa, Yasui, Nakano, Tokiwadani and Sagano.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Uzumasa village, there were five Oaza: Uzumasa, Yasui, Nakano, Tokiwadani and Sagano.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>このうち、大字太秦と大字中野は「太秦」を冠称する65町、大字安井は「太秦安井」を冠称する18町、大字常盤谷は「常盤」を冠称する19町、大字嵯峨野は「嵯峨野」を冠称する17町に編成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among them, the Oaza Uzumasa and Oaza Nakano were reorganized into the sixty-five towns which had the name of &apos;Uzumasa&apos; on the head, the Oaza Yasui was into the eighteen towns which had the name of &apos;Uzumasa Yasui&apos; on the head, the Oaza Tokiwadani was into the nineteen towns which had the name of &apos;Tokiwa&apos; on the head, and the Oaza Sagano was into the seventeen towns which had the name of &apos;Sagano&apos; on the head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them, the Oaza Uzumasa and Oaza Nakano were reorganized into the sixty-five towns which were headed by the name &apos;Uzumasa&apos;, while Oaza Yasui was reorganized into eighteen towns which were headed by the name &apos;Uzumasa Yasui&apos;, Oaza Tokiwadani was reorganized into nineteen towns which were headed by the name &apos;Tokiwa&apos;, and Oaza Sagano reorganized into seventeen towns which were headed by the name &apos;Sagano&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them, the Oaza Uzumasa and Oaza Nakano were reorganized into the sixty-five towns which were prefixed by the name &apos;Uzumasa,&apos; while Oaza Yasui was reorganized into eighteen towns which were prefixed by the name &apos;Uzumasa Yasui,&apos; and Oaza Tokiwadani was reorganized into nineteen towns which were prefixed by the name &apos;Tokiwa,&apos; and Oaza Sagano reorganized into seventeen towns which were prefixed by the name &apos;Sagano.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>「太秦」を冠称する65町のうち、大字中野に属していたのは宮ノ前町、京ノ道町、北路町、中筋町、開日町、堀池町、御領田町、中山町、三尾町の9町である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the sixty-five towns which had the name of &apos;Uzumasa&apos; on the head, the nine towns had been included in the Oaza Nakano, which were Miyanomae-cho, Kyonomichi-cho, Kitaro-cho, Nakasuji-cho, Kainichi-cho, Horiike-sho, Goryoden-cho, Nakayama-cho and Sanbi-cho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among sixty-five towns which were headed by the name &apos;Uzumasa&apos;, the nine towns were included in Oaza Nakano, which included Miyanomae-cho, Kyonomichi-cho, Kitaro-cho, Nakasuji-cho, Kainichi-cho, Horiike-sho, Goryoden-cho, Nakayama-cho and Sanbi-cho.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among sixty-five towns which were prefixed by the name &apos;Uzumasa,&apos; the nine towns were included in Oaza Nakano, which included Miyanomaecho, Kyonomichicho, Kitarocho, Nakasujicho, Kainichicho, Horiikecho, Goryodencho, Nakayamacho and Sanbi-cho.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>上記の「嵯峨野」を冠称する地区は、観光名所としての「嵯峨野」とは別個の地区である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above district which has the name of &apos;Sagano&apos; is a different place of the famous sightseeing spot, &apos;Sagano.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above district bearing the name &apos;Sagano&apos; is different from the famous sightseeing spot, &apos;Sagano.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The above district bearing the name &apos;Sagano&apos; is other than the famous sightseeing spot, &apos;Sagano.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>旧梅津村</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former Umezu village</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Umezu village</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Umezu village</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="48">
<j>旧葛野郡梅津村は昭和6年京都市に編入され、右京区の一部となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former Umezu village, Kadono County, was integrated into the Kyoto City in 1931, and became a part of the Ukyo Ward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Umezu village, Kadono County, was integrated into Kyoto City in 1931, and became a part of the Ukyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Umezu village, Kadono County, was integrated into Kyoto City in 1931, and became a part of the Ukyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>梅津村には東梅津、西梅津の2つの大字があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Umezu village, there were the two Oaza of Higashi Umezu and Nishi Umezu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Umezu village, there were two Oaza: Higashi Umezu and Nishi Umezu.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Umezu village, there were two Oaza: Higashi Umezu and Nishi Umezu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>このうち、大字東梅津の区域は大部分が「梅津」を冠称する24町に編成され、残余は大字東梅津として残された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among them, the area of Oaza Higashi Umezu was mostly reorganized into the twenty-four towns which had the name of &apos;Umezu&apos; on the head, and the rest was remained as Oaza Higashi Umezu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them, the area of Oaza Higashi Umezu was mostly reorganized into twenty-four towns which were headed by the name &apos;Umezu&apos;, and the rest remained as Oaza Higashi Umezu.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them, the area of Oaza Higashi Umezu was mostly reorganized into twenty-four towns which were prefixed by the name &apos;Umezu,&apos; and the rest remained as Oaza Higashi Umezu.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除コンマ位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>大字西梅津の区域は「梅津」を冠称する6町（罧原町、フケノ川町、前田町、中倉町、尻溝町、大縄場町）となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The area of Oaza Nishi Umezu was reorganized into the six towns which had the name of &apos;Umezu&apos; on the head (Fushihara-cho, Fukenokawa-cho, Maeda-cho, Nakakura-cho, Shirimizo-cho and Onawaba-cho).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The area of Oaza Nishi Umezu was reorganized into six towns which were headed by the name &apos;Umezu&apos; (Fushihara-cho, Fukenokawa-cho, Maeda-cho, Nakakura-cho, Shirimizo-cho and Onawaba-cho).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The area of Oaza Nishi Umezu was reorganized into six towns which were prefixed by the name &apos;Umezu&apos; (Fushiharacho, Fukenokawacho, Maedacho, Nakakuracho, Shirimizocho and Onawaba-cho).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>その後、昭和44年に東構口町、南上田町が成立、長通町、畑田町、六竹町が廃止され、「梅津」を冠称する町名は現在は29町となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Higashi Kamaeguchi-cho and Minami Ueda-cho were established and Nagamichi-cho, Hatada-cho and Rokutake-cho were abolished in 1969, and there are twenty-nine towns which have the name of &apos;Umezu&apos; on the head at present.</e>
<cmt>長通町、畑田町、六竹町の読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Higashi Kamaeguchi-cho and Minami Ueda-cho were established and Nagamichi-cho, Hatada-cho and Rokutake-cho were abolished in 1969, and there are now twenty-nine towns which are headed by the name &apos;Umezu&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Higashi Kamaeguchicho and Minami Ueda-cho were established and Nagamichicho, Hatadacho and Rokutake-cho were abolished in 1969, and there are now twenty-nine towns which are headed by the name &apos;Umezu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="53">
<j>昭和40年（1965年）、当時の京都市内各所に残存していた「大字○○字XX」の区域はすべて「町」となり、「○○XX町」と改称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1965 the all districts which included the place-name, &apos;Oaza OOand Aza (section of village) XX,&apos; in those days were changed into &apos;town&apos; and their names were also changed into &apos;OOXX town.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1965 all districts which included the place-name, &apos;Oaza OOand Aza (section of village) XX,&apos; in those days were changed into &apos;town&apos; and their names were also changed into &apos;OOXX town.&apos;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1965, all places in Kyoto City whose names included the terms &apos;Oaza&apos; and &apos;Aza&apos; (the latter meaning a small section of a village) were renamed with the suffix &apos;cho&apos;, therefore, a place called &apos;Oaza XX Aza YY&apos; would have been renamed &apos;XXYY-cho&apos;.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。&quot;を &apos; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>この際、「大字東梅津」として存続していた区域は東梅津前子町となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, the district which had existed as &apos;Oaza Higashi Umezu&apos; was reorganized into Higashi Umezu Maeko-cho.</e>
<cmt>東梅津前子町の読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, the district which existed as &apos;Oaza Higashi Umezu&apos; was reorganized into Higashi Umezu Maeko-cho.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, the district which existed as &apos;Oaza Higashi Umezu&apos; was reorganized into Higashi Umezu Maeko-cho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>旧嵯峨町（下嵯峨、上嵯峨、天龍寺）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former Saga Town (Shimosaga, Kamisaga and Tenryuji)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Saga Town (Shimosaga, Kamisaga and Tenryuji)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Saga Town (Shimosaga, Kamisaga and Tenryuji)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="55">
<j>旧葛野郡嵯峨町は、昭和6年京都市に編入され、右京区の一部となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former Saga Town, Kadono County, was integrated into the Kyoto City in 1931, and became a part of the Ukyo Ward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Saga Town, Kadono County, was integrated into Kyoto City in 1931, and became a part of the Ukyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Saga Town, Kadono County, was integrated into Kyoto City in 1931, and became a part of the Ukyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>嵯峨町は明治22年（1889年）の市制町村制施行時には嵯峨村であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Saga Town had been the Saga village when the Municipal Government Act became effective in 1889.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saga Town was originally Saga village when the Municipal Government Act came into effect in 1889.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saga Town was originally Saga village when the Municipal Government Act came into effect in 1889.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>明治36年（1903年）に下嵯峨村を編入、大正12年に町制を施行している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It integrated Shimosaga village in 1903 and became Saga Town in 1923.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It integrated Shimosaga village in 1903 and became Saga Town in 1923.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It integrated Shimosaga village in 1903 and became Saga Town in 1923.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>嵯峨町には上嵯峨、下嵯峨、天龍寺、水尾、原、越畑の6つの大字があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Saga Town, there were the six Oaza of Kamisaga, Shimosaga, Tenryuji, Mizuo, Hara and Koshihata.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Saga Town, there were six Oaza of Kamisaga, Shimosaga, Tenryuji, Mizuo, Hara and Koshihata.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Saga Town, there were six Oaza: Kamisaga, Shimosaga, Tenryuji, Mizuo, Hara and Koshihata.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>このうち、大字上嵯峨は「嵯峨」を冠称する56町と「北嵯峨」を冠称する10町に、大字下嵯峨は「嵯峨」を冠称する16町に、大字天龍寺は「嵯峨」を冠称する23町に、それぞれ編成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among them, the Oaza Kamisaga was reorganized into the fifty-six towns which had the name of &apos;Saga&apos; on the head and the ten towns which had the name of &apos;Kitasaga&apos; on the head, the Oaza Shimosaga was into the sixteen towns which had the name of &apos;Saga&apos; on the head, and the Oaza Tenryuji was into the twenty-three towns which had the name of &apos;Saga&apos; on the head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them, the Oaza Kamisaga was reorganized into fifty-six towns which were headed by the name &apos;Saga&apos; and ten towns which were headed by the name &apos;Kitasaga&apos;, the Oaza Shimosaga into sixteen towns which were headed by the name &apos;Saga&apos;, and Oaza Tenryuji into twenty-three towns which were headed by the name &apos;Saga&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them, the Oaza Kamisaga was reorganized into fifty-six towns which were prefixed by the name &apos;Saga&apos; and ten towns prefixed by the name &apos;Kitasaga,&apos; the Oaza Shimosaga into sixteen towns prefixed by the name &apos;Saga,&apos; and Oaza Tenryuji into twenty-three towns which were prefixed by the name &apos;Saga.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>旧・大字上嵯峨には清滝地区、愛宕山頂の愛宕神社などが含まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former Oaza Kamisaga included the Kiyotaki district and the Atago-jinja Shrine on the top of Mt. Atago.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Oaza Kamisaga included the Kiyotaki district and the Atago-jinja Shrine on the top of Mt. Atago.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Oaza Kamisaga included the Kiyotaki district and the Atago-jinja Shrine on the top of Mt. Atago.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>旧嵯峨町（水尾、原、越畑）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former Saga Town (Mizuo, Hara and Koshihata)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Saga Town (Mizuo, Hara and Koshihata)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Saga Town (Mizuo, Hara and Koshihata)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="61">
<j>旧葛野郡嵯峨町のうち、大字水尾は「嵯峨水尾」を冠称する26町に、大字原は「嵯峨樒原」（さがしきみがはら）を冠称する26町に、大字越畑は「嵯峨越畑」を冠称する29町に、それぞれ編成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the Oaza of the former Saga Town, Kadono County, the Oaza Mizuo was reorganized into the twenty-six towns which had the name of &apos;Saga Mizuo&apos; on the head, the Oaza Hara was into the twenty-six towns which had the name of &apos;Saga Shikimigahara&apos; on the head, and the Oaza Koshihata was the twenty-nine towns which had the name of &apos;Saga Koshihata&apos; on the head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the Oaza of former Saga Town, Kadono County, Oaza Mizuo was reorganized into twenty-six towns which were headed by the name of &apos;Saga Mizuo&apos;, the Oaza Hara into twenty-six towns which were headed by the name of &apos;Saga Shikimigahara&apos;, and Oaza Koshihata which included twenty-nine towns and bore the name of &apos;Saga Koshihata&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the Oaza of former Saga Town, Kadono County, Oaza Mizuo was reorganized into twenty-six towns which were prefixed by the name of &apos;Saga Mizuo,&apos; the Oaza Hara into twenty-six towns which were prefixed by the name of &apos;Saga Shikimigahara,&apos; and Oaza Koshihata which included twenty-nine towns which bore the name of &apos;Saga Koshihata.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>旧花園村</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former Hanazono village</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Hanazono village</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Hanazono village</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="62">
<j>旧葛野郡花園村は、昭和6年京都市に編入され、右京区の一部となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former Hanazono Town, Kadono County, was integrated into the Kyoto City in 1931, and became a part of the Ukyo Ward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Hanazono Town, Kadono County, was integrated into Kyoto City in 1931, and became a part of the Ukyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Hanazono village, Kadono County, was integrated into Kyoto City in 1931, and became a part of the Ukyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>Town→village</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>花園村には花園、宇多野、谷口、御室の4つの大字があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Hanazono village, there were the four Oaza of Hanazono, Utano, Taniguchi and Omuro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Hanazono village, there were four Oaza: Hanazono, Utano, Taniguchi and Omuro.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Hanazono village, there were four Oaza: Hanazono, Utano, Taniguchi and Omuro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>このうち、大字花園は「花園」を冠称する28町に編成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among them the Oaza Hanazono was reorganized into the twenty-eight towns which had the name of &apos;Hanazono&apos; on the head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them the Oaza Hanazono was reorganized into twenty-eight towns which were headed by the name of &apos;Hanazono&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them the Oaza Hanazono was reorganized into twenty-eight towns which were prefixed by the name &apos;Hanazono.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>大字宇多野は「宇多野」を冠称する10町、「鳴滝」を冠称する24町、「山越」を冠称する5町、及び音戸山山ノ茶屋町に編成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Oaza Utano was reorganized into the ten towns which had the name of &apos;Utano&apos; on the head, the twenty-four towns which had the name of &apos;Narutaki&apos; on the head, the five towns which had the name of &apos;Yamagoe&apos; on the head, and the Ondoyama Yamanochaya-cho town.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Oaza Utano was reorganized into ten towns which were headed by the name of &apos;Utano&apos;, twenty-four towns which were headed by the name of &apos;Narutaki&apos;, five towns which were headed by the name of &apos;Yamagoe&apos;, and Ondoyama Yamanochaya-cho.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Oaza Utano was reorganized into ten towns which were prefixed by the name of &apos;Utano,&apos; twenty-four towns which were prefixed by the name of &apos;Narutaki,&apos; five towns which were prefixed by the name of &apos;Yamagoe,&apos; and Ondoyama Yamanochaya-cho.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>大字谷口は「谷口」を冠称する5町と「龍安寺」を冠称する11町に編成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Oaza Taniguchi was reorganized into the five towns which had the name of &apos;Taniguchi&apos; on the head and the eleven towns which had the name of &apos;Ryoanji&apos; on the head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Oaza Taniguchi was reorganized into five towns which were headed by the name of &apos;Taniguchi&apos; and eleven towns which were headed by the name of &apos;Ryoanji&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Oaza Taniguchi was reorganized into five towns which were prefixed by the name of &apos;Taniguchi&apos; and eleven towns which were prefixed by the name of &apos;Ryoanji.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>大字御室は大部分が「御室」を冠称する5町に編成され、残余は大字御室として残された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Oaza Omuro was mostly reorganized into the five towns which had the name of &apos;Omuro&apos; on the head, and the rest of them was left as Oaza Higashi Umeju.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Oaza Omuro was mostly reorganized into five towns which were headed by the name of &apos;Omuro&apos;, and the rest were left as Oaza Higashi Umeju.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Oaza Omuro was mostly reorganized into five towns which were prefixed by the name of &apos;Omuro,&apos; and the rest were left as Oaza Omuro.</e>
<cmt>Higashi Umeju→Omuro</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="68">
<j>昭和40年（1965年）、当時の京都市内各所に残存していた「大字○○字XX」の区域はすべて「町」となり、「○○XX町」と改称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1965 the all districts which included the place-name, &apos;Oaza OOand Aza (section of village) XX,&apos; in those days were changed into &apos;town&apos; and their names were also changed into &apos;OOXX town.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1965 all districts which included the place-name, &apos;Oaza OOand Aza (section of village) XX,&apos; in those days were changed into &apos;town&apos; and their names were also changed into &apos;OOXX town.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1965, in Kyoto City, all the districts the names of which included the terms &apos;Oaza&apos; and &apos;Aza&apos; (the latter meaning a small section of a village) were renamed with the suffix &apos;cho,&apos; so a place called &apos;Oaza XX Aza YY&apos; would have been renamed &apos;XXYY-cho&apos;.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。&quot;を &apos; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>この際、大字御室として存続していた区域は、御室住吉山町及び御室双岡町となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, the district of Oaza Omuro was reorganized as Omuro Sumiyoshiyama-cho and Omuro Narabigaoka-cho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, the district of Oaza Omuro was reorganized as Omuro Sumiyoshiyama-cho and Omuro Narabigaoka-cho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, the district of Oaza Omuro was reorganized as Omuro Sumiyoshiyama-cho and Omuro Narabigaoka-cho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>旧梅ケ畑村</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former Umegahata village</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Umegahata village</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Umegahata village</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="70">
<j>旧葛野郡梅ケ畑村は、昭和6年京都市に編入され、右京区の一部となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former Umegahata village, Kadono County, was integrated into the Kyoto City in 1931, and became a part of the Ukyo Ward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Umegahata village, Kadono County, was integrated into the Kyoto City in 1931, and became a part of the Ukyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Umegahata village, Kadono County, was integrated into Kyoto City in 1931, and became a part of the Ukyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>梅ケ畑村には大字はなく、旧村域は「梅ケ畑」を冠称する52町に編成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Umegahata village, there was no Oaza and its area was reorganized into the fifty-two towns which had the name of &apos;Umegahata&apos; on the head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Umegahata village, there was no Oaza and its area was reorganized into fifty-two towns which were headed by the name of &apos;Umegahata&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Umegahata village, there is no Oaza and its area was reorganized into fifty-two towns which were prefixed by the name of &apos;Umegahata.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>旧京北町</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former Keihoku Town</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Keihoku Town</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Keihoku Town</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="72">
<j>右京区の京北地区は、もとの北桑田郡京北町で、平成17年（2005年）にいわゆる「平成の大合併」で京都市右京区に編入された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Keihoku district in the Ukyo Ward was the former Keihoku Town, Kitakuwada County, which was integrated into the Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City, at the time of what was called &apos;the great merger of municipalities in the Heisei era&apos; in 2005.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Keihoku district in the Ukyo Ward was the former Keihoku Town, Kitakuwada County, which was integrated into the Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City, at the time of what was called &apos;the great merger of municipalities in the Heisei era&apos; in 2005.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Keihoku district in the Ukyo Ward was the former Keihoku Town, Kitakuwada County, which was integrated into the Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City, at the time of what was called &apos;the great merger of municipalities in the Heisei era&apos; in 2005.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>京都市への他自治体の合併は、昭和34年（1959年）の久世村（現・南区）、大原野村（現・西京区）の合併以来46年ぶりであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The merger of other municipalities into the Kyoto City was the first time in forty-six years after the merger of the Kuse village (the present Minami Ward) and the Oharano village (the present Nishikyo Ward) in 1959.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The merger of other municipalities into Kyoto City was the first time in forty-six years after the merger of Kuse village (the present Minami Ward) and Oharano village (the present Nishikyo Ward) in 1959.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The merger of other municipalities into Kyoto City was the first time in the forty-six years after the merger of the villages of Kuse (the present Minami Ward) and Oharano (the present Nishikyo Ward) in 1959.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="74">
<j>この地区は、明治22年（1889年）の市制町村制施行の時点では、北桑田郡の6つの村であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This area consisted of the six villages in the Kitakuwada County when the Municipal Government Act became effective in 1889.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This area consisted of six villages in the Kitakuwada County when the Municipal Government Act came into effect in 1889.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This area consisted of six villages in the Kitakuwada County when the Municipal Government Act came into effect in 1889.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>うち周山村は昭和18年（1943年）に町制を施行し、周山町となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among them, the Shuzan village became the Shuzan Town in 1943.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them, the Shuzan village became the Shuzan Town in 1943.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them, Shuzan village became Shuzan Town in 1943.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>周山町を含む1町5村は昭和30年（1955年）に合併し、京北町となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The single town and five villages including the Shuzan Town were merged into the Keihoku Town in 1955.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The single town and five villages including the Shuzan Town were merged into the Keihoku Town in 1955.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The single town and five villages including the Shuzan Town were merged into the Keihoku Town in 1955.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>これら1町5村とそれらが含んでいた大字の名称は次のとおりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The names of the villages and their Oaza are as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The names of the villages and their Oaza are as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The names of the villages and their Oaza are as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="78">
<j>黒田村 7大字（芹生、灰屋、片波、上黒田、宮、下黒田、広河原）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kuroda village there were seven Oaza (Seryo, Haiya, Katanami, Kamikuroda, Miya, Shimokuroda and Hirogawara)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kuroda village there were seven Oaza (Seryo, Haiya, Katanami, Kamikuroda, Miya, Shimokuroda and Hirogawara)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kuroda village there were seven Oaza (Seryo, Haiya, Katanami, Kamikuroda, Miya, Shimokuroda and Hirogawara)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>山国村 10大字（小塩、初川、井戸、大野、比賀江、中江、塔、辻、鳥居、下）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Yamakuni village there were ten Oaza (Oshio, Hatsukawa, Ido, Ono, Higae, Nakae, To, Tsuji, Torii and Shimo)</e>
<cmt>山国村の読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Yamakuni village there were ten Oaza (Oshio, Hatsukawa, Ido, Ono, Higae, Nakae, To, Tsuji, Torii and Shimo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Yamakuni village there were ten Oaza (Oshio, Hatsukawa, Ido, Ono, Higae, Nakae, To, Tsuji, Torii and Shimo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>弓削村 9大字（上中、下中、下弓削、塩田、井崎、赤石、田貫、室谷、上弓削）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Yuge village there were nine Oaza (Kaminaka, Shimonaka, Shimoyuge, Shiota, Izaki, Akaishi, Tanuki, Shittan and Kamiyuge)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Yuge village there were nine Oaza (Kaminaka, Shimonaka, Shimoyuge, Shiota, Izaki, Akaishi, Tanuki, Shittan and Kamiyuge)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Yuge village there were nine Oaza (Kaminaka, Shimonaka, Shimoyuge, Shiota, Izaki, Akaishi, Tanuki, Shittan and Kamiyuge)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>周山町 9大字（宇野、浅江、西、矢代中、漆谷、熊田、下熊田、五本松、周山）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Shuzan Town there were nine Oaza (Uno, Azae, Nishi, Yashironaka, Urushitani, Kumada, Shimokumada, Gohonmatsu and Shuzan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Shuzan Town there were nine Oaza (Uno, Azae, Nishi, Yashironaka, Urushitani, Kumada, Shimokumada, Gohonmatsu and Shuzan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Shuzan Town there were nine Oaza (Uno, Azae, Nishi, Yashironaka, Urushitani, Kumada, Shimokumada, Gohonmatsu and Shuzan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>細野村 大字なし</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Hosono village there was no Oaza.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Hosono village there was no Oaza.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Hosono village there is no Oaza.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>宇津村 6大字（柏原、弓槻、栃本、中地、明石、下宇津）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Uzu village there were six Oaza (Kashiwara, Yuzuki, Tochimoto, Chuji, Akashi and Shimouzu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Uzu village there were six Oaza (Kashiwara, Yuzuki, Tochimoto, Chuji, Akashi and Shimouzu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Uzu village there were six Oaza (Kashiwara, Yuzuki, Tochimoto, Chuji, Akashi and Shimouzu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="84">
<j>旧細野村の区域は京北町大字細野となり、残りのの1町4村の計41の大字は引き続き京北町の大字となり、発足当初の京北町は42の大字で構成されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The area of the former Hosono village became Oaza Hosono, Keihoku Town, and the other total forty-one Oaza of one town and four villages became the Oaza in the Keihoku Town, so that there were forty-two Oaza in the Keihoku Town at the time of the establishment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The area of the former Hosono village became Oaza Hosono, Keihoku Town, and the other forty-one Oaza of one town and four villages became the Oaza in Keihoku Town, so that there were forty-two Oaza in the Keihoku Town at the time of establishment.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The area of the former Hosono village became Oaza Hosono, Keihoku Town, and the other forty-one Oaza (one town and four villages) became the Oaza in Keihoku Town, therefore, there were forty-two Oaza in the Keihoku Town at the time of establishment.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>ただし、地理的に京都市方面との関係が強い大字広河原は昭和32年（1957年）京都市左京区に編入されたため、以後は41大字となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, after the Oaza Hirogawara which was near to the Kyoto City was integrated into the Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City in 1957, there had been forty-one Oaza in the Keihoku Town.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after Oaza Hirogawara which was near Kyoto City was integrated into the Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City in 1957, this number was reduced to forty-one Oaza in Keihoku Town.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after Oaza Hirogawara which was near Kyoto City was integrated into the Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City in 1957, this number was reduced to forty-one Oaza in Keihoku Town.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="86">
<j>平成17年（2005年）、京北町は京都市右京区に編入され、41大字は「京北」を冠称する1,232町に編成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 2005, the Keihoku Town was integrated into the Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City, and the forty-one Oaza was reorganized into the 1,232 towns which had the name of &apos;Keihoku&apos; on the head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 2005, the Keihoku Town was integrated into Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City, and forty-one Oaza were reorganized into 1,232 towns which were prefixed by the name of &apos;Keihoku&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 2005, Keihoku Town was integrated into Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City, and forty-one Oaza were reorganized into 1,232 towns which were prefixed by the name of &apos;Keihoku.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>町名は下の例のように、従前の「京北町大字A字B」を「右京区京北A町B」と改称する原則によって命名されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a following example shows, the town&apos;s name of &apos;Aza B, Oaza A, Keihoku Town&apos; was changed to &apos;B, Keihoku-A-cho, Ukyo Ward,&apos; in principle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the following example shows, in principle, the town&apos;s name of &apos;Aza B, Oaza A, Keihoku Town&apos; was changed to &apos;B, Keihoku-A-cho, Ukyo Ward.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the following example shows, in principle, town&apos;s name of &apos;Aza B, Oaza A, Keihoku Town&apos; was changed to &apos;B, Keihoku-A-cho, Ukyo Ward.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="88">
<j>京都府北桑田郡京北町大字周山字上寺田 → 京都府京都市右京区京北周山町上寺田</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aza Kamiterada, Oaza Shuzan, Keihoku Town, Kitakuwada County, Kyoto Prefecture =&gt; Kamiterada, Keihoku-Shuzan-cho, Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aza Kamiterada, Oaza Shuzan, Keihoku Town, Kitakuwada County, Kyoto Prefecture =&gt; Kamiterada, Keihoku-Shuzan-cho, Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aza Kamiterada, Oaza Shuzan, Keihoku Town, Kitakuwada County, Kyoto Prefecture&apos; was changed to &apos;Kamiterada, Keihoku-Shuzan-cho, Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>備考</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Remarks</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Remarks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Remarks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="89">
<j>西京極樋ノ詰町</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nishikyogoku Hinotsume-cho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nishikyogoku Hinotsume-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nishikyogoku Hinotsume-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>- 地図にみえないが、『角川日本地名大辞典 26 京都府』（以下「角川」）には水路のみの無人町とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the second volume of &quot;the Kadokawa dictionary of the place-name of Japan, No.26 Kyoto Prefecture&quot; (&apos;Kadokawa&apos; in bellow), it is a town with only waterway where no one lives, although it is not seen on a map.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the second volume of &quot;the Kadokawa dictionary of the place-name of Japan, No.26 Kyoto Prefecture&quot; (&apos;Kadokawa&apos; in bellow), it is a town with a sole waterway devoid of people, although it is not shown on any map.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the second volume of &quot;Kadokawa Nihon Chimei Daijiten No. 26 Kyoto-Fu&quot; (Kadokawa dictionary of place-names of Japan, No.26 Kyoto Prefecture), (hereinafter &apos;Kadokawa&apos;), it is a town with a sole waterway uninhabited, even though it is not shown on any map.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="91">
<j>東梅津前子町</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Higashiumezu Maeko-cho</e>
<cmt>東梅津前子町の読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Higashiumezu Maeko-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Higashiumezu Maeko-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>- 地図にみえないが、「角川」には道路用地のみの無人町とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &apos;Kadokawa,&apos; it is a town with only road site where no one lives, although it is not seen on a map.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &apos;Kadokawa,&apos; it is the only town with a road devoid of any people, although this is not shown on any map.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &apos;Kadokawa,&apos; it is the only town inhabited having a road running through, even though this is not shown on any map.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="93">
<j>鳴滝池ノ谷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Narutaki Ikenotani</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Narutaki Ikenotani</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Narutaki Ikenotani</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>- 地図にみえないが、「角川」には山間部に位置する無人町とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &apos;Kadokawa,&apos; it is a mountain area where no one lives, although it is not seen on a map.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &apos;Kadokawa,&apos; it is a mountainous area where no one lives, although this is not shown on any map.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &apos;Kadokawa,&apos; it is a mountainous area where no one lives, although this is not shown on any map.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="95">
<j>梅ケ畑高雄西谷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Umegahata Takao Nishitani</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Umegahata Takao Nishitani</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Umegahata Takao Nishitani</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>- 地図にみえないが、「角川」には山間部に位置する無人町とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &apos;Kadokawa,&apos; it is a mountain area where no one lives, although it is not seen on a map.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &apos;Kadokawa,&apos; it is a mountainous area where no one lives, although this is not shown on any map.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &apos;Kadokawa,&apos; it is a mountainous area inhabited, even though this is not shown on any map.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="97">
<j>西京極郡附洲町（こおりつきすちょう）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nishikyogoku Kori Tsukisu-cho</e>
<cmt>「郡附洲町」はyu-bin.net には「ゴオリフズチョウ」とありますが、原文の読み方の通りにしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nishikyogoku Kori Tsukisu-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nishikyogoku Kori Tsukisu-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>郵便番号一覧表には当町が収録されているが、「角川」では昭和44年（1969年）に廃止された旧町とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &apos;Kadokawa,&apos; it was abolished in 1969, although there is the name on the postal code list.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &apos;Kadokawa,&apos; it was abolished in 1969, although the name is still on the postal code list.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &apos;Kadokawa,&apos; it was abolished in 1969, although the name is still on the postal code list.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>京都市の各区に属する公称町名を列挙した「京都市区の所管区域条例」（昭和24年4月1日京都市条例第7号）にも西京極郡附洲町の名はみえない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &apos;the ordinance on the area of the Kyoto City&apos; (the No.7 ordinance of the Kyoto City as of April 1, 1949), the name of Nishikyogoku Kori Tsukisu-cho is not seen as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &apos;the ordinance on the area of the Kyoto City&apos; (the No.7 ordinance of the Kyoto City as of April 1, 1949), the name of Nishikyogoku Kori Tsukisu-cho is not shown either.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &apos;the ordinance on the area of Kyoto City&apos; (the No. 7 ordinance of Kyoto City as of April 1, 1949), the name of Nishikyogoku Kori Tsukisu-cho is not shown either.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>本項「京都市右京区の町名」における現行町名数は便宜上「角川」の説に準じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For convenience, the town numbers in this section are based on the numbers described in the &apos;Kadokawa Dictionary.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For convenience, the town numbers in this section are based on the numbers described in the &apos;Kadokawa Dictionary.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For convenience, the town numbers in this section are based on the numbers described in the &apos;Kadokawa.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Ash(id:15625), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>