<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>宇川温泉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ukawa-onsen Hot-Spring</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ukawa-onsen Hot-Spring</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ukawa-onsen Hot Spring</e>
<cmt>Hot Spring としました。</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>宇川温泉（うかわおんせん）は、京都府京丹後市丹後町にある温泉。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ukawa-onsen Hot-Spring is located in Tango-cho, Kyotango City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ukawa-onsen Hot-Spring is located in Tango-cho, Kyotango City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ukawa-onsen Hot Spring is located in Tango-cho, Kyotango City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Hot Spring としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>アクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>鉄道：北近畿タンゴ鉄道 峰山駅下車、丹後海陸交通バスに乗り換え、久僧下車、徒歩5分。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Railways: Get off at Mineyama Station of Kitakinki Tango Railway, get on a bus of Tango Kairiku Totsu Bus, get off it at Kyoso and walk for five minutes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Railways: Get off at Mineyama Station on the Kitakinki Tango Railway, transfer to the Tango Kairiku Totsu Bus,,get off at Kyoso and walk for five minutes.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By train: Get off at Mineyama Station on the Kitakinki Tango Railway, transfer to the Tango Kairiku Kotsu Bus, get off at Kyoso and walk for five minutes.</e>
<cmt>by train としました。スペルなど修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>自動車：京都縦貫自動車道宮津天橋立インターチェンジから府道9号線を北に2kmを左折、国道176号を4.5km西進し岩滝口駅前を右折、さらに国道178号を北へ35km走り、久僧交差点を左折。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cars: Drive along prefectural road 9 from the Miyazu-Amanohashidate interchange of Kyoto Jukan Expressway (an expressway running through Kyoto Prefecture in the north-south direction) for 2 km to the north, turn to the left there, drive anong national road 176 for 45 km to the west, turn to the right in front of Iwatakiguchi Station, further drive along national road 178 for 35 km to the north and turn to the left at the Kyuso crossing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cars: Drive along prefectural road 9 from the Miyazu-Amanohashidate interchange of Kyoto Jukan Expressway (an expressway running through Kyoto Prefecture in the north-south direction) for 2 km to the north, turn to the left, drive along National Route 176 for 45 km to the west, turn to the right in front of Iwatakiguchi Station, then drive further along National Route 178 for 35 km to the north and turn to the left at the Kyuso crossing.</e>
<cmt>Improper terms, capitazliation, flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By car: Drive along Prefectural Route 9 from the Miyazu-Amanohashidate Interchange of Kyoto Longitudinal Expressway (an expressway running through Kyoto Prefecture in the north-south direction) for two kilometers to the north, turn to the left, drive along National Route 176 for 4.5 km to the west, turn to the right in front of Iwatakiguchi Station, then drive further along National Route 178 for thirty-five km to the north and turn to the left at the Kyuso crossing.</e>
<cmt>by train としました。数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>駐車場あり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A parking lot is provided.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A parking lot is provided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A parking lot is provided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>泉質</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The characteristics of the spring water</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The characteristics of the spring water</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hot spring water quality</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>アルカリ性単純温泉（低張性アルカリ性高温泉）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Simple alkaline hot spring (expansive high-temperature alkaline hot spring)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Simple alkaline hot spring (expansive high-temperature alkaline hot spring)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Simple alkaline hot spring (expansive high-temperature alkaline hot spring)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>効能</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The effects</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Effects</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Effects</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>神経痛、筋肉痛、疲労回復、慢性消化器病、五十肩など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hot spring is said to be effective for nerve pain, muscle pain, recovery from fatigue, chronic illness about digestive organs, shoulder ache of older persons, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hot spring is said to be effective for nerve pain, muscle pain, recovery from fatigue, chronic illness related to the digestive tract, shoulder aches in the elderly, etc</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hot spring is said to be effective for nerve pain, muscle pain, recovery from fatigue, chronic illness related to the digestive tract, shoulder aches in the elderly, etc</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>※効能はその効果を万人に保証するものではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">* The effects are not guaranteed for everyone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">* The effects are not guaranteed for everyone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">* The effects are not guaranteed for everyone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>温泉地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hot spring site</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hot spring site</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hot spring site</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>日帰り入浴施設兼宿泊施設である、「宇川温泉よし野の里」のみが存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only &quot;Yoshino no Sato, Ukawa Onsen,&quot; where you can stay overnight or can only bathe in the hot spring without staying overnight, is available.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only &quot;Yoshino no Sato, Ukawa Onsen,&quot;is the only onsen which has facilities for overnight and daytrip stays.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ukawa Onsen, Yoshino no Sato&apos; is the only facility for overnight and daytrip stays.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>海を望む高台の静かな環境にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is located in a quiet environment placed on a hill from where the sea can be viewed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is located in a quiet environment on a hill overlooking the sea.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is located in a quiet environment on a hill overlooking the sea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>高台の露天風呂から日本海が一望でき、美しい夕日が望めることで知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You can enjoy a panoramic view of Japan sea from an out-door bathing place on the hill, and in particular, it is known that the setting-sun view from there is beautiful.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You can enjoy a panoramic view of the Japan sea from an out-door bathing place on the hill, and in particular,the sunset is known as being particularly beautiful.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You can enjoy a panoramic view of the Japan Sea from an open-air bathtub on the hill, and in particular, the sunset is known as being particularly beautiful.</e>
<cmt>スペルなど修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また同施設は丹後町では初めての温泉施設でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The facility is the first hot spring facility in Tango-cho as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The facility was the first hot spring facility in Tango-cho as well.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The facility was the first hot spring facility in Tango-cho as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>日帰り入浴施設の浴場は天然木をふんだんに使った内湯や日本海や竹林を望む露天風呂など意匠性が高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bathing facilities for the customers who ccome only for bathing there, not staying overnight, are designed elaborately: For examples, the indoor bathing places are made of natural wood and you can view Japan sea and a bamboo forest from the outdoor bathing place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bathing facilies for customers visiting the hotspring for only the day are elaborate. For example, the indoor baths are made of natural wood with the Japan Sea viewable. Bamboo forests can be seen from the outdoor baths.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bathing facilities for customers visiting the hot spring for only the day are elaborate; for example, the indoor baths are made of natural wood with the Japan Sea viewable, and bamboo forests can be seen from the outdoor baths.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>浴場は”海の温泉「竜宮」”ならびに”山の温泉「香具夜」があり、日替わりで男湯と女湯が入れかわるが、特に露天風呂から息をのむほど美しい夕日が望める”海の温泉「竜宮」”は人気を呼んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two bathing places of &quot;Ryugu (assuming a hot spring in the sea)&quot; and &quot;Kaguya (assuming a hot spring in the mountain&quot; are provided, with use of each of them switched daily for male or female customers, but &quot;Ryugu (assuming a hot spring in the sea)&quot; is particularly popular, because it allows a breathlessly beautiful setting-sunsun view to be enjoyed from there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two baths, known as &quot;Ryugu (assuming a hot spring in the sea)&quot; and &quot;Kaguya (assuming a hot spring in the mountain&quot; are provided, with use switched daily for male or female customers, but &quot;Ryugu (assuming a hot spring in the sea)&quot; is particularly popular, because it allows a breathlessly beautiful sunset.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two baths, known as &apos;Ryugu&apos; (assuming a hot spring in the sea) and &apos;Kaguya&apos; (assuming a hot spring in the mountain) are provided, with use switched daily for male or female customers, but &apos;Ryugu&apos; is particularly popular, because it allows a breathlessly beautiful sunset.</e>
<cmt>&apos; としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>入浴レシートを提示すれば、館内滞在中であれば1度の入浴料金を払うことで何度でも温泉に入ることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once paying the bathing fare to enter the facility, you can use the bathing places any number of times by presenting the fare receipt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After paying the entrance fee to the bath facility, you may use the facility any number of times upon presenting the fare receipt.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After paying the entrance fee to the bath facility, you may enjoy the hot spring any number of times upon presenting the fare receipt while in the facility.</e>
<cmt>訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MD242(id:11277), Kenshiro.com(id:143072), Snake Head 1995(id:146125), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>