<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>祇園東</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gion Higashi (East Gion)</e>
<cmt>祇園東→Gion Higashi[”東”の意味を説明するため、英訳を付けました]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gion Higashi (East Gion)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gion Higashi (East Gion)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>祇園東（ぎおんひがし）は京都市東山区四条通花見小路通上ル東側に位置する花街。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gion Higashi is a geisha square located on the east side of Hanamikoji-dori Agaru, Shijo-dori, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gion Higashi is a hanamachi (&apos;flower town,&apos; or geisha district), located on the east side of Hanamikoji-dori Agaru, Shijo-dori, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>hanamachi (&apos;flower town,&apos; or geisha district),</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gion Higashi is a hanamachi (&apos;flower town,&apos; or geisha district), located on the east side of the north of the intersection of the Shijo-dori Street and the Hanami-koji Street, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>住所（場所）はこのようにしました。。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>江戸初期に八坂神社の門前で営業された水茶屋がこの花街の始まりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This geisha square started from the establishment of Mizujaya (public teahouse) operated in front of Yasaka-jinja Shrine during the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This geisha square started from the establishment of Mizujaya (public teahouse) which operated in front of Yasaka-jinja Shrine during the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>Edited for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It started with the opening of a tea house in front of the gate of the Yasaka-jinja Shrine in the beginning of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>他ファイルと統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>後に行政からも花街として公認されることになったが、この際に団子をモチーフにした紋章が作られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, it was also certified officially as geisha square by the administration, and at this time, an emblem in the motif of Dango (rice dumpling) was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, it was also officially certified as a geisha square by the administration, and at this time, an emblem in the motif of Dango (rice dumpling) was established.</e>
<cmt>Edited for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, it received official approval for the hanamachi, and the emblem featuring a dumpling cake was created.</e>
<cmt>他ファイルと統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>この紋章は 現在も祇園甲部と祇園東の紋章として使われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This emblem is used as an emblem of both Gion Ko-bu and Gion Higashi even now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This emblem is used as an emblem for both Gion Ko-bu and Gion Higashi.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is still used as an emblem for both Gion Kobu and Gion Higashi.</e>
<cmt>他ファイルと統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>江戸末期にはお茶屋が500軒、芸妓、舞妓、娼妓合わせて1000人以上いたといい、文人や政治家等に愛され大いに繁栄した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Gion Higashi had 500 Ochaya (teahouses), and at least 1,000 geisha girls, apprentice geisha and prostitutes in total, during the late Edo period, and was flourished greatly thanks to appreciation by literary persons, politicians, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Gion Higashi had 500 Ochaya (teahouses), and at least 1,000 geisha girls, apprentice geisha and prostitutes during the late Edo period, and flourished thanks to appreciation by literary persons, politicians, etc.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of the Edo period, it was said to have boasted five hundred tea houses and more than one thousand of geisha, apprentice geisha and shogi (prostitutes) in total, and flourished thanks to appreciation by many prominent figures such as literati and politicians.</e>
<cmt>他ファイルと統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>明治に入ると祇園甲部から分離独立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Meiji period, Gion Higashi was separated from Gion Ko-bu, and became independent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Meiji period, Gion Higashi was separated from Gion Ko-bu, and became independent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Meiji period, Gion Higashi was separated from Gion Kobu, and became independent.</e>
<cmt>kobu としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>一時は『祇園乙部』と称されたが、戦後は名称を『祇園東』に改め現在に至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gion Higashi was temporarily named &quot;Gion Otsu-bu,&quot; but the name was changed to &quot;Gion Higashi&quot; after the war, and this name is still used now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gion Higashi was temporarily named &quot;Gion Otsu-bu,&quot; but the name was changed to &quot;Gion Higashi&quot; after the war, which is still used to this day.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gion Higashi was temporarily named &quot;Gion Otsubu&quot; (&apos;ko&apos; and &apos;otsu&apos; in Japanese are equivalent to a and b in English), but the name was changed to &quot;Gion Higashi&quot; after the war, which is still used to this day.</e>
<cmt>otsubu としました。 甲と乙の説明を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>祇園東の一帯はかつて膳所藩屋敷が存在していたことから地元では『膳所裏』と呼ばれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The area around Gion Higashi used to be called &quot;Zezeura (back of Zeze)&quot; because residences of the Zeze clan existed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The area around Gion Higashi used to be called &quot;Zezeura (back of Zeze)&quot; due to the Zeze clan which used to reside in the area.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The area around Gion Higashi used to be called &quot; (back of Zeze) due to the Zeze clan which used to reside in the area.</e>
<cmt>括弧の位置を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>近年の芸妓数減少で後継者難に極めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is quite difficult to find successors because the number of geisha girls decreases recently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is quite difficult to find successors due to the recent decrease in geisha girls.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is quite difficult to find successors due to the recent decrease in geisha.</e>
<cmt>geisha で統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="10">
<j>毎年、秋になると「祇園をどり」が開催される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In autumn, &apos;Gion Odori (Gion Dance)&apos; is held every year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &apos;Gion Odori (Gion Dance)&apos; is held every year in autumn.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;Gion Odori&apos; (Gion Dance) is held every year in autumn.</e>
<cmt>括弧の位置を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>舞踊の流派は藤間流。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The school of dance belongs to Fujima-ryu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The school of dance belongs to Fujima-ryu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The school of dance belongs to Fujima School.</e>
<cmt>School を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="12">
<j>主な行事</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major events</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major events</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major events</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>祇園東にはこのような行事があり、かつて温習会、練り物が催しされていたが現在は廃絶になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Gion Higashi, the following events are held, and the Onshukai Dance Performance and parade float which used to be held are not held now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Gion Higashi, the following events are held, while the Onshukai Dance Performance and parade float which used to be held are no longler held.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Gion Higashi, the following events are held, while the Onshukai Dance Performance and parade float which used to be held are no longler held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="14">
<j>始業式</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Opening ceremony</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Opening ceremony</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigyo-shiki (opening ceremony)</e>
<cmt>他ファイルと統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>節分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Setsubun (Bean Throwing Night)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Setsubun (Bean Throwing Night)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Setsubun (Bean Throwing Night)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>五花街合同公演</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Joint Performances by Five Hanamachi (geisha square) of Kyoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Joint Performances by Five Hanamachi (geisha square) of Kyoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Special Traditional Joint Performances by Five Hanamachi of Kyoto</e>
<cmt>他ファイルと統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>祇園祭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gion Matsuri Festival</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gion Matsuri Festival</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gion Matsuri Festival</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>八朔</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1st of August (lunar calendar)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1st of August (lunar calendar)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hassaku (an event in which geisha visit their teachers and teahouses to thank them) on August 1</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>祇園をどり</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gion Odori Dance</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gion Odori Dance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gion Odori Dance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>顔見世総見</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaomise Soken (theater-going to Grand Kabuki Show with an All-Star Cast by all geisha girls and apprentice geisha in each geisha quarter)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaomise Soken (theater-going to Grand Kabuki Show with an All-Star Cast by all geisha girls and apprentice geisha in each geisha quarter)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaomise soken (kabuki viewing by a group of geisha in the hanamachi)</e>
<cmt>他ファイルと統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>事始め</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kotohajime (traditional event held on December 13 to start preparations for New Year&apos;s Holidays)</e>
<cmt>事始め→Kotohajime (traditional event held on December 13 to start preparations for New Year&apos;s Holidays, and for geisha girls and apprentic geisha to visit their instructors of accomplishments and teahouses in order to convey their appreciation for the year and their promise of devotion for the coming year)[”事始め”とは、”12月13日に正月の準備を始める伝統行事”なので、説明の英訳を付記しました]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kotohajime (traditional event held on December 13 to start preparations for New Year&apos;s Holidays)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kotohajime (an event in which geisha visit their teachers and teahouses to thank them for their support in the year and for continued support in the new year)</e>
<cmt>他ファイルと統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Huemat(id:19503), 663highland(id:18755), Miyuki h(id:84952), 商事品川(id:68669), 今紫(id:9521), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>