<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>音羽山 (滋賀県・京都府)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otowa-yama Mountain (in Shiga prefecture and Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otowa-yama Mountain (in Shiga prefecture and Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mt. Otowa (Shiga Prefecture, Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>Mt. Otowa としました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>音羽山（おとわやま）は、滋賀県大津市と京都府京都市山科区の境界に所在する山で、山科区の最高峰である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otowa-yama Mountain exists at a boundary between Otsu City of Shiga prefecture and Yamashina Ward of Kyoto Prefecture, and is the highest one in Yamashina Ward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otowa-yama Mountain exists in the boundary between Otsu City of Shiga prefecture and Yamashina Ward of Kyoto Prefecture, and is the highest mountain in Yamashina Ward.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mt. Otowa exists in the boundary between Otsu City of Shiga prefecture and Yamashina Ward of Kyoto Prefecture, and is the highest mountain in Yamashina Ward.</e>
<cmt>Mt. Otowa としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>標高は593.2m。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its altitude is 593.2 m.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its altitude is 593.2 m.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its altitude is 593.2 m.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>山頂の三等三角点は山科区に所在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A third grade point of triangulation at the top of the mountain is placed in Yamashina Ward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A third grade point triangulation point is located at the top of the mountain within Yamashina Ward.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A third class triangulation point at the top of the mountain is located within Yamashina Ward.</e>
<cmt>三等三角点→A third class triangulation point　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>山科盆地の東、琵琶湖の南西に位置し、北には逢坂山、南には醍醐の山々が連なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is located in the east of Yamashina-bonchi Basin and in the southwest of Lake Biwa, with Osaka-yama Mountain in its north and many mountains in its southern area of Daigo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is located in eastern Yamashina-bonchi Basin and southwest of Lake Biwa, with Osaka-yama Mountain to the north and many mountains in the southern area of Daigo.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is located in eastern Yamashina Basin and southwest of Lake Biwa, with Mt. Osaka to the north and many mountains in the southern area of Daigo.</e>
<cmt>Mt. Osaka、Yamashina Basinとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>近江国と山城国の国境を形成していたことから、逢坂山との山間は古くより交通の要所となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because it was located at a boundary between Omi Province and Yamashiro Province, the area between this mountain and Osaka-yama Mountain was a strategic point for transportation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to its being located at a boundary between Omi Province and Yamashiro Province, the area between this mountain and Osaka-yama Mountain was a strategic point for transportation.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to its being located at a boundary between Omi Province and Yamashiro Province, the area between this mountain and Mt. Osaka was a strategic point for transportation.</e>
<cmt>Mt. Osaka としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>音羽山の支峰である牛尾山には法厳寺（牛尾観音）が創建され、同寺に対する信仰が広まるにつれ、音羽山も名所として知られていくこととなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hogon-ji Temple (Ushio Kannon) was established at Ushio-san Mountain, which is a branch peak of Otawa-san Mountain, and with the temple becoming worshiped widely, Otowa-yama Mountain has also become known as a place of interest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hogon-ji Temple (Ushio Kannon) was established at Ushio-san Mountain, which is a branch peak of Otawa-san Mountain. Otowa-yama Mountain became a place of interest after the temple bcame a popular for worship</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hogon-ji Temple (Ushio Kannon) was established at Mt. Ushio, which is a branch peak of Mt. Otowa; Mt. Otowa became a place of interest after the temple became a popular for worship.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>紀貫之、在原元方など多くの歌人が音羽山を歌枕として詠んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many poets, including KI no Tsurayukia and ARIWARA no Motokata, composed poems with Otowa-san used as an untamakura (a place name often used in ancient Japanes poems).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many poets, including KI no Tsurayukia and ARIWARA no Motokata, composed poems with Otowa-san used as an untamakura (a place name often used in ancient Japanes poems).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many poets, including KI no Tsurayuki and ARIWARA no Motokata, composed poems with &quot;Otowa-yama&quot; (Mt. Otowa) used as an utamakura (a place name often used in ancient Japans poems).</e>
<cmt>一部表現、スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、京都に三ヶ所所在したとされる「音羽の滝」のうち、「牛尾の音羽」については音羽山の西腹を流れる山科音羽川の滝と比定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of the three Otowa-no-taki Falls said to have been in Kyoto, &quot;Ushio-no-Otowa&quot; has been identified as a fall of Yamashina-Otowa-gawa River, which flows along the west foot of Otowa-san Mountain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of the three Otowa-no-taki Falls said to have been in Kyoto, &quot;Ushio-no-Otowa&quot; has been identified as a fall of Yamashina-Otowa-gawa River, which flows along the west foot of Otowa-san Mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of the three &apos;Otowa-no-taki Falls&apos; said to have been in Kyoto, &apos;Ushio-no-Otowa&apos; has been identified as a fall of Yamashina-Otowa-gawa River, which flows along the west foot of Mt. Otowa.</e>
<cmt>Mt. Otowa としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>「雍州府志」によると、江戸時代頃には小山とも呼ばれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Yoshu-shoshi (a book describing various aspects of Yamashiro Province), this mountain was also called Oyama Mountain (小山).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Yoshu-shoshi (a book describing various aspects of Yamashiro Province), this mountain was also called Oyama Mountain (小山).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &apos;Yoshu-shoshi&apos; (a book describing various aspects of Yamashiro Province), this mountain was also called Mt. Oyama (小山).</e>
<cmt>&apos; を追加しました。Mt. Oyama を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>「点の記」でも三角点の点名を「小山」としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The point of triangulation was listed as &quot;Oyama&quot; in &quot;Ten-no-ki (Records of points of triangulation)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The point of triangulation was listed as &quot;Oyama&quot; in &quot;Ten-no-ki (Records of points of triangulation)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The point of triangulation was listed as &apos;Oyama&apos; in &apos;Ten-no-ki&apos; (Records of points of triangulation).</e>
<cmt>&apos; を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>現代では東海自然歩道が山中を通過しており、また山頂からの展望も良いことから、一年を通じてハイカーが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, since the Tokai-shizen-hodo (Tokai walking path full of nature) runs through the mountain and the view from the mountain top is beautiful, many hikers visits this mountain all year round.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, since the Tokai-shizen-hodo (Tokai walking path full of nature) runs through the mountain and the view from the mountain top is beautiful, many hikers visits this mountain all year round.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, since the Tokai-shizen-hodo (Tokai walking path full of nature) runs through the mountain and the view from the mountain top is beautiful, many hikers visit this mountain all year round.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>登山道としては、大津市側の石山寺から東海自然歩道を経て登る、山科盆地側から牛尾観音を経て登る、逢坂山側から東海自然歩道を経て登る、などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the Otsu City side, the mountain is climed from Ishiyama-dera Temple via the Tokai-shizen-hodo, from the Yamashina basin side, via Ushio kannon, and from the Osaka-yam Mountain side, via the Tokai-shizen-hodo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the Otsu City side, the mountain can be climbed from Ishiyama-dera Temple via the Tokai-shizen-hodo, from the Yamashina basin side, via Ushio kannon, and from the Osaka-yam Mountain side, via the Tokai-shizen-hodo.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the Otsu City side, the mountain can be climbed from Ishiyama-dera Temple via the Tokai-shizen-hodo, from the Yamashina Basin side, via Ushio kannon, and from the Mt. Osaka side, via the Tokai-shizen-hodo.</e>
<cmt>Mt. Osaka としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>通行する鉄道・道路など</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Railways, roads, etc through the mountain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Railways, roads, etc through the mountain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Railroads, roads, etc through the mountain</e>
<cmt>railroads としました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>山頂直下を東海道新幹線のトンネルが通じており、逢坂山との山間部には京阪京津線が通じている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A tunnel for Tokaido Shinkansen (a Japanese bullet train line) passes through directly under the mountain top and the Keihan Keishin Line runs between this mountain and Osaka-yama Mountain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A tunnel for Tokaido Shinkansen (a Japanese bullet train line) passes directly under the mountain top and the Keihan Keishin Line runs between this mountain and Osaka-yama Mountain.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A tunnel for Tokaido Shinkansen (a Japanese bullet train line) passes directly under the mountain top and the Keihan Keishin Line runs between this mountain and Mt. Osaka.</e>
<cmt>Mt. Osaka としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>東海自然歩道が山中を通じており、東の石山寺方面から山頂付近、北の逢坂山方面を接続する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tokai-shizen-hodo, which passes through this mountain, connects the Ishiyama-dera Temple side in the east to around the mountain top and to the Osaka-yama side in the north.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tokai-shizen-hodo, which passes through this mountain, connects the Ishiyama-dera Temple side in the east to the mountain top and to the Osaka-yama side in the north.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tokai-shizen-hodo, which passes through this mountain, connects the Ishiyama-dera Temple side in the east to the mountain top and to the Mt. Osaka side in the north.</e>
<cmt>Mt. Osaka としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Ilovekyoto(id:94930), 春野秋葉(id:36725), Sbc(id:64835), ぱむ(id:24323), Goncyan(id:92158), Volfgang(id:98768), R28Bot(id:177951), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>