<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>雲母坂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kirara-zaka Slope</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kirara-zaka Slope</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kirara-zaka Slope</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>雲母坂（きららざか）は、京都市左京区修学院の修学院離宮脇より、比叡山の山頂に至る古道であり、また、延暦寺千日回峰行の行者道でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kirara-zaka Slope indicates the old road to the mountain top of Hiei-zan Mountain from a side of Shugakuin Rikyu (the Shugakuin imperial villa) in Shugakuin, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City, and is also a road used by the ascetics who practiced Sennichi-kaihogyo (a practice of walking around the mountain while paying visits to various sacred places for 1,000 day in total).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kirara-zaka Slope indicates the old road to the top of Hiei-zan Mountain from the side of Shugakuin Rikyu (the Shugakuin imperial villa) in Shugakuin, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City, and is also a road used by the ascetics who practiced Sennichi-kaihogyo (a practice of walking around the mountain while paying visits to various sacred places for 1,000 day in total).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kirara-zaka Slope indicates the old road to the top of Mt. Hiei from the side of Shugakuin Rikyu (the Shugakuin imperial villa) in Shugakuin, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City, and is also a road used by the ascetics who practiced Sennichi-kaihogyo (a practice of walking around the mountain while paying visits to various sacred places for 1,000 day in total).</e>
<cmt>Mt. Hiei としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>現在ではこの登山道が雲母坂として知られているが、具体的場所については同じくこの行者道の一部であった京都市左京区一乗寺 (京都市)の曼殊院道（京都府道104号高野修学院山端線部分）や、曼殊院参道とする説などもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, this mountain-climbing path is known as Kirara-zaka Slope, but there are other opinions saying that Kirara-zaka Slope indicates Manshuin-michi Road (the Takano Shugakuin-Yamabana road portion of Kyoto Prefectural road 104) in Ichijo-ji, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City or the road to approach Manju-in Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present, this path is known as Kirara-zaka Slope, but there are other theories which say that Kirara-zaka Slope indicates Manshuin-michi Road (the Takano Shugakuin-Yamabana road portion of Kyoto Prefectural road 104) in Ichijo-ji, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City or the road approaching Manju-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present, this path is known as Kirara-zaka Slope, but there are other theories which say that Kirara-zaka Slope indicates Manshuin-michi Road (the portion of the Takano Shugakuin-Yamabana Line of Kyoto Prefectural Route 104), which was also a road used by the ascetics, in Ichijo-ji, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City or the road approaching Manju-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>道路表現を統一しました。翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>坂の名である「雲母」の由縁は、この山道が花崗岩の砕けた地質であり、土砂中に雲母が含まれていることによる、とされるが、異説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason why the name of the slope is Kirara is said that the soil of the mountain path includes cracked granite, including Kirara (雲母: mica), but there exist other opinions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason why the name of the slope is Kirara is said to be due to the inclusion of cracked granite, which includes Kirara (雲母: mica), but other theories exist as well.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason why the name of the slope is Kirara is said to be due to the inclusion of cracked granite, which includes Kirara (雲母: mica), but other theories exist as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>なお上記場所についての異説の坂も舗装前は同様の地質であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The soils of the other slopes, said as candidate roads for the Kirara-zaka Slope as well, were simliar to that described above, before the roads were paved</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soil found at other slopes is similar in composition as to the description above, before the roads were paved.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soil found at other slopes mentioned above is similar in composition as to the description above, before the roads were paved.</e>
<cmt>「上記場所」を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経路</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>現在のこの登山道への経路は、叡山電鉄叡山本線修学院駅または京都市バス修学院離宮道より東方の山側に向かい、音羽川 (京都府)に沿った道を登る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To reach the present mountain-climbing road, walk toward the montain side in the east from Shugakuin Station on the Eizan Line of Eizan Electric Railway or from the Shugakuin Rikyu-michi Road bus stop of Kyoto City Bus, and then climb along the Otowa-gawa River (in Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To reach the present path up the mountain, walk toward the montain side from the the east from Shugakuin Station on the Eizan Line of Eizan Electric Railway or from the Shugakuin Rikyu-michi Road bus stop of Kyoto City Bus, and then climb along the Otowa-gawa River (in Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To reach the present path up the mountain, walk toward the mountain side from the east from Shugakuin Station on the Eizan Line of Eizan Electric Railway or from the Shugakuin Rikyu-michi Road bus stop of Kyoto City Bus, and then climb along the Otowa-gawa River (Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>スペル、ダブりを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>住宅街を抜け、雲母橋に至れば、そこが登山口である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You will reach Kirara-bashi Bridge after walking through a residential area, and the mountain-climbing road starts there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You will reach Kirara-bashi Bridge after walking through a residential area, where the path starts.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You will reach Kirara-bashi Bridge after walking through a residential area, where the path starts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>現在では親鸞ゆかりの石碑が立ち、音羽川 (京都府)の防災の仕組を示した公園になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A stone monument related to Shinran (a famous priest in the Kamakura era) is placed there, and the area around it has become a park to show how to prevent disaster in the Otowa-gawa River (in Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A stone monument related to Shinran (a famous priest in the Kamakura era) is placed there, and the area around it has become a park to show how to prevent disaster in the Otowa-gawa River (in Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A stone monument related to Shinran (a famous priest in the Kamakura period) is placed there, and the area around it has become a park to show how to prevent disaster in the Otowa-gawa River (Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>括弧内のin を削除しました。Era →　period としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>なお登山口までは通常の服装でも行けるが、登山口近くは舗装されて居ない小石のゴロゴロした道であることは注意を要する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You can reach the place from where you start climbing the mountain, wearing ordinary attire including shoes, but you must note that the area around the place is not paved, being full of many small stones.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the entrance to the path can be reached while wearing ordinary attire, it should be noted that the surrounding area is not paved and full of many small stones.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the entrance to the path can be reached while wearing ordinary attire, it should be noted that the surrounding area is not paved and full of many small stones.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>ここから修学院離宮の外縁を巡る登山道を登る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From there, climb the road around the periphery of Shugakuin Rikyu (the Shugakuin imperial villa).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From there, climb the road around the periphery of Shugakuin Rikyu (the Shugakuin imperial villa).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From there, climb the road around the periphery of Shugakuin Rikyu (the Shugakuin imperial villa).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>深くえぐれた様が、この坂の古さを物語る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The road is hollowed out in various places, showing how long this road has been used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The road is hollowed out in various places, signifying just how long this road has been used.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The road is hollowed out in various places, signifying just how long this road has been used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>水飲対陣跡を過ぎれば、眺望も開け、やがて、京福電気鉄道鋼索線のケーブル比叡駅に到着する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After passing &quot;Mizunomi-taizin-no-ato (a historical battle site),&quot; you will become able to enjoy viewing scenery, soon arriving at Cable Hiei Station of Keifuku Electric Railroad Kosaku Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After passing &quot;Mizunomi-taizin-no-ato (a historical battle site),&quot; the area opens up to beautiful scenery before soon arriving at Cable Hiei Station of Keifuku Electric Railroad Kosaku Line.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After passing &quot;Mizunomi-taizin-no-ato (a historical battle site),&quot; the area opens up to beautiful scenery before soon arriving at Cable Hiei Station of Keifuku Electric Railroad Kosaku Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>上記異説の坂のある曼殊院道を辿るのであれば叡山電鉄叡山本線一乗寺駅または京都市バス・京都バス一条寺下り松町バス停より東（山側）に向かい一条寺下り松の前を左に折れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To visit Manshuin-michi Road, another candidate for real Kirara-zaka Slope, walk to the east (in the direction of the mountain) from Ichijoji Station on the Eizan Line of Eizan Electric Railway or from the Ichijoji-Sagari-Matsucho bus stop for buses of Kyo to CIty Bus or for Kyoto Bus and turn to the left in front of Ichijoji-Sagari-Matsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To visit Manshuin-michi Road, another alternative to the actual Kirara-zaka Slope, walk to the east (in the direction of the mountain) from Ichijoji Station on the Eizan Line of Eizan Electric Railway or from the Ichijoji-Sagari-Matsucho bus stop for buses of Kyo to CIty Bus or for Kyoto Bus and turn left in front of Ichijoji-Sagari-Matsu.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To visit Manshuin-michi Road, another alternative to the actual Kirara-zaka Slope, walk to the east (in the direction of the mountain) from Ichijoji Station on the Eizan Line of Eizan Electric Railway or from the Ichijoji-Sagari-Matsucho bus stop of Kyoto City Bus and turn left in front of Ichijoji-Sagari-Matsu.</e>
<cmt>ダブりを削除しました（京都バスのくだり）。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>小さな川を渡った先の坂が1つ目の異説の坂である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After crossing a small river, you reach the first of the other candidate slopes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After crossing a small river, you will reach the first of the alternative slopes.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After crossing a small river, you will reach the first of the alternative slopes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>さらに先、2又に分かれる道を右側に進み、鷺の森神社の森を左手に見て、また小さな川を渡った先の坂が2つ目の異説の坂である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further walk and you reach a fork, take the road on the right, walk again while seeing the woods of Saginomori-jinja Shrine on the left, cross a small river again and you reach the second candidate slope.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Walk further, and you will reach a fork in the road. Take the road on the right, and walk straight ahead. Keep the woods of Saginomori-jinja Shrine on the left, and cross a small river again to reach the second alternative slope</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Walk further, and you will reach a fork in the road; take the road on the right, and walk straight ahead; keep the woods of Saginomori-jinja Shrine on the left, and cross a small river again to reach the second alternative slope</e>
<cmt>一つの文章にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>坂を登り曼殊院の前を左に折れ、修学院の町並を見下ろすように進むと屋敷に突き当たり道は左側に折れるが、その塀の横の坂を正面方向に下れば音羽川沿いに出る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Turn to the left on the uphill road in front of Manshu-in Temple, walk along the road, which allow you to look down the Shugakuin area, up to a mansion where the road turns to the left, walk down the slope beside the wall of the mansion, in the direction of going to the front side of the mansion, and you will reach a road along the Otowa-gawa River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Turn to the left on the road uphill in front of Manshu-in Temple, walk along the road, which allows you to look down the Shugakuin area, up to a mansion where the road turns to the left, walk down the slope beside the wall of the mansion, as if approaching the front side of the mansion, and you will reach a road along the Otowa-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Turn to the left on the road uphill in front of Manshu-in Temple, walk along the road, which allows you to look down the Shugakuin area, up to a mansion where the road turns to the left, walk down the slope beside the wall of the mansion, as if approaching the front side of the mansion, and you will reach a road along the Otowa-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>右に登ればすぐ登山口に着く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Walk up to the right, and you soon arrive at the place where the mountain-climbing road starts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Walk up to the right, and you soon arrive at the place where the path up the mountain starts.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Walk up to the right, and you soon arrive at the place where the path up the mountain starts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 七之輔(id:55793), Hideyuki(id:9577), Nyao148(id:93723), Ohura(id:5986), Chi-Ham(id:143515), Y3006(id:155535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>