<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>樫原</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katagihara</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katagihara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katagihara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>樫原（かたぎはら）とは、京都市西京区の一部をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katagihara refers to a part of Nishikyo Ward Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katagihara refers to a part of Nishikyo Ward Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katagihara refers to a part of Nishikyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>カンマを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>樫原は南北に通じる物集女街道、東西にのびる山陰街道の結節点にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The north-south running Mozume Kaido Road and the east-west running Sanin Kaido Road join in Katagihara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mozume Kaido Road running north-south and the Sanin Kaido Road running east-west join in Katagihara.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mozume Kaido Road running north-south and the Sanin Kaido Road running east-west join in Katagihara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>物集女街道は北摂から京都市域に入る幹線道路であり、嵐山に通じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mozume Kaido Road is a highway that extends from Hokusetsu to Kyoto City, and it continues to Arashiyama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mozume Kaido Road is a highway that extends from Hokusetsu to Kyoto City, and continues to Arashiyama.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mozume Kaido Road is a highway that extends from Hokusetsu to Kyoto City, and continues to Arashiyama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>四条街道と通じ、梅津や桂、嵐山の木材湾港と通じる古くからの商業路である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Connected to the Shijo Kaido Road, it has long been a road for a commercial use that leads not only to the Shijo Kaido Road but also to the river ports for lumbers located in Umezu, Katsura, and Arashiyama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Connected to the Shijo Kaido Road, it has long been a road for commercial use that leads not only to the Shijo Kaido Road but also to the river ports for lumbers located in Umezu, Katsura, and Arashiyama.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Connected to the Shijo Kaido Road, it has long been a road for commercial use that leads to the river ports for lumbers located in Umezu, Katsura, and Arashiyama.</e>
<cmt>ダブりを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>山陰街道は大枝山方面から丹波国地方にのびる幹線道路である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sanin Kaido Road is a highway that extends from Oe-yama Mountain toward the region of Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sanin Kaido Road is a highway that extends from Oe-yama Mountain toward the region of Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sanin Kaido Road is a highway that extends from the direction of Mt. Oe toward the region of Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt>Mt. Oe としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>樫原はこのような交通の要衝であることから、古くから街道町として栄えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such a transportation hub, Katagihara has long thrived as a town on a highway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a transportation hub, Katagihara has long thrived as a town on a highway.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a transportation hub, Katagihara has long thrived as a town on a highway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>丹波方面の計略を命じられた戦国時代の明智光秀による整備の歴史も語られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a historical story that Mitsuhide AKECHI, who was told to plan a strategy for seizing regions in Tanba Province, improved the roads during the age of civil war.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is story that says that Mitsuhide AKECHI, who was told to plan a strategy for seizing regions in Tanba Province, improved the roads during the warring states period.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a story that says that Mitsuhide AKECHI, who was told to plan a strategy for seizing regions in Tanba Province, improved the roads during the warring states period.</e>
<cmt>a story としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>幕末には志士を匿う豪商も多く存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the end of Edo Period, there were many wealthy merchants who gave shelters to loyal supporters.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the end of Edo Period, there were many wealthy merchants who gave shelter to loyal supporters.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the end of Edo period, there were many wealthy merchants who gave shelter to loyal supporters.</e>
<cmt>period を小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>ちなみに近郊の川島には、志士を経済的に支えた土豪・革嶋氏の拠点がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this connection, a local clan, Kawashima clan was based on nearby region, Kawashima, and gave financial support to the loyalists.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Addtionaly, a local clan, Kawashima clan was based out of a nearby region, Kawashima, and gave financial support to the loyalists.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, a local clan, Kawashima clan was based out of a nearby region, Kawashima, and gave financial support to the loyalists.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>現在も交通の要衝である一方、洛西ニュータウンと京都市域の連絡路であり、住宅街でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katagihara has still served as a transport hub, and today it is a transfer point between Kyoto City and Rakusai New Town and a residential area..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katagihara still served as a transport hub, and today is a transfer point between Kyoto City and Rakusai New Town as well as a residential area..</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Katagihara still serves as a transport hub, it is also a transfer point between Kyoto City and Rakusai New Town as well as a residential area today.</e>
<cmt>一部表現を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mnd(id:15140), Kusunose(id:5719), ＋－(id:17104), Saft(id:100518), Memeja(id:110500), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>