<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>洞ヶ峠</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Horaga-toge Pass</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Horaga-toge Pass</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Horaga-toge Pass</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>洞ヶ峠（ほらがとうげ）は、京都府八幡市八幡南山 と 大阪府枚方市高野道・長尾峠町の境にある峠。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Horaga-toge Pass is the pass forming the boundary between Yawata Minamiyama, Yawata City, Kyoto Prefecture and Nagaotoge-cho, Koyamichi, Hirakata City, Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Horaga-toge Pass is the pass forming the boundary between Yawata Minamiyama, Yawata City, Kyoto Prefecture and Nagaotoge-cho, Koyamichi, Hirakata City, Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Horaga-toge Pass is the pass forming the boundary between Yawata Minamiyama - Yawata City - Kyoto Prefecture and Nagaotoge-cho - Koyamichi - Hirakata City - Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>かつては東高野街道の中継地であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It used to be a stopping point of Higashi Koya-Kaido Road. National Route 1(Hirakata Bypass, Keihan-kokudo) runs a little east of the pass and Yawata-Horagatoge crossing (a crossing of Yamate Highway (Kyoto Prefecture)) is located just above (in the north of) the pass.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It used to be a stopping point on Higashi Koya-Kaido Road. National Route 1 (Hirakata Bypass, Keihan-kokudo) runs a little east of the pass and Yawata-Horagatoge crossing (a crossing on Yamate Highway - Kyoto Prefecture) is located just above (north of) the pass.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It used to be a relay station on Higashi Koya-Kaido Road (an ancient highway between Kyoto and Mt. Koya).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>現在はその少し東を国道1号（枚方バイパス、京阪国道）が通っており、峠のすぐ北に 八幡洞ヶ峠交差点（山手幹線 (京都府)の交点）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, National Route 1 (Hirakata Bypass, Keihan-kokudo National Road) runs slightly east of the pass and Yawata-Horagatoge crossing (a crossing on Yamate Highway - Kyoto Prefecture) is located immediately north of the pass.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>峠ではあるが、曲がりくねった坂道はなく、線形 (路線)の良い緩やかな勾配の4車線道路である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it is a pass, it is not a winding slope but a low-angled, good line-shaped four-lane roadway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is a pass, it is not a winding slope but a low-angled, good line-shaped four-lane roadway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is a pass, it is a low-angled, good line-shaped four-lane roadway without a winding slope.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>伝承</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tradition</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tradition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tradition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>峠のすぐ南西側の枚方市内に枚方バイパスに沿って「高野道」という地名（かつての集落名）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Hirakata city, which is in the southwestward of the pass, along Hirakata Bypass is a geographical name, &apos;Koyamichi&apos; (the name of a former settlement). The name derives from the road, leading to Mt. Koya, in the settlement near the pass.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Hirakata city, which is southwest of the pass, along Hirakata Bypass is a geographical name, &apos;Koyamichi&apos; (the name of a former settlement). The name derives from the road, leading to Mt. Koya, in the settlement near the pass.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Hirakata City, which is southwest of the pass, along the Hirakata Bypass is the area called &apos;Koyamichi&apos; (the name of a former settlement).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>峠のすぐ近くにあった集落に高野山へ続く街道が通っていたことが由来とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name is considered to derive from the road, leading to Mt. Koya, through the settlement near the pass.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>天正10年（1582年）、本能寺の変の直後に主君織田信長を討った明智光秀の軍と信長の重臣豊臣秀吉の軍が山城国山崎において激突した（山崎の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1582, soon after the Honnoji Incident, the army of Mitsuhide AKECHI, who killed his lord, Nobunaga ODA foughtagainst the army of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, a senior vassal of Nobunaga&apos;s at Yamazaki in Yamashiro Province (the Battle of Yamazaki).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1582, soon after the Honnoji Incident, the army of Mitsuhide AKECHI, (who killed his lord, Nobunaga ODA) fought against the army of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, a senior vassal of Nobunaga&apos;s at Yamazaki in Yamashiro Province (the Battle of Yamazaki).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1582, soon after the Honnoji Incident (June 21, 1582), the army of Mitsuhide AKECHI (who killed his lord Nobunaga ODA in the incident) fought against the army of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI (a senior vassal of Nobunaga) at Yamazaki in Yamashiro Province (the Battle of Yamazaki, July 2, 1582).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>この時、明智・羽柴の双方から加勢を依頼された大和国の戦国大名筒井順慶は、一度は明智側に従って山崎の南方にある洞ヶ峠まで兵を進めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Junkei TSUTSUI, a daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) in the Sengoku period, who was asked to support by both AKECHI and HASHIBA (Hideyoshi), once obeyed Akechi and advanced to Horaga-toge Pass, the southern part of Yamazaki. A legend said that Junkei was opportunistic, postponing deciding which side to support. Because of the legend, being opportunistic is sometimes described as being at Horaga-toge Pass.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Junkei TSUTSUI, a daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) during the Sengoku period, who was asked for support by both AKECHI and HASHIBA (Hideyoshi), obeyed Akechi and advanced to Horaga-toge Pass, the southern part of Yamazaki. Legend said that Junkei was opportunistic, postponing the decision as to which side to support. Because of the legend, being opportunistic is sometimes described as being at Horaga-toge Pass.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation, word spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this battle, Junkei TSUTSUI, a Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period), who was asked for support by both AKECHI and HASHIBA (TOYOTOMI), once took the side of Akechi and advanced to Horaga-toge Pass, which was located at south of Yamazaki.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>最終的にはどちらに付くか日和見主義をしたとの伝説が在る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But according to a legend, Junkei was opportunistic, postponing the decision as to which side to support.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>この為、日和見する事を洞ヶ峠と表現する事がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, being opportunistic is sometimes described as being at &apos;Horaga-toge Pass&apos;.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし、この伝説は史実に反している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this legend was against historical evidence. It is said that Junkei TSUTSUI didn&apos;t reach Horaga-toge Pass but withdrew to Yamato and straddled the fence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this legend goes against historical evidence. It is said that Junkei TSUTSUI didn&apos;t reach Horaga-toge Pass, but withdrew to Yamato and straddled the fence.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this legend goes against historical evidence.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>筒井順慶は最終的には洞ヶ峠に着くことなく大和へと撤兵して中立を保ったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Junkei TSUTSUI finally withdrew his army to Yamato to remain neutral, without reaching to Horaga-toge Pass.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>史実に関連するもののほかに、この峠は京の都・大坂を眺望できるため、民話の舞台となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to historical evidence, folktales related with this pass were made since the pass commanded an extensive prospect of Kyoto and Osaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to the historical evidence, folktales related to this pass abound because the pass held an extensive potential for Kyoto and Osaka.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally to the historical evidence, folktales related to this pass are many because the pass commands a panoramic view of Kyoto and Osaka.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>心霊スポット</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Psychic spot</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Psychic spot</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Psychic spot</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>1990年代初頭までこの周囲は雑木林で照明設備が少なく、昼夜問わず寂しさを感じさせていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until the early 1990s, the pass was a wooded area with few lighting facilities. The pass made people feel lonely noon and night.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until the early 1990s, the pass was a wooded area with few facilities for light. The pass made people feel lonely at noon as well as at night.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until the early 1990s, the pass was a wooded area with sparsely placed lights, making people feel lonely even in the daytime as well as at night.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>それゆえに幽霊がよく現れる場所、つまり「心霊スポット」としてよく知られ、地元住民やここを通行する人々の間で様々な伝説が語られてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So, the pass was known as a haunted area, or a &apos;psychic spot.&apos; The local public and the passers-by had various legends.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So, the pass was thought of as a haunted area, or a &apos;psychic spot.&apos; The local public and the passers-by created various legends.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the pass was thought of as a haunted area, or a &apos;ghostly place&apos;, and the local public and the passersby created various legends.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>雑誌やテレビにもしばしば取り上げられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The pass was often explained by magazines and television.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The pass was often described in magazines and on television.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The pass has been often reported in magazines and on television.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="19">
<j>現況</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The current state</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The current state</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The current situation</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>1966年に枚方バイパス（京阪国道）が開通し、1990年代に入ると住宅地や学校が建設され、峠周辺の様子は一変した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1966 Hirakata Bypass (Keihan-kokudo National Road) was opened. In 1990s, residential areas and schools were established, which changed the pass&apos;s surroundings greatly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1966 Hirakata Bypass (Keihan-kokudo National Road) was opened. In the 1990s, residential areas and schools were established, which greatly changed the pass&apos;s surroundings.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1966, Hirakata Bypass (Keihan-kokudo National Road) was opened, then in the 1990s, residential areas and schools were established, which greatly improved the pass&apos;s surroundings.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>交通量が多いことから、アミューズメント施設やファミリーレストランなどが続々と建設された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The busy traffic led to continuous establishment of amusiment facilities and family restaurants, and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The busy traffic led to the continuous establishment of amusiment facilities and family restaurants, and so on.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The traffic was heavy there, which led to the continuous establishment of facilities including amusement facilities and restaurants for family dining.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また、峠の北側は八幡市東部や京田辺市西部に造成された高級住宅街「京阪東ローズタウン」の玄関口（京都府道284号八幡インター線）となり、道路照明の整った交差点として整備された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The north side of the pass became the entrance (Kyoto prefectural road 284 planned to conect with the Yawata Interchange) to a high-class residential area, &quot;Keihan East Rose Town,&quot; which was developed in the eastern side of Yawata city and the western side of Kyotanabe city. It was properly maintained as an road lighting-equipped intersection.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The north side of the pass became the entrance (Kyoto prefectural road 284 planned to connect with the Yawata Interchange) to a high-class residential area, &quot;Keihan East Rose Town,&quot; which was developed in the eastern side of Yawata city and the western side of Kyotanabe city. It was properly maintained as a road light-equipped intersection.</e>
<cmt>spelling, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The north side of the pass became the entrance (Kyoto prefectural road 284, the Yawata Interchange Line) to a high class residential area &apos;Keihan East Rose Town&apos; (which was developed on the eastern side of Yawata City and the western side of Kyotanabe City) and was properly developed into a road lighting-installed intersection.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="23">
<j>その結果、周辺は若干緑が残るものの、周囲はほぼ開発され尽くした感がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, the pass&apos;s surroundings have been almost completely developed with only little green left.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, the pass&apos;s surroundings have been almost completely developed with only a little green left.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, the surroundings of the pass have been almost completely developed with only a little greenery is there.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>旧東高野街道もその痕跡を辿ることが困難となってしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has become difficult to find a trace of the old Higashi Koya-Kaido Road.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has become difficult to find a trace of the old Higashi Koya-Kaido Road.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Now, there is no track can be found to trace the old Higashi Koya-Kaido Road.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>国道沿いは深夜でも明るく、もはや幽霊の出る幕は何一つない状態となり、新しい住民の増加も伴って、前述の幽霊談義は過去のものとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is bright along the kokudo National Road even late at night, and there is no room for ghosts. With the increased new residents, &quot;ghost stories mentioned before are completely gone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is bright along the kokudo National Road even late at night, and there is no room for ghosts. With the increasing new residents, &quot;ghost stories&quot; mentioned before are completely gone.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since it is illuminated bright along the Keihan Kokudo (National Road) even late at night, there is no room for ghosts; besides, with the increase of new residents, ghost stories mentioned before have been completely gone.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Okapia2(id:98589), Pixan(id:24280), Kozagawa(id:195338), ラハール(id:72484), Kansai explorer(id:48975), Ikaxer(id:61759), 目蒲東急之介(id:34741), Ajax(id:11202), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>