<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>京都御苑</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Gyoen National Garden</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Gyoen National Garden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Gyoen National Garden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>京都御苑（きょうとぎょえん）は京都府京都市上京区にある国民公園。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Gyoen National Garden is a national garden located in Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Gyoen National Garden is a national garden located in Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Gyoen National Garden is a national garden located in Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>京都御所の周囲の地区を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It indicates an area around the Kyoto Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It indicates an area around the Kyoto Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It indicates an area around the Kyoto Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>明治天皇が明治2年（1869年）東京へ移った後、公家屋敷などが広がっていた京都御所周辺は荒廃し、この状況を嘆いた天皇は、明治10年（1877年）御所の保存を命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Emperor Meiji moved to Tokyo in 1869, the area around the Kyoto Imperial Palace where residences of the nobility existed fell into ruin, and the Emperor who grieved over this situation ordered to preserve the Imperial Palace in 1877.</e>
<cmt>公家屋敷→residences of the noble</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Emperor Meiji moved to Tokyo in 1869, the area around the Kyoto Imperial Palace where residences of the nobility existed fell into ruin, and the Emperor who grieved over this situation ordered the preservation of the Imperial Palace in 1877.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Emperor Meiji moved to Tokyo in 1869, the area around the Kyoto Imperial Palace where residences of the nobility existed fell into ruin, and the Emperor who grieved over this situation ordered the preservation of the Imperial Palace in 1877.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>これを受け、京都府が火災延焼を防ぐため御所周辺の空家となった公家屋敷を撤去して整備したのが京都御苑の始まりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In response to this order, Kyoto Prefecture removed empty residences of the nobility around the Imperial Palace in order to prevent the spread of the fire, and developed Kyoto Gyoen National Garden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In response to this order, Kyoto Prefecture removed empty residences of the nobility around the Imperial Palace as a precaution against fires which could spread due to the close proximity of the buildings, and developed Kyoto Gyoen National Garden.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response to this order, Kyoto Prefecture removed empty residences of the nobility around the Imperial Palace as a precaution against fires which could spread due to the close proximity of the buildings, and developed Kyoto Gyoen National Garden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>昭和24年（1949年）には国民公園として広く開放された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Gyoen National Garden was opened to the people as a national garden in 1949.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Gyoen National Garden was opened to the people as a national garden in 1949.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Gyoen National Garden was opened to the people as a national garden in 1949.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>現在は京都御所、仙洞御所、京都大宮御所の築地塀内は宮内庁が、それ以外は環境省が管理している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, the sites within the mud wall with a roof of the Kyoto Imperial Palace, Sento Imperial Palace and Kyoto Omiya Imperial Palace is managed by the Imperial Household Agency manages, and other sites are managed by the Ministry of the Environment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present, the sites within the mud wall with a roof of the Kyoto Imperial Palace, Sento Imperial Palace and Kyoto Omiya Imperial Palace is managed by the Imperial Household Agency manages, and other sites are managed by the Ministry of the Environment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present, the sites within the mud wall with a roof of the Kyoto Imperial Palace, Sento Imperial Palace and Kyoto Omiya Imperial Palace is managed by the Imperial Household Agency, and other sites are managed by the Ministry of the Environment.</e>
<cmt>manages　削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>今出川通（北側）、烏丸通（西側）、丸太町通（南側）、寺町通（東側）に囲まれた範囲で63ヘクタールの広さである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Gyoen National Garden is an area surrounded by Imadegawa-dori (north side), Karasuma-dori Street (west side), Marutamachi-dori (south side) and Teramachi-dori (east side), and covers 63 hectares.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Gyoen National Garden is an area surrounded by Imadegawa-dori (north side), Karasuma-dori Street (west side), Marutamachi-dori (south side) and Teramachi-dori (east side), and covers 63 hectares.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Gyoen National Garden is an area surrounded by Imadegawa-dori Street (north side), Karasuma-dori Street (west side), Marutamachi-dori (south side) and Teramachi-dori (east side), and covers sixty-three hectares.</e>
<cmt>Street 追加しました。数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>たくさんの木々が生い茂る公園内には、京都御所、仙洞御所、京都大宮御所、宮内庁京都事務所、皇宮警察本部京都護衛署などの宮内庁・皇宮警察関連の施設をはじめ、九条邸の拾翠亭などの数少ない公家屋敷の遺構、公園の管理を行う環境省京都御苑管理事務所のほか、グラウンドやテニスもあり、市民の憩いの場になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Gyoen is a relaxing place for citizens because, in the park where many trees bristle, there are facilities related to the Imperial Household Agency and Imperial Guard such as the Kyoto Imperial Palace, Sento Imperial Palace, Kyoto Omiya Imperial Palace, Kyoto Office of the Imperial Household Agency and Kyoto Guard Station of the Imperial Guard Headquarters, several remains of residences of the nobility such as Shusui-Tei which used to be Kujo House, Kyoto Gyoen National Garden Office, Ministry of the Environment which manages the garden, and athletic facilities such as playground and tennis court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Gyoen is a relaxing place for citizens with abundant trees, together with facilities related to the Imperial Household Agency and Imperial Guard such as the Kyoto Imperial Palace, Sento Imperial Palace, Kyoto Omiya Imperial Palace, Kyoto Office of the Imperial Household Agency and Kyoto Guard Station of the Imperial Guard Headquarters, several remains of residences of the nobility such as Shusui-Tei which used to be Kujo House, Kyoto Gyoen National Garden Office, Ministry of the Environment which manages the garden, and athletic facilities such as a playground and tennis court.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Gyoen is a relaxing place for citizens with abundant trees, together with facilities related to the Imperial Household Agency and Imperial Guard such as the Kyoto Imperial Palace, Sento Imperial Palace, Kyoto Omiya Imperial Palace, Kyoto Office of the Imperial Household Agency and Kyoto Guard Station of the Imperial Guard Headquarters, several remains of residences of the nobility such as Shusui-Tei which used to be Kujo House, Kyoto Gyoen National Garden Office, Ministry of the Environment which manages the garden, and athletic facilities such as a playground and tennis court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>又、2005年4月には京都迎賓館が開館した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, the Kyoto State Guest House opened in April 2005.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, the Kyoto State Guest House opened in April 2005.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, the Kyoto State Guest House opened in April 2005.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>公園内ではのんびりと散歩を楽しむ人やバードウォッチングをする人もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some people enjoy casual stroll or bird-watching in the park.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some people enjoy casual strolls or bird-watching in the park.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people enjoy casual strolls or bird-watching in the park.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>御苑の北隣には同志社大学と同志社女子大学（両校とも今出川キャンパス）があるため、ベンチで寝転ぶ学生の姿をよく見かける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Doshisha University and Doshisha Women&apos;s College of Liberal Arts have own campus (Imadegawa Campus) respectively next to the northern part of Kyoto Gyoen National Garden, students lying on the bench are often seen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Doshisha University and the Doshisha Women&apos;s College of Liberal Arts have their own campus (Imadegawa Campus) next to the northern part of Kyoto Gyoen National Garden, students are often seen relaxing on benches.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Doshisha University and the Doshisha Women&apos;s College of Liberal Arts have their own campus (Imadegawa Campus) next to the northern part of Kyoto Gyoen National Garden, students are often seen relaxing on benches.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また、住民の通り抜けルートにもなっているが、通路部分は舗装されている訳ではなく砂が敷き詰められているため自転車では走りづらい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Citizens pass through Kyoto Gyoen National Garden, but, since the passage is sanded, not paved, it is difficult to go through by bicycle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Citizens pass through Kyoto Gyoen National Garden, but, since the passage is sanded and not paved, it is difficult to traverse by bicycle.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Citizens pass through Kyoto Gyoen National Garden, but, since the passage is sanded and not paved, it is difficult to traverse by bicycle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>しかし、自転車の走行跡が砂地に出来て、走りやすくなっている部分もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, because wheel ruts are made by bicycle in the sand, it is easy to go through by bicycle in some part.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, wheel ruts made by bicycles in the sand make it easy-going in some areas.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, wheel ruts made by bicycles in the sand make it easy-going in some areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>この走行跡は御所の細道と呼ばれる事がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These ruts are sometimes called a narrow road to the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>御所の細道→narrow road to the Imperial Palace[”奥の細道”(Narrow Road to the Interior)に掛けていると解釈し、左記の通り英訳しました]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These ruts are sometimes called a narrow road to the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These ruts are sometimes called a narrow road to the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>ただし、走行跡は自転車一台分の幅しかないため、対向車が来た場合は譲り合うのが暗黙のルールである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since these ruts are only for one bicycle, there is an unspoken rule of giving way each other when a bicycle comes from the opposite direction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since these ruts are only for one bicycle, there is an unspoken rule of giving the right of way to each other when a bicycle comes from the opposite direction.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since these ruts are only for one bicycle, there is an unspoken rule of giving the right of way to each other when a bicycle comes from the opposite direction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>公園内は京都府警や皇宮警察が常に見回りをしていて、京都御所や仙洞御所の塀に近づくとセンサーが反応し、すぐに注意される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kyoto Prefectural Police and Imperial Guard always patrol the park, and somebody coming close to the wall of the Kyoto Imperial Palace or the Sento Imperial Palace is detected by a sensor, and receives a caution immediately.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kyoto Prefectural Police and Imperial Guard always patrol the park. Anyone who comes close to the wall of the Kyoto Imperial Palace or the Sento Imperial Palace is detected by a sensor, and receives a warning.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kyoto Prefectural Police and Imperial Guard always patrol the park; anyone who comes close to the wall of the Kyoto Imperial Palace or the Sento Imperial Palace is detected by a sensor, and receives a warning.</e>
<cmt>一つの文章にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>蛤御門</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hamaguri-gomon Gate</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hamaguri-gomon Gate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hamaguri-gomon Gate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>上記の蛤御門は、元々開かずの扉であったが、1788年の天明の大火の際に初めて開門された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above Hamaguri-gomon Gate was originally unopened, but, was opened for the first time when the Great Fire of Tenmei occurred in 1788.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above Hamaguri-gomon Gate was originally unopened, but, was opened for the first time when the Great Fire of Tenmei occurred in 1788.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The above Hamaguri-gomon Gate was originally unopened, but, was opened for the first time when the Great Fire of Tenmei occurred in 1788.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>この為、「炎で貝が開く」ことの比喩で蛤御門と呼ばれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this, the gate was called Hamaguri-gomon Gate using an analogy from a phrase that &quot;a shell is opened by fire.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this, the gate was called Hamaguri-gomon Gate using an analogy from a phrase that &quot;a shell is opened by fire.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this, the gate was called Hamaguri-gomon Gate using an analogy from a phrase that &quot;a shell is opened by fire.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>また、1864年（元治元年）に尊皇攘夷派（長州藩）と江戸幕府（会津藩）の戦いである禁門の変（蛤御門の変）が勃発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1864, the Kinmon no Hen (the Rebellion at the Hamaguri-gomon Gate), which was the battle between the faction (the Choshu clan) under the slogan advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners, and the faction (the Aizu clan) supporting the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), broke out.</e>
<cmt>尊皇攘夷派→faction under the slogan advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreighners</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1864, the Kinmon no Hen (the Rebellion at the Hamaguri-gomon Gate), which was the battle between the faction (the Choshu clan) under the slogan advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners, and the faction (the Aizu clan) supporting the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), broke out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1864, the Kinmon no Hen (the Rebellion at the Hamaguri-gomon Gate), which was the battle between the faction (the Choshu clan) under the slogan advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners, and the faction (the Aizu clan) supporting the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), broke out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>現在でもこの戦いの傷跡である銃弾の跡が門に残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bullet holes which are the marks of this battle remain in the gate even now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bullet holes, marks of this historical battle, remain in the gate even now.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bullet holes, marks of this historical battle, remain in the gate even now.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>アクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>京都市営バス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto City Bus</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto City Bus</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto City Bus</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>京都市営地下鉄烏丸線 丸太町駅 (京都市営地下鉄)、今出川駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Marutamachi Station (Kyoto City Subway) and Imadegawa Station on the Karasuma Line of Kyoto City Subway</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Marutamachi Station (Kyoto City Subway) and Imadegawa Station on the Karasuma Line of Kyoto City Subway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Marutamachi Station (Kyoto Municipal Subway) and Imadegawa Station on the Karasuma Line of Kyoto Municipal Subway</e>
<cmt>Municipal としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>京阪鴨東線 出町柳駅、丸太町駅 (京阪)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Demachiyanagi Station and Marutamachi Station (Keihan) on the Keihan Oto Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Demachiyanagi Station and Marutamachi Station (Keihan) on the Keihan Oto Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Demachiyanagi Station and Marutamachi Station (Keihan) on the Keihan Oto Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), Nakaful(id:17223), 翰林硯士(id:99377), ＋－(id:17104), 準急三条(id:25072), Ganman(id:96316), Mochi(id:9489), Takuan(id:29385), Wakkubox(id:30396), Antique1967(id:74701), うぃき野郎(id:53567), Ronko(id:209960), K-kazumasa(id:9265), Zz2(id:30288), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>