<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>紀伊山地の霊場と参詣道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sacred Sites and Pilgrimage Routes in the Kii Mountain Range</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sacred Sites and Pilgrimage Routes in the Kii Mountain Range</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sacred Sites and Pilgrimage Routes in the Kii Mountain Range</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>紀伊山地の霊場と参詣道（きいさんちのれいじょうとさんけいみち）は、和歌山県・奈良県・三重県にまたがる3つの霊場と参詣道（熊野古道、大峯奥駈道、高野山町石道）を登録対象とする世界遺産（文化遺産_(世界遺産)）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sacred Sites and Pilgrimage Routes in the Kii Mountain Range is a world heritage, and the three sacred sites and pilgrimage routes (Kumanokodo Road, Omine Okugake-michi, Koyasan Choishi-michi) in Kii Mountain Range straddling Wakayama, Nara, Mie Prefectures are registered as World Heritage (Cultural heritage_[World heritage])</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sacred Sites and Pilgrimage Routes in the Kii Mountain Range is a World Heritage (Cultural heritage) registered for the three sacred sites and pilgrimage routes (Kumano-kodo Road, Omine Okugake-michi Road, Koyasan Choishi-michi Road) in Kii Mountain Range straddling Wakayama, Nara, Mie Prefectures.</e>
<cmt>原文には「_(世界遺産)」 とありますが、リンク先の単語が抽出されるバグのようですので、訳出しておりません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sacred Sites and Pilgrimage Routes in the Kii Mountain Range is a World Heritage (Cultural heritage) registered for the three sacred sites and pilgrimage routes (Kumano-kodo Road, Omine Okugake-michi Road, Koyasan Choishi-michi Road) in Kii Mountain Range straddling Wakayama, Nara, Mie Prefectures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>2004年7月7日に登録された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was registered on July 7, 2004.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was registered on July 7, 2004.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was registered on July 7, 2004.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>遺産の種別</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cultural heritage_(World heritage) category</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Category of the heritage</e>
<cmt>原文には 「文化遺産_(世界遺産)カテゴリー」とありましたが、リンク先の単語のようです。ウェブで確認すると用語が「遺産の種別」となっており、本来はこちらの用語を使用していると思われますので、こちらを訳出し、原文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Category of the heritage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>文化遺産</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cultural heritage</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cultural heritage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cultural heritage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>記念工作物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monument</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Monument</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Monument</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>遺跡（文化的景観）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Site (cultural scenery)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Site (cultural scenery)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Site (cultural scenery)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>登録基準</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Registration standard</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Registration standard</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Registration standard</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>具体的には、(2) 紀伊山地の文化的景観を形成する記念碑と遺跡は神道と仏教のたぐいまれな融合であり、東アジアにおける宗教文化の交流と発展を例証する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Specifically, monuments and sites, which form cultural scenery in (2) Kii Mountain Range, are unusual syncretization of Shinto with Buddhism, while it illustrates the interaction and development of religious culture in the east Asia.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Specifically, (2) monuments and sites, which form cultural scenery in Kii Mountain Range, are unusual syncretization of Shinto with Buddhism, while it illustrates the interaction and development of religious culture in the east Asia.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Specifically, (2) monuments and sites, which form cultural scenery in Kii Mountain Range, are unusual syncretization of Shinto with Buddhism, while it illustrates the interaction and development of religious culture in the east Asia.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>(3) 紀伊山地の神社と仏教寺院は、それらに関連する宗教儀式とともに、1000年以上にわたる日本の宗教文化の発展に関するひときわ優れた証拠性を有する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(3) The shrines and Buddhist temples in Kii Mountain Range, together with their associated religious rites, are regarded as a particularly excellent evidence on the development of Japanese religious culture over 1000 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(3) The shrines and Buddhist temples in Kii Mountain Range, together with their associated religious rites, are regarded as particularly excellent evidence on the development of Japanese religious culture over 1000 years.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを削除し、表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(3) The shrines and Buddhist temples in Kii Mountain Range, together with their associated religious rites, are regarded as particularly excellent evidence on the development of Japanese religious culture over 1000 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>(4) 紀伊山地は神社・寺院建築のたぐいまれな形式の創造の素地となり、それらは日本の紀伊山地以外の寺院・神社建築に重要な影響を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(4) Kii Mountain Range served as a foundation to create Shrine and temple architecture with a unique style, and they significantly influenced shrine and temple architecture out of Kii Mountain Range in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(4) Kii Mountain Range served as a foundation to create shrine and temple architecture with a unique style, and they significantly influenced shrine and temple architecture out of Kii Mountain Range in Japan.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(4) Kii Mountain Range served as a foundation to create shrine and temple architecture with a unique style, and they significantly influenced shrine and temple architecture out of Kii Mountain Range in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>(6) と同時に、紀伊山地の遺跡と森林景観は、過去1200年以上にわたる聖山の持続的で並外れて記録に残されている伝統を反映している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to (6), the remains and forest scenery of Kii Mountain Range reflect the tradition of sacred peak which has been continuously and extraordinarily recorded over the past 1,200 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to (6), the remains and forest scenery of Kii Mountain Range reflect the tradition of sacred peak which has been continuously and extraordinarily recorded over the past 1,200 years.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to (6), the remains and forest scenery of Kii Mountain Range reflect the tradition of sacred peak which has been continuously and extraordinarily recorded over the past 1,200 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>遺産</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heritage</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heritage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heritage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>以下に登録資産の一覧を示す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following is the list of registered heritages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following is the list of registered heritages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following is the list of registered heritages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>登録資産のうち、「吉野・大峯」、「熊野三山（補陀洛山寺除く）」、「参詣道」の一部（大峯奥駈道および熊野参詣道の一部）は吉野熊野国立公園に含まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among registered heritages, `Yoshno, Omine,&apos; `Kumano Sanzan&apos; (three major shrines, Kumano-Hongu-Taisha, Kumano-Hayatama-Taisha and Kumano-Nachi-Taisha) (excluding Fudarakusanji Temple), a part of `pilgrimage routes&apos; (Omine Okugake-michi and a part of Kumano Pilgrimage Routes) are included in Yoshino-Kumano National Park.</e>
<cmt>登録資産→登録遺産と解釈し訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among registered heritages, &apos;Yoshino, Omine,&apos; &apos;Kumano Sanzan&apos; (three major shrines, Kumano-Hongu-Taisha, Kumano-Hayatama-Taisha and Kumano-Nachi-Taisha) (excluding Fudarakusan-ji Temple), a part of &apos;pilgrimage routes&apos; (Omine Okugake-michi Road and a part of Kumano Pilgrimage Routes) are included in Yoshino-Kumano National Park.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among registered heritages, &apos;Yoshino, Omine,&apos; &apos;Kumano Sanzan&apos; (three major shrines, Kumano-Hongu-Taisha, Kumano-Hayatama-Taisha and Kumano-Nachi-Taisha) (excluding Fudarakusan-ji Temple), a part of &apos;pilgrimage routes&apos; (Omine Okugake-michi Road and a part of Kumano Pilgrimage Routes) are included in Yoshino-Kumano National Park.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また、「高野山」、熊野参詣道の一部は高野龍神国定公園に含まれる</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, `Koya-san Mountain&apos; and a part of Kumano Pilgrimage Routes are included in Koya-Ryujin Quasi-National Park.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, &apos;Mt. Koya&apos; and a part of Kumano Pilgrimage Routes are included in Koya-Ryujin Quasi-National Park.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, &apos;Mt. Koya&apos; and a part of Kumano Pilgrimage Routes are included in Koya-Ryujin Quasi-National Park.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>問題</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Troubles</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Troubles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Troubles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>地権者との対立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Disputes with land owners</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Disputes with land owners</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Disputes with land owners</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>三重県尾鷲市で遺産登録地域の地権者が抗議の意を込めて参道の樹木などに落書きをしており問題になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Owase City, Mie Prefecture, the land owners of the area which is registered as world heritage protested against the registration as world heritage and drew graffiti on the trees of sando (an approach to the temple).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Owase City, Mie Prefecture, the land owners of the area which is registered as world heritage protested against the registration and drew graffiti on the trees of sando (an approach to the temple).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Owase City, Mie Prefecture, the land owners of the area which is registered as world heritage protested against the registration and drew graffiti on the trees of sando (an approach to the temple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>一般的ないたずらの落書きとは違い抗議が目的であるために強硬な措置は取られず話し合いにより解決する方向である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the graffiti is not a common graffiti, but it was intended to protest, therefore, dialogue is planned to solve the problem instead of taking a forceful action.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since it was not a common graffiti but intended to protest, therefore, dialogue is planned to solve the problem instead of taking a forceful action.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since it was not a common graffiti but intended to protest, therefore, dialogue is planned to solve the problem instead of taking a forceful action.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>これは、地権者に対する事前説明がなされずに遺産登録されたため、地権者の職業である林業ができなくなったためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is because the land of land owners was registered as world heritage without explanations to them, and forestry, which is their occupation, came to be prohibited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because their lands were registered as world heritage without explanations in advance, and forestry, which is their occupation, came to be prohibited.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because their lands were registered as world heritage without explanations in advance, and forestry, which is their occupation, came to be prohibited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>観光地化による影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Effects due to having the town as a tourist site</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Effects due to having the town as a tourist site</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Effects due to having the town as a tourist site</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>遺産本体部分やその緩衝地帯、さらには（世界遺産には含まれないが）その周辺地域での損壊が絶えない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are constant damages on the body of heritage, a buffer area, and the area in the vicinity of the heritage (not included in the world heritage).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are constant damages on the body of heritage, a buffer area, and even the area in the vicinity of the heritage (not included in the world heritage).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are constant damages on the body of heritage, a buffer area, and even the area in the vicinity of the heritage (not included in the world heritage).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>特に、参詣道跡である熊野古道周辺でそれが著しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is particularly prominent in the area around Kumanokodo Road which is a site of Pilgrimage Routes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is particularly prominent in the area around Kumano-kodo Road which is a site of Pilgrimage Routes.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is particularly prominent in the area around Kumano-kodo Road which is a site of Pilgrimage Routes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>また、世界遺産登録後、観光客の殺到によって一部の遺産では荒廃が進んでいるとの指摘もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some people pointed out that some heritages have been further devastated due to rush of tourists since it was registered as world heritage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some people pointed out that some heritages have been further devastated due to rush of tourists since it was registered as world heritage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people pointed out that some heritages have been further devastated due to rush of tourists since it was registered as world heritage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>関西電力の風力発電計画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The wind power generation plan by The Kansai Electric Power Co., Inc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The wind power generation plan by The Kansai Electric Power Co., Inc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The wind power generation plan by The Kansai Electric Power Co., Inc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>2005年1月、関西電力は果無山脈に風力発電のための風車を建設する計画を発表した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 2005, The Kansai Electric Power Co., Inc. announced the plan to construct wind turbines on the Hatenashi mountain range to generate wind power</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January 2005, The Kansai Electric Power Co., Inc. announced the plan to construct wind turbines on the Hatenashi mountain range to generate wind power</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January 2005, The Kansai Electric Power Co., Inc. announced the plan to construct wind turbines on the Hatenashi mountain range to generate wind power</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>果無山脈は遺産にも緩衝地帯にもあたらないが、熊野古道から容易に眺望しうる</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hatenashi mountain range is neither a world heritage nor a buffering zone, but Kumanokodo Road has an easy view of the Hatenashi mountain range.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hatenashi mountain range is neither a world heritage nor a buffering zone, but Kumano-kodo Road has an easy view of the Hatenashi mountain range.</e>
<cmt>半角スペースにし、用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hatenashi mountain range is neither a world heritage nor a buffering zone, but Kumano-kodo Road has an easy view of the Hatenashi mountain range.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>このため景観に悪影響を与える恐れがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, wind turbines may affect the scenery</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, wind turbines may affect the scenery.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, wind turbines may affect the scenery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また、果無山脈それ自体が近隣の河川（熊野川、日置川、富田川、日高川）の分水嶺となっており、工事による河川への悪影響が懸念されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the Hatenashi mountain range is a dividing mountain of neighboring rivers (Kumano River, Hiki-gawa River, Tonda River, and Hidaka River), and adverse effect caused by constructions on the rivers is concerned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the Hatenashi mountain range is a dividing mountain of neighboring rivers (the Kumano-gawa River, the Hiki-gawa River, the Tonda-gawa River, and the Hidaka-gawa River), and adverse effect caused by constructions on the rivers is concerned.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the Hatenashi mountain range is a dividing mountain of neighboring rivers (the Kumano-gawa River, the Hiki-gawa River, the Tonda-gawa River, and the Hidaka-gawa River), and adverse effect caused by constructions on the rivers is concerned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>古道の「整備」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">`Maintenance&apos; of Kodo (ancient method, ancient moral teachings, the way of learning)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maintenance&apos; of Kodo</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maintenance&apos; of Kodo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>中辺路・大辺路を中心に2002年頃から数度にわたり、地元自治体の公共事業（古道の整備を目的とする）、古道とその周辺での植生の刈り払いが何度か行われたが、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Public projects (aiming to maintain Kodo) by local government bodies and cutting of vegetation in Kodo and the surrounding area have been conducted several times since around 2002 mainly in Nakahechi and Ohechi (old roads to Kumano).</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Public projects (aiming to maintain Kodo) by local government bodies and cutting of vegetation in Kodo and the surrounding area have been conducted several times since around 2002 mainly in Nakahechi and Ohechi (Kumano-kodo Road).</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Public projects (aiming to maintain Kodo) by local government bodies and cutting of vegetation in Kodo and the surrounding area have been conducted several times since around 2002 mainly in Nakahechi and Ohechi (Kumano-kodo Road).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>景観の悪化や、貴重な照葉樹林の損失など、むしろ弊害が大きく批判の対象となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Adverse effects including devastation of scenery and loss of precious laurel forest are prominent and it is subject to criticism.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Adverse effects including devastation of scenery and loss of precious laurel forest are prominent and it is subject to criticism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Adverse effects including devastation of scenery and loss of precious laurel forest are prominent and it is subject to criticism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>加えて、いくつかの事例には和歌山県が関与している他、国の緊急地域雇用創出特別基金事業の下で行われた県の公共事業「緑の雇用事業」の一環であるものもあるなど、行政当局の遺産保護に対する姿勢や「縦割り」の弊害を問う声があがっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The attitude of administrative authorities on the protection of heritage or the adverse effect caused by `vertically-segmented administrative system&apos; are questioned in that Wakayama Prefecture is involved in some cases, and some projects were conducted as a part of Prefectural projects, `Green Employment Project &apos; under special subsidy for emergency regional employment creation of the nation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The attitude of administrative authorities on the protection of heritage or the adverse effect caused by &apos;vertically-segmented administrative system&apos; are questioned in that Wakayama Prefecture is involved in some cases, and some projects were conducted as a part of Prefectural projects, &apos;Green Employment Project&apos; under special subsidy for emergency regional employment creation of the nation.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変え、余分なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The attitude of administrative authorities on the protection of heritage or the adverse effect caused by &apos;vertically-segmented administrative system&apos; are questioned in that Wakayama Prefecture is involved in some cases, and some projects were conducted as a part of Prefectural projects, &apos;Green Employment Project&apos; under special subsidy for emergency regional employment creation of the nation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>世界遺産を守る取組み</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Efforts to protect world heritage</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Efforts to protect world heritage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Efforts to protect world heritage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>2005年7月、世界遺産条例が施行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July 2005, the World Heritage ordinance of Wakayama Prefecture was enforced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 2005, the World Heritage ordinance of Wakayama Prefecture was enforced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July 2005, the World Heritage ordinance of Wakayama Prefecture was enforced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MD242(id:11277), Yard(id:59322), Nnh(id:474), Urania(id:7213), 明石家くるみ(id:251693), Sina(id:10021), D.h(id:79056), CommonsDelinker(id:84593), Ultratomio(id:1090), Halfd(id:145364), Aska-sacra(id:8180), 漸音(id:10166), Call Tenderas(id:169753), ぎゅうひ(id:9206), Sunen(id:10700), 橄欖岩(id:24996), Autumn Sky(id:173580), Rosita97(id:27129), Chobot(id:20846), Knua(id:66861), Point136(id:211299), あなん(id:6904), Yosemite(id:5808), Sumaru(id:20609), Ajax(id:11202), Peppar(id:86991), ととりん(id:31982), たね(id:10372), Kalz(id:92749), 短髄彦(id:5555), Ｈｉｒｏ２００６(id:59115), Zzzz(id:16596), Histwr(id:15646), 公平(id:27915), ニューワーカー(id:16977), Vantey(id:22521), Rusk(id:9895), VolkovBot(id:105371), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Kyoto-u(id:96969), Kd(id:10262), Gliff(id:9384), ＮｉＫｅ(id:7512), N yotarou(id:60870), Tawashi2006(id:95112), Ikedat76(id:34218), Ash(id:15625), Eiri1028(id:74083), Iokseng(id:92490), 663highland(id:18755), 史跡めぐり(id:95651), Kosmos14(id:191215), Louperibot(id:128971), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>