<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>天王山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tennozan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mt. Tenno</e>
<cmt>指示書に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mt. Tenno</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>天王山（てんのうざん）は、京都府乙訓郡大山崎町の山。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tennozan is a mountain in Oyamazaki-cho, Otokuni-gun, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mt. Tenno is a mountain in Oyamazaki-cho, Otokuni-gun, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>用語を合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mt. Tenno is a mountain in Oyamazaki-cho, Otokuni-gun, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>西側の山腹を、摂津国（現在の大阪府）と山城国（現在の京都府）の国境がよぎる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the west side of the mountain, there is a border between Settsu Province (now Osaka Prefecture) and Yamashiro Province (now Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the west side of the mountain, there is a border between Settsu Province (now Osaka Prefecture) and Yamashiro Province (now Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the west side of the mountain, there is a border between Settsu Province (now Osaka Prefecture) and Yamashiro Province (now Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>山名は、中腹に牛頭天王を祀る山崎天王社（現 自玉手祭来酒解神社）があることに由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of the mountain comes from Yamazaki Tennosha Shrine (now Tamadeyori Matsurikitaru Sakatoke-jinja Shrine) enshrining Gozu Tenno (deity said to be the Indian god Gavagriva) on the mountainside.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of the mountain comes from Yamazaki Tennosha Shrine (now Tamadeyori Matsurikitaru Sakatoke-jinja Shrine) enshrining Gozu Tenno (deity said to be the Indian god Gavagriva) on the mountainside.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of the mountain comes from Yamazaki Tennosha Shrine (now Tamadeyori Matsurikitaru Sakatoke-jinja Shrine) enshrining Gozu Tenno (deity said to be the Indian god Gavagriva) on the mountainside.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>地理</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Geography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Geography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Geography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>京都盆地の西辺となる西山山系の南端に位置し、東の男山とのあいだで地峡を形成する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tennozan is located at the south end of Nishiyama mountain range on the west side of Kyoto Basin, and an isthmus is formed between Tennozan and Mt. Otoko, east of Tennozan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mt. Tenno is located at the south end of Nishi-yama mountain range on the west side of Kyoto Basin, and forms an isthmus with Mt. Otoko, east of Mt. Tenno.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mt. Tenno is located at the south end of Nishi-yama mountain range on the west side of Kyoto Basin, and forms an isthmus with Mt. Otoko, east of Mt. Tenno.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>この地峡には、桂川 (淀川水系)・淀川・木津川 (京都府)が合流して淀川となる川の流れに沿って、右岸にJR京都線（東海道本線）、東海道新幹線、阪急京都本線、国道171号（旧西国街道）が、左岸に京阪本線、旧国道1号（現・京都府道・大阪府道13号京都守口線、旧京街道）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the right side of this isthmus, there are JR Kyoto Line (Tokaido Main Line), Tokaido Shinkansen, Hankyu Kyoto Main Line and National Route 171 (Old Saigoku Kaido), and on the left side of this isthmus, there are Keihan Main Line and Old National Route 1 (now Kyoto-Moriguchi-sen, Kyoto Fudo 13 Go and Osaka Fudo 13 Go (Kyoto/Osaka Prefectural Road 13) and Old Kyokaido road) along Yodo-gawa River into which Katsura-gawa River (Yodo-gawa River system) and Kizu-gawa River flow.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this isthmus, along the course of the Yodo-gawa River into which the Katsura-gawa River (Yodo-gawa River system) and the Kizu-gawa River (Kyoto Prefecture) merge, JR Kyoto Line (Tokaido Main Line), Tokaido Shinkansen (bullet train), Hankyu Kyoto Main Line and National Route 171 (Old Saigoku Kaido Road) are on the right bank, and Keihan Main Line and Old National Route 1 (now Kyoto Moriguchi Line of Kyoto and Osaka Prefectural Road 13 and Old Kyokaido Road) are on the left.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this isthmus, along the course of the Yodo-gawa River into which the Katsura-gawa River (Yodo-gawa River system) and the Kizu-gawa River (Kyoto Prefecture) merge, JR Kyoto Line (Tokaido Main Line), Tokaido Shinkansen (bullet train), Hankyu Kyoto Main Line and National Route 171 (Old Saigoku Kaido Road) are on the right bank, and Keihan Main Line and Old National Route 1 (now Kyoto Moriguchi Line of Kyoto and Osaka Prefectural Road 13 and Old Kyokaido Road) are on the left.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>これらは、かつて水上交通路であった川筋をふくめて、近畿最大の大動脈である京阪間のほぼ全ての交通路が含まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These are almost all routes between Kyoto and Osaka, which can be called the biggest major transport artery in the Kinki region including rivers which were once water routes.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These are almost all routes between Kyoto and Osaka, which can be called the biggest major transport artery in the Kinki region including rivers which were once water routes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These are almost all routes between Kyoto and Osaka, which can be called the biggest major transport artery in the Kinki region including rivers which were once water routes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また、その京都府側では名神高速道路の大山崎ジャンクション/大山崎インターチェンジがあり、名神高速道路のバイパス機能を持つ京滋バイパスが宇治・滋賀（名神瀬田東ジャンクション）方面へ分岐する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the Kyoto Prefectural side of Tennozan, there is Oyamazaki Junction/Oyamazaki Interchange on Meishin Expressway where Keiji Bypass diverges into Uji and Shiga (Meishin Seta Higashi Junction).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the Kyoto Prefectural side, there is Oyamazaki Junction and Oyamazaki Interchange on Meishin Expressway where Keiji Bypass, which functions as a bypass of Meishin Expressway, diverges into Uji and Shiga (Meishin Seta Higashi Junction).</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the Kyoto Prefectural side, there is Oyamazaki Junction and Oyamazaki Interchange on Meishin Expressway where Keiji Bypass, which functions as a bypass of Meishin Expressway, diverges into Uji and Shiga (Meishin Seta Higashi Junction).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>また、当地は、豊富な地下水に恵まれており、南麓の大阪府側にサントリー山崎蒸留所が所在することでも有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tennozan is abundant in groundwater and is famous for Suntory Yamazaki Distillery on the Osaka Prefectural side of the south foot of Tennozan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is abundant in groundwater in this area and is famous for Suntory Yamazaki Distillery on the Osaka Prefectural side of the south foot.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is abundant in groundwater in this area and is famous for Suntory Yamazaki Distillery on the Osaka Prefectural side of the south foot.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>近畿地方では名神高速道路の渋滞箇所で有名な天王山トンネルの知名度が高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tennouzan Tunnel is also famous in the Kinki region for tie-ups on Meishin Expressway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kinki region, Tennozan Tunnel is famous for the traffic congestion on Meishin Expressway.</e>
<cmt>スペル、表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kinki region, Tennozan Tunnel is famous for the traffic congestion on Meishin Expressway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>上記のような地峡を扼する地であることから、南北朝時代 (日本)や応仁の乱でも戦略上の要地として争奪の舞台となり山城も築かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because Tennozan embraces the isthmus mentioned above, it was sought after as a place of strategic importance in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts, the Onin War, etc., and on it was built yamajiro (a castle built on a mountain to take advantage of the mountain&apos;s topography).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the area embraces the isthmus mentioned above, the scrambles occurred to get the strategically vital mountain in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts or in the Onin War, and yamajiro (a castle built on a mountain to take advantage of the mountain&apos;s topography) was built on it.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the area embraces the isthmus mentioned above, the scrambles occurred to get the strategically vital mountain in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts or in the Onin War, and yamajiro (a castle built on a mountain to take advantage of the mountain&apos;s topography) was built on it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>なかでも、天正10年（1582年）6月に織田信長を討った明智光秀とその仇討ちを果たそうとする豊臣秀吉が戦った山崎の戦いがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1582, Mitsuhide AKECHI who killed Nobunaga ODA fought with Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI who was going to get revenge against him at the Battle of Yamazaki.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them, in June, 1582, Mitsuhide AKECHI who killed Nobunaga ODA fought with Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI who was going to revenge for him at the Battle of Yamazaki.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them, in June, 1582, Mitsuhide AKECHI who killed Nobunaga ODA fought with Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI who was going to revenge for him at the Battle of Yamazaki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>この山を制した方が天下を取ることになるとして「天下分け目の天王山」という言葉で表現され、現在でもスポーツやゲームの重大な試合や局面の比喩に名を残す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, the metaphor &quot;Tenka-wakemeno-Tennozan&quot;, which means those who take hold of Tennozan rule the world, has been used especially in crucial matches or phases of sports or games.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The battle has been expressed as the metaphor &apos;Tenka wakeme no Tennozan&apos; (those who take hold of Mt. Tenno rule the world) which is still used especially in crucial matches or phases of sports or games.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The battle has been expressed as the metaphor &apos;Tenka wakeme no Tennozan&apos; (those who take hold of Mt. Tenno rule the world) which is still used especially in crucial matches or phases of sports or games.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>なお、この戦いを制した秀吉は、同年末に当地に山崎城（宝積寺城、宝寺城とも）を築いて、翌年に大坂城に移るまで本拠とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, Hideyoshi who took hold of that battle built Yamazaki-jo Castle (also known as Hoshakuji-jo Castle or Hoji-jo Castle) there in the same year, and was based in this castle until he moved to Osaka-jo Castle the next year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, Hideyoshi, the winner of the battle, built Yamazaki-jo Castle (also known as Hoshakuji-jo Castle or Hoji-jo Castle) there in the end of the same year, where he was based until his transfer to Osaka-jo Castle the next year.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, Hideyoshi, the winner of the battle, built Yamazaki-jo Castle (also known as Hoshakuji-jo Castle or Hoji-jo Castle) there in the end of the same year, where he was based until his transfer to Osaka-jo Castle the next year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>くだって幕末、禁門の変では、長州藩が当地を押さえた上で京都御所へ進撃するが、結果的に敗走し、参陣していた真木和泉ら十七烈士は当地で自刃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, at the end of the Edo period, although the Choshu clan took hold of Tennozan and marched into Kyoto Imperial Palace, they are eventually put to rout and Seventeen Patriots including Izumi MAKI committed suicide with their own swords there in Kinmon Incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, in Kinmon Incident at the end of the Edo period, Choshu clan captured the place to attack the Kyoto Imperial Palace, however, they were routed back eventually to have 17 Patriots including Izumi MAKI commit suicide there.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, in Kinmon Incident at the end of the Edo period, Choshu clan captured the place to attack the Kyoto Imperial Palace, however, they were routed back eventually to have 17 Patriots including Izumi MAKI commit suicide there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また、4年後の鳥羽・伏見の戦いでは、旧幕府軍が男山の麓の橋本と淀川の対岸にある大山崎に分かれて布陣して新政府軍を迎え撃った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">4 years later, at the Battle of Toba and Fushimi, the former army of bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) attacked the new government army from Hashimoto located at the foot of Mt. Otoko and from Oyamazaki located on the other side of Yodo-gawa River separately.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Four years later, at the Battle of Toba and Fushimi, the army of former bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) set up camps separately in Hashimoto at the foot of Mt. Otoko and Oyamazaki on the other side of the Yodo-gawa River to counter the new government army.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Four years later, at the Battle of Toba and Fushimi, the army of former bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) set up camps separately in Hashimoto at the foot of Mt. Otoko and Oyamazaki on the other side of the Yodo-gawa River to counter the new government army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし、大山崎に布陣していた津藩が新政府軍に寝返って橋本の旧幕府軍を砲撃した事で旧幕府軍は総崩れとなり、戦いの趨勢が決している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But because the Tsu clan in Oyamazaki sold out to the new government army and shelled the former army of bakufu in Hashimoto, the former army of bakufu completely collapsed and this decided the outcome of the battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Tsu clan in Oyamazaki switching to the new government army and shelling the former bakufu army in Hashimoto caused the former bakufu army completely collapsed and decided the outcome of the battle.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Tsu clan in Oyamazaki switching to the new government army and shelling the former bakufu army in Hashimoto caused the former bakufu army completely collapsed and decided the outcome of the battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>将棋では中央（5五）の位を制するのが重要であったことから、その地点を天王山と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Shogi (Japanese Chess), it is important to occupy the central square (Go-go no kurai) and that square is called Tennozan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Shogi (Japanese Chess), occupying the central square (in the fifth line of fifth row) means a lot where to be called Tennozan (Mt. Tenno).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Shogi (Japanese Chess), occupying the central square (in the fifth line of fifth row) means a lot where to be called Tennozan (Mt. Tenno).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Straysheep(id:42448), Bakkai(id:7233), Washisama(id:9333), Nnh(id:474), 経済準学士(id:22656), Reggaeman(id:6214), 水児玉(id:160455), お掃除大好き(id:99320), 亮来来(id:17212), 樒(id:35770), Kagetudo(id:163875), Aboshi(id:9318), Sixty-five(id:11022), おっとー(id:73395), Sunen(id:10700), Kyube(id:9866), Goki(id:7107), R28Bot(id:177951), アムネマチン(id:87480), 663highland(id:18755), Chikara1983(id:59556), Σ64(id:24481), Lincun(id:22742), Orihakat(id:99279), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>