<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>南丹</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nantan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nantan</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nantan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>南丹（なんたん）とは、京都府の丹波地方南部を指す呼称で、行政区分として京都府中央部の亀岡市、南丹市、船井郡京丹波町の3市町の地域（旧船井郡・旧北桑田郡・旧南桑田郡）をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term of Nantan is used for indicating the southern part of the Tanba area of Kyto Prefecture, and administratively includes the two cities and one town of Kameoka City, Nantan City and Kyo-tanba-cho Town of Funai-gun County (former Funai-gun COunty, former Kita-kuwata-gun County and former Minami-kuwata-gun County), all of which are located in the central part of Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nantan refers to the southern part of the Tanba area of Kyto Prefecture, and administratively includes the two cities and one town of Kameoka City, Nantan City and Kyo-tanba-cho Town of Funai-gun County (former Funai-gun COunty, former Kita-kuwata-gun County and former Minami-kuwata-gun County), all of which are located in the central part of Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nantan refers to the southern part of the Tanba area of Kyoto Prefecture, and administratively includes the two cities and one town of Kameoka City, Nantan City and Kyotanba-cho of Funai-gun (former Funai-gun, former Kitakuwada-gun and former Minamikuwada-gun), all of which are located in the central part of Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。County, town を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>かつては、南丹ではなく口丹波（くちたんば）や口丹（くちたん）と呼ぶのが一般的であり、現在でも使用する人びとは少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the past, the area was generally called &quot;Kuchitanba&quot; or &quot;Kuchitan&quot;, not Nantan, and even now, there are some persons who use these terms instead of Nantan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the past, the area was generally called &quot;Kuchitanba&quot; or &quot;Kuchitan&quot;, not Nantan, and even now, there are some people to the area with these terms instead of Nantan.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the past, the area was generally called &quot;Kuchitanba&quot; or &quot;Kuchitan&quot;, not Nantan, and even now, there are some people who refer to the area with these terms instead of Nantan.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>なお、京都府教育委員会は口丹通学圏等と使用している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Prefectural Board of Education uses the former terms, for example, in the way of the Kuchitan school area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Prefectural Board of Education uses the former terms, for example, within Kuchitan school area.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Prefectural Board of Education uses the former terms, for example, within Kuchitan school area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>丹波国域でありながら京都や大阪との結びつきが強く、大阪管区気象台・京都地方気象台では山城国＋南丹で京都府南部とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though being in the Tanba Province area, Nantan is closely related to Kyoto and Osaka, and, when Osaka District Meteorological Observatory and Kyoto Local Meteorological Observatory use the term of &quot;the south part of Kyoto Prefecture,&quot; it indicates the area including both Yamashiro Province and Nantan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though being in the Tanba Province area, Nantan is closely related to Kyoto and Osaka, and, when Osaka District Meteorological Observatory and Kyoto Local Meteorological Observatory use the term of &quot;the south part of Kyoto Prefecture,&quot; it refers to the area which includes both Yamashiro Province and Nantan.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Alhough being in the Tanba Province area, Nantan is closely related to Kyoto and Osaka, and, when Osaka District Meteorological Observatory and Kyoto Local Meteorological Observatory use the term of &quot;the south part of Kyoto Prefecture,&quot; it refers to the area which includes both Yamashiro Province and Nantan.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Though&quot; -&gt; &quot;Although&quot;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>物流でも、ヤマト運輸や日本通運や佐川急便の扱いでは山城国＋南丹を京都府南部としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the logistics business, Yamato Transport Co., Ltd., Nippon Express and Sagawa Express Co., Ltd. use the term of &quot;the south part of Kyoto Prefecture&quot; for indicating the area including both Yamashiro Province and Nantan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamato Transport Co., Ltd., Nippon Express and Sagawa Express Co., Ltd. use the term of &quot;the south part of Kyoto Prefecture&quot; to indicate the area which includes both Yamashiro Province and Nantan.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamato Transport Co., Ltd., Nippon Express and Sagawa Express Co., Ltd. use the term of &quot;the south part of Kyoto Prefecture&quot; to indicate the area which includes both Yamashiro Province and Nantan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>1965年（昭和40年）頃より行政用語として使われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nantan has been used as an administrative term since around 1965.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nantan has been used as an administrative term since around 1965.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nantan has been used as an administrative term since around 1965.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>地理的には南部が桂川 (淀川水系)流域、北部が由良川流域であり、普段から交流も多い地域であるが、文化圏としては方言など多少の差異もあり、必ずしも単一とはいえない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Much interaction exists generally between its southern part, which is located along the Katsura-gawa River (in the Yodo-gawa River warter system) and its northern part, which is located along the Yura-gawa River, but it cannot be said that the area constitutes a single cultural area, for example, because the dialects in the two parts are slightly different.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Much interaction exists between its southern part, which is located along the Katsura-gawa River (in the Yodo-gawa River warter system) and its northern part, which is located along the Yura-gawa River, but it cannot be said that the area constitutes a single cultural area, due to the slight differences in dialect which exist between the two regions.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Much interaction exists between its southern part, which is located along the Katsura-gawa River (Yodo-gawa River system) and its northern part, which is located along the Yura-gawa River, but it cannot be said that the area constitutes a single cultural area, due to the slight differences in dialect which exist between the two regions.</e>
<cmt>Yodo-gawa River system　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>現在では、行政区分としての用語に留まらず幅広く定着しており、官民問わず地域内の施設、事業所の名称に冠して用いられる事例が増えつつある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Now, this term is used not only for indicating an adminimistrative area but, increasingly more widely, for the names of various facilities and business sites, regardless of whether they are owned publicly or privately.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term is used not only to indicate an adminimistrative area, but is increasingly used to refer to the names of various facilities and business sites, regardless of whether they are owned publicly or privately.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term is used not only to indicate an adminimistrative area, but is increasingly used to refer to the names of various facilities and business sites, regardless of whether they are owned publicly or privately.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>京都府の地域振興局統合後の名称も南丹広域振興局（亀岡市）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after the area devlopment promotion bureaus were integrared, the term of Nantan remains in the Nantan regional development promotion bureau (located in Kameoka City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after the area devlopment promotion bureaus were integrated, the term Nantan remains in the Nantan regional development promotion bureau (located in Kameoka City).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after the regional promotion bureaus were integrated, the term Nantan remains in the Nantan Area Promotion Bureau (Kameoka City).</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。京都府南丹広域振興局 の表現を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>冠名施設</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Facilities with Nantan in its name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Facilities with Nantan in its name</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Facilities with Nantan in its name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>南丹市</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nantan City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nantan City</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nantan City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>京都府南丹家畜保健衛生所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Prefectural NANTAN Livestock Hygiene Center</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Prefectural NANTAN Livestock Hygiene Center</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Prefectural NANTAN Livestock Hygiene Center</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>京都府南丹広域振興局（亀岡市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nantan regional development promotion bureau of Kyoto Prefecture (located in Kameoka City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nantan regional development promotion bureau of Kyoto Prefecture (located in Kameoka City)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Prefecture Nantan Area Promotion Bureau (Kameoka City)</e>
<cmt>京都府南丹広域振興局 の表現を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>京都府南丹保健所（南丹市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nantan health care center of Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nantan health care center of Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nantan Health Care Center of Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>Health Care Center　としました（大文字に）。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>京都府南丹農業改良普及センター（南丹市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nantan center of Kyoto Prefecture for improving and popularizing agriculture (located in Nantan City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nantan center of Kyoto Prefecture for improving and popularizing agriculture (located in Nantan City)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nantan Center of Kyoto Prefecture for Improving and Popularizing Agriculture (Nantan City)</e>
<cmt>located in を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>京都府南丹土木事務所（南丹市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nantan engineering office of Kyoto Prefecture (located in Nantan City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nantan engineering office of Kyoto Prefecture (located in Nantan City)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nantan Engineering Office of Kyoto Prefecture (Nantan City)</e>
<cmt>located in を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="16">
<j>京都府南丹教育局（南丹市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nantan education bureau of Kyoto Prefecture (located in Nantan City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nantan education bureau of Kyoto Prefecture (located in Nantan City)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nantan Education Bureau of Kyoto Prefecture (Nantan City)</e>
<cmt>located in を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="17">
<j>公立南丹病院（南丹市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nantan General Hospital (located in Nantan City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nantan General Hospital (located in Nantan City)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nantan General Hospital (Nantan City)</e>
<cmt>located in を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="18">
<j>京都府立南丹高等学校（亀岡市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kyoto Prefectural Nantan high school (located in Kameoka City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kyoto Prefectural Nantan high school (located in Kameoka City)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kyoto Prefectural Nantan High School (Kameoka City)</e>
<cmt>located in を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 まったけ(id:130042), Los688(id:12316), 桂鷺淵(id:151322), ぱむ(id:24323), Nantan(id:171573), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>