<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大阪都市圏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Osaka urban area</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Osaka Metropolitan Area</e>
<cmt>&quot;urban area&quot;→&quot;Metropolitan Area&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Osaka Metropolitan Area</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大阪都市圏（おおさかとしけん）は、大阪府大阪市を中心とする経済地域で、大阪市と周辺の衛星都市とをまとめて指す呼び名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Osaka urban area is the centre of economy of Osaka City or other surrounded area, or it is used to call the area of Osaka city including surrounding satellite city.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Osaka Metropolitan Area is a term used to describe the economic area centered on Osaka city and including surrounding satellite cities.</e>
<cmt>&quot;urban area&quot;→&quot;Metropolitan Area&quot;Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Osaka Metropolitan Area is a name used to describe the economic area centered on Osaka city, expanding to its surrounding satellite cities.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>都市雇用圏（10%通勤圏）の中心部には大阪市のほか、東大阪市・門真市・守口市が含まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the central area of the city where people commute from outside of the city (the suburb more than 10% of whose population commuting to the central city) includes cities such as Osaka City, Higashi Osaka City, Kadoma City, Moriguchi City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The central region of the Urban Employment Area (an area where at least 10% of the population of the suburbs commute to the central city) includes Osaka City, Higashi Osaka City, Kadoma City and Moriguchi City.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The central region of the Urban Employment Area (an area where at least ten percent of the suburban population commutes to the central city) includes the cities of Osaka, Higashi-Osaka, Kadoma and Moriguchi.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>大阪市を中心とする都市雇用圏は、奈良県、兵庫県、京都府、和歌山県、三重県におよび、約1212万人（2000年）の人口を擁する日本第2位の都市圏を形成している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Urban Employment Area, surrounding of Osaka City, are Nara Prefecture, Hyogo Prefecture, Kyoto Prefecture, Wakayama Prefecture, Mie Prefecture, and the population in those areas is twelve million one hundred twenty thousand (year 2000), which is the second largest metropolitan area in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Urban Employment Area centered on Osaka City and comprising Nara Prefecture, Hyogo Prefecture, Kyoto Prefecture, Wakayama Prefecture, and Mie Prefecture has a population of approximately 12,120,000 (2000), making it the second largest metropolitan area in Japan.</e>
<cmt>&quot;surrounding of&quot;→&quot;centered on&quot;&quot;, are&quot;→&quot;and comprising&quot;Added &quot;and&quot;&quot;, and the&quot;→&quot;has a&quot;&quot;in those areas is &quot;→&quot;of&quot;Added &quot;approximately&quot;Changed the population to figuresDeleted &quot;year&quot;&quot;which is&quot;→&quot;making it&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Urban Employment Area centered on Osaka City expands to include the prefectures of Nara, Hyogo, Kyoto, Wakayama, and Mie and has a population of approximately 12,120,000 (in 2000), forming the second largest metropolitan area in Japan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>大阪市への流入超過人口は107万人であり、昼間人口は366万人となって、横浜市の昼間人口を越える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The excess inflow of population of Osaka City is one million seventy thousand, the daytime population is three million six hundred sixty thousand which is more than the daytime population of Yokohama City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With an excess inflow of population into Osaka City of 1,070,000, the daytime population is 3,660,000, which is more than the daytime population of Yokohama City.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;with&quot;&quot;the&quot;→&quot;an&quot;&quot;of&quot;→&quot;into&quot;&quot;is&quot;→&quot;of&quot;Changed the population to figures</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With an excess inflow into Osaka City of population of 1,070,000, the daytime population is 3,660,000, which is higher than the daytime population of Yokohama City.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>大阪市の周辺を見ると、京都市・神戸市・姫路市・和歌山市がそれぞれ中心機能を持って通勤・通学者を求心し、各々昼間人口が常住人口を越えているため、個別の都市圏を形成していると見なされている（）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The surrounding cities of Osaka City such as Kyoto City, Kobe City, Himeji City, Wakayama City, they all have centripetal force to centripetal commuters or students to commute to the city, and are considered as individual metropolitan area to since daytime population exceeds the population of actually living people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The cities of Kyoto City, Kobe City, Himeji City and Wakayama City, which surround Osaka City, all attract commuters for work and school and since their daytime populations exceed their nighttime populations, they are considered as individual metropolitan areas.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the cities of Kyoto, Kobe, Himeji and Wakayama, which surround Osaka, respectively function as a center and attract commuters going to work and school so that their daytime populations exceed their nighttime populations, they are taken to individually form metropolitan areas.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>京都都市圏：258万3304人、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto urban area : 2,580,304 people (two million five hundred eighty three thousand three hundred and four people)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Metropolitan Area: 2,580,304 people</e>
<cmt>&quot;urban area&quot;→&quot;Metropolitan Area&quot;Deleted &quot;space&quot; and section in brackets</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Metropolitan Area: 2,583,304 people</e>
<cmt>数字を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>神戸都市圏：229万6268人、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kobe urban area : 2,296,268 people (two million two hundred ninety six thousan two hundred sixty eight people)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kobe Metropolitan Areaa: 2,296,268 people</e>
<cmt>&quot;urban area&quot;→&quot;Metropolitan Area&quot;Deleted &quot;space&quot; and section in brackets</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kobe Metropolitan Area: 2,296,268 people</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>姫路都市圏：74万1759人、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Himeji urban area : 741,759 people (seven hundred forty one thousand seven hundred fifty nine people)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Himeji Metropolitan Area: 741,759 people</e>
<cmt>&quot;urban area&quot;→&quot;Metropolitan Area&quot;Deleted &quot;space&quot; and section in brackets</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Himeji Metropolitan Area: 741,759 people</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="9">
<j>和歌山都市圏：57万3308人、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wakayama urban area : 573,308 people (five hundred seventy three thousand three hundred eight people)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wakayama Metropolitan Area: 573,308 people</e>
<cmt>&quot;urban area&quot;→&quot;Metropolitan Area&quot;Deleted &quot;space&quot; and section in brackets</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wakayama Metropolitan Area: 573,308 people</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="10">
<j>ただし、業務機能は大阪が飛び抜けているため、これらの都市や都市圏は、衛星都市あるいは衛星都市圏と見ることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However in terms of business function, Osaka City is much more ahead of other cities, thus other cities or city urban area can be called satellite city or satellite urban area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since Osaka City is much more advanced in terms of business facilities, these other cities or metropolitan areas can be seen as satellite cities or satellite metropolitan areas.</e>
<cmt>&quot;in terms of business function, Osaka City is much more ahead of other cities&quot;→&quot;since Osaka City is much more advanced in terms of business facilities&quot;Deleted &quot;thus&quot;Added &quot;these&quot;&quot;urban area&quot;→&quot;metropolitan areas&quot;&quot;called&quot;→&quot;seen as&quot;Made &quot;city&quot; plural&quot;urban area&quot;→&quot;metropolitan areas&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Osaka City is much more advanced in terms of business facilities, however, these other cities or metropolitan areas are sometimes seen as satellite cities or metropolitan areas.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>そのような連結した都市圏と見なす総務省の定義では、大阪市・京都市・神戸市を中心市とした都市圏 (総務省)が設定され、京阪神大都市圏と名付けられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ministry of Internal Affairs defined those cities as combined urban area, and the urban area (Ministry of Internal Affairs and Communications), consist of major cities such as Osaka City, Kyoto City, Kobe City, were established, which is called Keihanshin Metropolitan area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ministry of Internal Affairs and Communications defined these cities as a combined urban area, and established the the Kyoto-Osaka-Kobe (or Keihanshin) Metropolitan Area, with these cities as the central cities.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;and Communications&quot;&quot;those&quot;→&quot;these&quot;Added &quot;a&quot;Reworded 2nd half of sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ministry of Internal Affairs and Communications defined these cities as a combined urban area, and established the Kyoto-Osaka-Kobe (or Keihanshin) Metropolitan Area, with these cities as the central cities.</e>
<cmt>the　のダブりを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>京阪神大都市圏は、人口が1864万3915人（2000年国勢調査）を抱え、三大都市圏あるいは七大都市圏の1つとされる一方、世界で十指に入る大都市圏でもある（世界の都市圏人口の順位）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The population of Keihanshin Metropolitan area is eighteen million six hundred forty three thousand three thousand nine hundred fifteen (national census in 2000), and is considered as one of the three major urban area or seven major urban area. (ranked by the population of urban area in the world)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The population of Keihanshin Metropolitan Area is 18,643,915 (2000 census), and is considered as one of the three major metropolitan areas and one of seven Greater Urban Areas as well as one of the top ten metropolitan areas in the world (as ranked by population)</e>
<cmt>Capitalised &apos;a&apos;Changed the population to figures&quot;national census in 2000&quot;→&quot;2000 census&quot;&quot;urban&quot;→&quot;metropolitan&quot;Made &quot;area&quot; plural&quot;or&quot;→&quot;and&quot;Added &quot;one of&quot;Made &quot;area&quot; plural - tried to make a distinction between 三大都市圏 and 七大都市圏 since if something is in the top three, it&apos;s obviously in the top sevenAdded &quot;as well as one of the top ten metropolitan areas in the world&quot;Added &quot;as&quot;Deleted &quot;the&quot;, &quot;of urban area in the world&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The population of Keihanshin Metropolitan Area is 18,643,915 (2000 census), and is considered one of Three Major Metropolitan Areas and one of Seven Greater Urban Areas as well as one of the top ten metropolitan areas in the world (as ranked by population).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>定義</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Definition</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Definition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Definition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>10%都市圏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the suburb more than 10% of whose population commuting to the central city</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;10% Metropolitan Area&quot; - an area where at least 10% of the population of the suburbs commute to the central city</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence for clarity and accuracy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;10% Metropolitan Area&quot; - an area where at least 10% of the population of the suburbs commute to the central city</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>2000年（平成12年）国勢調査「常住地による従業・通学市区町村別15歳以上就業者及び15歳以上通学者数」に基づいた、大阪市・東大阪市・門真市・守口市を中心市とする都市雇用圏（10%通勤圏）の人口は約1212万人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to national census in 2000 (Heisei 12) of &apos;the number of the employee and students older than fifteen years in different industries and different commuting area (district, town, village) sorted by the place where people live&apos;, the population of Urban Employment Area (the suburb more than 10% of whose population commuting to the central city), the population of the central cities including Osaka City, Higashi Osaka City, Kadoma City, Moriguchi City, is twelve million one hundred twenty thousand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on &apos;the numbers of employees and students over the age of fifteen, according to permanent residence and destination&apos; from the 2000 national census, the population of the Urban Employment Area (an area where at least 10% of the population of the suburbs commute to the central city), centered on Osaka City, Higashi Osaka City, Kadoma City, and Moriguchi City, is 12,120,000.</e>
<cmt>&quot;According to&quot;→&quot;Based on&quot;&quot;national census in 2000&quot;→&quot;from the 2000 national census&quot; and movedDeleted &quot;(Heisei 12)&quot; - unecessary for English speakersMade &quot;number&quot; pluralDeleted &quot;the&quot;Made &quot;employee&quot; plural&quot;older than fifteen years&quot;→&quot;over the age of fifteen&quot;&quot;in different industries and different commuting area (district, town, village) sorted by the place where people live&quot;→&quot;according to permanent residence and destination&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;the suburb more than 10% of whose population commuting&quot;→&quot;an area where at least 10% of the population of the suburbs commute&quot;&quot; the population of the central cities including&quot;→&quot;centered on&quot;Added &quot;and&quot;Changed the population to figures</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on &apos;the number of employees and students over the age of fifteen, according to permanent residence and destination&apos; from the 2000 national census, the population of the Urban Employment Area (an area where at least 10% of the suburban population commutes to the central city), centered on the cities of Osaka, Higashi-Osaka, Kadoma, and Moriguchi, is 12,120,000.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>その中で通勤率が最も高い自治体は奈良県生駒市の47.6%であり、最も低い自治体は奈良県天理市の10.0%である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those cities Ikoma City, Nara Prefecture has the highest commuting rate of 47, 6 percent, while other self-governing body, Tenri City, Nara Prefecture has the lowest commuting rate of 10 percent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those cities, the municipality with the highest commuting rate is Ikoma City, Nara Prefecture at 47.6 percent, while the lowest is Tenri City, Nara Prefecture at 10 percent.</e>
<cmt>Added commaAdded &quot;the municipality with&quot;Moved &quot;the highest commuting rate&quot;Added &quot;is&quot;Deleted &quot;has&quot;&quot;of&quot;→&quot;at&quot;comma→decimal point&quot;other self-governing body, Tenri City, Nara Prefecture has the lowest commuting rate of&quot;→&quot;the lowest is Tenri City, Nara Prefecture at&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those cities, the municipality with the highest commuting rate is Ikoma City of Nara Prefecture at 47.6 percent, while the lowest is Tenri City of Nara Prefecture at 10 percent.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>以下は通勤率上位5つの自治体である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above are five self-governing bodies which has the most higher commuting rate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The below are the five municipalities with the highest commuting rates.</e>
<cmt>&quot;above&quot;→&quot;below&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;self-governing bodies&quot;→&quot;municipalities&quot;&quot;which has&quot;→&quot;with&quot;&quot;most higher&quot;→&quot;highest&quot;Made &quot;rate&quot; plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The five municipalities with the highest commuting rates are shown below.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>都市圏の変遷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The change of the urban area</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Changes in metropolitan areas</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;The&quot;Made &quot;change&quot; plural&quot;of&quot;→&quot;in&quot;Deleted &quot;the&quot;&quot;urban area&quot;→&quot;metropolitan areas&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Changes in the Urban Employment Area (an area where at least 10% of the suburban population commutes to the central city)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>都市雇用圏（10%通勤圏）の変遷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The change of Urban Employment Area (the suburb more than 10% of whose population commuting to the central city)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Changes in Urban Employment Area (an area where at least 10% of the population of the suburbs commute to the central city)</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;The&quot;Made &quot;change&quot; plural&quot;of&quot;→&quot;in&quot;&quot;the suburb more than 10% of whose population commuting to the central city&quot;→&quot;an area where at least 10% of the population of the suburbs commute to the central city&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Changes in Urban Employment Area (an area where at least 10% of the population of the suburbs commute to the central city)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>※10%通勤圏に入っていない自治体は、各統計年の欄で灰色かつ「-」で示す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">*The self-governing body which was not included in the suburb more than 10% of whose population commuting to the central city are shown in either gray color or &apos; - &apos; mark in the total column of each year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">*Municipalities not included in areas where at least 10% of the population of the suburbs commute to the central city are shown either in either gray or by a &apos; - &apos; mark in the total column of each year.</e>
<cmt>&quot;The self-governing body&quot;→&quot;Municipalities&quot;Deleted &quot;which was&quot;&quot;the suburb more than 10% of whose population commuting to the central city&quot;→&quot;areas where at least 10% of the population of the suburbs commute to the central city&quot;Moved &quot;either&quot;Deleted &quot;color&quot;Added &quot;by a&quot;&quot;of&quot;→&quot;for&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Municipalities not included in &apos;the areas where at least 10% of the suburban population commutes to the central city&apos; are shown in gray with a mark &apos; - &apos; in the total column of each year.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="18">
<j>1987年10月1日、南河内郡大阪狭山市が市制施行して大阪狭山市となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 1, 1987, Osaka sayama City, Minami kawachi District made enforcement of municipal organization and became Osaka sayama City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 1, 1987, Osakasayama City, Minami kawachi District was reorganized into Osakasayama City.</e>
<cmt>I believe before 1987 the name was 狭山町 not 大阪狭山市 but left it as in original japaneseDeleted space&quot;made enforcement of municipal organization and became&quot;→&quot;was reorganized into&quot;Deleted space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 1, 1987, Sayama-cho, Minamikawachi-gun was reorganized into Osakasayama City.</e>
<cmt>（チェッカーの方が指摘下さっていますが）、原文の和文wiki では「南河内郡狭山町」となっておりますので、こちらも左記のように変更いたしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="19">
<j>1991年10月1日、泉南郡阪南町が市制施行して阪南市となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 1, 1991, Hannan-cho, Sennan district made enforcement of municipal organization and became Hannan City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 1, 1991, Hannan-cho, Sennan district was reorganized into Hannan City.</e>
<cmt>&quot;made enforcement of municipal organization and became&quot;→&quot;was reorganized into&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 1, 1991, Hannan-cho, Sennan-gun was reorganized into Hannan City.</e>
<cmt>Sennan-gun　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="20">
<j>1991年10月1日、北葛城郡香芝町が市制施行して香芝市となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 1, 1991, Hannan-cho, Sennan district made enforcement of municipal organization and became Kashiba City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 1, 1991, Kashiba-cho, Kitakatsuragi district was reorganized into Kashiba City.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Hannan-cho, Sennan district&quot;→&quot;Kashiba-cho, Kitakatsuragi district&quot;&quot;made enforcement of municipal organization and became&quot;→&quot;was reorganized into&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 1, 1991, Kashiba-cho, Kitakatsuragi-gun was reorganized into Kashiba City.</e>
<cmt>Kitakatsuragi-gun としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>1999年4月1日、多紀郡今田町・篠山町・丹南町・西紀町の4町が合併して篠山市となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 1, 1999, Konda-cho, Sasayama-cho, Tannan-cho and Nishiki-cho of Taki district, four towns were combined and became Sasayama City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 1, 1999, Konda-cho, Sasayama-cho, Tannan-cho and Nishiki-cho of Taki district merged to become Sasayama City.</e>
<cmt>&quot;, four towns were combined and became&quot;→&quot;merged to become&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 1, 1999, Konda-cho, Sasayama-cho, Tannan-cho and Nishiki-cho of Taki-gun merged to become Sasayama City.</e>
<cmt>taki-gun　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="22">
<j>2004年10月1日、北葛城郡新庄町・當麻町の2町が合併して葛城市となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 1, 2004, Konda-cho, Sasayama-cho, Tannan-cho and Nishiki-cho of Taki district, two towns were combined and became Iga City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 1, 2004, Konda-cho, Sasayama-cho, Tannan-cho and Nishiki-cho of Taki district, merged to become Iga City.</e>
<cmt>&quot;, two towns were combined and became&quot;→&quot;merged to become&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 1, 2004, Shinjo-cho and Taima-cho of Kitakatsuragi-gun merged to become Katsuragi City.</e>
<cmt>地名を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="23">
<j>2004年11月1日、上野市、名賀郡青山町、阿山郡伊賀町・阿山町・大山田村 (三重県)・島ヶ原村の1市3町1村が合併して伊賀市となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 1, 2004, Ueno City, Aoyama-cho of Naga district, Ayama-cho, Iga-cho, Oyamada-mura (Mie Prefecture), Shigarahara-mura of Ayama district, one city, three towns and one village were combined and became Iga City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 1, 2004, Ueno City, the towns of Aoyama-cho of Naga district, Ayama-cho, Iga-cho, and the villages of Oyamada-mura (Mie Prefecture) and Shigarahara-mura of Ayama district merged to become Iga City.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the towns of&quot;, &quot;and the villages of&quot;comma→&quot;and&quot;&quot;one city, three towns and one village were combined and became&quot;→&quot;merged to become&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 1, 2004, Ueno City; Aoyama-cho town of Naga-gun; and Iga-cho town, Ayama-cho town, Oyamada-mura village, and Shimagahara-mura village of Ayama-gun in Mie Prefecture merged to become Iga City.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="24">
<j>2005年2月1日、堺市が南河内郡美原町を編入した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 1, 2005, Sakai City incorporated Mihara-cho, Minamikawachi district into the same city.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 1, 2005, Sakai City annexed Mihara-cho, Minamikawachi district.</e>
<cmt>&quot;incorporated&quot;→&quot;annexed&quot;Deleted &quot;into the same city&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 1, 2005, Sakai City annexed Mihara-cho, Minamikawachi-gun.</e>
<cmt>Minamikawachi-gun としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="25">
<j>2005年4月1日、奈良市が山辺郡都祁村、添上郡月ヶ瀬村を編入した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 1, 2005, Nara City incorporated Tsuge-mura, Yamabe district and Tsukigase-mura, Soekami district into the same city.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 1, 2005, Nara City annexed Tsuge-mura, Yamabe district and Tsukigase-mura, Soekami district.</e>
<cmt>&quot;incorporated&quot;→&quot;annexed&quot;Deleted &quot;into the same city&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 1, 2005, Nara City annexed Tsuge-mura, Yamabe-gun and Tsukigase-mura, Soekami-gun.</e>
<cmt>Yamabe-gun, Soekami-gun としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="26">
<j>2005年10月24日、三木市が美嚢郡吉川町 (兵庫県)を編入した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 24, 2005, Miki City incorporated Yokawa-cho (Hyogo Prefecture), Mino district (Hyogo Prefecture) into the same city.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 24, 2005, Miki City annexed Yokawa-cho, Mino district (Hyogo Prefecture) into the same city.</e>
<cmt>&quot;incorporated&quot;→&quot;annexed&quot;Deleted &quot;(Hyogo Prefecture)&quot;, &quot;into the same city&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 24, 2005, Miki City annexed Yokawa-cho, Mino-gun (Hyogo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="27">
<j>2006年1月1日、宇陀郡榛原町・室生村・大宇陀町・菟田野町の3町1村が合併して宇陀市となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 1, 2006, three towns and one village, Haibara-cho, Muro-mura, Ouda-cho and Utano-cho of Uda district were combined into one city and became Uda City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 1, 2006, the towns of Haibara-cho, Ouda-cho, Utano-cho and the village of Muro-mura of Uda district were merged to become Uda City</e>
<cmt>&quot;three towns and one village, Haibara-cho, Muro-mura, Ouda-cho and Utano-cho&quot;→&quot;the towns of Haibara-cho, Ouda-cho, Utano-cho and the village of Muro-mura&quot;&quot; were combined into one city and became&quot;→&quot;merged to become&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 1, 2006, the towns of Haibara-cho, Ouda-cho, Utano-cho and the village of Muro-mura of Uda-gun merged to become Uda City</e>
<cmt>Uda-gun　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="28">
<j>2006年3月1日、橋本市、伊都郡高野口町の1市1町が合併して橋本市となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 1, 2006, Hashimoto City and Koyaguchi-cho, one city and one town combined into one and became Hasimoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 1, 2006, Hashimoto City and the town of Koyaguchi-cho, merged to become Hasimoto City.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the town of&quot;&quot;one city and one town combined into one and became&quot;→&quot;merged to become&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 1, 2006, Hashimoto City, and Koyaguchi-cho town of Ito-gun were integrated to form Hashimoto City.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="29">
<j>2007年3月12日、相楽郡木津町・加茂町・山城町 (京都府)の3町が合併して木津川市となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 12, 2007, three suburbs of Kizu-cho, Kamo-cho and Yamashiro-cho of Soraku district (in Kyoto-Prefecture) combined into one city, and became one Kizugawa City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 12, 2007, the three suburbs of Kizu-cho, Kamo-cho and Yamashiro-cho in Soraku district (in Kyoto Prefecture) merged to become Kizugawa City.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;of&quot;→&quot;in&quot;hyphen→space&quot;combined into one city, and became one&quot;→&quot;merged to become&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 12, 2007, the three suburbs of Kizu-cho, Kamo-cho and Yamashiro-cho in Soraku-gun (Kyoto Prefecture) merged to become Kizugawa City.</e>
<cmt>Soraku-gun としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kebosebo(id:203944), もね～るmoner(id:28477), Mx-k(id:22681), Knua(id:66861), Im224(id:57113), Seibuabina(id:37532), Fievarsty(id:201483), Zell(id:23939), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>