<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>秋篠</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akishino</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akishino</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akishino</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>秋篠（あきしの）は、奈良県奈良市にある地名で、現在の住居表示では秋篠町。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akishino is the name of place in Nara City, Nara Prefecture and, according to the present residence indication, it is Akishino-cho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akishino is the name of place in Nara City, Nara Prefecture, and according to the present residence indication, it is Akishino-cho.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を移動</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akishino is the name of place in Nara City, Nara Prefecture, and according to the present residence indication, it is Akishino-cho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>かつては大和国添下郡に属しており、平城京の北西端にあった西大寺 (奈良市)の北側に広がる地域にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It belonged once to Yamato Province and corresponds to the region which expands in the north of Saidaiji (Nara City) which, in turn, existed in the northwestern end of Heijokyo (ancient capital of Japan in present Nara).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It belonged once to Sonoshimo County, Yamato Province and corresponds to the region which expands in the north of Saidai-ji Temple (Nara City) which, in turn, existed in the northwestern end of Heijokyo (ancient capital of Japan in present Nara).</e>
<cmt>「添下郡」→訳漏れのため訳出、Saidaiji→Saidai-ji Templeとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It belonged once to Sonoshimo County, Yamato Province and corresponds to the region which expands in the north of Saidai-ji Temple (Nara City) which, in turn, existed in the northwestern end of Heijokyo (ancient capital of Japan in present Nara).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>現在の皇室の秋篠宮の宮号の由来の土地でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a land which is the origin of Miyago (reigning name) of Akishinonomiya, a member of present imperial family).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a land which is the origin of Miyago (reigning name) of Akishinonomiya, a member of present imperial family.</e>
<cmt>不要なカッコを削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a land which is the origin of Miyago (reigning name) of Akishinonomiya, a member of present imperial family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>古くから土師氏ゆかりの土地であったと言われており、延暦元年（782年）に土師安人の姓が宿禰から朝臣に改められた際に「居住地にちなんで」秋篠安人と改名している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the place is the place noted in relation with Haji clan since the old time and, when kabane (hereditary title) of Yasuhito HAJI was changed from Sukune (third highest of the eight hereditary titles) to Ason (second highest of the eight hereditary titles) in 782, he changed his name to Yasuhito AKISHINO &quot;after the place of residence.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Akishino was a place noted in connection with the Haji clan since the old time and, when kabane (hereditary title) of Yasuhito HAJI was changed from Sukune (third highest of the eight hereditary titles) to Ason (second highest of the eight hereditary titles) in 782, he changed his name to Yasuhito AKISHINO &apos;after the place of residence.&apos;</e>
<cmt>the place is the place noted in relation with Haji clan→Akishino was a place noted in connection with the Haji clanとし、シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Akishino was a place noted in connection with the Haji clan since older times and, when kabane (hereditary title) of Yasuhito HAJI was changed from Sukune (third highest of the eight hereditary titles) to Ason (second highest of the eight hereditary titles) in 782, he changed his name to Yasuhito AKISHINO &apos;in connection with the name of the place of residence.&apos;</e>
<cmt>after the place of residence→in connection with the name of the place of residence</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>この少し前（具体的年代には諸説あり）に秋篠寺が秋篠の南側に建立された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A little while before that (there are different views about the exact period), Akishino-dera Temple was established in the south of Akishino.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A little while before that (there are different views about the exact period), Akishino-dera Temple was established in the south of Akishino.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A little while before that (there are different views about the exact period), Akishino-dera Temple was established in the south of Akishino.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>承平 (日本)元年（931年）には神願寺（神護寺の旧称）名義の荘園・秋篠荘の存在が確認できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be made sure that, in 931, there was Akishinosho, a shoen (manor) owned under the name of Jingan-ji Temple (former name of Jingo-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be made sure that, in 931, there was Akishinosho, a shoen (manor) owned under the name of Jingan-ji Temple (former name of Jingo-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been established that, in 931, there existed Akishinosho, a shoen (manor) owned under the name of Jingan-ji Temple (former name of Jingo-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>It can be made sure that→It has been established thatwas →existed</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>後に保元3年（1158年）には所有権が石清水八幡宮の別当寺である護国寺に移っていることが確認できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be also made sure that, later n 1158, the ownership had been transferred to Gokoku-ji Temple, which was a bettoji (a temple attached to a shrine) of Iwashimizu-hachimangu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be also made sure that, later n 1158, the ownership had been transferred to Gokoku-ji Temple, which was a bettoji (a temple attached to a shrine) of Iwashimizu-hachimangu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been established that, later in 1158, the ownership had been transferred to Gokoku-ji Temple, which was a bettoji (a temple attached to a shrine) of Iwashimizu-hachimangu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>It can be made sure that→It has been established that</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>また、和歌の歌枕としても著名であり、西行の『新古今和歌集』に採録された「秋篠や 外山の里や 時雨らむ 生駒の岳に 雲のかかれる」の歌や慈円の『拾玉集』に採録された「旅の空 秋ぞ悲しき 秋篠の 鹿と虫とに 枕並べて」の歌などが代表作として知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also known as utamakura (a place famed in classical Japanese poetry) for waka and Saigyo&apos;s waka recorded in &quot;Shinkokin wakashu,&quot; &quot;It must be raining in Akishino and villages in mountains, because Mt. Ikoma is covered with cloud &quot; and Jien&apos;s waka recorded in &quot;Shugyoku-shu,&quot; &quot;In the course of my trip, it is sad in autumn hearing voice of Japanese deers and insects of Akishino in the night&quot; are known as representative ones.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also known as utamakura (a place famed in classical Japanese poetry) for waka and Saigyo&apos;s waka recorded in the &quot;Shinkokin Wakashu&quot; (New Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry), &apos;It must be raining in Akishino and villages in mountains, because Mt. Ikoma is covered with cloud&apos; and Jien&apos;s waka recorded in the &quot;Shugyoku-shu&quot; (Collection of Gathered Jewels), &apos;In the course of my trip, it is sad in autumn hearing voice of Japanese deers and insects of Akishino in the night&apos; are known as representative ones.</e>
<cmt>in the &quot;Shinkokin Wakashu&quot;、in the &quot;Shugyoku-shu&quot;とし、各補足追加、一部シングルクォーテーションに変更 (参照: 用語集、およびhttp://books.google.co.jp/books?id=U0KcAwrVksQC&amp;pg=PA421&amp;dq=Shugyoku-shu+jien&amp;hl=ja&amp;ei=cetPTLrgLY2yvgPMgoDIAw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=3&amp;ved=0CDcQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q=Shugyoku-shu%20jien&amp;f=false)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also known as utamakura (a place famed in classical Japanese poetry) for waka and Saigyo&apos;s waka recorded in the &quot;Shinkokin Wakashu&quot; (New Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry), &apos;It must be raining in Akishino and villages in mountains, because Mt. Ikoma is covered with cloud&apos; and Jien&apos;s waka recorded in the &quot;Shugyoku-shu&quot; (Collection of Gathered Jewels), &apos;In the course of my trip, it is sad in autumn hearing voice of Japanese deers and insects of Akishino in the night&apos; are known as representative ones.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Lemon pie(id:66842), Yonoemon(id:55450), Mooko(id:36162), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>