<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>三輪山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mt. Miwa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mt. Miwa (a cone-shaped gentle mountain in Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mt. Miwa (a cone-shaped gentle mountain in Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>三輪山（みわやま）は、奈良県の最北部一帯の奈良盆地の南東部も位置する奈良県桜井市の南東部にそびえる、なだらかな円錐形の山である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mt. Miwa (Miwa-yama) is a cone-shaped gentle mountain in the south-eastern part of Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture which is located in the south-eastern part of Nara Basin across the farthest north part of Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mt. Miwa is a cone-shaped gentle mountain in the southeastern part of Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture, which is located in the southeastern part of Nara Basin across the farthest north part of Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>補足を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mt. Miwa is a cone-shaped gentle mountain in the southeastern part of Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture, which is located in the southeastern part of Nara Basin across the farthest north part of Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>標高467m、周囲16km。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">467 meters high, 16 kilometers around.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">467 meters high, 16 kilometers around.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">467 meters high, 16 kilometers around.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>三諸山（みもろやま）ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called mimoroyama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called Mimoroyama.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called Mimoroyama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>伝記</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>三輪山は、おそらく縄文時代、あるいは弥生時代から、自然物崇拝をする原始信仰の対象であったとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Mt. Miwa has been worshipped as God, perhaps, since Jomon Period or Yayoi Period, as an object of primitive belief in natural objects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Mt. Miwa has been worshipped as a god, perhaps, since Jomon period or Yayoi period, as an object of primitive belief in natural objects.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Mt. Miwa has been worshipped as a god, perhaps, since Jomon period or Yayoi period, as an object of primitive belief in natural objects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>古墳時代にはいると、山麓地帯には次々と大きな古墳が作られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When it entered Tumulus Period, large tumuluses were made one after another along the foot of a mountain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When it entered Kofun period (Tumulus period), large tumuli were made one after another along the foot of a mountain.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When it entered Kofun period (Tumulus period), large tumuli were made one after another along the foot of a mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>そのことから、この一帯を中心にして日本列島を代表する政治的勢力、すなわちヤマト政権の初期の三輪政権（王朝）が存在したと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From here onwards, it is considered that a leading political force in Japan island, that is, Miwa Regime (dynasty), which is equivalent to the early Yamato regime, existed mainly in this area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From here onwards, it is considered that a leading political force in Japan island, that is, Miwa Regime (dynasty), which was equivalent to the early Yamato regime, existed mainly in this area.</e>
<cmt>過去形にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From here onwards, it is considered that a leading political force in Japan island, that is, Miwa Regime (dynasty), which was equivalent to the early Yamato regime, existed mainly in this area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>200から300メートルの大きな古墳が並び、そのうちには第10代の崇神天皇（行灯山古墳）、第12代の景行天皇（渋谷向山古墳）の天皇陵があるとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Large tumuluses, from 200 meters to 300 meters, were lined up, and it is said that the Imperial mausoleums of the tenth Emperor Sujin (Mt. Andon Tumulus) and the twelfth Emperor Keiko (Shibutani Mukoyama Tumulus) were among them.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。行灯山古墳→定訳不明ですが→Mt. Andon Tumulus　と訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Large tumuli, from 200 meters to 300 meters, were lined up, and it is said that the Imperial mausoleums of the 10th Emperor Sujin (Andonyama-kofun Tumulus) and the 12th Emperor Keiko (Shibutani Mukoyama-kofun Tumulus) were among them.</e>
<cmt>スペル、用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Large tumuli, from 200 meters to 300 meters, were lined up, and it is said that the Imperial mausoleums of the 10th Emperor Sujin (Andonyama-kofun Tumulus) and the 12th Emperor Keiko (Shibutani Mukoyama-kofun Tumulus) were among them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>さらに箸墓古墳（はしはかこふん）は魏志倭人伝にあらわれる邪馬台国の女王卑弥呼の墓ではないかと推測されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, it is assumed that Hashihaka Tumulus (Hashika kofun) is the tomb of Himiko, the queen of Yamatai-Koku kingdom, who was depicted in Gishiwajinden (an &apos;Account of the Wa [inhabitants of the western Japanese archipelago in the late third century]&apos; in &quot;The History of the Wei Dynasty&quot; which comprises &quot;The History of the Three Kingdoms&quot; written by Chen Shou, where the account is known as the first historical record of Japan).</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, it is assumed that Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus is the tomb of Himiko, the queen of Yamatai-Koku kingdom, who was depicted in Gishiwajinden (an &apos;Account of the Wa&apos; [inhabitants of the western Japanese archipelago in the late third century] in &quot;The History of the Wei Dynasty&quot; which comprises &quot;The History of the Three Kingdoms&quot; written by Chen Shou, where the account is known as the first historical record of Japan).</e>
<cmt>用語、表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides, it is assumed that Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus is the tomb of Himiko, the queen of Yamatai-Koku kingdom, who was depicted in Gishiwajinden (an &apos;Account of the Wa&apos; [inhabitants of the western Japanese archipelago in the late third century] in &quot;The History of the Wei Dynasty&quot; which comprises &quot;The History of the Three Kingdoms&quot; written by Chen Shou, where the account is known as the first historical record of Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>『記紀』には、三輪山伝説として、奈良県桜井市にある大神神社の祭神・大物主神（別称三輪明神）の伝説が、載せられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kiki&quot; (the Kojiki and Nihonshoki) contains the legend of Omononushi no kami (also known as Miwa-myojin), the enshrined deity of Omiwa-jinja Shrine in Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture as Miwayama Legend.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kiki&quot; (the Kojiki [The Records of Ancient Matters] and Nihonshoki [Chronicles of Japan]) contains the legend of Omononushi no mikoto (also known as Miwa-myojin), the enshrined deity of Omiwa-jinja Shrine in Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture as legend of Mt. Miwa.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせ、用語補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kiki&quot; (the Kojiki [The Records of Ancient Matters] and Nihonshoki [Chronicles of Japan]) contains the legend of Omononushi no mikoto (also known as Miwa-myojin), the enshrined deity of Omiwa-jinja Shrine in Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture as legend of Mt. Miwa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>よって三輪山は神の鎮座する山、神名備とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, it is believed that Mt. Miwa is kannabi (divine mountain), a mountain which holds God.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, it is believed that Mt. Miwa is kannabi (divine mountain), a mountain which holds a god.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, it is believed that Mt. Miwa is kannabi (divine mountain), a mountain which holds a god.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>太古より神宿る山とされ、三輪山そのものが神体であるとの考えから、常人は足を踏み入れることの出来ない、禁足地の山とされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since it has been believed since the ancient time that Mt. Miwa holds God and Mt. Miwa itself is God, Mt.Miwa was regarded as a mountain which common people are prohibited to enter.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As it has been believed since the ancient time that Mt. Miwa holds a god and Mt. Miwa itself is a god, Mt. Miwa was regarded as a mountain which common people are prohibited to enter.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As it has been believed since the ancient time that Mt. Miwa holds a god and Mt. Miwa itself is a god, Mt. Miwa was regarded as a mountain which common people are prohibited to enter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>江戸時代には幕府より厳しい政令が設けられ、神社の山札がないと入山出来なかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period, Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) issued a strict order, and people are allowed to enter the mountain only when they had 山札 from a shrine.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。山札→定訳・読み方不明のため原文のままとしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period, Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) issued a strict order that people are allowed to enter the mountain only when they had a tablet of the mountain (山札) from a shrine.</e>
<cmt>英訳補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period, Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) issued a strict order that people are allowed to enter the mountain only when they had a tablet of the mountain (山札) from a shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>明治以降はこの伝統に基づき、「入山者の心得」なるものが定められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Meiji Period, `the guideline for visitors&apos; were defined based on the tradition.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Meiji period, &apos;the guideline for visitors&apos; was defined based on the tradition.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Meiji period, &apos;the guideline for visitors&apos; was defined based on the tradition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>現在においてはこの規則を遵守すれば誰でも入山出来るようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, anybody can enter the mountain as long as one can follow the rules of the guideline.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, anybody who follows the guideline can enter the mountain.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, anybody who follows the guideline can enter the mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>登山を希望する場合は、大神神社から北北東250mあたりに位置し、境内にある摂社・狭井神社の社務所にて許可を得なければならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To climb the mountain, one should visit and obtain permission from the shrine office of Sai-jinja Shrine, which is an auxiliary shrine of Omiwa-jinja Shrine and is 250 meters away from Omiwa-jinja Shrine to the north-northeast in the precincts of Omiwa-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To climb the mountain, the climber have to receive the permission at the shrine office of Sai-jinja Shrine, an auxiliary shrine of Omiwa-jinja Shrine, which is located in the precincts, 250 meters away to the north-northeast from Omiwa-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To climb the mountain, the climber have to receive the permission at the shrine office of Sai-jinja Shrine, an auxiliary shrine of Omiwa-jinja Shrine, which is located in the precincts, 250 meters away to the north-northeast from Omiwa-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>そこにて氏名を記入し300円を納める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There, pay 300 yen after writing the one&apos;s name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There, pay 300 yen after writing the one&apos;s name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There, pay 300 yen after writing the one&apos;s name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>そして参拝証の白いたすきを受け取り御祓いを済ませる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then receive a white sash that is a permit to climb the mountain, and is purified.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then receive a white sash that is a permit to climb the mountain, and is purified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then receive a white sash that is a permit to climb the mountain, and is purified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>道中このたすきを外すことは禁止されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is prohibited to take off the sash during the trip.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is prohibited to take off the sash during the trip.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is prohibited to take off the sash during the trip.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>通例2時間ほどで下山出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In general it takes about two hours to go down the mountain.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In general it takes about two hours to go down the mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In general it takes about two hours to go down the mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>だが、3時間以内に下山しなければならないという規則が定められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a rule that one should go down the mountain within three hours.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a rule that one should go down the mountain within three hours.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a rule that one should go down the mountain within three hours.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>また山中にては、飲食、喫煙、写真撮影の一切が禁止されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, all activities including eating or drinking, smoking, and photography in the mountains are prohibited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, all activities including eating or drinking, smoking, and shooting photograph in the mountains are prohibited.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, all activities including eating or drinking, smoking, and shooting photograph in the mountains are prohibited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="22">
<j>数多くの巨石遺構、祭祀遺跡も散在するが、これに対しても原則として許可なしに撮影出来ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A number of megalithic remains, ritual sites are scattered in the mountains, but photography is not permitted as a general rule.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A number of megalithic remains, ritual sites are scattered in the mountains, but photography is not permitted as a general rule.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A number of megalithic remains, ritual sites are scattered in the mountains, but photography is not permitted as a general rule.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>さらに山内の一木一葉に至るまで神宿るものとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">God is considered to be in all trees and leaves in the mountains.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">God is considered to be in all trees and leaves in the mountains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">God is considered to be in all trees and leaves in the mountains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>それに斧を入れることは許されておらず、山はマツ、スギ、ヒノキなどの大樹に覆われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, cutting a tree is not permitted, and the mountains are covered in big trees such as pine trees, cedar, cypress.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, cutting the tree is not permitted, and the mountains are covered in big trees such as pine trees, cedar, and cypress.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, cutting the tree is not permitted, and the mountains are covered in big trees such as pine trees, cedar, and cypress.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="25">
<j>入山せずに参拝する際には、大神神社の拝殿から三輪山を仰ぎ拝むといった手法をとる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To worship Mt. Miwa without climbing, viewing and worshipping it out of Haiden (a hall of worship) of Omiwa-jinja Shrine is possible.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To visit Mt. Miwa without climbing, viewing and worshipping it out of Haiden (a hall of worship) of Omiwa-jinja Shrine is possible.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To visit Mt. Miwa without climbing, viewing and worshipping it out of Haiden (a hall of worship) of Omiwa-jinja Shrine is possible.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>大神神社には本殿がなく、拝殿から神体である三輪山を直接拝むことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Omiwa-jinja Shrine is not equipped with Honden (main shrine), Mt. Miwa, God, can be directly worshipped at Haiden (a hall of worship).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Omiwa-jinja Shrine is not equipped with Honden (main shrine), Mt. Miwa, a god, can be directly worshipped at Haiden (a hall of worship).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Omiwa-jinja Shrine is not equipped with Honden (main shrine), Mt. Miwa, a god, can be directly worshipped at Haiden (a hall of worship).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="27">
<j>三輪山の祭祀遺跡としては、辺津磐座、中津磐座、奥津磐座などの巨石群、大神神社拝殿裏の禁足地遺跡、山ノ神遺跡、狭井神社西方の新境内地遺跡などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ritual sites of Mt. Miwa include megalithic group such as Hetsuiwakura, Nakatsuiwakura, and Okitsuiwakura, and Kinsokuchi (tabooed land) site that is behind the Haiden of Omiwa-jinja Shrine, Yamanokami Site, and 新境内地 site in the west of Sai-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>新境内地遺跡→定訳不明のため→新境内地 site としています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ritual sites of Mt. Miwa include megalithic group such as Hetsu-iwakura, Nakatsu-iwakura, and Okitsu-iwakura, and Kinsokuchi (tabooed land) site that is behind the Haiden of Omiwa-jinja Shrine, Yamanokami Site, and Shin-keidaichi (新境内地) site in the west of Sai-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>想定できる読みを補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ritual sites of Mt. Miwa include megalithic group such as Hetsu-iwakura, Nakatsu-iwakura, and Okitsu-iwakura, and Kinsokuchi (tabooed land) site that is behind the Haiden of Omiwa-jinja Shrine, Yamanokami Site, and Shin-keidaichi (新境内地) site in the west of Sai-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="28">
<j>頂上には高宮神社が祀られているが、延喜式神名帳には式内大社として神坐日向神社が載せられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takamiya-jinja Shrine is worshipped on the mountain top, but Miwaniimasu-himukai-jinja Shrine as Shikinai Taisha (first-ranked shrine listed in Engishiki laws) is listed in Jinmyocho (the list of deities) of Engishiki (codes and procedures on national rites and prayers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takamiya-jinja Shrine is worshipped on the mountain top, but Miwaniimasu Himukai-jinja Shrine as Shikinai Taisha (first-ranked shrine listed in Engishiki laws) is listed in Jinmyocho (the list of deities) of Engishiki (codes and procedures on national rites and prayers).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takamiya-jinja Shrine is worshipped on the mountain top, but Miwaniimasu Himukai-jinja Shrine as Shikinai Taisha (first-ranked shrine listed in Engishiki laws) is listed in Jinmyocho (the list of deities) of Engishiki (codes and procedures on national rites and prayers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>この日向神社は、古代には三輪山の頂上に祀られ、太陽祭祀に深く関わっていた神社であったと推測されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is assumed that Miwaniimasu-himukai-jinja Shrine is worshipped on the top of Mt. Miwa, and it was deeply involved with rituals worshipping sun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is assumed that Miwaniimasu Himukai-jinja Shrine is worshipped on the top of Mt. Miwa, and it was deeply involved with rituals worshipping the sun.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is assumed that Miwaniimasu Himukai-jinja Shrine is worshipped on the top of Mt. Miwa, and it was deeply involved with rituals worshipping the sun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="30">
<j>頂上付近はかなり広い平地である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a large flat area around the top of the mountain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a large flat area around the top of the mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a large flat area around the top of the mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>この神社の東方に東西約30メートル、南北10メートルの広場に高さ約2メートルほどの岩がたくさんある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are a number of rocks as tall as 2 meters in the place, about 30 meters from east to west, and 10 meters from south to north, to the east of the shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are a number of rocks as tall as 2 meters in the place, about 30 meters from east to west, and 10 meters from south to north, to the east of the shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are a number of rocks as tall as 2 meters in the place, about 30 meters from east to west, and 10 meters from south to north, to the east of the shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>これが奥津磐座である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This place is Okitsuiwakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These are the Okitsu-iwakura.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These are the Okitsu-iwakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>現在、この山中で見学できるのはこの磐座だけである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the only iwakura (dwelling place of a god, usually in reference to a large rock) that can be viewed in the mountain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the only iwakura (dwelling place of a god, usually in reference to a large rock) that can be viewed in the mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the only iwakura (dwelling place of a god, usually in reference to a large rock) that can be viewed in the mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Higashi(id:8842), BoB774(id:148281), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Nnh(id:474), しるふぃ(id:11247), Ans(id:27735), Wondy(id:84974), Show-ichi(id:10061), Mintleaf(id:2216), Godaigo(id:133481), Ｈｉｒｏ２００６(id:59115), Aska-sacra(id:8180), ごまふあざ(id:36855), Gombe(id:27), SpBot(id:209743), Hamichan(id:4829), Carkuni(id:79281), Xqbot(id:273540), D5(id:60352), 静かな線分(id:240750), Rei-bot(id:94097), 663highland(id:18755), Σ64(id:24481), PuzzIeBacheIor(id:18744), Namazu-tron(id:135120), Lincun(id:22742), Aduma(id:32899), Bbt888s(id:8239), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>