<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>保津峡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hozukyo Gorge</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hozukyo Gorge</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hozukyo Gorge</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>保津峡（ほづきょう）は、京都府亀岡市から京都市右京区嵐山の渡月橋に至る大堰川（保津川）の景勝地。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hozukyo Gorge is a picturesque scenic spot on the Oi-gawa river (the Hozu River) starting from Kameoka City, Kyoto Prefecture, and running through to Togetsu-kyo Bridge in Arashiyama, Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hozukyo Gorge is a picturesque scenic spot on the Oi-gawa river (the Hozu River) starting from Kameoka City, Kyoto Prefecture, and running through to Togetsu-kyo Bridge in Arashiyama, Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hozukyo Gorge, a picturesque scenic spot on the Oi-gawa River (the Hozu-gawa River), starts at Kameoka City, Kyoto Prefecture to Togetsu-kyo Bridge in Arashiyama, Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。-ku削除the Oi-gawa river→the Oi-gawa River</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>保津川は渡月橋から桂川 (淀川水系)となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hozu River changes its name to the Katsura river (the Yodo river system) at the Togetsu-kyo Bridge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hozu River becomes the Katsura river (the Yodo river system) at the Togetsu-kyo Bridge.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hozu-gawa River ends at the Togetsu-kyo Bridge where it flows into the Katsura-gawa River (the Yodo-gawa river system).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。the Katsura-gawa river→the Katsura-gawa Fiver</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>府立保津峡自然公園に含まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The prefectural Hozukyo National Park includes the gorge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The prefectural Hozukyo National Park includes the gorge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto prefectural Hozukyo Natural Park includes the gorge.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>保津峡は江戸時代の1606年（慶長11年）に角倉了以が、丹波の産物を京都に運搬するために造った水路である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hozukyo Gorge is a waterway constructed by Ryoi SUMINOKURA in 1606, in the Edo period, to ship &quot;Made in Tanba&quot; products to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hozukyo Gorge is a waterway constructed by Ryoi SUMINOKURA in 1606, in the Edo period, to ship products from Tamba to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hozukyo Gorge is a waterway constructed by Ryoi SUMINOKURA (1554-1614, wealthy merchant, shipowner, builder, and excavator) in 1606 in the Edo period to ship products from Tanba province (northwest of Kyoto) to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。TanbaをTambaに変更しました。Tamba→Tanba</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>保津川は蛇行を繰り返す激流で大きな岩が無数にあったが、人力で引っ張ったり火薬を使って発破作業を行ったりしながら、高瀬舟の通れる水路を約5か月で完成させたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that although the Hozu River was a meandering, raging torrent and there were innumerable huge rocks in the river, the waterway was completed in five months by pulling rocks away by human strength and blasting them with gunpowder so that Takasebune boats were able to travel.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that although the Hozu River was a meandering, raging torrent and there were innumerable huge rocks in the river, the waterway was completed in five months by manually removing rocks and blasting them with gunpowder so that Takasebune boats were able to navigate the waters.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that although the Hozu-gawa River was a meandering, raging torrent and there were innumerable huge rocks in the river, the waterway was completed in five months by manually removing rocks and blasting them with gunpowder so that Takasebune boats were able to navigate the waters.</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>それ以後、保津川は丹波と京を結ぶ産業水路として発展した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, the Hozu River has developed as an industrial waterway connecting Tanba with Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, the Hozu River has developed as an industrial waterway connecting Tamba with Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, the Hozu-gawa River has developed as an industrial waterway connecting Tanba with Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>近世になって主要な運搬物であった木材の需要が減り、同時に鉄道網が発達すると舟運の役目は終え水路は廃れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In early-modern times, because the demand for lumber, which was the major freight, had dropped and a railway network developed at the same time, transportation by ship completed its role and the waterway became outdated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In early-modern times, because the demand for lumber-- a major freight--had dropped and a railway network developed at the same time, transportation by ship completed its role and the waterway became outdated.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In early-modern times, since the demand for lumber (major cargo) had dropped, while the railway network had been expanded, ship transportation completed its role and the waterway became obsolete.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>保津川下り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hozu river trip</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hozu river trip</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hozu-gawa River Trip</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>景勝地である嵯峨野・嵐山に近いことから観光化の道を進み、1885年（明治28年）に観光客を対象とした遊覧船による川下りが行われるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the gorge&apos;s being the neighbor of the picturesque scenery of Sagano and Arashiyama, developments for tourism proceeded and river trips for tourists using pleasure boats began in 1885.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the gorge neighboring the picturesque scenery of Sagano and Arashiyama, developments for tourism proceeded and river trips for tourists using pleasure boats began in 1885.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the gorge has the picturesque scenery of Sagano and Arashiyama in its neighbor, developments for tourism proceeded there and river trips for tourists using pleasure boats began in 1885.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>この風流な保津川下りは夏目漱石の『虞美人草』を始め、水上勉、薄田泣菫、大町桂月、三島由紀夫など幾つもの文学作品に登場した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Elegant trips down to the Hozu river appeared in the literary works of Tsutomu MINAKAMI, Kyukin SUSUKIDA, Keigetsu OMACHI and Yukio MISHIMA, to say nothing of &quot;Gubijinso&quot; (The Poppy) written by Soseki NATSUME..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Elegant trips down to Hozu river appeared in the literary works of Tsutomu MINAKAMI, Kyukin SUSUKIDA, Keigetsu OMACHI and Yukio MISHIMA, to say nothing of Gubijinso (The Poppy) written by Soseki NATSUME..</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Elegant trips down the Hozu-gawa River appeared in the literary works of Tsutomu MINAKAMI, Kyukin SUSUKIDA, Keigetsu OMACHI and Yukio MISHIMA, let alone &quot;Gubijinso (The Poppy) &quot; written by Soseki NATSUME.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。重複していたピリオドを一つ取り除きました。作品名に&quot;&quot;をつけました。the Hozu-gawa river→the Hozu-gawa River</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>当時は、京都から人力車にのって老の坂を越え、篠町王子を経て保津川の亀岡盆地から保津峡への入り口にあたる山本浜（現在のトロッコ亀岡駅辺り）から乗船した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those days, people left Kyoto, crossed the Oi no saka Pass by a jinrikisha (a taxi-like vehicle pulled by a man), passed Shinochooji and the Hozu river at the Kameoka basin, and embarked on a boat at Yamamoto-hama (the neighborhood of the present Kameoka Torokko Station), which was the entrance to the Hozukyo Gorge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those days, people left Kyoto, crossed the Oi no saka Pass in a jinrikisha (a taxi-like vehicle pulled by a man), passed Shinochooji and the Hozu river at the Kameoka basin, and embarked on a boat at Yamamoto-hama (the neighborhood of the present Kameoka Torokko Station), which was the entrance to the Hozukyo Gorge.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, a tourist took a rickshaw (a taxi-like vehicle pulled by a man) from Kyoto, crossed the Oi no saka toge path, passed Shinocho-oji and the Hozu-gawa River at the Kameoka basin, and embarked on a boat at Yamamoto-hama (the neighborhood of the present Kameoka Torokko Station), which was the entrance to the Hozukyo Gorge.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。the Hozu-gawa river→the Hozu-gawa River</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>ルーマニア皇太子やイギリス皇太子などの賓客も興じたことから、王子から山本浜までの道のりは『京都府道402号王子並河線』と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because honored guests such as the crown prince of Romania and the Prince of Wales also enjoyed this trip, the way from Oji to Yamamoto-hama was called &quot;Kyoto prefectural road No.402, Oji Namikawa Route&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because honored guests, such as the crown prince of Romania and the Prince of Wales, have also enjoyed this trip, the way from Oji to Yamamoto-hama was known as Kyoto prefectural road No.402, Oji Namikawa Route.</e>
<cmt>wording; punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since honored guests, including Crown Prince of Romania and the Prince of Wales, have also enjoyed this trip, the way from Oji (literally meaning prince) to Yamamoto-hama was known as &quot;Kyoto prefectural road No.402 (Oji Namikawa Route)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>その後、川下りは大衆的なものとなり、また、乗船場もJR嵯峨野線亀岡駅近くに移された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later the river trip came to be for the masses, and the boarding place was moved to the neighborhood of Kameoka Station, JR Sagano Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later the river trip came to be for the masses, and the boarding place was moved to the neighborhood of Kameoka Station, JR Sagano Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later the river trip became popularized, and the pleasure boats boarding place was moved to the vicinity of Kameoka Station, JR Sagano Line.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。Pleasureのｐを小文字に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>1960年代は阪急電鉄が経営にあたっていたことがある（乗船場付近にある旧亀岡商工会館は「保津川観光会館」と名付けられた阪急の観光ホテルだった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hankyu Corporation carried on this business in the 1960&apos;s(The former Kameoka Chamber of Commerce and Industry Building near the boarding place used to be a Hankyu Corporation resort hotel named &apos;Hozugawa Kanko Kaikan.&apos;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hankyu Corporation carried on this business in the 1960&apos;s(The former Kameoka Chamber of Commerce and Industry Building near the boarding place used to be a Hankyu Corporation resort hotel named &apos;Hozugawa Kanko Kaikan.&apos;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankyu Corporation carried on this business in the 1960&apos;s(The former Kameoka Chamber of Commerce and Industry Building near the boarding place used to be a Hankyu Corporation resort hotel named &apos;Hozugawa Kanko Kaikan.&apos;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>阪急が5年間で経営から撤退した後は保津川遊船企業組合が経営にあたっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Hankyu Corporation withdrew from the business, the Hozugawa River tour boat business union took it over.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Hankyu Corporation withdrew from the business, the Hozugawa River tour boat business union took it over.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Hankyu Corporation withdrew from the operation of the Hozu-gawa River trip in five years, the Hozugawa River Tour Boat Business Union took over the operation.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。the hozugawa river→the Hozu-gawa River</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>現在の保津川下りは、春のツツジ（亀岡市の花）や秋の紅葉などを楽しもうと、四季折々多くの観光客が訪れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The current Hozu river trip is popular among many tourists from season to season, to see,for example, rhododendrons in spring (Kameoka city&apos;s flower) and colored leaves in autumn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The current Hozu river trip is popular among many tourists from season to season, to see, for example, rhododendrons in spring (Kameoka city&apos;s flower) and colored leaves in autumn.</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The current Hozu-gawa River trip is popular among many tourists from season to season, to see, for example, rhododendrons in spring (Kameoka City&apos;s flower) and colored leaves in autumn.</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。Hozu-gawa river→Hozu-gawa River</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>途中の景勝地には地蔵ヶ淵、小鮎の滝瀬、宮の下の瀬などの名所がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The highlights of the river trip are the picturesque scenic spots, such as the Jizo ga fuchi abyss, the Koayunotaki Rapids, the Miyanoshita rapids, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The highlights of the river trip are the picturesque scenic spots, such as the Jizo ga fuchi abyss, the Koayunotaki Rapids, the Miyanoshita rapids etc.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The highlights of the river trip are the picturesque scenic spots including the Jizo ga fuchi abyss, the Koayunotaki Rapids, and the Miyanoshita rapids.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>かつては、一旦荷物を積んで川を下った高瀬舟は、人に曳かれて保津川を遡っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Takasebune boats which went down the river with cargo used to go back up the Hozu river towed by people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Takasebune boats which went down the river with cargo used to go back up the Hozu river towed by people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the old days, the Takasebune boats (flat-bottomed, high-powered, long narrow river boat) used to go down the river with cargo and be towed by people to go back up the Hozu-gawa river.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>保津川の右岸には曳舟道が造られ、人夫が川に浮かべた船を曳きながらここを川上へ歩いていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A route for towing boats was built on the right bank of the Hozu river, and laborers used to walk upriver towing boats.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A route for towing boats was built on the right bank of the Hozu river, and laborers used to walk upriver towing boats.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A route for towing boats was built on the right bank of the Hozu-gawa River, and laborers used to walk upriver towing boats.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。the Hozu-gawa river,→the Hozu-gawa River</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>遊覧船もかつてはこの道を使い川を溯らせて亀岡まで戻していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pleasure boats used to be gone upstream, using this route to go back to Kameoka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Pleasure boats used to travel upstream, using this route to go back to Kameoka.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Pleasure boats used to be returned to Kameoka through this route to the upstream.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。重複していたピリオドを一つ取り除きました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>現在では、遊覧船を積んだトラックを国道9号線で見かけることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In these day, you will see trucks loaded with pleasure boats running along National Route 9.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In these day, you will see trucks loaded with pleasure boats running along National Route 9.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These days, trucks transport the pleasure boats through National Route 9.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>一方、船頭は嵯峨野線の嵯峨嵐山駅から亀岡駅・園部駅方面行きの電車で、“保津川を溯って”亀岡へ戻っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the contrary, ferrymen go back to Kameoka by train, taking Sagano Line bound for Kameoka Station or Sonobe Station from Saga Arashiyama station, and &quot;goes back up the Hozu river&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the contrary, ferrymen go back to Kameoka by train, taking Sagano Line bound for Kameoka Station or Sonobe Station from Saga Arashiyama station, and &quot;return up the Hozu river&quot;.</e>
<cmt>wording; note: it is not clear why the wording in red lettering must be in quotes from either the Japanese or English texts.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, ferrymen &apos;ascended the Hozu-gawa River&apos; to Kameoka from Saga-Arashiyama Station by Sagano Line train bounded for the stations of Kameoka or Sonobe.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。the Hozu-gawa river→the Hozu-gawa River</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>嵯峨野観光線・トロッコ列車</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sagano Sight-seeing Tram Line, Sagano Sight-seeing Tram</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sagano Sight-seeing Tram Line, Sagano Sight-seeing Tram</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sagano Sight-seeing Line and Sagano Sight-seeing Tram</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>保津峡で保津川下りと並んで有名なのが嵯峨野観光鉄道が運行している嵯峨野観光鉄道嵯峨野観光線のトロッコ列車である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As popular as the Hozu river trip when seeing the Hozukyo Gorge is the Sagano Sight-seeing Tram on the Sagano Scenic Railway Sagano Sight-seeing Tram Line, which is run by Sagano Scenic Railway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As popular as the Hozu river trip when seeing the Hozukyo Gorge is the Sagano Sight-seeing Tram on the Sagano Scenic Railway Sagano Sight-seeing Tram Line, which is run by Sagano Scenic Railway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tram of the Sagano Sight-seeing Line run by Sagano Scenic Railway is a popular attraction in the Hozukyo Gorge sightseeing as well as the Hozu-gawa River trip.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。the Hozu-gawa river→the Hozu-gawa River</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>保津峡を縫うように走り、景観に優れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It runs as if meandering through the Hozukyo Gorge, and the landscape is outstanding.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It runs as if meandering through the Hozukyo Gorge, and the landscape is outstanding.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The line meanders through spectacular scenery of the Hozukyo Gorge.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>元々は山陰本線の旧線の一部だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was originally part of the old railway line of Sanin Main Line.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was originally part of the old railway line of Sanin Main Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The line uses once-abandoned tracks of the Sanin Main Line.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>嵯峨駅（現在は嵯峨嵐山駅と改名）から馬堀駅までの複線化に伴い、トンネル経由の新線に切り替えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The old railway line was switched over to the new one going by way of tunnels, accompanied with its double-tracking from Saga Station (which has now changed its name Saga-Arashiyama station) to Umahori Station.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The old railway line was switched over to the new one going by way of tunnels, accompanied with its double-tracking from Saga Station (which has now changed its name to Saga-Arashiyama station) to Umahori Station.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tracks were once replaced by the new line which consists of tunnels, when the route between Saga Station (which has now changed its name to Saga-Arashiyama Station) to Umahori Station was converted to a double-track.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>そのため、カーブが多く複線化も困難だった旧線は一旦廃線となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of that, the old railway line, which had many curves and was difficult to make double-tracked, was once discontinued.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of that, the old railway line, which had many curves and was difficult to make double-tracked, was once discontinued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, the old tracks which have many curves and are difficult to be double-tracked, was once abandoned.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>しかしながら、保津峡の優れた景観を惜しむ声も多かったため、それを活用するためにJR西日本の完全子会社の手により1991年から営業を開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as there were many calls from those who valued the superb scenery of the Hozukyo Gorge, the line has been in service since 1991 as a wholly-owned subsidiary of West Japan Railway Company (JR West) to make the best use of the scenery.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as there were many calls from those who valued the superb scenery of the Hozukyo Gorge, the line has been in service since 1991 as a wholly-owned subsidiary of West Japan Railway Company (JR West) to make the best use of the scenery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as there were many calls from those who valued the superb scenery of the Hozukyo Gorge, a wholly-owned subsidiary of West Japan Railway Company (JR West) has run the line to make the best use of it since 1991.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>以来、多くの観光客を集めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, many tourists have gathered there.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, many tourists have gathered there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, the line has attracted many tourists.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>ラフティング</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rafting</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rafting</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rafting</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>近年、主に若年層の間で人気を集めているのがラフティング（コマーシャルラフティング）による保津川下りである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Currently, trips down to the Hozu river using rafts (Commercial Rafting) are becoming popular, mainly among the younger generation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently, trips down to the Hozu river using rafts (Commercial Rafting) are becoming popular, mainly among the younger generation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Currently, trips down the Hozu-gawa River by raft (Commercial Rafting) are becoming popular, mainly among the younger generations.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。the Hozu-gawa river→the Hozu-gawa River</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>保津川下りとほぼ同じコースをゴム製のラフト（ゴムボート）で下るラフティングは、一般的には観光川下りよりもスリルが味わえ、かつ「自分で操作する」という満足感を味わえるために人気が高まり、複数の業者が開催している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This rafting, using rafts made from plastic (rubber boats) and going down almost the same course as the Hozu river trip, has become more popular not only becaue people are usually more thrilled by it than by a river trip for tourists, but also because people are able to savor a feeling of satisfaction due to &quot;operating the boat on their own&quot;, and several companies have this sort of trip.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This rafting, using rafts made from plastic (rubber boats) and going down almost the same course as the Hozu river trip, has become more popular not only becaue people are usually more thrilled by it than by a river trip for tourists, but also because people are able to savor a feeling of satisfaction due to operating the boat on their own. This has prompted several companies to have this sort of trip.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rafting--going down almost the same stream as that of the pleasure boat trip by rubber raft (rubber boat)--has become popular not only because people are usually more thrilled than the pleasure boat trip but also because people can experience a feeling of satisfaction in &apos;operating the raft by themselves&apos;; therefore, several companies has launched rafting trip here.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>時間帯によっては観光川下りの舟よりもラフトの方が多いこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At some times of the day, there are more rafting boats on the river than boats for tourists.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At some times of the day, there are more rafting boats on the river than boats for tourists.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some time periods of a day, there are more rafting boats than the pleasure boats on the river.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kesikurikararin(id:57386), Bergmann(id:85282), Laichuan Yinfu(id:152533), Wrin(id:157424), Goncyan(id:92158), Zz2(id:30288), 樒(id:35770), Zenzai-Doji(id:98967), Rusk(id:9895), ぱむ(id:24323), Fromm(id:71291), まったけ(id:130042), Ray go(id:51282), K-riner(id:255119), Nopira(id:29335), Guretaro(id:163381), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>