<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>国府</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokufu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokufu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokufu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>国府（こくふ）は、日本の奈良時代から平安時代に、令制国の国司が政務を執る施設が置かれた場所や都市を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kokufu&quot; is the place and city at which facilities were established for Kokushi (provincial governors in the nation&apos;s governing system in old days) to administer the government affairs in the Nara and Heian periods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kokufu&quot; is a place and city at which facilities were established for Kokushi (provincial governors in the nation&apos;s governing system in old days) to administer governmental affairs during the Nara and Heian periods.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kokufu&quot; is a place and city at which facilities were established for Kokushi (provincial governors in the nation&apos;s governing system in old days) to administer governmental affairs during the Nara and Heian periods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>国衙ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called &quot;Kokuga&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called &quot;Kokuga&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called &quot;Kokuga&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>国府の施設と配置</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Facilities in Kokufu and their arrangement</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Facilities in Kokufu and their arrangement</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Facilities in Kokufu and their arrangement</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>律令制において、国司が政務を執った施設を国庁といい、国庁の周囲は塀などによって方形に区画されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The facilities where the Kokushi administered the government affairs were called &quot;Kokucho&quot; under the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code), whose surroundings were squarely demarcated by a fence or others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The facilities where the Kokushi administered the government affairs were called &quot;Kokucho&quot; under the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code), whose surroundings were squarely demarcated by a fence or other means.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The facilities where the Kokushi administered the government affairs were called &quot;Kokucho&quot; under the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code), whose surroundings were squarely demarcated by a fence or other means.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>令制国、郡、城柵で政務の中心となる建物をまとめて政庁というので、国庁もしばしば政庁と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The building where the government affairs were mainly carried out was called &quot;Seicho&quot; (government office) in the province under the Ritsuryo system, county and &quot;Josaku&quot; (government office with defense system), therefore, Kokucho was often called Seicho as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The building where government affairs were mainly carried out was called &quot;Seicho&quot; (government office) in the province under the Ritsuryo system, county and &quot;Josaku&quot; (government office with defense system), therefore, Kokucho was often called Seicho as well.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The building where government affairs were mainly carried out was called &quot;Seicho&quot; (government office) in the province under the Ritsuryo system, county and &quot;Josaku&quot; (government office with defense system), therefore, Kokucho was often called Seicho as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>国庁とその周りの役所群、都市域を総称して国衙（こくが）、国府という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokucho and the surrounding government offices as well as its urban area were collectively called Kokuga or Kokufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokucho and the surrounding government offices as well as its urban area were collectively called Kokuga or Kokufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokucho and the surrounding government offices as well as its urban area were collectively called Kokuga or Kokufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>現在は役所群のほうを国衙、都市のほうを国府と分けて用いることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, the word &quot;Kokuga&quot; is sometimes used for the government offices only, as well as &quot;Kokufu&quot; for urban areas in the historical study.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present, the word &quot;Kokuga&quot; is sometimes used for the government offices only, as well as &quot;Kokufu&quot; for urban areas in historical study.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present, the word &quot;Kokuga&quot; is sometimes used for the government offices only, as well as &quot;Kokufu&quot; for urban areas in historical study.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし同時代的には置換可能な語であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in those days, both words could replace each other.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in those days, both words could replace each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in those days, both words could replace each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>歴史的には国府の方が先行し、8世紀にはもっぱら国府という言葉が用いられ、平安時代後期以降に国衙が一般的になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Historically, the word &quot;Kokufu&quot; spread earlier than &quot;Kokuga&quot;, therefore the word &quot;Kokufu&quot; was mainly used in the eighth century, while &quot;Kokuga&quot; was mainly used after the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historically, the word &quot;Kokufu&quot; spread earlier than &quot;Kokuga&quot;, therefore the word &quot;Kokufu&quot; was mainly used in the eighth century, while &quot;Kokuga&quot; was mainly used after the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historically, the word &quot;Kokufu&quot; spread earlier than &quot;Kokuga,&quot; therefore the word &quot;Kokufu&quot; was mainly used in the eighth century, while &quot;Kokuga&quot; was mainly used after the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>各国の差が小さいのは中心となる国庁であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was little difference among each province in the structure of Kokucho.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was little difference among each province in the structure of Kokucho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was little difference among each province in the structure of Kokucho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>方形の区画の中に中庭を囲んで正殿、東脇殿、西脇殿を冂字形に配置し、南に正門を持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokucho built in a square lot was usually equipped with three buildings in the north, east and west, which was called &quot;Seiden&quot;, &quot;Higashi-wakiden 東脇殿&quot; (wakiden in the east) and &quot;Nishi-wakiden 西脇殿&quot; (wakiden in the west) in that order, as well as a main gate in the south, all of which surrounded a square courtyard.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処。東，西脇殿の読み方がわかりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokucho built in a square lot was usually equipped with three buildings in the north, east and west, which was called &quot;Seiden&quot;, &quot;Higashi-wakiden 東脇殿&quot; (wakiden in the east) and &quot;Nishi-wakiden 西脇殿&quot; (wakiden in the west) in that order, as well as a main gate in the south, all of which surrounded a square courtyard.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokucho built in a square lot was usually equipped with three buildings in the north, east and west, which was called &quot;Seiden,&quot; &quot;Higashi-wakiden&quot; (palace located on the east side) and &quot;Nishi-wakiden&quot; (palace located on the west side) in that order, as well as a main gate in the south, all of which surrounded a square courtyard.</e>
<cmt>東脇殿、西脇殿　の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>外形上もっとも整備された形では、南門から出る南北道と、これと交差する東西道が中心街路をなす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kokufu with the most sophisticated appearance, intersecting roads running north to south and east to west--the former started at the main gate of Kokucho--were the main streets.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kokufu with the most sophisticated appearance, intersecting roads running north to south and east to west--the former started at the main gate of Kokucho--were the main streets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kokufu with the most sophisticated appearance, intersecting roads running north to south and east to west--the former started at the main gate of Kokucho--were the main streets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その他の官衙、国司館、その他施設が区画割りして配置される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, other facilities such as &quot;Kanga&quot; (government office), and &quot;Kokushi-kan&quot; (official residences for Kokushi) were established in the lot given after division.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, other facilities such as &quot;Kanga&quot; (government office), and &quot;Kokushi-kan&quot; (official residences for Kokushi) were established in the lot given after division.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, other facilities such as &quot;Kanga&quot; (government office), and &quot;Kokushi-kan&quot; (official residences for Kokushi) were established in the lot given after division.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>しかし多くの場合国庁をとりまく建物群の配置の規律は緩い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, loose regulations were applied to the arrangement of the buildings surrounding Kokucho in many cases.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, loose regulations were applied to the arrangement of the buildings surrounding Kokucho in many cases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, loose regulations were applied to the arrangement of the buildings surrounding Kokucho in many cases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>国府の内と外を区分する外郭線は、国府が城柵に置かれたような例外を除き、ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was no border between the inside and outside of Kokufu except the case that Kokufu was established at Josaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was no border between the inside and outside of Kokufu except the case that Kokufu was established at Josaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was no border between the inside and outside of Kokufu except the case that Kokufu was established at Josaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>国府に限らず、律令制時代の日本では役所の建物を曹司という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The building of the government office including Kokufu was called &quot;Zoshi 曹司&quot; in Japan at the Ritsuryo period (period governed by Ritsuryo system).</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処。曹司の読み方がわかりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The building of the government office including Kokufu was called &quot;Zoshi 曹司&quot; in Japan at the Ritsuryo period (period governed by Ritsuryo system).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The building of the government office including Kokufu was called &quot;Zoshi&quot; (曹司) in Japan at the Ritsuryo period (period governed by Ritsuryo system).</e>
<cmt>括弧を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>これらがまとまった一区画を院と呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When these buildings were grouped in an area, the area was called &quot;In&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When these buildings were grouped in an area, the area was called &quot;In&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When these buildings were grouped in an area, the area was called &quot;In.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>国司館は、守館、介館など、国司のために用意された公邸である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokushi-kan, including Kamiyakata 守館 (official residence for the highest-ranked Kokushi) and Sukeyakata 介館 (official residence for the second highest-ranked Kokushi), was an official residence for Kokushi.</e>
<cmt>守館，介館の読み方がわかりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokushi-kan, including Kamiyakata 守館 (official residence for the highest-ranked Kokushi) and Sukeyakata 介館 (official residence for the second highest-ranked Kokushi), was an official residence for Kokushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokushi-kan, including Kamiyakata (守館) (official residence for the highest-ranked Kokushi) and Sukeyakata (介館) (official residence for the second highest-ranked Kokushi), was an official residence for Kokushi.</e>
<cmt>→守館=かみやかた　でよいようです（参考：http://www.hb.pei.jp/shiro/kaga/awatabingonokami-yakata/）括弧を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>もと国司は国庁で政務をとったが、平安時代中期以降、国司館が政務の中心になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokushi had originally administered the government affairs at Kokucho, although the center of the administration was shifted to Kokushi-kan after the mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokushi originally administered the government affairs at Kokucho, although the center of the administration was shifted to Kokushi-kan after the mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokushi originally administered the government affairs at Kokucho, although the center of the administration was shifted to Kokushi-kan after the mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>国府には正倉が付属するが、奈良時代には徴税実務上郡の重要性が大きく、地方の正倉は大部分郡家にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In spite of the custom that &quot;Shoso&quot; (warehouse) was established in the site of Kokufu, most Shoso in the local area were established at &quot;Guke&quot; (municipal government office in a county) in the Nara period, because a county played important role in collecting tax.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In spite of the custom that &quot;Shoso&quot; (warehouse) was established in the site of Kokufu, most Shoso in the local area were established at &quot;Guke&quot; (municipal government office in a county) in the Nara period, because the county played an important role in collecting taxes.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In spite of the custom that &quot;Shoso&quot; (warehouse) was established in the site of Kokufu, most Shoso in the local area were established at &quot;Gunke&quot; (municipal government office in a county) in the Nara period, because the county played an important role in collecting taxes.</e>
<cmt>郡家→Gunke としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>また工房があって、国府勤務の官人の需要に応じ、都に送る調庸物を生産した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, there was also a workshop in Kokufu, where gifts for the central government were produced in compliance with the requests of officers working at the Kokufu.</e>
<cmt>庸調物の意味がわかりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, there was also a workshop in Kokufu, where gifts for the central government were produced in compliance with the requests of officers working at the Kokufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, there was also a workshop in Kokufu, where choyobutsu (national tax) for the central government was produced in compliance with the requests of officers working at the Kokufu.</e>
<cmt>調庸物→national tax としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>役所や工房で働く人には、国厨（国府厨）から給食が出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kuninokuriya&quot; (also called &quot;Kokufukuriya&quot;, a kitchen of &quot;Kokufu&quot;) provided meals for people working at office and workshop.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kuninokuriya&quot; (also called &quot;Kokufukuriya&quot;, a kitchen of &quot;Kokufu&quot;) provided meals for people working at offices and workshops.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kuninokuriya&quot; (also called &quot;Kokufukuriya,&quot; a kitchen of &quot;Kokufu&quot;) provided meals for people working at offices and workshops.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>工房で働いたり様々な雑務を行う労働者が住む竪穴住居群があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a tateanajukyo (a pit dwelling house) complex as the residence for workers being engaged in the works at workshop and various miscellaneous duties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a tateanajukyo (a pit dwelling house) complex as the residence for workers being engaged in the works at workshop and various miscellaneous duties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a tateanajukyo (a pit dwelling house) complex as the residence for workers being engaged in the works at workshop and various miscellaneous duties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>さらに市場もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, there was also a market.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, there was also a market.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, there was also a market.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>国府の陸上交通のためには駅家が置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Umaya&quot; (facilities for providing horses, foods, etc.) were established for the land traffic.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Umaya&quot; (facilities for providing horses, foods, etc.) were established for traffic over land.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Umaya&quot; (facilities for providing horses, foods, etc.) were established for traffic over land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>水運のために国府津と呼ばれる港が設けられることも多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Port, called &quot;Kozu&quot;, was often established for the water transportation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Port, called &quot;Kozu&quot;, was often established for water transportation.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Port, called &quot;Kozu,&quot; was often established for water transportation.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="26">
<j>741年（天平13年）以降、国ごとに国分寺と国分尼寺が建てられることになったが、それ以前から国府機能と密着した付属寺院を持つ国もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Provincial monastery and provincial nunnery had officially been built by each province since 741, however some provinces had already built their own temple having a collusive relationship with &quot;Kokufu&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A provincial monastery and provincial nunnery had officially been built by each province since 741, however some provinces had already built their own temple having a collusive relationship with &quot;Kokufu&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A provincial monastery and provincial nunnery had officially been built by each province since 741, however some provinces had already built their own temple having a collusive relationship with &quot;Kokufu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>平安時代にはさらに総社が建てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;So-ja shrine&quot; (shrine enshrining several gods) was built in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;So-ja shrine&quot; (shrine enshrining several gods) was built in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, &quot;So-ja shrine&quot; (shrine enshrining several gods) was built in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="28">
<j>これらの施設が一箇所に集中して建てられると都市的な景観になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When these facilities were concentrated in one place, it provided an urban spectacle.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When these facilities were concentrated in one place, it provided an urban spectacle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When these facilities were concentrated in one place, it provided an urban spectacle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>しかし距離を置いて分散する例も多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in many Kokufu, these facilities were built dispersively, not too closely.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in many Kokufu, these facilities were built dispersively, and not too close to each other.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in many Kokufu, these facilities were built dispersively, and not too close to each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>国府には国司の他、史生、国博士、国医師、徭丁などの職員が勤務しており、小国で数十人、大国では数百人の人数規模だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to Kokushi, there were various staff such as Shisho (a person doing miscellaneous duties about documents), Kunihakase (teacher of Japanese classical literature), Kuniishi (local governmental doctor) and Yocho (laborer), whose number reached several dozens for small province while several hundreds for large province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to Kokushi, there were various staff such as Shisho (a person doing miscellaneous duties about documents), Kunihakase (teacher of Japanese classical literature), Kuniishi (local governmental doctor) and Yocho (laborer), whose numbers reached several dozens for small provinces and several hundreds for large province.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to Kokushi, there were various staff such as Shisho (a person doing miscellaneous duties about documents), Kunihakase (teacher of Japanese classical literature), Kuniishi (local governmental doctor) and Yocho (laborer), whose numbers reached several dozens for small provinces and several hundreds for large province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>全体としての人口は、陸奥国や武蔵国のような多いところで2、3千人に達したと推定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The population is presumed to have reached 2,000 to 3,000 in a dense area such as Mutsu Province and Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The population is presumed to have reached 2,000 to 3,000 in a dense area such as Mutsu Province and Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The population is presumed to have reached 2,000 to 3,000 in a dense area such as Mutsu Province and Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>国府の推定と発掘</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Location and excavation of Kokufu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Location and excavation of Kokufu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Location and excavation of Kokufu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="32">
<j>国府は室町時代に完全に消滅し、ほとんどが所在不明となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokufu was entirely extinct in the Muromachi period, whose location became uncertain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokufu was entirely extinct in the Muromachi period, whose location became uncertain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokufu was entirely extinct in the Muromachi period, whose location became uncertain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>和名類聚抄が国府があった郡を伝えるが、それ以上に絞り込むのは難しかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wamyo-ruijusho (Japanese dictionary of Chinese characters) introduces the county where Kokufu existed, however further details were hardly obtained.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wamyo-ruijusho (Japanese dictionary of Chinese characters) introduces the county where Kokufu existed, however further details were difficult to obtain.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wamyo-ruijusho (Japanese dictionary of Chinese characters) introduces the county where Kokufu existed, however further details were difficult to obtain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>1960年代までの研究では、「国府（こう）」、「国分寺」、「総社」、あるいはそれと似た地名が探索された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the research conducted until the 1960&apos;s, such place whose name was associated with &quot;Kokufu&quot; as &quot;Ko&quot;, &quot;Kokubunji &quot; and &quot;Soja&quot; were searched.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In research conducted until the 1960&apos;s, places whose name was associated with &quot;Kokufu&quot; as &quot;Ko&quot;, &quot;Kokubunji &quot; and &quot;Soja&quot; were searched.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In research conducted until the 1960&apos;s, places whose name was associated with &apos;Kokufu&apos; as &apos;Ko,&apos; &apos;Kokubunji,&apos; &apos;Soja&apos; or names that are similar to the above were searched.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>そして他の状況証拠とあわせて様々に位置が推理された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Adding other circumstantial evidence to this research, the location of Kokufu was inferred variously.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Adding other circumstantial evidence to this research, the location of Kokufu was inferred to be a variety of different places.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Adding other circumstantial evidence to this research, the location of Kokufu was inferred to be a variety of different places.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>しかし推定地は通常複数唱えられ、みな決め手を欠いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not a few places were always put forward as a candidate of the location of Kokufu, however each place lacked decisive proof.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Not a few places were always put forward as a candidate of the location of Kokufu, however each place lacked decisive proof.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Not a few places were always put forward as a candidate of the location of Kokufu, however each place lacked decisive proof.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>国府の具体像に関する知識は皆無に近かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Almost no one had knowledge concerning a concrete image of Kokufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Almost no one had knowledge concerning a concrete image of Kokufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Almost no one had knowledge concerning a concrete image of Kokufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="38">
<j>1964年に近江国府が発掘されてから、国府跡の遺跡が次々と発掘されるようになって、状況は劇的に変わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, after the excavation of the Kokufu of Omi Province in 1964, the ruins of Kokufu were excavated next to next, which provided the research with dramatic change.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after the excavation of the Kokufu of Omi Province in 1964, the ruins of Kokufu were excavated one after the other, which provided desperately needed change to the research effort.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after the excavation of the Kokufu of Omi Province in 1964, the ruins of Kokufu were excavated one after the other, which provided desperately needed change to the research effort.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>あわせて郡衙、寺院の遺跡も見つかり、これらと照らし合わせて国府に共通する特徴が浮かび上がってきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the additional discovery of the ruins of gunga (county government offices) and temples, these elements made the common feature of Kokufu clear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the additional discovery of the ruins of gunga (county government offices) and temples, these elements made the common feature of Kokufu clear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the additional discovery of the ruins of gunga (county government offices) and temples, these elements made the common feature of Kokufu clear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>奈良時代から平安時代前半の国府では、方形区画と正殿・脇殿などで構成される政庁が他の施設にはない特徴であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokufu established from the Nara period to the early Heian period has a unique feature in its Seicho which consists of a square lot, Seiden, Wakiden and others.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokufu established from the Nara period to the early Heian period has a unique feature in its Seicho which consists of a square lot, Seiden, Wakiden and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokufu established from the Nara period to the early Heian period has a unique feature in its Seicho which consists of a square lot, Seiden, Wakiden and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>これが国府の中心施設でもあることから、政庁を発見した時点で国府位置確定とみなされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Seicho was the central facility of the Kokufu, discovering the Seicho is as good as fixing the location of the Kokufu.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Seicho was the central facility of the Kokufu, discovering the Seicho is as good as determining the location of the Kokufu.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Seicho was the central facility of the Kokufu, discovering the Seicho is as good as determining the location of the Kokufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="42">
<j>発掘が始まった当初、国府は平城京や平安京のような中央の都城の縮小版と考えられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the excavation was started, Kokufu was thought to be a miniature of a capital in the central government such as Heijo-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in current Nara) and Heian-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in current Kyoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the excavation was started, Kokufu was thought to be a miniature of a capital in the central government such as Heijo-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in current Nara) and Heian-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in current Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the excavation was started, Kokufu was thought to be a miniature of a capital in the central government such as Heijo-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in current Nara) and Heian-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in current Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>方形の外郭線を持つ都市が国府で、その中心に国衙という役所群、さらにその要に国庁があるという三重構造が想定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was assumed that Kokufu adopted threefold structure including a squarely demarcated line in the outer fold, placing Kokucho at the center of the lot surrounded by the government offices called Kokuga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was assumed that Kokufu adopted a threefold structure including a squarely demarcated line in the outer fold, placing Kokucho at the center of the lot surrounded by the government offices called Kokuga.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was assumed that Kokufu adopted a threefold structure including a squarely demarcated line in the outer fold, placing Kokucho at the center of the lot surrounded by the government offices called Kokuga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>発掘が進むと、国府に明確な外郭線が存在しないこと、都市域は付けたし程度で官衙域を包み込むほどの広がりを持たないことが判明した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the advance of the excavation, it turned out that there was not a definite outer demarcated line in Kokufu, and that the stretch of urban area was rather small to be called appendix than wide enough to embrace the Kanga area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the advance of the excavation, it turned out that there was not a definite outer demarcated line in Kokufu, and that the stretch of urban area was rather small to be called appendix than wide enough to embrace the Kanga area.</e>
<cmt>Robert: Translation doesn’t make sense &quot; that the stretch of urban area was rather small to be called appendix &quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As work on the excavation progressed, it was discovered that there was not a definite outer demarcated line in Kokufu, and that the stretch of urban area was not large enough to encompass the Kanga area; rather, it was a small additional parcel of land.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を一部修正しましたが、NC check　をお願いいたします。NR: I cannot find an established translation for &quot;付けたし&quot; so I have tried to communicate what I imagine it means. Please check.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>しかし、計画的な道路の敷設は認められる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the well-planned roads were constructed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the well-planned roads were constructed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the well-planned roads were constructed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>下野国庁の南正面に南北道路が、伊勢では国庁北側の一部に方格地割りが、大宰府では10世紀に方格地割りが認められる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such roads include the road running north to south at the south main gate of Kokucho in Shimotsuke Province, as well as the neatly designed roads like the grid on a go (a Japanese game played with black and white stones on a board) board in a north part of Kokucho in Ise Province as well as Dazaifu (Government Headquarters in Kyushu) in the tenth century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such roads include the road running north to south at the south main gate of Kokucho in Shimotsuke Province, as well as the neatly designed roads like the grid on a go (a Japanese game played with black and white stones on a board) board in a north part of Kokucho in Ise Province as well as Dazaifu (Government Headquarters in Kyushu) in the tenth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such roads include the road running north to south at the south main gate of Kokucho in Shimotsuke Province, as well as the neatly designed roads like the grid on a go (a Japanese game played with black and white stones on a board) board in a north part of Kokucho in Ise Province as well as Dazaifu (Government Headquarters in Kyushu) in the tenth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="47">
<j>2007年現在までに国府位置が判明した国は多いが、なお不明の所もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As of 2007, the number of Kokufu whose location was identified is large, nevertheless some Kokufu have not yet been identified.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As of 2007, the number of Kokufu whose location was identified is substantial, nevertheless some Kokufu have not yet been identified.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As of 2007, the number of Kokufu whose location was identified is substantial, nevertheless some Kokufu have not yet been identified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>国府の発掘は面積的に一つの都市を掘り出すのに等しいため、位置が確定しても全貌を完全に解明したことにはならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Considering the scale of Kokufu, its excavation amounts to excavating a whole city, therefore only identifying its location is insufficient for understanding all the details.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Considering the scale of Kokufu, its excavation amounts to excavating a whole city, therefore only identifying its location is insufficient to grasp all the details.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Considering the scale of Kokufu, its excavation amounts to excavating a whole city, therefore only identifying its location is insufficient to grasp all the details.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>各地で発掘調査が続いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The excavation continues in various districts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The excavation continues in various districts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The excavation continues in various districts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="50">
<j>国府の一覧表（国府所在郡）を記載した史料</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Historical materials with a list of Kokufu (location of Kokufu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historical materials with a list of Kokufu (location of Kokufu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historical materials with a list of Kokufu (location of Kokufu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>和名類聚抄の20巻本。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A set of &quot;Wamyo-ruijusho&quot; in 20 volumes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A set of &quot;Wamyo-ruijusho&quot; in 20 volumes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A set of &quot;Wamyo-ruijusho&quot; in 20 volumes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="52">
<j>色葉字類抄。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Irohajiru sho&quot; (one of Japanese dictionaries in the Heian period)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Irohajiru sho&quot; (one of Japanese dictionaries in the Heian period)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Irohajiru sho&quot; (one of Japanese dictionaries in the Heian period)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>とその増補版の伊呂波字類抄10巻本。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A set of the enlarged edition of &quot;Irohajiru sho&quot; in 10 volumes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A set of the enlarged edition of &quot;Irohajiru sho&quot; in 10 volumes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A set of the enlarged edition of &quot;Irohajiru sho&quot; in 10 volumes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="54">
<j>拾芥抄。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shugaisho&quot; (an ancient encyclopedia)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shugaisho&quot; (an ancient encyclopedia)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shugaisho&quot; (an ancient encyclopedia)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="55">
<j>易林本の節用集。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese-language dictionary in &quot;Ekirin-bon&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese-language dictionary in &quot;Ekirin-bon&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese-language dictionary in &quot;Ekirin-bon&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="56">
<j>※サイト上の大学図書館のデジタルアーカイブシステムなどで、原文の詳細を読むことができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">*The original text is introduced in detail on the internet through the digital archive system of the university library.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">*The original text is introduced in detail on the internet through the digital archive system of the university library.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">*The original text is introduced in detail on the internet through the digital archive system of the university library.</e>
<cmt>* に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="57">
<j>※各史料によって、国府の異同、国府の記載なし、国府所在郡のみで郷名の記載なし、などから、国府の時代による移転説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">* There is a theory that the location of Kokufu has changed with the times, which is based on such a matter that a certain record advocates one Kokufu is the same with another Kokufu, a certain record has no description on Kokufu and a certain record introduces only the name of the province where Kokufu was established without further details.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処。日本語がわかりません。とくに「国府所在・・・論争になる，」が文の前後でつながりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">* There is a theory that the location of Kokufu has changed with the times, which is based on a certain record that advocates one Kokufu is the same as another Kokufu, however this record has no description on Kokufu and it introduces only the name of the province where Kokufu were established without further details.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">* There is a theory that the location of Kokufu varied according to the era in which they were built, and this theory is based on the following facts: some descriptions on Kokufu agree, but others differ depending on the type of document; some documents do not contain any descriptions on certain Kokufu; and some documents mention only the name of the province in which the Kokufu was established without providing any further details.</e>
<cmt>NC check お願いします。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>国府所在候補地が複数挙がり論争になる、史料が平安時代中期以降の編纂のため大化の改新～平安時代初期の初期国府と史料記載国府は違うと見る説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also a theory that the location of Kokufu established from the period around the Taika Reforms to the early Heian period differed from that established after the mid-Heian period, which is based on a matter that the historical record were compiled after the mid-Heian period.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also a theory that the location of Kokufu established from the period around the Taika Reforms to the early Heian period differed from that established after the mid-Heian period, which is based on a matter that the historical record were compiled after the mid-Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historical records which have been subject to dispute because they record several candidate locations for Kokufu were compiled after the mid-Heian period, and there is another theory that the location of Kokufu that were established from the period around the Taika Reforms to the early Heian period differs from that established after the mid-Heian period.</e>
<cmt>NC check お願いします。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>また国分寺や総社のあった場所に国府もあったと見る説などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, there is a theory that Kokufu was also located at the site where Kokubun-ji Temple and So-ja shrine were constructed.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, there is a theory that Kokufu was also located at the site where Kokubun-ji Temple and So-ja shrine were constructed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, there is a theory that Kokufu was also located at the site where Kokubun-ji Temple and So-ja shrine were constructed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>よって国府の選定には注意を要する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These theory cause a controversy because they can nominate various locations, therefore the location of Kokufu must be identified carefully.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These theories caused controversy because they nominate various locations, and therefore the location of Kokufu must be identified carefully.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These theories caused controversy because they nominate various locations, and therefore the location of Kokufu must be identified carefully.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>国府に因む地名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Place names originated in Kokufu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Place names originating in Kokufu</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Place names originating in Kokufu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="61">
<j>古代の国府は現代では国府と書いて「こう」と読む地名として全国に残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An ancient Kokufu remains nationwide as a place name &quot;国府&quot; in Chinese characters, which is pronounced &quot;Ko&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An ancient Kokufu remains nationwide as a place name &quot;国府&quot; in Chinese characters, which is pronounced &quot;Ko&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An ancient Kokufu remains nationwide as a place name &quot;国府&quot; in Chinese characters, which is pronounced &apos;Ko.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>府中は中世・近世に生まれた地名で、当時の国府・守護所に由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;府中&quot; (Fuchu) is a place name created in the Medieval and early Modern periods, derived from Kokufu and Shugo-sho (governor&apos;s office).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;府中&quot; (Fuchu) is a place name created in the Medieval and early Modern periods, derived from Kokufu and Shugo-sho (governor&apos;s office).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;府中&quot; (Fuchu) is a place name created in the Medieval and early Modern periods, derived from Kokufu and Shugo-sho (governor&apos;s office).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>国府と書いて「こくふ」と読む地名には、近代以降に国府推定地に新たに付けられたものが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many place names written as &quot;国府&quot; in Chinese characters, which is pronounced &quot;Kokufu&quot;, have been applied to the estimated site where Kokufu was located since the modern period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many place names written as &quot;国府&quot; in Chinese characters, which is pronounced &quot;Kokufu&quot;, have been applied to the estimated site where Kokufu was located since the modern period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many place names written as &quot;国府&quot; in Chinese characters, which is pronounced &apos;Kokufu,&apos; have been applied to the estimated site where Kokufu was located since the modern period.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>国分寺に由来すると思われる国分（こくぶ）を国府に変更した例もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of the &quot;国分&quot; (Kokubu), which is assumably derived from Kokubun-ji Temple, changed their name to &quot;国府&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of the &quot;国分&quot; (Kokubu), which is assumably derived from Kokubun-ji Temple, changed their name to &quot;国府&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of the &quot;国分&quot; (Kokubu), which is assumably derived from Kokubun-ji Temple, changed their name to &quot;国府&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 箱板(id:149463), Non-stop24(id:10471), Nnh(id:474), S.S.Exp.Hashimoto(id:4001), 経済準学士(id:22656), Inabanet(id:1175), Cprobot(id:97843), Torneco(id:23897), Toto-tarou(id:16648), Sen-K(id:17895), Wikiwikicompany(id:14588), Natunohi(id:6550), MioUzaki(id:89034), Kinori(id:443), Frei(id:12101), Paotch(id:3039), こぶまき(id:38278), Shimoxx(id:9332), Windorch.man(id:190686), ウィキ豊(id:82961), Tamakko(id:284921), Makiharashouten(id:1021), 水野白楓(id:22811), Tokumiki0(id:12043), Yanahan(id:2437), Godaigo(id:133481), 梁山泊智多星呉用(id:127114), Goncyan(id:92158), Rusk(id:9895), Carkuni(id:79281), Zlan(id:11942), Newport8865(id:71168), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Ykiki(id:163867), Hyolee2(id:16439), 参謀中佐(id:11557), Wabisabix(id:16770), Komura Jutaro(id:35057), Suisui(id:69), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>