<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>京都</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>京都（きょうと、みやこ、きょうのみやこ、英語Kyōto、ローマ字Kyōto）は、日本の歴史的な都。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto (the kanji used is 京都 which is pronounced as Miyako or Kyo-no-miyako in Japanese, is described as Kyōto in English, and is described as Kyōto in Roman characters) was a capital of Japan in history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historically, Kyoto (the kanji used is 京都 which is pronounced as Miyako or Kyo-no-miyako in Japanese, is described as Kyōto in English, and is described as Kyōto in Roman characters) was a capital of Japan.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto (also known as Miyako and Kyo-no-Miyako in Japanese) was the historical capital of Japan.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>京、京師、皇都ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto was also called Kyo, Keishi or Koto (imperial capital).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto was also called Kyo, Keishi or Koto (imperial capital).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto was also called Kyo, Keishi or Koto (imperial capital).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>794年に日本の首都に定められた都城・平安京にあたり、日本の政治・日本の文化の中心地となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto was equivalent to Heian-kyo, Tojo (a capital designed and constructed in accordance with the Chinese capital system), which was specified as a capital of Japan in 794, and became the central place of politics and culture in Japan.</e>
<cmt>都城→Tojo (a capital designed and constructed in accordance with the Chinese capital system)[http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/都城 内に、「都城は、条坊制に則って設計・建設された首都」との説明があり、「条坊制」の英訳は、http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/藤原京 の英語版内の表記を採用しました。尚、後述の「都城」は、Tojo とのみ表記しました。]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto was equivalent to Heian-kyo, Tojo (a capital designed and constructed in accordance with the Chinese capital system), which was specified as a capital of Japan in 794, and became central to politics and culture in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto was formerly named Heian-kyo, which was designated Japan&apos;s capital in 794 and served as the political and cultural center of the country.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>名称</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>「京都」の由来</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin of &apos;Kyoto&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin of &apos;Kyoto&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin of &apos;Kyoto&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>東アジアでは古来、歴史的に「天子の住む都」「首都」を意味する普通名詞として京（きょう）、京師（けいし）が多く使用されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the history of East Asia, the term &quot;Kyo&quot; (京) or &quot;Keishi&quot; (京師) was often used as a common noun which meant a &apos;city where an emperor lives&apos; or &apos;capital&apos; since ancient times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In East Asia, the term &quot;Kyo&quot; (京) or &quot;Keishi&quot; (京師) was often used as a common noun which meant a &apos;city where an emperor lives&apos; or &apos;capital&apos; since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In East Asia, the words &apos;Kyo&apos; and &apos;Keishi&apos; have historically been used as common nouns meaning &apos;city in which the emperor resides&apos; and &apos;capital&apos; since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しました。語句についての説明なのでクォーテーションを補足しています。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>西晋時代に世宗（司馬師）の諱である「師」の文字を避けて京都（けいと）と言うようになり、以後は京、京師、京都などの呼び名が用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order not to use the kanji &apos;師&apos; which was used for the personal name of Shizong (Shima Shi; written as 司馬師 in kanji), the capital city came to be called &quot;Keito&quot; (京都) in the Western Jin Dynasty, and thereafter, the name of Kyo, Keishi or Kyoto came to be used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order not to use the kanji &apos;師&apos; which was used for the personal name of Shizong (Shima Shi; written as 司馬師 in kanji), the capital city came to be called &quot;Keito&quot; (京都) in the Western Jin Dynasty, and thereafter, the name of Kyo, Keishi or Kyoto came to be used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to avoid using the character &apos;shi&apos; which was the posthumous name of Shizong (Sima Shi), the city was later called &apos;Keito,&apos; and other common names including &apos;Kyo,&apos; &apos;Keishi&apos; and &apos;Kyoto&apos; subsequently came to be used.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しました。語句についての説明なのでクォーテーションを補足しています。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>日本でも飛鳥京や恭仁京などが京都とも呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ancient capitals such as Asuka-kyo and Kuni-kyo were also called Kyoto in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ancient capitals such as Asuka-kyo and Kuni-kyo were also called Kyoto in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ancient capitals of Asuka-kyo and Kuni-kyo were also called Kyoto in Japan.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。クォーテーションをのぞき用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>平安京は当初から京都とも呼ばれたが、定着したのは平安後期からで、京や京師という呼び名も併用されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Heian-kyo was also called Kyoto from the beginning, the name &quot;Kyoto&quot; became established in the later Heian period, and Kyo or Keishi was also used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Heian-kyo was also called Kyoto from the beginning, the use of &quot;Kyoto&quot; became established during the later Heian period, where Kyo or Keishi was also used.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heian-kyo was also originally called Kyoto but the name became established during the latter part of the Heian period when both the names Kyo and Keishi were used.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その後、次第に「京の都」（きょうのみやこ）、「京」（きょう）、「京都」（きょうと）が都市の固有名詞のようになり、定着していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequently, &apos;Kyo-no-miyako,&apos; &apos;Kyo&apos; or &apos;Kyoto&apos; came to be used as a proper noun meaning a city gradually, and became established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, &apos;Kyo-no-miyako,&apos; &apos;Kyo&apos; or &apos;Kyoto&apos; came to gradually be used as a proper noun meaning a city and became established.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyo-no-Miyako,&apos; &apos;Kyo&apos; and &apos;Kyoto&apos; later gradually became the proper nouns used to refer to the capital and their usage was established.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直し、クォーテーションの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>京都と洛陽</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto and Rakuyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto and Rakuyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto and Rakuyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>古く京都は、しばしば中国王朝の都となった洛陽に因み、京洛、洛中、洛陽などといわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In old times, Kyoto was often called Kyoraku (capital Kyoto), Rakuchu or Rakuyo after Rakuyo (Luoyang in Chinese) which became a capital of Chinese Dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In old times, Kyoto was often called Kyoraku (capital Kyoto), Rakuchu or Rakuyo after Rakuyo (Luoyang in Chinese) which became a capital of the Chinese Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In ancient times, Kyoto was frequently called names which included Kyoraku, Rakuchu and Rakuyo after Luoyang (Rakuyo in Japanese) which became the capital of imperial China.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>元々は平安京を東西に分割し、西側（右京）を「長安」、東側（左京）を「洛陽」と呼んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, upon severing Heian-kyo east from west, the west side (Ukyo) was called &apos;Changan,&apos; and the east side (Sakyo) was called &apos;Rakuyo.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, upon severing Heian-kyo east from west, the west side (Ukyo) was called &apos;Changan,&apos; and the east side (Sakyo) was called &apos;Rakuyo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heian-kyo was originally divided into eastern and western sections, with the western side (Ukyo) called &apos;Choan&apos; and the eastern side (Sakyo) called &apos;Rakuyo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しクォーテーションの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>ところが、右京すなわち「長安」側は湿地帯が多かったことなどから程なく廃れ、市街地は実質的に左京すなわち「洛陽」だけとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Ukyo, &apos;Changan&apos; side, went out of use soon because of many marshlands, and the urban area substantially existed in Sakyo, &apos;Rakuyo.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Ukyo, otherwise known as the &apos;Changan&apos; side, soon went out of use due to the many marshlands, with Sakyo, &apos;Rakuyo&apos; as the only resulting urban area.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Ukyo, otherwise known as the &apos;Choan&apos; side, soon fell out of use due to its many wetland areas, leaving Sakyo, or &apos;Rakuyo&apos; as it was also known, as the only urban area.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>このため京都を「洛陽」と呼ぶようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of this, Kyoto came to be called &apos;Rakuyo.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of this, Kyoto came to be called &apos;Rakuyo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Kyoto came to be called &apos;Rakuyo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しクォーテーションの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>京の都に上ることを上京、上洛と言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;Jokyo&quot; (coming up to the capital, Kyoto) or &quot;Joraku&quot; (going to the capital, Kyoto) was used as the term which means coming up to Kyo-no-miyako.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;Jokyo&quot; (coming up to the capital, Kyoto) or &quot;Joraku&quot; (going to the capital, Kyoto) to the act of going to Kyo-no-miyako.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The act of going to Kyo-no-Miyako was called Jokyo or Joraku.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>現在でも京都以外の地方（含東京）から京都へ行くことを「上洛する」「入洛する」ということが少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not a few people still use the term &apos;Joraku&apos; for the term which means visiting Kyoto from other regions (including Tokyo) than Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>「上洛する」「上洛する」→&apos;Joraku&apos;[誤記と解釈しました。]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some still use the term &apos;Joraku&apos; to refer to the act of visiting Kyoto from other regions (including Tokyo) than Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some still use the term &apos;Joraku suru&apos; and &apos;Nyuraku suru&apos; to refer to the act of visiting Kyoto from areas (including Tokyo) outside of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しシングルクォーテーションにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>平安遷都</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Transfer of national capital to the city of Heian-kyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Transfer of national capital to the city of Heian-kyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Relocation of the Capital to Heian-Kyo City</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>京都は、桓武天皇が784年（延暦3年）の長岡京に続いて、794年（延暦13年）平安京に遷都したことに始まる千年の都である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto has a history as long as one thousand years which began from the transfer of national capital to the city of Heian-kyo in 794 by Emperor Kanmu following the transfer of national capital to Nagaoka-kyo in 784.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto has a history as long as one thousand years beginning from the transfer of the national capital to the city of Heian-kyo in 794 by Emperor Kanmu following the transfer of the national capital to Nagaoka-kyo in 784.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto has a history going back over 1000 years to the year 794 when the capital was relocated to the city of Heian-kyo by Emperor Kanmu following the establishment of the capital in Nagaoka-kyo City in 784.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>京都に都が移された理由は諸説ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many opinions about reasons why the national capital was transferred to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many opinions as to the reasons surrounding why the move of the national capital to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various theories regarding the reasons for the relocation of the capital city to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>例えば、長岡京の建設責任者であった藤原種継が暗殺されたことや、奈良寺院の影響から脱するためであったや、天武天皇系の都を脱して天智天皇系の都を造るという意図説などである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, because FUJIWARA no Tanetsugu, responsible official for construction of Nagaoka-kyo, was assassinated, because it was necessary to escape from the influence of temples in Nara, because there was an intention to escape from the capital city under the influence of Emperor Tenmu and to build a capital city under the influence of Emperor Tenchi, and other reasons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of the many theories include the assassination of FUJIWARA no Tanetsugu, the official responsible for the construction of Nagaoka-kyo, the desire to escape the influence of the temples in Nara, the intention to escape the capital which was under the influence of Emperor Tenmu, or plans to build a capital under the influence of Emperor Tenchi, as well as other reasons.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These theories include the assassination of FUJIWARA no Tanetsugu who was responsible for the construction of Nagaoka-kyo, the intention to escape the influence of temples of Nara, and the desire to escape the capital of Emperor Tenmu and create a capital for Emperor Tenji.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>平安京は中国の風水に忠実に設計された都市で四方を山に囲まれ、東に鴨川 (淀川水系)が西に桂川 (淀川水系)が蛇行しながら南へと流れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heian-kyo was a city faithfully designed in accordance with feng sui in China, which was surrounded on all four sides by mountains, and through which the Kamo-gawa River (Yodo-gawa River system) in the east and the Katsura-gawa River (Yodo-gawa River system) in the west meandered to the south.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heian-kyo was a city faithfully designed in accordance with Chinese feng sui, and surrounded on all four sides by mountains, through which the Kamo-gawa River (Yodo-gawa River system) in the east and the Katsura-gawa River (Yodo-gawa River system) in the west meandered to the south.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heian-kyo was designed according to the principles of Chinese feng shui; surrounded by mountains on all sides with the Kamo-gawa River (the Yodo-gawa River system) in the east and the Katsura-gawa River (the Yodo-gawa River system) in the west which both meander southward.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>内部は都城を模倣した長方形の区画をもっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The inside had rectangular compartments on the model of Tojo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The inside had rectangular compartments on the model of Tojo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The inner city was divided into rectangular sections as found in castle towns.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>現在の千本通が当時の朱雀大路にあたり、真北には舩岡山が位置していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The present-day Senbon-dori Street is equivalent to the then Suzaku-dori Street, and Mt. Matsuoka lay immediately north.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The present-day Senbon-dori Street is equivalent to the then Suzaku-dori Street, and Mt. Matsuoka lay immediately north.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Present-day Senbon-dori Street corresponds to the original Suzaku-dori Street, immediately north of which stood Mt. Funaoka.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>平安時代の律令制の形骸化にともなって次第に本来の領域にとらわれない、鴨川と大内裏・京都御所を中心とする都市になり、経済的に発展していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Along with the hollowing out of the Ritsuryo System (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) during the Heian period, Kyoto was gradually transformed into a city which centered on the Kamo-gawa River, Daidairi (the Greater Imperial Palace) and Kyoto Imperial Palace without sticking to the original area, and made economic progress.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Along with the hollowing out of the Ritsuryo System (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) during the Heian period, Kyoto was gradually transformed into a city which centered on the Kamo-gawa River, Daidairi (the Greater Imperial Palace) and Kyoto Imperial Palace without sticking to the original area, and made economic progress.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Ritsuryo System (a system of centralized government based on the Ritsuryo Code) declined during the Heian period, the city gradually expanded beyond its original area to become centered around the Kamo-gawa River and the Kyoto Imperial Palace of the Daidairi (Greater Imperial Palace), and developed economically.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>鎌倉幕府の設置</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Establishment of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Establishment of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Establishment of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>鎌倉時代にも京都の朝廷は政治機能を発揮していたが、東国支配を強めていた鎌倉殿に1185年守護・地頭の設置を認め、鎌倉幕府が全国支配を強めたため、京都は相対的に経済都市としての性格を強めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Kamakura period, the imperial court in Kyoto also fulfilled its political function; however, since it allowed Kamakura-dono (lord of Kamakura) who strengthened the control over Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region) to appoint Shugo, Military Governor and Jito, Military Land Steward in 1185, and the Kamakura bakufu strengthened its control over the whole country, Kyoto relatively came to function as an economic city more than before.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Kamakura period, the imperial court in Kyoto also fulfilled its political function; however, since it allowed Kamakura-dono (lord of Kamakura) who strengthened control over Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region) to appoint Shugo, Military Governor and Jito, Military Land Steward in 1185. The Kamakura bakufu strengthened its control over the whole country and, Kyoto came to function as an economic city more than before.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The imperial court of Kyoto fulfilled a political function during the Kamakura period but Kyoto came to function more as a financial city as the imperial court allowed the Kamakura-dono (lord of Kamakura) who was gaining control over the eastern part of Japan to appoint shugo (provincial constables) and jito (managers and lords of a manor) in 1185.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>承久の乱を契機に鎌倉幕府は京に六波羅探題を設置して、公家勢力の監視を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the wake of the Jokyu War, the Kamakura bakufu established Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto) in Kyo, and supervised the power of court aristocracy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the wake of the Jokyu War, the Kamakura bakufu established Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto) in Kyo, and supervised the court aristocracy.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the wake of the Jokyu War, the Kamakura bakufu established Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto) in Kyo, and monitored the power held by court nobles.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>鎌倉時代末期に足利尊氏が京都の六波羅探題を滅ぼし、幕府滅亡後には京で後醍醐天皇による建武の新政が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the late Kamakura period, Takauji ASHIKAGA destroyed Rokuhara Tandai in Kyoto, and after the destruction of bakufu, the Kenmu Restoration was implemented by Emperor Godaigo in Kyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the late Kamakura period, Takauji ASHIKAGA destroyed Rokuhara Tandai in Kyoto, and after the destruction of the bakufu, the Kenmu Restoration was implemented by Emperor Godaigo in Kyo.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the late Kamakura period, Takauji ASHIKAGA destroyed the Rokuhara Tandai of Kyoto, and after the collapse of the bakufu, the Kenmu Restoration was initiated by Emperor Godaigo in Kyo.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>その後新政から離反した尊氏が北朝 (日本)を立て、南北朝時代 (日本)となると、京都争奪戦が何度も行われる（南北朝分裂以後、南朝 (日本)による京都占領は4度行われたが、いずれも短期間で足利軍に撃退されている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, Takauji who defected from the new government established the Northern Court (Japan), and in the period of the Northern and Southern Dynasties (Japan), battles to capture Kyoto broke out many times (after the separation between the Northern and Southern Court, the Southern Court (Japan) occupied Kyoto four times, but it was always beaten back by the Ashikaga side in a short time).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, Takauji who defected from the new government established the Northern Court (Japan), and in the period of the Northern and Southern Dynasties (Japan), battles to capture Kyoto broke out many times (after the separation between the Northern and Southern Court, the Southern Court (Japan) occupied Kyoto four times, but it was always beaten back by the Ashikaga side in a short time).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji, who distanced himself from the restoration, subsequently established the Northern Court (Japan), and numerous battles for control of Kyoto broke out during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan) (following the division into the Northern Court and Southern Court, the Southern Court (Japan) occupied Kyoto on four occasions but was repelled by the Ashikaga army within a short space of time).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>室町幕府の設置</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Establishment of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Establishment of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Establishment of the Muromachi bakufu</e>
<cmt>幕府の英語の説明を削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>南朝が衰微して、室町時代になると京には室町幕府が置かれたために政治都市として復活する一方で経済発展を遂げ、町衆と呼ばれる有力市民による自治の伝統が生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Southern Court declined, the Muromachi bakufu was established in Kyo in the Muromachi period; therefore, while reviving as a political city, Kyoto achieved economic development and a tradition of self-governance by influential citizens called machishu (merchant class) arose.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the decline of the Southern Court, the Muromachi bakufu was established in Kyo in the Muromachi period; therefore, while being revived as a political city, Kyoto achieved economic development and a tradition of self-governance by influential citizens called machishu (merchant class) arose.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the establishment of the Muromachi bakufu in Kyo during the Muromachi period following the decline of the Southern Court led to the revival of Kyoto as a political city, it also achieved economic development and a tradition of self-governance by influential citizens called machishu (merchant class) arose.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>足利義満は北小路室町（上京区）に花の御所と呼ばれる邸宅を建造し、応仁の乱で焼失するまで将軍家の在所となり、足利将軍は在所から「室町殿」と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA built a residence called Hana no Gosho (literally, Flower Palace) in Kitakoji Muromachi (Kamigyo Ward), which was used as a residence of the Shogun family until it was burned down due to the Onin War, and Ashikaga Shogun was called &apos;Muromachi-dono&apos; after the residence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA built a residence called Hana no Gosho (literally, Flower Palace) in Kitakoji Muromachi (Kamigyo Ward), which was used as a residence by the Shogun family until it was burned down due to the Onin War. Ashikaga Shogun was called &apos;Muromachi-dono&apos; after the residence.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA built a residence called Hana no Gosho (literally, Flower Palace) in Kitakoji Muromachi (Kamigyo Ward), which was used as a residence by the Shogun family until it was burned down during to the Onin War, and Ashikaga Shogun were also called as &apos;Muromachi-dono&apos; after the residence.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直し表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>戦国時代・安土桃山時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sengoku period (period of warring states) and Azuchi-Momoyama period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sengoku period (period of warring states) and Azuchi-Momoyama period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sengoku Period (period of warring states) and Azuchi-Momoyama Period</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。用集より補足しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)の端緒となる応仁の乱で市街、特に北側の大半が焼失し、その後もたびたび戦乱に巻き込まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the Onin War conductive to the Sengoku period, the urban area, particularly most part of north side, was burned down, and was often engulfed in conflicts thereafter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the Onin War conductive to the Sengoku period, the urban area, particularly most of the north side, was burned down, and often engulfed in conflicts thereafter.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Onin War which was the start of the Sengoku period, the city, in particular the majority of the northern side, was destroyed by fire and would later frequently become embroiled in conflict.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>この頃、京都は上京と下京に分かれ、それぞれ「構」によって囲まれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around this time, Kyoto was divided into two parts, Kamigyo (north part of capital) and Shimogyo (south part of capital), and each part was surrounded by &apos;Kamae&apos; (moat).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around this time, Kyoto was divided into two parts, Kamigyo (north part of capital) and Shimogyo (south part of capital), and each part was surrounded by &apos;Kamae&apos; (moat).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this period, Kyoto was divided into Kamigyo (the northern part of capital) and Shimogyo (the southern part of capital), and each part was surrounded by &apos;fortifications.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。クォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>その間は畑になっていたといわれ、室町通でかろうじてつながっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that a field lay between Kamigyo and Shimogo, and only the Muromachi-dori Street connected between Kamigyo and Shimogo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that a field lay between Kamigyo and Shimogo, and only the Muromachi-dori Street connected Kamigyo and Shimogo.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that fields were located between Kamigyo and Shimogyo, and the two parts were connected only by Muromachi-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>この後、織田信長、豊臣秀吉の保護と町衆の力により復興した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this, Kyoto revived through the protection by Nobunaga ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and the power of machishu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this, Kyoto revived through the protection by Nobunaga ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and the power of machishu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto was subsequently revived under the protection of Nobunaga ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and by the efforts of the machishu.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>特に、秀吉の都市改造は大規模なもので、聚楽第と武家町の建設、内裏の修理と公家町の建設、洛中に散在していた寺をあつめた寺町の建設などを行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular, through his large-scale city reconstruction projects, Hideyoshi constructed Jurakudai and Bukemachi (samurai residence district), repaired Dairi (Imperial Palace), constructed Kugemachi (court noble village), and constructed Teramachi (temple district) to concentrate temples which were scattered in Rakuchu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Through his large-scale city reconstruction projects, Hideyoshi constructed Jurakudai and Bukemachi (samurai residence district), repaired Dairi (Imperial Palace), constructed Kugemachi (court noble village) and Teramachi (temple district) to concentrate temples which were scattered in Rakuchu.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi&apos;s urban reconstruction was of a particularly large scale and led to the construction of Jurakudai (Hideyoshi&apos;s residence and office in Kyoto) and Bukemachi (a samurai residential district), the repair of the Dairi (Imperial Palace), and the construction of Kugemachi (a court noble village) and Teramachi (temple district) in order to assemble the temples which were once scattered throughout central Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しスペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>現在でもしばしばその都市構造を確認することができる（→天正の地割）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such city structure still remains in many places (=&gt;Tensho no Jiwari (lot allotment system in the Tensho period).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These structures still remain in many places (=&gt;Tensho no Jiwari (lot allotment system in the Tensho period).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These structures can still often be seen to this day (refer to Tensho no Jiwari (land allotment system in the Tensho era)).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>江戸幕府の設置</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Establishment of the Edo bakufu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Establishment of the Edo bakufu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Establishment of the Edo bakufu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>1603年3月24日（慶長8年2月12日）に徳川家康が征夷大将軍に任官され、江戸幕府の誕生とともに政治の中枢が江戸に移った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 24, 1603, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA was appointed as seii taishogun (literally, &quot;greater general who subdues the barbarians&quot;), and along with the establishment of the Edo bakufu, the center of government moved to Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 24, 1603, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA was appointed as seii taishogun (literally, &quot;greater general who subdues the barbarians&quot;), and along with the establishment of the Edo bakufu, the center of government was moved to Edo.</e>
<cmt>Tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 24, 1603, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA was appointed seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;), and the center of politics was relocated to Edo along with the establishment of the Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直し補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>しかしながら京都は都であることに変わりはなく、幕府の京都の拠点として二条城が築かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Kyoto was still a capital city, and as the base point of bakufu in Kyoto, the Nijo-jo Castle was built.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Kyoto was still the capital, and the Nijo-jo Castle was built as a base for the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Kyoto remained the capital, and Nijo-jo Castle was built as a base for the bakufu in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>また、文化工芸の中心地として人口が50万人を越え、政治の中心地の江戸や、経済の中心地の大坂に次ぐ都市として繁栄した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a central place of culture and industrial arts, Kyoto had a population exceeding 500,000, and was flourished as a city next to Edo which was a central place of politics, and Osaka which was a central place of economy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a center of culture and industrial arts, Kyoto had a population exceeding 500,000, and flourished as a city next to Edo which was a central place of politics, and Osaka which was central to economics.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a center of culture and the industrial arts, Kyoto had a population exceeding 500,000 and flourished as a city that ranked behind only the political center of Edo and the financial center of Osaka.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>又、江戸幕府は京都所司代・京都町奉行を設置して直轄下に置いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Edo bakufu established the Kyoto shoshidai (the Kyoto deputy), and Kyoto machi-bugyou (town magistrate of Kyoto), and placed Kyoto under its direct control.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Edo bakufu established the Kyoto shoshidai (the Kyoto deputy), and Kyoto machi-bugyou (town magistrate of Kyoto), placing Kyoto under its direct control.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Edo bakufu also placed Kyoto under its direct control by creating the posts of Kyoto shoshidai (Kyoto deputy), and Kyoto machi-bugyo (town magistrate of Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>東京の設置と東幸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Establishment of Tokyo and the Emperor going to the east</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Establishment of Tokyo and the Emperor&apos;s move to the East</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Establishment of Tokyo and the Emperor&apos;s move to the East</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="38">
<j>1867年11月9日（慶応3年）の大政奉還により、統治権が幕府から京都の朝廷に返上されて新政府が誕生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By Taisei Hokan (tansfer of power back to the Emperor) on November 9, 1867, the sovereignity was returned from the bakufu to the imperial court in Kyoto, and a new government was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By Taisei Hokan (transfer of power back to the Emperor) on November 9, 1867, sovereignity was returned from the bakufu to the imperial court in Kyoto, and a new government was established.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The restoration of imperial rule on November 9, 1867 saw the bakufu relinquish sovereignty to the Imperial Court in Kyoto, and a new government was formed.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>京都には京都府が置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Prefecture was established in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Prefecture was established in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Prefecture was established.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>しかし天皇が江戸で直接政治をみるため、江戸を東京として行幸・滞在（東京行幸）することになり、太政官（政府）も移動された（東京奠都参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since the Emperor directly supervised the politics in Edo, upon renaming the place name from Edo to Tokyo, the Emperor went to and stayed in Tokyo (Tokyo Gyoko; the Emperor&apos;s going to Tokyo), and Daijokan (Grand Council of State meaning the government) was also moved (refer to Tokyo Tento (transfer of the national capital to Tokyo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since the Emperor directly supervised the politics in Edo, upon renaming the place name from Edo to Tokyo, the Emperor went to and stayed in Tokyo (Tokyo Gyoko; the Emperor&apos;s going to Tokyo), and Daijokan (Grand Council of State meaning the government) was also moved (refer to Tokyo Tento (transfer of the national capital to Tokyo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, so that the Imperial Court could directly supervise the politics of Edo, the city was renamed Tokyo and became visited by and resided in by the emperor (Tokyo Gyoko; the emperor&apos;s visit to Tokyo), while the Daijokan (Grand Council of State) was also relocated (refer to Tokyo Tento (transfer of the national capital to Tokyo)).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>その後京都への還幸は延期され、明治天皇は1877年（明治10年）に京都御所の保存を命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, the Kyoto Kanko (the Emperor coming back to Kyoto) was postponed, and the Emperor Meiji ordered to preserve the Kyoto Imperial Palace in 1877.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, the Kyoto Kanko (the Emperor coming back to Kyoto) was postponed, and the Emperor Meiji ordered the preservation of the Kyoto Imperial Palace in 1877.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The period of time before the emperor returned to Kyoto grew longer, and in 1877 Emperor Meiji ordered the preservation of the Kyoto Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="42">
<j>1879年（明治12年）には郡区町村編制法により、京都に上京区と下京区の2区が置かれ、続いて1889年（明治22年）に上京区・下京区は府管轄下の「京都市」となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1879, two wards of Kamigyo and Shimogyo were established in Kyoto under the Gun-ku-cho-son Heniseiho (Act for the alignment of local government system), and in 1889, Kamigyo Ward and Shimogyo Ward constituted &apos;Kyoto City&apos; under the control of the prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1879, the two wards of Kamigyo and Shimogyo were established in Kyoto under the Gun-ku-cho-son Heniseiho (Act for the alignment of local government system), and in 1889, Kamigyo Ward and Shimogyo Ward constituted &apos;Kyoto City&apos; under the control of the prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1879, the two wards of Kamigyo and Shimogyo were established in Kyoto under the Gun-ku-cho-son Henseiho (an act for the organization of the administrative divisions), and in 1889, Kamigyo Ward and Shimogyo Ward became &apos;Kyoto City&apos; under the jurisdiction of the prefecture.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直し表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>現在の京都市は、伏見市をはじめとする周辺の市町村を編入したため、江戸時代以前からの伝統的な「京都」の範囲は、現在の京都市内の一部に過ぎない（京北町に至ってはかつては丹波国桑田郡の一部であった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the present-day Kyoto City was formed by merging surrounding cities, towns and villages including Fushimi City, the area of traditional &apos;Kyoto&apos; before the Edo period is only a part within the present-day Kyoto City (Keihoku-cho used to be part of Kuwata County, the Province of Tanba).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the present-day Kyoto City was formed by merging surrounding cities, towns and villages including Fushimi City, the area of traditional &apos;Kyoto&apos; before the Edo period is only a part within present-day Kyoto City (Keihoku-cho used to be part of Kuwata County, the Province of Tanba).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the fact that modern-day Kyoto City was formed by merging surrounding cities, towns and villages which included Fushimi City, the area of the traditional pre-Edo period &apos;Kyoto&apos; accounts for only part of modern-day Kyoto City (the area extending to Keihoku Town was formerly part of Kuwata District in Tanba Province).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けや表記などを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>また、戦前までは東京市様に京都市の大半は農地であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the war, agricultural lands extended in the most part of Kyoto City as in Tokyo City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the war, agricultural lands extended in most parts of Kyoto City as in Tokyo City.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As was the case for Tokyo, Kyoto also consisted mostly of agricultural land until the pre-war era.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="45">
<j>現在は世界有数の観光都市。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, Kyoto is one of the best sightseeing cities in the world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present, Kyoto is one of the best cities for sightseeing in the world.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto is currently one of the best sightseeing cities in the world.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>神社仏閣の本山を多数擁する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many head temples and shrines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many head temples and shrines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The city contains the headquarters of many Shinto shrines and Buddhist temples.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>なお、現在、名所・旧跡に立てられている案内碑は、そのほとんどが明治維新後に推定で置かれたものであり、必ずしも、実際の所在地と一致はしていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since most of existing information monuments established at famous places and historic sites were established after the Meiji Restoration based on the presumptions, those are not always established at the actual places.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since most of the existing information monuments established at famous places and historic sites were established after the Meiji Restoration based on these presumptions, they are not always established at their actual locations.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the majority of the current information plaques for famous places and historic sites were installed based on assumptions after the Meiji Restoration, they do not necessarily correspond to the actual locations.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>首都としての京都</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto as a capital</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto as a capital</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto as a Capital City</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="48">
<j>旧皇室典範では「即位ノ礼及大嘗祭ハ京都ニ於テ之ヲ行フ」とあり、また天皇の所在を示す高御座が京都御所に安置されていることから、天皇の東京行幸以降も京都は依然として都で、特別な機能を有する都市である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Former Imperial House Act specified that &apos;the Sokui no rei (ceremony of the enthronement) and Daijo-sai Festival (a festival to celebrate the succession of an emperor) should be held in Kyoto,&apos; and Takamikura (the imperial throne) indicating an Emperor&apos;s location is still placed in Kyoto; therefore, Kyoto is still a capital even after Tokyo Gyoko, and is a city having a special function.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Former Imperial House Act specified that &apos;the Sokui no rei (ceremony of the enthronement) and Daijo-sai Festival (a festival to celebrate the succession of an emperor) should be held in Kyoto,&apos; and Takamikura (the imperial throne) indicating the Emperor&apos;s location is still located in Kyoto; therefore, Kyoto is still a capital even after Tokyo Gyoko, and provides a special function.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The city of Kyoto maintains a special function as a result of the Former Imperial House Act which stipulated that &apos;the Sokui no rei (enthronement ceremony) and Daijosai (first ceremonial offering of rice by newly-enthroned Emperor) be held in Kyoto&apos; and the fact that the Takamikura (imperial throne) is housed at the Kyoto Imperial Palace, which mean that Kyoto remains a capital even after the emperor has departed for Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>しかし明治時代以降は肝心の首都機能を消失していることも確かで、首都に関する議論を複雑にしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is true that Kyoto lost the important function as a capital after the Meiji era, which complicates an argument about a capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is true that Kyoto lost it&apos;s importance as a capital after the Meiji era, complicating the argument about it being a capital.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is also true that Kyoto lost its function as a capital after the Meiji period, and the arguments regarding its status as a capital are complicated.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="50">
<j>「京都は今でも首都である」とする意見がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some opinions that &apos;Kyoto is a capital even now.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some hold that &apos;Kyoto is a capital even now.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some maintain the opinion that &apos;Kyoto is still the capital.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。クォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>例えば次のようなものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, the opinions are:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such opinions include:</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Examples of such opinions are given below.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="52">
<j>京都とは普通名詞としては首都を意味し、東京は京都に対して東の京（東の首都）を意味しており、2つの都である京都と東京が首都である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Kyoto as a common noun means a capital, and Tokyo means Kyo in the east (capital in the east) of Kyoto, two capitals, Kyoto and Tokyo, are to be the capital;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Kyoto as a common noun means a capital, and Tokyo means Kyo in the east (capital in the east) of Kyoto, two capitals, Kyoto and Tokyo, are to be the capital;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both Kyoto and Tokyo are capitals because Kyoto as a common noun means capital while Tokyo means eastern capital.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="53">
<j>天皇の在所を示す高御座は現在も京都御所に安置されており、京都市が現在でも首都のままである（日本の首都を示すのは行政府の所在ではなく、高御座の置かれている処である）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Takamikura indicating the Emperor&apos;s location is still placed in the Kyoto Imperial Palace, Kyoto City still remains as a capital (a capital of Japan is defined as a place where Takamikura is placed, not a place where the administration and government are located).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Takamikura, which indicates the Emperor&apos;s location, is still placed in the Kyoto Imperial Palace, Kyoto City still remains the capital (where the capital of Japan is defined as the location of Takamikura and not where the administration and government are located).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto City remains the capital because the Takamikura, which indicates the Emperor&apos;s residence, is still housed in the Kyoto Imperial Palace (the capital city of Japan is determined not by the location of the government but by the place in which the Takamikura is housed).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="54">
<j>東京遷都の詔勅が発布されていない故、天皇制が存続する現在もなお京都が、公式に日本の首都である事実に変わりは無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because Shochoku (imperial edict) to the effect of transferring of the national capital to Tokyo has not been promulgated, there is no change in the fact that Kyoto is officially a capital of Japan even now while the Emperor System continues.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to Shochoku (imperial edict) the effect of transferring the national capital to Tokyo has not been promulgated, and this does not change the fact that Kyoto is officially a capital of Japan even now while the Emperor System continues.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because there has never been a shochoku (imperial edict) for the transfer of the national capital to Tokyo, there has been no change to the fact that Kyoto is officially the capital of Japan even now while the imperial system continues.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="55">
<j>問題点としては、京都は「都」（都・京）であるが、首都（capital）という語が使われるのは主に戦後以降のことであり、「首都」に法令上の定義・規定ないことがあげられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The problem is that, Kyoto means a &apos;capital&apos; (Miyako or Kyo), but, the term &quot;capital&quot; came to be used mainly after the war, and the term &apos;capital&apos; is not defined or specified in the laws and ordinances.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The problem is that, Kyoto means a &apos;capital&apos; (Miyako or Kyo), but, the term &quot;capital&quot; came to be used mainly after the war, and the term &apos;capital&apos; is not defined or specified in laws and ordinances.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One problem with this argument is that, although Kyoto means capital, the term capital mainly came to be used after the Second World War, and is not defined or specified by any laws or ordinances.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>→日本の首都参照</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">=&gt;Refer to Capital of Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">=&gt;Refer to Capital of Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Please refer to The Capital of Japan.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>洛中・洛外・京中</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rakuchu, Rakugai and Kyochu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rakuchu, Rakugai and Kyochu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rakuchu, Rakugai and Kyochu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="57">
<j>平安京の頃から、後の京都の基礎となった左京地域を唐の都・洛陽に擬えて「洛陽」と呼び、市内を洛中（らくちゅう）、外側を辺土、後に洛外（らくがい）と呼んだが（京都と洛陽を参照）、具体的な定義は曖昧であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From around the time when Heian-kyo was established, the Sakyo area which became the basis for later Kyoto was called &apos;Rakuyo&apos; after Rakuyo (Luoyang in Chinese), Chinese capital, and the area within the city was called Rakuchu, and then the outside area was called Hendo (remote region), and then called Rakugai later (refer to Kyoto and Rakuyo); however, there were no concrete definitions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From around the time when Heian-kyo was established, the Sakyo area, which became the basis for later Kyoto, was called &apos;Rakuyo&apos; after Rakuyo (Luoyang in Chinese) the Chinese capital, and the area within the city was called Rakuchu, while the outside area was called Hendo (remote region), and then later called Rakugai (refer to Kyoto and Rakuyo); however, there were no concrete definitions.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From around the time of Heian-kyo, the Sakyo area, which became the basis for the subsequent city of Kyoto, was called &apos;Rakuyo&apos; after the Tang Dynasty Chinese capital Luoyang (Rakuyo in Japanese), and the area within the city was called Rakuchu, while the outside area was called Hendo (remote region) and later called Rakugai (refer to Kyoto and Rakuyo), but definitions were ambiguous.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。クォーテーションをのぞくなどしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="58">
<j>平安時代には洛中は京職・検非違使の管轄であるが、辺土（洛外）は山城国国府の管轄と考えられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Heian period, Rakuchu was under the control of Kyoshiki (the Capital Bureau), kebiishi (a police and judicial chief), but, Hendo (Rakugai) was considered to be under the control of kokufu (privincial office) of Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Heian period, Rakuchu was under the control of Kyoshiki (the Capital Bureau), kebiishi (a police and judicial chief), but, Hendo (Rakugai) was considered to be under the control of kokufu (privincial office) of Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Heian period, Rakuchu was under the control of the Kyoshiki (Capital Bureau) and kebiishi (a police and judicial chief), but Hendo (Rakugai) was considered to be under the control of the kokufu (provincial office) of Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>鴨長明の『方丈記』の養和の飢饉に関する件には、京（洛中）を「一条よりは南、九条よりは北、京極よりは西、朱雀よりは東」と記し、続いて辺土として白河_(京都市)や西の京（西京/西ノ京、かつての右京地域）を挙げている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the subject concerning Famine of Yowa in &quot;Hojoki&quot; (An Account of My Hut) written by KAMO no Chomei, Kyo (Rakuchu) was described as an area located in &apos;the south of Ichijo, the north of Kujo, the west of Kyogoku and the east of Suzaku,&apos; and Hendo was described as areas including Shirakawa (Kyoto City) and Nishinokyo (Nishikyo or Nishinokyo which used to be the Ukyo area).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the subject concerning Famine of Yowa in &quot;Hojoki&quot; (An Account of My Hut) written by KAMO no Chomei, Kyo (Rakuchu) was described as an area located in &apos;the south of Ichijo, the north of Kujo, the west of Kyogoku and the east of Suzaku,&apos; and Hendo was described as areas including Shirakawa (Kyoto City) and Nishinokyo (Nishikyo or Nishinokyo which used to be the Ukyo area).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The entry regarding the Famine of Yowa in KAMO no Chomei&apos;s &quot;Hojoki&quot; (An Account of My Hut) describes Kyo (Rakuchu) as the area &apos;south of Ichijo, north of Kujo, west of Kyogoku and east of Suzaku,&apos; while Hendo is described as consisting of Shirakawa and Nishinokyo (or Nishikyo, formerly the Ukyo area).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しクォーテーションの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>辺土のうち、鴨川の東を河東と呼称し、白河や六波羅などがこれに該当した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among areas called Hendo, the area in the east of Kamo-gawa River was called Kato, which was equivalent to Shirakawa and Rokuhara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the areas referred to as Hendo, the area in the east of Kamo-gawa River was called Kato, which was equivalent to Shirakawa and Rokuhara.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the areas referred to as Hendo, the area to the east of the Kamo-gawa River was called Kato, and was equivalent to Shirakawa and Rokuhara.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>『吉記』治承4年11月30日 (旧暦)（1180年12月18日）条によれば、安徳天皇が平清盛の六波羅第に滞在中の高倉上皇の元に行幸しようとした際に、記主の吉田経房が辺土への行幸に神鏡を持ち出す事に異論を唱えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the description on December 18, 1180 in &quot;Kikki&quot; (a diary of Tsunefusa YOSHIDA), when Emperor Antoku planned to visit the retired Emperor Takakura who was staying at Rokuhara-tei of TAIRA no Kiyomori, Tsunefusa YOSHIDA, writer, made an objection to bringing out a divine mirror to Hendo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a description on December 18, 1180 in &quot;Kikki&quot; (a diary of Tsunefusa YOSHIDA), when Emperor Antoku planned to visit the retired Emperor Takakura who was staying at Rokuhara-tei of TAIRA no Kiyomori, Tsunefusa YOSHIDA, writer, objected to bringing a divine mirror to Hendo.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the December 25, 1180 entry in &quot;Kikki&quot; (a diary of Tsunefusa YOSHIDA), the author Tsunefusa YOSHIDA objected to the taking of the divine mirror on the imperial visit to Hendo when Emperor Antoku planned to visit the Retired Emperor Takakura who was staying at the Rokuhara-tei residence of TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直し、グレゴリオ暦にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>鎌倉幕府が六波羅に六波羅探題を設置したのも、平家滅亡後に、京都における北条氏の邸宅が置かれていたこともあるが、検断権を巡る検非違使との直接的な衝突を避けたことも理由に挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was because the Kamakura bakufu established Rokuhara Tandai and a Kyoto residence of the Hojo clan was established after the defeat of the Taira forces, and also because of avoiding a direct conflict with kebiishi over the right to judge criminal cases.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was because the Kamakura bakufu established Rokuhara Tandai and a Kyoto residence of the Hojo clan was established after the defeat of the Taira forces, and also to avoid a direct conflict with kebiishi over the right to judge criminal cases.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was because the Kamakura bakufu established the Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency) in Rokuhara and because the Kyoto residence of the Hojo clan was established after the defeat of the Taira clan, but the avoidance of direct conflict with kebiishi over the right to judge criminal cases is also given as a reason.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>後に河東は六波羅探題の異称にもなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, Kato became another name of Rokuhara Tandai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, Kato became another name for Rokuhara Tandai.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, Kato also became another name for Rokuhara Tandai.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>正応元年6月10日 (旧暦)（1288年7月9日）の伏見天皇による殺生禁止の宣旨には、宣旨を適用する洛中の外側を「近境」と表現して、東は東山 (京都府)の下、南を赤江（現在の伏見区羽束師古川町）、西を桂川の東、北を賀茂の山と定めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the imperial order of prohibition of killing animals given by Emperor Fushimi on July 9, 1288, the outside of Rakuchu covered by the imperial order was called &apos;Kinkyo&apos; (close border), and the Rakuchu was specified to be an area which extended from the foot of Mt. Higashi (Kyoto Prefecture) to the Katsura-gawa River in an east-west direction, and from Kamo no Yama Mountain to Akae (present-day Furukawa-cho, Hazukashi, Fushimi Ward) in a north-south direction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The outside of Rakuchu covered by the imperial order prohibiting the killing of animals issued by Emperor Fushimi on July 9, 1288 was called &apos;Kinkyo&apos; (close border), and Rakuchu was specified to be an area which extended from the foot of Mt. Higashi (Kyoto Prefecture) to the Katsura-gawa River in an east-west direction, and from Kamo no Yama Mountain to Akae (present-day Furukawa-cho, Hazukashi, Fushimi Ward) in a north-south direction.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In an July 16, 1288, imperial decree by Emperor Fushimi prohibiting hunting and fishing, the area outside Rakuchu to which the ban applied was referred to as &apos;Kinkyo&apos; and specified as an area extending to the base of Mt. Higashi (Kyoto Prefecture) in the east, Akae (modern-day Furukawa-cho, Hazukashi, Fushimi Ward) in the south, the eastern side the Katsura-gawa River in the west, and Mt. Kamo in the north.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直し、グレゴリオ暦にし、クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>鎌倉時代末期の朝廷や室町幕府が酒屋役を「洛中辺土」に課しており、応仁の乱の頃から辺土に替わって洛外という語が一般的になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The imperial court in the late Kamakura period and the Muromachi bakufu imposed Sakaya yaku (taxed imposed on sake brewery by Muromachi bakufu) on &apos;Rakuchu Hendo,&apos; and after around the time when the Onin War broke out, the name &quot;Rakugai&quot; became popular instead of Hendo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The imperial court in the late Kamakura period and the Muromachi bakufu imposed Sakaya yaku (taxed imposed on sake brewery by Muromachi bakufu) on &apos;Rakuchu Hendo,&apos; and around the time when the Onin War broke out, the name &quot;Rakugai&quot; became popular instead of Hendo.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Court and the Muromachi bakufu imposed Sakaya yaku (taxes imposed on sake brewing) on &apos;Rakuchu Hendo&apos; at the end of the Kamakura period, and it became general practice to use the name Rakugai instead of Hendo since around the time of the Onin War.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しクォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="66">
<j>室町時代から戦国時代_(日本)にかけて三条通を境目として北側を上京（かみきょう）、南側を下京（しもきょう）と呼ぶ慣習が生まれ、上京と下京がそれぞれ別個の惣構を持った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Over the Muromachi period and the Sengoku period, a custom of calling the area in the north of Sanjo-dori Street Kamikyo, and the area in the south of such Street Shimokyo arose, and Kamikyo and Shimokyo had individual Sogamae (defense facilities such as moat and mound).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the Muromachi period to the Sengoku period, a custom of calling the area in the north of Sanjo-dori Street Kamikyo, and the area in the south, Street Shimokyo arose, with Kamikyo and Shimokyo having individual Sogamae (defense facilities such as moat and mound).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the Muromachi period to the Sengoku period (Japan), the custom arose of calling the area north of Sanjo-dori Street Kamikyo, and the area in the south of the street Shimokyo, with Kamikyo and Shimokyo each having their own sogamae (outer citadel).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>豊臣秀吉の京都改造の際に1587年頃より洛中の太閤検地を行い、続いて1591年には京都中心部を囲うように土居を建設した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When reconstructing Kyoto, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI implemented Taiko-kenchi (the land survey by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) in Rakuchu from around 1587, and in 1591, constructed Doi (mound) so as to surround the central part of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳分例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When reconstructing Kyoto, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI implemented Taiko-kenchi (the land survey by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) in Rakuchu from around 1587, and in 1591, constructed Doi (mound) so as to surround the central part of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When reconstructing Kyoto, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI implemented his Taiko-kenchi land survey in Rakuchu from around 1587, and in 1591 he constructed doi (mound) around central Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>また、土居の内側を洛中・外側を洛外として、洛中内部において更に農村として扱った上野・西ノ京・中堂寺・九条・塩小路などの村々を除いた洛中地域を特に京中（きょうちゅう）として上京・下京のそれぞれの町年寄（後に町代）による一定の自治を認めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon specifying the inside of Doi as Rakuchu and its outside as Rakugai, Hideyoshi especially specified the Rakuchu area excluding villages of Ueno, Nishinokyo, Chudoji, Kujo and Shiokoji in Rakuchu which were treated as farming villages as Kyochu, and allowed each machi-doshiyori (ward head; later chodai (a functionary established in each chogumi with the function of connecting the cho with the Tokugawa bakufu) of Shimokyo and Kaikyo to implement a degree of self-governance.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳分例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon specifying the inside of Doi as Rakuchu and its outside as Rakugai, Hideyoshi especially specified the Rakuchu area excluding villages of Ueno, Nishinokyo, Chudoji, Kujo and Shiokoji in Rakuchu which were treated as farming villages as Kyochu, and allowed each machi-doshiyori (ward head; later chodai (a functionary established in each chogumi with the function of connecting the cho with the Tokugawa bakufu) of Shimokyo and Kaikyo to implement a degree of self-governance.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon designating the area inside of the doi as Rakuchu and the area outside as Rakugai, Hideyoshi went on to specifically designate inner Rakuchu; with the exception of villages such as Ueno, Nishinokyo, Chudoji, Kujo and Shiokoji which were treated as agricultural villages; as Kyochu and allowed a certain degree of self-governance by machi-doshiyori (ward heads) and later by chodai (town officials who assisted government officials).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。余分なピリオドをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>これによって「惣組」（上京・下京）－「町組」（「組町」とも）－各町という近世京都の地縁共同体が形成される事になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of this, a territorially-connected community of &apos;Sogumi&apos; (ward community; Kamikyo and Shimokyo) consisting of &apos;Machigumi or Kumimachi (town society) consisting of each town was formed as seen in Kyoto in the early-modern times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of this, a territorially-connected community of &apos;Sogumi&apos; (ward community; Kamikyo and Shimokyo) consisting of &apos;Machigumi or Kumimachi (town society) consisting of each town was formed as seen in Kyoto in early-modern times.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of this, an early modern period Kyoto consisting a territorially-connected community of &apos;Sogumi&apos; (Kamikyo and Shimokyo), &apos;Machigumi&apos; (also known as kunimachi) and each &apos;machi&apos; (town) came to be formed.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直し、補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>その後、京中を越えて洛中全域そして洛外にも都市部が拡大し、1634年の征夷大将軍徳川家光の上洛を機に洛中全域と洛外の一部に地子免除が認められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, the city area extended in the whole Rakuchu area beyond Kyochu, and also to Rakugai, and when seiitaishogun Iemitsu TOKUGAWA visited Kyoto in 1634, the exemption from Jishi (land tax) was admitted in the whole Rakuchu area and part of Rakugai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, the city area extended in the whole Rakuchu area beyond Kyochu, and also to Rakugai, and when seiitaishogun Iemitsu TOKUGAWA visited Kyoto in 1634, the whole Rakuchu area and part of Rakugai were exempt from Jishi (land tax).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The city subsequently expanded beyond Kyochu into the entire Rakuchu area and even into Rakugai, and the entire Rakuchu area and part of Rakugai were made exempt from jishi (land tax) with the visit of the Seii Taishogun Iemitsu TOKUGAWA to Kyoto in 1634.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>1669年の京都町奉行の設置を機に、門跡寺院を除く寺社の管轄が町奉行となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Kyoto machi-bugyo was established in 1669, temples and shrines except for monzeki temples (temples of high rank where members of imperial family and nobility enter the priesthood) were placed under the control of machi-bugyo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳分例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Kyoto machi-bugyo was established in 1669, temples and shrines except for monzeki temples (temples of high rank where members of imperial family and nobility enter the priesthood) were placed under the control of machi-bugyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the establishment of the post of Kyoto machi-bugyo in 1669, all Buddhist temples and Shinto shrines with the exception of monzeki temples (temples of high rank where members of imperial family and nobility entered the priesthood) came under the control of machi-bugyo.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>また、直後に始まった鴨川 (淀川水系)の堤防設置工事にの完成（1670年）によって鴨川の河原が消えて水路化し、逆に五条以北の水路が消えたために洛中と洛外を区切る自然条件が大きく変化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Owing to the completion (in 1670) of embankment construction at the Kamo-gawa River (Yodo-gawa River System) which started immediately aftermath, the riverside of Kamo-gawa River was transformed into a channel; meanwhile, channels in the north of Gojo disappeared, and natural conditions dividing Rakuchu from Rakugai changed significantly.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳分例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Owing to the completion (in 1670) of embankment construction at the Kamo-gawa River (Yodo-gawa River System) which started immediately afterwards, the riverside of Kamo-gawa River was transformed into a channel; meanwhile, channels in the north of Gojo disappeared, and natural conditions dividing Rakuchu from Rakugai changed significantly.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Owing to the completion (in 1670) an embankment along the Kamo-gawa River (the Yodo-gawa River System) on which construction began immediately afterwards, the natural conditions dividing Rakuchu from Rakugai changed significantly when the river beach of the Kamo-gawa River was eliminated and the river transformed into a channel while channels to the north of Gojo disappeared.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>それにより急激に洛中の北側に市街が広がって「洛中洛外町続」と呼ばれる都市の拡大のきっかけになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of this, the urban area rapidly extended to the north side of Rakuchu, which led to an expansion of city called &apos;Rakuchu Rakugai Machituzuki (town extending from Rakuchu to Rakugai).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳分例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of this, the urban area rapidly extended to include the north side of Rakuchu, which led to an expansion of the city called &apos;Rakuchu Rakugai Machituzuki (town extending from Rakuchu to Rakugai).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of this, the urban area rapidly expanded to include the north of Rakuchu, which led to the expansion of a city called &apos;Rakuchu Rakugai Machitsuzuki&apos; (lit. town extending from Rakuchu to Rakugai).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>町奉行は町の拡大を抑制する方針を採ったが、実際には都市の拡大が先行して町奉行及び新しい町割の是非を審査する新地掛の与力がこれを追認する状況が幕末まで続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Machi-bugyo adopted a policy to restrain the expansion of town; however, as a matter of fact, the situation that the city expanded before such expansion was approved by machi-bugyo, and yoriki (a police sergeant) in charge of shinchigakari (town planning) to examine the appropriateness of new town planning continued until the end of Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Machi-bugyo adopted a policy to restrain the expansion of the town; however, as a matter of fact, the situation that the city expanded before such expansion was approved by machi-bugyo, and yoriki (a police sergeant) who were in charge of shinchigakari (town planning), or examining the appropriateness of plans for the new town continued to exist until the end of Edo period.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Machi-bugyo adopted a policy to restrain the expansion of the town but it was in fact the case that until then end of the Edo period, a situation continued in which the city&apos;s expansion preceded any ratification by the machi-bugyo or the yoriki (police sergeants) who were responsible for assessing the propriety of new town planning.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。actually→in fact に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>この洛外にまで広がった上京と下京が近代以後の京都市の基礎となっていくことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamikyo and Shimokyo which extended to Rakugai became the basis for Kyoto City after the end of Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamikyo and Shimokyo which extended to Rakugai became the basis for Kyoto City after the end of Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamikyo and Shimokyo which extended to Rakugai became the basis of early modern period Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>都市災害と文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Urban disaster and cultural properties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Urban disaster and cultural properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Disasters and Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="76">
<j>京都市内には活断層の存在が確認され、歴史的にも大きな被害をもたらしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An active fault of which the existence is confirmed in Kyoto City caused huge damage in the past.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A confirmed active fault in Kyoto City has caused huge damage in the past.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The presence of an active fault in Kyoto City has been confirmed, and this has historically caused great damage.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="77">
<j>ところで、現在京都市内には、多くの木造建築物や仏像などの文化財が数多く現存しているが、その理由として、これらの文化財は昭和初期までほとんどが住宅地の外にあり、幾たびかの市街地からの延焼をまぬがれてきたから存在するとの研究結果が認知されつつある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many wooden buildings and cultural properties such as Buddha statues exist in present-day Kyoto City, and the result of research, which shows that these cultural properties exist because most of them existed outside the residential area until the Early Showa era, and were rid of several fires spread from the residential area, is being recognized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many wooden buildings and cultural properties such as Buddha statues exist in present-day Kyoto City, and the result of research, which shows that these cultural properties exist because many of them existed outside the residential area until the Early Showa era, and managed to escape several fires which spread from the residential area, is being recognized.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many cultural properties including a large number of wooden buildings and Buddhist images exist in modern-day Kyoto City, and there is continuing recognition of research findings which claim that these cultural properties have survived because the majority of them were located outside of the residential area until the early Showa period and therefore escaped the fires that repeatedly spread from the urban center.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="78">
<j>ところが、近時住宅地にのみこまれた文化財は、地震等による大火で失われる確立が過去に無いほど非常に危険な状態にあると危惧する声が有識者の中から上がっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, intellectuals voice concern about the higher risk ever than before that cultural properties recently moved in the residential area may be lost by a conflagration caused by earthquake, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, intellectuals voice concern about the risk of losing cultural properties, recrecently moved to the residential area, due to earthquakes, etc now being higher than ever.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, experts are voicing the fear that the probability that cultural properties enveloped by the sprawl of recent residential areas can become lost in fires caused by earthquakes and other factors is greater than ever before.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="79">
<j>また、それら文化財自体の地震などへの耐震性についても、現在の基準で判断すると問題のある建物も相当数あるが、解体修理は世紀単位で一度しかできず、莫大な費用を要する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When checking the earthquake resistance of those cultural properties in accordance with the current standard, very many buildings are disqualified; however, the repair by demolition is conducted only once a century, and the enormous amount of money is required.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When checking the earthquake resistance of those cultural properties in accordance with the current standard, many buildings fail, however, repair through deconstruction is conducted only once a century, costing an enormous amount of money.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When judging the earthquake resistance of those cultural properties in accordance with current standards, there are many buildings that fail but dismantling and repair can only be conducted once every century and requires enormous amounts of money.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>そのため、万一耐震不足と認定されれば、入場制限を強いられる恐れがあり、診断さえ行われない場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, should a building be disqualified due to insufficiency of earthquake resistance, the restricted admission may be forced, and even the seismic capacity will not be evaluated in many cases.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, should a building be disqualified due to insufficient earthquake resistance, it may be forcibly qualified, in which case the capacity to withstand seismic shock may not be evaluated.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is therefore the fear that a building determined to be insufficiently earthquake resistant may be forced to restrict admission and there would be many cases for which even assessments could not be conducted.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>小学校</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Elementary school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Elementary schools</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Elementary Schools</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="81">
<j>日本における最初の学区制小学校は、国の学校制度創設（1872年）に先立ち、1869年に創設された64校の京都の番組小学校である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the first elementary school established in Japan under the school district system, sixty four Bangumi Shogakko Elementary Schools in Kyoto were established in 1869 before the national school system was established (in 1872).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the first elementary school established in Japan under the school district system, sixty four Bangumi Shogakko Elementary Schools in Kyoto were established in 1869 before the national school system was established (in 1872).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the first elementary schools established in Japan under the school district system were 64 District Elementary Schools in Kyoto which were founded in 1869, prior to the establishment of the national school system (in 1872).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>これらの小学校のうち多くは統廃合されたが、22校は現在も残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of these elementary schools were abolished or merged, but, twenty two schools still remain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of these elementary schools were abolished or merged, but, twenty two schools still remain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of these elementary schools were consolidated but 22 still remain.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>教育機関としての機能だけでなく、役所・警察・消防・保健所等の機能も併せ持っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above elementary schools had not only a function as an educational institution but also functions as a city hall, police station, fire department, healthcare center, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above elementary schools not only functioned as educational institutions but also as a city hall, police station, fire department, healthcare center, etc.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They not only functioned as educational institutions but also as government offices, police stations, fire departments, healthcare centers and so on.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>現在でも、番組小学校の学区は元学区と呼ばれ、自治会組織の単位となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The school district (Gakku in Japanese) of Bangumi Shogakko Elementary School is still called Motogakku (original school district), and is a unit of residents&apos; association.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The school district (Gakku in Japanese) of Bangumi Shogakko Elementary School is still called Motogakku (original school district), and is a residents&apos; association unit.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even today, the school district of a District Elementary School is called motogakku (original school district), and is a unit of council organization.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>観光名所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sightseeing spots</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sightseeing spots</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sightseeing Spots</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 KOSUGHI(id:248711), Nnh(id:474), Ans(id:27735), ちびっ子おじん(id:187166), Tekk(id:117325), Gombe(id:27), ＋－(id:17104), Swind(id:30993), らりた(id:1327), Michey.M(id:906), MUSASHI(id:11881), 秀の介(id:490), Yomibitoshirezu(id:2466), Waza fire(id:9029), 5816K(id:102574), Kyoww(id:126965), Empoor(id:27673), Haruno Akiha(id:107628), 白糸(id:47025), Kzhr(id:131), Hoge-(id:158), FlyMeToFullmoon(id:37559), ZZZ(id:9462), 樒(id:35770), Kagetudo(id:163875), Rusk(id:9895), Matsukaze(id:51778), SuisuiBot(id:10165), あんも騎士(id:139357), 倶楽部オータム(id:139861), Ojjiy(id:66737), オータムスネイク(id:134217), Junger(id:10282), Suisui(id:69), みょうじ(id:124419), HASIDATE(id:181052), Reggaeman(id:6214), Urania(id:7213), Charenji(id:7908), Araisyohei(id:378), 春野秋葉(id:36725), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Kumatora(id:16941), Boch(id:106342), 横浜大塚(id:107010), 沢田(id:40580), Sgi1962(id:80778), Bendono(id:85524), 平 誠(id:2586), Ganman(id:96316), Kinori(id:443), Goki(id:7107), 越中掾(id:149423), Nopira(id:29335), 捕澤(id:23785), 雉(id:2479), 水野白楓(id:22811), Juyukichi(id:16958), 俊平太郎(id:34056), 伊集院聖(id:53199), Shinkansen(id:13703), Carkuni(id:79281), Tanuki Z(id:612), Gamy-Gamy-Gamy(id:287400), Tigers(id:231656), Fromm(id:71291), Baba(id:2635), Muyo(id:14948), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), Safkan(id:423), 210.(id:9838), へなぎさわ(id:61857), ホイップ(id:44812), っ(id:4481), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>