<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>白河 (洛外)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shirakawa (the suburbs of Kyoto)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shirakawa (the suburbs of Kyoto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shirakawa (the surroundings of the old capital, Kyoto)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>白河（しらかわ・白川）とは、かつて京都洛外、山城国愛宕郡に属していた白川 (淀川水系)流域を指す名称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shirakawa is the name referring to Shira-kawa River basin (Yodogawa river system) which once belonged to Otagi-gun County, Yamashiro Province in Kyoto Rakugai (outside of the capital Kyoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shirakawa is the name referring to the Shira-kawa River basin (Yodogawa river system) which once belonged to Otagi-gun County, Yamashiro Province in Kyoto Rakugai (outside of the capital Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shirakawa (白河 or also written as 白川) is the name referring to the Shira-kawa River basin (Yodo-gawa River System) which was once included in Otagi County, Yamashiro Province, the Rakugai of Kyoto (outside of the capital Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。Yodogawa→Yodo-gawaOtagi-gun County,→Otagi County,</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>本来は白川の南側地域のみを指していたが、後に北側地域も含むようになり南側を「南白河/下白河」北側を「北白河」・と称した（『山城名勝志』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It originally referred only to the area on the south side of Shira-kawa River, but later came also to include the area on the north side, and the south side was named &quot;Minami Shirakawa/Shimo Shirakawa,&quot; and the north side &quot;Kita Shirakawa&quot; (&quot;Yamashiro Meishoshi&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It originally referred only to the area on the south side of Shira-kawa River, but later came also to include the area on the north side, and the south side that was named &quot;Minami Shirakawa/Shimo Shirakawa,&quot; and the north side &quot;Kita Shirakawa&quot; (&quot;Yamashiro Meishoshi&quot;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It originally referred only to the area on the south side of Shira-kawa River, but later came also to include the area on the north side, with the south side named &apos;Minami Shirakawa/Shimo Shirakawa&apos; and the north side named &apos;Kita Shirakawa&apos; (according to &quot;Yamashiro Meisho Shi&quot; (Annals of Yamashiro&apos;s picturesque sites)).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>現在では京都市左京区に属するが、南白河は岡崎 (京都市)・北白河は北白川に分割されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It currently belongs to Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City, but separated into Minami Shirakawa as Okazaki (Kyoto City) and Kita Shirakawa as Kita Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It currently belongs to Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City, but was separated into Minami Shirakawa as Okazaki (Kyoto City) and Kita Shirakawa as Kita Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It currently belongs to Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City, but was separated into Minami Shirakawa as Okazaki (Kyoto City) and Kita Shirakawa as Kita Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>領域</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Area</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Area</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Area</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>白河は、白川流域のうち、現在の左京区岡崎を中心として、北は北白川・東は東山 (京都府)・南は岡崎もしくは粟田口・西は鴨川 (淀川水系)に囲まれた地域とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shirakawa is understood as the area surrounded by Kita Shirakawa on the north, Higashiyama (Kyoto Prefecture) on the east, Okazaki or Awataguchi on the south and Kamogawa river (Yodogawa river system) on the west, centering around Okazaki, Sakyo Ward, in the Shira-kawa River basin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shirakawa is understood as the area surrounded by Kita Shirakawa in the north, Higashiyama (Kyoto Prefecture) in the east, Okazaki or Awataguchi in the south and Kamogawa river (Yodogawa river system) in the west, centering around Okazaki, Sakyo Ward, in the Shira-kawa River basin</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shirakawa is understood as the area surrounded by Kita Shirakawa to the north, Higashiyama (Kyoto Prefecture) to the east, Okazaki or Awataguchi to the south and Kamo-gawa River (Yodo-gawa River System) to the west, centering around present-day Okazaki, Sakyo Ward, in the Shira-kawa River basin.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。Yodogawa→Yodo-gawa</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>白川が形成した扇状地には縄文時代の住居跡が遺されるなど、有史以前から人間が居住していたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The alluvial fan formed by Shira-kawa River is thought to have been inhabited by human beings from the prehistoric age as evidenced by dwelling sites of the Jomon period remaining in the area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The alluvial fan formed by the Shira-kawa River is thought to have been inhabited by humans from the prehistoric age as evidenced by dwelling sites of the Jomon period remaining in the area.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The alluvial fan formed by the Shira-kawa River is thought to have been inhabited by humans from the prehistoric age as evidenced by dwelling sites from the Jomon period remaining in the area.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>平安遷都直後の白河は鳥辺野などとともに葬送地であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shirakawa immediately after the transfer of national capital to the city of Heian-kyo (current Kyoto) was a funeral place as Toribeno, etc. were.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shirakawa, immediately after the transfer of national capital to the city of Heian-kyo (current Kyoto), was a funeral place as was Toribeno, etc.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shirakawa, immediately after the transfer of national capital to the city of Heian-kyo (old capital, present-day Kyoto), was one of the funeral areas including Toribeno.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また、粟田口は逢坂関への入口であり、平安京から近江国を経て東国に至る道の起点として重要視された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And, Awataguchi was an entrance to Osaka no Seki checking station and regarded as the important starting point of the road from Heian-kyo to Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region) via Omi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And, Awataguchi was an entrance to Osaka no Seki checking station and regarded as the important starting point of the road from Heian-kyo to Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region) via Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Awataguchi was an entrance to Osaka no seki (Osaka Barrier, which was one of the barriers of the road system of old Japan) and regarded as a major starting point of the road from Heian-kyo to Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, the term is used in the old days) via Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、白川上流の東山 (京都府)を越える京都府道・滋賀県道30号下鴨大津線もこれを補完する経路として重要視された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And, Kyoto/Shiga Prefectural Road 30 Shimogamo-Otsu Line which cross over Higashiyama (Kyoto Prefecture) in the upstream area of Shira-kawa River was also regarded as an important path to complement it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And, Kyoto/Shiga Prefectural Road 30 Shimogamo-Otsu Line which cross over Higashiyama (Kyoto Prefecture) in the upstream area of Shira-kawa River was also regarded as an important path to complement it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also regarded as an important path to complement the road was Shimogamo-Otsu Line of Kyoto prefectural road and Shiga prefectural road No. 30, which crossed over Higashiyama (Kyoto Prefecture) in the upstream area of Shira-kawa River.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>ところが、藤原良房が白河に別業（別荘）である白河殿を造営して以後、別業・寺院の建立が相次いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, after FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa erected Shirakawa-dono Palace as his betsugyo (villa), villas and temples were erected one after the other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa erected Shirakawa-dono Palace as his betsugyo (villa), villas and temples were erected one after the other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa erected his betsugyo (villa), Shirakawa-dono Palace, villas and temples were erected one after another.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>藤原道長は白河殿でしばしば観桜の宴（花見）などの四季の行事を行い、庶流にあたる藤原済時や藤原公任も白河に別業を設けたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Michinaga frequently hosted seasonal events like Kano no utage (cherry blossom viewing party) at the Shirakawa-dono Palace and his branch families, FUJIWARA no Naritoki and FUJIWARA no Kinto are understood to have also set up their villas in Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Michinaga frequently hosted seasonal events like Kano no utage (cherry blossom viewing party) at the Shirakawa-dono Palace and his branch families, FUJIWARA no Naritoki and FUJIWARA no Kinto are understood to have also set up their villas in Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Michinaga frequently hosted seasonal events like &apos;Kano no utage&apos; (cherry blossom viewing party) and so force at the Shirakawa-dono Palace, and it is said that those from his branch families, FUJIWARA no Naritoki and FUJIWARA no Kinto, also set up their villas in Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>白河殿は藤原師実の代に時の白河天皇に献上される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shirakawa-dono Palace was presented to the reigning emperor, Emperor Shirakawa at the time of FUJIWARA no Morozane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shirakawa-dono Palace was presented to the reigning emperor, Emperor Shirakawa at the time of FUJIWARA no Morozane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shirakawa-dono Palace was dedicated to the reigning Emperor, Emperor Shirakawa at the time of FUJIWARA no Morozane.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。Emperorのeを大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>白河天皇により、師実実兄の覚円を別当とした法勝寺が造営された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hosho-ji Temple was erected by Emperor Shirakawa, who appointed Kakuen, Morozane&apos;s real elder brother as Betto (the head priest).</e>
<cmt>白河天皇が法勝寺を建て、覚円を別当に就任させたと解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hosho-ji Temple was erected by Emperor Shirakawa, who appointed Kakuen, Morozane&apos;s real elder brother as Betto (the head priest).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hossho-ji Temple was erected by Emperor Shirakawa, who appointed Kakuen, Morozane&apos;s biological elder brother Betto (the head priest).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その後、歴代天皇・皇后によって建てられた5つの寺院とともに「六勝寺」と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward, the temple was referred to as &quot;Rikushoji (The Six Victorious Temples)&quot; together with 5 temples which were erected by the successive emperors and empresses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterward, the temple was referred to as &quot;Rikushoji (The Six Victorious Temples)&quot; together with 5 temples which were erected by successive emperors and empresses.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, the temple was referred to as &apos;Rokushoji&apos; (or &apos;Rikushoji&apos;, The Six Victorious Temples) together with five temples which were erected by successive Emperors and Empresses.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。Emperor,Empressのeを大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また、白河天皇は退位後の寛治4年（1090年）頃に旧の覚円の僧房を御所（白河泉殿）とし、続いて永久 (日本)3年（1115年）に白河泉殿を改築して白河南殿を造営、更に元永元年（1118年）にはその隣接地に白河北殿を新造して2つの御所を行き来しながら院政を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And, Emperor Shirakawa started to use Kakuen&apos;s old living quarters as his Gosho (Palace) (Shirakawa Izumi-dono) around 1090 after his retirement, then in 1115, erected Shirakawa Minami-dono (South Palace) rebuilding Shirakawa Izumi-dono, furthermore in 1118, at the adjoining site, erected Shirakawa Kita-dono (North Palace), and conducted Insei (rule by the retired Emperor) shuttling between the 2 Palaces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And, Emperor Shirakawa started to use Kakuen&apos;s old living quarters as his Gosho (Palace) (Shirakawa Izumi-dono) around 1090 after his retirement, then in 1115, erected Shirakawa Minami-dono (South Palace) rebuilding Shirakawa Izumi-dono, furthermore in 1118, at the adjoining site, erected Shirakawa Kita-dono (North Palace), and conducted Insei (rule by the retired Emperor) shuttling between the 2 Palaces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Shirakawa started to use Kakuen&apos;s once-used living quarters as his Gosho (Imperial Palace) (Shirakawa Izumi-dono) around 1090 after his retirement, then in 1115, erected the Shirakawa Minami-dono (South Imperial Palace) rebuilding the Shirakawa Izumi-dono, further in 1118, at the adjoining site, erected the Shirakawa Kita-dono (North Imperial Palace), and conducted the Insei (rule by the Retired Emperor) shuttling between the two Palaces.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。Retiredのrを大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>白河が事実上の政治の中心となったため、本来は平安京の外であった白河が「京白河」と称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Shirakawa became the virtual center of mainstream politics, Shirakawa was called &quot;Kyo Shirakawa&quot; even if it was originally outside of Heian-kyo.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Kyo Shirakawa&quot;</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Shirakawa became the virtual center of mainstream politics, Shirakawa was called &quot;Kyo Shirakawa&quot; even if it was originally outside of Heian-kyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Shirakawa became the virtual center of mainstream politics, Shirakawa was called &apos;Kyo Shirakawa&apos;, even though it was originally located outside Heian-kyo.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>だが、源平合戦で交通の要所であった白河の地は荒廃し、窮民によって御所や寺院が荒らされていく様子が『玉葉』などに記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Gyokuyo&quot; (Diary of Kanezane KUJO), etc. described how much Shirakawa which had been an important area for traffic was devastated and how palaces and temples were kept ransacked by the poor and needy during and after the Genpei War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Gyokuyo&quot; (Diary of Kanezane KUJO), etc. described how much Shirakawa, which had been an important area for traffic, was devastated and how palaces and temples were kept ransacked by the poor and needy during and after the Genpei War.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Documents including &quot;Gyokuyo&quot; (Diary of Kanezane KUJO) described how the land of Shirakawa, which had been an important area for traffic, was devastated and how the imperial palace and temples were kept ransacked by the poor and needy during and after the Genpei War (1180-1185, a war between the Taira clan and the Minamoto clan in which the latter defeated the former and established the Kamakura shogunate government).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>鎌倉時代に入ると、白河の中心部は「岡崎」と称されるようになり、後鳥羽上皇が承元2年（1208年）に白河に御所を造営した際に「岡崎御所」と称されて（『百錬抄』）以後、岡崎という呼称も用いられるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Kamakura period started, the central part of Shirakawa came to be referred to &quot;Okazaki,&quot; and when the retired Emperor Gotoba erected his palace in Shirakawa in 1208, it was named &quot;Okazaki Palace&quot; (&quot;Hyakuren sho&quot; (History book from the Kamakura period), and after that, the name of Okazaki came to be used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Kamakura period began, the central part of Shirakawa came to be referred to as &quot;Okazaki,&quot; and when the retired Emperor Gotoba erected his palace in Shirakawa in 1208, it was named &quot;Okazaki Palace&quot; (&quot;Hyakuren sho&quot; - a History book from the Kamakura period), and after that, the name of Okazaki came to be used.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Kamakura period (1185-1333) began, the central part of Shirakawa have been referred to as &apos;Okazaki,&apos; and when the Retired Emperor Gotoba erected his palace in Shirakawa in 1208, it was named the &apos;Okazaki Imperial Palace&apos; (according to &quot;Hyakuren sho&quot;--a history book from the Kamakura period); since then, the name of Okazaki have been used too.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>この時代には岡崎（白河）の住宅地化が進み、元来白河に含まれていなかった白川の北側もその地域的範疇に含めるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those days, housing land development was advanced in Okazaki (Shirakawa), and the area on the north side of Shira-kawa River which was originally not included in Shirakawa was come to be also included in its geographical coverage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those days, housing land development was advanced in Okazaki (Shirakawa), and the area on the north side of the Shira-kawa River which was originally not included in Shirakawa came to be also included in its geographical coverage.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kamakura period, housing land development advanced in Okazaki (Shirakawa), and the north side of the Shira-kawa River which was originally not in Shirakawa was included in its geographical coverage.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>また南禅寺も創建された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And, Nanzen-ji Temple was also founded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And, Nanzen-ji Temple was also founded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, Nanzen-ji Temple was founded.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>南北朝時代 (日本)の法勝寺の火災も近くの民家火災によるとされている（『太平記』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fire which broke out at Hosho-ji Temple in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan) is understood to have been caused by the fire of a house nearby (&quot;Taiheiki&quot; (The Record of the Great Peace)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fire which broke out at Hosho-ji Temple during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan) is understood to have been caused by the fire from a house nearby (&quot;Taiheiki&quot; - The Record of the Great Peace).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that the fire which burnt Hossho-ji Temple in the Northern and Southern Court period was caused by the fire from a house nearby (according to &quot;Taiheiki&quot; (The Record of the Great Peace)--a Chronicle of Medieval Japan).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。Courts→Court</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="21">
<j>室町時代には南白河においては、「岡崎」の呼称が定着し、「白河」という地名は白川の北側の「北白川」を指すようになっていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Muromachi period, the name of &quot;Okazaki&quot; became established for Minami Shirakawa, and the geographical name of &quot;Shirakawa&quot; started and kept to refer to &quot;Kita Shirakawa&quot; which was on the north side of Shira-kawa River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Muromachi period, the name &quot;Okazaki&quot; became established for Minami Shirakawa, and the geographical name of &quot;Shirakawa&quot; started and continued to refer to &quot;Kita Shirakawa&quot; which was on the north side of the Shira-kawa River.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Muromachi period, &apos;Okazaki&apos; was established as a name for Minami Shirakawa, whereas &apos;Shirakawa&apos; became to refer to Kita Shirakawa, the area on the north side of the Shira-kawa River.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>だが、応仁の乱では岡崎が戦場となり、北白川も目前の東山に北白川城が築かれて度々攻防戦が行われるなど、戦国 (日本)乱世の影響を確実に受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, during the Onin War, Okazaki became a battleground, and the Kitashirakawa-jo Castle was built in Higashiyama which was within a stone&apos;s throw of Kita Shirakawa and offensive and defensive battles were frequently took place, thus both areas was definitely affected by the Sengoku period (Period of Warring States) (Japan) wild times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But, during the Onin War, Okazaki became a battleground, and Kitashirakawa-jo Castle was built in Higashiyama which was within a stone&apos;s throw of Kita Shirakawa and offensive and defensive battles frequently took place there, thus both areas were definitely affected by the Sengoku period (Period of Warring States in Japan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Onin War, both areas were directly affected by the turbulent war period such that Okazaki became a battleground, whereas Kitashirakawa-jo Castle was built in Higashiyama which was within a stone&apos;s throw of Kita Shirakawa where offensive and defensive battles were frequently fought.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>その一方で、北白川では水車による精米作業や「白川女」による花の行商などの活動で知られるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Kita Shirakawa came to be known by such activities as water wheel-driven rice milling and flower peddling by Shirakawame (women from Kita-Shirakawa who sell flowers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Kita Shirakawa came to be known by such activities as water wheel-driven rice milling and flower peddling by Shirakawame (women from Kita-Shirakawa who sell flowers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yet, Kita Shirakawa became famous by activities including water wheel-driven rice polishing and flower peddling by Shirakawame (women from Shirakawa selling flowers).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="24">
<j>江戸時代には、北白川のみをもって「白川村」を構成し、明治以後も愛宕郡白川村 (京都府)に引き継がれていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Edo period, Kita Shirakawa formed itself alone as &quot;Shirakawa-mura&quot; and since Meiji Era, continued as Shirakawa-mura, Otagi District (Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo period, Kita Shirakawa formed itself alone as &quot;Shirakawa-mura&quot; and since the Meiji Era, continued as Shirakawa-mura, Otagi District (Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period, Kita Shirakawa solely formed &apos;Shirakawa-mura village&apos;, which became Shirakawa-mura, Otagi County (Kyoto Prefecture) in the Meiji Era.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。Otagi-gun (Kyoto Prefecture)→Otagi County (Kyoto Prefecture)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>一方、岡崎は早くも明治21年（1888年）に京都市上京区（当時）に編入されて京都市の一部として市制確立を迎えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Okazaki was incorporated into Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City (at that time) as early as 1888 and became a part of municipally established Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>「市制確立」の意味がよく理解できませんが、このように訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Okazaki was incorporated into Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City (at that time) as early as 1888 and became a part of municipally established Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast, as early as 1888, Okazaki was incorporated into the then Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City and became a part of municipality established in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>明治29年（1896年）には平安神宮が創建されるなど、京都市中心部との一体化が進んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1896, Heian-jingu Shrine was founded in Okazaki, which facilitated the integration of the area with the central part of Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1896, Heian-jingu Shrine was founded in Okazaki, which facilitated the integration of the area with the central part of Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1896, Heian-jingu Shrine was founded in Okazaki, which facilitated the integration of the area with the central part of Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>明治30年（1897年）に白川村内に京都帝国大学理学部が設置されると、北白川もまた学生街としての要素を帯び始めていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1897, the science faculty of Kyoto Imperial University was established in Shirakawa-mura, which started to feature Kita Shirakawa also as a students&apos; quarter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1897, the science faculty of Kyoto Imperial University was established in Shirakawa-mura, which started to feature Kita Shirakawa also as students&apos; quartes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1897, the Faculty of Science, Kyoto Imperial University was established in Shirakawa-mura, which started to make Kita Shirakawa also the student quarter.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>大正7年（1918年）に白川村は京都市上京区に編入された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1918, Shirakawa-mura was incorporated into Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1918, Shirakawa-mura was incorporated into Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1918, Shirakawa-mura was merged with Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>昭和4年（1929年）の京都市の区の再編に伴い、岡崎、北白川は左京区に属するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Along with the ward-restructuring in 1929, Okazaki and Kita Shirakawa came to belong to Sakyo Ward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Along with the ward-restructuring in 1929, Okazaki and Kita Shirakawa came to belong to Sakyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Along with the ward-restructuring in 1929, Okazaki and Kita Shirakawa had belonged to Sakyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>白河夜船</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shirakawa yofune (being fast asleep and totally unaware of what is going on around one)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shirakawa yofune (being fast asleep and totally unaware of what is going on around one)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shirakawa-yofune (being fast asleep and totally unaware of what is going on around one)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。#を取り除きました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="30">
<j>京都に旅行へ行ったと嘘をつく人が、この白河（白川）の地について聞かれ川のことだと思い、夜に船で通ったのでよく知らないと答え、嘘がばれたという逸話から、熟睡して前後を知らないことを「白河夜船（白川夜船）」という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shirakawa yofune (Shira-kawa River yofune) means that someone was fast asleep and totally unaware of what is going on around him, based on an anecdote that someone said he went on a journey to Kyoto, which was not true, and when he was asked about the Shirakawa (Shirakawa) area, he thought it was about Shira-kawa River, so said it was unanswerable because he went through the area by boat at dark night.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shirakawa yofune (Shira-kawa River yofune) means that someone was fast asleep and totally unaware of what was going on around him, based on an anecdote that someone said he went on a journey to Kyoto, which was not true, and when he was asked about the Shirakawa (Shirakawa) area, he thought it was about the Shira-kawa River, so said it was unanswerable because he went through the area by boat in the dark of night.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shirakawa yofune&apos; (Sound asleep) means that someone was fast asleep and totally unaware of what was going on around, which is based on the anecdote-- when a lier told that he had been on a journey to Kyoto, and he was asked about the Shirakawa area, he thought he was asked about the Shira-kawa River and told that he was not aware much of the river because he traveled down the river by boat in darkness of night, there, he was caught in his lie.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。Shirakawa →Shira-kawa</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>かつては、見たことがないものをさも見たことがあるかのようにしったかぶって言うことの意味にも用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the past, this term was used to mean know-it-all attitude like acting as if he had seen things he hasn&apos;t seen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the past, this term was used to mean a &quot;know-it-all&quot; attitude, one acting as if he had seen things he hadn&apos;t.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the past, this term meant a &quot;know-it-all&quot; attitude such as saying as if someone had seen things he hadn&apos;t.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Hideyuki(id:9577), Straysheep(id:42448), うら(id:40695), Mooko(id:36162), Nopira(id:29335), Haruno Akiha(id:107628), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>