<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>鳥羽作道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toba no Tsukurimichi (Toba New Road)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toba no Tsukurimichi (an ancient road from Heian-kyo [the ancient capital of Japan in current Kyoto] to Yodo through Toba [Kyoto City])</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toba no Tsukurimichi (an ancient road from Heian-kyo [the ancient capital of Japan in current Kyoto] to Yodo through Toba [Kyoto City])</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>鳥羽作道（とばのつくりみち・鳥羽造道）は、平安京の中央部を南北に貫く朱雀大路の入口である羅城門より真南に伸びて鳥羽 (京都市)を経由して淀方面に通じた古代道路。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toba no Tsukurimichi (Toba New Road) was an ancient road that led to the direction of Yodo by way of Toba (Kyoto City) that stretched directly south from Rajo-mon gate, which was an entrance to the Suzaku-oji Street that ran through north to south of the center of Heian-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in current Kyoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toba no Tsukurimichi (Toba New Road) was an ancient road from Rajo-mon gate, the entrance to the Suzaku-oji Street running through north to south in the center of Heian-kyo, to Yodo through Toba (Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toba no Tsukurimichi (Toba New Road) was an ancient road from Rajo-mon gate, the entrance to the Suzaku-oji Street running through north to south in the center of Heian-kyo, to Yodo through Toba (Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>平安遷都以前からの道とする説や鳥羽天皇が鳥羽殿が造営した際に築かれたとする説もあるが、平安京建設時に淀川から物資を運搬するために作られた道であると考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It had been suggested that the road had existed prior to the transfer of national capital to the city of Heian-kyo, or that it had been constructed by Emperor Toba when Toba-dono Palace was built, but it was regarded as the road which had been constructed in order to transport supplies from the Yodo-gawa River when the Heiankyo capital was being built.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It had been suggested that the road had existed prior to the transfer of national capital to the city of Heian-kyo, or that it had been constructed by Emperor Toba when Toba-dono Palace was built, but it was regarded as the road which had been constructed in order to transport supplies from the Yodo-gawa River when the Heian-kyo capital was being built.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It had been suggested that the road had existed prior to the transfer of national capital to the city of Heian-kyo, or that it had been constructed by Emperor Toba when Toba-dono Palace was built, but it was regarded as the road which had been constructed in order to transport supplies from the Yodo-gawa River when the Heian-kyo capital was being built.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>『徒然草』において、重明親王が元良親王の元日の奏賀の声が太極殿から鳥羽作道まで響いたことを書き残した故事について記されているため、両親王が活躍していた10世紀前半には存在していたとされる（ただし、吉田兼好が見たとされる重明親王による元の文章が残っていないために疑問視する意見もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since it is written in &quot;Tsurezure gusa&quot; (Essays in Idleness) about a historical event where a note had been left behind by Imperial Prince Shigeakira regarding Imperial Prince Motoyoshi&apos;s voice being heard from Daigokuden (Council Hall in the Imperial Palace) to Toba no Tsukurimichi when he made a ceremonial speech on the morning of the new year, it was considered that the road existed in the early 10th century when the two Imperial princes were active (However, there are opinions that questions this, for the original writings of Imperial Prince Shigeakira which Kenko YOSHIDA is supposed to have seen do not exist.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since &quot;Tsurezure gusa&quot; (Essays in Idleness) shows about a historical event that Imperial Prince Shigeakira wrote down that the voice of Imperial Prince Motoyoshi making a ceremonial speech on the morning of the new year was heard from Daigokuden (Council Hall in the Imperial Palace) to Toba no Tsukurimichi, it was considered that the road existed in the early 10th century when the two Imperial princes were active (however, there are opinions that questions this, as the original writings of Imperial Prince Shigeakira which Kenko YOSHIDA is supposed to have seen do not exist).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since &quot;Tsurezure gusa&quot; (Essays in Idleness) shows about a historical event that Imperial Prince Shigeakira wrote down that the voice of Imperial Prince Motoyoshi making a ceremonial speech on the morning of the new year was heard from Daigokuden (Council Hall in the Imperial Palace) to Toba no Tsukurimichi, it was considered that the road existed in the early 10th century when the two Imperial princes were active (however, there are opinions that questions this, as the original writings of Imperial Prince Shigeakira which Kenko YOSHIDA is supposed to have seen do not exist).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="4">
<j>鳥羽殿造営後は平安京から鳥羽への街道として「鳥羽の西大路」（この時代に平安京の右京は荒廃して朱雀大路は京都市街の西側の道となっていた）と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the construction of Toba-dono Palace, it was regarded as a road from Heian-kyo capital to Toba, and was referred to as &apos;Toba no Nishioji&apos; (West Avenue to Toba) (In this period, the west part of the capital was already in ruins and the Suzaku-oji Street had become the road in the west side of the Kyoto town area.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the construction of Toba-dono Palace, it was regarded as a road from Heian-kyo capital to Toba, and was referred to as &apos;Toba no Nishioji&apos; (West Avenue to Toba) (in this period, the west part of the capital was already in ruins and the Suzaku-oji Street had become the road in the west side of the Kyoto town area).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the construction of Toba-dono Palace, it was regarded as a road from Heian-kyo capital to Toba, and was referred to as &apos;Toba no Nishioji&apos; (West Avenue to Toba) (in this period, the west part of the capital was already in ruins and the Suzaku-oji Street had become the road in the west side of the Kyoto town area).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>更に淀付近から淀川水運を利用して東は草津宿・南は奈良・西は難波方面に出る交通路として用いられたと考えられているが、その後の戦乱で荒廃し、現在では一部が旧大坂街道として残されているものの、多くの地域において経路の跡すら失われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, water transport in the Yodo-gawa River was utilized in the Yodo area, making it a road that led to the Kusatsujuku in the east, to Nara in the west, and to Nanba in the West; however, it became desolate from the disturbances of the later war, and although parts of the road exist today as Old Osaka-kaido Road, even the tracks of the course are lost in many of the areas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, water transport in the Yodo-gawa River was utilized in the Yodo area, making it a road that led to the Kusatsu-juku Post Station in the east, to Nara in the south, and to Nanba in the west; however, it became desolate from the disturbances of the later wars, and although parts of the road exist today as Old Osaka-kaido Road, even the tracks of the course are lost in many of the areas.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, water transport in the Yodo-gawa River was utilized in the Yodo area, making it a road that led to the Kusatsu-juku Post Station in the east, to Nara in the south, and to Nanba in the west; however, it became desolate from the disturbances of the later wars, and although parts of the road exist today as Old Osaka-kaido Road, even the tracks of the course are lost in many of the areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 うら(id:40695), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>