<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>御室</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omuro</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omuro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omuro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>御室（おむろ）は、京都府京都市右京区の地名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omuro is the location name of Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omuro is the location name of Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omuro is the location name of Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>宇多天皇の創建で、真言宗御室派の総本山、門跡寺院でもある仁和寺と、オムロンの創業地として知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was established by Emperor Uda, and known as the place of birth of Ninan-ji Temple, which was the Monseki-jiin (Temples of the high class) of the head temple of Omuro Branch, and the founding ground of Omron.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was established by Emperor Uda, and known as the place of birth of Ninan-ji Temple, which was the Monseki-jiin (Temples of the high class) of the head temple of Omuro Branch, and where Omron was founded.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was established by the Emperor Uda, and known as the place of birth of Ninna-ji Temple, which was the Monseki-jiin (temples of the high class) of the head temple of Omuro school of the Shingon sect, and where Omron was founded.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Emperor Uda&quot; -&gt; &quot;the Emperor Uda&quot; に変更しました。翻訳を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>なお、オムロンの跡地は現在住宅地となっているが、創業記念碑が建立されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The vacant lot of Omron is currently a residential area, but there is a monument celebrating the foundation of the company.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The vacant lot of Omron is currently a residential area, but there is a monument celebrating the foundation of the company.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The vacant lot of Omron is currently a residential area, but there is a monument celebrating the foundation of the company.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>また、仁和寺の東には「きゅうり封じ」で知られる蓮華寺 (京都市右京区)があり、仁和寺の北には御室八十八ヶ所霊場がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, there is Renge-ji Temple famous for &apos;Kyuri Fuuji&apos; (cucumber sealing) (Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City) east of Ninani-ji, and there is Omuro Eighty-eight Reijo Places (place where human souls gather) at north of Ninan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, there is Renge-ji Temple famous for &apos;Kyuri Fuuji&apos; (cucumber sealing) (Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City) east of Ninani-ji, and there is Omuro Eighty-eight Reijo Places (place where human souls gather) at north of Ninan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, there is Renge-ji Temple famous for &apos;Kyuri Fuji&apos; (cucumber sealing) (Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City) east of Ninna-ji Temple, and there is Omuro Eighty-eight Reijo Places (place where human souls gather) at north of Ninna-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Ninna-ji と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>南には吉田兼好が一時庵を結んだ双岡がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is Narabigaoka toward south where Kenko YOSHIDA temporarily spent the life of a hermit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is Narabigaoka toward south where Kenko YOSHIDA temporarily spent the life of a hermit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is Narabigaoka toward south where Kenko YOSHIDA temporarily spent the life of a hermit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>御室の名の由緒は、904年（延喜4年）、宇多法皇が仁和寺に「御室」を造営し、起居する御所としたことから、その建物が「御室御所」と呼ばれ、やがては、仁和寺の別称となったものとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of the name of Omuro came from the &quot;omuro&quot; (room) within Ninan-ji Temple called &quot;Omuro Gosho&quot; built by Emperor Uda and used as the residential gosho (area) and eventually became the alias of Ninan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of the name of Omuro came from the &quot;omuro&quot; (room) within Ninan-ji Temple called &quot;Omuro Gosho&quot; built by Emperor Uda and used as the residential gosho (area) and eventually became the alias of Ninan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of the name of Omuro came from the &apos;omuro&apos; (room) within Ninna-ji Temple called &apos;Omuro Gosho&apos; built by the Cloistered Emperor Uda in 904 and used as the residential gosho (area) and eventually became the alias of Ninna-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Emperor Uda&quot; -&gt; &quot;the Cloistered Emperor Uda&quot; に変更しました。Ninna-ji と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>更に、それが仁和寺一帯の地名として定着したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This became the location name around the Ninan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This became the location name around the Ninan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This became the location name around the Ninna-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Ninna-ji と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>現在は、風光明媚で閑静な住宅地として知られ、最寄駅は京福電気鉄道北野線の御室仁和寺駅である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Currently, it is known as the beautiful and quiet residential area, and the nearest station is the Omuro Ninan-ji Temple Station on Kitano Line, Keifuku Electric Railroad.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently, it is known as the beautiful and quiet residential area, and the nearest station is the Omuro Ninan-ji Temple Station on Kitano Line, Keifuku Electric Railroad.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Currently, it is known as the beautiful and quiet residential area, and the nearest station is the Omuro-Ninnaji Station on Kitano Line, Keifuku Electric Railroad.</e>
<cmt>Ninna-ji と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Shinchon(id:52810), Rusk(id:9895), Saft(id:100518), Tossy2379(id:73756), Chankolo(id:58929), Ikedat76(id:34218), あお(id:33504), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>