<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>京都市西京区の町名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Town&apos;s name of the Nishikyo Ward, Kyoto City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Name of Nishikyo Ward, Kyoto City</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Town names of the Nishikyo Ward, Kyoto City</e>
<cmt>他の記事に合わせる</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>本項京都市西京区の町名（きょうとし にしきょうくのちょうめい）では、同区内に存在する公称町名を一覧化するとともに、その成立時期・成立過程等について概説する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This section, the Town&apos;s name of the Nishikyo Ward, Kyoto City, shows the list of the official town&apos;s names in the Ukyo Ward and summarizes the period and process of their establishment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This section, shows the list of official town names in the Ukyo Ward and summarizes the period and process of their establishment.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This section shows the list of official town names in the Nishikyo Ward and summarizes the period and process of their establishment.</e>
<cmt>Ukyo→Nishikyo</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>区の概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The summary of the Nishikyo Ward</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary of the Nishikyo Ward</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary of the Nishikyo Ward</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>京都市街地の西南方、桂川の右岸に位置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is located in the right bank of the Katsura-gawa River, which is south-west of the urban area of Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is located on the right bank of the Katsura-gawa River, which is south-west of the urban area of Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ward is located on the right bank of the Katsura-gawa River, which is south-west of the urban area of Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>周囲を右京区、南区 (京都市)、京都府向日市、京都府長岡京市、大阪府島本町、大阪府高槻市、京都府亀岡市に接する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has a border with the Ukyo Ward, Minami Ward (Kyoto City), the Muko City and the Nagaokakyo City, Kyoto Prefecture, the Shimamoto Town and the Takatsuki City, Osaka Prefecture, and the Kameoka City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is bordered by Ukyo Ward, Minami Ward (Kyoto City), Muko City and Nagaokakyo City, Kyoto Prefecture, Shimamoto Town Takatsuki City, Osaka Prefecture, as well as Kameoka City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It shares a border with Ukyo Ward, Minami Ward (Kyoto City), Muko City and Nagaokakyo City in Kyoto Prefecture, Shimamoto Town and Takatsuki City in Osaka Prefecture, as well as Kameoka City in Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>面積59.20平方キロメートル。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is 59.20 square km in area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is 59.20 square km in area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is 59.20 square km in area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>2009年3月現在の推計人口は約153,000人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its population is estimated about 153,000 as of March 2009.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its population is estimated to be about 153,000 as of March 2009.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its population is estimated to be about 153,000 as of March 2009.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>観光地として名高い嵐山、松尾大社のある松尾地区、桂離宮のある桂地区、勝持寺（花の寺）や大原野神社がある大原野地区は当区に属する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It includes Arashiyama, a famous sightseeing spot, the Matsuo district where the Matsuo-taisha Shrine is located, the Katsura district where the Katsura Imperial Villa is located, and the Ohara district where the Shoji-ji Temple (the Temple of Flowers) and the Oharano-jinja Shrine are located.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It includes Arashiyama, a famous sightseeing spot, the Matsuo district where the Matsuo-taisha Shrine is located, the Katsura district where the Katsura Imperial Villa is located, and the Ohara district where the Shoji-ji Temple (the Temple of Flowers) and the Oharano-jinja Shrine are located.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It includes Arashiyama, a famous sightseeing spot, the Matsuo district where the Matsuo-taisha Shrine is located, the Katsura district where the Katsura Imperial Villa is located, and the Ohara district where the Shoji-ji Temple (the Temple of Flowers) and the Oharano-jinja Shrine are located.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。ji, jinjaの前に-を入れました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>他にも苔寺として知られる西芳寺、西国札所の善峯寺などの著名社寺が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to these, there are many famous temples and shrines such as the Saiho-ji Temple (known as Koke-dera Temple) and the Yoshimine-dera Temple which is one of the temples of Saigoku fudasho (temples for pilgrimage in western Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to these, there are many famous temples and shrines such as the Saiho-ji Temple (known as Koke-dera Temple) and the Yoshimine-dera Temple which is one of the temples of Saigoku fudasho (temples for pilgrimage in western Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to these, there are many famous temples and shrines such as the Saiho-ji Temple (known as Koke-dera Temple) and the Yoshimine-dera Temple which is one of the temples of Saigoku Fudasho (temples for pilgrimage in western Japan).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。jiの前に-を入れました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>洛西ニュータウンも当区に位置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also includes Rakusai New Town.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also includes Rakusai New Town.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also covers Rakusai New Town.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>西端の外畑（とのはた）、出灰（いずりは）地区は大阪府と接している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tonohata and Izuriha districts in the western edge have a border with the Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tonohata and Izuriha districts on the western edge are bordered by Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tonohata and Izuriha districts on the western edge are bordered by Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>当区はもと右京区の一部であり、昭和51年（1976年）に桂川右岸の地域が分区して成立したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This ward was originally a part of the Ukyo Ward, and it was established by the separation of the area of the right bank of the Katsura-gawa River in 1976.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This ward was originally a part of Ukyo Ward, and it was established when the area of the right bank of the Katsura-gawa River was separated in 1976.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This ward, originally a part of Ukyo Ward, was established when the area of the right bank of the Katsura-gawa River was separated in 1976.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>区の北部から東部は昭和6年（1931年）、当時の右京区に編入された、旧葛野郡（かどのぐん）の松尾村、桂村、川岡村の区域である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The area from the northern part to the eastern part consists of the former Matsuo, Katsura and Kawaoka villages, Kadono County, which were integrated into the Ukyo Ward in 1931.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The area from the northern part to the eastern part consists of the former Matsuo, Katsura and Kawaoka villages, Kadono County, which were integrated into Ukyo Ward in 1931.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The area from the northern to the eastern part consists of the former Matsuo, Katsura and Kawaoka villages, Kadono County, which were integrated into Ukyo Ward in 1931.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>区の南部から西部はもとの乙訓郡大枝村と同郡大原野村で、前者は昭和25年（1950年）、後者は昭和34年（1959年）、当時の右京区に編入されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The area from the southern part to the western part consists of the former Oeda and Ohara villages, Otokuni County, which were integrated into the Ukyo Ward in 1950 and in 1959, respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The area from the southern part to the western part consists of the former Oeda and Ohara villages, Otokuni County, which were integrated into Ukyo Ward in 1950 and in 1959, respectively.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The area from the southern part to the western part consists of the former Oeda and Oharano villages, Otokuni County, which were integrated into Ukyo Ward in 1950 and in 1959, respectively.</e>
<cmt>地名修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>町名の概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Summary of town&apos;s names</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary of town names</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary of town names</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>京都市内の町名には「大原来迎院町」のように旧村名、旧大字名に由来する地名（上記例の場合は「大原」）を冠称するものと、「亀屋町」「菊屋町」のような単独町名とがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The town&apos;s names in the Kyoto City are categorized into the one which uses the former village name or former Oaza (larger section of village) such as &apos;Ohara Raikoin-cho&apos; (in this case, &apos;Ohara&apos;) and the one which uses an independent name of town such as &apos;Kameya-cho&apos; and &apos;Kikuya-chi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The town names in Kyoto City are categorized into ones which use the former village name or former Oaza (larger section of village) such as &apos;Ohara Raikoin-cho&apos; (in this case, &apos;Ohara&apos;) and ones which uses an independent name such as &apos;Kameya-cho&apos; and &apos;Kikuya-chi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The town names in Kyoto City are categorized into ones which use the former village name or former Oaza (larger section of village) such as &apos;Ohara Raikoin-cho&apos; (in this case, &apos;Ohara&apos;) and ones which uses an independent name such as &apos;Kameya-cho&apos; and &apos;Kikuya-cho.&apos;</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>西京区内の町名はごく一部の例外を除いて、旧大字名などの地区名を冠した複合町名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The town&apos;s names in the Nishikyo Ward all includes district&apos;s names such as former Oaza on the head with no exceptions.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The town&apos;s names in the Nishikyo Ward all includes district&apos;s names such as former Oaza on the head with no exceptions.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The town names in Nishikyo Ward all include district names such as former Oaza as a prefix.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>区内の公称町名の数は、『角川日本地名大辞典 26 京都府』下巻によれば1980年現在276町であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the second volume of &quot;the Kadokawa dictionary of the place-name of Japan, No.26 Kyoto Prefecture,&quot; there were officially two-hundred and seventy-six towns in 1980.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the second volume of &quot;the Kadokawa dictionary of the place-name of Japan, No.26 Kyoto Prefecture,&quot; there were officially two-hundred and seventy-six towns in 1980.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the second volume of &quot;Kadokawa Nihon Chimei Daijiten No. 26 Kyoto-Fu&quot; (Kadokawa dictionary of place-names of Japan, No.26 Kyoto Prefecture), the ward had two-hundred and seventy-six officially declared towns in 1980.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>その後、一部地区で土地区画整理事業実施等に伴う町名町界の変更があり、16町が新たに起立、6町が廃止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, the names and borders of some towns were changed in accordance with the implementation of land readjustment projects, and the sixteen towns were newly created and the six towns were abolished.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, the names and borders of some towns were changed in accordance with the implementation of land readjustment projects, and sixteen towns were newly created and six towns were abolished.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After 1980, the names and borders of some towns were changed in accordance with the implementation of land readjustment projects, and sixteen towns were newly created and six towns were abolished.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>2009年現在は286町となっている（大枝北沓掛町一丁目〜七丁目のように「丁目」を有するものは全体を1町と数える）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As of 2009, there are two-hundred and eighty-six towns (the towns which have the name &apos;chome&apos; such as Oeda Kitakutsukake-cho from icchome (No.1) to nanachome (No.7), are counted as one town).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As of 2009, there are two-hundred and eighty-six towns (the towns which have the name &apos;chome&apos; such as Oeda Kitakutsukake-cho from icchome (No.1) to nanachome (No.7), are counted as one town).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As of 2009, there are two-hundred and eighty-six towns (towns which have the name &apos;chome&apos; such as Oeda Kitakutsukake-cho from 1-chome to 7-chome, are counted as a town).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="18">
<j>区内には「嵐山南松尾山」「御陵南谷」のように、末尾に「町」字を付さない町名が一部に存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some towns which have no letters of &apos;cho&apos; (which means &apos;town&apos;) as a suffix, such as &apos;Arashiyama Minami Matsuoyama&apos; and &apos;Goryo Minamitani.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are some towns which have no letters of &apos;cho&apos; (which means &apos;town&apos;) as a suffix, such as &apos;Arashiyama Minami Matsuoyama&apos; and &apos;Goryo Minamitani.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are some towns which have no letter of &apos;町&apos; (read as &apos;cho&apos;, meaning town) as a suffix, such as &apos;Arashiyama Minami Matsuoyama&apos; and &apos;Goryo Minamitani.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>これらは、山間部などで、昭和6年の町名成立時において当該区域内に人家が存在しなかったものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These were the mountain area where no one lived when the town&apos;s names were established in 1931.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These were mountainous areas where no one lived when the town&apos;s names were established in 1931.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These were mountainous areas inhabited when the town&apos;s names were established in 1931.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>公称町名一覧</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The list of the official town&apos;s names</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The list of the official town&apos;s names</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The list of the official town&apos;s names</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>旧松尾村</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former Matsuo village</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Matsuo village</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Matsuo village</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>旧葛野郡松尾村は、昭和6年（1931年）京都市に編入され、当時の右京区の一部となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former Matsuo village, Kadono County, was integrated into the Kyoto City in 1931, and became a part of the Ukyo Ward in those days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Matsuo village, Kadono County, was integrated into Kyoto City in 1931, and became a part of Ukyo Ward in those days.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Matsuo village, Kadono County, was integrated into Kyoto City in 1931, and became a part of the then Ukyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>松尾村には嵐山、松室、松尾谷、下山田、御陵の5つの大字があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were the five Oaza of Arashiyama, Matsumuro, Matsuodani, Shimoyamada and Goryo in the Matsuo village.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were the five Oaza of Arashiyama, Matsumuro, Matsuodani, Shimoyamada and Goryo in the Matsuo village.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were the five Oaza in the Matsuo village: Arashiyama, Matsumuro, Matsuodani, Shimoyamada and Goryo.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>このうち、大字嵐山（旧・上山田村）は昭和6年、「嵐山」を冠称する20町に編成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among them, the Oaza Arashiyama (the former Kamiyamada village) was reorganized into twenty towns which had the name of &apos;Arashiyama&apos; on the head in 1931.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them, the Oaza Arashiyama (the former Kamiyamada village) was reorganized into twenty towns which were headed by the name &apos;Arashiyama&apos; in 1931.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them, the Oaza Arashiyama (the former Kamiyamada village) was reorganized into twenty towns which were prefixed by the name &apos;Arashiyama&apos; in 1931.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>その後、昭和20年（1945年）頃に宮町、昭和26年（1951年）に虚空蔵山町が成立し、現在は22町となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, the Miyamachi town was established in 1945 and the Kokuzoyama-cho town was established in 1951, so that there are twenty-two towns at present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, the Miyamachi town was established in 1945 and Kokuzoyama-cho town was established in 1951, leading to the current twenty-two towns.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, the Miyamachi town was established in 1945 and Kokuzoyamacho Town was established in 1951; accordingly, there are currently twenty-two towns.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="24">
<j>大字松室は昭和6年、「松室」を冠称する13町に編成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Oaza Matsumuro was reorganized into the thirteen towns which had the name of &apos;Matsumoru&apos; on the head in 1931.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oaza Matsumuro was reorganized into thirteen towns which were headed by the name &apos;Matsumoru&apos; in 1931.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oaza Matsumuro was reorganized into thirteen towns which were prefixed by the name &apos;Matsumuro&apos; in 1931.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="25">
<j>大字松尾谷は昭和6年大部分が「松尾」を冠称する9町に編成され、残余は右京区大字松尾谷となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Oaza Matsuodani was mostly reorganized into the nine towns which had the name of &apos;Matsuo&apos; on the head in 1931, and the rest became Oaza Matsuodani, Ukyo Ward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Oaza Matsuodani was mostly reorganized into nine towns which were headed by the name &apos;Matsuo&apos; in 1931, and the rest became Oaza Matsuodani, Ukyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Oaza Matsuodani was mostly reorganized into nine towns which were prefixed by the name &apos;Matsuo&apos; in 1931, and the rest became Oaza Matsuodani, Ukyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>昭和17年、松尾大利町が成立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1942, the Matsuodairi-cho town was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1942, Matsuodairi-cho town was established.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1942, Matsuodairicho Town was established.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>昭和40年（1965年）、当時の京都市内各所に残存していた「大字○○字XX」の区域はすべて「町」となり、「○○XX町」と改称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1965 the all districts which included the place-name, &apos;Oaza OOand Aza (section of village) XX,&apos; in those days were changed into &apos;town&apos; and their names were also changed into &apos;OOXX town.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1965 all districts which included the place-name, &apos;Oaza OOand Aza (section of village) XX,&apos; were changed into &apos;town&apos; and their names also changed into &apos;OOXX town.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1965, all places in Kyoto City whose names included the terms &apos;Oaza&apos; and &apos;Aza&apos; (the latter meaning a small section of a village) were renamed with the suffix &apos;cho&apos;, therefore, a place called &apos;Oaza XX Aza YY&apos; would have been renamed &apos;XXYY-cho&apos;.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。&quot;を &apos; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>この際、「大字松尾谷」として存続していた区域は松尾谷松尾山町となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, the area of &apos;Oaza Mastuodani&apos; became the Matuodani Mastuoyama-cho town.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, the area of &apos;Oaza Mastuodani&apos; became the Matuodani Mastuoyama-cho town.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, the area of &apos;Oaza Matsuodani&apos; became the Matsuodani Matsuoyamacho Town.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>以上により、現在は「松尾」を冠称する町名が10、「松尾谷」を冠称する町名が1となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Through the above process, there are now ten towns which bear the name &apos;Matsuo&apos; as a prefix and one town which has the prefix of &apos;Matsuodani.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Through the above process, there are now ten towns which bear the name &apos;Matsuo&apos; as a prefix and one town which has the prefix of &apos;Matsuodani.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Through the above process, there are now ten towns which bear the name &apos;Matsuo&apos; as a prefix and one town which has the prefix of &apos;Matsuodani.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="30">
<j>大字下山田は昭和6年大部分が「山田」を冠称する29町に編成され、残余は右京区大字下山田となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Oaza Shimoyamada was mostly reorganized into the twenty-nine towns which had the name of &apos;Yamada&apos; on the head in 1931, and the rest became the Oaza Shimoyamada, Ukyo Ward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Oaza Shimoyamada was mostly reorganized into twenty-nine towns which were headed by the name &apos;Yamada&apos; in 1931, and the rest became the Oaza Shimoyamada, Ukyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Oaza Shimoyamada was mostly reorganized into twenty-nine towns which were prefixed by the name &apos;Yamada&apos; in 1931, and the rest became the Oaza Shimoyamada, Ukyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>昭和40年（1965年）、当時の京都市内各所に残存していた「大字○○字XX」の区域はすべて「町」となり、「○○XX町」と改称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1965 the all districts which included the place-name, &apos;Oaza OOand Aza (section of village) XX,&apos; in those days were changed into &apos;town&apos; and their names were also changed into &apos;OOXX town.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1965 all districts which included the place-name, &apos;Oaza OOand Aza (section of village) XX,&apos; were changed into &apos;town&apos; and their names also changed into &apos;OOXX town.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1965, in Kyoto City, all the districts whose names included the terms &apos;Oaza&apos; and &apos;Aza&apos; (&apos;Aza&apos; means a small section of a village) were renamed with the suffix &apos;cho&apos;, so a place called &apos;Oaza XX Aza YY&apos; would have been renamed &apos;XXYY-cho&apos;.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。&quot;を &apos; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>この際、「大字下山田」として存続していた区域は下山田上園生町、下山田下園生町、下山田丁塚町、下山田地蔵山町、山田嵐山町となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, the area of &apos;Oaza Shimoyamada&apos; became the new towns such as Shimoyamada Kamisou-cho, Shimiyamada Shimosou-cho, Shimoyamada Teizuka-cho (丁塚町), Shimoyamada Jizoyama-cho and Yamada Arashiyama-cho.</e>
<cmt>丁塚町の読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, the area of &apos;Oaza Shimoyamada&apos; became the new towns of Shimoyamada Kamisou-cho, Shimiyamada Shimosou-cho, Shimoyamada Teizuka-cho (丁塚町), Shimoyamada Jizoyama-cho and Yamada Arashiyama-cho.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, the area of &apos;Oaza Shimoyamada&apos; became the new towns of Shimoyamada Kamisoucho, Shimoyamada Shimosoucho, Shimoyamada Teizukacho, Shimoyamada Jizoyamacho and Yamada Arashiyama-cho.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>以上により、現在は「山田」を冠称する町名が10、「下山田」を冠称する町名が4となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Through the above process, there are ten towns which have the name of &apos;Yamada&apos; on the head and four towns which have the name of &apos;Shimoyamada&apos; on the head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Through the above process, there are now ten towns which have the name of &apos;Yamada&apos; and four towns which have the name of &apos;Shimoyamada&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Through the above process, there are now ten towns which bear the prefix of &apos;Yamada&apos; and four towns which bear the prefix of &apos;Shimoyamada.&apos;</e>
<cmt>スペース削除ピリオドの位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="34">
<j>大字御陵は昭和6年、「御陵」を冠称する16町に編成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Oaza Goryo was reorganized into the sixteen towns which had the name of &apos;Goryo&apos; on the head in 1931.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Oaza Goryo was reorganized into sixteen towns which were headed by the name &apos;Goryo&apos; in 1931.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Oaza Goryo was reorganized into sixteen towns which were prefixed by the name &apos;Goryo&apos; in 1931.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>桂坂ニュータウン開発に伴い、昭和61年、御陵北大枝山町、御陵大枝山町一丁目〜六丁目、御陵峰ケ堂町一丁目〜三丁目が成立し、19町となっている（「丁目」を有するものは全体を1町と数える）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In accordance with the development of Katsurazaka New Town, Goryo Kitaoedayama-cho, Goryo Oedayama-cho from icchome to rokuchome (No.1-6 chome), and Goryo Minegado-cho from icchome to sanchome (No.1-3 chome) were established in 1986, so that there are nineteen towns at present (the towns which have the name &apos;chome&apos; are counted as one town).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In accordance with the development of Katsurazaka New Town, Goryo Kitaoedayama-cho, Goryo Oedayama-cho from icchome to rokuchome (No.1-6 chome), and Goryo Minegado-cho from icchome to sanchome (No.1-3 chome) were established in 1986, so that there are nineteen towns at present (the towns which have the name &apos;chome&apos; are counted as one town).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In accordance with the development of Katsurazaka New Town, Goryo Kitaoedayamacho, Goryo Oedayamacho from 1-chome to 6-chome, and Goryo Minegadocho from 1-chome to 3-chome were established in 1986, therefore, that there are now nineteen towns at present (the towns which have the name &apos;chome&apos; are counted as one town).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>なお、西京区の「御陵」は「ごりょう」と読むが、山科区の「御陵」は「みささぎ」と読む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Chinese character &apos;御陵&apos; in the Nishikyo Ward is pronounced as &apos;Goryo,&apos; but the one in the Yamashina Ward is pronounced as &apos;Misasagi.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Chinese character &apos;御陵&apos; in Nishikyo Ward is pronounced as &apos;Goryo,&apos; but the one in Yamashina Ward is pronounced as &apos;Misasagi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">御陵&apos; in Nishikyo Ward is read as &apos;Goryo,&apos; but the one in Yamashina Ward is read as &apos;Misasagi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="37">
<j>上記のほか、平成15年（2003年）には御陵地区と山田地区にまたがって新町名「京都大学桂」が起立されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to this, a new town, &apos;Kyotodaigaku Katsura&apos; was created in the districts of Goryo and Yamada in 2003.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to this, a new town, &apos;Kyotodaigaku Katsura&apos; was created in the districts of Goryo and Yamada in 2003.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to this, a new town, &apos;Kyotodaigaku Katsura&apos; was created in the districts of Goryo and Yamada in 2003.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>旧桂村</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former Katsura village</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Katsura village</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Katsura village</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="38">
<j>旧葛野郡桂村は、昭和6年京都市に編入され、当時の右京区の一部となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former Katsura village, Kadono County, was integrated into the Kyoto City in 1931, and became a part of the Ukyo Ward in those days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Katsura village, Kadono County, was integrated into Kyoto City in 1931, and in those days became a part of Ukyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Katsura village, Kadono County, was integrated into Kyoto City in 1931, and became a part of the then Ukyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>桂村には下桂、上桂、千代原、徳大寺、上野（かみの）の5つの大字があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were the five Oaza of Shimokatsura, Kamikatsura, Chiyohara, Tokudaiji and Kamino in the Katsura village.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were five Oaza: Shimokatsura, Kamikatsura, Chiyohara, Tokudaiji and Kamino in the Katsura village.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were five Oaza: Shimokatsura, Kamikatsura, Chiyohara, Tokudaiji and Kamino in the Katsura village.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>このうち、大字下桂は昭和6年、「桂」を冠称する16町に編成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among them, the Oaza Shimokatsura was reorganized into the sixteen towns which had the name of &apos;Katsura&apos; on the head in 1931.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them, the Oaza Shimokatsura was reorganized into sixteen towns which were headed by the name &apos;Katsura&apos; in 1931.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them, the Oaza Shimokatsura was reorganized into sixteen towns which were prefixed by the name &apos;Katsura&apos; in 1931.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="41">
<j>大字上桂は昭和6年、「上桂」を冠称する15町に編成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Oaza Kamikatsura was reorganized into the fifteen towns which had the name of &apos;Kamikatsura&apos; on the head in 1931.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Oaza Kamikatsura was reorganized into fifteen towns which were headed by the name &apos;Kamikatsura&apos; in 1931.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Oaza Kamikatsura was reorganized into fifteen towns which were prefixed by the name &apos;Kamikatsura&apos; in 1931.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="42">
<j>大字千代原は昭和6年、「桂」を冠称する5町（千代原町、乾町、艮町、巽町、坤町）に編成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Oaza Chiyohara was reorganized into the five towns which had the name of &apos;Katsura&apos; on the head in 1931 (Chiyohara-cho, Inui-cho, Ushitora-cho, Tatsumi-cho and Hitsujisaru-cho).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Oaza Chiyohara was reorganized into five towns which were headed by the name &apos;Katsura&apos; in 1931 (Chiyohara-cho, Inui-cho, Ushitora-cho, Tatsumi-cho and Hitsujisaru-cho).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Oaza Chiyohara was reorganized into five towns which were prefixed by the name &apos;Katsura&apos; in 1931 (Chiyoharacho, Inuicho, Ushitoracho, Tatsumicho and Hitsujisaru-cho).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="43">
<j>大字徳大寺は昭和6年、「桂」を冠称する5町（河田町、後水町、畑ケ田町、大縄町、徳大寺町）及び徳大寺清水町（「桂」の冠称なし）の計6町に編成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Oaza Tokudaiji was reorganized into the six towns including the five towns which had the name of &apos;Katsura&apos; on the head (Kawada-cho, Kozu-cho, Hatekeda-cho, Onawa-cho and Tokudaiji-cho) and the Tokudaiji Shimizu-cho town (without the name of &apos;Katsura&apos; on the head) in 1931.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Oaza Tokudaiji was reorganized into six towns including the five towns which were headed by the name &apos;Katsura&apos; (Kawada-cho, Kozu-cho, Hatekeda-cho, Onawa-cho and Tokudaiji-cho) and the Tokudaiji Shimizu-cho town (without the name of &apos;Katsura&apos;) in 1931.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Oaza Tokudaiji was reorganized into six towns including five towns which were prefixed by the name &apos;Katsura&apos; (Kawadacho, Kozucho, Hatakedacho, Onawacho and Tokudaiji-cho) and the Tokudaiji Shimizucho Town (without the name of &apos;Katsura&apos;) in 1931.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="44">
<j>大字上野は昭和6年、「桂上野」を冠称する8町に編成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Oaza Kamino was reorganized into the eight towns which had the name of &apos;Katsurakamino&apos; on the head in 1931.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Oaza Kamino was reorganized into eight towns which were headed by the name &apos;Katsurakamino&apos; in 1931.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Oaza Kamino was reorganized into eight towns which were prefixed by the name &apos;Katsurakamino&apos; in 1931.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="45">
<j>その後、土地区画整理事業実施等に伴う以下のような町名町界の変更があり、「桂」を冠称する町名は33、「桂上野」を冠称する町名は8、、「上桂」を冠称する町名は15、計56となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, the names and borders of some towns were changed in accordance with the implementation of land readjustment projects as follows, and there are fifty-six towns in total including the thirty-three towns which have the name of &apos;Katsura&apos; on the head, the eight towns which have the name of &apos;Katsurakamino&apos; on the head and the fifteen towns which have the name of &apos;Kamikatsura&apos; on the head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, the names and borders of some towns were changed in accordance with the implementation of land readjustment projects as follows, and there are fifty-six towns in total including the thirty-three towns which have the name of &apos;Katsura&apos;, eight towns which have the name of &apos;Katsurakamino&apos; and fifteen towns which have the name of &apos;Kamikatsura&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, the names and borders of some towns were changed in accordance with the implementation of land readjustment projects as follows, and there are fifty-six towns in total including the thirty-three towns which are prefixed by the name of &apos;Katsura,&apos; eight towns which are prefixed by the name of &apos;Katsurakamino&apos; and fifteen towns which are prefixed by the name of &apos;Kamikatsura.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="46">
<j>（昭和23年成立）南巽町</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(established in 1947) Minamitatsumi-cho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(established in 1947) Minamitatsumi-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(established in 1947) Minamitatsumi-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>（平成3年成立）北・南・西滝川町</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(established in 1991) Kitatakigawa-cho, Minamitakigawa-cho, Nishitakigawa-cho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(established in 1991) Kitatakigawa-cho, Minamitakigawa-cho, Nishitakigawa-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(established in 1991) Kitatakigawa-cho, Minamitakigawa-cho, Nishitakigawa-cho</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。-choに統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>（平成17年成立）徳大寺北・南・東町</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(established in 2005) Tokudaijikita-cho, Tokudaijiminami-cho and Tokudaijihigashi-cho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(established in 2005) Tokudaijikita-cho, Tokudaijiminami-cho and Tokudaijihigashi-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(established in 2005) Tokudaijikitacho, Tokudaijiminamicho and Tokudaijihigashi-cho</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>（平成17年廃止）徳大寺清水町（「桂」の冠称なし）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(abolished in 2005) Tokudaiji Shimizu-cho (without the name of &apos;Katsura&apos; on the head)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(abolished in 2005) Tokudaiji Shimizu-cho (without the name of &apos;Katsura&apos; on the head)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(abolished in 2005) Tokudaiji Shimizu-cho (without the name of &apos;Katsura&apos; on the head)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>旧川岡村</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former Kawaoka village</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Kawaoka village</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Kawaoka village</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="50">
<j>旧葛野郡川岡村は、昭和6年（1931年）京都市に編入され、当時の右京区の一部となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former Kawaoka village, Kadono County, was integrated into the Kyoto City in 1931, and became a part of the Ukyo Ward in those days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Kawaoka village, Kadono County, was integrated into Kyoto City in 1931, and became a part of Ukyo Ward in those days.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Kawaoka village, Kadono County, was integrated into Kyoto City in 1931, and became a part of the then Ukyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>川岡村には牛ケ瀬、下津林、川島、樫原（かたぎはら）の4つの大字があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were the four Oaza of Ushigase, Simotsubayashi, Kawashima and Katagihara in the Kawaoka village.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were four Oaza in the Kawaoka village consisting of Ushigase, Simotsubayashi, Kawashima and Katagihara.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were four Oaza in the Kawaoka village consisting of Ushigase, Simotsubayashi, Kawashima and Katagihara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>このうち、大字牛ケ瀬は昭和6年、「牛ケ瀬」を冠称する20町に編成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among them, the Oaza Ushigase was reorganized into the twenty towns which had the name of &apos;Ushigase&apos; on the head in 1931.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them, the Oaza Ushigase was reorganized into twenty towns which were prefixed by the name &apos;Ushigase&apos; in 1931.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them, the Oaza Ushigase was reorganized into twenty towns which were prefixed by the name &apos;Ushigase&apos; in 1931.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>その後、土地区画整理事業実施に伴う以下のような町名町界の変更があり、「牛ケ瀬」を冠称する町名は計15となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, the names and borders of some towns were changed in accordance with the implementation of land readjustment projects as follows, and there are fifteen towns which have the name of &apos;Ushigase&apos; on the head at present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, the names and borders of some towns were changed in accordance with the implementation of land readjustment projects as follows, and there are fifteen towns which have the name of &apos;Ushigase&apos; at present.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, the names and borders of some towns were changed in accordance with the implementation of land readjustment projects to be mentioned later, therefore, there are fifteen towns which are prefixed by the name of &apos;Ushigase&apos; at present.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="54">
<j>（平成3年廃止）西ノ口町、桃ノ木町、長瀬、車ケ瀬、鮫呼、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(abolished in 1991) Nishinokuchi-cho, Momonoki-cho, Nagase, Kurumagase, and Sameko (鮫呼)</e>
<cmt>鮫呼の読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(abolished in 1991) Nishinokuchi-cho, Momonoki-cho, Nagase, Kurumagase, and Sameko (鮫呼)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(abolished in 1991) Nishinokuchi-cho, Momonoki-cho, Nagase, Kurumagase, and Sameko</e>
<cmt>(鮫呼)削除→読み方不明です。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>（平成3年改称）奥ノ防→奥ノ防町、林ノ本→林ノ本町、西柿→西柿町、堂田→堂田町、新田泓→新田泓町</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(changed the names in 1991) Okunobo=&gt;Okunobo-cho, Hayashinomoto=&gt;Hayashinomoto-cho, Nishigaki=&gt;Nishigaki-cho, Doden=&gt;Doden-cho, and Shindenbuke=&gt;Shindenbuke-cho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(changed the names in 1991) Okunobo=&gt;Okunobo-cho, Hayashinomoto=&gt;Hayashinomoto-cho, Nishigaki=&gt;Nishigaki-cho, Doden=&gt;Doden-cho, and Shindenbuke=&gt;Shindenbuke-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(the names were changed in 1991) Okunobo=&gt;Okunobo-cho, Hayashinomoto=&gt;Hayashinomoto-cho, Nishigaki=&gt;Nishigaki-cho, Doden=&gt;Doden-cho, and Shindenbuke=&gt;Shindenbuke-cho</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="56">
<j>大字下津林は昭和6年、「下津林」を冠称する12町に編成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Oaza Shimotsubayashi was reorganized into the twelve towns which had the name of &apos;Shimotsubayashi&apos; on the head in 1931.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Oaza Shimotsubayashi was reorganized into twelve towns which were prefixed by the name &apos;Shimotsubayashi&apos; in 1931.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Oaza Shimotsubayashi was reorganized into twelve towns which were prefixed by the name &apos;Shimotsubayashi&apos; in 1931.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>その後、土地区画整理事業実施に伴う以下のような町名町界の変更があり、「下津林」を冠称する町名は計17となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, the names and borders of some towns were changed in accordance with the implementation of land readjustment projects as follows, and there are seventeen towns which have the name of &apos;Shimotsubayashi&apos; on the head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, the names and borders of some towns were changed in accordance with the implementation of land readjustment projects as follows, and there are seventeen towns which have the name of &apos;Shimotsubayashi&apos;.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, the names and borders of some towns were changed in accordance with the implementation of land readjustment projects to be mentioned later, therefore, there are seventeen towns which are prefixed by the name &apos;Shimotsubayashi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="58">
<j>（平成3年成立）東・南大般若町、番条町、南中島町、東芝ノ宮町</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(established in 1991) Higashi Daihannya-cho, Minami Daihannya-cho, Banjo-cho, Minaminakajima-cho, Higashishibanomiya-cho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(established in 1991) Higashi Daihannya-cho, Minami Daihannya-cho, Banjo-cho, Minaminakajima-cho, Higashishibanomiya-cho</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(established in 1991) Higashi Daihannya-cho, Minami Daihannya-cho, Banjo-cho, Minaminakajima-cho, Higashishibanomiya-cho</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。-choに統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>（平成3年改称）中島→中島町、芝ノ宮→芝ノ宮町</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(changed the names) Nakajima=&gt;Nakajima-cho, Shibanomiya=&gt;Shibanomiya-cho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(changed the names) Nakajima=&gt;Nakajima-cho, Shibanomiya=&gt;Shibanomiya-cho</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(the names were changed in 1991) Nakajima=&gt;Nakajima-cho, Shibanomiya=&gt;Shibanomiya-cho</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>なお、「下津林番条」（昭和6年成立）と「下津林番条町」（平成3年成立）はともに存続している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, both &apos;Shimotsubayshi Banjo&apos; (established in 1931) and &apos;Shimotsubayashi Banjo-cho&apos; (established in 1991) have existed now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, both &apos;Shimotsubayshi Banjo&apos; (established in 1931) and &apos;Shimotsubayashi Banjo-cho&apos; (established in 1991) have existed now.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both &apos;Shimotsubayashi Banjo&apos; (established in 1931) and &apos;Shimotsubayashi Banjo-cho&apos; (established in 1991) still exist.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="61">
<j>大字川島は昭和6年、「川島」を冠称する16町に編成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Oaza Kawashima was reorganized into the sixteen towns which had the name of &apos;Kawashima&apos; on the head in 1931.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Oaza Kawashima was reorganized into sixteen towns which were headed by the name &apos;Kawashima&apos; in 1931.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Oaza Kawashima was reorganized into sixteen towns which were prefixed by the name &apos;Kawashima&apos; in 1931.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>その後、以下の町名新設があり、「川島」を冠称する町名は計21となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, the following towns were newly created, and there are twenty-one towns in total which were prefixed by the name of &apos;Kawashima&apos; on the head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, the following towns were newly created, and there are twenty-one towns in total which were prefixed by the name of &apos;Kawashima&apos; on the head.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, the following towns were newly created, and there are twenty-one towns in total which were prefixed by the name of &apos;Kawashima&apos;.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="63">
<j>（昭和23年成立）有栖川町</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(established in 1948) Arisugawa-cho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(established in 1948) Arisugawa-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(established in 1948) Arisugawa-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>（昭和39年成立）竹園町、松園町</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(established in 1964) Takezono-cho, Matsuzono-cho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(established in 1964) Takezono-cho, Matsuzono-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(established in 1964) Takezono-cho, Matsuzono-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>（昭和40年成立）梅園町、桜園町</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(established in 1965) Umezono-cho, Sakurazono-cho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(established in 1965) Umezono-cho, Sakurazono-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(established in 1965) Umezono-cho, Sakurazono-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="66">
<j>大字樫原は昭和6年、「樫原」を冠称する47町に編成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Oaza Katagihara was reorganized into the forty-seven towns which had the name of &apos;Katagihara&apos; on the head in 1931.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Oaza Katagihara was reorganized into forty-seven towns which were headed by the name &apos;Katagihara&apos; in 1931.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Oaza Katagihara was reorganized into forty-seven towns which were prefixed by the name &apos;Katagihara&apos; in 1931.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>旧大枝村、大原野村</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former Oeda village and Oharano village</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Oeda village and Oharano village</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Oeda village and Oharano village</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="67">
<j>旧乙訓郡大枝村は、昭和25年（1950年）京都市に編入され、当時の右京区の一部となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former Oeda village, Otokuni County, was integrated into the Kyoto City in 1950 and became a part of the Ukyo Ward in those days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Oeda village, Otokuni County, was integrated into the Kyoto City in 1950 and became a part of the Ukyo Ward in those days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Oeda village, Otokuni County, was integrated into the Kyoto City in 1950 and became a part of the then Ukyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>大枝村には沓掛、塚原、長野新田の3つの大字があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were the three Oaza of Kutsukake, Tsukahara and Naganoshinden in the Oeda village.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were the three Oaza: Kutsukake, Tsukahara and Naganoshinden in the Oeda village.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were three Oaza: Kutsukake, Tsukahara and Naganoshinden in the Oeda village.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>このうち、大字沓掛は大枝沓掛町、大字塚原は大枝塚原町となり、大字長野新田は大枝東長町、大枝西長町、大枝中山町の3町に編成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among them, the Oaza Kutsukake was reorganized into Oeda Kutsukake-cho, the Oaza Tsukahara was into Oeda tsukahara-cho, and the Oaza Naganoshinden was into the three towns of Oeda Higashinaga-cho, Oeda Nishinaga-cho and Oeda Nakayama-cho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them, Oaza Kutsukake was reorganized into Oeda Kutsukake-cho, Oaza Tsukahara into Oeda tsukahara-cho, and Oaza Naganoshinden into the three towns of Oeda Higashinaga-cho, Oeda Nishinaga-cho and Oeda Nakayama-cho.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them, Oaza Kutsukake was reorganized into Oeda Kutsukake-cho, Oaza Tsukahara into Oeda tsukahara-cho, and Oaza Naganoshinden into the three towns of Oeda Higashinaga-cho, Oeda Nishinaga-cho and Oeda Nakayama-cho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>その後洛西ニュータウン、桂坂ニュータウンの開発に伴い、以下の町名が新設され、「大枝」を冠称する町名は計10となっている（「丁目」を有するものは全体を1町と数える）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, in accordance with the development of Rakusai New Town and Katsurazaka New Town, the following towns were newly created and there are ten towns in total which have the name of &apos;Oeda&apos; on the head (the towns which have the name &apos;chome&apos; are counted as one town).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, in accordance with the development of Rakusai New Town and Katsurazaka New Town, the following towns were newly created and there are ten towns in total which have the name of &apos;Oeda&apos; on the head (the towns which have the name &apos;chome&apos; are counted as one town).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, in accordance with the development of Rakusai New Town and Katsurazaka New Town, the following towns were newly created and there are ten towns in total which have the name of &apos;Oeda&apos; (towns which have the name &apos;chome&apos; are counted as a town).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="71">
<j>（昭和50年成立）西新林町一丁目〜六丁目、東新林町一丁目〜三丁目、北福西町一丁目〜四丁目、南福西町一丁目〜三丁目</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(established in 1975) Nishishinbayashi-cho from icchome to rokuchome, Higashishinbayashi-cho from icchome to sanchome, Kitahukunisi-cho from icchome to yonchome (No.1-4 chome), and Minamifukunishi-cho from icchome to sanchome.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(established in 1975) Nishishinbayashi-cho from icchome to rokuchome, Higashishinbayashi-cho from icchome to sanchome, Kitahukunisi-cho from icchome to yonchome (No.1-4 chome), and Minamifukunishi-cho from icchome to sanchome.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(established in 1975) Nishishinbayashi-cho from 1-chome to 6-chome, Higashishinbayashi-cho from 1-chome to 3-chome, Kitafukunisi-cho from 1-chome to 4-chome, and Minamifukunishi-cho from 1-chome to 3-chome.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>（昭和61年成立）北沓掛町一丁目〜七丁目</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(established in 1986) Kitakutsukake-cho from icchome to nanachome</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(established in 1986) Kitakutsukake-cho from icchome to nanachome</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(established in 1986) Kitakutsukake-cho from 1-chome to 7-chome.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="73">
<j>旧乙訓郡大原野村は、昭和34年（1959年）京都市に編入され、当時の右京区の一部となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former Oharano village, Otokuni County, was integrated into the Kyoto City in 1959 and became a part of the Ukyo Ward in those days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Oharano village, Otokuni County, was integrated into Kyoto City in 1959 and became a part of Ukyo Ward in those days.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Oharano village, Otokuni County, was integrated into Kyoto City in 1959 and became a part of the then Ukyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>大原野村には大原野、石見上里（いわみかみざと）、上羽（うえば）、灰方、小塩、石作、出灰（いずりは）、外畑（とのはた）の8の大字があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were the eight Oaza of Oharano, Iwamikamizato, Ueba, Haikata, Oshio, Ishizukuri, Izuriha and Tonohata in the Oharano village.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were the eight Oaza: Oharano, Iwamikamizato, Ueba, Haikata, Oshio, Ishizukuri, Izuriha and Tonohata in the Oharano village.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were the eight Oaza: Oharano, Iwamikamizato, Ueba, Haikata, Oshio, Ishizukuri, Izuriha and Tonohata in the Oharano village.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>このうち、大字大原野は大原野北春日町、大原野南春日町の2町に、大字石見上里は大原野石見町、大原野上里上ノ町、大原野上里下ノ町の3町に編成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among them, the Oaza Oharano was reorganized into the two towns of Oharano Kitakasuga-cho and Oharano Minamikasuga-cho, and the Oaza Iwamikamizato was reorganized into the three towns of Oharano Iwami-cho, Oharano Kamizato Kamino-cho and Oharano Kamizato Shimono-cho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them, Oaza Oharano was reorganized into the two towns of Oharano Kitakasuga-cho and Oharano Minamikasuga-cho, Oaza Iwamikamizato was reorganized into the three towns of Oharano Iwami-cho, Oharano Kamizato Kamino-cho and Oharano Kamizato Shimono-cho.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them, Oaza Oharano was reorganized into the two towns of Oharano Kitakasuga-cho and Oharano Minamikasuga-cho, Oaza Iwamikamizato was reorganized into the three towns of Oharano Iwami-cho, Oharano Kamizato Kamino-cho and Oharano Kamizato Shimono-cho.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>残余の6大字はそれぞれ大原野上羽町、大原野灰方町、大原野小塩町、大原野石作町、大原野出灰町、大原野外畑町となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The rest six Oaza became Oharano Ueba-cho, Oharano Haikata-cho, Oharano Oshio-cho, Oharano Ishizukuri-cho, Oharano Izuriha-cho and Oharano Tonohata-cho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The remaining six Oaza became Oharano Ueba-cho, Oharano Haikata-cho, Oharano Oshio-cho, Oharano Ishizukuri-cho, Oharano Izuriha-cho and Oharano Tonohata-cho.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The remaining six Oaza became Oharano Ueba-cho, Oharano Haikata-cho, Oharano Oshio-cho, Oharano Ishizukuri-cho, Oharano Izuriha-cho and Oharano Tonohata-cho.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。-choに統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>その後洛西ニュータウン等の宅地開発に伴い、以下の町名が新設され、「大原野」を冠称する町名は計10となっている（「丁目」を有するものは全体を1町と数える）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, in accordance with the housing land development such as Rakusai New Town, the following towns were newly created and there are ten towns in total which are prefixed by the name &apos;Oharano&apos; (the towns which have the name &apos;chome&apos; are counted as one town).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, in accordance with the housing land development such as Rakusai New Town, the following towns were newly created and there are ten towns in total which are prefixed by the name &apos;Oharano&apos; (the towns which have the name &apos;chome&apos; are counted as one town).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, in accordance with the housing land development such as Rakusai New Town, the following towns were newly created and there are ten towns in total which are prefixed by the name &apos;Oharano&apos; (the towns which have the name &apos;chome&apos; are counted as one town).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="78">
<j>（昭和41年成立）上里男鹿町、上里勝山町、上里鳥見町、上里紅葉町</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(established in 1966) Kamizato Ojika-cho, Kamizato Katsuyama-cho, Katsuyama Torimi-cho and Kamizato Momiji-cho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(established in 1966) Kamizato Ojika-cho, Kamizato Katsuyama-cho, Katsuyama Torimi-cho and Kamizato Momiji-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(established in 1966) Kamizato Ojika-cho, Kamizato Katsuyama-cho, Kamizato Torimi-cho and Kamizato Momiji-cho</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>（昭和50年成立）西境谷町一丁目〜四丁目、東境谷町一丁目〜三丁目、西竹の里町一丁目〜二丁目、東竹の里町一丁目〜四丁目</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(established in 1975) Nishisakaidani-cho from icchome to yonchome, Higashisakaidani-cho from icchome to sanchome, Nishitakenosato-cho icchome and nichome and Higashi Tekenosato-cho from icchome to yonchome</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(established in 1975) Nishisakaidani-cho from icchome to yonchome, Higashisakaidani-cho from icchome to sanchome, Nishitakenosato-cho icchome and nichome and Higashi Tekenosato-cho from icchome to yonchome</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(established in 1975) Nishisakaidani-cho from 1-chome to 4-chome, Higashisakaidani-cho from 1-chome to 3-chome, Nishitakenosato-cho 1-chome and 2-chome and Higashitakenosato-cho from 1-chome to 4-chome.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。-choに統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>（昭和51年成立）東野町</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(established in 1976) Higashino-cho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(established in 1976) Higashino-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(established in 1976) Higashino-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>備考</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Remarks</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Remarks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Remarks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="81">
<j>山田鈴ケ尾、山田林、山田高尾、下山田地蔵山町、山田嵐山町</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamada Suzugao, Yamada Hayashi, Yamada Takao, Shimoyamada Jizoyama-cho, Yamada Arashiyama-cho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamada Suzugao, Yamada Hayashi, Yamada Takao, Shimoyamada Jizoyama-cho, Yamada Arashiyama-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamada Suzugao, Yamada Hayashi, Yamada Takao, Shimoyamada Jizoyama-cho, Yamada Arashiyama-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>- 以上は地図にみえない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These are not seen on a map.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These are not seen on any map.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These are not shown on any map.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>『角川日本地名大辞典 26 京都府』では山間部に位置する無人町とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the second volume of &quot;the Kadokawa dictionary of the place-name of Japan, No.26 Kyoto Prefecture&quot; (&apos;Kadokawa&apos; in bellow), they are the mountain area where no one lives.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the second volume of &quot;the Kadokawa dictionary of the place-name of Japan, No.26 Kyoto Prefecture&quot; (&apos;Kadokawa&apos; in bellow), they are mountainous areas where no one lives.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the second volume of &quot;Kadokawa Nihon Chimei Daijiten No. 26 Kyoto-Fu&quot; (Kadokawa dictionary of place-names of Japan, No.26 Kyoto Prefecture), they are mountainous areas uninhabited.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Ash(id:15625), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>