<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>元子女王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Princess Genshi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Princess Genshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Princess Genshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>元子女王（げんし（もとこ）じょおう、生没年不詳）は、平安時代前期の皇族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Princess Genshi (Motoko) (date of birth and death unknown) was a member of the imperial family in the first half of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Princess Genshi (Motoko) (date of birth and death unknown) was a member of the imperial family during the first half of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Princess Genshi (also known a Motoko) (year of birth and death unknown) was a member of the Imperial Family during the first half of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>also known a 補足用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>伊勢斎宮。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ise Saigu (vestal virgin princess serving at Ise-jingu Shrine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ise Saigu (vestal virgin princess serving at Ise-jingu Shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ise Saigu (vestal virgin princess serving at Ise-jingu Shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>仁明天皇の皇孫で、本康親王の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was an imperial descendant of Emperor Ninmyo, and was a daughter of Imperial Prince Motoyasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was an imperial descendant of Emperor Ninmyo, and was a daughter of Imperial Prince Motoyasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was an imperial descendant of Emperor Ninmyo, and was a daughter of Imperial Prince Motoyasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>兄弟に源兼似らがいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">源兼似 is one of her siblings.</e>
<cmt>源兼似→読み方不明のため原文のままとしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">源兼似 was one of her siblings.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">源兼似 was one of her siblings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>繁子内親王（光孝天皇皇女）の退下を受けて、寛平元年（889年）2月に従兄弟宇多天皇の斎宮に卜定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ａｆｔｅｒ Imperial Princess Hanshi (princess of Emperor Koko) resigned, she was designated as Saigu (Imperial Princess appointed to serve the deities of the Ise-jingu Shrine) of her cousin, Emperor Uda by bokujo (to decide by fortunetelling) in February 889.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ａｆｔｅｒ Imperial Princess Hanshi (princess of Emperor Koko) resigned, she was designated as Saigu (Imperial Princess appointed to serve the deities of the Ise-jingu Shrine) of her cousin, Emperor Uda by bokujo (decided by fortunetelling) in February 889.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ａｆｔｅｒ Imperial Princess Hanshi (princess of Emperor Koko) resigned, she was designated as Saigu (Imperial Princess appointed to serve the deities of the Ise-jingu Shrine) of her cousin, Emperor Uda by bokujo (decided by fortunetelling) in March 889.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>同年9月御禊。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September 889, she went through misogi (purification ceremony).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September 889, she went through misogi (purification ceremony).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October 889, she went through misogi (purification ceremony).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>寛平2年9月野宮に入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September 890, she entered into Nonomiya (Field Palace).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September 890, she entered Nonomiya (Field Palace).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September 890, she entered Nonomiya (Field Palace).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>寛平3年（991年）9月伊勢に下向し、寛平9年退下した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September 991, she went down to Ise, and resigned the post in Ise in 997.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September 991, she went down to Ise, and resigned her post in Ise in 997.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October 991, she went down to Ise, and resigned her post in Ise in 997.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その後の消息は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nothing was heard of her after that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nothing was heard of her after that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nothing was heard of her after that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), YOSHI438(id:174755), Tribot(id:186681), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>