<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原茂子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Moshi</e>
<cmt>翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 茂子（ふじわら の もし/しげこ、生年不詳 - 康平5年6月22日 (旧暦)（1062年7月30日））は、第71代後三条天皇の皇太子時代の妃、第72代白河天皇生母。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Moshi/Shigeko (the birth year is unknown - July 30, 1062) was the Empress of the seventy second Emperor Gosanjo while he was Crown Prince, and Emperor Shirakawa&apos;s birth mother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Moshi/Shigeko (the birth year is unknown - July 30, 1062) was the Empress of the seventy second Emperor Gosanjo while he was Crown Prince, and Emperor Shirakawa&apos;s birth mother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Moshi (Shigeko) (the birth year is unknown - August 5, 1062) was the Empress of the 71st Emperor Gosanjo while he was Crown Prince, and 72nd Emperor Shirakawa&apos;s birth mother.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。一部翻訳を追加・修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>中納言藤原公成の娘で、大納言藤原能信の養女となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was Chunagon (middle counselor), FUJIWARA no Kinnari&apos;s daughter and was adopted by a chief councilor of state, FUJIWARA no Yoshinobu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was Chunagon (middle counselor), FUJIWARA no Kinnari&apos;s daughter and was adopted by a chief councilor of state, FUJIWARA no Yoshinobu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was a daughter of Chunagon (vice-councilor of state), FUJIWARA no Kinnari and was adopted by Dainagon (chief councilor of state), FUJIWARA no Yoshinobu.</e>
<cmt>大納言、中納言　の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は藤原知光女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her mother was FUJIWARA no Tomomitsu&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her mother was FUJIWARA no Tomomitsu&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her mother was FUJIWARA no Tomomitsu&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>別名は・滋野井御息所。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was also called Shigenoi Miyasudokoro. (consort of the emperor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was also called Shigenoi Miyasudokoro. (consort of the emperor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was also called Shigenoi Miyasudokoro (consort of the emperor).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを括弧の後に移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>実父公成の姉妹藤原祉子が能信の妻であったことから、子のなかった能信夫妻の養女として引き取られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since her father, Kinnari&apos;s sister, FUJIWARA no Yoshiko was Yoshinobu&apos;s wife, Moshi/Shigeko was adopted by Yoshinobu and his wife.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since her father, Kinnari&apos;s sister, FUJIWARA no Yoshiko was Yoshinobu&apos;s wife, Moshi/Shigeko was adopted by Yoshinobu and his wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since her father, Kinnari&apos;s sister, FUJIWARA no Yoshiko was Yoshinobu&apos;s wife, Moshi was adopted by Yoshinobu and his wife.</e>
<cmt>ここではMoshi のみで表記し、Shigekoは削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>永承元年（1046年）、皇太子尊仁親王（後三条天皇）の副臥として入内。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1046, she made judai (an Imperial Consort&apos;s bridal entry into court) to Crown Prince, Imperial Prince Takahito as 副臥.</e>
<cmt>副臥→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1046, she made judai (an Imperial Consort&apos;s bridal entry into court) to Crown Prince, Imperial Prince Takahito as 副臥.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1046, she entered into court to marry Crown Prince Takahito (Emperor Gosanjo) as Soibushi (a lady who acts as a companion of a high-ranking person when he celebrates his coming-of-age ceremony).</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を追加・変更しました。副臥→Soibushi (a lady who acts as a companion of a high-ranking person when he celebrates his coming-of-age ceremony)　としました（参考：http://takonet.com/y_jiten.html）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>この時尊仁親王の異母兄後冷泉天皇はまだ若く、しかも尊仁親王とその母禎子内親王は関白藤原頼通と対立していたこともあって、はかばかしい後見のない皇太子に娘を入内させる公卿はいなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this occasion, under the circumstance of Imperial Prince Takahito&apos;s half older brother, Emperor Goreizei was still young, and there was a conflict between Imperial Prince and his mother, Imperial Princess Teishi and Kanpaku(chief adviser to the Emperor), FUJIWARA no Yorimichi, there was no other court nobles who would wish to send their daughters to the palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this occasion, under the circumstances of Imperial Prince Takahito&apos;s half older brother, Emperor Goreizei being still young, and the conflict between Imperial Prince and his mother, Imperial Princess Teishi and Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor), FUJIWARA no Yorimichi, there were no other court nobles who would wish to send their daughters to the palace.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this occasion, under the circumstances of Imperial Prince Takahito&apos;s older paternal half-brother, Emperor Goreizei being still young, and the conflict between Imperial Prince and his mother, Imperial Princess Teishi and Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor), FUJIWARA no Yorimichi, there were no other court nobles who would wish to send their daughters to the palace.</e>
<cmt>異母兄　表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>そのため能信が妻の姪にあたる養女茂子を妃に入れたのだが、いくら能信の養女でも実父が中納言では、東宮妃にはふさわしくないと非難されている（また、当時養女を妃に入れたのは最高実力者であった頼通のみであり、能信がそれを行うのは不相応であるという意味合いがあったとも言われている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the above background, Yoshinobu send his wife&apos;s nephew, and also his adopted daughter, Moshi/Shigeko to become Empress to the Imperial Palace, some people criticized it that Moshi/Shigeko did not suit for Crown Prince&apos;s Empress since her father&apos;s official rank was Chunagon. (middle counselor)　(Also it was only Yorimichi, who had the most political power at that time, to send adopted daughter to become Empress, thus it is said some people considered it was not appropriate for Yoshinobu to do the same. (because his official rank was not high enough))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the above background, Yoshinobu sent his wife&apos;s nephew, and also his adopted daughter, Moshi/Shigeko to become Empress, to the Imperial Palace, some people criticized that Moshi/Shigeko was not suitable as the Crown Prince&apos;s Empress since her father&apos;s official rank was Chunagon. (middle counselor)　(Also it was only Yorimichi, who had the most political power at that time, to send an adopted daughter to become Empress, thus it is said that some people considered it was not appropriate for Yoshinobu to do that. (because his official rank was not high enough))</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the above background, Yoshinobu sent his wife&apos;s niece, and also his adopted daughter, Moshi to the Imperial Palace to become Empress; however, some people criticized that Moshi was not suitable as the Crown Prince&apos;s Empress since her real father&apos;s official rank was mere Chunagon (also it was only Yorimichi, who had the most political power at that time, to send an adopted daughter to become Empress, thus it is said that some people considered it was not appropriate for Yoshinobu to do that because his official rank was not high enough).</e>
<cmt>姪ですので、niece としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>しかしその後、後冷泉天皇に皇子女が恵まれないのとは対照的に、茂子は王子貞仁（白河天皇）・篤子内親王（堀河天皇中宮）ら一男四女を次々と産んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, after Moshi/Shigeko made judai, on the contrary to Emperor Goreizei who did not have any children, she had one son and four daughters such as 王子貞仁 (Emperor Shirakawa), Imperial Princess Tokushi. (Emperor Horikawa&apos;s chugu (the second consort of an emperor))</e>
<cmt>王子貞仁→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after Moshi/Shigeko made judai, on the contrary to Emperor Goreizei who did not have any children, she had one son and four daughters such as 王子貞仁 (Emperor Shirakawa), Imperial Princess Tokushi. (Emperor Horikawa&apos;s chugu (the second consort of an emperor))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after Moshi entered into court, on the contrary to Emperor Goreizei who did not have any children, she had one son and four daughters such as Prince Sadahito (Emperor Shirakawa), Imperial Princess Tokushi (Emperor Horikawa&apos;s Chugu (the second consort of an emperor)).</e>
<cmt>王子貞仁→Prince Sadahito としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>正妃馨子内親王にも子女はなかったので、いずれ尊仁親王が即位すれば茂子は次期東宮の生母、やがては国母にもなるはずだったが、康平5年（1062年）尊仁親王の即位を見ることなく死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Emperor&apos;s Empress, Imperial Princess Keishi(Kaoruko) had no children, soon Moshi/Shigeko was going to become next Crown Prince&apos;s birth mother, or kokumo (mother of Emperor) after Imperial Prince Takahito&apos;s succession to the throne, however she died in 1062 before the Prince&apos;s succession to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Emperor&apos;s Empress, Imperial Princess Keishi (Kaoruko) had no children, soon Moshi/Shigeko was going to become the next Crown Prince&apos;s birth mother, or kokumo (mother of Emperor) after Imperial Prince Takahito&apos;s succession to the throne, however she died in 1062 before the Prince&apos;s succession to the throne.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Emperor&apos;s Empress, Imperial Princess Keishi (Kaoruko) had no children, soon Moshi was going to become the next Crown Prince&apos;s birth mother, or kokumo (mother of Emperor) after Imperial Prince Takahito&apos;s succession to the throne, however she died in 1062 before the Prince&apos;s succession to the throne.</e>
<cmt>Moshi としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>延久3年（1071年）後三条天皇即位にあたり従二位を、また同5年（1073年）白河天皇即位により皇太后を追贈された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1071, she was raised Junior Second Rank when Emperor Gosanjo succeeded to the throne, and was given the rank of Empress Dowager after Emperor Shirakawa&apos;s succession to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1071, she was raised to the Junior Second Rank when Emperor Gosanjo succeeded to the throne, and was given the rank of Empress Dowager after Emperor Shirakawa&apos;s succession to the throne.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1071, she was raised to the Junii (Junior Second Rank) when Emperor Gosanjo succeeded to the throne in 1071, and was given the rank of Empress Dowager after Emperor Shirakawa&apos;s succession to the throne in 1073.</e>
<cmt>1071, 1073 を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>茂子自身は若くして亡くなったが、これ以後茂子の実家である閑院流からは歴代天皇の后や生母が次々と輩出、院政期の歴史に大きく関わっていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Moshi/Shigeko died young, there were Empresses of the successive Emperors or birth mothers of the Emperor came from her family, Kanin line one after another, and it gave big influence to the history of the politics during cloister government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Moshi/Shigeko died young, there were Empresses of successive Emperors or birth mothers of the Emperor came from her family, Kanin line one after another, and it made big influence to the history of the politics during cloister government.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Moshi died young, there were Empresses or birth mothers of successive Emperors came from her family, Kanin line one after another, and it made big influence to the history of the politics during cloister government.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>陵墓は宇治陵（京都府宇治市木幡）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her mausoleum was in Uji no misasagi. (the Uji Mausoleum) (Kohata, Uji City, Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her mausoleum iss in Uji no misasagi. (the Uji Mausoleum) (Kohata, Uji City, Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her mausoleum is in Uji no misasagi (the Uji Mausoleum) (Kohata, Uji City, Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), 味っ子(id:17086), Masyu(id:31065), YOSHI438(id:174755), Goki(id:7107), 代言人(id:33675), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>