<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>重明親王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Shigeakira</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Shigeakira</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Shigeakira</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>重明親王（しげあきらしんのう、延喜6年（906年） - 天暦8年9月14日（954年10月13日））は、醍醐天皇第四皇子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Shigeakira (906 - October 13, 954) was the forth prince of Emperor Daigo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Shigeakira (906 - October 13, 954) was the forth prince of Emperor Daigo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Shigeakira (906 - October 13, 954) was the forth prince of Emperor Daigo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>母は更衣源昇女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was koi (a lady in waiting in the court), MINAMOTO no Noboru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was koi (a lady in waiting in the court), MINAMOTO no Noboru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was koi (a lady in waiting in the court), MINAMOTO no Noboru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>別名吏部王（式部省の唐名）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another name was Ribu (Riho) O (Chinese name of Shikibu sho).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another name was Ribu (Riho) O (Chinese name of Shikibu sho).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another name was Ribu (Riho) O (Chinese name of Shikibu sho).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>延喜8年4月5日（908年5月7日）、親王宣下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 7, 908, he received a title of Imperial Prince by the emperor</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 7, 908, he received the title of Imperial Prince by the emperor</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 7, 908, he received the title of Imperial Prince by the emperor.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>始め将保親王と称したが、同11年（911年）重明と改名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was first called 将保親王, but renamed as Shigeakira in 911.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was first called 将保親王, but renamed Shigeakira in 911.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was first called 将保親王, but renamed Shigeakira in 911.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>同21年（921年）、清涼殿において元服。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had a coming-of-age ceremony at Seiryoden in 921.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had a coming-of-age ceremony at Seiryoden in 921.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had a coming-of-age ceremony at Seiryoden in 921.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その後は延長6年（928年）上野国太守、同8年（930年）弾正尹、承平7年（937年）に弾正尹を辞職の後中務卿を歴任、天慶6年（943年）三品に序され、その後式部卿となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he served as the governor of Kozuke Province in 928 and as danjo no kami in 930, continued to serve as nakatsukasa kyo after resigned from danjo no kami in 937, given a title of sanbon (the third of Imperial Princes&apos; rank) in 943, and became shikibu kyo afterward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he served as the governor of Kozuke Province in 928 and as danjo no kami in 930, continued to serve as nakatsukasa kyo after resigning from danjo no kami in 937, given the title of sanbon (the third rank for an Imperial Princes) in 943, and afterwards became shikibu kyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he served as the governor of Kozuke Province in 928 and as danjoin (President of the Board of Censors) in 930, continued to serve as Nakatsukasa-kyo (Minister of the Ministry of Central Affairs) after resigning from danjoin in 937, given the title of sanbon (the third rank for an Imperial Princes) in 943, and afterwards became Shikibukyo (Minister of the Ministry of Ceremonial).</e>
<cmt>役職名に英語の説明を加えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また子女のうち、長女徽子女王、次女悦子女王の二人が相次いで斎宮に卜定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, among his children, the eldest daughter, Princess Yoshiko (Kishi), and the second daughter, Princess Yoshiko (Esshi), were assigned as Saigu (an unmarried princess who, in former times, was sent by the emperor to serve at Ise Shrine) by bokujo(bokutei) (to decide by fortunetelling).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, among his children, the eldest daughter, Princess Yoshiko (Kishi), and the second daughter, Princess Yoshiko (Esshi), were assigned as Saigu (unmarried princess who, in former times, was sent by the emperor to serve at Ise Shrine) by bokujo (bokutei - to decide by fortune telling).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, among his children, the eldest daughter, Princess Yoshiko (Kishi), and the second daughter, Princess Yoshiko (Esshi), were assigned as Saigu (unmarried princess who, in former times, was sent by the emperor to serve at Ise Shrine) by bokujo (bokutei - to decide by fortune telling).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>皇位を巡る争いとは生涯無縁であったが、学識豊かで楽才にも優れた風流人であり、父醍醐天皇は崩御の間際に重明親王を代明親王共々召して遺詔を託した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He never had disputes over imperial throne, but he had great attainments and refined taste with excellent musical talent, so his father, Emperor Daigo, left him a will at the presence of both Imperial Prince Shigeakira and Imperial Prince Yoshiakira in Emperor Daigo&apos;s last moment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He never had any disputes over the imperial throne, but he had made great attainments and had refined taste and excellent musical talent, so his father, Emperor Daigo, left him a will in the presence of both Imperial Prince Shigeakira and Imperial Prince Yoshiakira during the Emperor&apos;s last moment.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He never had any disputes over the imperial throne, but he had made great attainments and had refined taste and excellent musical talent, so his father, Emperor Daigo, left him a will in the presence of both Imperial Prince Shigeakira and Imperial Prince Yoshiakira during the Emperor&apos;s last moment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また異母弟村上天皇の宮中でもことに重んじられて、宴などでは必ず和琴や笛に加わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, his half brother, Emperor Murakami, was much accounted in the Imperial Palace and always played thirteen-stringed koto and a flute at a banquet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, his half brother, Emperor Murakami, was much appreciated in the Imperial Palace and always played the thirteen-stringed koto and a flute at banquets.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, in the Imperial Palace of his half brother, Emperor Murakami, he was much appreciated and always played the thirteen-stringed koto and a flute at banquets.</e>
<cmt>ここでは村上天皇が主語ではなく、重明親王つまりheが主語なので、そのように修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>摂関家との関係も良好で、始めに太政大臣藤原忠平の娘藤原寛子と結婚、天慶8年（945年）に寛子が死去すると、天暦2年（948年）に寛子の姪にあたる藤原登子を後妻としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His relationship with the clan[family] eligible for regents was good, so he first married to a daughter, FUJIWARA no Kanshi (Hiroko), of the Grand Minister, FUJIWARA no Tadahira, and he remarried to FUJIWARA no Toshi (Nariko), who was Kanshi (Hiroko)&apos;s niece after Kanshi(Hiroko)&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His relationship with the clan (family), eligible to become regents, was good, so he first married a daughter, FUJIWARA no Kanshi (Hiroko), of the Grand Minister, FUJIWARA no Tadahira, and he later remarried to FUJIWARA no Toshi (Nariko), who was Kanshi (Hiroko)&apos;s niece after Kanshi (Hiroko)&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His relationship with the family, eligible to become regents, was good, so he first married a daughter, FUJIWARA no Kanshi (Hiroko), of the Grand Minister, FUJIWARA no Tadahira, and he later remarried to FUJIWARA no Toshi (Nariko), who was Kanshi (Hiroko)&apos;s niece in 948 after Kanshi (Hiroko)&apos;s death in 945.</e>
<cmt>年号補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また寛子所生の長女徽子女王は、斎宮を退下したのち村上天皇に入内した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Kanshi (Hiroko)&apos;s eldest daughter, Princess Yoshiko (Kishi), made her bridal entry into the court after resigned from Saigu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, Kanshi (Hiroko)&apos;s eldest daughter, Princess Yoshiko (Kishi), made her bridal entry into the court after resigning from Saigu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, Kanshi (Hiroko)&apos;s eldest daughter, Princess Yoshiko (Kishi), made her bridal entry into the court to Emperor Murakami after resigning from Saigu.</e>
<cmt>Emperor Murakami 補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>重明親王は一風変わった逸話の多い人物で、日輪が家に入り鳳凰が飛来する夢を見て、将来帝位に関わる兆しかと期したという伝説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Shigeakira had a lot of unusual anecdotes, and there was a legend that he dreamed a phoenix flying when the sun came into the house, so he expected it was the sign to get involved in crown in the future.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Shigeakira had a lot of unusual anecdotes, and there was a legend that he dreamed about a phoenix flying when the sun came into the house, so he expected it was the sign of becoming involved in the crown in the future.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Shigeakira had a lot of unusual anecdotes, and there was a legend that he dreamed about a phoenix flying when the sun came into the house, so he expected it was the sign of becoming involved in the crown in the future.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>（親王の邸宅は後に藤原兼家が住んだ東三条殿であった） また『江家次第』によれば、ある時蕃客（渤海の使者）が参入した時、親王が鴨毛の車に黒貉の皮衣を八重重ねで纏っていたので使者たちが大いに恥じたと言われ、風雅を愛する一方で豪気な一面も持ち合わせていたらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The residence of Imperial Prince was later the Higashi sanjo dono where FUJIWARA no Kaneie lived.) Also, according to &quot;Goke shidai,&quot; when foreigners (envoys from Bokkai) broke into his residence, Imperial Prince wrapped an ox-drawn carriage made with duck&apos;s fur with eight layers of badger&apos;s fur, so the envoys were very ashamed, and it revealed that he seemed to love elegance but also have the strong and brave part of himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The residence of the Imperial Prince was later the Higashi sanjo dono where FUJIWARA no Kaneie lived.) Also, according to &quot;Goke shidai,&quot; when foreigners (envoys from Bokkai) broke into his residence, Imperial Prince wrapped an ox-drawn carriage made with duck&apos;s feathers with eight layers of badger&apos;s fur, so the envoys were very ashamed, and it revealed that he seemed to love elegance, but also had a strong and brave character.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The residence of the Imperial Prince was later the Higashi sanjo dono where FUJIWARA no Kaneie lived.) Also, according to &quot;Goke shidai,&quot; when foreigners (envoys from Bokkai) broke into his residence, Imperial Prince wrapped an ox-drawn carriage made with duck&apos;s feathers with eight layers of badger&apos;s fur, so the envoys were very ashamed, and it revealed that he seemed to love elegance, but also had a strong and brave character.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また『今昔物語』に登場する話では、東三条殿の庭園に怪しい太った五位が夜な夜な姿を見せるので、親王が怪しんで陰陽師に占わせると東南の隅から銅の提（ひさげ）が現れ、以後五位は姿を見せなくなったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the story in &quot;Konjaku monogatari (Tales of Times Now Past)&quot; told that suspicious fat night heron appeared every night in the garden of Higashi sanjo dono, so Imperial Prince made a yin-yang diviner divine, and a copper hisage (a Japanese sake bottle) appeared from the corner of south-east, then night heron never appeared since then.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the story in &quot;Konjaku monogatari (Tales of Times Now Past)&quot; told that a suspicious fat night heron appeared every night in the garden of Higashi sanjo dono, so the Prince called a yin-yang diviner, and a copper hisage (a Japanese sake bottle) appeared from the corner of south-east, then the night heron never appeared again..</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the story in &quot;Konjaku monogatari&quot; (Tales of Times Now Past) told that a suspicious fat night heron appeared every night in the garden of Higashi sanjo dono, so the Prince called a yin-yang diviner, and a copper hisage (a Japanese sake bottle) appeared from the corner of south-east, then the night heron never appeared again.</e>
<cmt>(Tales of Times Now Past)位置移動ピリオド重複削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>なお親王の日記『吏部王記』は原本も写本も現存しないが、後世の日記や書物に引用された逸文から見て、朝議に関する詳細な記録を書き留めたものであったらしく、当時の朝廷の儀式・典礼に関する貴重な史料である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, for Imperial Prince&apos;s diary &quot;Ribu (Rihi) O ki,&quot; an original book and a duplicate copy do not exist at the present, but the excellent document referred from the later diary and document, it seemed that it was the detailed report of the conference at Imperial Court, and it is the valuable historical records on ceremony and ritual of Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, as forthe Imperial Prince&apos;s diary &quot;Ribu (Rihi) O ki,&quot; the original book and a duplicate copy does not exist at present, but from an excellent document about the diary, it seems that it was a detailed report of a conference at the Imperial Court, and is a valuable historical record on ceremonies and rituals of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, although the original manuscript for Ribuoki (also pronounced Rihioki), the diary of Imperial Prince Shigeakira, has not survived and no copies are presently known to exist, extracts from it that appear in later diaries and documents suggest that it included detailed reports on conferences held at the Imperial Court, providing a valuable historical record of the ceremonies and rituals practiced at the Imperial Court at that time.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入逸文にはexcellent documentの意味はありません。ここでの意味は「引用した文章」です。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), YOSHI438(id:174755), トホホ川(id:50502), Yonoemon(id:55450), 蘇民(id:87832), 代言人(id:33675), Cprobot(id:97843), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>