<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>惟喬親王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Koretaka</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Koretaka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Koretaka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>惟喬親王（これたかしんのう、承和11年（844年） - 寛平9年2月20日（897年3月30日）は、平安時代前期の皇族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Koretaka (844 - March 30, 897) was the Imperial family during early Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Koretaka (844 - March 30, 897) was an Imperial family member during the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Koretaka (844 - March 30, 897) was an Imperial family member during the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>文徳天皇の第一皇子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the Emperor Montoku&apos;s first Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was Emperor Montoku&apos;s first Prince.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was Emperor Montoku&apos;s first Prince.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は紀名虎の娘・更衣紀静子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was KI no Natora&apos;s daughter, Koi (a lady in waiting in the court, a consort of an emperor), KI no Shizuko.</e>
<cmt>(a lady in waiting in the court, a consort of an emperor[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was KI no Natora&apos;s daughter, Koi (a lady in waiting in the court, a consort of the emperor), KI no Shizuko.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was KI no Natora&apos;s daughter, Koi (a lady in waiting in the court, a consort of the emperor), KI no Shizuko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>別名小野宮。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His different name was Ononomiya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His other name was Ononomiya.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His other name was Ononomiya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>同母妹に恬子内親王がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His real younger sister was Imperial Princess Tenshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His real younger sister was Imperial Princess Tenshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His real younger sister was Imperial Princess Tenshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>父・文徳天皇は皇太子として第四皇子である惟仁親王（後の清和天皇）を立てた後、惟喬親王にも皇位を継承させようとしたが、藤原良房の反対を危惧した源信の諫言により実現できなかったといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father, Emperor Montoku appointed his forth Prince, Imperial Prince Korehito (later called Emperor Seiwa) as Crown Prince, and tried to let Imperial Prince Koretaka to succeed to the throne, however this did not happned as MINAMOTO no Makoto concerned that FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa would go against this and he remonstrated his concern to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father, Emperor Montoku appointed his forth Prince, Imperial Prince Korehito (later called Emperor Seiwa) as Crown Prince, and tried to let Imperial Prince Koretaka succeed to the throne, however this did not happned as MINAMOTO no Makoto was concerned that FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa would be against this and he remonstrated his concern to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father, Emperor Montoku appointed his forth Prince, Imperial Prince Korehito (later called Emperor Seiwa) as Crown Prince, and tried to let Imperial Prince Koretaka succeed to the throne, however this did not happened as MINAMOTO no Makoto was concerned that FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa would be against this and he remonstrated his concern to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除。happenedスペル訂正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>これは、惟喬親王の母が紀氏の出身で後ろ盾が弱く、一方惟仁親王の母が良房の娘藤原明子であったことによるものとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was due to the background that Imperial Prince Koretaka&apos;smother was from the Ki clan and did not have strong political support, on the other hand, Imperial Prince Korehito&apos;s mother was Yoshifusa&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Meishi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was due to the background that Imperial Prince Koretaka&apos;s mother was from the Ki clan and did not have strong political support, on the other hand, Imperial Prince Korehito&apos;s mother was Yoshifusa&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Meishi.</e>
<cmt>word spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was due to the background that Imperial Prince Koretaka&apos;s mother was from the Ki clan and did not have strong political support, on the other hand, Imperial Prince Korehito&apos;s mother was Yoshifusa&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Meishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>ただ、この決定に対する不満が朝廷内部にあったとされ、100年以上経った後でさえその是非が議論の対象になったとされる（『権記』寛弘8年5月27日条。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However there was critisism against this decision within the Imperial Palace, and it was said there was an argument whether the decision was right or wrong, even after more than one hundred years had passed. (&quot;Gonki&quot; Kanko 8, an article issued on May 27)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However there was critisism against this decision within the Imperial Palace, and there were arguments as to whether the decision was right or not, even after more than one hundred years had passed. (&quot;Gonki&quot; Kanko 8, an article issued on May 27)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However there was criticism against this decision within the Imperial Palace, and there were arguments as to whether the decision was right or not, even after more than one hundred years had passed (&quot;Gonki&quot; Kanko 8, an article issued on May 27 (July 7, 1011).</e>
<cmt>criticismスペル訂正。ピリオドを後にしました。新暦補足しました。)削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>この時も次期皇太子を巡る敦康親王派と敦成親王派（後の後一条天皇）の確執があり、惟喬と敦康の境遇が類似していた）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This time as well, there was a conflict between Imperial Prince Atsuyasu and Imperial Prince Atuhira (later called Emperor Goichijo), which was the similer situation when there was a conflict between Koretaka and Atsuyasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This time as well, there was a conflict between Imperial Prince Atsuyasu and Imperial Prince Atuhira (later called Emperor Goichijo), which was a similar situation when there was a conflict between Koretaka and Atsuyasu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This time as well, there was a conflict between Imperial Prince Atsuyasu and Imperial Prince Atsuhira (later called Emperor Goichijo), which was a similar situation when there was a conflict between Koretaka and Atsuyasu.)</e>
<cmt>Atsuhiraスペル訂正。)補足。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>その後、大宰帥・弾正尹・常陸太守・上野太守を歴任した後出家し、近江国滋賀郡小野に隠棲。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that he successively held the positions like Dazai no Sotsu (the Minister of Dazaifu), Ddanjo no kami (the Minister of Judical office), the Governor of Hitachi Province, the Governor of Kozuke Province, then he entred into the priesthood and went to live in seclusion in Ono, Shiga Country, Omi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that he successively held positions like Dazai no Sotsu (the Minister of Dazaifu), Ddanjo no kami (the Minister of Judical office), the Governor of Hitachi Province, the Governor of Kozuke Province, then he entred into the priesthood and went to live in seclusion in Ono, Shiga Country, Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that he successively held positions like Dazai no sochi (Governor-General of the Dazai-fu offices), Danjoin (President of the Board of Censors), the Governor of Hitachi Province, the Governor of Kozuke Province, then he entred into the priesthood and went to live in seclusion in Ono, Shiga Country, Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>大宰帥→Dazai no sochi (Governor-General of the Dazai-fu offices)と訂正しました。弾正尹→Danjoin (President of the Board of Censors)と訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その後、山崎・水無瀬にも閑居し、在原業平・紀有常らと交流したといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said later on he also lived in retirement in Yamazaki and Minase, where he socialized with ARIWARA no Narihira and KI no Aritsune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later on it is said that he also lived in retirement in Yamazaki and Minase, where he socialized with ARIWARA no Narihira and KI no Aritsune.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later on it is said that he also lived in retirement in Yamazaki and Minase, where he socialized with ARIWARA no Narihira and KI no Aritsune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>近江国神崎郡君ヶ畑をはじめ、木地師のなかには惟喬親王を祖とする伝承が全国的に見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were some oral traditions of woodturner in the place like Kimigahara, Kanzaki Country, Omi Province, which it said Imperial Prince Koretaka was the originator of the traditions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were some oral traditions of woodturner in the place like Kimigahara, Kanzaki Country, Omi Province, which it said Imperial Prince Koretaka was the originator of the traditions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were some oral traditions of woodturner in the place like Kimigahara, Kanzaki Country, Omi Province, which it said Imperial Prince Koretaka was the originator of the traditions.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), Wiki0825(id:34646), 代言人(id:33675), 水野白楓(id:22811), Cprobot(id:97843), UMBRO(id:100484), うぃき野郎(id:53567), Andee(id:20421), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>