<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>後伏見天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Gofushimi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Gofushimi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Gofushimi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>後伏見天皇（ごふしみてんのう、弘安11年3月3日（1288年4月5日）- 延元元年/建武3年4月6日（1336年5月17日)）は鎌倉時代の第93代天皇（在位：永仁6年7月22日（1298年8月30日）- 正安3年1月21日（1301年3月2日））。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Gofushimi (April 5th, 1288 - May 17th, 1336) was the ninety third Emperor during the Kamakura period. (his reign was August 30th, 1298 - March 2nd, 1301)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Gofushimi (April 5th, 1288 - May 17th, 1336) was the ninety third Emperor during the Kamakura period. (his reign was from August 30th, 1298 to March 2nd, 1301)</e>
<cmt>&quot;from, to&quot; added</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Gofushimi (April 5, 1288 - May 17, 1336) was the ninety third Emperor during the Kamakura period (his reign was from August 30, 1298 to March 2, 1301).</e>
<cmt>日付表記ピリオドの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>諱は胤仁（たねひと）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His posthumous name was Tanehito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His posthumous name was Tanehito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His posthumous name was Tanehito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>系譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>伏見天皇の第一皇子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the first Prince of Emperor Fushimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the first Prince of Emperor Fushimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the first Prince of Emperor Fushimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>母は、参議左近衛中将五辻経氏の娘、藤原経子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was the Councilor of State, lieutenant general of Imperial Guard of the left, Tsuneuji ITSUTSUJI&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Keishi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was the Councilor of State, lieutenant general of Imperial Guard of the left, Tsuneuji ITSUTSUJI&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Keishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was the Councilor of State, lieutenant general of Imperial Guard of the left, Tsuneuji ITSUTSUJI&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Keishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>持明院統。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Jimyo-in Imperial line</e>
<cmt>持明院統→the Jimyo-in Imperial line [定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Jimyo-in Imperial line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Jimyo-in Imperial line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>他のファイルに合わせる</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>1289年、立太子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became Crown Prince in 1289.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became Crown Prince in 1289.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1289: He became Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>&quot;He became Crown Prince in 1289.&quot;→&quot;1289: He became Crown Prince.&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>1298年、伏見天皇からの譲位により即位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1298 he succeeded to the throne after Emperor Fushimi passed the throne to him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1298 he succeeded to the throne after Emperor Fushimi passed the throne to him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1298: He succeeded to the throne after Emperor Fushimi passed the throne to him.</e>
<cmt>&quot;In 1298 he succeeded to the throne after Emperor Fushimi passed the throne to him.&quot;→&quot;1298: He succeeded to the throne after Emperor Fushimi passed the throne to him.&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>伏見天皇が院政を執り行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Fushimi ruled the cloister government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Fushimi ruled the cloisteedr government.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Fushimi ruled the cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>1301年に大覚寺統の巻き返しにより後二条天皇に譲位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1301 the Daikaku-ji Imperial line made a recovery of the political power and Emperor Nijo succeeded to the throne.</e>
<cmt>大覚寺統→the Daikaku-ji Imperial line [定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1301 the Daikaku-ji Imperial line recovered political power and Emperor Nijo succeeded to the throne.</e>
<cmt>cut out wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1301: The Daikaku-ji Imperial line recovered political power and Emperor Gonijo succeeded to the throne.</e>
<cmt>Nijo→Gonijoスペース削除&quot;In 1301 the Daikaku-ji Imperial line recovered political power and Emperor Gonijo succeeded to the throne.&quot;→&quot;1301: The Daikaku-ji Imperial line recovered political power and Emperor Gonijo succeeded to the throne.&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>1308年に弟の花園天皇が即位すると、しばらく後、伏見上皇が院政を停止したので、これを引き継いで1313年から1318年の間、院政を敷いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1308 after his brother, Emperor Hanazono enthroned, since Emperor Fushimi suspended ruling the cloister government for a while, Emperor Gofushimi took over it and he ruled the cloister government from 1313 to 1318.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1308 after his brother, Emperor Hanazono was enthroned, since Emperor Fushimi suspended ruling the cloistered government for a while, Emperor Gofushimi took it over and he ruled the cloistered government from 1313 to 1318.</e>
<cmt>revisions for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1308: After his brother, Emperor Hanazono was enthroned, since Retired Emperor Fushimi suspended ruling the cloistered government for a while, Emperor Gofushimi took it over and he ruled the cloistered government from 1313 to 1318.</e>
<cmt>Retired補足&quot;In 1308 after his brother, Emperor Hanazono was enthroned, since Retired Emperor Fushimi suspended ruling the cloistered government for a while, Emperor Gofushimi took it over and he ruled the cloistered government from 1313 to 1318. &quot;→&quot;1308: After his brother, Emperor Hanazono was enthroned, since Retired Emperor Fushimi suspended ruling the cloistered government for a while, Emperor Gofushimi took it over and he ruled the cloistered government from 1313 to 1318.&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>花園天皇の在位の間、鎌倉幕府と折衝し持明院統と大覚寺統から交互に天皇を出すと言う取り決めを行おうとした（文保の御和談）が失敗に終わる（両統迭立を参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During Emperor Hanazono&apos;s reign, he negotiated with the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a Shogun) and tried to establish an agreement to send the successor to the Imperial throne from the both parties, the Jimyo-in Imperial line and the Daikaku-ji Imperial line (Bunpo no go-wadan (negotiation for reconciliation), however it did not happen.(Please refer to the Ryoto Tetsuritsu section.)</e>
<cmt>両統迭立→Ryoto Tetsuritsu[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During Emperor Hanazono&apos;s reign, he negotiated with the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a Shogun) and tried to establish an agreement to send a successor to the Imperial throne from either party, the Jimyo-in Imperial line or the Daikaku-ji Imperial line (Bunpo no go-wadan (negotiation for reconciliation), however it was not realized.(Please refer to the Ryoto Tetsuritsu section.)</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During Emperor Hanazono&apos;s reign, he negotiated with the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a Shogun) and tried to establish an agreement to send a successor to the Imperial throne from either party, the Jimyo-in Imperial line or the Daikaku-ji Imperial line (Bunpo no go-wadan (negotiation for reconciliation)), however it was not realized. (Please refer to the Ryoto Tetsuritsu section.)</e>
<cmt>)補足スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="13">
<j>1318年、後醍醐天皇が即位するとそのまま天皇は親政を続け、1331年幕府に反旗を翻し、捕らえられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1318, after Emperor Godaigo succeeded to the throne, the Emperor Gofushimi continued to rule the politics directly, he tried to overthrow the government and he was caught.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1318, after Emperor Godaigo succeeded to the throne, the Emperor Gofushimi continued to rule directly, he tried to overthrow the government and he was prevented.</e>
<cmt>revision for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1318: After Emperor Godaigo succeeded to the throne, the Emperor Gofushimi continued to rule directly, he tried to overthrow the government in 1331and he was prevented.</e>
<cmt>年号補足&quot;In 1318, after Emperor Godaigo succeeded to the throne, the Emperor Gofushimi continued to rule directly, he tried to overthrow the government in 1331and he was prevented.&quot;→&quot;1318: After Emperor Godaigo succeeded to the throne, the Emperor Gofushimi continued to rule directly, he tried to overthrow the government in 1331and he was prevented.&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>幕府は、代わりに上皇の皇子・光厳天皇を立て、しばらく院政を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The government appointed the retired Emperor&apos;s Prince, Emperor Kogon to continue ruling the cloister government after a while.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The government appointed the retired Emperor&apos;s Prince, Emperor Kogon, to continue ruling the cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>revision for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The government appointed the Retired Emperor&apos;s Prince, Emperor Kogon, to continue ruling the cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>&quot;retired Emperor&quot;→&quot;Retired Emperor&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="15">
<j>1333年、足利尊氏が後醍醐天皇に呼応して鎌倉幕府を倒した結果、光厳天皇が廃位されると院政は停止し、そのまま出家した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1333 Takauji ASHIKAGA called to each others to Emperor Godaigo, he overthrown the Kamakura bakufu, the cloister government was suspended after Emperor Kogon abdicated, the Emperor Gofushimi became a priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1333 Takauji ASHIKAGA called each party to Emperor Godaigo, he overthrew the Kamakura bakufu, the cloistered government was suspended after Emperor Kogon abdicated, and Emperor Gofushimi became a priest.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;1333: Takauji ASHIKAGA responded to Emperor Godaigo&apos;s call to arms and overthrew the Kamakura bakufu, the cloistered government was suspended after Emperor Kogon abdicated, and Emperor Gofushimi became a priest.</e>
<cmt>This is a little 意訳 but I think it fits the context. &quot;In 1333 Takauji ASHIKAGA responded to Emperor Godaigo&apos;s call to arms and overthrew the Kamakura bakufu, the cloistered government was suspended after Emperor Kogon abdicated, and Emperor Gofushimi became a priest.&quot;→&quot;1333: Takauji ASHIKAGA responded to Emperor Godaigo&apos;s call to arms and overthrew the Kamakura bakufu, the cloistered government was suspended after Emperor Kogon abdicated, and Emperor Gofushimi became a priest.&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="16">
<j>1336年、崩御。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died in 1336.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died in 1336.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1336: He died.</e>
<cmt>&quot;He died in 1336.&quot;→&quot;1336: He died.&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>在位中の元号</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eras during his reign</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Era&apos;s during his reign</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eras during his reign</e>
<cmt>&quot;Era&apos;s&quot; is simply incorrect. &quot;Eras&quot; was correct and did not require editing.</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>永仁 （1298年7月22日） - 1299年4月25日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Einin (July 22, 1298) - April 25, 1299</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Einin (July 22, 1298) - April 25, 1299</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Einin (July 22, 1298) - April 25, 1299</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>正安 1299年4月25日 - （1301年1月21日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoan April 25, 1299 - (January 21, 1301)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoan April 25, 1299 - (January 21, 1301)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoan April 25, 1299 - (January 21, 1301)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>陵墓・霊廟</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial Mausoleum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Mausoleum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial mausoleum</e>
<cmt>他のファイルに合わせる</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>京都市伏見区深草坊町の深草北陵（ふかくさきたのみささぎ）に葬られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor was entombed in Fukakusa no Kita no Misasagi in Fukakusa Bo-cho Town, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor was entombed in Fukakusa no Kita no Misasagi in Fukakusa Bo-cho Town, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor was entombed in Fukakusa no Kita no Misasagi in Fukakusa Bo-cho, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>住所表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Lemon pie(id:66842), Lonicera(id:20638), BOTarate(id:185620), 霧木諒二(id:9795), Nnh(id:474), DragonBot(id:161936), Cprobot(id:97843), 味っ子(id:17086), Ash Crow(id:26765), Zwobot(id:23873), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), でここ(id:9565), Masyu(id:31065), 中右(id:50196), Nidarin(id:6420), SuisuiBot(id:10165), 玄史生(id:43670), 代言人(id:33675), 総督(id:124846), Shimoxx(id:9332), 平惣衛門(id:99387), YOSHI438(id:174755), けんち(id:5147), FlaBot(id:30804), LeonardoRob0t(id:25875), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>