<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>皇国史観</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokokushikan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokokushikan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokokushikan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>皇国史観（こうこくしかん）は、日本国と日本人は歴代天皇を中心とした国造りが行われ、現代までに到る伝承と歴史が紡がれ継承されて来たとする歴史観。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokokushikan is the historical understanding that Japanese people live in the country of Japan built up with the history of the successive Emperors, the lore and the history was passed from generations to generations until the present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokokushikan is the understanding that Japanese people live in Japan, a country with a history of successive Emperors, lore and the history of which was passed from generation to generation to the present.</e>
<cmt>cut down wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokokushikan is the understanding that Japanese people live in Japan, a country with a history of successive Emperors, lore and the history of which was passed from generation to generation to the present.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>第二次世界大戦以前</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the World War Ⅱ</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before World War Ⅱ</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before World War Ⅱ</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>南北朝時代に南朝の北畠親房が南朝の正統性を示すために著した『神皇正統記』が先駆的なものであり、江戸時代に展開した水戸学や国学でその基礎が作られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Jinnoshotoki; A Chronicle of Gods and Sovereigns&quot; written by Chikafusa KITABATAKE of the Southern Dynasty during the period of Northern and Southern Dynasties, for the purpose of showing the orthodoxy of the Southern Dynasty, was the progenitor of the Kokokushikan, the base was established by Mito gaku (studies) and the Japanese classical literature which became popular in Edo period..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Jinnoshotoki; A Chronicle of Gods and Sovereigns&quot; written by Chikafusa KITABATAKE of the Southern Dynasty during the period of Northern and Southern Dynasties, for the purpose of showing the orthodoxy of the Southern Dynasty, was the progenitor of Kokokushikan, the base was established by Mito gaku (studies) and Japanese classical literature which became popular during the Edo period..</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Jinnoshotoki&quot; (A Chronicle of Gods and Sovereigns) written by Chikafusa KITABATAKE of the Southern Court during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts, for the purpose of showing the orthodoxy of the Southern Court, was the progenitor of Kokokushikan, the base was established by Mito gaku (studies) and study of Japanese classical literature which became popular during the Edo period..</e>
<cmt>A Chronicle of Gods and Sovereigns位置移動Dynasty→Courtstudy of補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>幕末の尊王攘夷運動の過程で強化され、明治維新後には政治体制によって正統な歴史観として確立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It gave the strong influence to the society after the campaign to restore the emperor and expel the barbarians at the last days of the Tokugawa government, it was established as an orthodox historical view by the new political system after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It strongly influenced society after a campaign to restore the emperor and expel the barbarians during the last days of the Tokugawa government, it was established as an orthodox historical view by the new political system after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was strongly influenced by a campaign to restore the emperor and expel the barbarians during the last days of the Tokugawa government, it was established as an orthodox historical view by the new political system after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>society 削除　原文に意味合うよう修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>しかし、当初祭政一致を掲げていた明治政府は、近代国家を目指して政教分離・信教の自由を建前に学問の自由を尊重する方向に政策転換し、明治十年代には記紀神話に対する批判など比較的自由な議論が行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Meiji government insisted the unity of Japanese Temples and Shrines and state, they changed the policy to respect the freedom of study as they were pushing the separation of religion and politics, and the freedom of the religion to achieve the modern nation, in its Maiji 10th, there was a free discussion held about the criticism of the Kojiki, Nihonshoki and mythology.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the Meiji government insisted upon the unity of Japanese Temples, Shrines, and the state, the policy was changed to respect the freedom to study as they were pushing for the separation of religion and politics, and the freedom of religion to achieve a modern nation, in Meiji 10, there were a free discussion held about criticizing the Kojiki, Nihonshoki and mythology.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the Meiji government insisted upon the unity of Japanese Temples, Shrines, and the state, the policy was changed to respect the freedom to study as they were pushing for the separation of religion and politics, and the freedom of religion to achieve a modern nation, during the last half of 1870s and the first half of 1880s, there were a free discussion held about criticizing the Kojiki (The Records of Ancient Matters), Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan) and mythology.</e>
<cmt>in Meiji 10→during the last half of 1870s and the first half of 1880s(The Records of Ancient Matters)補足(Chronicles of Japan)補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また考古学も発展し、教科書には神代ではなく原始社会の様子も記述されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also the archeology was developed, there was a description of the details of primitive society, instead of the age of the god, in the school textbook.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also archeology was developed, and detailed descriptions of primitive society replaced the age of the gods, in school textbooks.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also archeology was developed, and detailed descriptions of primitive society replaced the age of the gods, in school textbooks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>しかし明治24年（1891年）東京帝国大学教授久米邦武の「神道は祭天の古俗」という論文が皇室への不敬に当たると批判を受け職を追われ、学問的自由に制限が加わるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However Kunitake KUME of the professor of Tokyo Imperial University, who wrote an essay of &apos; Shintoism is to enshrine God in old way&apos;, was criticized his essay as it is rude to the Imperial family, he was removed from his positon and the political pressure started to put on to the freedom of study.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However Kunitake KUME, a professor of Tokyo Imperial University, wrote the essay titled; &apos; Shintoism is to Enshrine God in the Old Way,&apos; which was criticized as being rude to the Imperial family, he was removed from his positon and political pressure started to mount against the freedom to study.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However Kunitake KUME, a professor of Tokyo Imperial University, wrote the essay titled; &apos; Shintoism is to Enshrine God in the Old Way,&apos; which was criticized as being rude to the Imperial family, he was removed from his position in 1891 and political pressure started to mount against the freedom to study.</e>
<cmt>in 1891 補足スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>このような変化は、神道内においては伊勢派が出雲派を放逐したことと機を一つにする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason of the above change was partly due to the incident Ise force expelled Izumo force in Shintoism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason for the above change was partly due to the incident that occurred when the Ise forces expelled Izumo forces in Shintoism.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason for the above change was partly due to the incident that occurred when the Ise forces expelled Izumo forces in Shintoism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>その後大正デモクラシーの高まりを受けて歴史学にも再び自由な言論が活発になり、マルクス主義の唯物史観に基づく歴史書も出版されたが、社会主義運動の高まりと共に統制も強化された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that the movement of the freedom of speech became popular again in historical studies as the Taisho Democracy became more popular, some historical books about Marxist based on historical materialism were published, there was more strict control as the movement of the socialism became more popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, movement towards freedom of speech became popular again in historical studies as the Taisho Democracy became more popular, some historical books about Marxism based upon historical materialism were published, there was more strict control as the socialist movement became more popular.</e>
<cmt>revised for grammar and clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, movement towards freedom of speech became popular again in historical studies as the Taisho Democracy became more popular, some historical books about Marxism based upon historical materialism were published, there was more strict control as the socialist movement became more popular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>世界恐慌を経て軍国主義が台頭するに及び、昭和10年（1935年）、美濃部達吉の天皇機関説が学会では主流であったにも拘らず問題視されて発禁処分となり、昭和15年（1940年）には早稲田大学教授津田左右吉の記紀神話への批判が問題となり著作が発禁処分となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the world crisis happened, as the militarism came into power, although Tatsukichi MINOBE&apos;s Emperor-as-organ theory was the main stream of the academic conference, it was issued in question and was under prohibition of publication in 1935, there was another occasion in 1940, when the criticism towards mythology of Kojiki and Nihonshoki written by Sokichi TSUDA, the professor of Waseda University there became an issue, this book became under the prohibition of publication.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the world fell into crisis with the growth of militarism, although Tatsukichi MINOBE&apos;s Emperor-as-organ theory was the main theme at an academic conference, it was in question and was prohibited from being published in 1935, and in 1940, when mythology of the Kojiki and the Nihonshoki was written about and criticized by Sokichi TSUDA, a professor of Waseda University became an issue, the publication of this book was prohibited.</e>
<cmt>revised for grammar and clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the growth of militarism after the Great Depression of the 1930s, although Tatsukichi MINOBE&apos;s theory that the Emperor was an organ of the state was the main theme at academic conferences, it was regarded as questionable and books on this subject were banned in 1935, and then in 1940, criticism of the mythology of the Kojiki and the Nihonshoki by Sokichi TSUDA, a professor of Waseda University, became an issue so the publication of books on this subject was also banned.</e>
<cmt>after the Great Depressn of the 1930s世界恐慌を訳文に反映させるため補足スペルを修正原文に沿うかたちで訳し直しました。I have assumed that the theory was not only discussed at one conference and made this plural.Also, I think &quot;books on this subject were banned&quot; would read more naturally than &quot;prohibited from being published&quot;. &quot;Emperor-as-organ&quot; does get a few hits on Google but it doesn&apos;t make much sense so I have rewritten this as an explanation.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>一般の歴史書でも、皇国史観に正面から反対する学説を発表する事は困難となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a difficulty of publication for the general textbooks which have theories to strongly oppose to Kokokushikan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was difficult to get general textbooks published that had theories strongly opposed to Kokokushikan.</e>
<cmt>revised for grammar and clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was difficult to get general textbooks published that had theories strongly opposed to Kokokushikan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>19世紀末から1945年の終戦まで、学校で用いる歴史教科書は日本神話に始まり天皇家を中心にした出来事を述べ、歴史上の人物や民衆を皇国史観によって記述していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the historical textbook used in the schools between nineteen century and 1945, it started with the Japanese mythology and the description of the main events related to the Imperial family, which explained the famous people in the history and the popular people based on the Teikokushikan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historical textbooks used in schools between nineteen century and 1945, started with Japanese mythology and the description of the main events related to the Imperial family, which explained the famous people in history and popular people based upon the Teikokushikan.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historical textbooks used in schools between nineteen century and 1945, started with Japanese mythology and the description of the main events related to the Imperial family, which explained the famous people in history and popular people based upon the Kokokushikan.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>（国定教科書）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(A government-designated textbook)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(government-designated textbook)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Government-designated textbook)</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>南北朝正閏論</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nanbokucho seijun (legitimacy) theory</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nanbokucho seijun (legitimacy) theory</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Northern and Southern Courts Controversy</e>
<cmt>「南北朝」は「the Northern and Southern Courts」で統一しているので、それを使って訳しなおしてください。また、ここでの「論」はtheoryではなく、「論争」の意味が強く、適切です。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>1911年（明治44年）、小学校の歴史教科書に鎌倉幕府滅亡以後の時代を「南北朝時代」とする記述があった点が、南朝と北朝を対等に扱っているとして帝国議会で問題とされた（南北朝正閏論）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1911 it became an issue in the Imperial Diet that there was a description of the era after the Kamakura shogunate was called &apos;the period of the Southern and the Northern Dynasties&apos;, as it was said the Southern and the Northern Dynasties were treated equally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1911 there was an issue raised in the Imperial Diet concerning the description of the post Kamakura shogunate era called &apos;the period of the Southern and Northern Dynasties,&apos; because it was said that both Dynasties were treated equally.</e>
<cmt>revised for wordiness and redundancy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1911 there was an issue raised in the Imperial Diet concerning the description of the post Kamakura shogunate era called &apos;the period of the Northern and Souther Courts,&apos; because it was said that both Courts were treated equally.</e>
<cmt>Dynastie→CourtSouthern and Northern→Northern and Southernに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>文部省の喜田貞吉は責任を取って休職処分にされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadakichi KIDA of the Ministry of Education was given a leave of absence from work for the responsibility for the above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadakichi KIDA of the Ministry of Education was given a leave of absence from work to take responsibility for the above.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadakichi KIDA of the Ministry of Education was given a leave of absence from work to take responsibility for the above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>これ以後の教科書では、文部省は後醍醐天皇から南北朝合一までの時代を「吉野朝時代」と記述するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this incident, the description of the era between Emperor Godaigo and the united era of the Southern and the Northern Dynasties of the textbook from the Ministry of Education was stated as &apos; era of Yoshino cho&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this incident, the description of the era between Emperor Godaigo and the united era of the Southern and the Northern Dynasties in the textbook from the Ministry of Education was rewritten as &apos; era of Yoshino cho&apos;.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this incident, the description of the era between Emperor Godaigo and the united era of the Southern and the Northern Courts in the textbook from the Ministry of Education was rewritten as &apos;era of Yoshino Court.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Yoshino cho→Yoshino Court</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>現実の天皇家は北朝の流れであり、北朝の天皇の祭祀も行っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The current Imperial Family has the Northern Dynasty stream, they used to do Emperor&apos;s ritual.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The current Imperial Family is from the Northern Dynasty lineage, that they base performing the Emperor&apos;s rituals on.</e>
<cmt>&quot;stream&quot; changed to &quot;lineage&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The current Imperial Family is from the Northern Court lineage, that they base performing the Emperor&apos;s rituals on.</e>
<cmt>Dynastie→Court</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかし、足利尊氏を逆臣とする水戸学では南朝を正統と唱えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However in Imogayu which consider Takauji ASHIKAGA as a rebellious subject, they insisted the Sourthen Dynasty as the orthodox theory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However in Mitogaku, which considers Takauji ASHIKAGA a rebellious subject, they insisted on the Sourthen Dynasty as being the orthodox theory.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However in Mitogaku, which considers Takauji ASHIKAGA a rebellious subject, they insisted on the Sothern Court as being the orthodox theory.</e>
<cmt>Dynastie→Courtスペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>また幕末の尊王論に影響を与えた儒学者頼山陽は、後小松天皇は後亀山天皇からの禅譲を受けた天皇であり、南朝正統論と現皇室の間に矛盾はないと論じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also the Confucianist, Sanyo RAI who influenced Imperialism at the the last days of the Tokugawa government, he insisted there was no contradiction between the orthdox theory of Northern Dynasty and the current Imperial family since Emperor Gokomatsu and Emperor Gokameyama both received the smooth transference of power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also the Confucianist, Sanyo RAI, who influenced Imperialism at the the last days of the Tokugawa government, insisted there was no contradiction between the orthdox theory of Northern Dynasty and the current Imperial family since Emperor Gokomatsu and Emperor Gokameyama both received a smooth transference of power.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also the Confucianist, Sanyo RAI, who influenced Imperialism at the last days of the Tokugawa government, insisted there was no contradiction between the orthodox theory of Northern Court and the current Imperial family since Emperor Gokomatsu received a smooth transference of power from Emperor Gokameyama.</e>
<cmt>原文に合うよう、後半を修正Dynastie→Courtthe削除スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>南北朝正閏論以降、宮内省も南朝が正統であるという見解を取った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After having discussion whether the Southern and Northern Dynasties theory, the Department of the Imperial Household took the position of being the Sour then Dynasty was the orthodox line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After having discussing the Southern and Northern Dynasties theory, the Department of the Imperial Household took the position that being from the Southern Dynasty was the orthodox line.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After having discussing the Southern and Northern Courts controversy, the Department of the Imperial Household took the position that being from the Southern Court was the orthodox line.</e>
<cmt>Dynastie→Courttheoryをcontroversyに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>第二次世界大戦後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the World War Ⅱ</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After World War Ⅱ</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After World War Ⅱ</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>戦後、思想、信条の自由が保障されると、戦前は取り締まりの対象であったマルクス主義の唯物史観が興隆する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the War, the freedom of the thoughts and the religion became secured, the historical materialism of Marxist became popular which was targeted by the regulation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the War, the freedom of thought and religion was secured, the historical materialism of Marxist became popular which was targeted by regulations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the War, the freedom of thought and religion was secured, the historical materialism of Marxist became popular which was targeted by regulations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>これにより、皇国史観下ではタブー視されていた古代史や考古学の研究が大いに進展した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to this, the study of the ancient history and archaeology which were considered as taboo under the vision of Teikoku shikan, were developed in a large scale.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this, the study of ancient history and archaeology, previously considered as taboo from the vew of Teikoku shikan, were developed on a large scale.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this, the study of ancient history and archaeology, previously considered as taboo from the view of Kokokushikan, were developed on a large scale.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>これら戦後の歴史学は一般的に「戦後史学」と呼ばれ、こうした戦後民主主義の流れの中で、従来の価値観である皇国史観も衰退することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This historical studies after the War are generally called &apos; History after the War&apos;, the Kokokushikan decayed which were existing concept of values during the stream of post modern democracy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This historical studies after the War are generally called &apos; History after the War&apos;, the Kokokushikan decayed which were existing concept of values during the stream of post modern democracy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This historical studies after the War are generally called &apos;History after the War,&apos; and the Kokokushikan, which was the existing concept of values, decayed during the stream of post modern democracy.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除コンマの位置移動原文に沿って訳し直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>戦後の評価</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The assessment after the War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Assessment after the War</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Assessment after the War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>肯定的意見</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The positive opinion</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Positive opinion</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Positive opinion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>『産経新聞』紙上で連載された「教科書が教えない歴史」の反響から執筆者達は新しい歴史教科書をつくる会（つくる会）を作った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the reverberation of the serial publication the on the &apos;Sankei Shimbun&apos;, &apos;The history which textbook does not teach&apos;, the creative group, &apos;Tsukuru kai&apos; was established out of the authors to make new history textbook, it is said the recent textbook which exaggerate the review of the War and the colonial control was to make people misunderstand, the historical understandings, when Japan lost the War, and it also cause the misunderstanding of Japanese traditional history which continued from the mythological age as, &apos;masochistic view of the history&apos; or &apos;the black history&apos;, so the Tsukuru kai published &quot;new history textbook&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to reverberations from a serial publication in the &apos;Sankei Shimbun,&apos; titled; &apos;The history that the textbook does not teach,&apos; the creative group, &apos;The Tsukuru kai&apos; was established composed of the authors to write a new history textbook, it is said the recent textbook which exaggerates the review of the War and colonial control, was to decieve people about the historical reality, when Japan lost the War, and it also caused a misunderstanding of Japanese traditional history which continued from the mythological age as a, &apos;masochistic view of the history&apos; or &apos; black history,&apos; so the Tsukuru kai published &quot;new history textbook&apos;.</e>
<cmt>grammar, revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to reverberations from a serial publication in the &apos;Sankei Shimbun&apos; titled &apos;History that the textbooks don&apos;t teach,&apos; a creative group composed of the authors that was called the &apos;Tsukuru kai&apos; was established to write a new history textbook.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>戦後民主主義教育について、近代の戦争と植民地支配への反省を過度に強調する歴史教科書は歴史認識を誤認させ、敗戦を節目として神話時代から続いている日本の伝統ある歴史を貶める「自虐史観」（東京裁判史観）または「暗黒史観」であるとして、つくる会による『新しい歴史教科書』が作られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some say that recent textbooks reflect on the War and colonial control too much and that this is done prevent people from learning the historical reality about when Japan lost the War, and these textbooks have also caused a misunderstanding of Japanese traditional history, which has continued from the mythological age, by presenting a &apos;masochistic view of Japanese history&apos; or a &apos; dark history&apos; so the Tsukuru kai published their &quot;new history textbook.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>2001年に文部科学省の教科用図書検定に合格し、2002年から一部の中学校などで使用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was approved by the official approval of the textbook organized by the Ministry of Education in 2001, it was in partly use in the Junior High School.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was officially approved by a group of officials organized by the Ministry of Education in 2001, and was partly use in Junior High School.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was officially approved as a textbook by the Ministry of Education Culture. Sports, Science and Technology in 2001, and was partly use in Junior High School.</e>
<cmt>文部科学省の正式名称を使用by a group of officials organizedは原文にないので削除スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>これは戦時体制下で過度に利用されたが、皇国史観それ自体は極度に否定されるものではなく、長い日本の歴史の歩みの中で国民に継承されてきた伝統、文化的な価値観として肯定的に評価するものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was utalized an unreasonable demand under the regulation after the War, the Teikokushikan itself was not something being denied dramatically, it was positively valued as the cultural and historical point of view which was succeeded by the nation in the long Japanese history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was utilized an unreasonable demand under regulations after the War, the Teikokushikan itself was not something being dramatically denied, it was positively valued as the cultural and historical point of view which was succeeded by the nation over a long period of Japanese history.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it was overly exploited by the wartime regime, the Kokoku Shikan (an emperor-centered historiography which is based on state Shinto) itself should not be seen as something to be vehemently denied, but as something that should be positively valued as representing cultural values that have been passed down from one generation of the Japanese people to the next over the course of Japan&apos;s long history.</e>
<cmt>・after the Warではなく、「戦時体制下」つまり「戦争中は」という意味です。・ Teikokushikanではなく「皇国史観」です。・the Teikokushikan itself was not something being以下ですが、原文では「～否定されるものではなく、～するものである」と一般論を述べているので、過去形では意味がずれると思います。以上の点から全体を訳し直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>否定的意見</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The negative opinion</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Negative opinion</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Negative opinion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="27">
<j>永原慶二『皇国史観』（岩波ブックレット・1983年）は皇国史観を超国家主義の国家政策の一環とし、「周到な国家的スケールのもとに創出されたいわば国定の虚偽観念の体系」としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Kokoku Shikan&apos; written by Kenji NAGAHARA (Iwanami Booklet, 1983), the Teikoko shikan was considered as a part of National policy, it is said &apos;It has the system of the national false concept created by carefully prepared national scale&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Kokoku Shikan&apos; written by Kenji NAGAHARA (Iwanami Booklet, 1983), the Teikoko shikan was considered as a part of National policy, it is said &apos;It was a system of false national concepts created and carefully prepared on a national scale&apos;.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Kokoku Shikan&quot;, which was written by Keiji NAGAHARA (Iwanami Booklet, 1983), the Kokokushikan was considered to be a part of the national policy of extreme nationalism and &apos;was a system of false national concepts created and carefully prepared on a national scale.&apos;</e>
<cmt>→&quot;Kenji→Keiji スペルを修正ピリオドの位置移動「超国家主義の」を訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="28">
<j>つくる会など保守派について自慰史観または歴史修正主義とする立場から、神話と史実とを峻別せず、天皇や国家へ無批判であるとして「皇国史観の復活」だと批判する声もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The conservative group like the creative group did not separate the mythology and historical fact as they believe in the concept of self-consolation and the principle to amend the history, some people said it is &apos;the revival of the Kokushikan&apos; since there is no criticism towards Emperor and the nation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The conservative group, like the creative group, did not separate mythology and historical fact, as they believed in the concept of self-consolation and the principle to amend the history, some people said it is &apos;the revival of the Kokushikan&apos; since there was no criticism of the Emperor and the nation.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The conservative group, like the creative group, did not separate mythology and historical fact, as they believed in the concept of self-consolation and the principle to amend the history, some people said it is &apos;the revival of the Kokokushikan&apos; since there was no criticism of the Emperor and the nation.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Los688(id:12316), Straysheep(id:42448), 霧木諒二(id:9795), 経済準学士(id:22656), MIsogi(id:20599), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), YuTanaka(id:7689), Sfad(id:206689), Johncapistrano(id:969), Lahem(id:33122), らりた(id:1327), Hermeneus(id:380), 海行かば(id:115823), 日本一弱い男(id:92046), 怪蘇(id:45514), 竹麦魚(id:11012), Ttfcache(id:56475), Auxgllot(id:110551), Ich57(id:43158), KASAGI(id:24405), Bankokuya(id:91191), 井上経介(id:32753), Poe(id:16973), Sweeper tamonten(id:183520), TEy(id:32722), カウティリヤ(id:106346), 葉月(id:25674), Memosa(id:131221), せいすいえいこ(id:169927), 太宰由紀夫(id:41690), かしぱん(id:33839), ＮｉＫｅ(id:7512), Nutcracker(id:39494), Mook(id:131189), 上(id:14148), 兵庫大将(id:129966), Sekai s2(id:112331), 伏儀(id:142093), Chuta(id:10457), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>