<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>聖助法親王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monk-Imperial Prince Seijo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Monk-Imperial Prince Seijo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Monk-Imperial Prince Seijo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>聖助法親王（せいじょほっしんのう、生没年不詳）は、南北朝時代の法親王。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monk Imperial Prince Seijyo (date of birth and death unknown) was the Monk Imperial Prince in the period of the Southern and Northern Dynasties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Monk Imperial Prince Seijyo (date of birth and death unknown) was the Monk Imperial Prince during the period of the Southern and Northern Dynasties.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Monk Imperial Prince Seijo (date of birth and death unknown) was the Monk Imperial Prince during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt>人名のスペルを修正Dynasties→CourtsSouthern and Northern→Northern and Southernに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は後醍醐天皇。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Emperor Godaigo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Emperor Godaigo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Emperor Godaigo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は正三位菅原在仲の娘少将内侍。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother is Shosho no naish, the daughter of SUGAWARA no Arinaka, shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother is Shosho no naish, the daughter of SUGAWARA no Arinaka, shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was Shosho no naishi, the daughter of SUGAWARA no Arinaka, Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>is→wasスペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>出家後、京都青蓮院に入り、1335年（建武2年）親王宣下を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became a priest, and entered into Kyoto Shoren-in Temple; he was announced as the imperial prince in 1335.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became a priest, and entered Kyoto Shoren-in Temple; he was announced as the imperial prince in 1335.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became a priest, and entered Kyoto Shoren-in Temple; he was announced as the Imperial Prince in 1335.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>その後熊野三山検校・園城寺長吏に就任している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he assumed the posts; kengyo of Three Shrines of Kumano; chori (the head priest who governs the affair of a temple) of Onjo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he assumed the posts; kengyo of Three Shrines of Kumano; chori (the head priest who governs the affairs of a temple) of Onjo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he assumed the posts; kengy (temple or shrine administrator) of Three Shrines of Kumano; chori (the head priest who governs the affairs of a temple) of Onjo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除「kengyo」に英語の説明を加えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), 代言人(id:33675), R28Bot(id:177951), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>