<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>降嫁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">koka</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koka</e>
<cmt>最初の一文字を大文字に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>降嫁（こうか）とは、皇女や王女が皇族・王族以外の男性に嫁ぐことをいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koka means that a Princess or a princess marry a man who is not a member of Imperial family nor the royal family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koka means that an Imperial princess or a princess marries a man who is not a member of Imperial family nor the royal family.</e>
<cmt>a Princess or a princess -&gt; an Imperial princess or a princess</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koka means that an Imperial princess or a princess marries a man who is not a member of Imperial family nor the royal family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日本では皇族女性、特に内親王が非皇族（臣下）に嫁ぐ場合を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, koka refers to the case of marriage between a woman in Imperial family, especially an Imperial Princess, and a man from a non-royal family (a subject).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, koka refers to the case of marriage between a woman from Imperial family, especially an Imperial Princess, and a man from a non-imperial family (a subject).</e>
<cmt>in Imperial family -&gt; from Imperial familynon-royal -&gt; non-imperial</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, koka refers to the case of marriage between a woman from Imperial family, especially an Imperial Princess, and a man from a non-imperial family (a subject).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>内親王の結婚相手は律令の「継嗣令」では天皇もしくは四世以上の皇族に限るとされ、古代には非皇族との結婚はなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;the Heir Decree&quot; in the Ritsuryo codes, an Imperial Princess should marry an Emperor or a member of Imperial family who is second, third or fourth generation of an Emperor, and in ancient times there was no marriage between an Imperial Princess and non-royalty.</e>
<cmt>継嗣令→the Heir Decree と訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;the Heir Decree&quot; in the Ritsuryo codes, an Imperial Princess should marry an Emperor or a member of Imperial family who was within the fourth generations of an Emperor, and in ancient times there was no marriage between an Imperial Princess and non-imperial family.</e>
<cmt>non-royal -&gt; non-imperial「４世以上」はwithin the forth generationsとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;the Heir Decree&quot; in the Ritsuryo codes, an Imperial Princess should marry an Emperor or a member of Imperial family who was within the fourth generations of an Emperor, and in ancient times there was no marriage between an Imperial Princess and non-imperial family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>しかし平安時代に入り、皇女が臣下に嫁ぐ例が見られるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in Heian period, some Imperial princesses got married to subjects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in Heian period, some Imperial princesses got married to subjects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in Heian period, some Imperial princesses got married to subjects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>これを降嫁といい、皇女を妻に貰い受けることは男性にとっては非常に名誉な事とされ、主に平安中期に多く行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is koka, and it was extremely honorable for men to take a Princess to wife and there were much cases of koka in the middle of Heian period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is koka, and it was extremely honorable for a man to take a Princess to his wife and there were many cases of koka in the middle of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>men -&gt; a manmuch cases -&gt; many cases</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is koka, and it was extremely honorable for a man to take a Princess to his wife and there were many cases of koka in the middle of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>同時代の文学作品である『源氏物語』においても、大宮 (源氏物語)（左大臣正室、葵の上の母）、女三宮（光源氏正室）、落葉の宮（柏木 (源氏物語)正室、のち夕霧 (源氏物語)と再婚）、女二宮（薫正室）などの例が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Genji), a literary work of this period, we can find much cases of koka of women such as Omiya (Genji Monogatari) (the lawful wife of the Sadaijin [Minister of the left] and the mother of Aoi no ue [Lady Aoi]), Onna Sannomiya (the lawful wife of Hikaru Genji), Ochiba no miya (the lawful wife of Kashiwagi [Genji Monogatari], who had second marriage to Yugiri [Genji Monogatari]), and Onnaninomiya (the lawful wife of Kaoru) and so on.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Genji), a literary work of this period, we can find many cases of koka such as Omiya (the lawful wife of the Sadaijin [Minister of the left] and the mother of Aoi no ue [Lady Aoi]), Onna Sannomiya (the lawful wife of Hikaru Genji), Ochiba no miya (the lawful wife of Kashiwagi, who later remarried to Yugiri), and Onna Ninomiya (the lawful wife of Kaoru) and so on.</e>
<cmt>much cases -&gt; many cases(Genji Monogatari)/[Genji Monogatari] 英文では分かりにくいため、カッコ部分を削除しました。Onnaninomiya -&gt; Onna Ninomiya</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Genji), a literary work of this period, we can find many cases of koka such as Omiya (the lawful wife of the Sadaijin [Minister of the left] and the mother of Aoi no ue [Lady Aoi]), Onna Sannomiya (the lawful wife of Hikaru Genji), Ochiba no miya (the lawful wife of Kashiwagi, who later remarried to Yugiri), and Onna Ninomiya (the lawful wife of Kaoru) and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>その後は女院の増加や親王宣下の減少などにより、平安後期から鎌倉時代・室町時代にかけて、内親王の降嫁は殆ど途絶える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, from the late Heian period to Kamakura and Muromachi period, koka of Imperial Princess had come to an end because of the increase of nyoin (woman bestowed with the title &quot;in&quot;) and the decrease of giving the title of Imperial Princess.</e>
<cmt>この場合、親王宣下の減少により内親王が減少したと判断し、親王宣下を　given the title of Imperial Princess　としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the late Heian period to the Kamakura and the Muromachi period, koka of Imperial Princess came to an end because of the increase of nyoin (woman bestowed with the title &quot;in&quot;) and the decrease of giving the title of Imperial Princess.</e>
<cmt>After that, を削除しました。had come to -&gt; came to</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the late Heian period to the Kamakura and the Muromachi period, koka of Imperial Princess came to an end because of the increase of nyoin (woman bestowed with the title &quot;in&quot;) and the decrease of giving the title of Imperial Princess.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>江戸時代に入り五摂家への降嫁が復活した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Edo period, koka to Gosekke, the five biggest court nobles, began to be done again.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period, koka to Gosekke, the five biggest court noble families, started again.</e>
<cmt>In Edo preiod -&gt; In the Edo period （用語統一リスト「明治時代」の表記に合わせました。）to be done -&gt;started</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period, koka to Gosekke, the five biggest court noble families, started again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また幕末には和宮親子内親王が征夷大将軍徳川家茂に嫁し、唯一武家への降嫁の例となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, in the end of Edo period, Imperial Princess Kazunomiya Chikako married to a Seii Taishogun (commander-in-chief of the expeditionary force against the barbarians, great, unifying leader), Iemochi TOKUGAWA and this was the only case of koka to a samurai family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, in the end of Edo period, Imperial Princess Kazunomiya Chikako married to a Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;), Iemochi TOKUGAWA and this was the only case of koka to a samurai family.</e>
<cmt>Then -&gt; Later…unifying leader)の半角スペースを削除しました。原文「、また幕末・・・」を「また幕末・・・」に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, in the end of Edo period, Imperial Princess Kazunomiya Chikako married to a Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;), Iemochi TOKUGAWA and this was the only case of koka to a samurai family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>なお内親王は非皇族と結婚しても、本人の皇族としての身分はそのままであり、皇族を離れて嫁ぎ先の姓を名乗ることはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Princesses kept their Imperial family lineage after their marriage to non-royal men, so they wouldn&apos;t identify themselves as their husband&apos;s family names.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Princesses kept their Imperial family status after they married to men from non-imperial families, so they weren&apos;t identified themselves by their husbands&apos; family names.</e>
<cmt>grammarnon-royal -&gt; non-imperial</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Princesses kept their Imperial family status after they married to men from non-imperial families, so they weren&apos;t identified themselves by their husbands&apos; family names.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>このため厳密には「降嫁」ではないとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore some people say those are strictly not the cases of &quot;koka.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, such cases are not considered &apos;koka&apos; in a strict sense.</e>
<cmt>英文を書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, such cases are not considered &apos;koka&apos; in a strict sense.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし現代は皇室典範により、非皇族との結婚に際しては皇籍離脱が定められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In modern age, however, Imperial House Act stipulates that an Imperial Princess should leave from Imperial family when she marries a man from non-royal family, therefore Imperial Princesses who did koka after the accession of Emperor Showa identified themselves as their husband&apos;s family names.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In modern age, however, Imperial House Act provides that an Imperial Princess should leave Imperial family when she marries a man from non-imperial family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。grammarnon-royal -&gt; non-imperial</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In modern age, however, Imperial House Act provides that an Imperial Princess should leave Imperial family when she marries a man from non-imperial family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>このため、昭和天皇以降の内親王は臣籍降下している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore Imperial Princesses who did koka (got married a man from non-imperial family) after the enthronement of Emperor Showa were identified themselves by their husbands&apos; family names.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。&apos;did koka&apos; にカッコ書きで補足説明を追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore Imperial Princesses who did koka (got married a man from non-imperial family) after the enthronement of Emperor Showa were identified themselves by their husbands&apos; family names.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>降嫁した内親王・皇女</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Princesses and Princesses who did koka</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Princesses and Princesses who did koka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Princesses and Princesses who did koka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>皇女の降嫁の初例としてよく挙げられるのは、嵯峨天皇皇女源潔姫と藤原良房の婚姻であるが、潔姫の場合は結婚前に既に源氏姓を賜り臣籍に下っており、内親王と臣下が結婚した初例は醍醐天皇皇女勤子内親王と藤原師輔である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although many people regards the marriage between MINAMOTO no Kiyohime, an Imperial princess of Emperor Saga, and FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa as the first case of koka, Kiyohime had already been given the name of Minamoto clan and decended to subject status before their marriage, so the first case of marriage between an Imperial Princess and a subject is that of Imperial Princess Isoko; Imperial Princess Kinshi, a daughter of Emperor Godaigo, and FUJIWARA no Morosuke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the marriage between MINAMOTO no Kiyohime, an Imperial princess of Emperor Saga, and FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa is regarded as the first case of koka, Kiyohime had already been given the name of Minamoto clan and descended to the subject status before their marriage, so the first case of marriage between an Imperial Princess and a subject is that of Imperial Princess Isoko (Kinshi), a daughter of Emperor Godaigo, and FUJIWARA no Morosuke.</e>
<cmt>英文を書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the marriage between MINAMOTO no Kiyohime, an Imperial princess of Emperor Saga, and FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa is regarded as the first case of koka, Kiyohime had already been given the name of Minamoto clan and descended to the subject status before their marriage, so the first case of marriage between an Imperial Princess and a subject is that of Imperial Princess Isoko (Kinshi), a daughter of Emperor Godaigo, and FUJIWARA no Morosuke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>ただしこの時は父天皇の許可を得ていなかったと見られ、天皇により内親王の降嫁が裁可されたのは、三条天皇皇女禔子内親王の例が最初とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Imperial Princess Isoko supposedly did not get permission from her father Emperor and therefore it is said that the first case of koka with an emperor&apos;s permission is that of Imperial Princess Teishi, a daughter of Emperor Sanjo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Imperial Princess Isoko supposedly did not get permission from her father Emperor and therefore it is said that the first case of koka with an emperor&apos;s approval is that of Imperial Princess Teishi, a daughter of Emperor Sanjo.</e>
<cmt>降嫁を認めて許すという意味で禔子内親王の場合はpermission -&gt; approval　としています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Imperial Princess Isoko supposedly did not get permission from her father Emperor and therefore it is said that the first case of koka with an emperor&apos;s approval is that of Imperial Princess Teishi, a daughter of Emperor Sanjo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), MioUzaki(id:89034), YukkeBot2(id:251491), COCKY(id:19672), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>