<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>譲位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Abdication of the throne</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Abdication of the throne</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Abdication of the throne</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>譲位（じょうい）は、皇帝、国王、天皇といった君主の地位にある者が、その地位を後継者へ譲り渡すことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Abdication of the throne means that a person with the position of a monarch, such as odai, emperor, and king, transfers the position to a successor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Abdication of the throne means that a person with the position of a monarch, such as czar, emperor, and king, transfers the position to a successor.</e>
<cmt>皇帝と天皇は用語集ではemperorですが、言い分けるのであればodaiよりもczarが適切だと思われます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Abdication of the throne means that a person with the position of a monarch, such as emperor and king, transfers the position to a successor.</e>
<cmt>用語集、過去のファイルでも、天皇と皇帝は同じemperorを使用しているようですのでそのようにしました（czar削除）。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>特に、世襲を原則とした地位の継承について言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular, it is succession of the position by heredity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, it is succession of the position by heredity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, it is succession of the position by heredity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>また、東アジアの漢字文化圏においては、地位を譲り受けることを、受禅（じゅぜん）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inheritance of the position is called juzen (accession to the throne as a result of sb&apos;s abdication) in East-Asian countries where Chinese characters are used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inheritance of the position is called juzen (accession to the throne as a result of sb&apos;s abdication) in East-Asian countries where Chinese characters are used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Succession to the throne in this fashion is called juzen (accession to the throne as a result of the monarch&apos;s abdication) in East-Asian countries where Chinese characters are used.</e>
<cmt>sb&apos;s→the monarch&apos;sとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>概説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>君主を含む権力者が、世襲その他のあらかじめ決められている地位継承の規定や慣例によらず、有能であるなどの理由で、その地位にふさわしいと考える者に自分の地位を譲ることは、譲位ではなく、禅譲と言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The transfer of the position by a powerful person, including a monarch, to another person who he considers is appropriate for the position because he was capable, without depending on regulations or customs of heredity or predetermined rules of succession of positions is not abdication of the throne, but peaceful transfer of power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The transfer of a position from a powerful person, including a monarch, to another person who he considers is appropriate for the position because he is capable, regardless of heredity or predetermined regulations or customs of succession of a position, is not an abdication of the throne, but jozen (peaceful transfer of power).</e>
<cmt>時制や言い回しを訂正しました。また、譲位と禅譲の違いを説明している箇所なので、禅譲をzenjoとして、そのあとに説明を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The transfer of a position from a powerful person, including a monarch, to another person who he considers is appropriate for the position because he is capable, regardless of heredity or predetermined regulations or customs of succession of a position, is not an abdication of the throne, but jozen (peaceful transfer of power).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また、前任者の意思によらずにその地位についた場合の継承は、譲位とは言わない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If a person succeeds the position without the intension of a predecessor, it is not called abdication of the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If a person succeeds the position without the intension of a predecessor, it is not called an abdication of the throne, either.</e>
<cmt>言い回しを訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If a person succeeds the position without the intension of a predecessor, it is not called an abdication of the throne, either.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>譲位は、君主の意思の表現、とみなすことができる場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Abdication of the throne may be considered as representation of the intension of a monarch.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Abdication of the throne may be considered as representation of the intension of a monarch.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Abdication of the throne may be considered as representation of the intension of a monarch.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>たとえば、江戸時代の後水尾天皇は、紫衣事件など、天皇の権威を失墜させる江戸幕府の行いに耐えかね、幼少の興子内親王（後の明正天皇）へ譲位を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, Emperor Gomizunoo in the Edo period was unable to endure the deeds of the Edo bakufu which lost the authority of the emperor, such as the Shie Incident (the great conflict between the shogunate and the Imperial Court), and abdicated the throne to infant Princess Okiko (later Emperor Meisho).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, Emperor Gomizunoo in the Edo period was unable to endure the deeds of the Edo bakufu which eroded the authority of the emperor, like the Shie Incident (the great conflict between the shogunate and the Imperial Court), and abdicated the throne to an infant Princess Okiko (later Emperor Meisho).</e>
<cmt>語句を訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, Emperor Gomizunoo in the Edo period was unable to endure the deeds of the Edo bakufu which eroded the authority of the emperor, like the Shie Incident (the great conflict between the shogunate and the Imperial Court), and abdicated the throne to an infant Princess Okiko (later Emperor Meisho).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>この譲位は、幕府に対する天皇の抗議、という意味でとらえられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This abdication is regarded as a protest of the emperor against the bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This abdication is regarded as a protest from the emperor against the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>語句を訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This abdication is regarded as a protest from the emperor against the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>通常、譲位した天皇は太上天皇（上皇）の尊号を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Normally, retired emperors had honorary titles of Daijo Tenno.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Normally, retired emperors had the honorary title of Daijo Tenno (or Joko).</e>
<cmt>文法を訂正し、（上皇）の訳を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Normally, retired emperors had the honorary title of Daijo Tenno (or Joko).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>上皇となった天皇が再び天皇に即位した例もある（重祚）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some retired emperors acceded to the throne again (choso).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some retired emperors acceded to the throne again (choso [a second accession to the imperial throne]).</e>
<cmt>（重祚）の訳を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some retired emperors acceded to the throne again (choso [a second accession to the imperial throne]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>ただし、譲位がたとえ君主の意思表示であったとしてもそれだけでは不可能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, abdication of the throne is impossible even if a monarch expresses his will.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is not enough for a monarch to expresses his will to actually carry out the abdication of the throne.</e>
<cmt>言い回しを訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is not enough for a monarch to expresses his will to actually carry out the abdication of the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>譲位の儀式及び退位後の上皇の御所造営には莫大な費用がかかり、朝廷がそれを負担出来なければ譲位は行えなかったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since it required enormous expenses to carry out an abdication ceremony and build an imperial palace for the retired emperor, he could not abdicate the throne if the imperial court could not bear them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since it required enormous expenses to carry out an abdication ceremony and build a court for the retired emperor, he could not abdicate the throne if the imperial court could not bear the cost.</e>
<cmt>この場合の御所は単語リストの院御所に当たると思われますのでcourtとしました。最後のthemを具体的にcostとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since it required enormous expenses to carry out an abdication ceremony and build a court for the retired emperor, he could not abdicate the throne if the imperial court could not bear the cost.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>実際、室町幕府の支援で儀式を行った後花園天皇と豊臣政権の支援で儀式を行った正親町天皇の間の戦国時代_(日本)に在位した3代の天皇（後土御門天皇・後柏原天皇・後奈良天皇）は全て在位のまま崩御している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The three emperors (Emperor Gotsuchimikado, Emperor Gokashiwabara, and Emperor Gonara) in the Sengoku period (Japan), between Emperor GoHanazono who carried out a ceremony in support of the Muromachi bakufu and Emperor Ogimachi who carried out a ceremony in support of the Toyotomi regime, died on the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The three emperors (Emperor Gotsuchimikado, Emperor Gokashiwabara, and Emperor Gonara) in the Sengoku period (period of warring states) (Japan), between Emperor Gohanazono who carried out his abdication ceremony in support of the Muromachi bakufu and Emperor Ogimachi who carried out his ceremony in support of the Toyotomi regime, died on the throne.</e>
<cmt>戦国時代の説明を補いました。儀式が譲位の儀式であることを明確にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The three emperors (Emperor Gotsuchimikado, Emperor Gokashiwabara, and Emperor Gonara) in the Sengoku period (period of warring states) (Japan), between Emperor Gohanazono who carried out his abdication ceremony in support of the Muromachi bakufu and Emperor Ogimachi who carried out his ceremony in support of the Toyotomi regime, died on the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>大日本帝国憲法下、また日本国憲法下の近代日本においては、天皇の譲位は認められていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The abdication of the throne is not permitted in Japan in modern times under the Constitution of the Empire of Japan or the Constitution of the Empire of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The abdication of the throne is not permitted in Japan in modern times under the Constitution of the Empire of Japan or the Constitution of Japan.</e>
<cmt>日本国憲法の訳を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The abdication of the throne is not permitted in Japan in modern times under the Constitution of the Empire of Japan or the Constitution of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>1889年に制定された旧皇室典範では、その第10条で「天皇崩スルトキハ皇嗣即チ践祚シ祖宗ノ神器ヲ承ク」と規定し、天皇の死去によって皇位の継承が行われることを定め、占領下の1947年に法律として制定された現行の皇室典範でも、その第4条で「天皇が崩じたときは、皇嗣が、直ちに即位する」と規定し、旧皇室典範と同様に、皇位の継承は天皇の死去によってのみ行われることを定めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Article 10 of the Former Imperial House Act established in 1889 stipulates &apos;When the emperor dies, the Crown Prince ascends the throne and inherits his jingi&apos;, which specifies that the crown prince takes the throne when the emperor dies, and article 4 of the Imperial House Act established in 1947 in Japan under occupation also specifies &apos;When the emperor dies, the Crown Prince ascends the throne immediately&apos;, indicating that the crown prince takes the throne only when the emperor dies, like the Former Imperial House Act.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Article 10 of the Former Imperial House Law established in 1889 stipulates, &apos;When the emperor dies, the Crown Prince ascends the throne and inherits his jingi [the sacred treasures]&apos;, which specifies that the crown prince takes the throne when the emperor dies, and article 4 of the Imperial House Law established in 1947 in Japan under occupation also specifies, &apos;When the emperor dies, the Crown Prince ascends the throne immediately&apos;, indicating that the crown prince takes the throne only when the emperor dies, like the Former Imperial House Law.</e>
<cmt>旧皇室典範の訳を単語リストに揃えました。神器の説明を追加しました。文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Article 10 of the Former Imperial House Law established in 1889 stipulates, &apos;When the emperor dies, the Crown Prince ascends the throne and inherits his jingi [the sacred treasures]&apos;, which specifies that the crown prince takes the throne when the emperor dies, and article 4 of the Imperial House Law established in 1947 in Japan under occupation also specifies, &apos;When the emperor dies, the Crown Prince ascends the throne immediately&apos;, indicating that the crown prince takes the throne only when the emperor dies, like the Former Imperial House Law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また、旧皇室典範では、皇位継承の順序を明確に規定しており、現行の皇室典範でも、第2条で皇位継承の順序を、第3条でその順序の変更について規定しており、天皇はみずからの意思によって継承者を指名することはできない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Former Imperial House Act specifies the order of succession to the Imperial Throne clearly, and article 3 of the current Imperial House Act specifies changes of the order of succession and the emperor cannot appoint his successor on his own free will.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Former Imperial House Law specifies the order of succession to the Imperial Throne clearly, and the article 2 of the current Imperial House Law stipulates the order of succession to the Imperial Throne and the article 3 specifies the changes of the order, so the emperor cannot appoint his successor on his own free will.</e>
<cmt>旧皇室典範の訳を単語リストに揃えました。第2条の記述漏れを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Former Imperial House Law specifies the order of succession to the Imperial Throne clearly, and the article 2 of the current Imperial House Law stipulates the order of succession to the Imperial Throne and the article 3 specifies the changes of the order, so the emperor cannot appoint his successor on his own free will.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 いろはにほへと(id:89648), Nnh(id:474), 経済準学士(id:22656), 水野白楓(id:22811), 秀の介(id:490), Ideal(id:236), 梅澤 威志(id:17353), Extrahitz(id:26245), Gappei2006(id:69935), 伏儀(id:142093), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>