<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>章子内親王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Princess Shoshi(Akiko)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Princess Shoshi</e>
<cmt>Headings should generally be kept as short as possible so try not to include information that can best be dealt with in the main text (such as alternative readings of someone&apos;s name)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Princess Shoshi</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>章子内親王（しょうし（あきこ）ないしんのう、万寿3年12月9日（1027年1月19日） - 長治2年9月17日（1105年10月26日））は第68代後一条天皇第一皇女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Princess Shoshi(Akiko) (January 19, 1027 - October 26, 1105) was the first princess of the sixty-eighth Emperor Goichijo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Princess Shoshi (her given name can also be pronounced &quot;Akiko&quot;) (January 19, 1027 - October 26, 1105) was the first daughter of the sixty-eighth emperor, Emperor Goichijo.</e>
<cmt>Expressions like &quot;first princess of the emperor&quot; are a bit vague and can be difficult to understand. In addition to the usual meaning of &quot;princess&quot;, the Kenkyusha Online Dictionary also gives &quot;daughter of a monarch&quot; as a possible translation for 皇女. Please try to translate the meaning according to the context rather than the individual words.Also, if you just put &quot;Akiko&quot; in parentheses without any explanation, a native speaker of English will not necessarily be able to work out what this is supposed to mean. Try to add a short phrase to help the reader.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Princess Shoshi (her given name can also be pronounced &quot;Akiko&quot;) (January 19, 1027 - October 26, 1105) was the first daughter of the sixty-eighth emperor, Emperor Goichijo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>母は藤原道長女・中宮藤原威子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her mother was the second consort of an emperor, FUJIWARA no Ishi (Takeko), who was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Michinaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her mother was FUJIWARA no Ishi, who was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Michinaga and the second consort of an emperor.</e>
<cmt>As FUJIWARA no Ishi is not really the main focus of this page, I don&apos;t think it is necessary to provide alternative readings of her name (unless the Japanese expressly does so).</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her mother was FUJIWARA no Ishi, who was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Michinaga and the second consort of an emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>第70代後冷泉天皇中宮、女院。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was the second consort of the seventieth Emperor Goreizei, and nyoin (an honorific title for the mother of emperor(s), etc).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was the second consort of the seventieth Emperor, Emperor Goreizei, and held the title Nyoin (an honorific title for the mother of an emperor, etc).</e>
<cmt>It would be helpful if the translator could indicate how they arrived at the translation for a term such as &quot;女院&quot; or label it as 仮訳 if it is their own creation. I cannot imagine what the &quot;etc.&quot; means in the definition of Nyoin. The brother/sister of an Emperor, perhaps? Please check whether the &quot;etc.&quot; is necessary.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was the second consort of the seventieth Emperor, Emperor Goreizei, and held the title Nyoin (an honorific title for the mother of an emperor, etc).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>院号は二条院。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her ingo (a title of respect given to close female relatives of the Emperor or a woman of comparable standing) was Nijoin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her Ingo (a title of respect given to close female relatives of the Emperor or a woman of comparable standing) was Nijoin.</e>
<cmt>Capital</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her Ingo (a title of respect given to close female relatives of the Emperor or a woman of comparable standing) was Nijoin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>同母妹に馨子内親王（後三条天皇中宮）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her half sister was Imperial Princess Keishi (Kaoruko)(the second consort of Emperor Gosanjo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her half-sister was Princess Keishi (the second consort of Emperor Gosanjo).</e>
<cmt>I don&apos;t think you need to say &quot;Imperial Princess&quot;, just &quot;Princess&quot; is enough. Again, I don&apos;t think it is necessary to provide alternative readings for a name unless the Japanese expressly does so.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her half-sister was Princess Keishi (the second consort of Emperor Gosanjo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>万寿4年（1027年）内親王宣下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1027, she received a title of Imperial Princess by the emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1027, she received a title of Imperial Princess by the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1027, she received a title of Imperial Princess by the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>長元3年（1030年）着袴と共に准后・一品に叙される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was given the title of jugo and ippon (the first of Imperial Princes&apos; rank) with chakko (dressing children a hakama to celebrate their growth) at the same time in 1030.</e>
<cmt>着袴の説明を（）内に加えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was given the title of jugo and ippon (the first rank for an Imperial Princes) with chakko (dressing children in a hakama to celebrate their growth) at the same time in 1030.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was given the title of jugo and ippon (the first rank for an Imperial Princes) with chakko (dressing children in a hakama to celebrate their growth) at the same time in 1030.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>同9年（1036年）に父後一条天皇と母中宮威子が相次いで崩御、幼くして両親と死別した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She lost her father, Emperor Goichijo, and her mother, the second consort of an emperor, Ishi (Takeko), one after another in 1036, so she lost both of her parents at a young age.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She lost her father, Emperor Goichijo, and her mother, the second consort of the emperor, Ishi (Takeko), one after another in 1036, so she lost both of her parents at a young age.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She lost her father, Emperor Goichijo, and her mother, the second consort of the emperor, Ishi (Takeko), one after another in 1036, so she lost both of her parents at a young age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>長暦元年（1037年）着裳、12歳で皇太子親仁親王（のちの後冷泉天皇）に入内。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She had chakumo (dressing adult woman in kimono for the first time) in 1037 and made her bridal entry into the court of the Crown Prince of Imperial Prince Chikahito (who would later become Emperor Goreizei) at the age of twelve.</e>
<cmt>着裳→chakumo (dressing adult woman in kimono for the first time)［定訳不明］</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She had chakumo (dressing as an adult woman in kimono for the first time) in 1037 and made her bridal entry into the court of the Crown Prince Chikahito (who would later become Emperor Goreizei) at the age of twelve.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She had chakumo (dressing as an adult woman in kimono for the first time) in 1037 and made her bridal entry into the court of the Crown Prince Chikahito (who would later become Emperor Goreizei) at the age of twelve.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>寛徳2年（1045年）親仁親王の受禅に伴って女御宣下を受け、永承元年（1046年）中宮に冊立される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With juzen (accession to the throne as a result of sb&apos;s abdication) of Imperial Prince Chikahito in 1045, she received a title of nyogo (a court title given to a consort of the Emperor) and was officially appointed as the second consort of the emperor in 1046.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the juzen (accession to the throne as a result of abdication) of Imperial Prince Chikahito in 1045, she received the title of nyogo (a court title given to a consort of the Emperor) and was officially appointed as the second consort of the emperor in 1046.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the juzen (accession to the throne as a result of abdication) of Imperial Prince Chikahito in 1045, she received the title of nyogo (a court title given to a consort of the Emperor) and was officially appointed as the second consort of the emperor in 1046.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>治暦4年（1068年）皇太后、その2日後に後冷泉天皇崩御。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Goreizei died two days after the Empress Dowager died in 1068.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Goreizei died two days after the Empress Dowager died in 1068.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Goreizei died two days after the Empress Dowager died in 1068.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>延久元年（1069年）落飾、太皇太后となり、同6年（1074年）院号宣下を受けて以後二条院と称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She shaved her head to entered the priesthood, became the Grand Empress Dowager in 1069, and named herself as Nijyoin by receiving a title of ingo in 1074.</e>
<cmt>落飾→shaving head to enter the priesthood【定訳不明】</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She shaved her head to enter the priesthood, became the Grand Empress Dowager in 1069, and named herself Nijyoin after receiving the title ingo in 1074.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She shaved her head to enter the priesthood, became the Grand Empress Dowager in 1069, and named herself Nijoin after receiving the title ingo in 1074.</e>
<cmt>名前スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>長治2年（1105年）崩御。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She died in 1105.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She died in 1105.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She died in 1105.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>享年80。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was eighty years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was eighty years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was eighty years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>後一条天皇の第一子に生まれ、期待された男御子ではなかったが両親に非常に鍾愛された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was the first child of Emperor Goichijo, not an Imperial prince as expected, but her parents loved her very much.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was the first child of Emperor Goichijo, not an Imperial prince as expected, but her parents loved her very much.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was the first child of Emperor Goichijo, not an Imperial prince as expected, but her parents loved her very much.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>温順な性格の美しい皇女であったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was a docile and well-natured Imperial princess.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was a docile and well-natured Imperial princess.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was a docile and well-natured Imperial princess.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>両親亡き後は祖母（母方では伯母）藤原彰子の庇護を受けて成長し、東宮妃として入内した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After her parents&apos; death, she was raised by her grandmother (maternal aunt), FUJIWARA no Shoshi (Akiko) and made her bridal entry into the court as the Crown Princess.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After her parents&apos; death, she was raised by her grandmother (maternal aunt), FUJIWARA no Shoshi (Akiko) and made her bridal entry into the court as the Crown Princess.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After her parents&apos; death, she was raised by her grandmother (maternal aunt), FUJIWARA no Shoshi (Akiko) and made her bridal entry into the court as the Crown Princess.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>藤原道長の死後はその子息たちが後宮政策で互いに牽制し合う状況にあり、当時は関白藤原頼通の娘がいまだ幼かったため恐らく折衷案として、道長一族に連なり上東門院の後見を受ける章子内親王が選ばれたと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After FUJIWARA no Michinaga&apos;s death, his sons warned against each other regarding the inner palace policy, so it would appear that Imperial Princess Shoshi(Akiko) was placed under the guardianship of Jotomonin as one of Michinaga clan, and this was probably the compromise plan since the daughter of FUJIWARA no Yorimichi was too young at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After FUJIWARA no Michinaga&apos;s death, his sons warned each other regarding the inner palace policy, so it would appear that Princess Shoshi (Akiko) was placed under the guardianship of Jotomonin as one of the members of the Michinaga clan, and this was probably a compromise plan since the daughter of FUJIWARA no Yorimichi was too young at that time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After FUJIWARA no Michinaga&apos;s death, his sons warned each other regarding the inner palace policy, so it would appear that Princess Shoshi (Akiko) was placed under the guardianship of Jotomonin as one of the members of the Michinaga clan, and this was probably a compromise plan since the daughter of FUJIWARA no Yorimichi was too young at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>後に頼通の娘藤原寛子入内に際して、内親王がこのまま中宮でよいと言ったという話が『栄花物語』に見えるが、これは先帝後朱雀天皇の後宮で同じく中宮であった禎子内親王（章子内親王には母方の従姉妹にあたる）が頼通の養女藤原嫄子の立后で皇后に押し上げられ、宮中入りもままならなかった状況を見ていたためでもあるだろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When FUJIWARA no Kanshi (Hiroko), a daughter of Yorimichi, made her bridal entry into the court in later times, &quot;Eiga monogatari (Tale of Flowering Fortunes)&quot; described that Imperial Princess said she would continue to be the second consort of an emperor, but it was because she saw the situation where Imperial Princess Teishi (Yoshiko/Sadako)(maternal cousin for Imperial Princess Shoshi(Akiko)), the second consort of the former Emperor Gosuzaku at the inner palace, was forced to become an empress by the order from FUJIWARA no Genshi, adopted daughter of Yorimichi, and barely entered the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When FUJIWARA no Kanshi (Hiroko), a daughter of Yorimichi, made her bridal entry into the court in later times, &quot;Eiga monogatari (Tale of Flowering Fortunes)&quot; described that the Princess said she would continue to be the second consort of an emperor, but it was because she saw the situation where Princess Teishi (Yoshiko/Sadako - maternal cousin of Imperial Princess Shoshi (Akiko), the second consort of the former Emperor Gosuzaku at the inner palace, was forced to become an empress by the order from FUJIWARA no Genshi, adopted daughter of Yorimichi, and barely entered the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When FUJIWARA no Kanshi (Hiroko), a daughter of Yorimichi, made her bridal entry into the court in later times, &quot;Eiga monogatari&quot; (Tale of Flowering Fortunes) described that the Princess said she would continue to be the second consort of an emperor, but it was because she saw the situation where Princess Teishi (Yoshiko/Sadako - maternal cousin of Imperial Princess Shoshi (Akiko)), the second consort of the former Emperor Gosuzaku at the inner palace, was forced to become an empress by the order from FUJIWARA no Genshi, adopted daughter of Yorimichi, and barely entered the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>(Tale of Flowering Fortunes)位置移動)補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>とはいえ、高貴でおっとりした人柄であったという章子内親王は夫後冷泉天皇が他の妃を寵愛しても気にすることなく、従って頼通らとの関係も穏やかだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Imperial Princess Shoshi(Akiko) was a noble and gentle person, so she did not mind when her husband, Emperor Goreizei, loved another princess, so the relationship with Yorimichi was peaceful.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Princess Shoshi (Akiko) was a noble and gentle person, so she did not mind when her husband, Emperor Goreizei, loved another princess, so the relationship with Yorimichi was peaceful.</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Princess Shoshi (Akiko) was a noble and gentle person, so she did not mind when her husband, Emperor Goreizei, loved another princess, so the relationship with Yorimichi was peaceful.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>また夫帝や後見の上東門院没後も、国母ではない后としては初めてとなる女院号の宣下さえ受けて、安定した余生を送ったようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, after her husband and the guardian, Jotomonin, died, she even received a title of nyoingo (an honorific title for the mother of emperor(s), etc) which was the first time for the empress who was not the empress dowager to receive it, and lived a stable life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, after her husband and the guardian, Jotomonin, died, she even received the title of nyoingo (an honorific title for the mother of an emperor) which was the first time for the empress, who was not an empress dowager, to receive it, and she lived a stable life.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, after her husband and the guardian, Jotomonin, died, she even received the title of nyoingo (an honorific title for the mother of an emperor) which was the first time for the empress, who was not an empress dowager, to receive it, and she lived a stable life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>（ただし女院宣下については、時の白河天皇女御藤原賢子を立后させるためだったともいわれ、非国母の故か院分受領は給わっていない）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(However, it was said that in order for FUJIWARA no Kenshi, a nyogo of Emperor Shirakawa, to become an empress, she received a title of nyoin and did not receive a title of inbun zuryo (a head of administrative supervisors for a Imperial Palace), it maybe because she was not the empress dowager.) Maybe due to the thick blood relationship with her husband, they were less fortunate to have any children, but because of that, she did not get involved in any Imperial succession conflict and lived out her peaceful life, so maybe she was happy in a way.</e>
<cmt>院分受領→inbun zuryo (a head of administrative supervisors for a Imperial Palace)【定訳不明】</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(However, in order for FUJIWARA no Kenshi, a nyogo of Emperor Shirakawa, to become an empress, she received the title of nyoin and did not receive a title of inbun zuryo (a head of administrative supervisors for a Imperial Palace), it maybe because she was not the empress dowager.) Maybe due to the thick blood relationship with her husband, they were less fortunate not to have any children, but because of that, she did not get involved in any Imperial succession conflict and lived out her peaceful life, so maybe she was happy in a way.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(However, in order for FUJIWARA no Kenshi, a nyogo of Emperor Shirakawa, to become an empress, she received the title of nyoin and did not receive a title of inbun zuryo (a head of administrative supervisors for a Imperial Palace), it maybe because she was not the empress dowager.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>余りにも濃すぎる血縁関係のためか、夫帝との間にはついに御子は恵まれなかったが、それゆえに皇位継承争いに巻き込まれることもなく平穏な生涯をまっとうできたのは、ある意味で内親王にとっては幸せだったのかもしれない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maybe due to the thick blood relationship with her husband, they were less fortunate not to have any children, but because of that, she did not get involved in any Imperial succession conflict and lived out her peaceful life, so maybe she was happy in a way.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="24">
<j>陵墓は父後一条天皇と同じく、菩提樹院陵（京都府京都市左京区吉田神楽岡町）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her ryobo is in Bodaijuin ryo (Yoshida Kaguraoka-cho Town, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture) as same as her father, Emperor Goichijo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her ryobo is in Bodaijuin ryo (Yoshida Kaguraoka-cho Town, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture) the same as her father, Emperor Goichijo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The imperial mausoleum is in Bodaijuin ryo (Yoshida Kaguraoka-cho, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture) the same as her father, Emperor Goichijo.</e>
<cmt>ryobo→imperial mausoleum</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), やりたこ(id:113528), Flénu(id:159955), 代言人(id:33675), Suisui(id:69), 呆庵入道(id:74721), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>