<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>脩子内親王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Princess Shushi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Princess Shushi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Princess Shushi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>脩子内親王（しゅうし / ながこ ないしんのう、長徳2年12月16日 (旧暦)（997年1月27日） - 永承4年2月7日 (旧暦)（1049年3月13日））は、第66代一条天皇の第一皇女で、母は皇后藤原定子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Princess Shushi/Nagako 脩子 (January 27, 997-March 13, 1049) was the first princess of the sixty sixth Emperor Ichijo, and her mother was Empress FUJIWARA no Teishi.</e>
<cmt>文意を明確にするため「しゅうし」を漢字表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Princess Shushi/Nagako 脩子 (January 27, 997-March 13, 1049) was the first princess of the sixty sixth Emperor Ichijo, and her mother was Empress FUJIWARA no Teishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Princess Shushi/Nagako (脩子) (February 1, 997 - March 19, 1049) was the first princess of the sixty sixth Emperor Ichijo, and her mother was Empress FUJIWARA no Teishi.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>『大日本史』では「修子」と表記。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Dainihonshi,&quot; it was indicated as `修子.&apos;</e>
<cmt>文意を明確にするため「しゅうし」を漢字表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Dainihonshi,&quot; it was indicated as `修子.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Dainihonshi&quot; (Great history of Japan), it was indicated as &apos;修子.&apos;</e>
<cmt>大日本史　の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>同母弟妹に敦康親王、び子内親王。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Atsuyasu and Imperial Princess Bishi were her sibling with the same mother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Atsuyasu and Imperial Princess Bishi were her siblings by the same mother.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Atsuyasu and Imperial Princess Bishi were her maternal half-siblings.</e>
<cmt>同母兄弟　表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>早くに母后を亡くし、宮中で育った（一条天皇の詔）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She lost her mother, the empress dowager early, and was brought up in the palace (the imperial edict of Emperor Ichijo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She lost her mother, the empress dowager early, and was brought up in the palace (the imperial edict of Emperor Ichijo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She lost her mother, the empress dowager early, and was brought up in the palace (the imperial edict of Emperor Ichijo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>父帝鍾愛の皇女にして、裳着とともに三品に直叙した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since she was adored by her father, the emperor, she went through Mogi (coming-of-age ceremony for girls) and became Sanbon (the third rank of the Imperial Princess&apos;s ranks) under jikijo (to appoint a rank directly without following the order).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since she was adored by her father, the emperor, she went through Mogi (coming-of-age ceremony for girls) and became Sanbon (the third rank of the Imperial Princess&apos;s ranks) under jikijo (to appoint a rank directly without following the order).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since she was adored by her father, the emperor, she went through Mogi (coming-of-age ceremony for girls) and was conferred the rank of Sanbon (the third rank of the Imperial Princess&apos;s ranks) without following the order.</e>
<cmt>一部英語のみの表現にし、分かりやすくしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>寛弘4年（1007年）正月、12歳の時に一品親王准后の位を授けられ、本封の外千戸を加えられた（この時の詔書が『大日本史』に載っている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On New Years Day in 1007, she was granted the rank of Ippon Shinno (The first rank Imperial Prince) Jugo (honorary rank next to the three Empresses: Great Empress Dowager, Empress Dowager, and Empress) at the age of twelve, and 本封の外千戸 was added (the Shosho (imperial edict, decree) she received at that time was contained in &quot;Dainihonshi&quot;)</e>
<cmt>「本封の外千戸」が読み方・意味共に不明なため原文のままとしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On New Years Day in 1007, she was granted the rank of Ippon Shinno (The first rank Imperial Prince) Jugo (honorary rank next to the three Empresses: Great Empress Dowager, Empress Dowager, and Empress) at the age of twelve, and 本封の外千戸 was added (the Shosho (imperial edict, decree) she received at that time was contained in &quot;Dainihonshi&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On New Years Day in 1007, she was granted the rank of Ippon Shinno (The first rank Imperial Prince) Jugo (honorary rank next to the three Empresses: Great Empress Dowager, Empress Dowager, and Empress) at the age of twelve, and 本封の外千戸 was added (the Shosho (imperial edict, decree) she received at that time was contained in &quot;Dainihonshi&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>父帝の死後、藤原道長・藤原彰子の庇護下にいるのを良しとせず、道長と彰子の不興を存知で叔父藤原隆家邸へ移った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After her father died, she was not happy to spend her life under the protection of FUJIWARA no Michinaga and FUJIWARA no Shoshi, she moved to the residence of her uncle, FUJIWARA no Takaie knowing that FUJIWARA no Michinaga and FUJIWARA no Shoshi were not pleased about it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After her father died, she was not happy to spend her life under the protection of FUJIWARA no Michinaga and FUJIWARA no Shoshi, she moved to the residence of her uncle, FUJIWARA no Takaie knowing that FUJIWARA no Michinaga and FUJIWARA no Shoshi were not pleased about it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After her father died, she was not happy to spend her life under the protection of FUJIWARA no Michinaga and FUJIWARA no Shoshi, she moved to the residence of her uncle, FUJIWARA no Takaie knowing that FUJIWARA no Michinaga and FUJIWARA no Shoshi were not pleased about it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>その後長和2年（1013年）1月27日に三条宮に遷御（小右記）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, she moved to Sanjo no miya on January 27, 1013 (Shoyuki (Diary of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, she moved to Sanjo no miya on January 27, 1013 (Shoyuki (Diary of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, she moved to Sanjo no miya on March 17, 1013 (Shoyuki (Diary of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>彰子のもとに引き取られた同母弟の敦康親王とは別々に暮らしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She lived separately with Imperial Prince Atsuyasu, her younger brother with the same mother who was adopted by Shoshi.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She lived separately with Imperial Prince Atsuyasu, her younger brother by the same mother who was adopted by Shoshi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She lived separately with Imperial Prince Atsuyasu, her younger maternal half-brother who was adopted by Shoshi.</e>
<cmt>同母弟　表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>親王が20歳の若さで薨去した際には非常に嘆き悲しんだという（『栄花物語』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She wailed over the death of Imperial Prince when he died at the age of twenty (&quot;Eiga Monogatari&quot;, the Tale of Glory).</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She wailed over the death of the Imperial Prince when he died at the age of twenty (&quot;Eiga Monogatari,&quot; the Tale of Glory).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She wailed over the death of the Imperial Prince when he died at the age of 20 (&quot;Eiga Monogatari,&quot; the Tale of Glory).</e>
<cmt>数字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>大変信心深く、治安 (日本)4年（1024年）3月に落飾、入道一品宮などと称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was so religious that she took the tonsure in March 1024; she was referred to as Nyudo Ippon no Miya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was so religious that she took the tonsure in March 1024; she was referred to as Nyudo Ippon no Miya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was so religious that she took the tonsure in April 1024; she was referred to as Nyudo Ippon no miya.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>高貴な皇女の多くがそうであったように、終生未婚であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Like many other noble ranking princesses, she was not married for the entire lifetime.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Like many other noble ranking princesses, she was not married for her entire lifetime.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Like many other noble ranking princesses, she was not married for her entire lifetime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>藤原頼宗の次女藤原延子（母は藤原伊周女で脩子内親王の従姉妹）を養女とし、延子が後朱雀天皇に入内した際には養母として付き添った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She adopted FUJIWARA no Enshi, the second daughter of FUJIWARA no Yorimune (her mother was FUJIWARA no 伊周女, a cousin of Imperial Princess Shushi), and she accompanied Enshi as her foster mother when Eishi married into Emperor Gosuzaku&apos;s place.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。伊周女の読み方が不明のため原文のままとしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She adopted FUJIWARA no Enshi, the second daughter of FUJIWARA no Yorimune (her mother was FUJIWARA no 伊周女, a cousin of Imperial Princess Shushi), and she accompanied Enshi as her foster mother when Eishi married into Emperor Gosuzaku&apos;s palace.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She adopted FUJIWARA no Enshi, the second daughter of FUJIWARA no Yorimune (her mother was the daughter of FUJIWARA no Korechika, a cousin of Imperial Princess Shushi), and she accompanied Enshi as her foster mother when Enshi married into Emperor Gosuzaku&apos;s palace.</e>
<cmt>the daughter of FUJIWARA no Korechika としました。Enshi としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>内親王は書に長じ、御側には琴、琵琶を善く弾く人々が多く侍っていたため、延子も筝の琴に優れていたという（『栄花物語』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Princess Shushi was good at calligraphy, while Eishi was good at koto (a long Japanese zither with thirteen strings) of So (a long Japanese zither with thirteen strings) as there were many players of koto and biwa (Japanese lute) around Imperial Princess Shushi (&quot;Eiga Monogatari&quot;, the Tale of Glory).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Princess Shushi was good at calligraphy, while Eishi was good at koto (a long Japanese zither with thirteen strings) of So (a long Japanese zither with thirteen strings) as there were many players of koto and biwa (Japanese lute) around Imperial Princess Shushi (&quot;Eiga Monogatari,&quot; the Tale of Glory).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Princess Shushi was good at calligraphy, while Enshi was good at koto (a long Japanese zither with thirteen strings) of So (a long Japanese zither with thirteen strings) as there were many players of koto and biwa (Japanese lute) around Imperial Princess Shushi (&quot;Eiga Monogatari&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Enshi としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>永承四年春に薨去し、葬送の日はちょうど釈迦入滅の日であったため、「成仏間違いなし」と言われた（『後拾遺和歌集』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She passed away in the spring of 1049, and the day of her death was the day of Shaka&apos;s death; people said `Her soul must rest in peace&apos; (&quot;GoShui wakashu&quot;, Later gleanings of Japanese poems).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She passed away in the spring of 1049, and the day of her death was the day of Shaka&apos;s death; people said `Her soul must rest in peace&apos; (&quot;GoShui wakashu&quot;, Later gleanings of Japanese poems).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She passed away in the spring of 1049, and the day of her death was the day of Shaka&apos;s death; people said `Her soul must rest in peace&apos; (&quot;Goshui wakashu&quot;, Later gleanings of Japanese poems).</e>
<cmt>Goshui としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>内親王は外戚家の零落後に生まれ、同母弟の敦康親王同様、後見人に恵まれなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Imperial Princess Shushi was born after her maternal relative was degraded, she was not fortunate regarding her guardian.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Imperial Princess Shushi was born after her maternal relative was degraded, she was not fortunate regarding her guardian.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Imperial Princess Shushi was born after her maternal relative was degraded, she was not fortunate regarding her guardian, just like the Imperial Prince Atsuyasu, her younger brother by the same mother.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかし、父帝は長女である内親王を非常に可愛がり、また帝の近臣達はそれを熟知していたために、内親王のためによく奉仕した（『権記』『小右記』など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, her father, the emperor adored Imperial Princess Shushi, his eldest daughter, very much; the emperor&apos;s vassal close aide who knew it well was dedicated to serve her (&quot;Gonki&quot; (FUJIWARA no Yukinari&apos;s diary), &quot;Shoyuki&quot; (the diary of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke), etc.).</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, her father, the emperor adored Imperial Princess Shushi, his eldest daughter, very much; the emperor&apos;s vassal close aide who knew it well was dedicated to serve her (&quot;Gonki&quot; (FUJIWARA no Yukinari&apos;s diary), &quot;Shoyuki&quot; (the diary of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke), etc.).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, her father, the emperor adored Imperial Princess Shushi, his eldest daughter, very much; the emperor&apos;s vassal close aide who knew it well was dedicated to serve her (&quot;Gonki&quot; (FUJIWARA no Yukinari&apos;s diary), &quot;Shoyuki&quot; (the diary of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke), etc.).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>また内親王は後一条天皇・後朱雀天皇の両天皇（ともに彰子所生）にとって、異母とはいえ唯一人の皇姉であったため、生涯を通して朝廷でそれなりに尊重された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, Imperial Princess Shushi was the only elder sister for the emperors; Emperor Goichijo, Emperor Gosuzaku (both were the birth children of Shoshi&apos;s place); for this reason, she was treated by the imperial court with respect for the entire her life.</e>
<cmt>彰子所生→the birth chilren of Shoshi&apos;s placeと訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, Imperial Princess Shushi was the only elder sister for the emperors; Emperor Goichijo, Emperor Gosuzaku (both were the birth children of Shoshi&apos;s place); for this reason, she was treated by the imperial court with respect for her entire life.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides, Imperial Princess Shushi was the only elder sister for the emperors; Emperor Goichijo, Emperor Gosuzaku (both were the birth children of Shoshi&apos;s place) although she was a paternal half-sister; for this reason, she was treated by the imperial court with respect for her entire life.</e>
<cmt>異母姉　の表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="19">
<j>『枕草子』伝来に関係したらしい（枕草子能因本奥書）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was involved in the legacy of Makura no soshi&quot; (the Pillow Book) (Makura no soshi 能因本奥書).</e>
<cmt>能因本奥書→読み方不明のため、原文のままとしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was involved in the legacy of Makura no soshi&quot; (the Pillow Book) (Makura no soshi 能因本奥書).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was involved in the legacy of &quot;Makura no soshi&quot; (the Pillow Book) (according to the postscript written in the Noinbon (type of transcription) of Makura no soshi).</e>
<cmt>翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>また、歌人相模 (歌人)が仕えたことでも知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is known that kajin (waka poet) Sagami served her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is known that kajin (waka poet) Sagami served her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is known that kajin (waka poet) Sagami served her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="21">
<j>寛仁4年（1020年）ごろ三条宮西に住む菅原孝標女が内親王家から「めでたき草子ども」を下賜されたというエピソードが『更級日記』にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The episode that SUGAWARA no Takasue&apos;s daughter who lived in the west of Sanjo no miya was granted `めでたき草子ども&apos; as an imperial gift by the Imperial Princess Shushi family was contained in &quot;Sarashina Nikki&quot; (The Sarashina Diary).</e>
<cmt>めでたき草子ども→意味・定訳不明のため原文のままとしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The episode about SUGAWARA no Takasue&apos;s daughter who lived in the west of Sanjo no miya being granted `めでたき草子ども&apos; as an imperial gift by the Imperial Princess Shushi family was contained in &quot;Sarashina Nikki&quot; (The Sarashina Diary).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The episode about SUGAWARA no Takasue&apos;s daughter who lived in the west of Sanjo no miya being granted &apos;Medetaki Soshi domo&apos; (wonderful books) (めでたき草子ども) as an imperial gift by the Imperial Princess Shushi family around 1020 was contained in &quot;Sarashina Nikki&quot; (The Sarashina Diary).</e>
<cmt>めでたき草子ども→ Medetaki Soshi domo (wonderful books)　と補足をしました。1020年ごろ　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Masyu(id:31065), PiaCarrot(id:2115), 代言人(id:33675), 水野白楓(id:22811), UMBRO(id:100484), Yume149(id:17504), こぶまき(id:38278), Viking rollo(id:250883), LERK(id:4460), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>