<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>天皇陵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Mausoleum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Mausoleum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Mausoleum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>天皇陵（てんのうりょう）とは、天皇の墓として宮内庁が指定している墓。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial mausoleum is a grave for an emperor assigned by Imperial Household Agency.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial mausoleum is a grave for an emperor assigned by Imperial Household Agency.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An imperial mausoleum is a grave designated as an emperor&apos;s grave by the Imperial Household Agency.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>考古学者の調査は厳しく制限されており大仙陵古墳のように実際に天皇あるいは皇族の墓であるか不明なものも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The investigation by archaeologists is strictly limited, and many graves that are unknown whether these are actually the graves for emperors or imperial family, such as Daisenryu-kofun Tumulus.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Investigation carried out by archaeologists is strictly limited, and many graves are unknown as to whether they are actually the graves for emperors or imperial family, such as Daisenryu-kofun Tumulus.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Surveys of imperial mausoleums by archaeologists are conducted under highly restricted conditions, and there are many graves, such as the Daisenryo Tumulus, about which it is doubtful whether or not they are truly graves of emperors or imperial family members.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>現在の宮内庁による区分では、天皇・皇族の墓のうち、天皇・皇后・太皇太后・皇太后のものを陵（みささぎ・りょう）、それ以外の皇太子や親王などの皇族のものを墓（はか・ぼ）と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the current classification by Imperial Household Agency, among graves for the emperor and the imperial family, it is called a mausoleum that is for the emperor, the empress, the grand empress dowager, and the empress dowager and called a grave that is for the others, such as the crown prince and the imperial prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the current classification by Imperial Household Agency, graves for the emperor and the imperial family, such as the empress, the grand empress dowager, and the empress dowager are called mausoleums while those for others such as the crown prince and the imperial prince are known as graves.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the current classification by Imperial Household Agency, graves for the emperor and the imperial family, such as the empress, the grand empress dowager, and the empress dowager are called mausoleums while those for others such as the crown prince and the imperial prince are known as graves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>なお、実際には天皇・皇后・太皇太后・皇太后の墓の他にも、「追尊天皇」・「尊称天皇」の墓所や、いわゆる「神代三代」（日向三代とも、ニニギ・ホオリ・ウガヤフキアエズ）の墓所、ヤマトタケルの墓所の一部および飯豊青皇女（飯豊天皇とも）の墓所は「陵」を名乗っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, other than the graves for the emperor, the empress, the grand empress dowager, and the empress dowager, and all of the following are called &apos;mausoleum,&apos; such as the graveyards of &apos;Emperor Tsuison&apos; (a title of emperor given to an imperial prince who have never acceded to the imperial throne after his death), &apos;Emperor Sonsho&apos; (a title of Retired Emperor given to an imperial prince who have never acceded to the imperial throne during his lifetime), so-called &apos;Kamiyo Sanyo&apos; (three deities) (also called Hinata Sanyo, Ninigi, Hoori, and Ugayafukiaezu), a part of graveyard of Yamato Takeru, and a graveyard of Iitoyo no himemiko (Crown Princess Iitoyo) (also called Emperor Iitoyo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, other than the graves for the emperor, the empress, the grand empress dowager, and the empress dowager, and all of the following are called &apos;mausoleum,&apos; such as the graveyards of &apos;Emperor Tsuison&apos; (a title of emperor given to an imperial prince who have never acceded to the imperial throne after his death), &apos;Emperor Sonsho&apos; (a title of Retired Emperor given to an imperial prince who have never acceded to the imperial throne during his lifetime), so-called &apos;Kamiyo Sanyo&apos; (three deities) (also called Hinata Sanyo, Ninigi, Hoori, and Ugayafukiaezu), a part of graveyard of Yamato Takeru, and a graveyard of Iitoyo no himemiko (Crown Princess Iitoyo) (also called Emperor Iitoyo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, other than the graves for the emperor, the empress, the grand empress dowager, and the empress dowager, all of the following are called &apos;mausoleum,&apos; such as the graveyards of &apos;Emperor Tsuison&apos; (a title of emperor given to an imperial prince who never ascended to the imperial throne after his death), &apos;Emperor Sonsho&apos; (a title of Retired Emperor given to an imperial prince who never ascended to the imperial throne during his lifetime), so-called &apos;Kamiyo Sanyo&apos; (three deities) (also called Hinata Sanyo, Ninigi, Hoori, and Ugayafukiaezu), a part of graveyard of Yamato Takeru, and a graveyard of Iitoyo no himemiko (Crown Princess Iitoyo) (also called Emperor Iitoyo).</e>
<cmt>and を一箇所削除しました。文法を修正しました（who never ascended としました）。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>これらのほか、宮内庁が現在管理しているものには、分骨所・火葬塚・灰塚など陵に準じるもの、髪・歯・爪などを納めた髪歯爪塔などの一種の供養塔、被葬者を確定できないものの皇族の墓所の可能性が考えられる陵墓参考地、などがあり、一般にはこれらを総称して陵墓（りょうぼ）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than those, the ones that Imperial Household Agency is currently administering are the place to bury ashes in separate places, cremation mound, and ashes mound that were equivalent to mausoleum, memorial tower of sort such as Hasshiso-to pagoda that held hair, teeth, and nail, referable mausoleum that were possible graveyards for imperial family even thought the deceased person could not be defined, and all of these are collectively called mausoleum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than these, the Imperial Household Agency currently administers those places collectively known as mausoleum, such as the separate places used to bury ashes, cremation and ashes mounds that were equivalent to mausoleums, memorial towers such as the Hasshiso-to pagoda that held hair, teeth, and nail, referable mausoleum that were possible graveyards for imperial family even thought the deceased person could not be defined, and all of these are collectively called mausoleum.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Apart from these graves, the Imperial Household Agency currently manages various other properties, including quasi-mausoleums (such as cinerariums, cremation mounds and ash mounds), memorial pagodas used to bury hair, teeth and nails, and potential mausoleums with unidentified owners that have the possibility of being imperial family members&apos; graves, and all these properties are collectively called mausoleums.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>陵墓に指定されている古墳のうち、天皇陵は41基、皇后陵は11基、皇太子などの墓は34基であり、天皇、皇后、皇子名を合葬したものを差し引くと合計85基ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Out of the tumuluses that have been designated as the imperial mausoleums, there are forty one imperial mausoleums, eleven mausoleums for the empresses, thirty four graves for the crown princes, and there are eighty five graves after subtracting the graves for the emperors, the empresses, and the princes that were buried together.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Out of the tumuluses that have been designated as the imperial mausoleums, there are forty one imperial mausoleums, eleven mausoleums for the empresses, thirty four graves for the crown princes, and there are eighty five graves after subtracting the graves for the emperors, the empresses, and the princes that were buried together.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are a total of 896 mausoleums, including 42 quasi-mausoleums, 68 memorial pagodas and 46 potential mausoleums that have the possibility of being imperial family members&apos; graves according to tradition.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="7">
<j>宮内庁管理の陵墓は、北は山形県から南は鹿児島県まで1都2府30県にわたって所在しており、歴代天皇陵が112、皇后陵など76で計188。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The imperial mausoleums that Imperial Household Agency administers are located in thirty three prefectures from Yamagata prefecture in the north to Kagoshima prefecture in the south, and there are one hundred eighty eight mausoleums in total including one hundred twelve imperial mausoleums for the successive emperors and seventy six mausoleums for the empresses.</e>
<cmt>「1都2府30県」は33 prefecturesと訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The imperial mausoleums that the Imperial Household Agency administers are located in thirty three prefectures from Yamagata prefecture in the north to Kagoshima prefecture in the south, and there are one hundred eighty eight mausoleums in total including one hundred twelve imperial mausoleums for the successive emperors and seventy six mausoleums for the empresses.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The imperial mausoleums that the Imperial Household Agency administers are located in thirty-three prefectures from Yamagata Prefecture in the north to Kagoshima Prefecture in the south, and there are one hundred eighty-eight mausoleums in total including one hundred twelve imperial mausoleums for the successive emperors and seventy-six mausoleums for the empresses.</e>
<cmt>Prefecture としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>皇族等の墓が552。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are five hundred fifty two graves for the imperial family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are five hundred fifty two graves for the imperial family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are five hundred fifty-two graves for the imperial family.</e>
<cmt>数字の間にハイフンをいれました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>準陵が42、髪歯爪塔などが68、伝承などから陵墓の可能性がある陵墓参考地が46あり、総数は896である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are forty two semi-mausoleums, sixty eight Hasshiso-to pagodas, forty six referable mausoleums that are considered as possible imperial mausoleums according to the tradition, so there are eight hundred ninety six in total.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are forty two semi-mausoleums, sixty eight Hasshiso-to pagodas, forty six referable mausoleums that are considered as possible imperial mausoleums according to the tradition, so there are eight hundred ninety six in total.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are forty-two semi-mausoleums, sixty-eight Hasshiso-to pagodas, forty-six referable mausoleums that are considered as possible imperial mausoleums according to the tradition, so there are eight hundred ninety-six in total.</e>
<cmt>数字の間にハイフンをいれました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>同じ場所に所在するものもあるので、箇所数は458となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are four hundred fifty eight locations since some of the mausoleums are located in the same place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are four hundred fifty eight locations since some of the mausoleums are located in the same place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are four hundred fifty-eight locations since some of the mausoleums are located in the same place.</e>
<cmt>数字の間にハイフンをいれました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="11">
<j>これら陵墓は現在も皇室による祭祀が行われており、研究者などが自由に立ち入って調査することができない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The imperial household still runs the rituals for these imperial mausoleums even today, so researchers cannot enter the mausoleums freely to investigate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The imperial household still carries out the rituals for these imperial mausoleums even today, so researchers cannot enter the mausoleums freely to investigate.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The imperial household still carries out the rituals for these imperial mausoleums even today, so researchers cannot enter the mausoleums freely to investigate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかしながら調査の許可を求める考古学界の要望もあり、近年は地元自治体などとの合同調査を認めたり、修復のための調査に一部研究者の立ち入りを認めるケースも出てきている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there has been a demand to request for a permission to investigate the mausoleums in the archaeological world, so the joint investigation with local governments was recently permitted and there was a case that some researchers were permitted to enter the mausoleums to investigate for renovation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there has been a demand to request permission to investigate the mausoleums in the archaeological world, so a joint investigation with local governments was recently permitted and there was a case where some researchers were permitted to enter the mausoleums to investigate for renovation purposes.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, due to archaeologists&apos; repeated requests for permission to conduct surveys on these mausoleums, researchers are often allowed to enter mausoleums in recent years to conduct joint research with local communities or to participate in repair surveys.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="13">
<j>陵墓の名前などは、下記の宮内庁管理の天皇陵一覧参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the names of mausoleums, please refer to the following list of imperial mausoleums administered by Imperial Household Agency.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the names of mausoleums, please refer to the following list of imperial mausoleums administered by Imperial Household Agency.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the names of mausoleums, please refer to the following list of imperial mausoleums administered by Imperial Household Agency.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>変遷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Transition</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Transition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Transition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>天皇が大王 (ヤマト王権)（おおきみ）と呼ばれていた古墳時代には、その陵は巨大な前方後円墳であった（9代開化陵～30代敏達陵）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During Kofun period (tumulus period) when the emperor was called Okimi (Yamato sovereignty (the ancient Japan sovereignty)), the mausoleum was a giant keyhole-shaped tomb mound (from Mausoleum of Emperor Kaika, the ninth to that of Emperor Bidatsu, the thirtieth).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During Kofun period (tumulus period) when the emperor was called Okimi (Yamato sovereignty (the ancient Japan sovereignty)), the mausoleum was a giant keyhole-shaped tomb mound (from Mausoleum of Emperor Kaika, the ninth to that of Emperor Bidatsu, the thirtieth).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Tumulus period, when emperors were called &quot;Great Kings&quot; (&quot;okimi&quot; in Japanese) in the Yamato kingdom, an emperor&apos;s tumulus was built in a circular shape with a rectangular frontage (from the tumulus of Kaika, the ninth emperor to that of Bidatsu, the thirtieth emperor).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>7世紀になり、ヤマト王権が大陸の政治システムの影響を受けるようになると大型の方墳、円墳へと変化し、さらに7世紀中頃から8世紀初頭まで天皇陵には八角墳が採用されるようになる（舒明陵の段ノ塚古墳、天智陵の御廟野古墳、天武・持統合葬陵の野口王墓、文武陵の中尾山古墳）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the seventh century, when Yamato sovereignty was affected by the political system of the mainland, the mausoleum was changed to large square tumulus and a round barrow, and during the mid seventh century to the early eighth century, Hakkaku-fun Tumulus was adopted to the imperial mausoleum (Dannozuka-kofun Tumulus of Emperor Jomei Mausoleum, Gobyono-kofun Tumulus of Emperor Tenchi Mausoleum, Noguchino Ono-haka Tumulus of Emperor Tenmu Mausoleum where Empress Jito buried together, and Nakaoyama-kofun Tumulus of Emperor Monmu Mausoleum).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the seventh century, when Yamato sovereignty was affected by the political system of the mainland, the mausoleum was changed to a large square tumulus and a round barrow, and during the mid seventh century to the early eighth century, Hakkaku-fun Tumulus was adopted to the imperial mausoleum (Dannozuka-kofun Tumulus of Emperor Jomei Mausoleum, Gobyono-kofun Tumulus of Emperor Tenchi Mausoleum, Noguchino Ono-haka Tumulus of Emperor Tenmu Mausoleum where Empress Jito buried together, and Nakaoyama-kofun Tumulus of Emperor Monmu Mausoleum).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the 7th century, when the Yamato kingdom came under the influence of the political system of the Chinese continent, emperors&apos; tumuli came to be built in a large rectangular or round shape, and from the mid-7th to early 8th centuries, in an octagonal shape (e.g. Dannozuka Tumulus of Emperor Jomei, Gobyono Tumulus of Emperor Tenchi, Noguchino Imperial Tumulus of Emperor Tenmu and Empress Jito, and Nakaoyama Tumulus of Emperor Monmu).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>このような特別な八角墳が大王にのみ採用されたのは、畿内を中心とした首長連合の盟主であった大王の地位を、一般の首長を超越して中国の天子のような唯一の最高権力者として地位を確立しようとして形に表したという解釈がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was an interpretation that the reason for this kind of special Hakkaku-fun Tumulus to be adopted to the mausoleum for Okimi was to physicalize the post of Okimi who was a leader of chief association mainly in Kinai region (provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara) in order to established the post as a unique person in paramount authority such as a Chinese emperor rising above a common chief.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some interpret that the reason for this kind of special Hakkaku-fun Tumulus to be adopted to the mausoleum for Okimi was to physicalize the post of Okimi who was a leader of chief association mainly in Kinai region (provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara) in order to established the post as a unique person in paramount authority such as a Chinese emperor rising above a common chief.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people argue that these octagonal tumuli, which were built only for Great Kings, were built as symbols designed to establish the status of these kings, who led the union of chiefs in and around the Kinai region (region around Kyoto and Nara), as supreme rulers like Chinese emperors ranking far above other ordinary chiefs.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>奈良時代から平安時代初頭にかけての天皇陵は、土葬される例（聖武天皇）や、墳丘を作ったと思われる事例（桓武天皇）を経て、仏教思想の影響により、火葬の導入（持統天皇）や火葬後に散骨して大規模な造営を行わない事例（嵯峨天皇、淳和天皇）などが見られるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the imperial mausoleums from Nara period to the early Heian period, there were some cases where burial was adopted (Emperor Shomu&apos;s case) and some cases where grave mounds were built (Emperor Kanmu&apos;s case), and after that, adoption of cremation (Empress Jito&apos; case) and scattering of ashes after cremation without large-scale building (the cases of Emperor Saga and Emperor Junna) have been visible.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the imperial mausoleums from Nara period to the early Heian period, there were some cases where burial was adopted (Emperor Shomu&apos;s case) and some cases where grave mounds were built (Emperor Kanmu&apos;s case), and after that, adoption of cremation (Empress Jito&apos; case) and scattering of ashes after cremation without large-scale building (the cases of Emperor Saga and Emperor Junna) have been visible.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mausoleums built from the Nara to the early Heian periods include graves of emperors (e.g. Emperor Shomu) whose bodies were buried, graves with burial mounds (Emperor Kanmu), graves of emperors in later periods (Empress Jito) whose bodies were cremated due to the influence of Buddhism and graves of cremated emperors that were built without large-scale construction work (Emperors Saga and Junna).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>院政期の白河天皇にいたって仏式のお堂に納骨する方式が現れ、江戸時代の後水尾天皇以降は代々京都泉涌寺に石造塔形式の陵墓が建立された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time of Emperor Shirakawa in cloister government period, a method to place ashes in the main hall of Buddhist-style was appeared and imperial mausoleums of stone tower-style were built in Sennyu-ji Temple in Kyoto after the Emperor Gomizuno in Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time of Emperor Shirakawa during the cloister government period, a method to place ashes in the main hall of Buddhist-style appeared and imperial mausoleums of stone tower-style were built in Sennyu-ji Temple in Kyoto after the Emperor Gomizuno in Edo period.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the period of the cloister government by Emperor Shirakawa, a new funeral style was adopted, in which the ashes of a deceased person were placed in a Buddhist chapel, and during the Edo period, tower-shaped stone graves were built at Senyu-ji Temple in Kyoto for the emperors after Emperor Gomizuno.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>幕末にいたって尊皇思想が高揚すると天皇陵にも復古調が取り入れられ、孝明天皇陵は大規模な墳丘を持つ形式で築造された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Sonno thought (thought of reverence for the emperor) was enhanced at the end of Edo period, imperial mausoleums adopted revival mood and Mausoleum of Emperor Komei was built with the style that had a large-scale grave mound.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Sonno&apos;s thought (thought of reverence for the emperor) was enhanced at the end of Edo period, imperial mausoleums adopted a revival mood and the Mausoleum of Emperor Komei was built in a style that had a large-scale grave mound.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a political philosophy advocating the reverence for the emperor was adopted by many people toward the end of the Edo period, an ancient style was revived in the construction of imperial mausoleums; thus, Emperor Komei&apos;s mausoleum was built with a large burial mound.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>明治天皇陵では、天智天皇陵に範を取ったといわれる上円下方式が採用され、以降、今日に至っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mausoleum of Emperor Meiji adopted the style of a dome-shaped mound on a square base which modeled after Mausoleum of Emperor Tenchi and continued after that to this day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mausoleum of Emperor Meiji adopted the style of a dome-shaped mound on a square base which was modeled after Mausoleum of Emperor Tenchi and continued after that to this day.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mausoleum of Emperor Meiji adopted the style of a dome-shaped mound on a square base which was modeled after Mausoleum of Emperor Tenchi and continued after that to this day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>また、皇后陵は中国の古式に則って（例西太后の「定東陵」）天皇陵の東に造営されることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, the imperial mausoleum for the empress was built on the east side of the imperial mausoleum following the ancient Chinese style (Empress Dowager Cixi&apos;s &apos;Teitoryo&apos;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, the imperial mausoleum for the empress was built on the east side of the imperial mausoleum following the ancient Chinese style (Empress Dowager Cixi&apos;s &apos;Teitoryo&apos;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, the imperial mausoleum for the empress was built on the east side of the imperial mausoleum following the ancient Chinese style (Empress Dowager Cixi&apos;s &apos;Teitoryo&apos;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>そのため皇后陵は「○○東陵（○○のひがしのみささぎ）」と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the mausoleum of the empress was called &apos;xx no Higashino Misasagi.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the mausoleum of the empress was called &apos;xx no Higashino Misasagi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the mausoleum of the empress was called &apos;xx no Higashino Misasagi&apos; (literally, mausoleum of xx on the east side).</e>
<cmt>「ひがしのみささぎ」の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="23">
<j>大正天皇以後、天皇・皇后の陵は現東京都八王子市の御料地内に作られることになり、武蔵陵墓地が成立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Emperor Taisho, the imperial mausoleums for the emperors and the empresses were built inside goryochi (an Imperial estate) in present Hachioji City, Tokyo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Emperor Taisho, the imperial mausoleums for the emperors and the empresses were built inside goryochi (an Imperial estate) in present Hachioji City, Tokyo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Emperor Taisho, the imperial mausoleums for the emperors and the empresses were built inside goryochi (an Imperial estate) in present Hachioji City, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>prefecture を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>一方、皇族の墓は明治天皇の皇子の死を契機として現東京都文京区大塚の護国寺裏山に設けられることとなり、現在、豊島岡墓地となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, graves for the imperial family were built on a hill at the back of Gokoku-ji Temple in present Otsuka, Bunkyo Ward, Tokyo Prefecture, which triggered by the death of Prince of Emperor Meiji, and it is currently called Toshimagaoka Cemetery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, graves for the imperial family were built on a hill at the back of Gokoku-ji Temple in present Otsuka, Bunkyo Ward, Tokyo Prefecture, which triggered by the death of Prince of Emperor Meiji, and it is currently called Toshimagaoka Cemetery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, after the death of the Meiji Emperor&apos;s son, graves for the imperial family came to be built on a hill at the back of Gokoku-ji Temple in Otsuka, Bunkyo Ward, Tokyo, which is today known as the Toshimagaoka Cemetery.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>管理</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Administration</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Administration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Administration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>陵墓が今日のように整備され、管理が強化されるようになったのは明治以後のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was after Meiji period that the imperial mausoleums were maintained as of today and its administration was strengthen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was after Meiji period that the imperial mausoleums were maintained as of today and its administration was strengthened.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was not until the Meiji period that imperial mausoleums began to be carefully maintained under the close supervision of the government.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>律令制下においては、天皇陵をはじめとする陵墓は国家によって管理されることになっており、大宝令・養老令では担当部署として治部省下に諸陵司が置かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code), the imperial mausoleums were supposed to be controlled by the state and with Taiho-ryo (Taiho Code) and Yoro-ryo (Yoro Code), Shoryoshi (a government office responsible for administering the mausoleums) was located under Jibusho (the Ministry of Civil Administration) as the division responsible.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code), the imperial mausoleums were supposed to be controlled by the state and with Taiho-ryo (Taiho Code) and Yoro-ryo (Yoro Code), Shoryoshi (a government office responsible for administering the mausoleums) was located under Jibusho (the Ministry of Civil Administration) as the division responsible.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the Ritsuryo code), graves, including imperial mausoleums, were supposed to be managed by the central government, and the codes of law formulated during the Taiho and Yoro eras (known respectively as the Taiho-ryo and the Yoro-ryo) defined a government officer (called &quot;shoryoshi&quot; in Japanese) who managed graves under the supervision of the Ministry of Civil Administration (Jibusho).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>その後、天平年間には諸陵司が拡充され、諸陵寮となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Shoryoshi was improved during 729-748 and renamed as Shoryoryo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Shoryoshi was improved during 729-748 and renamed as Shoryoryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Shoryoshi was improved during 729-748 and renamed as Shoryoryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>平安時代前期に編纂された延喜式には、諸陵寮管理下の陵墓の一覧表が記載されているが、このころの墓には外戚（皇妃の実家：藤原氏など）の墓も含まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the Engishiki (codes and procedures on national rites and prayers) that was edited in the early Heian period, a list of the mausoleums that were under Shoryoryo control was written, but the graves at that time included the ones for maternal relatives (home of princess: Fujiwara clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the Engishiki (codes and procedures on national rites and prayers) that was edited in the early Heian period, a list of the mausoleums that were under Shoryoryo control was written, but the graves at that time included ones for maternal relatives (home of princess: Fujiwara clan).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Engishiki, a book of laws and regulations compiled in the early Heian period, contains a list of mausoleums managed under the jurisdiction of Shoryoryo, which shows that the graves of maternal relatives of the imperial family (such as the members of the Fujiwara clan, which married daughters to emperors) were included among these mausoleums.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>管理の具体的内容としては、陵戸・墓戸の設置がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The concrete contents of the administration were to place Ryoko (imperial tomb guard) and Boko (grave guard).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The concrete contents of the administration were to place Ryoko (imperial tomb guard) and Boko (grave guard).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this period, certain special families were appointed to serve as keepers of imperial graves (called &quot;ryoko&quot; or &quot;boko&quot; in Japanese) in order to maintain mausoleums.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>醍醐天皇陵の管理が醍醐寺に委ねられて以後、寺院内に造営された陵墓の管理は所領を与える条件で各寺院に任されることになり、陵墓管理が国家の手から離れていく要因となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After entrusting the administration of Mausoleum of Emperor Daigo to Daigo-ji Temple, the administration of the imperial mausoleums that were built in the temples left to each temple under the condition of giving territories, and it became the reason that the administration of the mausoleums went out of the hands of the state.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After entrusting the administration for Mausoleum of Emperor Daigo to Daigo-ji Temple, the administration of the imperial mausoleums that were built in the temples were left to each temple under the condition that territories were awarded, and it became the reason that the administration of the mausoleums went out of the hands of the state.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the management of Emperor Daigo&apos;s mausoleum was left in the hands of Daigo-ji Temple, graves built on temple grounds came to be managed by temples in exchange for territories awarded by the government, causing the management of graves to leave the hands of the government.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="31">
<j>一方、各陵墓に対しては荷前の幣（のさきのへい）と呼ばれる国家による祭祀が行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, to each imperial mausoleum, the state run the ritual called Nosaki no Hei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the state run the ritual called Nosaki no Hei for each imperial mausoleum.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the state ran the ritual called Nosaki no Hei for each imperial mausoleum.</e>
<cmt>ran としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>この祭祀はすべての陵墓に等しく行われたのではなく、重要視されたものは近陵・近墓、そうでないものは遠陵・遠墓とのランク分けがなされ、祭祀に際しての貢物の量が異なっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This ritual was not run equally for all the imperial mausoleums, but the important ones were ranked as Kinryo and Kinbo (mausoleum and grave for the close relatives of the emperor), the others were ranked as Enryo and Enbo (mausoleum and grave for the distantly-related emperor or empress), and the amount of offerings at rituals was different.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This ritual was not run equally for all imperial mausoleums, but important ones were ranked as Kinryo and Kinbo (mausoleum and grave for the close relatives of the emperor), the others were ranked as Enryo and Enbo (mausoleum and grave for the distantly-related emperor or empress), and the amount of offerings at rituals was different.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This ritual was not equally performed for all imperial mausoleums; mausoleums were distinguished into groups of different ranks, from important ones built for the close relatives of the imperial family to less important ones for distant relatives, and amounts of offerings made in rituals also differed between mausoleums.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>祭祀に際しては貴族が派遣されることになっており、その役目を荷前の使と呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time of the ritual, nobles were supposed to be dispatched and their role was called Nosaki no Tsukai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time of the ritual, nobles were supposed to be dispatched and their role was called Nosaki no Tsukai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobles who were sent to attend mausoleum rituals were known as &quot;nosaki no tsukai&quot; (messengers sent to pay tributes).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>しかし、陵墓に対する「墓＝死＝穢れ」といったイメージが貴族たちに嫌われたことから、次第に忌避されるようになり、陵墓の所在が不明確になっていく理由のひとつになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the image against the imperial mausoleums such as &apos;grave=death=unclean&apos; was unpopular among the nobles, so it was gradually avoided and became one of the reasons that the location of the imperial mausoleum was unclear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the image against the imperial mausoleums such as &apos;grave=death=unclean&apos; was unpopular among the nobles, so it was gradually avoided and became one of the reasons that the location of the imperial mausoleum became unclear.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to negative images about mausoleums (graves = death = uncleanliness), nobles came to avoid mausoleum rituals, causing the locations of imperial mausoleums to be forgotten.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="35">
<j>中世になり天皇家の力が衰えると荒れ放題となる陵墓もあり、中には伝安閑陵古墳のように戦国大名の城として改造されたものまであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the power of the imperial family diminished in the Medieval Period, some of the imperial mausoleums were left dilapidation and some were converted into a castle of the Warring loads such as Denankanryo-kofun Tumulus.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the power of the imperial family diminished in the Medieval Period, some of the imperial mausoleums were left in a state of dilapidation while some were converted into a castle of the Warring loads such as Denankanryo-kofun Tumulus.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of the mausoleums were left in ruins as the imperial family declined in power during the medieval period, while others, like the tumulus which is believed to the tomb of Emperor Ankan, were converted into castles of Sengoku daimyo (territorial lords in the Sengoku period).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="36">
<j>現在治定されている天皇陵のうち、奈良時代までの天皇陵については、歴史学的・考古学的に同意できるものは推古天皇陵、天智天皇陵、天武・持統天皇陵など数か所程度とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding the imperial mausoleums until Nara period out of the ones that are currently ruled as the imperial mausoleums, only a few sites are agreed historically and archaeologically, such as Mausoleums of Emperor Suiko, Emperor Tenchi, Emperor Tenmu, and Empress Jito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding the imperial mausoleums until Nara period, out of the ones that are currently ruled as the imperial mausoleums, only a few sites are agree both historically and archaeologically, such as Mausoleums of Emperor Suiko, Emperor Tenchi, Emperor Tenmu, and Empress Jito.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among graves built during or before the Nara period that are currently recognized as imperial mausoleums, only a few (including mausoleums of Emperor Suiko, Emperor Temchi, Emperor Tenmu and Empress Jito) can be historically and archaeologically certified as such.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>平安時代～室町時代のものは、薄葬によって位置を特定することが困難なものや陵が置かれた寺院が廃滅したことによって所在が不明になってしまったものなどが多く、ますます歴史学的・考古学的信頼度は低下する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many mausoleums from Heian period to Muromachi period were difficult to specify the locations due to the simple funeral and the extinction of the temples where had the mausoleums, so the historical and archaeological reliability declined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many mausoleums from the Heian period to Muromachi period were difficult to pinpoint location-wise, due to the simple funeral and extinction of temples that had mausoleums, so reliable historical and archaeological information declined.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The locations of many of the mausoleums built from the Heian to the Muromachi period are difficult to identify due to simplified burial styles, or are unknown due to temple closures, further reducing the historical and archaeological reliability of identification.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>後白河天皇の法住寺陵、後醍醐天皇の如意輪寺などのように近世にいたるまで管理され、伝えられたものはむしろ少数派である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The mausoleums that have been administered and transmitted to recent times, such as Hoju-ji Mausoleum of Emperor Goshirakawa and Nyoirin-ji Temple of Emperor Godaigo, are in a minority.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of mausoleums that have been administered and transmitted to recent times, such as Hoju-ji Mausoleum of Emperor Goshirakawa and Nyoirin-ji Temple of Emperor Godaigo, are few.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Examples of mausoleums, such as Emperor Goshirakawa&apos;s Hoju-ji Mausoleum and Emperor Godaigo&apos;s mausoleum at Nyoirin-ji Temple, that were carefully maintained and passed down to succeeding generations until the Edo period are relatively rare.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>宮内庁は「陵墓は皇室祭祀の場であり、静安と尊厳を保持しなければならない」という理由で考古学的調査の許可を拒み続けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Household Agency has been refused to give permission to archaeological investigations because &apos;the imperial mausoleums are the places for the imperial rituals, so static and dignity must be maintained.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Household Agency has refused to allow archaeological investigations because &apos;the imperial mausoleums are places for imperial rituals, so static and dignity must be maintained.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Household Agency has refused to allow archaeological investigations because &apos;the imperial mausoleums are places for imperial rituals, so their tranquility and dignity must be maintained.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;静安&quot; is difficult to handle but &quot;static&quot; doesn&apos;t really make much sense here.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>また、歴史学的・考古学的信頼度については「たとえ誤って指定されたとしても、祭祀を行っている場所が天皇陵である」としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Household Agency also said that &apos;even a mausoleum was assigned by mistake, a place where holds the ritual is supposed to be the imperial mausoleum&apos; concerning the historical and archaeological reliability.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Household Agency also said that &apos;even if a mausoleum was assigned by mistake, a place where ritual are held are considered to be an imperial mausoleum&apos; concerning the reliability of information from a historical and archaeological perspective.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Commenting on the historical and archaeological reliability of identification, the Imperial Household Agency also maintains that sites where mausoleum rituals are performed are imperial mausoleums even if they are wrongly designated as such.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="41">
<j>現在は全国の陵墓所在地を5つに分け、宮内庁書陵部が以下のように管理を行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The locations of the mausoleums are currently divided into five throughout the country, and the following offices of Imperial Household Archives, such as</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The mausoleums are currently divided into five different locations throughout the country, and the following offices of Imperial Household Archives, such as</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The mausoleums are currently divided into five different locations throughout the country, and the following offices of Imperial Household Archives administer the mausoleums.</e>
<cmt>セルが。で終わるように原文を修正・英訳もそれに応じて変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="42">
<j>多摩陵墓監区事務所（東京都八王子市・武蔵陵墓地＝大正天皇陵・昭和天皇陵、管轄＝山形・新潟・栃木・東京・神奈川・長野）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tama Mausoleum Regional Office (Hachioji City, Tokyo Prefecture, Musashi Imperial mausoleum=Mausoleum of Emperor Taisho and Emperor Showa, jurisdiction=Yamagata, Nigata, Tochigi, Tokyo, Kanagawa, and Nagano Prefectures),</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tama Mausoleum Regional Office (Hachioji City, Tokyo Prefecture, Musashi Imperial mausoleum=Mausoleum of Emperor Taisho and Emperor Showa, jurisdiction=Yamagata, Nigata, Tochigi, Tokyo, Kanagawa, and Nagano Prefectures),</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tama Mausoleum Regional Office (Hachioji City, Tokyo, Musashi Imperial mausoleum=Mausoleum of Emperor Taisho and Emperor Showa, jurisdiction=Yamagata, Nigata, Tochigi, Tokyo, Kanagawa, and Nagano Prefectures),</e>
<cmt>prefecture を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="43">
<j>桃山陵墓監区事務所（京都市伏見区・桃山陵墓地＝明治天皇陵・昭憲皇太后陵、管轄＝京都・大阪・兵庫・岡山・広島・山口・福岡・佐賀・長崎・熊本・宮崎・鹿児島）、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Momoyama Mausoleum Regional Office (Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City, Momoyama Imperial mausoleum=Mausoleum of Emperor Meiji and Empress Dowager Shoken, jurisdiction=Kyoto, Osaka, Hyogo, Okayama, Hiroshima, Yamaguchi, Fukuoka, Saga, Nagasaki, Kumamoto, Miyazaki, and Kagoshima Prefectures),</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Momoyama Mausoleum Regional Office (Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City, Momoyama Imperial mausoleum=Mausoleum of Emperor Meiji and Empress Dowager Shoken, jurisdiction=Kyoto, Osaka, Hyogo, Okayama, Hiroshima, Yamaguchi, Fukuoka, Saga, Nagasaki, Kumamoto, Miyazaki, and Kagoshima Prefectures),</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Momoyama Mausoleum Regional Office (Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City, Momoyama Imperial mausoleum=Mausoleum of Emperor Meiji and Empress Dowager Shoken, jurisdiction=Kyoto, Osaka, Hyogo, Okayama, Hiroshima, Yamaguchi, Fukuoka, Saga, Nagasaki, Kumamoto, Miyazaki, and Kagoshima Prefectures),</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="44">
<j>畝傍陵墓監区事務所（奈良県橿原市・神武天皇陵＝奈良・三重・岐阜・愛知・静岡）、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unebi Mausoleum Regional Office (Kashihara City, Nara Prefecture, Mausoleum of Emperor Jinmu=Nara, Mie, Gifu, Aichi, and Shizuoka Prefectures),</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unebi Mausoleum Regional Office (Kashihara City, Nara Prefecture, Mausoleum of Emperor Jinmu=Nara, Mie, Gifu, Aichi, and Shizuoka Prefectures),</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unebi Mausoleum Regional Office (Kashihara City, Nara Prefecture, Mausoleum of Emperor Jinmu=Nara, Mie, Gifu, Aichi, and Shizuoka Prefectures),</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="45">
<j>月輪（つきのわ）陵墓監区事務所（京都市東山区・泉山陵墓地＝孝明天皇陵・月輪陵、管轄＝富山・石川・滋賀・京都・兵庫・鳥取・島根）、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsukinowa Mausoleum Regional Office (Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City, Senzan Imperial mausoleum=Mausoleum of Emperor Komei and Tsukinowa, jurisdiction=Toyama, Ishikawa, Shiga, Kyoto, Hyogo, Tottori, and Shimane Prefectures),</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsukinowa Mausoleum Regional Office (Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City, Senzan Imperial mausoleum=Mausoleum of Emperor Komei and Tsukinowa, jurisdiction=Toyama, Ishikawa, Shiga, Kyoto, Hyogo, Tottori, and Shimane Prefectures),</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukinowa Mausoleum Regional Office (Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City, Senzan Imperial mausoleum=Mausoleum of Emperor Komei and Tsukinowa, jurisdiction=Toyama, Ishikawa, Shiga, Kyoto, Hyogo, Tottori, and Shimane Prefectures),</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="46">
<j>古市陵墓監区事務所（大阪府羽曳野市・応神天皇陵、管轄＝大阪・兵庫・和歌山・香川・徳島・愛媛・高知）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furuichi Mausoleum Regional Office (Habikino City, Osaka Prefecture, Mausoleum of Emperor Ojin, jurisdiction=Osaka, Hyogo, Wakayama, Kagawa, Tokushima, Ehime, and Kochi Prefectures),</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furuichi Mausoleum Regional Office (Habikino City, Osaka Prefecture, Mausoleum of Emperor Ojin, jurisdiction=Osaka, Hyogo, Wakayama, Kagawa, Tokushima, Ehime, and Kochi Prefectures),</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furuichi Mausoleum Regional Office (Habikino City, Osaka Prefecture, Mausoleum of Emperor Ojin, jurisdiction=Osaka, Hyogo, Wakayama, Kagawa, Tokushima, Ehime, and Kochi Prefectures),</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>山陵探索・治定・修陵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mausoleum search, ruling, and repair</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mausoleum search, ruling, and repair</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Search, identification and repair of mausoleums</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="47">
<j>現在につながる天皇陵の探索および治定は、そのほとんどが江戸時代に行われており、一部のものについては明治時代以降にまでずれこんだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of the search and ruling of the imperial mausoleums that currently exist have done in Edo period, and some of that were delayed until Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of the search concerning imperial mausoleums that currently exist was conducted in the Edo period, and some of were delayed until the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of the attempts to search for and identify imperial mausoleums that are recognized as such today were made during the Edo period and some of these attempts continued into the Meiji period and even later.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="48">
<j>江戸時代には、尊皇思想の勃興とともに、天皇陵探索の気運が高まり、松下見林、本居宣長、蒲生君平、北浦定政、谷森善臣、平塚瓢斎などが、陵墓の所在地を考証したり、現地に赴いたりしており、江戸幕府による修陵もこうした動きと無関係ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Edo period, with rise of Sonno thought, momentum of search for the imperial mausoleums was gained, Kenrin MATSUSHITA, Norinaga MOTOORI, Kunpei GAMO, Sadamasa KITAURA, Yoshiomi TANIMORI, and Hyosai HIRATSUKA studied the historical evidences and proceeded to the actual sites, so repair by Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) was not so irrelevant to this move.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period, with the rise of Sonno&apos;s thought, momentum gained behind the search for imperial mausoleums, and Kenrin MATSUSHITA, Norinaga MOTOORI, Kunpei GAMO, Sadamasa KITAURA, Yoshiomi TANIMORI, and Hyosai HIRATSUKA studied the historical evidence, and proceeded to the actual sites. Therefor the repair carried out by Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) was not so irrelevant in this case.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the philosophy advocating the reverence for the emperor was adopted by an increasing number of people, attempts were made to search for lost imperial mausoleums, with scholars such as Kenrin MATSUSHITA, Norinaga MOTOORI, Kunpei GAMO, Sadamasa KITAURA, Yoshiomi TANIMORI, and Hyosai HIRATSUKA studying historical evidence and visiting past mausoleum sites; mausoleum repairs performed by the Tokugawa government are not unrelated to these attempts.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="49">
<j>現在の学問的水準からみれば問題の多い江戸時代の治定作業ではあるが、それらは決していい加減なものではなく、天皇陵について記載された文献資料を集め、それと地名や土地の伝承などを照らし合わせることで行われており、当時としてはかなりの高水準のものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the current academic level, ruling operations in Edo period had a lot of problems, but they were certainly not careless, and the ruling operations were done by collecting literatures and references that described the imperial mausoleums and run them with geographical names and traditions of the land, so the operations were at a fairly high standard for that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the current academic level, ruling operations in Edo period contained many issues, but they were certainly not careless. Ruling operations were done by collecting literatures and references that described imperial mausoleums, and ran with the geographical names and traditions of the land, so the operations were at a fairly high standard for that time.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Judged by current academic standards, the identifications of mausoleums during the Edo period had various problems, but these identifications were never made based on arbitrary standards; various documents regarding imperial mausoleums were collected and compared against place names and local traditions in order to identify mausoleums and relatively high levels of research was conducted by the standards at the time.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="50">
<j>「修陵」とは、荒れ果てた陵を修繕することである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shuriku&apos; means to repair the ruined mausoleums.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shuriku&apos; means to repair the ruined mausoleums.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shuriku&apos; means to repair the ruined mausoleums.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>江戸時代の元禄・万治・延宝・享保・文久などの各時期に修陵事業が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Repairing was enforced in each era of Genroku, Manji, Empo, Kyoho, and Bunkyu during Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Repairing was enforced in each era of Genroku, Manji, Empo, Kyoho, and Bunkyu during Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period, mausoleums were repaired in the Genroku, Manji, Enpo, Kyoho and Bunkyu eras.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>中でも、幕末の「文久の修陵」は、大がかりな土木工事を伴った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Repairing in Bunkyu era&apos; in the end of Edo period involved large-scale engineering work.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Repairing in Bunkyu era&apos; in the end of Edo period involved large-scale engineering work.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A repair project known as the Bunkyu Mausoleum Repair undertaken toward the end of the Edo period involved particularly large civil engineering work.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="53">
<j>水戸藩主の徳川光圀は元禄期に幕府へ陵墓の修理を願い出たが、この時には許可されず、代わって幕府が行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsukuni TOKUGAWA, the lord of the Mito Domain, requested bakufu to repair the mausoleum during Genroku era, but it was not permitted at that time and enforced by bakufu instead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsukuni TOKUGAWA, the lord of the Mito Domain, requested bakufu to repair the mausoleum during Genroku era, but it was not permitted at that time and enforced by bakufu instead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Mitsukuni TOKUGAWA, the lord of the Mito Domain, requested permission from the Tokugawa government to repair mausoleums in the Genroku era, the government performed repairs by itself without granting the permission.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>文久の修陵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Repairing in Bunkyu era</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Repairing in Bunkyu era</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Repairing in Bunkyu era</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="54">
<j>宇都宮藩の建議で幕府が1862年（文久2）から行った事業が「文久の修陵」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the proposal by the Utsunomiya Domain, the operation enforced from 1862 was called &apos;Repairing in Bunkyu era.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the proposal by the Utsunomiya Domain, the operation enforced from 1862 was called &apos;Repairing in Bunkyu era.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A mausoleum repair project, known as the Bunkyu Mausoleum Repair, was undertaken starting in 1862 by the Tokugawa government based on a proposal made by the Utsunomiya Domain.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>こうした事業を幕府が許可した背景には、幕末という当時の世情が大きく影響している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the background that bakufu permitted the operations, state of society of that time as the end of Edo period had a major effect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bakufu permitted these operations as a result of the state of society of that time at the end of Edo period</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tokugawa government permitted this project as a result of the circumstances during the last days of its reign.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>この際に、各陵の工事前と工事後の様子を絵師に描かせ、上下二卷にまとめて1867年（慶応3）朝廷と幕府に献上したものがいわゆる「文久山陵図」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, Eshi painter painted the conditions before and after constructions and presented the paintings of volumes one and two to the Imperial court and bakufu in 1867, and those were the so-called &apos;Bunkyu Sanrikuzu.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, Eshi painters painted before and after conditions, presenting volumes one and two of these paintings to the Imperial court and bakufu in 1867, which were the so-called &apos;Bunkyu Sanrikuzu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, Eshi painters painted before and after conditions, presenting volumes one and two of these paintings to the Imperial court and bakufu in 1867, which were the so-called &apos;Bunkyu Sanrikuzu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>現在、朝廷献上本は宮内庁書陵部の、幕府献上本は国立公文書館の所蔵となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, the books presented to the Imperial court were possessed by Imperial Household Archives and the books presented to bakufu were possessed by the National Archives of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Presently these books are possessed by Imperial Household Archives and the books presented to bakufu are possessed by the National Archives of Japan.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Presently the books presented to the Imperial court are possessed by Imperial Household Archives and those presented to bakufu are possessed by the National Archives of Japan.</e>
<cmt>一部修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>2005年に国立公文書館本を元版とする『文久山陵図』が出版された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Bunkyu Sanrikuzu&quot; was published in 2005 that its pattern was the books of the National Archives of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Bunkyu Sanrikuzu&quot; which was published in 2005, was based on the books of the National Archives of Japan.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Bunkyu Sanrikuzu&quot; which was published in 2005, was based on the books of the National Archives of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="59">
<j>文久の修陵で多少でも手が加わったのは109か所におよぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were one hundred nine places where had some repair works in Repairing in Bunkyu era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were one hundred nine places where repair work had taken place during the Bunkyu era.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were one hundred nine places where repair work had taken place during the Bunkyu era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>天皇陵だけでも、山城34、大和34、河内24、和泉3、摂津1、丹波2で全部で76か所となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only with the imperial mausoleums, there are thirty four places in Yamashiro, thirty four in Yamato, twenty four in Kawachi, three in Izumi, one in Settsu, and two in Tanba, so seventy six places in total.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only with the imperial mausoleums, there are thirty four places in Yamashiro, thirty four in Yamato, twenty four in Kawachi, three in Izumi, one in Settsu, and two in Tanba, so seventy six places in total.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperors&apos; mausoleums that were repaired during this period, without counting other graves, amounted to 34 in Yamashiro, 34 in Yamato, 24 in Kawachi, 3 in Izumi, 1 in Settsu and 2 in Tanba, amounting to 76 in total.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ちょるや氏(id:88738), Los688(id:12316), Nnh(id:474), BJP039(id:47469), 瑞雲(id:27410), MIsogi(id:20599), Greenleaf(id:126500), Charlesy(id:137799), Extrahitz(id:26245), Lupinoid(id:68), 味っ子(id:17086), Rai koku(id:1661), ずもも(id:40267), ブレイズマン(id:183852), 柑橘類(id:112137), PaPa(id:24691), Nakaoka7675(id:39645), Toto-tarou(id:16648), Johncapistrano(id:969), Geizhals(id:1544), DAN99(id:177138), Yukichi99(id:29402), Ks aka 98(id:35909), Knua(id:66861), Tamago915(id:11009), 20060908(id:80818), シバタニヒデオ(id:40942), Kzhr(id:131), Toki-ho(id:10691), Higashi(id:8842), Izayohi(id:13095), Sakura-no-kuni(id:115977), J-ishikawa(id:74471), Bergmann(id:85282), Japan Maik(id:254359), Stanislaus(id:1806), Hukurou(id:115254), Web.dweller(id:153933), Aoiya(id:44787), Yanahan(id:2437), VanishingDuck(id:125995), 黒砂糖(id:38164), Nekolab(id:226401), 伊集院聖(id:53199), KENPEI(id:11349), 彩華1226(id:64711), ごまふあざ(id:36855), Geogie(id:143809), Mochi(id:9489), 小林　藤隆(id:20695), 新アルパカ(id:65850), Wases(id:155337), Fairuse(id:155332), NDR(id:5500), Komura Jutaro(id:35057), Teruz(id:45192), 伏儀(id:142093), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>