<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>岩倉宮忠成王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Iwakuranomiya Tadanari</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Iwakuranomiya Tadanari</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Iwakuranomiya Tadanari</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>岩倉宮忠成王（いわくらのみやただなりおう、承久3年（1221年） - 弘安2年3月11日 (旧暦)（1279年4月23日））は鎌倉時代の皇族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Iwakuranomiya Tadanari (1221-April 23rd, 1279) was a member of the Imperial family in the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Iwakuranomiya Tadanari (1221 - April 23, 1279) was a member of the Imperial Family in the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Iwakuranomiya Tadanari (1221 - April 23, 1279) was a member of the Imperial Family in the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>順徳天皇皇子で母は熱田神宮大宮司従三位藤原清季の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Emperor Juntoku, and his mother was a daughter of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) FUJIWARA no Kiyosue who was also the Daiguji (high priest of a great shrine) of Atsuta-jingu Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Emperor Juntoku, and his mother was a daughter of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) FUJIWARA no Kiyosue, who was also the Daiguji (high priestess of a great shrine) of Atsuta-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">the sister-uterine</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>同母の兄弟に天台座主尊覚法親王・園城寺長吏覚恵法親王、異母兄弟に仲恭天皇・善統親王がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Sonkakuho, Tendai-zasu (head priest of the Tendai sect) and Imperial Prince Kakueho, Chori (chief priest) of Onjo-ji Temple were his real brothers, and Emperor Chukyo and Imperial Prince Yoshimune were half brothers with the same father.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Sonkakuho, Tendai-zasu (head priest of the Tendai sect) and Imperial Prince Kakueho, Chori (chief priest) of Onjo-ji Temple were his real brothers, and Emperor Chukyo and Imperial Prince Yoshimune were half brothers by the same father.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cloistered Imperial Prince Sonkaku, Tendai-zasu (head priest of the Tendai sect) and Cloistered Imperial Prince Kakue, Chori (chief priest) of Onjo-ji Temple were his uterine brothers, and Emperor Chukyo and Imperial Prince Yoshimune were half brothers by the same father.</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースを削除、「法親王」「同母の兄弟」の表現を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>王子に源彦仁・彦豊王がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had two male children, MINAMOTO no Hikohito and Prince Hikotoyo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had two male children: MINAMOTO no Hikohito and Prince Hikotoyo.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had male children: MINAMOTO no Hikohito and Prince Hikotoyo.</e>
<cmt>「two」を除きました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>仁治3年（1242年）1月9日 (旧暦)四条天皇崩御の際、天皇は僅か12歳での崩御であった為皇太子が定まっておらず後継者選定に時間がかかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Emperor Shijo was only 12 years old when he died in 1242, the crown prince had not yet been selected, so it spent lots of time to select the successor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Emperor Shijo had died in 1242 at the age of 12, a crown prince hadn&apos;t yet been selected, so the choice of a successor took considerable time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Emperor Shijo had died on February 10, 1242 at the age of only 12, a crown prince hadn&apos;t yet been selected, so the choice of a successor took considerable time.</e>
<cmt>「1月9日(旧暦)」を西暦に直し補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>王は皇嗣候補の1人として名が挙がり、一方の候補は土御門天皇皇子の後嵯峨天皇であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Tadanari was one candidate for the successor to the throne, and Emperor Gosaga, a prince of Emperor Tsuchimikado, was another.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Tadanari was one candidate for the successor to the throne, and Emperor Gosaga, a prince of Emperor Tsuchimikado, was another.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Tadanari was one candidate for the successor to the throne, and Emperor Gosaga, a prince of Emperor Tsuchimikado, was another.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>忠成王には縁戚の九条道家がつき、邦仁王には土御門定通がつき夫々幕府に働き掛けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Tadanari supported by his relative, Michiie KUJO, and Prince Kunihito (Emperor Gosaga) supported by Sadamichi TSUCHIMIKADO made approaches to the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) separately.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Tadanari, supported by his relative, Michiie KUJO, and Prince Kunihito (Emperor Gosaga) supported by Sadamichi TSUCHIMIKADO, made separate approaches to the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Tadanari, supported by his relative, Michiie KUJO, and Prince Kunihito (Emperor Gosaga) supported by Sadamichi TSUCHIMIKADO, made separate approaches to the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>鎌倉幕府執権の北条泰時は順徳天皇の皇子である忠成王の即位に難色を示し、一時は軍事介入を仄めかしながら、鶴岡八幡宮の神意であるとして同じく後鳥羽天皇の孫にあたる邦仁王を推した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Disapproving of Prince Tadanari&apos;s enthronement because he was a prince of Emperor Juntoku, Yasutoki HOJO, the shogunal regent of the Kamakura bakufu, recommended Prince Kunihito, a grandchild of Emperor Gotoba, for the successor saying it was the god&apos;s will of Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine, hinting at a military intervention at one time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Disapproving of Prince Tadanari&apos;s enthronement because he was a prince of Emperor Juntoku, Yasutoki HOJO, the shogunal regent of the Kamakura bakufu, recommended as the successor Prince Kunihito, a grandchild of Emperor Gotoba, saying it was the will of the god of Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine, this being also a hint at military intervention.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Disapproving of Prince Tadanari&apos;s enthronement because he was the prince of Emperor Juntoku, Yasutoki HOJO, the shogunal regent of the Kamakura bakufu, while insinuating military intervention at times, recommended as the successor, Prince Kunihito, the grandchild of Emperor Gotoba, claiming it was the divine will of Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>FBに基いて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>同年の3月18日 (旧暦)に邦仁王（後嵯峨天皇）が即位する事となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Kunihito (Emperor Gosaga) ascended the throne in 1242.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Kunihito (Emperor Gosaga) ascended to the throne in 1242.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Kunihito (Emperor Gosaga) ascended to the throne in April 19, 1242.</e>
<cmt>「3月18日 (旧暦)」を西暦に直し補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>王はこの後宝治3年（1249年）2月25日 (旧暦)に元服し、岩倉宮と呼ばれるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the coming-of-age ceremony in 1249, the Prince Tadanari was called Iwakuranomiya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the coming-of-age ceremony in 1249, the Prince Tadanari was called Iwakuranomiya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the coming-of-age ceremony in April 9, 1249, the Prince Tadanari was called Iwakuranomiya.</e>
<cmt>「2月25日 (旧暦)」を西暦に直し補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), 代言人(id:33675), Cprobot(id:97843), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>