<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>鳥羽天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor TOBA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor TOBA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Toba</e>
<cmt>TOBA→Toba</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>鳥羽天皇（とばてんのう、康和5年1月16日（1103年2月24日） - 保元元年7月2日（1156年7月20日））は平安時代後期の第74代天皇（在位1107年 - 1123年）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor TOBA (February 24th, 1103 - July 20th, 1156) was the 74th Emperor in late Heian Period. (His reign was 1107 - 1123.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Toba (February 24, 1103 - July 20, 1156) was the seventy-fourth Emperor in the late Heian period (his reign was from 1107 - 1123).</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Toba (February 24, 1103 - July 20, 1156) was the seventy-fourth Emperor in the late Heian period (his reign was from 1107 - 1123).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>諱は宗仁（むねひと）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His posthumous name was Munehito.</e>
<cmt>諱→personal name[いみな] 諱　サンプル訳より</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His posthumous name was Munehito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His posthumous name was Munehito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>系譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>堀河天皇の皇子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the Prince of Emperor HORIKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the prince of Emperor Horikawa.</e>
<cmt>capital</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the prince of Emperor Horikawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>母は贈皇太后藤原苡子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was the Empress Dowager, posthumously conferred, FUJIWARA no Ishi.</e>
<cmt>贈皇太后→the Empress Dowager, posthumously conferred [定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was the Empress Dowager (posthumously conferred), FUJIWARA no Ishi.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was the Empress Dowager (posthumously conferred), FUJIWARA no Ishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>外祖父は藤原実季。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His maternal grandfather was FUJIWARA no Sanesue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His maternal grandfather was FUJIWARA no Sanesue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His maternal grandfather was FUJIWARA no Sanesue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>崇徳天皇、近衛天皇、後白河天皇は子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His children were Emperor SUTOKU, Emperor KONOE and Emperor GO-SHIRAKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children were Emperor SUTOKU, Emperor KONOE and Emperor GO-SHIRAKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children were Emperor Sutoku, Emperor Konoe and Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>SUTOKU→SutokuKONOE→KonoeGO-SHIRAKAWA→Goshirakawa</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>『古事談』の記述では崇徳天皇を白河天皇の実子としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the description in &quot;Kojidan&quot;, it was said Emperor SUTOKU is Emperor SHIRAKAWA&apos;s child.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the description in &quot;Kojidan,&quot; it was said that Emperor Sutoku was Emperor Shirakawa&apos;s child.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the description in &quot;Kojidan,&quot; it was said that Emperor Sutoku was Emperor Shirakawa&apos;s child.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>&quot;Biography&quot; -&gt; &quot;Brief Personal History&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>生後間もなく母苡子が没し、祖父の白河法皇の下に引き取られて養育された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother, Ishi died soon after the Emperor was born, he was then taken and raised by his grandfather, the retired Emperor SHIRAKAWA in pious life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother, Ishi, died soon after the Emperor was born, and then he was then taken and raised by his grandfather, the retired Emperor Shirakawa in pious life.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother, Ishi, died soon after the Emperor was born, and then he was then taken and raised by his grandfather, the Cloistered Emperor Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>retired→Cloistered法皇をCloistered Emperorとすると、そのあとに続くin pious lifeと意味が重なるため、In pious lifeは削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>父堀河天皇の死後、5歳で即位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He succeeded to the throne when he was five, after his father, the retired Emperor HORIKAWA died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He succeeded to the throne when he was five, after the death of his father, the retired Emperor Horikawa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He succeeded to the throne when he was five, after the death of his father, the Emperor Horikawa.</e>
<cmt>retired削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>政務は白河法皇が執った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The retired Emperor SHIRAKAWA in pious life took actual control of the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The retired Emperor Shirakawa in pious life took actual control of the government.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Cloistered Emperor Shirakawa took actual control of the government.</e>
<cmt>retired→Cloistered法皇をCloistered Emperorとすると、そのあとに続くin pious lifeと意味が重なるため、In pious lifeは削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>永久5年（1117年）白河法皇の養女である藤原璋子（待賢門院）が入内、翌年中宮とし五男二女をもうける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1117, the retired Emperor SHIRAKAWA&apos;s (in pious life) adopted daughter, FUJIWARA no Shoshi (Taiken mon in) made an Imperial Consort&apos;s bridal entry into court, she then became the second consort of an emperor, and had five boys and two girls.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1117, the retired Emperor Shirakawa&apos;s (in pious life) adopted daughter, FUJIWARA no Shoshi (Taiken mon in) made an Imperial consort&apos;s bridal entry into court, whereupon she became the second consort of an Emperor, and had five boys and two girls.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1117, the Cloistered Emperor Shirakawa&apos;s adopted daughter, FUJIWARA no Shoshi (Taiken mon in), made her bridal entry as an Imperial Consort into the court, whereupon she became the second consort of the Emperor, and had five boys and two girls.</e>
<cmt>retired→Cloistered法皇をCloistered Emperorとすると、そのあとに続くin pious lifeと意味が重なるため、In pious lifeは削除しました。consort&apos;s→Consort&apos;s文法。 “an Emperor” ではｄの天皇か不明。「入内」の訳確認。 “The” Emperor?</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>保安4年（1123年）1月23日長子崇徳天皇に譲位、その後も実権は白河法皇が握り続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 23rd 1123, the eldest child, Emperor SUTOKU succeeded to the throne, however after this the retired Emperor Shirakawa in pious life still took control of the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 23, 1123, the eldest child, Emperor Sutoku, succeeded to the throne; however, after this the retired Emperor Shirakawa in pious life retained control of the government.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 23, 1123, the eldest child, Emperor Sutoku, succeeded to the throne; however, after this the Cloistered Emperor Shirakawa retained control of the government.</e>
<cmt>retired→Cloistered法皇をCloistered Emperorとすると、そのあとに続くin pious lifeと意味が重なるため、In pious lifeは削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>白河法皇の死後、大治4年（1129年）より院政を敷く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the retired Emperor Shirakawa in pious life died, Emperor TOBA started ruling his cloister government.</e>
<cmt>院政 →cloister government　英次郎 on the web</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the retired Emperor Shirakawa in pious life died, Emperor TOBA started ruling his cloister government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Cloistered Emperor Shirakawa died, Emperor Toba started ruling his cloister government in 1129.</e>
<cmt>retired→Cloistered法皇をCloistered Emperorとすると、そのあとに続くin pious lifeと意味が重なるため、In pious lifeは削除しました。TOBA→Tobain 1129補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>白河法皇に疎んじられていた藤原忠実を呼び戻して娘の藤原泰子（高陽院）を入内させるなど、院の要職を自己の側近で固める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor called back FUJIWARA no Tadazane who was disfavored by the retired Emperor SHIRAKAWA in pious life, he then arranged his daughter, FUJIWARA no Taishi (Kaya no in) an Imperial Consort&apos;s bridal entry into court, also established all the significant post with his close aides.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor called back FUJIWARA no Tadazane, who was disfavored by the retired Emperor Shirakawa in pious life, and he then arranged his daughter, FUJIWARA no Taishi (Kaya no in) an Imperial Consort&apos;s bridal entry into the court, and filled all the significant posts with his close aides.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor called back FUJIWARA no Tadazane, who was disfavored by the Cloistered Emperor Shirakawa, and he then arranged his daughter, FUJIWARA no Taishi (Kaya no in) an Imperial Consort&apos;s bridal entry into the court, and filled all the significant posts with his close aides.</e>
<cmt>retired→Cloistered法皇をCloistered Emperorとすると、そのあとに続くin pious lifeと意味が重なるため、In pious lifeは削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>さらに白河法皇の後ろ盾を失った中宮璋子にかわり、藤原得子（美福門院）を寵愛して、所生の皇子体仁親王（近衛天皇）を即位させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, the Emperor loved FUJIWARA no Tokushi (Bifuku mon in), taking over the second consort of the emperor, Shoshi, and appointed his son, Prince Narihito (the Emperor Konoe) to succeed the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the Emperor loved FUJIWARA no Tokushi (Bifuku mon in), taking over as the second consort of the emperor, Shoshi, and appointed his son, Prince Narihito (the Emperor Konoe) to succeed the throne.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the Emperor loved FUJIWARA no Tokushi (Bifuku mon in), taking over as the second consort of the emperor, Shoshi who lost support from the Cloister government Goshirakawa, and appointed his son, Prince Narihito (the Emperor Konoe) to succeed the throne.</e>
<cmt>原文の「白河法皇の後ろ盾を失った」を訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>崇徳天皇、近衛天皇、後白河天皇の三代28年に渡り実権を掌握。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He took control of the politics for twenty eight years, during three generation from Emperor SUTOKU, Emperor KONOE and Emperor GO-SHIRAKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He held control of the politics for 28 years, during the three generations from Emperor Sutoku, Emperor Konoe and Emperor Go-Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He held control of the politics for 28 years, during the three generations from Emperor Sutoku, Emperor Konoe and Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>Go-Shirakawa→Goshirakawa</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>康治元年（1142年）には東大寺戒壇院にて受戒し、法皇となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1142 he became a retired Emperor in pious life after being ordained as a Buddhist priest by receiving the commandments of Buddhism at Todai-ji Temple Kaidan in [the building that houses &apos;the ordination platform&apos;].</e>
<cmt>東大寺戒壇院→Todai-ji Temple Kaidan in [the building that houses &apos;the ordination platform&apos;]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1142 he became a retired Emperor in pious life after being ordained as a Buddhist priest by receiving the orders of Buddhism at Todai-ji Temple Kaidan in [the building that houses the &apos;ordination platform&apos;].</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1142 he became a Cloistered Emperor after being ordained as a Buddhist priest by receiving the orders of Buddhism at Todai-ji Temple Kaidan in [the building that houses the &apos;ordination platform&apos;].</e>
<cmt>retired→Cloistered法皇をCloistered Emperorとすると、そのあとに続くin pious lifeと意味が重なるため、In pious lifeは削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="18">
<j>皇后美福門院に動かされて崇徳上皇を疎んじ、鳥羽法皇の崩御の直後に保元の乱が勃発する原因を作った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He disfavored the ex-Emperor SUTOKU as he followed Empress Bifuku mon in and indirectly caused the Hogen War just before the retired Emperor TOBA in pious life died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He disfavored the ex-Emperor Sutoku since he followed Empress Bifuku mon in, and indirectly caused the Hogen War just before the death of the retired Emperor Toba in pious life.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He disfavored the retired Emperor Sutoku since he followed Empress Bifuku mon in, and indirectly caused the Hogen War just after the death of the Cloistered Emperor Toba.</e>
<cmt>ex-Emperor→retired Emperorbefore→afterretired→Cloistered法皇をCloistered Emperorとすると、そのあとに続くin pious lifeと意味が重なるため、In pious lifeは削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>在位中の元号</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eras during his reign</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eras during his reign</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eras during his reign</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>嘉承 （1107年8月9日）- 1108年8月3日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kasho (August 9th, 1107) - August 3rd, 1108</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kasho (August 9, 1107) - August 3, 1108</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kasho (August 9, 1107) - August 3, 1108</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>天仁 1108年8月3日- 1110年7月13日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ten-nin August 3rd, 1108 - July 13th, 1110</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ten-nin August 3, 1108 - July 13, 1110</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tennin August 3, 1108 - July 13, 1110</e>
<cmt>Ten-nin→Tennin</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="21">
<j>天永 1110年7月31日- 1113年7月13日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ten-ei July 31st, 1110 - July 13th, 1113</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ten-ei July 31, 1110 - July 13, 1113</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenei July 31, 1110 - July 13, 1113</e>
<cmt>Ten-ei→Tenei</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="22">
<j>永久 1113年7月13日- 1118年4月3日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eikyu July 13th, 1113 - April 3rd, 1118</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eikyu July 13, 1113 - April 3, 1118</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eikyu July 13, 1113 - April 3, 1118</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="23">
<j>元永 1118年4月3日- 1120年4月10日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genei April 3rd, 1118 - April 10th, 1120</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genei April 3, 1118 - April 10, 1120</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genei April 3, 1118 - April 10, 1120</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="24">
<j>保安 1120年4月10日- （1123年1月28日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoan April 10th, 1120 - (January 28th, 1123)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoan April 10, 1120 - (January 28, 1123)</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoan April 10, 1120 - (January 28, 1123)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>御陵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial mausoleum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Mausoleum</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Mausoleum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>京都府京都市伏見区竹田内畑町の安樂壽院陵（あんらくじゅいんのみささぎ）に葬られる｡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor was entombed in Anrakujuin no misasagi, Uchihata-cho Town, Takeda, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor was entombed in Anrakujuin no misasagi, Uchihata-cho Town, Takeda, in the Fushimi ward of Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor was entombed in Anrakujuin no misasagi, Uchihata-cho Town, Takeda, in the Fushimi Ward of Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>ward→Ward</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>登場作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Related television programs, movies</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Related television programs, movies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Related television programs, movies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>『新・平家物語 (映画)』（1955年 監督：溝口健二、演：夏目俊二）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shin Heike Monogatari (The New Tale of the Heike) (movie)&quot; (1955 directed by Kenji MIZOGUCHI, played by Shunji NATSUME</e>
<cmt>新・平家物語 Shin Heike Monogatari [The New Tale of the Heike? 定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shin Heike Monogatari (The New Tale of the Heike)&quot; (a 1955 movie directed by Kenji MIZOGUCHI, played by Shunji NATSUME)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shin Heike Monogatari (The New Tale of the Heike)&quot; (a 1955 movie directed by Kenji MIZOGUCHI, played by Shunji NATSUME)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>『新・平家物語 (NHK大河ドラマ)』（1972年 NHK大河ドラマ、演：野村万蔵七世野村万蔵）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shin Heike Monogatari (The New Tale of the Heike) (NHK drama)&quot;, NHK period Drama, played by Manzo NOMURA (7th generation) Manzo NOMURA</e>
<cmt>NHK period Drama[英辞郎on the web]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shin Heike Monogatari (The New Tale of the Heike)&quot; an NHK period drama, played by Manzo NOMURA (seventh generation)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shin Heike Monogatari (The New Tale of the Heike)&quot; a 1972 NHK period drama, played by Manzo NOMURA (seventh generation)</e>
<cmt>1972 を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>(TBSドラマ)』（1992年 TBS、演：松方弘樹）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(TBS TV drama series) (1992 TBS, played by Hiroki MATSUKATA)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(TBS TV drama series) (1992, TBS, played by Hiroki MATSUKATA)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(TBS TV drama series) (1992, TBS, played by Hiroki MATSUKATA)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Lemon pie(id:66842), พริกขี้หนู(id:131976), Lonicera(id:20638), BOTarate(id:185620), 霧木諒二(id:9795), Nnh(id:474), Equaly(id:89792), Cprobot(id:97843), Charenji(id:7908), PixelBot(id:166734), 春野秋葉(id:36725), 味っ子(id:17086), 矢刺幹人(id:10639), 彩華1226(id:64711), MDR-SK(id:192066), Masyu(id:31065), 玄史生(id:43670), SuisuiBot(id:10165), 代言人(id:33675), 海行かば(id:115823), 名無し(id:7386), Rei-bot(id:94097), 怪蘇(id:45514), Shimoxx(id:9332), こぶまき(id:38278), YOSHI438(id:174755), Alexbot(id:157199), 唐棣色(id:64681), Richknight(id:141069), LeonardoRob0t(id:25875), LERK(id:4460), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>