<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>内裏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dairi (the Imperial palace)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dairi (the Imperial palace)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dairi (the Imperial palace)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>内裏（だいり）とは、古代都城の宮城における天皇の私的区域のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Dairi&quot; is the emperor&apos;s private area in the palace of ancient walled city.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Dairi&quot; is the emperor&apos;s private area in the palace of ancient walled city.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Dairi&quot; is the emperor&apos;s private area in the palace of ancient walled city.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>御所（ごしょ）、禁裏（きんり）、大内（おおうち）などの異称がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also known as &quot;Gosho,&quot; &quot;Kinri,&quot; and &quot;Ouchi.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also known as &quot;Gosho,&quot; &quot;Kinri,&quot; and &quot;Ouchi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also known as &quot;Gosho,&quot; &quot;Kinri,&quot; and &quot;Ouchi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>都城の北辺中央に 官庁エリアである宮城（皇城）があり、宮城内部に 天皇の私的な在所である内裏があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The palace (the emperor&apos;s house), which was the civic center, was located at the northern center of the walled city, and the dairi, which was the Emperor&apos;s private residence, was located inside the palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The palace (the emperor&apos;s house), which was the civic center, was located at the northern center of the walled city, and the dairi, which was the Emperor&apos;s private residence, was located inside the palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The palace (the emperor&apos;s house), which was the civic center, was located at the northern center of the walled city, and the dairi, which was the Emperor&apos;s private residence, was located inside the palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>平安京の内裏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dairi in Heiankyo (the ancient capital of Heian-kyo)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dairi in Heiankyo (the ancient capital of Heian-kyo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dairi in Heiankyo (the ancient capital of Heian-kyo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>平安京の北辺には宮城である平安宮（大内裏）があり、その内部の中央東寄りに南北約300m、東西約200mの内裏が存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heiangu (the Outer Palace Precincts), the palace, was located on the northern side of Heiankyo, and the dairi measured approximately 300m from north to south and 200m from east to west in the easterly of the center within the Heiangu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heiangu (the Outer Palace Precincts), the palace, was located on the northern side of Heiankyo, and the dairi measured approximately 300m from north to south and 200m from east to west in the easterly of the center within the Heiangu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heiangu (the Outer Palace Precincts), the palace, was located on the northern side of Heiankyo, and the dairi measured approximately 300 m from north to south and 200 m from east to west in the easterly of the center within the Heiangu.</e>
<cmt>単位の前にスペース</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>その場所は、現在の千本丸太町交差点付近である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This place is near the present-day Senbon Marutamachi intersection.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This place is near the present-day Senbon Marutamachi intersection.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This place is near the present-day Senbon Marutamachi intersection.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>内裏は、宮城の中央政庁である「朝堂院」の北側に位置し、周囲を築地塀に囲まれ、その内部は北側に後宮、南側に天皇の政務所である紫宸殿や日常生活の中心地である清涼殿などがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dairi was located on the north side of &apos;Chodoin&apos; which was the central government of the palace, surrounded by tsuijibei (a roofed mud-wall), and the inner palace was located on the north side and Shishinden (the Hall for State Ceremonies) which was the emperor&apos;s state affairs office (Seimusho) and Seiryouden which was the center of daily life were located on the south side inside the dairi.</e>
<cmt>後宮→the inner palace プログレッシブ和英中辞典 on the web清涼殿→Seiryouden→Seiryoden［ヘボン式表記に修正］政務所→Seimusho (state affairs office) ［定訳不明］</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dairi was located on the north side of &apos;Chodoin&apos; which was the central government of the palace, surrounded by tsuijibei (a roofed mud-wall), and the inner palace was located on the north side and Shishinden (the Hall for State Ceremonies) which was the emperor&apos;s state affairs office (Seimusho) and Seiryouden which was the center of daily life were located on the south side inside the dairi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dairi was located on the north side of &apos;Chodoin&apos; which was the central government of the palace, surrounded by tsuijibei (a roofed mud-wall), and the inner palace was located on the north side and Shishinden (the Hall for State Ceremonies) which was the emperor&apos;s state affairs office (Seimusho) and Seiryoden which was the center of daily life were located on the south side inside the dairi.</e>
<cmt>Seiryouden→Seiryodenスペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>平安京内裏は960年（天徳4年）火災で全焼したあと、幾度も火災に見舞われ、やがて里内裏が現れてくると天皇はもっぱらそちらに常住するようになり、内裏の意義は低下してくる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Heiankyo dairi was burned down in 960, it suffered several fires, and when satodairi (a temporary palace) became available, the emperor spent most of his time there, so the significance of the dairi was diminished.</e>
<cmt>里内裏→satodairi (a temporary palace)[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Heiankyo dairi was burned down in 960, it suffered several fires, and when satodairi (a temporary palace) became available, the emperor spent most of his time there, so the significance of the dairi was diminished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Heiankyo dairi was burned down in 960, it suffered several fires, and when satodairi (a temporary palace) became available, the emperor spent most of his time there, so the significance of the dairi was diminished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>平安宮の内裏は鎌倉時代に焼亡したのち再建されることはなく、南北朝以後は内裏の東に位置する里内裏であった京都御所（つちみかどひがしのとういんどの）が御所となり、近世になってその内域に紫宸殿、清涼殿などが復元された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dairi in Heiangu was never rebuilt after it was burned down in the Kamakura period, and Kyoto Imperial Palace (Tsuchimikado Higashi no Toindono) which was the satodairi located on the east side of the dairi became the palace after the Southern and Northern Dynasties, and Shishinden and Seiryoden were rebuilt within the palace in the recent times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dairi in Heiangu was never rebuilt after it was burned down during the Kamakura period, and Kyoto Imperial Palace (Tsuchimikado Higashi no Toindono) which was the satodairi located on the east side of the dairi became the palace after the Southern and Northern Dynasties, and Shishinden and Seiryoden were rebuilt within the palace in the recent times.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dairi in Heiangu was never rebuilt after it was burned down during the Kamakura period, and Kyoto Imperial Palace (Tsuchimikado Higashi no Toindono) which was the satodairi located on the east side of the dairi became the palace after the Southern and Northern Courts, and Shishinden and Seiryoden were rebuilt within the palace in the recent times.</e>
<cmt>Dynasties→Courts</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>現在の京都御所がこれである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the present-day Kyoto Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the present-day Kyoto Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the present-day Kyoto Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), Okura(id:23087), Kawai(id:5634), くっちゃめ(id:86793), VoidAimai(id:212464), うぃき野郎(id:53567), Louperibot(id:128971), Jade0416(id:104181), Dojo(id:32472), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>