<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>皇女</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Himemiko (phonetic alphabet of 皇女, Imperial Princess)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Himemiko (Imperial Princess)</e>
<cmt>カッコ内を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Himemiko (Imperial Princess)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>皇女（ひめみこ、おうじょ、こうじょ）とは、天皇の女子を指す呼称である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Himemiko (phonetic alphabet of 皇女, also Ojo or Kojo) is the naming of daughters of Teno (Emperor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Himemiko (also referred to as Ojo or Kojo) is the naming of daughters of Tennoo (emperor).</e>
<cmt>カッコ内を修正しました。Teno→Tenno,Emperor→emperor と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Himemiko (also referred to as Ojo or Kojo) is the naming of daughters of Tennoo (emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>内親王号が成立する以前に存在した女性皇族の身位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The naming was used before the appellation of Naishino (Imperial Princess) was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a status of the female Imperial Family members, before the establishment of the title of Naishino (imperial princess).</e>
<cmt>「身位＝身分や地位」として修正しました。Imperial Princess→imperial princess と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a status of the female Imperial Family members, before the establishment of the title of Naishino (imperial princess).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>これに対して男子を皇子という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, sons of Emperor were called Miko (Imperial Prince).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, the sons of the emperors were called Miko (imperial prince).</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。Emperor→emperors,Imperial Prince→imperial prince と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, the sons of the emperors were called Miko (imperial prince).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>転じて、日本以外の国の帝王の女子を呼ぶのにも用いる（例：アナスタシア・ニコラエヴナ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also Himemiko is used to refer to daughters of Emperor of other countries than Japan (example; Anastasia Nikolaeva Romanova)</e>
<cmt>「アナスタシア･ニコラエブナ－Wikipedia」に記載のある、「ニコライ2世とアレキサンドラ皇后の第4皇女。ロシア大公女。」から転用したと思われますが、「皇女－Wikipedia」最終更新 2010年6月26日 (土) 13:36には記載無し。→脈絡的にも唐突似思われます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shifting from it, the Himemiko is also used to call the daughters of the sovereigns of other countries other than Japan (example; Anastasia Nikolaeva Romanova).</e>
<cmt>「転ずる＝変わって、移り変わって」帝王：sovereigns としました。（様々な国が考えられるため）the を補いました。ピリオドを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shifting from it, the Himemiko is also used to call the daughters of the sovereigns of other countries other than Japan (example; Anastasia Nikolaeva Romanova).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>皇女</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nippon (Japan)</e>
<cmt>「皇子－Wikipedia」の稿に照らし、項目を日本としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Himemiko (Imperial Princess)</e>
<cmt>原文に忠実に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Himemiko (Imperial Princess)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>もともとは、ヤマト王権の時代に有力豪族の子弟をさして広く「みこ」と称されており、しかし、次第に大王 (ヤマト王権)の子弟を指すようになるにつれ、大王の女子を「ひめみこ」と呼称するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, children of Gozoku (local ruling family) were widely called &quot;Miko&quot; in the period of Yamato sovereignty, and while the naming became to be used refer to children of Okimi (great king of Yamato sovereignty), &quot;Himemiko&quot; became to be used to refer to daughters of Okimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, the children of Gozoku (local ruling family) were widely called &apos;Miko&apos; in the period of Yamato sovereignty, and while the naming came to refer to the children of Okimi (great king of Yamato sovereignty), the daughters of Okimi came to be called &apos;Himemiko.&apos;</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。 クォーツ、スペースを修正しました。became→came と修正しました。be used を削除しました。最後の部分をスムースに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, the children of Gozoku (local ruling family) were widely called &apos;Miko&apos; in the period of Yamato sovereignty, and while the naming came to refer to the children of Okimi (great king of Yamato sovereignty), the daughters of Okimi came to be called &apos;Himemiko.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>天皇の成立とともに皇女の字があてられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And 皇女, the character of Himemiko, started to be used for the naming at the same time as the establishment of Teno (Emperor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And, the characters of 皇女 came to be applied for Himemiko, along with the establishment of Tenno (emperor).</e>
<cmt>文脈に応じて修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And, the characters of 皇女 came to be applied for Himemiko, along with the establishment of Tenno (emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし、天皇の子女の身位として親王や内親王が定着すると、特定の皇族子女の呼称としての皇子や皇女は使用されなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Miko and Himemiko stopped to be used as naming of specific Imperial children, upon the establishment of Shino (Imperial Prince) and Naishino as names of standing of Imperial children.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Miko and Himemiko stopped to be used as the naming of the specific imperial children, upon the establishment of Shino (imperial prince) and Naishino as the statuses of the emperors&apos; children.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。Imperial children→imperial children,Imperial Prince→imperial prince,names of standing→statuses,Imperial children→emperors&apos; children と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Miko and Himemiko stopped to be used as the naming of the specific imperial children, upon the establishment of Shino (imperial prince) and Naishino as the statuses of the emperors&apos; children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>但し、天皇の女子一般を皇女と呼ぶ習慣は残り、第一皇女、第二皇女というように、天皇との続柄を指す場合に多用されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But it remained as customs to generally call Imperial daughters Himemiko which became to be often used to refer to their relationship with Emperor like the first Himemiko, second Himemiko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But, it remained as the customs to generally call the emperors&apos; daughters Himemiko, which became to be often used to refer to their relationship with the emperors as the first Himemiko, second Himemiko.</e>
<cmt>the, カンマを補いました。Imperial daughters→emperors&apos; daughters, Emperor→emperors,like→as と修正しました。スペースを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But, it remained as the customs to generally call the emperors&apos; daughters Himemiko, which became to be often used to refer to their relationship with the emperors as the first Himemiko, second Himemiko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>特に貴族の社会では、母系の血筋も家門繁栄や昇進の目安であり、内親王を母に持つ者は、皇女腹（みこばら）といわれ、皇后を母とするという意味である后腹（きさいばら）と並び、尊い生まれとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially in the society of nobles, the genealogy of the maternal line was a criterion of prosperity of the family and promotion, and children whose mothers were Naishino were described as children by Himemiko and regarded as children of noble birth, as well as children by Empress.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially in the society of nobles, the genealogy of the maternal line was a criterion of prosperity of the family and promotions; and the ones whose mothers were Naishino were described as Mikobara (children by Himemiko) and regarded as the children of noble birth, along with Kisaibara (children by empress).</e>
<cmt>promotion→promotions,children→ones,Empress→empress,as well as→along with と修正しました。パンクチュエーションを修正しました。the を補いました。より意味が通りやすくするため「皇女腹（みこばら）」「后腹（きさいばら）」を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially in the society of nobles, the genealogy of the maternal line was a criterion of prosperity of the family and promotions; and the ones whose mothers were Naishino were described as Mikobara (children by Himemiko) and regarded as the children of noble birth, along with Kisaibara (children by empress).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="11">
<j>今日では、例えば「悲劇の皇女　和宮親子内親王」というように皇族の名前や身位とは別に、その皇族の境遇を強調する場合にも多用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, &quot;Himemiko&quot; is also often used to stress the situation of specific Imperial family like &quot; Tragic Himemiko, Kazunomiya Chikako Naishino (Imperial Princess Kazunomiya Chikako) apart from naming or standing of Imperial family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, &quot;Himemiko&quot; is also often used to stress a situation of specific Imperial Family such as &apos;The tragic Himemiko, Kazunomiya Chikako Naishino&apos; (the Imperial Princess Kazunomiya Chikako) apart from the names or statuses of the members of the Imperial Family.</e>
<cmt>スペースを修正しました。the→a,Imperial family→Imperial Family,like→such as,クォーツを修正しました。the を補いました。naming→names,standing→statuses と修正しました。members を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, &quot;Himemiko&quot; is also often used to stress a situation of specific Imperial Family such as &apos;The tragic Himemiko, Kazunomiya Chikako Naishino&apos; (the Imperial Princess Kazunomiya Chikako) apart from the names or statuses of the members of the Imperial Family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), Loveless(id:129239), Aphaia(id:3132), 伏儀(id:142093), 松茸(id:27535), 海衛士(id:19229), 彩華1226(id:64711), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>