<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>高岳親王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Takaoka</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Takaoka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Takaoka</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>高岳親王（たかおかしんのう、延暦18年（799年） - 貞観 (日本)7年（865年））は平安時代初期の皇族・僧侶。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Takaoka (799 - 865) was the Imperial family and a priest during early Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Takaoka (799 - 865) was a member of the Imperial family and a priest during early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Takaoka (799 - 865) was a member of the Imperial family and a priest during early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>平城天皇の第三皇子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the third Prince of Emperor Heizei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the third Prince of Emperor Heizei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the third Prince of Emperor Heizei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>真如法親王。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monk-Imperial Prince Shinnyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Monk-Imperial Prince Shinnyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Monk-Imperial Prince Shinnyo</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>子に在原善淵ら。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His children were ARIWARA no Yoshibuchi and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children were ARIWARA no Yoshibuchi and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children were ARIWARA no Yoshibuchi and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>子孫は在原氏を称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His descendants named the Ariwara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His descendants were named the Ariwara clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His descendants were named the Ariwara clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>在原業平は甥にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His nephew was ARIWARA no Narihira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His nephew was ARIWARA no Narihira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His nephew was ARIWARA no Narihira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>809年、父の平城天皇が譲位して嵯峨天皇が即位すると皇太子に立てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 809 after his father, Emperor Heizei passed the throne and Emperor Saga succeeded to the throne, he became Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 809 after his father, Emperor Heizei passed the throne to Emperor Saga, he became Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 809 after his father, Emperor Heizei passed the throne to Emperor Saga, he became Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>810年、薬子の変で皇太子を廃される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He lost his position of Crown Prince after the Kusuko Incident in 809.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He lost his position of Crown Prince after the Kusuko Incident in 809.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He lost his position of Crown Prince after the Kusuko Incident in 810.</e>
<cmt>年号修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>822年、四品の位を受け名誉回復がなされるが、出家し、名を真如と改めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had his honor back by receiving Shihon (the fourth rank of Imperial Prince&apos;s rank), but he entered into priesthood and changed his name as Shinnyo.</e>
<cmt>真如→読み方不明でした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He got his honor back by receiving Shihon (the fourth rank of Imperial Prince&apos;s rank), but he entered into priesthood and changed his name to Shinnyo.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He got his honor back by receiving Shihon (the fourth rank of Imperial Prince&apos;s rank) in 822, but he entered into priesthood and changed his name to Shinnyo.</e>
<cmt>「822年」を訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>奈良の宗叡・修円、また空海の弟子として修行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He practiced asceticism as the disciple of Shuei, Shuen and Kukai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He practiced asceticism as the disciple of Shuei, Shuen and Kukai.</e>
<cmt>reformated cell, ticked the wrap text box,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He practiced asceticism as the disciple of Shuei, Shuen and Kukai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>弘法大師の十大弟子の一人となり、高野山に親王院を開いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became one of Kobo Daishi&apos;s, (Great Teacher) ten great disciple, and opened Shino-in Temple in Koya san Mountain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became one of Kobo Daishi&apos;s, (Great Teacher) ten great disciples, and opened the Shino-in Temple on Mount Koyasan..</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity and grammar, note: &quot;Koyasan&quot; mean&apos;s &quot;koya mountain&quot; in English, so the English and Japanese together could be translated as &quot;Mount Koya Mountain&quot; which is strange in English. Perhaps &quot;mount Koya&quot; would suffice as a translation, but I left the Japanese &quot;san&quot; as most readers will not understand Japanese anyway, those that do will discover the discrepancy.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became one of Kobo Daishi&apos;s, (Great Teacher) ten great disciples, and opened the Shino-in Temple on Mt. Koya.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除高野山の表記は他ファイルと統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>阿闍梨の位をうけ、また『胎蔵次第』を著した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He received the rank of Ajari (a master in esoteric Buddhism; a high priest), and wrote &quot;Taizo Sidai&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He received the rank of Ajari (master in esoteric Buddhism; a high priest), and wrote &quot;Taizo Sidai&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He received the rank of Ajari (master in esoteric Buddhism; a high priest), and wrote &quot;Taizo Sidai.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>835年、空海が入定すると、高弟のひとりとして遺骸の埋葬に立ち会った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 835 when Kukai became the death of holy person, he accompanied to bury Kukai&apos;s remains as Kukai&apos;s best disciple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 835 when Kukai died, he attended the burial of Kukai&apos;s remains as Kukai&apos;s best disciple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 835 when Kukai died, he attended the burial of Kukai&apos;s remains as one of the Kukai&apos;s best disciples.</e>
<cmt>「ひとりとして」を反映</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>855年、地震により東大寺東大寺盧舎那仏像の仏頭が落ちたとき、東大寺大仏司検校に任じられ修理を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 855 when there was an earthquake, the head of Buddha of the statues of Rushana Bu of Todai-ji Temple fell off, he was ordered by the Kengyo (supervisor of the temple affairs) of government office of the Great Buddha of Todai-ji Temple and repaired the damage.</e>
<cmt>東大寺大仏司→the government office of the Great Buddha of Todai-ji Temple[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 855 during an earthquake, the head of a Buddhist statue fell off, specifically, it was the Rushana Bu of Todai-ji Temple, he was ordered by the Kengyo (supervisor of the temple affairs) of government office of the Great Buddha of Todai-ji Temple to repair the damage.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 855 during an earthquake, the head of a Buddhist statue fell off, specifically, it was the Rushana Bu of Todai-ji Temple, he was ordered by the Kengyo (supervisor of the temple affairs) of government office of the Great Buddha of Todai-ji Temple to repair the damage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>その後、入唐求法を志して朝廷に願い出る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he applied to the Imperial Palace of Nitto Guho. (entering Tang and seeking after Buddhism)</e>
<cmt>入唐求法→Nitto Guho (entering Tang and seeking after Buddhism)[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he applied to the Imperial Palace of Nitto Guho. (entered Tang and continuing to pursue Buddhism)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he applied to the Imperial Palace of Nitto Guho (entered Tang and continuing to pursue Buddhism).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>861年、親王の一行23人は奈良から九州に入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 861 twenty three people of Imperial Prince&apos;s group went from Nara to Kyushu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 861 twenty three people of the Imperial Prince&apos;s group went from Nara to Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 861 twenty three people of the Imperial Prince&apos;s group went from Nara to Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>862年、太宰府を出帆して明州（寧波）に到着。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 862 they sailed from Dazaifu and arrived at Meishu. (Ningbo)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 862 they sailed from Dazaifu and arrived at Meishu. (Ningbo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 862 they sailed from Dazaifu and arrived at Meishu (Ningbo).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>864年、長安に到着する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 864 they arrived at Changan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 864 they arrived at Changan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 864 they arrived at Changan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>在唐40年になる留学僧円載の手配により西明寺に迎えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were welcomed by Saimyo-ji Temple after Ensai&apos;s arrangement, who was an overseas monk and lived in Tang for forty years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were welcomed by the Saimyo-ji Temple after Ensai&apos;s arrangement, who was an overseas monk and they lived in Tang for forty years.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were welcomed by the Saimyo-ji Temple thanks to arrangements made by Ensai, who was a monk who had lived overseas in Tang for forty years.</e>
<cmt>原文に沿って、訳し直しました。&quot;overseas monk&quot; sounds pretty unnatural to me so I&apos;ve written around it.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>しかし、当時の唐は武宗の仏教弾圧政策（会昌の廃仏）の影響により仏教は衰退の極にあったため親王は長安で優れた師を得られなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However due to the Wu Zong&apos;s Buddhism suppression policy (the anti-Buddhist movement in the Kaisho era) in Tang in those days, the Buddhism was on the edge of declining, Imperial Prince was not able to get his great teacher in Changan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However due to Wu Zong&apos;s policy of suppressing Buddhism (the anti-Buddhist movement during the Kaisho era) in Tang at the time, Buddhism was on the edge of a decline, the Imperial Prince was not able to find his great teacher in Changan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However due to Wu Zong&apos;s policy of suppressing Buddhism (the anti-Buddhist movement during the Kaisho era) in Tang at the time, Buddhism was on the edge of a decline, the Imperial Prince was not able to find his great teacher in Changan.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>このため天竺行きを決意。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to this situation, he decided to go to Tenjiku. (India)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to this situation, he decided to go to Tenjiku. (India)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to this situation, he decided to go to Tenjiku (India).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>865年、皇帝の勅許を得て従者3人とともに広州より海路天竺を目指し出発したが、その後の消息は不明となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 865, after obtaining Emperor&apos;s Imperial sanction, he left for Tenjiku (India) from Canton with three other aides, however there was no news heard about him since then.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 865, after obtaining Emperor&apos;s Imperial sanction, he left for Tenjiku (India) from Canton with three other aides, however there was never any news heard about him since then.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 865, after obtaining Emperor&apos;s Imperial sanction, he left for Tenjiku (India) from Canton with three other aides, however there was never any news heard about him since then.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="23">
<j>『日本三代実録』には16年後の881年、唐の留学僧からの報告で親王は羅越国（マレー半島の南端と推定されている）で死亡したと伝える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku&quot;, after sixteen years, there was a report of overseas monk from Tang that it is said the Imperial Prince died in Raetsu country (presumed to be the southern edge of Malay island) in 881.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku,&quot; after sixteen years, there was a report about an overseas monk from Tang said to be the Imperial Prince who died in Raetsu country (presumed to be the southern edge of the Malay peninsula) in 881.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity, I believe &quot;Malay Island&quot; to be a mistake, it is a peninsula rather than an island.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku&quot; (Veritable Records of Three Reigns of Japan), a report was received from monks based overseas in Tang saying that the Imperial Prince had died in a country called Raetsu (presumed to be located on the southern edge of the Malay peninsula) sixteen years later in 881.</e>
<cmt>『日本三代実録』に英語の説明を加え、全体的に再翻訳しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>虎の害に遭ったとも言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said he was attacked by a tiger.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said he was attacked by a tiger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said he was attacked by a tiger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="25">
<j>現在、マレーシアのジョホールバルの日本人墓地には、親王院が日本から御影石を運んだ親王の供養塔が建立されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Currently in the cemetery of Japanese people in Johor Baharu, there is a memorial tower of Imperial Prince with granite stones which were brought from Japan by Imperial Prince in.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently in the cemetery of Japanese people in Johor Baharu, there is a memorial tower of theImperial Prince made of granite stones which were brought from Japan by Imperial Prince in.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Currently in the cemetery of Japanese people in Johor Baharu, there is a memorial tower of the Imperial Prince made of granite stones which were brought from Japan by Imperial Prince in.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="26">
<j>澁澤龍彦の遺作『高丘親王航海記』のモデル。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was the model of &quot;The Record of Imperial Prince Takaoka&apos;s voyage&quot; by Tatsuhiko SHIBUSAWA who passed away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thisstory was the model for &quot;The Record of Imperial Prince Takaoka&apos;s voyage&quot; by Tatsuhiko SHIBUSAWA who has since passed away.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This story was the model for &quot;The Record of Imperial Prince Takaoka&apos;s Voyage&quot; by Tatsuhiko SHIBUSAWA who has since passed away.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入小文字→大文字</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="27">
<j>｢轟轟戦隊ボウケンジャー｣6人目の戦士・ボウケンシルバー：高丘映士の名前の元にもなっている(字は違うが)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It became the name of the sixth soldier of &apos;Go Go Sentai (squadron) Gokenja&apos;, Goken Silver: Eiji TAKAOKA. (It is written in different character.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It became the name of the sixth soldier of &apos;Go Go Sentai (squadron) Gokenja&apos;, Goken Silver: Eiji TAKAOKA.(written with a different character.)</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It became the name of the sixth soldier of &apos;Go Go Sentai (squadron) Bokenja&apos;, Goken Silver: Eiji TAKAOKA (written with a different character).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置移動人名スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Lemon pie(id:66842), Kanejan(id:78613), 霧木諒二(id:9795), ノトス(id:42992), Ko-ken(id:49348), 代言人(id:33675), Kstigarbha(id:13376), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), 海衛士(id:19229), 味っ子(id:17086), Aphaia(id:3132), Tcyiswalk(id:7279), ５１６(id:45205), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>