<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>人康親王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Saneyasu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Saneyasu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Saneyasu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>人康親王（さねやすしんのう、天長8年（831年） - 貞観14年5月5日（872年6月14日））は平安時代の皇族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Saneyasu (831 - June 14, 872) was the Imperial family in Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Saneyasu (831 - June 14, 872) was an Imperial family member in Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Saneyasu (831 - June 14, 872) was an Imperial family member in Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>仁明天皇第四皇子で、母は贈皇太后藤原沢子（贈太政大臣正一位藤原総継の娘）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was Emperor Ninmyo&apos;s fourth Prince, and his mother was Empress Dowager, posthumously conferred, FUJIWARA no Takushi. (Sawako) (the Grand Minister, posthumously conferred, Shoichii (Senior First Rank), FUJIWARA no Fusatsugu&apos;s daughter.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was Emperor Ninmyo&apos;s fourth Prince, and his mother was Empress Dowager, posthumously conferred, FUJIWARA no Takushi. (Sawako) (the Grand Minister, posthumously conferred, Shoichii (Senior First Rank), FUJIWARA no Fusatsugu&apos;s daughter.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was Emperor Ninmyo&apos;s fourth Prince, and his mother was Empress Dowager, posthumously conferred, FUJIWARA no Takushi (Sawako) (the Grand Minister, posthumously conferred, Shoichii (Senior First Rank), FUJIWARA no Fusatsugu&apos;s daughter).</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除、ピリオド位置訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>同母兄に光孝天皇。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His half older brother was Emperor Koko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His half older brother was Emperor Koko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His half older brother was Emperor Koko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>弾正尹兼常陸太守となったが、病気の為出家して隠棲した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became Danjo no kami (the Minister of Judical office) as well as the Governor of Hitachi Province, however he entered into priesthood due to his illness, and went into his secluded life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became Danjo no kami (the Minister of the Judical office) as well as the Governor of Hitachi Province, however he entered into priesthood due to his illness, and went into a secluded life.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became Danjo no kami (the Minister of the Judicial office) as well as the Governor of Hitachi Province, however he entered into priesthood due to his illness, and went into a secluded life.</e>
<cmt>Judicialスペル訂正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>山科宮人康親王とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also called Yamashinanomiya Imperial Prince Saneyasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also called Yamashinanomiya Imperial Prince Saneyasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also called Imperial Prince Yamashinanomiya Saneyasu.</e>
<cmt>Imperial Prince Yamashinanomiya Saneyasuに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>親王の王子は元慶4年（880年）に興基王が、元慶6年（882年）に興範王と興扶王が源氏朝臣の姓を賜り臣籍降下している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Princes, Prince Okimoto made demotion from nobility to subject in 880, Prince Okinori and Prince Okisuke did the same after receiving surname of the Minamoto clan Asomi in 882.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Princes, Prince Okimoto made demotion from nobility to subject in 880, Prince Okinori and Prince Okisuke did the same after receiving surnames of the Minamoto clan Asomi in 882.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Princes, Prince Okimoto made demotion from nobility to subject in 880, Prince Okinori and Prince Okisuke did the same after receiving surnames of the Minamoto clan Asomi in 882.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>なお、興基王が臣籍降下の際、興基王の王子の忠相王、敏相王、宜子女王（清和天皇女御）も同時に臣籍に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way when Prince Okimoto made demotion from nobility to subject, his Prince, Prince Tadasuke, Prince Toshisuke and Princess Gishi (Yoshiko) also made demotion from nobility to subject.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Prince Okimoto was demoted from nobility to subject, his Prince, Prince Tadasuke, Prince Toshisuke and Princess Gishi (Yoshiko) (Emperor Seiwa&apos;s Nyogo (a high-ranking lady in the court) also were demoted from nobility to subject.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Prince Okimoto was demoted from nobility to subject, his Prince, Prince Tadasuke, Prince Toshisuke and Princess Gishi (Yoshiko) (Emperor Seiwa&apos;s Nyogo (a high-ranking lady in the court)) also were demoted from nobility to subject.</e>
<cmt>)補足。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>貞観元年（859年）、両目を患い隠棲した場所が諸羽山の麓、現在の京都府京都市山科区四ノ宮（四ノ宮と言う地名は、仁明天皇の第四皇子であった親王を指すとする説が一般的）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 859, he went into his secluded life in the current Shinomiya, Yamashina Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, top of the Moroha Mountain, after he had disease of his eyes. (There was a common theory that the name of Shinomiya meant Emperor Ninmyo&apos;s fourth Prince.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 859, he went into secluded life in the current Shinomiya, Yamashina Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, at the top of the Mt. Moroha, after he got an eye disease. (There was a common theory that the name of Shinomiya meant Emperor Ninmyo&apos;s fourth Prince.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 859, he went into secluded life in the current Shinomiya, Yamashina Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, at the top of the Mt. Moroha, after he got an eye disease (there was a common theory that the name of Shinomiya meant Emperor Ninmyo&apos;s fourth Prince).</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>親王は琵琶の名手であったとされ、江戸時代には座頭・琵琶法師等の祖先とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial Prince was said to be a professional biwa (four-stringed Japanese) lute player, he was known as an originator of zato (a blind musician) of a blind biwa player (who traveled about performing and reciting the sutras) in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Prince was said to be a professional biwa (four-stringed Japanese) lute player, he was known as an originator of zato (a blind musician) of a blind biwa player (who traveled about performing and reciting the sutras) during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Prince was said to be a professional biwa (four-stringed Japanese) lute player, he was known as an originator of zato (a blind musician) of a blind biwa player (who traveled about performing and reciting the sutras) during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>当時検校の位にある琵琶法師が毎年当地に集まり琵琶を演奏し親王の霊を慰めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During this time the blind biwa player, who were in Kengyo (the highest rank of blind court musicians) came to this place every year to pray for the Imperial Prince&apos;s spirit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this time, blind biwa players, who were in Kengyo (the highest rank of blind court musicians) came to this place every year to pray for the Imperial Prince&apos;s spirit.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this time, blind biwa players, who were in Kengyo (the highest rank of blind court musicians) came to this place every year to pray for the Imperial Prince&apos;s spirit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、親王は『伊勢物語』に登場する「山科の禅師親王」とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial Prince was also said to be &apos;Imperial Prince Zenji&apos; (Reverend) who was in &quot;Ise monogatari&quot; (The Tales of Ise)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Prince was also said to be &apos;Imperial Prince Zenji&apos; (Reverend) who was in &quot;Ise monogatari&quot; (The Tales of Ise)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Prince was also said to be &apos;Imperial Prince Zenji&apos; (Reverend) who was in &quot;Ise monogatari&quot; (The Tales of Ise).</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>山科区四ノ宮柳山町の諸羽神社の境内には、親王の山荘跡とされる場所があり石碑が設けられている外、同四ノ宮泉水町には四宮地蔵があり、「人康親王　蝉丸　供養塔」と書かれた石碑が建っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a (stone) monument where the Imperial Prince&apos;s mountain villa used to be, in the precincts of Moroha Shrine in Yanagiyama-cho Town, Shinomiya, Yamashina Ward, there is also a Shinomiya Jizo (the Guardian Deity of Travelers and Children) in Sensui-cho Town, Shinomiya and a (stone) monument written as, &apos;Imperial Prince Saneyasu Semimaru (the name as famous poet) Kuyoto (a tower erected for the repose of a dead person&apos;s spirit)&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a (stone) monument where the Imperial Prince&apos;s mountain villa used to be, in the precincts of Moroha Shrine in Yanagiyama-cho Town, Shinomiya, Yamashina Ward, there is also a Shinomiya Jizo (the Guardian Deity of Travelers and Children) in Sensui-cho Town, Shinomiya and a (stone) monument written as, &apos;Imperial Prince Saneyasu Semimaru (the name as famous poet) Kuyoto (a tower erected for the repose of a dead person&apos;s spirit)&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a (stone) monument where the Imperial Prince&apos;s mountain villa used to be, in the precincts of Moroha Shrine in Yanagiyama-cho Town, Shinomiya, Yamashina Ward, there is also a Shinomiya Jizo (the Guardian Deity of Travelers and Children) in Sensui-cho Town, Shinomiya and a (stone) monument written as, &apos;Imperial Prince Saneyasu Semimaru (the name as famous poet) Kuyoto (a tower erected for the repose of a dead person&apos;s spirit).&apos;</e>
<cmt>スペース削除。ピリオド補足。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), H-shige(id:19751), Equaly(id:89792), 代言人(id:33675), 水野白楓(id:22811), Cprobot(id:97843), 唐棣色(id:64681), Kodai99(id:83937), BAKU(id:55205), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>