<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>吉備内親王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Princess Kibi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Princess Kibi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Princess Kibi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>吉備内親王（きびないしんのう、生年不詳 - 神亀6年2月12日 (旧暦)（729年3月20日））は、草壁皇子と元明天皇の次女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Princess Kibi, year of birth unknown, died on 20 March 729, is the second daughter of Prince Kusakabe and Empress Genmei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Princess Kibi (year of birth unknown - March 20, 729) is the second daughter of Prince Kusakabe and Empress Genmei.</e>
<cmt>日付がスタイル違反です。原文に合わせて、括弧を使用しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Princess Kibi (year of birth unknown - March 20, 729) is the second daughter of Prince Kusakabe and Empress Genmei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>元正天皇、文武天皇の姉妹。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A sister of Empress Gensho and Emperor Monmu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sister of Empress Gensho and Emperor Monmu.</e>
<cmt>定冠詞が必要です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sister of Empress Gensho and Emperor Monmu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>長屋王の妃。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wife of Prince Nagaya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The wife of Prince Nagaya.</e>
<cmt>定冠詞が必要です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The wife of Prince Nagaya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>長屋王の変で自殺に追い込まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was forced into suicide in Nagayao no Hen (Conspiracy of Nagayao).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was forced into suicide in the Nagayao no Hen (Conspiracy of Nagayao).</e>
<cmt>定冠詞が必要です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was forced into suicide in the Nagayao no Hen (Conspiracy of Nagayao).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>吉備内親王は長屋王に嫁ぎ、膳夫王・葛木王・鉤取王を産んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She married Prince Nagaya and gave birth to Kashiwade no Okimi, Prince Katsuragi, and Kagitori no Okimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She married Prince Nagaya and gave birth to Kashiwade no Okimi, Prince Katsuragi, and Kagitori no Okimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She married Prince Nagaya and gave birth to Kashiwade no Okimi, Prince Katsuragi, and Kagitori no Okimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>和銅8年（715年）2月25日に、息子達が皇孫待遇になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On 25 February 715 her Musuko (sons) came to be treated as imperial descendants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 25, 715, her sons became imperial descendants.</e>
<cmt>日付がスタイル違反です。カンマが必要です。不要な箇所を一部削除、変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 7, 715, her sons became imperial descendants.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>同年、元号が霊亀となった後に三品に叙される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year she was ordained Sanbon (the third rank of the Imperial Princes&apos; rank) after the era name turned to Reiki.</e>
<cmt>霊亀はこの文脈では生物の名前ではなく元号と判断し、定訳を採用しませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, she was ordained Sanbon (the third rank of the Imperial Princes&apos; rank) after the era name turned to Reiki.</e>
<cmt>カンマが必要です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, she was ordained Sanbon (the third rank of the Imperial Princes&apos; rank) after the era name turned to Reiki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>神亀元年（724年）2月4日に二品に叙される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On 4 February 724 she was ordained Nihon (the second court rank for Imperial Princes).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 4, 724, she was ordained Nihon (the second court rank for Imperial Princes).</e>
<cmt>日付がスタイル違反です。カンマが必要です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 7, 724, she was ordained Nihon (the second court rank for Imperial Princes).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変換</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>しかし、神亀6年（729年）2月、長屋王の使用人であった漆部造君足と中臣宮処連東人の密告により、長屋王が国を傾けるため「左道」を行ったとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However in February 729, employees of Prince Nagaya, Nuribeno Miyatsuko Kimitari and Nakatomino Miyakono Muraji Azumabito laid information against him saying that he did &quot;Sato (an evil course)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>・中臣宮処連東人 なかとみのみやこ の むらじあずまびと：このかたまりで1つの人名であるため、定訳は採用しませんでした。http://homepage.mac.com/kamekokishi/nagayaou.html・一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in February 729, employees of Prince Nagaya, Nuribeno Miyatsuko Kimitari and Nakatomino Miyakono Muraji Azumabito laid information against him saying that he did &quot;Sato (an evil course)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>カンマが必要です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in March 729, employees of Prince Nagaya, Nuribeno Miyatsuko Kimitari and Nakatomino Miyakono Muraji Azumabito laid information against him saying that he did &quot;Sato (an evil course)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>彼は自刃に追い込まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Nagaya was forced to kill himself.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Nagaya was forced to kill himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Nagaya was forced to kill himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>吉備内親王も、3人の息子達と共に縊死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Princess Kibi died by hanging with her three sons.</e>
<cmt>ぬりべのみやつこ きみたり</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Princess Kibi died by hanging with her three sons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Princess Kibi died by hanging with her three sons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>彼女は長屋王と同じく、生駒山に埋葬された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was buried on the Mt. Ikoma as was Prince Nagaya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was buried on Mt. Ikoma as was Prince Nagaya.</e>
<cmt>定冠詞は不要です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was buried on Mt. Ikoma as was Prince Nagaya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>当時皇太子基王が急死し、自らも病弱であった聖武天皇に万が一の事があれば、天皇の叔母にあたる内親王やその子供達の皇位継承の可能性もあったと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If Prince Motoi, Crown Prince suddenly died and if anything happened to Emperor Shomu who was sickly himself at that time, Imperial Princess who was aunt of Emperor and her sons are thought to have had possibility to succeed the Imperial Throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If Prince Motoi, the Crown Prince suddenly died and if anything happened to Emperor Shomu who was sick himself at that time, the Imperial Princess who was the aunt of the Emperor and her sons were thought to have had the possibility of succeeding the Imperial Throne.</e>
<cmt>定冠詞が必要です。時制、文法等が一部間違っていたため、変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If Prince Motoi, the Crown Prince suddenly died and if anything happened to Emperor Shomu who was sick himself at that time, the Imperial Princess who was the aunt of the Emperor and her sons were thought to have had the possibility of succeeding the Imperial Throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>天皇が根拠のない密告を信じて政府首班の長屋王を死に追い込んだ背景には、皇位を巡る天皇の疑心暗鬼があったとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some say in the context of Emperor&apos;s believing in information without solid foundation to force Prince Nagaya, the leader of government, to commit suicide was Emperor&apos;s doubts and fears about the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some say in the context of the Emperor&apos;s believing in the information without solid foundation to force Prince Nagaya, the leader of the government, to commit suicide was the Emperor&apos;s doubts and fears about the throne.</e>
<cmt>定冠詞が必要です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some say in the context of the Emperor&apos;s believing in the information without solid foundation to force Prince Nagaya, the leader of the government, to commit suicide was the Emperor&apos;s doubts and fears about the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), こぶまき(id:38278), たね(id:10372), 代言人(id:33675), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松平定治(id:146386), UMBRO(id:100484), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>