<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>治天の君</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chiten no Kimi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chiten no Kimi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chiten no Kimi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>治天の君（ちてんのきみ）は、日本の古代末期から中世において、天皇家の家督者として政務の実権を握った太上天皇又は天皇を指す用語。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chiten no Kimi was the word for the retired emperor or emperor who took control of the politics as the headship of Imperial family during the last ancient times to the Medieval period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chiten no Kimi was the word for the retired emperor or emperor who took control of politics as the head of Imperial family from ancient times to the Medieval period.</e>
<cmt>wordiness, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chiten no Kimi was the word for the retired emperor or emperor who took control of politics as the head of Imperial Family from ancient times to the Medieval period.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>事実上の国王として君臨した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chiten no Kimi actually reigned the relitics as Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chiten no Kimi actually reigned as Emperor.</e>
<cmt>deleted unknown word &quot;relitics&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chiten no Kimi in fact reigned as Emperor.</e>
<cmt>&quot;actually&quot;→&quot;in fact&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>上皇が治天の君である場合、現役の天皇は在位の君とよばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the retired emperor was actual Chiten no Kimi, the current emperor was called Zaii no Kimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the retired emperor was actual Chiten no Kimi, the current emperor was called Zaii no Kimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the retired emperor was actual Chiten no Kimi, the current emperor was called Zaii no Kimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また上皇が治天の君として行う院政に対して、現役の天皇が治天として政務に当たることを親政という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While retired emperor governed the cloister government as Chiten no Kimi, on the other hand it was called Shinsei (Emperor&apos;s directly ruled government) when the current emperor take the control of the politics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While a retired emperor governed the cloistered government as Chiten no Kimi, it was called Shinsei (Emperor&apos;s directly ruled government) when the current emperor takes control of the politics.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While a retired emperor governed the cloistered government as Chiten no Kimi, it was called Shinsei (Emperor&apos;s directly ruled government) when the current emperor takes control of the politics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>治天の君は、治天下（ちてんか）、治天（ちてん）、政務（せいむ）などとも呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chiten no Kimi was also called as Chitenka, Chiten, Seimu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chiten no Kimi was also called Chitenka, Chiten, Seimu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chiten no Kimi was also called Chitenka, Chiten, Seimu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>以下、本項では治天の君を「治天」という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From now on Chiten no Kimi is called &apos;Chiten&apos; in this chapter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From now on Chiten no Kimi is called &apos;Chiten&apos; in this chapter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From now on Chiten no Kimi is called &apos;Chiten&apos; in this section.</e>
<cmt>&quot;chapter&quot;→&quot;section&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>成立と意義</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The establishment and the meaning</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The establishment and the meaning of Chiten</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The establishment and the meaning of Chiten</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>治天という地位は、平安時代後期の院政の開始により登場した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The rank of Chiten started in the late Heian period when the cloister government was introduced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rank of Chiten started in the late Heian period when the cloistered government was introduced.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rank of Chiten started in the late Heian period when the cloistered government was introduced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>それまでは、藤原北家が摂政・関白（天皇の代行者・補佐者）として政治実権を持つ摂関政治が行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until then the regency government was run which the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan took the actual control of the politics as regent and chancellor. (acted as Emperor&apos;s proxy or supporter)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until then, the regency government was run by the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan who took the actual control of politics as regent and chancellor (acted as Emperor&apos;s proxy or supporter).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until then, the regency government was run by the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan who took the actual control of politics as regent and chancellor (acted as Emperor&apos;s proxy or supporter).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>あくまで律令官制の最高位に君臨するのは天皇であり、その天皇を代行・補佐することが、摂関の権力の源泉となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the Emperor who was the top position of the organization of government according to the ritsuryo codes, it was the source of regent and chancellor&apos;s authority to act as Emperor or support the emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the Emperor who was at the top position of the organization of government, according to the ritsuryo codes, it was the source of regent and chancellor&apos;s authority to act as Emperor or to support the emperor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was the Emperor who was at the top position of the organization of government, according to the ritsuryo codes, it was the source of regent and chancellor&apos;s authority to act as Emperor or to support the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし、白河天皇に始まる院政では、上皇が子へ譲位した後も、直接的な父権に基づき政治の実権を握るようになったため、摂関政治はその存立根拠を失った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However after Emperor Shirakawa started his cloister government, the retired Emperor still took the control of the politics to use direct paternal rights after he passed the position to his son, there was no base for regency government to exist any longer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Howeve, after Emperor Shirakawa started his cloister government, the retired Emperor still took the control of politics to use his direct paternal rights after he passed the position to his son, there was no basis for regency government to exist any longer.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after Emperor Shirakawa started his cloister government, the retired Emperor still took the control of politics to use his direct paternal rights after he passed the position to his son, there was no basis for regency government to exist any longer.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>この変遷は、天皇の母系にあたる摂関家が、天皇の父系にあたる上皇に、権力を奪われたものとみることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This change of the politics could be seen as the political power was taken away by the retired emperor who was the Emperor&apos;s paternal line, from regent and chancellor family who were from maternal line of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This change in politics could be seen as political power was taken away by the retired emperor who was the Emperor&apos;s paternal line, from the regent and chancellor families who were from maternal line of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This change in politics could be seen as political power was taken away by the retired emperor who was the Emperor&apos;s paternal line, from the regent and chancellor families who were from maternal line of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>平安中期から後期頃から、特定の官職を一つの家系で担うことが貴族社会の中で徐々に一般化しつつあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was gradually getting popular for one noble family to succeed a certain government official position in one family within the society of court nobles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was gradually becoming popular for one noble family to succeed a certain government official positions in one family within the society of court nobles.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From around the mid to the end of Heian period, it was gradually becoming popular for one noble family to succeed a certain government official positions in one family within the society of court nobles.</e>
<cmt>From around the mid to the end of Heian period補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>官職に就くことは、その官職に付随する収益権を得ることも意味しており、官職に就いた家系の長（家督者）は、収益を一族へ配分する権限・義務を持った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To succeed the government official position means to have the right to receive profit came with the position, the head of the family of the government official position had a right and duty to contribute the profit to the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To succeed the official government position means to have the right to receive profit that came with the position, the head of the family of the official government position had a right and a duty to contribute the profit to the family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To succeed the official government position means to have the right to receive profit that came with the position, the head of the family of the official government position had a right and a duty to contribute the profit to the family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>このような社会的な風潮が天皇家へも影響し、天皇家の家督者となった者が、本来の天皇の権限を執行するようになったのだろうと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This kind of social trend influenced to Imperial family, it was presumed that the head of the Imperial family started using authority that Emperor originally had was being used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This kind of social trend influenced the Imperial family, it was presumed that the head of the Imperial family started using authority that Emperor originally had.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This kind of social trend influenced the Imperial Family, it was presumed that the head of the Imperial Family started using authority that Emperor originally had.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>この天皇家の家督者が、実質的な国王であり、治天と呼ばれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This person, head of the Imperial family was actual Emperor, he started to be called Chiten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This person, head of the Imperial family was actually the Emperor, he started to be called Chiten.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This person, head of the Imperial Family was in fact the Emperor, he started to be called Chiten.</e>
<cmt>スペル&quot;actually&quot;→&quot;in fact&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>複数の上皇が併存することもあったが、治天となりうるのは1人のみであり、治天の地位を巡って上皇・天皇同士の闘争さえ発生した（保元の乱）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there were times when some retired emperors existed, however only one person was called Chiten, there was even an incident to fight between retired emperor and emperors to take the position as Chiten. (the Hogen War)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there were times when some retired emperors existed, only one person was called Chiten, there was even an incidents of fighting between a retired emperor and the emperor to take the position of Chiten (the Hogen War).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there were times when some retired emperors existed, only one person was called Chiten, there was even an incidents of fighting between a retired emperor and the emperor to take the position of Chiten (the Hogen War).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>治天が実質的な国王になると、天皇はあたかも東宮（皇太子）のようだ、とも言われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Chiten became actual Emperor, Emperor was called as if he was Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Chiten became the actual Emperor, the Emperor was called as if he was Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Chiten became the actual Emperor, the Emperor was called as if he was Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>実際、院政が本格化すると皇太子を立てることがなくなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, when cloister government became full-scale, there was no need to have official Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, when the cloistered government developed full-scale, there was no need to have an official Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, when the cloistered government developed full-scale, there was no need to have an official Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="19">
<j>治天となりうる資格要件は大きく2つある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were two main conditions to become Chiten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were two main conditions required to become Chiten.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were two main conditions required to become Chiten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>まず、天皇位を経験していること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First of all it should be a person who was once Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First of all it should be a person who was once Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First of all it should be a person who was once Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>次に、現天皇の直系尊属であること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Secondly he should be direct ascendant of the current emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Secondly he should be a direct ascendant of the current emperor.</e>
<cmt>&quot;a&quot; inserted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Secondly he should be a direct ascendant of the current emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>この結果、治天になれなければ、自らの子孫へ皇位継承できないことを意味しており、治天の座を獲得することは死活問題であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the result of this, it was necessary to become Chiten to pass the Imperial succession to his descendant, therefore is was a matter of life and death to obtain the position of Chiten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the result of this, it was necessary to become Chiten to pass the Imperial succession to his descendant, therefore it was a matter of life and death to obtain the position of Chiten.</e>
<cmt>&quot;is&quot; changed to &quot;it&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the result of this, it was necessary to become Chiten to pass the Imperial succession to his descendant, therefore it was a matter of life and death to obtain the position of Chiten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>略史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Short history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Short history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Short history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>平安後期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the late Heian period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the late Heian period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the late Heian period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>1086年（応徳3年）に白河天皇が実子の堀河天皇へ譲位し、院政を開始した時が、治天の成立だと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was said the establishment of Chiten was when Emperor Shirakawa passed the Imperial succession to his son, Emperor Horikawa and started the cloister government in 1086.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was said the establishment of Chiten was when Emperor Shirakawa passed the Imperial succession to his son, Emperor Horikawa and started the cloistered government in 1086.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was said the establishment of Chiten was when Emperor Shirakawa passed the Imperial succession to his biological son, Emperor Horikawa and started the cloistered government in 1086.</e>
<cmt>son→biological sonに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>堀河は皇位にありながら、政治の実務は白河が行っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Emperor Horikawa was Emperor, the retired Emperor Shirakawa took control of the politics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Emperor Horikawa was Emperor, the retired Emperor Shirakawa took control of the politics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Emperor Horikawa was Emperor, the Retired Emperor Shirakawa took control of the politics.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>堀河が没してその子鳥羽天皇が即位しても白河が政務を担った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after Emperor Horikawa died and his son, Emperor Toba succeeded to the throne, the retired Emperor Shirakawa kept on ruling the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after Emperor Horikawa died and his son, Emperor Toba succeeded to the throne, the retired Emperor Shirakawa kept on ruling the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after Emperor Horikawa died and his son, Emperor Toba succeeded to the throne, the Retired Emperor Shirakawa kept on ruling the government.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>白河が没すると、崇徳天皇に譲位し既に上皇となっていた鳥羽が治天となり、院政を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Shirakawa died, the retired Emperor Toba, who passed the throne to Emperor Sutoku, became Chiten and started the cloister government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Shirakawa died, the retired Emperor Toba, who passed the throne to Emperor Sutoku, became Chiten and started the cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Shirakawa died, the Retired Emperor Toba, who passed the throne to Emperor Sutoku, became Chiten and started the cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>白河も鳥羽も積極的な政策展開を行い、専制的な院政の典型とも、院政の最盛期とも評されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both Shirakawa and Toba worked on the positive development of the politics, it was criticized as the typical style of despotic cloister government or the golden age of the cloister government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both Shirakawa and Toba worked to positively develop politics, it was criticized as the typical style of despotic cloistered government or the golden age of the cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both Shirakawa and Toba worked to positively develop politics, it was criticized as the typical style of despotic cloistered government or the golden age of the cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="28">
<j>1156年（保元元年）、鳥羽が没すると、崇徳天皇と後白河天皇の兄弟が治天の座を巡って争い、後白河が勝利した（保元の乱）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1156 after Toda died, the brothers of Emperor Sutoku and Emperor Goshirakawa fought against each others to take position of Chiten, Emperor Goshirakawa won the battle. (The Hogen War)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1156 after Toda died, the brothers of Emperor Sutoku and Emperor Goshirakawa fought against each other to take the position of Chiten, Emperor Goshirakawa won the battle (The Hogen War).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1156 after Toda died, the brothers of Emperor Sutoku and Emperor Goshirakawa fought against each other to take the position of Chiten, Emperor Goshirakawa won the battle (The Hogen War).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>後白河は2年後の1158年に退位すると院政を開始し、途中、平清盛による院政停止や高倉天皇院政などがあったものの、1192年（建久3年）に没するまで治天の地位にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Goshirakawa abdicated from the throne two years later in 1158, he started the cloister government, there was incidents happened when Kiyomori TAIRA stopped the cloister government or Emperor Takakura took control of the cloister government during this period, however Goshirakawa was in the position of Chiten until he died in 1192.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Goshirakawa abdicated from the throne two years later in 1158, he started the cloistered government, there were incidents that happened when Kiyomori TAIRA stopped the cloistered government or when Emperor Takakura took control of the cloistered government during this period, however Goshirakawa was in the position of Chiten until he died in 1192.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Goshirakawa abdicated from the throne two years later in 1158, he started the cloistered government, there were incidents that happened when Kiyomori TAIRA stopped the cloistered government or when Emperor Takakura took control of the cloistered government during this period, however Goshirakawa was in the position of Chiten until he died in 1192.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="30">
<j>さて、白河院政の後期以降、院への荘園寄進が非常に集中するようになり、天皇家は莫大な経済基盤を得ることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the late era of the retired emperor Shirakawa&apos;s government, there were many donation of private estate (owned by a noble, temple or shrine) to the retired Emperor&apos;s Palace, it created the Imperial Palace to have an enormous financial base.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the late era of retired emperor Shirakawa&apos;s government, there were many donations of private estates (owned by a noble, a temple or a shrine) to the retired Emperor&apos;s Palace, it caused the Imperial Palace to have an enormous financial base.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the late era of Retired Emperor Shirakawa&apos;s government, there were many donations of private estates (owned by a noble, a temple or a shrine) to the retired Emperor&apos;s Palace, it caused the Imperial Palace to have an enormous financial base.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>これらの荘園はいくつかのグループに分けられ、別々に相続されていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These private estates were sorted by some groups and succeeded to different families individually.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These private estates were sorted by some groups and succeeded to different families individually.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These private estates were sorted by some groups and succeeded to different families individually.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>例としては、鳥羽が娘の八条院に相続した荘園群である八条院領、後白河が長講堂という寺院に寄進した長講堂領などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Examples of above are the group of private estate, Hachijoin estate, which Toba let his daughter, Hachijoin to succeed, and others are the the estate of Chokodo which Goshirakawa donated to the temple called Chokodo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Examples of above are seen in groups of private estates, Hachijoin estate, in which Toba let his daughter Hachijoin to succeed, and others are the the estates of Chokodo which Goshirakawa donated to the temple called Chokodo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Examples of above are seen in groups of private estates, Hachijoin estate, in which Toba let his daughter Hachijoin to succeed, and others are the the estates of Chokodo which Goshirakawa donated to the temple called Chokodo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>治天は天皇家の家督者として、これらの厖大な荘園群を総括する権限を有していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chiten had a right to control those enormous group of private estate as the head of the Imperial family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chiten had a right to control those enormous groups of private estates as the head of the Imperial family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chiten had a right to control those enormous groups of private estates as the head of the Imperial Family.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>鎌倉期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kamakura period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kamakura period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kamakura period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>後白河の次に治天となったのは、その孫の後鳥羽天皇だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The next Chiten after Goshirakawa was his grandchild, Emperor Gotoba.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The next Chiten after Goshirakawa was his grandchild, Emperor Gotoba.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The next Chiten after Goshirakawa was his grandchild, Emperor Gotoba.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>1180年代の治承・寿永の乱の結果、東国に鎌倉幕府が成立し、独自の支配権を獲得していたが、治天として専制を指向する後鳥羽には、幕府の存在が我慢ならないものだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1180 as the result of the Jisho, Juei War, there was an establishment of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by shogun) in the eastern province and had their own right to rule the government, however Gotoba who had the absolute power to direct despotisms government as Chiten, he could not stand the existence of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1180 as the result of the Jisho, Juei War, the Kamakura bakufu was established (Japanese feudal government headed by shogun) in the eastern province and had their own right to rule the government, however Gotoba who had the absolute power to direct a despotic government as Chiten, he could not stand the existence of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1180 as the result of the Jisho, Juei War, the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by shogun) was established in the eastern province and had their own right to rule the government, however Gotoba who had the absolute power to direct a despotic government as Chiten, he could not stand the existence of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>(Japanese feudal government headed by shogun)位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>1221年（承久3年）、まだ誕生して間もなく、源実朝が暗殺された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1221 soon after the bakufu was established, MINAMOTO no Sanetomo was assassinated who was the Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general subdues the barbarians&quot;), Toba attempted to overthrow the bakufu with armed force since he thought the bakufu was in insecure condition without having the Seii Taishogun, however his force lost the battle against bakufu. (The Jokyu War)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1221 soon after the bakufu was established, MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, who was the Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general subdues the barbarians&quot;), was assassinated. Toba attempted to overthrow the bakufu with armed force since he thought the bakufu was in an insecure condition without having the Seii Taishogun, but his forces lost the battle against the bakufu. (The Jokyu War)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1221 soon after the bakufu was established, MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, who was the Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general subdues the barbarians&quot;), was assassinated.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>これにより征夷大将軍不在となった幕府の体制を不安定と見た後鳥羽は、幕府の武力排除を試みたが、幕府軍に敗北してしまった（承久の乱）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toba attempted to overthrow the bakufu with armed force since he thought the bakufu was in an insecure condition without having the Seii Taishogun, but his forces lost the battle against the bakufu. (The Jokyu War)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>これにより、後鳥羽及びその直系の上皇・天皇は追放され、後堀河天皇が即位した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to this Gotoba and other retired Emperors and Emperors who were direct line of Gotoba, were taken their positions away, and Emperor Gohorikawa succeeded to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to this, Gotoba and other retired Emperors and Emperors who were direct line of Gotoba, had their positions taken away, and Emperor Gohorikawa succeeded to the throne.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to this, Gotoba and other retired Emperors and Emperors who were direct line of Gotoba, had their positions taken away, and Emperor Gohorikawa succeeded to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>後堀河の父守貞親王が天皇家の家督者として、治天に就任することとなったが、守貞親王は天皇位に就いたことがなく、治天の資格要件を欠いていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gohorikawa&apos;s father, Imperial Prince Morisada was decided to become Chiten as the head of the Imperial family, however the Prince had never been an Emperor and did not satisfy the condition to become Chiten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gohorikawa&apos;s father, Imperial Prince Morisada, was decided to become Chiten as the head of the Imperial family, however the Prince had never been an Emperor and, therefore, did not satisfy conditions to become Chiten.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gohorikawa&apos;s father, Imperial Prince Morisada, was decided to become Chiten as the head of the Imperial Family, however the Prince had never been an Emperor and, therefore, did not satisfy conditions to become Chiten.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>しかし、緊急事態であることが考慮され、特別に治天となり、後高倉院（天皇の例に倣い没後に院号を贈られた）として院政を布いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However it was considered that as an emergency, he became Chiten exceptionally, he started ruling the cloister government as Gotakakurain. (Following the example of the Emperor, he received in go title (a posthumous title given to an emperor) after he died.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However it was considered that as an emergency, he became an exceptional Chiten, he started ruling the cloistered government as Gotakakurain. (Following the example of the Emperor, he received in go title (a posthumous title given to an emperor) after death.))</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However it was considered that as an emergency, he became an exceptional Chiten, he started ruling the cloistered government as Gotakakurain. (Following the example of the Emperor, he received in go title (a posthumous title given to an emperor) after death.))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>これは、既に治天の存在が不可欠になっていたことを表している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This showed that the existence of Chiten became necessary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This showed that the existence of Chiten became necessary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This showed that the existence of Chiten became necessary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="42">
<j>承久の乱以降、治天がそれ以前と同等の権力を有することはなく、重要事項は幕府と協議した上で決定することが常態化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Jokyu War, Chiten did not have absolute political authority like it use to have, it became common to have meeting with the bakufu to decide an important issue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Jokyu War, Chiten did not have absolute political authority like it use to have, it became common to have meetings with the bakufu to decide an important issue.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Jokyu War, Chiten did not have absolute political authority like it use to have, it became common to have meetings with the bakufu to decide an important issue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>13世紀中期には、次代の治天の座を巡って後深草天皇の系統（持明院統）と亀山天皇の系統（大覚寺統）が対立したが、治天である後嵯峨天皇は亀山系による皇位継承を遺言して没し、後深草系はこれに反発して幕府に力添えを頼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After thirteenth century, there was a conflict between Emperor Gofukakusa&apos;s line (Jimyoin Imperial line) and Emperor Kameyama&apos;s line (Daikakuji Imperial line) to succeed to the next position of Chiten, but Emperor Gosaga died and left his will to let Emperor Kameyama&apos;s line to succeed to the throne, Emperor Gofukakusa&apos;s line was against it and asked the bakufu to support their force.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After middle of thirteenth century, there was a conflict between Emperor Gofukakusa&apos;s line (Jimyoin Imperial line) and Emperor Kameyama&apos;s line (Daikakuji Imperial line) to succeed to the next position of Chiten, but Emperor Gosaga died and left his will to have Emperor Kameyama&apos;s line succeed to the throne, Emperor Gofukakusa&apos;s line was against it and asked the bakufu to support their force.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After middle of thirteenth century, there was a conflict between Emperor Gofukakusa&apos;s line (Jimyoin Imperial line) and Emperor Kameyama&apos;s line (Daikakuji Imperial line) to succeed to the next position of Chiten, but Emperor Gosaga died and left his will to have Emperor Kameyama&apos;s line succeed to the throne, Emperor Gofukakusa&apos;s line was against it and asked the bakufu to support their force.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>最終的には幕府が仲介に入って双方が交互に治天の地位に就く両統迭立が行われるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Finally, the bakufu worked as mediation between two parties, it was decided to have Ryoto tetsuritsu (sharing the Imperial succession) to become Chiten in by turns.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Finally, the bakufu worked as mediator between the two parties, and it was decided to have Ryoto tetsuritsu (sharing the Imperial succession) become Chiten by turns.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Finally, the bakufu worked as mediator between the two parties, and it was decided to have Ryoto tetsuritsu (sharing the Imperial succession) become Chiten by turns.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>本来なら治天が次代の治天を指名するべきところ、その指名を幕府に委ねたという事実は、治天の権威が低下しただけでなく、治天の権限の一部を幕府が代行していたことも意味している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally Chiten would have appointed the next successor to the position, but the authority to appoint the successor was requested for the bakufu to decide, this proved that Chiten&apos;s authority became weak and the bakufu partly acted to use the authority of Chiten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally Chiten would have appointed the next successor to the position, but the authority to appoint the successor was requested to be the bakufu, this proved that Chiten&apos;s authority became weak and the bakufu partly acted to use the authority of Chiten.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally Chiten would have appointed the next successor to the position, but the authority to appoint the successor was requested to the bakufu, this proved that Chiten&apos;s authority became weak and the bakufu partly acted to use the authority of Chiten.</e>
<cmt>OKbe削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="46">
<j>1318年（文保2年）に即位した大覚寺統の後醍醐天皇は、上記の状況を大きく変革した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1318 Emperor Godaigo of Daikakuji Imperial line changed the above situation dramatically.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1318 Emperor Godaigo of Daikakuji Imperial line dramatically changed the above situation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1318 Emperor Godaigo of Daikakuji Imperial line dramatically changed the above situation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>まず、父であり治天でもある後宇多天皇の院政を停止し自ら政務に当たる親政を始め、また、2度にわたって倒幕を企てたが、いずれも天皇位への権力集中（権力の一元化）を指向したものだと見られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First of all he stopped his father, Emperor Uda&apos;s cloister government and started to rule the government directly by himself, he tried to overthrow the bakufu twice although he failed, it was presumed that these were both aimed to point to have concentrated political power. (unification of the authority)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First of all, he stopped his father, Emperor Uda&apos;s cloistered government and started to rule the government directly by himself, he tried to overthrow the bakufu twice although he failed, it was presumed that these attempts were both aimed at having concentrated political power. (unification of authority)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First of all, he stopped his father, Emperor Uda&apos;s cloistered government and started to rule the government directly by himself, he tried to overthrow the bakufu twice although he failed, it was presumed that these attempts were both aimed at having concentrated political power (unification of authority).</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>室町期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Muromachi period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Muromachi period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Muromachi period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="48">
<j>1333年（元弘3年）に始まる後醍醐の建武の新政は数年で失敗に至り、当時最大の実力者だった足利尊氏が幕府政権を樹立することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kenmu Restoration started by Emperor Godaigo ended just in a few years, the person in power at that time, Takauji ASHIKAGA was to open the bakufu. (the Muromachi bakufu ((Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kenmu Restoration started by Emperor Godaigo in 1333, ended in just a few years, the person in power at that time, Takauji ASHIKAGA was to open the bakufu (the Muromachi bakufu ((Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kenmu Restoration started by Emperor Godaigo in 1333, ended in just a few years, the person in power at that time, Takauji ASHIKAGA was to open the bakufu (the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)).</e>
<cmt>(削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>その際、尊氏は、持明院統の光厳天皇を治天とし、その弟の光明天皇を即位させ、自らは征夷大将軍に就任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time Takauji himself became Seii Taishogun, while he appointed Emperor Kogon of the Jimyoin Imperial line as Chiten, and appointed his younger brother, Emperor Komyo as Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time Takauji himself became Seii Taishogun, while he appointed Emperor Kogon, of the Jimyoin Imperial line, as Chiten, and also appointed his younger brother, Emperor Komyo as Emperor.</e>
<cmt>revised grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time Takauji himself became Seii Taishogun, while he appointed Emperor Kogon, of the Jimyoin Imperial line, as Chiten, and also appointed his younger brother, Emperor Komyo as Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>後醍醐は治天の地位を否定したけれども、社会はそれを必要としていたことを表している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Emperor Godaigo denied the the needs of position of Chiten, it showed that it was necessary for the society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Emperor Godaigo denied the the need for the position of Chiten, it showed that it was necessary for society.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Emperor Godaigo denied the need for the position of Chiten, it showed that it was necessary for society.</e>
<cmt>the削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>後に美濃国守護土岐頼遠が光厳上皇に矢を射掛ける事件を起こした際に、尊氏から事件の処理を任された弟の足利直義は幕府内外から起こる頼遠助命の声を無視してその斬首を強行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later on Military governor of Mino Province, Yorito TOKI caused an incident to throw an arrow to the retired emperor Kogon, Takauji&apos;s younger brother, Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA, who was asked to deal with this incident from Takauji, did not take advice of other people inside and outside of the bakufu to save Yorito&apos;s life, and forced the death penalty to him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later on Military governor of Mino Province, Yorito TOKI threw an arrow at the retired emperor Kogon, Takauji&apos;s younger brother, Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA, who was asked to deal with this incident from Takauji, did not take the advice of other people inside and outside of the bakufu to save Yorito&apos;s life, and forced the death penalty on him.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later on Military governor of Mino Province, Yorito TOKI threw an arrow at the Retired Emperor Kogon, Takauji&apos;s younger brother, Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA, who was asked to deal with this incident from Takauji, did not take the advice of other people inside and outside of the bakufu to save Yorito&apos;s life, and forced the death penalty on him.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>直義は光厳上皇の治天としての権威のみが、室町幕府の政治的な正統性を保障していることを理解していたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadayoshi understood that only authority from the retired emperor as Chiten, would have proved the legitimate political power of the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadayoshi understood that only authority from the retired emperor as Chiten, would have proved the legitimate political power of the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadayoshi understood that only authority from the Retired Emperor Kogon as Chiten, would have proved the legitimate political power of the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt>スペルKogon補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="53">
<j>1352年（正平7年/観応3年）、北朝・幕府と対立していた南朝は、観応の擾乱に乗じ、北朝側の治天・天皇・皇太子を拉致することに成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1352 the Southern Dynasty who was going against the Northern Dynasty and the bakufu, attempted to cause the Kanno Disturbance and was able to kidnap the Chiten, Emperor, Crown Prince of the Northern Dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1352 the Southern Court that was going against the Northern Court and the bakufu, attempted to cause the Kanno Disturbance and was able to kidnap the Chiten, Emperor, and Crown Prince of the Northern Court.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1352 the Southern Court that was going against the Northern Court and the bakufu, attempted to cause the Kanno Disturbance and was able to kidnap the Chiten, Emperor, and Crown Prince of the Northern Court.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>建前であっても、政治決定には治天の裁可を必要としていたため、幕府及び北朝側の公家は北朝の再開に取り組むこととなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Chiten had to give official approval making any political decision even though just as formality, the bakufu and the court nobles of Northern Dynasty started working the restoration of the Northern Dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Chiten had to give official approval for making any political decision even though it may be just a formality, the bakufu and the court nobles of Northern Court started working on restoring the Northern Court.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Chiten had to give official approval for making any political decision even though it may be just a formality, the bakufu and the court nobles of Northern Court started working on restoring the Northern Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>治天・天皇・皇太子の奪還は困難と見られたため、出家していた弥仁親王（光厳の子）を後光厳天皇とし、京都に残る天皇家の中で最高位者だった広義門院（西園寺寧子、後伏見の女御・光厳の生母）を治天とすることで対応した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They thought it would be hard to have their Chiten, Emperor, Crown Prince back, they appointed Imperial Prince Iyahito (Emperor Kogon&apos;s son) as Emperor Gokogon, who was in the priesthood, they also decided to appoint Kogimonin (Neishi/Yasuko SAIONJI, Gofushimi&apos;s Nyogo (high-ranking lady in the court, Emperor Kogon&apos;s birth mother) as Chiten, who had the highest rank in the Imperial family who remained in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They thought it would be hard to get their Chiten, Emperor, and Crown Prince back, they appointed Imperial Prince Iyahito (Emperor Kogon&apos;s son) as Emperor Gokogon, who was in the priesthood, they also decided to appoint Kogimonin (Neishi/Yasuko SAIONJI, Gofushimi&apos;s Nyogo (high-ranking lady in the court, Emperor Kogon&apos;s birth mother) as Chiten, who had the highest rank in the Imperial family among those who remained in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They thought it would be hard to get their Chiten, Emperor, and Crown Prince back, they appointed Imperial Prince Iyahito (Emperor Kogon&apos;s son) as Emperor Gokogon, who was in the priesthood, they also decided to appoint Kogimonin (Neishi/Yasuko SAIONJI, Gofushimi&apos;s Nyogo (high-ranking lady in the court, Emperor Kogon&apos;s birth mother) as Chiten, who had the highest rank in the Imperial Family among those who remained in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>女性で、しかも天皇家の出自でない者が治天となるのは前代未聞の事態だったが、これにより北朝は存続することができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the first time to have female Chiten who was not from Imperial family, however due to this succession, the Northern Dynasty was able to survive.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the first time to have a female Chiten who was not from Imperial family, however due to this succession, the Northern Court was able to survive.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was the first time to have a female Chiten who was not from Imperial Family, however due to this succession, the Northern Court was able to survive.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>どのような形であれ、治天という存在が政治上、必要不可欠だったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whatever the political form was, it was necessary to keep the style of Chiten as it was.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whatever the political form was, it was necessary to keep the style of Chiten as it was.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whatever the political form was, it was necessary to keep the style of Chiten as it was.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="58">
<j>最後の治天と呼べるのは、後光厳の子の後円融天皇である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The last Chiten could have been Emperor Goenyu, who was Emperor Gokogon&apos;s son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The last Chiten might have been Emperor Goenyu, who was Emperor Gokogon&apos;s son.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The last Chiten might have been Emperor Goenyu, who was Emperor Gokogon&apos;s son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>後円融は1393年（明徳4年）に没した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Goenyu died in 1393.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Goenyu died in 1393.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Goenyu died in 1393.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>その後、院政を行った上皇はいるが、天皇家の家督者としての実権を有していたとは言えず、治天と呼ぶにはふさわしくないと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that although some retired emperor ruled the cloister government, however it was different from the head of the Imperial family ruling the politics, thus this type of government could not be called as Chiten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that although some retired emperor ruled the cloistered government, it was different from the head of the Imperial family ruling politics, therefore, this type of government could not be called Chiten.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that although some retired emperor ruled the cloistered government, it was different from the head of the Imperial Family ruling politics, therefore, this type of government could not be called Chiten.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>例えば、後円融の子後小松天皇は、1392年（元中9年/明徳3年）に南北朝合一を実現して後醍醐以来の唯一の天皇となり、皇子称光天皇に譲位して院政を行い、1428年（正長元年）に称光が没して皇統が絶えると、伏見宮家から後花園天皇を立てて院政を続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example Emperor Goenyu&apos;s son, Emperor Gokomatsu made the unity of the Southern and the Northern Dynasty happen in 1392, and became only one Emperor since Emperor Godaigo&apos;s era, he then passed the Imperial throne to his Prince, Emperor Shoko to start his cloister government, after Emperor Shoko died and there was no one to succeed to the throne, he appointed Emperor Gohanazono from Fushiminomiya family as a successor to continue to rule his government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example Emperor Goenyu&apos;s son, Emperor Gokomatsu made the unity of the Southern and the Northern Court happen in 1392, and became the only Emperor since Emperor Godaigo&apos;s era, he then passed the Imperial throne to his Prince, Emperor Shoko to start his cloistered government, after Emperor Shoko died and there was no one to succeed to the throne, he appointed Emperor Gohanazono from the Fushiminomiya family as a successor to continue to rule his government.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example Emperor Goenyu&apos;s son, Emperor Gokomatsu made the unity of the Southern and the Northern Courts happen in 1392, and became the only Emperor since Emperor Godaigo&apos;s era, he then passed the Imperial throne to his Prince, Emperor Shoko to start his cloistered government, after Emperor Shoko died in 1428 and there was no one to succeed to the throne, he appointed Emperor Gohanazono from the Fushiminomiya family as a successor to continue to rule his government.</e>
<cmt>スペルin 1428補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>これらは、南北朝合一の約束であった両統迭立を死文化し、持明院統による皇位継承を既成事実化するための将軍足利義満の意向であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was planned by Shogun, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA who tried to cancel the mutual agreement of Ryototetsuritsu between Southern and the Northern Dynasty, and to make the Imperial succession of Jimyoin Imperial line happen as existing fact.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was planned by Shogun, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA who tried to cancel the mutual agreement of Ryototetsuritsu between the Southern and the Northern Court, and to make the Imperial succession of the Jimyoin Imperial line become an existing fact.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was planned by Shogun, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA who tried to cancel the mutual agreement of Ryoto tetsuritsu between the Southern and the Northern Courts, and to make the Imperial succession of the Jimyoin Imperial line become an existing fact.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>なお、後円融の死後、足利義満が事実上の治天となっており、子の義嗣を天皇位に就けようと画策していたとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way, after Goenyu died, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA was actual Chiten, there was a theory that he planned to appoint his son, Yoshitsugu as Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Goenyu died, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA was theactual Chiten, there was a theory that he planned to appoint his son, Yoshitsugu, as Emperor.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Goenyu died, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA was the actual Chiten, there was a theory that he planned to appoint his son, Yoshitsugu, as Emperor.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>また、義満死後に生じた後花園天皇の擁立は、後小松上皇による治天としての行為であるとも考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also presumed that Emperor Hanazono was appointed to Emperor after Yoshimitsu died by the retired emperor Gokomatsu&apos;s intention as Chiten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also presumed that Emperor Hanazono was appointed to Emperor after Yoshimitsu died from retired emperor Gokomatsu&apos;s intention as Chiten.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also presumed that Emperor Gohanazono was appointed to Emperor after Yoshimitsu died from Retired Emperor Gokomatsu&apos;s intention as Chiten.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 PANYNJ(id:38638), Reggaeman(id:6214), MIsogi(id:20599), 経済準学士(id:22656), 水野白楓(id:22811), Tcyiswalk(id:7279), LifeGuards(id:159934), Tanoshimo(id:151030), Hrs885(id:104160), Murasagi(id:79122), Whiteapple(id:1178), 怪蘇(id:45514), Shimoxx(id:9332), 伏儀(id:142093), のりまき(id:53470), 遠野能史(id:86555), Dojo(id:32472), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>