<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>後光厳天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Go-Kogon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Go-Kogon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Gokogon</e>
<cmt>Go-kogon→Gokogon</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>後光厳天皇（ごこうごんてんのう 延元3年/暦応元年3月2日（1338年3月23日） - 文中3年/応安7年1月29日（1374年3月12日） 在位：正平8年/文和元年8月17日（1352年9月25日） - 建徳2年/応安4年 3月23日（1371年4月9日））は、南北朝時代の北朝第4代天皇である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Go-Kogon (March 23rd, 1338 - March 12th, 1374), his reign was September 25th, 1352 - April 9th, 1371, he was the fourth Emperor of the Northern Dynasty during the period of the Northern and Southern Dynasties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Go-Kogon (March 23rd, 1338 - March 12th, 1374), his reign was from September 25th, 1352 to April 9th, 1371, he was the fourth Emperor of the Northern Dynasty during the period of the Northern and Southern Dynasties.</e>
<cmt>&quot;from&quot; &quot;to&quot; inserted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Gokogon (March 23, 1338 - March 12, 1374), his reign was from September 25, 1352 to April 9, 1371, he was the fourth Emperor of the Northern Court during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt>Go-kogon→Gokogon　Dynasty -&gt; Court に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>名を弥仁（いやひと）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His first name was Iyahito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His first name was Iyahito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His first name was Iyahito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>明治44年（1911年）に南朝が正統とされたため、歴代天皇からは除外されてしまっている（それまでは一貫して現皇統につながる北朝が正統とされていた）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was excluded from the successive Emperors since the Southern Dynasty was considered as standard era in 1911. (Since then the Northern Dynasty which leads to current Imperial line, was considered as standard era.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was excluded from the successive Emperors since the Southern Dynasty was considered the standard era in 1911. (Since that time the Northern Dynasty which led to current Imperial line, was considered as standard era.)</e>
<cmt>&quot;as&quot; deleted, tense corrected</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was excluded from the successive Emperors since the Southern Court was considered the standard era in 1911. (Until then the Northern Court which led to current Imperial line, was considered as standard era.)</e>
<cmt>Since that time→Until then　Dynasty -&gt; Court に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>系譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>光厳天皇の第二皇子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the second Prince of Emperor Kogon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the second Prince of Emperor Kogon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the second Prince of Emperor Kogon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>母は、正親町公秀の娘、陽禄門院・藤原秀子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was Kinhide OGIMACHI&apos;s daughter, Yorokumon in FUJIWARA no Hideko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was Kinhide OGIMACHI&apos;s daughter, Yorokumon in FUJIWARA no Hideko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was Kinhide OGIMACHI&apos;s daughter, Yorokumon-in FUJIWARA no Hideko.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>Brief Personal Historyに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>幼少時には、後伏見天皇の女御で祖母にあたる広義門院（西園寺寧子）に後見される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his childhood he was supervised by Kogimon in (Neishi (Yasuko) SAIONJI), who was a high-ranking lady in the court; an empress of Emperor Go-Fushimi and his grandmother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his childhood he was supervised by Kogimon in (Neishi (Yasuko) SAIONJI), who was a high-ranking lady in the court; an empress of Emperor Go-Fushimi and his grandmother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his childhood he was supervised by Kogimon-in (Neishi (Yasuko) SAIONJI), who was a high-ranking lady in the court; an empress of Emperor Gofushimi and his grandmother.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン挿入Go-Fushimi→Gofushimi</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>1351年、北朝を擁する足利尊氏が南朝に帰順し、皇統が一時的に南朝へ統一される観応の擾乱正平一統が成立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1351, after the leader of the Northern Dynasty, Takauji ASHIKAGA submitted to the Southern Dynasty, there was an unification of the Imperial line in the Shohei era of the Kanno Disturbance, and the Imperial line was given to the Southern Dynasty temporally.</e>
<cmt>正平一統→unification of the Imperial line in the Shohei era[定訳不明. Shohei Itto]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1351, after the leader of the Northern Dynasty, Takauji ASHIKAGA, submitted to the Southern Dynasty, unification of the Imperial line took place in the Shohei era during the Kanno Disturbance, and the Imperial lineage was given to the Southern Dynasty temporarily.</e>
<cmt>comma inserted, words revised, spelling corrected</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1351, after the leader of the Northern Court, Takauji ASHIKAGA, submitted to the Southern Court, unification of the Imperial line took place in the Shohei era during the Kanno Disturbance, and the Imperial lineage was given to the Southern Court temporarily.</e>
<cmt>Dynasty -&gt; Court に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>翌52年には南朝が京を軍事的に制圧して足利義詮を追い、正平一統は破綻。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following year of 1352, the unification was not concluded after the Southern Dynasty suppressed Kyoto with military force and chased Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following year, 1352, unification had not been concluded after the Southern Dynasty suppressed Kyoto with military force and pursued Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>words edited out, tense revised,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following year, 1352, unification had not been concluded after the Southern Dynasty suppressed Kyoto with military force and pursued Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>北朝は京都を奪還するものの、南朝方が撤退する際に北朝の光厳天皇（父）、光明天皇（叔父）、崇光天皇（兄）及び皇太子の直仁親王を吉野へ連行する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Northern Dynasty recaptured Kyoto, when the Southern Dynasty evacuated, Emperor Kogon (father), Emperor Komyo (uncle), Emperor Suko (brother) and Crown Prince, Prince Naohito were taken away to Yoshino.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Northern Dynasty recaptured Kyoto, the Southern Dynasty evacuated and Emperor Kogon (father), Emperor Komyo (uncle), Emperor Suko (brother) and Crown Prince, Prince Naohito were taken away to Yoshino.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity and readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Northern Court recaptured Kyoto, the Southern Court evacuated and Emperor Kogon (father), Emperor Komyo (uncle), Emperor Suko (brother) and Crown Prince, Imperial Prince Naohito were taken away to Yoshino.</e>
<cmt>Imperial補足Dynasty -&gt; Court に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>三上皇の拉致により、北朝では公事が停止し、院宣を発する治天の君や三種の神器も無い状態であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After three ex-Emperors were taken away, the public affairs were suspended in the Northern Dynasty, and there was no Chikun no Kimi who give a command from the ex-emperor or they did not have three sacred emblems of the Imperial Family.</e>
<cmt>治天の君→[定訳不明, 院政において実権を握って政治に当たった上皇を指す]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the three ex-Emperors were taken away, public affairs were suspended in the Northern Dynasty, and there was either no Chikun no Kimi to issue commands from the ex-emperor or they did not have the three sacred crests of the Imperial Family.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity and readability, &quot;symbols&quot; changed to &quot;crests&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the three retired Emperors were taken away, public affairs were suspended in the Northern Court, and there was either no Chikun no Kimi to issue commands from the ex-emperor or they did not have the three sacred emblems of the Imperial Family.</e>
<cmt>ex-→retiredcrests→emblems他ファイルと統一Dynasty -&gt; Court に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>弥仁は妙法院への入室が予定されていたが、京都の足利義詮は二条良基と相談の上、北朝再建のために広義門院に要請し、延臣に擁立されて即位した古代の継体天皇の先例も引照して、8月17日に弥仁は践祚され、後光厳天皇として即位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Prince Iyahito was expected to enter into Myohoin, after Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA of Kyoto discussed the situation with Yoshimoto NIJO, they asked help for Kogimon in, Prince Iyahito had an order of accession to the throne and enthroned as Emperor Go-Kogen, followed the example of ancient Emperor Keitai who enthroned after being appointed by 延臣.</e>
<cmt>延臣の読み方が不明でした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Prince Iyahito was expected to enter Myohoin, after Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA of Kyoto discussed the situation with Yoshimoto NIJO, they asked for help for Kogimon in, Prince Iyahito received the order to succeed to the throne and was enthroned as Emperor Go-Kogen, following the example of ancient Emperor Keitai who was enthroned after being appointed by 延臣.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity and readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Prince Iyahito was expected to enter Myohoin, after Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA of Kyoto discussed the situation with Yoshimoto NIJO, they asked for help for Kogimon-in, Prince Iyahito received the order to succeed to the throne and was enthroned as Emperor Gokogon in August 17, following the example of ancient Emperor Keitai who was enthroned after being appointed by Enshin (延臣).</e>
<cmt>ハイフン補足Go-kogen→Gokogon延臣→Enshin［正しい読み方が不明です］</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>後光厳の正統性の欠如などで北朝権威は弱体化し、南朝は京を奪還するなど活発に活動、後光厳も京都から近江国などへ下向することも何度かあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Northern Dynasty got weak due to the lack of orthodoxy of Emperor Go-Kogon, on the other hand the Southern Dynasty positively acted to recapture Kyoto, Emperor Go-Kogon came down to Kyoto to Omi Province several times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Northern Dynasty became weak due to the lack of orthodoxy on the part of Emperor Go-Kogon, to the contrary, the Southern Dynasty took positive steps to recapture Kyoto, Emperor Go-Kogon went down to Kyoto to Omi Province several times.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity and readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Northern Court became weak due to the lack of orthodoxy on the part of Emperor Gokogon, to the contrary, the Southern Court took positive steps to recapture Kyoto, Emperor Gokogon went down to Kyoto to Omi Province several times.</e>
<cmt>Go-kogon→Gokogonスペース削除Dynasty -&gt; Court に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="14">
<j>1370年（応安2年8月）には、第一皇子の緒仁親王（後円融天皇）への譲位を幕府に諮問するが、1357年に帰京していた兄の崇光が自らの皇子である伏見宮栄仁親王への皇統返還を主張する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1370 the Emperor requested the government for advice why the first Prince, Prince Ohito (the Emperor Go-Enyu) was passed the throne, his brother, Emperor Suko who returned to Kyoto in 1357, insisted to let his own Prince, Fushimi no Miya Prince Yoshihito to succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1370 the Emperor requested the government&apos;s advice as to why the first Prince, Prince Ohito (the Emperor Go-Enyu) was passed over for the throne, his brother, Emperor Suko who returned to Kyoto in 1357, insisted to have his own son, Fushimi no Miya Prince Yoshihito succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity and readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1370 the Emperor requested the government&apos;s advice as to why the first Prince, Imperial Prince Ohito (the Emperor Goenyu) was passed over for the throne, his brother, Emperor Suko who returned to Kyoto in 1357, insisted to have his own son, Fushimi no Miya Imperial Prince Yoshihito succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt>Imperial補足Go-Enyu→Goenyu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>幕府では3代将軍足利義満のもと、管領の細川頼之が後光厳の意思を尊重するべきであると回答し、翌1371年（応安4年3月23日）に、緒仁へ譲位して院政を敷く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kamakura government, under the supervision of the third Shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, a shogunal deputy (kanrei), Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA answered back to respect Emperor Go-Kogon&apos;s intention, on the following year of 1371, the Emperor passed the throne to Prince Ohito and started ruling cloister government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kamakura government, under the supervision of the third Shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, a shogunal deputy (kanrei), Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA answered Emperor Go-Kogon&apos;s, and the following year, 1371, the Emperor passed the throne to Prince Ohito who ruled a cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity and readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), under the supervision of the third Shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, a shogunal deputy (kanrei), Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA answered Emperor Gokogon&apos;s, and the following year, 1371 (March 23), the Emperor passed the throne to Prince Ohito and started a cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>Go-kogon→Gokogongovernment→bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) who ruled→and started原文に沿うように修正(March 23)補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>1374年（文中3年/応安7年1月29日）に病を得て崩御。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1374 he died of illness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1374 he died of illness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1374 (January 29) he died of illness.</e>
<cmt>(January 29)補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>在位中の元号</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eras during his reign</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Era&apos;s during his reign</e>
<cmt>changed to &quot;Era&apos;s&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eras during his reign</e>
<cmt>Era&apos;s を Eras に変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>観応 （1351年8月17日） - 1352年9月27日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanno (August 17, 1351) - September 27, 1352</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanno (August 17, 1351) - September 27, 1352</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanno (August 17, 1351) - September 27, 1352</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>文和 1352年9月27日 - 1356年3月28日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bunna September 27, 1352 - March 28, 1356</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bunna September 27, 1352 - March 28, 1356</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bunna September 27, 1352 - March 28, 1356</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>延文 1356年3月28日 - 1361年3月29日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enbun March 28th, 1356 - March 29th, 1361</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enbun March 28th, 1356 - March 29th, 1361</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enbun March 28, 1356 - March 29, 1361</e>
<cmt>日付表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>康安 1361年3月29日 - 1362年9月28日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koan March 29th, 1361 - September 28, 1362</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koan March 29th, 1361 - September 28, 1362</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koan March 29, 1361 - September 28, 1362</e>
<cmt>日付表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="21">
<j>貞治 1362年9月28日 - 1368年2月17日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jouji September 28, 1362 - February 17, 1368</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jouji September 28, 1362 - February 17, 1368</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Joji September 28, 1362 - February 17, 1368</e>
<cmt>Jouji→Joji</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="22">
<j>応安 1368年2月17日 - （1371年3月23日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oan February 17, 1368 - (March 23, 1371)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oan February 17, 1368 - (March 23, 1371)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oan February 17, 1368 - (March 23, 1371)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>陵墓・霊廟</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial mausoleum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial mausoleum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial mausoleum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>京都市伏見区深草坊町にある深草北陵（ふかくさのきたのみささぎ）に葬られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor was entombed in Fukakusa no Kita no Misasagi at Fukakusa Bo-cho Town, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor was entombed in Fukakusa no Kita no Misasagi at Fukakusa Bo-cho Town, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor was entombed in Fukakusa no Kita no Misasagi at Fukakusa Bo-cho Town, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Lemon pie(id:66842), Lonicera(id:20638), Izayohi(id:13095), BOTarate(id:185620), 霧木諒二(id:9795), Bergmann(id:85282), China(id:10362), Equaly(id:89792), たね(id:10372), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), Charenji(id:7908), Yanahan(id:2437), Ash Crow(id:26765), Toto-tarou(id:16648), でここ(id:9565), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), Masyu(id:31065), Nidarin(id:6420), SuisuiBot(id:10165), 代言人(id:33675), 総督(id:124846), 海行かば(id:115823), UMBRO(id:100484), Shikai shaw(id:14306), Loveless(id:129239), Caminante(id:39410), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>