<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>仁明天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor NINMTO</e>
<cmt>仁明天皇 the Emperor Ninmyo, 以下天皇名、人名の読み方は、ブリタニカ国際大百科事典、広辞苑、kotobank.jpで確認。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor NINMTO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Nimmyo</e>
<cmt>NINMTO→Nimmyo ヘボン式</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>仁明天皇（にんみょうてんのう 弘仁元年（810年） - 嘉祥3年3月21日（850年5月6日） 在位 天長10年3月6日（833年3月30日） - 嘉祥3年3月19日（850年5月4日））は、平安時代初期の第54代天皇。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor NINMYO (810 - May 6th 850), his reign was March 30th, 833 - May 4th, 850, who was the 54th Emperor during early Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Ninmyo (810 - May 6, 850), his reign was March 30, 833 - May 4, 850, who was the fifty-fourth Emperor (his reign occurring in the early Heian period).</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Nimmyo (810 - May 6, 850), the fifty-fourth Emperior, reigned from March 30, 833 to May 4, 850 (in the early Heian period).</e>
<cmt>Ninmyo→Nimmyo ヘボン式from to補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>名は正良（まさら）親王。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His first name was Prince Masara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His first name was Prince Masara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His first name was Prince Masara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>Biography→Brief Personal Historyに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>天長10年（833年）3月6日、叔父に当たる淳和天皇の譲りを受けて即位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 6th 833, he succeeded to the Imperial Throne after his uncle Emperor JUNNA passed the position to him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 6, 833, he succeeded to the Imperial Throne after his uncle, Emperor Junna, passed the position to him.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 6, 833, he succeeded to the Imperial Throne after his uncle, Emperor Junna, passed the position to him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>当初、淳和天皇の皇子恒貞親王を皇太子に立てたが、承和9年（842年）の承和の変により、恒貞は廃せられ、代わりに仁明天皇の第一皇子道康親王が立太子した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first Emperor JUNNA&apos;s Prince, Prince Tsunesada was recommended to become Crown Prince, however after the Showa Incident (842) Prince Tsunesada was dethroned, instead Emperor NINMYO&apos;s first Prince, Prince Michiyasu became Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the first prince of Emperor Junna, Prince Tsunesada was recommended to become the crown prince; however, after the Showa Incident (842) Prince Tsunesada was dethroned, so instead Emperor Ninmyo&apos;s first prince, Michiyasu, became the crown prince.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially, a prince of Emperor Junna, Prince Tsunesada, was recommended to become the crown prince; however, after the Showa Incident (842) Prince Tsunesada was dethroned, so instead Emperor Nimmyo&apos;s first prince, Michiyasu, became the crown prince.</e>
<cmt>Ninmyo→Nimmyo ヘボン式At the first→At first</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>これには自らの息子に皇位を継がせたい帝の意思と、それを利用して甥である道康を立太子させたい藤原良房の陰謀があったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said this incident happened since the Emperor wished his son to succeed the throne, on the other hand FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa used Emperor&apos;s intention and formed a plot against him to let his nephew Michiyasu to succeed the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that this incident happened because the Emperor wanted his son to succeed the throne; on the other hand, FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa used the Emperor&apos;s intentions and formed a plot against him in order that his nephew Michiyasu could succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that this incident happened because the Emperor wanted his son to succeed the throne; on the other hand, FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa used the Emperor&apos;s intentions and formed a plot against him in order that his nephew Michiyasu could succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>嘉祥3年（850年）3月19日に病にかかり、文徳天皇に譲位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ON March 19th, 850 the Emperor NINMYO passed the Imperial Throne to Emperor MONTOKU due to his illness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ON March 19, 850 the Emperor Ninmyo passed the Imperial Throne to Emperor Montoku due to his illness.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 19, 850 the Emperor Nimmyo passed the Imperial Throne to Emperor Montoku due to his illness.</e>
<cmt>ON→Onスペース削除Ninmyo→Nimmyo ヘボン式</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>同年3月21日に崩御。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died on March 21st, 850.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died on March 21, 850.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died on March 21, 850.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>天皇は幼少時から病弱であったとされ、『続日本後紀』には7歳の頃からの様々な病歴が記載され、即位後もしばしば薬（丹薬・石薬）の調薬をして医師並みの知識を有していたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said the Emperor was born weak from his childhood, on the record of &quot;Shoku Nihon Koki&quot; there is a list of his medical history since he was seven year old, after his enthronement he often compounded medicine (Tanyaku, Ishiyaku) and his knowledge was as good as professional doctors.</e>
<cmt>丹薬　石薬　定訳不明 丹薬は不老不死の仙薬。石薬は鉱物質の薬剤。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor had been weak since birth, and in the record of &quot;Shoku Nihon Koki&quot; his medical history since age seven is listed; after his enthronement he often compounded medicines (Tanyaku, Ishiyaku), and his knowledge was as good as that of a doctor in his time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor had been weak since birth, and in the record of &quot;Shoku Nihon Koki&quot; his medical history since age seven is listed; after his enthronement he often compounded medicines (Tanyaku, Ishiyaku), and his knowledge was as good as that of a doctor in his time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また、『三代実録』の藤原良相の死去の記事では良相ら側近に自分が作成した薬の試飲を命じたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to an article of FUJIWARA no Yoshimi&apos;s death in &quot;Sandai Jitsuroku&quot;, it is said the Emperor ordered Yoshimi to try his own made medicine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to an article of FUJIWARA no Yoshimi&apos;s death in &quot;Sandai Jitsuroku,&quot; it is said that the Emperor ordered Yoshimi to try his own, self-made medicine.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to an article of FUJIWARA no Yoshimi&apos;s death in &quot;Sandai Jitsuroku,&quot; it is said that the Emperor ordered Yoshimi to try his own, self-made medicine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>江戸時代の儒学者・頼山陽は、天皇が恒貞親王が度々皇太子を辞退した際には受け付けず、事件にかこつけてこれを廃して自分の実子を立てたことを厳しく非難している（『日本政記』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rai Sanyo who is aConfucianist; a Confucian scholar of Edo Period, criticized Emperor NINMYO that he did not accept Prince Tsunesada&apos;s previous frequent resignation from Crown Prince, but he removed the Prince and let his own son enthrone as Crown Prince when the incident happened. (&quot;Nihon Seiki&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rai Sanyo, who was a Confucianist (a Confucian scholar of the Edo period), criticized Emperor Ninmyo for not accepting Prince Tsunesada&apos;s previous frequent resignation from the crown prince, but he removed the prince and let his own son be enthroned as the crown prince when the incident occurred (&quot;Nihon Seiki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanyo RAI, who was a Confucianist (a Confucian scholar of the Edo period), criticized Emperor Nimmyo for not accepting Prince Tsunesada&apos;s previous frequent resignations from the position of Crown Prince, but he removed the prince and let his own son be enthroned as the crown prince when the incident occurred (&quot;Nihon Seiki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Rai Sanyo→Sanyo RAINinmyo→Nimmyo ヘボン式</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>異名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Different names</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Different names</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Different names</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>御陵の在所を以って深草帝（ふかくさのみかど）と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was called Fukakusa no Mikado which came from the name of the place where his mausoleum is.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was called &quot;Fukakusa no Mikado,&quot; which came from the name of the place in which his mausoleum was located.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was called &quot;Fukakusa no Mikado,&quot; which came from the name of the place in which his mausoleum was located.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>和風諡号は「日本根子天璽豊聡慧尊」（やまとねこあまつみしるしとよさとのみこと）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese style posthumous name is Yamato neko amatsu mishirushi toyosato no mikoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Japanese-style posthumous name is Yamato neko amatsu mishirushi toyosato no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Japanese-style posthumous name is Yamato neko amatsu mishirushi toyosato no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>和風諡号を奉贈された最後の天皇である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the last Emperor who received Japanese style posthumous name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the last Emperor to receive a Japanese-style posthumous name.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the last Emperor to receive a Japanese-style posthumous name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="16">
<j>在位中の元号</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eras during his reign</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eras during his reign</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eras during his reign</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>天長</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tencho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tencho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tencho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>承和834年 - 847年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jowa 834 - 847</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jowa (834 - 847)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jowa (834 - 847)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>嘉祥 848年 - 850年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kasho 848 - 850</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kasho (848 - 850)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kasho (848 - 850)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="20">
<j>陵墓・霊廟</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial mausoleum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Mausoleum</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Mausoleum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>深草陵（ふかくさのみささぎ 京都市伏見区深草東伊達町）に葬られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor was entombed in Fukakusa no Misasagi. (Higashi Date-cho Town, Fukakusa, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor was entombed in Fukakusa no Misasagi (Higashi Date-cho Town, Fukakusa, Fushimi ward, Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor was entombed in Fukakusa no Misasagi (Higashi Date-cho Town, Fukakusa, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>ward→Ward</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Yūchan62(id:147650), JAnDbot(id:66507), Lonicera(id:20638), Albambot(id:195288), 霧木諒二(id:9795), Nnh(id:474), Equaly(id:89792), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), Cprobot(id:97843), 味っ子(id:17086), Andee(id:20421), Aphaia(id:3132), MDR-SK(id:192066), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), Masyu(id:31065), Murasagi(id:79122), Yonoemon(id:55450), SEEK(id:46629), Nidarin(id:6420), SuisuiBot(id:10165), 代言人(id:33675), 名無し(id:7386), UMBRO(id:100484), Loveless(id:129239), YOSHI438(id:174755), 唐棣色(id:64681), Emonue(id:11273), LeonardoRob0t(id:25875), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>