<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>茅渟王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chinu no Okimi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chinu no Okimi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chinu no Okimi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>茅渟王（ちぬのおおきみ・ちぬのみこ、生没年不詳）は、6世紀後半から7世紀にかけての日本の皇族（王族）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chinu no Okimi (date of birth and death unknown) was a member of the Imperial (royal) family between the late sixth century and seventh century in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chinu no Okimi (year of birth and death unknown) was a member of the Imperial (royal) Family between the late sixth century and seventh the century in Japan.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。 「生没年不詳」を修正しました。family→Family と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chinu no Okimi (year of birth and death unknown) was a member of the Imperial (royal) Family between the late sixth century and seventh the century in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>茅渟皇子、智奴王とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His name was also written 茅渟皇子 and 智奴王.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His name is also written 茅渟皇子 or 智奴王.</e>
<cmt>was→is,and→or と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His name is also written 茅渟皇子 or 智奴王.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>押坂彦人大兄皇子（敏達天皇の皇子）の王子で、母は漢王の妹・大俣王。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Oshisaka no Hikohito no Oenomiko (a son of Emperor Bidatsu) and his mother was Omata no miko, sister of Aya no Okimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Oshisaka no Hikohito no Oenomiko (a son of the Emperor Bidatsu) and his mother was Omata no miko, a sister of Aya no Okimi.</e>
<cmt>the, a を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Oshisaka no Hikohito no Oenomiko (a son of the Emperor Bidatsu) and his mother was Omata no miko, a sister of Aya no Okimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>舒明天皇の異母兄に当たる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was an older paternal half-brother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was an older paternal half-brother of the Emperor Jomei.</e>
<cmt>「舒明天皇の」を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was an older paternal half-brother of the Emperor Jomei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>桜井皇子（欽明天皇の皇子）の女・吉備姫王（きびひめのみこ、吉備島皇祖母命）を妃とし、宝女王（皇極天皇, 斉明天皇）・軽王（孝徳天皇）を儲けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He married a daughter of Prince Sakurai (Prince of Emperor Kinmei), Kibihime no miko and had Takara hime (Empress Kogyoku and Emperor Saimei and Karu no miko (Emperor Kotoku).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He married a daughter of the Prince Sakurai (Prince of the Emperor Kinmei), Kibihime no miko and had Takara hime (the Empress Kogyoku and the Emperor Saimei) and Karu no miko (Emperor Kotoku) as children.</e>
<cmt>the, as children を補いました。スペース、カッコを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He married a daughter of the Prince Sakurai (Prince of the Emperor Kinmei), Kibihime no miko and had Takara hime (the Empress Kogyoku and the Emperor Saimei) and Karu no miko (Emperor Kotoku) as children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>茅渟王はその名が系譜に現われるのみで、事績は全く伝わっていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chinu no Okimi was recorded in a genealogy but none of his achievements were kept on record.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no record about his achievement, while only the name of Chinu no Okimi appears on the genealogy.</e>
<cmt>よりスムースに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no record about his achievement, while only the name of Chinu no Okimi appears on the genealogy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>歴史学者の塚口義信氏は、『新撰姓氏録』左京皇別に見える百済王 (皇族) （百済親王）に同一人としているものの、確かとは思われない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yosinobu TSUKAGUCHI, a historian, insisted that he was the same person as Kudara no okimi who appeared in Sakyo Kobetsu (clans branched out from the Imperial family) in &quot;Shinsen Shojiroku&quot; (Newly Compiled Register of Clan Names and Titles of Nobility).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yosinobu TSUKAGUCHI, a historian, insisted that he was the same person as Kudara no okimi who appeared in Sakyo Kobetsu (clans branched out from the Imperial Family) in &quot;Shinsen Shojiroku&quot; (Newly Compiled Register of Clan Names and Titles of Nobility); however, it does not seem to be certain.</e>
<cmt>「確かとは思われない」の部分を補いました。Imperial family→Imperial Family と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yosinobu TSUKAGUCHI, a historian, insisted that he was the same person as Kudara no okimi who appeared in Sakyo Kobetsu (clans branched out from the Imperial Family) in &quot;Shinsen Shojiroku&quot; (Newly Compiled Register of Clan Names and Titles of Nobility); however, it does not seem to be certain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>『延喜式』諸陵寮によれば、片岡葦田墓（かたおかのあしたのはか）に葬られたとされ、塚口氏は奈良県香芝市の平野塚穴山古墳（方墳・辺18m、国史跡）をそれに当てている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;the Engishiki&quot; (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers), he was buried in Kataoka no Ashitaka graveyard and Mr. Tsukaguchi insisted that it is Hirano Tsukaanayama Tumulus (square tumulus, side 18 meters, national historical site).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Engishiki&quot; (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers), he was buried in Kataoka no Ashitaka graveyard and Mr. Tsukaguchi guesses that to be Hirano Tsukaanayama Tumulus (square tumulus, 18 m sides, national historical site).</e>
<cmt>&quot;the Engishiki&quot;→the &quot;Engishiki,&quot;insisted→guesses,it is→to be,side 18 meters→18 m sides と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Engishiki&quot; (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers), he was buried in Kataoka no Ashitaka graveyard and Mr. Tsukaguchi guesses that to be Hirano Tsukaanayama Tumulus (square tumulus, 18 m sides, national historical site).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), かえるちゃん(id:197260), BAKU(id:55205), 代言人(id:33675), 果心居士(id:248111), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>