<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>誉津別命</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Homutsuwake no mikoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Homutsuwake no mikoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Homutsuwake no mikoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>誉津別命（ほむつわけのみこと、生没年未詳）は、記紀における皇族（王族）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Homutsuwake no mikoto (誉津別命: year of birth and death unknown) was a member of the Imperial family (Royal family), who appears in &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and &quot;Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>下記に名前漢字表記についての記述があるので、名前の漢字表記を加えました。記紀&quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) 記紀→統一用語リストではthe Kojiki (The Records of Ancient Matters) and the Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan)とするように指示がありましたが、どちらの書物も初出なので他の書物同様の扱いにし、以下は統一用語リスト表記に従いました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Homutsuwake no mikoto (誉津別命: year of birth and death unknown) was a member of the Imperial family (Royal family), who appears in &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and &quot;Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Homutsuwake no mikoto (誉津別命: year of birth and death unknown) was a member of the Imperial family (Royal family), who appears in &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and &quot;Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>『日本書紀』では誉津別命、『古事記』では本牟都和気命、本牟智和気命。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Nihonshoki, his name was written as 誉津別命, while in the Kojiki, it was written as 本牟都和気命 or 本牟智和気命.</e>
<cmt>名前の漢字表記を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Nihonshoki, his name is written as 誉津別命, while in the Kojiki, it is written as 本牟都和気命 or 本牟智和気命.</e>
<cmt>was をisに変更（2か所）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Nihonshoki, his name is written as 誉津別命, while in the Kojiki, it is written as 本牟都和気命 or 本牟智和気命.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>『尾張国風土記』逸文に品津別皇子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a itsubun (unknown or lost writings) of &quot;Owari no Kuni Fudoki (Records of the culture and geography of the Owari Province), his name was written as 品津別皇子.</e>
<cmt>名前の漢字表記を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a itsubun (unknown or lost writings) of &quot;Owari no Kuni Fudoki&quot; (Records of the culture and geography of the Owari Province), his name is written as 品津別皇子.</e>
<cmt>右引用符を追加、wasをisに変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a itsubun (unknown or lost writings) of &quot;Owari no Kuni Fudoki&quot; (Records of the culture and geography of the Owari Province), his name is written as 品津別皇子.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>垂仁天皇の第一皇子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is the first Imperial Prince of Emperor Suinin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the first Imperial Prince of Emperor Suinin.</e>
<cmt>isを wasに変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the first Imperial Prince of Emperor Suinin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>母は皇后の狭穂姫命（さほひめのみこと。彦坐王の女）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was Sahohime no mikoto (Hikoimasu no miko&apos;s daughter).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was Sahohime no mikoto (Hikoimasu no miko&apos;s daughter).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was Sahohime no mikoto (Hikoimasu no miko&apos;s daughter).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>神話における記述</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Description in the mythologies</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Description in the mythologies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Description in the mythologies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>出生</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Birth</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Birth</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Birth</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>名の由来を記では稲城の焼かれる火中で生まれたので、母により本牟智和気御子と名づけられたとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of his name, according to the Kojiki, derived from the fact that he was born in the middle of the flames burning the稲城Inagi Castle, and, therefore, his mother named him Homuchiwake no miko (son born through the flames)</e>
<cmt>本牟智和気御子→Homuchiwake no miko (son born through the flames)と名前の説明を（）に入れました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of his name, according to the Kojiki, derived from the story that he was born in the middle of the flames burning the Inagi Castle, whereby his mother named him Homuchiwake no miko (son born through the flames).</e>
<cmt>「稲城」の削除、文の最後にピリオド追記、その他表現の見直し。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of his name, according to the Kojiki, derived from the story that he was born in the middle of the flames burning the Inagi Castle, whereby his mother named him Homuchiwake no miko (son born through the flames).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>母の狭穂姫命はその兄狭穂彦王の興した叛乱（狭穂姫命狭穂毘古の叛乱）の際に自殺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother Sahohime no mikoto killed herself, involved in the rebellion (Rebellion of Sahohime no mikoto and Sahohiko no miko) touched off by her elder brother Sahohiko no miko.</e>
<cmt>狭穂姫命狭穂毘古の叛乱→定訳不明：Rebellion of Sahohime no mikoto and Sahohiko no miko としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother Sahohime no mikoto killed herself, involved in the rebellion (Rebellion of Sahohime no mikoto and Sahohiko no miko) touched off by her elder brother Sahohiko no miko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother Sahohime no mikoto killed herself, involved in the rebellion (Rebellion of Sahohime no mikoto and Sahohiko no miko) touched off by her elder brother Sahohiko no miko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>紀では叛乱の前に生まれていたとするが、火中から救い出されたのは記に同じ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to 紀the Nihonshoki, he had been already born when the rebellion was initiated, and the same as described in the Kojiki, he was rescued from the fire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the Nihonshoki, he had been already born when the rebellion was initiated, and the same as described in the Kojiki, he was rescued from the fire.</e>
<cmt>「紀」を削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the Nihonshoki, he had been already born when the rebellion was initiated, and the same as described in the Kojiki, he was rescued from the fire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>火中出産はコノハナノサクヤビメのうけいに繋がるとの指摘がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are persons who point out that the delivery scene in the fire has a certain similarity with the ukei (pledge) of Princess Konohanano sakuyahime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some people point out that the delivery scene in the fire has a certain similarity with the ukei (pledge) of Princess Konohanano sakuyahime.</e>
<cmt>主語をSome peopleに変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people point out that the delivery scene in the fire has a certain similarity with the ukei (pledge) of Princess Konohanano sakuyahime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>誉津別皇子は父天皇に大変鍾愛されたが、長じてひげが胸先に達しても言葉を発することがなく、特に『日本書紀』では赤子のように泣いてばかりであったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Homutsuwake no mikoto was deeply loved by his father, but although he grew up and even had the beard long enough to reach his breast, he did not pronounce a word, and moreover, according to the Nihonshoki, he kept only crying like a baby.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Homutsuwake no mikoto was deeply loved by his father, but although he grew up and even had the beard long enough to reach his breast, he did not speak a word, and moreover, according to the Nihonshoki, he kept only crying like a baby.</e>
<cmt>pronounceを speakに変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Homutsuwake no mikoto was deeply loved by his father, but although he grew up and even had the beard long enough to reach his breast, he did not speak a word, and moreover, according to the Nihonshoki, he kept only crying like a baby.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>言葉を発するまで</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until he gained speech</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until he spoke words</e>
<cmt>表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until he spoke words</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>『日本書紀』によると皇子はある日、鵠（くぐい、今のハクチョウ）が渡るさまを見て「是何物ぞ」と初めて言葉を発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the Nihonshoki, one day when the Imperial Prince was looking at a kugui (present swan) flying over the sky, he pronounced, for the first time, the words, &apos;what is it?&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the Nihonshoki, one day when the Imperial Prince saw a kugui (present swan) flying in the sky, he spoke, for the first time, the words &apos;what is it?&apos;</e>
<cmt>表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the Nihonshoki, one day when the Imperial Prince saw a kugui (present swan) flying in the sky, he spoke, for the first time, the words &apos;what is it?&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>天皇は喜び、その鵠を捕まえることを命じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor was pleased and ordered to capture the kugui (swan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor was pleased and ordered to capture the kugui (swan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor was pleased and ordered to capture the kugui (swan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>湯河板挙（鳥取造の祖）が出雲国（一書に但馬国）で捕まえて献上し、鵠を遊び相手にすると、誉津別命は言葉を発するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikawadana (the ancestor of Totori no miyatsuko) captured the swan in Izumo Province (in Tajima Province according to another document) and presented the bird to the Imperial Prince, then, Prince Homutsuwake, no mikoto became able to speak out while playing with the swan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ikawadana (the ancestor of Totori no miyatsuko) captured the swan in Izumo Province (in Tajima Province according to another document) and presented the bird to the Imperial Prince, then, Prince Homutsuwake no mikoto became able to speak out while playing with the swan.</e>
<cmt>「Homutsuwake, no mikoto」 からカンマを除去</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikawadana (the ancestor of Totori no miyatsuko) captured the swan in Izumo Province (in Tajima Province according to another document) and presented the bird to the Imperial Prince, then, Prince Homutsuwake no mikoto became able to speak out while playing with the swan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>ここに鳥取部、鳥飼部、誉津部を設けたとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that, hereto, Totoribe (unit of bird capturing), Torikaibe (unit of bird rearing), and Homutsube (unit serving Prince Homutsu) were set up.</e>
<cmt>鳥取部→定訳不明：Totoribe (unit of bird capturing) と（）内説明を加えました。 鳥飼部→定訳不明：Torikaibe (unit of bird rearing) と（）内説明を加えました。 誉津部→定訳不明：Homutsube (unit serving Prince Homutsu) と（）内説明を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that, hereto, Totoribe (unit of bird capturing), Torikaibe (unit of bird rearing), and Homutsube (unit serving Prince Homutsu) were set up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that, hereto, Totoribe (unit of bird capturing), Torikaibe (unit of bird rearing), and Homutsube (unit serving Prince Homutsu) were set up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>一方『古事記』では、誉津別皇子についてより詳しい伝承が述べられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the Kojiki offered more detailed descriptions on the Homutsuwake no mikoto&apos;s myth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the Kojiki offered more detailed descriptions on the Homutsuwake no mikoto&apos;s myth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the Kojiki offered more detailed descriptions on the Homutsuwake no mikoto&apos;s myth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>天皇は尾張の国の二股に分かれた杉で二股船を作り、それを運んできて、市師池、軽池に浮かべて、皇子とともに戯れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor made a boat with two hulls cutting a two truncal Japanese cedar that was growing in Owari Province, and took it back to the capital to play with the prince, launching it into the Ichishi Pond and Karonoike Pond.</e>
<cmt>二股船→定訳不明： boat with two hullsとしました。 二股に分かれた杉→定訳不明：two truncal Japanese cedarとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor made a boat with two hulls by cutting a two truncal Japanese cedar in Owari Province, and took it to the capital to play with the prince, launching it on the Ichishi Pond and Karonoike Pond.</e>
<cmt>表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor made a boat with two hulls by cutting a two truncal Japanese cedar in Owari Province, and took it to the capital to play with the prince, launching it on the Ichishi Pond and Karonoike Pond.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>あるとき皇子は天を往く鵠を見て何かを言おうとしたので、天皇はそれを見て鵠を捕らえるように命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One day, as the Emperor saw that the prince tried to say something, looking at a kugui (swan) flying over the sky, he ordered to capture that kugui.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One day, as the Emperor saw the prince try to say something, looking at a kugui (swan) flying in the sky, he ordered to capture that kugui.</e>
<cmt>saw that the prince triedを　saw the prince try に変更、over the sky in the skyに変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One day, as the Emperor saw the prince try to say something, looking at a kugui (swan) flying in the sky, he ordered to capture that kugui.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>鵠は紀伊国、播磨国、因幡国、丹波国、但馬、近江国、美濃国、尾張国、信濃国、越国を飛んだ末に捕らえられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The kugui (swan) was finally captured, after it had traveled far over Kii Province, Harima Province, Inaba Province, Tanba Province, Tajima Province, Omi Province, Mino Province, Owari Province, Shinano Province, and Koshi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kugui (swan) was finally captured, after it had traveled far over Kii Province, Harima Province, Inaba Province, Tanba Province, Tajima Province, Omi Province, Mino Province, Owari Province, Shinano Province, and Koshi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kugui (swan) was finally captured, after it had traveled far over Kii Province, Harima Province, Inaba Province, Tanba Province, Tajima Province, Omi Province, Mino Province, Owari Province, Shinano Province, and Koshi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>しかし皇子は鵠を得てもまだ物言わなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the prince did pronounce a word, even after having the kugui (swan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the prince did not speak a word, even after having the kugui (swan).</e>
<cmt>did pronounce a word をdid not speak a wordに変更。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the prince did not speak a word, even after having the kugui (swan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>ある晩、天皇の夢に何者かが現れて「我が宮を天皇の宮のごとく造り直したなら、皇子はしゃべれるようになるだろう」と述べた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One night, the Emperor dreamed about a man who said, &apos;if you reconstruct and make my palace like the palace where you, the Emperor, are living, the Prince will be able to speak.&apos;</e>
<cmt>宮→palace 文脈から話者が神だということが未だ明らかにされていないので、このようにしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One night, the Emperor dreamed about a man who said, &apos;if you reconstruct and make my palace like the palace where you, the Emperor, are living, the Prince will be able to speak.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One night, the Emperor dreamed about a man who said, &apos;if you reconstruct and make my palace like the palace where you, the Emperor, are living, the Prince will be able to speak.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>そこで天皇は太占で夢に現れたのが何者であるか占わせると、言語（物言わぬ）は出雲大神の祟りとわかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, the Emperor ordered to practice a scapulimancy to find the identity of the person he dreamed about, and it was revealed that the Prince&apos;s illocution (impaired speech) was the curse of Izumo no Okami (Great God of Izumo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, the Emperor ordered to practice a scapulimancy to find the identity of the person he had dreamed about, and it was revealed that the Prince&apos;s illocution (impaired speech) was the curse of Izumo no Okami (Great God of Izumo).</e>
<cmt>dreamed had dreamedと時制を調整</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, the Emperor ordered to practice a scapulimancy to find the identity of the person he had dreamed about, and it was revealed that the Prince&apos;s illocution (impaired speech) was the curse of Izumo no Okami (Great God of Izumo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>天皇は皇子を曙立王、菟上王とともに出雲に遣わし、大神を拝させると皇子はしゃべれるようになったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, the Emperor sent the Prince to Izumo with Aketatsu no o and Unakami no o to make them bow to Okami, and the Prince recovered the speech.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, the Emperor sent the Prince to Izumo with Aketatsu no o and Unakami no o to make them bow to Okami, and the Prince recovered the speech.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, the Emperor sent the Prince to Izumo with Aketatsu no o and Unakami no o to make them bow to Okami, and the Prince recovered the speech.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>その帰り、皇子は肥長比売と婚姻したが、垣間見ると肥長比売が蛇体であったため、畏れて逃げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On his way back, the Prince got married with Hinagahime, however, when he glimpsed her body and see that she was a snake, the terrified Prince scurried away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On his way back, the Prince got married to Hinagahime, however, when he glimpsed her body and found that she was a snake, the terrified Prince scurried away.</e>
<cmt>got married with をgot married to に変更。seeをfoundに変更。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On his way back, the Prince got married to Hinagahime, however, when he glimpsed her body and found that she was a snake, the terrified Prince scurried away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>すると肥長比売は海原を照らしながら追いかけてきたので、皇子はますます畏れて、船を山に引き上げて大和に逃げ帰った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To know that, Hinagahime chased after him casting a light over the sea, and the Prince, caught by terror even more, drew up the ship and ran back to Yamato.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Hinagahime chased after him casting a light over the sea, and the Prince, caught by terror even more, drew up the ship and ran back to Yamato.</e>
<cmt>To know that をThenに変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Hinagahime chased after him casting a light over the sea, and the Prince, caught by terror even more, drew up the ship and ran back to Yamato.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>天皇は皇子が話せるようになったことを知って喜び、菟上王を出雲に返して大神の宮を造らせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor, who was delighted to know that the Prince was able to speak, ordered Unakami no o to go back to Izumo and construct a new Okami&apos;s shrine</e>
<cmt>宮→shrine ここでは、Okami&apos;s shrineとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor, who was delighted to know that the Prince was able to speak, ordered Unakami no o to go back to Izumo and construct a new Okami&apos;s shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor, who was delighted to know that the Prince was able to speak, ordered Unakami no o to go back to Izumo and construct a new Okami&apos;s shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>また鳥取部、鳥甘部、品遅部、大湯坐、若湯坐を設けたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the Emperor also set up the units (called &apos;be&apos;) to serve the Prince, such as Totoribe (unit of bird capturing), Torikaibe (unit of bird rearing), Homuchi (unit of attendants for the prince in trip to Izumo), Oyue (unit to serve the prince to take bath), Wakayue (another unit to serve the prince to take bath).</e>
<cmt>鳥甘部→定訳不明：Torikaibe (unit of bird rearing) と（）内説明を加えました。 品遅部→定訳不明：Homuchi (unit of attendants for the prince in trip to Izumo) と（）内説明を加えました。 大湯坐→定訳不明：Oyue (unit to serve the prince to take bath) と（）内説明を加えました。 若湯坐→定訳不明：Wakayue (another unit to serve the prince to take bath) と（）内説明を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And the Emperor also set up the units (called &apos;be&apos;) to serve the Prince, such as Totoribe (unit of bird capturing), Torikaibe (unit of bird rearing), Homuchi (unit of attendants for the prince in a trip to Izumo), Oyue (unit to serve the prince to take a bath), Wakayue (another unit to serve the prince to take a bath).</e>
<cmt>take path をtake a bathに変更。trip to Izumoをa trip to Izumoに変更。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And the Emperor also set up the units (called &apos;be&apos;) to serve the Prince, such as Totoribe (unit of bird capturing), Torikaibe (unit of bird rearing), Homuchi (unit of attendants for the prince in a trip to Izumo), Oyue (unit to serve the prince to take a bath), Wakayue (another unit to serve the prince to take a bath).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="27">
<j>さらに、『釈日本紀』に引く『尾張国風土記』逸文では阿麻乃彌加都比女の祟りとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, according to a Itsubun (lost or unknown writings) of&quot;Owari no kuni Fudoki&quot; (Records of the culture and geography of the Owari Province), a text written using &quot;Shaku Nihongi&quot; (an annotated text of the Nihonshoki) as its reference, the Prince&apos;s impaired speech was a curse of Amanomikatsuhime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, according to a Itsubun (lost or unknown writings) of &quot;Owari no kuni Fudoki&quot; (Records of the culture and geography of the Owari Province), a text written with reference to &quot;Shaku Nihongi&quot; (an annotated text of the Nihonshoki), the Prince&apos;s impaired speech was a curse of Amanomikatsuhime.</e>
<cmt>表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, according to a Itsubun (lost or unknown writings) of &quot;Owari no kuni Fudoki&quot; (Records of the culture and geography of the Owari Province), a text written with reference to &quot;Shaku Nihongi&quot; (an annotated text of the Nihonshoki), the Prince&apos;s impaired speech was a curse of Amanomikatsuhime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>それによると誉津別皇子は7歳になっても話すことができなかったが、皇后の夢に多具の国の神・阿麻乃彌加都比売が現れて、「自分にはまだ祝（はふり）がいないので、自分を祭祀してくれる者を与えてくれたなら、皇子は話せるようになり、寿命も延びるであろう」と言った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to it, Homutsuwake no mikoto was not able to speak even at the age of 7, and one day in a dream dreamed by the Empress, Amanomikatsuhime, the female deity of Tagu Province, appeared and said, &apos;I haven&apos;t received any cerebration yet, if you sent someone who would undertake a religious service for me, the Prince would be able to speak and would live longer&apos;.</e>
<cmt>阿麻乃彌加都比売 →女性の神であることが分かるように、Amanomikatsuhime, the female deityとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to it, Homutsuwake no mikoto was not able to speak even at the age of seven, and one day in a dream dreamed by the Empress, Amanomikatsuhime, the female deity of Tagu Province, appeared and said, &apos;I haven&apos;t had any Hafuri (a subordinate priest) yet, if you sent someone who would undertake a religious service for me, the Prince would be able to speak and would live longer&apos;.</e>
<cmt>cerebrationに代えて、Hafuri (a subordinate priest) とした。At the age of 7の7をsevenとした。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to it, Homutsuwake no mikoto was not able to speak even at the age of seven, and one day in a dream dreamed by the Empress, Amanomikatsuhime, the female deity of Tagu Province, appeared and said, &apos;I haven&apos;t had any Hafuri (a subordinate priest) yet, if you sent someone who would undertake a religious service for me, the Prince would be able to speak and would live longer&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>そこで天皇は日置部らの祖・建岡君にこの神がどこにいるかを占わせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, the Emperor ordered Takeoka no kimi, who was the ancestor of Hiokibe (a family unit undertaking religious service) and other families, to have a divine prophecy of the whereabouts of this deity.</e>
<cmt>建岡君→定訳不明：Takeoka no kimi 統一用語リストではTakeokakimiとなっていましたが、&apos;no&apos;　を入れました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, the Emperor ordered Takeoka no kimi, who was the ancestor of Hiokibe (a family unit undertaking religious service) and other families, to have a divine prophecy of the whereabouts of this deity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, the Emperor ordered Takeoka no kimi, who was the ancestor of Hiokibe (a family unit undertaking religious service) and other families, to have a divine prophecy of the whereabouts of this deity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>建岡君は美濃国の花鹿山に行き、サカキを折って鬘（髪飾り）を作り、うけいして「この鬘の落ちたところに神はいらっしゃるだろう」と言った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeoka no kimi went to Mt. Hanashika in Mino Province, to practice ukei (pledge), wearing a kazura (chaplet) (hair accessory) made by herself with branches of sakaki (Cleyera ochnacea), and said, &apos;the deity can be found where this kazura (chaplet) gets down.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takeoka no kimi went to Mt. Hanashika in Mino Province, to practice ukei (pledge), wearing a kazura (chaplet) (hair accessory) made by herself with branches of sakaki (Cleyera ochnacea), and said, &apos;the deity can be found where this kazura (chaplet) falls to land.&apos;</e>
<cmt>gets down をfalls to landに変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeoka no kimi went to Mt. Hanashika in Mino Province, to practice ukei (pledge), wearing a kazura (chaplet) (hair accessory) made by herself with branches of sakaki (Cleyera ochnacea), and said, &apos;the deity can be found where this kazura (chaplet) falls to land.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>すると鬘は空を飛んで尾張国丹羽郡に落ちたので、建岡君は同地に社を建て、また同地も阿豆良（あづら）が訛って阿豆良（あづら）の里と呼ばれるようになったとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, as the kazura flew in the air and fell down in Niwa Country, Owari Province, Takeoka no kimi constructed a shrine there, since then the place where the shrine was constructed came to be called Azura no sato (Village of Azura), phonetically modified from the word &apos;kazura&apos; (chaplet).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, as the kazura flew in the air and landed in Niwa Country, Owari Province, Takeoka no kimi constructed a shrine there, since then the place where the shrine was constructed has been called Azura no sato (Village of Azura), phonetically modified from the word &apos;kazura&apos; (chaplet).</e>
<cmt>fell down をlanded に変更、時制の調整</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, as the kazura flew in the air and landed in Niwa Country, Owari Province, Takeoka no kimi constructed a shrine there, since then the place where the shrine was constructed has been called Azura no sato (Village of Azura), phonetically modified from the word &apos;kazura&apos; (chaplet).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="32">
<j>多具の国とは、出雲国の多久川流域とされ、また阿麻乃彌加都比売は『出雲国風土記』秋鹿郡伊農郷にみえる天ミカ津日女（もしくは楯縫郡神名樋山の項の天御梶日女）と同神とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tagu Province is considered to have been existed along the basin of Taku River in Izumo Province, and Amanomikatsuhime is said to be the same goddess as Amanomikatsuhime (or Amenomikajijhime featuring in the &apos;tale of Mt. Kannabi of Tatenui Country&apos;) in &quot;Izumo no kuni Fudoki&quot; (Records of the culture and geography of the Izumo Province).</e>
<cmt>天御梶日女AmenomikajijhimeAme no mikaji-himeとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tagu Province is considered to have existed along the basin of Taku River in Izumo Province, and Amanomikatsuhime is said to have been the same goddess as Amanomikatsuhime (or Amenomikajijhime featuring in the &apos;tale of Mt. Kannabi of Tatenui Country&apos;) who appears in the section of Inunosato, Aika County in &quot;Izumo no kuni Fudoki&quot; (Records of the culture and geography of the Izumo Province).</e>
<cmt>「秋鹿郡伊農郷」訳漏れ対応。To have been existed をto have existed に変更。said to be をsaid to have beenに変更。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tagu Province is considered to have existed along the basin of Taku River in Izumo Province, and Amanomikatsuhime is said to have been the same goddess as Amanomikatsuhime (or Amenomikajijhime featuring in the &apos;tale of Mt. Kannabi of Tatenui Country&apos;) who appears in the section of Inunosato, Aika County in &quot;Izumo no kuni Fudoki&quot; (Records of the culture and geography of the Izumo Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="33">
<j>これらの話は神話研究では、記紀でのスサノオが大人になっても泣いてばかりであったことや、また『出雲国風土記』でのアヂスキタカヒコネが口が利けなかったという神話と比較されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the mythology, these tales are compared to &apos;the myth of Susanoo&apos; in the Kojiki and the Nihonshoki, in which Susanoo was said to be crying all the time even he had arrived at manhood, and to &apos;the myth of Azisukitakahikone&apos; in &quot;Izumo no kuni Fudoki,&quot; in which Azisukitakahikone was not able to speak.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the mythology, these tales are compared to &apos;the myth of Susanoo&apos; in the Kojiki and the Nihonshoki, in which Susanoo was said to be crying all the time even after he had arrived at manhood, and to &apos;the myth of Azisukitakahikone&apos; in the Izumo no kuni Fudoki, in which Azisukitakahikone was not able to speak.</e>
<cmt>he had arrived の前のafterを挿入。&quot;Izumo no kuni Fudoki&quot; から　the Izumo no kuni Fudoki に変更。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the mythology, these tales are compared to &apos;the myth of Susanoo&apos; in the Kojiki and the Nihonshoki, in which Susanoo was said to be crying all the time even after he had arrived at manhood, and to &apos;the myth of Azisukitakahikone&apos; in the Izumo no kuni Fudoki, in which Azisukitakahikone was not able to speak.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 文姫(id:66661), Monaneko(id:28864), 月下薄氷(id:47743), Nnh(id:474), 暗黒な方(id:44101), Goki(id:7107), Chinamie(id:213556), Vigilante(id:175380), Cave cattum(id:41235), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>