<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原多子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Masaruko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Masaruko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Masaruko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 多子（ふじわら の まさるこ、保延6年（1140年） - 建仁元年12月24日（1202年1月19日））は平安時代末期の后妃。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Masaruko (1140-January 19, 1202) is the Empress in the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Masaruko (1140-January 19, 1202) was the Empress at the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Masaruko (1140 - January 19, 1202) was the Empress at the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>近衛天皇の皇后、次いで二条天皇の后となり「二代の后」と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was called `Empress of two generations&apos;; she first became the empress of Emperor Konoe, and then became the empress of Emperor Nijyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was called the `Empress of two generations;&apos; she first became the empress of Emperor Konoe, and then became the empress of Emperor Nijyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was called the `Empress of two generations&apos;; she first became the empress of Emperor Konoe, and then became the empress of Emperor Nijo.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正&apos;の位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>父は徳大寺公能で、母は藤原豪子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her father was Kinyoshi TOKUDAIJI, and her mother was FUJIWARA no Goshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her father was Kinyoshi TOKUDAIJI, and her mother was FUJIWARA no Goshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her father was Kinyoshi TOKUDAIJI, and her mother was FUJIWARA no Goshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>養父は藤原頼長。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The adopted father was FUJIWARA no Yorinaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her adopted father was FUJIWARA no Yorinaga.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her adopted father was FUJIWARA no Yorinaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>他の記事と合わせる</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>頼長は徳大寺実能の長女・幸子（多子の伯母）と結婚して、徳大寺家の人々と大炊御門高倉邸に住んでいたことから、義弟・公能の娘を幼い頃から養女としていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorinaga married the eldest daughter of Saneyoshi TOKUDAIJI, Koshi (the aunt of Masaruko), and lived in Oimikado Takakura tei with the Tokudaiji family members; he adopted the daughter of his brother in law, Kinyoshi when the daughter was young.</e>
<cmt>下記の用語を追加しました。公能→kinyoshi</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yorinaga married the eldest daughter of Saneyoshi TOKUDAIJI, Koshi (the aunt of Masaruko), and lived in Oimikado Takakura tei with Tokudaiji family members; he adopted the daughter of his brother in law, Kinyoshi when the daughter was young.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorinaga married the eldest daughter of Saneyoshi TOKUDAIJI, Koshi (the aunt of Masaruko), and lived in Oimikado Takakura tei with Tokudaiji family members; he adopted the daughter of his brother in law, Kinyoshi when the daughter was young.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>永治2年（1142年）養女は3歳となり、3月に魚味始（まなはじめ）、8月に着袴（はかまぎ）の儀を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1142, the adopted daughter turned three years old, performed the ceremony of Manahajime in March, and the ceremony of Hakama-gi in August.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1142, the adopted daughter turned three years old, performed the ceremony of Manahajime in March, and the ceremony of Hakama-gi in August.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1142, the adopted daughter turned three years old, performed the ceremony of Manahajime (ceremony of giving fish meat to the child for the first time) in March, and the ceremony of Hakama-gi (first clothing) in August.</e>
<cmt>「魚味始（まなはじめ）」、「着袴（はかまぎ）」に英語の説明を加えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>久安4年（1148年）6月、頼長は近衛天皇への養女の入内を鳥羽天皇に奏請して承諾を得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June 1148, Yorinaga asked Emperor Toba for the entry of his adopted daughter into the palace of Emperor Konoe, obtaining the approval for it.</e>
<cmt>下記の用語を追加しました。近衛天皇→Emperor Konoe</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June 1148, Yorinaga asked Emperor Toba for the entry of his adopted daughter into the palace of Emperor Konoe, obtaining approval.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June 1148, Yorinaga asked Emperor Toba for the entry of his adopted daughter into the palace of Emperor Konoe, obtaining approval.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>8月、頼長が養女の名字を側近の儒者に勘申させると、「多」の字に賛成意見が集まった（『台記別記』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August, Yorinaga made his aides; Confucian scholars, suggest the first name of his adopted daughter; the name containing kanji character `多&apos; was agreed by many aides (&quot;Taiki Bekki&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August, Yorinaga had his aides; Confucian scholars, suggest the first name of his adopted daughter; the name containing kanji character `多&apos; was agreed to by many aides (&quot;Taiki Bekki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August, Yorinaga had his aides; Confucian scholars, suggest the first name of his adopted daughter; the name containing kanji character `多&apos; was agreed to by many aides (&quot;Taiki Bekki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>「夫婦の儀、愛を以って先と為す。文は既に夕を重ね、情は同じく夜に専らとす。文は既に夕を重ね、情は同じく夜に専らとす。しかのみならず子孫衆多、后妃の至徳なり」という理由により、多子と命名され従三位に叙せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the reason`夫婦の儀,愛を以って先と為す.文は既に夕を重ね,情は同じく夜に専らとす.文は既に夕を重ね,情は同じく夜に専らとす.しかのみならず子孫衆多,后妃の至徳なり&apos;, the adopted daughter was named as Masaruko and awarded as jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>文書の意味が不明（検索不能）なため原文のままとしています。「夫婦の儀、愛を以って先と為す。文は既に夕を重ね、情は同じく夜に専らとす。文は既に夕を重ね、情は同じく夜に専らとす。しかのみならず子孫衆多、后妃の至徳なり」の解釈が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the reason`夫婦の儀,愛を以って先と為す.文は既に夕を重ね,情は同じく夜に専らとす.文は既に夕を重ね,情は同じく夜に専らとす.しかのみならず子孫衆多,后妃の至徳なり&apos;, the adopted daughter was named as Masaruko and awarded as jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the reason`夫婦の儀,愛を以って先と為す.文は既に夕を重ね,情は同じく夜に専らとす.文は既に夕を重ね,情は同じく夜に専らとす.しかのみならず子孫衆多,后妃の至徳なり,&apos; the adopted daughter was named as Masaruko and awarded as jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>コンマの位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>頼長は入内実現に向けて準備を進めていたが、12月に藤原忠実の正室・源師子が死去したため、翌年正月に予定されていた近衛天皇元服の儀式が中止となり、入内も延引となってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorinaga proceeded with the preparation for her entry into the palace, however, Genpuku ceremony (Coming-of Age ceremony) of Emperor Konoe was called off, and her entry was also postponed since the official empress; MINAMOTO no Shishi (Moroko) of FUJIWARA no Tadazane died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yorinaga proceeded with the preparation for her entry into the palace, however, the Genpuku ceremony (Coming-of Age ceremony) for Emperor Konoe was called off, and her entry was also postponed since the official empress; MINAMOTO no Shishi (Moroko) of FUJIWARA no Tadazane died.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorinaga proceeded with the preparation for her entry into the palace, however, the Genpuku ceremony (Coming-of-age ceremony) for Emperor Konoe which had been scheduled in the following new year was called off, and her entry was also postponed since the official empress; MINAMOTO no Shishi (Moroko) of FUJIWARA no Tadazane died in December.</e>
<cmt>in December補足「翌年正月に予定されていた」を訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>入内</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Entry into the Palace</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Entry into the Palace</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Entry into the Palace</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>久安6年（1150年）正月4日、近衛天皇は摂関家の本邸・東三条殿で元服の式を挙げ、藤原忠通が加冠役、頼長が理髪役を勤めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 4, 1150, Emperor Konoe performed Ganpuku Ceremony (Coming-of Age ceremony) at Higashi Sanjo dono (palace), the main palace of the clan [family] eligible for regents; FUJIWARA no Tadamichi played the role of crowing, while Yorinaga played the role of hair cutting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 4, 1150, Emperor Konoe performed the Ganpuku Ceremony (Coming-of Age ceremony) at Higashi Sanjo dono (palace), the main palace of the clan (family) eligible for regents; FUJIWARA no Tadamichi played the role of crowning, while Yorinaga played the role of hair cutting.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 4, 1150, Emperor Konoe performed the Genpuku Ceremony (Coming-of-age ceremony) at Higashi Sanjo dono (palace), the main palace of the clan (family) eligible for regents; FUJIWARA no Tadamichi played the role of crowning, while Yorinaga played the role of hair cutting.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>同月10日に多子は入内、19日に女御となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 10, Masaruko entered into the palace, and became nyogo (a high-ranking lady in the court; a consort of the emperor) on January 19.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 10, Masaruko entered into the palace, and became nyogo (a high-ranking lady in the court; a consort of the emperor) on January 19.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 10, Masaruko entered into the palace, and became nyogo (a high-ranking lady in the court; a consort of the emperor) on January 19.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>近衛天皇は12歳、多子は11歳だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Konoe was twelve years old, and Masaruko was eleven years old then.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Konoe was twelve years old, and Masaruko was eleven years old then.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Konoe was twelve years old, and Masaruko was eleven years old then.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし、2月になると藤原伊通の娘・藤原呈子（20歳）が入内するという風聞が立った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February, there was a rumor that the daughter of FUJIWARA no Koremichi, FUJIWARA no Teishi (twenty years old) would enter into the palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February, there was a rumor that the daughter of FUJIWARA no Koremichi, FUJIWARA no Teishi (twenty years old) would enter into the palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February, there was a rumor that the daughter of FUJIWARA no Koremichi, FUJIWARA no Teishi (twenty years old) would enter into the palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>驚いた頼長はただちに法皇に多子の立后を求めるが、明確な返答は得られなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorinaga was surprised to hear that, immediately asked the Monk Imperial Prince for Masaruko to be enthroned as an empress; a clear answer was not obtained.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yorinaga was surprised to hear that, and immediately asked the Monk Imperial Prince for Masaruko to be enthroned as an empress; a clear answer was not obtained.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorinaga was surprised to hear that, and immediately asked the Cloistered Emperor for Masaruko to be enthroned as an empress; a clear answer was not obtained.</e>
<cmt>monk-Imperial Prince→Cloistered Emperor</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>忠通は呈子を養女に迎えると、法皇に「摂関以外の者の娘は立后できない」と奏上した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadamichi adopted Teishi, and advised the Monk Imperia prince saying `a daughter of someone who is other than the clan is not able to be enthroned&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadamichi adopted Teishi, and advised the Monk Imperial prince saying `a daughter of someone who is other than the clan is not able to be enthroned.&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadamichi adopted Teishi, and advised the Cloistered Emperor saying `a daughter of someone who is other than the clan is not able to be enthroned.&apos;</e>
<cmt>monk-Imperial Prince→Cloistered Emperor</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>忠通は頼長を養子にしていたが、実子・近衛基実が生まれたことで摂関の地位を自らの子孫に継承させようと考えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Tadamichi had adopted Yorinaga, he came to intend to let his son, Motozane KONOE, succeed his position as the clan after his son was born.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Tadamichi had adopted Yorinaga, he intended to have his son, Motozane KONOE, succeed his position in the clan after his son was born.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Tadamichi had adopted Yorinaga, he intended to have his son, Motozane KONOE, succeed his position in the clan after his son was born.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>頼長は宇治にいる忠実に助けを求め、上洛した忠実は法皇に対して、藤原道長の娘・藤原彰子や非執政者の娘（藤原師輔の娘・藤原安子、藤原師実の養女・藤原賢子）が立后した例を示し、頼長には近衛天皇の母・美福門院に書を送って嘆願することを命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorinaga sought Tadazane who was in Uji for help; Tadazane who had come out of Uji, ordered to send the document to Bifukumonin, the mother of Emperor Konoe, to ask for Masaruko to be enthroned, presenting the case that the daughter of Michinaga Fujiwara, FUJIWARA no Shoshi, and daughters either of which was not the daughter of a governor; FUJIWARA no Anshi; the daughter of FUJIWARA no Kenshi; FUJIWARA no Kenshi, the adopted daughter of FUJIWARA no Morozan were enthroned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yorinaga sought Tadazane who was in Uji for help; Tadazane came out of Uji, ordered the document to be sent to Bifukumonin, the mother of Emperor Konoe, to ask for Masaruko to be enthroned, presenting the case examples that the daughter of Michinaga Fujiwara, FUJIWARA no Shoshi, and daughters either of which was not the daughter of a governor; FUJIWARA no Anshi; the daughter of FUJIWARA no Kenshi; FUJIWARA no Kenshi, the adopted daughter of FUJIWARA no Morozan were enthroned.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorinaga sought Tadazane who was in Uji for help; Tadazane came out of Uji, ordered Yorinaga to send the document to Bifukumonin, the mother of Emperor Konoe, to ask for Masaruko to be enthroned, presenting the case examples to the Cloistered Emperor that the daughter of Michinaga FUJIWARA, FUJIWARA no Shoshi, and daughters either of which was not the daughter of a governor; FUJIWARA no Anshi; the daughter of FUJIWARA no Morosuke; FUJIWARA no Kenshi, the adopted daughter of FUJIWARA no Morozane were enthroned.</e>
<cmt>名字大文字人名修正「法皇に対して」、「頼長には」を訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>頼長は諸大夫出身の美福門院を日頃から見下していたので躊躇するが、忠実は「已に国母たり」と説得した（『台記』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorinaga who looked down Bifukumonin who was from Shodaibu (generic term for the fourth or fifth rank) hesitated to do so, but, Tadazane persuaded him saying `已に国母たり&apos;(`Taiki&apos;)(diary of FUJIWARA no Yorinaga).</e>
<cmt>左記の用語を改訳・追加しました。「已に国母たり」の解釈が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yorinaga who looked down on Bifukumonin who was Shodaibu (generic term for the fourth or fifth rank) hesitated to do so, but, Tadazane persuaded him saying `已に国母たり&apos;(`Taiki&apos;)(diary of FUJIWARA no Yorinaga).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorinaga who looked down on Bifukumonin who was Shodaibu (generic term for the fourth or fifth rank) hesitated to do so, but, Tadazane persuaded him saying `已に国母たり&apos; (&quot;Taiki&quot; (diary of FUJIWARA no Yorinaga)).</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入 (diary of FUJIWARA no Yorinaga)位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="22">
<j>呈子が従三位に叙されて入内が間近に迫ると、頼長は「もし呈子が多子より先に立后したら自分は遁世する」と言い出し、忠実も粘り強く法皇に立后を奏請したことで、3月14日に多子は皇后となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Teishi had been awarded Jyusanni, and her entry into the palace was forthcoming, Yorinaga started to say `If Teishi is enthroned before Masaruko, I would retire&apos;, and Tadazane also persistently asked the Monk Imperial Prince for Masaruko to be enthroned; Masaruko became an empress on March 14.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Teishi had been awarded Jyusanni, and her entry into the palace was forthcoming, Yorinaga started to say `If Teishi is enthroned before Masaruko, I will retire&apos;, and Tadazane also persistently asked the Monk Imperial Prince for Masaruko to be enthroned; Masaruko became empress on March 14.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Teishi had been awarded Jusanmi, and her entry into the palace was forthcoming, Yorinaga started to say `If Teishi is enthroned before Masaruko, I will retire,&apos; and Tadazane also persistently asked the Cloistered Emperor for Masaruko to be enthroned; Masaruko became empress on March 14.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正コンマの位置移動monk-Imperial Prince→Cloistered Emperor</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>皇后宮大夫には実父・公能、権大夫には頼長の子・藤原兼長が就任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masaruko&apos;s birth father, Kinyoshi, assumed the post of Kogogu taifu; FUJIWARA no Kanenaga, the son of Yorinaga assumed the post of gon no taifu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masaruko&apos;s birth father, Kinyoshi, assumed the post of Kogogu taifu; FUJIWARA no Kanenaga, the son of Yorinaga assumed the post of gon no taifu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masaruko&apos;s birth father, Kinyoshi, assumed the post of kogogu-daibu (Master of the Empress&apos;s Household); FUJIWARA no Kanenaga, the son of Yorinaga assumed the post of Gon no daibu (provisional master).</e>
<cmt>「皇后宮大夫」、「権大夫」に英語の説明を加えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>多子の後を追うように、4月21日に呈子も入内して、6月22日に立后、中宮となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 21, as if Teishi followed Masaruko, she entered into the palace, and was enthrone; she became the second consort of an emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 21, as if Teishi followed Masaruko, she entered into the palace, and was enthrone; she became the second consort of an emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 21, as if Teishi followed Masaruko, she entered into the palace, and was enthrone; she became the second consort of an emperor on June 22.</e>
<cmt>on June 22補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>この事件により、忠通と頼長の関係は修復不可能となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Through this incident the relation ship between Tadamichi and Yorinaga became unrecoverable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Through this incident the relation ship between Tadamichi and Yorinaga became unrecoverable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Through this incident the relationship between Tadamichi and Yorinaga became unrecoverable.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>美福門院は呈子の早期出産を期待していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bifukumonin expected that she would have a child soon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bifukumonin expected that to have a child soon.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bifukumonin expected that Teishi would have a child soon.</e>
<cmt>to→Teishi would</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>仁平2年（1152年）に呈子は懐妊の兆候を見せるが、周囲の期待に促された想像妊娠であったらしく空騒ぎに終わってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1152, Teishi showed signs of pregnancy, but it was just her imagination due to the pressure around her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1152, Teishi showed signs of pregnancy, but it was just her imagination due to the pressure around her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1152, Teishi showed signs of pregnancy, but it was just her imagination due to the pressure around her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="28">
<j>近衛天皇崩御</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Konoe Passed away</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Konoe Passed away</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Konoe passed away</e>
<cmt>文頭以外の語頭を小文字に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>病弱だった近衛天皇は、久寿2年（1155年）7月に崩御。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Konoe who was not in good health passed away in July 1155.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Konoe who was not in good health passed away in July 1155.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Konoe who was not in good health passed away in July 1155.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>多子は近衛河原に幽居した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masaruko moved to Konoe Kawara to live quietly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masaruko moved to Konoe Kawara to live quietly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masaruko moved to Konoe Kawara to live quietly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>保元元年（1156年）の保元の乱では養父・頼長が戦死するが、徳大寺家は、祖父・実能が皇太子・守仁親王（後の二条天皇）の東宮傅（とうぐうのふ）となり、多子の姉・藤原忻子（よしこ）が後白河天皇の後宮に入るなど、すでに頼長派から離脱していたため打撃は受けなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time of the Hogen War in 1156, her adopted father, Yorinaga was killed, but it didn&apos;t affect her; the Tokudaiji family had already disaffiliated from Yorinaga force; her grandfather, Saneyoshi had become Togu no fu of Prince/Imperial Prince Morihito (future Emperor nijyo); Fujiwara no Yoshiko, Masaruko&apos;s elder sister entered into the inner palace of Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time of the Hogen War in 1156, her adopted father, Yorinaga was killed, but it didn&apos;t affect her; the Tokudaiji family had already disaffiliated itself from the Yorinaga forces; her grandfather, Saneyoshi had become Togu no fu of Prince/Imperial Prince Morihito (future Emperor nijyo); Fujiwara no Yoshiko, Masaruko&apos;s elder sister entered into the inner palace of the Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time of the Hogen War in 1156, her adopted father, Yorinaga was killed, but it didn&apos;t affect her; the Tokudaiji family had already disaffiliated itself from the Yorinaga forces; her grandfather, Saneyoshi had become togu-no-fu (an official in charge of education of the Crown Prince) of Prince/Imperial Prince Morihito (future Emperor Nijo); FUJIWARA no Yoshiko, Masaruko&apos;s elder sister entered into the inner palace of the Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>「東宮傅（とうぐうのふ）」に英語の説明を加えました。名字を大文字名前スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>保元元年（1156年）10月、忻子が後白河の中宮に、呈子が皇后となったことから、多子は皇太后に移り、保元3年（1158年）2月、統子内親王が皇后になると、呈子が皇太后に移ったことから太皇太后となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October 1156, Yoshiko became the second consort of the emperor, and Teishi became an empress; Masaruko was assigned as the empress dowager, and then became a grand empress dowager, after Teishi was assigned to the empress dowager when Imperial Princess Toshi became an empress in February 1158.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October 1156, Yoshiko became the second consort of the emperor, and Teishi became an empress; Masaruko was assigned as the empress dowager, and then became a grand empress dowager, after Teishi was assigned to the empress dowager when Imperial Princess Toshi became an empress in February 1158.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October 1156, Yoshiko became the second consort of the Emperor Goshirakawa, and Teishi became an empress; Masaruko was assigned as the empress dowager, and then became a grand empress dowager, after Teishi was assigned to the empress dowager when Imperial Princess Toshi became an empress in February 1158.</e>
<cmt>Goshirakawa補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>しかし、天皇の祖母でもなくその地位は名ばかりのものだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, she was not a grandmother of the emperor, her position was in name only.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, she was not the grandmother of the emperor, her position was in name only.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, she was not the grandmother of the emperor, her position was in name only.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>太皇太后の地位は多子の死後、女院制の盛行もあり消滅する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Masaruko, the position of Grand Empress Dowager disappeared as female cloister system was flourished.</e>
<cmt>左記に用語を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Masaruko, the position of Grand Empress Dowager disappeared as the female cloistered system flourished.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Masaruko, the position of Grand Empress Dowager disappeared as the female cloistered system flourished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="35">
<j>再入内</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reentry into the Palace</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reentry into the Palace</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reentry into the Palace</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>永暦元年（1160年）正月、二条天皇の強い要請により多子は再び天皇の後宮に入った（『帝王編年記』によれば正月26日）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On New years day in 1160, Masaruko reentered into the inner palace of Emperor Nijyo as the emperor strongly asked her (according to &quot;Teio Hennen ki&quot;, it was January 26).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On New years day in 1160, Masaruko reentered the inner palace of Emperor Nijyo as the emperor strongly requested (according to &quot;Teio Hennen ki,&quot; it was January 26).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On New Years day in 1160, Masaruko reentered the inner palace of Emperor Nijo as the emperor strongly requested (according to &quot;Teio Hennen ki&quot;(the Chronicle of emperors), it was January 26).</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正「帝王編年記」に英語の説明を加えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>21歳であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was twenty one years old then.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was twenty one years old then.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was twenty one years old then.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>多子は二条天皇の寵愛深かったが、この再入内は多子の望みではなく近衛天皇が崩御したとき出家しなかったことを嘆き、「おもひきや、うき身ながらにめぐりきて、をなじ雲井の月を見んとは（憂き身の上ながら、また再び宮中に戻ってきて昔ながらの月を眺めようとは…）」と歌を詠んだ（『平家物語』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masaruko was in Emperor Nijyo&apos;s favor, but she sorrowed that she didn&apos;t become a priest when Emperor Konoe died, and the reentry into the inner palace was not by her will; she wrote a the poem `I have had so many difficulties, yet came back to the palace and view the moon that used to be the moon I once viewed &apos;(&quot;Heike Monogatari (The Tale of the Heike)&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masaruko was in Emperor Nijyo&apos;s favor, but she sorrowed that she didn&apos;t become a priest when Emperor Konoe died, and the reentry into the inner palace was not according to her will; she wrote a the poem `I have had so many difficulties, yet came back to the palace and view the moon that used to be the moon I once viewed &apos;(&quot;Heike Monogatari - The Tale of the Heike)&quot;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masaruko was in Emperor Nijo&apos;s favor, but she sorrowed that she didn&apos;t become a priest when Emperor Konoe died, and the reentry into the inner palace was not according to her will; she wrote a poem `I have had so many difficulties, yet came back to the palace and view the moon that used to be the moon I once viewed&apos; (&quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Heike)).</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正the削除(&quot;Heike Monogatari - The Tale of the Heike)&quot;)表記修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>ただ多子が入内したのは、平治の乱が終結した直後という異常な状況下であり、二条の後見である美福門院や側近の藤原経宗・藤原惟方がこの件に関与しなかったとは考えにくいことから、父・後白河に対する牽制（自分が鳥羽・近衛両帝の後継者）を目的とした政略結婚とする見方もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Masaruko reentered into the inner palace just after the Heiji War was over, under abnormal situation; there is a view that it was the political marriage in order to control her father and Goshirakawa (he is the successor of Emperor Toba and Emperor Konoe) in that Bifukumonin who was the guardian of Emperor Nijyo and the aides of Emperor Nijyo; FUJIWARA no Tsunemune, FUJIWARA no Korekata didn&apos;t interfere in this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Masaruko reentered into the inner palace just after the Heiji War was over, under abnormal situation; there is a view that it was the political marriage in order to control her father and Goshirakawa (he is the successor of Emperor Toba and Emperor Konoe) in that Bifukumonin who was the guardian of Emperor Nijyo and the aides of Emperor Nijyo; FUJIWARA no Tsunemune, FUJIWARA no Korekata didn&apos;t interfere in this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Masaruko reentered into the inner palace just after the Heiji War was over, under abnormal situation; there is a view that it was the political marriage in order to control her father and Goshirakawa (he was the successor of Emperor Toba and Emperor Konoe) in that it is unlikely that Bifukumonin who was the guardian of Emperor Nijo and the aides of Emperor Nijo; FUJIWARA no Tsunemune, FUJIWARA no Korekata didn&apos;t interfere in this.</e>
<cmt>「この件に関与しなかったとは考えにくいことから」の意味が明確に出るように訳し直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="40">
<j>二条天皇崩御</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Nijyo Passed away</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Nijyo Passed away</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Nijo passed away</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正文頭以外の語頭を小文字に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>永万元年（1165年）7月、二条天皇は23歳の若さで崩御した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July 1165, Emperor passed away at the young age of twenty three years old</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 1165, Emperor passed away at the young age of twenty three years old</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July 1165, Emperor Nijo passed away at the young age of twenty three years old.</e>
<cmt>Nijo補足ピリオド補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>多子は同年12月出家する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masaruko became a priest in December 1165.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masaruko became a priest in December 1165.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masaruko became a priest in December 1165.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>同月、後白河の第二皇子・以仁王が多子の近衛河原の御所で元服している（『平家物語』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second prince of Goshirakawa, Prince Mochihito performed Ganpuku ceremony (Coming-Age of Ceremony) in the same month (Heike Monogatari (&quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second prince of Goshirakawa, Prince Mochihito performed Ganpuku ceremony (Coming-Age of Ceremony) in the same month (Heike Monogatari (&quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second prince of Goshirakawa, Prince Mochihito performed Genpuku ceremony (Coming-of-age Ceremony) at Masaruko&apos;s palace at Konoe Kawara in the same month (&quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Heike).</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正(Heike Monogatari (&quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot;)表記修正「多子の近衛河原の御所で」を訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>以仁王は二条天皇の准母・八条院の猶子になっているため元服の背景には、後白河や平氏一門に対抗する旧二条親政派の支援があった可能性も考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mochihito might have been supported by the old force close to the Nijyo that was against Goshirakawa and the Taira clan in the context of performance of Ganpuku Ceremony since he was adopted by Hachijo-in, junnbo (a woman of comparable standing to the birth mother of an emperor) Emperor Nijyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochihito might have been supported by the old force close to the Nijyo that was against Goshirakawa and the Taira clan performing a Ganpuku Ceremony since he was adopted by Hachijo-in, junnbo (a woman of comparable standing to the birth mother of an emperor) Emperor Nijyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Mochihito might have been supported by the old force close to the Nijo that was against Goshirakawa and the Taira clan performing a Genpuku Ceremony since he was adopted by Hachijo-in, junbo (a woman of comparable standing to the birth mother of an emperor) of Emperor Nijo.</e>
<cmt>Prince補足スペルを修正of補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="45">
<j>徳大寺家は西行が出家前に仕えていたこともあり、歌壇の中心的存在だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the Tokudaiji family was the key player of as Saigyo had served before he became a priest</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the Tokudaiji family was the key player as Saigyo had served before he became a priest</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tokudaiji family was the key player of poetry circles as Saigyo had served before he became a priest.</e>
<cmt>文頭大文字「歌壇の」を訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>多子の母・豪子も、藤原俊成・藤原定家の出た御子左家の出身であり、両親の文化的素養を受け継いだ影響から、多子も書・絵・琴・琵琶の名手として知られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taeko&apos;s mother, Goshi was also from the Mikohidari family from which FUJIWARA no Toshinari and FUJIWARA no Sadaie were originated; Masaruko was known for the expert of calligraphy, painting, Japanese harp, Japanese lute, taking over the cultural talent of her parents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taeko&apos;s mother, Goshi was also from the Mikohidari family from which FUJIWARA no Toshinari and FUJIWARA no Sadaie were originated; Masaruko was known for being an expert in calligraphy, painting, Japanese harp, Japanese lute, taking over the cultural talent of her parents.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masaruko&apos;s mother, Goshi was also from the Mikohidari family from which FUJIWARA no Toshinari and FUJIWARA no Sadaie were originated; Masaruko was known for being an expert in calligraphy, painting, Japanese harp, Japanese lute, taking over the cultural talent of her parents.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>太皇太后宮大進・藤原清輔や太皇太后宮亮・平経盛など、周囲に仕えた者も歌人としての評価が高かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The people including FUJIWARA no Kiyosuke, daishin (high-ranking official who serves Grand Empress Dowager), TAIRA no Tsunemori, ryo (high-ranking official who serves Grand Empress Dowager) who served Masaruko also had good reputation as a poet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The people including FUJIWARA no Kiyosuke, daishin (high-ranking official who serve the Grand Empress Dowager), TAIRA no Tsunemori, ryo (high-ranking official who serves the Grand Empress Dowager) who served Masaruko also had good reputation as a poet.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The people including FUJIWARA no Kiyosuke, daishin (high-ranking official who serve the Grand Empress Dowager), TAIRA no Tsunemori, ryo (high-ranking official who serves the Grand Empress Dowager) who served Masaruko also had good reputation as a poet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>その後は二人の天皇の菩提を弔い、建仁元年（1201年）62歳で死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward, she lived mourning for two emperors who died, and passed away at the age of 62 in 1201.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, she lived mourning for two emperors who died at the age of 62 in 1201.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, she lived mourning for two emperors who died, and she passed away at the age of 62 in 1201.</e>
<cmt>原文に則して訳し直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), Masyu(id:31065), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), 水野白楓(id:22811), 味っ子(id:17086), Point136(id:211299), Andee(id:20421), 伏儀(id:142093), 小者(id:172526), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>