<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>皇霊祭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koreisai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koreisai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koreisai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>皇霊祭（こうれいさい）は、すなわち春季皇霊祭・秋季皇霊祭をさす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koreisai is a collective term for shunkikoreisai (imperial ceremony of ancestor worship formerly held on the vernal equinox) and shukikoreisai (imperial ceremony of ancestor worship formerly held on the autumnal equinox).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koreisai is a collective term for shunkikoreisai (imperial ceremony of ancestor worship formerly held on the vernal equinox) and shukikoreisai (imperial ceremony of ancestor worship formerly held on the autumnal equinox).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koreisai is a collective term for shunkikoreisai (imperial ceremony of ancestor worship formerly held on the vernal equinox) and shukikoreisai (imperial ceremony of ancestor worship formerly held on the autumnal equinox).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>明治11年（1878年）にそれまでの歴代天皇や主たる皇族の忌日を春と秋に纏め奉祀したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It started in 1878, when successive emperors and main imperial family members were equinoctially enshrined, twice a year in spring and autumn, according to the dates of their death.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It started in 1878, when successive emperors and main imperial family members were equinoctially enshrined, twice a year in spring and autumn, according to the dates of their death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These festivals were established in 1878 by putting together the deathdays of successive emperors and major Imperial family members to worship them in the spring and the autumn.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しましたスペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>現在は「国民の祝日に関する法律」によりそれぞれ春分の日・秋分の日となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Act on National Holidays&apos; stipulates each day as Spring Equinox Day and Autumnal Equinox Day nowadays.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Act on National Holidays&apos; stipulates each day as Spring Equinox Day and Autumnal Equinox Day nowadays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The days for these festivals are now respectively called Vernal Equinox Day and Autumnal Equinox Day by the &apos;Act on National Holidays.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>もともとこの日に最も近い戊の日は、社日として氏子が氏神たる神社に参詣し、春は五穀豊穣を祈り、秋は実りある収穫に感謝する習わしがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsuchinoe days (that fall closest to the Equinox Days) were originally known as shanichi, when shrine parishioner visited their ujigami shrine to pray for a good harvest in spring and to thank for a successful harvest in autumn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsuchinoe days (that fall closest to the Equinox Days) were originally known as shanichi, when shrine parishioners visited their ujigami shrine to pray for a good harvest in spring and to thank for a successful harvest in autumn.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Tsuchinoe day that falls closest to the vernal or autumnal equinox day was originally known as a shanichi day, and shrine parishioners visited shrines which enshrined their local deities to pray for a good harvest on the spring shanich day or to thank for a successful harvest on the autumn shanichi day.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>中国の歴史では祖廟を祀る日であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dates were to worship before a sobyo (mausoleum containing the remains of one&apos;s ancestors) in traditional China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dates were to worship before a sobyo (mausoleum containing the remains of one&apos;s ancestors) in traditional China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People worshipped a sobyo (a mausoleum containing the remains of one&apos;s ancestors) on this day in traditional China</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しましたスペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Charlesy(id:137799), 翰林硯士(id:99377), Tenko(id:102318), 伏儀(id:142093), Nnh(id:474), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>