<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>恂子内親王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Princess Junshi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Princess Junshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Princess Junshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>恂子内親王（じゅんしないしんのう、寛治7年（1093年） - 長承元年10月16日 (旧暦)（1132年11月25日））は、平安時代後期の皇族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Princess Junshi (1093-November 25, 1132) was a member of the imperial family in the latter half of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Princess Junshi (1093-November 25, 1132) was a member of the imperial family during the latter half of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Princess Junshi (1093 - December 2, 1132) was a member of the Imperial Family during the latter half of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>用語統一グレゴリオ歴に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>伊勢斎宮。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ise Saigu (an unmarried princess serving at Ise-jingu Shrine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ise Saigu (an unmarried princess serving at Ise-jingu Shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ise Saigu (an unmarried princess serving at Ise-jingu Shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>白河天皇の第6皇女で、母は木工寮藤原季実女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was the sixth princess of Emperor Shirakawa, and her mother was a daughter of Mokuryo (Bureau of Carpentry), FUJIWARA no Suezane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was the sixth princess of Emperor Shirakawa, and her mother was the daughter of Mokuryo (Bureau of Carpentry), FUJIWARA no Suezane.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was the sixth princess of Emperor Shirakawa, and her mother was the daughter of Mokuryo (Bureau of Carpentry), FUJIWARA no Suezane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>堀河天皇の異母妹。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was a younger sister of Emperor Horikawa with a different mother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was a younger sister of Emperor Horikawa by a different mother.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was a younger sister of Emperor Horikawa by a different mother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>母である藤原季実女は密かに恂子内親王を出産し、天仁元年（1108年）に白河院に認知されたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her mother, the daughter of FUJIWARA no Suezane secretly gave birth to Imperial Princess Junshi, and she was approved by Shirakawa-in in 1108.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her mother, the daughter of FUJIWARA no Suezane secretly gave birth to Imperial Princess Junshi, and she was approved by Shirakawa-in in 1108.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her mother, the daughter of FUJIWARA no Suezane secretly gave birth to Imperial Princess Junshi, and she was approved by Shirakawain in 1108.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>同年10月28日に内親王宣下を受け、同日伊勢斎宮に卜定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 28, 1108, she was given the title of princess, and had bokujo (to decide by fortunetelling) at Ise saigu on the same day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 28, 1108, she was given the title of princess, and had bokujo (decided by fortunetelling) at Ise saigu on the same day.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 9, 1108, she was given the title of princess, and was designated as Ise Saigu (vestal virgin princess serving at Ise-jingu Shrine) by bokujo (decided by fortunetelling) on the same day.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に後半部分訳修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>天永元年（1110年）9月伊勢に赴き、樋口斎宮と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September 1110, she was posted to Ise, and was called Higuchi Saigu (Water pipe gate Saigu, unmarried princess serving at Ise-jingu Shrine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September 1110, she was posted to Ise, and was called Higuchi Saigu (Water pipe gate Saigu, unmarried princess serving at Ise-jingu Shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October 1110, she was posted to Ise, and was called Higuchi Saigu (Water pipe gate Saigu, unmarried princess serving at Ise-jingu Shrine).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>在任13年の後、保安 (元号)4年（1123年）1月に鳥羽天皇譲位のため退下し、帰京。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After thirteen years of her service, she resigned and left for Kyoto in January 1123 due to the abdication of Emperor Toba.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After thirteen years of service, she resigned and left for Kyoto in January 1123 due to the abdication of Emperor Toba.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After thirteen years of service, she resigned and left for Kyoto in February 1123 due to the abdication of Emperor Toba.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>長承元年（1132年）10月16日、40歳で薨去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She passed away on 16 October in 1132 at the age of forty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She passed away on 16 October in 1132 at the age of forty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She passed away on December 2, 1132 at the age of forty.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), Masyu(id:31065), YOSHI438(id:174755), Tribot(id:186681), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>