<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>間人皇女</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hashihito no Himemiko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hashihito no Himemiko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hashihito no Himemiko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>間人皇女（はしひとのひめみこ、生年不詳 - 天智天皇4年2月25日 (旧暦)（665年3月16日））は飛鳥時代の皇族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hashihito no Himemiko (year of birth unknown - March 16, 665) was an Imperial family member during the Asuka period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hashihito no Himemiko (year of birth unknown - March 16, 665) was an Imperial Family member during the Asuka period.</e>
<cmt>Imperial family→Imperial Family と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hashihito no Himemiko (year of birth unknown - March 16, 665) was an Imperial Family member during the Asuka period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>間人大后とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was also known as Taiza okisaki (Taiza Empress.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was also known as Taiza okisaki (the Taiza Empress).</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was also known as Taiza okisaki (the Taiza Empress).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>孝徳天皇の皇后。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was the empress of Emperor Kotoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was the empress of the Emperor Kotoku.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was the empress of the Emperor Kotoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>父は舒明天皇、母は皇極天皇（斉明天皇）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her father was Emperor Jomei and her mother was Empress Kogyoku (Empress Saimei)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her father was Emperor Jomei and her mother was Empress Kogyoku (Empress Saimei)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her father was Emperor Jomei and her mother was Empress Kogyoku (Empress Saimei)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>天智天皇の同母妹、天武天皇の同母姉に当たる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was a younger sister of Emperor Tenchi and an older sister of Emperor Tenmu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was a younger sister of the Emperor Tenchi and an older sister of the Emperor Tenmu.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was a younger sister of the Emperor Tenchi and an older sister of the Emperor Tenmu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>乙巳の変（645年6月）により皇極天皇が譲位し、軽皇子（孝徳天皇）が即位する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Empress Kogyoku abdicated the throne in favor of Prince Karu (Emperor Kotoku) after the coup of the Murder in the Year of Ishhi (June 645.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Empress Kogyoku abdicated the throne in favor of the Prince Karu (the Emperor Kotoku) after the coup of the Murder in the Year of Ishhi (June 645).</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Empress Kogyoku abdicated the throne in favor of the Prince Karu (the Emperor Kotoku) after the coup of the Murder in the Year of Ishhi (June 645).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>間人皇女はそれに伴い皇后となり、葛城皇子（中大兄皇子、後の天智天皇）を皇太子とし、大化の年号が採用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following the enthronement of Emperor Kotoku, Hashihito no Himemiko became the empress and Katsuragi no Miko (Naka no Oe no Oji, who later became Emperor Tenchi) held the rank of crown prince and the new era name, Taika was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following the enthronement of the Emperor Kotoku, Hashihito no Himemiko became the empress and Katsuragi no Miko (Naka no Oe no Oji, who later became the Emperor Tenchi) held the rank of crown prince and the new era name, Taika was established.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following the enthronement of the Emperor Kotoku, Hashihito no Himemiko became the empress and Katsuragi no Miko (Naka no Oe no Oji, who later became the Emperor Tenchi) held the rank of crown prince and the new era name, Taika was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>大化元年（646年）末に、板蓋宮から難波長柄豊崎宮に遷都する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of 646 Emperor Kotoku moved his residence from Itabuki no miya Imperial residence to Naniwa nagara toyosaki no miya Imperial residence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of 646, the Emperor Kotoku moved his residence from Itabuki no miya Imperial residence to Naniwa nagara toyosaki no miya Imperial residence.</e>
<cmt>the, カンマ を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of 646, the Emperor Kotoku moved his residence from Itabuki no miya Imperial residence to Naniwa nagara toyosaki no miya Imperial residence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>葛城皇子は孝徳の治世下で実質的に改革を推進しており、天皇と不仲になっていたらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Kotoku was on bad terms with Katsuragi no Miko, who was the de facto leader of political reforms during his reign.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor Kotoku was on bad terms with Katsuragi no Miko, who was the de facto leader of the political reforms during the reign of Kotoku.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。his reign→the reign of Kotoku と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor Kotoku was on bad terms with Katsuragi no Miko, who was the de facto leader of the political reforms during the reign of Kotoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>白雉4年（653年）に葛城皇子は天皇の意に反し、皇極や間人皇女の他、多くの官僚を率いて飛鳥に戻ってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 653 ignoring Emperor Kotoku&apos;s opposition, Katsuragi no Miko moved back to Asuka taking Kogyoku, Hashihito no Himemiko and many government officials with him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 653 ignoring the Emperor Kotoku&apos;s opposition, Katsuragi no Miko moved back to Asuka taking Kogyoku, Hashihito no Himemiko and many government officials with him.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 653 ignoring the Emperor Kotoku&apos;s opposition, Katsuragi no Miko moved back to Asuka taking Kogyoku, Hashihito no Himemiko and many government officials with him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>天皇はこれを恨み退位も考えたが、山碕（後の京都府乙訓郡）に宮殿を造営中に病に倒れ、白雉5年10月10日 (旧暦)（654年）に難波の宮殿で崩御した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Kotoku got very angry and thought about abdication of the throne, however, shortly after that he fell ill when his new palace in Yamazaki (present-day Oto-gun Kyoto Prefecture) was in the course of construction and passed away at Naniwa Imperial residence in 654.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor Kotoku became very angry and thought about the abdication of the throne, however, he fell ill when his new palace in Yamazaki (present-day Oto-gun Kyoto Prefecture) was in the course of construction, and passed away at Naniwa Imperial residence on November 27, 654.</e>
<cmt>the, カンマを補いました。got very angry→became very angry,shortly after that を削除しました。白雉5年10月10日→November 27, 654 （グレゴリオ暦に変換）として補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor Kotoku became very angry and thought about the abdication of the throne, however, he fell ill when his new palace in Yamazaki (present-day Oto-gun Kyoto Prefecture) was in the course of construction, and passed away at Naniwa Imperial residence on November 27, 654.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>この間、天皇が皇后である間人皇女に宛てた歌が『日本書紀』に残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) contains a poem Emperor Kotoku wrote to his wife, Hashihito no Himemiko when she went away with Katsuragi no Miko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) contains a poem the Emperor Kotoku wrote to his wife, Hashihito no Himemiko when she went away with Katsuragi no Miko.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) contains a poem the Emperor Kotoku wrote to his wife, Hashihito no Himemiko when she went away with Katsuragi no Miko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>金木着け　吾が飼ふ駒は　引出せず　吾が飼ふ駒を　人見つらむか</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though I shackled my chess piece to me, it was impossible for me to take it with me, but seems like someone succeeded in seeing my piece.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though I shackled my chess piece to me, it was impossible for me to take it with me, but seems like someone succeeded in seeing my piece.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though I shackled my chess piece to me, it was impossible for me to take it with me, but seems like someone succeeded in seeing my piece.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>繫於金木 吾飼駒當無出兮 吾之駒至今何以為所獲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">繫於金木 吾飼駒當無出兮 吾之駒至今何以為所獲</e>
<cmt>繫於金木 吾飼駒當無出兮 吾之駒至今何以為所獲→〔漢詩　読み方不明〕</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">繫於金木 吾飼駒當無出兮 吾之駒至今何以為所獲</e>
<cmt>「繫於金木 吾飼駒當無出兮 吾之駒至今何以為所獲」の読み定訳共に確認できておりません。意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">繫於金木 吾飼駒當無出兮 吾之駒至今何以為所獲</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>皇女が夫である天皇を離れ葛城皇子と共に飛鳥に遷った理由は明らかでない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is unknown why Hashihito no Himemiko left her husband, Emperor Kotoku, and followed Katsuragi no Miko to Asuka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is unknown why Hashihito no Himemiko left her husband, the Emperor Kotoku, and followed Katsuragi no Miko to Asuka.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is unknown why Hashihito no Himemiko left her husband, the Emperor Kotoku, and followed Katsuragi no Miko to Asuka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし、うえの歌の「駒」が間人を譬喩しており、古代の「見る」が恋愛の直結するものであることから、自分の妻をほかの男に見られたの意に理解し、中大兄との近親相姦の関係を説く吉永登のような見解もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minoru YOSHINAGA who interprets Emperor Kotoku&apos;s poem to mean that some man has stolen his wife, based on the assumption that &quot;a chess piece&quot; is as an allusion to Hashihito and that in the ancient times &quot;to see someone&quot; implies &quot;to love someone,&quot; says that Hashihito no Himemiko had incestuous affairs with her brother, Naka no Oe no Oji.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minoru YOSHINAGA who interprets the Emperor Kotoku&apos;s poem to mean that some man has stolen his wife, based on the assumption that &apos;a chess piece&apos; is the metaphor of Hashihito and that in the ancient times &apos;to see someone&apos; implies to love someone, says that Hashihito no Himemiko had an incestuous relationship with her brother, Naka no Oe no Oji.</e>
<cmt>the, を補いました。クォーツを修正しました。as an allusion to→the metaphor of,incestuous affairs→an incestuous relationship と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minoru YOSHINAGA who interprets the Emperor Kotoku&apos;s poem to mean that some man has stolen his wife, based on the assumption that &apos;a chess piece&apos; is the metaphor of Hashihito and that in the ancient times &apos;to see someone&apos; implies to love someone, says that Hashihito no Himemiko had an incestuous relationship with her brother, Naka no Oe no Oji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>この見解は直木孝次郎らによって支持されているが、これに対しては曽倉岑・荒井秀規らに反論があり、荒井は「穿ちすぎであろう」と疑義を示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">YOSHINAGA&apos;s argument is supported by historians such as Kojiro NAOKI, but it is questioned by Takeshi SOKURA and Hideki ARAI, who claims that YOSHINAGA is too imaginative.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">YOSHINAGA&apos;s argument is supported by historians including Kojiro NAOKI, but it is questioned by Takeshi SOKURA and Hideki ARAI, who claims that YOSHINAGA is &apos;too inquisitive.&apos;</e>
<cmt>such as→including,imaginative→inquisitive と修正しました。「穿ちすぎ＝物事の真相や人情の機微のとらえ方が深入りしすぎて、かえって本質から遠ざかること」（大辞林）クォーツを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">YOSHINAGA&apos;s argument is supported by historians including Kojiro NAOKI, but it is questioned by Takeshi SOKURA and Hideki ARAI, who claims that YOSHINAGA is &apos;too inquisitive.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>『万葉集』に「中皇命（「なかつすめらみこと」の訓が一般的）」とある人物が間人皇女のことを指すのではないかとする説が荷田春満以来ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, KADA no Azumamaro argued that Hashihito no Himemiko was identical to a person named &apos;Nakatsusumera Mikoto&apos; appearing in &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, KADA no Azumamaro argued that Hashihito no Himemiko was identical to a person named &apos;Nakatsusumera Mikoto&apos; appearing in &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves).</e>
<cmt>スペースを修正しました。ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, KADA no Azumamaro argued that Hashihito no Himemiko was identical to a person named &apos;Nakatsusumera Mikoto&apos; appearing in &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>この説は土屋文明などによって広く支持されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His argument has been widely supported by many literati including Tsuchiya BUNMEI.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His argument has been widely supported by many literati including Tsuchiya BUNMEI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His argument has been widely supported by many literati including Tsuchiya BUNMEI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>さらに「中皇命」の号をもって、母・斉明の崩後に葛城皇子が即位する環境が整うまでの中継ぎとして一時的に皇位に就いていたとする説が押部佳周・小林敏男らによって展開されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What&apos;s more, Yoshikane OSHIBE and Toshio KOBAYSHI argue that &apos;Nakatsusumera Miko&quot; was the name given to Hashihito no Himemiko, who ascended the throne temporarily before the stage was set for the enthronement of Katsuragi no Miko after the demise of his mother, Saimei Empress.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, Yoshikane OSHIBE and Toshio KOBAYSHI argue that &apos;Nakatsusumera Miko&apos; was the name given to Hashihito no Himemiko, who ascended the throne temporarily before the stage was set for the enthronement of Katsuragi no Miko after the demise of his mother, the Empress Saimei.</e>
<cmt>What&apos;s more→Moreover,クォーツを修正しました。Saimei Empress→the Empress Saimei と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, Yoshikane OSHIBE and Toshio KOBAYSHI argue that &apos;Nakatsusumera Miko&apos; was the name given to Hashihito no Himemiko, who ascended the throne temporarily before the stage was set for the enthronement of Katsuragi no Miko after the demise of his mother, the Empress Saimei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>しかし『万葉集』の註には斉明天皇作との旨が記されているなどの異伝も見られ、必ずしも確証があるわけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it has been pointed out that their argument is lacking in sufficient evidence, and some researchers argue that there are notes in &quot;Manyoshu&quot; saying a poem was written by Empress Saimei.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処,　「斉明天皇作との旨が記されている」→[斉明天皇が何を作ったか原文では不明でしたが、一応詩を作ったとして訳しました。]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it has been pointed out that the argument is lacking in sufficient evidence, and some researchers argue that there are notes in &quot;Manyoshu&quot; saying the poem was written by the Empress Saimei.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。their argument→the argument,a poem→the poem と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it has been pointed out that the argument is lacking in sufficient evidence, and some researchers argue that there are notes in &quot;Manyoshu&quot; saying the poem was written by the Empress Saimei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>斉明天皇を中皇命とする説も沢潟久孝をはじめすくなくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hisataka OMODA and many other literati view that Saimei Empress and Nakatsusumera Mikoto were the same person.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hisataka OMODA and many other literati view that the Empress Saimei and Nakatsusumera Mikoto were the same person.</e>
<cmt>Saimei Empress→the Empress Saimei と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hisataka OMODA and many other literati view that the Empress Saimei and Nakatsusumera Mikoto were the same person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>なお、中皇命ついては中大兄そのひとを指すのではないかとする東野治之や大平聡らの説も近年提出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently Haruyuki TONO and Satoshi OHIRA have put forward the new opinion that Naka no Oe no Oji was identical to Nakatsusumera Mikoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently Haruyuki TONO and Satoshi OHIRA have presented the new opinion that Naka no Oe no Oji was identical to Nakatsusumera Mikoto.</e>
<cmt>put forward→presented と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently Haruyuki TONO and Satoshi OHIRA have presented the new opinion that Naka no Oe no Oji was identical to Nakatsusumera Mikoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="24">
<j>天智天皇4年2月25日（665年3月16日）に薨去し、斉明天皇陵である皇極天皇陵墓に合葬された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hashihito no Himemiko passed away in March 16, 665 and was buried in the burial mound of Empress Kogyoku, namely Empress Saimei&apos;s tomb.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hashihito no Himemiko passed away in March 16, 665 and was buried in the burial mound of the Empress Kogyoku, that is the Empress Saimei&apos;s tomb.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。namely→that is と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hashihito no Himemiko passed away in March 16, 665 and was buried in the burial mound of the Empress Kogyoku, that is the Empress Saimei&apos;s tomb.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), Izayohi(id:13095), たね(id:10372), Charlotte1125(id:85323), 代言人(id:33675), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), UMBRO(id:100484), Zerozeros(id:189962), The Side(id:69360), BAKU(id:55205), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>