<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>後の三房</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nochi no Sanbo (三房)</e>
<cmt>漢字が話題となっていますので敢えて全角文字を残しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nochi no Sanbo (三房)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nochi no Sanbo (三房)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>後の三房（のちのさんぼう）とは、鎌倉時代末期より南北朝時代にかけて、後醍醐天皇の側近として仕えた北畠親房・万里小路宣房・吉田定房の3人の事。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">`Nochi no Sanbo&apos; refers to the three; Chikafusa KITABATAKE, Nobufusa MADENOKOJI, Sadafusa YOSHIDA, who served as aides of Emperor Godaigo from the end of Kamakura Period to the period of the Southern and Northern dynasties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">`Nochi no Sanbo&apos; refers to the three; Chikafusa KITABATAKE, Nobufusa MADENOKOJI, Sadafusa YOSHIDA, who served as aides of Emperor Godaigo from the end of Kamakura Period to the period of the Southern and Northern dynasties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">`Nochi no Sanbo&apos; refers to the three; Chikafusa KITABATAKE, Nobufusa MADENOKOJI, Sadafusa YOSHIDA, who served as aides of Emperor Godaigo from the end of Kamakura period to the period of the Southern and Northern Courts.</e>
<cmt>dynasties→Courtsスペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>平安時代の白河天皇に仕えた名前に「房」の字が付く3人の賢臣(藤原伊房・大江匡房・藤原為房)が、「前の三房」と称された事に因んで命名された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of `Nochi (later) no Sanbo&apos; came from the fact that the three of wise subordinate; FUJIWARA no Korefusa, OE no Masafusa, FUJIWARA no Tamefusa, who served Emperor Shirakawa in the Heian period had a kanji character of `fusa&apos; (房) in their names, they were called `Mae (previous) no Sanbo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>漢字が話題となっていますので敢えて全角文字をも越しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of `Nochi (later) no Sanbo&apos; came from the fact that the three of wise subordinate; FUJIWARA no Korefusa, OE no Masafusa, FUJIWARA no Tamefusa, who served Emperor Shirakawa during the Heian period had a kanji character of `fusa&apos; (房) in their names, they were called `Mae (previous) no Sanbo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of `Nochi (later) no Sanbo&apos; came from the fact that the three of wise subordinate; FUJIWARA no Korefusa, OE no Masafusa, FUJIWARA no Tamefusa, who served Emperor Shirakawa during the Heian period had a kanji character of `fusa&apos; (房) in their names, they were called `Mae (previous) no Sanbo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>いずれも、後醍醐天皇の信頼が厚い賢臣であり、彼らの家柄では通常考えられない権大納言にまで昇進して、政務に携わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Any of the three was a wise subordinate; they promoted to the rank of gon dainagon, which was incredible for their ancestries, and engaged in government practices.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All three were wise subordinates; they were promoted to the rank of gon dainagon, which was incredible for their ancestries, and engaged in government practices.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All three were wise subordinates of Emperor Godaigo; they were promoted to the rank of gon dainagon (provisional major counselor), which was incredible for their ancestries, and engaged in government practices.</e>
<cmt>of Emperor Godaigo補足「gon dainagon」に英語の説明を加えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>後に親房は源氏長者に、定房は内大臣に昇る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Chikafusa promoted to the head of the Minamoto clan; Sadafusa promoted to the rank of nai daijin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Chikafusa was promoted to head of the Minamoto clan; and Sadafusa was promoted to the rank of nai daijin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Chikafusa was promoted to head of the Minamoto clan; and Sadafusa was promoted to the rank of nai daijin (minister of the center).</e>
<cmt>「nai daijin」に英語の説明を加えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>だが、信頼が厚い賢臣が直ちに後醍醐天皇の忠臣であったかと言えばやや疑問も残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However. It is still questionable if the three of the wise subordinate that were well trusted were the loyal subordinates of Emperor Godaigo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However. It is still questionable if all three of the wise subordinatse were that well trusted as loyal subordinates of Emperor Godaigo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is still questionable if all three of the wise subordinates were that well trusted as loyal subordinates of Emperor Godaigo.</e>
<cmt>IT→it文中のピリオド削除スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>元弘の変で後醍醐天皇が流されて持明院統の光厳天皇が在位していた時期には、3人とも新天皇に仕えている（ただし、既に出家していた親房の場合は嫡男の北畠顕家が出仕。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The three served Emperor Kogon in the reign of Emperor Kogon on the Jimyo-in Imperial line after Emperor Godaigo was transported at the time of Genko Disturbance; in Chikafysa&apos;s case, his nephew, Akiie KITABATAKE served instead of him since he already had become a priest until then.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The three served Emperor Kogon during the reign of Emperor Kogon of the Jimyo-in Imperial line after Emperor Godaigo was transported during the Genko Disturbance; in Chikafysa&apos;s case, his nephew, Akiie KITABATAKE served instead of him since he already had become a priest by then.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The three served Emperor Kogon during the reign of Emperor Kogon of the Jimyo-in Imperial line after Emperor Godaigo was transported during the Genko Disturbance; in Chikafusa&apos;s case, his son, Akiie KITABATAKE served instead of him since he already had become a priest by then.</e>
<cmt>nephew→son</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>だが、当時の公家社会では良く見られる現象でもあった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That phenomenon was often found in the court noble society at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This phenomenon was often found among court nobles at that time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This phenomenon was often found among court nobles at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、親房が『神皇正統記』で後醍醐天皇の建武の新政を痛烈に批判している事や、定房が武力討幕に反対して元弘の変における天皇の挙兵計画を鎌倉幕府に密告している事は良く知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, it is well known that he bitingly criticized the Kenmu Restoration in `Jinno Shoto ki&apos; (A Chronicle of Gods and Sovereigns) by Emperor Godaigo; Sadafusa was against overthrow of Bakufu, and secretly informed Kamakura Bakufy of the Emperor&apos;s plan to rise in arms at the time of Genko Disturbance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, it is well known that he viciously criticized the Kenmu Restoration in `Jinno Shoto ki&apos; (A Chronicle of Gods and Sovereigns) by Emperor Godaigo; Sadafusa was against the overthrow of the Bakufu, and secretly informed the Kamakura Baku of the Emperor&apos;s plan to rise in arms at the time of Genko Disturbance.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides, it is well known that he viciously criticized the Kenmu Restoration in &quot;Jinno Shoto ki&quot; (A Chronicle of Gods and Sovereigns) by Emperor Godaigo; Sadafusa was against the overthrow of the bakufu, and secretly informed the Kamakura bakufu of the Emperor&apos;s plan to rise in arms at the time of Genko Disturbance.</e>
<cmt>原文の『』に合わせ&apos;を&quot;にスペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>宣房に至っては息子・万里小路藤房が後醍醐天皇へ行った諫言が受け入れられずに出奔してしまうと、天皇と袂を分かっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for Nobufusa, he part ways with the emperor after his son, Fujifusa MADENOKOJI absconded when his advise to Emperor Godaigo was not accepted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for Nobufusa, he part ways with the emperor after his son, Fujifusa MADENOKOJI absconded when his advise to Emperor Godaigo was not accepted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for Nobufusa, he parted ways with the emperor after his son, Fujifusa MADENOKOJI absconded when his advise to Emperor Godaigo was not accepted.</e>
<cmt>時制</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>「三房」と称された3人はそれぞれのやり方で後醍醐天皇に忠義を尽くそうとしたと考えられるが、個性的な天皇のやり方についていけなかったのもまた事実のようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is assumed that the three; so-called `sanfusa&apos; attempted to serve Emperor Godaigo faithfully; they couldn&apos;t follow the emperor&apos;s unique way.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is assumed that the three; so-called `sanfusa&apos; attempted to serve Emperor Godaigo faithfully; but they couldn&apos;t follow the emperor&apos;s unique ways.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is assumed that the three; so-called `sanfusa&apos; attempted to serve Emperor Godaigo faithfully; but they couldn&apos;t follow the emperor&apos;s unique ways.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>それでも、親房と定房は最終的に吉野朝廷の一員としてその生涯を終えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yet, Chikafusa and Sadafusa eventually ended their lives as a member of the Yoshino Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yet, Chikafusa and Sadafusa eventually ended their lives as members of the Yoshino Court.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yet, Chikafusa and Sadafusa eventually ended their lives as members of the Yoshino Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>