<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大喪の礼</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taiso no rei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taiso no rei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taiso no rei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大喪の礼（たいそうのれい）とは、皇室典範第25条の規定により国の儀式として行われる天皇の葬儀の事。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taiso no rei means Emperor&apos;s funeral which is conducted as Imperial ceremony under the law of Imperial House Act, Clause 25.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taiso no rei means an Emperor&apos;s funeral which is conducted as an Imperial ceremony under the law of the Imperial House Act, Clause 25.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taiso no rei means an Emperor&apos;s funeral which is conducted as an Imperial ceremony under the law of the Imperial House Act, Clause 25.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>皇室の儀式として行われる大行天皇の葬送儀礼である「天皇大喪儀」と区別され、国の儀式として行われる葬儀を「大喪の礼」という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is separated from funeral ceremony of Taiko-Tenno (the departed emperor) as the ceremony of the Imperial Palace, &apos;Tenno Taisogi&apos;, the funeral held as nation&apos;s ceremony is called &apos;Taiso no rei&apos;.</e>
<cmt>天皇大喪儀→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is separated from the funeral ceremony of Taiko-Tenno (the departed emperor) as the ceremony of the Imperial Palace, &apos;Tenno Taisogi&apos;, the funeral held as a national ceremony is called &apos;Taiso no rei&apos;.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A funeral held as a national ceremony is called &apos;Taiso no Rei&apos; separately from &apos;Tenno Taiso Gi,&apos; which is a funeral ceremony for the late Emperor held by the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>皇室行事は神道に則って行われる為、1947年の憲法改正以後初となる昭和天皇の大喪の際には政教分離の原則への配慮がなされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial ceremony is held in accordance with Shinto religion, when there was Emperor Showa&apos;s Taiso no rei held in 1947, for the first time since the revision of the Constitute of Japan, after &apos;Sojoden no gi&apos; out of &apos;Renso no gi&apos; which is part of Imperial ceremony, &apos;Tenno Taisogi&apos; was held, since there was a consideration of separation of government and religion, the objects with religious input such as torii (an archway to a Shinto shrine) was removed from the place where the funeral was, then national ceremony, &apos;Taiso no rei&apos; was continuously held in the same place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial ceremony is held in accordance with Shinto religion, and there was Emperor Showa&apos;s Taiso no rei held, for the first time since the revision of the Constitution of Japan in 1947, after &apos;Sojoden no gi&apos; out of &apos;Renso no gi&apos; which is part of Imperial ceremony, and &apos;Tenno Taisogi&apos; was held, since there was a consideration of separation of government and religion, the objects with religious input such as torii (archway to a Shinto shrine) were removed from the place where the funeral was, and a national ceremony, &apos;Taiso no rei&apos; was held in the same place.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Imperial ceremonies are held according to Shinto rules, the separation of religion and politics was taken into consideration when they performed the funeral ceremony for Emperor Showa, which was the first national funeral ceremony after the revision of the Constitution in 1947.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正一原文一訳文の例外対処原文を分割、原文の文末を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>皇室の儀式「天皇大喪儀」の一部である「斂葬の儀」の内の「葬場殿の儀」の後、葬場から鳥居等の宗教的要素を持つものを撤去して、引き続いて、国の儀式である「大喪の礼」が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They removed religious things such as torii (an archway to a Shinto shrine) after the &apos;Sojoden no Gi&apos; within the &apos;Renso no Gi,&apos; which is a part of the Imperial Court&apos;s private ceremony &apos;Tenno Taiso Gi,&apos; in order to hold the national ceremony &apos;Taiso no Rei&apos; after that.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正一原文一訳文の例外対処原文を分割、原文の文頭を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>昭和天皇の大喪の礼</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Showa&apos;s Taiso no rei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Showa&apos;s Taiso no rei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Showa&apos;s funeral ceremony</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>昭和天皇の大喪の礼は1989年2月24日に新宿御苑において行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Showa&apos;s funeral ceremony was held at the Shinjuku Imperial Gardens on February 24, 1989.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Showa&apos;s funeral ceremony was held at the Shinjuku Imperial Gardens on February 24, 1989.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Showa&apos;s funeral ceremony was held at the Shinjuku Imperial Gardens on February 24, 1989.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>葬列（車列）は自衛隊による21発の弔砲に送られて皇居正門を出発し、葬送曲「哀の極」の奏楽の中を桜田門、国会議事堂正門前、憲政記念館前、三宅坂、赤坂見附、青山一丁目、外苑前、青山三丁目を経て新宿御苑の葬場総門に到着した後、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The funeral procession departed from the main gate of the Imperial Palace after Japan Self-Defense Forces made twenty one funeral salute, then while funeral music of 哀の極 was playing, it went through the Sakuradamon Gate, Kokkai gijido mae (in front of the Diet Building), Kensei Kinenka mae (in front of Constitution Memorial Centre), Miyakezaka, Akasakamitsuke, Aoyama 1-chome, Gaienmae, Aoyama 3-chome, finally reached the main gate of the place where funeral was going to be held in Shinjuku Goen.</e>
<cmt>哀の極→読み方不明 一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The funeral procession departed from the main gate of the Imperial Palace after the Japan Self-Defense Forces made a twenty one gun funeral salute, then, while the funeral music of 哀の極 was playing, it went through the Sakuradamon Gate, Kokkai gijido mae (in front of the Diet Building), Kensei Kinenka mae (in front of Constitution Memorial Centre), Miyakezaka, Akasakamitsuke, Aoyama 1-chome, Gaienmae, Aoyama 3-chome, and finally reached the main gate of the place where the funeral was going to be held in Shinjuku Goen.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the funeral motorcade departed from the main gate of the Imperial Palace as the Japan Self-Defense Forces made a twenty-one gun funeral salute, it passed the Sakurada-mon Gate, the main gate of the Diet Building, Parliamentary Museum, Miyakezaka, Akasakamitsuke, Aoyama 1-chome, Gaienmae, and Aoyama 3-chome with playing the funeral music called &apos;Kanashimi no Kiwami&apos; (a funeral march composed by Franz Eckert) before reaching the main gate of the funeral place at the Shinjuku Gyoen National Garden.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>皇室の儀式（葬場殿の儀）として霊柩が轜車（じしゃ霊柩車）から葱華輦（そうかれん：天皇が用いる屋上に葱坊主形の吉祥飾りを着けた輿）に遷され、徒歩の葬列を組んで葬場殿に到着し、霊輦（霊柩がおさめられた葱華輦）が葬場殿に安置された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As part of Imperial funeral ceremony, the coffin was moved from hearse to Sokaren (a palanquin with decoration of good omen which had onion head shape being used by the Emperor), then the coffin was carried to the Sojoden and 霊輦 (Sokaren which had coffin inside) was kept in Sojoden.</e>
<cmt>霊輦→読み方、定訳不明 一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As part of the Imperial funeral ceremony, the coffin was moved from the hearse to Sokaren (a palanquin with decorations of good omens which had an onion head shape that was used by the Emperor), then the coffin was carried to the Sojoden and 霊輦 (Sokaren which had the coffin inside) was kept in Sojoden.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, in the Imperial Family&apos;s ceremony called Sojoden no Gi, the coffin was moved to the Sokaren (a palanquin for an emperor with a good omen decoration in a leek flower head shape on its rooftop) from the hearse before they formed a new funeral procession, and then the palanquin with the coffin inside was laid in state at the funeral hall after the procession arrived at the hall.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正hearese　は単数が良いと思います。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>その後、皇室の儀式としての奠饌幣や天皇の拝礼と「御誄」の奏上、皇后を始めとする皇族や親族の拝礼が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that 奠饌幣 which was Imperial ceremony, or Emperor&apos;s pray and the report of &apos;Oshinobigoto&apos; (speech for the funeral oration), Imperial family member and other relatives pray were conducted.</e>
<cmt>奠饌幣→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that 奠饌幣 which was an Imperial ceremony, or Emperor&apos;s prayer, and the report of &apos;Oshinobigoto&apos; (speech for the funeral oration), Imperial family member and other relatives prayers were conducted.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, the Imperial Family performed some private ceremonies such as Tensenpei (a Shinto rite to present Shinto offerings such as cloth, paper, and rope), the present Emperor&apos;s prayer, a speech called &apos;Onrui&apos; (a condolence message by the Emperor), and prayer by the Empress, other Imperial Family members, and their relatives.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>以上の皇室の儀式の後に鳥居等を葬場から撤去して国の儀式である「大喪の礼御式」の開式を小渕恵三内閣官房長官が告げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the above Imperial ceremony, Torii and other things were removed from the place, the Chief Cabinet Secretary, Keizo Obuchi announced the opening of &apos;the ceremony of Taiso no rei&apos; which was national ceremony, Akihito ahd Empress Michiko walked in front of Sojoden to pray silently for one minute, then Chiefs of three organization of powers such as the Prime Minister, Noboru TAKESHITA and others prayed and made funeral address.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the above Imperial ceremony, Torii and other things were removed and the Chief Cabinet Secretary, Keizo Obuchi announced the opening of &apos;the ceremony of Taiso no rei&apos; which was a national ceremony, Akihito and Empress Michiko walked in front of Sojoden to pray silently for one minute, then the Chiefs of the three organizations of power, such as the Prime Minister, Noboru TAKESHITA and others prayed and made funeral address.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After these Imperial Family ceremonies were finished and religious objects such as torii were removed from the funeral hall, the Chief Cabinet Secretary Keizo OBUCHI declared the national funeral ceremony&apos;s opening.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正一原文一訳文の例外対処原文を分割、原文の文末を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その後、明仁と皇后美智子が葬場殿前に進み正午から1分間の黙祷が行われ、竹下登内閣総理大臣を始めとした三権の長が拝礼の上で弔辞を述べた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Akihito and Empress Michiko walked to the front of the funeral hall to offer a one-minute silent prayer at noon, and the heads of the three powers (legislative, executive and judicial) such as the Prime Minister Noboru TAKESHITA expressed their condolences after prayer.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正一原文一訳文の例外対処原文を分割、原文の文頭を修正、文末も修正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>外国元首・弔問使節の拝礼、参列者の一斉拝礼の後、再び葬列を組んで四谷四丁目、新宿三丁目、新宿四丁目、首都高速道路首都高速4号新宿線初台出入口、中央自動車道八王子インターチェンジを経て陵所（武蔵陵墓地昭和天皇陵「武蔵野陵」）へ向かった</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was followed by the pray of the head of state of the overseas country and delegate of condolence caller, the attendance&apos;s pray simultaneously, then again the funeral procession was organized to go towards Yotsuya 4-chome, Shinjuku 3-chome, Shinjuku 4-chome, the entrance and exit of Hatsudai, Shinjuku-sen line of the capital super highway No.4, then went to 陵所 (Musashi Imperial mausoleum, Emperor Showa&apos;s mausoleum, the Musashino Imperial Mausoleum) via &apos;Hachioji interchange of the Chuo Expressway.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処 陵所→読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was followed by the prayers of the head of state of overseas countries and delegates calling to give condolence, and the attendees prayed simultaneously, then again the funeral procession was organized to go towards Yotsuya 4-chome, Shinjuku 3-chome, Shinjuku 4-chome, the entrance and exit of Hatsudai, Shinjuku-sen line of the capital super highway No.4, then went to 陵所 (Musashi Imperial mausoleum, Emperor Showa&apos;s mausoleum, the Musashino Imperial Mausoleum) via &apos;Hachioji interchange of the Chuo Expressway.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A funeral procession was re-formed after prayer by heads of states, funeral envoys from other countries, and other attendants, and then they went to His Majesty&apos;s Mausoleum named the Musashino no Misasagi in the Musashino Imperial Graveyard via Yotsuya 4-chome, Shinjuku 3-chome, Shinjuku 4-chome, the Hatsudai exit of the Metropolitan Expressway No. 4 Shinjuku Route, and the Chuo Expressway Hachioji Interchange.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>陵所では再び皇室の儀式として「陵所の儀」が行われ、昭和天皇の霊柩が陵に納められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 陵所, &apos;the ceremony of 陵所&apos; was held again as Imperial ceremony, Emperor Showa&apos;s coffin was put into the mausoleum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 陵所, &apos;the ceremony of 陵所&apos; was held again as an Imperial ceremony, and Emperor Showa&apos;s coffin was put into the mausoleum.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the graveyard, the Imperial Family&apos;s ceremony called &apos;Ryosho no Gi&apos; was performed to deposit the Emperor Showa&apos;s coffin in the mausoleum.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>大喪の礼の参列者は、国外からはイギリスのフィリップ (エディンバラ公)、アメリカ合衆国のジョージ・H・W・ブッシュ大統領、フランスのフランソワ・ミッテラン大統領等、164か国･EC、27国際機関に及んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The attendances of Taiso no rei were from one hundred and sixty four countries, EC, twenty seven international authority, such as Prince Philip, Duke of Edinburgh of England, President George. H. W. Bush of United States of America, President Francois Mitterrand of France.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The attendance at the Taiso no rei included individuals from from one hundred and sixty four countries, EC, twenty seven international authorities, such as Prince Philip, Duke of Edinburgh of England, President George. H. W. Bush of the United States of America, President Francois Mitterrand of France.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a large attendance at the ceremony of Taiso no Rei, and they were from 164 countries, the European Communities, and 27 international organizations, including Prince Philip, Duke of Edinburgh from the United Kingdom, President George H. W. Bush from the United States of America, and President Francois Mitterrand from France.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>国内からは皇族、三権の長をはじめとした幹部公務員、都道府県知事等の地方代表者、各界の代表者等である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The attendances in Japan were Imperial families, the executives of government officials such as Chiefs of three organization of powers, the representatives of districts such as governor of each prefecture, or representatives of different social circles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The attendance in Japan consisted of Imperial families, executives of government officials, such as Chiefs of the three organizations of power, representatives of districts such as the governor of each prefecture, or representatives of different social circles.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese attendants at the ceremony were the Imperial family, executive government officials such as the heads of the three powers, local representatives such as prefectural governors, and representatives from every sector or industry of the society.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正「各界の代表者」の訳語をご確認ください。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>日本では、大喪の礼の当日が国民の祝日となった（「昭和天皇の大喪の礼の行われる日を休日とする法律」（平成元年法律第4号）による）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan the day of Taiso no rei became national holiday. (This was due to the law, it is said the day Emperor Showa&apos;s Taiso no rei is held will become national holiday&apos; (the law of the first year of Heisei, No.4)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan the day of Taiso no rei became a national holiday. (This was due to the law, which stated that the day of Emperor Showa&apos;s Taiso no rei will become a national holiday&apos; (law of the first year of Heisei, No.4)</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, the day when the ceremony was held became a national holiday (according to the &apos;Act on the National People&apos;s Day for the Emperor Showa Funeral&apos; [Act No. 4 of 1989]).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>各地で半旗が掲揚された他、全国のテレビ・ラジオ放送（NHK教育テレビ・NHKラジオ第二を除く）も終夜報道特別番組が編成され、テレビコマーシャルが自粛、公共広告機構のCMに差し替えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were flags fly at half-mast in many places, and TV, radio station in Japanese (except NHK Educational TV and NHK radio No.2) broadcast special program about it all night, there was self-restraint of TV advertisement and it was changed to the advertisement of public advertisement organization.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were flags flying at half-mast in many places, and TV and radio stations in Japanese (except NHK Educational TV and NHK radio No.2) broadcast special programs about it all night, and there was self-restraint in TV advertisements and it was changed advertisements by public service organizations.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People flew a flag at half-mast throughout the country, and national TV and radio broadcasting stations (except NHK Educational Television and NHK Radio 2) organized special program schedules for the whole day with the voluntary replacement of TV commercials with advertisements of the Japan Ad Council.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>昭和天皇の崩御以来の自粛ムード再来といわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was said the social atmosphere was second coming of self-restraint since the death of the Emperor Showa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was said that the social atmosphere was the second coming of self-restraint after the death of Emperor Showa.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was said that there was the most widespread hesitation of social activities on that day after the demise of Emperor Showa.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>またほとんどの小売店や施設等が休業する事態となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also most of the small shops and other facilities closed their business on the day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also most of the small shops and other facilities closed their business on the day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, most shops and facilities were closed on that day.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 翰林硯士(id:99377), TRIBESMAN(id:4735), 唐変木(id:17050), Blizzardbreaker(id:248394), Sakura-no-kuni(id:115977), いろはにほへと(id:89648), Kizukadakufu(id:79135), たんじゅんそぼく(id:61057), Nnh(id:474), Cheebot(id:14114), 0null0(id:582), 経済準学士(id:22656), MIsogi(id:20599), 水野白楓(id:22811), Charenji(id:7908), Taisyo(id:6896), 夏竹(id:231789), Tribot(id:186681), 無言雀師(id:13124), スーパーゴルフ(id:82367), 酒井貴広(id:52017), Nakaoka7675(id:39645), Brown Hound(id:56241), Sana yokohama(id:114274), くまたろう(id:46892), Tietew(id:4054), 代言人(id:33675), Kone(id:377), Solla(id:198437), 伏儀(id:142093), NIKE(id:16342), ゆーりん(id:164919), さーとる(id:96104), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>