<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>葛原親王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Kazurawara</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Kazurawara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Kazurawara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>葛原親王（かずらわらしんのう、延暦5年11月7日 (旧暦)（786年） - 仁寿3年6月4日 (旧暦)（853年7月17日））は、平安時代の皇族で、平氏の祖。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Kazurawara (786-853) was a member of the Imperial family in the Heian period and the founder of the Taira family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Kazurawara (786 to 853), a member of the Imperial Family in the Heian period, was the founder of the Taira family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Kazurawara (December 1, 786 - July 17, 853), a member of the Imperial Family in the Heian period, was the founder of the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>旧暦を西暦に直して補足し、Taira family →　Taira clanとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は桓武天皇。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Emperor Kanmu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Emperor Kanmu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Emperor Kanmu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は多冶比真宗（貞子）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was TAJIHI no Mahito Mamune (Sadako).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was TAJIHI no Mahito Mamune (Sadako).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was TAJIHI no Mahito Mamune (Sadako).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>子に平高棟、平善棟、高見王がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Takamune, TAIRA no Yoshimune and Prince Takami were his children.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Takamune, TAIRA no Yoshimune and Prince Takami were his children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Takamune, TAIRA no Yoshimune and Prince Takami were his children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>平氏の祖で、幼少から俊秀として知られており、798年（延暦17年）、異母兄弟の大伴皇子（後の淳和天皇）と共に元服。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Known as a person of genius from his childhood, Imperial Prince Kazurawara, who was also the founder of the Taira family, celebrated his coming of age along with Prince Otomo (later Emperor Junna), a half brother with the same father, in 789.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Known since childhood as a person of genius, Imperial Prince Kazurawara, who was also a founder of the Taira family, celebrated his coming of age along with Prince Otomo (later Emperor Junna), a half-brother by the same father, in 789.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Known since childhood as a person of genius, Imperial Prince Kazurawara, who was also a founder of the Taira clan, celebrated his coming of age along with Prince Otomo (later Emperor Junna), a half-brother by the same father, in 789.</e>
<cmt>Taira family →　Taira clanとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>803年（延暦22年）治部省に叙任され、以降大蔵省、弾正尹、式部省などを歴任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the appointment to the Minister of Jibu-sho Ministry in 803, he assumed the posts of the Minister of Okura-sho Ministry, Shikibu-sho Ministry, and the Danjoin (President of the Board of Censors) and others successively.</e>
<cmt>・・省に叙任，・・省を歴任，という意味がわかりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the appointment as Minister of the Jibu-sho Ministry in 803, he assumed successive posts as Minister of the Okura-sho Ministry, Minister of the Shikibu-sho Ministry, Danjoin (President of the Board of Censors), and others.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the appointment as Minister of Jibu-sho (the Ministry of Civil Administration) in 803, he assumed successive posts as Minister of Okura-sho (Ministry of the Treasury), Danjoin (President of the Board of Censors), Minister of Shikibu-sho (the Ministry of Ceremonial), etc.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>特に式部省については、810年（弘仁元年）に任じられ、途中823年（同14年）から830年（天長7年）を除いて、850年（嘉祥3年）に大宰帥に任じられるまでの33年間にわたってその職にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Appointed to the Minister of Shikibu-sho Ministry in 810, he kept the post for 33years until he was appointed to the Dazai-no-sotsu (Director of Dazaifu (Kyushu branch government)) in 850, except 7years from 823 to 830.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳分の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Appointed as Minister of Shikibu-sho Ministry in 810, he kept the post for 33 years until appointment as Dazai-no-sotsu (Director of Dazaifu (Kyushu branch government)) in 850, except for the seven-year period from 823 to 830.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Appointed as Minister of Shikibu-sho in 810, he kept the post for 33 years until appointed as Dazai no sochi (Governor-General of the Dazai-fu offices (local government office in Kyushu region)) in 850, except for the period between 823 and 830.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>831年（天長8年）には80年ぶりに一品親王に叙せられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 831, the Ippon Shinno (the first rank Imperial Prince) was granted to him for the first time in 80 years.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳分の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 831, the Ippon Shinno (the first-rank Imperial Prince) was granted to him, marking the first time in 80 years that such a distinction was given.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 831, the Ippon Shinno (the first-rank Imperial Prince) was granted to him, marking the first time in 80 years that such a distinction was given.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>親王の薨去を記した『文徳実録』の記事でも「久在式部 諳職務 凡在旧典 莫不達練 挙朝重之」と記して親王が式部省の長官として実際に省を統率していたことを記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Montoku Jitsuroku (official national history book), in which the death of the Imperial Prince is described, introduces that he actually directed the Shikibu-sho Ministry as a chief officer.</e>
<cmt>漢文の意味がわかりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Montoku Jitsuroku (official national history book), in which the death of the Imperial Prince is described, asserts that he actually directed the Shikibu-sho Ministry as a chief officer.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An article in &quot;The Montoku Jitsuroku&quot; (official national history book), in which the death of the Imperial Prince is described, asserts that he actually directed the Shikibu-sho as a chief officer, describing &apos;久在式部 諳職務 凡在旧典 莫不達練 挙朝重之.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>この間に825年（天長2年）王子女に平（たいら）の姓を称することを上奏して許された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He made a comment to the emperor for having his sons and daughters adopt the family name of Taira in 825, with the result that he was given the emperor&apos;s approval.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 825 he commented to the Emperor that he should have his sons and daughters adopt the family name Taira, and as a result he was given the Emperor&apos;s approval.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 825, he made a request to the Emperor to have his sons and daughters adopt the family name Taira, and was approved.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その後、上野国太守、常陸国太守を兼務して一品親王に叙せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Serving concurrently as the governors of Kozuke Province and Hitachi Province, he was bestowed the Ippon Shinno afterward.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳分の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having served concurrently as the governor of Kozuke and Hitachi provinces, he was later bestowed the Ippon Shinno.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having served concurrently as the governor of Kozuke and Hitachi provinces, he was later bestowed the Ippon Shinno.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>835年（承和 (日本)2年）、甲斐国巨麻郡の牧であった「馬相野空閑地五百町」（旧山梨県中巨摩郡八田村・白根町、現南アルプス市）を与えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, he received &quot;Umaaino kyukanchi five hundred cho (500ha of unused land)&quot;, which had been the ground to raise horses and cattle in Koma District, Kai Province (now Minami-Alps City, former Shirane City, Hatta Village, Nakakoma District, Yamanashi Prefecture) in 835.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳分の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, in 835 he received &quot;Umaaino kyukanchi 500 cho (500 hectares of unused land),&quot; which had been the ground to raise horses and cattle in the Koma district of Kai Province (now Minami-Alps City, formerly Shirane City, Hatta Village, Nakakoma District, Yamanashi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, in 835 he received &apos;Umaaino kyukanchi 500 cho&apos; (500 hectares of unused land in Umaaino), which had been the ground to raise horses and cattle in the Koma district of Kai Province (now Minami-Alps City, formerly Shirane-cho and Hatta-mura of Nakakoma-gun, Yamanashi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションにして、住所表記などを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>850年（嘉祥3年）には大宰帥に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to the Dazai-no-sotsu in 850.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to the Dazai-no-sotsu in 850.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to the Dazai-no-sotsu in 850.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), Horlicks(id:62133), Equaly(id:89792), Charenji(id:7908), 水野白楓(id:22811), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), UMBRO(id:100484), 味っ子(id:17086), 唐棣色(id:64681), Bonten2007(id:156965), 小者(id:172526), Hasegawa Naomi(id:205891), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>