<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>輔仁親王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Sukehito</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Sukehito</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Sukehito</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>輔仁親王（すけひとしんのう、延久5年1月19日（1073年2月28日） － 元永2年11月28日（1119年12月31日））は、平安時代の皇族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Sukehito (February 28th, 1073 ~ December 31st, 1119) was a member of Imperial Family of the Heain period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Sukehito (February 28th, 1073 ~ December 31st, 1119) was a member of the Imperial Family during the Heain period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Sukehito (February 28, 1073 - December 31, 1119) was a member of the Imperial Family during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>日付表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>後三条天皇の第三皇子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is the 3rd prince of the Emperor Gosanjo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the 3rd prince of the Emperor Gosanjo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the 3rd prince of the Emperor Gosanjo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は源基平の娘源基子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother is a daughter of MINAMOTO no Motohira, MINAMOTO no Kishi (Motoko).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was the daughter of MINAMOTO no Motohira, MINAMOTO no Kishi (Motoko).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was the daughter of MINAMOTO no Motohira, MINAMOTO no Kishi (Motoko).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>異母兄に白河天皇、同母兄に実仁親王がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had a elder half brother Emperor Shirakawa, and elder brother-uterine Imperial Prince Sanehito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had an elder half brother Emperor Shirakawa, and elder brother-uterine Imperial Prince Sanehito.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had an elder half brother Emperor Shirakawa, and elder brother-uterine Imperial Prince Sanehito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>源有仁の父。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is father of MINAMOTO no Arihito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the father of MINAMOTO no Arihito.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the father of MINAMOTO no Arihito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>1075年（承保2年）に親王宣下を受け、1087年（寛治元年）元服する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to Imperial Prince in 1075 and pass over genpuku (coming of age) ceremony in 1087.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed as Imperial Prince in 1075 and celebrated his genpuku (coming of age) ceremony in 1087.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed as Imperial Prince in 1075 and celebrated his genpuku (coming of age) ceremony in 1087.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>兄弟揃って英明の資質を備えていたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the both brothers were clever.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was said that both brothers were clever.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was said that both brothers were clever.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>父・後三条天皇は、傍流とはいえ藤原北家の血を引く長男の貞仁親王（白河天皇）よりも同家と外戚関係を有しない源基子との子供に皇位継承候補者として期待をかけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father Emperor Gosanjo expected the son with MINAMOTO no Motoko who has no maternal relation with the Fujiwara family as the successor of the throne rather than his elder brother Imperial Prince Sadahito who had a line of the Northern House of Fujiwara clan though it was a collateral line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father Emperor Gosanjo expected a son with MINAMOTO no Motoko who had no maternal relation with the Fujiwara family as the successor of the throne rather than his elder brother Imperial Prince Sadahito who had a collateral line of the Northern Household of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father Emperor Gosanjo expected a son with MINAMOTO no Motoko who had no maternal relation with the Fujiwara family as the successor of the throne rather than his elder other Imperial Prince Sadahito (later became Emperor Shirakawa) who had a collateral line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>(later became Emperor Shirakawa)補足&quot;Household&quot;→&quot;House&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>そこで1072年（延久4年）に白河天皇即位の際に実仁親王を皇太弟とし、翌年の輔仁誕生直後に太上天皇となっていた後三条が重態に陥ると、重ねて実仁親王が即位した後には、輔仁親王を皇太弟とするよう遺言した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then when Emperor Shirakawa acceded the throne in 1072, Gosanjo made the Imperial Prince Sanehito as the younger brother of Crown Prince, and Gosanjo, who retired Emperor soon after Sukehito was born in the next year, became heavy ill in bed and left a will repeatedly that Sukehito be the next younger brother (who has the right to succeed the position) of Crown Prince after Imperial Prince Sanehito acceded the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then when Emperor Shirakawa acceded the throne in 1072, Gosanjo made the younger brother Imperial Prince Sanehito the Crown Prince, and Gosanjo, who retired as Emperor the next year soon after Sukehito was born, became very ill in bed and repeatedly left his will that Sukehito, the next younger brother (who has the right to succeed the position) be the Crown Prince after Imperial Prince Sanehito acceded the throne.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then when Emperor Shirakawa acceded the throne in 1072, Gosanjo made the younger brother Imperial Prince Sanehito the Crown Prince, and Gosanjo, who retired as Emperor the next year soon after Sukehito was born, became very ill in bed and repeatedly left his will that Sukehito, the next younger brother (who has the right to succeed the position) be the Crown Prince after Imperial Prince Sanehito acceded the throne.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし、1085年（応徳2年）に実仁が亡くなると、白河天皇は翌年には父の遺言を無視して実子である善仁親王を皇太子に立ててその日のうちに皇太子への譲位を宣言して堀河天皇を即位させるという手段に出た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Emperor Shirakawa ignored his father&apos;s will when Sanehito died in 1085, he formally installed his own son Imperial Prince Taruhito as the Crown Prince in the next year and within the day, Shirakawa declared to give the throne to Emperor Horikawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Emperor Shirakawa ignored his father&apos;s will when Sanehito died in 1085, he formally installed his own son Imperial Prince Taruhito as the Crown Prince and in the next year, within a day, Shirakawa declared to give the throne to Emperor Horikawa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Emperor Shirakawa ignored his father&apos;s will when Sanehito died in 1085, he formally installed his biological son Imperial Prince Taruhito as the Crown Prince in the next year, and within the day, Shirakawa declared to give the throne to Emperor Horikawa.</e>
<cmt>and位置移動within a day→within the dayown son→biological sonに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>輔仁親王は仁和寺のあたりに幽居したが、1113年（永久元年）に護持僧で醍醐寺の僧仁寛らによる輔仁親王即位にからむ計画にまきこまれ閉門されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the Imperial Prince Sukehito was forced to hermitise around Ninna-ji temple, in 1113, he was involved in the plan by gojiso (a priest who prays to guard the emperor) and a monk of Daigo-ji temple, Ninkan and fellows to let Sukehito to accede the throne and Sukehito was confined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the Imperial Prince Sukehito was forced to become a hermit around Ninna-ji temple, in 1113, he became involved in the plan by gojiso (a priest who prays to guard the emperor) and a monk of Daigo-ji temple, Ninkan and fellows to have Sukehito accede the throne and Sukehito was confined.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the Imperial Prince Sukehito was forced to become a hermit around Ninna-ji Temple, in 1113, he became involved in the plan by gojiso (a priest who prays to guard the emperor) and a monk of Daigo-ji Temple, Ninkan and fellows to have Sukehito accede the throne and Sukehito was confined.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>詩歌に秀で、風雅の士として知られていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was good at poetry and also known as a man of refined taste.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was good at poetry and also known as a man of refined taste.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was good at poetry and also known as a man of refined taste.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), 玄史生(id:43670), Equaly(id:89792), 代言人(id:33675), 松茸(id:27535), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), Extrahitz(id:26245), 春野秋葉(id:36725), YOSHI438(id:174755), 唐棣色(id:64681), BAKU(id:55205), Aoooooooo(id:101274), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>