<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>栗隈王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kurikuma no Okimi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kurikuma no Okimi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kurikuma no Okimi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>栗隈王（くりくまのおおきみ、生年不明 - 天武天皇5年（676年）6月）は、日本の飛鳥時代の皇族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kurikuma no Okimi (the date of birth and death unknown) was a member of Japanese Imperial family from Asuka period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kurikuma no Okimi (year of birth unknown - July, 676) was a member of the Japanese Imperial Family in the Asuka period.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。カッコ内を修正しました。Imperial family→Imperial Family,from→in と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kurikuma no Okimi (year of birth unknown - July, 676) was a member of the Japanese Imperial Family in the Asuka period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>栗前王とも書く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His name is written two ways in Japanese characters; &quot;栗隈王&quot; or &quot;栗前王.&quot;</e>
<cmt>記載の違いを明記するために漢字を追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His name is written two ways in Kanji characters; 栗隈王 or 栗前王.</e>
<cmt>Japanese→Kanji と修正しました。クォーツを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His name is written two ways in Kanji characters; 栗隈王 or 栗前王.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>旧仮名遣いでの読みは共に「くりくまのおほきみ」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">栗隈王&quot; and &quot;栗前王&quot; are pronounced &quot;Kurikuma no Ohokimi&quot; in old Japanese syllabary characters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">栗隈王 and 栗前王 are both pronounced &apos;Kurikuma no Ohokimi&apos; in old Japanese syllabary characters.</e>
<cmt>クォーツを修正しました。both を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">栗隈王 and 栗前王 are both pronounced &apos;Kurikuma no Ohokimi&apos; in old Japanese syllabary characters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>敏達天皇の孫（曾孫か）、難波皇子の子（孫か）、美努王の父。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the grandson (or the great-grandson) of Emperor Bidatsu, the son (or the grandson) of Prince Naniwa and the father of Minu no Okimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the grandson (or the great-grandson) of the Emperor Bidatsu, the son (or the grandson) of the Prince Naniwa and the father of Minu no Okimi.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the grandson (or the great-grandson) of the Emperor Bidatsu, the son (or the grandson) of the Prince Naniwa and the father of Minu no Okimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>橘氏の祖である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kurikuma no Okimi was the patriarch of the Tachibana clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kurikuma no Okimi was the founder of the Tachibana clan.</e>
<cmt>patriarch→founder と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kurikuma no Okimi was the founder of the Tachibana clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>筑紫率（筑紫大宰）として唐 (王朝)と新羅の使者を送迎した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kurikuma no Okimi, as Tsukushi no Sotsu (Tsukushi no Omikotomochi no Tsukasa; the head of Dazai-fu [local government office in Kyushu region]), welcomed and entertained the envoys from Tang (ancient Chinese dynasty) and Shiragi (Silla, ancient kingdom in Korea).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対応。唐と新羅は表記を合わせ、カッコ内に英文の説明を追記しました。新羅の英文説明は、百済、高句麗等と表記を合わせているため、記載の対訳とは違っています。「使者を送迎した」は「使者を歓迎した」と解釈し、英訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kurikuma no Okimi, as Tsukushi no Sotsu (Tsukushi no Omikotomochi no Tsukasa; the head of Dazai-fu [local government office in Kyushu region]), welcomed and entertained the envoys from Tang (ancient Chinese dynasty) and Shiragi (Silla, ancient kingdom in Korea).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kurikuma no Okimi, as Tsukushi no Sotsu (Tsukushi no Omikotomochi no Tsukasa; the head of Dazai-fu [local government office in Kyushu region]), welcomed and entertained the envoys from Tang (ancient Chinese dynasty) and Shiragi (Silla, ancient kingdom in Korea).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>672年の壬申の乱では外国への備えを理由に中立を保った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He took a neutral stance giving the priority to the maintenance of the defense system in Dazai-fu when Jinshin War broke out in 672.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対応。「大宰府における外国への備え」と解釈し、英訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He took a neutral stance as giving the priority to the maintenance of the defense system in Dazai-fu when Jinshin War broke out in 672.</e>
<cmt>as を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He took a neutral stance as giving the priority to the maintenance of the defense system in Dazai-fu when Jinshin War broke out in 672.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>675年に兵政官長。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was assppointed to Heiseikan Cho (Minister of War) in 675.</e>
<cmt>「兵政官長」の読みは「へいせいかんちょう」とし、「軍事をつかさどる省の長官」としています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to Heiseikan Cho (Minister of War) in 675.</e>
<cmt>assppointed→appointed と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to Heiseikan Cho (Minister of War) in 675.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>贈従二位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Junii (Junior Second Rank) was posthumously conferred on Kurikuma no Okimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Junii (Junior Second Rank) was posthumously conferred on Kurikuma no Okimi.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Junii (Junior Second Rank) was posthumously conferred on Kurikuma no Okimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>筑紫大宰・率・帥</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsukushi no Omikotomochi no Tsukasa, Tsukushi no Kami, or Tsukushi no Sotsu.</e>
<cmt>「筑紫率」は用語集に&apos;Tsukushi no kami&apos;とありましたが、「筑紫大宰」と表記を合わせるため&apos;Tsukushi no Kami&apos;としました。「筑紫師」の読みは「つくしのそつ」としています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsukushi no Omikotomochi no Tsukasa, Tsukushi no Kami, or Tsukushi no Sotsu</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukushi no Omikotomochi no Tsukasa, Tsukushi no Kami, or Tsukushi no Sotsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>『日本書紀』には、天智天皇7年（668年）7月に栗前王が筑紫率、8年（669年）正月に蘇我赤兄が筑紫率、10年（671年）5月に栗隈王が筑紫帥に任命されたとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), Kurikuma no Okimi (栗前王) was appointed to Tsukushi no Kami in July 668, SOGA no Akae to the same rank in January 669, and Kurikuma no Okimi (栗隈王) to Tsukushi no Sotsu in May 671.</e>
<cmt>「正月」は「一月」と解釈しました。原文の漢字表記が違うため、訳文にも漢字を追記しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), Kurikuma no Okimi (栗前王) was appointed to Tsukushi no Kami in August 668, SOGA no Akae to the same rank in February 669, and Kurikuma no Okimi (栗隈王) to Tsukushi no Sotsu in June 671.</e>
<cmt>天智天皇7年（668年）7月→西暦668年8月と修正しました。8年（669年）正月→西暦669年2月、10年（671年）5月→西暦671年6月と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), Kurikuma no Okimi (栗前王) was appointed to Tsukushi no Kami in August 668, SOGA no Akae to the same rank in February 669, and Kurikuma no Okimi (栗隈王) to Tsukushi no Sotsu in June 671.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>この栗前王と栗隈王は同一人物とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;栗前王&quot; and &quot;栗隈王&quot; are considered to be a same person.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">栗前王 and 栗隈王 are considered to be the same person.</e>
<cmt>クォーツを削除しました。a→the と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">栗前王 and 栗隈王 are considered to be the same person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>7年と10年の任命記事は同じことが別の年に再掲されたものだとする説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a view that the articles regarding the appointment in 668 and 671 are the same, but the second one was written again in another year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a view that the articles regarding the appointment in 668 and 671 are the same, but the second one was written again in another year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a view that the articles regarding the appointment in 668 and 671 are the same, but the second one was written again in another year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>栗隈王は壬申の乱が勃発したときにも筑紫太宰の地位にあって筑紫にいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had been serving as Tsukushi no Omikotomochi no Tsukasa in Tsukushi when Jinshin War broke out.</e>
<cmt>「筑紫」の読みは「つくし」で統一しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had been serving as Tsukushi no Omikotomochi no Tsukasa in Tsukushi when the Jinshin War broke out.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had been serving as Tsukushi no Omikotomochi no Tsukasa in Tsukushi when the Jinshin War broke out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>筑紫率、筑紫帥、筑紫大宰は同じ官職の別表記と考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;筑紫率 (Tsukushi no kami),&quot; &quot;筑紫帥 (Tsukushi no Sotsu),&quot; and &quot;筑紫大宰 (Tsukushi no Omikotomochi no Tsukasa)&quot; all represent the same governmental post written in different Japanese Kanji characters.</e>
<cmt>漢字表記についての説明であるため、漢字も記載しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">筑紫率 (Tsukushi no kami), 筑紫帥 (Tsukushi no Sotsu), and 筑紫大宰 (Tsukushi no Omikotomochi no Tsukasa) all refer to the same governmental post written in different Japanese Kanji characters.</e>
<cmt>クォーツを削除しました。 represent→refer to と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">筑紫率 (Tsukushi no kami), 筑紫帥 (Tsukushi no Sotsu), and 筑紫大宰 (Tsukushi no Omikotomochi no Tsukasa) all refer to the same governmental post written in different Japanese Kanji characters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>当時の日本は白村江の戦いで敗れてから朝鮮半島への進出を断念していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan, at that time, abandoned its ambition to invade Korean Peninsula after the loss of Battle of Hakusukinoe.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan, at that time, abandoned its ambition to invade Korean Peninsula after the loss of the Battle of Hakusukinoe.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan, at that time, abandoned its ambition to invade Korean Peninsula after the loss of the Battle of Hakusukinoe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし、半島では新羅と唐 (王朝)が戦い続けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Shiragi and Tang were still at war in the Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Shiragi and Tang (Dynasty) were still at war in the Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>(Dynasty)を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Shiragi and Tang (Dynasty) were still at war in the Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>百済・高句麗は滅ぼされたが、唐は新羅支配下にある百済の復興運動を、新羅は唐支配下にある高句麗の復興運動を後押しした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the coalition troops of Tang and Shiragi conquered Kudara (Baekje) and Kokuri (Goguryeo) which were ancient kingdoms in Korea, Tang supported the restoration movement of Kudara which was then ruled by Shiragi, and Shiragi supported the movement in Tang-ruling Kokuri.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。百済、高句麗、新羅は全て日本語読みとし、カッコ内に韓国語読みを追記しました。また、訳文で &apos;ancient kingdoms of Korea&apos; と補足しています。「百済、高句麗は唐と新羅の連合軍に滅ぼされた」と英語で補足しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the coalition troops of Tang and Shiragi conquered Kudara (Baekje) and Kokuri (Goguryeo) which were ancient kingdoms in Korea, Tang supported the restoration movement of Kudara which was then ruled by Shiragi, and Shiragi supported the movement in Tang-ruling Kokuri.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the coalition troops of Tang and Shiragi conquered Kudara (Baekje) and Kokuri (Goguryeo) which were ancient kingdoms in Korea, Tang supported the restoration movement of Kudara which was then ruled by Shiragi, and Shiragi supported the movement in Tang-ruling Kokuri.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>各国とも日本に使者を派遣して親を通じようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each ruler sent its envoy to Japan to establish diplomatic relations.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each ruler sent its envoy to Japan to establish diplomatic relations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each ruler sent its envoy to Japan to establish diplomatic relations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>それゆえ筑紫帥の役割は軍事・外交ともに重要であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Tsukushi no Sotsu played a significant role in military affairs and diplomacy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the Tsukushi no Sotsu played a significant role in military affairs and diplomacy.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the Tsukushi no Sotsu played a significant role in military affairs and diplomacy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="20">
<j>天智天皇10年（671年）6月には新羅が調を進め、7月には唐の使者李守真と百済の使者が帰国し、10月には新羅の使者金万物が再び調を進め、12月17日に帰った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June 671, Shiragi started the preliminary research to build diplomatic relations with Japan, Tang envoy Rishushin and Kudara envoy returned to their countries in July, and Shiragi envoy, Komumanmotsu restarted his research in October, leaving Japan on December 17th.</e>
<cmt>「調を進め」は「日本と外交関係を築くための事前調査」と解釈しました。「李守真」の読みは「りしゅしん」、「金万物」の読みは「こむまんもつ」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 671, Shiragi started the preliminary research to build diplomatic relations with Japan, the Tang envoy Rishushin and the Kudara envoy returned to their countries in August, and the Shiragi envoy, Komumanmotsu restarted his research in November, leaving Japan on January 24, 672.</e>
<cmt>天智天皇10年（671年）6月→西暦671年7月,the を補いました。July→August,October→November,December 17th→January 24, 672 （グレゴリオ暦に変換）と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July 671, Shiragi started the preliminary research to build diplomatic relations with Japan, the Tang envoy Rishushin and the Kudara envoy returned to their countries in August, and the Shiragi envoy, Komumanmotsu restarted his research in November, leaving Japan on January 24, 672.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>11月には対馬から報告があって、唐の使者郭務そうと百済の送使孫登ら二千人の来朝の意が伝えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November, the envoys of Tang, Kakumusou and Kudara, Sontou announced their will to visit Japan with 2,000-member diplomatic mission through the Japanese bureau in Tsushima.</e>
<cmt>「郭務そう」の読みは「かくむそう」、「孫登」の読みは「そんとう」としました。「対馬から」は「対馬にある中央省庁の支部を通じて」と解釈し&apos; through the Japanese bureau in Tsushima&apos;と訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December, the envoys of Tang, Kakumuso and Kudara, Sonto announced their will to visit Japan with 2,000-member diplomatic mission, through the Japanese bureau in Tsushima.</e>
<cmt>11月（天智天皇10年）→December （グレゴリオ暦に変換）と修正しました。 カンマを補いました。Kakumunou→Kakumuso,Sontou→Sonto と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December, the envoys of Tang, Kakumuso and Kudara, Sonto announced their will to visit Japan with 2,000-member diplomatic mission, through the Japanese bureau in Tsushima.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>12月3日に天智天皇が亡くなり、皇太子の大友皇子（弘文天皇）が朝廷を率いることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the demise of Emperor Tenchi on December 3rd, the Crown Prince, Prince Otomo (Emperor Kobun) led the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the demise of the Emperor Tenchi on January 10, 672, the Crown Prince, the Prince Otomo (the Emperor Kobun) led the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。12月3日（天智天皇10年）→西暦672年1月10日 と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the demise of the Emperor Tenchi on January 10, 672, the Crown Prince, the Prince Otomo (the Emperor Kobun) led the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>翌年3月30日に郭務悰は帰ったが、3月28日には高句麗の使者富加べんらが調を進めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 28th, the following year, Kokuri envoy, Fukaben carried out their research, while Kakumusou left Japan on March 30th.</e>
<cmt>「富加べん」の読みは「ふかべん」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 3, 672, the Kokuri envoy, Fukaben carried out their research, while Kakumuso left Japan on May 5.</e>
<cmt>翌年3月30日＝(天武)1年3月30日→西暦672年5月5日、3月28日→西暦672年5月3日として修正しました。the を補いました。Kakumusou→Kakumuso と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 3, 672, the Kokuri envoy, Fukaben carried out their research, while Kakumuso left Japan on May 5.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>これらの日付の大半は近江宮からみたものであろうから、筑紫の栗隈王にとっては多少のずれがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These dates were presumably recorded by Omi no miya, then Japanese central government, so there should be some discrepancies between the historical record and what Kurikuma no Okimi experienced in Tsukushi, far away from Omi no miya.</e>
<cmt>「近江宮」は「当時の日本中央政府」と補足しており、筑紫は中央政府から離れた場所にあるため「ずれ」が生じたとしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These dates were presumably recorded by Omi no miya, then Japanese central government, so there should be some discrepancies between the historical record and what Kurikuma no Okimi experienced in Tsukushi, far away from Omi no miya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These dates were presumably recorded by Omi no miya, then Japanese central government, so there should be some discrepancies between the historical record and what Kurikuma no Okimi experienced in Tsukushi, far away from Omi no miya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>この頃の使節の往来は他の時期と比べて格段に多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, the mutual visits of the envoys between Japan and foreign countries were much more frequent compared to other periods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, the mutual visits of those envoys between Japan and foreign countries were much more frequent compared to other periods.</e>
<cmt>the→those と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, the mutual visits of those envoys between Japan and foreign countries were much more frequent compared to other periods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>壬申の乱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jinshin War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jinshin War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jinshin War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>壬申の乱は6月から7月の一か月間の出来事であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jinshin War continued for one month from June to July.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jinshin War continued for one month from June to July.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jinshin War continued for one month from June to July.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>乱の勃発時、近江宮の朝廷は筑紫大宰に対して兵力を送るよう命じる使者を出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the outbreak of Jinshin War, the Imperial Court in Omi no miya ordered Tsukushi no Omikotomochi no Tsukasa to send troops through an emissary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the outbreak of Jinshin War, the Imperial Court in Omi no miya ordered Tsukushi no Omikotomochi no Tsukasa to send troops through an emissary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the outbreak of Jinshin War, the Imperial Court in Omi no miya ordered Tsukushi no Omikotomochi no Tsukasa to send troops through an emissary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>このとき大友皇子（弘文天皇）は、栗隈王がかつて大海人皇子（天武天皇）の下についていたことを危ぶみ、使者に対して「もし服従しない様子があったら殺せ」と命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Otomo (Emperor Kobun) told the emissary to kill Kurikuma no Okimi if he showed any signs of refusal, because the prince was skeptical about Kurikuma no Okimi&apos;s loyalty as he used to serve Prince Oama (Emperor Tenmu), the enemy of the prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Prince Otomo (the Emperor Kobun) told the emissary to kill Kurikuma no Okimi if he showed any signs of refusal, because the prince was skeptical about Kurikuma no Okimi&apos;s loyalty as he used to serve the Prince Oama (the Emperor Tenmu), the enemy of the prince.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Prince Otomo (the Emperor Kobun) told the emissary to kill Kurikuma no Okimi if he showed any signs of refusal, because the prince was skeptical about Kurikuma no Okimi&apos;s loyalty as he used to serve the Prince Oama (the Emperor Tenmu), the enemy of the prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>使者に渡された符（命令書）を受けた栗隈王は、国外への備えを理由に出兵を断った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kurikuma no Okimi declined dispatch of troops as to maintain the defense system against foreign countries when he received Fu (mandate) from the emissary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kurikuma no Okimi declined the dispatch of troops as to maintain the defense system against foreign countries when he received Fu (mandate) from the emissary.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kurikuma no Okimi declined the dispatch of troops as to maintain the defense system against foreign countries when he received Fu (mandate) from the emissary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>書紀（現代文訳）には次のような栗隈王の言葉が載せられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Modern translation of Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan) reads the words of Kurikuma no Okimi as follows. &quot;Tsukushi Province has always been prepared for the rebels around the border.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The modern translation of Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan) contains the words of Kurikuma no Okimi as follows:</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。reads→contains,クォート、パンクチュエーションを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The modern translation of Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan) contains the words of Kurikuma no Okimi as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>「筑紫国は以前から辺賊の難に備えている。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsukushi Province has always been prepared for the rebels around the border.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukushi Province has always been prepared for the rebels around the border.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文にかぎ括弧をつけました。英文を&apos;&apos;で囲みました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>「そもそも城を高くし溝を深くし、海に臨んで守るのは、内の賊のためではない。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">We are serving as coast guards with tall ramparts and deep trenches, but not to deal with internal insurgence.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">We are serving as coast guards with tall ramparts and deep trenches, but not to deal with the internal insurgence.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">We are serving as coast guards with tall ramparts and deep trenches, but not to deal with the internal insurgence.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文にかぎ括弧をつけました。英文を&apos;&apos;で囲みました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>「今、命をかしこんで軍を発すれば、国が空になる。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If we followed the order respectfully and dispatch troops now, the province would be defenseless in security.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If we followed the order respectfully and dispatch troops now, the province would be defenseless in security.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If we followed the order respectfully and dispatch troops now, the province would be defenseless in security.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文にかぎ括弧をつけました。英文を&apos;&apos;で囲みました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>「そこで予想外の兵乱があればただちに社稷が傾く。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under such circumstances, an outbreak of any revolts could lead the country to immediate crisis.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under such circumstances, an outbreak of any revolts could lead the country to immediate crisis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under such circumstances, an outbreak of any revolts could lead the country to immediate crisis.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文にかぎ括弧をつけました。英文を&apos;&apos;で囲みました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>「その後になって臣を百回殺しても何の益があろうか。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, how can I find any meanings in killing retainers again and again?</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「百回」は「何度も」と訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, how can I find any meanings in killing retainers again and again?</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, how can I find any meanings in killing retainers again and again?&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文にかぎ括弧をつけました。英文を&apos;&apos;で囲みました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>「あえて徳に背こうとはするのではない。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I don&apos;t intend to disobey.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I do not intend to disobey.&apos;</e>
<cmt>don&apos;t→do not と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I do not intend to disobey.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文にかぎ括弧をつけました。英文を&apos;&apos;で囲みました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>「兵を動かさないのはこのためである。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the reason I do not send my troops.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the reason why I do not send my troops.&apos;</e>
<cmt>why を補いました。クォートを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the reason why I do not send my troops.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文にかぎ括弧をつけました。英文を&apos;&apos;で囲みました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="38">
<j>使者の佐伯男は、大友皇子の命令に従って栗隈王を殺そうと剣を握って進もうとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saeki no Otoko, the emissary, followed Prince Otomo&apos;s order and tried to take step forward to kill Kurikuma no Okimi with his sword.</e>
<cmt>「佐伯男」の読みは「さえきのおとこ」としています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saeki no Otoko, the emissary, followed the Prince Otomo&apos;s order and tried to take step forward to kill Kurikuma no Okimi with his sword.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saeki no Otoko, the emissary, followed the Prince Otomo&apos;s order and tried to take step forward to kill Kurikuma no Okimi with his sword.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>しかし、栗隈王の二人の子、三野王（美努王）と武家王が側にいて剣を佩き、退く気配がなかったため、恐れて断念した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Minu no Okimi and Takeie no Okimi, the two sons of Kurikuma no Okimi were standing close to their father with their swords ready to fight back, so Saeki gave up his plot for fear of being defeated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Minu no Okimi and Takeie no Okimi, the two sons of Kurikuma no Okimi were standing close to their father with their swords ready to fight back, so Saeki gave up his plot for fear of being defeated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Minu no Okimi and Takeie no Okimi, the two sons of Kurikuma no Okimi were standing close to their father with their swords ready to fight back, so Saeki gave up his plot for fear of being defeated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="40">
<j>兵政官長任命と死</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Appointment of Heiseikan Cho and the death of Kurikuma no Okimi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Appointment of Heiseikan Cho and the death of Kurikuma no Okimi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Appointment of Heiseikan Cho and the death of Kurikuma no Okimi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="41">
<j>天武天皇4年（675年）3月16日に、諸王四位の栗隈王が兵政官長に、大伴御行が大輔に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 16, 675, Kurikuma no Okimi, Shoo Shii (princes without imperial proclamation but had Forth Court Rank), was appointed to Heiseikan Cho, and OTOMO no Miyuki to Taifu (vice-minister).</e>
<cmt>「大輔」は用語集を参照しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 19, 675, Kurikuma no Okimi, Shoo Shii (princes without imperial proclamation but had Forth Court Rank), was appointed to Heiseikan Cho, and OTOMO no Miyuki to Taifu (vice-minister).</e>
<cmt>天武天皇4年（675年）3月16日→西暦675年4月19日と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 19, 675, Kurikuma no Okimi, Shoo Shii (princes without imperial proclamation but had Forth Court Rank), was appointed to Heiseikan Cho, and OTOMO no Miyuki to Taifu (vice-minister).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="42">
<j>天武天皇5年（676年）6月、四位で病死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died of illness in June 676, his rank being Shii (Forth Court Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died of illness in July 676, his rank being Shii (Forth Court Rank).</e>
<cmt>June→July （グレゴリオ暦に変換）と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died of illness in July 676, his rank being Shii (Forth Court Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>『続日本紀』『新撰姓氏録』に贈従二位とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot;(Chronicle of Japan Continued) and &quot;Shinsen Shojiroku (Newly Compiled Register of Clan Names and Titles of Nobility)&quot;, he was posthumously conferred Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot;(Chronicle of Japan Continued) and &quot;Shinsen Shojiroku&quot; (Newly Compiled Register of Clan Names and Titles of Nobility), he was posthumously conferred Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>クォーツを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot;(Chronicle of Japan Continued) and &quot;Shinsen Shojiroku&quot; (Newly Compiled Register of Clan Names and Titles of Nobility), he was posthumously conferred Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>なお、『姓氏録』を基に栗隈王の父を難波皇子とする説が広く行われているが、二者の活動年代には隔たりが大きく（約80年）、父子関係を疑問視する向きもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an opinion that Kurikuma no Okimi was a son of Prince Naniwa which is based on the description in &quot;Shinsen Shojiroku&quot; (New Selection and Record of Hereditary Titles and Family Names), but considering the long gap (about 80 years) between their active periods, some are dubious about their relation as a father and a son.</e>
<cmt>「姓氏録」は「新撰姓氏録」と解釈しています。訳は用語集を参照しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an opinion that Kurikuma no Okimi was a prince of the Prince Naniwa, which is based on the description in &quot;Shinsen Shojiroku&quot; (New Selection and Record of Hereditary Titles and Family Names), but considering the long gap (about 80 years) between their active periods, some are dubious about their relation as a father and a son.</e>
<cmt>the, カンマを補いました。son→prince と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an opinion that Kurikuma no Okimi was a prince of the Prince Naniwa, which is based on the description in &quot;Shinsen Shojiroku&quot; (New Selection and Record of Hereditary Titles and Family Names), but considering the long gap (about 80 years) between their active periods, some are dubious about their relation as a father and a son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>この場合、『公卿補任』『尊卑分脈』の記載から、難波皇子と栗隈王の間に「大俣王（おおまたのおおきみ）」を1代補うことが出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this case, &apos;Omata no Miko&apos; can be added as one generation between Prince Naniwa and Kurikuma no Okimi according to the descriptions in &quot;Kugyobunin&quot; (directory of court nobles) and &quot;Sonpibunmyaku&quot; (a text compiled in the fourteenth century that records the lineages of the aristocracy).</e>
<cmt>「尊卑分脈」は用語集を参照して補足説明しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this case, &apos;Omata no Miko&apos; can be added as one generation between the Prince Naniwa and Kurikuma no Okimi according to the descriptions in &quot;Kugyobunin&quot; (directory of court nobles) and &quot;Sonpibunmyaku&quot; (a text compiled in the fourteenth century that records the lineages of the aristocracy).</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this case, &apos;Omata no Miko&apos; can be added as one generation between the Prince Naniwa and Kurikuma no Okimi according to the descriptions in &quot;Kugyobunin&quot; (directory of court nobles) and &quot;Sonpibunmyaku&quot; (a text compiled in the fourteenth century that records the lineages of the aristocracy).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="46">
<j>伝説等</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Legend etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Legend etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Legend etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>伝説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Legend</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Legend</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Legend</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="48">
<j>長崎県には、栗隈王を日本の水の中に住んでいる動物を取り纏める人であったとし、彼の子孫の神主が河童に慕われるという昔話がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Nagasaki Prefecture, there is a folk tale that Kappas (water imps) adore Shinto priests who are descendants of Kurikuma no Okimi, as Kurikuma no Okimi was thought to be the chief of creatures living in the water in Japan.</e>
<cmt>「河童」は用語集を参照しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Nagasaki Prefecture, there is a folk tale that Kappa (water imps) adore Shinto priests who are the descendants of Kurikuma no Okimi, as Kurikuma no Okimi was thought to be the chief of creatures living in the water in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Kappas→Kappa と修正しました。the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Nagasaki Prefecture, there is a folk tale that Kappa (water imps) adore Shinto priests who are the descendants of Kurikuma no Okimi, as Kurikuma no Okimi was thought to be the chief of creatures living in the water in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="49">
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="50">
<j>小説家の井沢元彦が、栗隈王を天武天皇による天智天皇暗殺の共犯者とする説を著書である「逆説の日本史」で展開しているが、学会からの賛同はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A novelist Motohiko IZAWA explains his idea in his book &quot;Paradox of Japanese History&quot; saying that Kurikuma no Okimi was an accomplice in the assassination of Emperor Tenchi which was mainly plotted by Emperor Tenmu, but he hasn&apos;t received any academic approval.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A novelist Motohiko IZAWA explains his idea in his book &apos;Paradox of Japanese History&apos; saying that Kurikuma no Okimi was an accomplice in the assassination of the Emperor Tenchi which was mainly plotted by the Emperor Tenmu, but he has not received any academic approval.</e>
<cmt>クォーツを修正しました。the を補いました。hasn&apos;t→has not と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A novelist Motohiko IZAWA explains his idea in his book &apos;Paradox of Japanese History&apos; saying that Kurikuma no Okimi was an accomplice in the assassination of the Emperor Tenchi which was mainly plotted by the Emperor Tenmu, but he has not received any academic approval.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), 代言人(id:33675), Kinori(id:443), Law soma(id:45202), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>