<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>常盤井宮滿仁親王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Tokiwai no miya Mitsuhito</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Tokiwai no miya Mitsuhito</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Tokiwainomiya Mitsuhito</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>常盤井宮滿仁親王（ときわいのみやみつひとしんのう、文和3年/正平 9年（1354年） - 応永33年10月8日 （1426年11月7日））は室町時代前期の皇族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Tokiwai no miya Mitsuhito (1354 ~ November 7th, 1426) is a member of the Imperial family of the former Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Tokiwainomiya Mitsuhito (1354 - November 7th, 1426) was a member of the Imperial family during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar, wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Tokiwainomiya Mitsuhito (1354 - November 16, 1426) was a member of the Imperial family during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除~ を-に訂正しました。&quot;November 7th&quot;→&quot;November 16 &quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>常盤井宮3代当主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 3rd head of the house of the Imperial Prince Tokiwai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 3rd head of the house of the Imperial Prince Tokiwai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 3rd head of the house of the Imperial Prince Tokiwai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>弾正尹になったものの位は無く、「無品親王」と言われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he became danjoin (President of the Board of Censors), he had no court rank and was called &quot;Muhon-Shinno&quot;(Imperial Prince without court rank.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he became danjoin (President of the Board of Censors), he had no court rank and was called &quot;Muhon-Shinno&quot;(Imperial Prince without court rank.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he became danjoin (President of the Board of Censors), he had no court rank and was called &apos;Muhon-Shinno&apos; (Imperial Prince without court rank).</e>
<cmt>原文に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>常盤井宮全仁親王の子として生まれ、永徳元年（1381年）に親王宣下を受けるが、これは愛妾の一人である小少将なる女性を足利義満に差し出し、その結果、義満の根回しによって為された物だったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though he was born as a son of Imperial Prince Tokiwai no miya Matahito and given the title of the Imperial Prince in 1381, this was made by that Prince Masahito offered one of the beloved concubines called Koshosho to Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA and Yoshimitsu made her child as the Imperial Prince by the behind-the-scenes work.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though he was born the son of Imperial Prince Tokiwai no miya Matahito and was given the title of Imperial Prince in 1381, this was accomplished behind-the-scenes because Prince Masahito offered one of his beloved concubines called Koshosho to Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA and Yoshimitsu produced a child with her who would become the Imperial Prince.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though he was born the son of Imperial Prince Tokiwainomiya Matahito and was given the title of Imperial Prince in 1381, this was accomplished behind-the-scenes because Prince Masahito offered one of his beloved concubines called Koshosho to Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA and Yoshimitsu produced a child with her who would become the Imperial Prince.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>その後更に弾正尹に任ぜられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, the Imperial Prince Mitsuhito was further posted to danjoin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Imperial Prince Mitsuhito was posted to danjoin.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Imperial Prince Mitsuhito was posted to danjoin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>しかし応永2年（1395年）、足利義満は出家、滿仁は出家する気は毛頭なかったが、上記のように弱みを握られていたため、同年7月2日に無理矢理出家に追い込まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1395, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA became a priest while prince Mitsuhito did not wish to become a priest at all, however, he was held his weak point and on July the 2nd, he was forced to be a priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1395, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA became a priest while prince Mitsuhito did not at all wish to become one, however, on July the 2nd, he was forced to become a priest.</e>
<cmt>wordiness, revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1395, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA became a priest while prince Mitsuhito did not at all wish to become one, however, on July 27 of the same year, he was forced to become a priest.</e>
<cmt>the、nd削除of the same year補足&quot;July 2&quot;→&quot;July 27 &quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>以後「常盤井入道親王」と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he was called &quot;Tokiwai Nyudo Shinno&quot; (Imperial Prince and Monk Tokiwai.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he was called &quot;Tokiwai Nyudo Shinno&quot; (Imperial Prince and Monk Tokiwai.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he was called &apos;Tokiwai-nyudo Shinno&apos; (Imperial Prince and Monk Tokiwai.)</e>
<cmt>スペース補足原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に-補足、Nを小文字に訂正。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>応永33年（1426年）に薨去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died in 1426.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died in 1426.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died in 1426.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Resto1578(id:168692), こぶまき(id:38278), K. Takeda(id:119013), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>