<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>尊秀王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sonshuo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sonshuo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sonshuo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>自天王（じてんのう、永享12年（1440年） - 長禄元年12月2日 (旧暦)（1457年12月18日）は、南朝 (日本)の再建を図った後南朝の最後の指導者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jitenno (1440 - December 18, 1457) was the last leader of the Gonancho (the Second Southern Court) who attempted to rebuild the Southern Court (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jitenno (1440 - December 18, 1457) was the last leader of the Gonancho (the Second Southern Court) who attempted to rebuild the Southern Court (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jitenno (1440 - December 18, 1457) was the last leader of the Gonancho (the Second Southern Court) who attempted to rebuild the Southern Court (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>北山宮尊秀王。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also called Kitayama no Miya Sonshuo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also called Kitayama no Miya Sonshuo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also called Kitayama no Miya Sonshuo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>本来は自称どおり、自天皇と書くべきであるが、当時の資料が北朝の天皇をはばかって「天王」としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fundamentally, his name should be written as Jitenno (自天皇）, but articles at that time write his name as &apos;Tenno&apos; (天王）, with a hesitation against the Emperor in the Northern Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fundamentally, his name should be written as Jitenno (自天皇), but articles at that time wrote his name as &apos;Tenno&apos; (天王), to irk the Emperor in the Northern Court.</e>
<cmt>changed the “with hesitation against” part</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fundamentally, his name should be written as Jitenno (自天皇), but articles at that time wrote his name as &apos;Tenno&apos; (天王), to irk the Emperor in the Northern Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>自天王の生涯についてはよくわかっていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Facts about the life of Jitenno is not known for sure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Facts about the life of Jitenno are not known for sure.</e>
<cmt>Noun-verb agreement (number)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Facts about the life of Jitenno are not known for sure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>父は空因（尊義・金蔵主）といわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father is said to be Kuin (空因) (Songi, Konzosu).</e>
<cmt>空因→読み不明です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father is said to be Kuin (Songi, Konzosu).</e>
<cmt>removed original Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father is said to be Kuin (also known as Songi or Konzosu).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その空因の父は小倉宮良泰(後亀山天皇の子)ともいわれるし、後亀山天皇の弟の子（後聖院宮説成？）ともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, father of Kuin (空因) is said to be as either 良泰 OGURANOMIYA (a child of Emperor Gokameyama) or a son of a younger brother of Emperor Gokameyama (Goseiin no Miya Tokinari?) (後聖院宮説成).</e>
<cmt>小倉宮良泰→読み不明です後聖院宮説成→読み不明です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, the father of Kuin is said to be either 良泰 OGURANOMIYA (a child of Emperor Gokameyama) or a son of a younger brother of Emperor Gokameyama (Goseiin no Miya Tokinari?).</e>
<cmt>part of a name is Untranslated</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, the father of Kuin is said to be either 良泰 OGURANOMIYA (a child of Emperor Gokameyama) or a son of a younger brother of Emperor Gokameyama (Goseiin no Miya Tokinari?).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>自天王は大和国・紀伊国国境付近の北山（奈良県吉野郡上北山村か）あるいは三之公（同郡川上村 (奈良県)）に本拠を置いていたといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jitenno is said to have located his headquarters in Kitayama (present-day Kamikitayama mura, Yoshino district, Nara prefecture?) around the border between Yamato Province and Kii Province, or Sannoko (Kawakami mura, Yoshino district (Nara prefecture)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jitenno is said to have located his headquarters in Kitayama (present-day Kamikitayama mura, Yoshino district, Nara prefecture?) around the border between Yamato Province and Kii Province, or Sannoko (Kawakami mura, Yoshino district, Nara prefecture).</e>
<cmt>removed nested parentheses</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jitenno is said to have located his headquarters in Kitayama (present-day Kamikitayama-mura, Yoshino-gun, Nara Prefecture?) around the border between Yamato Province and Kii Province, or Sannoko (Kawakami-mura, Yoshino-gun, Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>地名表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>1443年の禁闕の変の後、神璽は後南朝の自天王の元にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Kinketsu Incident in 1443, the sacred jewel was in hand of Jitenno of the Gonancho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Kinketsu Incident in 1443, the sacred jewel was in the hands of Jitenno of the Gonancho.</e>
<cmt>the hands</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Kinketsu Incident in 1443, the sacred jewel was in the hands of Jitenno of the Gonancho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その後、に旧赤松家家臣の石見太郎、丹生屋帯刀、上月満吉らが自天王に仕えるとの申し出があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Taro IWAMI, Tatewaki NIBUYA, Mitsuyoshi KOZUKI, and others who were the vassals of old Akamatsu family, made a proposal to serve to Jitenno.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Taro IWAMI, Tatewaki NIBUYA, Mitsuyoshi KOZUKI, and others who were the vassals of the old Akamatsu family, made a proposal to serve Jitenno.</e>
<cmt>articles, prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Taro IWAMI, Tatewaki NIBUYA, Mitsuyoshi KOZUKI, and others who were the vassals of the old Akamatsu family, made a proposal to serve Jitenno.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかしこれは石見太郎らの策略であり、自天王とその弟河野宮忠義王（後南朝の征夷大将軍ともいわれるがさだかではない、御所からは抜け出すが本村高原で没したとも）は敗北し御所で討たれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this was a stratagem by Taro IWAMI and others, and Jitenno and his younger brother Prince Chugi Konomiya (he is said to be a Seii Taishogun, or literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot; of the Gonancho, but it is not known for sure, and he is also said to have escaped from the palace, but died in Motomura Plateau) were defeated and was killed in the Gosho (Imperial Palace).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this was a plot by Taro IWAMI and others, and Jitenno and his younger brother Prince Chugi Konomiya (he is said to be a Seii Taishogun of the Gonancho, but it is not known for sure, and he is also said to have escaped from the palace only to die in the Motomura Plateau) were defeated and killed in the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>strategem-&gt;plot; also shortened by removing some unnecessary bits</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this was a plot by Taro IWAMI and others, and Jitenno and his younger brother Prince Chugi Konomiya (he is said to be a Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of the Gonancho, but it is not known for sure, and he is also said to have escaped from the palace only to die in the Motomura Plateau) were defeated and killed in the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>英語説明補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>18歳であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was 18 years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was 18 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was 18 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>これを（長禄の変）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is called the Choroku Incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is called the Choroku Incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is called the Choroku Incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kazukiokumura(id:142935), 立志堂(id:132177), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>