<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>均子内親王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Princess Kinshi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Princess Kinshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Princess Kinshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>均子内親王（きんしないしんのう、寛平2年（890年） - 延喜10年2月25日 (旧暦)（910年4月7日））は、平安時代の皇族・皇女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Princess Kinshi (890-April 7, 910) was a member of the imperial family and a princess in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Princess Kinshi (890-April 7, 910) was a member of the imperial family and a princess during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Princess Kinshi (890 - April 12, 910) was a member of the Imperial Family and a princess during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父親は宇多天皇（源定省）、母親は藤原温子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her father was Emperor Uda (MINAMOTO no Sadami), and her mother was FUJIWARA no Onshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her father was Emperor Uda (MINAMOTO no Sadami), and her mother was FUJIWARA no Onshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her father was Emperor Uda (MINAMOTO no Sadami), and her mother was FUJIWARA no Onshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>藤原温子の一人娘である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was the only daughter of FUJIWARA no Onshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was the only daughter of FUJIWARA no Onshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was the only daughter of FUJIWARA no Onshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>後に異母兄である敦慶親王の妃となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, she became a wife of Imperial Prince Atsuyoshi who was a half elder brother to her with a different mother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, she became the wife of Imperial Prince Atsuyoshi who was a half elder brother to her by a different mother.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, she became the wife of Imperial Prince Atsuyoshi who was her older paternal half-brother.</e>
<cmt>異母兄　の表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>日本の歌物語『伊勢物語』には、藤原温子・春澄洽子・伊勢 (歌人)・藤原高経女と共に和歌の集まりに参加する姿が描かれており、歌人としても名を残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Ise Monogatari&quot; (The tales of Ise), a tale of poems of Japan, she appeared as a poet who participated the waka gathering with FUJIWARA no Onshi, HARUSUMI, Amaneiko, Ise (waka poet), a daughter of FUJIWARA no Takatsune; she left her name as a poet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Ise Monogatari&quot; (The tales of Ise), a tale of poems of Japan, she appeared as a poet who participated in waka gathering with FUJIWARA no Onshi, HARUSUMI, Amaneiko, Ise (waka poet), the daughter of FUJIWARA no Takatsune; she left her name as a poet.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Ise Monogatari&quot; (The tales of Ise), a tale of poems of Japan, she appeared as a poet who participated in waka gathering with FUJIWARA no Onshi, HARUSUMI no Amaneiko, Ise (waka poet), the daughter of FUJIWARA no Takatsune; she left her name as a poet.</e>
<cmt>人名を一部修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Japan Maik(id:254359), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>