<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>後三条天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Gosanjo</e>
<cmt>[以下天皇名、人名の読み方は、ブリタニカ国際大百科事典、広辞苑、kotobank.jpで確認]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Gosanjo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Gosanjo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>後三条天皇（ごさんじょうてんのう、長元7年7月18日（1034年9月3日） - 延久5年5月7日（1073年6月15日））は、第71代の天皇。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Gosanjo (September 3rd, 1034 - June 15th, 1073) was the 71st Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Gosanjo (September 3, 1034 - June 15, 1073) was the seventy-first Emperor.</e>
<cmt>71st → seventy-first</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Gosanjo (September 3, 1034 - June 15, 1073) was the seventy-first Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>諱は尊仁（たかひと）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His posthumous name was Takahito.</e>
<cmt>諱→personal name [いみな]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His posthumous name was Takahito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His posthumous name was Takahito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>享年40。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was forty years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was 40 years old.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was 40 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>在位は治暦4年4月19日（1068年5月22日）から延久4年12月8日（1073年1月18日）まで。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His reign was from May 22nd, 1068 to January 18th, 1073.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His reign lasted from May 22, 1068 to January 18, 1073.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His reign lasted from May 22, 1068 to January 18, 1073.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>系譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>後朱雀天皇の第二皇子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the second Prince of Emperor Gosuzaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the second prince of Emperor Gosuzaku.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the second prince of Emperor Gosuzaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>母は三条天皇第三皇女、皇后禎子内親王（陽明門院）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was Emperor Sanjo&apos;s the 3rd Princess, Princess Teishi.(Yomei mon in)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was Emperor Sanjo&apos;s third princess, Teishi (Yomei mon in).</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was Emperor Sanjo&apos;s third princess, Teishi (Yomei mon in).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>後冷泉天皇の異母弟。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the half younger brother of Emperor Reizei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the younger half-brother of Emperor Reizei.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the younger half-brother of Emperor Reizei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>宇多天皇以来170年ぶりの藤原氏を外戚としない天皇となった（ただし、禎子内親王は藤原道長の外孫である）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the first Emperor who has no maternal relationship to FUJIWARA clan since Emperor Uda, for the first time in a hundred and seventy years.(However Princess Teishi was FUJIWARA no Michinaga&apos;s maternal grandchild.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the first Emperor since Uda, 170 years earlier, who had no maternal relationship to the FUJIWARA clan (but Princess Teishi was the maternal grandchild of FUJIWARA no Michinaga).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the first Emperor since Uda, 170 years earlier, who had no maternal relationship to the FUJIWARA clan (but Princess Teishi was the maternal grandchild of FUJIWARA no Michinaga).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>Life→Biography</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>東宮時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Crown Prince period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Period of the Crown Prince</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Period of the Crown Prince</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>生母が藤原の出でない為、関白藤原頼通や弟の藤原教通に疎んじられたが、彼等の異母弟の藤原能信の支援を受けたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the Emperor&apos;s birth mother was not from FUJIWARA clan, he was treated coldly by chancello (chief advisor to the emperor), FUJIWARA no Yorimichi and his brother, FUJIWARA no Norimichi, however it is said their half yonger brother, FUJIWARA no Yorinobu supported Emperor Go-Sanjo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the Emperor&apos;s birth mother was not from the FUJIWARA clan, he was treated coldly by the chancellor (chief advisor to the Emperor), FUJIWARA no Yorimichi and his brother, FUJIWARA no Norimichi; however, it is said their younger half-brother, FUJIWARA no Yorinobu, supported Emperor Go-Sanjo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the Emperor&apos;s birth mother was not from the FUJIWARA clan, he was treated coldly by the chancellor (chief advisor to the Emperor), FUJIWARA no Yorimichi and his brother, FUJIWARA no Norimichi; however, it is said their younger half-brother, FUJIWARA no Yorinobu, supported Emperor Gosanjo.</e>
<cmt>Go-Sanjo→Gosanjo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>『今鏡』によると、後朱雀天皇が尊仁親王を兄の親仁親王（後冷泉天皇）の皇太弟にと考えていたのを、頼通が抑えていたのに対し、能信が強く薦めて、その遺詔により皇太弟となる事が出来たとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Ima Kagami, &quot;The Mirror of the Present&quot;, Emperor Go-Suzaku considered Prince Takahito as his brother, Prince Chikahito&apos;s (Emperor Go-Reizei) Crown Prince, although Yorimichi was against it, Yoshinobu supported and Pince Takahito became Crown Prince due to Yoshinobu&apos;s will.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Ima Kagami&apos;s &quot;The Mirror of the Present,&quot; Emperor Go-Suzaku considered Prince Takahito as his brother and Prince Chikahito (Emperor Go-Reizei) as the crown prince, so although Yorimichi was against it, at Yoshinobu&apos;s insistence Prince Takahito became the crown prince.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Ima Kagami (The Mirror of the Present),&quot; Emperor Gosuzaku considered Prince Takahito of his older brother, Prince Chikahito&apos;s (Emperor Goreizei) successor, as Crowin Princes&apos; younger brother, although Yorimichi was against it, at Yoshinobu&apos;s insistence Prince Takahito became the crown prince.</e>
<cmt>Ima Kagami&apos;s &quot;The Mirror of the Present,&quot;→&quot;Ima Kagami (The Mirror of the Present),&quot; Go-Suzaku→GosuzakuGo-Reizei→Goｒeizei原文の「後朱雀天皇が尊仁親王を兄の親仁親王（後冷泉天皇）の皇太弟にと考えていたのを」の部分ですが、「後朱雀天皇は、尊仁親王を兄である親仁親王（後冷泉天皇）の皇太弟（つまり兄が死んだら次に天皇になる立場）にしたいと考えていたのを」という意味が出るように訳しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし、頼通や教通は、後冷泉天皇の後宮に娘を入内させて外祖父として権力を握る為に、尊仁親王に対して陽に陰に圧迫を加えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However Yorimichi and Norimichi kept on putting pressure on Prince Takahito directly or indirectly, to send their daughters to Emperor Go-Suzaku&apos;s Palace and take control of political power as maternal grandfather.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However Yorimichi and Norimichi kept on putting pressure on Prince Takahito directly or indirectly, to send their daughters to Emperor Go-Suzaku&apos;s Palace and take control of political power as maternal grandfather.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However Yorimichi and Norimichi kept on putting pressure on Prince Takahito directly or indirectly, to send their daughters to Emperor Gosuzaku&apos;s Palace and take control of political power as maternal grandfather.</e>
<cmt>Go-Suzaku→Gosuzaku</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その一例として、歴代の東宮が伝領する「壷切の剣」を頼通が「藤原氏（特に摂関家）腹の東宮の宝物」との理由で、23年もの間、親王が即位するまで献上しなかった事が、大江匡房の談話集『江談抄』に記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Go Dan Sho&quot; written by Oe no Masafusa, there is an example of above, Yorimichi did not give away Tsubo kiri no ken passed through successive Princes as for twenty three years until the enthronement of the Prince, the reason being &apos;The Tsubo kiri no ken was FUJIWARA clan (especially for the clan [family] eligible for regent&apos;s treasure&apos;.</e>
<cmt>壷切の剣→Tsubo kiri no ken[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Go Dan Sho,&quot; written by Oe no Masafusa, there is an example of the above: Yorimichi did not give away Tsubo kiri no ken but passed through successive princes for 23 years until the enthronement of the prince, the reason being that &apos;the Tsubo kiri no ken was meant for the FUJIWARA clan (specially for the clan [family] eligible for the regent&apos;s treasure).</e>
<cmt>AWFUL</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Go Dan Sho,&quot; written by Oe no Masafusa, there is an example of the above: Yorimichi did not give away Tsubo kiri no ken (a traditional sword handed down from emperor to crown prince) which passed through successive princes for 23 years until the enthronement of the prince, the reason being that &apos;the Tsubo kiri no ken was meant for the FUJIWARA clan&apos;s (specially the Sekkan-ke (families of the Fujiwara clan whose members were eligible to become regent) treasure.&apos;</e>
<cmt>最後の&apos;を補足But→whichTsubo kiri no ken に英語の説明を加えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>しかし、結局後冷泉天皇にはついに皇子がなく、天皇の死後、尊仁親王は即位した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But Emperor Go-Reizei did not have any children and after Emperor died, Prince Takahito enthroned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Emperor Go-Reizei had no children, so after he died, Prince Takahito was enthroned.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Emperor Goreizei had no children, so after he died, Prince Takahito was enthroned.</e>
<cmt>Go-Reizei→Goｒeizei</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>即位後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the enthronement</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the enthronement</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the enthronement</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>頼通が失意のあまり引退した後、藤原彰子の推挙で弟の教通を関白にしたが、反摂関家の急先鋒で東宮時代の天皇を庇護していた故能信の養子の藤原能長や、村上源氏の源師房等を登用して摂関家の政権独占打破を図り、大江匡房や藤原実政等の下級役人などを登用し、積極的に親政を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Yorimichi abdicated with the disappointment, his brother, Yorimichi became chancellor (chief advisor to the emperor) with the help of FUJIWARA no Shoshi, Fujiwara no Yoshinobu&apos;s adopted son, FUJIWARA no Yoshinaga and MINAMOTO no Morofusa from the Genji [MINAMOTO] family were appointed to the position to defeat the dominant politics of the clan [family] eligible for regents while FUJIWARA no Yoshinobu used to support the Emperor when he was Crown Prince and was an active leader of anti clan [family] eligible for regents.</e>
<cmt>村上源氏→the Genji [MINAMOTO] family originated from the Emperor Murakami[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Yorimichi abdicated with great disappointment, his brother Yorimichi became chancellor (chief advisor to the Emperor) with the help of FUJIWARA no Shoshi; moreover, Fujiwara no Yoshinobu&apos;s adopted son FUJIWARA no Yoshinaga and MINAMOTO no Morofusa, of the Genji [MINAMOTO] family, were given the positions needed to defeat the dominant politics of the clan [family] eligible for regency, even though FUJIWARA no Yoshinobu had supported the Emperor when he was the crown prince and was an active leader in opposition to the clan [family] eligible for regency.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Yorimichi abdicated with great disappointment, his brother Norimichi became chancellor (chief advisor to the Emperor) with the help of FUJIWARA no Shoshi; moreover, Fujiwara no Yoshinobu&apos;s adopted son FUJIWARA no Yoshinaga and MINAMOTO no Morofusa, of the Murakami Minamoto clan, were given the positions needed to defeat the dominant politics of the Sekkan-ke, and appointed the lower government officials such as OE no Masafusa and FUJIWARA no Sanemasa, because FUJIWARA no Yoshinobu had supported the Emperor when he was the crown prince and was an active leader in opposition to the Sekkan-ke.</e>
<cmt>Yorimichi→NorimichiGenji [MINAMOTO] family→Murakami Minamoto clan原文の意味に合うようeven though→because「大江匡房や藤原実政等の下級役人などを登用し」を訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また、源隆国のように、東宮時代の天皇を頼通に気兼ねして蔑ろにしていた者に対しても、隆国の子息の源俊明を登用する等、決して報復的態度を取らないように公正な態度を示した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People like MINAMOTO no Takakuni, who treated the Emperor with contempt while he was Crown prince, since he felt timid towards Yorimichi, were treated fairly by recruiting Katakana&apos;s son, MINAMOTO no Toshiakira, as to make sure there is no fear the possibility of reprisals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People such as MINAMOTO no Takakuni, who treated the Emperor with contempt while he was the crown prince because he felt intimidated by Yorimichi, obtained fair treatment by recruiting Katakana&apos;s son, MINAMOTO no Toshiakira, in order to ensure that there was no possibility of a reprisal.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People such as MINAMOTO no Takakuni, who treated the Emperor with contempt while he was the crown prince because he felt intimidated by Yorimichi, obtained fair treatment by recruiting Takakuni&apos;s son, MINAMOTO no Toshiakira, in order to ensure that there was no possibility of a reprisal.</e>
<cmt>Katakana→Takakuni</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>延久の善政</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Good government during Enkyu Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Good Government During the Enkyu Period</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Good Government During the Enkyu Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>1069年荘園整理令を発布して記録荘園券契所を設置し、1070年には絹布の制、1072年には延久宣旨枡や估価估価法の制定等、律令制度の形骸化により弱体化した皇室の経済基盤の強化を図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1069 the Decree Restricting the Expansion of Private Estates was issued and and an contract office to record the Estate was established, followed by issuing silk fabric regulation in 1070, then Enkyu measuring cup fixed by Emperor&apos;s order; the official measuring cup and the price regulation were established, the Emperor tried to build strong financial base of Imperial Court, which was destabilized due to the system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo codes become a mere facade.</e>
<cmt>記録荘園券契所→[定訳不明。券契は、地券・手形・割符などの総称]絹布の制→[定訳不明]宣旨枡→the measuring cup fixed by the Emperor&apos;s order; the official measuring cup[定訳不明]估価法→[定訳不明, 估価は、ねだんの意。]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1069, the Decree Restricting the Expansion of Private Estates was issued and a contract office to record estates was established, followed by the issuance of the silk fabric regulation in 1070 and the setting of the Enkyu measuring cup by the Emperor&apos;s order; the official measuring cup and the price regulation were established in 1072, and the Emperor tried to build a strong financial base for the Imperial Court, which had been destabilized due to the system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo codes and had become a mere facade.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1069, the Decree Restricting the Expansion of Private Estates was issued and a contract office to record estates was established, followed by the issuance of the silk fabric regulation in 1070 and the setting of the Enkyu measuring cup by the Emperor&apos;s order; the official measuring cup and the price regulation were established in 1072, and the Emperor tried to build a strong financial base for the Imperial Court, which had been destabilized due to the system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo codes and had become a mere facade.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>特に延久の荘園整理令は、今までの整理令に見られなかった緻密さと公正さが見られ、その為に基準外の摂関家領が没収される等（『後二条師通記』に記載有り）、摂関家の経済基盤に大打撃を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially Enkyu Decree Restricting the Expansion of Private Estates gave a big damage towards weakened financial bases of the clan [family] eligible for regents, since it had absolute fairness and details.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially Enkyu Decree Restricting the Expansion of Private Estates gave a big damage towards weakened financial bases of the clan [family] eligible for regents, since it had absolute fairness and details.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Enkyu Decree Restricting the Expansion of Private Estates was much more detailed and much fairer than any previous such decrees; as a result, it was particularly harmful to the weakened finances of the Sekkan-ke (families of the Fujiwara clan whose members were eligible to become regent) as the private estates of the Sekkan-ke were confiscated, for example (details of these events were recorded in the &quot;Gonijo Moromichiki,&quot; which was the diary of FUJIWARA no Moromichi, who later became Chancellor).</e>
<cmt>全体的に不明瞭なため訳し直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>この事が官や荘園領主、農民に安定をもたらした事で、『古事談』はこれを延久の善政と称えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to this fact it achieved the security to feudal lords of the private estate and the farmers, it is mentioned as Good government during Enkyu Period in &quot;Koji Dan&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Given this fact, it provided security for the feudal lords of the private estate and the farmers, and consequently in &quot;Koji Dan&quot; it is described as a good government during the Enkyu period.</e>
<cmt>AWFUL</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Given this fact, it provided security for the feudal lords of the private estate and the farmers, and consequently in &quot;Koji Dan&quot; (the collection of stories from the Kamakura period) it is described as a good government during the Enkyu period.</e>
<cmt>Koji Dan に英語の説明を加えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>一方、摂関家側は頼通・教通兄弟が対立関係にあったために天皇への積極的な対抗策を打ち出すことが出来なかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand the clan [family] eligible for regents did not come up with the positive counter plan again the Emperor since there was an adversary relationship between Yorimichi and Norimichi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the clan [family] eligible for regency did not come up with a constructive plan to counter the Emperor, mainly since there was an adversarial relationship between Yorimichi and Norimichi.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the Sekkan-ke did not come up with a constructive plan to counter the Emperor, mainly since there was an adversarial relationship between Yorimichi and Norimichi.</e>
<cmt>Sekkan-ke に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>また、同時代に起きた延久蝦夷合戦にて、津軽半島や下北半島までの本州全土が朝廷の支配下に入る等、地方にも着実に影響を及ぼすようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also there was the Battle against Ezo (a Japanese northerner) occurred in the same period, the Tsugaru Peninsula and the Shimokita Peninsula, whole area of Honshu would become under Imperial Palaces&apos; supervision, there would have been a big influence to the local area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, the battle against Ezo (a Japanese northerner) occurred during the same period; therefore, if the Tsugaru and Shimokita peninsulas and the whole area of Honshu had come under the supervision of the Imperial Palace, there would have been a great influence on the local area.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, the battle against Ezo (the name used at that time to refer to the lands located to the north of Japan), which occurred during the same period, brought the whole of Honshu (the main island), including the Tsugaru and Shimokita peninsulas, under the control of the Imperial Court, and this had a significant impact on local areas throughout the island.</e>
<cmt>原文に合うように、修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="21">
<j>1072年、即位後4年にて第一皇子白河天皇に譲位して院政を開こうと図ったが、翌年には病に倒れ、40歳で崩御した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1072, after four years of his enthronement, the Emperor intended to pass the throne to his first Prince, Emperor Shirakawa and start the cloister government, however he became ill on the following year and died when he was forty years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1072, after four years of his enthronement, the Emperor intended to pass the throne to his first Prince, Emperor Shirakawa and start the cloister government, however he became ill on the following year and died when he was forty years old.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1072, after four years of his enthronement, the Emperor intended to pass the throne to his first Prince, Emperor Shirakawa and start the cloister government, however he became ill on the following year and died when he was forty years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>尚、近年の研究では、天皇の退位は院政の実施を図ったものではなく、病によるものとする説が有力である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From recent study, it is said there is a potent theory that the Emperor abdicated from the throne due to his illness, not due to his intention to rule the cloister government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on recent studies, there is a strong theory that the Emperor abdicated the throne due to his illness, not due to his intention to rule the cloister government.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on recent studies, there is a strong theory that the Emperor abdicated the throne due to his illness, not due to his intention to rule the cloister government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>在位中の元号</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eras during his reign</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eras During His Reign</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eras During His Reign</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>治暦（1068年4月19日） - 1069年4月13日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jiryaku (April 19, 1068) - April 13, 1069</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jiryaku (April 19, 1068) - April 13, 1069</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jiryaku (April 19, 1068) - April 13, 1069</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="24">
<j>延久 1069年4月13日 - （1072年12月8日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enkyu April 13, 1069 - (December 8, 1072)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enkyu April 13, 1069 - (December 8, 1072)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enkyu April 13, 1069 - (December 8, 1072)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>陵墓</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial mausoleum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Mausoleum</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Mausoleum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>京都市右京区龍安寺朱山町。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is located at Suyama-cho(?) Town, Ryoan-ji, Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>京都市右京区龍安寺朱山町→Suyama-cho(?) Town, Ryoan-ji, Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City[朱山町の読み方不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is located at Suyama-cho(?) Town, Ryoan-ji, Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is located at Shuyama, Ryoan-ji, Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>朱山町は朱山ではないかと考え、Shuyamaとしました。[http://map.yahoo.co.jp/address?ac=26108r]</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>圓宗寺陵（えんそうじのみささぎ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor was entombed in Enso-ji no misasagi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor was entombed in Enso-ji no misasagi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor was entombed in Enso-ji no misasagi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 JAnDbot(id:66507), Lonicera(id:20638), BOTarate(id:185620), 霧木諒二(id:9795), Nnh(id:474), Equaly(id:89792), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), Huemat(id:19503), 味っ子(id:17086), Greenland4(id:114494), Zwobot(id:23873), Ktoetx(id:104437), Aoooooooo(id:101274), Masyu(id:31065), NoriBeat(id:2074), 玄史生(id:43670), SuisuiBot(id:10165), 代言人(id:33675), 名無し(id:7386), YOSHI438(id:174755), Alexbot(id:157199), 李(id:10582), 唐棣色(id:64681), Kouko0515(id:100370), LeonardoRob0t(id:25875), Wybot(id:81801), Zippin(id:9885), LERK(id:4460), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>