<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>作宮</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakunomiya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saku-no-miya</e>
<cmt>「Sakunomiya」　⇒　『Saku-no-miya』に変更しました。他の宮名表記と統一するためです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saku-no-miya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>作宮（さくのみや、元禄2年6月27日 (旧暦)（1689年8月12日） - 元禄5年4月23日 (旧暦)（1692年6月7日））は江戸時代中期の皇族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakunomiya (August 12, 1689-June 7, 1692) was the imperial family in the middle of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saku-no-miya (August 12, 1689 - June 7, 1692) was a member of the Imperial family who lived in the middle of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>下記のとおり変更、修正しました。・「Sakunomiya」　⇒　『Saku-no-miya』・「the imperial family」　⇒　『a member of the Imperial family』・「in the middle of the Edo period」　⇒　『who lived in the middle of the Edo period』</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saku-no-miya (August 12, 1689 - June 7, 1692) was a member of the Imperial family who lived in the middle of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>常磐井宮（桂宮）第6代。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokiwainomiya (Katsura no miya) the sixth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the sixth family head of Tokiwai-no-miya (also known as Katsura-no-miya) family.</e>
<cmt>主語のない句の形になってましたので、一文章の形に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the sixth family head of Tokiwai-no-miya (also known as Katsura-no-miya) family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>霊元天皇の第十皇子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tenth imperial prince of the Emperor Reigen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the tenth son of the Emperor Reigen.</e>
<cmt>・主語のない句の形になってましたので、一文章の形に修正しました。・「tenth imperial prince」　⇒　『tenth son』に修正しました。（人々から見て「皇子」ですが、霊元天皇との続柄は「息子＝son」)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the tenth son of the Emperor Reigen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>母は五条為庸女菅原経子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was Keishi SUGAWARA, the daughter of Tamenobu GOJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was Keishi SUGAWARA, a daughter of Tamenobu GOJO.</e>
<cmt>「the daughter」　⇒　『a daughter』に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was Keishi SUGAWARA, a daughter of Tamenobu GOJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>幼少は最初、正宮（まさのみや）で元禄4年（1691年）作宮に改称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was Masanomiya, but in 1691 it was changed to Sakunomiya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Masanomiya, and in 1691 it was renamed Saku-no-miya.</e>
<cmt>下記のとおり変更、修正しました。・「but」　⇒　『and』・「changed to Sakunomiya」　⇒　『renamed Saku-no-miya』</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Masanomiya, and in 1691 it was renamed Saku-no-miya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>元禄2年8月八条宮尚仁親王が継嗣となる王子のないまま薨去したため、父帝の命によって、親王の継嗣として同年10月宮家を相続し、常磐井宮の宮号を賜る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Hachijonomiya Imperial Prince Naohito died without heir in August 1689, following the order by his father (the Emperor), Sakunomiya succeeded the Miyake (house of an imperial prince) as an heir of the Imperial Prince in December the same year, and was granted a Miyago (reigning name) of Tokiwainomiya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Imperial Prince Hachijo-no-miya Naohito who had no heir in 1689, Saku-no-miya became the heir of Imperial Prince to succeed to the Miyake (house of an imperial prince) as designated by his father (the Emperor) in December of the same year, and was granted the Miyago (reigning name) of Tokiwai-no-miya.</e>
<cmt>下記のように変更＆修正しました。・「When Hachijonomiya Imperial Prince Naohito died without heir」　⇒　『After the death of Imperial Prince Hachijo-no-miya Naohito who had no heir』 ・「in August 1689」　⇒　『in 1689』　（和文「元禄2年8月」は、西暦1689年では正確な月の記載がありませんので、August（=8月）は削除しました。原文の参考により、‘in October（10月） 1689’ではないかとは思いますが。）・「following the order by his father (the Emperor)」　⇒　『as designated by his father (the Emperor) 』・「Sakunomiya succeeded the Miyake (house of an imperial prince) as an heir of the Imperial Prince」　⇒　『Saku-no-miya became the heir of Imperial Prince to succeed to the Miyake (house of an imperial prince)』・「in December the same year」　⇒　『in December of the same year』・「Tokiwainomiya」　⇒　『Tokiwai-no-miya』</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Imperial Prince Hachijo-no-miya Naohito who had no heir in September 1689, Saku-no-miya became the heir of Imperial Prince to succeed to the Miyake (house of an imperial prince) as designated by his father (the Emperor) in November of the same year, and was granted the Miyago (reigning name) of Tokiwai-no-miya.</e>
<cmt>in 1689→in September 1689December →November（グレゴリオ歴）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>元禄4年上述のように作宮に改称するが、翌元禄5年4月23日薨去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As mentioned above, his name was changed into Sakunomiya in 1691, but he died on June 7, 1692.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As mentioned above, his name was changed into Saku-no-miya in 1691, but he passed away on June 7, 1692.</e>
<cmt>・「Sakunomiya」　⇒　『Saku-no-miya』 に変更しました。・「he died」 ⇒　『he passed away』 に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As mentioned above, his name was changed into Saku-no-miya in 1691, but he passed away on June 7, 1692.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>4歳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Died at the age of 4.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 4.</e>
<cmt>主語のない句の形から文章の形に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 4.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>法名は、浄功徳院。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His posthumous Buddhist name was 浄功徳院.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His posthumous Buddhist name was Jokudoku-in.</e>
<cmt>「浄功徳院」　⇒　『Jokudoku-in』 ? 正確な読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His posthumous Buddhist name was Jokudoku-in.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>作宮については、宮家を継承しているが、宮家の屋敷に入っていなかったため、桂宮歴代に加えない場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Sakunomiya succeeded the Miyake, he did not live in Miyake&apos;s residence, sometimes he is not counted as a Katsura no miya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Saku-no-miya succeeded to the Miyake, he did not live in the Miyake&apos;s residence, therefore sometimes he is not counted as a member of the Katsura-no-miya clan.</e>
<cmt>下記のように変更＆修正しました。・「Sakunomiya」　⇒　『Saku-no-miya』 ・「succeeded the Miyake」　⇒　『succeeded to the Miyake』・「in Miyake&apos;s residence」　⇒　『in the Miyake&apos;s residence』・「sometimes」　⇒　『therefore sometimes』 ・「as a Katsura no miya」　⇒　『as a member of the Katsura-no-miya clan』</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Saku-no-miya succeeded to the Miyake, he did not live in the Miyake&apos;s residence, therefore sometimes he is not counted as a member of the Katsura-no-miya clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 VolkovBot(id:105371), Suisui(id:69), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>