<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>身位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shini</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shini</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shini</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>身位(しんい)とは、身分や地位のことをいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shini means a social status and a position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shini means a social status and a position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shini means a social status and a position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>主に日本の皇族の身分及び地位を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Specifically, it indicates a social status and a position of the Japanese Imperial family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Specifically, it indicates a social status and a position of the Japanese Imperial family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Specifically, it indicates a social status and a position of the Japanese Imperial family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>日本の皇室における身位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shini in the Imperial House of Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shini in the Imperial House of Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shini in the Imperial House of Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>日本の皇室において、皇族の身位とは、皇后、太皇太后、皇太后、皇太子、皇太子妃、皇太孫、皇太孫妃、親王、親王妃、内親王、王 (皇族)、王妃 (皇族)、女王 (皇族)をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Imperial House of Japan, the Imperial family&apos;s Shini includes the Empress, the Grand Empress Dowager, the Empress Dowager, crown prince, crown princess, the son of crown prince, the daughter of crown prince, Imperial Prince, Imperial Princess (wife of Imperial Prince), Imperial Princess (daughter of the Emperor), King (of the Imperial family), Queen (wife of King), and Queen (sister of the King born into the Imperial family).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Imperial House of Japan, the Imperial family&apos;s Shini includes the Empress, the Grand Empress Dowager, the Empress Dowager, crown prince, crown princess, the son of crown prince, the daughter of crown prince, Imperial Prince, Imperial Princess (wife of Imperial Prince), Imperial Princess (daughter of the Emperor), King (of the Imperial family), Queen (wife of King), and Queen (sister of the King born into the Imperial family).</e>
<cmt>()と文字の間を直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Imperial House of Japan, the Imperial family&apos;s Shini includes the Empress, the Grand Empress Dowager, the Empress Dowager, crown prince, crown princess, the son of crown prince, the daughter of crown prince, Imperial Prince, Imperial Princess (wife of Imperial Prince), Imperial Princess (daughter of the Emperor), King (of the Imperial family), Queen (wife of King), and Queen (sister of the King born into the Imperial family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>皇族身位令（明治43年皇室令第2号、皇室令及附属法令廃止ノ件(昭和22年皇室令第12号)により廃止）では、皇族はそれぞれの身位に応じ、叙勲任官を受けることとされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Act of Imperial Family Status (the Imperial Families&apos; Act No.2 of 1910 which was eliminated by Abolition of the Imperial Families&apos; Act and Attached Ordinance [the Imperial Families&apos; Act No.12 of 1947]), the Imperial family are bestowed to appointments and orders according to their statuses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Act of Imperial Family Status (the Imperial Families&apos; Act No.2 of 1910 which was eliminated by Abolition of the Imperial Families&apos; Act and Attached Ordinance [the Imperial Families&apos; Act No.12 of 1947]), the Imperial family were bestowed appointments and orders according to their statuses.</e>
<cmt>過去文にするため動詞をなおしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Act of Imperial Family Status (the Imperial Families&apos; Act No.2 of 1910 which was eliminated by Abolition of the Imperial Families&apos; Act and Attached Ordinance [the Imperial Families&apos; Act No.12 of 1947]), the Imperial family were bestowed appointments and orders according to their statuses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>皇后は大婚成立時に勲一等宝冠章（宝冠大綬章）、皇太子・皇太孫は成年時に大勲位菊花大綬章、皇太子妃・皇太孫妃は婚約成立時に勲一等宝冠章（宝冠大綬章）、親王は成年時に大勲位菊花大綬章、親王妃は婚約成立時に勲一等宝冠章（宝冠大綬章）、内親王は成年時に勲一等宝冠章（宝冠大綬章）、王は成年時に勲一等旭日桐花大綬章（桐花大綬章）、王妃は婚約成立時に勲二等宝冠章（宝冠牡丹章）、女王は成年時に勲二等宝冠章（宝冠牡丹章）を叙勲することとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Empress gets the First Order of the Precious Crown (Grand Cordon of the Order of the Precious Crown) when she gets married; crown prince, the son of crown prince, and Imperial Prince get Grand Cordon of the Supreme Order of the Chrysanthemum when they come of age; crown princess, the daughter of crown prince and Imperial Princess (wife of Imperial Prince) get the First Order of the Precious Crown when they are engaged; Imperial Princess (daughter of the Emperor) gets the First Order of the Precious Crown when she reaches her majority; King (of the Imperial family) gets Grand Cordon of the Order of the Rising Sun with Paulownia Flower (the Order of the Paulownia Flowers); and both Queen - wife of King and sister of the King of the Imperial family- get the Second Order of the Precious Crown (the Order of the Precious Crown, Peony) when they are engaged and come of age respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Empress gets the First Order of the Precious Crown (Grand Cordon of the Order of the Precious Crown) when she gets married; crown prince, the son of crown prince, and Imperial Prince get Grand Cordon of the Supreme Order of the Chrysanthemum when they come of age; Crown Princess, the daughter of Crown Prince and Imperial Princess (wife of Imperial Prince) get the First Order of the Precious Crown when they are engaged; Imperial Princess (daughter of the Emperor) gets the First Order of the Precious Crown when she reaches maturity; King (of the Imperial family) gets Grand Cordon of the Order of the Rising Sun with Paulownia Flower (the Order of the Paulownia Flowers); and both Queen-wife of the King and sister of the King of the Imperial family-get the Second Order of the Precious Crown (the Order of the Precious Crown, Peony) when they are engaged and come of age respectively.</e>
<cmt>空欄の必要のないところを省きました。maturityにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Empress gets the First Order of the Precious Crown (Grand Cordon of the Order of the Precious Crown) when she gets married; crown prince, the son of crown prince, and Imperial Prince get Grand Cordon of the Supreme Order of the Chrysanthemum when they come of age; Crown Princess, the daughter of Crown Prince and Imperial Princess (wife of Imperial Prince) get the First Order of the Precious Crown when they are engaged; Imperial Princess (daughter of the Emperor) gets the First Order of the Precious Crown when she reaches maturity; King (of the Imperial family) gets Grand Cordon of the Order of the Rising Sun with Paulownia Flower (the Order of the Paulownia Flowers); and both Queen-wife of the King and sister of the King of the Imperial family-get the Second Order of the Precious Crown (the Order of the Precious Crown, Peony) when they are engaged and come of age respectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="7">
<j>もっとも、皇族身位令の廃止後も、同令に準じて、皇族には叙勲されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, even after abolition of Act of Imperial Family Status, the Imperial family is decorated according to the act.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, even after abolition of Act of Imperial Family Status, the Imperial family is decorated according to the act.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, even after abolition of Act of Imperial Family Status, the Imperial family is decorated according to the act.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>なお、2003年11月3日の勲章制度改正以降に授与される勲章には「勲一等」のように数字で表現される勲等は冠されないが、改正前に叙授されたものは引き続き旧来どおりに呼称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The decorations which are bestowed after a revision of the decoration system don&apos;t have a number prefix such as &apos;the First Order&apos; but the ones before the revision are called as they used to be.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the decorations, which are bestowed since a revision of the decoration system in November 3, 2003, don&apos; have a number prefix such as &apos;the First Order&apos; but the ones before the revision are called as they used to be.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ「なお、2003年11月3日の」さらにこの日付が入ったことで必要な動詞等を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the decorations, which are bestowed since a revision of the decoration system in November 3, 2003, do not have a number prefix such as &apos;the First Order&apos; but the ones before the revision are called as they used to be.</e>
<cmt>don&apos;→do not</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 野良人(id:58574), Sakura-no-kuni(id:115977), 伏儀(id:142093), 無言雀師(id:13124), MIsogi(id:20599), 海衛士(id:19229), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>