<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>亀山天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Kameyama</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Kameyama</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Kameyama</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>亀山天皇（かめやまてんのう、建長元年5月27日（1249年7月9日） - 嘉元3年9月15日（1305年10月4日））は、鎌倉時代の第90代天皇（在位：正元元年11月26日（1259年1月9日） - 文永11年1月26日（1274年3月6日））。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Kameyama (July 9th, 1249 - October 4th, 1305) was the ninetieth Emperor during the Kamakura period. (his reign was January 9th, 1259 - March 6th, 1274.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Kameyama (July 9th, 1249 - October 4th, 1305) was the ninetieth Emperor during the Kamakura period. (his reign was from January 9th, 1259 to March 6th, 1274.)</e>
<cmt>&quot;from, to&quot; added</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Kameyama (July 9, 1249 - October 4, 1305) was the ninetieth Emperor during the Kamakura period (his reign was from January 9, 1259 to March 6, 1274).</e>
<cmt>日付表記ピリオドの意ｔ</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>諱は恒仁（つねひと）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His posthumous name was Tsunehito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His posthumous name was Tsunehito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His posthumous name was Tsunehito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>系譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>後嵯峨天皇の第七皇子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the seventh Prince of Emperor Gosaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the seventh Prince of Emperor Gosaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the seventh Prince of Emperor Gosaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>母は太政大臣西園寺実氏女、大宮院藤原姞子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was the Grand Minister, Saneuji SAIONJI&apos;s daughter, Omiyain FUJIWARA no Kitsushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was the Grand Minister, Saneuji SAIONJI&apos;s daughter, Omiyain FUJIWARA no Kitsushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was the Grand Minister, Saneuji SAIONJI&apos;s daughter, Omiyain FUJIWARA no Kitsushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>后腹では後深草天皇に次ぐ次男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the second son followed by Emperor Gofukakusa of the Empress.</e>
<cmt>后腹→a child by an empress[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the second son, followed by Emperor Gofukakusa, of the Empress.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the second son, followed by Emperor Gofukakusa, of the Empress.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>他のファイルに合わせる</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>正嘉2年（1258年）8月、惨烈を極めた正嘉の飢饉の最中、10歳で立太子、翌正元元年兄の後深草天皇の譲りを受けて践祚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the most horrible Shoka Famine, he became Crown Prince when he was ten years old, then he succeeded to the throne in the following year after his brother, Emperor Gofukakusa passes the throne to him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the most horrible Shoka Famine, he became Crown Prince when he was just ten years old, then he succeeded to the throne in the following year after his brother, Emperor Gofukakusa passed the throne to him.</e>
<cmt>grammar, cell needed word wrap formatting</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the most horrible Shoka Famine, he became Crown Prince when he was just ten years old in August 1258, then he succeeded to the throne in the following year after his brother, Emperor Gofukakusa passed the throne to him.</e>
<cmt>年号補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>即位には父の後嵯峨天皇や、生母の大宮院の意向があったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was an intention of his father, Emperor Gosaga and his birth mother, Omiyain for the enthronement of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father, Emperor Gosaga and his birth mother, Omiyain for intende for him to be enthroned as Emperor.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father, Emperor Gosaga and his birth mother, Omiyain intended for him to be enthroned as Emperor.</e>
<cmt>for削除intend→intended</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>弘長3年（1263年）、鎌倉騒動で、第6代征夷大将軍の宗尊親王が鎌倉から送り返され、代わって惟康親王の下向を要請した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kamakura Disturbance in 1263, &quot;barbarian-quelling generalissimo&quot;, Imperial Prince Munetaka was sent back from Kamakura, instead Imperial Prince Koreyasu was demanded to take his position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kamakura Disturbance in 1263, &quot;barbarian-quelling generalissimo,&quot; Imperial Prince Munetaka was sent back from Kamakura, in his stead Imperial Prince Koreyasu demanded to fill his position.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kamakura Disturbance in 1263, the sixth seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;), Imperial Prince Munetaka was sent back from Kamakura, in his stead Imperial Prince Koreyasu demanded to fill his position.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;barbarian-quelling generalissimo,&quot;→seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>文永2年（1265年）には、元のクビライからの国書が高麗を介して伝えられ、鎌倉から送達される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1265 a sovereign letter from Kublai (Khan) of the the Yuan [Mongol] dynasty was delivered through Koryo; Goryeo, it was sent from the Kamakura government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1265 a sovereign letter from Kublai (Khan) of the the Yuan [Mongol] dynasty was delivered through Koryo; Goryeo, it was sent from the Kamakura government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1265 a sovereign letter from Kublai (Khan) of the Yuan [Mongol] Dynasty was delivered through Goryeo, it was sent from the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>the重複削除dynasty→DynastyKoryo;削除government→bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>幕府は元に備えると共に、朝廷は神社に異国降伏の祈願を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The government prepared for the battle against the Yukan [Mongol] dynasty while the Imperial Palace made a prayed them to yield to Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The government prepared for battle against the Yukan [Mongol] dynasty while the Imperial Palace prayed that they would yield to Japan.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bakufu prepared for battle against the Yuan [Mongol] Dynasty while the Imperial Palace prayed that they would yield to Japan.</e>
<cmt>dynasty→Dynastygovernment→bakufu スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>院政中には2回の元の対日侵攻（元寇）が起こり、自ら伊勢神宮で祈願するなど積極的な活動を行った（当時の治天・亀山上皇と天子・後宇多天皇の父子いずれかが「身を以って国難に代える祈願」を伊勢大神宮に奉ったことは史実のようだが、さて父子のどちらにその祈願を帰すべきかは、大正年間に学者の間で大論争を呼んでいまだ決着のつかない問題である）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During his reign the Mongolia invaded Japan (Genko, Mongolian Expeditions against Japan) twice, the Emperor acted eagerly to pray at Ise Jingu Shrine and so on. (It seems faithful that the retired Emperor Kameyama and the Emperor Gouda during this period, both father and son prayed at Ise Jingu Shrine and were ready to sacrifice themselves to help the nation, however it is unknown whether who to appreciate for the work, either the retired Emperor Kameyama or Emperor Gouda, it was a big controversial theory between the scholars during the Taisho period and the issue has not come to the conclusion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During his reign the Mongolians invaded Japan (Genko, Mongolian Expeditions against Japan) twice, the Emperor acted eagerly to pray at Ise Jingu Shrine, etc. (During this period, both the retired Emperor Kameyama and Emperor Gouda, father and son, prayed at Ise Jingu Shrine and were ready to sacrifice themselves to help the nation, however it is not clear who to appreciate for this, the retired Emperor Kameyama or Emperor Gouda, and this was a big controversial theory between the scholars during the Taisho period and the issue still has not been concluded.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During his reign the Mongolians invaded Japan (Genko, Mongolian Expeditions against Japan) twice, the Emperor acted eagerly to pray at Ise Jingu Shrine, etc. (During this period, both the Retired Emperor Kameyama and Emperor Gouda, father and son, prayed at Ise Jingu Shrine and were ready to sacrifice themselves to help the nation, however it is not clear who to appreciate for this, the Retired Emperor Kameyama or Emperor Gouda, and this was a big controversial theory between the scholars during the Taisho period and the issue still has not been concluded.)</e>
<cmt>上皇の表現</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>文永4年（1267年）には皇后の腹に皇子の世仁親王（後宇多天皇）が生まれ、翌五年後嵯峨院の意向をもとにこれを立太子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1267 the Empress gave a birth to Imperial Prince Yoshito, and he became Crown Prince due to the retired Emperor Gosaga in&apos;s intention on the following year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1267 the Empress gave a birth to Imperial Prince Yoshito, and he became Crown Prince due to the retired Emperor Gosaga in&apos;s intention the following year.</e>
<cmt>minor revision</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1267 the Empress gave a birth to Imperial Prince Yohito (Emperor Gouda), and he became Crown Prince due to the Gosaga in&apos;s intention the following year.</e>
<cmt>retired Emperor 削除(Emperor Gouda補足スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>文永9年（1272年）2月に後嵯峨法皇が崩御し、治天の君の継承と、皇室荘園領の問題が起こる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February 1272 after the Cloister Emperor Gosaga died, there was issues caused who to succeed the Chiten no Kimi and the private estate owned by the Imperial Family.</e>
<cmt>治天の君→Chiten no Kimi [院政において実権を握って政治に当たった上皇をさす] 皇室荘園領→the private estate owned by Imperial Family[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February 1272 after the Cloistered Emperor Gosaga died, there were issues as to who would succeed the Chiten no Kimi and concerning the private estate owned by the Imperial Family.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 1272 after the Cloistered Emperor Gosaga died, there were issues as to who would succeed the Chiten no Kimi and concerning the private estate owned by the Imperial Family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>後嵯峨は治天下の指名を幕府に求める遺勅を残していたとされ、幕府は後嵯峨の内意を問い、大宮院の内意が亀山であったとする証言から亀山親政と定まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said the cloister Emperor Gosaga left his will asking the Kamakura Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a Shogun) to appoint the successor to rule the cloister government, after the government asked Omiyain of the Gosaga&apos;s intention of the Imperial succession, she testified his intention was Emperor Kameyama, thus it was decided Emperor Kameyama to rule the direct government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said the cloistered Emperor Gosaga left his will asking the Kamakura Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a Shogun) to appoint the successor to rule the cloistered government, after the government asked Omiyain about who Gosaga&apos;s intented to succeed she named Emperor Kameyama, thus it was decided that Emperor Kameyama was to rule the direct government.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said Gosaga left his will asking the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a Shogun) to appoint the successor to rule the cloistered government, after the government asked Omiyain about who Gosaga&apos;s intended to succeed she named Emperor Kameyama, thus it was decided that Emperor Kameyama was to rule the direct government.</e>
<cmt>the Cloistered Emperor 削除Bakufu→bakufuスペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>文永11年（1274年）正月、亀山は皇太子世仁に譲位して院政を開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Kameyama abdicated and passed the throne to Crown Prince, Prince Yohito in the New Year of 1274 and started the cloister government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Kameyama abdicated and passed the throne to the Crown Prince, Prince Yohito in the New Year of 1274 and started the cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Kameyama abdicated and passed the throne to the Crown Prince, Prince Yohito in the New Year of 1274 and started the cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>亀山は院評定制の改革に取り組み、一定の成果を上げて「厳密之沙汰」、「徳政興行」と評された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Kameyama worked on improving the council system supervised by a retired emperor; In Hyojo Sei, he made a certain achievement and was commented as an Emperor who has &apos;strict self discipline&apos; and performed &apos;benevolent government.&apos;</e>
<cmt>院評定制→the council system supervised by a retired emperor;In Hyojo Sei [定訳不明]「厳密之沙汰」「徳政興行」→&quot;strict order&quot;&quot;benevolent adminisiration&quot;? [定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Kameyama worked on improving the system of council supervised by a retired emperor; In Hyojo Sei, based upon his acheivements, was thought to be an Emperor who exercises &apos;strict self discipline&apos; and yet, operates a &apos;benevolent government.&apos;</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Kameyama who worked on improving the system of council supervised by a retired emperor; In Hyojo Sei, based upon his achievements, was thought to be an Emperor who exercises &apos;strict self discipline&apos; and yet, operates a &apos;benevolent government.&apos;</e>
<cmt>who補足スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>また、後深草天皇の血統（持明院統）とは別に、自らの血統（大覚寺統）の繁栄に力を注ぎ、皇統が分裂して交互に皇位継承を行う両統迭立の端緒となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor worked hard to continue his own Imperial line apart from Emperor Gofukakusa&apos;s line (the Jimyo-In Imperial line, it was the beginning of the separation of the Imperial line and sharing the Imperial succession for both parties.</e>
<cmt>持明院統→the Jimyo-in Imperial line [定訳不明 Jimyo-in To]大覚寺統→the Daikaku-ji Imperial line [定訳不明 Daikaku-ji To]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor worked hard to continue his own Imperial line apart from Emperor Gofukakusa&apos;s (the Jimyo-In Imperial line, this was the beginning of the separation of the Imperial lineage and sharing of Imperial succession for both parties.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor worked hard to continue his own Imperial line (the Daikaku-ji Imperial line) apart from Emperor Gofukakusa&apos;s (the Jimyo-in Imperial line), this was the beginning of the separation of the Imperial lineage and sharing of Imperial succession for both parties.</e>
<cmt>(the Daikaku-ji Imperial line)補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>後深草院が出家の意向を示すと、幕府は持明院統の冷遇を危惧し、妥協案として後深草皇子熙仁親王（伏見天皇）の立太子を推進。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bakufu concerned about the Jimyo-in Imperial line to treat the retired Emperor Gokukakusa in coldly when he made an intention to become a priest, they recommended Gofukakusa&apos;s Prince, Imperial Prince Hirohito (the Emperor Fushimi) to become Crown Prince as a compromise proposal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bakufu, concerned about the Jimyo-in Imperial line cold treatment of the retired Emperor Gokukakusa when he made known his intention to become a priest, they recommended Gofukakusa&apos;s Prince, Imperial Prince Hirohito (the Emperor Fushimi) to become Crown Prince as a compromised proposal.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bakufu, concerned about the Jimyo-in Imperial line cold treatment of the Retired Emperor Gofukakusa when he made known his intention to become a priest, they recommended Gofukakusa&apos;s Prince, Imperial Prince Hirohito (the Emperor Fushimi) to become Crown Prince as a compromised proposal.</e>
<cmt>上皇表記スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>建治元年（1275年）に熙仁は亀山の猶子となり親王宣下、ついで皇太子となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1275 Imperial Prince Hirohito was adopted by Kameyama and received to title Prince by Imperial Order, then became Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>親王宣下→to title Prince by Imperial Order [定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1275 Imperial Prince Hirohito was adopted by Kameyama and received the title Prince by Imperial Order, then became Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1275 Imperial Prince Hirohito was adopted by Kameyama and received the title Prince by Imperial Order, then became Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>続いて弘安9年（1287年）には亀山の嫡孫にあたる後宇多皇子邦治王（後二条天皇）が親王宣下された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequently Kameyama&apos;s grandchild and Emperor Gouda&apos;s Prince, Prince Kuniharu (the Emperor Gonijo) received to title Prince by Imperial Order in 1287.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently Kameyama&apos;s grandchild and Emperor Gouda&apos;s Prince, Prince Kuniharu (the Emperor Gonijo) received the title Prince by Imperial Order in 1287.</e>
<cmt>minor revision</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently Kameyama&apos;s grandchild and Emperor Gouda&apos;s Prince, Prince Kuniharu (the Emperor Gonijo) received the title Prince by Imperial Order in 1287.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="21">
<j>だが、亀山は関東申次の西園寺実兼との不和に加えて、霜月騒動で失脚した安達泰盛と親しかった事が幕府を刺激する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However the bakufu did not like the fact that Kameyama did not go well with Kano Moshitsugi, Sanekane SAIONJI, also he was close to Yasumori ADACHI who lost his position from the Shimotsuki Disturbance.</e>
<cmt>関東申次→Kanto Moshitsugi [鎌倉時代、朝廷にあって武家との連絡に当たった役] 霜月騒動→the Shimotsuki Disturbance[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However the bakufu did not like the fact that Kameyama did not get along well with Kano Moshitsugi, Sanekane SAIONJI, also he was close to Yasumori ADACHI who lost his position from being involved in the Shimotsuki Disturbance.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However the bakufu did not like the fact that Kameyama did not get along well with Kanto Moshitsugi, Sanekane SAIONJI, also he was close to Yasumori ADACHI who lost his position from being involved in the Shimotsuki Disturbance.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>このため弘安10年（1287年）10月には後宇多天皇に代わって伏見天皇が即位し、その父である後深草院政が開始されて総領権を奪われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to above, Emperor Fushimi succeeded to the throne after Emperor Gouda in October 1287, Emperor Fushimi&apos;s father&apos;s Gofukakusa cloister government started and he took whole control of the politics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to above, Emperor Fushimi succeeded to the throne after Emperor Gouda in October 1287, Emperor Fushimi&apos;s father&apos;s Gofukakusa cloistered government started and he took complete control of politics.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to above, Emperor Fushimi succeeded to the throne after Emperor Gouda in October 1287, Emperor Fushimi&apos;s father&apos;s Gofukakusa cloistered government started and he took complete control of politics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>さらに、鎌倉では鎌倉将軍の惟康親王が廃されて後深草皇子の久明親王が将軍になり、持明院統に有利な情勢が続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Kamakura Shogun, Imperial Prince Koreyasu lost his position in Kamakura, instead Gofukakusa&apos;s Prince, Imperial Prince Hisaakira took this position, this lead the Jimyo-in Imperial line to the favorable situation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, the Kamakura Shogun, Imperial Prince Koreyasu lost his position in Kamakura,and instead Gofukakusa&apos;s Prince, Imperial Prince Hisaakira, took this position, this put the Jimyo-in Imperial line in a favorable position.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, the Kamakura Shogun, Imperial Prince Koreyasu lost his position in Kamakura, and instead Gofukakusa&apos;s Prince, Imperial Prince Hisaakira, took this position, this put the Jimyo-in Imperial line in a favorable position.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="24">
<j>正応2年（1289年）9月、亀山は南禅寺で出家して、法皇となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September 1289, Kameyama became a priest at Nanzen-ji Temple and became Cloister Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September 1289, Kameyama became a priest at Nanzen-ji Temple and also became the Cloistered Emperor.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September 1289, Kameyama became a priest at Nanzen-ji Temple and also became the cloistered emperor.</e>
<cmt>Cloistered Emperor小文字に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>法名は金剛源。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Buddhist name was Kongogen.</e>
<cmt>金剛源→Kongogen [読み方確認できず]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Buddhist name was Kongogen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Buddhist name was Kongogen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>禅宗に帰依し、亀山の出家で公家の間にも禅宗が徐々に浸透していく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He become a believer in the Zen sect and it spread gradually to the court nobles due to Kamerama becoming a priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He become a believer in the Zen sect and it spread gradually to the court nobles due to Kameyama becoming a priest.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He become a believer in the Zen sect and it spread gradually to the court nobles due to Kameyama becoming a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>その一方で、好色ぶりでも知られ、出家後も様々な女性と関係をもって多くの子供を儲けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand he had many relationship with different woman after he became a priest, he had many children.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, he had many relationships with different woman after becoming a priest and he had many children.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, he had many relationships with different woman after becoming a priest and he had many children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="28">
<j>孫・後二条天皇代、嘉元3年（1305年）9月に亀山殿で崩御、享年57。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While his grandchild, temporally Emperor, Gonijo was in power, Kameyama died in Kameyama mansion in September 1305 when he was fifty seven years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While his grandchild, temporary Emperor Gonijo was in power, Kameyama died at the Kameyama mansion in September 1305 when he was fifty seven years old.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While his grandchild, temporary Emperor Gonijo was in power, Kameyama died at the Kameyama mansion in September 1305 when he was fifty seven years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>遺詔で末子であり当時3歳の常盤井宮恒明親王の立太子の意思を示し、親王の伯父である左大臣西園寺公衡が実現工作に動いたために、後宇多上皇の強い反発を招き大覚寺統内部に混乱を招いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He left his will for his youngest child, Tokiwai no Miya Imperial Prince Tsuneaki, who was three years old at that time, to become Crown Prince, the Prince&apos;s uncle, the Minister of the Left, Kinhira SAIONJI tried to make it happen, the retired Emperor Gouda opposed to this movement strongly and it caused a confusion within Daikaku-ji Imperial line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He left his will for his youngest child, Tokiwai no Miya Imperial Prince Tsuneaki, who was three years old at that time, to become Crown Prince, the Prince&apos;s uncle, the Minister of the Left, Kinhira SAIONJI tried to make it happen, the retired Emperor Gouda opposed to this strongly and this caused confusion within the Daikaku-ji Imperial line.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He left his will for his youngest child, Tokiwai no Miya Imperial Prince Tsuneaki, who was three years old at that time, to become Crown Prince, the Prince&apos;s uncle, the Sadaijin (Minister of the Left), Kinhira SAIONJI tried to make it happen, the Retired Emperor Gouda opposed to this strongly and this caused confusion within the Daikaku-ji Imperial line.</e>
<cmt>上皇の表記&quot;Minister of the Left&quot;→&quot;Sadaijin (Minister of the Left&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>諡号・追号・異名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Posthumous name, Tsugo, different name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Posthumous name, Tsugo, different name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Posthumous name, Tsuigo, different name</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="30">
<j>追号の亀山院は、御在所の名亀山殿にちなむ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Tsuigo, Kameyamain came from the name of his Palace, Kameyama mansion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Tsuigo, Kameyamain came from the name of his Palace, Kameyama mansion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Tsuigo, Kameyamain came from the name of his Palace, Kameyama mansion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>父後嵯峨院が嵯峨野に建造した離宮亀山殿を天皇が伝領し、退位後は仙洞としてそこで崩御している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father, Gosaga in built the Palace, Kameyama mansion in Sagano was passed to Emperor Kameyama, he spent his time in the Palace after he abdicated and died.</e>
<cmt>仙洞→the Palace for a retired emperor [定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father, Gosaga in built the Palace, Kameyama mansion in Sagano was passed to Emperor Kameyama, he spent his time in the Palace after he abdicated and then died.</e>
<cmt>revised</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father, Gosaga in built the Palace, Kameyama mansion in Sagano was passed to Emperor Kameyama, he spent his time in the Palace after he abdicated and then died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>ほかに以下の異称もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are other names as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were other names as follows.</e>
<cmt>minor revision</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were other names as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="33">
<j>禅林寺殿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zenrin-ji dono</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zenrin-ji dono</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zenrin-ji dono</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>この名は、文永元年（1264年）に父、後嵯峨天皇が、洛東東山（永観堂）禅林寺の南部に造営された離宮禅林寺殿に由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This name came from the Palace, Zenrin-ji dono, which was built by his father, Emperor Gosaga on the south of Rakuto Higahsiyama (Eikan-do) Zenrin-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This name came from the Palace, Zenrin-ji dono, which was built by his father, Emperor Gosaga, on the south side of Rakuto Higahsiyama (Eikan-do) Zenrin-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>minor revision for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This name came from the Palace, Zenrin-ji dono, which was built by his father, Emperor Gosaga, on the south side of Rakuto Higahsiyama (Eikan-do) Zenrin-ji Temple in 1264.</e>
<cmt>年号補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>なお、この離宮は亀山天皇自身が寺院化し、正応4年（1291年）に京都五山の上位南禅寺 となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This Palace was made into the real temple and it became Nanzen-ji, high ranking temple of Five Great zen Temple of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Palace was made into a real temple and it became the Nanzen-ji, a high ranking temple among Five Great zen Temples of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Palace was made into a real temple by Emperor Kameyama himself and it became the Nanzen-ji, a high ranking temple among Five Great zen Temples of Kyoto in 1291.</e>
<cmt>年号補足by Emperor Kameyama himself 補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="36">
<j>万里小路殿（居所から）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Made no Koji dono (named after the place where the Palace located)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Made no Koji dono (named after the place where the Palace is located)</e>
<cmt>minor revision</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Made no Koji dono (named after the place where the Palace is located)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>文応皇帝（年号から）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Bun-o (named after the era)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Bun-o (named after the era)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Buno (named after the era)</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>在位中の元号</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eras during his reign</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Era&apos;s during his reign</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eras during his reign</e>
<cmt>Eras に戻しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="38">
<j>正元 （1259年11月26日） - 1260年4月13日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shogen (November 26, 1259) - April 13, 1260</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shogen (November 26, 1259) - April 13, 1260</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shogen (November 26, 1259) - April 13, 1260</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>文応 1260年4月13日 - 1261年2月20日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bun-ou April 13, 1260 - February 20, 1261</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bun-ou April 13, 1260 - February 20, 1261</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buno April 13, 1260 - February 20, 1261</e>
<cmt>元号スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>弘長 1261年2月20日 - 1264年2月28日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kocho February 20, 1261 - February 28, 1264</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kocho February 20, 1261 - February 28, 1264</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kocho February 20, 1261 - February 28, 1264</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>文永 1264年2月28日 - （1274年1月16日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bunei February 28, 1264 - (January 16, 1274)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bunei February 28, 1264 - (January 16, 1274)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bunei February 28, 1264 - (January 16, 1274)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>陵墓・霊廟</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial Mausoleum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Mausoleum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial mausoleum</e>
<cmt>小文字に</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="42">
<j>遺体は火葬に付され、嵯峨野にあった浄金剛院や亀山殿法華堂、法皇御願の南禅寺、高野山金剛峯寺にそれぞれ分骨されたが、亀山殿法華堂を以って天皇陵とし、現在は京都市右京区嵯峨天龍寺芒ノ馬場町の天龍寺境内にある亀山陵（かめやまのみささぎ）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor was cremated and his remain was kept at Jo Kongo-in Temple in Sagano, Kameya dono Hokke do, Nanzen-ji Temple built by the cloister Emperor Kameyama, Koya-san Mountain Kongobu-ji, however Kameyama dono Hokke do was considered as the Imperial mausoleum, which is current Kameya no Misasagi located within Tenryu-ji Temple in Susuki no Baba-cho Town, Saga Tenryu-ji, Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor was cremated and his remains were kept at Jo Kongo-in Temple in Sagano, Kameya dono Hokke do, Nanzen-ji Temple built by the cloistered Emperor Kameyama, Koya-san Mountain Kongobu-ji, however Kameyama dono Hokke do was considered as the Imperial mausoleum, which is currently Kameya no Misasagi located within Tenryu-ji Temple in Susuki no Baba-cho Town, Saga Tenryu-ji, Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor was cremated and his remains were kept at Jo Kongo-in Temple in Sagano, Kameyama dono Hokke do, Nanzen-ji Temple built by the Cloistered Emperor Kameyama, Mt. Koya Kongobu-ji, however Kameyama dono Hokke do was considered as the Imperial mausoleum, which is currently Kameyama no Misasagi located within Tenryu-ji Temple in Susuki no Baba-cho, Saga Tenryu-ji, Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>san Mountain削除その他スペル住所表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>法華堂形式の陵である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This Mausoleum is in Hokkedo style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Mausoleum is in Hokkedo style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Mausoleum is in Hokkedo style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>また、天龍寺に隣接した右京区嵯峨亀ノ尾町の亀山公園には火葬塚がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also cremation mound in Kameyama Park in Saga Kame no o-cho Town, Ukyo Ward, which is next to Tenryu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also a cremation mound in Kameyama Park in Saga Kame no o-cho Town, Ukyo Ward, which is next to Tenryu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Does &quot;cremation mound&quot; mean &quot;burial mound&quot; or are there two types of mounds?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also a cremation mound (a burial mound for cremated remains) in Kameyama Park in Saga Kame no o-cho, Ukyo Ward, which is next to Tenryu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>住所表記&quot;a cremation mound (a burial mound for cremated remains) &quot; としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="45">
<j>福岡市博多区の東公園に銅像が建てられている（1904年完成）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Cloister Emperor&apos;s bronze statue was built in Higashi (East) Park in Hakata Ward, Fukuoka City. Completed in 1904)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Cloistered Emperor&apos;s bronze statue was built in Higashi (East) Park in Hakata Ward, Fukuoka City. Completed in 1904)</e>
<cmt>spelling, tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Cloistered Emperor&apos;s bronze statue was built in Higashi (East) Park in Hakata Ward, Fukuoka City (Completed in 1904).</e>
<cmt>(補足ピリオドの位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ÉdeC(id:103767), 霧木諒二(id:9795), Nnh(id:474), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Webkid(id:5484), DragonBot(id:161936), Cprobot(id:97843), Eskimbot(id:29676), Charenji(id:7908), Miyabix(id:212560), Hégésippe Cormier(id:13846), Ohura(id:5986), パの字(id:34188), でここ(id:9565), Masyu(id:31065), らりた(id:1327), Pontafon(id:33761), 玄史生(id:43670), 代言人(id:33675), Rei-bot(id:94097), くっちゃめ(id:86793), UMBRO(id:100484), Yas(id:739), Lemon pie(id:66842), Nike(id:15576), Lonicera(id:20638), Bergmann(id:85282), 水野白楓(id:22811), Escarbot(id:59151), Rusk(id:9895), Nidarin(id:6420), SuisuiBot(id:10165), Yume149(id:17504), Muyo(id:14948), YOSHI438(id:174755), こいつぅ(id:2105), Suisui(id:69), LeonardoRob0t(id:25875), Louperibot(id:128971), Jade0416(id:104181), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>