<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>欠史八代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kesshi-Hachidai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kesshi-Hachidai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kesshi-Hachidai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>欠史八代（けっしはちだい）（正確な表記は、闕史八代）とは、『古事記』および『日本書紀』において、系譜（帝紀）は存在するもののその事績（旧辞）が記されていない第2代綏靖天皇から第9代開化天皇までの8人の天皇のこと、あるいはその時代を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kesshi-Hachidai (Eight Undocumented Sovereigns)(correct notation was 闕史八代) indicated the eight emperors from Emperor Suizei, the second, to Emperor Kaika, the eighth, that their pedigree records (Teiki (records of Emperor&apos;s family tree)) existed but their achievements (Kyuji (a record of stories current at court)) were not written in &quot;Kojiki&quot; and &quot;Nihonshoki&quot;or their periods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kesshi-Hachidai (Eight Undocumented Sovereigns) (the correct notation was 闕史八代) indicated the eight emperors from Emperor Suizei, the second, to Emperor Kaika, the eighth, that their pedigree records (Teiki (records of the imperial family tree)) existed but neither achievements (Kyuji (a record of stories current at court)) nor their periods were written in &quot;Kojiki&quot; and &quot;Nihon Shoki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The expression &quot;eight undocumented eras&quot; (&quot;kesshi hachidai&quot; in Japanese) refers to the eight emperors from Emperor Suizei (second emperor) to Emperor Kaika (ninth emperor) whose pedigree records (called &quot;Teiki&quot; in Japanese) exist but whose achievements are not recorded in &quot;Kojiki&quot; and &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; and the period represented by these emperors.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>これらの天皇は実在せず後に創作された架空のものだとする考えが戦後史学界で支配的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a ruling idea in the postwar history that these emperors did not exist and were imaginary characters created later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a prevalent assumption in the postwar history that these emperors didn&apos;t exist but were imaginary characters created in later times.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is widely accepted among scholars in the post-war period that these emperors did not in fact exist but are imaginary characters created at later times.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。actually → in fact</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>欠史八代の天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperors of Kesshi-Hachidai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The emperors Kesshi to Hachidai</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The emperors of Kesshi-Hachidai</e>
<cmt>翻訳を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>綏靖天皇 - 神渟名川耳天皇（かむぬなかわみみのすめらみこと）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Suizei - Kamununakawamimi no Sumeramikoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Suizei - Kamununakawamimi no Sumeramikoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Suizei - Kamununakawamimi no Sumeramikoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>安寧天皇 - 磯城津彦玉手看天皇（しきつひこたまてみのすめらみこと）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Annei - Shikitsuhikotamatemi no Sumeramikoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Annei - Shikitsuhikotamatemi no Sumeramikoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Annei - Shikitsuhikotamatemi no Sumeramikoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>懿徳天皇 - 大日本彦耜友天皇（おおやまとひこすきとものすめらみこと）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Itoku - Oyamatohikosukitomo no Sumeramikoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Itoku - Oyamatohikosukitomo no Sumeramikoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Itoku - Oyamatohikosukitomo no Sumeramikoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>孝昭天皇 - 観松彦香殖稲天皇（みまつひこかえしねのすめらみこと）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Kosho - Mimatsuhikokaeshine no Sumeramikoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Kosho - Mimatsuhikokaeshine no Sumeramikoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Kosho - Mimatsuhikokaeshine no Sumeramikoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>孝安天皇 - 日本足彦国押人天皇（やまとたらしひこくにおしひとのすめらみこと）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Koan - Yamatotarashihikokunioshihito no Sumeramikoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Koan - Yamatotarashihikokunioshihito no Sumeramikoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Koan - Yamatotarashihikokunioshihito no Sumeramikoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>孝霊天皇 - 大日本根子彦太瓊天皇（おおやまとねこひこふとにのすめらみこと）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Korei - Oyamatonekohikofutoni no Sumeramikoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Korei - Oyamatonekohikofutoni no Sumeramikoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Korei - Oyamatonekohikofutoni no Sumeramikoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>孝元天皇 - 大日本根子彦国牽天皇（おおやまとねこひこくにくるのすめらみこと）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Kogen - Oyamatonekohikokunikuru no Sumeramikoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Kogen - Oyamatonekohikokunikuru no Sumeramikoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Kogen - Oyamatonekohikokunikuru no Sumeramikoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>開化天皇 - 稚日本根子彦大日日天皇（わかやまとねこひこおおびびのすめらみこと）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Kaika - Wakayamatonekohikoobibi no Sumeramikoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Kaika - Wakayamatonekohikoobibi no Sumeramikoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Kaika - Wakayamatonekohikoobibi no Sumeramikoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>そもそもこれらの八代の天皇については、中国の革命思想（辛酉革命）に合わせ、また天皇家のルーツがかなり古いところにあると思わせるべく、系譜上の天皇を偽作したため生まれたのであろうとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding these emperors of eight generations, combined with Chinese revolutionary idea (Shinyu-kakumei (revolution in Kanototori of the Chinese astrological calendar)), and in order for the root of the Imperial Family to be considered as very old, they were created by pirating emperors on the pedigree record.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding these emperors of eight generations, combined with the Chinese revolutionary idea (Shinyu-kakumei (revolution in Kanototori of the Chinese astrological calendar)), and in order for the roots of the Imperial Family to be considered as very old, they were created by pirating emperors on the pedigree record.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is generally believed that these eight generations of emperors are fictive characters created for the pedigree record based on the Chinese Shinyu (year of the Metal-Rooster (&quot;Kanototori&quot; in Japanese) in the Chinese sixty-year calendar cycle) revolution philosophy in order to make the origin of the Imperial Family look more ancient than it actually was.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>辛酉とは干支のひとつで中国では革命の年とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanototori is one of the zodiac signs in Chinese astrology and is said to be the year of revolution in China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanototori is one of the zodiac signs in Chinese astrology and is said to be the year of revolution in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanototori is one of the zodiac signs in Chinese astrology and is said to be the year of revolution in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>21回目の辛酉の年には大革命が起きる（讖緯説）とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was said that the twenty first Kanototori year was the year of great revolution (Shinisetsu), and in Japan, it was the year that Prince Shotoku started politics in 601 (it was strictly in the end of sixth century, but there was no record of outward activities) and was the Kanototori, big revolutional year according to this theory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was said that the twenty-first year of Kanototori was the year of great revolution (Shinisetsu), and in Japan it was the year that Prince Shotoku started politics in 601 (it was strictly at the end of the sixth century, but there was no record of outward activity) and was the Kanototori, or big revolutionary year, according to this theory.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ancient Chinese legend has it that a great revolution occurs in the twenty-first Kanototori year in the astrological calendar.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>この説によれば日本では聖徳太子が政治を始めた601年（厳密には6世紀末とされているが、表立った活動の記録はない。）が辛酉の大革命の年である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to this legend, 601 A.D., when Prince Shotoku took office (although he is believed to have taken office at the end of the 5th century, there is no record of his activities before 601), was the year of the great Shinyu revolution.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>すると21×601260よりAD601－1260BC660（西暦0年はない）が神武天皇即位年と算出される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, by 21X601260, it was calculated that AD601－1260BC660 was the enthronement year of Emperor Jimmu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, based on 21X60 = 1260, it was calculated that AD601－1260 = 66 B.C. was the enthronement year of Emperor Jimmu.</e>
<cmt>numbers</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, by subtracting 1260 (21 times 60) from 601, one is led to conclude that 660 B.C. (note that there is no such year as 0 A.D.) is the year when Jinmu was entrhroned as the first emperor.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>第10代崇神天皇は別名ハツクニシラススメラミコトといい、すなわち初めて天下を治めた天皇であることを名称で物語っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Sujin, the tenth, had another name as Hatsukunishirasumera Mikoto and this name implied that he was the first emperor to govern the world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Sujin, the tenth, had another name as Hatsukunishirasumera Mikoto, which implied that he was the first emperor to govern the world.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Sujin (10th emperor) is also known as Hatsukunishirasu Sumeramikoto and this name (literally meaning the &quot;first emperor who ruled the country&quot;) implies that he was the first emperor to govern the country.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これは本来の系図では、崇神天皇が初代天皇とされたもので、それ以前はある時期に加えられたものであろうことを推察させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was said that Emperor Sujin was the first emperor on the primary genealogy and estimated that other emperors before that were created at some point.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was said that Emperor Sujin was the first emperor on the primary genealogy, and it was estimated that other emperors before that were created at some point.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This leads us to believe that Emperor Suijin was the first empeor in the original pedigree and that the preceding generations of emperors were added to the pedigree at some later point in time.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="19">
<j>1978年埼玉県稲荷山古墳から出土した金錯銘鉄剣に、大彦命から始まる8代の系譜が刻まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the iron sword with gold inscription excavated from Inariyama-kofun Tumulus in Saitama Prefecture in 1978, the pedigree record of eight generations starting from Obiko no Mikoto were carved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the iron sword with a gold inscription excavated from Inariyama-kofun tumulus in Saitama Prefecture in 1978, the pedigree record of eight generations, starting from Obiko no Mikoto, was carved.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The pedigree of the eight generations of emperors starting from Obiko no Mikoto is inscribed on the blade of a gold-inlaid sword excavated from the Inariyama-kofun tumulus in Saitama Prefecture in 1978.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>このオホヒコは、記紀にいう四道将軍大彦命と考えられ、第8代孝元天皇の皇子のはずであるが、銘文では何も触れられていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This Ohohiko was considered as Shido Shogun Obiko no Mikoto on kiki (the Kojiki and Nihonshoki) and he should be Imperial Prince of Emperor Kogen, the eighth, but there were no statements about it on the inscription.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Ohohiko was considered as Shido Shogun Obiko no Mikoto on kiki (the Kojiki and Nihon Shoki), and he should be the Imperial Prince of Emperor Kogen, the eighth, but there was no statement to that effect in the inscription.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ohiko no Mikoto that appear in this pedigree is estimated to be the general (Ohiko) mentioned in &quot;Kojiki&quot; and &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; who conquered four countries - i.e. the Imperial Prince of Emperor Kogen (eighth emperor), but there is nothing inscribed on the sword blade that shows his relationship to the emperor.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>鉄剣が作られた頃はそのような天皇（大王）の存在は系図上確立されていなかったことを物語る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It implied that the existence of such emperors (kings) was not established on the genealogy when the iron sword was made.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It implied that the existence of such emperors (kings) wasn&apos;t established in the genealogy when the iron sword was made.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It implied that the existence of such emperors (kings) wasn&apos;t established in the genealogy when the iron sword was made.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="22">
<j>4代・6代～9代の天皇の名は明らかに和風諡号と考えられるが、記紀のより確実な史料による限り、和風諡号の制度ができたのは6世紀半ばごろであるし、神武・綏靖のように、伝えられる名が実名であるとすると、それに「神」がつくのも考え難く、やはり神話的ないし和風諡号的なものであるので、これらの天皇は後世になって皇統に列せられたものと推定できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The emperors&apos; names of forth, from sixth to ninth generations were obviously Japanese shigo (a posthumous name), but according to more assured historical material on kiki, the system of Japanese shigo was established in the mid sixth century and if the transmitted names were their real names such as Jinmu and Suizei, it was hard to believe that &apos;神 (god)&apos; was added to their names, after all the names should be mythical or like Japanese shigo, so it was estimated that these emperors were put on the imperial line after ages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The emperors&apos; names of the fourth and sixth to ninth generations were obviously Japanese shigo (posthumous names), but according to more assured historical material on kiki, the system of Japanese shigo was established in the mid-sixth century, and if the transmitted names were their real names, such as Jinmu and Suizei, it was hard to believe that &apos;神 (god)&apos; was added to their names, since the names should be mythical or like Japanese shigo; therefore, it was estimated that these emperors were put on the imperial line in subsequent ages.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The names of the fourth and sixth to ninth generations of emperors are obviously Japanese-style posthumous names, but according to reliable descriptions in &quot;Kojiki&quot; and &quot;Nihon Shoki,&quot; Japanese-style posthumous names came to be used around the mid-sixth century; and although names like Jinmu and Suizei may sound like names of emperors used when they were alive, names that contain characters representing god (as in Jinmu) is unlikely to have been used as names of living persons, which leads us to believe that these were names for legendary characters or something similar to posthumous names and that, therefore, these emperors were added to the imperial lineage later in history.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="23">
<j>陵墓に関しても欠史八代の天皇群には矛盾が存在している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding the imperial mausoleum, there was inconsistency in a group of emperors of Kesshi-Hachidai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding the imperial mausoleum, there was inconsistency among the group of emperors from Kesshi to Hachidai.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are also inconsistencies about the mausoleums of these eight generations of emperors.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>第10代崇神天皇以降は、多くの場合その陵墓の所在地には、考古学の年代観とさほど矛盾しない大規模な古墳が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Emperor Sujin, the tenth, in the location of the imperial mausoleum in many cases, there were large tumuluses that was not so inconsistence with the archaeological sense of generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Emperor Sujin, the tenth, in the location of the imperial mausoleum in many cases there were large tumuluses that weren&apos;t very inconsistent with the generations from an archaeological standpoint.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are huge burial mounds consistent in appearance with the archaeological chronology at the locations of mausoleums built for Sujin, the tenth emperor, and later.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>だが、第9代開化天皇以前は、考古学的に見て後世になって築造された古墳か、自然丘陵のいずれかが存在している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, before Emperor Kaika, the ninth, either tumuluses that were built after ages or natural hills existed from archaeological point of view.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, before Emperor Kaika, the ninth, either the tumuluses that were built in later ages or natural hills existed from the archaeological point of view.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, burial mounds for Kaika, the ninth emperor, and earlier are either burial mounds that are likely to have been built in later periods from an archaeological viewpoint or natural hills.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>その上、そういった当時（古墳時代前～中期頃）に築造された可能性のある古墳もなければ、さりとて弥生時代の墳丘墓と見られるものもない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were no tumuluses as well that could possibly build around that time (early to mid-Kofun period (tumulus period)) and no grave mounds of Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were no tumuluses that could possibly have been built around that time (early to mid-Kofun period (tumulus period)), nor were there any grave mounds from the Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were no tumuluses that could possibly have been built around that time (early to mid-Kofun period (tumulus period)), nor were there any grave mounds from the Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="27">
<j>系譜などの『帝紀』的記述に止まり、事跡などの『旧辞』的記述がなく、あっても綏靖天皇がタギシミミの反逆を討ち取ったという、綏靖天皇即位の経緯ぐらいしかない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only &quot;teiki&quot; such as the pedigree record was written and &quot;Kyuji (a record of stories current at court)&quot; such as the achievement was not written, only how Emperor Suizei ascended the throne by winning the rebellion by Tagishimimi was written.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only a &quot;teiki&quot; (such as the pedigree record) was written and &quot;Kyuji (a record of stories current at court),&quot; and therefore the achievement wasn&apos;t written; only the description of how Emperor Suizei ascended the throne by winning the rebellion by Tagishimimi was written.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The only records available about these emperors are descriptions about their pedigrees and there are no descriptions of their actual achievements, except for a story about how Emperor Suizei ascended to the throne by crushing the rebellion of Tagishimimi.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>これらは、伝えるべき史実の核がないまま系図だけが創作された場合にありがちな例である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These were the typical examples of genealogy being created without the core historical facts to transmit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These were the typical examples of genealogy being created without the core historical facts to convey.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This fact strongly suggests that their pedigrees were created out of materials unrelated to historical facts.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="29">
<j>総て父子相続となっており、兄弟相続は否定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Everything was succeeded from father to son, so succession by sibling was denied.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Everything was succeeded from father to son, so succession by sibling was denied.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All cases of succession observed among these emperors are from father to son and no case of succession between brothers is found.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>父子相続が兄弟相続に取って代わられたのはかなり後世になるため、歴史に逆行していることにもなってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was much later that succession by sibling was replaced by succession from father to son, so it would mean regressing the history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was much later that succession by sibling was replaced by succession from father to son, so it would mean the regression of history.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These cases run counter to the actual historical development, since succession between brothers was replaced by father-to-son succession in a much later period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 霧木諒二(id:9795), 講師(id:71860), Nnh(id:474), 経済準学士(id:22656), Law soma(id:45202), Aibot(id:104981), 曲学の徒(id:83449), アスカ(id:9205), Godaigo(id:133481), Ohura(id:5986), Escarbot(id:59151), ごまふあざ(id:36855), Gombe(id:27), MDR-SK(id:192066), るがこむ(id:181), 玄史生(id:43670), Kinori(id:443), 代言人(id:33675), 海行かば(id:115823), 秀の介(id:490), Ribbon(id:172), 16toki(id:60127), Waza fire(id:9029), Loveless(id:129239), Shimoxx(id:9332), わたあめひみつ(id:81640), 竹麦魚(id:11012), 倭太郎(id:87388), Koika(id:16738), KASAGI(id:24405), Katsuya(id:21306), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>