<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>明治天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Meiji</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Meiji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Meiji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>明治天皇（めいじてんのう、嘉永5年9月22日（1852年11月3日） - 明治45年（1912年）7月30日）は、第122代天皇（在位慶応3年（1867年） - 明治45年（1912年））。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Meiji (November 3, 1852 - July 30, 1912) was the hundred and twenty second Emperor. (his reign was 1867 - 1912)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Meiji (November 3, 1852 - July 30, 1912) was the hundred and twenty second Emperor. (his reign was 1867 - 1912)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Meiji (November 3, 1852 - July 30, 1912) was the hundred and twenty second Emperor. (his reign was 1867 - 1912)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>諱は睦仁（むつひと）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His posthumous name was Mutsuhito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His posthumous name was Mutsuhito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His posthumous name was Mutsuhito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>幼少時の御称号は祐宮（さちのみや）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His respected name from childhood was Sachinomiya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His respected name from childhood was Sachinomiya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His respected name from childhood was Sachinomiya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>印は永（えい）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His seal was Ei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His seal was Ei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His seal was Ei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>倒幕・攘夷派の象徴として、また近代国家日本の指導者として活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was acted as a symbol of the force to overthrowing the Shogunate and antiforeign sentiment, and also a leader of Japan in the modern nation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He acted as a symbol of the force to overthrow the Shogunate and antiforeign sentiment, and was also a leader of modern Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He acted as a symbol of the force to overthrow the Shogunate and antiforeign sentiment, and was also a leader of modern Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その功績から戦前には、明治大帝、明治聖帝、睦仁大帝（Mutsuhito the Great）とも呼ばれたこともあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to his successful achievement, he was also called Meiji Taitei (Meiji the Great), Holy Emperor Meiji, Mutsuhito the Great before the War.</e>
<cmt>Holy Emperor Meiji→ [定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to his successful achievements, he was also called Meiji Taitei (Meiji the Great), Holy Emperor Meiji, Mutsuhito the Great before the War.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to his successful achievements, he was also called Meiji Taitei (Meiji the Great), Holy Emperor Meiji, Mutsuhito the Great before the War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>明治天皇は、孝明天皇の第二皇子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was Emperor Komei&apos;s second Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was Emperor Komei&apos;s second Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was Emperor Komei&apos;s second Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>母は権大納言中山忠能の娘・慶子（よしこ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was Gon Dainagon (Interim Chief Councilor of State), Tadayasu NAKAYAMA&apos;s daughter, Yoshiko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was Gon Dainagon (Interim Chief Councilor of State), Tadayasu NAKAYAMA&apos;s daughter, Yoshiko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was Gon Dainagon (Interim Chief Councilor of State), Tadayasu NAKAYAMA&apos;s daughter, Yoshiko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>嘉永5年9月22日（1852年11月3日）に、京都・中山忠能邸で生まれ、祐宮（さちのみや）と命名された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born on November 3, 1852 in Tadayasu NAKAYAMA&apos;s residence in Kyoto, and was named Sachinomiya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born on November 3, 1852 in the Tadayasu NAKAYAMA&apos;s residence in Kyoto, and was named Sachinomiya.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born on November 3, 1852 in the Tadayasu NAKAYAMA&apos;s residence in Kyoto, and was named Sachinomiya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>万延元年（1860年）5月、儲君（皇太子）となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became Crown Prince in May 1860.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became Crown Prince in May 1860.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became Crown Prince in June and July 1860.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>9月28日、（父・孝明天皇から）親王宣下を受け、「睦仁」の名を賜る（＝睦仁親王となる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He received to title Imperial Princess from her father, Emperor Komei, and became Imperial Prince Mutsuhito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He received the title Imperial Prince from his father, Emperor Komei, and became Imperial Prince Mutsuhito.</e>
<cmt>gender correction</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 10, he received the title Imperial Prince from his father, Emperor Komei, and became Imperial Prince Mutsuhito.</e>
<cmt>日付補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>慶応2年12月25日（1867年1月30日）、父・孝明天皇が俄かに崩御。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father, Emperor Komei suddenly died on January 30, 1867.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father, Emperor Komei suddenly died on January 30, 1867.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father, Emperor Komei suddenly died on January 30, 1867.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>慶応3年1月9日、満14歳の若さで践祚した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He ascended the throne on January 9, Keio 3 when he was fourteen years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He ascended the throne on January 9, Keio 3 when he was fourteen years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He ascended the throne on February 13, 1867, when he was fourteen years old.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>幕末の動乱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The disturbance during last days of the Tokugawa government</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The disturbance during last days of the Tokugawa government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The disturbance during last days of the Tokugawa government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>この頃、江戸幕府と討幕派は、それぞれ朝廷への工作を強めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During this time both Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and the opposition force who tried to overthrow the Shogunate strongly approached Imperial Palace for political maneuvering.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this time both the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and the opposition force that tried to overthrow the Shogunate strongly approached the Imperial Palace for political maneuvering.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this time both the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and the opposition force that tried to overthrow the Shogunate strongly approached the Imperial Palace for political maneuvering.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>慶応3年10月15日（1867年11月10日）に、明治天皇は、征夷大将軍・徳川慶喜からの大政奉還の上表を勅許し、政権を朝廷に戻した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 10, 1867, Emperor Meiji accepted the Imperial sanction of Taisei Houkan (the return of political power to the Emperor by the Tokugawa Shogunate) from Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians), Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA, after this political power was returned to the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 10, 1867, Emperor Meiji accepted the Imperial sanction of Taisei Houkan (the return of political power to the Emperor by the Tokugawa Shogunate) from Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians), Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA, after this political power was returned to the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 10, 1867, Emperor Meiji accepted the Imperial sanction of Taisei Hokan (the return of political power to the Emperor by the Tokugawa Shogunate) from Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians), Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA, after this political power was returned to the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>さらに慶応3年12月9日（1868年1月3日）には（討幕派の主導において）王政復古を発し、「新政府樹立」を宣言。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, on January 3, 1868, (it was supported by the opposition force who tried to overthrow the Shogunate) The Restoration of Imperial Rule was issued, and &apos;the establishment of the new government&apos; was announced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, on January 3, 1868, (it was supported by the opposition force who tried to overthrow the Shogunate) the Restoration of Imperial Rule was issued, and &apos;the establishment of the new government&apos; was announced.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, on January 3, 1868, (it was supported by the opposition force who tried to overthrow the Shogunate) the Restoration of Imperial Rule was issued, and &apos;the establishment of the new government&apos; was announced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>東征を命じ、旧幕府軍と　明治元年（1868年）から明治2年（1869年）にかけて戦い勝利した（戊辰戦争）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He ordered to conquer the eastern part of Japanese and won the battle against the former bakufu force which occurred between 1868 and 1869. (the Boshin War)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He issued an order to conquer the eastern part of Japan and won the battle against the former bakufu forces which occurred between 1868 and 1869 (the Boshin War).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He issued an order to conquer the eastern part of Japan and won the battle against the former bakufu forces which occurred between 1868 and 1869 (the Boshin War).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>新時代・明治</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">New era, Meiji</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">New era, Meiji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">New era, Meiji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>この間、明治元年3月14日（1868年4月6日）には五箇条の御誓文を発布して新政府の基本方針を表明し、4月21日（6月11日）には政体書によって新しい政治制度を採用。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During this time the new policy of the new government was announced when the Imperial Coverant Consisting of Five Articles was issued on April 6, 1868, the new political system was introduced with the Constitution of 1868, on June 11.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this time the new policy of the new government was announced when the Imperial Covenant Consisting of Five Articles was issued on April 6, 1868, the new political system was introduced with the Constitution of 1868, on June 11.</e>
<cmt>vocabulary</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this time the new policy of the new government was announced when the Imperial Covenant Consisting of Five Articles was issued on April 6, 1868, the new political system was introduced with the Constitution of 1868, on June 11.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>また、明治と改元して一世一元の制を定めた（改元の詔書が発せられたのは、慶応4年9月8日（1868年10月23日）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also the era was changed to Meiji and the regulation of Issei Ichigen (practice of assigning one era name to the reign of each emperor) (an Imperial rescript of a change in era name) on October 23, 1868.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also the era was changed to Meiji and the regulation of Issei Ichigen (practice of assigning one era name to the reign of each emperor - an Imperial rescript of a change in era name) on October 23, 1868.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also the era was changed to Meiji and the regulation of Issei Ichigen (practice of assigning one era name to the reign of each emperor - an Imperial rescript of a change in era name) on October 23, 1868.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>しかし改元は、慶応4年1月1日（1868年1月25日）に遡って適用されるとした）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However the change in era name was decided to date back to January 25, 1868.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However the change in era name was decided to date back to January 25, 1868.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However the change in era name was decided to date back to January 25, 1868.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="22">
<j>明治2年（1869年）、東京に遷って東京城（旧・江戸城）を皇居と改称し、6月17日（7月25日）には版籍奉還の上表を勅許した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1869 the Imperial Palace was moved to Tokyo and it was renamed as Tokyo Castle (the former Edo Castle), the Emperor permitted the Imperial sanction of the documents of the return of the han (domain) register to the Meiji Emperor on July 25.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1869 the Imperial Palace was moved to Tokyo and it was renamed Tokyo Castle (the former Edo Castle), the Emperor permitted the Imperial sanction of the documents of the return of the han (domain) register to the Meiji Emperor on July 25.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1869 the Imperial Palace was moved to Tokyo and it was renamed Tokyo-jo Castle (the former Edo-jo Castle), the Emperor permitted the Imperial sanction of the documents of the return of the han (domain) register to the Meiji Emperor on July 25.</e>
<cmt>-jo補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>当初、新政府内では公家や旧大名が中心を占めていたが、東京へ遷ったことも一つのきっかけとして、次第に三条実美、岩倉具視、木戸孝允、大久保利通らの発言権が大きくなっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the beginning the court nobles and the former feudal lords had the power in the new government, gradually a group of people such as Sanetomi SANJO, Tomomi IKAKURA, Takayoshi KIDO, Toshimichi OKUBO started having the voice in politics, and one of the reason for this was moving the Imperial Palace to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the beginning the court nobles and the former feudal lords had the power in the new government, gradually a group of people such as Sanetomi SANJO, Tomomi IKAKURA, Takayoshi KIDO, Toshimichi OKUBO started having a voice in politics, and one of the reason for this was the moving of the Imperial Palace to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the beginning the court nobles and the former feudal lords had the power in the new government, gradually a group of people such as Sanetomi SANJO, Tomomi IWAKURA, Takayoshi KIDO, Toshimichi OKUBO started having a voice in politics, and one of the reason for this was the moving of the Imperial Palace to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>明治4年7月14日（1871年8月29日）には廃藩置県を断行し、中央集権体制を確立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 29, 1871, the government conducted the abolition of the han system (feudal domains) and establishment of prefectures to establish the system of one consolidated political power into the centre of the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 29, 1871, the government absolved the han system (feudal domains) and the establishment of prefectures to establish the system of one consolidated political power into the centre of the government.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 29, 1871, the government absolved the han system (feudal domains) and the establishment of prefectures to establish the system of one consolidated political power into the center of the government.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="25">
<j>他方、明治3年1月3日（1870年2月3日）には、宣教使ヲ置クノ詔（大教宣布の詔）を発して、神道の国教化（国家神道）と天皇の絶対化を推し進めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the Imperial Edict (of 1870) for Establishment of Shinto was issued of February 3, 1870 to make Shintoism as nation&apos;s religion and to set up the political system for the Emperor to have absolute power drastically.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the Imperial Edict (of 1870) for Establishment of Shinto was issued on February 3, 1870 to make Shintoism the nation&apos;s religion and to set up the political system for the Emperor to have absolute power.</e>
<cmt>redundancy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the Imperial Edict (of 1870) for Establishment of Shinto was issued on February 3, 1870 to make Shintoism the nation&apos;s religion and to set up the political system for the Emperor to have absolute power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>岩倉、大久保らは、天皇を近代国家の主体的君主として育成するため、宮廷改革を行なって旧習を廃し、天皇親政体制への切り替えと君徳の培養に尽くした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iwakura and Okubo put effort into abolishing the old system of the Imperial Palace and to establish new system for the Emperor to rule the government directly, and educate the moral of the Emperor, as to educate the Emperor to become a sovereign of the modern nation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iwakura and Okubo put effort into abolishing the old system of the Imperial Palace and to establish a new system for the Emperor to rule the government directly, and to educate the Emperor to become the sovereign of the modern nation.</e>
<cmt>redundancy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iwakura and Okubo put effort into abolishing the old system of the Imperial Palace and to establish a new system for the Emperor to rule the government directly, and to educate the Emperor to become the sovereign of the modern nation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="27">
<j>※注：1872年（明治5年）に太陽暦を導入し、明治5年12月2日（1872年12月31日）の次の日（1873年1月1日）を「明治6年1月1日」と定めた（明治5年太政官布告第337号）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">*In 1872 the solar calendar was introduced, and the following day of December 31, 1872, (January 1, 1873) was decided as January 1st Meiji 6. (The No. 337 proclamation of the Grand Council of State in Meiji 5)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">*In 1872 the solar calendar was introduced, and the day following December 31, 1872, (January 1, 1873) was decided as January 1st Meiji 6. (The No. 337 proclamation of the Grand Council of State in Meiji 5)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">*In 1872 the solar calendar was introduced, and the day following December 31, 1872, (January 1, 1873) was decided as January 1, Meiji 6. (The No. 337 proclamation of the Grand Council of State in Meiji 5)</e>
<cmt>*に修正日付表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>征韓論</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Drastic theory against Korea</e>
<cmt>征韓論→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Drastic theory against Korea</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The drastic theory against Korea</e>
<cmt>語頭小文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>明治6年（1873年）に征韓論を巡って政府部内が紛糾した明治六年政変では、勅旨をもって西郷隆盛の朝鮮派遣を中止させてこれを収め、明治7年（1874年）から明治8年（1875年）にかけて続いた自由民権運動では、立憲政体の詔（漸次立憲政体樹立の詔）を発して政体改革を進めるなど、天皇は政府内部の政治的対立を調停する役割を果たした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1873 when the politics became complicated with the issue of the drastic theory against Korea, and political change happened in Meiji 6, the Emperor worked as a mediator to stop the conflict between the government, by stopping to send Takamori SAIGO&apos;s armed force to Korea with Emperor&apos;s official order, and he proceeded the political development by issuing an Imperial rescript of constitutional government (Imperial rescript of establishing gradual constitutional government) while there was the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement between 1874 and 1875.</e>
<cmt>立憲政体の詔（漸次立憲政体樹立の詔）→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1873 when politics became complicated with the issue of the drastic theory against Korea, and political change occurring in Meiji 6, the Emperor worked as a mediator to stop the conflict within the government, by stopping Takamori SAIGO&apos;s armed force from going to Korea by issuing the Emperor&apos;s official order, and he proceeded to issue an Imperial rescript to establish a gradual constitutional government while there was a Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement between 1874 and 1875.</e>
<cmt>wordiness, redundancy, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1873 when politics became complicated with the issue of the drastic theory against Korea, and political change occurring in Meiji 6, the Emperor worked as a mediator to stop the conflict within the government, by stopping Takamori SAIGO&apos;s armed force from going to Korea by issuing the Emperor&apos;s official order, and he proceeded to issue an Imperial rescript to establish a gradual constitutional government while there was a Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement between 1874 and 1875.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>この自由民権運動への対応として、明治14年（1881年）には、国会開設の勅諭を発して議会創設の時期を明示し、運動の沈静化を図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To keep up with the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement, the Emperor issued an Imperial mandate to establish the Diet and expressed the time of the establishment of the Diet to suppress the movement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To keep up with the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement, the Emperor issued an Imperial mandate to establish the Diet and expressed the time of the establishment of the Diet to suppress the movement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To keep up with the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement, the Emperor issued an Imperial mandate in 1881 to establish the Diet and expressed the time of the establishment of the Diet to suppress the movement.</e>
<cmt>in 1881補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>近代国家の確立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Establishment of the modern nation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Establishment of the modern nation</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Establishment of the modern nation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="30">
<j>明治15年（1882年）、軍隊を「天皇の軍隊」と規定した軍人勅諭を発し、大元帥として軍隊の統率にあたり、軍備の増強に努めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1882, the Emperor issued an the Imperial Rescript to Soldiers and Sailors to state the army as &apos;Emperor&apos;s army&apos;, he commanded the army as a commander in chief to strength the military power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1882, the Emperor issued an the Imperial Rescript to Samurai and Sailors to declare the army as the &apos;Emperor&apos;s army,&apos; he commanded the army as commander in chief to strengthen military power.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1882, the Emperor issued an the Imperial Rescript to Samurai and Sailors to declare the army as the &apos;Emperor&apos;s army,&apos; he commanded the army as commander in chief to strengthen military power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="31">
<j>明治17年（1884年）以降は、間近に控えた議会創設に備えて、立憲制に対応する諸制度を創設した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After 1884, the Emperor established various regulations for the constitutionalism to prepare for the establishment of the Diet which was drawing near.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After 1884, the Emperor established various regulations for the constitution to prepare for the establishment of the Diet, which was drawing near.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After 1884, the Emperor established various regulations for the constitution to prepare for the establishment of the Diet, which was drawing near.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>内閣制度、市町村制、府県制、郡制の制定など、津々浦々に至る官僚制支配体系の整備と並行して、莫大な皇室財産の設定を行なった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor also set up the huge Imperial property along with all sorts of maintenance of bureaucratic control system such as the establishment of the Cabinet system, municipalities system, Prefectural system and the district system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor also set up the huge Imperial property along with all sorts of maintenance of bureaucratic control systems such as establishing the Cabinet system, municipality system, Prefectural system, and the district system.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor also set up the huge Imperial property along with all sorts of maintenance of bureaucratic control systems such as establishing the Cabinet system, municipality system, Prefectural system, and the district system.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="33">
<j>明治22年（1889年）2月11日、大日本帝国憲法を公布した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 11, Japanese Constitution of 1889 was issued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 11, the Japanese Constitution of 1889 was issued.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 11, the Japanese Constitution of 1889 was issued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>この憲法は、日本史上初めて天皇の権限（天皇大権）を明記しており、近代天皇制国家確立の基礎となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This constitution clearly stated the the Emperor&apos;s prerogative lights (Tenno Taiken) for the first time in the history, this became the base to establish the modern Emperor System of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This constitution clearly stated the Emperor&apos;s prerogative rights (Tenno Taiken) for the first time in history, this became the basis to establish the modern Emperor System of Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This constitution clearly stated the Emperor&apos;s prerogative rights (Tenno Taiken) for the first time in history, this became the basis to establish the modern Emperor System of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>翌・明治23年（1890年）には教育勅語を発し、近代天皇制国家を支える臣民（国民）道徳の涵養に努めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the following year in 1890, the Imperial Rescript of Education was issued, the Emperor put effort to cultivate the moral of the nation who support the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following year, 1890, the Imperial Rescript of Education was issued, the Emperor put his efforts into cultivating the morality of the nation.</e>
<cmt>grammar, redundancy, wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following year, 1890, the Imperial Rescript of Education was issued, the Emperor put his efforts into cultivating the morality of the nation who supported the modern Emperor System.</e>
<cmt>who supported the modern Emperoro System補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>帝国議会開設当初は、超然主義を唱える藩閥政府と衆議院に依拠する政党勢力が鋭く対立衝突したが、天皇はしばしば詔勅を発し、調停者的機能を発揮した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the beginning of the opening of the Imperial Diet, there was often conflict happened between the Han-dominated government who support the detached policy and the government force who based on the House of Representatives, the Emperor sometimes issued an Emperor&apos;s order and worked as an arbitrator.</e>
<cmt>超然主義→ 定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the beginning of the opening of the Imperial Diet, there was often conflict between the Han-dominated government who support the detached policy, and the government force who was based on the House of Representatives, the Emperor sometimes issued an order and worked as an arbitrator.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the beginning of the opening of the Imperial Diet, there was often conflict between the Han-dominated government who support the detached policy, and the government force who was based on the House of Representatives, the Emperor sometimes issued an order and worked as an arbitrator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>また、藩閥政府内の元勲間にあった政策や感情の上での対立においても、天皇は宥和に努めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor also worked to suppress the political or emotional conflict between the elder statesmen of the han-dominated government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor also worked to suppress political or emotional conflicts between the elder statesmen of the han-dominated government.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor also worked to suppress political or emotional conflicts between the elder statesmen of the han-dominated government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>列強への道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The history to become the Great Powers</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The history, on the way to become a Great Power</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The history, on the way to become a Great Power</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="38">
<j>日本が初めて直面した近代戦争である日清戦争と日露戦争では、天皇は大本営で直接戦争指導に当たった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the first War Japan was involved, the Sinto-Japanese War and the Russo-Japanese War, the Emperor directly trained the soldiers at the Imperial headquarters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the first War Japan was involved in, the Sino-Japanese War and the Russo-Japanese War, the Emperor directly trained the soldiers at the Imperial headquarters.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the first War Japan was involved in, the Sino-Japanese War and the Russo-Japanese War, the Emperor directly trained the soldiers at the Imperial headquarters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>また、外交上は日英同盟を締結し、列強の一員たるべく、軍事的・経済的な国力の増強を図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor concluded the Anglo-Japanese Alliance in diplomatic relations and tried to strength the military and the financial power as the member of the Great Power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor concluded an Anglo-Japanese Alliance in diplomatic relations and tried to strengthen the military and the financial power as the member of the Great Powers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor concluded an Anglo-Japanese Alliance in diplomatic relations and tried to strengthen the military and the financial power as the member of the Great Powers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>日露戦争後は、韓国併合や満州経営を進め、日本を植民帝国へと膨張させる政策を採用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Russo-Japanese War, the Emperor proceeded the policy of the annexation of Korean and ruling Manchuria to expand Japan into the Colonial empire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Russo-Japanese War, the Emperor proceeded with the policy of annexing of Korea and ruling Manchuria to expand Japan&apos;s Colonial empire.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Russo-Japanese War, the Emperor proceeded with the policy of annexing of Korea and ruling Manchuria to expand Japan&apos;s Colonial empire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="41">
<j>明治44年（1911年）には、開国以来の懸案であった条約改正を完了させ、名実共に日本は列強の一員となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1911 he completed the revision of a treaty which had been the big headache since Japan opened a country to foreign trade and diplomatic relations, as a result, Japan became a member of the Great Powers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1911 he completed the revision of a treaty which had been a big headache since Japan opened a country to foreign trade and diplomatic relations, as a result, Japan became a member of the Great Powers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1911 he completed the revision of a treaty which had been a big headache since Japan opened a country to foreign trade and diplomatic relations, as a result, Japan became a member of the Great Powers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>崩御（死去）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Meiji&apos;s death</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Meiji&apos;s death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Meiji&apos;s death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="42">
<j>明治45年（1912年）7月30日、持病の糖尿病が悪化し、尿毒症を併発して崩御した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 30, 1912, he got sick with his chronic illness, diabetes, which then led to uremia and he died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 30, 1912, he became sick with a chronic illness, diabetes, which then led to uremia and he died.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 30, 1912, he became sick with a chronic illness, diabetes, which then led to uremia and he died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="43">
<j>なお、実際の崩御は「7月29日午後10時43分頃」と言われているが、宮内省告示に拠る崩御日時は「7月30日午前0時43分」となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way actual time and date of his death was said to be &apos;on July 29th, around 10 o&apos;clock forty three minutes in the afternoon&apos;, however the officially announced date and time by the Department of the Imperial Household was &apos;on July 30th, twelve o&apos;clock forty three minutes in the morning.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The actual time and date of his death was said to be &apos;on July 29th, around 10 o&apos;clock forty three minutes in the afternoon&apos;, however the officially announced date and time by the Department of the Imperial Household was &apos;on July 30th, twelve o&apos;clock forty three minutes in the morning.&apos;</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The actual time and date of his death was said to be &apos;on July 29, around 10 o&apos;clock forty three minutes in the afternoon,&apos; however the officially announced date and time by the Department of the Imperial Household was &apos;on July 30, twelve o&apos;clock forty three minutes in the morning.&apos;</e>
<cmt>日付表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>これは建前上、崩御当日に（皇太子嘉仁親王が践祚して新帝となる）一連の宮中儀式を執り行なったということにせねばならなかったからだと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was presumed that they had to considered that they were supposed to hold the series of Imperial event (Crown Prince, Imperial Prince Yoshihito to succeed to the throne and become new Emperor) on the day when the Emperor died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was presumed to be because they had to consider they were supposed to hold a series of Imperial events (Crown Prince, Imperial Prince Yoshihito to succeed to the throne and become the new Emperor) on the day when the Emperor died.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was presumed to be because they had to consider they were supposed to hold a series of Imperial events (Crown Prince, Imperial Prince Yoshihito to succeed to the throne and become the new Emperor) on the day when the Emperor died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="45">
<j>同年（大正元年）9月13日、東京・青山の陸軍演習（現在の神宮外苑）に於いて大喪の礼が執り行なわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 13 in the same year, the Rites of an Imperial Funeral was held at Rukugun (the Army) Enshu in Aoyama, Tokyo. (current Jungu Gaien (the Outer Gardens of the Meiji Shrine)</e>
<cmt>陸軍演習→ 定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 13 in the same year, the Rites of an Imperial Funeral were held at Rukugun (the Army) Enshu in Aoyama, Tokyo. (current Jungu Gaien (the Outer Gardens of the Meiji Shrine)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 13 in the same year, the Rites of an Imperial Funeral were held at Rikugun (the Army) Enshu in Aoyama, Tokyo (current Jingu Gaien (the Outer Gardens of the Meiji Shrine)).</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動スペル修正)補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>大葬終了後、明治天皇の柩は霊柩車に乗せられ、東海道本線経由で京都南郊の伏見桃山陵に運ばれ、9月14日に埋葬された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Emperor&apos;s funeral Emperor Meiji&apos;s coffin was put on a hearse and it was carried to the Fushimi Momoyama Mausoleum in the southern suburb of Kyoto via the Tokaido Main Line and buried on September 14.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Emperor&apos;s funeral, Emperor Meiji&apos;s coffin was put on a hearse and it was carried to the Fushimi Momoyama Mausoleum in the southern suburb of Kyoto via the Tokaido Main Line and buried on September 14.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Emperor&apos;s funeral, Emperor Meiji&apos;s coffin was put on a hearse and it was carried to the Fushimi Momoyama Mausoleum in the southern suburb of Kyoto via the Tokaido Main Line and buried on September 14.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>なお、明治天皇大喪の為にしつらえた葬儀の跡地には『聖徳記念絵画館』が建てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way there was a &quot;Seitoku Kinen Kaigakan (Meiji Memorial Picture Gallery) was built where the place which was prepared for Emperor Meiji&apos;s Imperial funeral.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a &quot;Seitoku Kinen Kaigakan (Meiji Memorial Picture Gallery) built in the place that was prepared for Emperor Meiji&apos;s Imperial funeral.</e>
<cmt>redundancy, wordiness, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a &quot;Seitoku Kinen Kaigakan&quot; (Meiji Memorial Picture Gallery) built in the place that was prepared for Emperor Meiji&apos;s Imperial funeral.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="48">
<j>人柄と影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor&apos;s personality and his influence</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor&apos;s personality and his influence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor&apos;s personality and his influence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="49">
<j>明治天皇は、近代の天皇制が確立した時期の天皇である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Meiji was the Emperor during the time the modern Emperor system was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Meiji was the Emperor during a time when the modern Emperor system was established.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Meiji was the Emperor during a time when the modern Emperor system was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>若年で即位して以来、大政奉還、王政復古と戊辰戦争、明治維新、日清戦争、日露戦争など、激動の幕末から明治時代を経験し、明治新政府、近代国家日本の指導者、象徴として、絶対君主として国民から畏敬された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He succeeded to the throne since he was young, then he experienced Taiseihokan (the return of political power to the Emperor by the Tokugawa Shogunate), Oseifukko (the restoration of Imperial rule), the Boshin War, the Meiji Restoration, the Sino-Japanese War and the Russo-Japanese War, difficult times from the the last days of the bakufu era through to the Meiji period, and he was respected by the nation as the leader of the modern Japanese nation and symbol, as a sovereign.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He succeeded to the throne when he was young, then he experienced Taiseihokan (the return of political power to the Emperor by the Tokugawa Shogunate), Oseifukko (the restoration of Imperial rule), the Boshin War, the Meiji Restoration, the Sino-Japanese War and the Russo-Japanese War, difficult times from the the last days of the bakufu era through to the Meiji period, and he was respected by the nation as the leader of the modern Japanese nation and a symbol, as a sovereign.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He succeeded to the throne when he was young, then he experienced Taiseihokan (the return of political power to the Emperor by the Tokugawa Shogunate), Oseifukko (the restoration of Imperial rule), the Boshin War, the Meiji Restoration, the Sino-Japanese War and the Russo-Japanese War, difficult times from the last days of the bakufu era through to the Meiji period, and he was respected by the nation as the leader of the modern Japanese nation and a symbol, as a sovereign.</e>
<cmt>the削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>日常生活は質素を旨とし、自己を律すること峻厳にして、天皇としての威厳の保持に努めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His policy of his everyday life was to live frugal and disciplined himself strictly, he tried to keep his authority as an emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His policy of his everyday life was to live frugal and disciplined himself strictly, he tried to keep his authority as an emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His policy of his everyday life was to live frugal and disciplined himself strictly, he tried to keep his authority as an emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>また、乗馬と和歌を好み、文化的な素養にも富んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was fond of horse riding and making waka poems, he had talent in arts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was fond of horseback riding and writing waka poems, he had talent in the arts.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was fond of horseback riding and writing waka poems, he had talent in the arts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>しかし、普段は茶目っ気のある性格で、皇后や女官達は自分が考えたあだ名で呼んでいたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But he had another aspect that he was playful, he called his Empress or court ladies with nicknames that he named.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But he had another aspect of being playful, he called his Empress or court ladies by nicknames that he thought of.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But he had another aspect of being playful, he called his Empress or court ladies by nicknames that he thought of.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="54">
<j>若い頃（とりわけ明治10年代）には、侍補で親政論者である漢学者元田永孚や佐々木高行の影響を強く受けて、西洋の文物に対しては懐疑的であり、また自身が政局の主導権を掌握しようと積極的であった時期がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he was young, (especially in the Meiji 10&apos;s) he was skeptical about western literature since he was influenced by his jiho (aide) and also scholars of the Chinese classics, Nagazane MOTODA and Takayuki SASAKI, there was a period when he himself was keen to take control of the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he was young, (especially in the Meiji 10&apos;s) he was skeptical about western literature since he was influenced by his jiho (aide) and also scholars of the Chinese classics, Nagazane MOTODA and Takayuki SASAKI, there was a period when he himself was keen to take control of the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During his younger days (especially between 1876 to 1885), he was greatly influenced by Nagazane MOTODA and Takayuki SASAKI, scholars of the Chinese classics who acted as his jiho (aides) and were supporters of direct imperial rule, and there was a period when he was skeptical about western literature and tried to actively gain control of the government.</e>
<cmt>左記赤字部分が訳出されておりません。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>元田永孚の覚書（「古稀之記」）によると、天皇は伊藤博文の欠点を「西洋好き」と評していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Nagazane MOTODA&apos;s memorandum, (&apos;Koki no ki&apos;), the Emperor mentioned Hitobumi ITO&apos;s weak point as &apos; a man who affects a European manner&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Nagazane MOTODA&apos;s memorandum, (&apos;Koki no ki&apos;), the Emperor mentioned Hitobumi ITO&apos;s weak point as &apos;a man who affects a European manner.&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Nagazane MOTODA&apos;s memorandum, (&apos;Koki no ki&apos;), the Emperor mentioned Hirobumi ITO&apos;s weak point as &apos;a man who affects a European manner.&apos;</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>特に教育に関しては儒学を基本にすべしとする元田の最大の理解者でもあり、教育行政のトップに田中不二麿や森有礼のような西洋的な教育論者が任命された事には不快感を抱いていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially when it came to education, he duly understood MOTODA&apos;s philosophy based on the Confucianism, he was frustrated when Fujimaro TANAKA and Arinori MORI who were both educational debaters prefer western way of thinking, were appointed as educational administrators.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially when it came to education, he duly understood MOTODA&apos;s philosophy based on Confucianism, he was frustrated when Fujimaro TANAKA and Arinori MORI who were both educational debaters preferred the western way of thinking, and were appointed as educational administrators.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially when it came to education, he duly understood Motoda&apos;s philosophy based on Confucianism, he was frustrated when Fujimaro TANAKA and Arinori MORI who were both educational debaters preferred the western way of thinking, were appointed as educational administrators.</e>
<cmt>名前表記and 削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>特に明治17年（1884年）4月下旬に森が文部省の顧問である御用掛に任命される事を知ると、「病気」を口実に伊藤（宮内卿兼務）ら政府高官との面会を一切拒絶し、6月25日まで2ヶ月近くも公務を放棄して引籠もって承認を遅らせている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially there was one occasion when the Emperor knew Mori was appointed to a general affairs official of the Imperial Household of advisor of the the Ministry of Education in the late April, 1884, he refused to see anyone of high officials of the government such as Ito (he also worked as kunai Kyo (the director of the Imperial House hold) using an excuse him being sick, he did not show his appearance to the public and cancelled his government affairs for more than two months until 25 June, since he did not wish to approve Ito&apos;s appointment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially there was one occasion when the Emperor knew Mori was appointed as a general affairs official of the Imperial Household, an advisor to the the Ministry of Education in the late April, 1884, he refused to see any high officials of the government such as Ito (he also worked as kunai Kyo (the director of the Imperial House hold) using the excuse of being sick, he did not appear in public and cancelled his government affairs for more than two months until 25 June, since he did not wish to approve Ito&apos;s appointment.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially there was one occasion when the Emperor knew Mori was appointed as a general affairs official of the Imperial Household, an advisor to the Ministry of Education in the late April, 1884, he refused to see any high officials of the government such as Ito (he also worked as kunai Kyo (the director of the Imperial House hold)) using the excuse of being sick, he did not appear in public and cancelled his government affairs for more than two months until 25 June, since he did not wish to approve Ito&apos;s appointment.</e>
<cmt>)補足スペース削除the削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>こうした事態を憂慮した伊藤は初代内閣総理大臣就任とともに引き続き初代宮内大臣を兼ねて天皇の意向を内閣_(日本)に伝えることで天皇の内閣への不信感を和らげ、伊藤の目指す立憲国家建設への理解を求めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After considering above fact, Ito seeked Emperor&apos;s understanding of his intention to establish constitutional government, he tried to take Emperor&apos;s suspicion towards the Cabinet by passing Emperor&apos;s intention to the Cabinet after he officially became the first Prime Minister and successively became the first Minister of the Imperial House Hold.</e>
<cmt>宮内卿→kunai kyo (the director of the Imperial House hold [定訳不明])</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After considering above, Ito sought the Emperor&apos;s understanding of his intention to establish a constitutional government, he tried to take Emperor&apos;s suspicion towards the Cabinet into consideration by passing the Emperor&apos;s intentions to the Cabinet after he officially became the first successful Minister of the Imperial House Hold.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity, wordiness, redundancy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concerned about this, Ito told the Cabinet (Japan) of the emperor&apos;s intention once he had been appointed to serve as the first Prime Minister while also serving as the Minister of the Imperial Household at the same time in order to quell the emperor&apos;s distrust of the Cabinet and gain his acceptance for the constitutional government Ito sought to implement.</e>
<cmt>左記赤字部分が訳出されておりません。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>その結果、明治19年（1886年）6月23日に宮中で皇后以下の婦人が洋装することを許可し、9月7日には天皇と内閣の間で「機務六条」という契約を交わされて天皇は内閣の要請がない限り閣議に出席しないことなどを約束（「明治天皇紀」）して天皇自らが親政の可能性を放棄したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of above, the women in the Imperial Palace who were lower rank than Empress were allowed to wear western clothes on June 23, 1886, and the Emperor agreed to the contract of &apos;Kimu Rokujo&apos; by promising not to attend the Cabinet meeting unless asked to join in by the Cabinet (Meiji Tenno ki), the Emperor had to gave up the possibility to rule the government directly.</e>
<cmt>機務六条,明治天皇紀→kimu rokujo [定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, women in the Imperial Palace who ranked lower than the Empress were allowed to wear western clothes on June 23, 1886, and the Emperor agreed to the contract of &apos;Kimu Rokujo&apos; by promising not to attend the Cabinet meeting unless asked to join in by the Cabinet (Meiji Tenno ki), the Emperor had to gave up the possibility to rule the government directly.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, women in the Imperial Palace who ranked lower than the Empress were allowed to wear western clothes on June 23, 1886, and the Emperor agreed to the contract of &apos;Kimu Rokujo&apos; on September 7, by promising not to attend the Cabinet meeting unless asked to join in by the Cabinet (Meiji Tenno ki), the Emperor had to give up the possibility to rule the government directly.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正September 7補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="60">
<j>写真嫌いは有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was well known that the Emperor Meiji did not like to be taken photograph of his.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was well known that Emperor Meiji did not like to have his photograph taken.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was well known that Emperor Meiji did not like to have his photograph taken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>現在最も有名なエドアルド・キヨッソーネによる肖像画は写真嫌いの明治天皇の壮年時の「御真影」がどうしても必要となり、苦心の末に作成されたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The most famous Emperor&apos;s portlate at present by Edoardo Chiossone, was painted as the result of a lot of hard work with the Emperor who did not liked be painted or photographed, since Emperor&apos;s portlate in his prime was badly needed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The most famous Emperor&apos;s portrate at present by Edoardo Chiossone, was painted as the result of a lot of hard work with an Emperor who did not liked to pose for a painting or be photographed, even though the Emperor&apos;s portrate in his prime was badly needed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The most famous Emperor&apos;s portrait at present by Edoardo Chiossone, was painted as the result of a lot of hard work with an Emperor who did not liked to pose for a painting or be photographed, even though the Emperor&apos;s portrait in his prime was badly needed.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>ただ、最晩年の明治44年（1911年）に軍事演習閲兵中の姿を遠くから隠し撮りした写真が残っており、これが明治天皇が最後に撮影された姿と言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When it was his last year in 1911, (Just one year before he died in 1911) there was the Emperor&apos;s photograph secretly taken from distance while he was reviewing troops in the military exercise, this was said to be the last photograph taken before he died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When it was his last year in 1911, (Just one year before he died in 1911) the Emperor&apos;s photograph was secretly taken from a distance while he was reviewing troops on the military exercise, this was said to be the last photograph taken before he died.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When it was his last year in 1911, the Emperor&apos;s photograph was secretly taken from a distance while he was reviewing troops on the military exercise, this was said to be the last photograph taken before he died.</e>
<cmt>(Just one year before he died in 1911) この英語説明は必要ないと思いますので、削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="63">
<j>「明治天皇は明治国家そのものであり、明治天皇の死は明治国家の終焉」と認識されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was recognized that &apos;Emperor Meiji represented the Meiji nation itself and the Emperor&apos;s death was the end of the Meiji nation.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was recognized that &apos;Emperor Meiji represented the Meiji nation itself and the Emperor&apos;s death was the end of the Meiji nation.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was recognized that &apos;Emperor Meiji represented the Meiji nation itself and the Emperor&apos;s death was the end of the Meiji nation.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>大喪の日には、陸軍大将・乃木希典夫妻を初め、多くの人が殉死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the day when the Emperor Meiji&apos;s Imperial funeral was held, many people followed their master (Emperor Meiji) to the grave, such as the Military Minister, Maresuke Nogi and his wife.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the day of Emperor Meiji&apos;s Imperial funeral, many people followed their master (Emperor Meiji) to the grave, such as the Military Minister, Maresuke Nogi and his wife.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the day of Emperor Meiji&apos;s Imperial funeral, many people followed their master (Emperor Meiji) to the grave, such as the Military Minister, Maresuke Nogi and his wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>明治天皇を中軸として作り上げられた明治国家は、この後、変容していくこととなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Meiji nation established having Emperor Meiji in the central figure, was going to change after this period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Meiji nation established having Emperor Meiji as the central figure, was going to change after this period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Meiji nation established having Emperor Meiji as the central figure, was going to change after this period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="66">
<j>非西欧諸国の中で近代化に成功した日本の君主ということで、海外での評価は日本国内以上に高く、エチオピアのハイレ・セラシエ1世やパラグアイのアルフレド・ストロエスネル、イラクのサダム・フセインなど、明治天皇を尊敬する人は多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Emperor Meiji was respected as the sovereign as non western countries, he was highly regarded in overseas, more that he was in Japan by the people such as Haile Selassie Ⅰin Ethiopia, Alfredo Stroessner in Paraguay, Saddam Husayn in Iraq.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Emperor Meiji was respected as a sovereign, as for non western countries, he was highly regarded overseas, more than he was in Japan, by the people such as Haile SelassieⅠin Ethiopia, Alfredo Stroessner in Paraguay, Saddam Husain in Iraq.</e>
<cmt>spelling, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Emperor Meiji was respected as a sovereign, as for non western countries, he was highly regarded overseas, more than he was in Japan, by the people such as Haile SelassieⅠin Ethiopia, Alfredo Stroessner in Paraguay, Saddam Husain in Iraq.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="67">
<j>著名な御製</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The famous poems</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Famous poems</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Famous poems</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>明治天皇は和歌を好み、多くの御製（天皇の自作和歌）を遺している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Meiji was fond of waka poems and left many poems of his own. (Emperor&apos;s own poems)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Meiji was fond of waka poems and left many poems of his own. (Emperor&apos;s own poems)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Meiji was fond of waka poems and left many poems of his own (Emperor&apos;s own poems).</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>その数は、約93,000首を超えると言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said they were more than ninety three thousand poems.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said there were more than ninety three thousand poems.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said there were more than ninety three thousand poems.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="70">
<j>よきをとり　あしきをすてて外国（とつくに）に　おとらぬ国となすよしもがな</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When I think of leaving Japan for overseas just by taking good things and leave bad things behind, I wish Japan become good country as the one in overseas.</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When I think about leaving Japan for overseas just by taking the good things and leaving the bad things behind, I wish for Japan to become a good country like those overseas.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When I think about leaving Japan for overseas just by taking the good things and leaving the bad things behind, I wish for Japan to become a good country like those overseas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>よもの海　みなはらからと思ふ世に　など波風のたちさわぐらむ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I wonder why there is trouble happen although all the countries overseas in any directions are considered to be all brothers and sisters in this world.</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I wonder why there is trouble, even though all the countries overseas in all directions are considered to be brothers and sisters in this world.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I wonder why there is trouble, even though all the countries overseas in all directions are considered to be brothers and sisters in this world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>系譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="72">
<j>父は孝明天皇、母は中山慶子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Emperor Komei, mother was Yoshiko Nakayama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Emperor Komei, mother was Yoshiko Nakayama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Emperor Komei, mother was Yoshiko NAKAYAMA.</e>
<cmt>人名表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>父・孝明帝の正妃・九条夙子（英照皇太后）を「実母」と公称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father, Emperor Komei&apos;s Empress, Asako KUJO (the Empress Dowager Eisho) was officially called &apos;real mother&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father, Emperor Komei&apos;s Empress, Asako KUJO (the Empress Dowager Eisho) was officially called the &apos;real mother.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father, Emperor Komei&apos;s Empress, Asako KUJO (the Empress Dowager Eisho) was officially called the &apos;real mother.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="74">
<j>乳母は当初「伏屋みの」だったが「乳の質が良くない」として1年余りで「木村らい」に変わり乳児期を過ごす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His nurse was initially &apos;Mino Fuseya&apos; but as she was not able to breast feed the Emperor with good quality milk, within one year the nurse was changed to &apos;Rai KIMURA&apos; while the Emperor was a baby.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His nurse was initially &apos;Mino Fuseya&apos; but as she was not able to breast feed the Emperor with good quality milk, within one year the nurse was changed to &apos;Rai KIMURA&apos; while the Emperor was a baby.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His wet nurse was initially &apos;Mino FUSEYA&apos; but as she was not able to breast feed the Emperor with good quality milk, within one year the nurse was changed to &apos;Rai KIMURA&apos; while the Emperor was a baby.</e>
<cmt>用語統一人名表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="75">
<j>皇子女</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Princesses</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Princesses</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Princesses</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>皇后は一条美子（昭憲皇太后）だが、子女はいない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Empress was Haruko ICHIJO (the Empress Dowager Shoken) but she did not have any Princes or Princesses with the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Empress was Haruko ICHIJO (the Empress Dowager Shoken) but she did not have any Princes or Princesses with the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Empress was Haruko ICHIJO (the Empress Dowager Shoken) but she did not have any Princes or Princesses with the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>側室との間の子女は以下の通り。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor had the following Princes and the Princesses with Emperor&apos;s mistresses.</e>
<cmt>子女名が抜けています</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor had the following Princes and the Princesses with his mistresses.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor had the following Princes and the Princesses with his mistresses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>在位中の元号</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The eras during his reign</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The eras during his reign</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The eras during his reign</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="78">
<j>慶応</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keio</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keio</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keio</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="79">
<j>明治</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meiji</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meiji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meiji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>諡号・追号</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Posthumous name, Tsuigo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Posthumous name, Tsuigo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Posthumous name, Tsuigo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="80">
<j>在位期間の元号からとって、明治天皇と追号された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was given Tsuigo of Emperor Meiji, came from the name of a Japanese era while he was in power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was given Tsuigo of Emperor Meiji, came from the name of a Japanese era while he was in power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was given Tsuigo of Emperor Meiji, came from the name of a Japanese era while he was in power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>明治天皇の代から、一人の天皇在位中に元号を変えず、またその元号を追号とする一世一元の制を採用したので、以後、諡（おくりな）を持つ天皇はいない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the era of Emperor Meiji, Issei Ichigen system (the practice of assigning one era name to the reign of each emperor) was introduced, which the one era name remain the same for each emperor and the name of the era was given to the Emperor as Tsuigo, since then there were no emperors who had the posthumous name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the era of Emperor Meiji, the Issei Ichigen system (the practice of assigning one era name to the reign of each emperor) was introduced, which the one era name remain the same for each emperor and the name of the era was given to the Emperor as Tsuigo, since then there were no emperors who had a posthumous name.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the era of Emperor Meiji, the Issei Ichigen system was introduced, which the one era name remain the same for each emperor and the name of the era was given to the Emperor as Tsuigo, since then there were no emperors who had a posthumous name.</e>
<cmt>(the practice of assigning one era name to the reign of each emperor)同じセル内に説明があるので、削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>（追号も諡号の一種とする説もあるが、厳密には異なる）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(sometimes Tsuigo is considered to be a type of posthumous name, however strictly speaking these are two different names)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(sometimes Tsuigo is considered to be a type of posthumous name, however strictly speaking these are two different names)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(sometimes Tsuigo is considered to be a type of posthumous name, however strictly speaking these are two different names)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>霊廟・陵墓</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial Mausoleum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Mausoleum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Mausoleum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="83">
<j>京都府京都市伏見区桃山町にある上円下方墳の伏見桃山陵（ふしみのももやまのみささぎ）に葬られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor was entombed in Fushimi momoyamano misasagi of a tomb with a dome-shaped mound on a square base at Momoyama-cho Town, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor was entombed in Fushimi momoyamano misasagi in a tomb with a dome-shaped mound on a square base at Momoyama-cho Town, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor was entombed in Fushimi momoyamano misasagi in a tomb with a dome-shaped mound on a square base at Momoyama-cho, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>住所表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>京都（畿内）に葬られた、最後の天皇である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the last Emperor who was entombed in Kyoto. (near Imperial Palace)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the last Emperor who was entombed in Kyoto. (near the Imperial Palace)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the last Emperor who was entombed in Kyoto (near the Imperial Palace).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除ピリオド位置</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="85">
<j>大正9年（1920年）、明治神宮に祀られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was enshrined in Meiji-jingu Shrine in 1290.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was enshrined in Meiji-jingu Shrine in 1290.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was enshrined in Meiji-jingu Shrine in 1290.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>その後、関東神宮（在関東州・廃社）、また朝鮮神宮（在ソウル・廃社）などの海外神社に多く祀られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that he was enshrined in Kanto-jingu Shrine (the current Kwantung Leased Territory, abolished) and Chosen-jingu Shrine (current Seoul, abolished) or other many shrines in overseas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that he was enshrined in Kanto-jingu Shrine (the currently Kwantung Leased Territory, abolished) and Chosen-jingu Shrine (currently Seoul, abolished) or other many shrines overseas.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that he was enshrined in Kanto-jingu Shrine (the currently Kwantung Leased Territory, abolished) and Chosen-jingu Shrine (currently Seoul, abolished) or other many shrines overseas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>戦後、北海道神宮（在札幌）にも合祀されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the War, he was enshrined in Hokkaido-jingu Shrine (current Sapporo)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the War, he was enshrined in Hokkaido-jingu Shrine (currently Sapporo).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the War, he was enshrined in Hokkaido-jingu Shrine (currently Sapporo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>全ての歴代天皇は皇居の宮中三殿の一つの皇霊殿に祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All the past Emperors are enshrined in Koreiden, one of the Three Palace Sanctuaries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All the past Emperors are enshrined in Koreiden, one of the Three Palace Sanctuaries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All the past Emperors are enshrined in Koreiden, one of the Three Palace Sanctuaries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="89">
<j>明治天皇替玉説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The theory of Emperor Meiji&apos;s substitute</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The theory of Emperor Meiji&apos;s substitute</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The theory of Emperor Meiji&apos;s substitute</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="90">
<j>明治天皇（睦仁親王）は暗殺され、南朝の血をひく長州の大室寅之祐にすり替えられたという説があるが、孝明天皇暗殺説よりも信憑性は薄いと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a theory that Emperor Meiji (Imperial Prince Mutsuhito) was assassinated and Toranosuke OMURO of Choshu who had the blood line of Southern Dynasty played his substitute, but there is not much credibility on this compare to the theory of Emperor Komei being assassinated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a theory that Emperor Meiji (Imperial Prince Mutsuhito) was assassinated and Toranosuke OMURO of Choshu who had the blood line of the Southern Court played his substitute, but there is not much credibility about this when compared to the theory of Emperor Komei being assassinated.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a theory that Emperor Meiji (Imperial Prince Mutsuhito) was assassinated and Toranosuke OMURO of Choshu who had the blood line of the Southern Court played his substitute, but there is not much credibility about this when compared to the theory of Emperor Komei being assassinated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nnh(id:474), 123456(id:67803), Sy-sy(id:116336), つくば(id:83270), 経済準学士(id:22656), Cprobot(id:97843), Eskimbot(id:29676), Kamakura(id:472), Abismo(id:54591), Arpeggio(id:9385), るがこむ(id:181), Huugo(id:61491), Shin-改(id:9914), Keiryou(id:136539), A-Taul(id:41790), 名無し(id:7386), Haco(id:26084), Yas(id:739), Maakun(id:16735), 遠野能史(id:86555), Mikomaid(id:56139), DCyokohama(id:26779), M-sho-gun(id:88956), Krs13(id:23984), Deepimpact(id:129352), いろはにほへと(id:89648), Carbuncle(id:346), Balmung0731(id:99201), Bletilla(id:38919), Stanislaus(id:1806), 松茸(id:27535), 2ch(id:213), L III (N)(id:72793), Martin(id:6394), Kagetudo(id:163875), Xmaseve(id:101900), Mx-k(id:22681), D5(id:60352), Tietew(id:4054), 総督(id:124846), ひろくん(id:79638), Аки(id:75169), トホホ川(id:50502), 伏儀(id:142093), 王八蛋(id:107410), 唐棣色(id:64681), けんち(id:5147), NIKE(id:16342), Suisui(id:69), Zell(id:23939), TT(id:46431), Aotake(id:34929), Charenji(id:7908), 鹿両性証明(id:71252), Rai koku(id:1661), ShikiH(id:181574), ML JIN(id:140817), Nakaoka7675(id:39645), Johncapistrano(id:969), 薔薇騎士団(id:169274), Huaquero(id:128772), 下総大納言(id:43461), 玄史生(id:43670), Nevylax(id:38464), Kadzuwo(id:3701), Sho-gun(id:74168), 16toki(id:60127), Rei-bot(id:94097), Loveless(id:129239), こぶまき(id:38278), 竹麦魚(id:11012), Themeofn(id:52958), LERK(id:4460), Izayohi(id:13095), Sakura-no-kuni(id:115977), Kcm367(id:97653), BlackPonix(id:20108), 福いたら里(id:33988), Samuel(id:344), 水野白楓(id:22811), Race(id:131322), 愛国の歌人(id:173428), Aphaia(id:3132), ( ^ω^)(id:71899), Daidouji(id:59718), Shutok(id:202467), G7zs(id:38568), Try2004(id:10561), VolkovBot(id:105371), Geogie(id:143809), Miya(id:1881), Bee(id:1189), Huzzlet the bot(id:85960), Earth01(id:61620), Louperibot(id:128971), きまま(id:183217), SieBot(id:126695), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>