<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>称制</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shosei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shosei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shosei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>称制（しょうせい）とは先帝崩御後、新帝（主に皇太子または皇后）が即位の式を挙げずに政務を執ること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shosei means new emperor (mainly Crown Prince or Empress) start to rule the government without having enthronement ceremony after the former emperor die.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shosei means new emperor (mainly Crown Prince or Empress) starts to rule the government without having an enthronement ceremony after the former emperor died.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shosei means new emperor (mainly Crown Prince or Empress) starts to rule the government without having an enthronement ceremony after the former emperor died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日本では飛鳥時代に中大兄皇子と持統天皇の二例が見られるが、どちらも日本書紀では一見してほとんど事実上の天皇と同然に記述されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were two examples of Shosei in Japan, Prince Naka no Oe and Emperor Jito in Asuka period, both are recorded in the &quot;Chronicles of Japan&quot; as if they were practically real Emperors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were two examples of Shosei in Japan, Prince Naka no Oe and Emperor Jito in Asuka period, both are recorded in the &quot;Chronicles of Japan&quot; as if they were practically real Emperors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were two examples of Shosei in Japan, Prince Naka no Oe and Emperor Jito in Asuka period, both are recorded in the &quot;Chronicles of Japan&quot; as if they were practically real Emperors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>日本の場合摂政と似ているが、摂政の場合、天皇が同時に存在しているが、称制の場合は、天皇がいない（称制している本人が事実上の天皇か天皇に準ずる存在）のが大きな違いである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, it is similar to Sessho (regency) although Emperor also exist with the Sessho, the big difference between Sessho and Shosei is there is no Emperor in case of Shosei. (the person who rule the Shosei is practically Emperor or a person who has political control equivalent to Emperor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, it is similar to Sessho (regency) although the Emperor also exist with the Sessho, the big difference between Sessho and Shosei is there is no Emperor in case of Shosei. (the one who rules Shosei is practically the Emperor or a person who has political control equivalent to Emperor)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, it is similar to Sessho (regency) although the Emperor also exist with the Sessho, the big difference between Sessho and Shosei is there is no Emperor in case of Shosei (the one who rules Shosei is practically the Emperor or a person who has political control equivalent to Emperor).</e>
<cmt>括弧書きの位置を訂正。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>中国の称制</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shosei in China</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shosei in China</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shosei in China</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>称制はもともと中国の漢文の言葉である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The word, Shosei originally came from Chinese kanbun. (Sino-Japanese)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The word, Shosei originally came from Chinese kanbun. (Sino-Japanese)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word, Shosei originally came from Chinese kanbun. (Sino-Japanese)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>先王が崩御して、新王が幼少である場合、太后（母后）が実権を握って政治を代行することをいう（垂簾聴政）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is used when the Empress takes control of the politics in case the new emperor is too young to do so after the death of the former Emperor. (Reign behind the curtain)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is used when the Empress takes control of politics if the new emperor is too young to do so after the death of the former Emperor (Reign behind the curtain).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is used when the Empress takes control of politics if the new emperor is too young to do so after the death of the former Emperor (Reign behind the curtain).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>古く春秋時代からみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It started in Chunqiu era in old times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It started in the Chunqiu era in olden times.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It started in the Chunqiu era in olden times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>日本と異なり、中国の場合は称制する者（母后）と別に正統の君主（幼君）が同時に存在しなければならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In China the structure was different from Japan, there should have been the Empress who rule the actual Shosei and the legitimate monarch (young emperor) exist at the same time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In China the structure was different from Japan, there should have been the Empress who ruled the actual Shosei while the legitimate monarch (young emperor) existed at the same time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In China the structure was different from Japan, there should have been the Empress who ruled the actual Shosei while the legitimate monarch (young emperor) existed at the same time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>日本の称制</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese Shosei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese Shosei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese Shosei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>日本においては、中大兄皇子（舒明天皇・斉明天皇の皇子で後の天智天皇）と持統天皇（天智天皇の皇女・天武天皇の皇后で後の持統天皇）の2例を「称制」としているが、この他に神功皇后・飯豊皇女・阿閉皇女の計3例のケースも称制に相当すると言う考えがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan there were two examples of Shosei which were, Prince Naka no Oe (Emperor Jomei and Empress Saimei&apos;s Prince, later called Emperor Tenchi (Tenji)) and Emperor Jito (Emperor Tenchi&apos;s Princess, Emperor Tenmu&apos;s Empress and later called Emperor Jito), however there are some opinions that the three examples of Empress Jingu and Iitoyo no Himemiko/Princess Iitoyo and Ahe no Himemiko/Princess Ahe were considered as Shosei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan there were two examples of Shosei which were, Prince Naka no Oe (Emperor Jomei and Empress Saimei&apos;s Prince, later called Emperor Tenchi or Tenji) and Emperor Jito (Emperor Tenchi&apos;s Princess, Emperor Tenmu&apos;s Empress and later called Emperor Jito), however there are some opinions that the three examples of Empress Jingu and Iitoyo no Himemiko/Princess Iitoyo and Ahe no Himemiko/Princess Ahe were considered as Shosei.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan there were two examples of Shosei which were, Prince Naka no Oe (Emperor Jomei and Empress Saimei&apos;s Prince, later called Emperor Tenchi or Tenji) and Emperor Jito (Emperor Tenchi&apos;s Princess, Emperor Tenmu&apos;s Empress and later called Emperor Jito), however there are some opinions that the three examples of Empress Jingu and Iitoyo no Himemiko (Princess Iitoyo) and Ahe no Himemiko (Princess Ahe) were considered as Shosei.</e>
<cmt>括弧に入れました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>中大兄皇子の称制</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Naka no Oe&apos;s Shosei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Naka no Oe&apos;s Shosei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Naka no Oe&apos;s Shosei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>斉明天皇は新羅出兵準備中に崩御したが、中大兄皇子は皇太子のまま即位せずに政務を執行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Emperor Jomei died when preparing raising army against Silla (Kingdom), Prince Naka no Oe conducted to rule the government when he was Crown Prince and he did not become Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Emperor Jomei died while raising an army against the Silla Kingdom, Prince Naka no Oe ruled the government when he was Crown Prince even though he did not become Emperor.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Emperor Saimei died while raising an army against the Silla Kingdom, Prince Naka no Oe ruled the government when he was Crown Prince even though he did not become Emperor.</e>
<cmt>Jomei→Saimeiに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>斉明天皇の崩御後も即位を先延ばしにしたが、この間は日本書紀や万葉集によると「中皇命（なかつすめらみこと）」と呼ばれた人物がいたらしく、これは間人皇女（孝徳天皇の皇后）のこととする説が有力である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after Emperor Saimei died, Prince Naka no Oe did not succeed to the throne, according to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) or &quot;The Anthology of Myriad [Ten Thousand] Leaves&quot;, it is said there was a person called &apos;Nakatsusumeramikoto&apos; during this period, there was a strong theory that she was said to be Princess Hashihito. (Emperor Kotoku&apos;s Empress)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after Emperor Saimei died, Prince Naka no Oe did not succeed to the throne, according to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) or &quot;The Anthology of Myriad [Ten Thousand] Leaves,&quot; it is said there was a person called &apos;Nakatsusumeramikoto&apos; during this period, there was a strong theory that she was said to be Princess Hashihito. (Emperor Kotoku&apos;s Empress)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after Emperor Saimei died, Prince Naka no Oe did not succeed to the throne, according to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) or &quot;The Anthology of Myriad [Ten Thousand] Leaves,&quot; it is said there was a person called &apos;Nakatsusumera-mikoto&apos; during this period, there was a strong theory that she was said to be Princess Hashihito (Emperor Kotoku&apos;s Empress).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除。ハイフン補足。括弧書きの位置を訂正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>先帝の后や母后ではなく皇太子の方が実権を握っている点で、中国の称制とは異なるが、まず母后（斉明天皇）のちに先帝の后（孝徳天皇の皇后・間人皇女）を名目上の上位者として立てていたために形式上「称制」という名称が選ばれたのであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Crown Prince had actual political control of the Japanese Shosei, it was different from the one in China which the Empress or the Empress Dowager used to take control of the politics, it is presumed that above case was formally called &apos;Shosei&apos; as firstly the Empress Dowager (Emperor Saimei) was appointed as the nominal highest position followed by former Emperor&apos;s Empress. (Emperor Kotoku&apos;s Empress, Princess Hashihito)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Crown Prince had actual political control of the Japanese Shosei, it was different from the one in China where the Empress or the Empress Dowager used to take control of politics, it is presumed that above case was formally called &apos;Shosei&apos; as the Empress Dowager (Emperor Saimei) was first appointed the nominal highest position followed by former Emperor&apos;s Empress (Emperor Kotoku&apos;s Empress, Princess Hashihito).</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Crown Prince had actual political control of the Japanese Shosei, it was different from the one in China where the Empress or the Empress Dowager used to take control of politics, it is presumed that above case was formally called &apos;Shosei&apos; as the Empress Dowager (Emperor Saimei) was first appointed the nominal highest position followed by former Emperor&apos;s Empress (Emperor Kotoku&apos;s Empress, Princess Hashihito).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>いずれにせよ、中大兄皇子は667年に近江大津宮に遷都し、668年旧正月1月3日にやっと正式に即位した（天智天皇）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In any case, Prince Naka no Oe moved the capital city to Imperial Palace Omi Otsu no Miya in 667, and he finally succeeded to the throne as Emperor Tenchi/Tenji on 3 January, 668.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In any case, Prince Naka no Oe moved the capital city to Imperial Palace Omi Otsu no Miya in 667, and he finally succeeded to the throne as Emperor Tenchi/Tenji on 3 January, 668.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In any case, Prince Naka no Oe moved the capital city to Imperial Palace Omi Otsu no Miya in 667, and he finally succeeded to the throne as Emperor Tenchi/Tenji on 3 January, 668.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>（一説に、中大兄皇子が同母妹の間人皇女と不倫関係を持っていた為に乙巳の変から15年以上経過してもなお即位できなかったとの説や、反対に間人皇女（＝中皇命）は中継ぎの大王として即位していたとの説もある。中大兄皇子が（結果的に）晩年にやっと即位した理由については他にも様々な説がある。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is another theory that Prince Naka no Oe could not succeed to the throne fifteen years after Isshi-no-hen (the Murder in the Year of Isshi), since he had an affair with his real younger sister, Princess Hashihito, or as opposed to this, it was said Princess Hashihito (Nakatsusumera-mikoto) enthroned as a temporal Emperor. There are various theory of the reason why Prince Naka no Oe finally enthroned in his later years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is another theory that Prince Naka no Oe could not succeed to the throne fifteen years after Isshi-no-hen (a Murder in the Year of Isshi), since he had an affair with his real younger sister, Princess Hashihito, or as opposed to this, it was said Princess Hashihito (Nakatsusumera-mikoto) was enthroned as a temporal Emperor. There are various theories concerning the reason why Prince Naka no Oe was finally enthroned in his later years.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(There is another theory that Prince Naka no Oe could not succeed to the throne fifteen years after Isshi-no-hen (a Murder in the Year of Isshi), since he had an affair with his real younger sister, Princess Hashihito, or as opposed to this, it was said Princess Hashihito (Nakatsusumera-mikoto) was enthroned as a temporal Emperor. There are various theories concerning the reason why Prince Naka no Oe was finally enthroned in his later years.)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除。括弧を付けました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>菟野讃良皇后の称制</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uno no Sarara no Himemiko&apos;s Shosei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uno no Sarara no Himemiko&apos;s Shosei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uno no Sarara no Himemiko&apos;s Shosei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>天智天皇崩御後に勃発した壬申の乱に勝利した夫・大海人皇子（天武天皇）崩御後、菟野皇后は息子・草壁皇子への皇位継承を望んでいたのだが、ライバルの大津皇子を自害に追いやった為に却って反発を買い、草壁の凡庸な器量も相まって、草壁を即位させる事が出来なかったため、母后である菟野が政務を執り草壁を支えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Emperor Tenchi/Tenji died, the Junshin war happened and Prince Oama (Emperor Tenmu) won the war, after he died as well, Uni no Sarara no Himemiko wished her son, Prince Kusakabe to succeed to the throne, however she put pressure to Prince Kusakabe&apos;s opposition, Prince Otsu to kill himself and was blamed for it, she was not able to make her wish happen (for Prince Kusakabe to succeed to the throne), also Prince Kusakabe had an ordinary character, (he was not good enough to become Emperor) thus the Empress Dowager, Uno no Sarara no Himemiko took control of the politics to support Prince Kusakabe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Emperor Tenchi/Tenji died, the Junshin war happened and Prince Oama (Emperor Tenmu) won the war, after he died as well, Uni no Sarara no Himemiko wished her son, Prince Kusakabe to succeed to the throne, however she put pressure on Prince Kusakabe&apos;s opposition, Prince Otsu to kill himself and was blamed for it, she was not able to make her wish happen (for Prince Kusakabe to succeed to the throne), also Prince Kusakabe had an ordinary character, (he was not good enough to become Emperor) thus the Empress Dowager, Uno no Sarara no Himemiko took control of politics to support Prince Kusakabe.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Emperor Tenchi/Tenji died, the Junshin War happened and Prince Oama (Emperor Tenmu) won the war, after he died as well, Uno no Sarara no Himemiko wished her son, Prince Kusakabe to succeed to the throne, however she put pressure on Prince Kusakabe&apos;s opposition, Prince Otsu to kill himself and was blamed for it, she was not able to make her wish happen (for Prince Kusakabe to succeed to the throne), also Prince Kusakabe had an ordinary character, (he was not good enough to become Emperor) thus the Empress Dowager, Uno no Sarara no Himemiko took control of politics to support Prince Kusakabe.</e>
<cmt>War大文字にしました。Unoスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>結局皇太子のまま草壁は早世してしまい、彼女は草壁の遺児・軽皇子（後の文武天皇）が成人するまでの中継ぎとして、690年旧正月にようやく持統天皇として即位した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Prince Kusakabe ended up as Crown Prince and died young, Uno no Sarara no Himemiko succeeded to the throne temporarily as Emperor Jito in the lunar New Year in 690, until Prince Kusakabe&apos;s son, Prince Karu (Emperor Monmu) to become old enough to enthrone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Prince Kusakabe ended up as Crown Prince and died young, Uno no Sarara no Himemiko succeeded to the throne temporarily as Emperor Jito in the lunar New Year in 690, until Prince Kusakabe&apos;s son, Prince Karu (Emperor Monmu) became old enough to enthrone.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Prince Kusakabe ended up as Crown Prince and died young, Uno no Sarara no Himemiko succeeded to the throne temporarily as Emperor Jito in the lunar New Year in 690, until Prince Kusakabe&apos;s son, Prince Karu (Emperor Monmu) became old enough to enthrone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>天智天皇の皇女・菟野皇后の称制は自らが産んだ草壁皇子の血統が続くのをより確実にしたいがためであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Tenchi/Tenji&apos;s Prince, Uno no Sarara no Himemiko conducted the Shosei since she wished to secure her son, Prince Kusakabe to succeed the blood line to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Tenchi/Tenji&apos;s Prince, Uno no Sarara no Himemiko conducted the Shosei since she wished to secure her son, Prince Kusakabe to succeed the blood line to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Tenchi/Tenji&apos;s Prince, Uno no Sarara no Himemiko conducted the Shosei since she wished to secure her son, Prince Kusakabe to succeed the blood line to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>彼女は草壁の早世にめげず、強いリーダーシップで律令国家体制確立への舵を執り、孫・軽皇子への譲位（直前に天武天皇第一皇子高市皇子が薨去したが、菟野・藤原不比等による暗殺説もある。）を果たした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although her son, Prince Kusakabe died young, she showed strong leadership and was brave enough to take control of the politics to establish the Japanese nation under the ritsuryo codes, she finally passed the throne to her grandchild, Prince Karu. (there was a theory Uno no and FUJIWARA no Fuhito planned assassination when Prince Takechi, Emperor Tenmu&apos;s first Prince died just before Prince Karu&apos;s enthronement.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although her son, Prince Kusakabe died young, she showed strong leadership and was brave enough to take control of politics to establish the Japanese nation under the ritsuryo codes, she finally passed the throne to her grandchild, Prince Karu. (there was a theory Uno no and FUJIWARA no Fuhito planned an assassination when Prince Takechi, Emperor Tenmu&apos;s first Prince died just before Prince Karu&apos;s enthronement.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although her son, Prince Kusakabe died young, she showed strong leadership and was brave enough to take control of politics to establish the Japanese nation under the ritsuryo codes, she finally passed the throne to her grandchild, Prince Karu (there was a theory Uno no and FUJIWARA no Fuhito planned an assassination when Prince Takechi, Emperor Tenmu&apos;s first Prince died just before Prince Karu&apos;s enthronement).</e>
<cmt>括弧書きの位置を訂正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>天武と持統の間から生まれた草壁皇子の子孫は奈良時代の皇統となって平城京で政治･文化の担い手になったが、称徳天皇を最後に断絶してしまい、皇統は天智天皇系（すなわち白壁王、のちの光仁天皇）に戻る事となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The descendants of Prince Kusakabe, who was a child between Emperor Tenmu and Emperor Jito, became main Imperial blood line of the Nara Period and actively involved in the politics and the culture, however the Imperial line was discontinued after having Emperor Shotoku as the last Emperor, the Imperial line was returned to Emperor Tenchi/Tenji&apos;s line. (what it was called Prince Shirakabe, later called Emperor Konin)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The descendant of Prince Kusakabe, who was a child between Emperor Tenmu and Emperor Jito, became the main Imperial blood line during the Nara Period and was actively involved in politics and culture, however the Imperial line was discontinued after Emperor Shotoku was the last Emperor, the Imperial line was returned to Emperor Tenchi/Tenji&apos;s line (Prince Shirakabe, later became Emperor Konin).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The descendant of Prince Kusakabe, who was a child between Emperor Tenmu and Emperor Jito, became the main Imperial blood line during the Nara period and was actively involved in politics and culture, however the Imperial line was discontinued after Emperor Shotoku was the last Emperor, the Imperial line was returned to Emperor Tenchi/Tenji&apos;s line (Prince Shirakabe, later became Emperor Konin).</e>
<cmt>period小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="23">
<j>称制であるとする見方があるケース</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The example which had a possibility to be called Shosei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An example which had a possibility of being called Shosei</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An example which had a possibility of being called Shosei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>神功皇后の摂政</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Empress Jingu&apos;s Regent</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Empress Jingu&apos;s Regent</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Empress Jingu&apos;s Regent</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>日本書紀によると、仲哀天皇の崩御後、世継ぎの応神天皇が生まれたばかりであり、その母の神功皇后が摂政となったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan)&quot;, after Emperor Chuai died, the successor to the Imperial throne, Emperor Ojin was just born, thus it was said that his mother, Empress Jungu became the regent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan),&quot; after Emperor Chuai died, the successor to the Imperial throne, Emperor Ojin was just born, thus his mother, Empress Jungu became the regent.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), after Emperor Chuai died, the successor to the Imperial throne, Emperor Ojin was just born, thus his mother, Empress Jungu became the regent.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>ここであえて摂政という用語を使い「称制」とはいってない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this case, it was said as Regent in stead of being called &apos;Shosei&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this case, it was called Regent in stead of being called &apos;Shosei.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this case, it was called Regent in stead of being called &apos;Shosei.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>むろん伝説時代のことであるので当時に摂政だの称制だのという漢文の用語が使われたわけもなく、古事記では摂政とも称制ともいってはいない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Off course this was the time in early Japanese legend and there was no record that Chinese worlds being used such as Sessho (Regent) or Shosei, in the &apos;Nihonshoki&quot; it was not called either Sessho or Shosei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Off course this was an early Japanese legend and there was no record of Chinese words being used like Sessho (Regent) or Shosei, in the &apos;Nihonshoki&quot; it was called neither Sessho nor Shosei.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of course this was an early Japanese legend and there was no record of Chinese words being used like Sessho (Regent) or Shosei, in the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; it was called neither Sessho nor Shosei.</e>
<cmt>Of courseに訂正しました。&apos;を&quot;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>が、日本書紀が編纂にあたって天智称制・持統称制にあわせて用語を統一しなかったのはどういうわけであろうか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However there is a question raised why the description of Sessho and Shose were not unified in accordance with the government of Emperor Tenchi/Tenji&apos;s Shosei or Emperor Jito&apos;s Shosei when Nihonshoki was edited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However this raises a question as to why the description of Sessho and Shose were not unified in accordance with the government of Emperor Tenchi/Tenji&apos;s Shosei or Emperor Jito&apos;s Shosei when the Nihonshoki was edited.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However this raises a question as to why the description of Sessho and Shose were not unified in accordance with the government of Emperor Tenchi/Tenji&apos;s Shosei or Emperor Jito&apos;s Shosei when the Nihonshoki was edited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>その理由は、「仲哀天皇がいまだ崩御していないという建前をとったためその代理だから」という意味か、または「特に理由はなく、称制も広義の摂政の中の一種という建前でただ慣習的に称制という言葉が使われなかっただけ」というわけなのか、あるいは「応神天皇は胎中天皇と称されたように胎児の頃からすでに正式な天皇であってその代理」という主旨なのか、いずれにしてもよくわからない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason for above is unknown, although there are some possibilities of the following, &apos;since Emperor Chuai&apos;s death was not announced officially after he died, and it was temporally measure&apos;, or &apos;there was no particular reason, the word &apos;Shosei&apos; was being used as custom, since it also meant &apos;Regent&apos; after all, or &apos;Shosei meant temporally government since Emperor Ojin was officially considered as proper Emperor and he was called Emperor Taichu.&apos; (Taichu means inside mother&apos;s womb)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason for above is unknown, although there are some possibilities of the following, &apos;since Emperor Chuai&apos;s death was not announced officially after he died, and it was temporary measure,&apos; or &apos;there was no particular reason, the word &apos;Shosei&apos; was being used as a custom, since it also meant &apos;Regent&apos; after all, or &apos;Shosei meant temporarily government since Emperor Ojin was officially considered as proper Emperor and he was called Emperor Taichu.&apos; (Taichu means inside mother&apos;s womb)</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason for above is unknown, although there are some possibilities of the following, &apos;since Emperor Chuai&apos;s death was not announced officially after he died, and it was temporary measure,&apos; or &apos;there was no particular reason, the word Shosei was being used as a custom, since it also meant Regent after all,&apos; or &apos;Shosei meant temporarily government since Emperor Ojin was officially considered as proper Emperor and he was called Emperor Taichu (Taichu means inside mother&apos;s womb).&apos;</e>
<cmt>括弧書きの位置を訂正。原文に合わせて&apos; &apos;削除、および補足。スペース削除。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="30">
<j>飯豊皇女の執政</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iitoyo no himemiko&apos;s (Crown Princess Iitoyo) government</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iitoyo no himemiko&apos;s (Crown Princess Iitoyo) government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iitoyo no Himemiko&apos;s (Crown Princess Iitoyo) government</e>
<cmt>Himemiko大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>日本書紀によると、清寧天皇の崩御後、世継ぎの候補である仁賢天皇（おけのみこと）と顕宗天皇（おけのみこと）の兄弟が互いに皇位を譲り合って後継が定まらなかったために、その姉とも叔母とも言われている飯豊皇女が政務を執ったといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &apos;Nihonshoki&apos;, after Emperor Seinei died, since two Imperial successors, Emperor Ninken and Emperor Kenzo made mutual concessions and could not decide who to succeed to the throne, Itoyo no himemiko took control of the government, who was said to be their sister or aunt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &apos;Nihonshoki,&apos; after Emperor Seinei died, since two Imperial successors, Emperor Ninken and Emperor Kenzo made mutual concessions and could not decide who to succeed to the throne, Itoyo no himemiko took control of the government, who was said to be their sister or aunt.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the Nihonshoki, after Emperor Seinei died, since two Imperial successors, Emperor Ninken and Emperor Kenzo made mutual concessions and could not decide who to succeed to the throne, Itoyo no himemiko took control of the government, who was said to be their sister or aunt.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて&apos; &apos;削除。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="32">
<j>阿閉皇女の執政</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ahe no Himemiko/Princess Ahe</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ahe no Himemiko/Princess Ahe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ahe no Himemiko (Princess Ahe)</e>
<cmt>括弧書きにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>続日本紀によると、文武天皇の崩御後、世継ぎの聖武天皇が幼少であったため後継問題が浮上し、そこで文武天皇の母で天智天皇の皇女にあたる阿閉皇女が仮に政務を執った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Shoku-Nihongi/the chronicles of Japan, after Emperor Monmu died, since the successor, Emperor Shomu was too young to enthrone and the issue that who to succeed to the throne was raised, it was decided for Ahe no Himemiko to rule the government temporally, who was Emperor Munmu&apos;s mother and Emperor Tenchi/Tenji&apos;s Princess.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Shoku-Nihongi/the chronicles of Japan, after Emperor Monmu died, since the successor, Emperor Shomu was too young to enthrone and the issue as to who should succeed to the throne was raised, it was decided that Ahe no Himemiko rule the government temporarily, who was Emperor Monmu&apos;s mother and Emperor Tenchi/Tenji&apos;s Princess.</e>
<cmt>spelling, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Shoku Nihongi (Chronicle of Japan Continued), after Emperor Monmu died, since the successor, Emperor Shomu was too young to enthrone and the issue as to who should succeed to the throne was raised, it was decided that Ahe no Himemiko rule the government temporarily, who was Emperor Monmu&apos;s mother and Emperor Tenchi/Tenji&apos;s Princess.</e>
<cmt>続日本紀→Shoku Nihongi (Chronicle of Japan Continued) に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>だが、後継は定まらず、2ヵ月後に諸臣の要請を受けて首皇子成人までの中継ぎとして元明天皇として即位した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However the successor to the throne was not officially decided, she was asked by the vassals and succeeded to the throne as Emperor Genmei under the condition of being in the position until Obito no Miko/Prince Obito become old enough to succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However the successor to the throne was not officially decided, she was asked by the vassals and temporarily occupied the throne as Emperor Genmei until Obito no Miko/Prince Obito become old enough to succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt>spelling, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the successor to the throne was not officially decided, and two months later, she was asked by the vassals and temporarily occupied the throne as Emperor Genmei until Obito no Miko (Prince Obito) become old enough to succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt>括弧書きにしました。「2ヵ月後」を訳出</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>息子である天皇の崩御から元明天皇即位までの2ヶ月間は形式的には阿閉皇女の称制が成立していたと考えられているが、期間が短かったために、称制としての実質はほとんどなかったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was considered that the period of two months, after the Emperor, Ahe no Himemiko died and she succeeded to the throne, the official Shosei of Aheno Himemiko was established, however the government itself was not ruled properly since it was short period of time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was considered to be a period of two months, after Emperor Ahe no Himemiko died that she succeeded to the throne, and the official Shosei of Aheno Himemiko was established, however, the government itself was not ruled properly during this short period of time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was considered to be a period of two months, after Emperor Ahe no Himemiko died that she succeeded to the throne, and the official Shosei of Ahe no Himemiko was established, however, the government itself was not ruled properly during this short period of time.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除、補足。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Murasagi(id:79122), りーや(id:23189), Enthousiasme(id:42600), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>