<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>葛野王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kado no okimi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kado no okimi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kado no okimi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>葛野王（かどののおおきみ、天智天皇8年（669年）頃?-慶雲2年（705年）12月）は大友皇子（弘文天皇）の第一皇子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kado no okimi (669? - December, 705) was the first son of Prince Otomo (Emperor Kobun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kado no okimi (c. 669 - December, 705) was the first prince of the Prince Otomo (the Emperor Kobun).</e>
<cmt>?→c.,son→prince と修正しました。the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kado no okimi (c. 669 - December, 705) was the first prince of the Prince Otomo (the Emperor Kobun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>母は十市皇女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was Tochi no Himemiko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was Tochi no Himemiko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was Tochi no Himemiko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>子に池辺王・藤並王、孫には淡海三船がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His sons were Ikebe no okimi, Fujinami no okimi and his grandson was Omi no Mifune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His sons were Ikebe no okimi, Fujinami no okimi, and his grandson was Omi no Mifune.</e>
<cmt>カンマを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His sons were Ikebe no okimi, Fujinami no okimi, and his grandson was Omi no Mifune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>文に長けていたと伝えられているが、壬申の乱で敗れた弘文天皇の皇子であるため、朝廷内でも当初は評判が悪かったようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that even though he had literal talent, as he was a son of Emperor Kobun who lost the Jinshin war, his reputation was quite low from the beginning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he is said to have been literally talented, as he was a prince of the Emperor Kobun who lost the Jinshin war, he seemed to have a bad reputation in the beginning.</e>
<cmt>文脈に応じて全体的に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he is said to have been literally talented, as he was a prince of the Emperor Kobun who lost the Jinshin war, he seemed to have a bad reputation in the beginning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>『懐風藻』によると696年（持統10年）の高市皇子の死去の後、持統天皇が数ある天武天皇の皇子達を退け孫の軽皇子（後の文武天皇）を皇太子にしようとした際、それに与し、日本では古来から直系相続が行われており、兄弟相続は争いのもとだとして天皇位の直系相続を主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Kaifusou&quot; (Fond Recollections of Poetry), when Emperor Jito rejected Emperor Tenmu&apos;s princes as successors and selected a grandson, Prince Karu after Takechi no miko died in 696, Kado no okimi conveyed opposition in that since direct line succession has been in place since ancient Japan, an interfraternal succession would cause conflict and insisted that the direct line succession be continued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Kaifusou&quot; (Fond Recollections of Poetry), when the Emperor Jito intended to make the grandson, the Prince Karu (later the Emperor Monmu) as the crown prince after Takechi no miko died in 696 rejecting the Emperor Tenmu&apos;s princes, Kado no okimi insisted the direct line succession of the imperial throne which had been carried form ancient Japan, and the interfraternal succession would cause conflict.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。スペースを修正しました。（後の文武天皇）を補い、文中、よりスムースに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Kaifusou&quot; (Fond Recollections of Poetry), when the Emperor Jito intended to make the grandson, the Prince Karu (later the Emperor Monmu) as the crown prince after Takechi no miko died in 696 rejecting the Emperor Tenmu&apos;s princes, Kado no okimi insisted the direct line succession of the imperial throne which had been carried form ancient Japan, and the interfraternal succession would cause conflict.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>(これについては藤原不比等が入れ知恵したのだとする意見もある。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Some say that FUJIWARA no Fuhito put this idea into Kado no okimi&apos;s head)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Some say that FUJIWARA no Fuhito suggested this idea to Kado no okimi.)</e>
<cmt>オリジナル部分の、下段に残っていた”）”をこの段に移動しました。ピリオドを補いました。put this idea into Kado no okimi&apos;s head→suggested this idea to Kado no okimi と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Some say that FUJIWARA no Fuhito suggested this idea to Kado no okimi.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>実際には古来から兄弟間での天皇位の相続は一般的であり、それについて弓削皇子が葛野王に問いかけようとした矢先、葛野王は弓削皇子を一喝。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Actually, a dispute over succession to the Imperial Throne between brothers was common in ancient time, and when Yuge no miko was going to ask Kado no okimi about this, Kado no okimi thundered out Yuge no miko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Actually, the succession of the imperial throne between brothers was common from ancient time, and when Yuge no miko was going to ask Kado no okimi about this, Kado no okimi scolded loudly Yuge no miko.</e>
<cmt>a dispute over succession to the Imperial Throne→the succession of the imperial throne,in→from,thundered out→scolded loudly と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Actually, the succession of the imperial throne between brothers was common from ancient time, and when Yuge no miko was going to ask Kado no okimi about this, Kado no okimi scolded loudly Yuge no miko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>弓削皇子も持統天皇の意向を結局は呑み、軽皇子を皇太子とすることが決定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Finally Yuge no miko accepted Emperor Jito&apos;s intention and the decision to make Prince Karu Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yuge no miko eventually accepted the Emperor Jito&apos;s intention, and the decision was made to make the Prince Karu as the crown prince.</e>
<cmt>Finally→eventually, to make Prince Karu Crown Prince→was made to make the Prince Karu as the crown prince と修正しました。the, カンマを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yuge no miko eventually accepted the Emperor Jito&apos;s intention, and the decision was made to make the Prince Karu as the crown prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>葛野王は後に正四位の位を授けられ、式部卿の地位に任ぜられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later Kado no okimi was granted Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank) and assigned to Shikibukyo (Minister of the Ministry of Ceremonial).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later Kado no okimi was granted Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank) and assumed the position of Shikibukyo (Minister of the Ministry of Ceremonial).</e>
<cmt>assigned to→assumed the position of と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later Kado no okimi was granted Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank) and assumed the position of Shikibukyo (Minister of the Ministry of Ceremonial).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>この時年齢37歳とあるが、薨去時の年齢が誤って伝えられたとする考えが一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His age at this time was 37 years old, but it is believed that the age of his death was reported incorrectly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he was 37 years old at that time, but it is believed that the age of his death was reported incorrectly.</e>
<cmt>It is said that を補い、文最初の部分を</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he was 37 years old at that time, but it is believed that the age of his death was reported incorrectly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>父弘文天皇は母方の祖父、天武天皇との皇位争いに敗れて自殺、母十市皇女も早世(自殺・暗殺説もある。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father, Emperor Kobun out in the succession to the Imperial Throne against maternal grandfather, Emperor Tenmu, and he committed suicide and his mother, Hochi no Himemiko also died young (there are theories saying she committed suicide or was assassinated),</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father, the Emperor Kobun who was out in the succession to the imperial throne against his maternal grandfather, the Emperor Tenmu, committed suicide, and his mother, Hochi no Himemiko also died young (There are theories saying she committed suicide or was assassinated.)</e>
<cmt>よりスムースに修正しました。カッコ部分を修正しました。オリジナル部分、下段に残されていた”）”をここに移動しました。”し、”は削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father, the Emperor Kobun who was out in the succession to the imperial throne against his maternal grandfather, the Emperor Tenmu, committed suicide, and his mother, Hochi no Himemiko also died young (There are theories saying she committed suicide or was assassinated.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>自身も複雑な血統の中、それなりの出世は果たすも、結局早世してしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he struggled with a complicated blood line, he was promoted to certain position, but he died young finally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he was promoted to a certain position despite of the complicated blood line, he died young after all.</e>
<cmt>オーダーを修正し、文脈に応じてスムースに修正しました。finally→after all と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he was promoted to a certain position despite of the complicated blood line, he died young after all.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>子孫も孫の三船以降は天武系から天智系への皇統移行とほぼ同時に歴史に埋もれてしまう事となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His descendants were buried in history after Mifune along with the change in the imperial line Emperor Tenmu to Tenji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His descendants were buried in history after Mifune, along with the change of the imperial line from the Tenmu to the Tenji.</e>
<cmt>in→the と修正しました。Emperor を削除しました。from, the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His descendants were buried in history after Mifune, along with the change of the imperial line from the Tenmu to the Tenji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Izayohi(id:13095), 代言人(id:33675), Charenji(id:7908), 松茸(id:27535), 平惣衛門(id:99387), Ponsaku(id:31417), YOSHI438(id:174755), 青山コロハ(id:118527), Snap55(id:89773), HUIKUFUCK(id:39810), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>