<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>壱志姫王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ichishihime no Okimi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ichishihime no Okimi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ichishihime no Okimi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>壱志姫王（いちしひめのおおきみ、生没年不詳）は、飛鳥時代の人物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ichishihime no Okimi (the date of birth and death unknown) was a person from Asuka period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ichishihime no Okimi (year of birth and death unknown) was a person from the Asuka period.</e>
<cmt>the date→year と修正しました。the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ichishihime no Okimi (year of birth and death unknown) was a person from the Asuka period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>壱志姫王の名は『日本書紀』『続日本紀』などの基本史料に確認出来ず、遥か時代を下った『本朝皇胤紹運録』に弘文天皇の女として見えるだけである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name Ichishihime no Okimi is not found in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) or &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued), which were thought to be the basic historical documents, but appears as the princess of Emperor Kobun in &quot;Honcho koin jounroku&quot; (the Emperor&apos;s family tree) which was edited after a long period of time, in Muromachi.</e>
<cmt>『続日本紀』、『本朝皇胤紹運録』の英訳は用語集を参照しました。用語集では『本朝皇胤紹運録』の説明として&apos;made in the Muromachi period&apos;がカッコ内に入っていましたが、英訳時に内容が重複するため、カッコ内からは削除し、「遥か時代を下った室町時代に」と訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name Ichishihime no Okimi is not found in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) or &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued), which were thought to be the basic historical documents, but only appears as the princess of the Emperor Kobun in &quot;Honcho koin jounroku&quot; (the Emperor&apos;s family tree) which was edited after a long period of time.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。only を補いました。in Muromachi を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name Ichishihime no Okimi is not found in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) or &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued), which were thought to be the basic historical documents, but only appears as the princess of the Emperor Kobun in &quot;Honcho koin jounroku&quot; (the Emperor&apos;s family tree) which was edited after a long period of time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>同書に付された「従四下、母大織冠（鎌足）女耳面刀自」の注記から、母は耳面刀自であることも分かる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Honcho koin jounroku&quot; comments &quot;Ichishihime no Okimi was Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), and her mother was Mimimotoji, the daughter of Taishokkan (Holder of the Grand Crown), FUJIWARA no Kamatari.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。「従四下」は「従四位下」と解釈し、読みは「じゅしいのげ」としています。「耳面刀自」の読みは「みみもとじ」としています。原文では「大織冠（鎌足）」とありますが、英訳時に「大織冠　藤原鎌足」としています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an annotation in &quot;Honcho koin jounroku&quot; as this; &apos;Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), and the mother was Mimimotoji, the daughter of Taishokkan (Holder of the Grand Crown), FUJIWARA no Kamatari,&apos;so it is clear that her mother was Mimimotoji.</e>
<cmt>クォーツを修正しました。文脈に応じて修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an annotation in &quot;Honcho koin jounroku&quot; as this; &apos;Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), and the mother was Mimimotoji, the daughter of Taishokkan (Holder of the Grand Crown), FUJIWARA no Kamatari,&apos;so it is clear that her mother was Mimimotoji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>耳面刀自なる人物も他に見えないが、『懐風藻』大友皇子伝によれば、鎌足が娘を大友皇子に捧げたことがあるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no description about Mimimotoji in any documents, but according to &quot;Kaifuso&quot; (Fond Recollections of Poetry), Kamatari was said to marry his daughter to Prince Otomo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no description about Mimimotoji in any documents, but according to &quot;Kaifuso&quot; (Fond Recollections of Poetry), Kamatari gave his daughter marry to the Prince Otomo.</e>
<cmt>Kamatari was said to marry his daughter to Prince Otomo→Kamatari gave his daughter marry to the Prince Otomo と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no description about Mimimotoji in any documents, but according to &quot;Kaifuso&quot; (Fond Recollections of Poetry), Kamatari gave his daughter marry to the Prince Otomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>「従四下」の官位が信用出来れば、大宝 (日本)2年（702年）の大宝律令施行以後も生存していたと推される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She had been living after the enforcement of Taiho Ritsuryo (Taiho Code) in 702 if the description of her official rank &quot;Jushiinoge&quot; was true.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She had been living after the enforcement of Taiho Ritsuryo (Taiho Code) in 702 if the description of her official rank &apos;Jushiinoge&apos; is creditable.</e>
<cmt>クォーツを修正しました。 was→is,true→creditable と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She had been living after the enforcement of Taiho Ritsuryo (Taiho Code) in 702 if the description of her official rank &apos;Jushiinoge&apos; is creditable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>当時の皇族の名は資養者の関係から命名され、乳母のウジが採られることが多いが、壱志姫王の場合も伊勢国一志郡に興る壱師君（後に宿禰）が扶養者であったと推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The members of Imperial family at that time were usually named after their guardians, most of the time their menoto (wet nurse), and we can assume that Ichishihime no Okimi was dependent of the Ichishi no kimi clan (later Sukune [third highest of the eight hereditary titles]) which emerged in Ichishi County, Ise Province.</e>
<cmt>「資養者」は定訳不明のため&apos;guardian&apos;と訳しています。「壱師君」は氏族の名前と解釈し&apos;the Ichishi no kimi clan&apos;としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The members of the Imperial Family at that time were usually named after their guardians, most of the time their menoto (wet nurse), and we can assume that Ichishihime no Okimi was dependent of the Ichishi no kimi clan (later Sukune [the third highest of the eight hereditary titles]) which emerged in Ichishi County, Ise Province.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。Imperial family→Imperial Family と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The members of the Imperial Family at that time were usually named after their guardians, most of the time their menoto (wet nurse), and we can assume that Ichishihime no Okimi was dependent of the Ichishi no kimi clan (later Sukune [the third highest of the eight hereditary titles]) which emerged in Ichishi County, Ise Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), こぶまき(id:38278), Carkuni(id:79281), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>