<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原げん子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Genshi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Genshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Genshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原嫄子（ふじわら の げんし（もとこ）、長和5年7月10日 (旧暦)（1016年8月15日） - 長暦3年8月28日 (旧暦)（1039年9月19日））は、平安時代中期の皇妃。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Genshi (Motoko) (August 15, 1016 - September 19, 1039) was an empress consort in the middle of Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Genshi (Motoko) (August 15, 1016 - September 19, 1039) was an empress consort in the middle of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Genshi (Motoko) (August 21, 1016 - September 25, 1039) was an empress consort in the middle of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>一品式部卿敦康親王の長女、母は具平親王次女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was the eldest daughter of Imperial Prince Atsuyasu, Ippon (the first rank for Imperial princes) Shikibukyo (the minister of ceremonial), and her mother was the second daughter of Imperial Prince Tomohira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was the eldest daughter of Imperial Prince Atsuyasu, Ippon (the first rank for Imperial princes) Shikibukyo (the minister of ceremonies), and her mother was the second daughter of Imperial Prince Tomohira.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was the eldest daughter of Imperial Prince Atsuyasu, Ippon (the first rank for Imperial Princes) Shikibukyo (the minister of ceremonies), and her mother was the second daughter of Imperial Prince Tomohira.</e>
<cmt>Imperial Prince としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>後朱雀天皇中宮。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was Chugu (an empress consort) of the Emperor Gosuzaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was Chugu (an empress consort) of Emperor Gosuzaku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was Chugu (an empress consort) of Emperor Gosuzaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>初名は嫄子女王。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was originally named Princess Genshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was originally named Princess Genshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was originally named Princess Genshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief personal history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief personal history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief personal history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>寛仁2年（1018年）、実父敦康親王が薨去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her father, Imperial Prince Atsuyasu, died in 1018.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her father, Imperial Prince Atsuyasu, died in 1018.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her father, Imperial Prince Atsuyasu, died in 1018.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>母が関白藤原頼通の正室隆姫女王の妹であった縁で、娘のない頼通夫妻の養女となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because her mother was the younger sister of Princess Takahime, the legal wife of Kanpaku (the chief advisor to the emperor) FUJIWARA no Yorimichi, she became the adopted daughter of Yorimichi couple who had no daughters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because her mother was the younger sister of Princess Takahime, the legal wife of Kanpaku (the chief advisor to the emperor) FUJIWARA no Yorimichi, she became the adopted daughter of the Yorimichi couple who had no daughters.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because her mother was the younger sister of Princess Takahime, the legal wife of Kanpaku (the chief advisor to the emperor) FUJIWARA no Yorimichi, she became the adopted daughter of the Yorimichi couple who had no daughters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>長元9年（1036年）、後朱雀天皇の女御代に。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1036, she became Nyogodai (a deputy Nyogo (second consort)) of the Emperor Gosuzaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1036, she became Nyogodai (a deputy Nyogo - second consort) of Emperor Gosuzaku.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1036, she became Nyogodai (a deputy Nyogo; a high-ranking lady in the court (a consort of an emperor)) of Emperor Gosuzaku.</e>
<cmt>女御代の補足を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>同10年（1037年）1月入内、女御の宣旨を受け正四位下に叙される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 1037, she entered into court, became Nyogo by the Imperial decree and was conferred the court rank of Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January 1037, she entered into court, became Nyogo by Imperial decree and was conferred the court rank of Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 1037, she entered into court, became Nyogo by Imperial decree and was conferred the court rank of Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>同年3月、中宮に冊立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March of the same year, she became Chugu (an empress consort).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March of the same year, she became Chugu (an empress consort).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April of the same year, she became Chugu.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>天皇の寵愛を受け、祐子内親王・ばい子内親王 (後朱雀天皇皇女)の二皇女をもうけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was deeply loved by the Emperor and gave birth to two princesses, namely Imperial Princess Yushi and Imperial Princess Baishi (a princess of the Emperor Gosuzaku).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was deeply loved by the Emperor and gave birth to two princesses, namely Imperial Princess Yushi and Imperial Princess Baishi (a princess of Emperor Gosuzaku).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was deeply loved by the Emperor and gave birth to two princesses, namely Imperial Princess Yushi and Imperial Princess Baishi (a princess of Emperor Gosuzaku).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし、皇子出生を見る事なく産褥死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She, however, had no princes and died of puerperal fever.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She, however, had no princes and died of puerperal fever.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She, however, had no princes and died of postnatal complications.</e>
<cmt>産褥死→died of postnatal complications　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>享年24。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The age of her death was 24.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her age at the time of her death was 24.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her age at the time of her death was 24.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>逝去当時、源氏でありながら藤原氏の養女として立后した事で、藤原氏の氏神である春日大社の神の怒りを買った為に亡くなったのだという噂が流れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When she died, the rumor spread saying she died due to the anger of deities of Kasuga-taisha Shrine, which was a private deity of the FUJIWARA family, because she became an empress consort as the adopted daughter of FUJIWARA family though she originally had been a member of the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When she died, the rumor spread saying she died due to the anger of deities of Kasuga-taisha Shrine, which was a private deity of the FUJIWARA family, because she became an empress consort as the adopted daughter of the FUJIWARA family though she originally had been a member of the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When she died, the rumor spread saying she died due to the anger of deities of Kasuga-taisha Shrine, which was a private deity of the FUJIWARA family, because she became an empress consort as the adopted daughter of the FUJIWARA family though she originally had been a member of the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>なお嫄子を擁立したことで先に中宮となっていた禎子内親王は皇后に押しやられ、頼通との関係が悪化したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Imperial Princess Teishi, who had become Chugu earlier, was forced to become Kogo (the title of empress consort which is conferred when another woman becomes Chugu) when Genshi became Chugu, it is purported that her relationship with Yorimichi became worse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Imperial Princess Teishi, who had become Chugu earlier, was forced to become Kogo (the title of empress consort which is conferred when another woman becomes Chugu) when Genshi became Chugu, it was purported that her relationship with Yorimichi became worse.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Imperial Princess Teishi, who had become Chugu earlier, was forced to become Kogo (the title of empress consort which is conferred when another woman becomes Chugu) when Genshi became Chugu, it was purported that her relationship with Yorimichi became worse.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), 五代雄介(id:67888), พริกขี้หนู(id:131976), Masyu(id:31065), ポピュラーポプラ(id:157724), 代言人(id:33675), 水野白楓(id:22811), Cprobot(id:97843), BitBucket(id:30999), Andee(id:20421), Emk(id:78926), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>