<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>久邇宮</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuni no Miya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuni no Miya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuni no Miya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>久邇宮（くにのみや）は、明治時代前期に伏見宮邦家親王の第4王子・久邇宮朝彦親王が創立した宮家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuni no Miya was the princely house established by Fushimi no Miya Imperial Prince Kuniie&apos;s fourth Prince, Kuni no Miya Imperial Prince Asahiko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuni no Miya was the palace established by Fushimi no Miya Imperial Prince Kuniie&apos;s fourth Prince, Kuni no Miya Imperial Prince Asahiko.</e>
<cmt>terminiology</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuni no Miya was the Miyake (house of an imperial prince) established by Fushimi no Miya Imperial Prince Kuniie&apos;s fourth Prince, Kuni no Miya Imperial Prince Asahiko during the early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除during the early Meiji period補足&quot;palace&quot;→&quot;Miyake (house of an imperial prince) &quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>朝彦親王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Asahiko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Asahiko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Asahiko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>初代・朝彦親王は、文政7年（1824年）に誕生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first Imperial Asahiko was born in 1824.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first Imperial Asahiko was born in 1824.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first Imperial Asahiko was born in 1824.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>初名は成憲。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His initial name was Narinori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His initial name was Narinori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His initial name was Narinori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>奈良一乗院の門主となり、親王宣下の後、出家して京都青蓮院門跡となり、天台座主を兼ね尊融入道親王と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became the chief priest of Nara Ichijo-in Temple, after he received to title Prince by Imperial order, he became priest and the priest-prince of Shoren-in Temple, he was the head priest of the Tendai sect of Buddhism and named as the monk-Prince Sonyu.</e>
<cmt>親王宣下→to title Prince by Imperial order[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became the chief priest of Nara Ichijo-in Temple, after he received the title Prince by Imperial order, he became a priest and the priest-prince of Shoren-in Temple, he was the head priest of the Tendai sect of Buddhism and named as the monk-Prince Sonyu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became the chief priest of Nara Ichijo-in Temple, after he received the title Prince by Imperial order, he became a priest and the priest-prince of Shoren-in Temple, he was the head priest of the Tendai sect of Buddhism and named as the monk-Prince Sonyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>還俗して中川宮の宮号を賜り、名を朝彦と改める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He returned to secular life to receive miya go title of Nakagawa no Miya, he renamed Asahiko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He returned to a secular life to receive the miya go title of Nakagawa no Miya, he was renamed Asahiko.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He returned to a secular life to receive the miya go title of Nakagawa no Miya, he was renamed Asahiko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>国事御用掛として孝明天皇を補佐し、天皇が嫌悪した尊王攘夷派を朝廷から追放することに努めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He supported Emperor Komei as a general official of the Imperial Household in charge of the State affair, he put his effort into getting rid of people who are the supporters of the doctrine of restoring the emperor (to power) and expelling the barbarians out of the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>国事御用掛→a general official of the Imperial Household in charge of the State affair[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He supported Emperor Komei as a general official of the Imperial Household in charge of State affairs, and put his effort into getting rid of people who were supporters of the doctrine of restoring the emperor (to power) and expelling the barbarians from the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He supported Emperor Komei as a general official of the Imperial Household in charge of State affairs, and put his effort into getting rid of people who were supporters of the doctrine of restoring the emperor (to power) and expelling the barbarians from the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そのため、明治維新後は、反政府陰謀の疑いで逮捕され、親王の身分を剥奪されて安芸国広島藩に預けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus he was arrested after the Meiji Restoration under the suspicion of forming a plot against the government, and his position of Imperial Prince was taken away, he was left with the Hiroshima domain in Aki Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, he was arrested after the Meiji Restoration, suspected of forming a plot against the government, and his position of Imperial Prince was taken away, he was left with the Hiroshima domain in Aki Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, he was arrested after the Meiji Restoration, suspected of forming a plot against the government, and his position of Imperial Prince was taken away, he was left with the Hiroshima Domain in Aki Province.</e>
<cmt>domain→Domain</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>明治3年（1870年）に伏見宮に復帰。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He returned to Fushimi no Miya in 1870.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He returned to Fushimi no Miya in 1870.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He returned to Fushimi no Miya in 1870.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>1875年（明治8年）に久邇宮の宮号を賜った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He received a Miya go title of Kuni no Miya in 1875.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He received the Miya go title of Kuni no Miya in 1875.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He received the Miya go title of Kuni no Miya in 1875.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>宮号の由来は、恭仁京にちなんだ、あるいは伏見宮の当主が1代おきに「邦」の1字を偏諱としていたことによるなどと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Miya go title came from the ancient capital of Kuni-kyo, or it was from the history that the head of the family used the Kanji character &apos;邦&apos; every second generation to prevent from bad luck.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the Miya go title came from the ancient capital of Kuni-kyo, or from the historical tradition that the head of the family used the Kanji character &apos;邦&apos; every second generation to prevent bad luck.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the Miya go title came from the ancient capital of Kuni-kyo, or from the historical tradition that the head of the family used the Kanji character &apos;邦 (kuni)&apos; every second generation to prevent bad luck.</e>
<cmt>(kuni)補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その後、朝彦親王は神宮祭主として古儀復興に取り組み、1891年（明治24年）に68歳で薨去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that Imperial Prince Asahiko put his effort into restoration of traditional Imperial events as a chief mourner of the Shinto Shrine, he died in 1891 when he was sixty eight years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that Imperial Prince Asahiko, as chief mourner of the Shinto Shrine, put his efforts into restoring traditional Imperial events, he died in 1891 when he was sixty eight years.</e>
<cmt>restructured, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that Imperial Prince Asahiko, as chief mourner of the Shinto Shrine, put his efforts into restoring traditional Imperial event, he died in 1891 when he was sixty eight years.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>朝彦親王には王子女が多く、賀陽宮邦憲王、邦彦王、梨本宮守正王、多嘉王、朝香宮鳩彦王、東久邇宮稔彦王などがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Asahito had many Princes and Princesses, such as Kaya no Maya Prince Kuninori, Prince Kuniyoshi, Nashimoto no Miya Prince Morimasa,Prince Taka, Asaka no Miya prince Yasuhiko and Higashi Kuni no Miya Prince Naruhiko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Asahito had many Princes and Princesses, such as Kaya no Maya Prince Kuninori, Prince Kuniyoshi, Nashimoto no Miya Prince Morimasa,Prince Taka, Asaka no Miya prince Yasuhiko and Higashi Kuni no Miya Prince Naruhiko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Asahito had many Princes and Princesses, such as Kaya no Maya Prince Kuninori, Prince Kuniyoshi, Nashimoto no Miya Prince Morimasa,Prince Taka, Asaka no Miya Prince Yasuhiko and Higashi Kuni no Miya Prince Naruhiko.</e>
<cmt>prince→Prince</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>邦彦王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Kuniyoshi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Kuniyoshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Kuniyoshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>2代・久邇宮邦彦王は、1873年（明治6年）に誕生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second Kunino Miya Prince Kuniyoshi was born in 1873.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second Kunino Miya Prince Kuniyoshi was born in 1873.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second Kunino Miya Prince Kuniyoshi was born in 1873.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>1891年（明治24年）に父宮薨去によって、宮家を相続した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He succeeded the princely house after his father died in 1891.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He succeeded the palace after his father died in 1891.</e>
<cmt>terminology</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He succeeded the Miyake after his father died in 1891.</e>
<cmt>&quot;palace&quot;→&quot;Miyake&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>陸軍士官学校、陸軍大学校を卒業し、陸軍大将にまで昇る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he graduated from the Military Academy and the Army Academy, he achieved to become a Full General.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he graduated from the Military Academy and the Army Academy, he achieved the rank of Full General.</e>
<cmt>cell format, word wrap, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he graduated from the Military Academy and the Army Academy, he achieved the rank of Full General.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>1899年（明治32年）に公爵島津忠義の娘俔子（ちかこ）と結婚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1899 he married to Prince Tadayoshi SHIMAZU&apos;s daughter, Chikako.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1899 he married Prince Tadayoshi SHIMAZU&apos;s daughter, Chikako.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1899 he married Prince Tadayoshi SHIMAZU&apos;s daughter, Chikako.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>1928年（昭和3年）、台湾滞在中に朝鮮人テロリストによる暗殺未遂事件に遭ったがけがはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had an assassination attempt by Korean terrorist during his stay in Taiwan but he had no injury.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the victum of an assassination attempt by Korean terrorist during his stay in Taiwan, but escaped injury.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the victim of an assassination attempt by Korean terrorist during his stay in Taiwan in 1929, but escaped injury.</e>
<cmt>年号補足スペース削除スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>1929年（昭和4年）、潰瘍性腹膜炎により56歳で薨去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1929 he died of cankerous peritonitis when he was fifty six years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1929 he died of cankerous peritonitis when he was fifty six years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1929 he died of cankerous peritonitis when he was fifty six years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>王子女には、久邇宮朝融王、久邇邦久（1923年臣籍降下）、東伏見慈洽（1931年臣籍降下）、香淳皇后、三条西信子（三条西公正に嫁す）、大谷智子（大谷光暢に嫁す）がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Princes and Princesses are Kuni no Miya Prince Asa akira,Kunihisa KUNI, (demotion from nobility to subject in 1923), Jigo HIGASHIFUSHIM (demotion from nobility to subject in 1931),the Empress Kojun, 信子 SANJONISHI (marred to Kin osa SANJONISHI), Satoko OTANI. (married to Kocho OTANI)</e>
<cmt>三条西信子→Nobuko?[読み方確認できず] SANJONISHI</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Princes and Princesses are Kuni no Miya Prince Asa akira,Kunihisa KUNI, (demoted from nobility to subject in 1923), Jigo HIGASHIFUSHIM (demoted from nobility to subject in 1931),the Empress Kojun, 信子 SANJONISHI (marred to Kin osa SANJONISHI), Satoko OTANI. (married to Kocho OTANI)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Princes and Princesses are Kuni no Miya Prince Asa akira, Kunihisa KUNI, (demoted from nobility to subject in 1923), Jigo HIGASHIFUSHIMI (demoted from nobility to subject in 1931), the Empress Kojun, Nobuko SANJONISHI (married to Kinosa SANJONISHI), Satoko OTANI. (married to Kocho OTANI).</e>
<cmt>改行削除スペル人名スペルピリオド補足信子→Nobuko［正しい読み方が不明です］</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>多嘉王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Taka</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Taka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Taka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>邦彦王の弟宮多嘉王は、京都に在住し、、結局、独立した宮家を興すことはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Kuniyoshi&apos;s younger brother, Prince Taka lived in Kyoto and did not establish new princely house until the end.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Kuniyoshi&apos;s younger brother, Prince Taka lived in Kyoto and did not establish a new palace until the end.</e>
<cmt>terminology</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Kuniyoshi&apos;s younger brother, Prince Taka lived in Kyoto and did not establish a new Miyake until the end.</e>
<cmt>&quot;palace&quot;→&quot;Miyake&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>妃静子との間に3男3女を儲け、神宮祭主を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had three boys and three girls with his Empress, Shizuko, and he worked as a chief mourner of the Shinto Shrine.</e>
<cmt>静子→Shizuko?[読み方確認できず]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had three boys and three girls with his Empress, Shizuko, and he worked as a chief mourner of the Shinto Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had three boys and three girls with his Empress, Shizuko, and he worked as a chief mourner of the Shinto Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>1937年（昭和12年）、63歳で薨去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died when he was sixty three year old in 1937.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died when he was sixty three yeasr old in 1937.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died when he was sixty three years old in 1937.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>朝融王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Asa Akira</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Asa Akira</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Asa Akira</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>3代・久邇宮朝融王は、1901年（明治34年）に誕生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The third Kuni no Miya Prince Asa Akira was born in 1901.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The third Kuni no Miya Prince Asa Akira was born in 1901.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The third Kuni no Miya Prince Asa Akira was born in 1901.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>婚約破棄事件もあったが、1925年（大正14年）に伏見宮博恭王の王女・知子女王と結婚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there was an incident he cancelled his engagement, he married to Fushimi no Miya Prince Hiroyasu&apos;s Princess, Princess Tomoko in 1925.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he cancelled his engagement, he later married Fushimi no Miya Prince Hiroyasu&apos;s Princess, Princess Tomoko in 1925.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he cancelled his engagement, he later married Fushimi no Miya Prince Hiroyasu&apos;s Princess, Princess Tomoko in 1925.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>1929年（昭和4年）に宮家を相続する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1929 he succeeded to the princely house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1929 he succeeded to the prince&apos;s palace.</e>
<cmt>terminology</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1929 he succeeded to the Miyake.</e>
<cmt>&quot;prince&apos;s palace&quot;→&quot;Miyake&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>海軍兵学校 (日本海軍)卒業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He graduated from the Naval Academy (Japanese Navy).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He graduated from the Naval Academy (Japanese Navy).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He graduated from the Naval Academy (Japanese Navy).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>終戦時には、海軍中将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became the Vice Admiral when the War finished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became Vice Admiral when the War finished.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became Vice Admiral when the War finished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>終戦後の1947年（昭和22年）に妃知子が薨去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1947, after the War, Empress Tomoko died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1947, after the War, Empress Tomoko died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1947, after the War, Empress Tomoko died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>同年、皇籍離脱し久邇朝融となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, he made a demotion from nobility to subject and became Asaakira KUNI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, he was demoted from nobility to subject and became Asaakira KUNI.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, he was demoted from nobility to subject and became Asaakira KUNI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>いろいろな事業に手を染めるが、連合国軍占領下の日本の荒波を受けてうまくはいかなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went into various businesses however none of them were successful since it was tough time in Japan under the occupation of the Allied Forces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He ventured into various businesses, however, none were successful during the tough period in Japan under the occupation of the Allied Forces.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He ventured into various businesses, however, none were successful during the tough period in Japan under the occupation of the Allied Forces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>1959年（昭和34年）に58歳で逝去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died fifty eight years old in 1959.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at fifty eight years old in 1959.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at fifty eight years old in 1959.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="32">
<j>麻布にあった久邇宮邸の敷地は、現在は聖心女子大学のキャンパスとなっており、御常御殿（日常の居所）は久邇ハウスと呼ばれ現存している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The land of Kunino Miya mansion which used to be in Azabu, is currently used as a campus of the University of the Sacred Heart, Tokyo, and the Onjo/gojo Goten (a part of the mansion being used every day) still exist and is called Kuni house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The land where the Kunino Miya palace used to stand in Azabu, is currently used as a campus for the University of the Sacred Heart, Tokyo, and the Onjo/gojo Goten (a part of the palace being used every day) still exists and is called Kuni house.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The land where the Kunino Miya palace used to stand in Azabu, is currently used as a campus for the University of the Sacred Heart, Tokyo, and the Onjo/gojo Goten (a part of the palace being used every day) still exists and is called Kuni house.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>久邇宮邸は香淳皇后の生家であり、聖心女子大学は今上天皇の皇后である美智子の出身校でもあるため、くしくも二代にわたり皇后と縁のある地となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kuni no Miya mansion was the house where the Empress Kojun, the present Emperor&apos;s Empress, Michiko graduated from the same University, thus the place is related through second generations to the Imperial family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kuni no Miya palace was where the Empress Kojun, the present Emperor&apos;s Empress, Michiko graduated from the same University, thus the place is related via the second generation to the Imperial family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kuni no Miya palace was where the Empress Kojun was born, the present Emperor&apos;s Empress, Michiko graduated from the University of the Sacred Heart, thus the place is related via the second generation to the Imperial family.</e>
<cmt>was born補足same University→University of the Sacred Heart</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="34">
<j>現当主は久邇宮朝融王の長男、久邇邦昭。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The current head of the family is Kunino Miya Prince Asa Akira&apos;s oldest son, Kuniaki KUNI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The current head of the family is Kunino Miya Prince Asa Akira&apos;s oldest son, Kuniaki KUNI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The current head of the family is Kunino Miya Prince Asa Akira&apos;s oldest son, Kuniaki KUNI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 文姫(id:66661), Los688(id:12316), R-h(id:46562), Nnh(id:474), 玄史生(id:43670), Miya(id:1881), 代言人(id:33675), Charenji(id:7908), Punipico(id:25163), けんち(id:5147), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), Sh(id:2707), 呆庵入道(id:74721), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>