<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>崇峻天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Sushun</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Sushun</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Sushun</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>崇峻天皇（すしゅんてんのう、生年不明 - 崇峻天皇5年11月3日 (旧暦)（ユリウス暦592年12月12日））は、第32代天皇（在位：用明天皇2年8月2日 (旧暦)（587年9月9日） - 崇峻天皇5年11月3日（592年12月12日））。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Sushun (Year of birth unknown - December 12, 592), the thirty-second Japanese Emperor, was in power from September 9, 587 to December 12, 592.</e>
<cmt>宇多天皇のファイルを参考に、旧暦の標記は取り、在位期間を()を取って文章にしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Sushun (Year of birth unknown - December 12, 592), the thirty-second Japanese Emperor, was in power from September 9, 587 to December 12, 592.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Sushun (Year of birth unknown - December 12, 592), the thirty-second Japanese Emperor, was in power from September 9, 587 to December 12, 592.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>弟（おと）、長谷部（はつせべ）の若雀（わかささぎ）天皇、倉橋（くらはし）の柴垣（しばかき）宮に坐しまして、天の下治らしめすこと、四歳（よとせ）なりき。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The younger brother, Emperor Hasetsube no Wakasagi, lived in the palace of Shibakaki at Kurahashi and governed the country for four years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His younger brother, Emperor Hasetsube no Wakasasagi, lived in the palace of Shibakaki at Kurahashi and governed the country for four years.</e>
<cmt>冠詞を修正しました。ローマ字を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His younger brother, Emperor Hasetsube no Wakasasagi, lived in the palace of Shibakaki at Kurahashi and governed the country for four years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>（分注、壬子の年の十一月十三日に崩りたましき。）御陵は倉橋の岡の上にあり。（『古事記』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Annotation, he died in November 13, the year of Mizunoe-Ne [one of the Oriental Zodiac].) His mausoleum sits on the hill of Kurahashi. (&quot;Kojiki&quot;.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Annotation: he died on November 13, the year of Mizunoe-Ne [one of the Oriental Zodiac years].) His mausoleum sits on the hill of Kurahashi (&quot;Kojiki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>句読点、前置詞を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Annotation: he died on November 13, the year of Mizunoe-Ne [one of the Oriental Zodiac years].) His mausoleum sits on the hill of Kurahashi (&quot;Kojiki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>倉橋の柴垣宮は、奈良県磯城郡。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The palace of Shibakaki at Kurahashi is located in Shiki District, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The palace of Shibakaki at Kurahashi is located in Shiki County, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>郡→county</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The palace of Shibakaki at Kurahashi is located in Shiki County, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>系譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>欽明天皇の第12皇子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 12th Prince of Emperor Kinmei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 12th Prince of Emperor Kinmei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 12th Prince of Emperor Kinmei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>母は蘇我稲目の女・小姉君（おあねのきみ）で、敏達天皇、用明天皇、推古天皇の異母弟にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother is Oane no kimi, the daughter of SOGA no Iname, and Emperor Bidatsu, Emperor Yomei and Empress Suiko are his brothers with different mothers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother is Oane no kimi, the daughter of SOGA no Iname, and Emperor Bidatsu, Emperor Yomei and Empress Suiko are his paternal elder half-brothers.</e>
<cmt>異母→paternal half-</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother is Oane no kimi, the daughter of SOGA no Iname, and Emperor Bidatsu, Emperor Yomei and Empress Suiko are his paternal elder half-brothers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>即位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enthronement</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enthronement</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enthronement</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>大臣 (日本)（おおおみ）の蘇我馬子によって推薦され即位した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He took over the throne with the backing by SOGA no Umako, Oomi (Japan) (a highest officer in national politics of the Yamato dynasty).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He took over the throne with the backing by SOGA no Umako, Oomi (Japan) (a highest officer in national politics of the Yamato dynasty).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He took over the throne with the backing by SOGA no Umako, Oomi (Japan) (a highest officer in national politics of the Yamato dynasty).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>一方連（おおむらじ）の物部氏は、穴穂部皇子（あなほべのみこ）を即位させようとはかるが、穴穂部皇子は蘇我馬子によって逆に殺されてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the Mononobe clan, Omuraji (the most powerful of Muraji [one of the highest family names]) attempted to enthrone Prince Anahobe no Miko who, in reverse, was killed by SOGA no Umako.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mononobe clan of Omuraji (the most powerful of Muraji [one of the highest family names]) attempted to enthrone Prince Anahobe no Miko who, in reverse, was killed by SOGA no Umako.</e>
<cmt>この文脈でOn the other handは不適切なので削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mononobe clan of Omuraji (the most powerful of Muraji [one of the highest family names]) attempted to enthrone Prince Anahobe no Miko who, in reverse, was killed by SOGA no Umako.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その後、蘇我馬子は、物部守屋を滅ぼし、これ以降物部氏は没落してしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, SOGA no Umako destroyed MONONOBE no Moriya, which eventually ruined the Mononobe clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, SOGA no Umako killed MONONOBE no Moriya, which eventually ruined the Mononobe clan.</e>
<cmt>Destroyは人には使わないので変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, SOGA no Umako killed MONONOBE no Moriya, which eventually ruined the Mononobe clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>仏教興隆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prosperity of Buddhism</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prosperity of Buddhism</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prosperity of Buddhism</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>物部氏の没落によって欽明天皇以来の崇仏廃仏論争に決着が付き、法興寺（飛鳥寺）や四天王寺などの、造寺事業を積極的に行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fall of the Mononobe clan settled the controversy over whether to worship or to abandon the Buddha which started in the Emperor Kinmei era, and Emperor Sushun actively undertook construction of temples, including Hoko-ji Temple (Asuka-dera Temple) and Shitenno-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fall of the Mononobe clan settled the controversy which had started in Emperor Kinmei&apos;s time over whether to worship or to abandon Buddhism, and Emperor Sushun actively undertook the construction of temples, including Hoko-ji Temple (Asuka-dera Temple) and Shitenno-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>より自然な英語に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fall of the Mononobe clan settled the controversy which had started in Emperor Kinmei&apos;s time over whether to worship or to abandon Buddhism, and Emperor Sushun actively undertook the construction of temples, including Hoko-ji Temple (Asuka-dera Temple) and Shitenno-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし、即位したあとでも政治の実権は常に馬子が握っており、次第に不満を感じるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But he gradually becomes discontent about Umako who continued to remain at the political helm even after his enthronement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But he gradually became discontent about the fact that Umako continued to remain at the political helm even after his enthronement.</e>
<cmt>時制を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But he gradually became discontent about the fact that Umako continued to remain at the political helm even after his enthronement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>天皇暗殺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Assassination of Emperor</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Assassination of the Emperor</e>
<cmt>冠詞を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Assassination of the Emperor</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>592年10月4日 (旧暦)に、猪を献上する者があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 4, 592 (on the old calendar), a man presented Emperor Sushun a wild boar.</e>
<cmt>新暦での日付がわかりませんでしたので旧暦のまま記載しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 4, 592 (on the old calendar), a man presented Emperor Sushun with a wild boar.</e>
<cmt>前置詞を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 4, 592 (on the old calendar), a man presented Emperor Sushun with a wild boar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>天皇は笄刀（こうがい）を抜いてその猪の目を刺し、「いつかこの猪の首を斬るように、自分が憎いと思っている者を斬りたいものだ」と発言。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Sushun drew Kogai (Japanese hairpin sword), thrusted it into the eye of the boar, and said &quot;Someday, like slashing the throat of this boar, I want to cut the man I hate.&quot;</e>
<cmt>笄であればhairpinですが、文脈からより刀に近いもののようですので、hairpinとはしませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Sushun drew his kogai (Japanese hairpin sword), thrusted it into the eye of the boar and said, &quot;someday, like slashing the throat of this boar, I want to slash the man I hate.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Cutは浅い傷を表すのでslashに変更しました。冠詞を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Sushun drew his kogai (Japanese hairpin sword), thrusted it into the eye of the boar and said, &quot;someday, like slashing the throat of this boar, I want to slash the man I hate.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>そのことを聞きつけた馬子が「天皇は自分を嫌っている」と警戒し、部下に暗殺命令を下した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Umako heard this incident and became wary that the Emperor might dislike him, so he commanded his subordinate to assassinate the emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Umako heard about this incident and became wary that the Emperor might detest him, so he commanded his subordinate to assassinate the emperor.</e>
<cmt>Hear “about”この文脈でDislikeは弱すぎるので変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Umako heard about this incident and became wary that the Emperor might detest him, so he commanded his subordinate to assassinate the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>そして東国の調（ちょう）を進めると偽って天皇を儀式に臨席させ、その席で東漢駒（やまとのあやのあたいこま）の手により暗殺した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He invited the Emperor to a false ceremony, saying he would present him with products of Togoku (Eastern Provinces), and it was there that the Emperor was assassinated by YAMATO no Aya no Koma.</e>
<cmt>同一人物ですが、読みは以下が正しいようです。登録され訳もYAMATO no Aya no Komaですので、こちらに合わせました。東漢直駒（やまとのあやのあたいこま）東漢駒（やまとのあやのこま）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He invited the Emperor to a false ceremony by saying he would present him with products of Togoku (eastern provinces), and it was there that the Emperor was assassinated by YAMATO no Aya no Koma.</e>
<cmt>大文字を修正しました。句読点を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He invited the Emperor to a false ceremony by saying he would present him with products of Togoku (eastern provinces), and it was there that the Emperor was assassinated by YAMATO no Aya no Koma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>臣下により天皇が殺害されたのは、確定している例では唯一である（他には、毒殺の疑いのある孝明天皇の例が未確定である。安康天皇は同じ皇族によって殺害されているが、史実性が低いので除外されることが多い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the only confirmed case that an Emperor was killed by his vassal (There is an unconfirmed case of Emperor Komei who was allegedly poisoned to death. Also, Emperor Anko was allegedly killed by one of the members of the Imperial family, but his case is often excluded due to its low historicity.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the only confirmed case of an Emperor being killed by his vassal. (There is an unconfirmed case of Emperor Komei who was allegedly poisoned to death. Also, Emperor Anko was allegedly killed by one of the members of the Imperial family, but his case is often excluded due to its low historicity.)</e>
<cmt>句読点を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the only confirmed case of an Emperor being killed by his vassal. (There is an unconfirmed case of Emperor Komei who was allegedly poisoned to death. Also, Emperor Anko was allegedly killed by one of the members of the Imperial family, but his case is often excluded due to its low historicity.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>死亡した当日に葬ったことと、陵地・陵戸がないことは、他に例が無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no other emperor who was burried on the day of his death and who has no imperial property or imperial tomb guard.</e>
<cmt>陵地の定訳が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no other emperor who was brried on the day of his death and who has no imperial property or imperial tomb guard.</e>
<cmt>綴りを直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no other emperor who was brried on the day of his death and who has no imperial property or imperial tomb guard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>陵墓</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial Mausoleum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Mausoleum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Mausoleum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>『日本書紀』の崇峻天皇の五年十一月条に「馬子宿禰、群臣を詐めて曰はく、『今日、東国の調（ちょう）を進る。』という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), the article on November, Emperor Sushun era 5 tells &apos;Umako Sukune (third highest of the eight hereditary titles) deceived his subordinates, saying &quot;Today, I will present the Emperor with products of Togoku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>http://www.kunaicho.go.jp/ryobo/guide/032/index.html一原文一訳文の例外処置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), the chapter on November, 592 has the following entry: &apos;Umako Sukune (third highest of the eight hereditary titles) deceived his subordinates, saying &quot;today, I will present the Emperor with products of Togoku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>西暦に変更しました。Article→chapter一原文一訳文の例外処置</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), the chapter on November, 592 has the following entry: &apos;Umako Sukune (third highest of the eight hereditary titles) deceived his subordinates, saying &quot;today, I will present the Emperor with products of Togoku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>乃ち東漢直駒（やまとのあやのあたいこま）をして、天皇を弑せまつらしむ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And he made YAMATO no Aya no Ataikoma kill the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He made YAMATO no Aya no Ataikoma kill the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処置</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He made YAMATO no Aya no Ataikoma kill the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>是の日に、天皇を倉梯岡（くらはし）陵に葬りまつる。」と出ている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor was buried in Kurahashino Okano Misasagi Mausoleum on the day.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor was buried in Kurahashino Okano Misasagi Mausoleum on that day.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処置</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor was buried in Kurahashino Okano Misasagi Mausoleum on that day.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="21">
<j>『延喜式』に「無陵地幷無戸」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Engishiki&quot; (codes and procedures on national rites and prayers) says that his mausoleum had no imperial property or imperial tomb guard&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Engishiki&quot; (codes and procedures on national rites and prayers) says &apos;his mausoleum had no imperial property or imperial tomb guard.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを移動しました。引用府を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Engishiki&quot; (codes and procedures on national rites and prayers) says &apos;his mausoleum had no imperial property or imperial tomb guard.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="22">
<j>現在、崇峻陵は、倉梯柴垣宮の旧地と伝えられてきた小字「天皇屋敷」に桜井市倉橋にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Now, Sushun Mausoleum is located in koaza (small administrative unit) called &apos;Tenno Yashiki&apos; (Emperor&apos;s residence) which has been said to be the former property of the palace of Shibakaki at Kurahashi in Kurahashi, Sakurai City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Now, Sushun Mausoleum is located in a koaza (small administrative unit) called &apos;Tenno Yashiki&apos; (Emperor&apos;s residence) which has been said to be the former property of the palace of Shibakaki at Kurahashi in Kurahashi, Sakurai City.</e>
<cmt>冠詞を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Now, Sushun Mausoleum is located in a koaza (small administrative unit) called &apos;Tenno Yashiki&apos; (Emperor&apos;s residence) which has been said to be the former property of the palace of Shibakaki at Kurahashi in Kurahashi, Sakurai City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>同地に、崇峻天皇の位牌を祀る金福寺があったことから、陵地として1889年（明治22年）に決定したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The quarter was concluded as the mausoleum land of Emperor Sushun in 1889 because there was Konpuku-ji Temple where his Buddhist mortuary tablet was enshrined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The quarter was designated as the mausoleum land of Emperor Sushun in 1889 because of Konpuku-ji Temple, where his Buddhist mortuary tablet was enshrined, was located on the same land.</e>
<cmt>Concludeは不適切なので変えました。「同地」を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The quarter was designated as the mausoleum land of Emperor Sushun in 1889 because of Konpuku-ji Temple, where his Buddhist mortuary tablet was enshrined, was located on the same land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="24">
<j>1876年（明治9年）、治定、改修あり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was authorized and repaired in 1876.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was authorized and repaired in 1876.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was authorized and repaired in 1876.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="25">
<j>ただし根拠に乏しく、近年では、桜井市倉橋にある巨大方墳、赤坂天王山古墳を崇峻陵とする森浩一の見解が有力視されるようになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But because the conclusion lacks foundation, recently, the most prevailing view presented by Koichi MORI, believes Akasaka Tennozan Tumulus, a giant square tumulus in Kurahashi, Sakurai City is Sushun Mausoleum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But the authorization lacks foundation, and in recent years, Koichi MORI&apos;s view that Akasaka Tennozan Tumulus, a giant square tumulus in Kurahashi, Sakurai City is Sushun&apos;s Mausoleum is most prevalent.</e>
<cmt>Because：不適切なので削除しました。より自然な英語に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But the authorization lacks foundation, and in recent years, Koichi MORI&apos;s view that Akasaka Tennozan Tumulus, a giant square tumulus in Kurahashi, Sakurai City is Sushun&apos;s Mausoleum is most prevalent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>同古墳は6世紀末から7世紀初頭に築造された方墳で、東西44.5m、南北42.2m、高さ約9.1m、全長17mの横穴式石室を持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a square tumulus built between late 6th century and early 7th century, measuring 44.5m from east to west, 42.2m from north to south, with a horizontal stone chamber of about 9.1m tall and 17m long.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a square tumulus built between the late 6th century and early 7th century, measuring 44.5m from east to west, 42.2m from north to south, with a horizontal stone chamber about 9.1m tall and 17m long.</e>
<cmt>前置詞、冠詞を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a square tumulus built between the late 6th century and early 7th century, measuring 44.5m from east to west, 42.2m from north to south, with a horizontal stone chamber about 9.1m tall and 17m long.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="27">
<j>また、斑鳩町法隆寺にある藤ノ木古墳の被葬者を崇峻天皇とする説も出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the theories claims that the Emperor buried in Fujinoki Tumulus in Horyuji, Ikaruga-cho Town is Emperor Sushun.</e>
<cmt>この文の法隆寺は寺の名前ではないのでHoryu-ji Templeとはしませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is yet another theory that the person buried in Fujinoki Tumulus in Horyuji, Ikaruga-cho Town is Emperor Sushun.</e>
<cmt>より適切は表現に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is yet another theory that the person buried in Fujinoki Tumulus in Horyuji, Ikaruga-cho Town is Emperor Sushun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 BOTarate(id:185620), 霧木諒二(id:9795), Nnh(id:474), China(id:10362), Ojigiri(id:329), Eskimbot(id:29676), アスカ(id:9205), Greenland4(id:114494), Mari(id:1553), Abentz(id:12270), Masyu(id:31065), 新芽(id:50924), Goki(id:7107), Kinori(id:443), 代言人(id:33675), 日本一弱い男(id:92046), Mts1008(id:61633), Point136(id:211299), Shimoxx(id:9332), 麦塚ほとり(id:54917), Klesha(id:203751), LERK(id:4460), Higashi(id:8842), M-sho-gun(id:88956), Decosu(id:89170), XXx(id:75211), Carbuncle(id:346), ウース(id:31355), 松茸(id:27535), VanishingDuck(id:125995), Robbot(id:3063), Sh(id:2707), Oh!wenka(id:53059), Alecs.bot(id:194707), かえるちゃん(id:197260), VolkovBot(id:105371), Kaba(id:17904), Nidarin(id:6420), SuisuiBot(id:10165), R28Bot(id:177951), 斎東小世(id:134120), YOSHI438(id:174755), Mipu(id:5360), Suisui(id:69), LeonardoRob0t(id:25875), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>