<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>好子内親王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Princess Koshi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Princess Koshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Princess Koshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>好子内親王（こうし（よしこ）ないしんのう、生年不詳 - 建久3年7月3日 (旧暦)（1192年8月12日））は、平安時代末期の皇族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Princess Koshi (Koshi (Yoshiko) Naishinno, year of birth unknown - August 12, 1192) was a member of Imperial family in the end of Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Princess Koshi (Koshi/Yoshiko Naishinno, year of birth unknown - August 12, 1192) was a member of the Imperial family in the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Princess Koshi (also known as Yoshiko, year of birth unknown - August 12, 1192) was a member of the Imperial Family in the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>also known as 補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>伊勢斎宮。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was Ise Saigu (vestal virgin princess serving at Ise-jingu Shrine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was an Ise Saigu (a vestal virgin princess serving at Ise-jingu Shrine).</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was an Ise Saigu (a vestal virgin princess serving at Ise-jingu Shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>後白河天皇の第2皇女で、母は高倉三位藤原成子（大納言藤原季成女）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was second Princess of Emperor Goshirakawa, and her mother was Takakura-Sanmi FUJIWARA no Shigeko (daughter of Dainagon, or chief councilor of state, FUJIWARA no Suenari).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was the second Princess of Emperor Goshirakawa, and her mother was Takakura-Sanmi FUJIWARA no Shigeko (daughter of Dainagon, or chief councilor of state, FUJIWARA no Suenari).</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was the second Princess of Emperor Goshirakawa, and her mother was Takakura-Sanmi FUJIWARA no Shigeko (daughter of Dainagon, or chief councilor of state, FUJIWARA no Suenari).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>同母兄弟に以仁王・守覚法親王・亮子内親王（殷富門院）・式子内親王・休子内親王らがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She had Prince Mochihito, Cloistered Imperial Prince Shukaku, Imperial Princess Ryoshi (Inpumonin), Imperial Princess Shikishi, Imperial Princess Kyushi, and others as her real brothers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her siblings included Prince Mochihito, Cloistered Imperial Prince Shukaku, Imperial Princess Ryoshi (Inpumonin), Imperial Princess Shikishi, and Imperial Princess Kyushi.</e>
<cmt>this translator needs to learn that “brothers” are all male</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her siblings included Prince Mochihito, Cloistered Imperial Prince Shukaku, Imperial Princess Ryoshi (Inpumonin), Imperial Princess Shikishi, and Imperial Princess Kyushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>保元3年（1158年）異母兄二条天皇の斎宮に卜定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1158, she was selected by bokujo (to decide by fortunetelling) as Saigu of Emperor Nijo, her older half-brother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1158, she was selected by divination to be the Saigu of Emperor Nijo, her older half-brother.</e>
<cmt>divination</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1158, she was selected by bokujo (to decide by fortunetelling) to be the Saigu of Emperor Nijo, her older half-brother.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>永暦元年（1160年）伊勢に群行。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1160, she made Gunko (Saigu heading to Ise after the purification) to Ise.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1160, she went to Ise.</e>
<cmt>I don&apos;t think what was written really made the meaning any clearer that simply “went”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1160, she went to Ise.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>永万元年（1165年）二条天皇の譲位により退下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1165, she resigned by abdication of the throne of Emperor Nijo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1165, she resigned because of Emperor Nijo&apos;s abdication of the throne.</e>
<cmt>rephrased for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1165, she resigned because of Emperor Nijo&apos;s abdication of the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>建久3年7月薨去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She died in July, 1192.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She died in July, 1192.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She died in August, 1192.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), Masyu(id:31065), YOSHI438(id:174755), Tribot(id:186681), 可怜(id:206074), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>