<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>天豊津媛命</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amatoyotsuhime no mikoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amatoyotsuhime no mikoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amatoyotsuhime no mikoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>天豊津媛命（あまとよつひめのみこと）は、欠史八代、懿徳天皇の皇后。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amatoyotsuhime no mikoto was the Empress of Emperor Itoku, one of the eight emperors living during the Kesshi-Hachidai (Eight Undocumented Sovereigns).</e>
<cmt>欠史八代→定訳不明：Kesshi-Hachidai (Eight Undocumented Sovereigns)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amatoyotsuhime no mikoto was the Empress of Emperor Itoku, one of the eight emperors living during the Kesshi-Hachidai (Eight Undocumented Sovereigns).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amatoyotsuhime no mikoto was the Empress of Emperor Itoku, one of the eight emperors living during the Kesshi-Hachidai (Eight Undocumented Sovereigns).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>孝昭天皇と武石彦奇友背の生母。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was the real mother of Emperor Kosho and Takeishihikokushitomose.</e>
<cmt>武石彦奇友背→Takeishihikokushitomoseと統一用語リストの表記に従いました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was the real mother of Emperor Kosho and Takeishihikokushitomose.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was the real mother of Emperor Kosho and Takeishihikokushitomose.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>『日本書紀』本文での皇后で、息石耳命の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was the Empress who appears in the main text of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), and the daughter of Ikisomimi no mikoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was an empress in the main text of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), and a daughter of Ikisomimi no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>冠詞の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was an empress in the main text of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), and a daughter of Ikisomimi no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>なお『古事記』での皇后は、師木県主の祖である賦登麻和訶比売（飯日比売）、『日本書紀』第1の一書では磯城県主葉江の男弟猪手の娘である泉媛、第2の一書では磯城県主太眞稚彦の娘である飯日媛 である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Empress that appears in &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) is Futomawakahime (飯日比売Iihihime), who was the ancestor of Shiki no agatanonushi, while in the &apos;alternate writing 1-1&apos; transmitted by the Nihonshoki, the Empress is Izumihime, the daughter of Inode (猪手), who was the smaller brother of Shiki no agatanonushi Hae, and in the &apos;alternate writing 2-1,&apos; the Empress is Iihihime, who was the daughter of Shiki no agatanushi Futomawakahiko.</e>
<cmt>師木県主→Shiki no agatanonushiとしました。 『日本書紀』第1の一書→定訳不明：the &apos;alternate writing 1-1&apos; transmitted by the Nihonshoki としました。 猪手→正式な読み方不明です：Inode (猪手) としました。 男弟→定訳不明：smaller brotherとしました。 磯城県主葉江→Shiki no agatanonushi Hae としました。 第2の一書→定訳不明the &apos;alternate writing 2-1&apos; としました。 磯城県主太眞稚彦→Shiki no agatanushi Futomawakahikoとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Empress that appears in &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) is Futomawakahime (飯日比売Iihihime), who was an ancestor of Shiki no agatanonushi, while in a first writing in the Nihonshoki, the Empress is Izumihime, a daughter of Inode (猪手), who was a younger brother of Shiki no agatanonushi Hae, and in a second writing, the Empress is Iihihime, who was a daughter of Shiki no agatanushi Futomawakahiko.</e>
<cmt>『日本書紀』第1の一書→a first writing in the Nihonshoki と訳出し（他も同様に訳出し）。冠詞の見直し。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Empress that appears in &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) is Futomawakahime (飯日比売Iihihime), who was an ancestor of Shiki no agatanonushi, while the frist addendum to the Nihonshoki mentions the Empress is Izumihime, a daughter of Inode (猪手), who was a younger brother of Shiki no agatanonushi Hae, and the second addendum describes the Empress as Iihihime, who was a daughter of Shiki no agatanushi Futomawakahiko.</e>
<cmt>a first writing in→the frist addendum toa second writing→the second addendum</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Izayohi(id:13095), かえるちゃん(id:197260), Kaboyose-DSD(id:123658), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>