<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>懐良親王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Kanenaga</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Kanenaga</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Kanenaga</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>懐良親王（かねながしんのう/かねよししんのう、元徳元年（1329年）? - 弘和3年/永徳3年3月27日 (旧暦)（1383年4月30日））は、後醍醐天皇の皇子である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Kanenaga (Kaneyoshi) (1329?-April 30, 1383) was a prince of Emperor Godaigo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Kanenaga (Kaneyoshi) (1329?-April 30, 1383) was the prince of Emperor Godaigo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Kanenaga (Kaneyoshi) (c. 1329 - May 8, 1383) was the prince of Emperor Godaigo.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>母は二条為道の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of Tamemichi NIJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was the daughter of Tamemichi NIJO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was the daughter of Tamemichi NIJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>南北朝時代 (日本)、南朝 (日本)の征西大将軍であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a seisei taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the western barbarians&quot;) of the Southern Court (Japan) in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a seisei taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the western barbarians&quot;) of the Southern Court (Japan) during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a seisei taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the western barbarians&quot;) of the Southern Court (Japan) during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>このことから征西将軍宮（せいせいしょうぐんのみや）と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From this, he was called seisei shogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the western barbarians&quot;) no miya (Imperial prince).</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From this, he was called seisei shogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the western barbarians&quot;) no miya (Imperial prince).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From this, he was called seisei shogun no miya (Imperial Prince).</e>
<cmt>征西将軍　既出のため、補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>肥後国隈府（熊本県菊池市）を拠点に征西府の勢力を広げ、九州における南朝方の全盛期を築いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He enhanced the force of Seiseifu fortress based in Waifu, Higo province (Kikuchi City, Kumamoto Prefecture), and achieved the heyday of the Southern Court in Kyusyu region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He enhanced the force of Seiseifu fortress based in Waifu, Higo province (Kikuchi City, Kumamoto Prefecture), and achieved the heyday of the Southern Court in the Kyushu region.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He enhanced the force of Seiseifu fortress based in Waifu, Higo province (Kikuchi City, Kumamoto Prefecture), and achieved the heyday of the Southern Court in the Kyushu region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>名前の読みが二種類あることについては、後醍醐天皇皇子の読みを参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Refer to the section of how to read the names of princes of Emperor Godaigo for that his name has two readings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Refer to the section of how to read the names of princes of Emperor Godaigo because his name has two readings.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Refer to the section of how to read the names of princes of Emperor Godaigo because his name has two readings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>建武の新政が崩壊した後、後醍醐天皇は各地に自分の皇子を派遣し、味方の勢力を築こうと考えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Kenmu Restoration collapsed, Emperor Godaigo dispatched his princes to various regions to gain support forces.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Kenmu Restoration collapsed, Emperor Godaigo dispatched his princes to various regions to gain support forces.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Kenmu Restoration collapsed, Emperor Godaigo dispatched his princes to various regions to gain support forces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>延元元年/建武 (日本)3年（1336年）（時期については諸説あり）にまだ幼い懐良親王を征西大将軍に任命し、九州に向かわせることにした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1336 (there are various theories regarding the year of the incident), Emperor Godaigo appointed the young Imperial Prince Kanenaga to a seisei taishogun, and made him head for Kyusyu.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1336 (there are various theories regarding the year of the incident), Emperor Godaigo appointed the young Imperial Prince Kanenaga to seisei taishogun, and made him the head for Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1336 (there are various theories regarding the year of the incident), Emperor Godaigo appointed the young Imperial Prince Kanenaga to seisei taishogun, and sent him to Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>sent him としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>親王は五条頼元らに補佐されて四国伊予国忽那島（愛媛県松山市）へ渡り、当地の宇都宮貞泰や瀬戸内海の海賊衆である熊野水軍の援助を得て数年間滞在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The imperial prince, with the support of Yorimoto GOJO or others, crossed the sea to Kutsuna-jima Island, Iyo Province in Shikoku region, and stayed in there for a few years with the support of Sadayasu UTSUNOMIYA in that region or Kumano Suigun Navy, pirates around Seto Inland Sea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The imperial prince, with the support of Yorimoto GOJO or others, crossed the sea to Kutsuna-jima Island, Iyo Province in Shikoku region, and stayed in there for a few years with the support of Sadayasu UTSUNOMIYA in that region or Kumano Suigun Navy, pirates around Seto Inland Sea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Prince, with the support of Yorimoto GOJO or others, crossed the sea to Kutsuna-jima Island, Iyo Province (Matsuyama City, Ehime Prefecture) in Shikoku region, and stayed there for a few years with the support of Sadayasu UTSUNOMIYA in that region or Kumano Suigun Navy, pirates around Seto Inland Sea.</e>
<cmt>愛媛県松山市　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>その後、興国2年（1341年）頃に薩摩国に上陸。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he landed in Satsuma Province around 1341.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he landed in Satsuma Province around 1341.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he landed in Satsuma Province around 1341.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>谷山城にあって北朝 (日本)・室町幕府方の島津氏と対峙しつつ九州の諸豪族の勧誘に努める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was in Taniyama-jo Castle, making efforts to solicit various Gozoku (local ruling family) in Kyusyu, while he confronted the Shimazu clan on the side of Muromachi Bakufu in the Northern Court (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was in Taniyama-jo Castle, making an effort to solicit various Gozoku (local ruling family) in Kyushu, while he confronted the Shimazu clan on the side of Muromachi Bakufu in the Northern Court (Japan).</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was in Taniyama-jo Castle, making an effort to solicit various Gozoku (local ruling family) in Kyushu, while he confronted the Shimazu clan on the side of Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) in the Northern Court (Japan).</e>
<cmt>幕府　の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>ようやく肥後国の菊池武光や阿蘇惟直を味方につけ、正平 (日本)3年（1348年）に隈府城に入って征西府を開き、九州経略を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Finally, he won Takemitsu KIKUCHI or Korenao ASO in Higo Province over to his side, and entered Waifu-jo Castle to open Seiseifu fortress in 1348, which was his start-up of Kyusyu-keiryaku (govern the kyusyu region).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Finally, he won Takemitsu KIKUCHI or Korenao ASO in Higo Province over to his side, and entered Waifu-jo Castle to open Seiseifu fortress in 1348, which was his start-up of Kyushu-keiryaku (governing the kyushu region).</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Finally, he won Takemitsu KIKUCHI or Korenao ASO in Higo Province over to his side, and entered Waifu-jo Castle to open Seiseifu fortress in 1348, which was his start-up of Kyushu-keiryaku (governing the Kyushu region).</e>
<cmt>Kyushu と大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>この頃、足利幕府は博多に鎮西総大将として一色範氏、仁木義長らを置いており、これらと攻防を繰り返した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He kept struggling with Noriuji ISSHIKI and Yoshinaga NIKI in Hakata, the commanders in chiefs of Kyushu region deployed by Ashikaga Shogunate around this time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He continued to struggle with Noriuji ISSHIKI and Yoshinaga NIKI in Hakata, the commanders in chiefs of Kyushu region deployed by Ashikaga Shogunate around this time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He continued to struggle with Noriuji ISSHIKI and Yoshinaga NIKI in Hakata, the commanders in chiefs of Kyushu region deployed by Ashikaga Shogunate around this time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>正平5年（1350年）、観応の擾乱と呼ばれる幕府の内紛で将軍足利尊氏とその弟足利直義が争うと、直義の養子足利直冬が九州へ入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the infighting of bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) called Kanno Disturbance in which Shogun Takauji ASHIKAGA and Takauji&apos;s younger brother, Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA fought in 1350, the adopted child of Naoyoshi, Tadafuyu ASHIKAGA entered Kyusyu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the infighting of the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) called the Kanno Disturbance in which Shogun Takauji ASHIKAGA and Takauji&apos;s younger brother, Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA fought in 1350, the adopted child of Naoyoshi, Tadafuyu ASHIKAGA entered Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the infighting of the bakufu called the Kanno Disturbance in which Shogun Takauji ASHIKAGA and Takauji&apos;s younger brother, Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA fought in 1350, the adopted child of Tadayoshi, Tadafuyu ASHIKAGA entered Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>直義→Tadayoshi としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>筑前国の少弐頼尚がこれを支援し、九州は幕府、直冬、南朝3勢力の鼎立状態となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorinao SHONI in Chikuzen Province supported Tadafuyu, and consequently Kyusyu turned out to be three-way struggle with Bakufu, Tadafuyu, and the Southern court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yorinao SHONI in Chikuzen Province supported Tadafuyu, and consequently Kyushu turned out to be a three-way struggle with the Bakufu, Tadafuyu, and the Southern court.</e>
<cmt>spelling, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorinao SHONI in Chikuzen Province supported Tadafuyu, and consequently Kyushu turned out to be a three-way struggle between the bakufu, Tadafuyu, and the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>three-way struggle between としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかし、正平7年/文和元年（1352年）に直義が殺害されると、直冬は中国に去った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Naoyoshi was killed in 1352, and Tadafuyu left for china.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Naoyoshi was killed in 1352, and Tadafuyu left for china.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Tadayoshi was killed in 1352, and Tadafuyu left for China.</e>
<cmt>直義→Tadayoshi としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これを機に一色範氏は少弐頼尚を攻めたが、頼尚に支援を求められた菊池武光は針摺原の戦い（福岡県太宰府市）で一色軍に大勝する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This triggered Noriuji ISSHIKI to attack Yorinao SHONI, but Takemitsu KIKUCHI who was asked to support Noriuji won a great victory over the Ishiki force in the Battle of Harisurubaru (Dazaifu City, Fukuoka Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This triggered Noriuji ISSHIKI to attack Yorinao SHONI, but Takemitsu KIKUCHI, who was asked to support Noriuji, won a great victory over the Ishiki forces in the Battle of Harisurubaru (Dazaifu City, Fukuoka Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This triggered Noriuji ISSHIKI to attack Yorinao SHONI, but Takemitsu KIKUCHI, who was asked to support Noriuji, won a great victory over the Isshiki forces in the Battle of Harisurubaru (Dazaifu City, Fukuoka Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>Isshiki としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>さらに懐良親王は菊池・少弐軍を率いて豊後国の大友氏泰を破り、一色範氏は九州から逃れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What&apos;s more, Imperial Prince Kanenaga who led the Kikuchi and Shoni force defeated Ujiyasu OTOMO in Bungo Province, and Noriuji ISSHIKI escaped from Kyusyu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What&apos;s more, Imperial Prince Kanenaga who led the Kikuchi and Shoni forces defeated Ujiyasu OTOMO in Bungo Province, and Noriuji ISSHIKI escaped from Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What&apos;s more, Imperial Prince Kanenaga who led the Kikuchi and Shoni forces defeated Ujiyasu OTOMO in Bungo Province, and Noriuji ISSHIKI escaped from Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="20">
<j>一色範氏が去った後、少弐頼尚が幕府方に転じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Noriuji ISSHIKI left, Yorinao SHONI switched to the bakufu side.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Noriuji ISSHIKI left, Yorinao SHONI switched to the bakufu side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Noriuji ISSHIKI left, Yorinao SHONI switched to the bakufu side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>菊池武光、赤星武貫、宇都宮貞久、草野永幸ら南朝方は正平14年/延文4年（1359年）の筑後川の戦い（大保原の戦い、福岡県小郡市）でこれを破り、正平16年（1361年）には九州の拠点である大宰府を制圧する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The southern court force including Takemitsu KIKUCHI, Taketsura AKABOSHI, Sadahisa UTSUNOMIYA, Nagayuki KUSANO defeated Yorinao SHONI in the Battle of Chikugo-gawa River (the Battle of Ohobaru, Ogori City, Fukuoka Prefecture) in 1359, and conquered Dazaifu, a stronghold of Kyusyu in 1361.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The southern court forces, including Takemitsu KIKUCHI, Taketsura AKABOSHI, Sadahisa UTSUNOMIYA, Nagayuki KUSANO, defeated Yorinao SHONI in the Battle of Chikugo-gawa River (the Battle of Ohobaru, Ogori City, Fukuoka Prefecture) in 1359, and conquered Dazaifu, a stronghold of Kyusyu in 1361.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The southern court forces, including Takemitsu KIKUCHI, Taketsura AKABOSHI, Sadahisa UTSUNOMIYA, Nagayuki KUSANO, defeated Yorinao SHONI in the Battle of Chikugo-gawa River (the Battle of Ohobaru, Ogori City, Fukuoka Prefecture) in 1359, and conquered Dazaifu, a stronghold of Kyushu in 1361.</e>
<cmt>Kyushu としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="22">
<j>幕府は2代将軍足利義詮の代に斯波氏経、渋川義行を九州探題に任命する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bakufu appointed Ujitsune SHIBA and Yoshiyuki SHIBUKAWA to Kyushu Tandai (local commissioner) in the generation of the second Shogun, Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bakufu appointed Ujitsune SHIBA and Yoshiyuki SHIBUKAWA to Kyushu Tandai (local commissioner) in the generation of the second Shogun, Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bakufu appointed Ujitsune SHIBA and Yoshiyuki SHIBUKAWA to Kyushu Tandai (local commissioner) in the generation of the second Shogun, Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>しかし、九州制圧は進まず、正平22/貞治6年（1367年）には幼い3代将軍足利義満を補佐した管領細川頼之が今川貞世（了俊）を九州探題に任命して派遣する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, conquering Kyusyu was not well proceeded, and in 1367, Shogunal Deputy, Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA who supported the third young shogun, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA appointed and dispatched Sadayo (Ryoshun) IMAGAWA to Kyushu Tandai.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, conquering Kyushu did not go well, and in 1367, Shogunal Deputy, Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA who supported the third young shogun, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA appointed and dispatched Sadayo (Ryoshun) IMAGAWA to Kyushu Tandai.</e>
<cmt>spelling, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, conquering Kyushu did not go well, and in 1367, Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA, a Kanrei (shogunal deputy) who supported the third young shogun, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, appointed and dispatched Sadayo (Ryoshun) IMAGAWA to Kyushu Tandai.</e>
<cmt>管領　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="24">
<j>明の朱元璋がこの頃北九州で活動していた倭寇と呼ばれる海上勢力の鎮圧を要求する国書を懐良親王に送ると、懐良ははじめは断った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Gensho SHU in Ming sent to Imperial Prince Kanenaga a sovereign&apos;s message that SHU required to have Imperial Prince Kanenaga suppress the pirates called wako (Japanese pirates) that were active in Kyusyu around that time, at first, Kanenaga refused it.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Gensho SHU in Ming sent to Imperial Prince Kanenaga a sovereign&apos;s message that SHU required to have Imperial Prince Kanenaga suppress the pirates called wako (Japanese pirates) that were active in Kyushu around that time, at first, Kanenaga refused.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Gensho SHU in Ming sent to Imperial Prince Kanenaga a sovereign&apos;s message that SHU required to have Imperial Prince Kanenaga suppress the pirates called wako (Japanese pirates) that were active in Kyushu around that time, at first, Kanenaga refused.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>しかし、後に臣従して「日本国王良懐」（『太祖実録』の記述による）として冊封を受け、中央では既に南朝勢力は衰微していたものの、懐良親王は明の権威と勢力を背景に独自に九州に南朝勢力を築く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, later on, Kanenaga followed SHU, and he was granted the title of `King of Japan Kanenaga&apos; (based on the record of &quot;Taiso Jitsuroku&quot; (the history of the founder)) under sakuho (homage by Chinese emperors), and with the help of Ming&apos;s authority and power, Imperial Prince Kanenaga built the Southern court force in Kyusyu, even though the Southern court force had waned in the central Kyusyu.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, later on, Kanenaga followed SHU, and he was granted the title of `King of Japan Kanenaga&apos; (based on the record of &quot;Taiso Jitsuroku&quot; - the history of the founder) under sakuho (homage by Chinese emperors), and with the help of Ming&apos;s authority and power, Imperial Prince Kanenaga built the Southern court force in Kyushu, even though the Southern court forces had waned in central Kyusyu.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, later on, Kanenaga followed SHU, and he was granted the title of &apos;King of Japan Kanenaga&apos; (based on the record of &quot;Taiso Jitsuroku&quot; - the history of the founder) under sakuho (homage by Chinese emperors), and with the help of Ming&apos;s authority and power, Imperial Prince Kanenaga built the Southern Court force in Kyushu, even though the Southern Court forces had waned in the center of the politics.</e>
<cmt>中央→政治の中央　と解釈し、center of the politicsとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="26">
<j>その後は今川貞世（了俊）に大宰府・博多を追われ、足利直冬も幕府に屈服したため九州は平定される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, Imperial Prince Kanenaga was forced by Sadayo (Ryoshun) IMAGAWA to leave Dazaifu and Hakata, and Kyusyu was settled after Tadafuyu ASHIKAGA surrendered to the bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, Imperial Prince Kanenaga was forced by Sadayo (Ryoshun) IMAGAWA to leave Dazaifu and Hakata, and Kyushu was settled after Tadafuyu ASHIKAGA surrendered to the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, Imperial Prince Kanenaga was forced by Sadayo (Ryoshun) IMAGAWA to leave Dazaifu and Hakata, and Kyushu was settled after Tadafuyu ASHIKAGA surrendered to the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>懐良は征西将軍の職を良成親王（後村上天皇皇子）に譲り筑後国矢部村で病没したと伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanenaga was said to have died of disease in Yabe-mura, Chikugo Province after he ceded the post of seisei shogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the western barbarians&quot;) to the Imperial Prince Yoshinari (prince of Emperor Gomurakami).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanenaga was said to have died of disease in Yabe-mura, Chikugo Province after he ceded the post of seisei shogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the western barbarians&quot;) to the Imperial Prince Yoshinari (prince of Emperor Gomurakami).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanenaga was said to have died of disease in Yabe-mura, Chikugo Province after he ceded the post of seisei shogun to the Imperial Prince Yoshinari (prince of Emperor Gomurakami).</e>
<cmt>征西将軍　既出のため、補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="28">
<j>また、懐良親王が「良懐」として明と冊封関係を結んでしまったため、義満が日明貿易（勘合貿易）を開始する際に新たに建文帝から冊封をうけ「日本国王」となるまでは、北朝や薩摩の島津氏なども明に使節を送る場合は「良懐」の名義を用いねばならないという事態も発生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because Imperial Prince Kanenaga was in Sakuho relationship (vassal relationship) with Ming as `良懐,&apos; to commence Japan-Ming trade (the tally trade), the Northern court or the Shimazu clan in Satsuma Province had to use the name of `良懐&apos; to send an ambassador to Ming until Yoshimitsu was granted the title of `King of Japan&apos; under sakuho by Kenbun-tei (Jianwen Emperor).</e>
<cmt>`良懐&apos; →読み方不明のため原文のままとしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Imperial Prince Kanenaga was in Sakuho relationship (vassal relationship) with Ming as `良懐,&apos; to commence Japan-Ming trade (the tally trade), the Northern court or the Shimazu clan in Satsuma Province had to use the name of `良懐&apos; to send an ambassador to Ming until Yoshimitsu was granted the title of `King of Japan&apos; under sakuho by Kenbun-tei (Jianwen Emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Imperial Prince Kanenaga was in Sakuho relationship (vassal relationship) with Ming as &apos;良懐,&apos; to commence Japan-Ming trade (the tally trade), the Northern Court or the Shimazu clan in Satsuma Province had to use the name of &apos;良懐&apos; to send an ambassador to Ming until Yoshimitsu was granted the title of &apos;King of Japan&apos; under sakuho by Kenbun-tei (Jianwen Emperor).</e>
<cmt>アポストロフィーを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>その足利義満も、当初は明国から、「良懐と日本の国王位を争っている持明の臣下」と看做されて、外交関係を結ぶ相手と認識されず、苦労している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA was regarded by Ming as `a vassal of Jimyo who competed for the rank of Japanese King with 良懐&apos;, and had a difficulty in having Ming approve Yoshimitsu as a partner for diplomatic relations.</e>
<cmt>`良懐&apos; →読み方不明のため原文のままとしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA was regarded by Ming as `a vassal of Jimyo who competed for the rank of Japanese King with 良懐&apos;, and had difficulty with having Ming approve Yoshimitsu as a partner for diplomatic relations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA was regarded by Ming as &apos;a vassal of Jimyo who competed for the rank of Japanese King with 良懐&apos;, and had difficulty with having Ming approve Yoshimitsu as a partner for diplomatic relations.</e>
<cmt>アポストロフィーを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="30">
<j>墓所・霊廟</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Grave site, Mausoleum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Grave site, Mausoleum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Grave site, Mausoleum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>墓所の伝承地はいくつかあるが、宮内庁は熊本県八代市のものとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His grave site was said to be in several places; the imperial court approved the one in Yatsushiro City, Kumamoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grave site was said to be in several places; the imperial court approved the one in Yatsushiro City, Kumamoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grave site was said to be in several places; the Imperial Household Agency approved the one in Yatsushiro City, Kumamoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>宮内庁→Imperial Household Agency　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>明治時代になって同市の八代宮に祀られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was enshrined in Yatsushiro-gu Shrine in Yatsushiro City in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was enshrined in Yatsushiro-gu Shrine in Yatsushiro City during the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was enshrined in Yatsushiro-gu Shrine in Yatsushiro City during the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="33">
<j>エピソード</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Episode</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Episode</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Episode</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>「賀蘭山前に相逢うて、いささか以って博戯せん」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">`賀蘭山前に相逢うて、いささか以って博戯せん&apos;</e>
<cmt>意味不明のため原文のままとしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">`賀蘭山前に相逢うて、いささか以って博戯せん&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&apos;Why don&apos;t we march first and win the battle against Ming in front of Mt. Garan and enjoy playing sugoroku (Japanese game) afterwards&apos; (賀蘭山前に相逢うて、いささか以って博戯せん)</e>
<cmt>意味を以下のサイトで探し、左記のように追加いたしました。（参考：http://nagoshi2showa.web.fc2.com/two.html）</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="35">
<j>辞世の歌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Farewell poem composed on the eve of one&apos;s death</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Farewell poem composed on the eve of one&apos;s death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Farewell poem composed on the eve of his death</e>
<cmt>懐良の辞世の歌なので、one&apos;s →his　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>「雲井にものぼるべき身のさはなくて　雲雀の床に音をのみぞなく」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">`雲井にものぼるべき身のさはなくて　雲雀の床に音をのみぞなく&apos;</e>
<cmt>意味不明のため原文のままとしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">`雲井にものぼるべき身のさはなくて　雲雀の床に音をのみぞなく&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&apos;雲井にものぼるべき身のさはなくて　雲雀の床に音をのみぞなく&apos;</e>
<cmt>アポストロフィーを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Lonicera(id:20638), Stanislaus(id:1806), 水野白楓(id:22811), Cprobot(id:97843), PATMAN(id:145791), Lupinoid(id:68), Himazin(id:22034), 味っ子(id:17086), Udon-ya(id:48431), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), 沢田(id:40580), でここ(id:9565), らりた(id:1327), Mymelo(id:122034), 鞠智(id:48755), Amler(id:101250), 代言人(id:33675), UMBRO(id:100484), Mfac(id:120195), Junger(id:10282), Suisui(id:69), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>