<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>神武天皇祭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jinmu tenno sai (Emperor Jinmu Ceremony)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jinmu tenno sai (Emperor Jinmu Ceremony)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jinmu tenno sai (Emperor Jinmu Ceremony)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>神武天皇祭（じんむてんのうさい）とは、神武天皇を祀る皇室祭礼。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jinmu tenno sai (Emperor Jinmu Ceremony) refers to the ceremony of the Imperial Household to honor Emperor Jinmu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jinmu tenno sai (Emperor Jinmu Ceremony) refers to the ceremony of the Imperial Household to honor Emperor Jinmu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jinmu tenno sai (Emperor Jinmu Ceremony) refers to the ceremony of the Imperial Household to honor Emperor Jinmu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>戦前の祝祭日の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of the public holidays in the prewar period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was one of the public holidays in the prewar period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was one of the public holidays in the prewar period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>現在では新暦4月3日に行なわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, it is performed on April 3 (based on the new calendar).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, it is performed on April 3 (based on the new calendar).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, it is performed on April 3 (based on the new calendar).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>初代天皇である神武天皇を記念したもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is performed in commemoration of the first emperor, Emperor Jinmu; the date of April 3 was evaluated by converting March 11(based on the old calendar), AD 586 when the emperor passed away into the Gregorian calendar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is performed in commemoration of the first emperor, Emperor Jinmu; the date of April 3 was evaluated by converting March 11 (based on the old calendar), AD 586, when the emperor passed away, into the Gregorian calendar.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is performed in commemoration of the first emperor, Emperor Jinmu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。一原文一訳文例外対処。原文を分割、文末を修正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>4月3日は、崩御の日とされる太歳己卯（紀元前586年）3月11日 (旧暦)をグレゴリオ暦に換算したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The date of April 3 is evaluated by converting the date of March 11, AD 586 (in the lunar calendar), which is said to be the day of the demise of the Emperor, into the Gregorian calendar.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。一原文一訳文例外対処。原文を分割。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>宮中の宮中三殿と神武天皇陵で儀式が行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ceremony is performed in Kyuchu sanden (the Three Shrines in the Imperial Court) and the Mausoleum of Emperor Jinmu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ceremony is performed in Kyuchu sanden (the Three Shrines in the Imperial Court) and the Mausoleum of Emperor Jinmu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ceremony is performed in Kyuchu sanden (the Three Shrines in the Imperial Court) and the Mausoleum of Emperor Jinmu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>神武天皇祭は幕末の孝明天皇代に始まり、明治4年（1871年）9月に定められた「四時祭典定則」で規則化された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jinmu tenno sai (Emperor Jinmu Ceremony) was commenced in the generation of Emperor Komei, it was regulated by `Shiji saiten saisoku&apos; (Seasonal Ceremony Regulations) which was defined in September 1871, and again it was legislated by `Koshitu Saishi Rei/Imperial household religious rites ordinance&apos; in 1908.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jinmu tenno sai (Emperor Jinmu Ceremony) commenced in the generation of Emperor Komei, it was regulated by `Shiji saiten saisoku&apos; (Seasonal Ceremony Regulations) which was defined in September 1871, and again it was legislated by `Koshitu Saishi Rei/Imperial household religious rites ordinance&apos; in 1908.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jinmu tenno-sai Festival commenced in the generation of Emperor Komei in the closing days of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and it was regulated under the &apos;Shiji Saiten Teisoku&apos; (the Regulations of Seasonal Ceremonies), which was defined in September 1871.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。一原文一訳文例外対処。原文を分割、文末を修正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その後、明治41年（1908年）の「皇室祭祀令」で改めて法制化された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, it was given legal force under the &apos;Koshitsu Saishi Rei&apos; (the Ordinance of Imperial Household Religious Rites) in 1908.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。一原文一訳文例外対処。原文を分割。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>昭和22年（1947年）に公的には廃止されたが、皇室の私的行事として存続している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was officially abolished in 1947, but it is still continuous as a personal ceremony of the Imperial Household.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was officially abolished in 1947, but it is still continues as a personal ceremony of the Imperial Household.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was officially abolished in 1947, but it still continues as a private ceremony of the Imperial Household.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>皇室の祖先祭祀のひとつであるが、他の歴代天皇とは別格の扱いを受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of religious services for ancestors in the Imperial Household; Emperor Jinmu was treated differently from other emperors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is one of religious services for ancestors in the Imperial Household; Emperor Jinmu was treated differently from other emperors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is just one of the religious services for the ancestors of the Imperial Household, Emperor Jinmu is treated differently from the other successive emperors.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>歴代天皇の祭祀は、先帝四代(現天皇の前4代の天皇)は毎年崩御日に祭祀されるが、それ以外の天皇は式年祭（3年・5年・10年・20年・30年・40年・50年・以後100年ごと）にのみ祭祀が行なわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A religious service is performed for four previous emperors (going back four generations from the current emperor) on the anniversary of death each year, while a religious service is performed for other emperors only on &quot;Shiki nen sai&quot;: 3 years, 5 years, 10years, 20 years, 30 years, 40 years, 50 years, subsequently 100 years after the death of an emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A religious service is performed for four previous emperors (going back four generations from the current emperor) on the anniversary of their death each year, while a religious service is performed for other emperors only on &quot;Shiki nen sai:&quot; 3 years, 5 years, 10years, 20 years, 30 years, 40 years, 50 years, subsequently 100 years after the death of an emperor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A religious service is performed for four previous emperors (going back four generations from the current emperor) on the anniversary of their death each year, while a religious service is performed for other emperors only on Shiki nen sai: 3 years, 5 years, 10 years, 20 years, 30 years, 40 years, 50 years, subsequently 100 years after the death of an emperor.</e>
<cmt>原文に『』のない&quot;を削除スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし、神武天皇に関しては、皇統の始祖として毎年祭祀されるのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, a religious service is performed for Emperor Jinmu each year as the earliest ancestor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, a religious service is performed for Emperor Jinmu each year as the earliest ancestor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the religious service for Emperor Jinmu is performed every year as he is the first ancestor of the Imperial line.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>そのため、名称も他の天皇のように神武天皇例祭ではなく、神武天皇祭となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it is called Jinmu tenno sai (Emperor Jinmu Ceremony) instead of Jinmu Tenno reisai (Emperor Jinmu Annual Ceremony); reisai (annual ceremony) is used for the other emperors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it is called Jinmu tenno sai (Emperor Jinmu Ceremony) instead of Jinmu Tenno reisai (Emperor Jinmu Annual Ceremony); reisai (annual ceremony) is used for the other emperors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore it is called Jinmu tenno-sai instead of Jinmu tenno-reisai, although the term &quot;reisai&quot; (an annual ceremony) is used for the festivals for the other emperors.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>当日、皇霊殿で儀式が行なわれるとともに、神武天皇陵には勅使が参向し奉幣される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the day of Jinmu tenno sai (Emperor Jinmu Ceremony), a ceremony is performed at Korei-den (the Imperial Ancestors&apos; Shrine) to honor the imperial ancestors; an imperial messenger visited there to give condolence money.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the day of Jinmu tenno sai (Emperor Jinmu Ceremony), a ceremony is performed at Korei-den (the Imperial Ancestors&apos; Shrine) to honor the imperial ancestors; an imperial messenger visits there to give condolence money.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the day of Jinmu tenno-sai Festival, a ceremony is performed at the Korei-den (the Imperial Ancestors&apos; Shrine), and an imperial messenger is sent to the Mausoleum of Emperor Jinmu to offer heihaku (Shinto offerings such as cloth, paper, and rope).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>なお、旧制では式年祭には、天皇自ら神武天皇陵へ行幸して参拝することが定められていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the old system, it was speculated that the emperor himself visits the mausoleum of Emperor Jinmu on shiki nen sai for worshipping.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the old system, it was speculated that the emperor himself visits the mausoleum of Emperor Jinmu on shiki nen sai for worshipping.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the old system, it was speculated that the emperor himself visits the mausoleum of Emperor Jinmu on shiki nen sai for worshipping.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>また、橿原神宮・宮崎神宮などの神武天皇を祀る神社を中心として、全国の神社の一部で祭典が行なわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major rites and festivals are performed in some shrines across the country mainly including the shrines that honor Emperor Jinmu such as Kashihara-Jingu Shrine or Miyazaki-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major rites and festivals are performed in some shrines across the country mainly including the shrines that honor Emperor Jinmu such as Kashihara-Jingu Shrine or Miyazaki-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rites and festivals are performed at some shrines across the country, mainly at the shrines that honor Emperor Jinmu such as Kashihara-jingu Shrine and Miyazaki-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Izayohi(id:13095), 伏儀(id:142093), Nnh(id:474), Stanislaus(id:1806), Saaki(id:43602), ごまふあざ(id:36855), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>