<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>勅旨牧</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chokushimaki (Imperial pastures)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chokushimaki (Imperial pastures)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chokushimaki (Imperial pastures)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>勅旨牧（ちょくしまき）は、古代日本において、天皇の 勅旨により開発された牧場であり、馬寮などが用いる軍馬などの供給源とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In ancient Japan Chokushimaki was a ranch developed by emperor&apos;s Chokushi, and was used as a supply source of war horses for Meryo (the section taking care of imperial horses)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In ancient Japan, Chokushimaki was a ranch developed by the emperor&apos;s Chokushi and was used to supply war horses for the Meryo (the section taking care of imperial horses).</e>
<cmt>文末のピリオド追加, 必要なところの冠詞、theとカンマを付け加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In ancient Japan, Chokushimaki was a ranch developed by the emperor&apos;s Chokushi and was used to supply war horses for the Meryo (the section taking care of imperial horses).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>御牧（みまき）とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also called Mimaki.</e>
<cmt>御牧ともいう。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also called Mimaki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also called Mimaki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>官牧には、ほかに諸国牧、近都牧が存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were Shokumaki and Kintomaki (pasture where animals were sent to graze) in Kanboku (state-owned sock farm.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were Shokumaki and Kintomaki (pasture where animals were sent to graze) in Kanboku (state-owned sock farm).</e>
<cmt>空欄が多いところを省き、()が抜けていたところ補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were Shokumaki and Kintomaki (pasture where animals were sent to graze) in Kanboku (state-owned sock farm).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>日本では古墳時代に古墳の副葬品として馬具が見られることからこの頃に乗馬文化が導入され、軍事的利用される馬の育成は日本列島の各地へ広まり、特に東国において分布が拡大する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From seeing the harness as burial goods of the old tomb it proved that a cavalry horse culture started at the tumulus period in Japan, and then raising horses for military use spreaded to various places in the Japanese Islands, especially the distribution expanded in the eastern country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From seeing the harness as burial goods of the old tomb it proved that a cavalry horse culture started at the tumulus period in Japan, and then raising horses for military use spreaded to various places in the Japanese Islands, especially the distribution expanded in the eastern country.</e>
<cmt>空欄が多いところを省きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From seeing the harness as burial goods of the old tomb it proved that a cavalry horse culture started at the tumulus period in Japan, and then raising horses for military use spreaded to various places in the Japanese Islands, especially the distribution expanded in the eastern country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>ヤマト王権では推古朝の頃には馬を管理する官職が存在しており、畿内の有力豪族により馬産が行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Yamato sovereignty (the ancient Japan sovereignty) at the Reign of Empress Suiko, the government post to manage the horses already existed, a powerful clan produced horses in and around the capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Yamato sovereignty (the ancient Japan sovereignty) at the Reign of Empress Suiko, the government post to manage the horses already existed, a powerful clan produced horses in and around the capital.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Yamato sovereignty (the ancient Japan sovereignty) at the Reign of Empress Suiko, the government post to manage the horses already existed, a powerful clan produced horses in and around the capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>地方においても在地首長による乗用馬の生産が行われ、律令制下には中央への貢馬が行われるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, in the provinces a principal of the local land produced cavalry horses, the horses were contributed to the central authority under the ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, in the provinces local leaders produced cavalry horses, which were contributed to the central authority under the ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>在地首長を言い換え、重複した主語をはずしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, in the provinces local leaders produced cavalry horses, which were contributed to the central authority under the ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>勅旨牧は、奈良時代後期に牧の管理を請け負ってきた兵部省から分離独立する形で、新たに設定されるようになったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Chokushimaki came to be set independently to separate from the Hyobusho (ministry of military) that has undertaken the management of Maki at the latter term of the Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that Chokushimaki was newly established to separate it from the Hyobusho (ministry of military) that had undertaken the management of Maki in the later part of the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ「新たに」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that Chokushimaki was newly established to separate it from the Hyobusho (ministry of military) that had undertaken the management of Maki in the later part of the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>この時期には令制国やそこに設置された牧（御厩）からのウマの貢馬が滞りがちとなり、更に太政官において軍権を握った最高責任者の藤原仲麻呂が乱を起こす（藤原仲麻呂の乱）など、天皇を守るための直轄の軍備の必要性が唱えられた時期であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time the contribution of horses from Ryoseikoku or Mimaki came to tend to stagnate, and also FUJIWARA no Nakamaro who gripped the military power in the Dajokan caused the war (FUJIWARA no Nakamaro&apos;s War), so it was time when the necessities of the armaments under the direct control of defending the emperor had been recited,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time the supply of horses from Ryoseikoku and Mimaki tended to stagnate, and also a chief executive, FUJIWARA no Nakamaro, who had a tight grip on military power in the Dajokan, caused a war (FUJIWARA no Nakamaro&apos;s War), so it was a time when the necessity to keep armaments under the direct control of those defending the emperor had been refuted.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ「最高責任者の」 必要な冠詞を付け加え　最後の文のカンマをピリオドに直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time the supply of horses from Ryoseikoku and Mimaki tended to stagnate, and also a chief executive, FUJIWARA no Nakamaro, who had a tight grip on military power in the Dajokan, caused a war (FUJIWARA no Nakamaro&apos;s War), so it was a time when the necessity to keep armaments under the direct control of those defending the emperor had been refuted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>このために当初は天皇直属の厩を管理していた内厩寮の下に置かれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For that reason Chokushimaki was under the control of Naikyuryo (Bureau of administration of barn in the imperial court) in the beginning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For that reason Chokushimaki was under the control of Naikyuryo (Bureau of administration of barn in the imperial court) in the beginning.</e>
<cmt>空欄が多いところを省きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For that reason Chokushimaki was under the control of Naikyuryo (Bureau of administration of barn in the imperial court) in the beginning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>『延喜式』によれば、勅旨牧は信濃国（16ヶ所）・甲斐国（穂坂牧、真衣野牧、柏前牧の3ヶ所）・上野国（9ヶ所）・武蔵国（4ヶ所）の計4ヶ国に設置され、前2ヶ国は左馬寮、後2ヶ国は右馬寮の管轄下であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Engishiki&quot; (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers), chokushimaki was set at four provinces: Shinano Province (16 locations), Kai Province (3 locations of Hosaka Maki, Maino Maki, and Kasshiwamae Maki), Kozuke Province (9 locations), and Musashi Province (4 locations), and the first two provinces were under the jurisdiction of Samaryo (Left Division of Bureau of Horses), and the last two provinces, under the jurisdiction of Umaryo (Right Division of Bureau of Horses).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Engishiki&quot; (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers), chokushimaki was established in four provinces: Shinano Province (16 locations), Kai Province (3 locations of Hosaka Maki, Maino Maki, and Kasshiwamae Maki), Kozuke Province (9 locations), and Musashi Province (4 locations), and the first two provinces were under the jurisdiction of Samaryo (Left Division of Bureau of Horses), and the last two provinces under the jurisdiction of Umaryo (Right Division of Bureau of Horses).</e>
<cmt>必要なかったカンマ消去</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Engishiki&quot; (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers), chokushimaki was established in four provinces: Shinano Province (16 locations), Kai Province (3 locations of Hosaka Maki, Maino Maki, and Kasshiwamae Maki), Kozuke Province (9 locations), and Musashi Province (4 locations), and the first two provinces were under the jurisdiction of Samaryo (Left Division of Bureau of Horses), and the last two provinces under the jurisdiction of Umaryo (Right Division of Bureau of Horses).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>なお、承平 (日本)年間には武蔵国で2ヶ所増設されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, in Johei era (Japan), there were two additional locations in Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, in Johei era (Japan), there were two additional locations in Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, in Johei era (Japan), there were two additional locations in Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>なお、追加された2牧は宇多天皇・陽成天皇の所持していた牧が勅旨牧に編入されたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way, the added two Maki are said to have been ones possessed by Emperor Uda and Emperor Yozei and incorporated later into Chokushimaki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, the additional two Maki are said to have been possessed by Emperor Uda and Emperor Yozei and later incorporated into Chokushimaki.</e>
<cmt>「なお」を文語調に変換。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, the additional two Maki are said to have been possessed by Emperor Uda and Emperor Yozei and later incorporated into Chokushimaki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>特に宇多院は信濃・武蔵両国を院宮分国制として国司の任免権にも関与していたと言われているために、勅旨牧の経営に何らかの関与したとする見方もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Particularly, because Udain (the posthumous name of Emperor Uda) is said to have been involved in the rights for appointment and removal of Kokushi (provincial governor) for Shinano and Musashi Provinces under Ingu bunkoku sei (provincial allotment system), there is a viewpoint that he was also somehow involved in Chokushimaki administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, because Udain (the posthumous name of Emperor Uda) is said to have been involved in the rights for appointment and removal of Kokushi (provincial governor) for Shinano and Musashi Provinces under Ingu bunkoku sei (provincial allotment system), there is another viewpoint that he was also somehow involved in the administration of Chokushimaki.</e>
<cmt>「とする見方もある」という言い方を表すためにanotherを追加。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, because Udain (the posthumous name of Emperor Uda) is said to have been involved in the rights for appointment and removal of Kokushi (provincial governor) for Shinano and Musashi Provinces under Ingu bunkoku sei (provincial allotment system), there is another viewpoint that he was also somehow involved in the administration of Chokushimaki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>これらの牧は各令制国毎に牧監（もくげん）が設置され（ただし、武蔵のみは各牧単位で別当が設置）、在庁官人が中央官庁より一定の任期を持って任命されて馬寮及び兵部省によって勤怠状況が監督されていたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered, in those Maki, that Bokugen (or Mokugen) was assigned for each Ryoseikoku (province), except for Musashi where Betto was assigned for each Maki, and Zaichokanjin from the central authority was stationed for a certain period of time while Meryo and Hyobusho were established to supervise work attendance.</e>
<cmt>牧監（もくげん）の定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that in those Maki, Bokugen (or Mokugen) was assigned for each Ryoseikoku (province), except for Musashi, where Betto was assigned for each Maki, and Zaichokanjin was stationed by the central authority for a certain period of time while Meryo and Hyobusho were established to supervise work attendance.</e>
<cmt>「中央官庁より」を「から」ではなく「によって」と認識させました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that in those Maki, Bokugen (or Mokugen) was assigned for each Ryoseikoku (province), except for Musashi, where Betto was assigned for each Maki, and Zaichokanjin was stationed by the central authority for a certain period of time while Meryo and Hyobusho were established to supervise work attendance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>毎年8月には勅旨牧から中央に貢馬牽進の儀式である駒牽が行われ、毎年240疋（甲斐60疋・信濃80疋・上野50疋・武蔵50疋、なお武蔵2牧増加後は60疋が追加されて110疋となり、毎年総計300頭となる）が朝廷に献上された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Every year in August, Komahiki (The Horse-Leading Ceremony), a ceremony of Komakenshin, horse presentation from Chokushimaki to the central authority, was held and 240 horses (Kai Province 60, Shinano Province 80, Kazusa Province 50, Musashi Province 50. 60 horses were added after inclusion of two Maki in Musashi, bringing the total to 110 horses from Musashi and the grand total horses presented to 300 per year) was presented to the Imperial Court every year. Those horses were kept at farms designated in the area adjacent to Heiankyo (ancient capital in current Kyoto) by Meryo and were accordingly used for public services. They were also granted in some occasions to Kugyo (court noble) or Konoefu (the Headquarters of the Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Every year in August, Komahiki (The Horse-Leading Ceremony), a ceremony of Komakenshin, horse presentation from Chokushimaki to the central authority, was held and 240 horses (Kai Province 60, Shinano Province 80, Kazusa Province 50, Musashi Province 50. In addition, 60 horses were added after inclusion of two Maki in Musashi, bringing the total to 110 horses from Musashi and the grand total horses presented to 300 per year) was presented to the Imperial Court every year.</e>
<cmt>空欄が多いところを省き、訳漏れ「なお」　一原文一訳文の対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Every year in August, Komahiki (The Horse-Leading Ceremony), a ceremony of Komakenshin, horse presentation from Chokushimaki to the central authority, was held and 240 horses (Kai Province 60, Shinano Province 80, Kazusa Province 50, Musashi Province 50. In addition, 60 horses were added after inclusion of two Maki in Musashi, bringing the total to 110 horses from Musashi and the grand total horses presented to 300 per year) was presented to the Imperial Court every year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>平安京周辺に馬寮が設定した「飼養牧（しようまき）」に預けられて公務の必要に応じて利用された他、公卿や近衛府などに下賜される場合もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The horses were sometimes placed in &apos;Shiyomaki&apos; which was set adjacent to Heiankyo (ancient capital of Japan, present day Kyoto) by Meryo and were accordingly used for public services or granted in some occasions to Kugyo (court nobles) or Konoefu (the Headquarters of the Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の対処と 訳漏れ「「飼養牧（しようまき）」　余分な空欄を省きました。平安京の（）内を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The horses were sometimes placed in &apos;Shiyomaki&apos; which was set adjacent to Heiankyo (ancient capital of Japan, present day Kyoto) by Meryo and were accordingly used for public services or granted in some occasions to Kugyo (court nobles) or Konoefu (the Headquarters of the Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>天慶の乱などによる軍事的緊張が高まった10世紀前半に一番の充実が図られたと言われているが、その後衰微した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said the system saw fullest administration in the first half of the tenth century when military tension caused by revolts such as Tengyonoran (the war of Tengyo) was heightened but diminished afterwards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said the system saw fullest administration in the first half of the tenth century when military tension caused by revolts such as Tengyonoran (the war of Tengyo) was heightened but diminished afterwards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said the system saw fullest administration in the first half of the tenth century when military tension caused by revolts such as Tengyonoran (the war of Tengyo) was heightened but diminished afterwards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>ただし、その後も馬寮の荘園や牧場として鎌倉時代まで残された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, they remained as Shoen (manor) or farms of Meryo up to the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, they remained as Shoen (manor) or farms of Meryo up to the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処置</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, they remained as Shoen (manor) or farms of Meryo up to the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>また、牧監や別当を務めた在庁官人の中には武士として成長する者もあり、信濃御牧の牧監とも伝えられる滋野氏末流には信濃小領主から近世大名化した真田氏がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of the Zaichokanjin who served as Bokugen or Betto (the head secretary of a temple) thrived as Samurai, and the Shigeno clan which is said to have been Bokugen for Shinanomimaki had the Sanada clan in its descendants, who later developed from a small feudal lord to a Kinsei (early modern) Daimyo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of the Zaichokanjin who served as Bokugen or Betto (the head secretary of a temple) thrived as Samurai, and the Shigeno clan which is said to have been Bokugen for Shinanomimaki had the Sanada clan in its descendants, who later developed from a small feudal lord to a Kinsei (early modern) Daimyo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処置</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of the Zaichokanjin who served as Bokugen or Betto (the head secretary of a temple) thrived as Samurai, and the Shigeno clan which is said to have been Bokugen for Shinanomimaki had the Sanada clan in its descendants, who later developed from a small feudal lord to a Kinsei (early modern) Daimyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>また信濃十六牧の筆頭とされる「望月の牧」を支配した望月氏の支流は、飼養牧のあった甲賀の地で甲賀五十三家（甲賀流忍者）筆頭の近江望月氏となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, the offshoot of the Mochizuki clan which ruled &quot;Mochizukinomaki&quot;, a Maki thought to have been the head of Juroku (one of the Noh drama masks which features a boy) Maki, became Omimochizuki clan, the head of Koga Gojyusanke (Koga 53 families)(Koga ninja families).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, the offshoot of the Mochizuki clan which ruled &apos;Mochizukinomaki&apos;, a Maki thought to have been the head of Juroku (one of the Noh drama masks which features a boy) Maki, became Omimochizuki clan, the head of Koga Gojyusanke (Koga 53 families)(Koga ninja families).</e>
<cmt>空欄が多いところを省き、「」のところは&apos; &apos;に直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, the offshoot of the Mochizuki clan which ruled &apos;Mochizukinomaki&apos;, a Maki thought to have been the head of Juroku (one of the Noh drama masks which features a boy) Maki, became Omimochizuki clan, the head of Koga Gojyusanke (Koga 53 families)(Koga ninja families).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), カイの迷宮(id:72682), 水野白楓(id:22811), ロロ(id:104252), Doorurban(id:132333), Point136(id:211299), 伏儀(id:142093), AAAⅢ(id:247161), ごまふあざ(id:36855), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>