<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>一条天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor ICHIJO</e>
<cmt>英辞郎on the WEB　（-天皇）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor ICHIJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Ichijo</e>
<cmt>ICHIJO→Ichijo 他の記事とあわせる。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>一条天皇（いちじょう てんのう、天元3年6月1日（980年7月15日） - 寛弘8年6月22日（1011年7月25日））は第66代天皇。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor ICHIJO (July 15th, 980 - July 25th, 1011) is 66th Emperor.</e>
<cmt>以下天皇名は同様の表記、また、読み方については、ブリタニカ国際大百科事典で調査</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor ICHIJO (July 15th, 980 - July 25, 1011) was the sixty-sixth Emperor.</e>
<cmt>space, number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Ichijo (July 15, 980 - July 25, 1011) was the sixty-sixth Emperor.</e>
<cmt>ICHIJO→Ichijo 他の記事とあわせる。15th→15</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>在位は寛和2年（986年）6月23日 - 寛弘8年（1011年）6月13日。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor ICHIJO&apos;s reign was from June 23rd, 986 and resigned on June 13th, 1011.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor ICHIJO&apos;s reign began on June 23, 986, and he resigned on June 13, 1011.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Ichijo&apos;s reign began on June 23, 986, and he resigned on June 13, 1011.</e>
<cmt>ICHIJO→Ichijo 他の記事とあわせる。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>名は懐仁（やすひと/かねひと）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His posthumous name was Yasuhito/Kanehito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His posthumous name was Yasuhito/Kanehito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His posthumous name was Yasuhito/Kanehito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>系譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>円融天皇の第1皇子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first prince of Emperor ENYU.</e>
<cmt>円融天皇 Emperor ENYU</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first prince of Emperor ENYU</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first prince of Emperor Enyu</e>
<cmt>ENYU→Enyu 他の記事とあわせる。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>母は藤原兼家の娘、藤原詮子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mother is FUJIWARA no Kaneie&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Senshi.</e>
<cmt>藤原兼家 FUJIWARA no Kaneie, 藤原詮子 FUJIWARA no Senshi</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was FUJIWARA no Kaneie&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Senshi.</e>
<cmt>pronoun</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was FUJIWARA no Kaneie&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Senshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>兄弟姉妹はいない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He does not have any brothers or sisters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had no brother or sister.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had no brother or sister.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>系図</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>Biography→Brief Personal Historyに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>永観2年（984年）、花山天皇の時、皇太子に立てられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became crown prince when Emperor KAZAN was in power in 984.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became the crown prince in 984, when Emperor KAZAN was in power.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became the crown prince in 984, when Emperor Kazan was in power.</e>
<cmt>KAZAN→Kazan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>寛和2年（986）6月23日（8月1日）、花山天皇が内裏を抜け出して出家してしまったために、数え年7歳で即位した（孫の早期即位を狙った兼家の陰謀と言われる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 1st, 986, Emperor KAZAN Left the Imperial palace for good to become Buddhist monk, after this Emperor ICHIJO enthroned in his 7th year. (It is said that this was conspiracy of Kaneie set up grandchild to enthrone in early age.)</e>
<cmt>花山天皇 Emperor KAZAN, 数え年7歳 in one&apos;s 7th year 英辞郎on the WEB, 内裏 Imperial Palace 研究社新和英辞典</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 1, 986, Emperor KAZAN left the Imperial Palace for good in order to become a Buddhist monk, and subsequently Emperor ICHIJO was enthroned in his seventh year (it is said that this was a conspiracy of Kaneie set up a grandchild for enthronement at an early age).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 1, 986, Emperor Kazan left the Imperial Palace for good in order to become a Buddhist monk, and subsequently Emperor Ichijo was enthroned in his seventh year (it is said that this was a conspiracy by Kaneie set up a grandchild for enthronement at an early age).</e>
<cmt>KAZAN→KazanICHIJO→Ichijo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>皇太子には冷泉天皇の皇子居貞親王（三条天皇）を立て、摂政に藤原兼家が就任した（のちに関白）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Crown Prince was Imperial Prince Okisada, son of Emperor REIZEI, FUJIWARA no Kaneie became regent. (later became Kanpaku/chief adviser to the Emperor)</e>
<cmt>居貞親王the Imperial Prince Okisada, 冷泉天皇 Emperor REIZEI, 三条天皇 Emperor SANJO, 摂政 regent, 関白Kampaku/chief adviser to the Emperor 英辞郎on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The crown prince was Imperial Prince Okisada, son of Emperor REIZEI, FUJIWARA no Kaneie became regent (later became kanpaku (chief adviser) to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The crown prince was Imperial Prince Okisada, son of Emperor Reizei (FUJIWARA no Kaneie), who became regent (and later became kampaku, or chief adviser, to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>REIZEI→Reizeikanpaku→kampaku</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>兼家の死後は長男の藤原道隆が引き続き外戚として摂政・関白を務め、一条天皇の中宮に娘の藤原定子（ていし）を入れるが、長徳元年（995年）に病没。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Kaneie died, his eldest son, FUJIWARA no Michitaka became regent and Kanpaku/chief adviser to the Emperor as his maternal relatives, and FUJIWARA no Teishi became Emperor ICHIJO&apos;s second consort, but he died in 995.</e>
<cmt>摂政 regent 英辞郎on the WEB, 藤原道隆 FUJIWARA no Michitaka, 中宮 the second consort of an emperor 研究社新和英辞典, 藤原定子 FUJIWARA no Teishi</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Kaneie died, his eldest son, FUJIWARA no Michitaka became regent and kanpaku (chief adviser) to the Emperor as his maternal relatives, and FUJIWARA no Teishi became Emperor ICHIJO&apos;s second consort; however, he died in 995.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Kaneie died, his eldest son, FUJIWARA no Michitaka, became regent and kampaku to the Emperor as his maternal relative, and FUJIWARA no Teishi became Emperor Ichijo&apos;s second consort; however, in 995 he died.</e>
<cmt>kanpaku→kampakuICHIJO→Ichijo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>代わりに弟の藤原道兼が関白に就任するがわずか7日後に没し、道隆の子藤原伊周との争いに勝利した道隆・道兼の弟藤原道長が、姉で天皇の生母・詮子の推挙を受け、内覧となって実権を掌握した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Michitaka&apos;s death, his brother FUJIWARA no Michikane became Kanpaku/chief adviser to the Emperor, but he also died after seven days, FUJIWARA no Michinaga, Michitaka and Michikane&apos;s brother, who won power struggle with Michitaka&apos;s son, FUJIWARA no Korechika, became Nairan/Chief secretary and took power after receiving his sister and Emperor&apos;s mother, Shoshi&apos;s recommendation.</e>
<cmt>藤原伊周 FUJIWARA no Korechika, 藤原道長 FUJIWARA no Michinaga, 内覧 Nairan/chief secretary　定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Michitaka&apos;s death, his brother FUJIWARA no Michikane became kanpaku (chief adviser) to the Emperor, but he died just seven days later; FUJIWARA no Michinaga, Michitaka and Michikane&apos;s brother, who won the power struggle with Michitaka&apos;s son, FUJIWARA no Korechika, became nairan (chief secretary) and took power after receiving his sister and the Emperor&apos;s mother, at Shoshi&apos;s recommendation.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Michitaka&apos;s death, his brother FUJIWARA no Michikane became kanpaku to the Emperor, but he died just seven days later; FUJIWARA no Michinaga, Michitaka and Michikane&apos;s brother, who had won the power struggle with Michitaka&apos;s son FUJIWARA no Korechika, became nairan (chief secretary) and took power after receiving the recommendation of his sister and the Emperor&apos;s mother, Shoshi.</e>
<cmt>kanpaku→kampakuat削除&quot;kampaku&quot;→&quot;kanpaku&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>道長は先に中宮であった定子を皇后とし、娘の藤原彰子（しょうし）を中宮に立てて、一帝二后の先例を開いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michinaga married to Shoshi and she became an Empress, who was previously second consort of an emperor, their daughter FUJIWARA no Shoshi, this was the first example of Ittei nigo.</e>
<cmt>皇后 Empress 研究社新和英辞典, 藤原彰子 FUJIWARA no Shoshi, 一帝二后 Ittei nigo (one Emperor having two Empresses) 定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michinaga married Shoshi and became an Empress, though she was previously the second consort of the Emperor, and had their daughter FUJIWARA no Shoshi; this was the first example of Ittei nigo.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michinaga set the precedent for Ittei-Nigo (an emperor having two empresses) when he made Teishi, who was the second consort of the emperor at the time, empress, and made his daughter, FUJIWARA no Shoshi, the new second consort.</e>
<cmt>Shoshi→Teishi&quot;though&quot;→&quot;although&quot;に変更しました。Neilさん、Would you rewrite the sentence on the left, considering the following?Michinaga made Teishi, who was previously the second consort of the Emperor, an Empress.And Michinaga made his daughter FUJIWARA no Shoshi the second consort of the Emperor.So, he set a precedent of Ittei-Nigo (an emperror having two empresses).</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>一条天皇の時代は道隆・道長兄弟のもとで藤原氏の権勢が最盛に達し、皇后定子に仕える清少納言、中宮彰子に仕える紫式部・和泉式部らによって平安女流文学が花開いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Emperor ICHIJO&apos;s enthronement, FUJIWARA clan was in their prime under Michitaka, Michinaga brothers supervision, Heian culture bloomed with Seishonagon who served Empress Shoshi and Murasakishikibu, Izumishikibu who both served Chugu Shoshi.</e>
<cmt>藤原氏 FUJIWARA clan 英辞郎on the WEB, 清少納言 Sei Shonagon, 紫式部 Murasaki Shikibu 英辞郎on the WEB, 和泉式部 Izumi Shikibu</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Emperor ICHIJO&apos;s enthronement, the FUJIWARA clan was in its prime under Michitaka, Michinaga brothers supervision, the Heian culture flourished with Seishonagon (who served Empress Shoshi and Murasakishikibu) and Izumishikibu, both of whom served Chugu Shoshi.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With Emperor Ichijo&apos;s enthronement, the FUJIWARA clan was in its prime under the supervision of Michitaka, Michinaga&apos;s brother; meanwhile, the Heian culture flourished with Seishonagon (who served Empress Teishi) and Murasakishikibu and Izumishikibu, both of whom served Chugu Shoshi.</e>
<cmt>ICHIJO→IchijoShoshi→Teishi）の位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>天皇自身、文芸に深い関心を示し、『本朝文粋』などに詩文を残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor himself was keen to learn literature and left his Chinese style poem in &quot;Honcho Monzui&quot;.</e>
<cmt>『本朝文粋』 &quot;Honcho Monzui&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor himself was keen to learn literature, and left his Chinese-style poem in &quot;Honcho Monzui.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor himself was keen to learn literature, and left his Chinese-style poem in &quot;Honcho Monzui.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>音楽にも堪能で、笛を能くしたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor had a talent in music and loved to pay a recorder.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor was musically talented and loved to play the recorder.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor was musically talented and loved to play the recorder.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>また、人柄は温和で好学だったといい、多くの人に慕われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was popular among people with his warm personality and he loved to study.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With his warm personality he was popular among people, and he loved to study.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With his warm personality he was popular among people, and he loved to study.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>また、天皇が道長を関白とせずに内覧に留めたのは、天皇自身が長ずるにつれ、曽祖父の醍醐天皇・祖父の村上天皇のように、摂政関白を置かずに親政する事を志したのと、道長自身も、当時閣議に出られない決まりがある摂政関白よりも、内覧を兼ねたまま一上（閣員の首座）として実権を掌握しようとした事が一致した為で、これにより、後に大江匡房が『続本朝往生伝』で藤原実資や藤原行成等の有能な人材を輩出したと称えたほど、有為な政治体制が確立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor decided Michinaga to be Nairan/chief secretary instead of Kampaku/chief adviser to the Emperor, as he got older, since he wished to run the government directly instead of having regent and Kampaku, like his great grandfather, Emperor DAIGO and his grandfather, Emperor MURAKAMI, on the other hand Michinaga agreed to be Nairan and also the top of various section to control the government, as regent and Kampaku do not have a right to attend the Cabinet meeting, thus the strong political framework was set up and OE no Masahusa honored in &quot;Zoku Honcho Ojoden&quot; that talented people like FUJIWARA no Sanesuke and FUJIWARA no Yukinari were produced.</e>
<cmt>醍醐天皇 Emperor DAIGO, 村上天皇 Emperor MURAKAMI, 大江匡房 OE no Masahusa　定訳不明,『続本朝往生伝』&quot;Zoku Honcho Ojoden&quot;, 一上 chief member of the cabinet 定訳不明, 藤原実資 FUJIWARA no Sanesuke and 藤原行成 FUJIWARA no Yukinari</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor decided Michinaga to be nairan (chief secretary) instead of kampaku (chief adviser) to the Emperor, as he got older, since he wanted to run the government directly instead of having a regent and kampaku, like his great-grandfather, Emperor DAIGO and his grandfather, Emperor MURAKAMI; on the other hand, Michinaga agreed to be nairan and also the top of various sections to control the government, as the regent and kampaku weren&apos;t entitled to attend the meetings of the Cabinet; thus the strong political framework was set up and OE no Masahusa acknowledged through &quot;Zoku Honcho Ojoden&quot; that talented people like FUJIWARA no Sanesuke and FUJIWARA no Yukinari were produced.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor decided that Michinaga would be nairan (chief secretary) instead of kampaku (chief adviser) to the Emperor, once he became older, since he wanted to run the government directly instead of having a regent and kampaku, like his great-grandfather Emperor Daigo and his grandfather, Emperor MurakamiI; on the other hand, Michinaga agreed to be nairan and also the head of various sections to control the government, since the regent and kampaku weren&apos;t entitled to attend the meetings of the Cabinet; thus a strong political framework was set up and OE no Masahusa acknowledged through &quot;Zoku Honcho Ojoden,&quot; with which talented people like FUJIWARA no Sanesuke and FUJIWARA no Yukinari were produced.</e>
<cmt>DAIGO→DaigoMurakami→Murakami</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="20">
<j>その一方で、鎌倉時代初期に書かれた道長の6代目の子孫にあたる慈円の著した『愚管抄』によれば、天皇の死後道長は天皇の遺品の中に一通の手紙を発見し、その中には「三光明ならんと欲し、重雲を覆ひて大精暗し」と書かれていて、これを「道長の専横によって国は乱れている」という意味に解した道長はその文を焼き捨てたという一件がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, according to &quot;Gukan-sho&quot; which was written in early Kamakura period, by Jien who is Michinaga&apos;s 6th descendent, Michinaga found a letter in Emperor&apos;s memento saying &apos;one person tried to have all the power to himself, therefore the world is covered by the clouds and people are unhappy&apos;, Michinaga burned this letter as he took it as saying, &apos;Because of Michinaga&apos;s own way of ruling the government, the world is not in peace.&apos;</e>
<cmt>『愚管抄』Gukan-sho, 慈円 Jien 研究社新和英辞典, 三光明ならんと欲し、重雲を覆ひて大精暗し」定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, according to &quot;Gukan-sho,&quot; which was written early in the Kamakura period by Jien, who was Michinaga&apos;s sixth descendent, Michinaga found a letter in the Emperor&apos;s mementos saying that &apos;one person tried to have all the power to himself, therefore the world is covered by clouds and people are unhappy&apos;; Michinaga burned this letter, since he took it as saying, &apos;Because of Michinaga&apos;s own way of ruling the government, the world is not in peace.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, according to &quot;Gukan-sho,&quot; which was written early in the Kamakura period by Jien, who was Michinaga&apos;s sixth descendent, Michinaga found a letter in the Emperor&apos;s mementos saying that &apos;one person tried to have all the power to himself, therefore the world is covered by clouds and people are unhappy&apos;; Michinaga burned this letter, since he took it as saying, &apos;Because of Michinaga&apos;s own way of ruling the government, the world is not in peace.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>これは摂関家にとっては不都合な事実であるが、慈円は事実関係そのものは否定せずに、天皇の認識不足を激しく責めて道長の忠節を称えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is an inconvenient fact for the clan (family) eligible for regents, although Jien did not deny the fact relevance, he accused Emperor&apos;s ignorance and honored Michinaga remained faithful to the Emperor..</e>
<cmt>摂関家 the clan (family) eligible for regents</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was an inconvenient fact for the clan (family) eligible for regency, and although Jien did not deny the relevance of the fact, he accused the Emperor of ignorance and honored Michinaga, remaining faithful to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was an inconvenient fact for the clan (family) eligible for regency, and although Jien did not deny the relevance of the fact, he accused the Emperor of ignorance and honored Michinaga, remaining faithful to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また、これと似たような話は同時期に書かれた『古事談』にも記載されていることや晩年に次期東宮に定子が生んだ敦康親王を望みながらこれを阻まれたことが『権記』に記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This kind of story is written in &quot;Kojidan&quot; or there is another story in &quot;Gon-ki&quot; that in Emperor&apos;s late life he wished Teishi&apos;s son, Imperial Prince Atsuyasu to be Crown Prince however this was blocked by Michinaga, this could have been a true story or part of the story was true, thus there is a theory the relationship between the Emperor and Michinaga was not necessary good.</e>
<cmt>『古事談』&quot;Kojidan&quot;, 『権記』 &quot;Gon-ki&quot;, 東宮 Crown Prince, 敦康親王 Imperial Prince Atsuyasu http://d.hatena.ne.jp/keyword/%C6%D8%B9%AF%BF%C6%B2%A6</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This kind of story is written in &quot;Kojidan,&quot; but there is another story in &quot;Gon-ki&quot; stating that the Emperor, late in life, wished for Teishi&apos;s son, Imperial Prince Atsuyasu, to be the crown prince, but this was blocked by Michinaga. This story could be entirely or partly true; nevertheless, there is a theory that the relationship between the Emperor and Michinaga was not necessarily good.</e>
<cmt>Two sentences needed</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This kind of story is written in &quot;Kojidan,&quot; but there is another story in &quot;Gon-ki&quot; stating that the Emperor, late in life, wished for Teishi&apos;s son, Imperial Prince Atsuyasu, to be the crown prince, but this was blocked by Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>一文一訳対象外</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>この話は実話かそれに近い出来事があり、天皇と道長の関係が必ずしも順調に行っていなかったのではと見る説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This story could be entirely or partly true; nevertheless, there is a theory that the relationship between the Emperor and Michinaga wasn&apos;t necessarily good.</e>
<cmt>一文一訳対象外</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="24">
<j>諡号・追号・異名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Posthumous name, posthumous title (Tsuigo), different name</e>
<cmt>諡号・追号 a posthumous title 研究社新和英辞典</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Posthumous name, posthumous title (Tsuigo), a different name</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Posthumous name, posthumous title (Tsuigo), a different name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="25">
<j>在位中の里内裏（臨時の皇居）の名称により「一条院」と追号された（追号も諡号の一種とする場合もあるが、厳密には諡号とは異なる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The a posthumous title of the &apos;Ichijo-in&apos; (the ex-Emperor Ichijo) came from the name of the temporally residence, Satodairi where the Emperor stayed in his reign. (sometimes posthumous title (Tsuigo) is considered to be a type of pothumous name, however strictly speaking these are two different names.)</e>
<cmt>里内裏 Satodairi (temporaly residence where Emperor spent his time), 「一条院」the ex-Emperor Ichijo</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The posthumous title of the &apos;Ichijo-in&apos; (the ex-Emperor Ichijo) came from the name of the temporary residence, Satodairi, where the Emperor stayed during his reign (the posthumous title (tsuigo) is sometimes considered to be a type of posthumous name, but strictly speaking these are two different names).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The posthumous title of the &apos;Ichijo-in&apos; (the ex-Emperor Ichijo) came from the name of the temporary residence, Satodairi, where the Emperor stayed during his reign (the posthumous title (tsuigo) is sometimes considered to be a type of posthumous name, but strictly speaking these are two different names).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>明治以後、「院」の号は廃止され、「一条天皇」とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Meiji Period, the name &apos;In&apos; was no longer being used and called &apos;Emperor ICHIJO&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji period, the name &apos;In&apos; was no longer being used and he was called &apos;Emperor ICHIJO.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji period, the name &apos;In&apos; was no longer used, so he was called &apos;Emperor Ichijo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ICHIJO→Ichijo</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="27">
<j>在位中の元号</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eras during his reign</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eras during his reign</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eras during his reign</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="28">
<j>寛和</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanna/Kanwa</e>
<cmt>寛和 Kanna/Kanwa Yahoo Japan 辞書</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanna/Kanwa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanna/Kanwa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="29">
<j>永延</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eien</e>
<cmt>永延 Eien　Yahoo Japan 辞書</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eien</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eien</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="30">
<j>永祚</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eiso</e>
<cmt>永祚 Eiso　Yahoo Japan 辞書</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eiso</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eiso</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="31">
<j>正暦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoryaku</e>
<cmt>正暦 Shoryaku　Yahoo Japan 辞書</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoryaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoryaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="32">
<j>長徳</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chotoku</e>
<cmt>長徳 Chotoku　Yahoo Japan 辞書</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chotoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chotoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="33">
<j>長保</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chohou</e>
<cmt>長保 Chohou Yahoo Japan 辞書</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chohou</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Choho</e>
<cmt>Chohou→Choho ヘボン式</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="34">
<j>寛弘</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanko</e>
<cmt>寛弘 Kanko Yahoo Japan 辞書</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>陵墓・霊廟</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Mausoleum</e>
<cmt>サンプル訳より</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Mausoleum</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Mausoleum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="35">
<j>京都市右京区竜安寺にある円融寺北陵（えんゆうじのきたのみささぎ）に葬られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor was entombed in the North Imperial Mausoleum in Enyuji, Ryoan-ji Temple, Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>京都市右京区竜安寺 Ryoan-ji Temple, Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City, 円融寺北陵North Imperial Mausoleum in Enyuji 研究社新和英辞典 定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor was entombed in the North Imperial Mausoleum at Enyuji, Ryoan-ji Temple, Ukyo ward, in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor was entombed in the North Imperial Mausoleum at Enyuji, Ryoan-ji Temple, Ukyo Ward, in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>ward→Ward</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>天皇は生前、父円融院の隣に土葬されることを望んだが、道長は故院を荼毘に付してからそのことを思い出し、御骨を円融寺に納めたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor wished to be entombed next to the ex-Emperor ENYU, his father&apos;s Mausoleum, Michinaga remembered this after the late ex-Emperor was cemented, his Okotsu (remain/ashes) were kept in Enyu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>円融院 the ex-Emperor Enyu, 故院 the late ex-emperor, 御骨 remain/ashes 定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor wished to be entombed next to the ex-Emperor ENYU in his father&apos;s mausoleum; Michinaga remembered this after the late ex-Emperor was cremated, and his okotsu (remain/ashes) were kept at Enyu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor wished to be entombed next to the ex-Emperor Enyu in his father&apos;s mausoleum; Michinaga remembered this after the late ex-Emperor was cremated, and his okotsu (remain/ashes) were kept at Enyu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>ENYU→Enyu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>また全ての天皇は皇居の宮中三殿の一つの皇霊殿に祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All the past Emperors are enshrined in Koreiden, one of the Three Palace Sanctuaries.</e>
<cmt>宮中三殿 Kyuchu-sanden(three shrines of the imperial court) http://opac.ndl.go.jp/articleid/9723073/jpn サンプル訳より, 皇霊殿 Koreiden</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All the past emperors are enshrined in Koreiden, one of the Three Palace Sanctuaries.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All the past emperors are enshrined in Koreiden, one of the Three Palace Sanctuaries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 霧木諒二(id:9795), Nnh(id:474), Novo(id:87875), Ojigiri(id:329), 0null0(id:582), Cprobot(id:97843), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), 味っ子(id:17086), Ash Crow(id:26765), Masyu(id:31065), 玄史生(id:43670), 代言人(id:33675), Rei-bot(id:94097), TF-gene(id:580), LERK(id:4460), M-sho-gun(id:88956), Lonicera(id:20638), Carbuncle(id:346), Albambot(id:195288), Equaly(id:89792), Stanislaus(id:1806), 水野白楓(id:22811), Web.dweller(id:153933), Nikai(id:1648), SuisuiBot(id:10165), Yume149(id:17504), YOSHI438(id:174755), Safkan(id:423), けんち(id:5147), 唐棣色(id:64681), LeonardoRob0t(id:25875), Zippin(id:9885), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>