<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>宮中三殿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyuchu sanden (the Three Shrines in the Imperial Court)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyuchu sanden (the Three Shrines in the Imperial Court)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyuchu sanden (the Three Shrines in the Imperial Court)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>宮中三殿（きゅうちゅうさんでん）は、皇居にある賢所（かしこどころ、けんしょ）、皇霊殿（こうれいでん）、神殿（しんでん）という三つの神殿の総称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyuchu sanden is a general term for the three Shrines in the Imperial Court, Kashidokoro (or Kensho), Koreiden and Shinden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyuchu sanden is a general term for the three Shrines in the Imperial Court, Kashidokoro (or Kensho), Koreiden and Shinden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kyuchu Sanden&quot; is a general term which refers to the three shrines in the Imperial Court: the Kashikodokoro (also known as Kensho), the Koreiden, and the Shinden.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>吹上御苑の東南に位置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They locate at east south of the Fukiage Imperial Gardens.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are located south east of the Fukiage Imperial Gardens.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are located south east of the Fukiage Imperial Gardens.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>一年を通して、掌典職と呼ばれる天皇の私的使用人集団に属する掌典と呼ばれる神職と、内掌典と呼ばれる女性(巫女)が清め護っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is Shinto priest called Shoten who belong to emperor&apos;s personal servant group, ceremonial staff, and female Shinto priest called Nai Shoten (Uchi Shoten) (a shrine maiden) stay there to purify and protect the Kyuchu sanden all year around.</e>
<cmt>内掌典→読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is Shinto priest called Shoten who belongs to the emperor&apos;s personal group of servants, ceremonial staff, and female Shinto priest called Nai Shoten (Uchi Shoten) (a shrine maiden) stay there to purify and protect the Kyuchu sanden all year around.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinto priests called shoten and female Shinto priests (or shrine maidens) called nai-shoten, who both belong to the emperor&apos;s personal servant group called shoten-shoku (literally, &quot;the board of shoten&quot;), purify and protect the Kyuchu Sanden all year round.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>毎朝、午前8時から、清酒、赤飯などを供える日供の儀（にっくのぎ）を、賢所、皇霊殿には内掌典が、神殿には掌典がそれぞれ奉仕する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nai Shoten (Uchi Shoten) serve refined sake and red rice (beans and mochi) for auspicious occasions to Kenjo and Koreiden at eight o&apos;clock in the morning, Shoten serve the same at Shinden, after that at eight thirty, a person in duty from the Board of Chamberlains of the Imperial Household Agency, or if the Emperor is away for a visit or going oversea trip, there is a custom to have an event that a person in duty from the Board of Chamberlains while Emperor&apos;s absence will pray for Kashidokoro or Kenjo, Koreiden, Shinden as Emperor&apos;s substutute to conduct Maicho godaihai.</e>
<cmt>日供の儀, 毎朝御代拝→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nai Shoten (Uchi Shoten) serve refined sake and red rice (beans and mochi) for auspicious occasions to Kenjo and Koreiden at eight o&apos;clock in the morning, Shoten serves the same at Shinden, after that at eight thirty, a person is on duty from the Board of Chamberlains of the Imperial Household Agency, or if the Emperor is away for a visit or goes on an overseas trip, there is a custom to have a person on duty from the Board of Chamberlains while the Emperor is absent, he will pray for Kashidokoro or Kenjo, Koreiden, Shinden as Emperor&apos;s substutute to conduct Maicho godaihai.</e>
<cmt>spelling, wordiness, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nikku no Gi (the rite of providing daily food offerings to the deceased), in which sake and sekihan (glutinous rice steamed with red beans) are offered, is held at 8:00 am every day served by nai-shoten at the Kashikodokoro and the Koreiden, and by shoten at the Shinden.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました一原文一訳文の例外対処原文を分割、文末を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>午前8時30分に宮内庁侍従職の当直侍従が、また天皇が行幸及び外国旅行に際して不在でも居残り役の侍従が毎朝御代拝（まいちょうごだいはい）として、賢所、皇霊殿、神殿を天皇に代わって拝礼する行事を行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An on-duty chamberlain from the Board of Chamberlains, the Imperial Household Agency, or a chamberlain who is told to stay at the Imperial Court to take care of affairs while the Emperor is absent to attend an event or visit another country, performs a rite called Maicho-godaihai (literally, &quot;every morning worship on behalf of the Emperor&quot;) at 8:30 am and worships the deceased at the Kashikodokoro, the Koreiden, and the Shinden on behalf of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました一原文一訳文の例外対処原文を分割</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>日供の儀及び毎朝御代拝は、廃朝や宮中喪が発せられているときにおいても欠かさずに行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nikku no gi and Maicho godaihai are both conducted every morning even there was an occasion that the Emperor does not participate in the event for special reason or there is an announcement that the Imperial Palace is in mourning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nikku no gi and Maicho godaihai are both conducted every morning even when the Emperor does not participate for a special reason or when there is an announcement that the Imperial Palace is in mourning.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both the Nikku no Gi and the Maicho-godaihai are conducted every morning even when the Emperor is away from any public affairs due to some special reasons or the Court mourning is declared.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>四方拝、新嘗祭は宮中三殿の近くにある神嘉殿で、鎮魂祭は宮中三殿近くの綾綺殿で執り行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shihohai (a Shinto ceremony held on New Year&apos;s Day in which the Emperor pays respect to the deities in all quarters) and Niiname-sai festival (ceremonial offering by the Emperor of newly-harvested rice to the deities) are held at Shinki-den and the Mass or ceremony for the repose of a soul is held at Ryoki-dan, they both locate at near Kyuchu sanden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shihohai (a Shinto ceremony held on New Year&apos;s Day in which the Emperor pays respect to the deities in all quarters) and Niiname-sai festival (ceremonial offering by the Emperor of newly-harvested rice to the deities) are held at Shinki-den and the Mass or ceremony for the repose of a soul is held at Ryoki-dan, they both locate at near Kyuchu sanden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shihohai (a Shinto ceremony held on New Year&apos;s Day in which the Emperor pays respect to the deities in all quarters) and Niiname-sai Festival (ceremonial offering by the Emperor of newly-harvested rice to the deities) are held at the Shinkaden, which is a shrine located near the Kyuchu Sanden, and Chinkon-sai Festival (a ceremony for the repose of a soul) is held at the Ryokiden, which is a shrine also located near the Kyuchu Sanden.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しましたShinkiden→Shinkaden</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>宮中三殿の改修工事の間、「ご神体」は仮殿にそれぞれ「移御」されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While there was a renovation work of Kyuchu sanden, &apos;goshintai&apos; (the object of worship in a Shinto shrine) was moved into each of temporary Kyuchu sanden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While there was renovation work on Kyuchu sanden, &apos;goshintai&apos; (the object of worship in a Shinto shrine) was moved into a temporary Kyuchu sanden.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While there was renovation work on Kyuchu sanden, &apos;goshintai&apos; (the object of worship in a Shinto shrine) was moved into a temporary Kyuchu sanden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="9">
<j>賢所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kashidokoro, Kensho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kashidokoro, Kensho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kashidokoro, Kensho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>皇祖神天照大神を祀る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kososhin (Imperial ancestor), Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess) is enshrined in this palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kososhin (Imperial ancestor), Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess) is enshrined in this palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a shrine to enshrine the Imperial ancestor called Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その御霊代である神鏡（八咫鏡の複製とされる）が奉斎されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Amaterasu Omikami&apos;s goreidai (an object that is honored in place of a person&apos;s soul [deity&apos;s spirit]), a divine mirror (it is called a replica of the sacred mirror of Yata) is enshrined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Amaterasu Omikami&apos;s goreidai (an object that is honored in place of a person&apos;s soul - &quot;deity&apos;s spirit&quot;), a divine mirror (it is called a replica of the sacred mirror of Yata) is enshrined.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A divine mirror which is regarded as a mitamashiro (an object that is honored in place of a person&apos;s soul or a deity&apos;s sprit) of this goddess is enshrined, and the mirror is said to be a replica of the Yata no Kagami (which literally means &quot;eight-span mirror,&quot; referring to one of the Imperial regalia).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しましたmitamashito→mitamashiro</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>神鏡そのものを指すこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sometimes it can mean the divine mirror itself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sometimes it can mean the divine mirror itself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sometimes it can mean the divine mirror itself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>古代より宮中で祭祀されてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It had been enshrined in the Imperial palace since ancient times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It had been enshrined in the Imperial palace since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It had been enshrined in the Imperial palace since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>京都にあった頃は「内侍所」と呼ばれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Imperial Palace was in Kyoto, it was called Naishidokoro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Imperial Palace was in Kyoto, it was called Naishidokoro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Imperial Palace was in Kyoto, it was called &apos;Naishidokoro&apos;.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&apos;を補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>掌典及び内掌典が御用を奉り、「忌火」（「神聖な火」の意味）が点され、掌典及び内掌典はそれを護り続けているといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said Shoten or Nai Shoten (Uchi Shoten) was ordered something and &apos;Umubi&apos; (holly fire) was put on, since then they both continued to protect the holly fire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said Shoten or Nai Shoten (Uchi Shoten) was ordered to do something and &apos;Umubi&apos; (holy fire) was lit, since then they both continued to protect the holy fire.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that shoten and nai-shoten serve to take care of everything and they keep watching over a holy fire called &apos;imibi&apos; after lighting it at this shrine.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="16">
<j>平安時代においては温明殿(うんめいでん)、鎌倉時代以後は春興殿にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was in Unmeiden in the Heian period, and it was in Shunkyo-den (a part of Heiankyo Palace) in the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was in Unmeiden in the Heian period, and it was in Shunkyo-den (a part of Heiankyo Palace) in the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kashikodokoro was in the Unmeiden Hall in the Heian period, and it has been in the Shunkyoden Hall since the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しましたhad→has</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="17">
<j>いにしえから続くとされる宮中祭祀が執り行われ、皇后美智子、徳仁親王妃雅子をはじめとする皇族の妃らを宮中に迎え入れる結婚の儀もここで執り行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The court ritual which was said to be continued since the old days, was held in this palace, and the marriage ceremony to welcome Empress and Princess to the palace, such as Empress Michiko, Imperial Prince Naruhito&apos;s princess, Masako was also held in this palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Court rituals that were continued since the old days, were held in this palace, and the marriage ceremony to welcome the Empress and Princess to the palace, such as Empress Michiko, Imperial Prince Naruhito&apos;s princess, Masako, was also held in this palace.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This shrine is the place to hold Court rituals that date back to ancient times, including wedding ceremonies to welcome Imperial princesses such as Empress Michiko and Crown Princess Masako.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="18">
<j>この場合、男性皇族の結婚は賢所を出たときに成立したとみなされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this case, it is considered the marriage of male Imperial family member is completed when he exit the Kashidokoro, Kensho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that the marriage of a male Imperial family member is completed when he exits the Kashidokoro, Kensho.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The marriage of a male Imperial family member is considered to be completed when he exits the Kashikodokoro.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="19">
<j>神聖な場所とされるが故に、たいへん穢れを嫌い、例えば「次清」の別などの厳格な規律が存在するとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As it is respected as holly place, the place can not be dispurifyed, for example, it is said there is a strict rule like &apos;次清&apos;.</e>
<cmt>次清→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As it is respected as a holy place, it can not be desecrated, for example, it is said there is a strict rule like &apos;次清&apos;.</e>
<cmt>spelling, wordiness, terminology, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that they have very strict rules such as a distinction between &apos;tsugi&apos; (uncleanness) and &apos;kiyo&apos; (cleanness) because this place is respected as a sanctuary which should avoid any impurity.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="20">
<j>皇霊殿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koreiden</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koreiden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koreiden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>歴代天皇および皇族の霊を祀る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sprits of the successive Emperors and the Imperial family are enshrined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The spirits of successive Emperors and the Imperial family are enshrined here.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The spirits of successive Emperors and the Imperial family are enshrined here.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>明治に再興された神祇官は附属の神殿を創建し、併せて歴代天皇の霊をも祀った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jingikan (department of worship) was restored during the Meiji period and they established an attached shrine where they enshrined the spirits of the successive Emperors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jingikan (department of worship) was restored during the Meiji period and an attached shrine was built where the spirits of successive Emperors were enshrined.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jingikan (department of worship) was restored during the Meiji period and an attached shrine was built where the spirits of successive Emperors were enshrined.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>またこれに伴って、平安時代より宮中にある歴代天皇を仏式で祀る「黒戸」は廃止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to above, the custom to enshrine the successive Emperors in the Imperial palace since the Heian period in Buddhist style was abolished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the above, the custom to enshrine successive Emperors in the Imperial palace since the Heian period in Buddhist style was abolished.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A custom called &apos;Kurodo,&apos; in which successive Emperors were enshrined in the Buddhist style, had been succeeded at Court since the Heian period, but this was abolished in accordance with the above event.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="24">
<j>神祇官が神祇省に降格するに伴い、1871年（明治4年）9月に宮中に遷座し、賢所と共に「皇廟」と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Jingikan (department of worship) get promoted to Jingisho (Ministry of Divinities), the Koreiden was transferred to the Imperial Palace in September 1871, it was then called &apos;Kobyo&apos; (Imperial mausoleum) together with Kashidokoro, Kensho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Jingikan (department of worship) was promoted to Jingisho (Ministry of Divinities), the Koreiden was transferred to the Imperial Palace in September 1871, it was then called &apos;Kobyo&apos; (Imperial mausoleum) together with Kashidokoro, Kensho.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Jingikan was demoted to the Jingisho (Ministry of Divinities), the Koreiden was transferred to the Imperial Palace in September 1871, and it was then called &apos;Kobyo&apos; (Imperial mausoleum) together with the Kashikodokoro (Kensho).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>1878年（明治11年）には皇妃や皇族の霊が合祀された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1878 the spirits of the Empresses and the Imperial family were enshrine together.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1878 the spirits of the Empresses and the Imperial family were enshrine together.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1878 the spirits of the Empresses and the Imperial family were enshrine together.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>天皇・皇族の霊は、その死後1年をもって皇霊殿に合祀される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The spirits of Emperors and the Imperial family were enshrined together into the Koreiden after one year of their death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The spirits of Emperors and the Imperial family were enshrined together in the Koreiden one year after their deaths.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A spirit of an emperor or an Imperial family member is moved to the Koreiden to be enshrined together with spirits of other emperors and Imperial family members one year after his or her death.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>毎年、春分の日と秋分の日には春季、秋季の皇霊祭が行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is Koreisai festival is held on shunbunnohi (the Vernal Equinox Day) in spring and and on shubunnohi (autumn equinox holiday) in autumn time every year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is Koreisai festival held on shunbunnohi (the Vernal Equinox Day) in spring and and on shubunnohi (autumn equinox holiday) in autumn time every year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Spring Korei-sai Festival is held on Vernal Equinox Day and the Autumn Korei-sai Festival is held on Autumnal Equinox Day every year.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="28">
<j>神殿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinden</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>天津神国津神を祀る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amatsukami (god of heaven) and Kunitsukami (god of land) were enshrined in the palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amatsukami (god of heaven) and Kunitsukami (god of land) were enshrined in the palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amatsukami (god of heaven) and Kunitsukami (god of land) were enshrined in the palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="30">
<j>明治に再興された神祇官（のち神祇省）は附属の神殿を創建し、天神地祇および古代の律令制での神祇官の八神殿で祀られた八神を祀った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jingikan which was restored during the Meiji period (later called Jingi sho) established an attached shrine and enshrined eight gods which were enshrined in Hasshinden (eight shrines) of Jingikan during the gods of heaven and earth time and the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) from ancient times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jingikan was restored during the Meiji period (later called Jingi sho) and an attached shrine was built where eight gods were enshrined in Hasshinden (eight shrines) during the time of the gods of heaven and earth from ancient times under the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code).</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jingikan was restored during the Meiji period (later called Jingisho) and an attached shrine was built where eight gods were enshrined in Hasshinden (eight shrines) during the time of the gods of heaven and earth from ancient times under the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>明治5年、神祇省の祭祀は宮中に移されることになり、八神殿は宮中に遷座し、八神を天神地祇に合祀して神殿と改称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Meiji 5, the ritual of Jingi sho was to move to the Imperial Palace, Hasshinden transferred the Shinto shrine, and eight gods were enshrined in the gods of heaven and earth, it was then called Shinden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Meiji 5, the ritual of Jingi sho was to move to the Imperial Palace, Hasshinden transferred the Shinto shrine, and the eight gods were enshrined in the gods of heaven and earth, it was then called Shinden.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1872, as rituals of the Jingisho were moved to the Imperial Court, the Hasshinden was also transferred to the Imperial Court to enshrine the eight gods with Amatsukami and Kunitsukami, and this shrine&apos;s name was changed to Shinden.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 翰林硯士(id:99377), Sakura-no-kuni(id:115977), Nnh(id:474), たね(id:10372), Stanislaus(id:1806), Charenji(id:7908), Himazin(id:22034), Tenko(id:102318), 伏儀(id:142093), けんち(id:5147), 伊集院聖(id:53199), あばさー(id:95106), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>