<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>新田部親王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Niitabe</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Niitabe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Niitabe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>新田部親王（にいたべのしんのう、生年不詳 - 天平7年9月30日 (旧暦)（735年10月24日））は天武天皇の第10皇子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince niitabe (year of birth unknown - October 24, 735) was the tenth son of Emperor Tenmu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Niitabe (year of birth unknown - October 24, 735) was the tenth son of the Emperor Tenmu.</e>
<cmt>niitabe→Niitabe と修正しました。the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Niitabe (year of birth unknown - October 24, 735) was the tenth son of the Emperor Tenmu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>母は大原大刀自（藤原鎌足の娘）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was OHARA no Otoji (daughter of FUJIWARA no Kamatari).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was OHARA no Otoji (a daughter of FUJIWARA no Kamatari).</e>
<cmt>a を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was OHARA no Otoji (a daughter of FUJIWARA no Kamatari).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>塩焼王・道祖王の父。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the father of Prince Shioyaki and Prince Funado.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the father of the Prince Shioyaki and the Prince Funado.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the father of the Prince Shioyaki and the Prince Funado.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>官位は一品大将軍に昇る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His official rank was Ippon (First Order of an Imperial Prince) great general.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His official court rank was Ippon (First Order of an Imperial Prince) great general.</e>
<cmt>official rank→official court rank,スペースを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His official court rank was Ippon (First Order of an Imperial Prince) great general.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>新田部皇子（にいたべのみこ）とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also called Niitabe no Miko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also called Niitabe no Miko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also called Niitabe no Miko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>707年文武天皇大葬の際、舎人親王と共に皇太子聖武天皇（のちの聖武天皇）の補佐を命ぜられ、両親王の内舎人・大舎人・衛士が増員される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since he was assigned to support of Crown Prince Shomu (later Emperor Shomu) together with Imperial Prince Toneri at an imperial funeral of Emperor Monmu in 707, the number of Central Secretariat officers, Royal attendants and guards of both the imperial princes were increased.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As he was assigned to support the Crown Prince Shomu (later the Emperor Shomu) with the Imperial Prince Toneri at the imperial funeral of the Emperor Monmu in 707, the number of Central Secretariat officers, Royal attendants and guards of both the imperial princes were increased.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。Since→As,support of→support,スペースの修正、together with→with,an→the と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As he was assigned to support the Crown Prince Shomu (later the Emperor Shomu) with the Imperial Prince Toneri at the imperial funeral of the Emperor Monmu in 707, the number of Central Secretariat officers, Royal attendants and guards of both the imperial princes were increased.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>これは、天武天皇の皇子は舎人親王と新田部親王の両名しか存命していなかったため、重要な立場である事認識させるためだったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is because only the Imperial Prince Toneri and imperial Prince Niitabe lived among Emperor Tenmu&apos;s princes and also needed to generate public awareness that they were in important positions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because of making the public aware that there were only the Imperial Prince Toneri and the Imperial Niitabe as the princes of the Emperor Tenmu, therefore they were in the important position.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。文脈に応じて修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because of making the public aware that there were only the Imperial Prince Toneri and the Imperial Niitabe as the princes of the Emperor Tenmu, therefore they were in the important position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>720年に右大臣藤原不比等が没すると知五衛及授刀舎人人事に任命され禁衛軍を掌握する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to 知五衛 and Inner Palace Guard after the death of the minister of the right, FUJIWARA no Fuhito, and controlled the imperial army.</e>
<cmt>読み方・定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to 知五衛 and the Inner Palace Guard after the death of the minister of the right, FUJIWARA no Fuhito in 720, and controlled the imperial army.</e>
<cmt>the, 720 を補いました。「知五衛」の読みは確認できておりません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to 知五衛 and the Inner Palace Guard after the death of the minister of the right, FUJIWARA no Fuhito in 720, and controlled the imperial army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>724年首皇子が即位し、一品に叙せられる（異説あり）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 724, Prince Obito assumed the throne and was granted Ippon (First Order of an Imperial Prince) (Different theory exists).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 724, the Prince Obito ascended the throne, and was conferred Ippon (First Order of an Imperial Prince) (Different theory exists.)</e>
<cmt>the, カンマを補いました。assumed→ascended, granted→conferred,ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 724, the Prince Obito ascended the throne, and was conferred Ippon (First Order of an Imperial Prince) (Different theory exists.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>729年大将軍であった時、知太政官事舎人親王・藤原武智麻呂らと共に長屋王邸に派遣され、王の罪状を審議する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 729, when he was a command in chief, he was dispatched to Prince Nagaya house together with Deputy Prime Minister, FUJIWARA no Muchimaro to deliberate on the prince&apos;s accusation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 729, when he was the commander in chief, he was sent to the residence of the Prince Nagaya together with the Deputy Prime Minister, FUJIWARA no Muchimaro to deliberate on the prince&apos;s accusation.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。a command→the commander,dispatched→sent,Prince Nagaya house→residence of the Prince Nagaya と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 729, when he was the commander in chief, he was sent to the residence of the Prince Nagaya together with the Deputy Prime Minister, FUJIWARA no Muchimaro to deliberate on the prince&apos;s accusation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その後、畿内大惣官を経て735年平城京で没する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he attained a military position with power over the provinces of the Kinai (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto) and died in 735.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he attained the military position with power over the provinces of the Kinai (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto) and died in 735 in Heijo-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in current Nara).</e>
<cmt>a→the と修正しました。「平城京で」を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he attained the military position with power over the provinces of the Kinai (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto) and died in 735 in Heijo-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in current Nara).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>生年は判っていないが、50代であったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His year of birth is unknown, but it is assumed that he was in his 50&apos;s when he died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His age at that point is unknown, but it is assumed that he was in his 50&apos;s when he died.</e>
<cmt>「生年＝生まれてからの年数、年齢」とし、修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His age at that point is unknown, but it is assumed that he was in his 50&apos;s when he died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>756年5月の聖武天皇崩御の際、天皇の遺詔により子の道祖王が皇太子に立てられるが、翌757年品行不良を理由に皇太子を解かれ、同年7月橘奈良麻呂の乱に加担したとして拷問され獄死。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although his son, Prince Funado became Crown Prince based on Emperor Shomu&apos;s will when the Emperor died, he was demoted from Crown Prince due to his bad behavior in 757. He was tortured and died in prison on suspicion of involvement in TACHIBANA no Naramaro&apos;s war in July that year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although his son, the Prince Funado became the Crown Prince by the Emperor Shomu&apos;s will when the Emperor died, he was demoted from the Crown Prince due to his bad behavior in 757, then he was tortured and died in prison on the accusation of the involvement in the revolt of TACHIBANA no Naramaro in July of the same year.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。based on→by,パンクチュエーションを修正しました。suspicion→accusation,TACHIBANA no Nakamao&apos;s war→the revolt of TACHIBANA no Naramaro,that year→of the same year と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although his son, the Prince Funado became the Crown Prince by the Emperor Shomu&apos;s will when the Emperor died, he was demoted from the Crown Prince due to his bad behavior in 757, then he was tortured and died in prison on the accusation of the involvement in the revolt of TACHIBANA no Naramaro in July of the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>同じ年に塩焼王が氷上真人の姓を賜り臣籍降下するが、やはり藤原仲麻呂の乱で処刑される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, Prince Shioyaki was granted Hikami no Mahito (the highest of the eight hereditary titles) and demoted from nobility to subject, but he was also executed for FUJIWARAWA no Nakamaro&apos;s war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, the Prince Shioyaki was granted Hikami no Mahito (the highest of the eight hereditary titles) and demoted from nobility to subject, but he was also executed for the Rebellion of FUJIWARA no Nakamaro.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。 FUJIWARAWA no Nakamaro&apos;s war→Rebellion of FUJIWARA no Nakamaro と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, the Prince Shioyaki was granted Hikami no Mahito (the highest of the eight hereditary titles) and demoted from nobility to subject, but he was also executed for the Rebellion of FUJIWARA no Nakamaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また、新田部親王の邸宅は764年に鑑真に与えられ唐招提寺となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Imperial Prince Niitabe&apos;s house was granted to Jianzhen and it was turned into Toshodai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the Imperial Prince Niitabe&apos;s residence was granted to Jianzhen and it turned into Toshodai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。house→residence,was turned→turned と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the Imperial Prince Niitabe&apos;s residence was granted to Jianzhen and it turned into Toshodai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), たね(id:10372), 代言人(id:33675), 可怜(id:206074), 松茸(id:27535), UMBRO(id:100484), こぶまき(id:38278), Point136(id:211299), Andee(id:20421), ごまふあざ(id:36855), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>