<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>六条天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Rokujo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Rokujo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Rokujo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>六条天皇（ろくじょうてんのう、長寛2年11月14日（1164年12月28日） - 安元2年7月17日（1176年8月23日））は日本の第79代天皇（在位永万元年6月25日（1165年8月3日） - 仁安3年2月29日（1168年3月30日））。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Rokujo (February 28th,1164 - August 23rd, 1176) was the seventy ninth Emperor in Japan. (his reign was August 3rd, 1165 - March 30th, 1168.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Rokujo (February 28th,1164 - August 23rd, 1176) was the seventy ninth Emperor in Japan. (his reign was from August 3rd, 1165 to March 30th, 1168.)</e>
<cmt>&quot;from,&quot; &quot;to,&quot; added</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Rokujo (December 28, 1164 - August 23, 1176) was the seventy-ninth Emperor in Japan. (his reign was from August 3, 1165 to March 30, 1168.)</e>
<cmt>日付表記February→Decemberスペース挿入ハイフン挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>名を順仁（のぶひと）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His first name was Nobuhito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His first name was Nobuhito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His first name was Nobuhito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>系譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>二条天皇皇子、生母は大蔵大輔伊岐致遠女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the second Prince of Emperor Nijo, birth mother was Okura Taifu, IKI no Muneto&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the second Prince of Emperor Nijo, his birth mother was Okura Taifu, IKI no Muneto&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt>&quot;his&quot; added</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the second Prince of Emperor Nijo, his birth mother was Okura Taifu, IKI no Muneto&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>左大臣徳大寺実能の娘・皇后藤原育子を母后とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was Empress FUJIWARA no Ikushi, daughter of the Minister of the left, Saneyoshi TOKUDAIJI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was Empress FUJIWARA no Ikushi, the daughter of the Minister of the left, Saneyoshi TOKUDAIJI.</e>
<cmt>changed to &quot;the daughter&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was Empress FUJIWARA no Ikushi, the daughter of the Minister of the left, Saneyoshi TOKUDAIJI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>Biography→Brief Personal History</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>生後7ヶ月と11日（数え年で2歳）で親王宣下・立太子し、その日のうちに践祚（歴代最年少即位）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He received to title Prince by Imperial order when he was seven month and eleven days old (two years old by counting in the old Japanese way) and became Crown Prince, then succeeded to the throne on the same day. (the youngest Emperor in the history)</e>
<cmt>親王宣下→to title Prince by Imperial order[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He received the title of Prince by Imperial order when he was seven months and eleven days old (two years old by counting in the old Japanese way) and became Crown Prince, he then succeeded to the throne on the same day. (the youngest Emperor in the history)</e>
<cmt>particles revised/added to correct sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He received the title of Prince by Imperial order when he was seven months and eleven days old (two years old by counting in the old Japanese way) and became Crown Prince, he then succeeded to the throne on the same day. (the youngest Emperor in the history)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その2か月後の8月27日に即位式が行われるも、途中で泣き出して中断したために慌てて乳母（蔵人頭・藤原邦綱の娘、成子）が授乳させてやっと落ち着いたという（参議・中山忠親が、赤ん坊には儀式よりも乳の方が大切であると機転を利かせたのだという）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two months after that, on August 27th, the enthronement ceremony was held, however the ceremony was stopped since the Emperor started crying, his nanny (Kurodo no To,FUJIWARA no Kunitsuna) gave some milk and became calm finally. (It is said that Tadachika NAKAYAMA, the state councilor, had a quick witty think that it is more important for the baby to have milk than having enthronement ceremony.)</e>
<cmt>蔵人頭→[定訳不明、Kurodo no To]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two months later, on August 27th, the enthronement ceremony was held, however the ceremony was stopped because the Emperor started crying, his nanny (Kurodo no To,FUJIWARA no Kunitsuna) gave him some milk and he finally calmed down. (It is said that Tadachika NAKAYAMA, the quick witted state councilor, remarked that it was more important for the baby to have milk than have an enthronement ceremony.)</e>
<cmt>sentence restructured and corrected</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two months later, on August 27, the enthronement ceremony was held, however the ceremony was stopped because the Emperor started crying, his nanny (Kurodo no To, FUJIWARA no Kunitsuna&apos;s daughter Nariko) gave him some milk and he finally calmed down. (It is said that Tadachika NAKAYAMA, the quick witted state councilor, remarked that it was more important for the baby to have milk than have an enthronement ceremony.)</e>
<cmt>日付表記スペース挿入&apos;s daughter Nariko補足スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>勿論政務が執れるわけも無く、摂政・近衛基実（育子の兄）と邦綱が表向きを取り仕切った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was no way the young Emperor was able to rule the government, the regent, Motozane KONOE (Ikushi&apos;s older brother) and Kunitsuna took control of the politics officially.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was no way the young Emperor was able to rule the government, the regent, Motozane KONOE (Ikushi&apos;s older brother) and Kunitsuna officially took control of politics.</e>
<cmt>last part of the sentence restructured</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was no way the young Emperor was able to rule the government, the regent, Motozane KONOE (Ikushi&apos;s older brother) and Kunitsuna officially took control of politics.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>在位2年8ヶ月で祖父・後白河上皇の意向により、叔父の憲仁親王（後の高倉天皇）に譲位する（歴代最年少太上天皇）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After two years of being in power, the Emperor abdicated and passed the throne to his uncle, Prince Norihito (later called Emperor Takakura) as it was insisted by the ex-Emperor Go-Shirakawa. (the youngest ex-emperor in the history)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After two years of being in power, the Emperor abdicated and passed the throne to his uncle, Prince Norihito (later called Emperor Takakura) as it was insisted upon by the ex-Emperor Go-Shirakawa. (the youngest ex-emperor in the history)</e>
<cmt>revised to &quot;it was insisted upon&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After two years and eight months of being in power, the Emperor abdicated and passed the throne to his uncle, Imperial Prince Norihito (later called Emperor Takakura) as it was insisted upon by the retired Emperor Goshirakawa. (the youngest retired emperor in the history)</e>
<cmt>eight months補足Imperial補足ex-Emperor→retired EmperorGo-Shirakawa→Goshirakawa</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その後は世間からも忘れ去られた寂しい生涯を送り、元服を行う事も無く13歳で死去（死因は赤痢と言われる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that the Emperor did not have much attention from the public and spent a lonely time, he died at the age of thirteen, even without having a coming-of age ceremony. (It is said that he died of dysentery.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, the Emperor did not get much attention from the public and he spent a lonely time, he died at the age of thirteen, without even having a coming-of age ceremony. (It is said that he died of dysentery.)</e>
<cmt>commas inserted, wordage reordered to provide a correct sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, the Emperor did not get much attention from the public and he spent a lonely time, he died at the age of thirteen, without even having a coming-of age ceremony. (It is said that he died of dysentery.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>后妃なく、遺児なし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He did not have Empress or children.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He did not have an Empress nor any children.</e>
<cmt>corrected</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He did not have an Empress nor any children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>父である二条天皇は在世中に親政を行おうとして後白河と対立した上、異母弟・憲仁の擁立を画策したとして、憲仁の叔父・平時忠を流罪、平教盛・藤原成親・藤原信隆を解官して後白河の院政を停止させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father, Emperor Nijo tried to rule the government directly and opposed against Go-Shirakawa, he stopped Go-Shirakawa&apos;s cloister government by saying him laid a scheme to let half younger brother, Prince Norihito enthrone, and Norihito&apos;s uncle, TAIRA no Tokitada was sentenced to deportation, TAIRA no Norimori, FUJIWARA no Narichika and FUJIWARA no Nobutaka lost their positions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father, Emperor Nijo tried to directly rule the government and was opposed to Go-Shirakawa, he put an end to Go-Shirakawa&apos;s cloister government by saying he was scheming to allow his half younger brother, Prince Norihito, ascend to the throne, and Norihito&apos;s uncle, TAIRA no Tokitada was sentenced to deportation, TAIRA no Norimori, FUJIWARA no Narichika and FUJIWARA no Nobutaka lost their positions.</e>
<cmt>sentence restructured, words and phrases replaced, to provide clariy and a correct sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father, Emperor Nijo tried to directly rule the government and was opposed to Goshirakawa, he put an end to Goshirakawa&apos;s cloister government by saying he was scheming to allow his half younger brother, Prince Norihito, ascend to the throne, and Norihito&apos;s uncle, TAIRA no Tokitada was sentenced to deportation, TAIRA no Norimori, FUJIWARA no Narichika and FUJIWARA no Nobutaka lost their positions.</e>
<cmt>Go-Shirakawa→Goshirakawa</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>二条天皇の死後に、政治の実権を奪われていた後白河が清盛と手を結んで、甥から叔父へと言う不自然な皇位継承を実現させたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Emperor Nijo died, Go-shirakawa who lost political power worked together with Kiyomori, it is said the Imperial succession was passed nephew to his uncle in unusual way.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Emperor Nijo died, Go-shirakawa, who lost his political power, worked together with Kiyomori, and it is said that Imperial succession was passed from his nephew to his uncle in an unusual way.</e>
<cmt>commas placement and sentence corrected,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Emperor Nijo died, Goshirakawa, who lost his political power, worked together with Kiyomori, and it is said that Imperial succession was passed from his nephew to his uncle in an unusual way.</e>
<cmt>Go-Shirakawa→Goshirakawa</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>在位中の元号</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eras during his reign</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Era&apos;s during his reign</e>
<cmt>changed to &quot;Era&apos;s&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eras during his reign</e>
<cmt>Era&apos;s を Eras に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="16">
<j>永万 （1165年6月5日） - 1166年8月27日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(June 5, 1165) - August 27, 1166</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(June 5, 1165) - August 27, 1166</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eiman (June 5, 1165) - August 27, 1166</e>
<cmt>Eiman補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="17">
<j>仁安 1166年8月27日 - （1169年4月8日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 27, 1166 - (April 8, 1169)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 27, 1166 - (April 8, 1169)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ninan August 27, 1166 - (April 8, 1169)</e>
<cmt>Ninan補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="18">
<j>陵墓・霊廟</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial mausoleum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial mausoleum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial mausoleum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>京都市東山区清閑寺歌ノ中山町の清閑寺陵（せいかんじのみささぎ）に葬られたとされる｡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor was entombed in Seikan-ji no Misasagi at Uta no Nakayama-cho Town, Seikan-ji, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor was entombed in Seikan-ji no Misasagi at Uta no Nakayama-cho Town, Seikan-ji, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor was entombed in Seikan-ji no Misasagi at Uta no Nakayama-cho Town, Seikan-ji, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Lemon pie(id:66842), JAnDbot(id:66507), Lonicera(id:20638), Shi-tan(id:87611), Bletchingly(id:21356), 霧木諒二(id:9795), Nnh(id:474), 経済準学士(id:22656), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), Extrahitz(id:26245), Huemat(id:19503), 味っ子(id:17086), Ash Crow(id:26765), BAKU(id:55205), Zwobot(id:23873), MDR-SK(id:192066), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), Alecs.bot(id:194707), SuisuiBot(id:10165), 代言人(id:33675), 海行かば(id:115823), 名無し(id:7386), Rei-bot(id:94097), Yume149(id:17504), Homer(id:12084), Louperibot(id:128971), LeonardoRob0t(id:25875), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>