<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>久子内親王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Princess Hisako</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Princess Hisako</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Princess Hisako</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>久子内親王（ひさこないしんのう、生年不詳 - 貞観 (日本)18年6月18日 (旧暦)（876年7月12日））は、平安時代前期の皇族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Princess Hisako (date of birth unknown-July 12, 876) was a member of the imperial family in the first half of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Princess Hisako (date of birth unknown-July 12, 876) was a member of the imperial family during the first half of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Princess Hisako (year of birth unknown - July 16, 876) was a member of the Imperial Family during the first half of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>用語統一グレゴリオ暦に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>仁明天皇の皇女で、母は宮人の従五位高宗女王（従四位岡屋王の娘）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was a princess of Emperor Ninmyo, and her mother was a Kyujin (court lady), Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank), Princess Takamune (daughter of Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank), Prince Okaya).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was the princess of Emperor Ninmyo, and her mother was a Kyujin (court lady), Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank), Princess Takamune (daughter of Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank, - Prince Okaya).</e>
<cmt>grammar,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was the princess of Emperor Ninmyo, and her mother was a Kyujin (court lady), Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank), Princess Takamune (daughter of Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank), - Prince Okaya).</e>
<cmt>)補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>伊勢斎宮。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ise Saigu (vestal virgin princess serving at Ise-jingu Shrine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ise Saigu (vestal virgin princess serving at Ise-jingu Shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ise Saigu (vestal virgin princess serving at Ise-jingu Shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>母・高宗女王は高市皇子（天武天皇皇子）の曾孫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her mother, Princess Takamune was a great-grandchild of Prince Takechi (prince of Emperor Tenmu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her mother, Princess Takamune was the great-grandchild of Prince Takechi (prince of Emperor Tenmu).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her mother, Princess Takamune was the great-grandchild of Prince Takechi (prince of Emperor Tenmu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>久子内親王は天長10年（833年）3月に父仁明天皇の斎宮に卜定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Princess Hisako was designated as Saigu (Imperial Princess appointed to serve the deities of the Ise-jingu Shrine) of her father, Emperor Ninmyo by bokujo (to decide by fortunetelling) in March, 833.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Princess Hisako was designated as Saigu (Imperial Princess appointed to serve the deities of the Ise-jingu Shrine) for her father, Emperor Ninmyo by bokujo (decided by fortunetelling) in March, 833.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Princess Hisako was designated as Saigu (Imperial Princess appointed to serve the deities of the Ise-jingu Shrine) for her father, Emperor Ninmyo by bokujo (decided by fortunetelling) in March, 833.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>承和 (日本)2年（835年）9月5日伊勢に群行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 5, 835, she went to Ise for Gunko (three years of purification for Saigu at Nonomiya, and returning to Ise).</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 5, 835, she went to Ise for Gunko (three years of purification for Saigu at Nonomiya) and then returned to Ise.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 4, 835, she went to Ise for Gunko (three years of purification for Saigu at Nonomiya) and then returned to Ise.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そして仁明天皇の崩御を受けて嘉祥3年（850年）5月退下した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May 850, she resigned after Emperor Ninmyo passed away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May 850, she resigned after Emperor Ninmyo passed away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June 850, she resigned after Emperor Ninmyo passed away.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>清和天皇の治世末期の貞観18年（876年）6月18日に薨去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She passed away in the end of the reign of Emperor Seiwa, on June 18, 876.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She passed away at the end of the reign of Emperor Seiwa, on June 18, 876.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She passed away at the end of the reign of Emperor Seiwa, on July 16, 876.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>無品だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was muhon (without a court rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was muhon (without a court rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was muhon (without a court rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), YOSHI438(id:174755), Tribot(id:186681), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>