<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>直仁親王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Naohito</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Naohito</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Naohito</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>直仁親王（なおひとしんのう、建武2年（1335年）－応永2年5月14日（1398年））は、南北朝時代の持明院統の皇族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Naohito (1335-May 14, 1398) was a member of Imperial family on the Jimyo-in Imperial line in the period of the Southern and Northern Dynasties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Naohito (1335-May 14, 1398) was a member of the Imperial family of the Jimyo-in Imperial line in the period of the Southern and Northern Dynasties.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Naohito (1335 - June 10, 1395) was a member of the Imperial Family of the Jimyo-in Imperial line in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入グレゴリ歴に原文の1398は1395が正しい年号です。スペルを修正Dynasties→CourtsSouthern and Northern→Northern and Southernに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>花園天皇の皇子で母は宣光門院正親町実子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the child of Emperor Hanazono; his mother was Senkomonin Jisshi(Saneko) Ogimachi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the child of Emperor Hanazono; his mother was Senkomonin Jisshi (Saneko) Ogimachi.</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the child of Emperor Hanazono; his mother was Senkomonin Jisshi (Saneko) Ogimachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>北朝・崇光天皇の皇太子（厳密には皇太弟）に立てられたが、正平一統の際に南朝軍によって吉野へと連行されて廃太子された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he had been enthroned as the prince (in a precise sense, the younger brother of an Emperor who is heir apparent), he was taken to Yoshino by the Southern dynasty army at the time of the incident; Shohei itto, and he was deprived his throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After enthroned as prince (younger brother of an Emperor who is heir apparent), he was taken to Yoshino by the Southern dynasty army at the time of the Shohei itto incident; and was deprived of his throne.</e>
<cmt>grammar, wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After enthroned as prince (younger brother of an Emperor who is heir apparent) of Northern Court Emperor Suko, he was taken to Yoshino by the Southern court army at the time of the Shohei itto (temporal unification of the Northern and Southern Courts) incident; and was deprived of his throne.</e>
<cmt>of Northern Court Emperor Suko補足「正平一統」に英語の説明を加えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>父・花園上皇の御所であった「萩原殿」を継承したことから萩原宮（はぎわらみや）の通称がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also called Hagiwara no miya as he succeeded `Hagiwaradono&apos; (Hagiwara palace) which was the palace of his father, the Retired Emperor Hanazono.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also called Hagiwara no miya as he succeeded `Hagiwaradono&apos; (Hagiwara palace) which was the palace of his father, the Retired Emperor Hanazono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also called Hagiwara no miya as he succeeded `Hagiwaradono&apos; (Hagiwara palace) which was the palace of his father, the Retired Emperor Hanazono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一Career→Backgroundに変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>本来、父の花園天皇は持明院統においては傍流であり、その皇位は嫡流である後伏見天皇－光厳天皇－崇光天皇の系統に引き継がれるものと考えられていたために親王は皇位継承に与れる立場にはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father, Emperor Hanazono was originally a branch line of the Jyomyo-in Imperial line and was not in a position who succeeds the throne; the throne was supposed to be succeeded by the main line; Emperor Gofushime-Emperor Kogon-Emperor Suko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father, Emperor Hanazono was originally a branch line of the Jyomyo-in Imperial line and was not in a position to succeed the throne; the throne was supposed to be succeeded by the main line; Emperor Gofushime-Emperor Kogon-Emperor Suko.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because his father, Emperor Hanazono was originally a branch line of the Jimyo-in Imperial line, Imperial Prince was not in a position to succeed the throne; the throne was supposed to be succeeded by the main line; Emperor Gofushimi-Emperor Kogon-Emperor Suko.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正Because補足Imperial Prince補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>ところが、1348年（貞和4年/正平3年）に元服すると光厳天皇の猶子として皇位継承権が与えられ、その年の10月27日に義兄にあたる崇光天皇の皇太子に立てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when he had Genpuku ceremony (coming-age of ceremony for a man after the Nara period), he was granted the right to the imperial throne; he was enthroned as the prince of Emperor Suko (his brother in law) on October 27 in the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when he had the Genpuku ceremony (coming-age of ceremony for a young man after the Nara period), he was granted the right to the imperial throne; and was enthroned as the prince of Emperor Suko (his brother in law) on October 27 in the same year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when he had the Genpuku ceremony (coming- of-age ceremony for a young man after the Nara period) in 1348, he was granted the right to the imperial throne as the adopted child of Emperor Kogen, and was enthroned as the prince of Emperor Suko (his brother in law) on October 27 in the same year.</e>
<cmt>年号補足coming-age of ceremony→coming- of-age「光厳天皇の猶子として」を訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>ところが、観応の擾乱の最中の1351年（観応2年/正平6年）、室町幕府の征夷大将軍である足利尊氏が南朝の後村上天皇に降伏、これを受けて南朝軍が京都を制圧して北朝方皇族を拘禁した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1351 in the middle of the Kano Disturbance, Takauji ASHIKAGA, seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), surrendered Emperor Gomurakami; in response to this, the Southern dynasty army conquered Kyoto, and held the imperial family members on the Northern dynasty side in custody.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1351 in the middle of the Kano Disturbance, Takauji ASHIKAGA, seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), surrendered Emperor Gomurakami; in response to this, the Southern dynasty army conquered Kyoto, and held the imperial family members on the Northern dynasty side in custody.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1351 in the middle of the Kano Disturbance, Takauji ASHIKAGA, seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), surrendered Emperor Gomurakami of Southern Court; in response to this, the Southern court army conquered Kyoto, and held the imperial family members on the Northern court side in custody.</e>
<cmt>Dynasty→Court</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>11月7日（11月26日）、南朝によって崇光天皇と直仁皇太子の廃位が宣言された（正平一統）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 7, the abolishment of the throne of Emperor Suko and Prince Naohito was announced by the Southern dynasty (Shohhei itto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 7, the abolishment of the throne of Emperor Suko and Prince Naohito was announced by the Southern dynasty (Shohhei itto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 7, the abolishment of the throne of Emperor Suko and Prince Naohito was announced by the Southern court (Shohei itto).</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正Dynasty→Court</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>やがて、尊氏と南朝が再度対立して南朝軍が京都からの撤退を余儀なくされると、南朝軍は光厳・光明天皇・崇光の3太上天皇と廃太子直仁親王は南朝の本拠である大和国吉野に連行され、続いて賀名生（現在の奈良県五條市）に幽閉された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soon after, the Southern dynasty army was forced to move out of Kyoto due to the opposition between Takauji and the Southern dynasty; the Southern dynasty army with Emperor Kogon, Emperor Komyo, the Retired three Emperors of Suko, the abolished Imperial Prince Naohito were taken to Yoshino, Yamato Province; the base of the southern dynasty, and they were confined in Anou (present-day Gojo City, Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon after, the Southern dynasty army was forced to move out of Kyoto due to the opposition between Takauji and the Southern dynasty; the Southern dynasty army with Emperor Kogon, Emperor Komyo, the Retired three Emperors of Suko, the abolished Imperial Prince Naohito were taken to Yoshino, Yamato Province; the base of the southern dynasty, and they were confined in Anou (present-day Gojo City, Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon after, the Southern court army was forced to move out of Kyoto due to the opposition between Takauji and the Southern court; the Southern court army with Emperor Kogon, Emperor Komyo, the Retired three Emperors of Suko, the abolished Imperial Prince Naohito were taken to Yoshino, Yamato Province; the base of the southern court, and they were confined in Ano (present-day Gojo City, Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>Dynasty→Courtスペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>1356年（延文元年/正平11年）に解放されて、翌年に京都に帰還するが、京都では既に崇光天皇の実弟である後光厳天皇が尊氏によって擁立された後であり、崇光天皇と直仁皇太子の復位要求は拒絶された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After their release in 1356, they returned to Kyoto in the following year, however, their demands for reinstatement of Emperor Suko and Imperial Prince Naohito were denied; in Kyoto, the younger bother of Emperor Suko, Emperor Kogon had been enthroned by Takauji until then.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After their release in 1356, they returned to Kyoto in the following year, however, their demands for reinstatement of Emperor Suko and Imperial Prince Naohito were denied; in Kyoto, the younger bother of Emperor Suko, Emperor Kogon had been enthroned by Takauji until then.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After their release in 1356, they returned to Kyoto in the following year, however, their demands for reinstatement of Emperor Suko and Imperial Prince Naohito were denied; in Kyoto, the younger bother of Emperor Suko, Emperor Kogon had been enthroned by Takauji until then.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>直仁親王は失意のうちに出家して父の御所であった萩原殿に隠退し、南北朝合一後にこの世を去った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Naohito was disappointed and became a priest; he retired into Hagiwaradono (Hagiwara palace), his father&apos;s palace, and passed away after the Southern and Northern dynasties were united.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Naohito was disappointed and became a priest; he retired into Hagiwaradono (Hagiwara palace), his father&apos;s palace, and passed away after the Southern and Northern dynasties were united.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Naohito was disappointed and became a priest; he retired into Hagiwaradono (Hagiwara palace), his father&apos;s palace, and passed away after the Southern and Northern courts were united.</e>
<cmt>Dynasty→Court</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), Equaly(id:89792), 代言人(id:33675), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), UMBRO(id:100484), Extrahitz(id:26245), Andee(id:20421), Yas(id:739), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>