<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>糠手姫皇女</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nukadehime no himemiko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nukadehime no himemiko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nukadehime no himemiko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>糠手姫皇女（ぬかでひめのひめみこ、生年不詳 - 天智天皇3年（664年）6月）は古墳時代末期から飛鳥時代にかけての皇族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nukadehime no himemiko (year of birth unknown - June, 664 or the third year of Emperor Tenchi&apos;s reign) was an imperial princess during the time from the late Tumulus period to Asuka period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nukadehime no himemiko (year of birth unknown - July, 664) was a member of the Imperial Family from the late Tumulus period to Asuka period.</e>
<cmt>カッコ内を修正しました。天智天皇3年（664年）6月→西暦664年7月と修正しました。an imperial princess→a member of the Imperial Family と修正しました。during the time を削除しました。the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nukadehime no himemiko (year of birth unknown - July, 664) was a member of the Imperial Family from the late Tumulus period to Asuka period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>『日本書紀』では他に田村皇女、『古事記』では宝王、糠代比売王と表記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She is referred to by other names, such as Princess Tamura in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), and Takara no miko or Nukade hime no miko in &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She is referred to by other names, such as the Princess Tamura in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), and Takara no miko or Nukade hime no miko in &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters).</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She is referred to by other names, such as the Princess Tamura in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), and Takara no miko or Nukade hime no miko in &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>押坂彦人大兄皇子の妃。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was a wife of Oshisaka no Hikohito no Oenomiko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was a wife of Oshisaka no Hikohito no Oenomiko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was a wife of Oshisaka no Hikohito no Oenomiko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>舒明天皇の母。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was the mother of Emperor Jomei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was the mother of the Emperor Jomei.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was the mother of the Emperor Jomei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>父は第30代敏達天皇、母は伊勢大鹿首小熊の女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her father was the thirtieth Emperor Bidatsu, and her mother was a daughter of Ise no Ooka no obito oguma.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her father was the thirtieth Emperor Bidatsu, and her mother was a daughter of Ise no Ooka no obito oguma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her father was the thirtieth Emperor Bidatsu, and her mother was a daughter of Ise no Ooka no obito oguma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>同母姉妹には太姫皇女がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Futohime no miko was a sister-uterine to her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Futohime no miko was her sister-uterine.</e>
<cmt>a sister-uterine to her→her sister-uterine と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Futohime no miko was her sister-uterine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>正確な年は不明だが、590年前後頃に異母兄の押坂彦人大兄皇子と結婚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the exact year is unknown, around 590, she married with Oshisaka no Hikohito no Oenomiko, who was her half-elder brother by a different mother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the exact year is unknown, around 590, she married Oshisaka no Hikohito no Oenomiko, who was her older paternal half-brother.</e>
<cmt>married with→married,half -elder brother by a different mother→older paternal half-brother と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the exact year is unknown, around 590, she married Oshisaka no Hikohito no Oenomiko, who was her older paternal half-brother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>彼は敏達天皇の嫡男だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a legitimate son of the Emperor Bidatsu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a legitimate son of the Emperor Bidatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a legitimate son of the Emperor Bidatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし、蘇我氏が勢威を振るっていた中、母親がその血を引いていなかった為だったのか、王位につけないまま若い内に死別する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he died young without being able to accede to the throne probably because his mother was not descended from Soga clan, which was exercising great power at the time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he died young without being able to accede to the throne, probably because his mother was not descended from the Soga clan, which was exercising great power at the time.</e>
<cmt>カンマを補いました。the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he died young without being able to accede to the throne, probably because his mother was not descended from the Soga clan, which was exercising great power at the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>この間593年（推古天皇元年）頃に後の舒明天皇こと田村皇子を儲ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During this time, around 593 (the first year of Emperor Suiko&apos;s reign), she bore Prince Tamura, who was later to become the Emperor Jomei.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the marriage, around 593, she bore the Prince Tamura, who was later to become the Emperor Jomei.</e>
<cmt>this time→the marriage と修正しました。カッコ部分を削除し、the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the marriage, around 593, she bore the Prince Tamura, who was later to become the Emperor Jomei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その後中津王・多良王を儲ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequently, she bore Nakatsu miko and Tara no miko.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, she bore Nakatsu miko and Tara no miko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, she bore Nakatsu miko and Tara no miko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>『日本書紀』によれば、時の推古天皇（推古天皇）には彼女にとっていとこ（従姉弟？）にあたる厩戸皇子（聖徳太子）が皇太子・摂政として天皇を助けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot;, Prince Umayado (Prince Shotoku), who was a cousin to her, supported Emperor Suiko then in power as a crown prince or Sessho (regent).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; the Prince Umayado (the Prince Shotoku), who was a cousin to her, supported the Empressr Suiko then in power as a crown prince and Sessho (regent).</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を修正しました。the を補いました。Emperor→Empress,or→and と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; the Prince Umayado (the Prince Shotoku), who was a cousin to her, supported the Empressr Suiko then in power as a crown prince and Sessho (regent).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>そのため、長男の田村皇子にも王位継承の可能性はないかに思われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it was considered that there was no possibility for her eldest son, Prince Tamura to succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it was considered that there was no possibility for her first son, the Prince Tamura to succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt>eldest→first と修正しました。the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it was considered that there was no possibility for her first son, the Prince Tamura to succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>けれども、蘇我馬子の娘、法提郎女と結婚し、その間に初孫と思われる古人大兄皇子を儲けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he married with Hotei no irazume, a daughter of SOGA no Umako, by whom he had Furuhito no Oe no Miko, who seems to have been the first grandchild to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he married Hotei no irazume, a daughter of SOGA no Umako, by whom he had Furuhito no Oe no Miko, who seems to have been the first grandchild to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>married with→married と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he married Hotei no irazume, a daughter of SOGA no Umako, by whom he had Furuhito no Oe no Miko, who seems to have been the first grandchild to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>これにより、結果的に先に亡くなった厩戸皇子より長生きした大王からは後継者に明確に指定はされなかったものの、蘇我氏の力を背景に629年（舒明天皇元年）に即位した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, backed by the power of Soga clan, he acceded to the throne in 629 (as the Emperor Jomei) even though he had not been officially assigned by the okimi (great king), who outlived the Imperial Prince Umayado, who consequently died earlier than the okimi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, backed by the power of the Soga clan, he acceded to the throne in 629 although he had not been officially assigned by the okimi (great king), who outlived the Imperial Prince Umayado, who consequently died earlier than the okimi.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。カッコ部分を削除しました。even though→although と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, backed by the power of the Soga clan, he acceded to the throne in 629 although he had not been officially assigned by the okimi (great king), who outlived the Imperial Prince Umayado, who consequently died earlier than the okimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>この結果、彼女は大王の母となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, she became the mother of okimi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, she became the mother of okimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, she became the mother of okimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>しかし、641年（舒明天皇13年）に田村大王は彼女に先立って崩御してしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Tamura Okimi demised in 641(the thirteenth year of Emperor Jomei&apos;s reign) leaving behind him his mother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Tamura Okimi met his demise in 641, leaving his mother.</e>
<cmt>カッコ部分を削除しました。demised→met his demise と修正しました。behind him を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Tamura Okimi met his demise in 641, leaving his mother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>その後はまだ山背大兄王や後の天智天皇こと異母弟の天智天皇等競争相手がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Probably because of that, Empress Kogyoku (a granddaughter of Oshisaka no Hikohito no Oenomiko), who was the wife of her son, Tamura Okimi, as well as her granddaughter in law and her first cousin twice removed, acceded to the throne.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were still many rivals after that, including the Prince Yamashiro no oe and the Emperor Tenchi, a younger paternal half-brother.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ対応しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were still many rivals after that, including the Prince Yamashiro no oe and the Emperor Tenchi, a younger paternal half-brother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>その為か、息子の嫁で、義理の孫・姪孫でもある皇后・皇極天皇（押坂彦人大兄皇子の孫娘）が王位（皇極天皇）につく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Probably because of that, Empress Kogyoku (a granddaughter of Oshisaka no Hikohito no Oenomiko), who was the wife of her son, Tamura Okimi, as well as her granddaughter in law and her first cousin twice removed, acceded to the throne.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Probably because of that, the Empress Kogyoku (a granddaughter of Oshisaka no Hikohito no Oenomiko), who was the wife of her son, Tamura Okimi, as well as her granddaughter in law and her grand niece, acceded to the throne.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。first cousin twice removed→grandniece と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Probably because of that, the Empress Kogyoku (a granddaughter of Oshisaka no Hikohito no Oenomiko), who was the wife of her son, Tamura Okimi, as well as her granddaughter in law and her grand niece, acceded to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="21">
<j>しかし、645年（皇極天皇4年）に乙巳の変で蘇我蝦夷・蘇我入鹿親子の宗本家が滅ぼされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 645 (the fourth year of Empress Kogyoku&apos;s reign), however, Soga no Emishi, the father and his son, SOGA no Iruka of the head family of Soga clan were ruined in Isshi-no-hen (the Murder in the Year of Isshi).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 645, however, the head family of the Soga clan of Soga no Emishi, the father and his son, SOGA no Iruka was destroyed in Isshi-no-hen (the Murder in the Year of Isshi).</e>
<cmt>カッコ部分を削除しました。 the を補いました。オーダーを修正しました。ruined→destroyed と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 645, however, the head family of the Soga clan of Soga no Emishi, the father and his son, SOGA no Iruka was destroyed in Isshi-no-hen (the Murder in the Year of Isshi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>すると、彼らに擁立されていた古人大兄皇子がクーデターの首謀者だった中大兄皇子・藤原鎌足に抹殺される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This incident entailed the murder of Furuhito no Oe no Miko, who had been supported by the Soga clan, done by Naka no Oe no Oji and FUJIWARA no Kamatari, who were the principal architects of the coup.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This incident entailed the murder of Furuhito no Oe no Miko, who had been pressed by the Soga clan, by Naka no Oe no Oji and FUJIWARA no Kamatari, who were the ringleaders of the coup.</e>
<cmt>supported→pressed,done by→by,principal architects→ringleaders と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This incident entailed the murder of Furuhito no Oe no Miko, who had been pressed by the Soga clan, by Naka no Oe no Oji and FUJIWARA no Kamatari, who were the ringleaders of the coup.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>こうして、彼女は孫同士の殺し合いを見る悲哀を味わう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, she felt sorrow at seeing her grandsons kill each other.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, she felt sorrow at seeing her grandsons kill each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, she felt sorrow at seeing her grandsons kill each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>更に、654年（白雉4年）にはやはり姪孫にあたる軽大王（孝徳天皇）が崩御。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 654, Karu no miko (Emperor Kotoku), who was also a first cousin twice removed to her, was demised.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 654, Karu no miko (the Emperor Kotoku), who was also a grandnephew to her, met his demise.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。first cousin twice removed→grandnephew, was demised→met his demise と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 654, Karu no miko (the Emperor Kotoku), who was also a grandnephew to her, met his demise.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>658年（皇極天皇4年）には曾甥孫にあたる有間皇子が処刑、曾孫である建皇子が早世。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 658 (the fourth year of Empress Kogyoku&apos;s reign), Prince Arima, who was great-grandnephew to her, was executed, and Takeru no miko, who was a great-grandchild to her, died young.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 658, the Prince Arima, who was a great-grandnephew to her, was executed, and Takeru no miko, who was a great-grandchild to her, died young.</e>
<cmt>カッコ部分を削除しました。 the, a を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 658, the Prince Arima, who was a great-grandnephew to her, was executed, and Takeru no miko, who was a great-grandchild to her, died young.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>661年（斉明天皇7年）には重祚していた宝大王（斉明天皇）が崩御。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 661 (the fourth year of Empress Saimei&apos;s reign), Takara no miko (Empress Saimei) deceased.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 661, Takara no miko (the Empress Saimei) who had twice acceded the throne passed away.</e>
<cmt>カッコ部分を削除しました。the を補いました。「重祚していた」を補いました。deceased→passed away と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 661, Takara no miko (the Empress Saimei) who had twice acceded the throne passed away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>このように、多くの近親者に先立たれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this way, she was bereaved of many of her close relatives.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this way, many of her close relatives died before her.</e>
<cmt>よりスムースに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this way, many of her close relatives died before her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>自身も白村江の戦いの敗戦直後、孫の葛城皇子（後の天智天皇）の正式な即位を見ないまま、664年に薨去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 664, immediately after the defeat in Battle of Hakusukinoe, she herself deceased without being able to see the official enthronement of her grandson, Katsuragi no Miko (who was later to become the Emperor Tenchi).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 664, immediately after the defeat in the Battle of Hakusukinoe, she passed away without being able to see the official enthronement of her grandson, Katsuragi no Miko (who was later to become the Emperor Tenchi).</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。herself deceased→passed away と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 664, immediately after the defeat in the Battle of Hakusukinoe, she passed away without being able to see the official enthronement of her grandson, Katsuragi no Miko (who was later to become the Emperor Tenchi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>尚、その時既に、玄孫にあたる大来皇女・草壁皇子・大津皇子が誕生していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, great-great-grandsons, Oku no himemiko, Prince Kusakabe and Prince Otsu had already come into being.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, the great-great-grandsons, Oku no himemiko, the Prince Kusakabe and the Prince Otsu had already been born.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。come into being→been born と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, the great-great-grandsons, Oku no himemiko, the Prince Kusakabe and the Prince Otsu had already been born.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>享年は不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her age of death is unknown.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her age of death is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her age of death is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>（彼女にとって）長男田村皇子の有力生年から、彼女自身には伝わる事績は多いとはいえないが、崇仏や王位継承などを巡って対立した蘇我・物部両氏の二頭体制から、厩戸皇子が活躍したとされている推古朝、彼亡き後深まった蘇我氏の専横、大化の改新、対外戦争等と数多くの事件を見ながら当時としてはかなりの長寿を全うしたと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She does not have numerous exploits to her credit but judging from the most convincing theory about the year of the birth of her son, Prince Tamura, she seems to have lived a longest life in those days going through various incidents, such as the diarchy system of the Soga clan and the Mononobe clan, which conflicted each other on the Buddha worship and the succession to the throne, the Reign of Empress Suiko, during which Prince Umayado seemingly wielded great power, the despotism of the Soga clan which have enforced after the demise of the Prince, the Taika Reforms, and the wars against other countries.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She does not have numerous exploits to her credit but judging from the most convincing theory about the year of the birth of her son, the Prince Tamura, she seems to have lived a long life in those days going through various incidents, such as the diarchy system of the Soga clan and the Mononobe clan, which conflicted each other on the Buddha worship and the succession to the throne, the reign of the Empress Suiko, during which the Prince Umayado seemingly wielded great power, the despotism of the Soga clan which enforced after the demise of the Prince, the Taika Reforms, and the wars against other countries.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。longest→long,Reign→reign,have enforced→enforced と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She does not have numerous exploits to her credit but judging from the most convincing theory about the year of the birth of her son, the Prince Tamura, she seems to have lived a long life in those days going through various incidents, such as the diarchy system of the Soga clan and the Mononobe clan, which conflicted each other on the Buddha worship and the succession to the throne, the reign of the Empress Suiko, during which the Prince Umayado seemingly wielded great power, the despotism of the Soga clan which enforced after the demise of the Prince, the Taika Reforms, and the wars against other countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>既に実質上の大王だった葛城皇子の祖母であり、飛鳥嶋宮に住んだことから没後には嶋皇祖母命と称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As she was the grandmother of Katsuragi no Miko, who already became okimi (great king) substantially, and she lived in Shimanomiya (detached palace) in Asuka, she was called Shima no sumemiya no mikoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As she was the grandmother of Katsuragi no Miko, who had already become actual okimi (great king), and she lived in Shimanomiya (detached palace) in Asuka, she was called Shima no sumemiya no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>already became→had already become,substantially→actual （オーダー修正） と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As she was the grandmother of Katsuragi no Miko, who had already become actual okimi (great king), and she lived in Shimanomiya (detached palace) in Asuka, she was called Shima no sumemiya no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="33">
<j>御名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The emperor&apos;s name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Name of the emperor</e>
<cmt>よりスムースに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Name of the emperor</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="34">
<j>なお、彼女は前述どおり田村皇女との別名がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As stated above, she had another name, Tamura no hime miko.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As stated above, she had another name, Tamura no hime miko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As stated above, she had another name, Tamura no hime miko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>息子舒明天皇の御名田村は彼女のその別名をそのまま継承したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her son, the Emperor Jomei also had another imperial name, Tamura, because he succeeded to her byname as it was.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The imperial name of the Emperor Jomei, her son, Tamura is what he succeeded her another name as it was.</e>
<cmt>文脈に応じて修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The imperial name of the Emperor Jomei, her son, Tamura is what he succeeded her another name as it was.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>また、皇極・斉明天皇の宝皇女もその可能性が高いと平林章仁氏（大和高田市片塩中学校教諭）等は指摘している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akihito HIRABAYSHI (Teacher, Katashio Junior High School in Yamatotakada City) and others point out that it is highly likely that Empress Kogyoku or Saimei was called Takara no Himemiko for the same reason.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akihito HIRABAYSHI (a teacher of Katashio Junior High School in Yamatotakada City) and others point out that it is highly likely that the Empress Kogyoku or the Saimei was called Takara no Himemiko for the same reason.</e>
<cmt>Teacher,→a teacher of と修正しました。the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akihito HIRABAYSHI (a teacher of Katashio Junior High School in Yamatotakada City) and others point out that it is highly likely that the Empress Kogyoku or the Saimei was called Takara no Himemiko for the same reason.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>宝（財）の名は古代においては反正天皇や仁賢天皇の皇女にその名が見え、また厩戸皇子の子にも財皇子がいたなど、珍しい名前ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The word Takara (zai or treasure) used as a name was not so uncommon in the ancient times as it was seen in the names of imperial princesses of Emperor Hanzei or Emperor Ninken, and there was Zai no miko as a son of the Prince Umayado.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The word Takara (zai or treasure) used as a name was not so uncommon in the ancient times as it was seen in the names of the imperial princesses of the Emperor Hanzei or the Emperor Ninken, and there was Zai no miko as a son of the Prince Umayado.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word Takara (zai or treasure) used as a name was not so uncommon in the ancient times as it was seen in the names of the imperial princesses of the Emperor Hanzei or the Emperor Ninken, and there was Zai no miko as a son of the Prince Umayado.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>これは、皇子女の養育に伴造直属の部下が担ったことから来ている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This originated in the fact that the upbringing of imperial princes and princesses was left largely to their Tomonomiyatsuko (the chief of various departments at the Imperial Court).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This originated in the fact that the upbringing of the imperial princes and the princesses was left largely to their Tomonomiyatsuko (the chief of various departments at the Imperial Court).</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This originated in the fact that the upbringing of the imperial princes and the princesses was left largely to their Tomonomiyatsuko (the chief of various departments at the Imperial Court).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MIO(id:31681), MDR-SK(id:192066), Masyu(id:31065), 平惣衛門(id:99387), かえるちゃん(id:197260), 彩華1226(id:64711), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>