<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>小倉宮恒敦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsuneatsu OGURANOMIYA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsuneatsu OGURANOMIYA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuneatsu OGURANOMIYA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>小倉宮恒敦（おぐらのみや つねあつ、生年不詳 － 応永29年7月15日 (旧暦)（1422年8月11日））は、南北朝時代 (日本)の第99代、南朝 (日本)最後の第4代天皇である後亀山天皇の皇子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsuneatsu OGURANOMIYA (year of birth unknown - August 2, 1422) was a Prince of Emperor Gokameyama, who was the ninety-ninth Emperor in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts, and was the last, the fourth Emperor of the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsuneatsu OGURANOMIYA (year of birth unknown - August 2, 1422) was a Prince of Emperor Gokameyama, who was the 99th Emperor in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts, and was the fourth and last Emperor of the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>fourth and last</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuneatsu OGURANOMIYA (year of birth unknown - August 11, 1422) was a Prince of Emperor Gokameyama, who was the 99th Emperor in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts, and was the fourth and last Emperor of the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>没日をセル14に合わせました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>小倉宮家初代。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the first generation of the Oguranomiya family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the first generation of the Oguranomiya family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the first generation of the Oguranomiya family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>親王宣下があったかどうか不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whether he was conferred as an Imperial Prince or not remains unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not know whether he was made an Imperial Prince or not.</e>
<cmt>edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not know whether he was made an Imperial Prince or not.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>南北朝合一の際、北朝 (日本)側は恒敦を後小松天皇の皇太子とする約束をした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time of the unification of the Southern and the Northern Courts, the side of Northern Court promised to make Tsuneatsu as the Crown Prince of Emperor Gokomatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time of the unification of the Southern and Northern Courts, the Northern Court promised to make Tsuneatsu as the Crown Prince of Emperor Gokomatsu.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time of the unification of the Southern and Northern Courts, the Northern Court promised to make Tsuneatsu as the Crown Prince of Emperor Gokomatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>しかし、後亀山上皇と恒敦は、応永17年（1410年）吉野に逃亡する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the retired Emperor Gokameyama and Tsuneatsu escaped to Yoshino Province in 1410.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the retired Emperor Gokameyama and Tsuneatsu escaped to Yoshino Province in 1410.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Retired Emperor Gokameyama and Tsuneatsu escaped to Yoshino in 1410.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>（経済的理由を根拠としてと自称した）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(they said that they made the escape from economical reasons).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(they said that they made the escape for economic reasons).</e>
<cmt>economic</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(They said that they made the escape for economic reasons.)</e>
<cmt>スペルピリオド位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかしこの逃亡は本当は南朝側に皇位を継がせることを快く思っていなかった後小松天皇をはじめとする北朝側を牽制する目的があったのではないかという説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there is an opinion telling that actually, they might have tried to restrain the Northern Court side, including Emperor Gokomatsu, by escaping from them, since the Northern Court side was not in favor of the Southern Court side succeeding the Imperial Throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, some say that they actually might have been trying to restrain the Northern Court, including Emperor Gokomatsu, by escaping from them, since the Northern Court was not in favor of the Southern Court succeeding the Imperial Throne.</e>
<cmt>deleted “side”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, some say that they actually might have been trying to restrain the Northern Court, including Emperor Gokomatsu, by escaping from them, since the Northern Court was not in favor of the Southern Court succeeding the Imperial Throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>実際に応永19年（1412年）8月、北朝側の称光天皇が践祚する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And actually, in August 1412, Emperor Shoko of the side of the Northern Court succeeds the Imperial Throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And actually, in August 1412, Emperor Shoko of the Northern Court succeeded the Imperial Throne.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And actually, in September 1412, Emperor Shoko of the Northern Court succeeded the Imperial Throne.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その後、応永23年（1416年）に後亀山上皇は室町幕府の要請で京に帰る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, in 1416, by the request of the Muromachi bakufu, the retired Emperor Gokameyama returns to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, in 1416, at the request of the Muromachi bakufu, the retired Emperor Gokameyama returned to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, in 1416, at the request of the Muromachi bakufu, the retired Emperor Gokameyama (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) returned to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>英語説明補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし、恒敦は父には従わず、この後も吉野で更に抵抗を続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Tsuneatsu didn&apos;t follow his father, and continued his resistance in Yoshino Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Tsuneatsu didn&apos;t follow his father, and continued his resistance in Yoshino Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Tsuneatsu didn&apos;t follow his father, and continued his resistance in Yoshino.</e>
<cmt>Province削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その後、恒敦は応永29年7月15日に亡くなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Tsuneatsu dies on August 2, 1422.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Tsuneatsu died on August 2, 1422.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Tsuneatsu died on August 11, 1422.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>恒敦らの抵抗はその後の自天王(尊秀王)まで続く後南朝の抵抗のさきがけとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This resistance by Tsuneatsu and others became as the herald of the resistance of the Gonancho (Second Southern Court) which continued until the time of Jitenno (Sonshuo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This resistance by Tsuneatsu and others heralded the resistance of the Gonancho (Second Southern Court) which continued until the time of Jitenno (Sonshuo).</e>
<cmt>deleted “became as the”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This resistance by Tsuneatsu and others heralded the resistance of the Gonancho (Second Southern Court) which continued until the time of Jitenno (Prince Sonshu).</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>子に小倉宮聖承がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had Seisho OGURANOMIYA as his child.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seisho OGURANOMIYA was his child.</e>
<cmt>this is more natural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seisho OGURANOMIYA was his child.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 立志堂(id:132177), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>