<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>木寺宮邦康親王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Kideranomiya Kuniyasu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Kideranomiya Kuniyasu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Kideranomiya Kuniyasu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>木寺宮邦康親王（きでらのみやくにやすしんのう、1416年-没年未詳）は室町時代の皇族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Kideranomiya Kuniyasu (1416 - date of death unknown) was a member of the Imperial family in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Kideranomiya Kuniyasu (1416 - date of death unknown) was a member of the Imperial family during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Kideranomiya Kuniyasu (1416 - date of death unknown) was a member of the Imperial family during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>大覚寺統の嫡流である木寺宮家の4代目の当主とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he was the 4th head of the Kideranomiya family, which was the main branch of Daikakuji-to (imperial lineage starting with Emperor Kameyama).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he was the 4th head of the Kideranomiya family, which was the main branch of Daikakuji-to (imperial lineage starting with Emperor Kameyama).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he was the 4th head of the Kideranomiya family, which was the main branch of Daikakuji-to (imperial lineage starting with Emperor Kameyama).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>官位は三品、役職は中務卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His official court rank was Sanbon (third-ranked of Imperial Prince), and his title was Nakatsukasa-kyo (Minister of the Ministry of Central Affairs).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His official court rank was Sanbon (third-rank for an Imperial Prince), and his title was Nakatsukasa-kyo (Minister of the Ministry of Central Affairs).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His official court rank was Sanbon (third-rank for an Imperial Prince), and his title was Nakatsukasa-kyo (Minister of the Ministry of Central Affairs).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>兄に後小松天皇猶子として仁和寺に入った承道法親王、妙法院に入った明仁法親王が、子に仁和寺に入った法深法親王がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monk-Imperial Prince Shodo, who entered Ninna-ji Temple as an adopted child of Emperor Gokomatsu, and Cloistered Imperial Prince Myojin, who entered Myoho-in Temple, were his elder brothers, and Cloistered Imperial Prince Hoshin who entered Ninna-ji Temple was his son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Monk-Imperial Prince Shodo, who entered Ninna-ji Temple as an adopted child of Emperor Gokomatsu, and Cloistered Imperial Prince Myojin, who entered Myoho-in Temple, were his elder brothers, and Cloistered Imperial Prince Hoshin who entered Ninna-ji Temple was his son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cloistered Imperial Prince Shodo, who entered Ninna-ji Temple as an adopted child of Emperor Gokomatsu, and Cloistered Imperial Prince Myojin, who entered Myoho-in Temple, were his elder brothers, and Cloistered Imperial Prince Hoshin who entered Ninna-ji Temple was his son.</e>
<cmt>法親王→Cloistered Imperial Prince に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>先代・世平王の末息子として生まれ、享徳4年（1455年）2月、40歳の時に伏見宮貞成親王の猶子として親王宣下を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as the last son of Prince Yohira, the former family head, and in February 1455, when he was forty years old, he was given the title of Imperial Prince as an adopted child of Imperial Prince Fushiminomiya Sadafusa.</e>
<cmt>世平王の読み方（ご参考：　http://crd.ndl.go.jp/GENERAL/servlet/detail.reference?id=1000057743）。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born as the last son of Prince Yohira, the former family head, and in February 1455, when he was forty years old, he was given the title of Imperial Prince as an adopted child of Imperial Prince Fushiminomiya Sadafusa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born as the last son of Prince Yohira (世平王), the former family head, and in February 1455, when he was forty years old, he was given the title of Imperial Prince as an adopted child of Imperial Prince Fushiminomiya Sadafusa.</e>
<cmt>Prince Yohira (世平王)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その半年後に元服し、三品の位を授けられ、中務卿に任ぜられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Six months later, he was given the rank of Sanbon, and appointed as Nakatsukasa-kyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Six months later, he was given the rank of Sanbon, and appointed as Nakatsukasa-kyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Six months later, he was given the rank of Sanbon, and appointed as Nakatsukasa-kyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>但し、この当時としても40歳になるまで出家も元服もさせてもらえず放置されていたのは異様である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it was most unusual even in those days that he did not experience genpuku (celebration of one&apos;s coming of age) nor did he become a priest, and just remained ignored until he became forty years old. Compared with the Tokiwai no Miya Family, it seems that the Kideranomiya family was valued less.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処常盤井宮家に比べて「木寺宮家が」軽視されていた、と補って訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it was most unusual even in those days that he did not experience genpuku (celebration of one&apos;s coming of age) nor did he become a priest, and was just ignored until he became forty years old. Compared with the Tokiwai no Miya Family, it seems that the Kideranomiya family was valued less.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it was most unusual even in those days that he did not experience genpuku (celebration of one&apos;s coming of age) nor did he become a priest, and was just ignored until he became forty years old.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>常盤井宮家に比べて軽視されていたことが伺える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Compared with the Tokiwainomiya family, it seems that the Kideranomiya family was valued less.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処Tokiwainomiya に訂正しました。familyに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>その後の事績や没年は不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His subsequent achievements and the year of his death are unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His subsequent achievements and the year of his death are unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His subsequent achievements and the year of his death are unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>木寺宮家はその後京に於ける明確な消息が途絶え、宮家としては廃絶したと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, the specific information on the Kideranoiya family in Kyoto became scarce, and it is believed that the Kideranomiya family line as Miyake (families allowed to be in status of Imperial family) ended.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The specific information on the Kideranoiya family in Kyoto became scarce, and it is believed that the Kideranomiya family line as Miyake (families allowed the status of Imperial family) ended.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The specific information on the Kideranoiya family in Kyoto became scarce, and it is believed that the Kideranomiya family line as Miyake (house of an imperial prince) ended.</e>
<cmt>&quot;families allowed the status of Imperial family&quot; -&gt; &quot;house of an imperial prince&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 こぶまき(id:38278), Komitomo9654(id:114181), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>