<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>迦邇米雷王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Kanimeikazuchi (Kanimeikazuchi no Miko)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Kanimeikazuchi (Kanimeikazuchi no Miko)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Kanimeikazuchi (Kanimeikazuchi no Miko)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>迦邇米雷王（かにめいかずちのみこ、生没年不詳）は、『古事記』に伝える古墳時代の皇族（王族）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Kanimeikazuchi [(迦邇米雷王) Kanimeikazuchi no Miko; his date of birth and death are unknown] first appeared in the &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) as an Imperial family (royal family) during the Kofun period (tumulus period) in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Kanimeikazuchi (Kanimeikazuchi no Miko; his date of birth and death are unknown) was a member of an Imperial family (royal family) during the Kofun period (tumulus period) appeared in the &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters).</e>
<cmt>()と[]の訂正、など行いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Kanimeikazuchi (Kanimeikazuchi no Miko; his date of birth and death are unknown) was a member of an Imperial family (royal family) during the Kofun period (tumulus period) appeared in the &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>稚筒城王（『帝王系図』）・若角城命とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Prince Kanimeikazuchi (迦邇米雷王) was written in different ways such as: &quot;稚筒城王 [appeared in &quot;Teio Keizu&quot; (genealogical table of emperor)] and &quot;若角城命&quot; (appeared in other documents).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, Prince Kanimeikazuchi (迦邇米雷王) was written in different ways such as: &quot;稚筒城王 (appeared in &quot;Teio Keizu&quot; [genealogical table of emperor]) and &quot;若角城命.&quot;</e>
<cmt>()と[]の訂正、など行いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, Prince Kanimeikazuchi (迦邇米雷王) was written in different ways such as: 稚筒城王 (appeared in &quot;Teio Keizu&quot; [genealogical table of emperor]) and 若角城命.</e>
<cmt>“ ” → &quot; &quot;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>『古事記』によれば、父は山代之大筒木真若王で、母は伊理泥王の女・丹波能阿治佐波毘売（たにわのあじさわびめ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the &quot;Kojiki,&quot; the father of Prince Kanimeikazuchi was &apos;Prince Yamashirono Ootsutsukimawaka&apos; (山代之大筒木真若王), and the mother of Prince Kanimeikazuchi was &apos;Taniwa no Ajisawabime&apos; (丹波能阿治佐波毘売) who was a daughter of &apos;Irine no Miko&apos; (伊理泥王).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Kojiki,&quot; the father of Prince Kanimeikazuchi was Prince Yamashirono Ootsutsukimawaka, and the mother of Prince Kanimeikazuchi was Taniwa no Ajisawabim&apos; who was a daughter of Irine no Miko.</e>
<cmt>シングルクオートの削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Kojiki,&quot; the father of Prince Kanimeikazuchi was Prince Yamashirono Ootsutsukimawaka, and the mother of Prince Kanimeikazuchi was Taniwa no Ajisawabime who was a daughter of Irine no Miko.</e>
<cmt>“ ” → &quot; &quot;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また、彦坐王の孫、すなわち開化天皇の曾孫に当たる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further more, Prince Kanimeikazuchi was the grandson of Prince Hikoimasu (彦坐王), in other words, he was a great-grandchild of the Emperor Kaika.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Prince Kanimeikazuchi was the grandson of Prince Hikoimasu, in other words, he was a great-grandchild of the Emperor Kaika.</e>
<cmt>Furthermoreを訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Prince Kanimeikazuchi was the grandson of Prince Hikoimasu, in other words, he was a great-grandchild of the Emperor Kaika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>外祖父の伊理泥王は山代之大筒木真若王の同母弟ゆえ、父と母は伯父・姪の続柄になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Irine no Miko,&apos; the maternal grandfather of &apos;Kanimeikazuchi no Miko,&apos; was the younger maternal half brother of &apos;Prince Yamashirono Ootsutsukimawaka&apos;; this would result in the father and the mother of Prince Kanimeikazuchi, having been related as an uncle to a niece.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Irine no Miko, the maternal grandfather of Kanimeikazuchi no Miko, was the younger maternal half-brother of Prince Yamashirono Ootsutsukimawaka, his father and mother were in the relationship between an uncle and a niece.</e>
<cmt>シングルクオートの削除、ハイフンの追加をし、文を簡略化しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Irine no Miko, the maternal grandfather of Kanimeikazuchi no Miko, was the younger maternal half-brother of Prince Yamashirono Ootsutsukimawaka, his father and mother were in the relationship between an uncle and a niece.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>迦邇米雷王は丹波之遠津臣の女・高材比売（たかきひめ）を妃とし、息長宿禰王（おきながのすくねのみこ、気長宿禰王）を儲けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Kanimeikazuchi married Takakihime (高材比売), a daughter of &apos;Taniha no Towotsu Omi&apos; (丹波之遠津臣), as his princess; and then she gave birth to a son (prince),&apos;Prince Okinaga no Sukune&apos; [(息長宿禰) Okinaga no Sukune no Miko; he was also known as &apos;Okinaga no Sukune no Okimi (or Miko)&apos; (気長宿禰王)].</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Kanimeikazuchi married Takakihime, a daughter of Taniha no Towotsu Omi, as his princess; and then she gave birth to a son (prince), Prince Okinaga no Sukune (Okinaga no Sukune no Miko; he was also known as Okinaga no Sukune no Okimi [or Miko]).</e>
<cmt>シングルクオートの削除、()と[]の訂正をしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Kanimeikazuchi married Takakihime, a daughter of Taniha no Towotsu Omi, as his princess; and then she gave birth to a son (prince), Prince Okinaga no Sukune (Okinaga no Sukune no Miko; he was also known as Okinaga no Sukune no Okimi [or Miko]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>息長宿禰王は神功皇后の父である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, &apos;Prince Okinaga no Sukune&apos; was to become the father of the Empress Jingu,</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Prince Okinaga no Sukune became the father of the Empress Jingu,</e>
<cmt>was to become→becameとシングルクオートの削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Prince Okinaga no Sukune became the father of the Empress Jingu,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>他、2人の王子は近江国国造・吉備国品治国造・但馬国国造の祖と伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, two of his sons (princes) were considered to be ancestors of &apos;Omino kuni no miyatsuko&apos; (近江国国造), &apos;Kibi no kuni Honji kunino miyatsuko&apos; (吉備国品治国造), and &apos;Tajima no kunino miyatsuko&apos; (但馬国国造).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His two other sons (princes) were considered to be ancestors of Omino kuni no miyatsuko, Kibi no kuni Honji kunino miyatsuko, and Tajima no kunino miyatsuko.</e>
<cmt>最初の部分の変更とシングルクオートの削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His two other sons (princes) were considered to be ancestors of Omino kuni no miyatsuko, Kibi no kuni Honji kunino miyatsuko, and Tajima no kunino miyatsuko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>なお、迦邇米雷王は京都府京田辺市・朱智神社の主祭神であるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, Prince Kanimeikazuchi had been the shusaijin (main enshrined deities) of the Suchi-jinja Shrine, which is located in Kyotanabe City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, Prince Kanimeikazuchi had been the shusaijin (main enshrined deities) of the Suchi-jinja Shrine, which is located in Kyotanabe City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, Prince Kanimeikazuchi had been the shusaijin (main enshrined deities) of the Suchi-jinja Shrine, which is located in Kyotanabe City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>子孫は朱智姓を名乗ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, offspring of Prince Kanimeikazuchi seemed to assume the surname &quot;Suchi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, offspring of Prince Kanimeikazuchi seemed to assume the surname &quot;Suchi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, offspring of Prince Kanimeikazuchi seemed to assume the surname &quot;Suchi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>“ ” → &quot; &quot;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 アレシンロ(id:170344), Yanahan(id:2437), BAKU(id:55205), Goki(id:7107), 代言人(id:33675), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>