<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>王 (皇族)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">King (of imperial family)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">King (of imperial family)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">King (of imperial family)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>王（おう、みこ、古くはおおきみ）は、皇族の身位または称号の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kings (O, miko, or okimi in ancient time) were one of positions or titles of the Imperial family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">King (O, miko, or okimi in ancient time) is one of the positions or titles of the Imperial family.</e>
<cmt>時制修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">King (O, miko, or okimi in ancient time) is one of the positions or titles of the Imperial family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>または、王の身位を授けられた皇族のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Or a member of an Imperial family who receives the position of the king.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Or a member of an Imperial family who receives the position of the king.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Or a member of an Imperial family who receives the position of the king.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>律令では皇族の男子のうち親王宣下のない者を指した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Ritsuryo codes, they refer to sons of the Imperal family who were not given the title of Imperial Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Ritsuryo codes, it referred to sons of the Imperial family who were not given the title of Imperial Prince.</e>
<cmt>時制修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Ritsuryo codes, it referred to sons of the Imperial family who were not given the title of Imperial Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>現行の皇室典範では、天皇から直系で三親等以上離れた皇族男子を指す（傍系でなく直系尊属の天皇から数える）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the present Imperial House Act, they refer to sons of the imperial family who are in a direct line and in the three or more degree of kinship from the emperor (not in collateral line and counted from the emperor who is a direct ancestor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the present Imperial House Law, it refers to sons of the Imperial family who are in the direct line and in the three or more degree of kinship from the emperor (not in collateral line and counted from the emperor who is a direct ancestor).</e>
<cmt>主語修正しました。皇室典範の訳を単語リストに揃えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the present Imperial House Law, it refers to sons of the Imperial family who are in the direct line and in the three or more degree of kinship from the emperor (not in collateral line and counted from the emperor who is a direct ancestor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>ちなみに、王の妃を王妃 (皇族)という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The wife of the king is called empress (of imperial family).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The wife of the king is called empress (of imperial family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The wife of the king is called empress (of imperial family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>ただし、2007年9月時点で日本には女王 (皇族) は存在するものの、王は一人も出生していない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As of September, 2007, there were queens (of imperial family), but no kings in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As of September, 2007, there were queens (of imperial family), but no kings in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As of September, 2007, there were queens (of imperial family), but no kings in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>王は皇族身位令に準じ、成年となったときに桐花大綬章を授与される（2003年11月2日までに成年に達した場合は勲一等旭日桐花大綬章であった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a king becomes an adult, he is given Grand Cordon of the Order of the Paulownia Flowers of the Rising Sun (or Grand Cordon of the Order of the Rising Sun with Paulownia Flower if he becomes an adult before November 2, 2003).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a king becomes an adult, he is given Grand Cordon of the Order of the Paulownia Flowers of the Rising Sun (or Grand Cordon of the Order of the Rising Sun with Paulownia Flower if he became an adult before November 2, 2003).</e>
<cmt>時制修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a king becomes an adult, he is given Grand Cordon of the Order of the Paulownia Flowers of the Rising Sun (or Grand Cordon of the Order of the Rising Sun with Paulownia Flower if he became an adult before November 2, 2003).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>なお、韓国併合条約及び関連する詔書により、「韓国皇帝陛下太皇帝陛下皇太子殿下並其ノ后妃及後裔」に該当する者を王族とし、李王家の当主も王というが、皇族の王と王族の王は全く違うものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the treaty of the annexation of Korea, &apos;emperor of Korea, his Majesty, emperor, crown prince and princess and descendents&apos; were called the royal family, the head of the Lee royal family was called a king, but the king of the imperial family was different from the king of the royal family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the Japan-Korea Annexation Treaty and the related imperial edict, &apos;His Majesty the Emperor of Korea, His Majesty the Retired Emperor, His Majesty the Crown Prince and their empresses and descendents&apos; were called the royal family, and the head of the Lee royal family was also called a king, but the king of the imperial family was different from the king of the royal family.</e>
<cmt>「李王家の当主も」というニュアンスを出しました。「関連する詔書」の訳を補いました。王族の称号を修正しました。「太皇帝」の定訳不明。日韓併合条約は&quot;Japan-Korea Annexation Treaty&quot;が定訳と思われます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the Japan-Korea Annexation Treaty and the related imperial edict, &apos;His Majesty the Emperor of Korea, His Majesty the Retired Emperor, His Majesty the Crown Prince and their empresses and descendents&apos; were called the royal family, and the head of the Lee royal family was also called a king, but the king of the imperial family was different from the king of the royal family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="9">
<j>なお、幕末以後日本が西洋と国交を開いた直後には、西洋の皇帝（＝天皇）と王の関係を日本や中国と同様の非対等な関係と誤解をして、帝制の国家と王制の国家あての国書に格差を付けてしまった為に、紛糾したと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soon after Japan established diplomatic relations with the West at the end of Edo Period, the Japanese government misunderstood that the relationship between the emperor (Japanese emperor) and king of the West was an unequal relationship like that in Japan and Chine, and discriminated sovereign&apos;s messages to imperial states from those to royal states, causing confusions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon after Japan established diplomatic relations with the West at the end of Edo Period, the Japanese government misunderstood that the relationship between the emperor (Japanese emperor) and king of the West was an unequal relationship like that of Japan and China, and discriminated sovereign&apos;s messages to imperial states from those to royal states, causing confusions.</e>
<cmt>中国のつづりを修正しました。文法修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon after Japan established diplomatic relations with the West at the end of Edo Period, the Japanese government misunderstood that the relationship between the emperor (Japanese emperor) and king of the West was an unequal relationship like that of Japan and China, and discriminated sovereign&apos;s messages to imperial states from those to royal states, causing confusions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Sakura-no-kuni(id:115977), いろはにほへと(id:89648), Nnh(id:474), 砂場(id:27896), 海衛士(id:19229), Aphaia(id:3132), 伏儀(id:142093), 無言雀師(id:13124), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>