<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大嘗祭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onienomatsuri festival</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onie no Matsuri Festival</e>
<cmt>Onienomatsuri festival→Onie no Matsuri Festivalとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onie no Matsuri Festival</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大嘗祭（おおにえのまつり）は、天皇が即位の礼の後、初めて行う新嘗祭。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Onienomatsuri festival is the first Niiname-sai festival (ceremonial offering by a emperor of newly-harvested rice to the deities) solemnized by a emperor after his or her Sokui no rei (ceremony of enthronement).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Onie no matsuri Festival is the first Niiname-sai Festival (ceremonial offering by a emperor of newly-harvested rice to the deities) solemnized by an emperor after his or her Sokui no rei (ceremony of enthronement).</e>
<cmt>Onienomatsuri festival→Onie no matsuri Festival、Niiname-sai festival→Niiname-sai Festivalとし、a emperor→an emperorに修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Onie no matsuri Festival is the first Niiname-sai Festival (ceremonial offering by a emperor of newly-harvested rice to the deities) solemnized by an emperor after his or her Sokui no rei (ceremony of enthronement).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>一代一度限りの大祭であり、実質的に践祚の儀式。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a grand festival that takes place only once in a generation, and is virtually the ritual of Senso (succession to the throne).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a grand festival that takes place only once in a generation, and is virtually the ritual of Senso (succession to the throne).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a grand festival that takes place only once in a generation, and is virtually the ritual of Senso (succession to the throne).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>践祚大嘗祭ともいい、「だいじょうさい」「おおむべのまつり」とも呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called &apos;Senso daijosai festival,&apos;&apos;Daijosai festival&apos; or &apos;Omubeno-matsuri festival.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called &apos;Senso Daijo-sai Festival,&apos; &apos;Daijo-sai Festival&apos; or &apos;Omube no matsuri Festival.&apos;</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーションを半角に修正、クォーテーション内の表記を修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called &apos;Senso Daijo-sai Festival,&apos; &apos;Daijo-sai Festival&apos; or &apos;Omube no matsuri Festival.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>毎年11月に、天皇が行う収穫祭を新嘗祭という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The harvest festival solemnized by an emperor, every November is called the Niiname-sai festival.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The harvest festival solemnized by an emperor, every November is called the Niiname-sai Festival.</e>
<cmt>festivalの頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The harvest festival solemnized by an emperor, every November is called the Niiname-sai Festival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その年の新穀を天皇が神に捧げ、天皇自らも食す新嘗祭のことを、古くは「毎年の大嘗」と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Niiname-sai festival, in which an emperor devotes the Shinkoku (the first crop of the year) to the God and also eats it himself, was called &apos;Yearly daijo&apos; in ancient times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Niiname-sai Festival, in which an emperor devotes the Shinkoku (the first crop of the year) to the God and also eats it himself, was called &apos;Yearly daijo&apos; in ancient times.</e>
<cmt>festivalの頭文字を大文字に変更、全角クォーテーションを半角に修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Niiname-sai Festival, in which an emperor devotes the Shinkoku (the first crop of the year) to the God and also eats it himself, was called &apos;Yearly daijo&apos; in ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>当初は通常の新嘗祭と区別されなかったものの、後に即位後初めて一世一度行われる祭として、「毎世の大嘗」「大嘗祭」として重視された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the beginning, it wasn&apos;t separated from the regular Niiname-sai festival, but later as a ritual, solemnized only once in an emperor&apos;s lifetime, it could be called &apos;Daijo once in a lifetime,&apos; &apos;the Onienomatsuri festival,&apos; and became important.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the beginning, it wasn&apos;t separated from the regular Niiname-sai Festival, but later as a ritual, solemnized only once in an emperor&apos;s lifetime, it became important being called &apos;Daijo once in a lifetime&apos; and &apos;Onie no matsuri Festival.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Niiname-sai Festival、Onie no matsuri Festivalとし、全角クォーテーションを半角に修正、一部訳文を修正NC_Check</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the beginning, it wasn&apos;t separated from the regular Niiname-sai Festival, but later as a ritual, solemnized only once in an emperor&apos;s lifetime, it became important being called &apos;Daijo once in a lifetime&apos; and &apos;Onie no matsuri Festival.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>大嘗祭と新嘗祭が区別されたのは、天武天皇の大嘗祭のときとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the Onienomatsuri festival and the Niiname-sai festival have been separated ever since the Emperor Tenmu solemnized his Onienomatsuri festival.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the Onie no matsuri Festival and the Niiname-sai Festival have been separated ever since the Emperor Tenmu solemnized his Onie no matsuri Festival.</e>
<cmt>Niiname-sai Festival、Onie no matsuri Festivalとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the Onie no matsuri Festival and the Niiname-sai Festival have been separated ever since the Emperor Tenmu solemnized his Onie no matsuri Festival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>大嘗祭の儀式の形が定まったのは、7世紀の皇極天皇の頃とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that the ritual outlines of Onienomatsuri festival were established around the era of the Empress Kogyoku in the 7th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that the ritual outlines of Onie no matsuri Festival were established around the era of the Empress Kogyoku in the seventh century.</e>
<cmt>Onie no matsuri Festivalとし、7th→seventhに修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that the ritual outlines of Onie no matsuri Festival were established around the era of the Empress Kogyoku in the seventh century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>律令制が整備されると共に、祭の式次第など詳細についても整備された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) was established, the program of the festival was also decided in detail.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) was established, the program of the festival was also decided in detail.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) was established, the program of the festival was also decided in detail.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>延喜式に定められたもののうち「大祀」とされたのは大嘗祭のみである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Onienomatsuri festival was the only festival to be considered as a Taishi (the most important festival) amongst other festivals included in the Engishiki (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Onie no matsuri Festival was the only festival to be considered as a Taishi (the most important festival) amongst other festivals included in the Engishiki (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers).</e>
<cmt>Onie no matsuri Festivalとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Onie no matsuri Festival was the only festival to be considered as a Taishi (the most important festival) amongst other festivals included in the Engishiki (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>延喜式に式次第が定められた後も、多少変化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The program was changed in a sort of way even after it was included in the Engishiki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The program was changed in a sort of way even after it was included in the Engishiki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The program was changed in a sort of way even after it was included in the Engishiki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>室町時代末期、戦国時代_(日本)には、朝廷の窮乏や戦乱のため、延期または行われなかったことなどもあるものの、天皇の代替わりに伴う重要な祭儀として、古くから継承されてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it was often delayed or canceled due to the financial difficulties of the Imperial court or the maelstrom of war in the last stage of the Muromachi period, that is to say, the Sengoku period (Japan) (period of warring states), the Onienomatsuri festival has been succeeded as an important ceremony related to enthronements of emperors since long ago.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it was often delayed or canceled due to the financial difficulties of the Imperial court or the maelstrom of war in the last stage of the Muromachi period, that is to say, the Sengoku period (Japan) (period of warring states), the Onie no matsuri Festival has been succeeded as an important ceremony related to enthronements of emperors since long ago.</e>
<cmt>Onie no matsuri Festivalとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it was often delayed or canceled due to the financial difficulties of the Imperial court or the maelstrom of war in the last stage of the Muromachi period, that is to say, the Sengoku period (Japan) (period of warring states), the Onie no matsuri Festival has been succeeded as an important ceremony related to enthronements of emperors since long ago.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>最近では、1990年（平成2年）11月に、明仁の即位に伴う大嘗祭が行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The most recent Onienomatsuri festival was solemnized in November 1990, accompanied by the enthronement of Emperor Akihito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The most recent Onie no matsuri Festival was solemnized in November 1990, accompanied by the enthronement of Emperor Akihito.</e>
<cmt>Onie no matsuri Festivalとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The most recent Onie no matsuri Festival was solemnized in November 1990, accompanied by the enthronement of Emperor Akihito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>この際、即位の礼に関わる儀式が国の行事とされたのに対し、大嘗祭に関わる儀式は皇室の行事とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, the rituals related to the Sokui no rei were considered a national event, and the rituals related to the Onienomatsuri festival was treated as an event of the Imperial family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, the rituals related to the Sokui no rei were considered a national event, and the rituals related to the Onie no matsuri Festival was treated as an event of the Imperial family.</e>
<cmt>Onie no matsuri Festivalとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, the rituals related to the Sokui no rei were considered a national event, and the rituals related to the Onie no matsuri Festival was treated as an event of the Imperial family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しばしば誤解されているが、ここで「皇室の行事」というのは、「皇室の私的な行事」という意味ではなく、「皇室の公的な行事」という意味である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is sometimes misunderstood that &apos;an event of the Imperial family&apos; means &apos;a private event of the Imperial family,&apos; but it is actually &apos;a public event of the Imperial family.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is sometimes misunderstood that &apos;an event of the Imperial family&apos; means &apos;a private event of the Imperial family,&apos; but it is actually &apos;a public event of the Imperial family.&apos;</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーションを半角に修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is sometimes misunderstood that &apos;an event of the Imperial family&apos; means &apos;a private event of the Imperial family,&apos; but it is actually &apos;a public event of the Imperial family.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>当然、大嘗祭の予算は通常の内廷費以外の臨時のものが組まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Obviously the extraordinary budget for the Onienomatsuri festival is formulated separately to the emperor&apos;s family budget.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Obviously the extraordinary budget for the Onie no matsuri Festival is formulated separately to the emperor&apos;s family budget.</e>
<cmt>Onie no matsuri Festivalとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Obviously the extraordinary budget for the Onie no matsuri Festival is formulated separately to the emperor&apos;s family budget.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>当時の政府発表（最終のもの）によれば、大嘗祭が「国事行為」とされなかった理由は、憲法上の天皇の「国事行為」とは漠然と国に関わる行為を指すものではなく、すべて「内閣の助言と承認」を必要とするものであり、皇室の伝統祭祀である大嘗祭は「国事行為」に当たらない（大嘗祭は政務上の「国事行為」と次元を異にする尊貴な行為である）ためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the final announcement of the government at that time, the Onienomatsuri festival was not considered as a state act, because unlike the emperor&apos;s state acts, which were not related to the state vaguely but needed advisement and authorization of the ministry, the Onienomatsuri festival, a traditional noble ritual, was in a different category to the state acts belonging to the affairs of State, and thus was not considered as a state act.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the final announcement of the government at that time, the Onie no matsuri Festival was not considered as a state act, because unlike the emperor&apos;s state acts, which were not related to the state vaguely but needed advisement and authorization of the ministry, the Onie no matsuri Festival, a traditional noble ritual, was in a different category to the state acts belonging to the affairs of State, and thus was not considered as a state act.</e>
<cmt>Onie no matsuri Festivalとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the final announcement of the government at that time, the Onie no matsuri Festival was not considered as a state act, because unlike the emperor&apos;s state acts, which were not related to the state vaguely but needed advisement and authorization of the ministry, the Onie no matsuri Festival, a traditional noble ritual, was in a different category to the state acts belonging to the affairs of State, and thus was not considered as a state act.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="19">
<j>式次第</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Program</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Program</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Program</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>近年における即位の礼・大嘗祭関連儀式の具体的な日程等については、即位の礼の項目を参照のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Please refer to the article of Sokui no rei about the specific dates of Sokui no rei and the Onienomatsuri festivals in recent years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Please refer to the article of Sokui no rei about the specific dates of Sokui no rei and the Onie no matsuri Festivals in recent years.</e>
<cmt>Onie no matsuri Festivalとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Please refer to the article of Sokui no rei about the specific dates of Sokui no rei and the Onie no matsuri Festivals in recent years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="21">
<j>即位と大嘗祭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enthronement and the Onienomatsuri festival</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enthronement and the Onie no matsuri Festival</e>
<cmt>Onie no matsuri Festivalとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enthronement and the Onie no matsuri Festival</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>延喜式によれば、天皇の即位がその年の7月以前の場合にはその年に、8月以降の場合には翌年に行われることになっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the Engishiki, the Onienomatsuri festival was solemnized in same year as the emperors&apos; enthronement, if it took place before July, but was solemnized in the following year if the enthronement was held after July.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the Engishiki, the Onie no matsuri Festival was solemnized in same year as the emperors&apos; enthronement if it took place before July, but was solemnized in the following year if the enthronement was held after August.</e>
<cmt>Onie no matsuri Festivalとし、カンマ削除、after July→after Augustに修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the Engishiki, the Onie no matsuri Festival was solemnized in same year as the emperors&apos; enthronement if it took place before July, but was solemnized in the following year if the enthronement was held after August.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="23">
<j>悠紀と主基</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yuki (the first province to offer the first rice crop of the year at the Onienomatsuri festival) and Suki (place where the Onienomatsuri festival takes place).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yuki (the first province to offer the first rice crop of the year at the Onie no matsuri Festival) and Suki (place where the Onie no matsuri Festival takes place)</e>
<cmt>Onie no matsuri Festivalとし、ピリオド削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yuki (the first province to offer the first rice crop of the year at the Onie no matsuri Festival) and Suki (place where the Onie no matsuri Festival takes place)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>大嘗祭が行われる年には、まず、所司（官庁の役人）が、その祭に供えるイネを出す斎田を選ぶため、悠紀（ゆき）・主基（すき）の国・郡を卜定（ぼくじょう）する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the year, in which the Onienomatsuri festival would be held, at first, Shoshi (Governor of the Board of Retainers) Bokujo (to decide by fortunetelling) a Kuni (Province) and Gun (county) for the Yuki and the Suki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the year, in which the Onie no matsuri Festival would be held, at first, Shoshi (Governor of the Board of Retainers) decided by fortunetelling a province and a county for the Yuki and the Suki in order to select the rice fields that would provide rice plants for the festival.</e>
<cmt>「その祭に供えるイネを出す斎田を選ぶため」→訳漏れのため訳出、「国・郡を卜定（ぼくじょう）する」の部分を修正、Onie no matsuri Festivalとしました。NC_CHECK→grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the year, in which the Onie no matsuri Festival would be held, at first, Shoshi (Governor of the Board of Retainers) decided by fortunetelling a province and a county for the Yuki and the Suki in order to select the rice fields that would provide rice plants for the festival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>悠紀・主基の国を斎国（いつきのくに）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The countries of the Yuki and the Suki are called Itsuki no kuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The provinces of the Yuki and the Suki are called Itsuki no kuni.</e>
<cmt>countries→provincesとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The provinces of the Yuki and the Suki are called Itsuki no kuni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>悠紀は東日本、主基は西日本から選ばれ、畿内の国から選ばれたことは一度もない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yuki was chosen from eastern Japan and the Suki was chosen from western Japan, but they never have been chosen from Kinai Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yuki was chosen from eastern Japan and the Suki was chosen from western Japan, but they never have been chosen from provinces in Kinai region.</e>
<cmt>Kinai Province→provinces in Kinai regionとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yuki was chosen from eastern Japan and the Suki was chosen from western Japan, but they never have been chosen from provinces in Kinai region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>中世以降は、近江国が悠紀、丹波国と備中国が交互に主基とされ、その国の中で郡を卜定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the medieval period, Omi Province took the role of the Yuki, and Tanba Province and Bicchu Province swapped the role of the Suki; they Bokujo Gun within the Kuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the medieval period, Omi Province took the role of the Yuki, and Tanba Province and Bitchu Province swapped the role of the Suki; they decided by fortunetelling a county within the province.</e>
<cmt>Bicchu→Bitchuに修正、they Bokujo Gun within the Kuni→they decided by fortunetelling a county within the provinceとしました。NC_Check</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the medieval period, Omi Province took the role of the Yuki, and Tanba Province and Bitchu Province swapped the role of the Suki; they decided by fortunetelling a county within the province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="28">
<j>明治以降の悠紀・主基</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yuki and the Suki after the Meiji era</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yuki and the Suki after the Meiji period</e>
<cmt>the Meiji era→the Meiji periodとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yuki and the Suki after the Meiji period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="29">
<j>本祭当月までの儀式</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The related rituals which are held before the month in which the Onienomatsuri festival takes place</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The related rituals held before the month in which the Onie no matsuri Festival takes place</e>
<cmt>which are held→held、Onie no matsuri Festivalとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The related rituals held before the month in which the Onie no matsuri Festival takes place</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>8月上旬には、大祓使（おおはらえし）を卜定し、左京・右京に1人、五畿内に1人、七道に各1人を差し遣わして祓った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In early August, an Oharaeshi chosen by Bokujo was sent to Sakyo (east part of capital), Ukyo (west part of capital), Gokinai capital region, and each district of Shichido (the seven districts of ancient Japan) to perform exorcisms.</e>
<cmt>一例文一翻訳の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In early August, an Oharaeshi chosen by Bokujo (to decide by fortunetelling) was sent to Sakyo (east part of capital), Ukyo (west part of capital), Gokinai capital region, and each district of Shichido (the seven districts of ancient Japan) to perform exorcisms.</e>
<cmt>Bokujoの補足追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In early August, an Oharaeshi chosen by Bokujo (to decide by fortunetelling) was sent to Sakyo (east part of capital), Ukyo (west part of capital), Gokinai capital region, and each district of Shichido (the seven districts of ancient Japan) to perform exorcisms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>8月下旬にはさらに祓使を差し遣わして祓った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Haraeshi were also sent to those regions and districts to perform exorcisms in late August.</e>
<cmt>一例文一翻訳の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Haraeshi were also sent to those regions and districts to perform exorcisms in late August.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Haraeshi were also sent to those regions and districts to perform exorcisms in late August.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>この祓いが済むと、伊勢神宮以下、各国の天神地祇に幣帛を供え、告文（こうもん）を奏じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After performing the exorcisms, they presented heihaku (paper or silk cuttings or red and white cloth, presented to the gods) and notified Imperial instructions to every god of heaven and earth in Japan including Ise-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After performing the exorcisms, they presented heihaku (paper or silk cuttings or red and white cloth, presented to the gods) and notified Imperial instructions to every god of heaven and earth in Japan including Ise-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After performing the exorcisms, they presented heihaku (paper or silk cuttings or red and white cloth, presented to the gods) and notified Imperial instructions to every god of heaven and earth in Japan including Ise-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>また、8月下旬には、抜穂使を卜定して斎国に遣わし、抜穂使はその国で斎田と斎場雑色人、造酒童女らを卜定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, in late August, Nukihoshi (Imperial envoy sent to gather ears of rice) chosen by Bokujo were sent to Itsuki no kuni and they chose Saiden, Saijozoshikinin and Sakatsuko (girls brew sake presented to gods) by using Bokujo in those Kuni.</e>
<cmt>抜穂使→Nukihoshihttp://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=ぬき&amp;dtype=0&amp;stype=0&amp;dname=0na&amp;pagenum=51&amp;index=16431414202800斎場雑色人→読み方不明http://webcache.googleusercontent.com/search?q=cache:0DBIekDZLbgJ:www.sol.dti.ne.jp/~hiromi/kansei/e_taihoyoro.html+雑色人&amp;cd=2&amp;hl=ja&amp;ct=clnk&amp;gl=jp&amp;client=safari造酒童女→Sakatsukohttp://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?p=造&amp;enc=UTF-8&amp;stype=0&amp;dtype=0</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, in late August, Nukihoshi (Imperial envoy sent to gather ears of rice) chosen by Bokujo were sent to Itsuki no kuni and they chose Saiden (rice fields to cultivate rice plants for deities), Saijo zoshikinin (lower-level functionaries in the provincial government) and Sakatsuko (girls brew sake presented to gods) by using Bokujo in those provinces.</e>
<cmt>Saidenの補足追加、Saijo zoshikininとし、補足追加 (用語集参照)、in those Kuni→in those provincesに修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, in late August, Nukihoshi (Imperial envoy sent to gather ears of rice) chosen by Bokujo were sent to Itsuki no kuni and they chose Saiden (rice fields to cultivate rice plants for deities), Saijo zoshikinin (lower-level functionaries in the provincial government) and Sakatsuko (girls brew sake presented to gods) by using Bokujo in those provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>9月になると斎田から稲穂を抜き取り、初めに抜いた4束を御飯（みい）とし、あとは黒酒（くろき）・白酒（しろき）として供される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They gathered in ears of rice in September, making the first four sheaves they gathered into Mii (rice) and making the rest into Kuroki (black sake) and Shiroki (white sake) and presented them to the gods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They gathered in ears of rice in September, making the first four sheaves they gathered into Mii (rice) and making the rest into Kuroki (black sake) and Shiroki (white sake) and presented them to the gods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They gathered in ears of rice in September, making the first four sheaves they gathered into Mii (rice) and making the rest into Kuroki (black sake) and Shiroki (white sake) and presented them to the gods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>御飯や黒酒、白酒は、9月下旬から祭日まで、都に設けられた斎場院外の仮屋に収められる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mii, Kuroki (black sake) and Shiroki (white sake) were kept in a temporary building out side of the Saijouin building built in the Miyako (capital) from late September until the festival started.</e>
<cmt>斎場院→Saijouin building読方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mii, Kuroki and Shiroki were kept in a temporary building outside of the Saijoin building built in the Miyako (capital) from late September until the festival started.</e>
<cmt>Kuroki, Shiroki→前出のため補足削除、out side of→outside of、Saijouin→Saijoinに修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mii, Kuroki and Shiroki were kept in a temporary building outside of the Saijoin building built in the Miyako (capital) from late September until the festival started.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>10月下旬には、天皇は川に臨んで御禊（ぎょけい）した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In late October, an emperor went to a river to perform Gyokei (purification ceremony).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In late October, an emperor went to a river to perform Gyokei (purification ceremony).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In late October, an emperor went to a river to perform Gyokei (purification ceremony).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>この御禊は、江戸時代中期以降になると皇居内で行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This gyokei was performed inside of the Imperial Palace after the middle of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Gyokei was performed inside of the Imperial Palace after the middle of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>表記統一のため、gyoki→Gyokiとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Gyokei was performed inside of the Imperial Palace after the middle of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="38">
<j>本祭当月の儀式</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The rituals within the month in which the Onienomatsuri festival takes place</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rituals within the month in which the Onie no matsuri Festival takes place</e>
<cmt>Onie no matsuri Festivalとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rituals within the month in which the Onie no matsuri Festival takes place</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>祭は、11月の卯の日に行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The festival was held on U no hi (the day of rabbit) in November.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The festival was held on U no hi (the day of rabbit) in November.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The festival was held on U no hi (the day of rabbit) in November.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>11月に卯の日が3回あれば、中の卯の日に行われるものとされたが、後世には下の卯の日に行う習いとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If there were 3 U no hi in November, the second one used to be chosen, however, in after ages the last U no hi in November was chosen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If there were three U no hi in November, the second one used to be chosen, however, in after ages the last U no hi in November was chosen.</e>
<cmt>&quot;3&quot;をスペルアウト</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If there were three U no hi in November, the second one used to be chosen, however, in after ages the last U no hi in November was chosen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>現在では11月23日の勤労感謝の日に新嘗祭が行われるため、大嘗祭もこの日に行われる（平成2年の今上天皇の大嘗祭は、11月22日深夜から23日未明にかけて行われた）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, because the Niiname-sai festival takes place on the Labor Thanksgiving Day, November 23, the Onienomatsuri festival also takes place on the same day (the Onienomatsuri festival of the present Emperor was performed from the late-evening of November 22 to the early hours of 23.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, because the Niiname-sai Festival takes place on the Labor Thanksgiving Day, November 23, the Onie no matsuri Festival also takes place on the same day (the Onie no matsuri Festival of the present Emperor in 1990 was performed from the late-evening of November 22 to the early hours of 23).</e>
<cmt>「平成2年の」→訳漏れのため訳出、Niiname-sai Festival、Onie no matsuri Festivalとし、ピリオドの位置を移動</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, because the Niiname-sai Festival takes place on the Labor Thanksgiving Day, November 23, the Onie no matsuri Festival also takes place on the same day (the Onie no matsuri Festival of the present Emperor in 1990 was performed from the late-evening of November 22 to the early hours of 23).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="42">
<j>11月になると、1日から晦日（みそか。月末）までは散斎（あらいみ。簡略な物忌。）、祭儀の行われる卯の日の前の丑（うし）の日から3日間は致斎（まいみ。厳重な物忌。）とされ、穢れに触れることを戒めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November, from the first day to the Misoka (last day of month) was Araimi (capsule Monoimi, &apos;avoiding something regarding as ominous&apos;); the 3 days from Ushi no hi (the day of ox), right before the U no hi on which the festival was held, were Maimi (strict Monoimi) and associating with impurities were admonished during the period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November, from the first day to the Misoka (last day of month) was Araimi (capsule Monoimi, &apos;avoiding something regarding as ominous&apos;); the three days from Ushi no hi (the day of ox), right before the U no hi on which the festival was held, were Maimi (strict Monoimi) and associating with impurities was admonished during the period.</e>
<cmt>&quot;3&quot;をスペルアウト、全角クォーテーションを半角に修正、associating with impurities were→associating with impurities wasに修正NC_Check→word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November, from the first day to the Misoka (last day of month) was Araimi (capsule Monoimi, &apos;avoiding something regarding as ominous&apos;); the three days from Ushi no hi (the day of ox), right before the U no hi on which the festival was held, were Maimi (strict Monoimi) and associating with impurities was admonished during the period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>悠紀・主基の斎場を設け、それぞれに神供、神酒、調度などを調理製作する諸屋を建てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They laid on the ceremony space for the Yuki and the Suki, building related facilities on the space for cooking and producing the Jinku, Miki (sacred wine or sake) and Chodo (furnishing).</e>
<cmt>神供→Jinkuhttp://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?stype=1&amp;dtype=0&amp;dname=0ss&amp;p=%BF%C0%B6%A1</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They laid on the ceremony space for the Yuki and the Suki, building related facilities on the space for cooking and producing the Jinku (offering to gods), Miki (sacred wine or sake) and Chodo (furnishing).</e>
<cmt>Jinkuの補足追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They laid on the ceremony space for the Yuki and the Suki, building related facilities on the space for cooking and producing the Jinku (offering to gods), Miki (sacred wine or sake) and Chodo (furnishing).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>祭の7日前から大嘗宮を造り始め、5日以内に造り終える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They started building the Daijo-gu (temporary shrine prepared at the palace for the Onienomatsuri festival) 7 days before the festival and completed within 5 days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They started building the Daijo-gu (temporary shrine prepared at the palace for the Onie no matsuri Festival) seven days before the festival and completed within five days.</e>
<cmt>&quot;7&quot;&quot;5&quot;をスペルアウト、Onie no matsuri Festivalとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They started building the Daijo-gu (temporary shrine prepared at the palace for the Onie no matsuri Festival) seven days before the festival and completed within five days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>大嘗宮は悠紀殿・主基殿の2殿から成る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Daijo-gu consisted of the Yuki-den building and the Suki-den building.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Daijo-gu consisted of the Yuki-den building and the Suki-den building.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Daijo-gu consisted of the Yuki-den building and the Suki-den building.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="46">
<j>本祭の儀式</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The rituals of the Onienomatsuri festival</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rituals of the Onie no matsuri Festival</e>
<cmt>Onie no matsuri Festivalとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rituals of the Onie no matsuri Festival</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>祭の当夜、天皇は廻立殿（かいりゅうでん）に渡御し、小忌御湯（おみのおゆ）で潔斎して斎服を着け、深夜、悠紀殿（千木は伊勢神宮外宮と同じ外削ぎ）に入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The night of the day in which the festival is held, an emperor goes to the Kairyu-den building, taking Omi no oyu for purification, wearing Saifuku (priestly vestments), and after that, in the late-evening, goes into the Yuki-den building (the figure of Chigi, &apos;ornamental crossbeams on the gable of a Shinto shrine&apos; is Sotosogi, &apos;the ends of the former are terminated with a vertical cut&apos; and is same as that of the Ise-jingu Shrine, the Geku, &apos;outer shrine.&apos;)</e>
<cmt>小忌御湯→http://www.weblio.jp/content/大忌の御湯</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The night of the day in which the festival is held, an emperor goes to the Kairyu-den building, taking Omi no oyu for purification, wearing Saifuku (priestly vestments), and after that, in the late-evening, goes into the Yuki-den building (the figure of Chigi [ornamental crossbeams on the gable of a Shinto shrine] is Sotosogi, or the ends of the former are terminated with a vertical cut, and is same as that of the Outer Shrine of Ise-jingu).</e>
<cmt>（千木は伊勢神宮外宮と同じ外削ぎ）の部分を修正、ピリオドの位置を移動</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The night of the day in which the festival is held, an emperor goes to the Kairyu-den building, taking Omi no oyu for purification, wearing Saifuku (priestly vestments), and after that, in the late-evening, goes into the Yuki-den building (the figure of Chigi [ornamental crossbeams on the gable of a Shinto shrine] is Sotosogi, or the ends of the former are terminated with a vertical cut, and is same as that of the Outer Shrine of Ise-jingu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>悠紀殿には、南枕に布団（衾）が敷いてあり、礼服 (宮中)と沓を載せる台も布団の北隣に置いてある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Yuki-den building, there are Fusuma put down in a southerly direction and a rack to place formal attire (court) and Kutsu (shoe, footwear) is put on the north side of the Fusuma.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Yuki-den building, there are Fusuma (bedding) put down in a southerly direction and a rack to place formal attire (court) and Kutsu (shoe, footwear) is put on the north side of the Fusuma.</e>
<cmt>Fusumaの補足追加 (参照: http://tangorin.com/words/衾)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Yuki-den building, there are Fusuma (bedding) put down in a southerly direction and a rack to place formal attire (court) and Kutsu (shoe, footwear) is put on the north side of the Fusuma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>布団に置いてある枕の名は坂枕（さかまくら：逆枕の意味か？）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The pillow on the Fusuma is called Sakamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The pillow on the Fusuma is called Sakamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The pillow on the Fusuma is called Sakamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>この寝具類は神座、神の為に設けられたものであり、この中に天皇が直接入ることはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bedclothes are Kamukura (the place of god) and emperors don&apos;t use them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bedclothes are Kamukura (the place of god) and emperors don&apos;t use them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bedclothes are Kamukura (the place of god) and emperors don&apos;t use them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>悠紀殿では、神饌を神に供し、告文を奏して神と直会（なおらい）、つまり神に献じた神饌を、天皇親ら（みずから）聞こし召す（食べる）のである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Yuki-den building, emperors present Shinsen (food and alcohol offering to the gods) and notify Imperial instructions to the god; they Naorai (feast) the god, or they eat the Shinsen, presented to the god, themselves.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Yuki-den building, emperors present Shinsen (food and alcohol offering to the gods) and notify Imperial instructions to the god; they Naorai (feast) the god, or they eat the Shinsen, presented to the god, themselves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Yuki-den building, emperors present Shinsen (food and alcohol offering to the gods) and notify Imperial instructions to the god; they Naorai (feast) the god, or they eat the Shinsen, presented to the god, themselves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>廻立殿に戻り、次いで主基殿（千木は伊勢神宮内宮と同じ内削ぎ）に入り、悠紀殿と同じことを行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later emperors go back to the Kairyu-den building once again and then go into the Suki-den building (the figure of Chigi is uchisogi, &apos;the ends of the former are terminated with a horizontal cut&apos; and is same as that of the Inner Shrine of Ise), to repeat what he did in the Yuki-den building.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later emperors go back to the Kairyu-den building once again and then go into the Suki-den building (the figure of Chigi is Uchisogi, or the ends of the former are terminated with a horizontal cut, and is same as that of the Inner Shrine of Ise-jingu), to repeat what he did in the Yuki-den building.</e>
<cmt>前出の&quot;Sotosogi&quot;に合わせuchisogi→Uchisogiとし、（千木は伊勢神宮内宮と同じ内削ぎ）の部分を修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later emperors go back to the Kairyu-den building once again and then go into the Suki-den building (the figure of Chigi is Uchisogi, or the ends of the former are terminated with a horizontal cut, and is same as that of the Inner Shrine of Ise-jingu), to repeat what he did in the Yuki-den building.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="53">
<j>付属する儀式</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Adjunct rituals</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Adjunct rituals</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Adjunct rituals</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>この中心的な祭のほか、辰（たつ）の日には中臣氏が天神寿詞（あまつかみのよごと）を奏する行事、巳（み）の日には和舞（やまとまい）・風俗舞が催され、午（うま）の日には五節舞（ごせちのまい）が催されるなど、多くの行事がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than this main ritual, there are more events such as Amatsukami no yogoto presented by the Nakatomi clan on Tatsu no hi (the day of dragon), Yamatomai Dance and Fuzokumai dance on Mi no hi (the day of snake), and Gosechi no mai Dance (dance performance as part of a harvest festival).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than this main ritual, there are more events such as Amatsukami no yogoto presented by the Nakatomi clan on Tatsu no hi (the day of dragon), Yamatomai Dance and Fuzokumai Dance on Mi no hi (the day of snake), and Gosechi no mai Dance (dance performance as part of a harvest festival).</e>
<cmt>Yamatomai Danceに合わせ、Fuzokumai Danceとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than this main ritual, there are more events such as Amatsukami no yogoto presented by the Nakatomi clan on Tatsu no hi (the day of dragon), Yamatomai Dance and Fuzokumai Dance on Mi no hi (the day of snake), and Gosechi no mai Dance (dance performance as part of a harvest festival).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Dr jimmy(id:111486), 伏儀(id:142093), Myopia(id:9335), Kanbun(id:37114), 水野白楓(id:22811), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>