<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>岩倉宮</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iwakuranomiya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iwakuranomiya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iwakuranomiya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>岩倉宮（いわくらのみや）は鎌倉時代初期に存在した宮家の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iwakuranomiya was a Miyake (house of an Imperial prince) which existed in the beginning of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iwakuranomiya was Miyake (house of an Imperial prince) in the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>Miyake の前の a を削除しました。鎌倉時代初期に存在した：自然な表現に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iwakuranomiya was Miyake (house of an Imperial prince) in the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>しかし、宮内庁には宮家の一つとして公式には認められていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Imperial Household Agency does not recognize it as an official Miyake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Imperial Household Agency does not recognize it as an official Miyake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Imperial Household Agency does not recognize it as an official Miyake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>概略</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outline</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>用語集にある表現に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>順徳天皇皇子・忠成王は、順徳天皇流刑先の佐渡島で流刑先へ供奉した女房「従三位清季卿女」を母として誕生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial Prince of Emperor Juntoku, Prince Tadanari, was born as &quot;the daughter of Lord Jyunsanmi (Junior Third Rank) Kiyosuke,&quot; the court lady who accompanied Emperor Jutoku to Sadoga-shima island where he was deported, as his mother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Prince of Emperor Juntoku, Prince Tadanari, was born as a son of &apos;Lord Jyunsanmi (Junior Third Rank) Kiyosuke,&apos; the court lady who accompanied Emperor Jutoku to Sadoga-shima island where he was deported.</e>
<cmt>the daughter ⇒ a sonに訂正しました。 &apos; &apos; の位置を訂正しました。最後の as his mother を削除しました。”　”　⇒ &apos; &apos; に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Prince of Emperor Juntoku, Prince Tadanari, was born as a son of &apos;Lord Jyunsanmi (Junior Third Rank) Kiyosuke,&apos; the court lady who accompanied Emperor Jutoku to Sadoga-shima island where he was deported.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>その後経緯不詳ながら上洛し、宝治元年（1247年）2月に平経高の計らいにより密かに元服したとされる（『葉黄記』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, the background is unknown, but he traveled to Kyoto, and on Febuary 1247, he is thought to have secretly celebrated his attainment of manhood at the discretion of TAIRA no Tsunetaka (&quot;Yokoki&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, the background is unknown, but he went to Kyoto, and on Febuary 1247, he is thought to have secretly celebrated his attainment of manhood at the discretion of TAIRA no Tsunetaka (&quot;Yokoki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>上洛：　用語集の用語に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, the background is unknown, but he went to Kyoto, and on Febuary 1247, he is thought to have secretly celebrated his attainment of manhood at the discretion of TAIRA no Tsunetaka (&quot;Yokoki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>『本朝皇胤紹運録』によればこの後「岩倉宮」また「広御所宮」を名乗ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Honcho koin jounroku&quot;(the Emperor&apos;s family tree, made in the Muromachi period) he is said to have announced his name as &quot;Iwakuramiya&quot; and &quot;Kogoshomiya.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Honcho koin jounroku&quot; (the Emperor&apos;s family tree, made in the Muromachi period) he is said to have announced his name as &apos;Iwakuramiya&apos; and &apos;Kogoshomiya.&apos;</e>
<cmt>”　”　⇒ &apos; &apos; および &quot; &quot; に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Honcho koin jounroku&quot; (the Emperor&apos;s family tree, made in the Muromachi period) he is said to have announced his name as &apos;Iwakuramiya&apos; and &apos;Kogoshomiya.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>忠成王は弘安2年に没したが、一子尊忠は後に梶井門跡の権僧正となり、「入江宮」「広御所宮」「岩倉宮」を名乗ったという（『梶井円融房在位親王伝』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Tadanari died in 1279, but his child, Takatada, is said to have later become a gon no sojo (highest ranking priest, next to a sojo) of Kajii-monzeki Temple, and announced his name as &quot;Iriemiya&quot; &quot;Kogoshomiya&quot; and &quot;Iwakuramiya&quot; (&quot;Kajii Enyu-bo Temple Reign Imperial Prince Den&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Tadanari died in 1279, but his child, Takatada, is said to have later become a gon no sojo (highest ranking priest, next to a sojo) of Kajii-monzeki Temple, and announced his name as &apos;Iriemiya&apos;, &apos;Kogoshomiya&apos;, and &apos;Iwakuramiya&apos; (&quot;Kajii Enyu-bo Temple Reign Imperial Prince Den&quot;).</e>
<cmt>”　”　⇒ &apos; &apos; および &quot; &quot; に訂正しました。カンマを追加しました。ピリオドを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Tadanari died in 1279, but his child, Takatada, is said to have later become a gon no sojo (highest ranking priest, next to a sojo) of Kajii-monzeki Temple, and announced his name as &apos;Iriemiya&apos;, &apos;Kogoshomiya&apos;, and &apos;Iwakuramiya&apos; (&quot;Kajii Enyu-bo Temple Reign Imperial Prince Den&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>忠成王、尊忠と親子で同じ宮号を名乗ったことから、岩倉宮を最初の世襲宮家と見る意見がある一方、宮内庁の資料『皇室制度資料』では岩倉宮を宮家の一つとしてみることに対して慎重な見解を取っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the fact that both Prince Tadanari and Takatada, parent and son, announced their name with the same reigning name, there is a view that Iwakuramiya was the first hereditary court noble, but on the other hand, the material in the Imperial Household Regency &quot;Koshitsueidoshiryo&quot; takes a cautious view on looking at Iwakuramiya as one of the Miyake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the fact that both Prince Tadanari and Takatada, parent and son, announced the same reigning name, there is a view that Iwakuramiya was the first hereditary court noble, but on the other hand, the material in the Imperial Household Regency &quot;Koshitsueidoshiryo&quot; takes a cautious view on looking at Iwakuramiya as one of the Miyake.</e>
<cmt>”　”　⇒ &quot; &quot; に訂正しました。Their name with を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the fact that both Prince Tadanari and Takatada, parent and son, announced the same reigning name, there is a view that Iwakuramiya was the first hereditary court noble, but on the other hand, the material in the Imperial Household Regency &quot;Koshitsueidoshiryo&quot; takes a cautious view on looking at Iwakuramiya as one of the Miyake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>由来</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>「岩倉」「広御所」とも宮号の由来は居所か領地に縁があると推測されるのみで、詳細は未詳である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The only guess for the origin of the reigning name &quot;Iwakura&quot; and &quot;Kogosho&quot; is from an address or a fief, and the details are unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is just a guess that the origin of the reigning name &apos;Iwakura&apos; and &apos;Kogosho&apos; is an address or demesne (land attached to a manor and retained by the owner for their own use), and the details are unknown.</e>
<cmt>冒頭を自然な表現に訂正しました。from を削除しました。領地：用語集の用語に訂正しました。”　”　⇒ &apos; &apos; に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is just a guess that the origin of the reigning name &apos;Iwakura&apos; and &apos;Kogosho&apos; is an address or demesne (land attached to a manor and retained by the owner for their own use), and the details are unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 こぶまき(id:38278), BAKU(id:55205), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>