<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>馨子内親王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Princess Keishi (Kaoruko)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Princess Keishi (Kaoruko)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Princess Keishi (Kaoruko)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>馨子内親王（けいし（かおるこ）ないしんのう、長元2年2月2日 (旧暦)（1029年2月17日） - 寛治7年9月4日 (旧暦)（1093年9月26日））は、第68代後一条天皇第二皇女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Princess Keishi (February 17th, 1029-September 26th, 1093), who was also called Kaoruko, was the second imperial princess of the 68th emperor Emperor Goichijo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Princess Keishi (February 17, 1029 - September 26, 1093), who was also called Kaoruko, was the second imperial princess of the sixty-eighth emperor, Goichijo.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Princess Keishi (February 17, 1029 - September 26, 1093), who was also called Kaoruko, was the second imperial princess of the sixty-eighth emperor, Goichijo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>母は中宮藤原威子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her mother was the Chugu (the consort of an emperor) FUJIWARA no Ishi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her mother was the chugu (the consort of an emperor) FUJIWARA no Ishi.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her mother was chugu (the second consort of an emperor), FUJIWARA no Ishi.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>斎院、のち後三条天皇中宮。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She became the Sai-in (Imperial Princess appointed to serve the deities of the Kamo-jinja Shrines) and later the Chugu of Emperor Gosanjo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She became the Sai-in (Imperial Princess appointed to serve the deities of the Kamo-jinja Shrines) and later the Chugu of Emperor Gosanjo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She became the Sai-in (Imperial Princess appointed to serve the deities of the Kamo-jinja Shrines) and later, the chugu of Emperor Gosanjo.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>別名西院皇后。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She had another name of Empress Saiin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was also called Empress Saiin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was also called Empress Sai-in.</e>
<cmt>Sai-inで統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>同母姉に章子内親王（後冷泉天皇中宮）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her elder sister with the same mother was Imperial Princess Shoshi (the Chugu of Emperor Goreizei).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her elder sister (by the same mother) was Imperial Princess Shoshi (the chugu of Emperor Goreizei).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her elder sister (by the same mother) was Imperial Princess Shoshi (the chugu of Emperor Goreizei).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>長元4年（1031年）着袴、二品に叙される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Chakko no gi (Imperial ceremony) in 1031, the nihon (the second highest Imperial rank) was conferred on her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Chakko no gi (imperial ceremony) in 1031, the nihon (the second-highest imperial rank) was conferred upon her.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the chakko (ceremony of first-time wearing of a hakama) in 1031, the nihon (the second-highest imperial rank) was conferred upon her.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>同年賀茂斎院に卜定、准后。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, she became the Sai-in of the Kamo-jinja Shrines by divination and the Jugo (honorary rank next to the three Empresses: Great Empress Dowager, Empress Dowager, and Empress).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, she became the Sai-in of the Kamo-jinja Shrines by divination and the Jugo (honorary rank next to the three empresses: Great Empress Dowager, Empress Dowager and Empress).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, she became the Sai-in of the Kamo-jinja Shrines by divination and the Jugo (honorary rank next to the three empresses: Great Empress Dowager, Empress Dowager and Empress).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>同9年（1036年）に父後一条天皇が崩御したため斎院を退下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As her father Emperor Goichijo died in 1036, she retired from the Sai-in.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon the death of her father, Emperor Goichijo, in 1036, she retired from the Sai-in.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon the death of her father, Emperor Goichijo, in 1036, she retired from the Sai-in.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>さらにその後半年足らずで母威子も後を追うように他界した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her mother FUJIWARA no Ishi also died in less than six months.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her mother, FUJIWARA no Ishi, also died less than six months later.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her mother, FUJIWARA no Ishi, also died less than six months later as if following him.</e>
<cmt>「後を追うように」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>その後は藤原彰子の元で養育された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After her parents&apos; deaths, she was reared by FUJIWARA no Shoshi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequent to her parents&apos; deaths, she was reared by FUJIWARA no Shoshi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequent to her parents&apos; deaths, she was reared by FUJIWARA no Shoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>永承6年（1051年）皇太子尊仁親王（のちの後三条天皇）に入内。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She entered into court to be the Crown Prince Takahito (later Emperor Gosanjo) consort in 1051.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She entered into the court in 1051 in order to be the consort of Crown Prince Takahito (later Emperor Gosanjo).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She entered into the court in 1051 in order to be the consort of Crown Prince Takahito (later Emperor Gosanjo).</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを除きました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>治暦4年（1068年）後三条天皇が即位、それに伴い翌延久元年（1069年）中宮に冊立される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the enthronement of Emperor Gosanjo in 1068, she was appointed to the Chugu in 1069.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the enthronement of Emperor Gosanjo in 1068, she was appointed to the Chugu in 1069.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the enthronement of Emperor Gosanjo in 1068, she was appointed to the Chugu in 1069.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>同4年（1072年）後三条天皇退位、翌同5年（1073年）病の後三条上皇と共に出家するがまもなく上皇は崩御。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She entered into priesthood with sick Emperor Gosanjo in 1073, who had abdicated the throne in 1072, however he died shortly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She entered the priesthood along with the ill Emperor Gosanjo in 1073, who had abdicated the throne in 1072; however, he died shortly afterward.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She entered the priesthood along with the ill Emperor Gosanjo in 1073, who had abdicated the throne in 1072; however, he died shortly afterward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>延久6年（1074年）皇后となり、寛治7年（1093年）崩御。享年65。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She became the Empress in 1074, but died in 1093 at age 65.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She became the Empress in 1074 and died in 1093 at age 65.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She became the Empress in 1074 and died in 1093 at age 65.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>姉の章子内親王に続いての皇女であったため、馨子内親王の誕生に際して皇子を期待していた宮中の反応は冷ややかなものであったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the birth of Imperial Princess Keishi was received coolly by the members of the Imperial Court, who had eagerly expected the birth of a prince, because she was a princess following her elder sister Princess Shoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the birth of Imperial Princess Keishi was given a cool reception by the members of the Imperial Court, who had eagerly expected the birth of a prince, because she was a princess following her elder sister, Princess Shoshi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the birth of Imperial Princess Keishi received a frosty welcome by the members of the Imperial Court, who had eagerly expected the birth of a prince, because she was another princess following her elder sister, Princess Shoshi.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>その後わずか3歳で大斎院選子内親王の退下を受けて斎院に選ばれ、宮中を離れることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Appointed to the Sai-in succeeding Daisaiin Princess Senshi at the age of only three, she left the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Appointed to the Sai-in, succeeding Daisaiin Princess Senshi at the age of just three, she left the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then appointed to the Sai-in, succeeding Daisaiin Princess Senshi at the age of only three, she left the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>表現を少し変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>母后威子は馨子内親王を特に可愛がり、斎院にも時折行啓した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her mother FUJIWARA no Ishi especially loved her and visited her in the Saiin occasionally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her mother FUJIWARA no Ishi particularly loved her, and would visit her in the Saiin occasionally.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her mother FUJIWARA no Ishi particularly loved her, and would visit her in the Sai-in occasionally.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>両親の相次ぐ死で斎院を退下の後は、姉と共に祖母上東門院に引き取られて養育された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After her parents&apos; successive deaths, she and her elder sister were taken custody and reared by their grandmother Jotomonin.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following the deaths of her parents, she and her elder sister were placed in the custody and rearing of their grandmother, Jotomonin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After retiring the Sai-in following the deaths of her parents, she and her elder sister were placed in the custody and rearing of their grandmother, Jotomonin.</e>
<cmt>「斎院を退下の後は」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>当時としては遅い23歳で東宮尊仁親王（のちの後三条天皇）に入内する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She entered into court to be the Crown Prince Takahito (later Emperor Gosanjo) consort at the age of 23, although it was a little older than the standard at that time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She had entered the court in order to be the consort of Crown Prince Takahito (later Emperor Gosanjo) at the age of 23, although at the time she was slightly past the usual age.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She had entered the court in order to be the consort of Crown Prince Takahito (later Emperor Gosanjo) at the age of 23, although at the time she was slightly past the usual age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>これも上東門院の意向であったが、尊仁親王とその生母禎子内親王は先帝後朱雀天皇の時代から頼通らと対立しており、馨子内親王の入内もその溝を埋めることはかなわなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her entry into the court was also an idea of Jotomonin, but even the entry could not fill the gap between Prince Takahito and his real mother Imperial Princess Teishi, and FUJIWARA no Yorimichi, who had confronted since the period of former emperor Emperor Gosuzaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her entry to the court was also an idea of Jotomonin, but even the entry couldn&apos;t fill the gap between Prince Takahito and his real mother, Imperial Princess Teishi, and FUJIWARA no Yorimichi, who had been a point of contention since the period of the former emperor, Gosuzaku.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was also the idea of Jotomonin, but Crown Prince Takahito and his birth mother, Imperial Princess Teishi were in conflict since the period of the former emperor, Gosuzaku, and even the entry of Imperial Princess Keishi into the court couldn&apos;t fill the gap between them.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>また尊仁親王には添伏として入内した御息所藤原茂子（藤原能信養女）がおり、馨子内親王の入内は茂子が第一子を出産後間もなくであったのだが、その後も尊仁親王と茂子の間には合計一男四女が生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Takahito had already had a prince consort Miyasundokoro FUJIWARA no Moshi (an adopted daughter of FUJIWARA no Yoshinobu), who gave birth to their first baby shortly before the Imperial Princess Keishi&apos;s entry into the court, having one male and four female children with FUJIWARA no Moshi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Takahito had already had a prince consort Miyasundokoro FUJIWARA no Moshi (an adopted daughter of FUJIWARA no Yoshinobu), who had given birth to their first child shortly before the Imperial Princess Keishi&apos;s entry into the court, having one male and four female children with FUJIWARA no Moshi.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Crown Prince Takahito already had a prince consort, Miyasundokoro FUJIWARA no Moshi (an adopted daughter of FUJIWARA no Yoshinobu), who entered the court through Soibushi (the acquisition ceremony of a feminine bed partner) and had given birth to their first child shortly before the Imperial Princess Keishi&apos;s entry into the court, and in succeeding years, one male and four female children were born between Crown Prince Takahito and Moshi.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>さらに茂子の死後は源基子が尊仁親王の寵愛を受けて二男を産んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of FUJIWARA no Moshi, MINAMOTO no Kishi was in the prince&apos;s favor and bore two male children.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of FUJIWARA no Moshi, MINAMOTO no Kishi was in the prince&apos;s favor and bore two baby boys.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of FUJIWARA no Moshi, MINAMOTO no Kishi was in the crown prince&apos;s favor and bore two boys.</e>
<cmt>「crown prince」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>後冷泉天皇に皇子誕生が見られず焦っていた頼通や上東門院は、摂関家と縁の深い内親王を東宮妃に入れることで打開を図ったと見られるが、馨子内親王には夭折した一男一女がいたきりであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being anxious whether Emperor Goreizei might have a prince, FUJIWARA no Yorimichi and Jotomonin tried to resolve the situation by having the Imperial Princess enter into the court to be a Crown Princess, who was closely related to the Sekkan-ke (line of regents and advisers), however, Imperial Princess Keishi had only one male and one female children, both of whom died young.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Being anxious about whether Emperor Goreizei might have a prince, FUJIWARA no Yorimichi and Jotomonin tried to resolve the situation by having the Imperial Princess enter the court and become the Crown Princess, given that was closely related to the Sekkan-ke (line of regents and advisers); however, Imperial Princess Keishi had only one male and one female children, both of whom had died young.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anxious about Emperor Goreizei, who did not have a prince, FUJIWARA no Yorimichi and Jotomonin tried to resolve the situation by having the Imperial Princess who had close ties with the Sekkan-ke (line of regents and advisers) enter the court and become the Crown Princess; however, Imperial Princess Keishi had only one male and one female children, both of whom had died young.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>（ただ、『栄花物語』には「やん事なく心苦しく思ひ申させ給へり（高貴な妃として大切にされた）」とある。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Eiga Monogatari (theTale of Glory)&quot;, however, there is a description that Imperial Princess Keishi was treated kindly as a noble princess.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, &quot;Eiga Monogatari (the Tale of Glory)&quot; contains a description that Imperial Princess Keishi was treated kindly as a noble.)</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(However, in the &quot;Eiga Monogatari&quot; (the Tale of Glory), it is described that &apos;Imperial Princess Keishi was treated kindly as a noble.&apos;)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="25">
<j>やがて後冷泉天皇が嗣子なくして崩御、後三条天皇が即位して馨子内親王も中宮に冊立される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Emperor Goreizei, who had no heir, Imperial Princess Keishi was appointed to the Chugu with the enthronement of Emperor Gosanjo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Emperor Goreizei, who had no heir, Imperial Princess Keishi was appointed to the Chugu with the enthronement of Emperor Gosanjo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Emperor Goreizei, who had no heir, Imperial Princess Keishi was appointed to the Chugu with the enthronement of Emperor Gosanjo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>しかし母后禎子内親王が女院陽明門院となって天皇の後ろに控えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Gosanjo was strongly protected and supported by his mother Imperial Princess Teishi, who had become the Nyoin (a title for the close female relative of the Emperor) Yomeimonin.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Gosanjo was strongly protected and supported by his mother, Imperial Princess Teishi, who had become the Nyoin (a title for a close female relative of the Emperor) Yomeimonin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Gosanjo was strongly protected and supported by his mother, Imperial Princess Teishi, who had become the Nyoin (a title for a close female relative of the Emperor) Yomeimonin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>天皇の寵愛は女御基子がもっぱらにしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, the emperor doted on the nyogo (a high-ranking lady in the court (a consort of an emperor)) Kishi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the emperor doted on the nyogo (a high-ranking lady in the court (a consort of the Emperor)) Kishi.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the emperor doted on the nyogo (a high-ranking lady in the court (a consort of the Emperor)) Kishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>それに対して、馨子内親王は正妃とはいえ皇女さえも持たない后であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Princess Keishi was the lawful wife of Emperor Gosanjo, but she was an empress who did not have even one princess.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Princess Keishi was the lawful wife of Emperor Gosanjo, but she was an empress who did not have even one princess.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, even though Imperial Princess Keishi was the lawful wife of Emperor Gosanjo, she was an empress who did not even have a princess.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>その頃には頼むべき摂関家も既に昔日の面影はなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Princess Keishi could no longer rely on the Sekkan-ke, because they had already lost their influence.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Princess Keishi could no longer rely on the Sekkan-ke because they had already lost their influence.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Princess Keishi could no longer rely on the Sekkan-ke because they had already lost their influence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>後三条天皇が在位5年足らずで退位の後他界してからは、落飾した馨子内親王は西院で余生を送り「西院皇后」と称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Emperor Gosanjo death, who had abdicated only five years after his enthronement, Imperial Princess Keishi spent her remaining years in the Saiin as a priest named &quot;Empress Saiin&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following the death of Emperor Gosanjo, who had abdicated only five years after his enthronement, Imperial Princess Keishi spent her remaining years in the Saiin as a priestess called &quot;Empress Saiin.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following the death of Emperor Gosanjo, who had abdicated only five years after his enthronement, Imperial Princess Keishi spent her remaining years in the Sai-in as a priestess called &quot;Empress Sai-in.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「Sai-in」にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 平惣衛門(id:99387), Masyu(id:31065), 代言人(id:33675), Cprobot(id:97843), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>