<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>後深草天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Gofukakusa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Gofukakusa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Gofukakusa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>後深草天皇（ごふかくさてんのう、寛元元年6月10日（1243年6月28日） - 嘉元2年7月16日（1304年8月17日））は、鎌倉時代の第89代天皇（在位：寛元4年1月29日（1246年2月16日） - 正元元年11月26日（1259年1月9日））。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Gofukakusa (June 28th, 1243 - August 17th, 1304) was the eighty ninth Emperor during the Kamakura period. (his reign was February 16th, 1246 - January 9th, 1259.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Gofukakusa (June 28th, 1243 - August 17th, 1304) was the eighty ninth Emperor during the Kamakura period. (his reign was from February 16th, 1246 to January 9th, 1259.)</e>
<cmt>&quot;from, to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Gofukakusa (June 28, 1243 - August 17, 1304) was the eighty ninth Emperor during the Kamakura period (his reign was from February 16, 1246 to January 9, 1259).</e>
<cmt>日付表記ピリオドの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>諱は久仁（ひさひと）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His posthumous name was Hisahito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His posthumous name was Hisahito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His posthumous name was Hisahito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>系譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>後嵯峨天皇の第二皇子（出家したものも含めると第四皇子）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the second Prince of Emperor Gosaga. (the fourth Prince including other Princes who became priests)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the second Prince of Emperor Gosaga. (the fourth Prince among othes who became priests)</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity conciseness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the second Prince of Emperor Gosaga (the fourth Prince among others who became priests).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置移動スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>母は太政大臣西園寺実氏女、大宮院西園寺姞子（姞＝女吉）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was the Grand Minister, Saneuji SANJO&apos;s daughter, Omiyain Kitsushi SAIONJI.(姞=女吉)</e>
<cmt>姞＝女吉→読み方、意味不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was the Grand Minister, Saneuji SANJO&apos;s daughter, Omiyain Kitsushi SAIONJI.(姞=女吉)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was the Grand Minister, Saneuji SAIONJI&apos;s daughter, Omiyain Kitsushi SAIONJI.</e>
<cmt>名前スペル（姞＝女吉）英語では必要ないと考え削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>他のファイルに合わせる</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>寛元元年（1243年）六月、外祖父太政大臣実氏の今出川邸第にて誕生、生後二ヶ月で立太子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in his maternal grandfather, who was the Grand Minister, Imadegawa residence in June 1243 and became Crown Prince when he was two months old.</e>
<cmt>今出川邸→the mansion of Imadegawa; Imadegawa residence[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born at his maternal grandfather&apos;s Imadegawa residence, who was the Grand Minister, in June 1243 and became Crown Prince when he was just two months old.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born at his maternal grandfather Saneuji&apos;s Imadegawa residence, who was the Grand Minister, in June 1243 and became Crown Prince when he was just two months old.</e>
<cmt>Saneuji補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>同四年（1246年）正月、後嵯峨天皇の譲位により4歳で即位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In New year of 1246, he succeeded to the throne after Emperor Gosaga passed the throne to him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the New year of 1246, he succeeded to the throne after Emperor Gosaga passed the throne to him.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the New Year of 1246, he succeeded to the throne after Emperor Gosaga passed the throne to him when he was four year old.</e>
<cmt>スペルwhen he was four year old補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>在位中は後嵯峨上皇が院政が敷き、直接政務を見ることは無かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During his reign he did not actually control the politics since the retired Emperor Gosaga ruled the cloister government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During his reign he did not actually control politics since the retired Emperor Gosaga ruled the cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During his reign he did not in fact control politics since the Retired Emperor Gosaga ruled the cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>上皇スペル&quot;actually&quot;→&quot;in fact&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>正元元年（1259年）に瘧病を患い、同十一月、後嵯峨上皇の要請で、17歳で亀山天皇に譲位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became Warawayami (an argue similar to malarial fever) in 1259 and passed the throne to Emperor Kameyama in November after receiving Emperor Gosaga&apos;s request.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became sick from Warawayami (similar to malaria fever) in 1259 and passed the throne to Emperor Kameyama in November after accepting Emperor Gosaga&apos;s request.</e>
<cmt>formatted cell, word wrap was not checked, revised terminology for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became sick from Warawayami (similar to malaria fever) in 1259 and passed the throne to Emperor Kameyama in November at the age of 17 after accepting Emperor Gosaga&apos;s request.</e>
<cmt>at the age of 17補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>この間に、鎌倉幕府による朝廷への介入が進み院評定制が置かれ、院政もまた幕府の管理下に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During this time the intervention of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a Shogun) in to the Imperial Palace became more obvious, the council system supervised by a retired emperor was established, and the cloister government was also controlled under the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this time intervention by the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a Shogun) into the Imperial Palace affairs became more obvious, the counciling system supervised by a retired emperor was established, and the cloistered government was also controlled&apos;.</e>
<cmt>wordiness trimmed for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this time intervention by the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a Shogun) into the Imperial Palace affairs became more obvious, the council system supervised by a retired emperor was established, and the cloistered government was also controlled.</e>
<cmt>削除スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また建長四年（1252年）には後嵯峨天皇の第三皇子・宗尊親王が征夷大将軍として鎌倉に迎え入れられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in 1252 Imperial Prince Munetaka, Emperor Gosaga&apos;s third Prince was accepted as a &quot;barbarian-quelling generalissimo&quot; to the Kamakura government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also in 1252, Imperial Prince Munetaka, Emperor Gosaga&apos;s third Prince was accepted as a &quot;barbarian-quelling generalissimo&quot; by the Kamakura government.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also in 1252, Imperial Prince Munetaka, Emperor Gosaga&apos;s third Prince was accepted as a seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) by the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>&quot;barbarian-quelling generalissimo&quot;→seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;)government→bakufu</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>文永五年（1268年）に、後嵯峨上皇の指示により、年長の後深草院皇子熈仁を差し置いて亀山皇子世仁親王が立太子した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1268 Emperor Kameyama&apos;s Prince, Imperial Prince Yohito became Crown Prince with the retired Emperor Gosaga&apos;s request, although there was another possible successor to the throne,Gofukakusa in&apos;s Prince, Hirohito who was older than him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1268 Emperor Kameyama&apos;s Prince, Imperial Prince Yohito, became Crown Prince at the request of retired Emperor Gosaga, although there was another possible successor to the throne, Gofukakusa in&apos;s Prince, Hirohito who was older than he.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1268 Emperor Kameyama&apos;s Prince, Imperial Prince Yohito, became Crown Prince at the request of Retired Emperor Gosaga, although there was another possible successor to the throne, Gofukakusa in&apos;s Prince, Hirohito who was older than he.</e>
<cmt>上皇表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>ここから、後深草天皇の血統（持明院統）と亀山天皇の血統（大覚寺統）の対立が始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was the beginning of two parties, Emperor Gofukakusa&apos;s lineage (the Jimyoin Imperial line) and Emperor Kameyama&apos;s lineage (the Daikakuji Imperial line) opposed each others.</e>
<cmt>持明院統→the Jimyoin Imperial line[定訳不明]大覚寺統→the Daikakuji Imperial line[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the beginning of two parties, Emperor Gofukakusa&apos;s lineage (the Jimyoin Imperial line) and Emperor Kameyama&apos;s lineage (the Daikakuji Imperial line) opposing each other.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the beginning of two parties, Emperor Gofukakusa&apos;s lineage (the Jimyoin Imperial line) and Emperor Kameyama&apos;s lineage (the Daikakuji Imperial line) opposing each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>同九年（1272年）、後嵯峨院が治天と皇位の決定権についてすべてを鎌倉幕府に委ねる形で崩御すると、幕府が後深草・亀山の兄弟どちらとも決めかねて、二人の母后大宮院に諮問したところ法皇の素意が亀山天皇親政にあるとの返答を得、二年後、文永十一年（1274年）正月、亀山天皇は後宇多天皇に譲位し治天の君として院政を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1272 the retired Emperor Gosaga left a will to approve the Kamakura bakufu to make decisions in terms of choosing who to rule the cloister government or who to succeed the Imperial throne, then after he died, the government could not chose either Emperor Gofukakusa or Emperor Kameyama, then they asked Emperor&apos;s mother, Omiyain, she mentioned the retired Emperor wished Emperor Kameyama to rule the government directly, thus two years later, in the New year of 1274, Emperor Kameyama abdicated and passed the throne to Emperor Gouda and started ruling the cloister government as Chiten no Kimi.</e>
<cmt>治天の君→Chiten no Kimi[院政において実権を握って政治に当たった上皇をさす]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1272 the retired Emperor Gosaga left his will to approve the Kamakura bakufu for making decisions in terms of choosing who will rule the cloistered government or who should succeed the Imperial throne, then after he died, the government was not able to chose either Emperor Gofukakusa nor Emperor Kameyama, and they asked the Emperor&apos;s mother, Omiyain, and she mentioned that the retired Emperor wished Emperor Kameyama to rule the government directly, thus, two years later, in the New year of 1274, Emperor Kameyama abdicated and passed the throne to Emperor Gouda and started ruling the cloister government as Chiten no Kimi.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1272 the Retired Emperor Gosaga left his will to approve the Kamakura bakufu for making decisions in terms of choosing who will rule the cloistered government or who should succeed the Imperial throne, then after he died, the government was not able to chose either Emperor Gofukakusa nor Emperor Kameyama, and they asked the Emperor&apos;s mother, Omiyain, and she mentioned that the Cloistered Emperor wished Emperor Kameyama to rule the government directly, thus, two years later, in the New Year of 1274, Emperor Kameyama abdicated and passed the throne to Emperor Gouda and started ruling the cloister government as Chiten no Kimi.</e>
<cmt>上皇表記法皇表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これに不満を抱いた後深草院は、翌建治元年（1275年）、太上天皇の尊号辞退と出家の意思を表明し、時の関東申次で後深草院寄りの西園寺実兼が執権北条時宗と折衝し、後深草天皇の皇子熈仁親王（伏見天皇）を同年中に立太子させることに成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The retired Emperor Gofukakusa in was not happy about the situation, he demonstrated his dissatisfaction by declining from his position as the retired emperor and to receive the respected name in 1275, Sanekane SAIONJI, who was the Kanto Moshitsuji in this period and favored the retired Emperor Gofukakusa, negotiated with the regent, Tokimune HOJO, he achieved Gofukakusa&apos;s Prince, Imperial Prince Hirohito (the Emperor Fushimi) to become Crown Prince in the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The retired Emperor Gofukakusa in was not happy about the situation, he demonstrated his dissatisfaction by declining from his position as the retired emperor and to receive the respected name in 1275, Sanekane SAIONJI, who was the Kanto Moshitsuji in this period and favored the retired Emperor Gofukakusa, negotiated with the regent, Tokimune HOJO, he succeded to have Gofukakusa&apos;s Prince, Imperial Prince Hirohito (the Emperor Fushimi) to become Crown Prince in the same year.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Gofukakusa in was not happy about the situation, he demonstrated his dissatisfaction by declining from his position as the retired emperor and to receive the respected name in 1275, Sanekane SAIONJI, who was the Kanto Moshitsugi in this period and favored the Retired Emperor Gofukakusa, negotiated with the regent, Tokimune HOJO, he succeeded to have Gofukakusa&apos;s Prince, Imperial Prince Hirohito (the Emperor Fushimi) to become Crown Prince in the same year.</e>
<cmt>retired Emperor 削除スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>その後、弘安三年（1280年）頃から後深草院方による後宇多退位と皇太子擁立の動きが強まり、ついに十年（1287年）十月、伏見天皇即位に伴い院政を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The retired Emperor Gofukakusa started showing the movement for Emperor Gouda to abdicate and appoint new Crown Prince since 1280, finally, when Emperor Fushimi succeeded to the throne, Gofukakusa started his cloister government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The retired Emperor Gofukakusa started a movement for Emperor Gouda to abdicate and to appoint the newest Crown Prince since 1280, finally, when Emperor Fushimi succeeded to the throne, Gofukakusa began his cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Gofukakusa-in started a movement for Emperor Gouda to abdicate and to appoint the newest Crown Prince since 1280, finally, when Emperor Fushimi succeeded to the throne in October 1287, Gofukakusa-in began his cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>retired Emperor 削除　in 補足October 128補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また正応二年（1289年）十月には第六皇子・久明親王を鎌倉将軍として下向させ、その後しばらく持明院統に有利な体勢が続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also the sixth Prince, Imperial Prince Hisaaki descended to the Kamakura Shogun in October 1289, after this the situation continued to be favorable to the Jimyoin Imperial line for a while.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also the sixth Prince, Imperial Prince Hisaaki became the Kamakura Shogun in October 1289, and afterwards the situation continued, for a while, to be favorable for the Jimyoin Imperial line.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also the sixth Prince, Imperial Prince Hisaaki became the Kamakura Shogun in October 1289, and afterwards the situation continued, for a while, to be favorable for the Jimyoin Imperial line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>正応三年（1290年）二月、出家し法諱を素実とし、公式の院政を停めたが、その後も政治への関与が続き、持明院統の中心としてその繁栄につとめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became priest in February 1290 and had a Buddhist name of Sojitsu, he stopped officially ruling the cloister government, however he continued to get involved into the politics after this, he contributed to act as a main person of the Jimyoin Imperial line.</e>
<cmt>法諱→a Buddhust nzme[定訳不明]素実→Sojitsu?[読み方確認できず]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became priest in February 1290 and had the Buddhist name of Sojitsu, he stopped officially ruling the cloistered government, however he continued to be involved in politics and later contributed as a main person in the Jimyoin Imperial line.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became priest in February 1290 and had the Buddhist name of Sojitsu, he stopped officially ruling the cloistered government, however he continued to be involved in politics and later contributed as a main person in the Jimyoin Imperial line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>嘉元二年（1304年）、冷泉富小路殿で崩御、享年62。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at Reizei Tomi no Koji dono (mansion) in 1304 when he was sixty two years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at Reizei Tomi no Koji dono (mansion) in 1304 when he was sixty two years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at Reizei Tomi no Koji dono (mansion) in 1304 when he was sixty two years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>在位中の元号</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eras during his reign</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Era,s during his reign</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eras during his reign</e>
<cmt>Eras に戻しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>寛元 （1246年1月19日） - 1247年2月28日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kangen (January 19, 1246) - February 28, 1247</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kangen (January 19, 1246) - February 28, 1247</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kangen (January 19, 1246) - February 28, 1247</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>宝治 1247年2月28日 - 1249年3月18日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoji February 28, 1247 - March 18, 1249</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoji February 28, 1247 - March 18, 1249</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoji February 28, 1247 - March 18, 1249</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="21">
<j>建長 1249年3月18日 - 1256年10月15日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kencho March 18, 1249 - October 15, 1256</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kencho March 18, 1249 - October 15, 1256</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kencho March 18, 1249 - October 15, 1256</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="22">
<j>康元 1256年10月15日 - 1257年3月14日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kogen October 15, 1256 - March 14, 1257</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kogen October 15, 1256 - March 14, 1257</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kogen October 15, 1256 - March 14, 1257</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="23">
<j>正嘉 1257年3月14日 - 1259年3月26日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoka March 14, 1257 - March 26, 1259</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoka March 14, 1257 - March 26, 1259</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoka March 14, 1257 - March 26, 1259</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="24">
<j>正元 1259年3月26日 - （1259年11月26日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shogen March 26, 1259 - (November 26, 1259)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shogen March 26, 1259 - (November 26, 1259)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shogen March 26, 1259 - (November 26, 1259)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>諡号・追号・異名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Posthumous name, Tshugo, different name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Posthumous name, Tshugo, different name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Posthumous name, Tsuigo, different name</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>御陵（深草北陵）に因んで「後深草院」と追号。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His posthumous name was &apos;Gofukakusa in&apos;, named from the Mausoleum. (Fukakusa Kita no Misasagi)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His posthumous name was &apos;Gofukakusa in&apos;, named from the Mausoleum. (Fukakusa Kita no Misasagi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His posthumous name was &apos;Gofukakusa-in,&apos; named from the Mausoleum (Fukakusa Kita no Misasagi).</e>
<cmt>コンマとピリオドの位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>第54代仁明天皇の別称が深草帝だったため、後の字が付くが、普通の天皇の加後号のように音読みすると「後深草（ごふかうさ）＝御不孝者」に通じるのを憚り、この天皇に限って、「後」の字を訓読みして「のちの―ふかうさ」院と称したという（『和長卿記』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the different name of the fifty fourth Emperor, Emperor Ninmyo was Fukakusa tei, the posthumous name has the character of go, when the name is read in Onyomi (Kanji character read in Chinese way), it is called &apos;Gofukausa&apos; which means someone undutiful to his parents, therefore it is said only the name of this Emperor is called &apos;Nochi no - Fukausa&apos; in (&apos;Go&apos; read by Kun yomi) (Kazunaga Kyo Ki (&quot;The Diary of Kazunaga Higashibojo&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the different name of the fifty fourth Emperor, Emperor Ninmyo was Fukakusa tei, his posthumous name has the character go, when the name is read in Onyomi (Kanji character read the Chinese way), it is called &apos;Gofukausa&apos; which means someone undutiful to his parents, therefore it is said that only this Emperor&apos;s name is called &apos;Nochi no - Fukausa&apos; in (&apos;Go&apos; read by Kun yomi) (Kazunaga Kyo Ki (&quot;The Diary of Kazunaga Higashibojo&quot;)</e>
<cmt>rervised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the different name of the fifty-fourth Emperor, Emperor Ninmyo was Fukakusa tei, his posthumous name has the character go, when the name is read in Onyomi (Kanji character read in the Chinese way), it is called &apos;Gofukausa&apos; which means someone undutiful to his parents, therefore it is said that only this Emperor&apos;s name is called &apos;Nochi no - Fukausa&apos; in (&apos;Go&apos; read by Kun yomi) (Kazunaga Kyo Ki (&quot;The Diary of Kazunaga Higashibojo&quot;).</e>
<cmt>in補足ピリオド補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>しかし、別の資料によれば宮中では依然として「ごふかうさ」と読んでいたとされ、不審でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However according to another materials, it is said the Emperor was still called &apos;Gofukausa&apos; in the Imperial Palace, there is no proof of the above information.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, according to another source, the Emperor was still called &apos;Gofukausa&apos; inside the Imperial Palace, and there is no proof of the above information.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, according to another source, the Emperor was still called &apos;Gofukausa&apos; inside the Imperial Palace, and there is no proof of the above information.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>明治以後、院号は廃止され、後深草天皇と称されるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Meiji period, in title was abolished and he was called Emperor Gofukakusa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji period, the &quot;in&quot; title was abolished and he was called Emperor Gofukakusa.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji period, the &quot;in&quot; title was abolished and he was called Emperor Gofukakusa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>それに伴い、読みも正式に「ごふかくさ」に定着。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to this change, the name was officially called &apos;Gofukakusa&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to this change, the name was officially called &apos;Gofukakusa&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to this change, the name was officially called &apos;Gofukakusa.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>ほかに居所とした常盤井殿や冷泉富小路殿にちなんだ異名もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are different names related to other Palace he lived in such as Tokiwai dono (mansion) or Reizei Tomi no Koji dono. (mansion)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are different names related to other Palaces he lived in such as Tokiwai dono (mansion) or Reizei Tomi no Koji dono. (mansion)</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are different names related to other Palaces he lived in such as Tokiwai dono (mansion) or Reizei Tomi no Koji dono (mansion).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>陵墓・霊廟</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial mausoleum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial mausoleum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial mausoleum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="31">
<j>生前の希望によって深草山中に葬られ、京都市伏見区深草坊町の深草北陵（ふかくさきたのみささぎ）の域内にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to his will while he was alive, the Emperor was entombed in the mountain of Fukakusa, it is located within Fukakusa Kita no Misasagi in Fukakusa Bo-cho Town, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In accordance with his will, the Emperor was entombed in on Mount Fukakusa, ocated within Fukakusa Kita no Misasagi in Fukakusa Bo-cho Town, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In accordance with his will, the Emperor was entombed in on Mt. Fukakusa, located within Fukakusa Kita no Misasagi in Fukakusa Bo-cho, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>Mount→Mt.住所表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Lemon pie(id:66842), Lonicera(id:20638), Hiroakita(id:25946), BOTarate(id:185620), 霧木諒二(id:9795), Nnh(id:474), China(id:10362), DragonBot(id:161936), Cprobot(id:97843), Eskimbot(id:29676), MIO(id:31681), 味っ子(id:17086), Escarbot(id:59151), Zwobot(id:23873), MDR-SK(id:192066), パの字(id:34188), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), Masyu(id:31065), Nidarin(id:6420), SuisuiBot(id:10165), 玄史生(id:43670), 代言人(id:33675), UMBRO(id:100484), Rei-bot(id:94097), Yume149(id:17504), Louperibot(id:128971), LeonardoRob0t(id:25875), Zippin(id:9885), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>