<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>覚行法親王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The monk-Imperial Prince Kakugyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The monk-Imperial Prince Kakugyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The monk-Imperial Prince Kakugyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>覚行法親王（かくぎょうほっしんのう、承保2年（1075年）4月 － 長治2年11月18日（1105年12月26日））は、平安時代中期から後期にかけての皇族・僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The monk-Imperial Prince Kakugyo Hosshino (April 1075 ~ December 26th, 1105) was a member of the Imperial Family and a monk of the middle to the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The monk-Imperial Prince Kakugyo Hosshino (April 1075 ~ December 26th, 1105) was a member of the Imperial Family and a monk of the middle to the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The monk-Imperial Prince Kakugyo Hosshino (April 1075 - December 26, 1105) was a member of the Imperial Family and a monk of the middle to the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>日付表記~→-</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>白河天皇の第二皇子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is the second prince of the Emperor Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is the second prince of the Emperor Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is the second prince of the Emperor Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は藤原経平の娘藤原経子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother is FUJIWARA no Keishi (Tsuneko), a daughter of FUJIWARA no Tsunehira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was FUJIWARA no Keishi (Tsuneko), a daughter of FUJIWARA no Tsunehira.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was FUJIWARA no Keishi (Tsuneko), a daughter of FUJIWARA no Tsunehira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>覚念・中御室とも称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is also called as Kakunen or Naka no Omuro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also called Kakunen or Naka no Omuro.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also called Kakunen or Naka no Omuro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>真言宗仁和寺の第3世門跡。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the third monseki (the chief priest who is Imperial Prince) of the Shingon sect of Buddhism, Ninna-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the third monseki (chief priest who is an Imperial Prince) of the Shingon sect of Buddhism, Ninna-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the third monseki (chief priest who is an Imperial Prince) of the Shingon sect of Buddhism, Ninna-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>仁和寺に入り1085年（応徳2年）性信入道親王の下で出家・受戒。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He entered Ninna-ji Temple and enter the priesthood and received commandments under the priest-Imperial Prince Shoshin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He entered the priesthood at Ninna-ji Temple and received commandments under the priest-Imperial Prince Shoshin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He entered the priesthood at Ninna-ji Temple in 1085 and received commandments under the priest-Imperial Prince Shoshin.</e>
<cmt>in 1085補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>性信の没後に仁和寺寺務に就任し、ついで寛意から灌頂を受け、1098年（承徳2年）円宗寺検校・法勝寺検校となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was posted to the Jimu (the representative of general affairs of the temple) after the death of Shoshin, and received kanjo (a ceremony similar to baptism) by a bonze Kani, and became kengyo (a post of supervisor of the office work at temples and shrines) of Enso-ji temple and Hossho-ji temple in 1098.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was posted to Jimu (the representative of general affairs of the temple) after the death of Shoshin, and received kanjo (a ceremony similar to baptism) by a bonze Kani, and became kengyo (a post of supervisor of the office work at temples and shrines) of Enso-ji temple and Hossho-ji temple in 1098.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was posted to Jimu (the representative of general affairs of the temple) after the death of Shoshin, and received kanjo (a ceremony similar to baptism) by a bonze Kani, and became kengyo (a post of supervisor of the office work at temples and shrines) of Enso-ji Temple and Hossho-ji Temple in 1098.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>翌1099年（承徳3年）親王宣下を受け最初の法親王となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the next year in 1099, he received royal command to be Imperial Prince and became the first monk-Imperial Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the next year of 1099, he received a royal command to be Imperial Prince and became the first monk-Imperial Prince.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the next year of 1099, he received a royal command to be Imperial Prince and became the first monk-Imperial Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>1102年（康和4年）尊勝寺落慶法要供養の導師をつとめ、尊勝寺長吏となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He worked as a Doshi (a sort of high priest) at the ceremony to celebrate the completion of the Sonsho-ji Temple in 1102 and became the chori (the head priest) of the Sonsho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He worked as a Doshi (a sort of high priest) at a ceremony to celebrate the completion of the Sonsho-ji Temple in 1102 and became the chori (the head priest) of the Sonsho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He worked as a Doshi (a sort of high priest) at a ceremony to celebrate the completion of the Sonsho-ji Temple in 1102 and became the chori (the head priest) of the Sonsho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>1105年（長治2年）、31歳で没。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died in 1105 at the age of 35.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died in 1105 at the age of 35.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died in 1105 at the age of 31.</e>
<cmt>数字修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>墓所は京都府南丹市園部町の鴫尾山九品寺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His grave is at the Shigiosan Kuhonn-ji Temple in Sonobe-cho Town, Nantan City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grave is at the Shigiosan Kuhonn-ji Temple in Sonobe-cho Town, Nantan City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grave is at the Shigiosan Kuhon-ji Temple in Sonobe-cho, Nantan City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>住所表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), Equaly(id:89792), 代言人(id:33675), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), UMBRO(id:100484), Yanahan(id:2437), 唐棣色(id:64681), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>