<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>朱雀天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor SUZAKU</e>
<cmt>以下天皇名、人名の読み方は、ブリタニカ国際大百科事典、広辞苑、kotobank.jpで確認。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor SUZAKU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Suzaku</e>
<cmt>SUZAKU→Suzaku</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>朱雀天皇（すざくてんのう、延長元年7月24日（923年9月7日） - 天暦6年8月15日（952年9月6日）、在位：延長8年11月22日（930年12月14日） - 天慶9年4月13日（946年5月16日））は第61代の天皇。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor SUZAKU (September 7th, 923 - September 6th, 952), his reign was December 14th, 930 - May 16th, 946), he was the 61st Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Suzaku (September 7, 923 - September 6th, 952) was the sixty-first Emperor (his reign was December 14, 930 to May 16th, 946).</e>
<cmt>SUZAKU → Suzaku61st → sixty-firstAdd (his reign was December 14, 930 to May 16th, 946)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Suzaku (September 7, 923 - September 6, 952) was the sixty-first Emperor (his reign was from December 14, 930 to May 16, 946).</e>
<cmt>日付表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>諱は寛明（ゆたあきら）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His posthumous name was Yutaakira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His posthumous name was Yutaakira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His posthumous name was Yutaakira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>系譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>第60代醍醐天皇の第十一皇子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the 60th Emperor and the 10th Prince of Emperor DAIGO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the sixtieth Emperor and the tenth prince of Emperor Daigo.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the eleventh prince of the sixtieth Emperor, Emperor Daigo.</e>
<cmt>全体の訳を修正&quot;sixtieth emperor&quot;→&quot;sixtieth Emperor&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>母は藤原基経の娘、中宮藤原穏子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was FUJIWARA no Mototsune&apos;s daughter, the second consort of an emperor, FUJIWARA no Onshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was FUJIWARA no Mototsune&apos;s daughter, the second consort of an Emperor, FUJIWARA no Onshi.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was FUJIWARA no Mototsune&apos;s daughter, the second consort of an Emperor, FUJIWARA no Onshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>Biography→Brief Personal Historyに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>延長4年（926年）、東宮となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became Crown Prince in 926.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became the crown prince in 926.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became the crown prince in 926.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>立太子の背景には、兄保明親王とその子慶頼王の二代にわたる東宮の夭折があり、母后穏子は怨霊を恐れて、幾重にも張られた几帳の中で寛明親王を育てたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the background how he became Crown Prince was previous Crown Prince, both his brother Prince Yasuakira and his son Prince Yoshiyori died young, thus the mother, Onshi was scared of bad spirit and looked after Prince Yutaakira inside the layered of Kicho. (partition made by fabric used in Heian Period)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the background how he became the crown prince was that the previous crown princes--his brother Prince Yasuakira and his son, Prince Yoshiyori--died young, thus the mother, Onshi, was afraid of bad spirits and looked after Prince Yutaakira within the layered Kicho (a partition of fabric used during the Heian period).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the background how he became the crown prince was that the previous crown princes--his brother Prince Yasuakira and his son, Prince Yoshiyori--died young, thus the mother, Onshi, was afraid of bad spirits and looked after Prince Yutaakira within the layered Kicho (a partition of fabric used during the Heian period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>延長8年（930年）醍醐天皇の崩御を受け同年9月の践祚後、11月に8歳で即位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 930, after Emperor DAIGO died, he succeeded to the throne in November when he was eight years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 930, following the death of Emperor Daigo, he succeeded to the throne in November at the age of eight.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 930, following the death of Emperor Daigo, he took over the throne (senso) in September and succeeded to the throne (sokui) in November at the age of eight.</e>
<cmt>「9月の践祚後」の訳を補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>政治は、伯父藤原忠平が摂政関白として取り仕切っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His uncle, FUJIWARA no Tadahira took actual control of the politics as a regent and chancellor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His uncle, FUJIWARA no Tadahira, took actual control of the politics as a regent and chancellor.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His uncle, FUJIWARA no Tadahira, took actual control of the politics as a regent and chancellor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>治世中の承平5年（935年）2月、平将門が関東で反乱を起こし、次いで翌年には瀬戸内海で藤原純友が乱を起こした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During his reign in 935, there was an incident caused by TAIRANO Masakado in Kanto area, and another one in the Inland Sea (of Japan) caused by FUJIWARA no Sumitomo on the following year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During his reign, in 935, there was an incident caused by TAIRANO Masakado in the Kanto area, and the following year there was another one in the Inland Sea (of Japan) caused by FUJIWARA no Sumitomo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 935, during his reign, there was an incident caused by TAIRA no Masakado in the Kanto area, and the following year there was another one in the Inland Sea (of Japan) caused by FUJIWARA no Sumitomo.</e>
<cmt>TAIRANO→Taira no</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>（承平・天慶の乱）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The Shohei and Tengyo Rebellion)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The Shohei and Tengyo Rebellion)</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The Shohei and Tengyo Rebellion)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>懐柔策を試みたがうまくいかず、天慶3年（940年）、藤原忠文を征夷大将軍に任命して将門征伐軍を送り、藤原秀郷の手により将門は討たれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The government tried to conciliate the incident however it failed, in 940 FUJIWARA no Tadafumi was appointed as barbarian-quelling generalissimo to send the troops to defeat Masakado, FUJIWARA no Hidesato subjugated Masakado.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The government tried to conciliate the incident but it failed, so in 940 FUJIWARA no Tadafumi was appointed as barbarian-quelling generalissimo to send the troops to defeat Masakado, FUJIWARA no Hidesato subjugated Masakado.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The government tried to reconcile the incident but it failed, so in 940 FUJIWARA no Tadafumi was appointed as Seii Raishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) to send the troops to defeat Masakado, FUJIWARA no Hidesato subjugated Masakado.</e>
<cmt>スペース取る改行取る&quot;barbarian-quelling generalissimo&quot;→&quot;Seii Raishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;)&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>翌年には橘遠保により藤原純友が討たれ、乱はようやく収束した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the following year FUJIWARA no Sumitomo was subjugated byTACHIBANA no Toyasu, both incidents finally converged.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following year FUJIWARA no Sumitomo was subjugated byTACHIBANA no Toyasu, and both incidents finally converged.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following year FUJIWARA no Sumitomo was subjugated byTACHIBANA no Toyasu, and both incidents finally converged.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>治世中はこのほかにも富士山の噴火や地震・洪水などの災害・変異が多く、また皇子女に恵まれなかったこともあってか、朱雀天皇は早々と同母弟成明親王（後の村上天皇）に譲位し、仁和寺に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During Emperor SUZAKU&apos;s reign, there were many disasters or abnormal changes, such as eructation of Fuji Mountain or earthquake and flooding, not only that the Emperor did not have any children, he abdicated to pass the throne to his half younger brother, Prince Nariakira (later called Emperor MURAKAMI) and left the Imperial Palace to live in Ninna-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During Emperor Suzaku&apos;s reign there were many disasters or abnormal events such as the eruptin of Mt. Fuji, earthquakes and flooding; moreover, not only did the Emperor have no children, but he also abdicated to pass the throne to his younger half-brother, Prince Nariakira (later called Emperor Murakami) and left the Imperial Palace to live at Ninna-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During Emperor Suzaku&apos;s reign there were many disasters or abnormal events such as the eruptin of Mt. Fuji, earthquakes and flooding; moreover, not only did the Emperor have no children, but he also abdicated to pass the throne to his younger half-brother, Prince Nariakira (later called Emperor Murakami) and left the Imperial Palace to live at Ninna-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかしその後、後悔して復位の祈祷をしたともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However he regretted it afterwards and gave an invocation to be restored to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he regretted it afterwards and gave an invocation to be restored to the throne.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he regretted it afterwards and gave an invocation to be restored to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>天暦6年（952年）に出家して、その年に30歳で亡くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became a priest in 952 and died in the same year when he was thirty years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became a priest in 952 and died in the same year at 30 years of age.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became a priest in 952 and died in the same year at 30 years of age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="18">
<j>諡号・追号・異名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Posthumous name, Tsuigo, different name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Posthumous name, Tsuigo, a different name</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Posthumous name, Tsuigo, a different name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>譲位後、朱雀院を「後院」としたため、「朱雀院」と追号。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had a posthumous name &apos;Suzaku in - ex-Emperor Suzaku&apos; as he spent his time in Suzaku as &apos;Go-in&apos; (the palace ex-emperor lives after his abdication) after he abdicated the throne.</e>
<cmt>後院 定訳不明。天皇在位中に、譲位後の御所として、あらかじめ定めておく離宮。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had the posthumous name &apos;Suzaku in - ex-Emperor Suzaku,&apos; since he spent his time in Suzaku as &apos;Go-in&apos; (the palace where an ex-emperor lived after his abdication) once he abdicated the throne.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had the posthumous name &apos;Suzaku in - the Retired Emperor Suzaku,&apos; since he spent his time in Suzaku as &apos;Go-in&apos; (the palace where an ex-emperor lived after his abdication) once he abdicated the throne.</e>
<cmt>&quot;ex-Emperor Suzaku&quot;→&quot;the Retired Emperor Suzaku&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="20">
<j>陵墓・霊廟</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial mausoleum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Mausoleum</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Mausoleum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>御陵は京都市伏見区醍醐御陵東裏町にある醍醐陵（だいごのみささぎ）で、父帝醍醐天皇の山科陵から遠くない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor was entombed in Daigo no misasagi (the Daigo (Imperial) Mausoleum), Higashi Ura cho-Town, Daigo (go?)ryo Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City Yamashina no misasagi, which is not too far from his father, Emperor DAIGO&apos;s mausoleum.</e>
<cmt>醍醐陵 醍醐御陵の誤り？（郵便番号簿に醍醐陵という住所は、なし）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor was entombed in Daigo no misasagi (the Daigo (Imperial) Mausoleum), Higashi Ura cho-Town, Daigo (go?)ryo of Fushimi ward, Kyoto City Yamashina no misasagi, which is not too far from the mausoleum of his father, Emperor Daigo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor was entombed in Daigo no misasagi (the Daigo (Imperial) Mausoleum), Higashi Ura cho-Town, Daigo goryo of Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City, which is not far from Yamashina no misasagi, the mausoleum of his father, Emperor Daigo.</e>
<cmt>which is not too far fromの位置を移動原文の住所に「御」を追加し訳も修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 JAnDbot(id:66507), Lonicera(id:20638), Izayohi(id:13095), BOTarate(id:185620), 霧木諒二(id:9795), Nnh(id:474), Equaly(id:89792), 松茸(id:27535), Cprobot(id:97843), 味っ子(id:17086), 矢刺幹人(id:10639), Escarbot(id:59151), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), Masyu(id:31065), Yonoemon(id:55450), Nidarin(id:6420), SuisuiBot(id:10165), 代言人(id:33675), 名無し(id:7386), YOSHI438(id:174755), Yas(id:739), 唐棣色(id:64681), LeonardoRob0t(id:25875), LERK(id:4460), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>