<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>倭姫命</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamatohime no Mikoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamatohime no Mikoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamatohime no Mikoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>倭姫命（やまとひめのみこと）は、日本神話中の登場人物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamatohime no Mikoto is a character in Japanese Mythology.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamatohime no Mikoto is a character in Japanese Mythology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamatohime no Mikoto is a character in Japanese Mythology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>第11代垂仁天皇の第4皇女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">4th Princess of the eleventh Emperor Suinin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was the 4th daughter of the eleventh Emperor, Suinin.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;She was the&quot;&quot;Princess&quot;→&quot;daughter&quot;Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was the 4th daughter of the eleventh Emperor Suinin.</e>
<cmt>,削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は皇后日葉酢媛命。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her mother is Empress Hibasu Hime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her mother was Empress Hibasu Hime.</e>
<cmt>&quot;is&quot;→&quot;was&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her mother was Empress Hibasu Hime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>またヤマトタケルの叔母とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She is also regarded as an aunt of Yamato Takeru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She is also regarded as an aunt of Yamato Takeru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She is also regarded as an aunt of Yamato Takeru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>第10代崇神天皇の皇女豊鍬入姫命の後を継ぎ天照大神の「御杖代（みつえしろ、神の意を受ける依代）」として大和国から伊賀国・近江国・美濃国・尾張国の諸国を経て伊勢国の国に入り、神託により現在地に伊勢神宮を創建したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She succeeded after Toyosukiiribime no Mikoto, Princess of the tenth Emperor Sujin, as &apos;Mitsueshiro, or yorishiro, which is an object receiving god&apos;s will&apos; of Amaterasu Omikami and went through from Yamato Province, Iga Province, Omi Province, Mino Province, Owari Province, and other provinces and entered Ise Province, and is said to have erected Ise Jingu Shrine at present location by an oracle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She succeeded Toyosukiiribime no Mikoto, the daughter of the tenth Emperor, Sujin, as the &apos;Mitsueshiro&apos;, a kind of prophet or oracle of the goddess Amaterasu Omikami, and traveled from Yamato Province, through Iga Province, Omi Province, Mino Province, and Owari Province, arriving in Ise Province, where she is said to have received an oracle to build Ise Jingu Shrine at its present location.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;after&quot;&quot;Princess&quot;→&quot;the daughter&quot;Added &quot;the&quot; or yorishiro, which is an object receiving god&apos;s will&apos; of&quot;→&quot;a kind of prophet or oracle of the goddess&quot;&quot;went through&quot;→&quot;traveled from&quot;Added &quot;through&quot;, &quot;and&quot;&quot;and entered&quot;→&quot;arriving in&quot;&quot;and&quot;→&quot;where she&quot;&quot;erected Ise Jingu Shrine at present location by an oracle&quot;→&quot;received an oracle to build Ise Jingu Shrine at its present location&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She succeeded Toyosukiiribime no Mikoto, the daughter of the tenth Empero, Sujin, as the &apos;Mitsueshiro,&apos; a kind of prophet or oracle of the goddess Amaterasu Omikami, and traveled from Yamato Province, through Iga Province, Omi Province, Mino Province, and Owari Province, arriving in Ise Province, where she is said to have received an oracle to build Ise Jingu Shrine at its present location.</e>
<cmt>,削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>倭姫命が伊勢神宮を建立するまでに八咫鏡を順次奉納した場所は元伊勢と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The locations where Yamatohime no Mikoto dedicated Yata no Kagami (sacred mirror) from place to place until she erected Ise Jingu Shrine are called Moto Ise.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The locations where Yamatohime no Mikoto dedicated the sacred mirror, Yata no Kagami, before building Ise Jingu Shrine are called Moto Ise.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;sacred mirror&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;Deleted bracketsDeleted &quot;from place to place&quot;&quot;until she erected&quot;→&quot;before building&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The locations where Yamatohime no Mikoto dedicated the sacred mirror, Yata no Kagami, before building Ise Jingu Shrine are called Moto Ise.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>後に、蛮族の討伐に東へ向かう日本武尊に天叢雲剣を与えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later granted Ama no Murakumo no Tsurugi Sword to Yamato Takeru no Mikoto, who was going east to subjugate savage tribe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, she presented the sacred sword, Ama no Murakumo no Tsurugi, to Yamato Takeru no Mikoto, who was going east to subjugate barbarian tribes.</e>
<cmt>Added comma&quot;granted&quot;→&quot;presented&quot;Added &quot;the sacred sword&quot;&quot;savage&quot;→&quot;barbarian&quot;Mnade &quot;tribe&quot; plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, she presented the sacred sword, Ama no Murakumo no Tsurugi, to Yamato Takeru no Mikoto, who was going east to subjugate barbarian tribes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>倭姫命への神託</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oracle to Yamatohime no Mikoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oracle to Yamatohime no Mikoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oracle to Yamatohime no Mikoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>伊勢神宮を建立したときの天照大神から倭姫命への神託は、『日本書紀』垂仁天皇25年春3月丁亥朔丙申条では「是神風伊勢國 則常世之浪重浪歸國也 傍國可怜國也 欲居是國」、『倭姫命世記』では「是神風伊勢國 即常世之浪重浪皈國也 傍國可怜國也 欲居是國」であり、神風（かむかぜ）の伊勢の国は常世の波の敷浪の帰（よ）する国、方国（かたくに）の美まし国なり。この国におらんと欲（おも）ふ　と伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The oracle which was given from Amaterasu Omikami to Yamatohime no Mikoto at time of erecting Ise Jingu Shrine was &apos;是神風伊勢國 則常世之浪重浪歸國也 傍國可怜國也 欲居是國&apos; in article of day of Hinotoi Hinoesaru of March in the spring of twenty-fifth year of Emperor Suinin in &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; and &apos;是神風伊勢國 即常世之浪重浪皈國也 傍國可怜國也 欲居是國&apos; in &quot;Yamatohime no Mikoto Seiki&quot; (articles about Ancient Japan), which both mean Ise Province, where Kamukaze (divine wind) is blowing, is a place where wave of the whole world gathers, and is a beautiful province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The oracle which Yamatohime no Mikoto received from Amaterasu Omikami at time of erecting Ise Jingu Shrine was recorded as &apos;是神風伊勢國 則常世之浪重浪歸國也 傍國可怜國也 欲居是國&apos; in the article from the day of Hinotoi Hinoesaru of the third month in the spring of the twenty-fifth year of Emperor Suinin&apos;s reign in the &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; and as &apos;是神風伊勢國 即常世之浪重浪皈國也 傍國可怜國也 欲居是國&apos; in &quot;Yamatohime no Mikoto Seiki&quot; (Chronicles of Yamatohime no Mikoto), both of which mean &apos;Ise Province, where the Kamukaze (divine wind) blows, and lapped by waves from all the world, is a beautiful province.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence, though don&apos;t think the kanji are necessary for English speakers, just a translation would suffice, especially as the quotes are only a couple of characters different&quot;March&quot;→&quot;third month&quot;- not sure &quot;3月&quot; corresponds exactly to March- not certain about&quot;亥朔丙申&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is written in both the Nihon Shoki and &quot;Yamatohime no Mikoto Seiki&quot; (Chronicles of Yamatohime no Mikoto) that when Ise Shrine was erected, Yamatohime no Mikoto was given an oracle by the great sun goddess Amaterasu Omikami that Ise Province, where divine winds blow, is a beautiful place where waves from all around the world lap on its shore and that the goddess will stay in this province forever.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。セル１５をセル１４に統合しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>邪馬台国の卑弥呼</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Himiko of Yamatai-koku Kingdom</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Himiko of Yamatai-koku</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;Kingdom&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Himiko of Yamatai-koku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>倭姫命は、『三国志』魏志倭人伝にでてくる邪馬台国の畿内説では「卑弥呼」とされることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamatohime no Mikoto is sometimes regarded as &apos;Himiko&apos; in theory which assumes that Yamatai-koku Kingdom was located in Kinai Region (provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara), stated in &quot;Sangokushi&quot; Gishi Wajin Den (the first written record of Japan&apos;s commerce).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamatohime no Mikoto is sometimes associated with &apos;Himiko,&apos; who according to the &apos;Records of Wei, Accounts of the People of Wa&apos;, a part of the Chinese &apos;Records of Three Kingdoms&apos;, was the queen of Yamatai-kokuin, near Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamatohime no Mikoto is sometimes associated with &apos;Himiko,&apos; who according to the &apos;Records of Wei, Accounts of the People of Wa&apos;, a part of the Chinese &quot;Records of Three Kingdoms,&quot; was the queen of Yamatai-kokuin, near Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>原文の『』に合わせ&apos;を&quot;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>これは、倭姫命が神を祀る役目を負っていたことに由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason for this is because Yamatohime no Mikoto had the role to worship and pray for god.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This association is based on both Yamatohime no Mikoto and Himiko were responsible for praying to the gods.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence and added &quot;and Himiko&quot; for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because Yamatohime no Mikoto served as a priest who performed rituals for gods.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>倭姫宮</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamatohime no Miya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamatohime no Miya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamatohime no Miya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>伊勢神宮鎮座後も倭姫命を祭る神社は存在しなかったが、大正にはいり神宮司庁と地元伊勢市から倭姫命を祭る神社を創建する運動を生じ、1920年1月4日に皇大神宮別宮として倭姫宮の創立が許可、1922年11月5日内宮と外宮の中間である倉田山に鎮座した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was no shrine dedicated to Yamatohime no Mikoto even after she was enshrined at Ise Jingu Shrine, but after entering Taisho period, a movement to erect shrine to enshrine Yamatohime no Mikoto arose from Jingu Shicho (organization to manage office works of Ise Jingu Shrine) and local Ise City, and on January 4, 1920, permission was given to erect Yamatohime no Miya as Kotai Jingu betsugu (branch shrine of Kotai Jingu), and on November 5, 1922, she was enshrined at Kurata-yama Mountain, located in the middle of Naiku (inner shrine) and Geku (outer shrine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even though Yamatohime no Mikoto was enshrined at Ise Jingu Shrine, there was no shrine specifically dedicated to her until the Taisho period, when a movement to erect a shrine to Yamatohime no Mikoto was proposed by Jingu Shicho (the administrative branch of Ise Jingu Shrine) and Ise City, with permission to build Yamatohime no Miya as a branch shrine of Kotai Jingu being granted on January 4, 1920, and on November 5, 1922, she was enshrined at Kurata-yama Mountain, located between the Naiku (inner shrine) and the Geku (outer shrine).</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after Yamatohime no Mikoto was enshrined at Ise-jingu Shrine, there was no chapel specifically dedicated to her until the Taisho period, when a proposal was made by the administrative branch of Ise-jingu Shrine and Ise City to erect a separate shrine for Yamatohime no Mikoto; the proposal was approved by the government on January 4, 1920 and on November 5, 1922, she was enshrined in Yamatohime no Miya Chapel on Mt. Kurata located between the inner shrine and the outer shrine.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>伊勢神宮を構成する神社と施設としては唯一近代以降の創立である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the only shrine and institution established as the component of Ise Jingu Shrine after the early modern times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the only part of Ise Jingu Shrine established in the modern era.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the only part of Ise-jingu Shrine established in the modern era.</e>
<cmt>Ise Jingu Shrine→Ise-jingu Shrine</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>宇治山田陵墓参考地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ujiyamada referable mausoleum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujiyamada mausoleum reference site</e>
<cmt>&quot;referable&quot;→&quot;reference site&quot; and moved</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujiyamada mausoleum reference site</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="17">
<j>伊勢市倭町に倭姫命を埋葬したと伝えられる古墳があり、伝承に基づき、1928年10月宮内省より陵墓参考地に指定、現在宮内庁により宇治山田陵墓参考地として整備、管理されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a tumulus which is said to have buried Yamatohime no Mikoto in Yamato Town, Ise City, and based on the folklore, it was designated as referable mausoleum by Imperial Household Ministry in October 1928, and it is now maintained and managed as Ujiyamada referable mausoleum by the Imperial Household Ministry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a tumulus where Yamatohime no Mikoto is said to buried in Yamato Town, Ise City, and based on tradition, it was designated a &apos;reference site&apos; (a term used for tombs believed to be of imperial family members but whose contents are unverifiable) by the Imperial Household Ministry in October 1928, and it is now maintained and managed as Ujiyamada mausoleum reference site by the Imperial Household Agency.</e>
<cmt>&quot;which is said to have buried Yamatohime no Mikoto&quot;→&quot;where Yamatohime no Mikoto is said to buried&quot;&quot;the folklore&quot;→&quot;tradition&quot;&quot;as referable mausoleum&quot;→&quot;a &apos;reference site&apos;&quot;Added &quot;(a term used for tombs believed to be of imperial family members but whose contents are unverifiable)&quot;- not sure if there&apos;s an official translation for &quot;陵墓参考地&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;referable&quot;→&quot;reference site&quot; and moved&quot;Ministry&quot;→&quot;Agency&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a tumulus where Yamatohime no Mikoto is said to buried in Yamato Town, Ise City, and based on tradition, it was designated a reference site (a term used for tombs believed to be of imperial family members but whose contents are unverifiable) by the Imperial Household Ministry in October 1928, and it is now maintained and managed as Ujiyamada mausoleum reference site by the Imperial Household Agency.</e>
<cmt>原文に「」がないので&apos;　&apos;を削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 翰林硯士(id:99377), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Masyu(id:31065), Izayohi(id:13095), Nnh(id:474), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), 123456(id:67803), N yotarou(id:60870), 代言人(id:33675), Stanislaus(id:1806), 水蜻蛉(id:71993), Nekosuki600(id:21263), Ha～Ha(id:36403), El bot de la dieta(id:181702), Excavator(id:25917), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>