<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>皇位継承</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Succession to the Imperial Throne</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Succession to the Imperial Throne</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Succession to the Imperial Throne</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>皇位継承（こういけいしょう）とは、一般的に皇位（天皇の位）を皇太子もしくは皇位継承者に譲ることである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Succession to the Imperial Throne generally means to pass the Imperial Throne (the position of the Emperor) to the Crown Prince or the successor of the Imperial Throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Succession to the Imperial Throne generally means to pass the Imperial Throne (the position of the Emperor) to the Crown Prince or the successor of the Imperial Throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Succession to the Imperial Throne generally means to pass the Imperial Throne (the position of the Emperor) to the Crown Prince or the successor of the Imperial Throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>諸外国における国王・皇帝の地位を継承を意味する王位継承あるいは帝位継承とほぼ同義語である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The meaning is almost the same as &apos;the succession to the Throne&apos; to pass the position of Emperor, or &apos;the succession to the Emperor&apos;, which are the words used in overseas countries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The meaning is almost the same as &apos;the succession to the Throne&apos; to pass the position of Emperor, or &apos;the succession to the Emperor,&apos; which are the words used in overseas countries.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, dangling apostrophe</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The meaning is almost the same as &apos;the succession to the Throne&apos; to pass the position of Emperor, or &apos;the succession to the Emperor,&apos; which are the words used in overseas countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>明治以後の歴代天皇については即位の礼を参照</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Please refer to the enthronement ceremony for the details of the successive emperors after the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Please refer to the enthronement ceremony for the details on the successive emperors after the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Please refer to the Enthronement Ceremony for the details on the successive emperors after the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>enthronement ceremony語頭大文字に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>天皇の皇位継承は、大日本帝国憲法及び日本国憲法で明文規定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial succession to the Emperor was regulated in the Constitution of the Empire of Japan and the Constitution of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial succession to Emperor was regulated in the Constitution of the Empire of Japan and the Constitution of Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial succession to Emperor was regulated in the Constitution of the Empire of Japan and the Constitution of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>日本国憲法では「皇位は、世襲のものであつて、國會（国会）の議決した皇室典範の定めるところにより、これを繼承（継承）する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the Constitution of Japan, it is said &apos;the Imperial succession is hereditary and it is under the law of the Imperial Family Law which was decided by the Diet, it will be succeeded (Imperial succession) according to the Law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the Constitution of Japan, Imperial succession is hereditary and it comes under Imperial Family Law which was decided upon by the Diet, Imperial succession will be conducted according to the Law.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the Constitution of Japan, Imperial succession is hereditary and it comes under Imperial Family Law which was decided upon by the Diet, Imperial succession will be conducted according to the Law.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>（日本国憲法第2条）」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(&apos;it was mention in the Clause 2 of the Constitution of Japan&apos;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(&apos;as mentioned in Clause 2 of the Constitution of Japan&apos;)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(&apos;as mentioned in Clause 2 of the Constitution of Japan&apos;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その皇室典範には「皇位は、皇統に屬（属）する男系の男子が、これを繼承（継承）する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Imperial Family Law, it is said &apos;Imperial Throne should be succeeded (succession) by the male members of the Imperial family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under Imperial Family Law, the &apos;Imperial Throne should be succeeded (succession) by male members of the Imperial family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under Imperial Family Law, the &apos;Imperial Throne should be succeeded (succession) by male members of the Imperial family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>（s皇室典範a1）」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(According to Clause 1 of the Imperial Family Law)</e>
<cmt>（s皇室典範a1）」とある →Clause 1 of the Imperial Family Lawとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(According to Clause 1 of the Imperial Family Law)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(According to Clause 1 of the Imperial Family Law)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>大日本帝国憲法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Constitution of the Empire of Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Constitution of the Empire of Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Constitution of the Empire of Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>皇位の継承について大日本帝国憲法第2条で「皇位ハ皇室典範ノ定ムル所ニ依リ皇男子孫之ヲ繼承ス」とあり、旧皇室典範第一章に皇位継承順位、第二章に践祚即位について規定されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In terms of the Imperial succession, it is mentioned in the Clause 2 of The Constitution of the Empire of Japan, &apos;Under the law of the Imperial Family Law, male members or their grandchildren of the Imperial family would succeed the throne&apos;, there was the order of the Imperial succession in the first chapter of the former Imperial Family Law, and in the second chapter of the same Law, there was a description about the accession to the throne.</e>
<cmt>皇位ハ皇室典範ノ定ムル所ニ依リ皇男子孫之ヲ繼承ス」→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In terms of Imperial succession, it is mentioned in Clause 2 of The Constitution of the Empire of Japan, &apos;Under Imperial Family Law, male members, or their grandchildren, of the Imperial family would succeed the throne,&apos; there was the order of Imperial succession in the first chapter of the former Imperial Family Law, and in the second chapter of the same Law, there was a description about accession to the throne.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In terms of Imperial succession, it is mentioned in Clause 2 of The Constitution of the Empire of Japan, &apos;Under Imperial Family Law, male members, or their grandchildren, of the Imperial family would succeed the throne,&apos; there was the order of Imperial succession in the first chapter of the former Imperial Family Law, and in the second chapter of the same Law, there was a description about accession to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>皇室典範第1条では「大日本國皇位ハ祖宗ノ皇統ニシテ男系ノ男子之ヲ繼承ス」と記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the first chapter of the former Imperial Family Law, it is said &apos;the Imperial Throne of the Empire of Japan should be succeeded by the male Imperial family member who are in the line of successive Emperor.</e>
<cmt>「大日本國皇位ハ祖宗ノ皇統ニシテ男系ノ男子之ヲ繼承ス」→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the first chapter of the former Imperial Family Law, it says &apos;the Imperial Throne of the Empire of Japan should be succeeded by male Imperial family members who are in the line of the successive Emperor.</e>
<cmt>grammer</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the first chapter of the former Imperial Family Law, it says &apos;the Imperial Throne of the Empire of Japan should be succeeded by male Imperial Family members who are in the line of the successive Emperor.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>皇位継承の儀式については、皇室典範を根拠とし皇室典範に属する法体系、いわゆる「宮務法」として公布された皇室令のひとつ、登極令（明治42年皇室令第1号）及び同附式によって細かく定められていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In terms of the ceremony of the Imperial succession, there was a detailed regulation in the Regulations Governing the Accession to the Throne (No.1 of Imperial Family Regulation in Meiji 42) or 同附式 which was issued as one of the Imperial Family Regulation, what it is called &apos;宮務法&apos;, while the style of these regulations belongs to Imperial Family Law based on the Imperial Family Law.</e>
<cmt>同附式 →読み方、定訳不明。宮務法 →読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In terms of the ceremony for Imperial succession, there were details in the Regulations Governing the Accession to the Throne (No.1 of Imperial Family Regulation in Meiji 42) or 同附式 which was issued as one of the Imperial Family Regulations, what it is called &apos;宮務法,&apos; while the form of these regulations belong to Imperial Family Law based on the Imperial Family Law.</e>
<cmt>grammar, &quot;style&quot; replaced with &quot;form&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In terms of the ceremony for Imperial succession, there were details in the Regulations Governing the Accession to the Throne (No.1 of Imperial Family Regulation in Meiji 42 (1909)) or 同附式 which was issued as one of the Imperial Family Regulations, what it is called &apos;宮務法,&apos; while the form of these regulations belong to Imperial Family Law based on the Imperial Family Law.</e>
<cmt>(1909)補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>なお、日本国憲法の施行に伴い、旧皇室典範及び皇室令は1947年（昭和22年）5月2日に廃止されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way after the Constitution of Japan was issued, the former Imperial Family Law and the Imperial Family Regulation was abolished on May 2, 1947.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Constitution of Japan was issued, the former Imperial Family Law and the Imperial Family Regulations were abolished on May 2, 1947.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Constitution of Japan was issued, the former Imperial Family Law and the Imperial Family Regulations were abolished on May 2, 1947.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>日本国憲法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Constitution of Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Constitution of Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Constitution of Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>皇位の継承について日本国憲法第2条で「皇位は、世襲のものであつて、国会の議決した皇室典範の定めるところにより、これを繼承する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In terms of the Imperial Succession, it is said in the Clause 2 of the Constitution of Japan, &apos;the Imperial Throne is hereditary and the Throne will be succeeded under the Law of Imperial Family Law decided by the Diet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In terms of Imperial Succession, it says in Clause 2 of the Constitution of Japan, &apos;the Imperial Throne is hereditary and the Throne will be succeeded under the Imperial Family Law decided by the Diet.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In terms of Imperial Succession, it says in Clause 2 of the Constitution of Japan, &apos;the Imperial Throne is hereditary and the Throne will be succeeded under the Imperial Family Law decided by the Diet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>」とあり、皇室典範第一章に皇位継承順位及び即位について、第四章に即位の礼について規定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a description in the first chapter of the Imperial Family Law of the order of the Imperial succession and the accession to the throne, in the fourth captor it was mentioned about the enthronement ceremony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a description in the first chapter of the Imperial Family Law of the order of Imperial succession and the accession to the throne, in the fourth chaptor it discusses the enthronement ceremony.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a description in the first chapter of the Imperial Family Law of the order of Imperial succession and the accession to the throne, in the fourth chapter it discusses the enthronement ceremony.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>皇室典範第1条では「皇位は、皇統に属する男系の男子が、これを継承する。」と記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Clause 1 of the Imperial Family Law, it is said &apos;The Imperial Throne should be succeeded by the male member of the Imperial family.&apos;</e>
<cmt>セル29，30を一文としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Clause 1 of Imperial Family Law, it says &apos;The Imperial Throne should be succeeded by a male member of the Imperial family.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Clause 1 of Imperial Family Law, it says &apos;The Imperial Throne should be succeeded by a male member of the Imperial family.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>皇位継承の儀式については、登極令（明治42年皇室令第1号）の廃止に伴い法律上の規定が存在しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In terms of the ceremony of the Imperial succession, there is no Lawful regulation after the abolishment of the Regulations Governing the Accession to the Throne. (No.1 of Imperial Family Regulation in Meiji 42)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In terms of the ceremony for Imperial succession, there are no Lawful regulations, after the abolishment of the Regulations Governing the Accession to the Throne. (No.1 of Imperial Family Regulation in Meiji 42)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In terms of the ceremony for Imperial succession, there are no Lawful regulations, after the abolishment of the Regulations Governing the Accession to the Throne. (No.1 of Imperial Family Regulation in Meiji 42)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また皇室典範には即位の礼を行う定めがあるにも拘らず、内容についての具体的な規定はされていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also there is no detailed regulation about the content of the enthronement ceremony in the Imperial Family Law, although the ceremony is compulsory under the Law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also there are no detailed regulations about the content of the enthronement ceremony in Imperial Family Law, although the ceremony is compulsory under the Law.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also there are no detailed regulations about the content of the enthronement ceremony in Imperial Family Law, although the ceremony is compulsory under the Law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>そのため、昭和天皇崩御に伴う皇太子明仁親王の皇位継承儀式、及び即位の礼は、廃止された旧登極令及び同附式を踏襲する形で執り行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the Succession ceremony and the enthronement ceremony of Crown Prince, Imperial Prince Akihito to succeed tho the throne after Emperor Showa died, was arranged to follow the law of former Regulations Governing the Accession to the Throne and 同附式.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the Succession ceremony and the enthronement ceremony of Crown Prince, Imperial Prince Akihito to succeed tho the throne after Emperor Showa died, was arranged to follow the law of former Regulations Governing the Accession to the Throne and 同附式.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the Succession ceremony and the enthronement ceremony of Crown Prince, Imperial Prince Akihito to succeed to the throne after Emperor Showa died, was arranged to follow the law of former Regulations Governing the Accession to the Throne and 同附式.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>以下の皇位継承儀式は、皇太子明仁親王（今上天皇）の皇位継承に際するものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following detailes of the ceremony of Imperial succession was the one for Crown Prince, Imperial Prince Akihito. (the present Emperor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following details of the ceremony for Imperial succession were taken from Crown Prince, Imperial Prince Akihito&apos;s enthronement ceremony (the present Emperor).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following details of the ceremony for Imperial succession were taken from Crown Prince, Imperial Prince Akihito&apos;s enthronement ceremony (the present Emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>剣璽等承継の儀</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ceremony of succession of the Sacred Sword, Jewel and other sort.</e>
<cmt>剣璽等承継の儀→the Ceremony of succession of the Sacred Sword, Jewel etc.[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ceremony of succession of the Sacred Sword, Jewel and other treasures.</e>
<cmt>&quot;other sort&quot; is not understood. Could this mean &quot;sacred treasures&quot;?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ceremony of succession of the Sacred Sword, Jewel and other treasures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>剣璽等承継の儀とは、旧登極令（明治42年皇室令第1号）附式の、第一編　践祚ノ式にある剣璽渡御ノ儀（けんじとぎょのぎ）にあたる国事行為たる儀式である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above ceremony is equivalent to the ceremony called &apos;Kenji to gyo no gi&apos; (the Ceremony of succession of the Sacred Sword, Jewel and other sort.), Volume 1 of the ceremony of accession to the throne of former Regulations Governing the Accession to the Throne (No.1 of Imperial Family Regulation in Meiji 42) and 附式, and it is the ceremony of the emperor&apos;s constitutional functions.</e>
<cmt>附式→[定訳不明] 同附式?</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above ceremony is equivalent to the ceremony called &apos;Kenji to gyo no gi&apos; (the Ceremony of succession of the Sacred Sword, Jewel, and other treasures.), Volume 1 of the ceremony for accession to the throne of former Regulations Governing the Accession to the Throne (No.1 of Imperial Family Regulations in Meiji 42) and 附式, and it is the ceremony of the emperor&apos;s constitutional functions.</e>
<cmt>&quot;other sort&quot; is not understood. Could this mean &quot;sacred treasures&quot;?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The above ceremony is equivalent to the ceremony called &apos;Kenji to gyo no gi&apos; (the Ceremony of succession of the Sacred Sword, Jewel, and other treasures.), Volume 1 of the ceremony for accession to the throne of former Regulations Governing the Accession to the Throne (No.1 of Imperial Family Regulations in Meiji 42) and 附式, and it is the ceremony of the emperor&apos;s constitutional functions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>剣とは天叢雲剣を指し、璽は八尺瓊勾玉を示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sword means Ama no murakumo no tsurugi (one of the three sacred treasures), and Ji (the seal of the state) means yasakani no magatama (a large ball, one of the three sacred treasure)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sword means Ama no murakumo no tsurugi (one of the three sacred treasures), and Ji (the seal of state) means yasakani no magatama (a large ball, one of the three sacred treasures).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sword means Ama no murakumo no tsurugi (one of the three sacred treasures), and Ji (the seal of state) means yasakani no magatama (a large ball, one of the three sacred treasures).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="22">
<j>これは皇位の証として伝わる三種の神器のうち、剣と璽を大行天皇（前天皇）から承継するもので、剣については宮中にある天叢雲剣の複製品を用い、神璽は本物とされる八尺瓊勾玉を用いる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the ceremony to succeed the Sword and Ji, which are one of tree sacred treasures passed from generations as a state of the Imperial succession, from the late Emperor (the former Emperor), the replica of the sword, Ama no murakumo no tsurugi, and the sacred jewel which is presumed to be real, yasakani no magatama from the Imperial Palace were used at the ceremony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the ceremony to succeed the Sword and Ji, which are two of three sacred treasures passed from generations as a state of the Imperial succession, from the late Emperor (the former Emperor), the replica of the sword, Ama no murakumo no tsurugi, and the sacred jewel which is presumed to be real, yasakani no magatama from the Imperial Palace were used at the ceremony.</e>
<cmt>spelling, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the ceremony to succeed the Sword and Ji, which are two of three sacred treasures passed from generations as a state of the Imperial succession, from the late Emperor (the former Emperor), the replica of the sword, Ama no murakumo no tsurugi, and the sacred jewel which is presumed to be real, yasakani no magatama from the Imperial Palace were used at the ceremony.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>同時に国璽と御璽の承継も行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, the succession of the seal of state and the Imperial Seal is held as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, the succession of the seal of state and the Imperial Seal are celebrated as well.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, the succession of the seal of state and the Imperial Seal are celebrated as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="24">
<j>1989年（昭和64年）1月7日、昭和天皇崩御に際しては天皇崩御直後、皇居正殿松の間で執り行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Emperor Showa died on January 7, 1989, the ceremony was held in the Main Hall of Matsu (Pine) of the Imperial Palace just after the Emperor died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Emperor Showa died on January 7, 1989, the ceremony was held in the Main Hall of Matsu (Pine) of the Imperial Palace just after the Emperor died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Emperor Showa died on January 7, 1989, the ceremony was held in the Main Hall of Matsu (Pine) of the Imperial Palace just after the Emperor died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>国民代表として内閣総理大臣、最高裁判所長官、衆議院参議院両院議長の行政司法立法の三権の長、全閣僚などが参列した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese Prime Minister, the Chief Justice of the Supreme Court, the Speaker of the House of Representatives, the head of three branches of government-legislative, administrative and judicial of the Speakers of the House of Representatives and the House of Councilors, all the Cabinet ministers attended to the ceremony as the representive of the nation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese Prime Minister, the Chief Justice of the Supreme Court, the Speaker of the House of Representatives, the head of three branches of government-legislature, administrative, and judicial branches, the Speakers of the House of Representatives and the House of Councilors, all the Cabinet ministers attended the ceremony as the representives of the nation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese Prime Minister, the Chief Justice of the Supreme Court, the head of three branches of government-legislature, administrative, and judicial branches, the Speakers of the House of Representatives and the House of Councilors, all the Cabinet ministers attended the ceremony as the representatives of the nation.</e>
<cmt>the Speaker of the House of Representatives, 削除スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>新天皇は宮内庁長官らに先導され皇族を従え松の間に臨場し、参列者に向合う形で正面の席に着き、剣・璽及び国璽・御璽を侍従が新天皇の前にある机に置く短い儀式が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The new Emperor went to the Main Hall of Matsu of the Imperial Palace accompanying other Imperial family members, guided by the Grand Steward of the Imperial Household Agency, he then sat down in the front seat facing the audience who attended the ceremony, there was a short ceremony of a chamberlain putting a sword and Ju and the seal of stateand the Imperial Seal on the desk in front of the new Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The new Emperor went to the Main Hall of Matsu of the Imperial Palace accompanying other Imperial family members, guided by the Grand Steward of the Imperial Household Agency, he then sat down in the front seat facing the audience who attended the ceremony, there was a short ceremony with the chamberlain placing a sword and Ju and the seal of stateand the Imperial Seal on the desk in front of the new Emperor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The new Emperor went to the Main Hall of Matsu of the Imperial Palace accompanying other Imperial Family members, guided by the Grand Steward of the Imperial Household Agency, he then sat down in the front seat facing the audience who attended the ceremony, there was a short ceremony with the chamberlain placing a sword and Ju and the seal of state and the Imperial Seal on the desk in front of the new Emperor.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正改行解除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>皇霊殿神殿に奉告の儀</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ceremony of reporting to the Imperial Ancestor&apos;s Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ceremony of reporting to the Imperial Ancestor&apos;s Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ceremony of reporting to the Imperial Ancestor&apos;s Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="27">
<j>宮中三殿皇霊殿宮中三殿神殿に奉告の儀とは、先祖代々の皇霊を奉る皇霊殿、及び天神地祇を奉る神殿において、新天皇の即位を奉告する儀式である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ceremony of reporting to the Three Shrines in the Imperial Court of the Imperial Ancestor&apos;s Shrine, means to report the enthronement of the new Emperor to the Imperial Ancestor&apos;s Shrine where successive Emperors were enthroned, or the Shrine where the gods of heaven and earth is enthroned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The purpose of the ceremony of reporting to the Three Shrines in the Imperial Court of the Imperial Ancestor&apos;s Shrine, is to report the enthronement of the new Emperor to the Imperial Ancestor&apos;s Shrine where successive Emperors were enthroned, or the Shrine where the gods of heaven and earth are enthroned.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The purpose of the ceremony of reporting to the Three Shrines in the Imperial Court of the Imperial Ancestor&apos;s Shrine, is to report the enthronement of the new Emperor to the Imperial Ancestor&apos;s Shrine where successive Emperors were enthroned, or the Shrine where the gods of heaven and earth are enthroned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>掌典長により宮中三殿で、剣璽等承継の儀が執り行われていた頃に執り行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a ceremony organized by the Chief Ritualist to pass the Sword and Jewell in the Three Shrines in the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a ceremony organized by the Chief Ritualist to pass the Sword and Jewel to the Three Shrines in the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>spelling, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a ceremony organized by the Chief Ritualist to pass the Sword and Jewel to the Three Shrines in the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>賢所の儀</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ceremony in the Sanctuary in the Imperial Palace</e>
<cmt>賢所の儀→the Ceremony in the Sanctuary in the Imperial Palace[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ceremony in the Sanctuary of the Imperial Palace</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ceremony in the Sanctuary of the Imperial Palace</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>宮中三殿賢所（けんしょ・かしこどころ）に御神体として奉られている神器、八咫鏡の承継儀式である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a ceremony to pass the sacred treasures, Yata no kagami (the sacred mirror) which is enshrined as God at Kensho, Kashikodokoro. (one of the palace in the Three Shrines in the Imperial Court)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a ceremony to pass the sacred treasures, Yata no kagami (the sacred mirror) which is enshrined as God at Kensho, Kashikodokoro. (one of the palaces in the Three Shrines in the Imperial Court)</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a ceremony to pass the sacred treasures, Yata no kagami (the sacred mirror) which is enshrined as God at Kensho, Kashikodokoro (one of the palaces in the Three Shrines in the Imperial Court).</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>1989年（平成元年）1月9日、昭和天皇崩御から2日後に掌典長により宮中三殿で執り行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ceremony was held by the Chief Ritualist in the Three Shrines in the Imperial Court on January 9, 1989, two days after the Emperor Showa died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ceremony was held by the Chief Ritualist in the Three Shrines in the Imperial Court on January 9, 1989, two days after Emperor Showa died.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ceremony was held by the Chief Ritualist in the Three Shrines in the Imperial Court on January 9, 1989, two days after Emperor Showa died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>八咫鏡は宮中に鎮座している複製品である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The replica of Yata no kagami (the sacred mirror) was used, which was enshrined in the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A replica of Yata no kagami (the sacred mirror) was used, and was enshrined in the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A replica of Yata no kagami (the sacred mirror) was used, and was enshrined in the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="32">
<j>この儀式によって、皇位の証である三種の神器を継承した天皇は正統な皇位継承者となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this ceremony is held, the successive Emperor who was passed the three sacred treasures as a proof of the Imperial succession, became officially new Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this ceremony is held, the successive Emperor who has passed the three sacred treasures as a proof of Imperial succession, officially became the new Emperor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this ceremony is held, the successive Emperor who has passed the three sacred treasures as a proof of Imperial succession, officially became the new Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>なお、過去に継承の儀を執り行うことが出来なかったため、正統な皇位継承者にはなりえなかった天皇が存在する（南北朝時代分裂期の北朝の天皇など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way there were some Emperors exist who were not being able to become Emperors officially since they did not have the successive ceremony in the past. (For example, there were Emperors of Northern Dynasty during the spilt of the political power between the Southern and the Northern Dynasties)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the way there were some Emperors that existed who were not able to officially become Emperors since they did not go through the successive ceremony in the past. (For example, Emperors of Northern Dynasty during the spilt of the political power between the Southern and the Northern Dynasties)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the way there were some Emperors that existed who were not able to officially become Emperors since they did not go through the successive ceremony in the past. (For example, Emperors of Northern Court during the spilt of the political power of the period of the Northern and Southern Courts)</e>
<cmt>北朝表記南北朝時代表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>即位後朝見の儀</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">he Ceremony of Audience with the Emperor afther the enthronment</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Audience Ceremony with the Emperor after the enthronment</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Audience Ceremony with the Emperor after the enthronement</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>新天皇が初めて内閣総理大臣らに言葉を述べる国事行為たる儀式である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the ceremony as the emperor&apos;s constitutional functions, and the new emperor gives speech to Japanese Prime Ministers and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a ceremony about the emperor&apos;s constitutional functions, and the new emperor makes a speech to Japanese Prime Ministers and others.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a ceremony about the emperor&apos;s constitutional functions, and the new emperor makes a speech to Japanese Prime Ministers and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>1989年（平成元年）1月9日に皇居正殿松の間で365人の参列者のもと執り行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ceremony was held on January 9, 1989 in the Main Hall of Matsu(Pine) of the Imperial Palace with the participants of three hundred and sixty five people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ceremony was held on January 9, 1989 in the Main Hall of Matsu (Pine) of the Imperial Palace with three hundred and sixty five people participating.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ceremony was held on January 9, 1989 in the Main Hall of Matsu (Pine) of the Imperial Palace with 365 people participating.</e>
<cmt>数字表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>大嘗宮の儀</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ceremony in Daijo-gu Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ceremony in Daijo-gu Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ceremony in Daijo-gu Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="36">
<j>1年の諒闇、喪も明けて最初の新嘗祭（にいなめさい）たる大嘗祭（だいじょうさい）が即位の翌年に執り行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the court mourning for the late emperor, (the period of mourning is over), this ceremony of Daijo-gu Shrine is held on the following year of the enthronement, also known as the first Harvest Festival.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After court mourning for the late emperor, (the period of mourning is over), this ceremony of the Daijo-gu Shrine is held on the following year of the enthronement, also known as the first Harvest Festival.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After one year court mourning for the late emperor, (the period of mourning is over), this ceremony of the Daijo-gu Shrine is held on the following year of the enthronement, also known as the first Harvest Festival.</e>
<cmt>one year補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>11月卯の日（4番目の日）に4日間に渡って執り行われ、皇位継承に伴う儀式はこれをもって最後とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the fourth day of November, this ceremony is held for four days, this is the last ceremony related to the Imperial succession.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the fourth day of November, this ceremony is held for four days, this is the last ceremony related to Imperial succession.</e>
<cmt>grammar &quot;the&quot; deleted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the fourth day of November, this ceremony is held for four days, this is the last ceremony related to Imperial succession.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>1990年（平成2年）11月23日に大嘗宮の儀が執り行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 23, 1990, the Ceremony in Daijo-gu Shrine was held.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 23, 1990, the Ceremony in Daijo-gu Shrine was held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 23, 1990, the Ceremony in Daijo-gu Shrine was held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="39">
<j>なお、継承された神器（天叢雲剣及び八咫鏡）は複製品であるので、時機を見て本物が奉られている伊勢神宮と熱田神宮へ即位奉告を行うことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way, since the replicas were used for sacred treasure (Ama no murakumo no tsurugi and Yata no kagami (the sacred mirror)), the enthronement of the new emperor will be reported to Ise-jingu Shrine and Atsuta-jingu Shrine where the real sacred treasures were enthroned accordingly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since replicas were used for sacred treasure (Ama no murakumo no tsurugi and Yata no kagami (the sacred mirror)), the enthronement of the new emperor will be reported to Ise-jingu Shrine and Atsuta-jingu Shrine where the real sacred treasures are enthroned.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since replicas were used for sacred treasure (Ama no murakumo no tsurugi and Yata no kagami (the sacred mirror)), the enthronement of the new emperor will be reported to Ise-jingu Shrine and Atsuta-jingu Shrine where the real sacred treasures are enthroned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>特に皇祖神である天照大神の奉られている伊勢神宮への奉告は早期に執り行われる事になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially the report to Ise-jinju Shrine should be completed in early stage, where 皇祖神 (the Goddess who is the Founder of the Imperial Family), Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess) was enshrined.</e>
<cmt>皇祖神→the Goddess who is the Founder of the Imperial Family[読み方、定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially the report to Ise-jinju Shrine should be completed at an early stage, where 皇祖神 (the Goddess who is the Founder of the Imperial Family), Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess) is enshrined.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially the report to Ise-jinju Shrine should be completed at an early stage, where Kososhin (the Goddess who is the Founder of the Imperial Family), Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess) is enshrined.</e>
<cmt>皇祖神→Kososhin</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>弥生期～飛鳥期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The period between the Yayoi period and the Asuka period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The period between the Yayoi period and the Asuka period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The period between the Yayoi period and the Asuka period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="41">
<j>日本では古代から皇位継承（王位継承）に関する問題が生じていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan there was an issue regarding the Imperial succession (the succession to the throne) from the ancient time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan there was an issue regarding Imperial succession (the succession to the throne) from the ancient times.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan there was an issue regarding Imperial succession (the succession to the throne) from the ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>弥生時代後期の2世紀後半、倭国王位の継承をめぐって倭国大乱が起こり、卑弥呼が倭国王となることで争乱が終息した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the latter second century during the late Yayoi period, there was a large scale of fighting in Japan due to the succession to the throne of Japan, the fighting ended after Himiko was decided to become the king of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the latter second century, during the late Yayoi period, there was large scale fighting in Japan due to the succession to the throne of Japan, the fighting ended after Himiko was decided to become the Queen of Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar, Himiko was female so, I believe she should be addressed as &quot;Queen&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the latter second century, during the late Yayoi period, there was large scale fighting in Japan due to the succession to the throne of Japan, the fighting ended after Himiko was decided to become the Queen of Japan.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>また卑弥呼の没後、男王が立ったが再度争乱が起こり、卑弥呼の宗女台与が王位について争乱は収まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Himiko died, although the new male king succeeded to the throne, there was a fighting happened again, after Toyo, a woman from the same family as Himiko, was decided to become King, the fighting finished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Himiko died, although a new male king succeeded to the throne, fighting broke out again, after Toyo, a woman from the same family as Himiko, was decided to become Queen, the fighting ended.</e>
<cmt>grammar, gender</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Himiko died, although a new male king succeeded to the throne, fighting broke out again, after Toyo, a woman from the same family as Himiko, was decided to become Queen, the fighting ended.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="44">
<j>古墳時代の5世紀にも王位継承をめぐる数々の紛争の発生が、日本書紀の記載から読みとれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In five century during the Kofun period, there were many dispute happened due to the Imperial succession according to the record of Nihon Shoki. (Chronicles of Japan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In five centuries during the Kofun period, there were many disputes due to Imperial succession according to the record of Nihon Shoki (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In five centuries during the Kofun period, there were many disputes due to Imperial succession according to the record of Nihon Shoki (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>6世紀前半には武烈天皇の死により一旦、倭国王統が断絶しているが、応神天皇の5世の子孫とされる継体天皇が皇位継承した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In early six century, after Emperor Buretsu died, the Imperial line of Japan discontinued, however Emperor Keitai who was believed to be the fifth descendant of Emperor Ojin succeeded to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In early six century, after Emperor Buretsu died, the Imperial line of Japan discontinued, however Emperor Keitai who was believed to be the fifth descendant of Emperor Ojin succeeded to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In early sixth century, after Emperor Buretsu died, the Imperial line of Japan discontinued, however Emperor Keitai who was believed to be the fifth descendant of Emperor Ojin succeeded to the throne.</e>
<cmt>six→sixth</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>実際に5世の子孫だったかには賛否両論あるが、この事例は5世の子孫までは皇位継承権を持ちうる先例となって、その後の皇位断絶に強く意識されることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was theories of approval or disapproval that whether the Emperor Keitai was in fact the descendant of Emperor Ojin or not, but this experience was accepted as an example of letting the descendant up to the fifth generation to succeed to the throne, it was strongly reflected to the discontinuity of the Imperial succession later on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were theories approving and disapproving whether the Emperor Keitai was in fact the descendant of Emperor Ojin or not, but this experience was accepted as an example of allowing descendants, up to five generations, succeed to the throne, it was strongly reflected in the discontinuity of Imperial succession later on.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were theories approving and disapproving whether the Emperor Keitai was in fact the descendant of Emperor Ojin or not, but this experience was accepted as an example of allowing descendants, up to five generations, succeed to the throne, it was strongly reflected in the discontinuity of Imperial succession later on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="47">
<j>古墳時代から飛鳥時代にかけて（6世紀中期～7世紀後期）も、皇位継承の紛争がたびたび生じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Kofun period and Asuka period, (middle of sixth century to later seventh century) there was the dispute often happened due to the issue of the Imperial succession.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Kofun and Asuka periods, (middle of sixth century to later seventh century) disputes often took place due to the issue of the Imperial succession.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Kofun and Asuka periods, (middle of sixth century to later seventh century) disputes often took place due to the issue of the Imperial succession.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>この頃の皇位継承のルールには、兄弟承継、大兄承継、群臣推挙、先帝遺詔（更に近年では即位要件に年齢制限（30歳以上）があったとする説もある）などがあり、これらが複雑にからんで皇位継承が行われていたと推定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a regulation in terms of Imperial succession in those days such as the succession between brothers, the succession in eldest brothers, the nomination from the aides, following the will of the former Emperor and so on, (there was a theory from the recent study that there was age limit up to thirty year old to succeed to the throne, it is presumed after fulfilling those complicated issues, the Imperial succession was decided.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a regulation in terms of Imperial succession in those days such as the succession between brothers, the succession of eldest brothers, being nominated by aides, following the will of aformer Emperor, etc, (there was a theory developed from a recent study that there was an age limit, up to thirty years old, for succeeding to the throne, it is presumed after fulfilling such complicated requirements, Imperial succession was decided.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity and grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a regulation in terms of Imperial succession in those days such as the succession between brothers, the succession of eldest brothers, being nominated by aides, following the will of a former Emperor, etc, (there was a theory developed from a recent study that there was an age limit, up to thirty years old, for succeeding to the throne), it is presumed after fulfilling such complicated requirements, Imperial succession was decided.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除・挿入)補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>継体天皇の後に安閑天皇・宣化天皇が数年間在位して欽明天皇が皇位承継しているが、欽明による皇位簒奪だったとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Emperor Keitai, Emperor Ankan and Emperor Senka succeeded to the throne for a few years followed by Emperor Kinmei, however there was a theory that it was a usurpation of the Imperial succession by Emperor Kinmei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Keitai, Emperor Ankan, and Emperor Senka, succeeded to the throne for a few years followed by Emperor Kinmei, however there is a theory that it was because of usurpation of Imperial succession by Emperor Kinmei.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity and grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Keitai, Emperor Ankan, and Emperor Senka, succeeded to the throne for a few years followed by Emperor Kinmei, however there is a theory that it was because of usurpation of Imperial succession by Emperor Kinmei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>その後、欽明の子孫が皇位継承しているが、その経緯は複雑であり、多くの皇位継承紛争が生じている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that the descendant of the Emperor Kinmei succeeded to the throne, however how it happened was the complicated story, there were many dispute happened due to the Imperial succession.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that the descendant of the Emperor Kinmei succeeded to the throne, however how it happened is a complicated story, because there were many disputes due to the Imperial succession.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity and grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that the descendant of the Emperor Kinmei succeeded to the throne, however how it happened is a complicated story, because there were many disputes due to the Imperial succession.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>皇位継承者の決定が難航したときは、女性天皇が選ばれることもあり、推古天皇、皇極天皇が即位して、他に適当な男子の皇位承継者が現れるまで皇位についた（女帝が選ばれた理由には諸説あり、律令制以前の中継ぎ説を認めないなどの異説が多く存在する）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was some occasion that the female Emperor was chosen when there was an issue to decide who to succeed to the throne, there were Emperor Suiko and Emperor Kogyoku who succeeded to the throne until there was appropriate male successor was found. (There were many theories of the reason why the female Emperors were chosen, some people are against the theory of not accepting the temporally Imperial succession until there was someone appropriate to become Emperor before the government of Ritsuyo codes system.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was some occasion that the female Emperor was chosen when there was an issue to decide who to succeed to the throne, there were Emperor Suiko and Emperor Kogyoku who succeeded to the throne until there was appropriate male successor was found. (There were many theories of the reason why the female Emperors were chosen, some people are against the theory of not accepting the temporally Imperial succession until there was someone appropriate to become Emperor before the government of Ritsuryo codes system.)</e>
<cmt>spell</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was some occasion that the female Emperor was chosen when there was an issue to decide who to succeed to the throne, there were Emperor Suiko and Emperor Kogyoku who succeeded to the throne until there was appropriate male successor was found. (There were many theories of the reason why the female Emperors were chosen, some people are against the theory of not accepting the temporally Imperial succession until there was someone appropriate to become Emperor before the government of Ritsuryo codes system.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="52">
<j>古代の皇位継承において、最大の争いとなったのは、672年の壬申の乱である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The biggest dispute in terms of the Imperial succession in ancient times was the Junshin War in 672.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The biggest dispute, in terms of the Imperial succession in ancient times, was the Junshin War in 672.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The biggest dispute, in terms of the Imperial succession in ancient times, was the Jinshin War in 672.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>天智天皇は直系の大友皇子（弘文天皇）に皇位継承したが、それを不服とする大海人皇子が大規模な叛乱を起こし、弘文天皇を滅ぼして天武天皇となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Tenji passed the Imperial throne to his direct line, Prince Otomo (Emperor Kobun), however Prince Oama, who was against it, caused the large scale of the dispute, and killed Emperor Kobun and became Emperor Tenmu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Tenji passed the Imperial throne to his direct line, Prince Otomo (Emperor Kobun), however, Prince Oama, who was against it, caused a large dispute, and killed Emperor Kobun, and became Emperor Tenmu.</e>
<cmt>revised</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Tenji passed the Imperial throne to his direct line, Prince Otomo (Emperor Kobun), however, Prince Oama, who was against it, caused a large dispute, and killed Emperor Kobun, and became Emperor Tenmu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>天武は、自身以降の皇位承継紛争を防止するため、兄弟承継を廃止し、直系男子が皇位承継するルールを定めようと試みたらしく、草壁皇子を皇太子に立てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Tenmu discontinued the Imperial succession between brothers to stop the dispute due to the Imperial succession after his era, it was said he tried to set up the rule for the male in his direct line to succeed the throne, he let Prince Kusakabe become Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Tenmu discontinued the Imperial succession between brothers to stop disputes due to the Imperial succession after his era, it was said he tried to set up a rule for the male in his direct line to succeed the throne, he allowed Prince Kusakabe become Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Tenmu discontinued the Imperial succession between brothers to stop disputes due to the Imperial succession after his era, it was said he tried to set up a rule for the male in his direct line to succeed the throne, he allowed Prince Kusakabe become Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>だが、政権基盤が固まる前に天武天皇が急逝してしまったために天武の皇后は草壁皇子が大友皇子の二の舞にならないように拙速な皇位継承を避けようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However Emperor Tenmu died suddenly before the establishment of the political base, Emperor Tenmu&apos;s Empress tried to avoid the sudden solution in terms of Imperial succession, as she was concerned about Prince Kusakabe would experience same as Prince Otomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However Emperor Tenmu died suddenly before the establishing a political base, Emperor Tenmu&apos;s Empress tried to avoid the sudden solution in terms of Imperial succession, as she was concerned that Prince Kusakabe would have the same experience as Prince Otomo.</e>
<cmt>revised</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However Emperor Tenmu died suddenly before the establishing a political base, Emperor Tenmu&apos;s Empress tried to avoid the sudden solution in terms of Imperial succession, as she was concerned that Prince Kusakabe would have the same experience as Prince Otomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>だが、その草壁皇子までが急死してしまった為に皇后は皇位承継紛争を防ぐために、自ら中継として皇位につき（持統天皇）、草壁皇子の子である軽皇子（後の文武天皇）を皇太子とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However after Prince Kusakabe, too, died suddenly, the Empress succeeded to the throne temporarily to prevent the dispute due to the Imperial succession (Emperor Jito), she let Prince Kusakabe&apos;s child, Prince Karu (later called Emperor Monmu) to become Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However after Prince Kusakabe, too, died suddenly, the Empress temporarily succeeded to the throne to prevent any dispute due to Imperial succession (Emperor Jito), she let Prince Kusakabe&apos;s child, Prince Karu (later called Emperor Monmu) become Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However after Prince Kusakabe, too, died suddenly, the Empress temporarily succeeded to the throne to prevent any dispute due to Imperial succession (Emperor Jito), she let Prince Kusakabe&apos;s child, Prince Karu (later called Emperor Monmu) become Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>奈良期～平安中期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Between the Nara and the mid-Heian period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Between the Nara and the mid-Heian period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between the Nara and the mid-Heian period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="57">
<j>奈良時代に入った後、文武天皇も皇位継承者である首皇子（後の聖武天皇）が成人する前に没したため、元明天皇と元正天皇の2人の女帝が後継した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the beginning of the Nara period, since Emperor Monmu died before his successor, Prince Obito (later called Emperor Shomu) reached twenty years old, two female Emperors, Emperor Genmei and Emperor Gensho succeeded to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the beginning of the Nara period, since Emperor Monmu died before his successor, Prince Obito (later called Emperor Shomu) reached twenty years old, two female Empresses, Empress Genmei and Empress Gensho, succeeded to the throne.</e>
<cmt>revised for accuracty and clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the beginning of the Nara period, since Emperor Monmu died before his successor, Prince Obito (later called Emperor Shomu) came of age, two Empresses, Empress Genmei and Empress Gensho, succeeded to the throne.</e>
<cmt>reached twenty years old→came of age奈良時代の成人は20歳ではなかったと判断しました。&quot;female Empresses&quot; -&gt; &quot;Empresses&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>聖武天皇は、皇位継承すべき男子を残せず、女性の孝謙天皇が後を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Shomu did not have male successor to succeed to the throne after him, thus female Emperor, Emperor Koken succeeded to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Shomu did not have a male successor to succeed to the throne, thus female Emperor, Emperor Koken succeeded to the throne.</e>
<cmt>revised for gender</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Shomu did not have a male successor to succeed to the throne, thus female Emperor, Empress Koken succeeded to the throne.</e>
<cmt>Emperor→Empress</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>その後、藤原仲麻呂の強い推挙により天武の孫の淳仁天皇が立ったが、藤原仲麻呂の乱に連座して淳仁は廃帝となり、孝謙が再度即位して称徳天皇となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Emperor Tenmu&apos;s grandchild, Emperor Junnin succeeded to the throne after the strong recommendation of FUJIWRA no Nakamaro, however he was involved in the dispute of FUJIWARA no Nakamaro, Emperor Junnin was removed from his position, Emperor Koken enthroned again to become Emperor Shotoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Emperor Tenmu&apos;s grandchild, Emperor Junnin succeeded to the throne upon the strong recommendation of FUJIWRA no Nakamaro, however he was involved in the FUJIWARA no Nakamaro dispute, Emperor Junnin was removed from his position, Empress Koken was enthroned again to become Empress Shotoku.</e>
<cmt>revised, gender,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Emperor Tenmu&apos;s grandchild, Emperor Junnin succeeded to the throne upon the strong recommendation of FUJIWARA no Nakamaro, however he was involved in the FUJIWARA no Nakamaro dispute, Emperor Junnin was removed from his position, Empress Koken was enthroned again to become Empress Shotoku.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>この間、他の皇族が皇位を狙ったがその都度謀叛と見なされ、適当な皇位継承者は不在となってしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During this time, other Imperial members attempted to succeed to the throne, however it was considered as a coup each time, there was no appropriate successor to succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this time, other Imperial members attempted to succeed to the throne, however it was considered as a coup each time, as there was no appropriate successor to succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt>&quot;as&quot; added</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this time, other Imperial members attempted to succeed to the throne, however it was considered as a coup each time, as there was no appropriate successor to succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>そのため、仏教に深く帰依していた称徳は僧道鏡を皇位に付けることを企図した（異説あり）が失敗し、後継を決めないまま称徳は没し、天武皇統が断絶することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to this, Emperor Shotoku, who deeply believed in Buddhism, attempted to let the monk, Dokyo to succeeded to the throne, (there was another theory exist) but failed, Emperor Shotoku died before deciding the successor, the Imperial line of Emperor Tenmu was decided to discontinue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to this, Emperor Shotoku, who deeply believed in Buddhism, attempted to allow the monk, Dokyo to succeeded to the throne, (there was another theory) but he failed, Emperor Shotoku died before deciding the successor, and the Imperial line of Emperor Tenmu was decided to discontinue.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to this, Emperor Shotoku, who deeply believed in Buddhism, attempted to allow the monk, Dokyo to succeeded to the throne, (there was another theory) but he failed, Emperor Shotoku died before deciding the successor, and the Imperial line of Emperor Tenmu was decided to discontinue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>天武から称徳に至るまでの皇位継承のルールは（承継すべき者が未成人などの場合には女帝が中継することもあったが）、原則として直系承継であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a principle rule of the Imperial succession during the period between Emperor Tenmu and Emperor Shotoku was to succeed the throne in direct Imperial line. (There was an example of having female Emperor in case of the appropriate successor was too young to succeed to the throne.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a principle rule of the Imperial succession during the period between Emperor Tenmu and Emperor Shotoku was to succeed the throne from the direct Imperial line. (There was an example of having a female Empress in case of the appropriate successor was too young to succeed to the throne.)</e>
<cmt>gender</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a principle rule of the Imperial succession during the period between Emperor Tenmu and Emperor Shotoku was to succeed the throne from the direct Imperial line. (There was an example of having an Empress in case of the appropriate successor was too young to succeed to the throne.)</e>
<cmt>&quot;female Empress&quot; -&gt; &quot;Empress&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>このルールは、激しい皇位承継紛争を未然に防止して天智皇統の復活を阻止しようとした代わりに、承継候補者を限定してしまったため、却って皇統の断絶（結果的には天智皇統の復活）という結果を招くこととなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although this rule prevented the severe dispute due to the Imperial succession from happening and stopped the Emperor Tenji&apos;s Imperial line to come back, it actually limited the successor of Imperial succession and it caused the discontinuity of the Imperial family line. (As a result of this, Emperor Tenji&apos;s Imperial line came back.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although this rule prevented severe disputes due to Imperial succession and stopped Emperor Tenji&apos;s Imperial line from returning, it actually limited the successors of Imperial succession and caused the discontinuity of the Imperial family line. (As a result of this, Emperor Tenji&apos;s Imperial line was restored.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although this rule prevented severe disputes due to Imperial succession and stopped Emperor Tenji&apos;s Imperial line from returning, it in fact limited the successors of Imperial succession and caused the discontinuity of the Imperial family line. (As a result of this, Emperor Tenji&apos;s Imperial line was restored.)</e>
<cmt>&quot;actually&quot; -&gt; &quot;in fact&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="64">
<j>称徳崩御による皇統断絶の危機に際して大臣らは協議を行い、その結果、天智の孫に当たる年配の光仁天皇が皇位承継することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Emperor Shotoku died, there was an incident of the discontinuity of the Imperial line, the Ministers had the meeting and it was decided for elderly Emperor Konin, who was the grandchild of Emperor Tenji, to succeeded to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Emperor Shotoku died, there was an incident of the discontinuity in the Imperial line, the Ministers had a meeting and it was decided for elderly Emperor Konin, who was the grandchild of Emperor Tenji, to succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Emperor Shotoku died, there was an incident of the discontinuity in the Imperial line, the Ministers had a meeting and it was decided for elderly Emperor Konin, who was the grandchild of Emperor Tenji, to succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>この事例は、臣下の協議による皇位継承の先例となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This became an example of the Imperial succession which was decided in the conference by the subject.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This became an example of Imperial succession decided in a conference.</e>
<cmt>&quot;by the subject&quot; deleted as this is not needed, use of this expression connotates either &quot;subject matter&quot; or can be confused with &quot;subject as defined by common subject or commoner, peasent, etc.)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This became an example of Imperial succession decided in a conference.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>また、この時には2つの点で継体天皇の先例が強く意識されていたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seemed the example of Emperor Keitai was strongly considered in two issues at this time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seemed like the example of Emperor Keitai was strongly considered in two issues at this time.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seemed like the example of Emperor Keitai was strongly considered in two issues at this time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>一つは必ず皇胤である事、もう一つは先代の天皇との婚姻関係を有する（光仁は称徳の異母妹の夫）ことであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One issue was it should be someone from the Imperial family line, another issue was it should be someone who has the maternal relationship to the former Emperor. (Emperor Konin was the husband of Emperor Shotoku&apos;s half younger sister)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One issue was it should be someone from the Imperial family line, another issue was it should be someone who has a maternal relationship to the former Emperor. (Emperor Konin was the husband of Emperor Shotoku&apos;s half younger sister)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One issue was it should be someone from the Imperial family line, another issue was it should be someone who has a maternal relationship to the former Emperor. (Emperor Konin was the husband of Emperor Shotoku&apos;s half younger sister)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>光仁は天武系断絶を教訓として息子の桓武天皇を後継とし、その弟の早良親王を桓武の皇太弟とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After learning the experience of the discontinuity of the Emperor Tenmu&apos;s Imperial line, Emperor Konin appointed his son, Emperor Kanmu as his successor, Kanmu&apos;s younger brother, Imperial Prince Sawara was chosen as the second successor of the Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After learning about the experience of the discontinuity in Emperor Tenmu&apos;s Imperial line, Emperor Konin appointed his son, Emperor Kanmu as his successor, Kanmu&apos;s younger brother, Imperial Prince Sawara was chosen as the second successor of the Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After learning about the experience of the discontinuity in Emperor Tenmu&apos;s Imperial line, Emperor Konin appointed his son, Emperor Kanmu as his successor, Kanmu&apos;s younger brother, Imperial Prince Sawara was chosen as the second successor of the Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>これにより、天智・天武以来の直系皇位継承は放棄され、大兄制が（一時的とは言え）事実上復活したと見ることも可能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to this, the Imperial succession apart from the Imperial line of Emperor Tenji and Emperor Tenmu was not allowed, in another words, it can be said, in fact the Imperial succession between the eldest brothers came back. (even though it was temporally)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to this, Imperial succession, apart from the Imperial line of Emperor Tenji and Emperor Tenmu, was not allowed, in fact Imperial succession between the eldest brothers was restored. (even though it was only temporary)</e>
<cmt>wordiness, punctuation, vocabulary</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to this, direct Imperial succession since Emperor Tenji and Emperor Tenmu, was not allowed, in fact Imperial succession between the eldest brothers was restored (even though it was only temporary).</e>
<cmt>apart from the Imperial line of 削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>だが、早良親王は謀叛の疑い（藤原種継暗殺事件）によりこれを廃し、早良は怒りもあらわに絶食死を遂げる事になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However Imperial Prince Sawara was under the suspicion of treason (the incident of assassinate FUJIWARA no Tanetsugu) and he was not allowed to succeed to the throne, he was furious about the situation and he ended up fasting until he died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However Imperial Prince Sawara was under suspicion of treason (the plot to assassinate FUJIWARA no Tanetsugu) and he was not allowed to succeed to the throne, he was furious about this and he ended up fasting until he died of starvation.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However Imperial Prince Sawara was under suspicion of treason (the plot to assassinate FUJIWARA no Tanetsugu) and he was not allowed to succeed to the throne, he was furious about this and he ended up fasting until he died of starvation.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>この壮絶な早良の死はその後の桓武を苦しめ、崇道天皇の号が贈られたが、桓武に始まる平安朝は長く早良の怨霊に恐れ苦しむこととなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Imperial Prince Sawara died heroically, Emperor Kanmu was scared and suffered from the Prince&apos;s curse for a long time since Emperor Kanmu&apos;s era started as the Heian court, the respective title of Emperor Sudo was given to Imperial Prince Sawara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Imperial Prince Sawara died heroically, Emperor Kanmu was scared and suffered from the Prince&apos;s curse for a long time, since Emperor Kanmu&apos;s era started as the Heian court, the respective title of Emperor Sudo was given to Imperial Prince Sawara.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Imperial Prince Sawara died heroically, Emperor Kanmu was scared and suffered from the Prince&apos;s curse for a long time, since Emperor Kanmu&apos;s era started as the Heian court, the respective title of Emperor Sudo was given to Imperial Prince Sawara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>桓武は多くの皇子をもうけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Kanmu had many Princes and Princesses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Kanmu had many Princes and Princesses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Kanmu had many Princes and Princesses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>桓武の後は、桓武長子の平城天皇が皇位継承し、その遺志に従う形で病弱であった平城の次にはその弟の神野親王（後の嵯峨天皇）が皇太弟に立った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Emperor Kanmu&apos;s era, his eldest son, Emperor Heizei succeeded to the throne, his younger brother, Imperial Prince Kamino (later called Emperor Gosaga) became the second successor to the Crown Prince by following Emperor&apos;s will after the Emperor Heizei, who was born weak.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Emperor Kanmu&apos;s era, his eldest son, Emperor Heizei succeeded to the throne, his younger brother, Imperial Prince Kamino (later called Emperor Gosaga) became the second successor to the Crown Prince by following the Emperor&apos;s will after the Emperor Heizei, who was born weak.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Emperor Kanmu&apos;s era, his eldest son, Emperor Heizei succeeded to the throne, his younger brother, Imperial Prince Kamino (later called Emperor Gosaga) became the second successor to the Crown Prince by following the Emperor&apos;s will after the Emperor Heizei, who was born weak.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>これに不満を抱いた平城は大兄である自分の直系に皇位継承することを企図して、一旦、嵯峨へ譲位して自身の子、高岳親王を皇太子とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Heizei opposed to this and he tried to let his eldest brother in his direct Imperial line to succeed to the throne, after that he passed the throne to Emperor Saga and let his own son, Imperial Prince Takaoka to become Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Heizei opposed this and tried to have his eldest brother in his direct Imperial line, succeed to the throne, after that he passed the throne to Emperor Saga and allowed his own son, Imperial Prince Takaoka to become Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Heizei opposed this and tried to have his eldest brother in his direct Imperial line, succeed to the throne, after that he passed the throne to Emperor Saga and allowed his own son, Imperial Prince Takaoka to become Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>この措置に今度は嵯峨は反発し、平城と嵯峨の武力衝突が起こり嵯峨が勝利した（薬子の変）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a dispute by armed force after this arrangement between Emperor Heizein and Emperor Saga, Emperor Saga won the dispute. (The Kusuko Incident)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this arrangement, there was an armed dispute between Emperor Heizein and Emperor Saga, and Emperor Saga won (The Kusuko Incident).</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this arrangement, there was an armed dispute between Emperor Heizei and Emperor Saga, and Emperor Saga won (The Kusuko Incident).</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>これによって平城の直系は皇位の可能性がなくなったものの、嵯峨は内外の批判を恐れて自分の実子を擁立する事に躊躇して弟の大伴親王（後の淳和天皇）を皇太弟とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to this the direct Imperial line of Emperor Heizei lost the possibility to succeed to the throne, Emperor Saga was scared of receiving the criticism from both inside and outside of the palace, he hesitated to appoint his own child to succeed to the throne, he appointed his younger brother, Imperial Prince Otomo (later called Emperor Junna) to become the second successor of the Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to this the direct Imperial line, Emperor Heizein lost the possibility to succeed to the throne, Emperor Saga was afraid of being criticised from both inside and outside the palace, he hesitated to appoint his own child to succeed to the throne, he appointed his younger brother, Imperial Prince Otomo (later called Emperor Junna) to become the second successor of the Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to this the direct Imperial line, Emperor Heizei lost the possibility to succeed to the throne, Emperor Saga was afraid of being criticized from both inside and outside the palace, he hesitated to appoint his own child to succeed to the throne, he appointed his younger brother, Imperial Prince Otomo (later called Emperor Junna) to become the second successor of the Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>嵯峨と皇位継承紛争を防ぐために、それぞれの直系を互いに皇位につける迭立（てつりつ）を採用することとし、実際、嵯峨－淳和－仁明天皇（嵯峨の子）と皇位継承され、仁明の次も恒貞親王（淳和の子、母は嵯峨の皇女）が皇太子に立てられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To prevent the dispute against Emperor Saga of the Imperial succession, there was an agreement of sharing the Imperial succession from both Imperial direct lines, in fact, the succession was conducted such as Emperor Saga - Emperor Junna - Emperor Ninmyo (Emperor Junna&apos;s child), after Emperor Ninmyo, Imperial Prince Tsunesada (Emperor Junna&apos;s child, his mother was Emperor Saga&apos;s Princess) was appointed as Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To prevent the dispute against Emperor Saga of Imperial succession, there was an agreement to share Imperial succession from both direct Imperial lines, in fact, the succession was conducted such as Emperor Saga - Emperor Junna - Emperor Ninmyo (Emperor Junna&apos;s child), after Emperor Ninmyo, Imperial Prince Tsunesada (Emperor Junna&apos;s child, his mother was Emperor Saga&apos;s Princess) was appointed as Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To prevent the dispute against Emperor Saga of Imperial succession, there was an agreement to share Imperial succession from both direct Imperial lines, in fact, the succession was conducted such as Emperor Saga - Emperor Junna - Emperor Ninmyo (Emperor Junna&apos;s child), after Emperor Ninmyo, Imperial Prince Tsunesada (Emperor Junna&apos;s child, his mother was Emperor Saga&apos;s Princess) was appointed as Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>これに対して淳和は却って紛争の原因となる事を危惧を抱いており、嵯峨に仁明の次にはその皇子を立てるべきであると忠告したものの受け入れられなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this arrangement, Emperor Saga concerned it would cause another dispute on the other hand, he advised Emperor Saga to appoint Emperor Ninmyo&apos;s Prince as a successor after the Emperor Ninmyo, however this advice was rejected.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this arrangement, Emperor However Saga was concerned it would cause another dispute, he advised Emperor Saga to appoint Emperor Ninmyo&apos;s Prince as a successor after the Emperor Ninmyo, however this advice was rejected.</e>
<cmt>grammar, trite expression replaced</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this arrangement however, Emperor Junna was concerned it would cause another dispute, he advised Emperor Saga to appoint Emperor Ninmyo&apos;s Prince as a successor after the Emperor Ninmyo, however this advice was rejected.</e>
<cmt>however位置移動Saga→Junna</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>しかし、淳和・嵯峨両上皇の相次ぐ崩御の直後、恒貞を廃太子（皇太子を廃すること）とする事件（承和の変）が起こり、皇位継承は嵯峨－仁明の系統に統一されることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Just after the both retired Emperor Junna and Sage died one after another, there was an incident to take Imperial Prince Tsunesada&apos;s position as Crown Prince, (the Showa Disturbance) the Imperial succession was unified to Emperor Saga - Emperor Ninmyo&apos;s Imperial line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Just after both retired Emperors Junna and Sage died one after another, Imperial Prince Tsunesada&apos;s position as Crown Prince was taken, (the Showa Disturbance) and Imperial succession was unified by Emperor Saga - along Emperor Ninmyo&apos;s Imperial line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Just after both Retired Emperors Junna and Sage died one after another, Imperial Prince Tsunesada&apos;s position as Crown Prince was taken, (the Showa Disturbance) and Imperial succession was unified by Emperor Saga - along Emperor Ninmyo&apos;s Imperial line.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>この事件は皇統統一を狙った仁明が、藤原北家の協力を得て起こしたとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was another theory of the incident that Emperor Ninmyo caused it to unify the Imperial line of the Imperial succession with the support from FUJIWARA hokke. (the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was another theory that Emperor Ninmyo caused the disturbance to unify the Imperial line of Imperial succession with the support of the FUJIWARA hokke (the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was another theory that Emperor Ninmyo caused the disturbance to unify the Imperial line of Imperial succession with the support of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>FUJIWARA hokke (the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan)→the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>かくして光仁以来の天智系皇統が天武系皇統を教訓にして取り入れた兄弟継承の相続（大兄制の実質復活）は、藤原種継暗殺事件から承和の変に至る皇位継承を巡る内紛の連鎖の招来に終わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus after Emperor Tenji&apos;s Imperial line learned the lesson from the Emperor Tenmu&apos;s Imperial line since Emperor Konin&apos;s era, the Imperial throne was succeeded between brothers (the practical return of the succession between the eldest brothers), it brought about the continuous dispute for Imperial succession, started from the incident to assassinate FUJIWARA no Tanetsugu and ended the Showa Disturbance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, after Emperor Tenji&apos;s Imperial line learned its lesson from Emperor Tenmu&apos;s Imperial line and since the era of Emperor Konin, the Imperial throne was succeeded between brothers (the practical return of the succession between the eldest brothers), and it was responsible for a continuous dispute for Imperial succession, starting from the incident to assassinate FUJIWARA no Tanetsugu and ended with the Showa Disturbance.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, after Emperor Tenji&apos;s Imperial line learned its lesson from Emperor Tenmu&apos;s Imperial line and since the era of Emperor Konin, the Imperial throne was succeeded between brothers (the practical return of the succession between the eldest brothers), and it was responsible for a continuous dispute for Imperial succession, starting from the incident to assassinate FUJIWARA no Tanetsugu and ended with the Showa Disturbance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="82">
<j>仁明の後、文徳天皇－清和天皇－陽成天皇と直系による皇位継承がほぼ順調に行われたが、陽成が内裏で重大事件（誤って殺人を犯したとする説が有力）を起こし退位に追い込まれてしまい、再び直系継承の下で皇統断絶の危機が訪れることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Emperor Ninmyo&apos;s era, the Imperial succession of the direct Imperial line was conducted almost smoothly like Emperor Montoku - Emperor Seiwa - Emperor Yozei, after Emperor Yozei caused serious incident in the Palace, (there was a theory of he accidentally killed someone) after he was forced to abdicated from the throne, again there was a crisis of the discontinuity of the Imperial succession under the direct Imperial line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the era of Emperor Ninmyo, Imperial succession of the direct Imperial line continued almost smoothly for example; Emperor Montoku - Emperor Seiwa - Emperor Yozei, later Emperor Yozei caused a serious incident in the Palace, (there was a theory about him accidentally killing someone) after he was forced to abdicated from the throne, and again there was a crisis of the discontinuity of Imperial succession of the direct Imperial line.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the era of Emperor Ninmyo, Imperial succession of the direct Imperial line continued almost smoothly for example; Emperor Montoku - Emperor Seiwa - Emperor Yozei, later Emperor Yozei caused a serious incident in the Palace, (there was a theory about him accidentally killing someone) after he was forced to abdicated from the throne, and again there was a crisis of the discontinuity of Imperial succession of the direct Imperial line.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>このときは、有力候補がおらず、廃太子となった恒貞親王や嵯峨の子である源融らが候補となったが、最終的には称徳崩御時の先例をとって、仁明の子で年配の光孝天皇が即位して皇位を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time there was no appropriate successor and Imperia Prince Tsunesada who previously lost his position of Crown Prince, and Emperor Saga&apos;s child, MINAMOTO no Toru were appointed as successors, finally it was decided for Emperor Ninmyo&apos;s child, Emperor Kotoku who was rather old to be a successor, became Emperor after following the example when Emperor Shoko died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time there wasn&apos;t an appropriate successor and Imperia Prince Tsunesada, who had previously lost his position as Crown Prince, and Emperor Saga&apos;s child, MINAMOTO no Toru, were both appointed as successors, finally it was decided if favor of Emperor Ninmyo&apos;s child, Emperor Kotoku who was rather old to become a successor, became Emperor after following the example of when Emperor Shoko died.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time there wasn&apos;t an appropriate successor and Imperia Prince Tsunesada, who had previously lost his position as Crown Prince, and Emperor Saga&apos;s child, MINAMOTO no Toru, were both appointed as successors, finally it was decided in favor of Emperor Ninmyo&apos;s child, Emperor Koko who was rather old to become a successor, became Emperor after following the example of when Emperor Shoko died.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>ただ、光孝はあくまで中継ぎとの立場をとり、自身の皇子を全て臣籍降下させていたが、死去直前になっても後継者を立てていなかったため、緊急措置として急遽、光孝の子の源定省が立太子され宇多天皇となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However Emperor Kotoku succeeded the throne temporally and he let all his children made demotion from nobility to subject, as an emergency measure, Emperor Koko&apos;s child, MINAMOTO no Sadami became Crown Prince in heist and succeeded to the throne as Emperor Uda.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Howeve,r Emperor Kotoku succeeded the throne temporarily and he allowed all his children to be demoted from nobility to subjects, as an emergency measure, Emperor Koko&apos;s child, MINAMOTO no Sadami became Crown Prince in a heist and succeeded to the throne as Emperor Uda.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Emperor Koko succeeded to the throne temporarily and he allowed all his children to be demoted to commoners; as he did not decide upon a successor before his death, Emperor Koko&apos;s child MINAMOTO no Sadami was hurriedly made Crown Prince as an emergency measure just prior to the emperor&apos;s death and he subsequently succeeded to the throne as Emperor Uda.</e>
<cmt>コンマ位置人名修正Neilさん、原文の赤字に対応する訳文は左記でよろしいでしょうか?NR: I would interpret &quot;死去直前になっても&quot; as meaning that right up until his death, he had still not named a successor rather than that he named one just before he died.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>一度臣籍に下った者が皇位につくのは、日本の皇位継承史の中でも極めて異例であるが天皇の子の身分の決定は天皇の専権事項である（臣籍に降ろした実子を皇族に戻す事も許される）として押し切ったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was unusual example for Imperial member who made demotion from nobility to subject to come back to succeed the throne in the history of Japanese Imperial succession, it was forced to decided as it was said the Emperor had a absolute right to chose the rank of the Emperor&apos;s children.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was an unusual example of Japanese Imprial succession for an Imperial member who had been demoted from nobility to subject, to come back and succeed the throne, it was a forced to decision because the Emperor had the absolute right to chose the rank of the Emperor&apos;s children.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was an unusual example of Japanese Imperial succession for an Imperial member who had been demoted from nobility to subject, to come back and succeed the throne, it was forced to decision because the Emperor had the absolute right to chose the rank of the Emperor&apos;s children.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正a削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>しかし、宇多とその子の醍醐天皇は積極的な政治を展開し、天皇親政の理想型を築いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However Emperor Uda and his child, Emperor Daigo established the style of Emperor&apos;s direct ruled government by actively getting involved in to the politics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But, Emperor Uda and his child, Emperor Daigo established the form of the Emperor&apos;s directly ruled government by actively becoming involved in politics.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But, Emperor Uda and his child, Emperor Daigo established the form of the Emperor&apos;s directly ruled government by actively becoming involved in politics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="87">
<j>文徳天皇の頃から藤原北家が天皇の外戚として摂政・関白につく摂関政治がある程度形成されていたが、醍醐の子である朱雀天皇・村上天皇兄弟の頃に、摂関政治が確立することとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Emperor Montoku&apos;s era, FUJIWARA hokke became Regent and Chancellor as Emperor&apos;s maternal relatives and the regency government was partly established, during the era of Emperor Daigo&apos;s child, brothers of Emperor Suzaku and Emperor Murakami, this government was fully established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the era of Emperor Montoku, the FUJIWARA hokke became Regent and Chancellor as the Emperor&apos;s maternal relatives and the regency government was partly established, during the era of Emperor Daigo&apos;s child, brothers of the Emperor Suzaku and Emperor Murakami, this government was fully established.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the era of Emperor Montoku, the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan became Regent and Chancellor as the Emperor&apos;s maternal relatives and the regency government was partly established, during the era of Emperor Daigo&apos;s child, brothers of the Emperor Suzaku and Emperor Murakami, this government was fully established.</e>
<cmt>FUJIWARA hokke (the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan)→the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>摂関家内部に複数の摂関候補者が登場することとなり、それぞれの候補者が別個に天皇に娘を入内させて子をもうけたため、皇位継承は摂関家のパワーバランスに左右されることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Within regency family, there were some candidate of Regent and Chancellor came forward, each candidate send their daughter to the Imperial Palace to become Emperor&apos;s consort and those daughters had children, the Imperial succession was controlled by the power struggle between the regency families.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Within the regency family, there were some candidates for Regent and Chancellor that came forward, each candidate sent their daughter to the Imperial Palace to become the Emperor&apos;s consort and those daughters had children, There were power struggles, between the regency families, to control Imperial seccession..</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Within the regency family, there were some candidates for Regent and Chancellor that came forward, each candidate sent their daughter to the Imperial Palace to become the Emperor&apos;s consort and those daughters had children, there were power struggles, between the regency families, to control Imperial secession.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>以上のような状況から、皇位継承候補者も複数存在することとなり、再び皇統の分裂－迭立－が見られるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the above circumstances, there were many candidates for the Imperial succession, again, the separation of the Imperial line - sharing the Imperial throne - became apparent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the above, there were many candidates for Imperial succession, again, the separation of the Imperial line - sharing the Imperial throne - became apparent.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the above, there were many candidates for Imperial succession, again, the separation of the Imperial line - sharing the Imperial throne - became apparent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>しかし、藤原道長が摂関家を統一したことに伴い、皇統も統一されることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However after FUJIWARA no Michinaga made the line of regency family into one, the Imperial line was also unified into one.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After FUJIWARA no Michinaga combined the line of regency family into one, the Imperial line was also unified into one.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After FUJIWARA no Michinaga combined the line of regency family into one, the Imperial line was also unified into one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>その後も迭立への動きは見られたが、王朝内部に皇統を統一する意思が働き続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, although there was tendency to share the Imperial throne, there was an intention inside the Imperial Palace to unify the Imperial line for the succession.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, although there was a tendency to share the Imperial throne, there was intention inside the Imperial Palace to unify the Imperial line for succession.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, although there was a tendency to share the Imperial throne, there was intention inside the Imperial Palace to unify the Imperial line for succession.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>院政期～鎌倉中期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Between the period of cloister government and the mid Kamakura period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Between the period of the cloistered government and the mid Kamakura period</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between the period of the cloistered government and the mid Kamakura period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="92">
<j>上記のような皇統統一の流れの中で後三条天皇が即位した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the movement of above unity of the Imperial line, Emperor Gosanjo succeeded to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the movement for unity of the Imperial line, Emperor Gosanjo succeeded to the throne.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the movement for unity of the Imperial line, Emperor Gosanjo succeeded to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>後三条は、皇統統一をより強固なものとするため、生前に直系男子へ譲位し上皇として政務に当たることを目論んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Gosanjo planned to pass the throne to the male successor of his direct line before he retire, and tried to rule the politics as an retired Emperor to establish the strong basement of unifying the Imperial line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Gosanjo had planned to pass the throne to a male successor of his direct line before he retired, and he tried to rule politics as an retired Emperor in order to establish a strong basis for unifying the Imperial line.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Gosanjo had planned to pass the throne to a male successor of his direct line before he retired, and he tried to rule politics as an retired Emperor in order to establish a strong basis for unifying the Imperial line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>後三条はその実現の前に没したが、その直系男子の白河天皇は後三条の遺志を継いで、上皇となって事実上の国王（治天の君）として政務に当たる院政を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Gosanjo died before he made his plan happene, his male successor of the direct line, Emperor Goshirakawa took Emperor Gosanjo&apos;s will, he became the retired Emperor and started the Cloister government to rule the politics as actual Emperor (Chiten no Kimi)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Gosanjo died before his plan could be realized, his male successor, directly in line, Emperor Goshirakawa abided by Emperor Gosanjo&apos;s will and he became the retired Emperor and started the Cloistered government to rule politics as the actual Emperor (Chiten no Kimi).</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Gosanjo died before his plan could be realized, his male successor, directly in line, Emperor Shirakawa abided by Emperor Gosanjo&apos;s will and he became the retired Emperor and started the Cloistered government to rule politics as the actual Emperor (Chiten no Kimi).</e>
<cmt>人名修正スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>上皇が国王の座につくことにより、天皇がそれまでの皇太子的立場となったため、皇太子の空位が常態化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the retired Emperor acted as Emperor, the Emperor himself became the current position of Crown Prince, there was often no one to become Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the retired Emperor acted as Emperor, the Emperor himself filled the current position of Crown Prince, there often was no one to become Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the retired Emperor acted as Emperor, the Emperor himself filled the current position of Crown Prince, there often was no one to become Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>いずれにせよ、皇統の安定化が院政の主要な目的の一つであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In any case, one of the important purpose of ruling the Cloister government was to secure the Imperial line for the succession.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In any case, one of the important purposes for ruling the Cloister government was to secure the Imperial line for succession.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In any case, one of the important purposes for ruling the Cloister government was to secure the Imperial line for succession.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>平安末期になると、鳥羽上皇の後継をめぐって崇徳天皇、近衛天皇、後白河天皇の兄弟間による皇位承継紛争が保元の乱・平治の乱という武力衝突により解決されることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the late Heian period, the dispute of the Imperial succession to the retired Emperor Toba happened, Emperor Sutoku, Emperor Konoe and Emperor Goshirakawa, between brothers, opposed to each others, but it was settled by armed conflict after the Hogen War, the Heiji War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the late Heian period, the dispute about Imperial succession to the retired Emperor Toba happened, Emperor Sutoku, Emperor Konoe, and Emperor Goshirakawa, between brothers, opposed to each other, but, it was settled by armed conflict after the Hogen War, the Heiji War.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the late Heian period, the dispute about Imperial succession to the Retired Emperor Toba happened, Emperor Sutoku, Emperor Konoe, and Emperor Goshirakawa, between brothers, opposed to each other, but, it was settled by armed conflict after the Hogen War, the Heiji War.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>最終の勝利者は後白河であったが、両乱を通じて武士を利用したため、その後の武士の台頭を許すこととなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Goshirakawa won the War finally, however since he used Samurai to win the War, this allowed Samurai to be involved in the politics later on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Goshirakawa finally won the War, however, since he used Samurai to win, this allowed Samurai to become involved in politics later on.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Goshirakawa finally won the War, however, since he used Samurai to win, this allowed Samurai to become involved in politics later on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="99">
<j>後白河の後、皇位継承者は非常に多くの系統に分かれたが、後白河が院＝治天の君として君臨し続け、むしろ皇統は安定していたといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Emperor Goshirakawa&apos;s era, the successor to the Imperial throne were from many different Imperial lines, however Emperor Goshirakawa continued to rule the government as In (Chiten no Kimi, the retired emperor), due to this the Imperial line was secured in a way.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the era of Emperor Goshirakawa, the successors to the Imperial throne were from many different Imperial lines, but Emperor Goshirakawa continued to rule the government as In (Chiten no Kimi, the retired emperor), due to this the Imperial line was, in a way, secured.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the era of Emperor Goshirakawa, the successors to the Imperial throne were from many different Imperial lines, but Emperor Goshirakawa continued to rule the government as In (Chiten no Kimi, the retired emperor), due to this the Imperial line was, in a way, secured.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>後白河は伊勢平氏・河内源氏など武士勢力の勃興に対して、王権の維持を図ろうとしたが、結局、王権の一部を鎌倉幕府へ委譲することとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Goshirakawa tried to maintain the power of the Imperial Palace against the sudden rise of the Samurai force, however he had to pass the part of the authority that Imperial Palace had to the Kamakura bakufu. (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Goshirakawa tried to maintain the power of the Imperial Palace against the sudden rise of the Samurai forces, however he had to pass part of the Imperial Palace authority to the Kamakura bakufu. (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity and ease of reading</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Goshirakawa tried to maintain the power of the Imperial Palace against the sudden rise of the Samurai forces such as Ise-Heishi (Taira clan) and Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto can), however he had to pass part of the Imperial Palace authority to the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>such as Ise-Heishi (Taira clan) and Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto can)補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>後白河の正当な後継者は後鳥羽天皇であり、皇統は後鳥羽の系統に統一され、後白河の死後、後鳥羽は院政を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Emperor Goshirakawa&apos;s proper successor was Emperor Gotoba, the Imperial line was unified to Emperor Gotoba&apos;s line, after Emperor Goshirakawa died, Emperor Gotoba started his Cloister government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Emperor Goshirakawa&apos;s proper successor was Emperor Gotoba, the Imperial line was unified along Emperor Gotoba&apos;s line, after Emperor Goshirakawa died, Emperor Gotoba started his Cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Emperor Goshirakawa&apos;s proper successor was Emperor Gotoba, the Imperial line was unified along Emperor Gotoba&apos;s line, after Emperor Goshirakawa died, Emperor Gotoba started his Cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>後鳥羽は鎌倉幕府に移った東国統治権を奪還するべく承久の乱を起こしたが、王朝が幕府に破れるという事態を招いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Gotoba caused the Jokyu Disturbance to take back the light to govern the eastern countries from the Kamakura bakufu, however it came to the conclusion that the Imperial Palace lost the battle against the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Gotoba caused the Jokyu Disturbance in order to take back the right to govern the eastern states from the Kamakura bakufu, however, the result was that the Imperial Palace lost the battle against the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity and ease of reading</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Gotoba caused the Jokyu Disturbance in order to take back the right to govern the eastern states from the Kamakura bakufu, however, the result was that the Imperial Palace lost the battle against the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>この結果、幕府によって後鳥羽院政と後鳥羽系統の皇統は全て廃されたが、皇位継承すべき者が不在という事態に至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of this, the Imperial line of Emperor Gotoba&apos;s Cloister government and Emperor Gotoba were abolished, there was a problem caused that there was no one to succeed to the Imperial throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, the Imperial line of Emperor Gotoba&apos;s Cloistered government and Emperor Gotoba were abolished, and this caused a problem because there was no one to succeed to the Imperial throne.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity and ease of reading</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, the Imperial line of Emperor Gotoba&apos;s Cloistered government and Emperor Gotoba were abolished, and this caused a problem because there was no one to succeed to the Imperial throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>当時、皇位承継するにはその父が院でなければならないという慣例ができており、やむなく皇位についたことのない守貞親王が後高倉院として治天の地位について院政を開始し、その子が後堀河天皇として即位することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, there was a custom that the successor of the Imperial throne should have father who was a retired Emperor, therefore Imperial Prince Morisada who had no position in the Imperial Palace previously, succeeded to the position to start to rule the Cloister government as Gotakakurain against his will, his son became Emperor as Emperor Gohorikawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, a custom prevailed that the successor of the Imperial throne should have a father who was a retired Emperor, therefore Imperial Prince Morisada who previously had no position in the Imperial Palace, succeeded to the position to start to rule the Cloistered government as Gotakakurain against his will, and his son became Emperor Gohorikawa.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity and ease of reading</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, a custom prevailed that the successor of the Imperial throne should have a father who was a retired Emperor, therefore Imperial Prince Morisada who previously had no position in the Imperial Palace, succeeded to the position to start to rule the Cloistered government as Gotakakurain against his will, and his son became Emperor Gohorikawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>しかし、後堀河の系統も次代の四条天皇が幼年のうちに没したことで断絶し、皇位は再び後鳥羽の系統へ戻った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However the Imperial line of Emperor Gohorikawa discontinued after the second Emperor, Emperor Shijo died young, the Imperial throne again went back to Emperor Gotoba&apos;s Imperial line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unfortunately, the Imperial line of Emperor Gohorikawa discontinued after the second Emperor, Emperor Shijo died young, the Imperial throne again went back to Emperor Gotoba&apos;s Imperial lineage.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unfortunately, the Imperial line of Emperor Gohorikawa discontinued after the second Emperor, Emperor Shijo died young, the Imperial throne again went back to Emperor Gotoba&apos;s Imperial lineage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>このとき皇位を承継したのは、後嵯峨天皇である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was Emperor Gosaga who succeeded the throne at this time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was Emperor Gosaga who succeeded the throne at this time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was Emperor Gosaga who succeeded the throne at this time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>後嵯峨の父は、父の後鳥羽に疎んじられて承久の乱の際も中立を守った土御門天皇であるが、このことが幕府の賛意を得ることになり、事実上、後嵯峨の皇位継承は幕府が決定したと言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Gosaga&apos;s father, Emperor Tsuchimikado, was treated coldly by his own father, Emperor Gotoba, took a neutral position at the Jokyu Disturbance, it gave good impression to the Kamakura bakufu and practically the bakufu approved Emperor Gosaga&apos;s Imperial succession to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Gosaga&apos;s father, Emperor Tsuchimikado, was treated coldly by his own father, Emperor Gotoba, took a neutral position at the Jokyu Disturbance, it made a good impression on the Kamakura bakufu and practically all the bakufu approved Emperor Gosaga&apos;s Imperial succession to the throne.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity and ease of reading</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Gosaga&apos;s father, Emperor Tsuchimikado, was treated coldly by his own father, Emperor Gotoba, took a neutral position at the Jokyu Disturbance, it made a good impression on the Kamakura bakufu and practically all the bakufu approved Emperor Gosaga&apos;s Imperial succession to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>これは、後世の先例となって江戸幕府に至るまで、皇位継承には幕府の承認が必要とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This example was followed until the period of Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), the bakufu needed to approve the Imperial succession to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This example was followed until the period of Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), the bakufu needed to approve the Imperial succession to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This example was followed until the period of Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), the bakufu needed to approve the Imperial succession to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>皇統分裂の時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The period of the division of Imperial line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The period of the division of Imperial lineage</e>
<cmt>line → lineage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The period of the division of Imperial lineage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="109">
<j>後嵯峨の子には、後深草天皇・亀山天皇の兄弟がいたが、互いに後嵯峨後継の治天の君の座を争い、その妥結として、両者の直系子孫が交互に皇位・治天位につく両統迭立が行われることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Gosaga&apos;s children, the brothers of Emperor Gofukakusa, Emperor Kameyama, both fight against each others to take the position of Chiten no kimi as his father&apos;s successor, they came to an agreement to conduct Ryoto Tetsuritsu (sharing the Imperial throne from the both Imperial line) that the direct descendants of the each Imperial line would take turn to share the Imperial throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Gosaga&apos;s children, the brothers of Emperor Gofukakusa, Emperor Kameyama, both fought against each for the position of Chiten no kimi as his father&apos;s successor, they came to an agreement to conduct Ryoto Tetsuritsu (sharing the Imperial throne from both Imperial lines) that the direct descendants of the each Imperial line would take turns to sharing the Imperial throne.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Gosaga&apos;s children, the brothers of Emperor Gofukakusa, Emperor Kameyama, both fought against each for the position of Chiten no kimi as his father&apos;s successor, they came to an agreement to conduct Ryoto Tetsuritsu (sharing the Imperial throne from both Imperial lines) that the direct descendants of the each Imperial line would take turns to sharing the Imperial throne.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>兄・後深草の系統を持明院統、弟・亀山の系統を大覚寺統というが、これが日本史上最大の皇位迭立となり、後世に大きな影響を与えることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The older brother, Emperor Gofukafusa&apos;s line was called the Jimyoin Imperial line, and the younger brother, Emperor Kameyama&apos;s line was called the Daikakuji Imperial line, this example of sharing throne was the biggest in the Japanese history and gave big influence to the later period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The older brother, Emperor Gofukafusa&apos;s line was called the Jimyoin Imperial line, and the younger brother, Emperor Kameyama&apos;s line was called the Daikakuji Imperial line, this example of sharing the throne was the biggest event in Japanese history that had a great impact on the later period.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The older brother, Emperor Gofukakusa&apos;s line was called the Jimyoin Imperial line, and the younger brother, Emperor Kameyama&apos;s line was called the Daikakuji Imperial line, this example of sharing the throne was the biggest event in Japanese history that had a great impact on the later period.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="111">
<j>しばらく両統迭立は順調に行われていたが、鎌倉時代末期になると両統の内部で皇統分裂が見られ始め、迭立の混乱が生じてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ryoto Tetsuritsu was conducted smoothly for a while, however the Imperial lines started to divide within the each Imperial line, the situation was getting confused in terms of sharing the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ryoto Tetsuritsu was conducted smoothly for a while, however the Imperial lines started to divide within the each Imperial line, the situation was getting confused in terms of sharing the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ryoto Tetsuritsu was conducted smoothly for a while, however the Imperial lines started to divide within the each Imperial line at the end of the Kamakura period, the situation was getting confused in terms of sharing the throne.</e>
<cmt>at the end of the Kamakura period補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>その状況下で大覚寺統の後醍醐天皇は、王権復興を目指して幕府追討計画を2度にわたって立て（正中の変・元弘の変）、幕府により廃位・流罪に処されるも、鎌倉幕府の滅亡をもたらし、京で復位した後、建武の新政を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under that circumstances, Emperor Godaigo attempted to overthrow the Bakufu twice to revive the royal authority for the Imperial Palace, (the Shochu Disturbance, the Genko Disturbance) his position was taken away from the bakufu and was sentenced to deportation, but it caused the ruin of the Kamakura bafuku, Emperor Godaigo became Emperor again in Kyoto and started the Kenmu Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under such circumstances, Emperor Godaigo attempted to overthrow the Bakufu twice to revive royal authority for the Imperial Palace, (the Shochu Disturbance, the Genko Disturbance) his position was taken away from the bakufu and he was banished,, but it caused the ruin of the Kamakura bafuku, Emperor Godaigo became Emperor again in Kyoto and started the Kenmu Restoration.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under such circumstances, Emperor Godaigo of the Daikakuji Imperial line attempted to overthrow the Bakufu twice to revive royal authority for the Imperial Palace (the Shochu Disturbance, the Genko Disturbance), his position was taken away from the bakufu and he was banished, but it caused the ruin of the Kamakura bakufu, Emperor Godaigo became Emperor again in Kyoto and started the Kenmu Restoration.</e>
<cmt>of the Daikakuji Imperial line 補足コンマ位置移動・削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>後醍醐は治天の地位につくことなく、約200年ぶりに天皇の地位のまま親政を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Godaigo did not become the retired Emperor, ut was first time in the last two hundred years (since the last Emperor did not become the retired Emperor to start the Cloister government) that the Emperor governed his directly ruled government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Godaigo did not become a retired Emperor, it was the first time in the last two hundred years (for the last Emperor not to become a retired Emperor and to start a Cloistered government) that the Emperor governed his directly ruled government.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Godaigo did not become a retired Emperor, it was the first time in the last two hundred years (for the last Emperor not to become a retired Emperor and to start a Cloistered government) that the Emperor governed his directly ruled government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>後醍醐は両統迭立状態を解消し、自身の系統に皇統を再度統一したと考えていたが、その後、後醍醐の新政へ多くの離反が相次ぎ、離反勢力からなる足利幕府は持明院統から光明天皇を擁立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor had an intention to solve the current problem of conducting Ryoto Tetsuritsu and re-unify the Imperial line to his line, however there were many disputes against the Emperor&apos;s new government, the Ashikaga shogunate who were the opposition against the Emperor appointed Emperor Komyo from the Jimyoin Imperial line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor had the intention to solve the current problem of conducting Ryoto Tetsuritsu and re-unifying the Imperial line to his lineage, however there were many disputes against the Emperor&apos;s new government, the Ashikaga shogunate who was in opposition to the Emperor appointed Emperor Komyo from the Jimyoin Imperial line.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor had the intention to solve the current problem of conducting Ryoto Tetsuritsu and re-unifying the Imperial line to his lineage, however there were many disputes against the Emperor&apos;s new government, the Ashikaga shogunate who was in opposition to the Emperor appointed Emperor Komyo from the Jimyoin Imperial line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>これにより北朝（持明院統）と南朝（大覚寺統）の2つの王朝が同時に存在する日本史上未曾有の事態となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to this, it caused the situation to have two Imperial lines in the same period, the Northern Dynasty (the Kumyoin Imperial line) and the Southern Dynasty (Daikakuji Imperial line), which was unprecedented in the Japanese history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this, it caused two Imperial lines to emerge during the same period, the Northern Court (the Kumyoin Imperial line) and the Southern Court (Daikakuji Imperial line), which was unprecedented in the Japanese history.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this, it caused two Imperial lines to emerge during the same period, the Northern Court (the Jimyoin Imperial line) and the Southern Court (Daikakuji Imperial line), which was unprecedented in the Japanese history.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>北朝は、幕府の擁護を受けて、従来どおりの院政を継続したが、南朝では後村上天皇以降、関白こそは復活させたものの天皇親政を貫いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Northern Dynasty had the support from the Ashikaga shogunate and continued ruling the Cloister government same as before, on the other hand, in the Southern Dynasty, after Emperor Gomurakami&apos;s era, although they had the position of the Chancellor back to the Palace, Emperor kept on conducting the directly ruled government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Northern Court had the support from the Ashikaga shogunate and continued ruling the Cloister government the same as before, on the other hand, in the Southern Court, after the era of Emperor Gomurakami, although the position of Chancellor had returned to the Palace, the Emperor continued to directly rule the government.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Northern Court had the support from the Ashikaga shogunate and continued ruling the Cloister government the same as before, on the other hand, in the Southern Court, after the era of Emperor Gomurakami, although the position of Chancellor had returned to the Palace, the Emperor continued to directly rule the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>1352年室町幕府内部の内紛に乗じて南朝軍が京都を占領して北朝の崇光天皇ら主だった皇族を拉致してしまう（正平一統）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1352, when there was a internal trouble happened within the Muromachi bakufu, the Southern Dynasty army took this opportunity and occupied Kyoto, and abducted the main Imperial members of the Northern Dynasty, such as Emperor Suko. (Shohei Itto)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1352, when there were internal problems within the Muromachi bakufu, the Southern Court army took the opportunity to occupy Kyoto, and abduct the main Imperial members of the Northern Court, such as Emperor Suko. (Shohei Itto)</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1352, when there were internal problems within the Muromachi bakufu, the Southern Court army took the opportunity to occupy Kyoto, and abduct the main Imperial members of the Northern Court, such as Emperor Suko. (Shohei Itto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>室町幕府は天皇の弟の一人が寺院に預けられている事を知って急遽後光厳天皇として即位させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Muromachi bakufu received the information that the Emperor&apos;s younger brother was left at a Temple, and let him succeeded to the throne as Emperor Gokogon in haste.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Muromachi bakufu received information that the Emperor&apos;s younger brother was left at a Temple, and they allowed him to hastily succeed to the throne as Emperor Gokogon.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Muromachi bakufu received information that the Emperor&apos;s younger brother was left at a Temple, and they allowed him to hastily succeed to the throne as Emperor Gokogon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>後に南朝方は崇光らを返還したものの、室町幕府は崇光の復位を認めず子孫には伏見宮の称号を贈って宥めようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the Southern Dynasty force released Emperor Suko and others later on, the Muromachi bakufu did not approve Emperor Suko to come back to the position as Emperor, the bakufu tried to appeased his descendants by giving the respective title of Fushiminomiya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the Southern Court forces later released Emperor Suko and others, the Muromachi bakufu did not approve Emperor Suko&apos;s return as Emperor, the bakufu tried to appeased his descendants by giving the respective title of Fushiminomiya.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the Southern Court forces later released Emperor Suko and others, the Muromachi bakufu did not approve Emperor Suko&apos;s return as Emperor, the bakufu tried to appeased his descendants by giving the respective title of Fushiminomiya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>だが、皇位継承が後光厳の直系子孫による方針が決められたために崇光と伏見宮家による後光厳と室町幕府に対する反感が高まって、北朝は事実上の分裂状態に陥ったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, after it was decided the direct descendants of Emperor Gokogon would succeed to the throne, there was antagonism raised against Emperor Gokogon and the Muromachi bakufu by Emperor Suko and Fushiminomiya family, practically there was a division within the Northern Dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after it was decided that the direct descendants of Emperor Gokogon would succeed to the throne, antagonism was raised against Emperor Gokogon and the Muromachi bakufu by Emperor Suko and the Fushiminomiya family, and this practically caused a division within the Northern Court.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after it was decided that the direct descendants of Emperor Gokogon would succeed to the throne, antagonism was raised against Emperor Gokogon and the Muromachi bakufu by Emperor Suko and the Fushiminomiya family, and this practically caused a division within the Northern Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="121">
<j>時代が進み北朝・室町幕府側の優位が明確になってくると、南朝側も妥結点を模索してきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the time went by, when it became apparent the Northern Dynasty and the Muromachi bakufu were on the superior situation, the Southern Dynasty started looking for an agreement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As time went by, when it became apparent the Northern Court and the Muromachi bakufu were in the superior position, the Southern Court started looking for an agreement.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As time went by, when it became apparent the Northern Court and the Muromachi bakufu were in the superior position, the Southern Court started looking for an agreement.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>そこで仲介に当たったのが足利義満である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA who worked as the intermediation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA who worked as the intermediator.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA who worked as the intermediator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>1392年、持明院統（北朝）と大覚寺統（南朝）の迭立再開が提案され、南朝の後亀山天皇が条件受諾したことにより、北朝の後小松天皇とともに南北朝合一が実現した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1392 after there was a suggestion to restart the sharing of the Imperial throne between the Jimyoin Imperial line (the Northern Dynasty) and the Daikakuji Imperial line (the Southern Dynasty), Emperor Gokameyama of the Southern Dynasty accepted the condition, and the unity of the Northern Dynasty and the Southern Dynasty came true, together with Emperor Gokomatsu of the Northern Dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1392 after the suggestion to restart the sharing of the Imperial throne between the Jimyoin Imperial lineage (the Northern Court) and the Daikakuji Imperial lineage (the Southern Court), Emperor Gokameyama of the Southern Court accepted, and the unity of the Northern Court and the Southern Court was realized, together with Emperor Gokomatsu of the Northern Court.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1392 after the suggestion to restart the sharing of the Imperial throne between the Jimyoin Imperial lineage (the Northern Court) and the Daikakuji Imperial lineage (the Southern Court), Emperor Gokameyama of the Southern Court accepted, and the unity of the Northern Court and the Southern Court was realized, together with Emperor Gokomatsu of the Northern Court.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>しかし、1412年に称光天皇が即位するに際して迭立再開の条件は撤回されることとなり、後小松天皇の直系子孫による皇位継承が宣言された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However after the Emperor Shoko succeeded to the throne in 1412, the condition to restart sharing the Imperial throne was cancelled, there was a declaration for Emperor Gokomatsu&apos;s direct descendants to succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However after Emperor Shoko succeeded to the throne in 1412, the agreement to restart sharing the Imperial throne was cancelled, there was a declaration for Emperor Gokomatsu&apos;s direct descendants to succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However after Emperor Shoko succeeded to the throne in 1412, the agreement to restart sharing the Imperial throne was cancelled, there was a declaration for Emperor Gokomatsu&apos;s direct descendants to succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>約束を反故にされた南朝側は憤慨し、後南朝としてその後も存続し続けた（太平洋戦争後まで南朝子孫を名乗る者がいた）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Southern Dynasty was furious after the condition of the sharing Imperial throne was cancelled, they continued to stay as the Gonancho (the Southern Dynasty in later years) later years. (There were some people named themselves as the descendants of the Southern Dynasty after the Pacific War.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Southern Court was furious after the agreement for sharing the Imperial throne was cancelled, they continued to stay as Gonancho (the Southern Court in later years) in later years. (There were some people who named themselves as the descendants of the Southern Court after the Pacific War.)</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Southern Court was furious after the agreement for sharing the Imperial throne was cancelled, they continued to stay as Gonancho (the Southern Court in later years) in later years. (There were some people who named themselves as the descendants of the Southern Court after the Pacific War.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="126">
<j>一見、南北朝合一により皇位継承は再び安定したように見られたが、もう一つの問題であった北朝内部の内紛は解消されなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seemed that the Imperial succession was sacred at glance, however another problem, the internal trouble within the Northern Dynasty did not get solved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seemed that Imperial succession was sacred at a glance, however, the internal trouble within the Northern Court did not become resolved.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seemed that Imperial succession was sacred at a glance with the unity of the Northern Court and the Southern Court, however, the internal trouble within the Northern Court did not become resolved.</e>
<cmt>with the unity of the Northern Court and the Southern Court補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>更に後小松には称光しか男子がおらず（称光の皇太子であった後小松の第2皇子は早世、実はこの他に名僧として知られた一休宗純も後小松の皇子であったが、政治的事情により早くから出家させられて皇位継承権を失っていた）、更に称光には子供がいない上に虚弱体質であったためにいつ崩御されてもおかしくない状態となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Emperor Gokomatsu only had one male child, Emperor Shoko, (Emperor Shoko&apos;s Crown Prince, Emperor Gokomatsu&apos;s second Prince died young, and in fact, Sojun IKKYU who was the famous monk was Emperor Gokomatsu&apos;s Prince, he had to enter into the priesthood with young age due to the political reasons, he did not have any light to succeed to the throne.) Emperor Shoko did not have any children and he was born weak, he was considered that he would not live long.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Emperor Gokomatsu only had one male child, Emperor Shoko, (Emperor Shoko&apos;s Crown Prince, Emperor Gokomatsu&apos;s second Prince died young, and in fact, Sojun IKKYU the famous monk was Emperor Gokomatsu&apos;s Prince, he had to enter into the priesthood at a young age for political reasons, he did not have any right to succeed to the throne.) Emperor Shoko did not have any children and he was born weak, and he was not expected to live long.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Emperor Gokomatsu only had one male child, Emperor Shoko, (Emperor Shoko&apos;s Crown Prince, Emperor Gokomatsu&apos;s second Prince died young, and in fact, Sojun IKKYU the famous monk was Emperor Gokomatsu&apos;s Prince, he had to enter into the priesthood at a young age for political reasons, he did not have any right to succeed to the throne.) Emperor Shoko did not have any children and he was born weak, and he was not expected to live long.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>そこで当時院政を行っていた後小松は崇光の孫である伏見宮貞成親王に対して万が一の際の皇位継承を極秘に要請した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus Emperor Gokomatsu, who was ruling the Cloister government at that time, secretly ordered to Fushininomiya Imperial Prince Sadafusa, who was the grandchild of Emperor Suko, to succeed to the throne in the case of the emergency.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus Emperor Gokomatsu, who was ruling the Cloistered government at the time, secretly ordered Fushininomiya Imperial Prince Sadafusa, who was the grandchild of Emperor Suko, to succeed to the throne in the event of an emergency.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus Emperor Gokomatsu, who was ruling the Cloistered government at the time, secretly ordered Fushiminomiya Imperial Prince Sadafusa, who was the grandchild of Emperor Suko, to succeed to the throne in the event of an emergency.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>ところがその話が称光に伝わると激怒して貞成親王を強引に出家させて皇位継承権を剥奪してしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Emperor Suko knew above arrangement, he was furious and let Imperial Prince Sadafusa enter into the priesthood forcefully, the Prince was taken away his light to succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Emperor Suko learned of the above arrangement, he was furious and had Imperial Prince Sadafusa forecefully enter into the priesthood, the Prince had his right to succeed to the throne taken away.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Emperor Suko learned of the above arrangement, he was furious and had Imperial Prince Sadafusa forcefully enter into the priesthood, the Prince had his right to succeed to the throne taken away.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>ところがそれから程ない1428年に肝心の称光が崩御して後小松系の皇統が断絶してしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way, the main person, Emperor Shoko died in 1428, Emperor Gokomatsu&apos;s Imperial line discontinued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Not too lon after that, Emperor Shoko died in 1428, and Emperor Gokomatsu&apos;s Imperial line discontinued.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Not too long after that, Emperor Shoko died in 1428, and Emperor Gokomatsu&apos;s Imperial line discontinued.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>そこで後小松は貞成親王の皇子であった後花園天皇を擁立させたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then Emperor Gokomatsu let Emperor Gohanazono succeed to the throne, who was the Imperial Prince Sadafusa&apos;s Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then Emperor Gokomatsu allowed Emperor Gohanazono, who was the Imperial Prince Sadafusa&apos;s Prince, to succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt>restructured for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then Emperor Gokomatsu allowed Emperor Gohanazono, who was the Imperial Prince Sadafusa&apos;s Prince, to succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>これに対して旧南朝側では北朝側の皇統は断絶しており、傍流の継承は認めないとして各地で蜂起を起こした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Southern Dynasty, they were against it by saying they would not accept the Imperial succession of the Northern Dynasty as their Imperial line had already discontinued, they raised revolt in many places.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Southern Dynasty was against it, and said they would not accept the Imperial succession of the Northern Dynasty as their Imperial lineage had already discontinued, they raised revolts in many places.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Southern Court was against it, and said they would not accept the Imperial succession of the Northern Court as their Imperial lineage had already discontinued, they raised revolts in many places.</e>
<cmt>南朝、北朝表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>一時は宮中に侵入した南朝側の武士によって三種の神器を奪われる（禁闕の変）などの危機にもあったが室町幕府はこれを鎮圧、ここにおいて初めて真の「南北朝合一」が実現したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One time there was a crisis that Samurai forces from the Southern Dynasty went into the Imperial Palace and the three sacred treasures, after the Muromachi bakufu suppressed it, it was the real &apos;unity of the Southern and the Northern Dynasty&apos; completed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a crisis that had occurred whereby some Samurai forces from the Southern Court went into the Imperial Palace and took the three sacred treasures, later the Muromachi bakufu suppressed the story, and this was a sign that real &apos;unity of the Southern and the Northern Court&apos; had come about.</e>
<cmt>revised, however, &quot;went into the Imperial Palace and the three sacred treasures&quot; I don&apos;t see how they could go into the &quot;three sacred treasures&quot; so, I can only guess that the translator meant they &quot;took&quot; the three sacred treasures. Please confirm.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a crisis that had occurred whereby some Samurai forces from the Southern Court went into the Imperial Palace and took the three sacred treasures (,Kinketsu Disturbance) later the Muromachi bakufu suppressed the story, and this was a sign that real &apos;unity of the Southern and the Northern Court&apos; had come about.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除(,Kinketsu Disturbance)補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>足利義満</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="134">
<j>1990年代前期ごろから足利義満は皇位簒奪を企図していたとする説が注目されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In early 1990, it became apparent that there was a theory that Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA planned to take the power back to succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In early 1990, it was suspected that Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA planned to take the power back to succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt>revised for wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In early 1990s, it was suspected that Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA planned to take the power back to succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt>1990→1990s</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>武家としてだけでなく、公家としても官位を極めた義満は、治天の君としての行動を徐々に始め、自身の子である足利義嗣を皇位につけることを計画していたが、計画成就の寸前に死去したため皇位簒奪がならなかったとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was in the high rank of not only as Samurai, but also as court noble, he gradually prepared to pretend starting the Cloister government, he planned to let his son, Yoshitsugu ASHIKAGA to succeed to the throne, however this Imperial succession did not happen as he died just before his plan was about to be completed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a high ranking Samurai, and also a court noble, he gradually prepared to pretend to start the Cloistered government, and he planned to have his son, Yoshitsugu ASHIKAGA succeed to the throne, however this Imperial succession did not happen as he died just before his plan was about to come to fruition.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a high ranking Samurai, and also a court noble, he gradually prepared to pretend to start the Cloistered government, and he planned to have his son, Yoshitsugu ASHIKAGA succeed to the throne, however this Imperial succession did not happen as he died just before his plan was about to come to fruition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>義満も清和天皇（又は陽成天皇）に始まる源氏ではあるが、代数が当時の天皇から十数代も離れていたため皇族としての資格はないものと見做されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimitsu also was from the Minamoto clan who&apos;s originator was Emperor Seiwa (or Emperor Yozei), however he was almost ten generations after the former Emperor who was in the same Imperial line, so he was not considered that he had a right to succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimitsu also was from the Minamoto clan who&apos;s founder was Emperor Seiwa (or Emperor Yozei), however he was almost ten generations removed from the former Emperor who was in the same Imperial lineage, so he was not considered to have the right to succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimitsu also was from the Minamoto clan who&apos;s founder was Emperor Seiwa (or Emperor Yozei), however he was almost ten generations removed from the former Emperor who was in the same Imperial lineage, so he was not considered to have the right to succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>日本の歴史上五代以上天皇位についていない家系に属する皇裔が即位した例はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was no example of the Imperial descendants who had not been succeeded to the throne for more that five generations, succeeded to the throne in the Japanese history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was no example, in Japanese history, of an Imperial descendant who had not succeeded to the throne for more that five generations.</e>
<cmt>revised wordiness for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was no example, in Japanese history, of an Imperial descendant who had not succeeded to the throne for more that five generations.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>しかし、上記説の論者は、当時の状況（後光厳系統断絶の危機など）を詳細に観察してみると、義満による皇位簒奪はかなりの可能性で成功したはずであり、もし成功していればその後の天皇（皇位）のあり方が劇的に変化していただろうと考えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However the present writer of the above theory seemed to think the Yoshimitsu had a great possibility to take back the rights of succeeding to the throne after observing the detailed situation, (such as the crisis of the discontinuity of the Emperor Gokogon&apos;s Imperial line) if Yoshimitsu had a chance to succeed to the throne, the way of the (Emperor) Imperial throne exist should have been changed dramatically.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However the present writer of the above seemed to think that Yoshimitsu had a great possibility to regain his rights of succeeding the throne after looking into the details of the situation, (such as the crisis of discontinuity of Emperor Gokogon&apos;s Imperial lineage) if Yoshimitsu had a chance to succeed to the throne, the existence of the (Emperor) Imperial throne should have been changed dramatically.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However the present writer of the above seemed to think that Yoshimitsu had a great possibility to regain his rights of succeeding the throne after looking into the details of the situation, (such as the crisis of discontinuity of Emperor Gokogon&apos;s Imperial lineage) if Yoshimitsu had a chance to succeed to the throne, the existence of the (Emperor) Imperial throne should have been changed dramatically.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>実際、義満の死後、太上天皇号が朝廷から贈られようとしている（義満の後継者足利義持がこれを辞退した）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, after Yoshimitsu died, the Imperial Palace intended to send the title of the retired emperor. (However Yoshimitsu&apos;s successor, Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA declined it.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, after Yoshimitsu died, the Imperial Palace intended to bestow the title of retired emperor. (However Yoshimitsu&apos;s successor, Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA declined it.)</e>
<cmt>revised vocabulary</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, after Yoshimitsu died, the Imperial Palace intended to bestow the title of retired emperor. (However Yoshimitsu&apos;s successor, Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA declined it.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>戦国期～現代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Sengoku period (Period of Warring States)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Sengoku period (Period of Warring States)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the Sengoku period (Period of Warring States) to present</e>
<cmt>to present補足</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="140">
<j>室町時代中期に入ると、皇室の権威は次第に低下していったが、それに伴い皇位継承紛争は見られなくなり、直系男子がすんなりと皇位継承するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the middle of the Muromachi period, the authority of the Imperial Palace was gradually lost, there was no dispute of the Imperial succession accordingly, the male Imperial member of the direct Imperial line succeeded to the throne smoothly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the middle of the Muromachi period, the authority of the Imperial Palace was gradually lost, however, there was no dispute concerning Imperial succession, the male Imperial member of the direct Imperial line succeeded smoothly to the throne.</e>
<cmt>restructured for grammar and clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the middle of the Muromachi period, the authority of the Imperial Palace was gradually lost, however, there was no dispute concerning Imperial succession, the male Imperial member of the direct Imperial line succeeded smoothly to the throne.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>誰が皇位についても構わないという状況が出現したことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In another words, there was a situation of anyone could succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In otherwords, the situation was such that anyone could succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt>revised for grammar and clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, the situation was such that anyone could succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>それでも伏見宮家から入った後花園天皇から17世紀前期（江戸時代初期）の後陽成天皇まで、直系男子が継承紛争もなく迭立もないまま順調に皇位を継承していき、日本史上もっとも皇位継承が長期間にわたり穏やかに行われた時代でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the period of Emperor Gohanazono who came from Fushiminomiya family to Emperor Goyozei of early seventeenth century (early Edo period), yet the Imperial succession was conducted smoothly by the male Imperial member of the direct line, without having any dispute or no sharing the throne, this was the longest period in Japanese history that the Imperial succession was conducted smoothly without having problem.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the period of Emperor Gohanazono who came from the Fushiminomiya family to Emperor Goyozei of early seventeenth century (early Edo period), Imperial succession was conducted smoothly by the male Imperial members of the direct lineage, without any disputes or sharing of the throne, this was the longest period in Japanese history when Imperial succession was conducted smoothly without problems.</e>
<cmt>revised for grammar and clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the period of Emperor Gohanazono who came from the Fushiminomiya family to Emperor Goyozei of early seventeenth century (early Edo period), Imperial succession was conducted smoothly by the male Imperial members of the direct lineage, without any disputes or sharing of the throne, this was the longest period in Japanese history when Imperial succession was conducted smoothly without problems.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="143">
<j>安土桃山時代後期・江戸初期の後陽成は自分の後継者が豊臣秀吉・徳川家康の2大権力者の思惑により擁立された事に不満を抱き、実子ながらこれらを廃して実弟の八条宮智仁親王に譲位しようとして豊臣政権や江戸幕府と衝突したが、最終的に家康の推す嫡男子の後水尾天皇に譲る事になったが長く親子間の不和が続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor Goyozei, during the Azuchi-Momoyama period and early Edo period, was frustrated as his successor was decided by two powerful leaders, Hideyoshi TOYOYOMI, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, he let his own child abdicated from the throne and tried to let his younger brother, Hachijonomiya Imperial Prince Toshihito to succeed to the throne however there was a conflict against Toyotomi government and Edo bakufu, finally he decided to pass the throne to Emperor Gomizunoo, who was the eldest son and was recommended by Ieyasu, but the unpleasant relationship between the father and son continued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Goyozei, during the Azuchi-Momoyama period and early Edo period, was frustrated as his successor was decided by two powerful leaders, Hideyoshi TOYOYOMI, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, he allowed his own child to abdicate from the throne and tried to have his younger brother, Hachijonomiya Imperial Prince Toshihito succeed to the throne, however, there was a conflict with the Toyotomi government and Edo bakufu, finally he decided to pass the throne to Emperor Gomizunoo, who was the eldest son and was recommended by Ieyasu, but an unpleasant relationship between the father and son continued.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Goyozei, during the late Azuchi-Momoyama period and early Edo period, was frustrated as his successor was decided by two powerful leaders, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, he allowed his own child to abdicate from the throne and tried to have his younger brother, Hachijonomiya Imperial Prince Toshihito succeed to the throne, however, there was a conflict with the Toyotomi government and Edo bakufu, finally he decided to pass the throne to Emperor Gomizunoo, who was the eldest son and was recommended by Ieyasu, but an unpleasant relationship between the father and son continued.</e>
<cmt>late補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>続く後水尾もたびたび幕府から高圧的に扱われたため、それに耐えかねて1629年、自らの女子に譲位した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The next successor to the throne, Emperor Gomizunoo was also often treated by the Edo bakufu with high pressure, he could not take this pressure and passed the throne to his daughter in 1629.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The next successor to the throne, Emperor Gomizunoo was also often highly pressured by the Edo bakufu and he could not take the pressure and passed the throne to his daughter in 1629.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The next successor to the throne, Emperor Gomizunoo was also often highly pressured by the Edo bakufu and he could not take the pressure and passed the throne to his daughter in 1629.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>このとき皇位継承した明正天皇は称徳天皇以来859年ぶりの女帝である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor Meisho who succeeded to the throne on this occasion, was the first female Emperor after Emperor Shotoku, first time in eight hundred and fifty nine years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Empress Meisho who succeeded to the throne on this occasion, was the first female Emperor after Emperor Shotoku, first time in eight hundred and fifty nine years.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Empress Meisho who succeeded to the throne on this occasion, was the first female Emperor after Empress Shotoku, first time in 859 years.</e>
<cmt>数字表記Emperor→Empress</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>明正はその後、異母弟の後光明天皇へ譲位した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Emperor Meisho passed the throne to her half younger brother, Emperor Gokomyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Emperor Meisho passed the throne to her half younger brother, Emperor Gokomyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Empress Meisho passed the throne to her half younger brother, Emperor Gokomyo.</e>
<cmt>Emperor→Empress</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="147">
<j>中継ぎとしての女帝の存在が江戸期にも見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were some examples of female Emperors succeeded to the throne temporally in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were some examples of female Emperors that temporarily succeeded to the throne in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were some examples of female Emperors that temporarily succeeded to the throne in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>後光明以降は、直系男子への継承を基本として、継承者が未成人などの場合に中継ぎとしての女帝が擁立されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Emperor Gokomyo&apos;s era, although the base rule for the Imperial succession was for male Imperial member to succeed to the throne, there were some female Emperors succeeded temporally in case of the other candidate of the Emperor was too young to become Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the era of Emperor Gokomyo, although the basic rule for Imperial succession was for a male Imperial member to succeed to the throne, there were some female Empresses that temporarily succeeded, in case the other candidates were too young to become Emperor.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the era of Emperor Gokomyo, although the basic rule for Imperial succession was for a male Imperial member to succeed to the throne, there were some female Empresses that temporarily succeeded, in case the other candidates were too young to become Emperor.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>その後、1779年に後桃園天皇が子を残さないまま若くして没したため、日本史上、数回目となる皇統断絶の危機が発生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, since Emperor Gomomozono died young without having children in 1779, there was a crisis of the discontinuity of the Imperial succession, which can be counted a several times in the Japanese history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, since Emperor Gomomozono died young in 1779, without having children, there was a crisis of the discontinuity of the Imperial succession, which can be seen several times in the Japanese history.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, since Emperor Gomomozono died young in 1779, without having children, there was a crisis of the discontinuity of the Imperial succession, which can be seen several times in the Japanese history.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>しかし、この約60年前に皇統断絶の可能性を予見していた新井白石は、皇位継承権をもつ皇族家系となる閑院宮を創設しており、後桃園の後継として閑院宮から光格天皇が迎えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However Hakuseki ARAI foresaw the possibility of the discontinuity of the Imperial throne sixty years ago, he had already established Kaninnomiya family, who were the Imperial family line and have the rights to succeed to the throne, Emperor Kokaku was accepted from the Kaninnomiya family as Emperor Gomomozono&apos;s successor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However Hakuseki ARAI foresaw the possibility of the discontinuity of the Imperial throne sixty years prior, he had already established the Kaninnomiya family, who were in the Imperial family line and had the right to succeed to the throne, Emperor Kokaku was accepted from the Kaninnomiya family as Emperor Gomomozono&apos;s successor.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However Hakuseki ARAI foresaw the possibility of the discontinuity of the Imperial throne sixty years prior, he had already established the Kaninnomiya family, who were in the Imperial family line and had the right to succeed to the throne, Emperor Kokaku was accepted from the Kaninnomiya family as Emperor Gomomozono&apos;s successor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="151">
<j>皇族の子孫は数代経た後に皇籍から離脱するのが律令以来の通例であったが、中世以後、伏見宮や閑院宮の様に皇統維持のために、何代経ても親王位につくことのできる家系（世襲親王家）を創出していったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there was a custom for the descants of the Imperial family to make demotion from nobility to subject from the government based on the ritsuryo legal codes, after the Medieval Period, the Imperial family line (the hereditary Imperial family) was established, such as Fushiminomiya and Kaninnomiya for the Imperial succession, in order for them to succeed to the throne after many generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there was a custom for the descants of the Imperial family to make demotion from nobility to subject from the government based on the ritsuryo legal codes, after the Medieval Period, the Imperial family line (the hereditary Imperial family) was established, such as Fushiminomiya and Kaninnomiya for the Imperial succession, in order for them to succeed to the throne after many generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there was a custom for the descants of the Imperial Family to make demotion from nobility to subject from the government based on the ritsuryo legal codes, after the Medieval Period, the Imperial Family line (the hereditary Imperial Family) was established, such as Fushiminomiya and Kaninnomiya for the Imperial succession, in order for them to succeed to the throne after many generations.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>また、当時天皇に複数の皇子がいる場合、複数の親王の生活を支える財政的ゆとりが無い事や臣籍降下をさせるだけの公家官位の余裕が無い事から、皇位継承者以外の皇子は全て幼くして出家を強要せざるを得ない（当然ながら出家した皇子には子孫が存在しない事になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those day, the Emperor with many Princes and Princesses had to let them enter into the priesthood while they were young, except for the candidate Prince to succeed to the throne, this was because the Emperor could not afford to support the Princes and Princesses lives financially, or the court officials could not afford to let them make demotion from nobility to subject, (It is needless to say that the Princes went into the priesthood would not had any children.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those days, the Emperor with many Princes and Princesses had to allow them to enter into the priesthood while they were young, except for the candidate Prince who will succeed to the throne, this was because the Emperor could not afford to financially support the Princes and Princesses, or the court officials could not afford to have them be demoted from nobility to subject, (It is needless to say that the Princes who went into the priesthood would not have any children.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those days, the Emperor with many Princes and Princesses had to allow them to enter into the priesthood while they were young, except for the candidate Prince who will succeed to the throne, this was because the Emperor could not afford to financially support the Princes and Princesses, or the court officials could not afford to have them be demoted from nobility to subject, (It is needless to say that the Princes who went into the priesthood would not have any children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>前近代の後宮制度の充実ぶりにも関わらず、中世以後に皇統断絶の危機が何度も生じたのはこうした事情がある）状態にあったが、世襲親王家が断絶した場合には天皇が実子を養子として送り込む事で子孫の安泰を図る事も行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was the reason why there was many crisis of the discontinuity of the Imperial succession after the Medieval Period, although the system of the Inner Palace in premodern time was well established.) there was an example of Emperor let his child being adopted to the hereditary Imperial family to secure the succession of the descendants, if there was a crisis of the discontinuity of the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the reason why there were many crisis of discontinuity of Imperial succession after the Medieval Period, even though the system of the Inner Palace in premodern time was well established.) there were even examples of an Emperor allowing his child to be adopted into the hereditary Imperial family to secure the succession of descendants, if there was a crisis of the discontinuity of the family.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the reason why there were many crisis of discontinuity of Imperial succession after the Medieval Period, even though the system of the Inner Palace in premodern time was well established.) there were even examples of an Emperor allowing his child to be adopted into the hereditary Imperial Family to secure the succession of descendants, if there was a crisis of the discontinuity of the family.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="154">
<j>光格以後は、すべて直系男子により皇位継承が行われて現在に至っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Emperor Kokaku&apos;s era, the Imperial throne was succeeded by the male Imperial member of the direct line which was continued to the present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the era of Emperor Kokaku, the Imperial throne was succeeded by a male Imperial member of the direct line which has continued to the present.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity and grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the era of Emperor Kokaku, the Imperial throne was succeeded by a male Imperial member of the direct line which has continued to the present.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>明治天皇の時に退位禁止と養子禁止と直系男子への皇位継承優先について定めた旧皇室典範が制定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While it was Emperor Meiji&apos;s era, a former Imperial Family Law was issued which included the prohibition of the abdication, prohibition of the adoption, and priority of the male direct Imperial member&apos;s succession to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During Emperor Meiji&apos;s era, a former Imperial Family Law was issued which included the prohibition of abdication, prohibition of adoption, and a priority for a male, direct Imperial member&apos;s, succession to the throne.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity and grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During Emperor Meiji&apos;s era, a former Imperial Family Law was issued which included the prohibition of abdication, prohibition of adoption, and a priority for a male, direct Imperial member&apos;s, succession to the throne.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>昭和時代、日本国憲法の下で皇室典範は再度制定されたが、退位禁止と養子禁止と直系男子への皇位継承優先とする基本性格は変わらず、非嫡出子を皇族としない規定が追加された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Showa period, the Imperial Family Law was re-issued under the Constitution of Japan, the basic rule of the prohibition of the abdication, prohibition of the adoption, and priority of the male direct Imperial member&apos;s succession to the throne, remained the same, there was another regulation added that the legimate children would not be included to the Imperial family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Showa period, the Imperial Family Law was re-issued under the Constitution of Japan, the basic rule of the prohibition of the abdication, prohibition of the adoption, and priority of the male direct Imperial member&apos;s succession to the throne, remained the same, there was another regulation added that illegitimate children would not be included to the Imperial family.</e>
<cmt>legimate is obviously spelled wrong, it is either legitimate or illegitimate and I suspect the latter, but it needs to be confirmed with the translator→ It should be illegitimate, my apology, it was spelling mistake.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Showa period, the Imperial Family Law was re-issued under the Constitution of Japan, the basic rule of the prohibition of the abdication, prohibition of the adoption, and priority of the male direct Imperial member&apos;s succession to the throne, remained the same, there was another regulation added that illegitimate children would not be included to the Imperial family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>課題</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subject</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subject</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subject</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="157">
<j>皇室典範の「皇統に屬（属）する男系の男子」という条文について、愛子内親王の生誕など天皇直系の皇位継承者の終端に女性しかいない問題が生じていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it was stated in the Imperial Family Law, &apos;the male member who belongs to Imperial family; there was an issue that there was no male Imperial successor in the direct line of the Imperial family, there was only female successor, after Imperial Princess Aiko was born.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is stated in Imperial Family Law, &apos;a male member who belongs to Imperial family;&apos; an issue appeared that there are no male Imperial successors in the direct line of the present Imperial family, there is only a female successor, after Imperial Princess Aiko was born.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is stated in Imperial Family Law, &apos;a male member who belongs to Imperial family;&apos; an issue appeared that there are no male Imperial successors in the direct line of the present Imperial family, there is only a female successor, after Imperial Princess Aiko was born.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>2006年の悠仁親王生誕により、一応は皇位継承者を確保できたが、依然として継承者不足に変わりはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Imperial Hisahito was born in 2006, there was an ease to have the Imperial successor, however the situation was yet the same that there were not enough successor to succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Imperial Hisahito was born in 2006, there was a sense of relief to have an Imperial successor, however the situation is still the same that there are not enough successors to succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Imperial Hisahito was born in 2006, there was a sense of relief to have an Imperial successor, however the situation is still the same that there are not enough successors to succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>そのため、女性天皇及び女系天皇の可能性も含めた議論が起こっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, there was an argument in terms of the succession to the throne including the possibility of the female Emperors or female Imperial family line to succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, there was a debate in terms of the succession to the throne including the possibility of a female Empress or female Imperial family line to succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, there was a debate in terms of the succession to the throne including the possibility of an Empress or female Imperial Family line to succeed to the throne.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正&quot;female Empress&quot; -&gt; &quot;Empress&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="160">
<j>日本の皇位継承を概観すると、歴史上、女帝は幾人かいたが、いずれも中継としての存在である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In general view of the Japanese Imperial succession, there were some female Emperors existed however they all succeeded to the throne temporally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In general view of Japanese Imperial succession, there have been some female Empresses, however, they all succeeded to the throne temporarily.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In general view of Japanese Imperial succession, there have been some Empresses, however, they all succeeded to the throne temporarily.</e>
<cmt>&quot;female Empresses&quot; -&gt; &quot;Empresses&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="161">
<j>皇統は男系によりつながれてきており、女系により次代へ継承された例はないことがわかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial line was continued by the male Imperial members, there was no example of the succession of the throne passed by the female Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial line was continued by the male Imperial members, there was no example of succession to the throne being passed on by a female Empress.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial line was continued by the male Imperial members, there was no example of succession to the throne being passed on by an Empress.</e>
<cmt>&quot;female Empress&quot; -&gt; &quot;Empress&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>そのため、直系男子による皇統が一旦断絶したとしても、古くは継体天皇から光仁天皇、光孝天皇、後嵯峨天皇、後花園天皇、光格天皇に至るまで、傍系ではあるが全て男系により皇統がつながれてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, even though Imperial line of the direct male Imperial members was one discontinued, between the era of Emperor Keitai in old days through to Emperor Konin, Emperor Kotoku, Emperor Gosaga, Emperor Gohanazono, Emperor Kokaku, the Imperial line was passed by the male Imperial members although it was with collateral line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, even though Imperial line of direct male Imperial members was discontinued, between the era of Emperor Keitai in old days through to Emperor Konin, Emperor Kotoku, Emperor Gosaga, Emperor Gohanazono, Emperor Kokaku, the Imperial line was passed by the male Imperial members although it was a collateral line.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, even though Imperial line of direct male Imperial members was discontinued, between the era of Emperor Keitai in old days through to Emperor Konin, Emperor Koko, Emperor Gosaga, Emperor Gohanazono, Emperor Kokaku, the Imperial line was passed by the male Imperial members although it was a collateral line.</e>
<cmt>名前修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="163">
<j>上皇（治天の君）－天皇の形態は男系での皇位継承を非常に安定させる形態だったが、明治以降、上皇の存在は廃止されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The retired emperor (Chiten no kimi) - the form of the succession to the Emperor was in secure form and it was passed by the male members of the Imperial family, however the position of the retired Emperor itself was abolished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The retired emperor (Chiten no kimi) - the form of the succession to the Emperor was in secure form and it was passed on by the male members of the Imperial family, however the position of the retired Emperor itself was abolished.</e>
<cmt>grammar &quot;on&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The retired Emperor (Chiten no kimi) - the form of the succession to the Emperor was in secure form and it was passed on by the male members of the Imperial family, however the position of the retired Emperor itself was abolished.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="164">
<j>このように皇統は男系で連綿と継続されてきたが、近年、皇室に男子の誕生が長らくなかったことなどから、女系継承の容認の可否が議論の対象となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this way, the Imperial succession by the male Imperial member was passed from generations to generations, since there was no male successors were born in the Imperial family for a while, there is an argument of whether or not to accept the Imperial succession by the female Imperial members.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this way, Imperial succession by a male Imperial member was passed from generation to generation, since there were no male successors born in the Imperial family for a while, there is a debate on whether or not to accept the Imperial succession by female Imperial members.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this way, Imperial succession by a male Imperial member was passed from generation to generation, since there were no male successors born in the Imperial family for a while, there is a debate on whether or not to accept the Imperial succession by female Imperial members.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>日本の皇位継承は、皇室始まって以来の男系の伝統をつないでいくか、女系を容認して旧来の皇統と決別し、新たな皇統を創設していくかの岐路に立っていると言えるだろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japanese Imperial succession, it is at the crossroad to end the old tradition and establish new Imperial line, whether to keep the traditional Imperial succession by the male Imperial line since the beginning of the Imperial family, or to accept the succession by the female Imperial line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese Imperial succession, it is at the crossroads to end the old tradition and establisha new Imperial lineage, whether to keep the traditional Imperial succession by the male Imperial line since the beginning of the Imperial family, or to accept succession from the female Imperial lineage.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese Imperial succession, it is at the crossroads to end the old tradition and establish new Imperial lineage, whether to keep the traditional Imperial succession by the male Imperial line since the beginning of the Imperial family, or to accept succession from the female Imperial lineage.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 唐変木(id:17050), 東 遥(id:37435), いろはにほへと(id:89648), 霧木諒二(id:9795), なめこ汁(id:128895), MIsogi(id:20599), 経済準学士(id:22656), ウィキピーディアン(id:38549), 水野白楓(id:22811), Brownsugar(id:20678), Hrs885(id:104160), マルシー(id:103194), Amler(id:101250), 海衛士(id:19229), Shimoxx(id:9332), 伏儀(id:142093), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>