<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>尊雅王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Songa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Songa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Songa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>尊雅王（そんがおう、生没年不詳）は、鎌倉時代後期の皇族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Songa (date of birth and death unknown) was a member of the Imperial family in the late Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Songa (date of birth and death unknown) was a member of the Imperial family during the late Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Songa (date of birth and death unknown) was a member of the Imperial Family during the late Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>Imperial Family としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>四辻宮家第2代。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the second generation of Yotsutsujinomiya family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the second generation of Yotsutsujinomiya family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the second generation of Yotsutsujinomiya family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>初代善統親王の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the son of Imperial Prince Yoshimune, who was the first generation of the Yotsutsujinomiya family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the son of Imperial Prince Yoshimune, who was the first generation of the Yotsutsujinomiya family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the son of Imperial Prince Yoshimune, who was the first generation of the Yotsutsujinomiya family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>子に紀通清妻智泉聖通（足利義満外祖母）及び左大臣四辻善成がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His children included 紀通清妻 Chisen Shotsu (the maternal grandmother of Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA) and Yoshinari YOTSUTSUJI, who held the title of Sadaijin (minister of the left).</e>
<cmt>「紀通清妻」は読み方が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children included 紀通清妻 Chisen Shotsu (the maternal grandmother of Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA) and Yoshinari YOTSUTSUJI, who held the title of Sadaijin (minister of the left).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children included Chisen Shotsu (the maternal grandmother of Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA) who was a wife of KI no Tsusei, and Yoshinari YOTSUTSUJI, who held the title of Sadaijin (minister of the left).</e>
<cmt>紀通清→KI no Tsusei　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>その生涯については謎が多く、父とされる善統親王死去の前年正和5年（1316年）に所領を譲られた「四辻若宮」と同一人物であったと推定できるのみである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His life is mostly unknown; it is only assumed that he was the same person as &quot;Yotsutsuji Wakamiya&quot; (a young imperial prince of Yotsutsuji) who was given the territory in 1316, one year before his father, supposedly Imperial Prince Yoshimune, died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His life is mostly unknown; it is only assumed that he was the same person as &quot;Yotsutsuji Wakamiya&quot; (a young imperial prince of Yotsutsuji) who was given the territory in 1316, one year before his father, supposedly Imperial Prince Yoshimune, died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His life is mostly unknown; it is only assumed that he was the same person as &apos;Yotsutsuji Wakamiya&apos; (a young Imperial Prince of Yotsutsuji) who was given the territory in 1316, one year before his father, supposedly Imperial Prince Yoshimune, died.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また、この時既に善統親王は84歳であり、「若宮」と呼ぶべき実子の存在を疑問視する説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this occasion, however, Imperial Prince Yoshimune was already 84 years old, and therefore some are skeptical about the hypothesis that he had a biological son called &quot;Wakamiya&quot; (a young imperial prince).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this occasion, however, Imperial Prince Yoshimune was already 84 years old, and therefore some are skeptical about the hypothesis that he had a biological son called &quot;Wakamiya&quot; (a young imperial prince).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this occasion, however, Imperial Prince Yoshimune was already 84 years old, and therefore some are skeptical about the hypothesis that he had a biological son called &apos;Wakamiya&apos; (a young imperial prince).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>小川剛生は、岩蔵宮忠房親王の子で善統親王の養子となったとする仮説を提示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeo OGAWA have hypothesized that Prince Songa was a son of Iwakuranomiya Imperial Prince Tadafusa and became adopted by Imperial Prince Yoshimune.</e>
<cmt>「岩蔵宮」は「岩倉宮」の誤記かと思われます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takeo OGAWA hypothesized that Prince Songa was the son of Iwakuranomiya Imperial Prince Tadafusa and was adopted by Imperial Prince Yoshimune.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeo OGAWA hypothesized that Prince Songa was the son of Imperial Prince Iwakuranomiya Tadafusa and was adopted by Imperial Prince Yoshimune.</e>
<cmt>Imperial Prince Iwakuranomiya Tadafusa としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>