<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>建皇子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeru no miko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takeru no miko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeru no miko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>建皇子（たけるのみこ、白雉2年（651年） - 皇極天皇4年（658年）は、飛鳥時代の皇族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeru no miko (651 - 658 or the fourth year of Empress Kogyoku&apos;s reign) was an imperial prince in Asuka period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takeru no miko (651 - 658) was a member of the Imperial Family in the Asuka period.</e>
<cmt>カッコ内を修正しました。an imperial prince→a member of the Imperial Family と修正しました。the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeru no miko (651 - 658) was a member of the Imperial Family in the Asuka period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>天智天皇の第二皇子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the second imperial prince of Emperor Tenchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the second prince of the Emperor Tenchi.</e>
<cmt>imperial prince→prince と修正しました。the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the second prince of the Emperor Tenchi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は蘇我倉山田石川麻呂の娘・遠智娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was Ochi no iratsume, who was a daughter of SOGANOKURA-YAMADA no Ishikawamaro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was Ochi no iratsume, who was a daughter of SOGANOKURA-YAMADA no Ishikawamaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was Ochi no iratsume, who was a daughter of SOGANOKURA-YAMADA no Ishikawamaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>同母姉に大田皇女・持統天皇がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had older maternal half-sisters, Ota no himemiko and Emperor Jito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had older sisters-uterine, Ota no himemiko and the Empress Jito.</e>
<cmt>maternal half-sisters→sisters-uterine,Emperor Jito→Empress Jito と修正しました。the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had older sisters-uterine, Ota no himemiko and the Empress Jito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>日本書紀に「唖にして語ふこと能はず」とあり、言葉を話せなかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he was incapable of speech, as described in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) that &apos;he was a dumb person who cannot speak&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he was incapable of speech, as described in Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan) that &apos;he was a dumb person who cannot speak.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーツを削除しました。スペース、ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he was incapable of speech, as described in Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan) that &apos;he was a dumb person who cannot speak.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>唖の原因として、母・遠智娘が父・倉山田石川麻呂（皇子にとっては祖父）を中大兄皇子に処刑され、悲しみのあまり狂乱した状態で出産したため、遠智娘の精神異常が皇子に影響したのではないか、という説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a theory about the cause of his mutism; mental disorder of his mother, Ochi no iratsume, might affect the prince because she gave birth to him in a frenzy of grief over the capital punishment on her father (the prince&apos;s grandfather), KURAYAMADA no Ishikawamaro, executed by Naka no Oe no Oji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a theory about the cause of his muteness saying that, the madness of his mother, the prince Ochi no iratsume might have affected, because she gave birth to him in a frenzied state of mind, since her father KURAYAMADA no Ishikawamaro (the prince&apos;s grandfather) was executed by Naka no Oe no Oji.</e>
<cmt>文脈に応じてスムースに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a theory about the cause of his muteness saying that, the madness of his mother, the prince Ochi no iratsume might have affected, because she gave birth to him in a frenzied state of mind, since her father KURAYAMADA no Ishikawamaro (the prince&apos;s grandfather) was executed by Naka no Oe no Oji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>皇子を憐れんで祖母・皇極天皇は皇子をとても可愛がったと日本書紀に記載されており、「萬歳千秋の後に、要ず朕が陵に合せ葬れ」と言い、自分が崩御した際一緒に合葬せよと命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot;, feeling pity towards the prince, his grandmother, Empress Kogyoku, doted so fondly on him that she ordered at the time of her demise to bury him together with her, saying that &apos;Even after a long period of time, be certain to bury him together with me in my tomb&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the Nihonshoki, feeling pity towards the prince, his grandmother, the Empress Kogyoku, doted so fondly on him that she ordered at the time of her demise to bury him together with her, saying that &apos;even after a long period of time, be certain to bury him together with me in my tomb.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーツを削除しました。the を補いました。Even→even,ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the Nihonshoki, feeling pity towards the prince, his grandmother, the Empress Kogyoku, doted so fondly on him that she ordered at the time of her demise to bury him together with her, saying that &apos;even after a long period of time, be certain to bury him together with me in my tomb.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その遺言通り、現在は斉明天皇陵に埋葬されている（近くには叔母・間人皇女と姉・大田皇女も埋葬されている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In accordance with the will, he is entombed in the Imperial mausoleum of Empress Saimei (His aunt, Hashihito no Himemiko and his elder sister, Ota no himemiko, is also entombed nearby).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In accordance with the will, he has been entombed in the Imperial mausoleum of the Empress Saimei (His aunt, Hashihito no Himemiko and his older sister, Ota no himemiko, have also been entombed nearby.)</e>
<cmt>is→has been と修正しました。the 補いました。カッコ内を修正しました。ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In accordance with the will, he has been entombed in the Imperial mausoleum of the Empress Saimei (His aunt, Hashihito no Himemiko and his older sister, Ota no himemiko, have also been entombed nearby.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), Masyu(id:31065), Tinecici(id:192914), きまま(id:183217), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>