<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>後小松天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Go-Komatsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Go-Komatsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Gokomatsu</e>
<cmt>Gokomatsu としました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>後小松天皇（ごこまつてんのう、永和3年/天授3年6月27日（1377年8月1日） - 永享5年10月20日（1433年12月1日））は、室町時代北朝最後の第6代、歴代第100代の天皇（在位永徳2年/弘和2年4月11日（1382年5月24日） - 応永19年8月29日（1412年10月5日））。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Go-Komatsu (August 1st, 1377 - December 1st, 1433) was the last 6th Emperor in the Muromachi period, Northern Dynasty, or the 100th Emperor. (his reign was May 24th, 1382 - October 5th, 1412.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Go-Komatsu (August 1, 1377 - December 1, 1433) was the sixth and last Emperor of the Muromachi period (Northern Dynasty), or the 100th Emperor (his reign was from May 24, 1382 to October 5, 1412).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Gokomatsu (August 1, 1377 - December 1, 1433) was the sixth and last Emperor of the Muromachi period (Northern Court), or the 100th Emperor (his reign was from May 24, 1382 to October 5, 1412).</e>
<cmt>Gokomatsu, Northern Court としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>名は幹仁（もとひと）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His first name was Motohito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His first name was Motohito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His first name was Motohito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>明治44年（1911年）に南朝が正統とされたため、在位期間が明徳の和約以降（1392-1412）に繰り下げられてしまっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1911 as the Southern Dynasty was considered as standard period, since the peace settlement of Meitoku Era, the period of the Emperor&apos;s reign was put off to 1392 - 1412.</e>
<cmt>明徳の和約→the peace settlement of Meitoku Era [定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1911, given that the Southern Dynasty was considered the standard period since the peace settlement of the Meitoku era, the period of the Emperor&apos;s reign was re-established as having lasted from 1392 to 1412.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Southern Court was determined to be the standard in 1911, the period of the Emperor&apos;s reign was re-established as having lasted from 1392 to 1412 which is after the peace settlement of the Meitoku era.</e>
<cmt>Southern Court としました。原文の通りに翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>それまでは一貫して現皇統につながる北朝が正統とされていたため北朝在位年数（1382-1412）を使用していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then it was considered the Northern Dynasty, which lead to current Imperial line all the time, to be the standard period, thus the period of the Emperor&apos;s reign was being used. (1382 - 1412)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then it was considered the Northern Dynasty, which ultimately led to the current imperial line as the standard period, so that the period of the Emperor&apos;s reign was used (1382 - 1412).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until then the Northern Court, which ultimately led to the current Imperial line, was considered as the standard period, therefore the period of the Emperor&apos;s reign in the Northern Court was used (1382 - 1412).</e>
<cmt>Northern Court としました。until thenとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>系譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>後円融天皇の第1皇子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the first Prince of Emperor Go-Enyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the first prince of Emperor Go-Enyo.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the first prince of Emperor Goenyu.</e>
<cmt>Goenyu　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>母は内大臣三条公忠の娘、通陽門院藤原厳子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was Naidaijin (Uchi no otodo), Kintada SANJO&apos;s daughter, Tsuyo mon in FUJIWARA no Takako.</e>
<cmt>内大臣→Naidaijin (Uchi no otodo) Yahoo 辞書　[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was Tsuyo mon in FUJIWARA no Takako, the daughter of Naidaijin (Uchi no otodo) (Kintada SANJO).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was Tsuyomonin FUJIWARA no Takako, the daughter of Kintada SANJO, who was a Naidaijin (Uchi no otodo: minister of the center).</e>
<cmt>内大臣に　minister of the centerと補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また、風狂の禅僧一休宗純は後小松の落胤とも伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also it is said a sophisticated Zen priest, Sojun IKKYU was the illegitimate child of Emperor Go-Komatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, it is said that a sophisticated Zen priest, Sojun IKKYU, was the illegitimate child of Emperor Go-Komatsu.</e>
<cmt>Also → Moreover</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, it is said that a sophisticated Zen priest, Sojun IKKYU, was the illegitimate child of Emperor Gokomatsu.</e>
<cmt>Gokomatsu としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>日野資教邸で養育される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was brought up in Sukenori HINO&apos;s palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was brought up in the palace of Sukenori HINO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was brought up in the palace of Sukenori HINO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>弘和2年（1382年）12月28日、父の後円融天皇の譲位を受けて6歳で即位、後円融上皇による院政が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 28th, 1382, Emperor Go-Komatsu succeeded to the throne when he was six years old, after his father, Emperor Go-Enyo passed the throne to him, the ex-Emperor Go-Enyo started the cloister government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 28, 1382, Emperor Go-Komatsu succeeded to the throne at the age of six, and after his father, Emperor Go-Enyo, passed the throne to him, Go-Enyo, now the ex-emperor, started the cloister government.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 28, 1382, Emperor Gokomatsu succeeded to the throne at the age of six after his father, Emperor Goenyu passed the throne to him, and the Emperor Goenyu, now the Retired Emperor, started the cloister government.</e>
<cmt>Goenyu, Gokomatsuに修正しました。　接続詞の場所を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>朝廷内部にまで政治的影響力を及ぼし多くの公家を主従関係の下に置いた室町幕府3代将軍足利義満と上皇の関係は険悪であり、両者は対立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The relationship between the Muromachi Shogunate, 3rd Shogun, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, who influenced his political power to inside the Imperial Palace and had many court nobles under the relation between master and servant, and the ex-Emperor was abrupt and both parties opposed each others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was an abrupt relationship between the ex-Emperor and the Muromachi shogunate--the third Shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, who influenced his political power within the Imperial Palace and held many court nobles in the relationship of master and servant--and each party opposed each other.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was an abrupt relationship between the Retired Emperor and the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) --the third Shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, who influenced his political power within the Imperial Palace and held many court nobles in the relationship of master and servant--and each party opposed each other.</e>
<cmt>Retired Emperorとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>明徳4年（1393年）に後円融上皇が死去すると、義満はさらに朝廷への影響を強め、事実上の上皇として、後世「義満の院政」などと呼ばれる権力を振るい、後小松はその下でまったくの傀儡に甘んじた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Emperor Go-Enyo died in 1393, Yoshimitsu had even strong power to influence the Imperial Palace, he took control of the politics as an actual ex-emperor, in later years it was called &apos;Yoshimitsu&apos;s cloister government, while Emperor Go-Komatsu acted as a real person&apos;s tool.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following the death of the ex-Emperor Go-Enyo in 1393, Yoshimitsu had even greater power to influence the Imperial Palace and took control of politics as an actual ex-emperor; in later years it was called &apos;Yoshimitsu&apos;s cloister government,&apos; while Emperor Go-Komatsu acted as the tool of another person.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following the death of the Retired Emperor Goenyu in 1393, Yoshimitsu had even stronger power to influence the Imperial Palace and took control of the politics as an actual retired emperor; in later years it was called &apos;Yoshimitsu&apos;s cloister government,&apos; while Emperor Gokomatsu acted as the tool of another person.</e>
<cmt>Retired Emperor, Koenyu, Kokomatsuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>応永19年（1412年）8月29日、後小松は皇子の実仁親王（称光天皇）に譲位し、院政を開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 29th 1412, Emperor Go-Komatsu abdicated to pass the throne to his Prince, Prince Mihito (the Emperor Shoko) and started his cloister government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 29, 1412, Emperor Go-Komatsu abdicated to pass the throne to his prince, Mihito (the future Emperor Shoko) and started his cloister government.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 29, 1412, Emperor Gokomatsu abdicated to pass the throne to his son, Imperial Prince Mihito (the future Emperor Shoko) and started his cloister government.</e>
<cmt>Imperial Prince　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>これは明徳3年（1392年）の南北朝合一の際の条件である両統迭立に反しており、その後南朝勢力はしばしば反発して武装蜂起する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was against the agreement of sharing Imperial succession decided on the Northern and Southern Dynasties union in 1392, after that both parties often opposed each others and armed uprising.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was against the agreement of sharing imperial succession as decided by the union of the Northern and Southern dynasties in 1392, and subsequently the two sides often opposed each other in armed conflicts.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was against the agreement of sharing imperial succession as decided by the union of the Northern and Southern Courts in 1392, and subsequently the two sides often opposed each other in armed conflicts.</e>
<cmt>courts としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>称光天皇は病弱でたびたび重態に陥り、皇子の誕生もなく、また後小松の次男小川宮も早世したため後継者問題が生じ、後小松上皇は4代将軍足利義持と協議、後継者として崇光流の伏見宮貞成親王が有力視され、一時は後小松の猶子として親王宣下された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Emperor Shoko was weak and often became serious condition, he did not have any children to succeed to be Price, also Go-Shirakawa&apos; s second son, Ogawa no miya died young, there was an issue who to succeed the throne, after ex-Emperor Go-Komatsu had a meeting with 4th Shogun Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA, Fushimi no miya Prince Sadfafusa of Suko Ryu (a descendant of the Emperor Suko) was appointed as a successor once he received to title Prince by the Imperial order and be Go-Komatsu&apos;s adopted child.</e>
<cmt>崇光流→Suko ryu (a descendant of the Emperor Suko) [定訳不明] [親王宣下→to title Prince by the Imperial order] [定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Emperor Shoko was weak and often in serious condition, he had no child who could succeed as a prince; moreover, Go-Shirakawa&apos;s second son Ogawa no miya died young, so there was the issue of who would succeed to the throne; however, after ex-Emperor Go-Komatsu had a meeting with the fourth shogun, Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA, Fushimi no miya Prince Sadafusa of Suko Ryu (a descendant of Emperor Suko) was appointed as a successor once he received the title of a prince by the imperial order and became Go-Komatsu&apos;s adopted child.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Emperor Shoko was weak and often in serious condition, he did not have any children to succeed as prince; moreover, Gokomatsu&apos;s second son Ogawanomiya died young, so there was the issue of who would succeed to the throne; however, after Retired Emperor Gokomatsu had a meeting with the fourth Shogun Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA, Imperial Prince Fushiminomiya Sadafusa of Suko Ryu (a descendant of Emperor Suko) was appointed as a successor once he received the title of a Imperial Prince by the imperial order and became Gokomatsu&apos;s adopted child.</e>
<cmt>retired emperor Ogawanomiya Fushiminomiya　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>しかし、これには称光が激しく反発したため、貞成は出家して皇位継承を断念した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However Emperor Shoko opposed to above severely and Sadafusa became a priest and gave up on succeeding the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Emperor Shoko was strongly opposed to the arrangement, and Sadafusa became a priest and gave up on the plan of succeeding to the throne.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Emperor Shoko was strongly opposed to the arrangement, and Sadafusa became a priest and gave up on the plan of succeeding to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>正長元年（1428年）にいよいよ称光が危篤となると、6代将軍足利義教の仲介で貞成の子息彦仁を猶子とし、後花園天皇として即位させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1428 when Emperor Shoko was in the critical condition, the 6th Shogun, Yoshinitsu ASHIKAGA acted as intermediary, Prince Shoko&apos;s son, Hikohito was adopted by the Emperor and succeeded to the throne as Emperor Go-Hanazono.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1428, when Emperor Shoko was in critical condition, the sixth shogun, Yoshinitsu ASHIKAGA, acted as an intermediary, and Prince Shoko&apos;s son Hikohito was adopted by the Emperor and succeeded to the throne as Emperor Go-Hanazono.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1428, when Emperor Shoko was in critical condition, the sixth Shogun Yoshinori ASHIKAGA acted as an intermediary, and Sadafusa&apos;s son Hikohito was adopted by the Emperor and succeeded to the throne as Emperor Gohanazono.</e>
<cmt>Yoshinori, Gohanazono としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>称光・後花園の2代にわたり院政を行い、この間永享3年（1431年）に出家している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During second generation Shoko and Go-Hanazono&apos;s eras, Emperor Go-Komatsu ruled his cloister government and became a priest while this period in 1431.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the eras of the second-generation Shoko and Go-Hanazono, Emperor Go-Komatsu ruled his cloister government; he became a priest during this period, in 1431.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the eras of the two generations, Shoko and Gohanazono, Emperor Gokomatsu ruled his cloister government; he became a priest during this period, in 1431.</e>
<cmt>second generation→two generationとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>永享5年（1433年）10月20日に死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died on October 20th, 1433.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died on October 20, 1433.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died on October 20, 1433.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>享年57。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was fifty seven years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was 57 years old.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was fifty-seven years old.</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>諡号・追号・異名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Posthumous name, Tsuigo, different name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Posthumous name, Tsuigo, a different name</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Posthumous name, Tsuigo, a different name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>遺諡により「後小松院」と追号された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had a posthumous name of &apos;Go-Komatsu in&apos;, followed by his own will.</e>
<cmt>遺諡→[諡号、追号を自らの遺勅によって決めること]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had the posthumous name &apos;Go-Komatsu in,&apos; which was conferred according to his will.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had the posthumous name &apos;Gokomatsuin,&apos; which was conferred according to his will.</e>
<cmt>Gokomatsuin としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>ちなみに「小松帝」は第58代光孝天皇の異名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For reference&apos;s sake, &apos;Emperor Komatsu is the different name of 58th Emperor Koko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For reference, &apos;Emperor Komatsu&apos; is the different name for the fifty-eighth Emperor, Koko.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For reference, &apos;Emperor Komatsu&apos; is the different name for the fifty-eighth Emperor, Koko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>光孝天皇は兄の孫・陽成天皇の廃位のち皇位につき、その子孫は長く皇位を保った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Koko enthroned after his brother&apos;s grandchild, Emperor Yozei died, and his descendant kept the succession to the Imperial Throne for a long time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Koko was enthroned after the death of his brother&apos;s grandchild, Emperor Yozei, and his descendants kept the succession to the Imperial Throne for a long time.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Koko was enthroned after the death of his brother&apos;s grandchild, Emperor Yozei, and his descendants kept the succession to the Imperial Throne for a long time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>崇光天皇系への皇統移行が現実となった今、自らの正統性を諡号によって示そうとした後小松の固い意志が感じ取れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the family line of Imperial succession changed to Emperor Suko&apos;s line, Emperor Go-Komatsu showed his strong will to justify his own Imperial line by having this posthumous name.</e>
<cmt>崇光天皇系→the family line of the Emperor Suko [定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the family line of imperial succession changed to Emperor Suko&apos;s line, Emperor Go-Komatsu showed his considerable will to justify his own imperial line by having this posthumous name.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the family line of imperial succession changed to Emperor Suko&apos;s line, Emperor Gokomatsu showed his considerable will to justify his own imperial line by having this posthumous name.</e>
<cmt>Gokomatsu としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>また、称光天皇の容態が思わしくなかった1426年に後小松が『本朝皇胤紹運録』の作成を命じて、皇室の系図の整理を行わせているのもこうした自身の正統性への思い入れの反映であると考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Go-Komatsu ordered to edit &quot;Honcho Koin Joun roku&quot; to organize the Imperial family records in 1426, while Emperor Shoko was ill, it also shows that the Emperor Go-Komatsu strongly believed the justice of his family line succeed the Imperial throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Go-Komatsu, in 1426, ordered that &quot;Honcho Koin Joun roku&quot; be edited so as to organize the Imperial Family records, at a time in which Emperor Shoko was ill; additionally, it shows that the Emperor Go-Komatsu strongly believed the justice of his family line in succeeding to the Imperial Throne.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Gokomatsu, in 1426, ordered that &quot;Honcho Koin Joun roku&quot; be edited so as to organize the Imperial Family records, at a time in which Emperor Shoko was ill; additionally, it shows that the Emperor Gokomatsu strongly believed the justice of his family line in succeeding to the Imperial Throne.</e>
<cmt>Gokomatsu としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>在位中の元号</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eras during his reign</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eras during his reign</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eras during his reign</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>永徳 （1382年4月11日) - 1384年2月27日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eitoku (April 11, 1382) - February 27, 1384</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eitoku (April 11, 1382) - February 27, 1384</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eitoku (April 11, 1382) - February 27, 1384</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="26">
<j>至徳 1384年2月27日 - 1387年8月23日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shitoku February 27, 1384 - August 23, 1387)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shitoku February 27, 1384 - August 23, 1387)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shitoku February 27, 1384 - August 23, 1387</e>
<cmt>括弧を削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="27">
<j>嘉慶 1387年8月23日 - 1389年2月9日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kakei August 23, 1387 - February 9, 1389</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kakei August 23, 1387 - February 9, 1389</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kakei August 23, 1387 - February 9, 1389</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="28">
<j>康応 1389年2月29日 - 1390年3月26日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ko-ou February 29, 1389 - July 5, 1394</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ko-ou February 29, 1389 - July 5, 1394</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koo February 29, 1389 - March 26, 1390</e>
<cmt>Kooとしました。数字を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="29">
<j>明徳 1390年3月26日 - 1394年7月5日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meitoku March 26, 1390 - July 5, 1394</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meitoku March 26, 1390 - July 5, 1394</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meitoku March 26, 1390 - July 5, 1394</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="30">
<j>応永 1394年7月5日 - （1421年12月19日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ouei July 5, 1394 - (December 19, 1421)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ouei July 5, 1394 - (December 19, 1421)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oei July 5, 1394 - (December 19, 1421)</e>
<cmt>Oei としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>陵墓・霊廟</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial mausoleum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Mausoleum</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial mausoleum</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="31">
<j>京都市伏見区深草坊町にある深草北陵（ふかくさのきたのみささぎ）に葬られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor was entombed in Fukakusano Kita no Misasagi at Fukakusa Bo-cho Town, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor was entombed in Fukakusano Kita no Misasagi at Fukakusa Bo-cho Town, in the Fushimi ward of Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor was entombed in Fukakusa no Kita no Misasagi at Fukakusa Bo-cho, in the Fushimi Ward of Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>Fukakusa no Kita no Misasagi としました。Town　を削除しました。Ward としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Sat666(id:127263), 霧木諒二(id:9795), Nnh(id:474), China(id:10362), Cprobot(id:97843), アダモステ(id:159115), Faso(id:11300), でここ(id:9565), 甲山(id:28084), 代言人(id:33675), 名無し(id:7386), Rei-bot(id:94097), Chobot(id:20846), 葉村史陽(id:15735), Kouko0515(id:100370), LERK(id:4460), Lemon pie(id:66842), Lonicera(id:20638), Equaly(id:89792), Bergmann(id:85282), 可怜(id:206074), 水野白楓(id:22811), Tiyoringo(id:70026), Tcyiswalk(id:7279), Zwobot(id:23873), 呆庵入道(id:74721), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), Nidarin(id:6420), YurikBot(id:18605), Geogie(id:143809), 総督(id:124846), Shikai shaw(id:14306), YOSHI438(id:174755), Yoyuuu!(id:18690), SieBot(id:126695), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>