<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>天智天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor TENCHI (TENJI)</e>
<cmt>英辞郎 on the WEB　(-天皇)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Tenchi (Tenji)</e>
<cmt>Lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Tenchi (Tenji)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>天智天皇（てんちてんのう／てんじてんのう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor TENCHI (TENJI)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Tenchi (Tenji)</e>
<cmt>Lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Tenchi (Tenji)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>男性。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Male</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Male</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Male</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>推古天皇34年（626年）- 天智天皇10年12月3日（672年1月7日）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor SUIKO (626) - Emperor TENCHI (TENJI) (7th January 672)</e>
<cmt>推古天皇 http://womenshistory.about.com/od/empresssuiko/p/empress_suiko.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Suiko (626) - Emperor Tenchi (Tenji) (January 7, 672)</e>
<cmt>Lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Empress Suiko (626) - Emperor Tenchi (Tenji) (January 10, 672)</e>
<cmt>性別の取り違えを修正しました。&quot;7&quot; -&gt; &quot;10&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>第38代天皇。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 38th Emperor</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 38th Emperor</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 38th Emperor</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>国風諡号は天命開別尊（あめみことひらかすわけのみこと／あまつみことさきわけのみこと）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokufu Shigo is Amemikoto hirakasuwake no mikoto/Amatsumikoto sakiwake no mikoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokufu Shigo is Amemikoto hirakasuwake no mikoto/Amatsumikoto sakiwake no mikoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokufu Shigo is Amemikoto hirakasuwake no mikoto/Amatsumikoto sakiwake no mikoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>諱は葛城（かづらき/かつらぎ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first name is Katsuraki/Katsuragi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first name is Katsuraki (Katsuragi).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first name is Kazuraki (Katsuragi).</e>
<cmt>読みを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>生前は葛城皇子（かづらきのみこ/かつらぎのみこ）と呼ばれていたと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is presumed that he used to be called Katsuraki no miko/Katsuragi no miko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is presumed that he used to be called Katsuraki no miko (Katsuragi no miko).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is presumed that he was once called Kazuraki no miko (Katsuragi no miko).</e>
<cmt>読みを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>一般には中大兄皇子（なかのおおえのおうじ／なかのおおえのみこ）として知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally known as NakanoOe no Oji/Nakano Oe no Miko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally known as Nakano Oe no Oji (Nakano Oe no Miko).</e>
<cmt>Spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is generally known as Nakano Oe no Oji (Naka no Oe no Miko).</e>
<cmt>スペース入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>「大兄」とは皇太子の意で、「中大兄」は「次の皇太子」を意味する語。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;oe&quot; means Prince and &quot;Nakanooe&quot; means &quot;2nd Prince&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;oe&quot; means &quot;prince,&quot; and &quot;Nakanooe&quot; means &quot;second prince.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;oe&quot; means &quot;prince,&quot; and &quot;Nakano oe&quot; means &quot;second prince.&quot;</e>
<cmt>スペース入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>概観</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Overview</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Overview</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Overview</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>舒明天皇の第二皇子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second prince of Emperor JOME</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the second prince of Emperor Jome.</e>
<cmt>Lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the second prince of Emperor Jome.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>母は宝皇女（のちの皇極天皇）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mother is Takara no Himemiko (later called Empress Kogyoku)</e>
<cmt>皇極天皇 http://p-www.iwate-pu.ac.jp/~acro-ito/Japan_pics/Japan_NNG/imageidx.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The mother was Takara no Himemiko (later called Empress Kogyoku)</e>
<cmt>Lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The mother was Takara no Himemiko (later called Empress Kogyoku).</e>
<cmt>ピリオド抜け</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>皇后は異母兄・古人大兄皇子の娘・倭姫王。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Empress is Yamatohime no Okimi, daughter of Emperor&apos;s half brother, Furuhito no Oe no Miko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Empress was Yamatohime no Okimi, daughter of Emperor&apos;s half-brother, Furuhito no Oe no Miko.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Empress was Yamatohime no Okimi, daughter of Emperor&apos;s half-brother, Furuhito no Oe no Miko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>中臣鎌足らと謀り、クーデターを起こして蘇我入鹿を殺害し、叔父・孝徳天皇を即位させ、自身は皇太子となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor TENCHI/TENJI plot a rebellion with NAKATOMI no Kamatari and seize power in a coup to kill SOGA no Iruka, his uncle Emperor KOTOKU came to power, and he himself became a prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor Tenchi/Tenji plotted a rebellion with Nakatomi no Kamatari and seized power in a coup to kill Soga no Iruka, by which his uncle Emperor Kotoku came to power and he became a prince.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor Tenchi (Tenji) plotted a rebellion with NAKATOMI no Kamatari and seized power in a coup to kill SOGA no Iruka, by which his uncle Emperor Kotoku came to power and he became a prince.</e>
<cmt>名字大文字</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>そして大化という元号を制定し、様々な改革を行なった（大化の改新の中心人物、乙巳の変）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He established new era, Taika and made many reforms of this period. (Key person of Taika reform, Itsushi no hen)</e>
<cmt>大化の改新 英辞郎 on the WEB, 乙巳の変 http://p-www.iwate-pu.ac.jp/~acro-ito/Japan_pics/Japan_NAS/imageidx.html）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He established a new era--the Taika--and made many reforms during this period (a pey person in the Taika reforms was Itsushi no hen).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He established a new era--the Taika--and made many reforms during this period (he was a key person in the Taika reforms and Itsushi no hen).</e>
<cmt>訳を一部修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また、有間皇子などのちのちクーデターを起こしそうな勢力を罠に嵌めて死刑とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He made a trap to an opposition group including ARIMA no Miko who may possibly cause a coop in the future, and they were executed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He devised a plan to trap an opposition group that included Arima no Miko, who might have caused a coup in the future, and they were executed.</e>
<cmt>Lowercase, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He devised a plan to trap an opposition group that included Arima no Miko, who might have caused a coup in the future, and they were executed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>百済が660年に唐・新羅に滅ぼされたため、朝廷に滞在していた百済王子・扶余豊璋を送り返し、百済復興を図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Baekje was destroyed by Silla (Kingdom)/Tang in 660 the Baekje prince, Buyeo Pung who was staying at the Imperial court was sent back to the country to save Baekje.</e>
<cmt>百済,唐,新羅 英辞郎 on the WEB, 扶余豊璋 http://www.geocities.jp/general_sasaki/naniwanomiya-eng.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Baekje was destroyed by the Silla (Kingdom) (Tang) in 660, the Baekje prince, Buyeo Pung, who was staying at the Imperial court, was sent back to his country to save Baekje.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Baekje was destroyed by the Silla (Kingdom) and Tang in 660, the Baekje prince, Buyeo Pung, who was staying at the Imperial Court, was sent back to his country to save Baekje.</e>
<cmt>NCでズレ</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>百済救援を指揮するために筑紫に滞在したが、661年、斉明天皇が崩御（死去）した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor stayed at Tsukushi to send a risqué troops to Baekje, however Emperor SAIMEI died in 661.</e>
<cmt>斉明天皇 http://p-www.iwate-pu.ac.jp/~acro-ito/Japan_pics/Japan_NNG/imageidx.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor stayed at Tsukushi to send covert troops to Baekje, but Emperor Saimei died in 661.</e>
<cmt>Lowercase, usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor stayed at Tsukushi to send covert troops to Baekje, but Empress Saimei died in 661.</e>
<cmt>性別の取り違えを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>その後、長い間皇位に即かず称制したが、663年、白村江の戦いで大敗を喫した後、大津市へ遷都してそこで即位した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After a while the Emperor took control of the government without having an enthronement ceremony, then he was severely defeated at Battle of Hakusukinoe and moved to Otsu-city to enthrone.</e>
<cmt>白村江の戦い http://www.docoja.com:8080/jisho/mainmap?dbname=histg&amp;mainword=Battle_of_Hakusukinoe、http://library.thinkquest.org/C001119/history/parse.php3?textonly=1&amp;src=early</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eventually, the Emperor took control of the government without having an enthronement ceremony, but then he was severely defeated at the Battle of Hakusukinoe and moved to Otsu-city to enthrone.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eventually, the Emperor took control of the government without having an enthronement ceremony, but then he was severely defeated in the Battle of Hakusukinoe and moved to Otsu City to be enthroned in 663.</e>
<cmt>年号を補いました。スペース削除ハイフン取る大文字</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>白村江の戦以後は、国土防衛の政策の一環として水城や烽火・防人を設置した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the battle of Hakusukinoe the castlele surrounded by the water was built and 烽火, Sakimori (conscript soldier system in old days) were organized to protect the territory.</e>
<cmt>烽火の読み、意味確認できず</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the battle of Hakusukinoe the castle surrounded by the water was built, and 烽火, Sakimori (the conscript soldier system in the old days) were organized to protect the territory.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Battle of Hakusukinoe a castle surrounded by water was built, and Noroshi and Sakimori (the conscript soldier system in the old days) were organized to protect the territory.</e>
<cmt>大文字烽火：のろし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>又、冠位もそれまでの十九階から二十六階に制度改革などを行なっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also the system to rank officials was changed from ninety levels into twelve levels.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, the system to rank officials was changed from 90 levels to 12 levels.</e>
<cmt>Numbering</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the system of ranking officials was changed from 19 levels to 26 levels.</e>
<cmt>数字の間違えを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また、670年には我が国最古の全国的な戸籍「庚午年籍」を作成させている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 670 the oldest national family registry &quot;Kogo-nenjaku&quot; was introduced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 670 the first national family registry, &quot;Kogo-nenjaku,&quot; was introduced.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 670 the first national family registry, &quot;Kogo-nenjaku,&quot; was introduced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="23">
<j>天智天皇は、第一皇子・大友皇子に皇位を継がせたかったと日本書紀は伝える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Chronicles of Japan (Nihon Shoki) the Emperor TENCHI/TENJI wished the first Prince, OTOMO Prince to be his successor.</e>
<cmt>日本書紀 英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Chronicles of Japan (Nihon Shoki),&quot; the Emperor Tenchi/Tenji wanted the first prince, Otomo, to be his successor.</e>
<cmt>Lowercase, redundancy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Chronicles of Japan (Nihon Shoki),&quot; the Emperor Tenchi (Tenji) wanted the first prince, Otomo no Miko, to be his successor.</e>
<cmt>「大友皇子」の訳を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>しかし、天智の死後に起きた壬申の乱において　弟・大海人皇子（天武天皇）が大友皇子に勝利して即位した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However after the death of Emperor TENCHI (TENJI) his brother Oama no Miko (Emperor Temmu) beated OTOMO no Miko at Jinshin war (Jinshin disturbance) and enthroned.</e>
<cmt>壬申の乱 http://www.docoja.com/dico/histxtg23.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after the death of Emperor Tenchi (Tenji) his brother, Oama no Miko (Emperor Temmu), defeated Otomo no Miko in the Jinshin War (the Jinshin Disturbance) and was enthroned.</e>
<cmt>Lowercase, uppercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after the death of Emperor Tenchi (Tenji) his brother, Oama no Miko (Emperor Temmu), defeated Otomo no Miko in the Jinshin War (the Jinshin Disturbance) and was enthroned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>以降、天武系統の天皇が称徳天皇まで続く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then Emperor TEMMU&apos;s ancestry continued to stay in power until Emperor Shotoku.</e>
<cmt>称徳天皇 http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110002362311/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, Emperor Temmu&apos;s ancestry remained in power until Emperor Shotoku.</e>
<cmt>Lowercase, usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, Emperor Temmu&apos;s ancestry remained in power until Empress Shotoku.</e>
<cmt>性別の取り違えを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>称徳の死後、天智の孫・白壁王が光仁天皇として即位し、それ以降は天智系統となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the enthronement of SIRAKABE no Okimi, a grandchild of Emperor TENCHI (TENJI) as an Emperor Konin, Emperor TENCHI&apos;s (TENJI) ancestry stayed in power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the enthronement of Sirakabe no Okimi--a grandchild of Emperor Tenchi (Tenji) as Emperor Konin--Emperor Tenchi&apos;s (Tenji&apos;s) ancestry stayed in power.</e>
<cmt>Lowercase, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Empress Shotoku, Sirakabe no Okimi, a grandchild of Emperor Tenchi (Tenji) was enthroned as Emperor Konin and subsequently Emperor Tenchi&apos;s (Tenji&apos;s) ancestry stayed in power.</e>
<cmt>一部訳を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="27">
<j>大海人皇子から額田王を奪ったので、罪滅ぼしとして（自分の）娘4人を大海人皇子の元に妃として送り込んだと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that because Emperor TENCHI (TENJI) took Nukata no Okimi away from Oama no Miko (Emperor Temmu), he sent his four daughters to Oama no Miko (Emperor Temmu) to become princesses for an expiation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that because Emperor Tenchi (Tenji) took Nukata no Okimi away from Oama no Miko (Emperor Temmu), he sent his four daughters to Oama no Miko (Emperor Temmu) to become princesses for an expiation.</e>
<cmt>Lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that because Emperor Tenchi (Tenji) took Nukata no Okimi away from Oama no Miko (Emperor Temmu), he sent his four daughters to Oama no Miko (Emperor Temmu) to become princesses for an expiation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="28">
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>&quot;Biography&quot; -&gt; &quot;Brief Personal History&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>推古34年（626年） - 誕生</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Born in 626.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Born in 626</e>
<cmt>No period</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Born in 626</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>皇極4年6月14日（645年7月12日） - 立太子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rittaishi (the ceremonial of instituting Crown Prince) on 12th July 645.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rittaishi (the ceremony to institute the Crown Prince) was held on July 12, 645.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rittaishi (the ceremony to institute the Crown Prince) was held on July 15, 645.</e>
<cmt>&quot;12&quot; -&gt; &quot;15&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>斉明7年7月24日（661年8月24日） - 称制</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Started the politics without having an enthronement ceremony on 24th August 661.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Politics began without having an enthronement ceremony August 24, 661.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Politics began without having an enthronement ceremony August 27, 661.</e>
<cmt>&quot;24&quot; -&gt; &quot;27&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>天智7年1月3日（668年2月20日） - 即位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enthroned on 20th February 668.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The enthronement was held on February 20, 668.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The enthronement was held on February 23, 668.</e>
<cmt>&quot;20&quot; -&gt; &quot;23&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>天智10年12月3日（672年1月7日） - 46歳で死去</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Died on 7th January 672 with forty six years of age, according to &quot;&quot;Fuso-Ryakki&quot; he died from his illness or another theory is he was missing in the mountain and there was a possibility of Emperor TEMMU tried to associate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died on January 7, 672 at age 46, and according to &quot;&quot;Fuso-Ryakki&quot; he died from his illness; another theory is that he was missing in the mountains and there was a possibility that Emperor Temmu tried to assassinate him.</e>
<cmt>Lowercase -- assassinate?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died on January 10, 672 at age 46.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処&quot;7&quot; -&gt; &quot;10&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>（『扶桑略記』では病死説の後一説として「一云 天皇駕馬 幸山階鄕 更無還御 永交山林 不知崩所 只以履沓落處爲其山陵 以往諸皇不知因果 恒事殺害」とあり山中で行方不明になったとされることから天武天皇側による暗殺説もある）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(According to &quot;Fuso-Ryakki&quot;, he died from an illness, but another explanation that has been offered is that he went missing in the mountains and that Emperor Temmu had him assassinated.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="35">
<j>天智天皇が長く即位しなかったことは、7世紀中葉の政治史における謎の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was one of the mystery on intermediate 7th century why Emperor TENCHI/TENJI did not stay in power for a long time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was one of the mysteries of the mid-seventh century that Emperor Tenchi (Tenji) did not stay in power for a long time.</e>
<cmt>Lowercase, numbering</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was one of the mysteries of the mid-seventh century that Emperor Tenchi (Tenji) did not stay in power for a long time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>このことについて議論されている説がいくつか存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some theories discussed about this matter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various theories have been suggested in regard to the matter.</e>
<cmt>Usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various theories have been suggested in regard to the matter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="37">
<j>天武天皇を推す勢力への配慮。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The consideration for setting up Emperor TEMMU&apos;s backbone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the consideration for setting up Emperor Temmu&apos;s backbone.</e>
<cmt>Lowercase, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the consideration for setting up Emperor Temmu&apos;s backbone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>即ち、従来定説とされてきた、天武天皇は天智天皇の弟であるというのは誤りで、皇極天皇が舒明天皇と結婚する前に生んだ漢皇子であり、彼は天智天皇の異父兄であるとする説に基づくものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was an accepted theory that Emperor TEMMU is a brother of Emperor TENCHI (TENJI) however this is denied and another theory is the Emperor TEMMU is Aya no Miko between Emperor Kogyoku and Empress JOMEI, and he is a half brother of Emperor TENCHI (TENJI).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was an accepted theory that Emperor Temmu was a brother of Emperor Tenchi (Tenji), but this is denied; another theory is that Emperor Temmu was Aya no Miko between Emperor Kogyoku and Empress Jomei, and that he was a half-brother of Emperor Tenchi (Tenji).</e>
<cmt>Lowercase, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was an accepted theory that Emperor Temmu was a younger brother of Emperor Tenchi (Tenji), but this is denied; another theory is that Emperor Temmu was Aya no Miko, whom Empress Kogyoku had before she married Emperor Jomei, and that he was an older half-brother of Emperor Tenchi (Tenji).</e>
<cmt>訳を一部修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>確かに、『日本書紀』の天智天皇と一部の歴史書に掲載される天武天皇の享年をもとに生年を逆算すれば、天武が年長となってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is apparent that Emperor TEMMU&apos;s died age was older than Emperor TENCHI (TENJI) after trucking back their ages according to &quot;Chronicles of Japan&quot; (Nihon Shoki) or other history book about Emperor TEMMU.</e>
<cmt>『日本書紀』&quot;Chronicles of Japan&quot;/&quot;the Nihonshoki&quot;</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is apparent that Emperor Temmu&apos;s age at death surpassed that of Emperor Tenchi (Tenji) after tracing back their ages according to &quot;Chronicles of Japan (Nihon Shoki)&quot; or other history books about Emperor Temmu.</e>
<cmt>Lowercase, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is apparent that Emperor Temmu was older than Emperor Tenchi (Tenji) after tracing back their ages according to the Emperor Tenchi&apos;s (Tenji&apos;s) age at death in &quot;Chronicles of Japan (Nihon Shoki)&quot; and the Emperor Temmu&apos;s age at death in other history books.</e>
<cmt>「日本書紀の天智天皇の享年とその他一部の歴史書に掲載されている天武天皇の享年をもとに逆算すると」という意味に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>しかし、同一史料間には矛盾は見られず、8～9歳程度の年齢差を設けている史料が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The both historical data contains the same information, there are eight to nine years age difference between two Emperors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both historical records contain the same information, and there are eight to nine years age difference between the two emperors.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The information is consistent in the same historical records, and there are eight to nine years of age difference between the two emperors.</e>
<cmt>「年齢を、違う資料間で比べると矛盾が生じるが、それぞれの資料の中に書かれている情報では矛盾は見られない」という意味に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>これに対しては『「父親が違うとはいえ、兄を差し置いて弟が」ということでは体裁が悪いので、意図的に天智の年齢を引き上げたのだ』との主張があるが、『「日本書紀」に見える、天智の年齢16歳は父舒明天皇が即位した時の年齢だったのを間違えて崩御した時の年齢にしてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some people said that Emperor TEMMU&apos;s age was purposely falsified as it was an embarrassing fact that younger brother&apos;s age was greater than older brother&apos;s age, according to &quot;Chronicles of Japan&quot; (NihonShoki) Emperor TEMMU&apos;s age was sixteen when his father, Emperor JOMEI enthroned, but was said he was sixteen when his father died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some people said that Emperor Temmu&apos;s age was purposely falsified since it was an embarrassing fact that the younger brother&apos;s age was greater than the older brother&apos;s age; according to &quot;Chronicles of Japan (Nihon Shoki),&quot; Emperor Temmu&apos;s age was 16 when his father, Emperor Jomei, was enthroned, but it was said he was 16 when his father died.</e>
<cmt>Lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people say that Emperor Temmu&apos;s age was purposely falsified since it was an embarrassing fact that the younger brother became the emperor before his older brother even though they are half-brothers with the same mother; but some argue that according to &quot;Chronicles of Japan (Nihon Shoki),&quot; Emperor Temmu&apos;s age was 16 when his father, Emperor Jomei, was enthroned, but it was said that he was 16 when his father died.</e>
<cmt>「父親が違うとはいえ」の訳を追加しました。「兄を差し置いて弟が」の意味が正しく訳されていませんでした。「兄を差し置いて弟が天皇になるのはまずい」という意味です。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>だから、本当の生年は本朝皇胤紹運録等が採用している614年だ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So Emperor&apos;s real year of birth is in 614 according to royal family tree (Honcho-koin-jounroku).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the Emperor&apos;s real year of birth is 614, according to the Royal Family Tree (Honcho-koin-jounroku).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the Emperor&apos;s real year of birth is 614, according to the Royal Family Tree (Honcho-koin-jounroku).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>』との反論、『古代においては珍しくなかった空位(実際、天武の前後に在位していた天智・持統も称制をしき、直ちに即位しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was not usual to have no successors for an imperial throne for some period. (In fact Emperor TENCHI (TENJI) and Emperor Jito who were in power before and after Emperor TEMMU took control of the government without having enthronement ceremony.)</e>
<cmt>原文の意味不明　持統 http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110000238058/en</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was unusual to have no successor to an imperial throne for some period (in fact, Emperor Tenchi (Tenji) and Emperor Jito, who were in power before and after Emperor Temmu, took control of the government without having enthronement ceremony).</e>
<cmt>Lowercase, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was usual to have no successor to the Imperial Throne for some period (in fact, Emperor Tenchi (Tenji) and Empress Jito, who were in power before and after Emperor Temmu, took control of the government without having an enthronement ceremony).</e>
<cmt>文頭の『との反論、はのセル内で訳すと意味が通じないため、２つ上のセル内で&quot;some argue that&quot;を挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>)の為に誤差が生じたのだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>原文の意味不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some argue that this caused the errors in their ages.</e>
<cmt>訳を補いました。前の文章と続いています。文頭の『との反論、はのセル内で訳すと意味が通じないため、1つ上のセル内で&quot;some argue that&quot;を挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>』との反論、また「日本書紀」と指摘されているその他歴史書は編纂された時代も性質も異なる為、同一には扱えないとの意見もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some people said history books apart from &quot;Chronicles of Japan&quot; (the Nihonshoki) are edited in various years and can not be treated same as &quot;Chronicles of Japan&quot; (Nihonshoki).</e>
<cmt>原文の意味不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some people have said that history books apart from &quot;Chronicles of Japan (Nihon Shoki)&quot; are edited in various years and cannot be treated the same as &quot;Chronicles of Japan (Nihon Shoki).&quot;</e>
<cmt>tensearticle</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people have said that because &quot;Chronicles of Japan (Nihon Shoki)&quot; and other indicated history books are edited in different years and they are different in character, they cannot be treated alike.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「性質も異なる」の訳を補いました。文全体の意味を考え訳しなおしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>（「天武天皇年齢」の項も参照の事）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Please refer to the section of &quot;The age of Emperor TEMMU&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Please refer to the section &quot;The Age of Emperor Temmu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Lowercase, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Please refer to the section &quot;The Age of Emperor Temmu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="47">
<j>乙巳の変は軽皇子(孝徳天皇)のクーデターであり、中大兄皇子は地位を追われたという説。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Isshi no Hen was a coup caused by Karu no Miko (Emperor KOTOKU) and Naka no Oe no Oji/Naka no Oe no Miko lost his position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Isshi no Hen was a coup caused by Karu no Miko (Emperor Kotoku), in which Naka no Oe no Oji/Naka no Oe no Miko lost his position.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a theory that the Isshi no Hen was a coup caused by Karu no Miko (Emperor Kotoku), in which Naka no Oe no Oji (Naka no Oe no Miko) lost his position.</e>
<cmt>「という説。」の訳を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>近年中大兄皇子と蘇我入鹿の関係が比較的良好であり、基本政策も似ていることが指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been indicated recently that Naka no Oe no Oji/Naka no Oe no Miko and SOGANO Iruka had a relatively good relationship and their basic policies were similar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has recently been indicated that Naka no Oe no Oji (Naka no Oe no Miko) and Sogano Iruka had a relatively good relationship and similar basic policies.</e>
<cmt>Structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has recently been indicated that Naka no Oe no Oji (Naka no Oe no Miko) and Sogano Iruka had a relatively good relationship and similar basic policies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>そうなると中大兄皇子が入鹿を殺害する動機がなくなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This way there is no reason for Naka no Oe no Oji/Naka no Oe no Miko to assassinate Iruka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This way there is no reason that Naka no Oe no Oji (Naka no Oe no Miko) would have assassinated Iruka.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This way there is no reason that Naka no Oe no Oji (Naka no Oe no Miko) would have assassinated Iruka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>また、日本書紀の大化の改新の記述には改竄が認められることから、この説が唱えられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because there is no falsification is allowed in the definition of &quot;Chronicles of Japan&quot; (the Nihonshoki) and Taika&apos;s reform, this theory became apparent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because there is no falsification allowed in the definition of &quot;Chronicles of Japan (Nihon Shoki)&quot; and Taika&apos;s reform, this theory has become apparent.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because there is falsification in the definition of Taika&apos;s reform in &quot;Chronicles of Japan (Nihon Shoki),&quot; this theory has become apparent.</e>
<cmt>一部訳を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>また、この説では皇極天皇の退位の理由や入鹿以外の蘇我氏がクーデター後も追放されていない理由など、その他の疑問点も説明できるため注目を浴びている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This theory get a lot of attention because it can be explained the reason Emperor Kogyoku&apos;s abdication or the reason why SOGA family except Iruka have not been displaced from the politics after the coup.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This theory gets a lot of attention because it can explain Emperor Kogyoku&apos;s abdication or the reason that the Soga Family (except Iruka) were not displaced from politics after the coup.</e>
<cmt>Lowercase, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This theory gets a lot of attention because it can explain Empress Kogyoku&apos;s abdication or the reason that the Soga Family (except Iruka) was not displaced from politics after the coup.</e>
<cmt>性別の取り違えを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="52">
<j>天智の女性関係に対しての反発から即位が遅れたとする説。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a theory that Emperor TENCHI&apos;s (TENJI) enthronement delayed due to the complains against his relationship with women.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a theory that the enthronement of Emperor Tenchi (Tenji) was delayed due to the complaints against his relationship with women.</e>
<cmt>Lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a theory that the enthronement of Emperor Tenchi (Tenji) was delayed due to the complaints against his relationship with women.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>これは、『日本書紀』に記載された孝徳天皇が妻の間人皇女（天智の同母妹）に当てた歌に彼女と天智との不倫関係を示唆するものがあるとするものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is based on the theory that Emperor KOTOKU sent a poem to his wife Hashihito no Himemiko (Emperor TENCHI&apos;s (TENJI) half sister) indicating Emperor TENCHI (TENJI) having an affair with her, which is in &quot;Chronicles of Japan&quot; (the Nihonshoki).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is based on the theory that Emperor Kotoku sent a poem to his wife Hashihito no Himemiko (Emperor Tenchi&apos;s (Tenji) half-sister) indicating that Emperor Tenchi (Tenji) was having an affair with her, which is contained in &quot;Chronicles of Japan (Nihon Shoki).&quot;</e>
<cmt>Lowercase, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is based on the theory that Emperor Kotoku sent a poem to his wife Hashihito no Himemiko (Emperor Tenchi&apos;s (Tenji) sister with the same mother) indicating that Emperor Tenchi (Tenji) was having an affair with her, which is contained in &quot;Chronicles of Japan (Nihon Shoki).&quot;</e>
<cmt>一部訳を修正しました。ハイフン削</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>異母兄弟姉妹間での恋愛・婚姻は許されるが、同母兄弟姉妹間でのそれは許されなかったのが当時の人々の恋愛事情だったが、里中満智子作の天上の虹では実際に関係があった解釈がなされ、説得して伯父の軽大王(孝徳天皇)に嫁がせた後も関係を持った事をたまたま有間皇子に見られ、激怒した彼に叱責された場面等が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those days the romance and marriage were allowed between half sisters and brothers from different mothers but not between half brothers and sisters from the same mothers, however in the comic story &quot;Tenjo no niji&quot; (the rainbow in the sky) by Machiko SATONAKA, it is described there was a romance between this type of forbitten love, Hashihito no Himemiko was persuaded to marry with Karu no Miko (Emperor KOTOKU) but she kept the relationship with Emperor TENCHI (TENJI), Arima no Miko was furious after knowing this and told Hashihito no Himemiko off.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those days the romance and marriage were allowed between half-sisters and brothers from different mothers but not between half-brothers and sisters from the same mother; however, in the comic story &quot;Tenjo no niji (The Rainbow in the Sky),&quot; by Machiko Satonaka, it is described that there was a romance involving this kind of forbitten love; Hashihito no Himemiko was persuaded to marry with Karu no Miko (Emperor Kotoku), but she kept the relationship with Emperor Tenchi (Tenji), and Arima no Miko was furious after knowing this and became angry at Hashihito no Himemiko.</e>
<cmt>Lowercase, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those days, romance and marriage were allowed between half-sisters and brothers from different mothers but not between half-brothers and sisters from the same mother; however, in the comic story &quot;Tenjo no niji (The Rainbow in the Sky),&quot; by Machiko SATONAKA, it is described that there was a romance involving this kind of forbidden love; Hashihito no Himemiko was persuaded to marry with Karu no Miko (Emperor Kotoku), but she kept the relationship with Emperor Tenchi (Tenji), and Arima no Miko was furious after knowing this and became angry at Hashihito no Himemiko.</e>
<cmt>名字大文字</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="55">
<j>斉明天皇の死後に間人皇女が先々代の天皇の妃として皇位を継いでいたのであるが、何らかの事情で記録が抹消されたという説である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a theory that Hashihito no Himemiko ascend the throne and became an Empress after the death of Emperor SAIMEI however her name was erased from the record for some reason.</e>
<cmt>http://p-www.iwate-pu.ac.jp/~acro-ito/Japan_pics/Japan_NNG/imageidx.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a theory that Hashihito no Himemiko ascend the throne and became an Empress after the death of Emperor Saimei however her name was erased from the record for some reason.</e>
<cmt>Lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a theory that Hashihito no Himemiko ascended the throne as the princess of the previous Emperor but one and became an Empress after the death of Empress Saimei; however, for some reason her name was erased from the record.</e>
<cmt>先々代の天皇の妃として追加翻訳しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>これは『万葉集』において「中皇命」なる人物を間人皇女とする説から来るもので、「中皇命」とは天智即位までの中継ぎの天皇であるという解釈出来るという主張である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Man&apos;yoshu (&quot;The Anthology of Myriad Leaves&quot;) &quot;Nakatsusumera-mikoto&quot; is considered as Hashihito no Himemiko and it is said the name &quot;Nakatsusumera-mikoto&quot; was a temporary Emperor until the enthronement of Emperor TENCHI (TENJI).</e>
<cmt>『万葉集』英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Man&apos;yoshu (&quot;The Anthology of Myriad Leaves),&quot; &quot;Nakatsusumera-mikoto&quot; is considered to be Hashihito no Himemiko, and it is said that the one named &quot;Nakatsusumera-mikoto&quot; was a temporary Emperor until the enthronement of Emperor Tenchi (Tenji).</e>
<cmt>Lowercase, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Man&apos;yoshu (&quot;The Anthology of Myriad Leaves),&quot; &quot;Nakatsusumera-mikoto&quot; is considered to be Hashihito no Himemiko, and it is said that the one named &quot;Nakatsusumera-mikoto&quot; was a temporary Emperor until the enthronement of Emperor Tenchi (Tenji).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>もし間人皇女＝「中皇命」とすれば、なぜ彼女だけが特別にこうした呼称で呼ばれる必要性があったのかを考えられるが、斉明天皇だとする説もあり、必ずしも確証は無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If Hashihito no Himemiko was the same person as &quot;Nakatsusumera-mikoto&quot;, there is a question why only she had this special name, or it is said this name could have been for Emperor SAIMEI but there is no proof.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If Hashihito no Himemiko was the same person as &quot;Nakatsusumera-mikoto&quot;, there is a question why only she had this special name, or it is said this name could have been for Emperor Saimei but there is no proof.</e>
<cmt>Lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If Hashihito no Himemiko was the same person as &quot;Nakatsusumera-mikoto,&quot; there is a question why only she had this special name; alternatively, it is said that this name could have been for Empress Saimei, but there is no proof.</e>
<cmt>コンマ位置性別の取り違えを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="58">
<j>政治史という性質・史料の制約などもあり、証明は困難ではあるが、考古学的成果との連携などとも含め、今後の研究の進展が待たれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is hard to prove as this is about political history with limited data, however it is expected to have clearer information from close study in relation with the achievement of archaeology.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is hard to prove, since this is about political history with limited data; however, it is expected to have clearer information from close study in relation to the findings of archaeology.</e>
<cmt>Usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is hard to prove, since this is about political history with limited data; however, it is expected to have clearer information from close study in relation to the findings of archaeology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="59">
<j>歌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Poems</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Poems</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Poems</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="60">
<j>万葉集に4首の歌が伝わる万葉歌人でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor TENCHI (TENJI) is a poet who has four poems in Man&apos;yoshu. (&quot;The Anthology of Myriad Leaves&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor Tenchi (Tenji)was a poet who had four poems in &quot;Man&apos;yoshu (The Anthology of Myriad Leaves).&quot;</e>
<cmt>Lowercase, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor Tenchi (Tenji) was a poet who had four poems in &quot;Man&apos;yoshu (The Anthology of Myriad Leaves).&quot;</e>
<cmt>スペース入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>小倉百人一首でも平安王朝の太祖としての敬意が張られ、冒頭に以下の歌が載せられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was respected as an Emperor and poet of Heian dynasty, his poem is in the beginning of one hundred waka poems. (the Ogura Anthology of One Hundred Tanka-poems by One Hundred Poets)</e>
<cmt>小倉百人一首 英辞郎 on the WEB、新和英中辞典</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was respected as the Emperor and a poet of the Heian dynasty, and one of his poems is found at the beginning of &quot;One Hundred Waka Poems (the Ogura Anthology of One Hundred Tanka-poems by One Hundred Poets).&quot;</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was respected as the Emperor of the Heian dynasty, and one of his poems is found at the beginning of &quot;One Hundred Waka Poems (the Ogura Anthology of One Hundred Tanka-poems by One Hundred Poets).&quot;</e>
<cmt>余分な訳を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="62">
<j>秋の田の　かりほのいほの苫を粗み　わが衣手は露にぬれつつ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I am sitting in the barn next to rice field when rice is harvested in autumn. My Kimono sleeves get wet by night dew as the roof of the barn is covered with roughly bladed hays.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I am sitting in the barn next to a rice field when rice is harvested in the autumn. My kimono sleeves get wet by night dew, as the roof of the barn is covered with rough-bladed hay.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I am sitting in the barn next to a rice field when rice is harvested in the autumn and my kimono sleeves get wet by night dew, as the roof of the barn is covered with rough-bladed hay.</e>
<cmt>一文にまとめました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="63">
<j>万葉集からも以下の一首。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following poem is from Man&apos;yoshu (&quot;The Anthology of Myriad Leaves&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following poem is from &quot;Man&apos;yoshu (The Anthology of Myriad Leaves).&quot;</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following poem is from &quot;Man&apos;yoshu (The Anthology of Myriad Leaves).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="64">
<j>香具山は畝傍を愛しと耳成と相争ひき神代よりかくなるらし古へもしかなれこそうつせみも褄を争ふらしき</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In ancient days Kagu-yama Mountain loved Unebi-yama Mountain and fought against Miminashi-yama Mountain for love, there is no doubt we still fight for love between wives as it has been the same since the age of the gods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In ancient days, Mt. Kagu-yama loved Mt. Unebi-yama and fought against Mt. Miminashi-yama for love; there is no doubt we still fight for love between wives, as it has been the same since the age of the gods.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In ancient days, Mt. Kagu-yama loved Mt. Unebi-yama and fought against Mt. Miminashi-yama for love; there is no doubt we still fight for love between wives, as it has been the same since the age of the gods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MD242(id:11277), ドラムスコ(id:40234), BOTarate(id:185620), 講師(id:71860), 霧木諒二(id:9795), Nnh(id:474), China(id:10362), Cprobot(id:97843), 味っ子(id:17086), 行動で挽回するしかない(id:31799), Oneuchi(id:70845), るがこむ(id:181), さららゆら(id:12274), 代言人(id:33675), IwaimBot(id:190695), Rei-bot(id:94097), UMBRO(id:100484), Chobot(id:20846), Gbr3(id:6539), Googooeyes(id:194699), Yuki80(id:163805), Nopira(id:29335), Sumaru(id:20609), Aduma(id:32899), Bankokuya(id:91191), LERK(id:4460), Higashi(id:8842), Izayohi(id:13095), 蒼海牧菜(id:78923), G(id:21), Carbuncle(id:346), ととりん(id:31982), Equaly(id:89792), 可怜(id:206074), 松茸(id:27535), 水野白楓(id:22811), VanishingDuck(id:125995), Aphaia(id:3132), Zwobot(id:23873), ごまふあざ(id:36855), MDR-SK(id:192066), Nikai(id:1648), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), Murasagi(id:79122), 住めら尊(id:173954), 悠卯斗(id:46277), Thijs!bot(id:69644), Kaba(id:17904), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), SuisuiBot(id:10165), 突撃 ひとり(id:48314), Oga(id:116), 斎東小世(id:134120), ねこぱんだ(id:35119), 平惣衛門(id:99387), 唐棣色(id:64681), Trek011(id:7105), きまま(id:183217), Jade0416(id:104181), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>