<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>御食国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miketsukuni</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miketsukuni</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miketsukuni</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>御食国（みけつくに）は、日本古代から平安時代まで、贄（にえ）の貢進国、すなわち皇室・朝廷に海水産物を中心とした御食料（穀類以外の副食物）を貢いだと推定される国を指す言葉。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miketsukuni indicated the province that was assumed to supply food (secondary component of his or her diet except grain), mainly marine products, to the supply provinces of offering, namely Imperial family and Imperial court, from ancient Japan to the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>貢進国→a supply province【定訳不明】</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miketsukuni indicated the province that was assumed to supply food (secondary diet component except for grain), mainly marine products, to the supply provinces making offerings, namely the Imperial family and Imperial court, from ancient Japan to the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miketsukuni indicated the supply provinces making offerings, namely the province that was assumed to supply food (secondary diet component except for grain), mainly marine products, to the Imperial family and Imperial court, from ancient Japan to the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>the supply provinces making offerings, namelyの位置移動　原文の意味に合わせるため</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>律令制のもと租庸調の税が各国に課せられたが、これとは別に贄の納付が定められていたと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soyocho (a tax system, corvee) under the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) was imposed to each province, but it was considered that offering had to be paid in addition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soyocho (a tax system, corvee) under the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) was imposed on each province, but it was considered that the offering had to be paid in addition to the tax.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soyocho (a tax system, corvee) under the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) was imposed on each province, but it was considered that the offering had to be paid in addition to the tax.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>『万葉集』にある郷土礼讃の歌に散見され、『延喜式』の贄の貢進国の記述、平城京跡から出土した木簡の記述などから、若狭国・志摩国・淡路国などへの該当が推定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As it was seen many times in the poems of home admiration written in &quot;Manyoshu (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves),&quot; it seemed that Wakasa Province, Shima Province, and Awaji Province to be the appropriate Miketsukuni from the statement of the supply provinces of offering in &quot;the Engishiki (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers)&quot; and the statement on mokan (a narrow strip of wood on which an official message is written) that was discovered from the former site of Heijo-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in current Nara).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As it was seen many times in the poems of home admiration written in &quot;Manyoshu (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves),&quot; it seemed that Wakasa Province, Shima Province, and Awaji Province to be the appropriate Miketsukuni from the statement of the supply provinces making offerings in the &quot;Engishiki&quot; (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers) and the statement on mokan (a narrow strip of wood on which an official message is written) that was discovered from the former site of Heijo-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in current Nara).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As it was seen many times in the poems of home admiration written in &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves), it seemed that Wakasa Province, Shima Province, and Awaji Province to be the appropriate Miketsukuni from the statement of the supply provinces making offerings in the &quot;Engishiki&quot; (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers) and the statement on mokkan (a narrow strip of wood on which an official message is written) that was discovered from the former site of Heijo-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in current Nara).</e>
<cmt>(Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves),位置移動スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>塩や鰒（アワビ）、海草などの海産物は、神事の際などに貢がれる神饌として古くから用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The marine products such as salt, abalones, and seaweed were used as shinsen (food and alcohol offering to the gods) at a Shinto ritual.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Marine products such as; salt, abalone, and seaweed were used as shinsen (food and alcohol offering to the gods) at a Shinto ritual.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Marine products such as; salt, abalone, and seaweed were used as shinsen (food and alcohol offering to the gods) at a Shinto ritual.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>またこれら海産物が豊富に捕れる地域の支配が、地域の権力者によって重要な政治的意味を持ったことは十分に想像できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was imaginable enough that dominating the areas where had abundant marine products had important political implications for local authority.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was imaginable enough that dominating the areas that had abundant marine products had important political implications for the local authority.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was imaginable enough that dominating the areas that had abundant marine products had important political implications for the local authority.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>贄の貢ぎが史料として現れるのは、日本書紀の大化の改新の詔の其の四のところで、「凡その調の副物の塩と贄（にえ）とは、亦（また）郷土（くに）の出せるに随へ」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The supply of offering appeared as the historical materials in the section 4 of mikotonori (an Imperial edict) in the Taika Reform in Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan), and it said &apos;Usually, by-products of the cho (tributes) such as salt and offering, need to be followed by the local capacity.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「」内の意味が明確に解釈できませんでしたが、直訳してみました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The supply of offerings appeared as historical materials in section 4 of mikotonori (an Imperial edict) in the Taika Reform in Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan), and it said &apos;Usually, by-products of the cho (tributes) such as salt and offerings, need to be followed according to local capacity.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The supply of offerings appeared as historical materials in section 4 of mikotonori (an Imperial edict) in the Taika Reform in Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan), and it said &apos;Usually, by-products of the cho (tributes) such as salt and offerings, need to be followed according to local capacity.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>実際、藤原京・平城京の発掘調査から多数の木簡が出土しており、これら木簡のほとんどは都に税として納められた物品を示す記述であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, many mokan were discovered from the excavation research of Fujiwara-kyo (the Fujiwara Palace; the ancient capital of Fujiwara) and Heijo-kyo, and the statements on those mokan indicated the commodities mostly paid to the capital as a tax.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, many mokan were discovered from excavation research of the Fujiwara-kyo (the Fujiwara Palace; the ancient capital of Fujiwara) and Heijo-kyo, and the statements on those mokan indicated the commodities were mostly paid to the capital as a tax.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, many mokkan were discovered from excavation research of the Fujiwara-kyo (the Fujiwara Palace; the ancient capital of Fujiwara) and Heijo-kyo, and the statements on those mokkan indicated the commodities were mostly paid to the capital as a tax.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>木簡の記述には納められた物品の名前とともに貢ぎ先の国名、郡名が記され、それが何の税にあたるか、すなわち租・庸・調の文字が記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the statement of the commodities described in those mokan, province and county to supply, category of taxes, more specifically, so (a rice tax), yo (tax in kind), and cho were written.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the statement of the commodities described on those mokan, province, and county to supply, category of taxes, more specifically, so (a rice tax), yo (tax in kind), and cho, could be read.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the statement of the commodities described on those mokkan, province, and county to supply, category of taxes, more specifically, so (a rice tax), yo (tax in kind), and cho, could be read.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>一部の木簡は租・庸・調ではなく、贄や御贄（みにえ）、大贄（おおにえ）の文字を見つけることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On some mokan, different kanji characters of offering, &apos;贄 (nie), &apos;御贄 (Minie),&apos; and &apos;大贄 (Onie), were found, not &apos;So,&apos; &apos;Yo,&apos;, and &apos;Cho.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On some mokan, different kanji characters for offerings, &apos;贄 (nie), &apos;御贄 (Minie),&apos; and &apos;大贄 (Onie), were found, not &apos;So,&apos; &apos;Yo,&apos; and &apos;Cho.&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On some mokkan, different kanji characters for offerings, &apos;贄&apos; (nie), &apos;御贄&apos; (Minie), and &apos;大贄&apos; (Onie), were found, not &apos;So,&apos; &apos;Yo,&apos; and &apos;Cho.&apos;</e>
<cmt>の位置移動および補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>また贄を納める義務を負ったものを贄人と呼んだが、贄を納めることで調などが一律に免除されたかどうかは断定できない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, it was called niebito who were obligated to pay offering, but it was indecisive whether the cho was exempted indiscriminately or not by paying offering.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, it was called niebito who were obligated to pay offerings, but it was indecisive whether the cho was exempted indiscriminately or not by paying offerings.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, it was called niebito who were obligated to pay offerings, but it was indecisive whether the cho was exempted indiscriminately or not by paying offerings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし神饌の意味する本来の自発的に土地の海産物を神々に貢進したというものから、首長（天皇）に贄を奉じこれを首長が食べることで贄の取れた土地を支配していることを誇示する儀式となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, from the original meaning of shinsen which was to voluntarily supply the local marine products to the gods, it became a ritual to display the dominance of the land where offering was caught by supplying offering to a chief (an emperor) and having a chief eat it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, from the original meaning of shinsen, a voluntarily supply of local marine products to the gods, it became a ritual to display the dominance of the land where offerings were caught by supplying it to a chief (an emperor) and having the chief eat it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, from the original meaning of shinsen, a voluntarily supply of local marine products to the gods, it became a ritual to display the dominance of the land where offerings were caught by supplying it to a chief (an emperor) and having the chief eat it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>さらに贄は律令制の下で税のように強制的な収奪へ変化したことが伺える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it revealed that offering changed to coercive stripping like taxes under the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, it revealed that offering changed to coercive stripping like taxes under the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, it revealed that offering changed to coercive stripping like taxes under the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>大宝律令および養老律令においては、贄の貢ぎに関する記載は見当たらない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were no statement on supply of offering under Taiho Code and Yoryo Code.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were no statements on supply of offerings under Taiho and Yoryo Codes.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were no statements on supply of offerings under Taiho and Yoryo Codes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>しかし『延喜式』には、御食国による贄として貢ぐ内容が詳細に記述されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, contents of supply offering by Miketsukuni were stated in &quot;the Engishiki&quot; in detail.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, contents of supply offerings by Miketsukuni were stated in detail in &quot;the Engishiki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, contents of supply offerings by Miketsukuni were stated in detail in &quot;the Engishiki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>『延喜式』によると、宮内省の内膳司（皇室、朝廷の食膳を管理した役所）の条に、「諸国貢進御贄」、「諸国貢進御厨御贄」などの項目がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;the Engishiki,&quot; in the article of Naizenshi (the office to manage dining for Imperial family and Imperial court) of the Department of the Imperial Household, there were items of &apos;Shokoku Koshin Onie (supply of offering from various provinces &apos; and &apos;Shokoku Koshin Mikuriya Onie (supply of offering to the kitchen from various provinces.&apos;</e>
<cmt>諸国貢進御贄→Shokoku Koshin Onie (supply of offering from various provinces)【定訳不明】諸国貢進御厨御贄→Shokoku Koshin Mikuriya Onie (supply of offering to the kitchen from various provinces)【定訳不明】</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;the Engishiki,&quot; in the articles of Naizenshi (office that manages dining for Imperial family and the Imperial court) of the Department of the Imperial Household, there were items of &apos;Shokoku Koshin Onie (supply of offerings from various provinces &apos; and &apos;Shokoku Koshin Mikuriya Onie - supply of offering to the kitchen from various provinces&apos;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;the Engishiki,&quot; in the articles of Naizenshi (office that manages dining for Imperial family and the Imperial court) of the Department of the Imperial Household, there were items of &apos;Shokoku Koshin Onie&apos; (supply of offerings from various provinces) and &apos;Shokoku Koshin Mikuriya Onie&apos; (supply of offering to the kitchen from various provinces).</e>
<cmt>の位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>この項には各国に割当てられた食材をそれぞれ毎月（旬料）・正月元旦や新嘗祭などの節日（節料）・年（年料）に一度というように内膳司に直接納めることが規定されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In these items, it defined for each province to supply assigned food directly to Naizenshi every month (shunryo), on New Year&apos;s day, on seasonal festival such as Ninamesai (the Harvest Festival)(setsuryo), and once a year (nenryo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In these items, it was defined for each province to supply the assigned food directly to Naizenshi every month (shunryo), on New Year&apos;s day, on seasonal festivals such as Ninamesai (the Harvest Festival) (setsuryo), and once a year (nenryo).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In these items, it was defined for each province to supply the assigned food directly to Naizenshi every month (shunryo), on New Year&apos;s day, on seasonal festivals such as Ninamesai (the Harvest Festival) (setsuryo), and once a year (nenryo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>若狭国の状況</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Situation in Wakasa Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Situation in Wakasa Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Situation in Wakasa Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>『延喜式』によると、若狭国は10日毎に「雑魚」、節日ごとに「雑鮮味物」、さらに年に一度「生鮭、ワカメ、モズク、ワサビ」を御贄として納めることが定められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;the Engishiki,&quot; Wakasa Province was obligated to supply &apos;small fish&apos; every ten days, &apos;sapid marine products&apos; on every seasonal festival, and additionally &apos;raw salmon, seaweed, mozuku (alga-like seaweed), and wasabi&apos; once a year as offering.</e>
<cmt>雑鮮味物→sapid marine products【定訳不明】</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Engishiki,&quot; Wakasa Province was obligated to supply &apos;small fish&apos; every ten days, &apos;sapid marine products&apos; for every seasonal festival, and additionally &apos;raw salmon, seaweed, mozuku, (alga-like seaweed), and wasabi&apos; once a year as offerings.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Engishiki,&quot; Wakasa Province was obligated to supply &apos;small fish&apos; every ten days, &apos;sapid marine products&apos; for every seasonal festival, and additionally &apos;raw salmon, seaweed, mozuku (alga-like seaweed), and wasabi&apos; once a year as offerings.</e>
<cmt>コンマ削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>すでに述べたとおり藤原京跡や平城京跡より、多量の木簡が発掘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As previously indicated, many mokan were discovered from the former sites of Fujiwara-kyo and Heijo-kyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As previously indicated, many mokan, like those that were discovered from the former sites of Fujiwara-kyo and Heijo-kyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As previously indicated, many mokkan were discovered from the former sites of Fujiwara-kyo and Heijo-kyo.</e>
<cmt>, like those that削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>調は絹や麻などの糸や布で納められることが一般的であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yarn and fabric such as silk and hemp were commonly paid as cho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yarn and fabric such as silk and hemp were commonly paid as cho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yarn and fabric such as silk and hemp were commonly paid as cho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>しかし木簡からは若狭国では塩により調が納められたという大きな特徴がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the outstanding characteristic was seen in mokan that Wakasa Province paid salt as cho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the outstanding characteristic seen on mokan was that Wakasa Province paid salt as cho.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the outstanding characteristic seen on mokkan was that Wakasa Province paid salt as cho.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="21">
<j>若狭には8世紀以降使用されていたと思われる製塩施設が、船岡遺跡・岡津遺跡（旧・大飯郡）などで発見されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Wakasa Province, the salt manufacturing facilities that seemed to be used after eighth century have been found in the Funaoka site and the Okozu site (former Oi County).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Wakasa Province, salt manufacturing facilities that seemed to be used after the eighth century have been found in the Funaoka site and the Okozu site (formerly Oi County).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Wakasa Province, salt manufacturing facilities that seemed to be used after the eighth century have been found in the Funaoka site and the Okozu site (formerly Oi County).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>これらの製塩施設は大規模で、周辺住民が日々に使用する塩を作るためというより、時の権力による強制力により労働力が集められて、製塩が行われたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These salt manufacturing facilities were large scale, but it was considered that authority at the time gathered manpower by using coercion to manufacture salt rather than for residents&apos; daily use.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These salt manufacturing facilities were large scale, but it was considered that authority, at the time, gathered manpower by using coercion to manufacture salt rather than for residents&apos; daily use.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These salt manufacturing facilities were large scale, but it was considered that authority, at the time, gathered manpower by using coercion to manufacture salt rather than for residents&apos; daily use.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="23">
<j>若狭国の地理的特長を見ると、海岸線はリアス式海岸で複雑に入り組んでおり、対馬海流の影響で海産物に恵まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By looking at the geographical features of Wakasa Province, the coast line was ria coast and highly indented, and it was affluent in marine products by the influence of Tsushima Current.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By looking at the geographical features of Wakasa Province, the coast line was the ria coast and highly indented, and it was abundant in marine products because of the influence of Tsushima Current.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By looking at the geographical features of Wakasa Province, the coast line was the ria coast and highly indented, and it was abundant in marine products because of the influence of Tsushima Current.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>一方で平野部は狭く限られており、田畑の面積は少ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the flat plains were narrow and limited, and the areas of the farm land were small.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the flat plains were narrow and limited, and the areas suitable for farm land were small.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the flat plains were narrow and limited, and the areas suitable for farm land were small.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>また、若狭国は、8世紀に置かれた郡は遠敷郡、三方郡の二郡であり、畿内で一国二郡は志摩国、淡路国とあわせて三国しかなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Wakasa Province had two counties of Onyu County and Mikata County sited on eighth century, and only three provinces including Wakasa Province, Shima Province, and Awaji Province had one province and two counties within Kinai region (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, Wakasa Province had Onyu and Mikata Counties in the eighth century, and only three provinces including Wakasa Province, Shima Province, and Awaji Province had one province and two counties within the Kinai region (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>wordiness, redundancy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, Wakasa Province had Onyu and Mikata Counties in the eighth century, and only three provinces including Wakasa Province, Shima Province, and Awaji Province had one province and two counties within the Kinai region (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>このように田畑の少ない場所が国単位として成立していたことは、皇室・朝廷にとって特殊な場所であったと推定される</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As just described, it was assumed as the special places for Imperial family and Imperial court since it was approved as one province even though it had small farm land.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As just described, it was assumed to be special places for the Imperial family and the Imperial court since it was approved as one province even though it had little farm land.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As just described, it was assumed to be special places for the Imperial family and the Imperial court since it was approved as one province even though it had little farm land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>志摩国の状況</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Situation in Shima Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Situation in Shima Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Situation in Shima Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="27">
<j>『延喜式』によると、志摩国は10日毎に「鮮鰒（なまのあわび）、さざえ、蒸鰒（むしあわび）」を納めることが定められていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Engishiki,&quot; Shima Province was obligated to supply &apos;raw abalone, turban shells, and boiled abalone&apos; every ten days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Engishiki,&quot; Shima Province was obligated to supply &apos;raw abalone, turban shells, and boiled abalone&apos; every ten days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Engishiki,&quot; Shima Province was obligated to supply &apos;raw abalone, turban shells, and boiled abalone&apos; every ten days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>また節日ごとに「雑鮮の味物」の献上も定められていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also obligated to supply &apos;sapid marine products&apos; on every seasonal festival.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also obligated to supply &apos;sapid marine products&apos; for each seasonal festival.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also obligated to supply &apos;sapid marine products&apos; for each seasonal festival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>平城京跡から発見された木簡に「志摩国志摩郡」の表記が見られ、当初は志摩国は一国一郡であったと推定される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The statement of &apos;Shima Province, Shima County&apos; was seen on the mokan discovered from the former site of Heijo-kyo, so it was assumed that Shima Province had one province and one county at first.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The words; &apos;Shima Province, Shima County&apos; was seen on mokan discovered from the former site of Heijo-kyo, so it was assumed that Shima Province consisted of one province and one county at first.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The words; &apos;Shima Province, Shima County&apos; was seen on mokkan discovered from the former site of Heijo-kyo, so it was assumed that Shima Province consisted of one province and one county at first.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>その後の『延喜式』では答志郡、英虞郡の二郡である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In subsequent &quot;the Engishiki,&quot; there were two counties of Toshi County and Ago County.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently in the &quot;Engishiki,&quot; there were Toshi and Ago Counties.</e>
<cmt>wordiness, redundancy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently in the &quot;Engishiki,&quot; there were Toshi and Ago Counties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>田畑はわずかで、口分田として尾張国、伊勢国にあった田が志摩国に割当てられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The farm land was small, and as kubunden (the farm land given to each farmer in the Ritsuryo system), the farm land in Owari Province and Ise Province were allocated to Shima Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The farm land was small, and as kubunden (the farm land given to each farmer in the Ritsuryo system), the farm land in Owari Province and Ise Province were allocated to Shima Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The farm land was small, and as kubunden (the farm land given to each farmer in the Ritsuryo system), the farm land in Owari Province and Ise Province were allocated to Shima Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>先に述べた若狭と同様にこのような小国の成立は、小島が点在した地理的条件とともに、政治・宗教的な特殊事情あったと推定される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As same as Wakasa Province in previous description, establishment of these small provinces seemed to have political and religious circumstances with geographical conditions where small island were scattered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Like Wakasa Province in the previous description, establishment of these small provinces seemed to have political and religious circumstances with geographical conditions where small islands were scattered.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Like Wakasa Province in the previous description, establishment of these small provinces seemed to have political and religious circumstances with geographical conditions where small islands were scattered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="33">
<j>膳氏との関連でも述べるように、志摩国と内膳司を支配していた高橋氏との間に特殊な関係を指摘する意見がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As it will be described in the section of &apos;The relationship with the Kashiwade clan&apos;, there is an opinion to point out the special relationship with the Takahashi clan who dominated Shima Province and Naizenshi existed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As will be described in the section on &apos;The relationship with the Kashiwade clan,&apos; there is an opinion that a special relationship existed with the Takahashi clan who dominated Shima Province and Naizenshi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As will be described in the section on &apos;The relationship with the Kashiwade clan,&apos; there is an opinion that a special relationship existed with the Takahashi clan who dominated Shima Province and Naizenshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>また平城京の木簡からは志摩国の贄を納めた氏族として大伴部の名前が多く見つかっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, many names of Otomobe (private-owned people of the Otomo clan) were found on mokan from Heijo-kyo as a clan who paid offering to Shima Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, many names of Otomobe (private-owned people of the Otomo clan) were found on mokan from Heijo-kyo as a clan who paid offerings to Shima Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, many names of Otomobe (private-owned people of the Otomo clan) were found on mokkan from Heijo-kyo as a clan who paid offerings to Shima Province.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>淡路国の状況</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Situation in Awaji Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Situation in Awaji Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Situation in Awaji Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="35">
<j>『延喜式』によると、淡路国は旬料・節料として「雑魚」を贄として納めることが記載されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;the Engishiki,&quot; Awaji Province was obligated to supply &apos;small fish&apos; as shunryo and setsuryo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;the Engishiki,&quot; Awaji Province was obligated to supply &apos;small fish&apos; as shunryo and setsuryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;the Engishiki,&quot; Awaji Province was obligated to supply &apos;small fish&apos; as shunryo and setsuryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>阿曇氏との関連でも述べるように、淡路国は海人（あま）を束ね、高橋氏と同様に内膳司の地位を争った阿曇氏が支配していた地域であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As it will be described in the section of &apos;The relationship with the Azumi clan,&apos; Awaji Province brought all male divers together, and it was where the Azumi clan who competed for the position of Naizenshi, as same as the Takahashi clan, dominated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As will later be described in the section on &apos;The relationship with the Azumi clan,&apos; Awaji Province brought all male divers together, and that was where the Azumi clan dominated and competed for the position of Naizenshi, like the Takahashi clan did.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As will later be described in the section on &apos;The relationship with the Azumi clan,&apos; Awaji Province brought all male divers together, and that was where the Azumi clan dominated and competed for the position of Naizenshi, like the Takahashi clan did.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>また若狭国・志摩国と同様に田畑が少ないにも関わらず一国として成立していた特殊性を見ることもできる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As same as Wakasa Province and Shima Province, the particularity was seen since it was approved as one province regardless of small farm land.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Like in Wakasa and Shima Provinces, the particularity was seen since it was approved as one province regardless of the limited farm land availabe.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Like in Wakasa and Shima Provinces, the particularity was seen since it was approved as one province regardless of the limited farm land availabe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="38">
<j>これらの贄は、都へは上り、下りとも7日間を要したとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It took seven days to deliver offering each way to and from the capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It took seven days to deliver offerings each way to and from the capital.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It took seven days to deliver offerings each way to and from the capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>陸路より日数が掛かっており、運搬は船を使って平安京に運ばれたと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It took more than the land route, so it was considered that the delivery was made by a ship to Heian-kyo (ancient Kyoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It took more than the land route, so it was considered that delivery was made by ship to Heian-kyo (ancient Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It took more than the land route, so it was considered that delivery was made by ship to Heian-kyo (ancient Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>膳氏との関連</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The relationship with the Kashiwade clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Relationship with the Kashiwade Clan</e>
<cmt>subtitle capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Relationship with the Kashiwade clan</e>
<cmt>文頭以外の語頭を小文字に</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="40">
<j>膳氏（かしわでうじ）は皇室や朝廷の御饌（みけつ）を担当した伴造氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kashiwade clan was the Tomonomiyatsuko clan who was responsible for meal for Imperial family and Imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kashiwade clan was the Tomonomiyatsuko clan who was responsible for supplying meals to the Imperial family and the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kashiwade clan was the Tomonomiyatsuko clan who was responsible for supplying meals to the Imperial family and the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>後になり高橋氏と改めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Renamed as the Takahashi clan later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Renamed as the Takahashi clan later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Renamed as the Takahashi clan later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>膳氏の出自を示した『高橋氏文』には、景行天皇が東国に行幸したおりに、安房国にて磐鹿六雁命（いわむつかりのみこと、膳氏の始祖とされる）が蛤（はまぐり）を捕り、天皇に料理をして献上したところ、天皇の子孫代まで御食（みけつ）を供するよう膳臣を授かったという記述がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Takahashi uji bumi&quot; where the place of the Kashiwade clan&apos;s origin was stated, it described that when Emperor Keiko visited the east province, Iwamutsukarinomikoto (known as the founder of the Kashiwade clan) in Awa Province caught clams, cooked and offered them to the Emperor, then he was offered to be Kashiwadenoomi (a leading figure who managed to supply food to the Emperor) to supply food down to the Emperor&apos;s posterity.</e>
<cmt>膳臣→Kashiwadenoomi (a leading figure who managed to supply food to the Emperor)大辞林 on the web【定訳不明】</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Takahashi uji bumi&quot; where the place of the Kashiwade clan&apos;s origin was stated to be, it described that when Emperor Keiko visited the eastern province, Iwamutsukarinomikoto (known as the founder of the Kashiwade clan) in Awa Province, caught clams, cooked, and offered them to the Emperor, then he was offered to be Kashiwadenoomi (a leading figure who managed to supply food to the Emperor) to supply food to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>wordiness, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Takahashi uji bumi&quot; where the place of the Kashiwade clan&apos;s origin was stated to be, it described that when Emperor Keiko visited the eastern province, Iwamutsukarinomikoto (known as the founder of the Kashiwade clan) in Awa Province, caught clams, cooked, and offered them to the Emperor, then he was offered to be Kashiwadenoomi (a leading figure who managed to supply food to the Emperor) to supply food to the Emperor&apos;s posterity.</e>
<cmt>s posterity を挿入。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="43">
<j>『高橋氏文』そのものが高橋氏の正統性を誇示する目的と考えられるため、全てを史実として受け入れることは困難である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Takahashi uji bumi&quot; itself was considered as to display the justice of the Takahashi clan, so it is difficult to accept everything as trueness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Takahashi uji bumi&quot; itself was considered as an example of justice amongst the Takahashi clan, so it is difficult to accept everything as true.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Takahashi uji bumi&quot; itself was considered as an example of justice amongst the Takahashi clan, so it is difficult to accept everything as true.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>しかし、膳氏（高橋氏）が6世紀には膳職の伴造の地位につき、東国とのゆかりが深いとする説が有力である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it was the widely-accepted theory that the Kashiwade clan (the Takahashi clan) was assigned as zenshoku position of the Tomonomiyatsuko clan in the sixth century.</e>
<cmt>膳職→zenshoku (an officer who prepared meal for the Emperor and dining for Imperial court)大辞林 on the web 【定訳不明】</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it was a widely-accepted theory that the Kashiwade clan (Takahashi clan) was assigned the zenshoku position in the Tomonomiyatsuko clan during the sixth century.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it was a widely-accepted theory that the Kashiwade clan (Takahashi clan) was assigned the zenshoku position in the Tomonomiyatsuko clan during the sixth century and had close connection with the east provinces.</e>
<cmt>and had close connection with the east provinces補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="45">
<j>『高橋氏文』には始祖の磐鹿六雁命（いわむつかりのみこと）が死去した際に、「稚桜部」（わかさくらべ）の号が送られたとの記述がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Takahashi uji bumi&quot; described when Iwamutsukarinomikoto, the founder, died, the pen name of &apos;Wakasakurabe&apos; was given.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Takahashi uji bumi&quot; described when Iwamutsukarinomikoto, the founder died, the pen name of &apos;Wakasakurabe&apos; was given.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Takahashi uji bumi&quot; described when Iwamutsukarinomikoto, the founder died, the pen name of &apos;Wakasakurabe&apos; was given.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>若狭の地名は「稚桜部」が由来であるとする説があり、若狭国との関係も伺える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is one theory that the geographical name of Wakasa came from &apos;Wakasakurabe,&apos; and it revealed the relationship with Wakasa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is one theory that the geographical name of Wakasa came from &apos;Wakasakurabe,&apos; and it revealed the relationship with Wakasa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is one theory that the geographical name of Wakasa came from &apos;Wakasakurabe,&apos; and it revealed the relationship with Wakasa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>実際に福井県の膳部山は膳氏の名前が由来であると言われ、膳部山周囲に多数の前方後円墳が残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the name of Mt. Zenbu (膳部山) in Fukui Prefecture came from the name of the Kashiwade clan (膳氏)(both has the same kanji character, 膳, with different readings), and many large keyhole-shaped tomb mounds remained around Mt. Zenbu.</e>
<cmt>同じ漢字「膳」が使われているという説明を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the name of Mt. Zenbu (膳部山) in Fukui Prefecture came from the name of the Kashiwade clan (膳氏)(both have the same kanji character, 膳, with different readings), and many large keyhole-shaped tomb mounds remain around Mt. Zenbu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the name of Mt. Zenbu (膳部山) in Fukui Prefecture came from the name of the Kashiwade clan (膳氏) (both have the same kanji character, 膳, with different readings), and many large keyhole-shaped tomb mounds remain around Mt. Zenbu.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>このため、一部では膳氏は5世紀から6世紀には若狭周辺の支配者であったとする説が支持されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, some supported the theory that the Kashiwade clan dominated Wakasa periphery from the fifth to the sixth century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, some supported the theory that the Kashiwade clan dominated Wakasa periphery from the fifth to the sixth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, some supported the theory that the Kashiwade clan dominated Wakasa periphery from the fifth to the sixth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="49">
<j>また8世紀以降で高橋人足、高橋子老、高橋安雄の三名が若狭国の国司に任命されており、律令制成立以後は、内膳司が直接支配した地域である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Hitotari TAKAHASHI, Kooyu TAKAHASHI, and Yasuo TAKAHASHI were assigned as kokushi (provincial governors) of Wakasa Province after the eighth century, and Naizenshi directly dominated the province after the establishment of the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Hitotari TAKAHASHI, Kooyu TAKAHASHI, and Yasuo TAKAHASHI were assigned as kokushi (provincial governors) of Wakasa Province after the eighth century, and Naizenshi directly dominated the province after the establishment of the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Hitotari TAKAHASHI, Kooyu TAKAHASHI, and Yasuo TAKAHASHI were assigned as kokushi (provincial governors) of Wakasa Province after the eighth century, and Naizenshi directly dominated the province after the establishment of the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>しかし高橋氏文の史料批判の程度とともに、膳部山の記載は江戸時代に初めて登場し、膳氏と膳部山との関連性は低いと主張する説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, with the level of the critics of the historical materials of Takahashi uji bumi, the description of Mt. Zenbu was first appeared in the Edo period, so some say the relationship between the Kashiwade clan and Mt. Zenbu was low.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, with the level of critics of historical materials on Takahashi uji bumi, the description of Mt. Zenbu first appeared during the Edo period, so some say the relationship between the Kashiwade clan and Mt. Zenbu was low key.</e>
<cmt>grammar, terminology for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, with the level of critics of historical materials on Takahashi uji bumi, the description of Mt. Zenbu first appeared during the Edo period, so some say the relationship between the Kashiwade clan and Mt. Zenbu was low key.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="51">
<j>一方、高橋氏は、幾つかの例外を除き、奈良時代から平安時代と長期にわたり志摩国の国司を世襲している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the Takahashi clan kept heredity of kokushi of Shima Province for a long time from the Nara period to the Heian period with some exceptions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the Takahashi clan maintained the heredity of kokushi in Shima Province for a long time from the Nara period to the Heian period with some exceptions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the Takahashi clan maintained the heredity of kokushi in Shima Province for a long time from the Nara period to the Heian period with some exceptions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>律令制下の一氏族による国司世襲は、きわめて例外的であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was extremely exceptional for one clan to keep heredity of kokushi under the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was extremely exceptional for one clan to maintain the heredity of kokushi under the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was extremely exceptional for one clan to maintain the heredity of kokushi under the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>志摩国の国司と内膳司が兼任していたことは、志摩国が御贄を貢ぐことを義務付けられていた「御食国」だったことを示しているといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokushi was doubled as Naizenshi in Shima Province, and it indicated that the Shima Province was &apos;Miketsukuni&apos; obligated to supply offering.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokushi doubled as Naizenshi in Shima Province, and it indicated that Shima Province was &apos;Miketsukuni&apos; obligated to supply offerings.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokushi doubled as Naizenshi in Shima Province, and it indicated that Shima Province was &apos;Miketsukuni&apos; obligated to supply offerings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>阿曇氏との関連</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The relationship with Azumi clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Relationship with the Azumi Clan</e>
<cmt>subtitle capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Relationship with the Azumi clan</e>
<cmt>文頭以外の語頭を小文字に</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="54">
<j>阿曇氏（あずみうじ）は安曇氏とも記し、律令制の下で、高橋氏とともの内膳司の奉膳の職を世襲した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">阿曇氏(the Azumi clan) could also be written as 安曇氏, and kept heredity of the head position of Naizenshi with the Takahashi clan under the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">阿曇氏(the Azumi clan) could also be written as 安曇氏, maintained the heredity of the head position of Naizenshi with the Takahashi clan under the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">阿曇氏 (the Azumi clan) could also be written as 安曇氏, maintained the heredity of the head position of Naizenshi with the Takahashi clan under the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>膳氏とは逆に瀬戸内海、壱岐など西国に影響力をもち、淡路島や小豆島などの海人、海部を支配していたとも言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike the Kashiwade clan, the Azumi clan had influence on the west provinces such as Seto Inland Sea and Iki, and dominated male divers and amabe (people who served the Imperial court with the techniques of ocean navigation) in Awaji-shima Island and Shodo-shima Island.</e>
<cmt>海部→amabe (people who served the Imperial court with the techniques of ocean navigation)大辞林 on the web【定訳不明】</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike the Kashiwade clan, the Azumi clan influenced on the western provinces such as; the Seto Inland Sea and Iki, and dominated male divers and amabe (people who served the Imperial court with their techniques of ocean navigation) in Awaji-shima Island and Shodo-shima Island.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike the Kashiwade clan, the Azumi clan influenced on the western provinces such as; the Seto Inland Sea and Iki, and dominated male divers and amabe (people who served the Imperial court with their techniques of ocean navigation) in Awaji-shima Island and Shodo-shima Island.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>一方で応神記に「海人が騒ぎをおこしたため、安曇連の祖大浜宿称を遣してこれを鎮撫し、海人の宰（みこともち）となる」というような内容もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, it was also described in Ojin ki that &apos;because the male divers caused a trouble, an ancestor of Azumi no muraji, OHAMA no Sukune, was sent to pacify it and became a head of male divers.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, it was also described in the Ojin ki that &apos;because male divers caused trouble, an ancestor of Azumi no muraji, OHAMA no Sukune, was sent to pacify them and became the head of male divers.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, it was also described in the Ojin ki that &apos;because male divers caused trouble, an ancestor of Azumi no muraji, OHAMA no Sukune, was sent to pacify them and became the head of male divers.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="57">
<j>若狭国や志摩国と膳氏との関係は、淡路国と阿曇氏との関係にも見て取れるという説も同様になされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some say that the relationship between Wakasa Province, Shima Province, and the Kashiwade clan could see with the relationship between Awaji Province and the Azumi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some say that the relationship between Wakasa Province, Shima Province, and the Kashiwade clan could be seen as the relationship between Awaji Province and the Azumi clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some say that the relationship between Wakasa Province, Shima Province, and the Kashiwade clan could be seen as the relationship between Awaji Province and the Azumi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>また768年に阿曇氏の阿曇石成が若狭国守を務めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, AZUMI no Ishinari of the Azumi clan served as the head of kokushi in Wakasa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, AZUMI no Ishinari of the Azumi clan served as the head of kokushi in Wakasa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, AZUMI no Ishinari of the Azumi clan served as the head of kokushi in Wakasa Province in 768.</e>
<cmt>in 768補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>これは高橋氏との権力争いとともに、道鏡との関連が指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It indicated the power struggle with the Takahashi clan and the relationship with Dokyo (a priest of Hosso Sect of Buddhism in the Nara period).</e>
<cmt>道鏡の説明を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It indicated the power struggle with the Takahashi clan and the relationship with Dokyo (a priest of Hosso Sect of Buddhism in the Nara period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It indicated the power struggle with the Takahashi clan and the relationship with Dokyo (a priest of Hosso Sect of Buddhism in the Nara period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>海人・海部との関連</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The relationship with male divers and amabe</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Relationship with Male Divers and Amabe</e>
<cmt>subtitle capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Relationship with male divers and amabe</e>
<cmt>文頭以外の語頭を小文字に</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="60">
<j>阿曇氏が海人を束ねる地位にあったことはすでに述べた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As previously stated, the Azumi clan was in the position to bring all the male divers together.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As previously stated, the Azumi clan was in the position to bring all the male divers together.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As previously stated, the Azumi clan was in the position to bring all the male divers together.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>また膳臣配下の膳大伴部も、志摩国の海人・海部を支配していたと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was considered that Kashiwade no Otomobe, a subordinate of Kashiwadenoomi, also dominated the male divers and amabe in Shima Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was considered that Kashiwade no Otomobe, a subordinate of Kashiwadenoomi, also dominated the male divers and amabe in Shima Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was considered that Kashiwade no Otomobe, a subordinate of Kashiwadenoomi, also dominated the male divers and amabe in Shima Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>万葉集での記述</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The description in Manyoshu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Description in the Manyoshu</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Description in the Manyoshu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="62">
<j>万葉集の歌の中に「御食国」（「御食津国」、「御食都国」とも）が確認できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miketsukuni could be found in the poems in Manyoshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miketsukuni could be found in the poems of the Manyoshu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miketsukuni could be found in the poems of the Manyoshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>それぞれ伊勢国（読み人不明）、志摩国（大伴）、淡路国（山部）など、その土地を賛美した歌となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each poem admired the land of Ise Province (anonymous), Shima Province (written by OTOMO no Yakamochi), and Awaji Province (written by YAMABE no Akahito).</e>
<cmt>大伴・山部の名前を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each poem admired the land of Ise Province (anonymous), Shima Province (written by OTOMO no Yakamochi), and Awaji Province (written by YAMABE no Akahito).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each poem admired the land of Ise Province (anonymous), Shima Province (written by OTOMO no Yakamochi), and Awaji Province (written by YAMABE no Akahito).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>天皇がその国・土地を賛美するということは、すなわち該当地域の支配を暗示したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the emperor admired the province and the land, it implied the dominance of the appropriate areas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the emperor admired the province and the land, it implied dominance of the appropriate areas.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the emperor admired the province and the land, it implied dominance of the appropriate areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>贄を貢がせてこれを食べることで贄の産地たる河川・山・海の支配を儀式的に示したものと同様のものと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was considered that by eating the supplied offering, it indicated a ritual indication of the dominance of rivers, mountains, and oceans where offering was produced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was considered that by eating the supplied offerings, it indicated a ritual indication of the dominance of rivers, mountains, and oceans where offerings were produced.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was considered that by eating the supplied offerings, it indicated a ritual indication of the dominance of rivers, mountains, and oceans where offerings were produced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>御食国の研究</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The study on Miketsukuni</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Study of Miketsukuni</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The study of Miketsukuni</e>
<cmt>文頭以外の語頭を小文字に</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="66">
<j>『若狭国』・『志摩国』・『淡路国』と万葉集にみる御食国への推定と、御食国が皇室・朝廷にとって特殊であるという説は、狩野久の研究によるところが大きい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Wakasa Province,&quot; &quot;Shima Province,&quot; and &quot;Awaji Province,&quot; the estimation of Miketsukuni from the descriptions in Manyoshu, and the theory that Miketsukuni was special for Imperial family and Imperial court, were mostly due to the study by Hisashi KANO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Wakasa Province,&quot; &quot;Shima Province,&quot; and &quot;Awaji Province,&quot; the estimation of Miketsukuni from the descriptions in the Manyoshu, and the theory that Miketsukuni was special for Imperial family and Imperial court, were mostly due to a study by Hisashi KANO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Wakasa Province,&quot; &quot;Shima Province,&quot; and &quot;Awaji Province,&quot; the estimation of Miketsukuni from the descriptions in the Manyoshu, and the theory that Miketsukuni was special for Imperial family and Imperial court, were mostly due to a study by Hisashi KANO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>推定の根拠をまとめると以下の3点である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were the following three points by summarizing the presumptions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are the following three points from summarizing the presumptions.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are the following three points from summarizing the presumptions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="68">
<j>これらの国が田畑の少なさにもかかわらず一国として成立していた</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each province was approved as one province despite small farm land.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each province was approved as one province despite the limited farm land.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each province was approved as one province despite the limited farm land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="69">
<j>海産物が豊富にとれ、中央政府のあった畿内に物理的に近い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The marine products were abundant, and kinai where there was the central government was geographically close.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Marine products were abundant, and kinai where there the central government was located, was geographically close.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Marine products were abundant, and kinai where there the central government was located, was geographically close.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="70">
<j>膳氏（高橋氏）や阿曇氏（安曇氏）との関わりが深い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kashiwade clan (the Takahashi clan) and Azumi clan had close relationships.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kashiwade clan (Takahashi clan) and Azumi clan had close relationships.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kashiwade clan (Takahashi clan) and Azumi clan had close relationships.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="71">
<j>しかし、平城京から発見されている木簡や『延喜式』で贄を納めることを義務付けられていた国は、信濃国、下野国など内陸で比較的畿内より遠い国もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, according to the mokan and &quot;the Engishiki&quot; discovered from Heijo-kyo, the provinces obligated to pay offering were sited in the inland areas such as Shinano Province and Shimotsuke Province, and those were relatively far from kinai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, according to the mokan and &quot;the Engishiki&quot; discovered from Heijo-kyo, the provinces obligated to pay offerings were sited in the inland areas such as Shinano Province and Shimotsuke Province, and those were relatively far from kinai.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, according to the mokkan and &quot;the Engishiki&quot; discovered from Heijo-kyo, the provinces obligated to pay offerings were sited in the inland areas such as Shinano Province and Shimotsuke Province, and those were relatively far from kinai.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>また、海産物以外の山野での収穫物や農作物に関する研究も今後すすめる必要が指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also noted that the further study is necessary on the harvests and crops, excluding marine products, in the countryside.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also noted that the further study is necessary concerning the harvests and crops, excluding marine products, in the countryside.</e>
<cmt>vocabulary</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also noted that the further study is necessary concerning the harvests and crops, excluding marine products, in the countryside.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="73">
<j>現在の御食国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The current Miketsukuni</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Current Miketsukuni</e>
<cmt>subtitle capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The current Miketsukuni</e>
<cmt>文頭以外の語頭を小文字に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>かつて御食国だった地域では、「御食国」という言葉を一種のブランドとして観光振興に使用している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the areas that were Miketsukuni once, the word &apos;Miketsukuni&apos; is now used for tourism promotion as one of the brand names.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the areas that were Miketsukuni once, the word &apos;Miketsukuni&apos; is now used for promoting tourism as one of the brand names.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the areas that were Miketsukuni once, the word &apos;Miketsukuni&apos; is now used for promoting tourism as one of the brand names.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>2006年10月6日には、「御食国」の歴史を持つ近畿地方の以下の6つの自治体が集まり、「御食国サミット」の初会合が開かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 6, 2006, the autonomous communities of the followings in Kinki area, where had the history of &apos;Miketsukuni,&apos; gathered and held their first meeting of &apos;Miketsukuni Summit.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 6, 2006, the autonomous communities of the in the Kinki area, that had a history of &apos;Miketsukuni,&apos; gathered and held their first meeting as a &apos;Miketsukuni Summit.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 6, 2006, the autonomous communities in the Kinki area, that had a history of &apos;Miketsukuni,&apos; gathered and held their first meeting as a &apos;Miketsukuni Summit.&apos;</e>
<cmt>of the 削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="76">
<j>小浜市（福井県）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Obama City (Fukui Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Obama City (Fukui Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Obama City (Fukui Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>伊勢市（三重県）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ise City (Mie Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ise City (Mie Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ise City (Mie Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>鳥羽市（三重県）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toba City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toba City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toba City (Mie Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>(Mie Prefecture) を挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>志摩市（三重県）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shima City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shima City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shima City (Mie Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>(Mie Prefecture) を挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>南伊勢町（三重県）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minami Ise-cho Town</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minami Ise-cho Town</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minami Ise-cho Town (Mie Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>(Mie Prefecture) を挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>洲本市（兵庫県）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumoto City (Hyogo Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sumoto City (Hyogo Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sumoto City (Hyogo Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nnh(id:474), Ypacaraí(id:11031), Yosemite(id:5808), Goki(id:7107), 廬舎那憂(id:168188), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>