<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>紫香楽宮</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigaraki no miya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigaraki no miya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigaraki no miya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>紫香楽宮／信楽宮（しがらきのみや）は、奈良時代、聖武天皇が近江国甲賀郡（現在の滋賀県甲賀市信楽町）に営んだ離宮。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigaraki no miya is the detached palace in Koga gun (county), Omi Province (present-day Shigaraki-cho Town, Koga City, Shiga Prefecture) which was operated by Emperor Shomu in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigaraki no miya is the detached palace in Koga gun (county side), Omi Province (present-day Shigaraki-cho Town, Koga City, Shiga Prefecture) that was operated by Emperor Shomu during the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigaraki no miya is the detached palace in Koga gun (county side), Omi Province (present-day Shigaraki-cho, Koga City, Shiga Prefecture) that was operated by Emperor Shomu during the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>住所表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>後に甲賀宮（こうかのみや）とも称され、都となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, it was referred to as Koka nomiya, and turned to be a capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, it was referred to as Koka nomiya, and turned into the capital.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, it was referred to as Koka nomiya, and turned into the capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>紫香楽宮</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigaraki no miya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigaraki no miya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigaraki no miya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>740年（天平12年）の藤原広嗣の乱ののち、聖武天皇は恭仁京（現在の京都府木津川市加茂町付近）に移り、742年（天平14年）には近江国甲賀郡紫香楽村に離宮を造営してしばしば行幸した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Rebellion of FUJIWARA no Hirotsugu in 740, Emperor Shomu moved to Kuni kyo (Kuni Palace) (present-day Kamo-cho Town, Kizugawa City, Kyoto Prefecture), and built and operated the detach palace in Kamo-cho Town, Kizugawa City, Kyoto Prefecture in 742; he often visited there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the FUJIWARA no Hirotsugu Rebellion in 740, Emperor Shomu moved to Kuni kyo (Kuni Palace) (present-day Kamo-cho Town, Kizugawa City, Kyoto Prefecture), and built and operated the detached palace in Kamo-cho Town, Kizugawa City, Kyoto Prefecture in 742; he often visited there.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the FUJIWARA no Hirotsugu Rebellion in 740, Emperor Shomu moved to Kuni kyo (Kuni Palace) (present-day Kamo-cho Town, Kizugawa City, Kyoto Prefecture), and built and operated the detached palace in Shigaraki Village, Koga gun, Omi Province in 742; he often visited there.</e>
<cmt>Kamo-cho Town, Kizugawa City, Kyoto Prefecture修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>これが紫香楽宮である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is how Shigaraki no miya was built.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is how Shigaraki no miya was built.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is how Shigaraki no miya was built.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>翌743年（天平15年）10月、天皇は紫香楽の地に盧舎那仏を造営することを発願した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October 743, the following year, Emperor set his mind to build Rushanabutsu (statue of Buddha) in the place of Shigaraki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October 743, the following year, the Emperor set his mind on building Rushanabutsu (statue of Buddha) in Shigaraki.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October 743, the following year, the Emperor set his mind on building Rushanabutsu (statue of Buddha) in Shigaraki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>これは恭仁京を唐の洛陽に見立て、その洛陽と関係の深い龍門石窟の盧舎那仏を紫香楽の地で表現しようとしたものとみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is assumed that he wanted to view Nikyo as Luoyang in Tan, and attempted to actualize Rushanabutsu (statue of Buddha) of Ryumon sekkutsu (stone cave) which was deeply connected to Rakuyo in the place of Shigaraki.</e>
<cmt>下記の用語を追加しました。恭仁京→Nikyo</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is assumed that he wanted to view Nikyo as Luoyang in Tan, and attempted to actualize Rushanabutsu (statue of Buddha) of Ryumon sekkutsu (stone cave) which was deeply connected to Rakuyo in Shigaraki.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is assumed that he wanted to view Kunikyo as Luoyang in Tan, and attempted to actualize Rushanabutsu (statue of Buddha) of Ryumon sekkutsu (stone cave) which was deeply connected to Luoyang in Shigaraki.</e>
<cmt>恭仁京→Nikyo→Kunikyoスペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>12月には恭仁宮の造営を中止して、紫香楽宮の造営が更に進められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December, he cancelled to build Nikyo, and shifted to focus on building Shigaraki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December, he cancelled building in Nikyo, and shifted his focus on building in Shigaraki.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December, he cancelled building in Kunikyo, and shifted his focus on building in Shigaraki.</e>
<cmt>恭仁京→Nikyo→Kunikyo</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>甲賀宮</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koka no miya</e>
<cmt>左記の用語を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koka no miya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koka no miya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>744年（天平16年）、信楽宮から甲賀宮へ宮名の変化が徐々にあらわれ、11月には甲賀寺に盧舎那仏像の体骨柱が建てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 744, the change in Miya (palace) name (from Shingaraki no miya to Koka no miya) was gradually appeared; in November, the body framework of Rushanabutsu (statue of Buddha) was built in Koga-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>下記の用語を追加しました。信楽宮→Shigaraki no miya</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 744, the change in Miya (palace) name (from Shingaraki no miya to Koka no miya) gradually appeared; in November, the body framework of Rushanabutsu (statue of Buddha) was built in Koga-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 744, the change in Miya (palace) name (from Shigaraki no miya to Koka no miya) gradually appeared; in November, the body framework of Rushanabutsu (statue of Buddha) was built in Koga-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>745年（天平17年）1月には新京と呼ばれ、宮門に大楯と槍が立てられ、甲賀宮が都とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 744, it was called Shinkyo and Koka no miya turned to be a capital, a large spear and a spear were built at the gate of the palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January 744, it was called Shinkyo and Koka no miya turned into the capital, a spear and a larger spear were built at the gate of the palace.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January 745, it was called Shinkyo and Koka no miya turned into the capital, a spear and a larger spear were built at the gate of the palace.</e>
<cmt>年号修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>更に同年4月15日には、流罪となっていた塩焼王を許して京に入ることを許していることから、実態は不明ながら京（紫香楽京）の範囲が設定されていたとみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is assumed that the area of the capital (Shigaraki no miya) was specified since Prince Shioyaki who had been transported was forgiven to enter into the capital in April 15, 745; the reality was uncertain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is assumed that the area of the capital (Shigaraki no miya) was specified since Prince Shioyaki who had been transported was forgiven to enter into the capital in April 15, 745; the reality was uncertain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is assumed that the area of the capital (Shigaraki no miya) was specified since Prince Shioyaki who had been transported was forgiven to enter into the capital in April 15, 745; the reality was uncertain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし人臣の賛同を得られず、また天災など不幸なことが相次ぎ、同年5月に平城京へ戻ることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he had to return to Heijyokyo (Heian Palace) in April in the same year since he couldn&apos;t receive corporation from his subordinate; subsequently, disasters occurred one after another.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he had to return to Heijyokyo (Heian Palace) in April the same year because he was not getting the corporation of his subordinate; subsequently, disasters occurred one after another.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he had to return to Heijokyo (Heian Palace) in May the same year because he was not getting the corporation of his subordinate; subsequently, disasters occurred one after another.</e>
<cmt>April→Mayスペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>このため甲賀寺の盧舎那仏の計画は、「奈良の大仏」東大寺盧舎那仏像として完成されることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, the plan of Rushanabutsu (statue of Buddha) at Koga-ji Temple turned out to be completed in the form of &quot;Nara daiutsu&quot; (Great Buddha of Nara); Rushanabutsu (statue of Buddha) in Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rushanabutsu (statue of Buddha) at Koga-ji Temple was completed in the form of &quot;Nara daiutsu&quot; (Great Buddha of Nara); Rushanabutsu (statue of Buddha) in Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rushanabutsu (statue of Buddha) at Koga-ji Temple was completed in the form of &apos;Nara daibutsu&apos; (Great Buddha of Nara); Rushanabutsu (statue of Buddha) in Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にスペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>紫香楽の地は、当時の感覚においては余りに山奥である事から、ここを都としたことを巡っては諸説があり、恭仁京周辺に根拠を持つ橘氏に対抗して藤原仲麻呂ら藤原氏に関与したとする説や天皇が自らの仏教信仰の拠点を求めて良弁・行基などの僧侶の助言を受けて選定したとする説などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are various theories for that Shigaraki became a capital even though it was too deep in the mountains including; a theory that he was connected to the Fujiwara clan including FUJIWARA no Nakamaro in opposition to the Tachibana clan that had their base around Nikyo; the Emperor selected Shigaraki in accordance with the advice from monks such as Roben (Ryoben) or Gyoki in pursuit for his own base of faith for Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various theories why Shigaraki became a capital even though it was too deep in the mountains ione that he was connected to the Fujiwara clan including FUJIWARA no Nakamaro in opposition to the Tachibana clan that had their base around Nikyo; the Emperor selected Shigaraki in accordance with the advice from monks such as Roben (Ryoben) or Gyoki in pursuit of his own base of faith for Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various theories why Shigaraki became a capital even though it was too deep in the mountains one that he was connected to the Fujiwara clan including FUJIWARA no Nakamaro in opposition to the Tachibana clan that had their base around Kunikyo; the Emperor selected Shigaraki in accordance with the advice from monks such as Roben (Ryoben) or Gyoki in pursuit of his own base of faith for Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>宮名の変化</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Change in Miya (palace) Name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Change in Miya (palace) Name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Change in Miya (palace) Name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>「紫香楽」の地名表記については、正倉院文書には「信楽宮」としたものが3件ある一方で、「紫香楽」と表記したものが全く無いため、続日本紀が編纂されたときの修辞の可能性が考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the description in geographical name of `紫香楽 (Shigaraki)&apos;, there was none of `紫香楽 (Shigaraki in kanji character)&apos; while there were three cases of `信楽宮 (Shigaraki in kanji character)&apos; in Shoso-in bunsho (the Record of Shoso-in), therefore, it might have been modified when Shoku Nihon gi (Continuation of Chronicles of Japan) was edited.</e>
<cmt>漢字表記自体を問題にしていると思われるため、あえて原文（全角文字）を残しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the description in the geographical name of `紫香楽 (Shigaraki),&apos;,there was no `紫香楽 (Shigaraki in kanji character)&apos; while there were three cases of `信楽宮 (Shigaraki in kanji character)&apos; in Shoso-in bunsho (the Record of Shoso-in), therefore, it might have been modified when Shoku Nihon gi (Continuation of Chronicles of Japan) was edited.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the description in the geographical name of `紫香楽&apos; (Shigaraki), there was no `紫香楽&apos; (Shigaraki in kanji character) while there were three cases of `信楽宮&apos; (Shigaraki in kanji character) in Shoso-in bunsho (the Record of Shoso-in), therefore, it might have been modified when Shoku Nihon gi (Continuation of Chronicles of Japan) was edited.</e>
<cmt>コンマ削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また744年（天平16年）を境に、宮名が「信楽宮」（続日本紀では「紫香楽宮」）から「甲賀宮」へと変化しており、これは単なる離宮から甲賀寺と一体の都とされたことにより宮名が改められたか、離宮の紫香楽宮とは別に宮町遺跡の地に甲賀宮が造営されたものとも言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, after 744, Miya (palace) name was changed from `信楽宮 (Shigaraki)&apos; to `甲賀宮 (Koka no miya)&apos;; it is said that the Miya (palace) name was revised as the detached palace was united with Koga-ji Temple to be a capital, or Kouka no miya was built and operated in the palace town of palace ruins apart from Shigaraki no miya in the detached palace.</e>
<cmt>漢字表記自体を問題にしていると思われるため、あえて原文（全角文字）を残しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, after 744, Miya (palace) name was changed from `信楽宮 (Shigaraki)&apos; to `甲賀宮 (Koka no miya),&apos; it is said that the Miya (palace) name was revised as the detached palace was united with Koga-ji Temple to become a capital, or Kouka no miya was built and operated in the palace town of palace ruins apart from Shigaraki no miya in the detached palace.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, after 744, Miya (palace) name was changed from `信楽宮&apos; (Shigaraki) to `甲賀宮&apos; (Koka no miya), it is said that the Miya (palace) name was revised as the detached palace was united with Koga-ji Temple to become a capital, or Koka no miya was built and operated in the palace town of palace ruins apart from Shigaraki no miya in the detached palace.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正&apos;の位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>宮跡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Palace Ruins</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Palace Ruins</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Palace ruins</e>
<cmt>文頭以外の語頭を小文字に</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>最近では国史跡・紫香楽宮跡の北約1kmに位置する宮町遺跡から大規模な建物跡や税納入を示す木簡が大量に出土したことから、ここが宮跡の有力地となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently, a lot of mokkan (a narrow strip of wood on which an official message is written) that describe the large remains of structures or tax delivery were unearthed in palace town ruins which was located 1km to the north from the palace ruins of Shigaraki no miya, therefore, it was considered as a probable place of the palace ruins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently, a lot of mokkan (narrow strip of wood on which an official message is written) that describe the large remains of structures, or delivery of taxes, were unearthed in the palace town ruins located 1km to the north from the palace ruins of Shigaraki no miya, therefore, it was considered as a probable place of the palace ruins.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently, a lot of mokkan (narrow strip of wood on which an official message is written) that describe the large remains of structures, or delivery of taxes, were unearthed in the palace town ruins located 1 km to the north from the palace ruins of Shigaraki no miya (ruins designated by the nation), therefore, it was considered as a probable place of the palace ruins.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入・削除(ruins designated by the nation) 補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>国史跡・紫香楽宮跡は甲賀寺（甲可寺）跡であるという説が有力である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is probable that the ruins of Shigarakino miya (ruins specified by nation) was the ruins of Koga-ji Temple (Koka-ji).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is probable that the ruins of Shigarakino miya (ruins designated by the nation) was the ruins of Koga-ji Temple (Koka-ji).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is probable that the ruins of Shigaraki no miya (ruins designated by the nation) was the ruins of Koga-ji Temple (Koka-ji).</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>現在でも、「宮町」「勅旨」「内裏野」などの地名が残り、往事の宮城の名残を残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In present day, geographic names such as `Miyamachi&apos;, `Chokushi&apos;, `Dairino&apos; that show the trace of Miyagi in the past are still remained.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Present day, geographical names such as `Miyamachi,&apos; `Chokushi,&apos; `Dairino&apos; show that a trace of Miyagi in the past still remains.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Present day, geographical names such as `Miyamachi,&apos; `Chokushi,&apos; `Dairino&apos; show that a trace of Miyagi in the past still remains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Sbc(id:64835), Bakkai(id:7233), Villeneuve1982(id:22620), Ganman(id:96316), Reggaeman(id:6214), 水野白楓(id:22811), うぃき野郎(id:53567), BitBucket(id:30999), 663highland(id:18755), Udon-ya(id:48431), Y.o-ji-nn(id:39866), Kyoww(id:126965), Yusuke.ogawa(id:61600), BAKU(id:55205), -1g(id:67660), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>