<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>源能有</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshiari</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Yoshiari</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshiari</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>源 能有（みなもと の よしあり、承和12年(845年)-寛平9年6月8日（897年7月11日)）は平安時代の貴族、政治家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshiari (845 - July 11, 897) was an aristocrat and politician who lived in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Yoshiari (845 - July 11, 897) was an aristocrat and politician who lived in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshiari (845 - July 11, 897) was an aristocrat and politician who lived in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>文徳天皇の皇子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a son of Emperor Montoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the son of Emperor Montoku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the son of Emperor Montoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>生母は伴氏で第一皇子であったと伝わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that his biological mother was the Tomo clan and he was the first son of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that his biological mother was from the Tomo clan and he was the first son of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that his biological mother was from the Tomo clan and he was the first son of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>号は近院大臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His sobriquet was Konin no otodo.</e>
<cmt>号→sobriquet[http://tangorin.com/words/号]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His sobriquet was Konin no otodo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His sobriquet was Konin no otodo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>同じ文徳天皇の皇子である惟仁親王（清和天皇）より年長でありながら、生母が藤原氏でなかったこともあり、皇嗣からは早い段階で除外されていたらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he was older than another son of Emperor Montoku, Imperial Prince Korehito (Emperor Seiwa), he was ruled out as a candidate of heir since his biological mother was not the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he was older than the other son of Emperor Montoku, Imperial Prince Korehito (Emperor Seiwa), he was ruled out as a candidate of heir since his biological mother was not of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he was older than the other son of Emperor Montoku, Imperial Prince Korehito (Emperor Seiwa), he was ruled out as a candidate of heir since his biological mother was not of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>第一親等の皇族でありながらも、当時の慣例に倣って源氏姓を賜り、臣籍降下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though he was a member of imperial family and the first degree of relationship, he was given the family name of Minamoto following the practice of that day and became subject of the state.</e>
<cmt>臣籍降下→becoming subjects of the state[http://tangorin.com/words/臣籍降下]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though he was a member of the imperial family and maintained a first degree relationship, he was given the family name of Minamoto following the practices of the times and he became subject of the state.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though he was a member of the imperial family and maintained a first degree relationship, he was given the family name of Minamoto following the practices of the times and he became subject of the state.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>能有の兄弟の多くがこれと同様の道をたどり、その子孫は後世文徳源氏と呼ばれることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of Yoshiari&apos;s brothers walked the same road and their descendants were called Montoku-Genji (Minamoto clan) after ages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of Yoshiari&apos;s brothers walked the same road and their descendants were called Montoku-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of Yoshiari&apos;s brothers walked the same road and their descendants were called Montoku-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>能有は朝廷の儀礼や政務に通じた有能な人物として知られ、貞観4年(862年)に従四位に初叙任されると、以後徐々に中央官界において頭角を顕し、弟の清和天皇、それに続く陽成天皇の治世をよく輔けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiari was known as a person of ability who was familiar with rites and government practices of the Imperial Court, after he was firstly given the rank of Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank) in 862, he gradually distinguished himself in the national political arena and supported his younger brother, Emperor Seiwa and subsequent Emperor Yozei well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiari was known as a person of ability who was familiar with rites and government practices of the Imperial Court, after he was first given the rank of Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank) in 862, he gradually distinguished himself in the national political arena and supported his younger brother, Emperor Seiwa and the subsequent Emperor Yozei well.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiari was known as a person of ability who was familiar with rites and government practices of the Imperial Court, after he was first given the rank of Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank) in 862, he gradually distinguished himself in the national political arena and supported his younger brother, Emperor Seiwa and the subsequent Emperor Yozei well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その能力は藤原基経からも評価されてその娘を娶る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His ability was valued by FUJIWARA no Mototsune and he married the daughter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His ability was valued by FUJIWARA no Mototsune and he married their daughter.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His ability was valued by FUJIWARA no Mototsune and he married his daughter.</e>
<cmt>their→his</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その後、正三位左衛門督、左近衛大将、大蔵卿、検非違使別当、民部卿、按察使を歴任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he was promoted to the rank of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and held positions such as Saemon no kami, Sakone no daisho (Western Commander), Okura kyo, Kebiishi Kebiishi Betto (a director of the police and justice department), Minbu kyo and Azechi (supervisor of local politics).</e>
<cmt>左衛門督→saemon no kami[定訳不明]大蔵卿→Okura kyo[定訳不明]民部卿→Minbu kyo[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he was promoted to the rank of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and held positions such as Saemon no kami, Sakone no daisho (Western Commander), Okura kyo, Kebiishi Kebiishi Betto (a director of the police and justice department), Minbu kyo and Azechi (supervisor of local politics).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he was promoted to the rank of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and held positions such as Saemon no kami (captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards), Sakone no daisho (Western Commander), Okura kyo (Minister of the Treasury), Kebiishi Kebiishi Betto (a director of the police and justice department), Minbu kyo and Azechi (supervisor of local politics).</e>
<cmt>(captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards)(Minister of the Treasury)補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>更に宇多天皇の信任が厚く、符宣上卿（太政官符を発給する際の上卿）として28回も名を連ね、『日本三代実録』編纂開始時には源融・藤原良世と先任の上卿2人がいるにも関わらず撰国史所総裁を務めていること、寛平7年（895年）には位階昇進の人事草案を提出する擬階奏を行っている（いずれも摂関もしくは一上が務める慣例であった）ことから、藤原基経没後は能有が事実上の政権担当者として寛平の治を押し進めたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, he won Emperor Uda&apos;s esteem and was assigned to serve as Fusen jyokyo, a commander who led dajokannpu (official documents from the Grand Council of State) 28 times, and from the fact that he served as the president of Senkokushisho (an organization which edits national history book) when the editing of &quot;Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku&quot;began even though there were 2 other senior commanders like MINAMOTO no Toru and FUJIWARA no Yoshiyo, also in 895, he submitted a personnel proposal for promotion in rank (generally, both of these roles were played by Regents and Chancellor or Ichinokami (Minister of the Left)), Yoshiari pushed forward the peaceful era of Kanpyo as a factual administration after FUJIWARA no Mototsune died.</e>
<cmt>太政官符→dajokannpu (official documents from the Grand Council of State [定訳不明])</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, he won Emperor Uda&apos;s esteem and was assigned to serve as Fusen jyokyo, a commander who led dajokannpu (official documents from the Grand Council of State) 28 times, and from the fact that he served as the president of Senkokushisho (an organization which edits national history books) when the editing of &quot;Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku&quot;began even though there were 2 other senior commanders like MINAMOTO no Toru and FUJIWARA no Yoshiyo, also in 895, he submitted a personnel proposal for promotion in rank (generally, both of these roles were played by Regents and Chancelloror Ichinokami - Minister of the Left), Yoshiari pushed forward the peaceful era of Kanpyo as a factual administration after FUJIWARA no Mototsune died.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, he won Emperor Uda&apos;s esteem and was assigned to serve as Fusen jokyo, a commander who led dajokanpu (official documents from the Grand Council of State) 28 times, and from the fact that he served as the president of Senkokushisho (an organization which edits national history books) when the editing of &quot;Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku&quot; (sixth of the six classical Japanese history texts) began even though there were 2 other senior commanders like MINAMOTO no Toru and FUJIWARA no Yoshiyo, also in 895, he submitted a personnel proposal for promotion in rank (generally, both of these roles were played by Regents and Chancellor Ichinokami - Minister of the Left), Yoshiari pushed forward the peaceful era of Kanpyo as a factual administration after FUJIWARA no Mototsune died.</e>
<cmt>スペル(sixth of the six classical Japanese history texts)補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>この年の暮れには「五畿内諸国別当」に任じられ、翌寛平8年(896年)には平季長を山城国問民苦使に任じて、その報告を元にして院宮王臣家による土地の不法拡大を禁じる太政官符などの農民保護政策を打ち出している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the end of the year, he was assigned to serve as a Gokinai Shokoku Betto (a director of the five central provinces), then he assigned TAIRA no Suenaga as a Momikushi (an inspector of local politics) of Yamashiro Province and according to his report, Yoshiari came up with policies covering farmers such as dajokannpu which banned illegal expansion of territory by Ingu oshin ke (imperial families and aristocrats who had strong connection with the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>院宮王臣家→Ingu oshin ke (imperial families and aristocrats who had strong connection with the Emperor)[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end of the year, he was assigned to serve as a Gokinai Shokoku Betto (a director of the five central provinces), then he assigned TAIRA no Suenaga as a Momikushi (an inspector of local politics) of Yamashiro Province and according to his report, Yoshiari came up with policies covering farmers such as dajokannpu which banned illegal expansion of territory by Ingu oshin ke (imperial families and aristocrats who had strong connection with the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end of the year, he was assigned to serve as a Gokinai Shokoku Betto (a director of the five central provinces), then in the following year of 896, he assigned TAIRA no Suenaga as a Momikushi (an inspector of local politics) of Yamashiro Province and according to his report, Yoshiari came up with policies covering farmers such as dajokanpu which banned illegal expansion of territory by Ingu oshin ke (imperial families and aristocrats who had strong connection with the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>in the following year of 896,補足スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>この年には右大臣左兵衛督加賀美濃権守の位に昇るが、これを極官として、その翌年に病を得て死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, he was promoted to the position of Udaijin (Minister of the Right), Sahyoe no kami and director of Kaga and Mino Provinces, it was his gokkann (the highest official rank) and he died of illness next year.</e>
<cmt>左兵衛督→sahyoe no kami[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, he was promoted to the position of Udaijin (Minister of the Right), Sahyoe no kami and director of Kaga and Mino Provinces, it was his gokkann (the highest official rank) and he died of illness next year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, he was promoted to the position of Udaijin (Minister of the Right), Sahyoe no kami and director of Kaga and Mino Provinces, it was his gokkan (the highest official rank) and he died of illness next year.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>享年53。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His age at death was 53.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His age at death was 53.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His age at death was 53.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>寛平9年6月16日に贈正一位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was given the rank of Zo shoichii (Senior First Rank, posthumously conferred) on June 16, 897.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was given the rank of Zo shoichii (Senior First Rank, posthumously conferred) on June 16, 897.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was given the rank of Zo shoichii (Senior First Rank, posthumously conferred) on July 23, 897.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ歴に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>また菅原道真と親しく、道真の詩文集『菅家文章』には能有に頼まれて自宅の竹を能有邸に移植した時の漢詩や能有追悼の漢詩が収録されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was friendly with SUGAWARA no Michizane and Michizane created a Chinese poem about the time when Michizane transplanted his bamboos in Yoshiari&apos;s residence at his request and an epitaph for Yoshiari, these poems were included in Michizane&apos;s poetry book called &quot;Kanke bunso&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was friendly with SUGAWARA no Michizane and Michizane created a Chinese poem about the time when Michizane transplanted his bamboos at Yoshiari&apos;s residence at his request along with an epitaph for Yoshiari, these poems were included in Michizane&apos;s poetry book called &quot;Kanke bunso.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was friendly with SUGAWARA no Michizane and Michizane created a Chinese poem about the time when Michizane transplanted his bamboos at Yoshiari&apos;s residence at his request along with an epitaph for Yoshiari, these poems were included in Michizane&apos;s poetry book called &quot;Kanke bunso.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また、宇多天皇も寛平御遺誡の中で右大臣（能有）の失った衝撃について触れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Emperor Uda described about the shock of Udaijin (Yoshiari)&apos;s death in &quot;Kanpyo goikai (instructions to one&apos;s descendants)&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, Emperor Uda described the shock at Udaijin (Yoshiari)&apos;s death in &quot;Kanpyo goikai (instructions to one&apos;s descendants)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, Emperor Uda described the shock at Udaijin (Yoshiari)&apos;s death in &quot;Kanpyo goikai&quot; (instructions to one&apos;s descendants).</e>
<cmt>(instructions to one&apos;s descendants)位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>能有の男系の子孫には、後代保元の乱で活躍した源季実などが出ている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Yoshiari&apos;s male descendants produced MINAMOTO no Suezane who fought bravely in the Hogen War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Yoshiari&apos;s male descendants produced MINAMOTO no Suezane who fought bravely in the Hogen War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Yoshiari&apos;s male descendants produced MINAMOTO no Suezane who fought bravely in the Hogen War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>一方、女系に目を転じると、娘の源昭子は藤原忠平の妻として藤原師輔らを産み、同じく源柄子は貞純親王の妻となって源経基を産んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for female descendants, his daughter, MINAMOTO no Shoshi (Akiko) got married to FUJIWARA no Tadahira and gave birth to FUJIWARA no Morosuke and another daughter, MINAMOTO no Karako got married to Imperial Prince Sadazumi and gave birth to MINAMOTO no Tsunemoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for female descendants, his daughter, MINAMOTO no Shoshi (Akiko) got married to FUJIWARA no Tadahira and gave birth to FUJIWARA no Morosuke and another daughter, MINAMOTO no Karako got married to Imperial Prince Sadazumi and gave birth to MINAMOTO no Tsunemoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for female descendants, his daughter, MINAMOTO no Shoshi (Akiko) got married to FUJIWARA no Tadahira and gave birth to FUJIWARA no Morosuke and another daughter, MINAMOTO no Karako got married to Imperial Prince Sadazumi and gave birth to MINAMOTO no Tsunemoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>即ち、師輔以降の摂関家と、経基以降の清和源氏という二つの大族に、その血統を伝えたことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the other words, his bloodline was descended to two big families: the regent family after Morosuke and the Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan) after Tsunemoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the other words, his bloodline was descended to two big families: the regent family after Morosuke and the Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan) after Tsunemoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the other words, his bloodline was descended to two big families: the regent family after Morosuke and the Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan) after Tsunemoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 阿波座行広(id:39667), Andee(id:20421), 代言人(id:33675), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>