<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>ばい子内親王 (後宇多天皇皇女)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Princess Baishi (Princess of Emperor Gouda)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Princess Baishi (Princess of Emperor Gouda)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Princess Baishi (Princess of Emperor Gouda)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>禖子内親王（ばいしないしんのう、生没年不詳）は、後宇多天皇の第二皇女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Princess Baishi (date of birth and death unknown) was the second Princess of Emperor Gouda.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Princess Baishi (date of birth and death unknown) was the second Princess of Emperor Gouda.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Princess Baishi (year of birth and death unknown) was the second Princess of Emperor Gouda.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>母は鎌倉幕府征夷大将軍宗尊親王王女揄子女王。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her mother was Princess Rinshi, the prince of Imperial Prince Munetaka who was seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her mother was Princess Rinshi, the prince of Imperial Prince Munetaka who was seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her mother was Princess Rinshi, the prince of Imperial Prince Munetaka who was seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>女院号は崇明門院（すうめいもんいん/そうめいもんいん）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her nyoingo (a title of respect given to close female relatives of the Emperor or a woman of comparable standing) was Sumeimonin (also pronounced Someimonin).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her nyoingo (title of respect given to close female relatives of the Emperor or a woman of comparable standing) was Sumeimonin (also pronounced Someimonin).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her nyoingo (title of respect given to close female relatives of the Emperor or a woman of comparable standing) was Sumeimonin (also pronounced Someimonin).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief personal history</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>元応元年10月28日 (旧暦)（1319年12月10日）に内親王宣下を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was given the title of the imperial princess on December 10, 1319.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was given the title of imperial princess on December 10, 1319.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was given the title of imperial princess on December 18, 1319.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ歴に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>後に甥にあたる皇太子邦良親王（後二条天皇嫡男）の妃となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She later became the wife of Crown Prince Kuniyoshi (the heir of Emperor Gonijo), who was her nephew.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She later became the wife of Crown Prince Kuniyoshi (the heir of Emperor Gonijo), who was her nephew.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She later became the wife of Crown Prince Kuniyoshi (the heir of Emperor Gonijo), who was her nephew.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>元亨3年（1323年）に親王妃の平産祈祷が行われており、この頃には禖子が皇太子妃になっていたことが知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A safe birth for the wife of Imperial Prince was prayed in 1323; on this occasion, it was known that Baishi became the wife of the Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A safe birth for the wife of Imperial Prince was prayed for in 1323; on this occasion, it was known that Baishi became the wife of the Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A safe birth for the wife of Imperial Prince was prayed for in 1323; on this occasion, it was known that Baishi became the wife of the Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>だが、皇太子の叔父で禖子には異母兄にあたる後醍醐天皇は自らの系統が大覚寺統の庶流に位置づけられたことに不満を抱き、大覚寺統の嫡流の地位を主張して譲位を求める邦良との確執を深めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Godaigo, who was the Crown Prince&apos;s uncle and Baishi&apos;s half brother, complained that his family line was positioned as the branch family of Daikakuji-to (imperial lineage starting with Emperor Kameyama) and insisted on the position as the direct descendant of Daikakuji-to, thus intensifying a feud with Kuniyoshi who was demanding Emperor Godaigo&apos;s abdication.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Godaigo, who was the Crown Prince&apos;s uncle and Baishi&apos;s half brother, complained that his family line was positioned as a branch family of Daikakuji-to (imperial lineage starting with Emperor Kameyama) and insisted on the position of direct descendant of Daikakuji-to, thus intensifying a feud with Kuniyoshi who was demanding Emperor Godaigo&apos;s abdication.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Godaigo, who was the Crown Prince&apos;s uncle and Baishi&apos;s half brother, complained that his family line was positioned as a branch family of Daikakuji-to (imperial lineage starting with Emperor Kameyama) and insisted on the position of direct descendant of Daikakuji-to, thus intensifying a feud with Kuniyoshi who was demanding Emperor Godaigo&apos;s abdication.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>ところが、嘉暦元年（1326年）に親王が急死、直後に禖子は出家して親王の遺児である康仁親王（母は権大納言花山院定教 (権大納言)の娘）を養育する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Imperial Prince Kuniyoshi suddenly died in 1326 and then Baishi entered into priesthood soon after his death to raise a bereaved child of the Imperial Prince Kuniyoshi, Imperial Prince Yasuhito (his mother was the daughter of Sadanori KAZANIN, who held the title of Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Imperial Prince Kuniyoshi suddenly died in 1326 and then Baishi entered into the priesthood soon after his death to raise a bereaved child of Imperial Prince Kuniyoshi, Imperial Prince Yasuhito (his mother was the daughter of Sadanori KAZANIN, who held the title of Gon Dainagon - provisional major counselor).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Imperial Prince Kuniyoshi suddenly died in 1326 and then Baishi entered into the priesthood soon after his death to raise a bereaved child of Imperial Prince Kuniyoshi, Imperial Prince Yasuhito (his mother was the daughter of Sadanori KAZANIN, who held the title of Gon Dainagon - provisional major counselor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>元徳3年（元弘元年/1331年）に、後醍醐天皇が鎌倉幕府倒幕を企てて廃位される（元弘の変）と、持明院統の光厳天皇が即位する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Emperor Godaigo was dethroned due to his attempt to overthrow the Kamakura bakufu (the Genko Incident) in 1331, Emperor Kogon of Jimyoin-to (imperial lineage from Emperor Gofukakusa to Emperor Gokomatsu) was enthroned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Emperor Godaigo was dethroned due to his attempt to overthrow the Kamakura bakufu (the Genko Incident) in 1331, Emperor Kogon of Jimyoin-to (imperial lineage from Emperor Gofukakusa to Emperor Gokomatsu) was enthroned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Emperor Godaigo was dethroned due to his attempt to overthrow the Kamakura bakufu (the Genko Incident) in 1331, Emperor Kogon of Jimyoin-to (imperial lineage from Emperor Gofukakusa to Emperor Gokomatsu) was enthroned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その際、元弘の変に関与していない大覚寺統嫡流の邦良親王家との両統迭立を求める鎌倉幕府の意向によって康仁親王が皇太子に立てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this occasion, Imperial Prince Yasuhito was installed as the Crown Prince by the intention of Kamakura bakufu who was demanding the alternate accedence from two ancestries of imperial families including the family of Imperial Prince Kuniyoshi, the main branch of Daikakuji-to that was not involved in the Genko Incident.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this occasion, Imperial Prince Yasuhito was installed as the Crown Prince by the intention of Kamakura bakufu who was demanding an alternate accedence from two ancestries of the imperial families including the family of Imperial Prince Kuniyoshi, the main branch of Daikakuji-to those who were not involved in the Genko Incident.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this occasion, Imperial Prince Yasuhito was installed as the Crown Prince by the intention of Kamakura bakufu who was demanding an alternate accedence from two ancestries of the Imperial Families including the family of Imperial Prince Kuniyoshi, the main branch of Daikakuji-to those who were not involved in the Genko Incident.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>禖子は母親に准じるとして同年10月25日 (旧暦)（11月25日）に康仁の立太子と同時に准三宮の称号を受け、女院宣下を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, Baishi was treated as the mother and thus awarded the rank of Jusangu (honorary rank next to the three Empresses: Great Empress Dowager, Empress Dowager, and Empress) upon the investiture for Yasuhito on November 25, 1331, and then was given the title of nyoin (a close female relative of the Emperor or a womwan of comparable standing).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, Baishi was treated as the mother and thus awarded the rank of Jusangu (honorary rank next to the three Empresses: Great Empress Dowager, Empress Dowager, and Empress) upon the investiture for Yasuhito on November 25, 1331, and then was given the title of nyoin (a close female relative of the Emperor or a womman of comparable standing).</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, Baishi was treated as the mother and thus awarded the rank of Jusangu (honorary rank next to the three Empresses: Great Empress Dowager, Empress Dowager, and Empress) upon the investiture for Yasuhito on December 3, 1331, and then was given the title of nyoin (a close female relative of the Emperor or a woman of comparable standing).</e>
<cmt>スペルグレゴリオ歴に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>だが、鎌倉幕府が滅亡し、後醍醐天皇が京都に帰還すると、元弘3年5月17日 (旧暦)（1333年6月29日）に女院号を廃されて内親王に貶された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, after the Kamakura bakufu collapsed and Emperor Godaigo returned to Kyoto, her title of nyoin was discarded and she was demoted to the imperial princess on June 29, 1333.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after the Kamakura bakufu collapsed and Emperor Godaigo returned to Kyoto, her title of nyoin was discarded and she was demoted to imperial princess on June 29, 1333.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after the Kamakura bakufu collapsed and Emperor Godaigo returned to Kyoto, her title of nyoin was discarded and she was demoted to imperial princess on July 7, 1333.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>建武政権崩壊後の建武 (日本)5年4月28日 (旧暦)（延元3年/1338年5月18日）に北朝 (日本)光明天皇の勅によって院号を復された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 18, 1338 in the Kenmu era after the fall of the Kenmu Government, she was awarded ingo (a title of respect given to close female relatives of the Emperor or a woman of comparable standing) again by the imperial decree of Emperor Komyo in the Northern Dynasty (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 18, 1338 in the Kenmu era after the fall of the Kenmu Government, she was awarded ingo (a title of respect given to close female relatives of the Emperor or a woman of comparable standing) again by the imperial decree of Emperor Komyo in the Northern Dynasty (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 26, 1338 in the Kenmu era after the fall of the Kenmu Government, she was awarded ingo (a title of respect given to close female relatives of the Emperor or a woman of comparable standing) again by the imperial decree of Emperor Komyo in the Northern Court (Japan).</e>
<cmt>用語統一グレゴリオ歴に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>その後の動向については不詳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her history thereafter is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her history thereafter is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her history thereafter is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>