<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>和宮親子内親王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazunomiya Imperial Princess Chikako</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazunomiya Imperial Princess Chikako</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazunomiya Imperial Princess Chikako</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>和宮 親子内親王（かずのみや ちかこないしんのう、（1846年7月3日 - 1877年9月2日）は、江戸時代後期の女性、江戸幕府第14代将軍徳川家茂の正室である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazunomiya Imperial Princess Chikako (July 3rd, 1846 - September 2nd, 1877) was a woman lived during the late Edo period, she was a wife of Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), fourteenth Shogun Iemochi TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazunomiya Imperial Princess Chikako (July 3rd, 1846 - September 2nd, 1877) was a woman who lived during the late Edo period, she was a wife of Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), fourteenth Shogun Iemochi TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazunomiya Imperial Princess Chikako (July 3, 1846 - September 2, 1877) was a woman who lived during the late Edo period, she was a wife of Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), fourteenth Shogun Iemochi TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>日付表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A person</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">personal</e>
<cmt>revised</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>personal→Personal Profileに変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>「和宮」は誕生の際に賜られた幼名で、「親子」は文久元年（1861年）の内親王宣下の際に賜られた諱である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazunomiya was her childhood name which was given when she was born, &apos;Chikako&apos; was given by the Emperor when she officially became the Princess in 1861.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazunomiya was her childhood name which was given when she was born, &apos;Chikako&apos; was given by the Emperor when she officially became the Princess in 1861.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazunomiya&apos; was her childhood name which was given when she was born, &apos;Chikako&apos; was given by the Emperor when she officially became the Princess in 1861.</e>
<cmt>補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>号は静寛院宮（せいかんいんのみや）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her go title was Seikaninnomiya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her go title was Seikaninnomiya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her go title was Seikaninnomiya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>江戸時代はもとより、それ以前に於いて、皇女が武家に降嫁し、関東下向した唯一の例である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was the only Princess who married to Samurai family and went to Kanto area from Edo, not only in Edo period but in the previous era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was the only Princess who married into a Samurai family and went to the Kanto area from Edo, not only during the Edo period, but in the previous era&apos;s as well.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was the only Princess who married into a Samurai family and went to the Kanto area from Edo, not only during the Edo period, but in the previous era&apos;s as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>当初和宮自身がこの結婚に疑義を唱えていたのは有名な話である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a famous story that Kazunomiya herself had doubts of this marriage in those days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a well known story that Kazunomiya, herself, had doubts about her marriage in those days.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a well known story that Kazunomiya, herself, had doubts about her marriage in those days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>結局家茂との結婚が決まった後も、幕府に異母姉桂宮淑子内親王の御殿の建設や、降嫁後も大奥風ではなく御所風の生活を守ることなどを約束させている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the marriage with Ienari was confirmed officially, she let the bakufu promises to build new Palace for her half younger sister, Katsuranomiya Imperial Princess Sumiko, or to make sure she would have her room in the Imperial Palace style, not in the inner rooms of the shogun&apos;s palace (Ooku) style after the marriage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the marriage with Ienari was confirmed officially, she made the bakufu promise to build a new Palace for her half younger sister, Katsuranomiya Imperial Princess Sumiko, or to make sure she would have her own room in the style of the Imperial Palace, not in the inner rooms of the shogun&apos;s palace (Ooku) style, after the marriage.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the marriage with Iemochi was confirmed officially, she made the bakufu promise to build a new Palace for her half younger sister, Katsuranomiya Imperial Princess Sumiko, or to make sure she would have her own room in the style of the Imperial Palace, not in the inner rooms of the shogun&apos;s palace (Ooku) style, after the marriage.</e>
<cmt>Ienari→Iemochi</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>但し、「御所風の生活」の方は幕府首脳が大奥に全く根回ししていなかったため約束は破棄同然となり、幕末の大奥が大混乱に陥った一因となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However the promises to have &apos;room of Imperial style&apos; was almost cancelled since the head of the bakufu did not communicate with the inner rooms of the shogun&apos;s (Ooku) at all on this matter, it caused the big confusion in Ooku in the last days of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Howeve,r the promise to have &apos;a room of Imperial style&apos; was almost cancelled, because the head of the bakufu did not communicate with the inner rooms of the shogun&apos;s (Ooku) at all on this matter, it caused big confusion in Ooku during the last days of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the promise to have &apos;a room of Imperial style&apos; was almost cancelled, because the head of the bakufu did not communicate with the inner rooms of the shogun&apos;s (Ooku) at all on this matter, it caused big confusion in Ooku during the last days of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>コンマ</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>江戸城内では武家の習いで将軍の正室を「御台様（みだいさま）」と呼んでいたが、親子はこれを拒否し「和宮様」と呼ばせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inside the Edo castle, due to the tradition, shogun&apos;s wife was called &apos;Midaisama&apos;, however Chikako refused to be called like that, she made others call her &apos;Kazunomiya sama&apos; instead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inside the Edo castle, due to tradition, the shogun&apos;s wife was called &apos;Midaisama,&apos; however Chikako refused to be called that, she made others call her &apos;Kazunomiya sama&apos; instead.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inside the Edo castle, due to tradition, the shogun&apos;s wife was called &apos;Midaisama,&apos; however Chikako refused to be called that, she made others call her &apos;Kazunomiya sama&apos; instead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>家茂は側室をおかず、和宮を生涯の伴侶とし、夫婦仲は良好であったとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iemochi did not have nobleman&apos;s concubine and had only Kazunomiya as his wife in all his life, it was said they had a good relationship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iemochi did not have a nobleman&apos;s concubine and had only Kazunomiya as his wife all his life, it was said they had a good relationship.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iemochi did not have a nobleman&apos;s concubine and had only Kazunomiya as his wife all his life, it was said they had a good relationship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>（実際には公にされてはいないものの愛妾があったようである。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Although it was not known in the public, Iemochi seemed to have his mistress.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Although it was not known in the public, Iemochi seemed to have a mistress.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Although it was not known in the public, Iemochi seemed to have a mistress.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="11">
<j>和宮と家茂の間に子はなく、家茂は田安慶頼の子亀之助（のちの徳川家達）に相続させることを表明していたが、家茂薨去後、和宮は「唯今の時勢、幼齢の亀之助にては如何あるべき、確かなる後見の人なくては協（かな）はざることなれば、然るべき人体を天下の為に選ぶべし」と語ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They did not have any children, Iemochi announced to let Yoshiyori TAYASU&apos;s son, Kamenosuke (later called Iesato TOKUGAWA) to succeed to his position, however after Iemochi died, it was said that Kazunomiya mentioned, &apos;In this time, the young Kamenosuke may not be good enough as a successor, since there is no one to supervise Kamenosuke, we need to choose someone appropriate for the country.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They did not have any children, Iemochi announced to let Yoshiyori TAYASU&apos;s son, Kamenosuke (later called Iesato TOKUGAWA) succeed to his position, however after Iemochi died, it was said that Kazunomiya mentioned, &apos;In this time, the young Kamenosuke may not be good enough as a successor, since there is no one to supervise Kamenosuke, we need to choose someone appropriate for the country.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They did not have any children, Iemochi announced to let Yoshiyori TAYASU&apos;s son, Kamenosuke (later called Iesato TOKUGAWA) succeed to his position, however after Iemochi died, it was said that Kazunomiya mentioned, &apos;In this time, the young Kamenosuke may not be good enough as a successor, since there is no one to supervise Kamenosuke, we need to choose someone appropriate for the country.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>老中板倉勝静らも多事多難の折柄、一橋慶喜をこそ将軍に立てるべきと斡旋し、慶喜の後継に亀之助をと和宮に伺ったところ、和宮は「御遺命さへ反故とならずば異存なし、中納言（慶喜）の後をば必ず亀之助に継がしむべし」と許可したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senior councilor Katsukiyo ITAKURA strongly recommended Yoshinobu HITOTSUBASHI during his busy days having one difficulty after another, he then asked Kazunomiya to have Kamenosuke as Yoshinobu&apos;s successor, she approved it by saying, &apos;As long as the will was kept, there is no problem, please make sure Kamenosuke succeed to Chunagon (Yoshinobu&apos;s) position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senior councilor Katsukiyo ITAKURA strongly recommended Yoshinobu HITOTSUBASHI during his busy days having one difficulty after another, he then asked Kazunomiya to have Kamenosuke as Yoshinobu&apos;s successor, she approved saying, &apos;As long as the will was kept, there is no problem, please make sure Kamenosuke succeeds to Chunagon (Yoshinobu&apos;s) position.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senior councilor Katsukiyo ITAKURA strongly recommended Yoshinobu HITOTSUBASHI during his busy days having one difficulty after another, he then asked Kazunomiya to have Kamenosuke as Yoshinobu&apos;s successor, she approved saying, &apos;As long as the will was kept, there is no problem, please make sure Kamenosuke succeeds to Chunagon (Yoshinobu&apos;s) position. &apos;</e>
<cmt>補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="13">
<j>幕府瓦解後一旦京都へ戻った和宮だが、明治天皇や市谷砂土原に居住していた実麗らの勧奨もあり再び東京へ戻ることを決め、明治七年七月、東京に戻った和宮は麻布市兵衛町にある八戸藩南部遠江守信順の元屋敷に居住した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the bakufu collapsed, Kazunomiya returned to Kyoto, however she decided to return to Tokyo after Emperor Meiji and Sanekira, who lived in Ichigaya Sadohara, encouraged her to come back, she lived in the former residence of Nobuyuki Totoumi no kami NANBU of the Hachinohe domain which is located in Hyoe-machi Town, Azabu City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the bakufu collapsed, Kazunomiya returned to Kyoto, however she decided to return to Tokyo after Emperor Meiji and Sanekira, who lived in Ichigaya Sadohara, encouraged her to come back, she lived in the former residence of Nobuyuki Totoumi no kami NANBU of the Hachinohe domain which is located in Hyoe-machi Town, Azabu City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the bakufu collapsed, Kazunomiya returned to Kyoto, however she decided to return to Tokyo after Emperor Meiji and Saneakira, who lived in Ichigaya Sadohara, encouraged her to come back, she lived in the former residence of Nobuyuki Totoumi no kami Nanbu of the Hachinohe Domain which is located in Hyoe-machi Town, Azabu City from July 1874.</e>
<cmt>NANBU→Nanbudomain→Domainfrom July 1874補足スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>東京移居後は皇族や天璋院や家達をはじめとした徳川一門など幅広い交流を持つようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After she started living in Tokyo, she socialized with wide range of people such as Iesato of Tokugawa family or other Imperial family or Tenshoin and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After she started living in Tokyo, she socialized with a wide range of people such as Iesato of the Tokugawa family or other Imperial family or Tenshoin and so on.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After she started living in Tokyo, she socialized with a wide range of people such as Iesato of the Tokugawa family or other Imperial family or Tenshoin and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>しかしこの頃より脚気を患い、明治十年八月、元奥医師の遠田澄庵の転地療養の勧めがあり箱根塔ノ沢へ向かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However she developed beriberi around this time, she went to Tonosawa, Hakone since it was recommended by former doctor of Ooku, Choan TODA to move to different place to rest her body.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However she developed beriberi around this time, she went to Tonosawa, Hakone since it was recommended by former doctor of Ooku, Choan TODA, to move to different place to rest her body.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However she developed beriberi around this time, she went to Tonosawa, Hakone in August 1877 since it was recommended by former doctor of Ooku, Choan TODA, to move to different place to rest her body.</e>
<cmt>in August 1877 補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>転地療養先では地元住民との交流も行われたようで、箱根塔ノ沢環水楼（和宮湯治時は中田暢平旅館）中野敬次郎氏に1960年代、当時98歳の平塚きわという老婆が幼い頃、村の子供達を招待して菓子を振舞われた宮の思い出を語っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seemed Kazunomiya had some contact with the local people where she stayed to rest up, Keijiro NAKANO of Kansuiro, Tonosawa, Hakone (it was Choan TODA Hotel while Kazunomiya stayed in the hot-spring resort) remembers an old lady, Kiwa HIRATSUKA who was ninety eight years old at that time, talked about Kazunomiya that she used to have children of the village over to give some sweats in 1960.</e>
<cmt>中野敬次郎→Keijiro[読み方確認できず] NAKANO</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seemed Kazunomiya had some contact with the local people where she stayed to rest up, Keijiro NAKANO of Kansuiro, Tonosawa, Hakone (it was Choan TODA Hotel while Kazunomiya stayed in the hot-spring resort) remembers an old lady, Kiwa HIRATSUKA who was ninety eight years old at that time, talking about Kazunomiya, that she used to have children of the village over to give some sweets in 1960.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seemed Kazunomiya had some contact with the local people where she stayed to rest up, Keijiro NAKANO of Kansuiro, Tonosawa, Hakone (it was Choan TODA Hotel while Kazunomiya stayed in the hot-spring resort) remembers an old lady, Kiwa HIRATSUKA who was ninety eight years old at that time, talking about Kazunomiya, that she used to have children of the village over to give some sweets during 1960s.</e>
<cmt>1960年代に合うように修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>平塚きわの語り残した宮の姿は大勢の侍女に囲まれ、白い着物を着て紫の帯を締め、おすべらかしを結っていた姿であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The way how Kazunomiya looked like how Kiwa HIRATSAUKA talked about was, she was surrounded by many lady&apos;s maids, and wearing white Kimono with a purple belt, with Osuberakashi hair style. (hair style with volume fringes tied up and had long straight hair at the back)</e>
<cmt>おすべらかし→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What Kazunomiya looked like, whatKiwa HIRATSAUKA talked about was like, she was surrounded by many maids, and wearing white Kimono with a purple belt, with Osuberakashi hair style. (hair style with volume fringes tied up and had long straight hair in the back)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What Kazunomiya looked like, what Kiwa HIRATSUKA talked about was like, she was surrounded by many maids, and wearing white Kimono with a purple belt, with Osuberakashi hair style (hair style with volume fringes tied up and had long straight hair in the back).</e>
<cmt>スペーススペルピリオド</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>また脚気のためか顔がひどく浮腫んでいたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was said her face was very swollen with beriberi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was said her face was very swollen with beriberi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was said her face was very swollen with beriberi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>程なく明治十年九月二日早朝、脚気衝心のため療養先の塔ノ沢で薨去する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not long after that, she died of breathing difficulty due to beriberi in Tonosawa in the morning on September 2nd, Meiji 10.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Not long after that, she died of breathing difficulties due to beriberi in Tonosawa in the morning on September 2nd, Meiji 10.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Not long after that, she died of breathing difficulties due to beriberi in Tonosawa in the morning on September 2, 1877.</e>
<cmt>日付表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>空蝉の袈裟</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An oblong piece of ornamental cloth worn over the robe by a Buddhist priest</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An oblong piece of ornamental cloth worn over the robe by a Buddhist priest</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Utsusemi&apos;s Kesa (an oblong piece of ornamental cloth worn over the robe by a Buddhist priest)</e>
<cmt>原文を反映</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>家茂が長州征討の為に上洛の際、凱旋の土産は何がよいかと問われた和宮は西陣織を所望したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Iemochi asked Kazunomiya what she would like as a souvenir when he came to Kyoto as his souvenir of triumph return to suppress Choshu domain, Kazunomiya asked him to get Nishijin Brocade for her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Iemochi asked Kazunomiya what she would like, when he returned to Kyoto, as a souvenir of triumphant return to suppress the Choshu domain, Kazunomiya asked him to get a Nishijin Brocade for her.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Iemochi left for Kyoto to subjugate the Choshu Domain, he asked Kazunomiya what she would like as a souvenir on his triumphant return and Kazunomiya asked him to get her a Nishijin Brocade.</e>
<cmt>原文に合うように修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>しかし家茂は征長の最中、大坂城にて病没。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However Iemochi died of illness in the Osaka Castle while suppressing Choshu domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However Iemochi died of illness in the Osaka Castle while suppressing the Choshu domain.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However Iemochi died of illness in the Osaka-jo Castle while suppressing the Choshu Domain.</e>
<cmt>-jo補足スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>西陣織は形見として和宮の元に届けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nishijin Brocade was delivered to Kazunomiya as Iemochi&apos;s momento.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nishijin Brocade was delivered to Kazunomiya as Iemochi&apos;s momento.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nishijin Brocade was delivered to Kazunomiya as Iemochi&apos;s memento.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>和宮は「空蝉の　唐織り衣　なにかせん　あやも錦も　君ありてこそ」の和歌を添えその西陣織を増上寺に奉納、のちに年忌の際、袈裟として仕立てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazunomiya gave the Nishijin brocade with the following poem to the Zojo-ji Temple, and later on the Nishijin brocade was made into Kesa (an oblong piece of ornamental cloth worn over the robe by a Buddhist priest) at the anniversary and is passed to the present, &quot; Even though I have this gorgeous Nishijin brocade Kimono, I would enjoy wearing it if you are still alive.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazunomiya gave the Nishijin brocade with the following poem to the Zojo-ji Temple, and later the Nishijin brocade was made into Kesa (an oblong piece of ornamental cloth worn over the robe by a Buddhist priest) on the anniversary and is passed to the present, &quot; Even though I have this gorgeous Nishijin brocade Kimono, I would enjoy wearing it if you are still alive.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazunomiya gave the Nishijin brocade with the following poem to the Zojo-ji Temple, and later the Nishijin brocade was made into Kesa (an oblong piece of ornamental cloth worn over the robe by a Buddhist priest) on the anniversary, &quot;Even though I have this gorgeous Nishijin brocade Kimono, I would enjoy wearing it if you are still alive.&quot;</e>
<cmt>and is passed to the present原文にないので削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>これは空蝉の袈裟として現在まで伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is passed on generations to generations as Utsusemi&apos;s Kesa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is passed from generation to generation as Utsusemi&apos;s Kesa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is passed from generation to generation as Utsusemi&apos;s Kesa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>年譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A chronological history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A chronological history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A chronological history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>弘化3年閏5月10日（1846年7月3日）未刻、仁孝天皇の第8皇女として誕生、生母は観行院（典侍・橋本経子）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 3rd, 1846, around two o&apos;clock in the afternoon, she was born as the eighth Princess of the Emperor Ninko, her birth mother was Kangyoin. (Nashinosuke Tsuneko HASHIMOTO)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 3rd, 1846, around two o&apos;clock in the afternoon, she was born as the eighth Princess of the Emperor Ninko, her birth mother was Kangyoin. (Nashinosuke Tsuneko HASHIMOTO)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 3, 1846, around two o&apos;clock in the afternoon, she was born as the eighth Princess of the Emperor Ninko, her birth mother was Kangyoin (Naishinosuke Tsuneko HASHIMOTO)</e>
<cmt>日付表記人名スペルピリオド</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>孝明天皇は異母兄。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her half older brother was Emperor Komei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her half older brother was Emperor Komei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her half older brother was Emperor Komei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>父仁孝天皇は親子の誕生前、弘化3年1月26日（1846年2月21日）に崩御していたため、勅命により、和宮は母観行院の生家橋本家で養育された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since her father, Emperor Ninko died before Chikako was born, (February 21st, 1846) she was brought up in her mother, Kangyoin&apos;s house, Hashimoto family, by the Imperial order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since her father, Emperor Ninko died before Chikako was born, (February 21st, 1846) she was brought up in her mother Kangyoin&apos;s house, with the Hashimoto family, by the Imperial order.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since her father, Emperor Ninko died before Chikako was born, (February 21, 1846) she was brought up in her mother Kangyoin&apos;s house, with the Hashimoto family, by the Imperial order.</e>
<cmt>日付表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="29">
<j>嘉永4年（1851年）、有栖川宮幟仁親王の長男・有栖川宮熾仁親王と婚約したが、岩倉具視らが推進する公武合体のため婚約破棄。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1851 she engaged with the eldest son of the Arisugawanomiya Imperial Prince, Prince Taruhito, however the engagement was cancelled due to the union of the Imperial Court and the Shogunate promoted by Tomomi IWAKURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1851 she was engaged to the eldest son of the Arisugawanomiya Imperial Prince, Prince Taruhito, however the engagement was cancelled due to the union of the Imperial Court and the Shogunate promoted by Tomomi IWAKURA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1851 she was engaged to the eldest son of the Arisugawanomiya Imperial Prince Takahito, Prince Taruhito, however the engagement was cancelled due to the union of the Imperial Court and the Shogunate promoted by Tomomi IWAKURA.</e>
<cmt>Takahito補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="30">
<j>文久元年10月20日（1861年9月26日）、徳川家茂との婚儀の為に京都を出発。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She departed from Kyoto for the marriage with Iemochi TOKUGAWA. (September 26th, 1861)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She departed from Kyoto for the marriage with Iemochi TOKUGAWA. (September 26th, 1861)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She departed from Kyoto for the marriage with Iemochi TOKUGAWA (September 26, 1861).</e>
<cmt>日付表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>攘夷派の妨害工作を避けるため、東海道ではなく中山道を経由して東下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She went down to the east through the Nakasendo instead of the Tokaido to avoid the disturbance by the exclusionists.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She went down to the east through the Nakasendo instead of the Tokaido to avoid disturbance created by the exclusionists.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She went down to the east through the Nakasendo road instead of the Tokaido road to avoid disturbance created by the exclusionists.</e>
<cmt>road補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="32">
<j>文久2年2月11日（1862年3月12日）、江戸に着き皇室から降嫁、家茂と婚儀を江戸城で挙行。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She arrived at Edo in March 12th, 1862 and decided to leave the Imperial family for the marriage, she had the ceremony at Edo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She arrived at Edo in March 12th, 1862 and decided to leave the Imperial family to be married, she had the ceremony at Edo Castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She arrived at Edo in March 12, 1862 and decided to leave the Imperial family to be married, she had the ceremony to marry Iemochi at Edo Castle.</e>
<cmt>日付表記to marry Iemochi補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>和宮が家茂に降嫁することで公武合体が完成し、和宮は大奥にて御年寄の瀧山、本寿院（徳川家定生母）と天璋院とともに過ごすこととなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Kazunomiya married with Iemochi, the union of the Imperial Court and the Shogunate was completed, she started her new life living with Otoshiyori, Takiyama and Honjuin (Iesada TOKUGAWA) in Ooku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Kazunomiya married with Iemochi, the union of the Imperial Court and the Shogunate was completed, she started her new life living with Otoshiyori, Takiyama, and Honjuin (Iesada TOKUGAWA) in Ooku.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Kazunomiya married with Iemochi, the union of the Imperial Court and the Shogunate was completed, she started her new life living with Otoshiyori, Takiyama, Honjuin (Iesada TOKUGAWA&apos;s mother) and Tenshoin in Ooku.</e>
<cmt>Tenshoin補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>和宮及びそのお付き女中は宮中風の生活習慣を守り（一例を挙げると天皇の許しがないため冬期でも足袋をはかず裸足であった）、一方、大奥になじまない和宮一行を大奥側も不遇な待遇をしていじめるなどし、当初は険悪な空気であったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazunomiya and her maids kept the same custom as Imperial style, (for example they spent winter time with bear foot without wearing socks since the Emperor did not allow them to do so), on the other hand, people in Ooku gave the hard time to Kazunomiya and her maids as they did not get used to the new life in Ooku, it is said there was a bad atmosphere inside the Ooku in those days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazunomiya and her maids kept the same customs like the Imperial style, (for example they spent winter time bear foot without wearing socks since the Emperor did not allow them to do so), on the other hand, people in Ooku gave the hard time to Kazunomiya and her maids as they did not get used to the new life in Ooku, it is said there was a bad atmosphere inside the Ooku in those days.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazunomiya and her maids kept the same customs like the Imperial style, (for example they spent winter time bear foot without wearing socks since the Emperor did not allow them to do so), on the other hand, people in Ooku gave the hard time to Kazunomiya and her maids as they did not get used to the new life in Ooku, it is said there was a bad atmosphere inside the Ooku in those days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>しかし人格に秀で、他者への気遣いが巧かった家茂の機転で和宮-大奥側は後に和解。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However Iemochi, who was smart and considerable to others, helped to solve the conflict with Ooku side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However Iemochi, who was smart and considerate to others, helped to solve the conflict with the Ooku side.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However Iemochi, who was smart and considerate to others, helped to solve the conflict with the Ooku side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="36">
<j>慶応2年7月20日（1866年8月29日）、夫家茂が大坂城にて死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 29th, 1866, Iemochi died in the Osaka Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 29th, 1866, Iemochi died in the Osaka Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 29, 1866, Iemochi died in the Osaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>日付表記-jo補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>落飾し、以後「静寛院宮」となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazunomiya shaved her hair and became &apos;Seikanin no Miya&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazunomiya shaved her head and became &apos;Seikanin no Miya&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar, terminology</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazunomiya shaved her head and became &apos;Seikanin no Miya.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>戊辰戦争の際、甥に当たる明治天皇に手紙を書き、将軍徳川慶喜の助命を嘆願した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the Boshin War, she wrote to her nephew, Emperor Meiji to ask to spare the Shogun, Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA&apos;s life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Boshin War, she wrote to her nephew, Emperor Meiji asking to spare the Shogun, Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA&apos;s life.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Boshin War, she wrote to her nephew, Emperor Meiji asking to spare the Shogun, Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA&apos;s life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="39">
<j>慶応4年（1868年）4月、江戸幕府は官軍に江戸城と大奥を明渡すことになり実成院とともに田安家屋敷へと移った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1868, since the Edo bakufu (Japanese Feudal government headed by a shogun) vacated the Edo Castle and Ooku to the government army, Kazunomiya moved to the Tayasu family residence with Jitsujoin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1868, since the Edo bakufu (Japanese Feudal government headed by a shogun) surrendered Edo Castle and Ooku to the government army, Kazunomiya moved to the Tayasu family residence with Jitsujoin.</e>
<cmt>&quot;vacated&quot; changed to &quot;surrendered&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1868, since the Edo bakufu (Japanese Feudal government headed by a shogun) surrendered Edo Castle and Ooku to the government army, Kazunomiya moved to the Tayasu family residence with Jitsujoin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>のち京都に戻るが、明治天皇の東京行幸のために居を東京へ移す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that she moved to Kyoto, however she moved back to Tokyo due to Emperor Meiji&apos;s visit to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that she moved to Kyoto, however she moved back to Tokyo due to Emperor Meiji&apos;s visit to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that she moved to Kyoto, however she moved back to Tokyo due to Emperor Meiji&apos;s visit to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>勝海舟の家で、天璋院と食事をし仲良くなったといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said she became close to Tenshoin after having meal together at Kaishu KATAU&apos;s house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said she became close to Tenshoin after having a meal together at Kaishu KATAU&apos;s house.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said she became close to Tenshoin after having a meal together at Kaishu KATSU&apos;s house.</e>
<cmt>人名スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="42">
<j>明治10年（1877年）9月2日に療養先の箱根塔ノ沢環翠楼にて死去、享年32。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 2nd, 1877, she died in Kansuiro, Tonosawa, Hakone where she stayed to rest up, she was thirty two years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 2nd, 1877, she died in Kansuiro, Tonosawa, Hakone where she stayed to rest up, she was thirty two years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 2, 1877, she died in Kansuiro, Tonosawa, Hakone where she stayed to rest up, she was thirty two years old.</e>
<cmt>日付表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>脚気衝心（脚気による心不全）が死因とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said the cause of her death was heart failure from beriberi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said the cause of her death was heart failure from beriberi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said the cause of her death was heart failure from beriberi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="44">
<j>墓所は東京都港区の増上寺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her cemetery was in Zojoji Temple in Minato Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her cemetery was in Zojoji Temple in Minato Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her cemetery was in Zojo-ji Temple in Minato Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>体格その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her height and weight</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her height and weight</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her height and weight</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="45">
<j>和宮が埋葬された増上寺の徳川家墓所は現在の東京プリンスホテルの場所にあったが、1950年代に同地がコクドに売却されたため、和宮をはじめ、歴代将軍及びその正側室の墓所と遺骸も発掘・改葬された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tokugawa family&apos;s cemetery where Kazunomiya was buried was located where the current Tokyo Prince Hotel was, Since this land was sold to Kokudo Corp in 1950, Kazunomiya&apos;s cemetery and the successive Shogun and their wives cemeteries and remains were excavated and re-buried.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tokugawa family&apos;s cemetery where Kazunomiya was buried was located where the current Tokyo Prince Hotel was, Since this land was sold to Kokudo Corp in 1950, Kazunomiya&apos;s cemetery and the successive Shogun and their wives cemeteries and remains were excavated, relocated, and re-buried.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tokugawa family&apos;s cemetery where Kazunomiya was buried was located where the current Tokyo Prince Hotel was, since this land was sold to Kokudo Corp in 1950, Kazunomiya&apos;s cemetery and the successive Shogun and their wives cemeteries and remains were excavated, relocated, and re-buried.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>その際の調査結果をまとめた『増上寺徳川将軍家墓とその遺品・遺体』によると、和宮は身長143cm、体重34kg（いずれも推定）であり、骨格の形状から極端な反っ歯と内股が特徴の小柄な女性であったと推定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the result of the investigation at that time called, &apos;The Zojoji Temple, Tokugawa Shogun cemetery and remains, bodies&apos;, Kazunomiya was presumed to be short lady with one meter forty three centimeter tall, the weight was thirty four kilogram, she was also presumed due to her shape of the framework, she had extreme buckteeth and tend to walk pigeon-toed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the result of the investigation at that time called, &apos;The Zojoji Temple, Tokugawa Shogun cemetery and remains, bodies&apos;, Kazunomiya was presumed to be short lady, one meter forty three centimeters tall, her weight was thirty four kilograms, she had extremely buckteeth and tended to walk pigeon-toed.</e>
<cmt>&quot;she was also presumed due to her shape of the framework,&quot; removed as it has no meaning</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the result of the investigation at that time called, &apos;The Zojo-ji Temple, Tokugawa Shogun cemetery and remains, bodies,&apos; Kazunomiya was presumed to be short lady, one meter forty three centimeters tall, her weight was thirty four kilograms, she had extremely buckteeth and tended to walk pigeon-toed.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>また、不思議な事に左手の手首から先の骨がいくら探しても見つからず、増上寺にある和宮の銅像も左手は不自然に隠れている事から、彼女が生前、何らかの理由で左手を欠損していたのではないかという説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a mysterious thing that there was no bone of left hand could be found, also there was a statue of Kazunomiya and her left hand is hidden in unnatural way, there is a legend that she lost her left hand for some reason when he was alive.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a mystery in that there was no bones from the left hand found, also there was a statue of Kazunomiya and her left hand is hidden in an unnatural way, there is a legend that she lost her left hand for some reason, when he was alive.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a mystery in that there was no bones from the left hand found, also there was a statue of Kazunomiya and her left hand is hidden in an unnatural way, there is a legend that she lost her left hand for some reason, when she was alive.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="48">
<j>古墳はともかく、陵墓や陵墓参考地の大半が宮内庁の方針により事実上の学術発掘調査不可となっている現在、和宮は墓所が発掘調査された数少ない皇族である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazunomiya is one of the rare Imperial family whose cemetery was excavated for investigation, since currently most of the Imperial mausoleum or the Imperial mausoleum for reference are actually not allowed to be excavated for investigation, as well as an ancient tomb, under the policy of the Imperial Household Agency.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazunomiya is one of the rare Imperial family members whose cemetery was excavated for investigation, since currently most Imperial mausoleum studied for reference are actually not allowed to be excavated for investigation purposes, ancient tombs also fall under the policy of the Imperial Household Agency.</e>
<cmt>grammar, revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazunomiya is one of the rare Imperial family members whose cemetery was excavated for investigation, since currently most Imperial mausoleum studied for reference are in fact not allowed to be excavated for investigation purposes, ancient tombs also fall under the policy of the Imperial Household Agency.</e>
<cmt>スペース&quot;actually&quot;→&quot;in fact&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="49">
<j>また、和宮の棺からは直垂姿をした若い男性の写真乾板が副葬品として見つかったが、その後の保存処理が悪かったため翌日には乾板はただのガラス板になっていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also there was a young man&apos;s dry picture plate found inside the Kazunomiya&apos;s coffin, but the plate was not kept property, it became just a glass plate on the following day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also there was a young man&apos;s dry picture plate found inside the Kazunomiya&apos;s coffin, but the plate was not kept property, it became just a glass plate on the following day.</e>
<cmt>not sure what a &quot;picture plate&quot; is?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also there was a young man&apos;s dry picture plate found inside the Kazunomiya&apos;s coffin, but the plate was not kept property, it became just a glass plate on the following day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>この男性の正体は未だに不明であるが、夫の家茂である可能性が強い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The man was not identified so far, there is a possibility that he was Kazunomiya&apos;s husband, Iemochi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The man has not been identified so far, there is a possibility that he was Kazunomiya&apos;s husband, Iemochi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The man has not been identified so far, there is a possibility that he was Kazunomiya&apos;s husband, Iemochi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>あるいは婚約者だった有栖川宮熾仁親王ではないかとの指摘もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Or there is another theory the man could be Kazunomiya&apos;s fiancee, Arisugawanomiya Imperial Prince Taruhito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Or there is another theory the man could be Kazunomiya&apos;s fiancee, Arisugawanomiya Imperial Prince Taruhito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Or there is another theory the man could be Kazunomiya&apos;s fiancee, Arisugawanomiya Imperial Prince Taruhito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="52">
<j>近年和宮が降嫁に際し中山道を通って江戸へ向う途中、信州小坂家で休息した折、小坂家の写真師が撮影した和宮の写真が発見された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent years when Kazunomiya married to Iemochi, on her way to Edo through Nakasendo, she took some rest at the Kosaka family in Shinshu, there was Kazunomiya&apos;s photograph found which was taken by a photographer of Kosaka family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Kazunomiya married to Iemochi, on her way to Edo through Nakasendo, she took a rest with the Kosaka family in Shinshu, Kazunomiya&apos;s photograph was found which was taken by a photographer of Kosaka family.</e>
<cmt>revised, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Kazunomiya married to Iemochi, on her way to Edo through Nakasendo road, she took a rest with the Kosaka family in Shinshu, Kazunomiya&apos;s photograph was found which was taken by a photographer of Kosaka family.</e>
<cmt>road補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>これはポジのガラス乾板で軍扇に収められており、複写したものを小坂家末裔の小坂憲次氏より、阿弥陀寺に寄進されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the photographic positive in the glass dry plate kept in the military style fan, the copy of the photograph was given to Amida-ji Temple by Kenji KOSAKA who is the descendant of Kosaka family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the photographic positive in on a dry glass plate kept in the military style fan, a copy of the photograph was given to Amida-ji Temple by Kenji KOSAKA who is a descendant of the Kosaka family.</e>
<cmt>revised, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was the photographic positive in on a dry glass plate kept in the military style fan, a copy of the photograph was given to Amida-ji Temple by Kenji KOSAKA who is a descendant of the Kosaka family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>この写真の和宮からは、袿の袖から僅かに両手の先を出している姿が確認できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazumimiya put her both hands slightly out of the sleeves in this photograph.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazumimiya posed with both her hands slightly out of her sleeves in this photograph.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazumomiya posed with both her hands slightly out of her sleeves in this photograph.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="55">
<j>異説（替え玉説）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The different theory (someone was acting as the double of Kazunomiya)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The different theory (someone was acting as the double in place of Kazunomiya)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The different theory (someone was acting as the double in place of Kazunomiya)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>在京の頃の歌風と比べ、東下後の歌風は、「雅」がまるで感じられず、まるで別人に取って代わったと言ってもいいような変化（それも、素人あるいは、一般庶民のような野臭い歌風に急変したとする）であるため、それをもって、替え玉であると言うことを唱える人もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some people said some of Kazunomiya&apos;s poems after she moved to Edo, compared with the ones while she was in Kyoto, were not elegant at all, it was almost someone else made the poem for her (it is said the poems were not even professionally made, her style changed into unprofessional, dull style all the sudden, there was a theory that someone was acting as the double of Kazunomiya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some people said some of Kazunomiya&apos;s poems after she moved to Edo, compared with the ones she wrote while she was in Kyoto, were not elegant at all, it was almost like someone else wrote the poems for her (it is said the poems were not even professionally written, her style changed into an unprofessional, dull style all of a sudden, there was a theory that someone was acting as a double in place of Kazunomiya.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people said some of Kazunomiya&apos;s poems after she moved to Edo, compared with the ones she wrote while she was in Kyoto, were not elegant at all, it was almost like someone else wrote the poems for her (it is said the poems were not even professionally written, her style changed into an unprofessional, dull style all of a sudden), there was a theory that someone was acting as a double in place of Kazunomiya.</e>
<cmt>)補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="57">
<j>その他、有吉佐和子などが、替え玉説をモチーフに小説『和宮様御留』を書いている（上記の説とはまた違った説を用いている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also Sawako ARIYOSHI wrote a novel, &quot;Kazunomiya-sama Otome&quot; with story of someone was acting as the double of Kazunomiya. (There was a totally different theory as above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also Sawako ARIYOSHI wrote a novel, &quot;Kazunomiya-sama Otome&quot; with a story about someone who was acting as a double for Kazunomiya. (There was a totally different theory compared with the above).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also Sawako ARIYOSHI wrote a novel, &quot;Kazunomiya-sama Otome&quot; with a story about someone who was acting as a double for Kazunomiya. (A totally different theory compared with the above was used in the novel.)</e>
<cmt>原文に合うように（）内を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="58">
<j>しかし、遺骨などの調査から当時の皇族女性独特の体躯であったことが判明、替え玉説は後世の流布である可能性が極めて高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However it was found out that Kazunomiya had typical body built of Imperial female members in those days due to the investigation of the bones, thus there is a strong possibility it was just a rumor that someone was acting as the double of Kazunomiya in later years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However it was discovered that Kazunomiya had a body build typical of Imperial female members in those days, due to the investigation of the bones, thus there is a strong possibility it was just a rumor that someone was acting as her double.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However it was discovered that Kazunomiya had a body build typical of Imperial female members in those days, due to the investigation of the bones, thus there is a strong possibility it was just a rumor that someone was acting as her double.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tommy6-bot(id:171289), Nnh(id:474), 瑞雲(id:27410), Charenji(id:7908), Cprobot(id:97843), Kunipoo(id:35872), Lupinoid(id:68), Nakaoka7675(id:39645), 佐々木承禎(id:50838), でここ(id:9565), Shelling ford 221b(id:35237), Shelling ford(id:35136), 代言人(id:33675), Mazbot(id:181195), こぶまき(id:38278), Number4(id:205983), Maakun(id:16735), Caminante(id:39410), DCyokohama(id:26779), M-sho-gun(id:88956), Izayohi(id:13095), Umebo(id:82785), Sakura-no-kuni(id:115977), BlackPonix(id:20108), Woyzzeck(id:8923), Aphaia(id:3132), Sh(id:2707), Sorrysorry(id:102591), JunK(id:14563), MDR-SK(id:192066), 香川産(id:207337), ゐ(id:795), 上田隼人(id:23104), Huzzlet the bot(id:85960), じんさん(id:106784), Jade0416(id:104181), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>