<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>惟明親王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Koreaki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Koreaki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Koreaki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>惟明親王（これあきしんのう、治承3年（1179年） - 承久3年5月3日 (旧暦)（1221年5月25日））は、高倉天皇の第三皇子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Koreaki (1170-May 25, 1221) was the third prince of Emperor Takakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Koreaki (1170 to May 25, 1221) was the third prince of Emperor Takakura.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Koreaki (1179 - May 25, 1221) was the third prince of Emperor Takakura.</e>
<cmt>FBにはありませんが、年号の間違い</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>安徳天皇・後高倉院は異母兄、後鳥羽天皇は異母弟にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Antoku and Gotakakura-in are elder brothers with different mothers, and Emperor Gotoba was younger brother with a different mother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Antoku and Gotakakura-in were elder brothers with different mothers, and Emperor Gotoba was a younger brother with a different mother.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Antoku and Gotakakurain were his older paternal half-brothers, and Emperor Gotoba was his younger paternal half-brother.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。用語統一リスト１７２により、「異母兄」「異母弟」の訳語を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は平義範の娘範子（少将局）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was Hanshi, the daughter of Taira no Yoshinori (shosho no tsubone; the office of minor captain).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was Hanshi, the daughter of Taira no Yoshinori (shosho no tsubone; the office of minor captain).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was Hanshi (also known as Shosho no Tsubone), a daughter of TAIRA no Yoshinori.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>異称は大炊御門宮（おおいみかどのみや）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had a different name of Oimikado no Miya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had another different name of Oimikado no Miya.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also called Oimikado no Miya.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>安徳天皇が平家に連れられて西国に落ちた後、皇位継承の有力者であったが母親の身分が低く、かつ外祖父が死亡していた事、弟の尊成親王（後の後鳥羽天皇）の方が祖父の後白河法皇に可愛がられていた事から、皇位は尊成親王が継ぐ事になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The imperial throne was succeeded by Imperial Prince Takahira; Imperial Prince Koreaki&apos;s mother who was strongly regarded to ascend to the throne after Emperor Antoku was transported to Saigoku (western part of Japan; esp. Kyushu, but ranging as far east as Kinki) with the Taira family was low in her rank; His grandfather on his mother&apos;s side was dead; his younger brother, Imperial Prince Takahira (future Emperor Gotoba) was favored by his grand father, Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa more.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The imperial throne was succeeded by Imperial Prince Takahira; Imperial Prince Koreaki&apos;s mother who was strongly regarded to ascend to the throne after Emperor Antoku was transported to Saigoku (western part of Japan; esp. Kyushu, but ranging as far east as Kinki) with the Taira family was low in her rank; His grandfather on his mother&apos;s side was dead; his younger brother, Imperial Prince Takahira (future Emperor Gotoba) was favored more by his grand father, Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Emperor Antoku was taken away to the western area of Japan by the Taira family, Imperial Prince Koreaki became one of the strong candidates for the next emperor, but his younger brother Imperial Prince Takahira (later Emperor Gotoba) eventually succeeded to the throne because Koreaki&apos;s mother was not nobly born and his maternal grandfather was already dead, and moreover, their grandfather Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa liked Imperial Prince Takahira better.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>11歳で親王宣下を受け、4年後に元服して三品親王となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was announced as the Imperial Prince at the age of 11, and went through Genpuku ceremony and became an Imperial Prince with the third court rank after 4 years.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was announced as the Imperial Prince at the age of 11, and went through the Genpuku ceremony and became an Imperial Prince with the third court rank after just 4 years.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was officially announced as Imperial Prince at the age of 11 by the Emperor, and four years later, he had a ceremony of attaining manhood and became Sanbon Shinno (the third-ranked Imperial Prince).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>不遇を儚んで33歳で出家して以後は聖円入道親王と名乗った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He despaired of his unfortunate life and became a priest at the age of 33, and named himself as Imperial Prince and Monk Shoen after that.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。聖円の読み方が不明なのですが暫定的にImperial and Monk Shoen と訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He despaired of his unfortunate life and became a priest at the age of 33, and named himself as Imperial Prince and Monk Shoen after that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was disappointed at his unfortunate life and became a Buddhist priest at the age of 33, and then he announced himself as Priestly Imperial Prince Shoen.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>和歌に優れており、式子内親王や藤原定家などの当代随一の歌人とも親交が深かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was excellent at Waka, and had a close relationship with the best poets in the generation; Imperial Princess Shikishi or FUJIWARA no Sadaie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was excellent at Waka, and had a close relationship with the best poets in the generation; Imperial Princess Shikishi or FUJIWARA no Sadaie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was excellent at making waka (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables), and he also had friendly relations with the greatest poets of those days such as Imperial Princess Shikishi and FUJIWARA no Sadaie.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>新古今和歌集などの勅撰和歌集にも歌が収められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His works of Waka were contained in Shin Chokusen Wakashu (New Imperial Collection) including Shinkokin Wakashu (New Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His works of Waka were contained in the Shin Chokusen Wakashu (New Imperial Collection) including the Shinkokin Wakashu (New Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His works of waka were contained in anthlogies of Japanese poetry compiled by Imperial command such as the Shinkokin Wakashu (the New Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), 代言人(id:33675), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>