<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>即位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sokui (Enthronement)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sokui (Enthronement)</e>
<cmt>スペースを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sokui (Enthronement)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>即位（そくい）とは、亡くなったり、譲位した君主（皇帝、国王など）の跡を継いで、その君主位に就くことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enthronement means an imperial heir&apos;s acceding to the throne, succeeding a monarch (emperor or king) who passed away or abdicated the throne</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The enthronement means an ascension to the throne, succeeding a monarch (emperor or king) who passed away or abdicated the throne.</e>
<cmt>the, ピリオドを補いました。imperial heir&apos;s acceding→ascension と修正しました。 （ここでは跡継ぎのことには触れていないため）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The enthronement means an ascension to the throne, succeeding a monarch (emperor or king) who passed away or abdicated the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>君主の第一子や弟が皇太子（王太子）や皇太弟（王太弟）に就任し、先代君主が亡くなった後に継ぐことが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is common that the first child or a younger brother of the monarch first become a crown prince (dauphin) or kotaitei (an emperor&apos;s younger brother considered heir apparent) and succeed to the throne after the death of his predecessor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is common that the first child or a younger brother of the monarch first becomes a crown prince (dauphin) or kotaitei (an emperor&apos;s younger brother considered heir apparent), then succeeds to the throne after the death of the predecessor.</e>
<cmt>become→becomes,succeed→succeeds, his→the,and→then と修正しました。カンマを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is common that the first child or a younger brother of the monarch first becomes a crown prince (dauphin) or kotaitei (an emperor&apos;s younger brother considered heir apparent), then succeeds to the throne after the death of the predecessor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>即位に際して儀式を執り行うことも多く、戴冠式（即位式）と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An enthronement is often celebrated with a ceremony called a coronation or an enthronement ceremony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An enthronement is often celebrated with a ceremony called a coronation or an enthronement ceremony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An enthronement is often celebrated with a ceremony called a coronation or an enthronement ceremony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>一般的に即位時期に合わせて行われるが、国内の政情不安などを理由に数年後に実施されることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A coronation usually takes place at the time of enthronement, but there are exceptional cases where the ceremony is postponed till several years later due to reasons such as domestic political instability.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A coronation usually takes place at the time of an enthronement, but there are exceptional cases such as the ceremony is postponed until several years later due to the reason of the domestic political instability.</e>
<cmt>an, the を補いました。where→such as, till→until,reasons such as→reason of と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A coronation usually takes place at the time of an enthronement, but there are exceptional cases such as the ceremony is postponed until several years later due to the reason of the domestic political instability.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>日本における即位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The enthronement in Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The enthronement in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The enthronement in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>日本では即位とは天皇がその位につくことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan enthronement means that an emperor accedes to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, the enthronement means that an emperor accedes to the throne.</e>
<cmt>the, カンマを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, the enthronement means that an emperor accedes to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>基本的には即位の礼を行い、天下に自分が天皇の位を継いだことを示すことで、昔は践祚との区別はなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It basically refers to the act of the new emperor demonstrating he has succeeded ex-emperor by holding the Sokui no rei (ceremony of the enthronement) and there was no distinction between sokui and senso (accession to the throne) in the past.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It basically refers to the act of the new emperor or empress demonstrating that he or she has succeeded the predecessor by holding the Sokui no rei (ceremony of the enthronement), and there was no distinction between sokui and senso (accession to the throne) in the past.</e>
<cmt>the, that, カンマ を補いました。empress, she を補いました。（女性天皇の場合もあり）ex-emperor→predecessor と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It basically refers to the act of the new emperor or empress demonstrating that he or she has succeeded the predecessor by holding the Sokui no rei (ceremony of the enthronement), and there was no distinction between sokui and senso (accession to the throne) in the past.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし、桓武天皇以後、三種の神器を先帝から受け継ぐことを践祚、皇位についたことを天下に布告することを即位というようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the enthronement of Emperor Kanmu, however, a separation between sokui and senso was created, with senso meaning the succession of Sanshu-no-jingi (Three Imperial Regalia) from the ex-emperor and sokui meaning the new emperor declaring to the people that he has acceded to the throne.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the enthronement of the Emperor Kanmu, however, a separation between sokui and senso was created, with senso meaning the succession of Sanshu-no-jingi (Three Imperial Regalia) from the ex-emperor and sokui meaning the new emperor declaring to the people that he has acceded to the throne.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the enthronement of the Emperor Kanmu, however, a separation between sokui and senso was created, with senso meaning the succession of Sanshu-no-jingi (Three Imperial Regalia) from the ex-emperor and sokui meaning the new emperor declaring to the people that he has acceded to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>ただ、皇室典範で践祚と即位が統合されたことから現在ではこの二つを一概に即位として扱い、区別しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the two concepts, senso and sokui, are treated as one in the Imperial House Law and considered as sokui as a whole, no distinction between the two is made today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the two concepts, senso and sokui, are integrated into one in the Imperial House Law and considered as sokui as a whole, no distinction between the two is made today.</e>
<cmt>treated as→ integrated into と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the two concepts, senso and sokui, are integrated into one in the Imperial House Law and considered as sokui as a whole, no distinction between the two is made today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 かぼ(id:79147), 曼珠沙華(id:26417), 伏儀(id:142093), YukkeBot2(id:251491), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>