<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>山階宮晃親王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Yamashinanomiya Akira</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Yamashinanomiya Akira</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Yamashinanomiya Akira</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>山階宮晃親王（やましなのみやあきらしんのう 文化 (元号)13年9月2日 (旧暦)（1816年10月22日） - 明治31年（1898年）2月17日）は、日本の皇族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Yamashinanomiya Akira (October 22, 1816 - February 17, 1898) was a member of the Imperial Family of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Yamashinanomiya Akira (October 22, 1816 - February 17, 1898) was a member of the Imperial Family in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Yamashinanomiya Akira (October 22, 1816 - February 17, 1898) was a member of the Imperial family in Japan.</e>
<cmt>familyに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>伏見宮邦家親王第一王子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the first Prince of Imperial Prince Fushiminomiya Kuniie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the first Prince of Imperial Prince Fushiminomiya Kuniie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the first Prince of Imperial Prince Fushiminomiya Kuniie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>北白川宮能久親王、華頂宮博経親王、小松宮彰仁親王、閑院宮載仁親王、東伏見宮依仁親王の兄。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An elder brother of Imperial Prince Kitashirakawanomiya Yoshihisa, Imperial Prince Kachonomiya Hirotsune, Imperial Prince Komatsunomiya Akihito, Imperial Prince Kaninnomiya Kotohito, and Imperial Prince Higashifushiminomiya Yorihito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An elder brother of Imperial Prince Kitashirakawanomiya Yoshihisa, Imperial Prince Kachonomiya Hirotsune, Imperial Prince Komatsunomiya Akihito, Imperial Prince Kaninnomiya Kotohito, and Imperial Prince Higashifushiminomiya Yorihito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An elder brother of Imperial Prince Kitashirakawanomiya Yoshihisa, Imperial Prince Kachonomiya Hirotsune, Imperial Prince Komatsunomiya Akihito, Imperial Prince Kaninnomiya Kotohito, and Imperial Prince Higashifushiminomiya Yorihito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>勧修寺宮済範親王。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Kajujinomiya Saihan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Kajujinomiya Saihan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Kajujinomiya Saihan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>二品。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nihon (the second court rank for Imperial Princes).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nihon (the second court rank for an Imperial Princes).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nihon (the second court rank for an Imperial Princes).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>親王は文化13年（1816年）に誕生、初名は清保（きよやす）といった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial Prince was born in 1816, first named &quot;Kiyoyasu.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Prince was born in 1816, first named &quot;Kiyoyasu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Prince was born in 1816, first named &quot;Kiyoyasu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>翌年の文化14年（1817年）、京都山科の門跡寺院・勧修寺を相続した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He inherited Kaju-ji Temple, a monzeki temple (a temple of high rank where members of imperial family and nobility enter the priesthood) in Yamashina, Kyoto in the following year 1817.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He inherited Kaju-ji Temple, a monzeki temple (a temple of high rank where members of the imperial family and nobility entered the priesthood) in Yamashina, Kyoto in the following year 1817.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He inherited Kaju-ji Temple, a monzeki temple (a temple of high rank where members of the imperial family and nobility entered the priesthood) in Yamashina, Kyoto in the following year 1817.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>文政7年（1824年）に出家し、済範（さいはん）入道親王と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1824, he became a priest to be called &quot;Priestly Imperial Prince Saihan.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1824, he became a priest and was called &quot;Priestly Imperial Prince Saihan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1824, he became a priest and was called &quot;Priestly Imperial Prince Saihan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>天保12年（1841年）10月8日妹の隆子女王と共に出奔するという不祥事を起こし、結果天保13年（1842年）7月22日に光格天皇養子・二品親王・勧修寺住職の地位が停止され、伏見宮より除籍されてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He caused a scandalous affair in which he ran away with his younger sister, Princess Takako, on October 8, 1841, resulting in termination of his positions of an adopted son of Emperor Kokaku, a second-ranked Imperial Prince, and a chief priest of Kaju-ji Temple on July 22, 1842, to be finally expelled from the Fushiminomiya family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He caused a scandalous affair in which he ran away with his younger sister, Princess Takako, on October 8, 1841, resulting in termination of his position as an adopted son of Emperor Kokaku, a second-ranked Imperial Prince, and a chief priest of Kaju-ji Temple on July 22, 1842, to be was finally expelled from the Fushiminomiya family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He caused a scandalous affair in which he ran away with his younger sister, Princess Takako, on November 20, 1841, resulting in termination of his position as an adopted son of Emperor Kokaku, a second-ranked Imperial Prince, and a chief priest of Kaju-ji Temple on August 27, 1842, to be was finally expelled from the Fushiminomiya family.</e>
<cmt>旧暦を新暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>元治元年（1864年）徳川慶喜らが還俗を孝明天皇に願い、同年(元号は文久)正月9日伏見宮に復し同18日勅許をもって復飾し改めて親王宣下と共に、山階宮の宮号を賜った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA, et al. asked for his return to secular life to Emperor Komei in 1864, he returned Fushiminomiya on January 9 in the same year, returned to the secular life under an imperial sanction on the eighteenth of the same month, and again received the reigning name of Yamashinanomiya along with the title of Imperial Prince by Imperial order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA, et al. asked for his return to secular life to Emperor Komei in 1864, he returned Fushiminomiya on January 9 in the same year, returned to the secular life under an imperial sanction on the eighteenth of the same month, and again received the reigning name of Yamashinanomiya along with the title of Imperial Prince by Imperial order.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA, et al. asked for his return to secular life to Emperor Komei in 1864, he returned Fushiminomiya on February 16 in the same year, returned to the secular life under an imperial sanction on 25 of the same month, and again received the reigning name of Yamashinanomiya along with the title of Imperial Prince by Imperial order.</e>
<cmt>旧暦を新暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その後は国事御用掛として幕末の政界で活躍し、明治維新後は、議定・外国事務総督などの要職を占めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he flourished as a Kokuji goyogakari (a general official of the Imperial Household in charge of the State affair) in the political world in the end of Edo Period, and occupied important positions such as a gijo (official post) and a ministerial governor of foreign affairs after the Meiji restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he flourished as a Kokuji goyogakari (a general official of the Imperial Household in charge of State affairs) in the political world at the end of the Edo Period, and occupied important positions such as a gijo (official post) and a ministerial governor of foreign affairs after the Meiji restoration.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he flourished as a Kokuji goyogakari (a general official of the Imperial Household in charge of State affairs) in the political world at the end of the Edo Period, and occupied important positions such as a gijo (official post) and a ministerial governor of foreign affairs after the Meiji restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>皇族がヨーロッパの王室に倣って軍人になる中、親王は固辞し文官であることを通した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While other members of the Imperial family became military men in accordance with customary practice of royal families in Europe, the Imperial Prince refused it and remained a civil officer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While other members of the Imperial family became military men in accordance with customary practice of royal families in Europe, the Imperial Prince refused and remained a civil officer.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While other members of the Imperial family became military men in accordance with customary practice of royal families in Europe, the Imperial Prince refused and remained a civil officer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>明治31年（1898年）2月、83歳で薨去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He passed away in February 1898 at the age of 83.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He passed away in February 1898 at the age of 83.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He passed away in February 1898 at the age of 83.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>1886年に大勲位菊花大綬章を受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He received Grand Cordon of the Supreme Order of the Chrysanthemum in 1886.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He received the Grand Cordon of the Supreme Order of the Chrysanthemum in 1886.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He received the Grand Cordon of the Supreme Order of the Chrysanthemum in 1886.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>親王には王子に山階宮菊麿王がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had a prince called Prince Yamashinanomiya Kikumaro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had a prince called Prince Yamashinanomiya Kikumaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had a prince called Prince Yamashinanomiya Kikumaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>菊麿王は親王の後を継ぎ山階宮第2代となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Kikumaro took over the Imperial Prince to become the second generation of Yamashinanomiya family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Kikumaro took over as Imperial Prince to become the second generation Yamashinanomiya family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Kikumaro took over as Imperial Prince to become the second generation Yamashinanomiya family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Fryed-peach(id:63402), 123456(id:67803), 経済準学士(id:22656), 代言人(id:33675), R28Bot(id:177951), 海行かば(id:115823), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), Panpulha(id:42950), Tiyoringo(id:70026), のりまき(id:53470), 「あなたには関係ない」(id:49400), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>