<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>橘嘉智子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TACHIBANA no Kachiko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TACHIBANA no Kachiko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TACHIBANA no Kachiko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>橘 嘉智子（たちばな の かちこ、延暦5年（786年） - 嘉祥3年5月4日（850年6月17日））は、第52代嵯峨天皇皇后。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TACHIBANA no Kaschiko (786 - June 17th, 850) was the fifty second Empress of Emperor Saga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TACHIBANA no Kaschiko (786 - June 17th, 850) was the fifty second Empress of Emperor Saga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TACHIBANA no Kachiko (786 - June 17, 850) was the Empress of the fifty-second Emperor Saga.</e>
<cmt>fifty-secondの位置移動日付表記人名のスペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>橘奈良麻呂の孫、橘清友の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was TACHIBANA no Naramaro&apos;s grandchild and TACHIBANA no Kiyotomo&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was TACHIBANA no Naramaro&apos;s grandchild and TACHIBANA no Kiyotomo&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was TACHIBANA no Naramaro&apos;s grandchild and TACHIBANA no Kiyotomo&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は贈正一位田口氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her mother was from Taguchi family who held the first court rank of the senior grade.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her mother was from Taguchi family who held the first court rank of the senior grade.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her mother was from Taguchi clan who held Zo Shoichii (Senior First Rank, posthumously conferred).</e>
<cmt>family→clan&quot;the first court rank of the senior grade&quot;→&quot;Zo Shoichii (Senior First Rank, posthumously conferred)&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>別名・檀林皇后（だんりんこうごう）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another name was the Empress Danrin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another name was the Empress Danrin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another name was the Empress Danrin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>右大臣橘氏公は弟（または兄）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her younger brother (or older brother) was the Minister of the Right, TACHIBANA no Ujikimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her younger brother (or older brother) was the Minister of the Right, TACHIBANA no Ujikimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her younger brother (or older brother) was the Udaijin (Minister of the Right), TACHIBANA no Ujikimi.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Minister of the Right&quot; →&quot;Udaijin (Minister of the Right)&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>世に類なき麗人であったといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said she was exceptionally beautiful.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said she was exceptionally beautiful.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said she was exceptionally beautiful.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>もとは嵯峨天皇の数多い夫人の一人に過ぎなかったが、桓武天皇皇女の高津内親王が后を廃された後、姻戚である藤原冬嗣（嘉智子の姉安子は冬嗣夫人藤原美都子の弟藤原三守の妻だった）らの後押しで立后した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Initially she was just one of Emperor SAGA&apos;s Empress but after Imperial Princess Takatsu, Emperor Kanmu&apos;s Princess, deposed from the Empress, her relative in law, FUJIWARA no Fuyutsugu (Kachiko&apos;s older sister, Yasuko was FUJIWARA no Mimori&apos;s wife, who was the younger brother of Fuyutsugu&apos;s wife, FUJIWARA no Mitsuko) supported Kachiko to become Empress.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially she was just one of Emperor SAGA&apos;s Empress but after Imperial Princess Takatsu, Emperor Kanmu&apos;s Princess, deposed from the Empress, her relative in law, FUJIWARA no Fuyutsugu (Kachiko&apos;s older sister, Yasuko was FUJIWARA no Mimori&apos;s wife, who was the younger brother of Fuyutsugu&apos;s wife, FUJIWARA no Mitsuko) supported Kachiko to become Empress.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially she was just one of Emperor SAGA&apos;s Empress but after Imperial Princess Takatsu, Emperor Kanmu&apos;s Princess, deposed from the Empress, her relative in law, FUJIWARA no Fuyutsugu (Kachiko&apos;s older sister, Yasuko was FUJIWARA no Mimori&apos;s wife, who was the younger brother of Fuyutsugu&apos;s wife, FUJIWARA no Mitsuko) supported Kachiko to become Empress.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>橘氏出身としては最初で最後の皇后である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was the first and the last Empress from the Tachibana family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was the first and the last Empress from the Tachibana family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was the first and the last Empress from the Tachibana clan.</e>
<cmt>&quot;family&quot;→&quot;clan&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>嵯峨天皇との間に仁明天皇（正良親王）・正子内親王（淳和天皇皇后）他二男五女をもうけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She gave birth to Emperor Ninmyo (Imperial prince Masara), Imperial Princess Seishi (Masako) and other two boys and five girls as Emperor Saga&apos;s children.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She gave birth to Emperor Ninmyo (Imperial prince Masara), Imperial Princess Seishi (Masako) and another two boys and five girls as Emperor Saga&apos;s children.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She gave birth to Emperor Ninmyo (Imperial prince Masara), Imperial Princess Seishi (Masako) (Emperor Junna&apos;s Empress) and another two boys and five girls as Emperor Saga&apos;s children.</e>
<cmt>(Emperor Junna&apos;s Empress)補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>仏教への信仰が篤く、嵯峨野に日本最初の禅院檀林寺を創建したことから檀林皇后と呼ばれるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She deeply believed in Buddhism, she was called Empress Danrin-ji since she built the first Japanese Zen temple, Danrin-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She deeply believed in Buddhism, she was called Empress Danrin-ji since she built the first Japanese Zen temple, Danrin-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She deeply believed in Buddhism, she was called Empress Danrin since she built the first Japanese Zen temple, Danrin-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>-ji削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>嵯峨天皇譲位後は共に冷然院・嵯峨院に住んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Emperor Saga&apos;s enthronement, she lived in Reizein in, Saga in together with him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Emperor Saga&apos;s enthronement, she lived in Reizein in, Saga in together with him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Emperor Saga&apos;s enthronement, she lived in Reizen in, Saga in together with him.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>嵯峨上皇の崩後も太皇太后として隠然たる勢力を有し、橘氏の子弟のために大学別曹学館院を設立するなど勢威を誇り、仁明天皇の地位を安定させるために承和の変にも深く関わったといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She had absolute power as a grand empress after the retired Emperor Saga died, she wielded her influence and established Daigaku besso Gakkan in (accommodation facility built near the University or college by the influential court nobles for their children in the Heian period) for the Tachibana family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She had absolute power as a grand empress after the retired Emperor Saga died, she wielded her influence and established Daigaku besso Gakkan in (accommodation facility built near the University or college by the influential court nobles for their children in the Heian period) for the Tachibana family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She had absolute power as a grand empress after the Retired Emperor Saga died, she wielded her influence and established Daigaku besso Gakkan in (accommodation facility built near the University or college by the influential court nobles for their children in the Heian period) for the Tachibana clan, and was deeply involved in the Showa Incident to secure the position for Emperor Ninmyo.</e>
<cmt>上皇の表記「仁明天皇の地位を安定させるために承和の変にも深く関わったといわれる」を訳出しました。&quot;family&quot;→&quot;clan&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>そのため、廃太子恒貞親王の実母である娘の正子内親王は嘉智子を深く恨んだと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore it is said her daughter, and the mother of the Deposed Imperial Crown Prince, Prince Tsunesada, Imperial Princess Seishi blamed Kachiko strongly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore it is said that her daughter, and the mother of the Deposed Imperial Crown Prince, Prince Tsunesada, Imperial Princess Seishi blamed Kachiko strongly.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore it is said that her daughter, and the mother of the Deposed Imperial Crown Prince, Prince Tsunesada, Imperial Princess Seishi blamed Kachiko strongly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>鳥や獣の飢を救うため、自分の死後に自らの死骸を埋葬することを禁じて道ばたに放置させ、それが腐乱してウジがわき、白骨化していく過程を絵師に描かせたという伝説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a legend she left a will forbidding to bury her body after her death, the body was left on the street for the birds and animals to eat to prevent them from the starvation, then a painter was ordered to paint the picture how the body was decomposed with maggots and it nearly turned into a skeleton.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a legend that she left a will forbidding the burial of her body after her death, the body was left on the street for the birds and animals to eat to prevent them from starvation, then a painter was ordered to paint the picture of how maggots decomposed the body and nearly turned into a skeleton.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a legend that she left a will forbidding the burial of her body after her death, the body was left on the street for the birds and animals to eat to prevent them from starvation, then a painter was ordered to paint the picture of how maggots decomposed the body and nearly turned into a skeleton.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Lemon pie(id:66842), Masyu(id:31065), 代言人(id:33675), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), 味っ子(id:17086), 平惣衛門(id:99387), Andee(id:20421), 伏儀(id:142093), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>