<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>掌典職</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ceremonial staff</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ceremonial staff</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoten-shoku (Ceremonial staff)</e>
<cmt>ローマ字読みを補足しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>掌典職（しょうてんしょく）は、日本の皇室において宮中祭祀を担当する部門である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ceremonial staff take charge of court rituals of Japanese Imperial Household as a department.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ceremonial staff take charge of court rituals of Japanese Imperial Household organized as a department.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shoten-shoku is a section in charge of Court rituals of the Japanese Imperial Household.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>宮中三殿においてその職務を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their duties are performed in the Three shrines of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their duties are performed in the Three shrines of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their duties are performed in the Three shrines of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>戦前、国家機関であった当時は、宮内省の外局として国家機関の位置付けであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It used to be a government organization before the war, and at that time, its position was the government organization as an external bureau of Imperial Household Ministry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It used to be a government organization before the war, and at that time, its position was an external bureau of the Imperial Household Ministry.</e>
<cmt>wordiness, redundancy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It used to be a government organization before the war, and at that time, its position was an external bureau of the Imperial Household Ministry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>宮内省式部職掌典部</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ceremony department, Board of Ceremonies of Imperial Household Ministry</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ceremony department, Board of Ceremonies of Imperial Household Ministry</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoten-bu (Ceremony Department), Shikibu-shoku (Board of Ceremonies), the Ministry of Imperial Household</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>「宮内省官制」（明治40年皇室令第3号）制定当時は、「典式」として宮内庁式部職の所掌とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When `Imperial Household Ministry Organization&apos; (Article 3 of Koshitsu-rei; the Imperial Families&apos; Act, in 1907) was established, it was under control of Board of Ceremonies of Imperial Household Agency as `tenshiki.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Web で検索にあたりましたが 典礼の語彙が不明でした。そのままローマ字表記しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the `Imperial Household Ministry Organization&apos; (Article 3 of Koshitsu-rei; the Imperial Families&apos; Act, in 1907) was established, it was under the control of The Board of Ceremonies of the Imperial Household Agency as `tenshiki.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the &apos;Kunai-sho Kansei&apos; (Imperial Household Ministry Organization) (Article 3 of Koshitsu-rei; the Imperial Families&apos; Act, in 1907) was established, it was under the control of Shikibu-shoku of Imperial Household Agency as &apos;tenshiki.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「`」→「&apos;」とし、ローマ字読みを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>式部職に掌典部が置かれ、掌典長、掌典次長、掌典、内掌典及び掌典補を置くことが定められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ceremony department was placed under Board of Ceremonies, and the establishment of positions; the Manager, Deputy manager, staff, Junior staff, assistant of Ceremony Department, was set forth.</e>
<cmt>内掌典及び掌典補の訳語が不明ですが暫定的に内掌典→Junior staff, 掌典補→assistant と訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ceremony department was placed under The Board of Ceremonies, and the establishment of positions; the Manager, Deputy manager, staff, Junior staff, assistant of Ceremony Department, were set forth.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shoten-bu was placed under the Shikibu-shoku, and it was decided that this section should consist of a position called shoten-cho (the chief ritualist), a position called shoten-jicho (the vice-chief ritualist), shoten (regular ritualists), nai-shoten (female regular ritualists), and shoten-ho (assistant staff).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>それぞれの職務権限を述べると、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The official authority for each position is:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The official authority for each position is:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The official authority for each position is:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>「掌典長」は親任官又は勅任官とされ、皇室祭祀に奉仕し、掌典部・掌典職の事務を掌理し、所部職員を監督する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">`Ceremony Department Manager&apos; corresponds to an official appointed by the emperor or an imperial appointee, and he/she engages in the services of court rituals, controls administration of ceremony staff and ceremony department, and supervise the staff of Ceremony Department.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">`Ceremony Department Manager&apos; corresponds to an official appointed by the emperor or an imperial appointee, and he/she engages in the services of court rituals, controls administration of ceremony staff and ceremony department, and supervises the staff of Ceremony Department.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;shoten-cho&apos; should be an official personally or directly appointed by the Emperor, and his duties are to serve for Court rituals, to manage tasks of the department and the staff, and to supervise all members in the department.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>「掌典次長」は勅任官とされ、掌典長をたすけ、掌典長に事故があるときはその職務を代理する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">`Ceremony Department Deputy Manager&apos; is an imperial appointee, and he/she supports Ceremony Department Manager; he/she acts for the manager when the manager is not available.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">`Ceremony Department Deputy Manager&apos; is an imperial appointee, and he/she supports Ceremony Department Manager; he/she acts for the manager when the manager is not available.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;shoten-jicho&apos; should be an official directly appointed by the Emperor, and his duties are to support the shoten-cho and to take over his responsibility when he is not available.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>「掌典」は12人を定員とされ、奏任官（名誉職とすることもできた。）とし、祭事を分掌する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of `Staff&apos; is limited to 12, and the duties of the staff are segregated to perform services; he/she is an official who is originally selected as a candidates by the Prime Minister (can be regarded as honorable position).</e>
<cmt>文が半ばで分割されていたため、B20, 21 のセルを結合し一文にしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of `Staff&apos; is limited to 12, and the duties of the staff are segregated to perform services; he/she is an official who is originally selected as a candidates by the Prime Minister (can be regarded as an honorable position).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoten&apos; staff consists of 12 members who are officials appointed with the Emperor&apos;s approval (such officials were called soninkan, and the position of soninkan was sometimes given as an honorary post), and they take partial charge of Court rituals.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="10">
<j>「内掌典」及び「掌典補」は判任官とし、「内掌典」のうち1人は奏任官とできた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">`Junior Staff&apos; or `Assistant&apos; is a Junior official and one of `Junior Staff&apos; can be an official who is originally selected as a candidates by the Prime Minister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">`Junior Staff&apos; or `Assistant&apos; is a Junior official and one of the `Junior Staff&apos; can be an official who is originally selected as a candidate by the Prime Minister.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nai-shoten&apos; and &apos;shoten-ho&apos; are officials at the position called hanninkan (a junior official), and one of nai-shoten members is given a position of soninkan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>ともに祭事に従事する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both of them engage in ceremonies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both engage in ceremonies.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both engage in ceremonies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="12">
<j>なお、「内掌典」は女性が就任する官職である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">`Junior Staff&apos; is a position which is exclusively assigned to women.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">`Junior Staff&apos; is a position exclusively assigned to women.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nai-shoten&apos; is a position assigned only to women.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>宮内省掌典職</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ceremonial Staff of Imperial Household Ministry</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ceremonial Staff of the Imperial Household Ministry</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoten-shoku (Board of the Ritualists), the Ministry of Imperial Household</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>「掌典職官制」（昭和14年皇室令第4号）により、宮内省に掌典職が置かれ、掌典職には、掌典長、掌典次長、掌典、内掌典、掌典補、事務官及び属を置くことが定められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">`Ceremonial Staff Organization&apos; (Article 4 of Koshitsu-rei; the Imperial Families&apos; Act, in 1939) specified Imperial Household Ministry set the ceremonial staff under which Manager, Deputy Manager, Staff, Junior staff, Assistant, Administrator and Attendant are placed in Imperial Household Ministry.</e>
<cmt>属の訳出が不明ですが暫定的に attendant としています。掌典職官制に関 しても訳出が不明ですが暫定的に Ceremonial staff organization と訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">`Ceremonial Staff Organization&apos; (Article 4 of Koshitsu-rei; the Imperial Families&apos; Act, in 1939) specified Imperial Household Ministry set the ceremonial staff under which Manager, Deputy Manager, Staff, Junior staff, Assistant, Administrator and Attendant are placed in the Imperial Household Ministry.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In accordance with the &apos;Shoten-shoku Kansei&apos; (the regulations for the organization of the shoten-shoku), which was announced in the Imperial Household Order No. 4 of 1939, the Ministry of Imperial Household established a department called Shoten-shoku, and they also decided to place the positions in this department as follows: the shoten-cho, the shoten-jicho, shoten, nai-shoten, shoten-ho, administrative officials, and minor officials.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>掌典長、掌典次長、掌典、内掌典及び掌典補は、宮内省式部職掌典部時代と同様の職掌である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The duties of Manager, Deputy Manager, Staff, Junior staff, Assistant are similar to the duties of Ceremony department in Board of Ceremonies of Imperial Household Ministry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The duties of Manager, Deputy Manager, Staff, Junior staff, Assistant are similar to the duties of the Ceremony department in the Board of Ceremonies of the Imperial Household Ministry.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The duties of the shoten-cho, the shoten-jicho, shoten, nai-shoten, and shoten-ho were respectively the same as the ones which had been decided when the previous organization had been established.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>「事務官」は奏任官として掌典職の庶務を掌り、「属」は判任官として掌典職の庶務に従事していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">`Administrator&apos; took charge of general affairs of ceremonial staff as an official who is originally selected as a candidates by the Prime Minister, and `Attendant&apos; was engaged in general affairs of ceremonial staff as a Junior official.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">`Administrator&apos; takes charge of general affairs of the ceremonial staff as an official who is originally selected as a candidate by the Prime Minister, and the `Attendant&apos; was engaged in the general affairs of the ceremonial staff as a Junior official.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Administrative officials, who were at the position of soninkan, were responsible for general affairs in this department, and they were supported by minor officials, who were at the position of hanninkan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>内廷機関としての掌典職</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ceremonial staff as an Imperial court organization</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ceremonial staff as an Imperial court organization</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoten-shoku as the Imperial Family&apos;s private agency</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>1947年（昭和22年）5月3日の日本国憲法施行に伴う同省の廃止（宮内府への移行）により、掌典職も国家機関としては廃止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ceremonial staff was abolished by the reason of the abolishment of Imperial Household Ministry (shift to Kunaifu; Imperial Household agency) due to enforcement of the Constitution of Japan on May 3, 1947.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ceremonial staff of the Imperial Household Ministry (shift for the Kunaifu; Imperial Household agency) due to enforcement of the Constitution of Japan on May 3, 1947.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shoten-shoku as a governmental organization was abolished due to the abolishment of the Ministry of Imperial Household (this Ministry was demoted to the Imperial Household Office) in accordance with the enforcement of the Constitution of Japan on May 3, 1947.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>その後も皇室費の内廷費をもって人件費に充てられる職員が置かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The staff whose employment cost is covered by the daily living expense of the Imperial Household still have been placed since then.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The staff, whose employment costs were covered by the daily living expense of the Imperial Household, is still in existence.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, they put some staff by using the budgeted allowance for the private expenses of the Imperial Family.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>現在は、天皇の私的使用人としての性格を有する『内廷の職員』とされ宮内庁職員（国家公務員）ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nowadays, the staff is regarded as &quot;staff of imperial court&quot; which is categorized as private staff of an emperor, not as &quot;staff of Imperial Household Agency (national service personnel).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nowadays, the staff is regarded as the &quot;staff of the Imperial Court&quot; which is categorized as the private staff of the emperor, not as &quot;staff of the Imperial Household Agency (national service personnel).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nowadays, the staff is regarded as the &quot;staff of the Imperial Court&quot; which is categorized as the private staff of the emperor, not as &quot;staff of the Imperial Household Agency (national service personnel).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>責任者の掌典長をはじめ掌典次長、掌典、内掌典、掌典補等、宮内省掌典職時代と同職名の職員が置かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The position of present staff is the same as that of the ceremonial staff of Imperial Household Ministry in name including Manager (a responsible person), Deputy Manager, Junior staff, Assistant, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The position of the present staff is the same as that of the ceremonial staff of the Imperial Household Ministry in name, including Manager (a responsible person), Deputy Manager, Junior staff, Assistant, etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They have personnel whose titles are the same as the ones in the Shoten-shoku, the Ministry of Imperial Household, such as the shoten-cho who works as a general manager, the shoten-jicho, shoten, nai-shoten, shoten-ho, and so on.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>1975年以後伊勢神宮や勅祭社における祭典では、天皇の使者である「勅使」をつとめる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They have been serving as `Chokushi&apos; (imperial messenger) in Ise-jingu Shrine or Chokusai-sha since 1975.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They have been serving as `Chokushi&apos; (imperial messenger) in Ise-jingu Shrine or Chokusai-sha since 1975.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They have served as a &apos;chokushi&apos; (imperial messenger) at festivals at Ise-jingu Shrine and chokusai-sha (shrines attended by an Imperial envoy) since 1975.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 翰林硯士(id:99377), Point136(id:211299), 伏儀(id:142093), 伊集院聖(id:53199), Geogie(id:143809), 無言雀師(id:13124), くっちゃめ(id:86793), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>