<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>垂仁天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Suinin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Suinin</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Suinin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>垂仁天皇（すいにんてんのう、崇神天皇29年1月1日 (旧暦)（紀元前69年1月26日） - 垂仁天皇99年7月14日 (旧暦)（70年8月8日）は『古事記』・『日本書紀』に伝えられる第11代の天皇（在位：垂仁天皇元年1月2日 (旧暦)（紀元前29年） - 垂仁天皇99年7月14日 (旧暦)（70年）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Suinin (January 26, 69 B.C. - August 8, 70) was the eleventh emperor according to &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) (Reign: February 2, 29 B.C. - August 6, 70).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Suinin (January 26, 69 B.C. - August 8, 70) was the eleventh emperor according to &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) (reigning from February 2, 29 B.C. to August 6, 70).</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Suinin (January 26, 69 B.C. - August 8, 70) was the eleventh emperor according to &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) (reigning from February 2, 29 B.C. to August 6, 70).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>活目入彦五十狭茅尊（いくめいりびこいさちのみこと）・活目尊。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another name was Ikume Iribiko Isachi no Mikoto or Ikume no Mikoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another name was Ikume Iribiko Isachi no Mikoto or Ikume no Mikoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also known as Ikume Iribiko Isachi no Mikoto, or Ikume no Mikoto.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>『古事記』に伊久米伊理毘古伊佐知命（いくめいりびこいさちのみこと）、『常陸国風土記』に伊久米天皇、『令集解』所引「古記」に生目天皇、『上宮記』逸文に伊久牟尼利比古（いくむにりひこ）大王と見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His name was seen as 伊久米伊理毘古伊佐知命 (Ikume Iribiko Isachi no Mikoto) in &quot;Kojiki,&quot; 伊久米天皇 (Emperor Ikume) in &quot;Hitachi Province Fudoki&quot; (a topography of Hitachi Province), 生目天皇 (Emperor Ikume) in quotations of &apos;Koki&apos; (Ancient records) in &quot;Ryonoshuge&quot; (Commentaries on the Civil Statutes), and 伊久牟尼利比古 (Ikumu Nirihiko) Daio in &quot;Joguki &quot;(Record of the Crown Prince) itsubun (a composition previously existed but doesn&apos;t exist now).</e>
<cmt>漢字が焦点になっているため、訳文に漢字表記を残しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His name was seen as 伊久米伊理毘古伊佐知命 (Ikume Iribiko Isachi no Mikoto) in &quot;Kojiki,&quot; 伊久米天皇 (Emperor Ikume) in &quot;Hitachi Province Fudoki&quot; (a topography of Hitachi Province), 生目天皇 (Emperor Ikume) in quotations of &apos;Koki&apos; (Ancient records) in &quot;Ryonoshuge&quot; (Commentaries on the Civil Statutes), and 伊久牟尼利比古 (Ikumu Nirihiko) Daio in the &quot;Joguki&quot; (Record of the Crown Prince) itsubun (a composition that formerly existed but no longer does).</e>
<cmt>gp</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His name appears in &quot;Kojiki&quot; (Record of Ancient Matters, &quot;Ikume Iribiko Isachi no Mikoto&quot;), &quot;Hitachi no Kuni Fudoki&quot; (Topography of Hitachi Province, &quot;Ikume Emperor&quot;), &quot;Koki&quot; (Ancient Records) quoted in &quot;Ryonoshuge&quot; (Commentaries on Civil Statutes; &quot;Emperor Ikume&quot;) and &quot;Joguki&quot; (history book written around the 7th century, &quot;Great King Ikumunirihiko&quot;).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>『日本書紀』、『古事記』に見える事績は総じて起源譚の性格が強く、その史実性については多分に疑問である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The all achievements described in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; and &quot;Kojiki&quot; had strong characters of Kigen tan (a story of origin), so its historicity was largely doubtful.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The all achievements described in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; and &quot;Kojiki&quot; had strong characteristics of Kigen tan (a story of origin), so its historicity was generally doubtful.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of the accounts in &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; (The Chronicles of Japan) and &quot;Kojiki&quot; are stories created to explain the origin of things and it is highly doubtful whether or not they are descriptions of facts.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>皇居</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Palace</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Palace</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Palace</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>都は纒向珠城宮（まきむくのたまきのみや。奈良県桜井市穴師か）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The capital was Makimuku no Tamakinomiya (Anashi, Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The capital was Makimuku no Tamakinomiya (Anashi, Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His palace was located at Makimuku no Tamakinomiya (presumably, present-day Anashi in Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>『古事記』に「師木玉垣宮（しきのたまかきのみや）」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was described as &apos;Shiki no Tamakakinomiya&apos; in &quot;Kojiki.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was described as &apos;Shiki no Tamakakinomiya&apos; in &quot;Kojiki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was described as &apos;Shiki no Tamakakinomiya&apos; in &quot;Kojiki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>事績</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Achievements</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Achievements</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Achievements</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>『日本書紀』の編年に拠る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those were subjected to chronology in &quot;Nihonshoki.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those were subjected to chronology in &quot;Nihon Shoki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following accounts are based on descriptions in &quot;Nihon Shoki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>崇神天皇29年1月1日（紀元前69年）に誕生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born on January 25, 69 B.C..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born on January 25, 69 B.C.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born on January 25, 69 B.C.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>48年4月（紀元前50年）、夢の前兆により皇太子に立てられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 22, 50 B.C., he was appointed to Imperial Prince by augury of dream.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 22, 50 B.C., he was appointed to Imperial Prince based on the augury of a dream.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 50 B.C., he was appointed as Imperial Prince by revelation in a dream.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>垂仁天皇元年1月（紀元前29年）、即位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was ascended the throne on February 2, 29 B.C..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He ascended to the throne on February 2, 29 B.C.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He ascended to the throne in February, 29 B.C.</e>
<cmt>原文では日付がないため、英訳も2月　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>2年2月（紀元前28年）に狭穂姫を立后、10月、纒向に遷都した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He defined Saohime (Princess Sao) as Empress on March 21, 28 B.C. and transferred the capital to Makimuku in October.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He decreed Saohime (Princess Sao) to be the Empress on March 21, 28 B.C., and transferred the capital to Makimuku in October.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He decreed Saohime (Princess Sao) to be the Empress in March, 28 B.C., and transferred the capital to Makimuku in November.</e>
<cmt>同上です。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>3年3月 (旧暦)（紀元前27年）、新羅王子の天日槍（あめのひほこ）が神宝を奉じて来朝。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 9, 27 B.C., Prince of Silla, Amenohihoko visited Japan to present sacred treasures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 9, 27 B.C., Amenohihoko, the Prince of Silla, visited Japan in orderto present sacred treasures.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April, 27 B.C., Amenohihoko, the Prince of Silla, visited Japan in order to present sacred treasures.</e>
<cmt>同上です。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>5年10月 (旧暦)（紀元前25年）、皇后の兄狭穂彦（さほびこ）が叛乱を起こし、皇后は兄に従って焼死。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 8, 25 B.C., a brother of the empress, Sahobiko, rebelled and the empress was burned to death by obeying her brother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 8, 25 B.C., a brother of the empress, Sahobiko, rebelled and the empress was burned to death for having obeyed her brother.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November, 25 B.C., a brother of the empress, Sahobiko, rebelled and the empress was burned to death for having obeyed her brother.</e>
<cmt>同上です。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="14">
<j>7年7月（紀元前23年）、野見宿禰（のみのすくね）が当麻蹴速（たいまのけはや）と相撲をとり蹴殺す（相撲節会の起源説話）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 20, 23 B.C., NOMI no Sukune had sumo-wrestled with TAIMA no Kehaya and kicked him to death (hypothesis story of Sumai no sechie (the Imperial ceremony of Sumo wrestling)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 20, 23 B.C., NOMI no Sukune sumo-wrestled with TAIMA no Kehaya and kicked him to death (a story hypothesized in Sumai no sechie (the imperial ceremony of sumo wrestling)).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August, 23 B.C., NOMI no Sukune kicked TAIMA no Kehaya to death in a sumo wrestling match (this match is regarded as the origin of Sumai no sechie (the imperial ceremony of sumo wrestling)).</e>
<cmt>「起源説話」の部分の表現などを変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="15">
<j>15年2月（紀元前15年）、丹波道主王の女たちを後宮に入れ、8月にその中から日葉酢媛を皇后とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 26, 15 B.C., he had daughters of Tanbano Michino Ushino Mikoto enter kokyu (empress&apos;s residence) and defined Hibasuhime as Empress in August.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 26, 15 B.C., he had the daughters of Tanbano Michino Ushino Mikoto enter the kokyu (empress&apos;s residence) and, in August, designated Hibasuhime to be the empress.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February, 15 B.C., he had the daughters of Tanbano Michino Ushino Mikoto enter the kokyu (empress&apos;s residence) and, in September, designated Hibasuhime to be the empress.</e>
<cmt>同上です。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="16">
<j>25年3月（紀元前5年）、天照大神の祭祀を皇女の倭姫命に託す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 5, 5 B.C., he left a religious service for Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess) with Princess Yamatohime no Mikoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 5, 5 B.C., he left a religious service for Amaterasu Omikami (the sun goddess) with Princess Yamatohime no Mikoto.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 5 B.C., he appointed Princess Yamatohime to perform rituals to worship the great sun goddess Amaterasu Omikami.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>倭姫は菟田（うだ。奈良県宇陀郡）・近江国・美濃国を経て伊勢国に至り、五十鈴川の辺に祠を建てて、伊勢神宮を興したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Yamatohime had been to Uda (Uda County, Nara Prefecture), Omi Province, and Mino Province, she reached Ise Province and built hokora (a small shrine) by Isuzu-gawa River to make Ise-jingu Shrine prosperous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Yamatohime had been to Uda (Uda County, Nara Prefecture), Omi Province and Mino Province, she reached Ise Province and built a hokora (a small shrine) by the Isuzu-gawa River in order to make Ise-jingu Shrine prosperous.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Yamatohime had been to Uda (Uda-gun, Nara Prefecture), Omi Province and Mino Province, she reached Ise Province and built a hokora (a small shrine) by the Isuzu-gawa River in order to make Ise-jingu Shrine prosperous.</e>
<cmt>Uda-gun としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="18">
<j>27年8月（紀元前3年）、諸神社に武器を献納し、神地・神戸を定める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 8, 3 B.C., he dedicated weapons to many shrines and governed sacred land and Kobe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 8, 3 B.C., he dedicated weapons to many shrines and governed sacred land as well as Kobe.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September 3 B.C., he dedicated weapons to shrines, established shrine parishes and chose families (called &quot;jinko&quot; or &quot;kanbe&quot; in Japanese) in these parishes to provide services for the shrines.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>この年、来目（橿原市久米町）に初めて屯倉を興す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this year, he established miyake (Imperial-controlled territory) for the first time in Kume (Kume-cho, Kashihara City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In that year he also established miyake (territory under imperial control) for the first time in Kume (Kume-cho, Kashihara City).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In that year he also established miyake (territory under imperial control) for the first time in Kume (Kume-cho, Kashihara City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="20">
<j>32年7月（3年）、日葉酢媛が薨去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 14, 3, Hibasuhime died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hibasuhime dies on August 14 of the year 3.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hibasushime died in August 3 A.D.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>野見宿禰の進言に従い、殉死に替えて土偶を葬る（埴輪の起源説話）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By following NOMI no Sukune&apos;s advise, he buried clay figure instead of following his master to the grave (hypothesis story of clay figure).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By following NOMI no Sukune&apos;s advise, he buried a clay figure instead of following his master to the grave (the story of the clay figure is hypothetical).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following NOMI no Sukune&apos;s advice, he buried a clay figure instead of following his wife to the grave (this is believed to be the origin of Haniwa, earthenware figures that line the exterior of some ancient Japanese burial mounds).</e>
<cmt>masterに従って殉死するのではなく、妻である皇后だと解釈し、wifeとしました。また、「はにわの起源説話」の英訳の部分も変更ました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>『古事記』に「石祝（棺か）作りを定め、土師部（はにしべ）を定めたまいき」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kojiki&quot; described &apos;he governed 石祝 (coffin) makers and Hanishibe (clay pot and clay figure maker).&apos;</e>
<cmt>「石祝」の正しい読み方が確認できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kojiki&quot; stated that &apos;he governed 石祝 (coffin) makers and Hanishibe (a maker of clay pots and figures).&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kojiki&quot; stated that &apos;he governed 石祝 (coffin) makers and Hanishibe (a maker of clay pots and figures).&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>石棺を作る部民や赤土で種々の器を作る部民を定めたというのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was said that he governed Bemin (people who belonged to Yamato dynasty) who made stone coffins and various pots by red-soil.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was said that he governed the Bemin (people who belonged to the Yamato dynasty), who made stone coffins and various pots of red clay.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was said that he governed the Bemin (people who belonged to the Yamato dynasty), who made stone coffins and various pots of red clay.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="24">
<j>35年（6年）、河内国の高石池や茅渟（ちぬ）池を始め、諸国に多くの池溝を開いて、農業を盛んにしたと伝える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 15, 6, he activated agriculture by developing Takaishi-ike Pond and Chinu-ike Pond in Kawachi Province and many rifts in many provinces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 15 in the year 6, he activated agriculture by developing the Takaishi-ike and Chinu-ike ponds in Kawachi Province as well as many rifts in various provinces.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 15 in the year 6, he is reported to have built ponds and canals in many provinces, including Takaishi-ike Pond and Chinu-ike Pond in Kawachi Province, in order to promote agriculture.</e>
<cmt>原文では日付がないため、英訳も2月　としました。FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="25">
<j>39年10月（10年）、五十瓊敷命が剣千振を作り、石上神宮に納める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 24, 10, Inishiki no Mikoto made one thousand swords and presented to Ishigami-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 24, 10, Inishiki no Mikoto presented 1,000 he had made to Ishigami-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October in the year 10, Inishiki no Mikoto presented 1,000 swords he had made to Ishigami-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>swordsを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>この後、五十瓊敷命に命じて、神宮の神宝を掌らせる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he ordered Inishiki no Mikoto to administer sacred treasures in the Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, he ordered Inishiki no Mikoto to administer sacred treasures in the Shrine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He subsequently appointed Inishiki no Mikoto to protect the sacred treasures of Isonokami-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="27">
<j>90年2月（61年）、田道間守（たじまもり）に命じて、常世国の非時香菓（ときじくのかぐのこのみ）を求めさせる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 8, 61, he ordered Tajimamori to request tokijikuno kagunokonomi (crackerberry) in Tokoyo no kuni (parallel universe beyond the sea).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 8 in the year 61, he ordered Tajimamori to request tokijikuno kagunokonomi (crackerberry) in Tokoyo no kuni (a parallel universe beyond the sea).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March 61 A.D., he ordered Tajimamori to go search for a rare fruit called &quot;tokijikuno kaguno konomi&quot; that grows in a country beyond the sea.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="28">
<j>99年7月（70年）、天皇崩御。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 24, 70, the Emperor Suinin died.</e>
<cmt>「垂仁」を付け加えて訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 24 in the year 70, Emperor Suinin died.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July in the year 70, Emperor Suinin died.</e>
<cmt>同上です。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>140歳（紀）、153歳（記）、139歳（大日本史）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was said to be one hundred forty years old in &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; one hundred fifty three years old in &quot;Kojiki,&quot; and one hundred thirty nine years old in &quot;Dainihonshi&quot; (Great history of Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was said to be 140 years old in &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; 153 years old in &quot;Kojiki,&quot; and 139 years old in &quot;Dainihonshi&quot; (Great History of Japan).</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was said to be 140 years old in &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; 153 years old in &quot;Kojiki,&quot; and 139 years old in &quot;Dainihonshi&quot; (Great History of Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>12月、菅原伏見陵に葬られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 18, 71, he was buried in Sugawara no Fushimi Mausoleum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 18 in the year 71, he was buried in Sugawara no Fushimi Mausoleum.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January in the year 71, he was buried in Sugawara no Fushimi Mausoleum.</e>
<cmt>原文では日付がないため、英訳も1月　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="31">
<j>『住吉大社神代記』には、在位53年で辛未年に崩御したとあり、これは『書紀』の編年と相違する点で注目される（『書紀』の垂仁天皇99年を計算すると庚午）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Sumiyoshi-taisha Shrine Jindaiki&quot; (Records of Sumiyoshi-taisha Shrine in Jindai Period) it stated that he died at the reign of fifty third, in Shinbi no toshi (the year of shinbi), and the focus was on the date of death different from &quot;Shoki&quot;(the year was Kanoe uma (the zodiac signs in Chinese astrology) when Emperor Suinin 99 in &quot;Shoki&quot; was calculated).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Sumiyoshi-taisha Shrine Jindaiki&quot; (Records of Sumiyoshi-taisha Shrine in the Jindai Period) it is stated that he died at the reign of fifty-third, in Shinbi no toshi (the year of shinbi), but the focus is on the date of death, which differs from &quot;Shoki&quot;(the year was Kanoe uma (according to the zodiac signs in Chinese astrology) when Emperor Suinin 99 in &quot;Shoki&quot; was calculated).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Sumiyoshi-taisha Jindaiki&quot; (Ancient Record of Sumiyoshi-taisha Shrine), it is stated that he died in his fifty-third year of reign, the year of the Metal-Sheep in the Chinese astrological calendar, but this contradicts the account given in &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; (the year of Emperor Suinin&apos;s death calculated based on his 99 years of reign recorded in &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; is the year of the Metal-Horse).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>御陵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Misasagi (Imperial mausoleum)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Misasagi (the imperial mausoleum)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Misasagi (the imperial mausoleum)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="32">
<j>『延喜式』諸陵寮に拠れば、菅原伏見東陵（すがわらのふしみのひがしのみささぎ）に葬られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;the Engishiki&quot; (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers), he was buried in Sugawara no Fushimino Higashino Misagi (East Mausoleum of Sugawara no Fushimi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;the Engishiki&quot; (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers), he was buried in Sugawara no Fushimino Higashino Misagi (the east mausoleum of Sugawara no Fushimi).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Engishiki&quot; (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers), he was buried in Sugawara no Fushimino Higashino Misasagi (the east mausoleum of Sugawara no Fushimi).</e>
<cmt>&quot; の位置を変更しました。Misasagi としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>『古事記』に「御陵は菅原の御立野（みたちの）の中にあり」、『日本書紀』に「菅原伏見陵（すがわらのふしみのみささぎ）」、『続日本紀』には「櫛見山陵」として見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kojiki&quot; described &apos;Misasagi was in Sugawara no Mitachino,&apos; &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; described &apos;it was in Sugawara no Fushimino Misagi, and &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued) described &apos;it was in Kushimi no Misasagi.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kojiki&quot; states that &apos;Misasagi was in Sugawara no Mitachino,&apos; &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; states that &apos;it was in Sugawara no Fushimino Misagi, and &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicles of Japan Continued) states that &apos;it was in Kushimi no Misasagi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kojiki states that the mausoleum was in &quot;Sugaware no Mitachino,&quot; while &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; states that it was in &quot;Sugawara no Fushimino&quot; and &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicles of Japan Continued) in &quot;Kushimi-yama&quot; (Mt. Kushimi).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>現在、同陵は奈良県奈良市尼辻西町の宝来山古墳（前方後円墳、全長227m）に比定される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, this Misagi is considered similar to Horaisan-kofun Tumulus (large keyhole-shaped tomb mound, 227m in length) in Amagatsujinishi-machi, Nara City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, this Misagi is considered similar to the Horaisan-kofun tumulus (a large, keyhole-shaped tomb mound 227m in length) in Amagatsujinishi-machi, Nara City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, this Misasagi is considered similar to the Horaisan-kofun tumulus (a large, keyhole-shaped tomb mound 227 meters in length) in Amagatsujinishi-machi, Nara City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="35">
<j>現在の宝来山古墳の濠の中、南東に田道間守の墓とされる小島がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Within the moat of current Horaisan-kofun Tumulus, there is a small island in the southeast that is said to be the grave of Tajimamori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Within the moat of the current Horaisan-kofun tumulus, there is a small island in the southeast that is said to be the grave of Tajimamori.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Within the moat of the current Horaisan-kofun tumulus, there is a small island in the southeast that is said to be the grave of Tajimamori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>この位置は、かっての濠の堤上に相当し、濠を貯水のため拡張して、島状になったと推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This location was equivalent to former tsutsuminoue in the moat, but the moat was expanded to collect water, so it became island-shape.</e>
<cmt>「堤上」の正しい意味が確認できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This location was equivalent to the former tsutsuminoue in the moat, but the moat was expanded to collect water so it took the form of an island.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The grave is located where the embankment of the moat used to be before the moat was expanded to collect water, resulting in the formation of an island.</e>
<cmt>濠の堤→embankment of the moat　と解釈した.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>しかし、戸田忠至等による文久の修陵図では、この墓らしきものは描かれていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, according to Shurikuzu (a chart to indicate mausoleum renovation) of Bunkyu by Tadayuki TODA, the potential graves were not depicted on it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, according to the shurikuzu (a chart to indicate mausoleum renovation) of Bunkyu by Tadayuki TODA, the potential graves weren&apos;t depicted on it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there is no grave shown on the map drawn by Tadayuki TODA when the mausoleum was repaired during the Bunkyu era.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="38">
<j>近鉄橿原線の尼ヶ辻駅の近く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is near the Amagatsuji Station of Kintetsu Kashihara Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is near Amagatsuji Station of the Kintetsu Kashihara Line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is near Amagatsuji Station of the Kintetsu Kashihara Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>（垂仁天皇陵）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Mausoleum of Emperor Suinin)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The mausoleum of Emperor Suinin)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The mausoleum of Emperor Suinin)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 霧木諒二(id:9795), Nnh(id:474), MIsogi(id:20599), Ojigiri(id:329), Eskimbot(id:29676), Aibot(id:104981), Tarosan(id:330), 行動で挽回するしかない(id:31799), Aska-sacra(id:8180), Gombe(id:27), Masyu(id:31065), Ponta2(id:129030), 代言人(id:33675), Goki(id:7107), 名無し(id:7386), TY(id:1386), Loveless(id:129239), Sumaru(id:20609), Higashi(id:8842), Izayohi(id:13095), Carbuncle(id:346), 松茸(id:27535), Yanahan(id:2437), Robbot(id:3063), Escarbot(id:59151), 文姫(id:66661), MDR-SK(id:192066), Xqbot(id:273540), VolkovBot(id:105371), SuisuiBot(id:10165), Homer(id:12084), YOSHI438(id:174755), 伏儀(id:142093), Suisui(id:69), LeonardoRob0t(id:25875), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>