<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>屋主忍男武雄心命</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yanushioshiotakeogokoro no mikoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yanushioshiotakeogokoro no Mikoto</e>
<cmt>頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yanushioshiotakeogokoro no Mikoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>屋主忍男武雄心命（やぬしおしおたけおごころのみこと生没年不詳）は、3世紀から4世紀頃の日本の皇族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yanushioshiotakeogokoro no mikoto (year of birth and death unknown) was a member of Japanese Imperial family, who lived in the period around the 3rd to 4th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yanushioshiotakeogokoro no mikoto (year of birth and death unknown) was a member of Japanese Imperial family, who lived in the period around the third to fourth century.</e>
<cmt>3rd→third、4th→fourthとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yanushioshiotakeogokoro no mikoto (year of birth and death unknown) was a member of Japanese Imperial family, who lived in the period around the third to fourth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>彦太忍信命（ひこふつおしのまことのみこと）の王子で第8代孝元天皇の親族呼称に当たる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the Prince of Hikofutsuoshinomakoto no mikoto, his name was the address term used for a family member of the eighth Emperor Kogen.</e>
<cmt>彦太忍信命（ひこふつおしのまことのみこと）→Hikofutsuoshinomakoto no mikotoとしましたが、長くて読辛そうです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the prince of Hikofutsuoshinomakoto no mikoto, his name was the address term used for a family member of the eighth Emperor Kogen.</e>
<cmt>Prince→princeとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the prince of Hikofutsuoshinomakoto no mikoto, his name was the address term used for a family member of the eighth Emperor Kogen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>莵道彦（うじひこ／宇豆比古）の続柄影媛（かげひめ）を妃とし武内宿禰を儲ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He took Kagehime, a woman who had a kinship with Ujihiko (written as 莵道彦 or 宇豆比古), to wife, and had a son, who was TAKENOUCHI no Sukune.</e>
<cmt>影媛（かげひめ）→Kagehimeとしました。 莵道彦（うじひこ／宇豆比古） →Ujihiko (written 莵道彦 or 宇豆比古）と名前の漢字表記を加えました。 </cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He took Kagehime, a woman who had a kinship with Ujihiko (written as 莵道彦 or 宇豆比古), to wife, and had a son, who was TAKENOUCHI no Sukune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He took Kagehime, a woman who had a kinship with Ujihiko (written as 莵道彦 or 宇豆比古), to wife, and had a son, who was TAKENOUCHI no Sukune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>古事記で武内宿禰は彦太忍信命の王子となっており、屋主忍男武雄心命は登場しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters), TAKENOUCHI no Sukune appears as the prince of Hikofutsuoshinomakoto no mikoto, however, there exists no description about Yanushioshiotakeogokoro no mikoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kojiki (The Records of Ancient Matters), TAKENOUCHI no Sukune appears as the prince of Hikofutsuoshinomakoto no mikoto, however, there exists no description about Yanushioshiotakeogokoro no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>原文表記に合わせ、&quot;Kojiki&quot;のクォーテーションをとり、theを追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kojiki (The Records of Ancient Matters), TAKENOUCHI no Sukune appears as the prince of Hikofutsuoshinomakoto no mikoto, however, there exists no description about Yanushioshiotakeogokoro no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>日本書紀景行紀によると景行天皇3年2月1日に、景行天皇が紀の国に行幸し、神祇を祀ろうとしたが、占いによると吉と出なかったため、命が天皇より紀の国に派遣された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &apos;Keiko-ki (the chapter of Emperor Keiko) of &quot;Nihonshoki (Chronicle of Japan), on the first day of the second month of the third year of the Emperor Keiko&apos;s reign, Emperor Keiko was scheduled to pay a visit to Kinokuni (present Wakayama Prefecture), to undertake a religious ceremony for gods of heaven and earth, however, as a result of a fortune-telling that did not predict him a good divination, the Emperor delegated him (Yanushioshiotakeogokoro no mikoto) to go to Kinokuni.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。[よると」を加えました。 景行天皇3年2月1日→定訳不明： the first day of the second month of the third year of the Emperor Keiko&apos;s reignとしました。 命→the mikotoとせずに　him (Yanushioshiotakeogokoro no mikoto)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the Keiko-ki (the chapter of Emperor Keiko) of the Nihonshoki (Chronicle of Japan), on February 23, 73, Emperor Keiko was scheduled to pay a visit to Kinokuni (present Wakayama Prefecture), to undertake a religious ceremony for gods of heaven and earth, however, as a result of a fortune-telling that did not predict him a good divination, the Emperor delegated him (Yanushioshiotakeogokoro no mikoto) to go to Kinokuni.</e>
<cmt>According to &apos;Keiko-ki→According to the Keiko-ki、&quot;Nihonshoki→the Nihonshokiに修正、旧暦→新暦に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the Keiko-ki (the chapter of Emperor Keiko) of the Nihonshoki (Chronicle of Japan), on February 23, 73, Emperor Keiko was scheduled to pay a visit to Kinokuni (present Wakayama Prefecture), to undertake a religious ceremony for gods of heaven and earth, however, as a result of a fortune-telling that did not predict him a good divination, the Emperor delegated him (Yanushioshiotakeogokoro no mikoto) to go to Kinokuni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>阿備の柏原で神祇を祀り、同地に定住して紀直の後裔莵道彦の娘影媛を娶り、武内宿禰が生まれたとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And after he undertook the ceremony for gods of heaven and earth at Kashiwabara (柏原) in Abi, he settled down there, and took the daughter of Ujihiko who was KI no Atai&apos;s descendent, to wife and TAKENOUCHI no Sukune was born.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。　柏原→正式な読み方が不明です：Kashiwabara (柏原)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And after he undertook the ceremony for gods of heaven and earth at Kashiwabara (柏原) in Abi, he settled down there, and took the daughter of Ujihiko who was KI no Atai&apos;s descendent, to wife and TAKENOUCHI no Sukune was born.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And after he undertook the ceremony for gods of heaven and earth at Kashiwabara (柏原) in Abi, he settled down there, and took the daughter of Ujihiko who was KI no Atai&apos;s descendent, to wife and TAKENOUCHI no Sukune was born.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>命は井石神社（長崎県東彼杵郡波佐見町）・千栗八幡宮（佐賀県三養基郡みやき町）・武雄神社（佐賀県武雄市）・江野神社（新潟県上越市）・甲良神社（滋賀県犬上郡甲良町）・五社神社 (日野町)（滋賀県蒲生郡日野町 (滋賀県)）・馬見岡綿向神社（滋賀県蒲生郡日野町)・若櫻神社摂社高屋安倍神社（奈良県桜井市）などで祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was enshrined at Iseki-jinja Shrine (Hasami-cho, Higashisonogi-gun, Nagasaki Prefecture), Chiriku-hachimangu Shrine (Miyaki-cho, Miyaki-gun, Saga Prefecture), Takeo-jinja Shrine (Takeo City, Saga Prefecture), Eno-jinja Shrine (Joetsu City, Niigata Prefecture), Kora-jinja Shrine (Kora-cho, Inugami-gun, Shiga Prefecture), Gosha-jinja Shrine, Hino-cho (Nino-cho, Gamo-gun, Shiga Prefecture), Umamiokawatamuki-jinja Shrine (Hino-cho, Gamo-gun, Shiga Prefecture), Takyaabe-jinja Shrine, sessha (auxiliary shrine [dedicated to a deity close-related to that of a main shrine]) of Wakazakura-jinja Shrine, and others.</e>
<cmt>若櫻神社摂社高屋安倍神社（奈良県桜井市）→定訳不明：Takyaabe-jinja Shrine, sessha (auxiliary shrine [dedicated to a deity close-related to that of a main shrine]) of Wakazakura-jinja Shrineとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was enshrined at Iseki-jinja Shrine (Hasami-cho, Higashisonogi County, Nagasaki Prefecture), Chiriku-hachimangu Shrine (Miyaki-cho, Miyaki County, Saga Prefecture), Takeo-jinja Shrine (Takeo City, Saga Prefecture), Eno-jinja Shrine (Joetsu City, Niigata Prefecture), Kora-jinja Shrine (Kora-cho, Inugami County, Shiga Prefecture), Gosha-jinja Shrine (Hino-cho, Gamo Counry, Shiga Prefecture), Umamiokawatamuki-jinja Shrine (Hino-cho, Gamo County, Shiga Prefecture), Takyaabe-jinja Shrine, sessha (auxiliary shrine [dedicated to a deity close-related to that of a main shrine]) of Wakazakura-jinja Shrine (Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture), and others.</e>
<cmt>&quot;-gun&quot;→&quot;County&quot;に修正、Gosha-jinja Shrine, Hino-cho→表記が重複するためHino-choを削除、Nino-cho→Hino-choに修正、（奈良県桜井市）→訳漏れのため訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was enshrined at Iseki-jinja Shrine (Hasami-cho, Higashisonogi County, Nagasaki Prefecture), Chiriku-hachimangu Shrine (Miyaki-cho, Miyaki County, Saga Prefecture), Takeo-jinja Shrine (Takeo City, Saga Prefecture), Eno-jinja Shrine (Joetsu City, Niigata Prefecture), Kora-jinja Shrine (Kora-cho, Inugami County, Shiga Prefecture), Gosha-jinja Shrine (Hino-cho, Gamo County, Shiga Prefecture), Umamiokawatamuki-jinja Shrine (Hino-cho, Gamo County, Shiga Prefecture), Takayaabe-jinja Shrine, sessha (auxiliary shrine [dedicated to a deity close-related to that of a main shrine]) of Wakazakura-jinja Shrine (Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture), and others.</e>
<cmt>Gamo Counry→Gamo CountyTakyaabe-jinja→Takayaabe-jinja</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Lupinoid(id:68), Nnh(id:474), ざざむし(id:9415), 0null0(id:582), 代言人(id:33675), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>