<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>履中天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Richu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Richu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Richu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>履中天皇（りちゅうてんのう、仁徳天皇24年（336年）？ - 履中天皇6年3月15日 (旧暦)（405年4月29日））は、第17代の天皇（在位：履中天皇元年2月1日 (旧暦)（400年3月12日） - 同6年3月15日（405年4月29日））。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Richu (336?-April 29, 405) was the seventeenth Emperor who was in the reign from March 12, 400 to April 29, 405.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Richu (circa 336 - April 29, 405) was the seventeenth Emperor who reigned from March 12, 400, to April 29, 405.</e>
<cmt>形式、簡潔化しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Richu (circa 336 - April 29, 405) was the seventeenth Emperor who reigned from March 12, 400, to April 29, 405.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>名は大兄去来穂別尊（おおえのいざほわけのみこと）、大江之伊邪本和気命。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His name was Oe no izahowake no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>名前の二つ目は読みは一緒で漢字が違うのみなので、訳は省略しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His name was Oe no izahowake no mikoto (the term mikoto referred to a god or person of great importance), which was written as &quot;大兄去来穂別尊&quot; or &quot;大江之伊邪本和気命&quot; in Japanese.</e>
<cmt>漢字表記の違いも重要と考え、補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His name was Oe no izahowake no mikoto (the term mikoto referred to a god or person of great importance), which was written as &quot;大兄去来穂別尊&quot; or &quot;大江之伊邪本和気命&quot; in Japanese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>中国の『宋書』に見える「倭の五王」中の倭王讃に比定する説がある（応神天皇もしくは仁徳天皇とする説もあり）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a theory which identifies him with the king of Wa (Japan), San, one of the &apos;five kings of Wa&apos; which appear in &quot;Sungshu&quot; (Book of the Sung dynasty) of China (there are other theories which identify Emperor Ojin or Emperor Nintoku with San).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a theory which identifies him with the king of Wa (Japan), whose name was King San, one of the &apos;five kings of Wa&apos; which appear in &quot;So-jo&quot; (literally, Book of Song [one of the Nanbeichao or the Southern Dynasties of China]), (whereas other theories identify Emperor Ojin or Emperor Nintoku with King San).</e>
<cmt>曖昧さ回避、用語訂正（Sungは10-13世紀の王朝であり、「宋書」の「宋」は南北朝時代5－6世紀のもの）、言い回し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a theory which identifies him with the king of Wa (Japan), whose name was King San, one of the &apos;five kings of Wa&apos; which appear in &quot;So-jo&quot; (literally, Book of Song [one of the Nanbeichao or the Southern Dynasties of China]), (whereas other theories identify Emperor Ojin or Emperor Nintoku with King San).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また古事記には「壬申年正月三日」に64歳で崩ずとの記事が見え、これが正しければ、在位期間が427年から432年となり、生年が逆算して369年という事になるが、定かではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, in Kojiki (The Records of Ancient Matters), there is an article that he passed away in 432 at the age of 64 and, if this is correct, he was in the reign from 427 to 432 and, counting back, the year of his birth was, though uncertain, 369.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, an article in &quot;Kojiki&quot; (literally, The Records of Ancient Matters) shows that Emperor Richu passed away at the age of 64 &apos;on the third day of the New Year&apos;s in the year of Jinshin or Mizunoe-saru (according to the Chinese sexagenary cycle)&apos; (in 432), and if this is correct, he should have reigned from 427 to 432, and as a result of back calculation the year of his birth should be, though uncertain, 369.</e>
<cmt>曖昧さ回避、言い回し、形式</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, an article in &quot;Kojiki&quot; (literally, The Records of Ancient Matters) shows that Emperor Richu passed away at the age of 64 &apos;on the third day of the New Year&apos;s in the year of Jinshin or Mizunoe-saru (according to the Chinese sexagenary cycle)&apos; (in 432), and if this is correct, he should have reigned from 427 to 432, and as a result of back calculation the year of his birth should be, though uncertain, 369.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>名称</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>大兄去来穂別尊（おおえのいざほわけのみこと）- 『日本書紀』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oe no izahowake no mikoto, according to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oe no izahowake no mikoto, which was written as &quot;大兄去来穂別尊&quot; in Japanese, according to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (literally, Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>漢字表記補足、形式</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oe no izahowake no mikoto, which was written as &quot;大兄去来穂別尊&quot; in Japanese, according to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (literally, Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>大江之伊邪本和気命（おおえのいざほわけのみこと）- 『古事記』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oe no izahowake no mikoto (Chinese character are different from above), according to &quot;Kojiki.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oe no izahowake no mikoto, which was written as &quot;大江之伊邪本和気命&quot; in Japanese, according to the &quot;Kojiki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>漢字表記補足、形式</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oe no izahowake no mikoto, which was written as &quot;大江之伊邪本和気命&quot; in Japanese, according to the &quot;Kojiki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>大兄伊射報本和気命（おおえのいざほわけのみこと）- 『播磨国風土記』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oe no izahowake no mikoto (Chinese character are different from the two above), according to &quot;Harimanokuni Fudoki&quot; (Records of the Culture and Geography of the Harima Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oe no izahowake no mikoto, which was written as &quot;大兄伊射報本和気命&quot; in Japanese, according to &quot;Harimanokuni Fudoki&quot; (literally, Records of the Culture and Geography of the Harima Province).</e>
<cmt>漢字表記補足、引用符全角→半角、形式</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oe no izahowake no mikoto, which was written as &quot;大兄伊射報本和気命&quot; in Japanese, according to &quot;Harimanokuni Fudoki&quot; (literally, Records of the Culture and Geography of the Harima Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>系譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>仁徳天皇の第一皇子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the first Prince of Emperor Nintoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oe no izahowake no mikoto (the future Emperor Richu) was the firstborn son of Emperor Nintoku.</e>
<cmt>曖昧さ回避、言い回し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oe no izahowake no mikoto (the future Emperor Richu) was the firstborn son of Emperor Nintoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>母は葛城襲津彦の女・磐之媛（いわのひめ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was Iwanohime, a daughter of KATSURAGI no Sotsuhiko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was Iwanohime, a daughter of KATSURAGI no Sotsuhiko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was Iwanohime, a daughter of KATSURAGI no Sotsuhiko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>皇居</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Palace</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Palace</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Palace</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>都は磐余稚桜宮（いわれのわかざくらのみや、奈良県桜井市池之内に稚桜神社がある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The capital was Iware no wakazakura no miya (there is Wakazakura-jinja Shrine at Ikenouchi, Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was Iware no wakazakura no miya Palace in the capital (the name of the palace can be seen in Wakazakura-jinja Shrine at Ikenouchi, Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>解釈訂正（「都は」は「都の」という意味の古語的表現だと解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was Iware no wakazakura no miya Palace in the capital (the name of the palace can be seen in Wakazakura-jinja Shrine at Ikenouchi, Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background</e>
<cmt>統一用語</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>仁徳天皇87年1月（399年2月）、仁徳天皇崩御。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February of 399, Emperor Nintoku passed away.</e>
<cmt>月の数字は旧暦と思われますので、グレゴリオ歴に変換しました。以後も同様です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February, 399, Emperor Nintoku passed away.</e>
<cmt>当時の西暦はグレゴリオ暦ではなくユリウス暦への変換ですが、原文にも補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February, 399, Emperor Nintoku passed away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>住吉仲皇子が皇位を奪おうとして叛するが、弟の瑞歯別皇子（後の反正天皇）に命じてこれを誅殺させ、履中天皇元年2月（400年3月）に即位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though Prince Suminoe no nakatsu rose in rebellion in an attempt to seize the Imperial throne, he ordered his brother, Prince Mizuhawake (later Emperor Hanzei) to kill the rebel and acceded to the throne in March, 400.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Suminoe no nakatsu miko (or Suminoe naka no oji, the terms miko and oji refer to imperial prince) rebelled in an attempt to seize the Imperial throne, Oe no izahowake no mikoto ordered his younger brother, Mizuhawake (or Mitsuhawake) no miko (the future Emperor Hanzei) to kill the rebel and acceded to the throne in March, 400.</e>
<cmt>原文に西暦対応月を補足。曖昧さ回避、言い回し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Suminoe no nakatsu miko (or Suminoe naka no oji, the terms miko and oji refer to imperial prince) rebelled in an attempt to seize the Imperial throne, Oe no izahowake no mikoto ordered his younger brother, Mizuhawake (or Mitsuhawake) no miko (the future Emperor Hanzei) to kill the rebel and acceded to the throne in March, 400.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>2年（401年）、蘇我満智（まち）・物部伊莒弗（いこふつ）・平群木菟（つく）・葛城円（つぶらのおおおみ）らを国政に参画させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 401, he made Soga no machi, Ikofutsu of the Mononobe clan, Heguri no tsuku, Katsuragi no Tsubura, etc. to participate in national administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 401, Emperor Richu ordered Soga no machi, MONONOBE no Ikofutsu, HEGURI no Tsuku and KATSURAGI no Tsubura no o-omi to participate in governmental affairs.</e>
<cmt>曖昧さ回避、人名訂正、原文「物部氏」の「氏」はリンク先表示につき削除、言い回し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 401, Emperor Richu ordered Soga no machi, MONONOBE no Ikofutsu, HEGURI no Tsuku and KATSURAGI no Tsubura no o-omi to participate in governmental affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>4年8月（403年9月）、諸国に国史（ふみひと）と呼ばれる書記官を設置し、国内の情勢を報告させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September, 403, he placed secretaries called Fumihito in every provinces and let them report situations in the provinces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September, 403, the Emperor placed secretaries called Fumihito in every province and let them report situations in the provinces.</e>
<cmt>原文に対応西暦月補足。文法、曖昧さ回避</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September, 403, the Emperor placed secretaries called Fumihito in every province and let them report situations in the provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>6年正月（405年2月）に蔵職（くらのつかさ）と蔵部を興し（『古語拾遺』には内蔵を興すとある）、3月（405年4月）に病気のため稚桜宮で崩御した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February, 405, he founded Kura no tsukasa and Kurabe (treasury section) (according to &quot;Kogo-shui&quot; (History of the Inbe clan), Uchikura (Inner Treasury) was founded) but in April, he passed away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February, 405, the Emperor established the positions of Kura no tsukasa (the emperor&apos;s treasure keeper) and Kurabe (lower-level officials in charge of managing the gain and loss of imperial treasures), (where &quot;Kogo-shui&quot; [historical record of the Inbe clan] indicated that the Emperor founded Uchikura [treasury of the imperial household],) but in April he died of illness at the Wakazakura no miya Palace.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れに対応しました。。原文に対応西暦月補足。曖昧さ回避、用語、「内倉」訳語：http://www.google.co.jp/search?hl=ja&amp;q=Emperor+Richu,+uchikura&amp;aq=f&amp;aqi=&amp;aql=&amp;oq=&amp;gs_rfai=　「蔵部」参考：http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=%E8%94%B5%E9%83%A8&amp;dtype=0&amp;dname=0ss&amp;stype=0&amp;pagenum=1&amp;index=105580600000</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February, 405, the Emperor established the positions of Kura no tsukasa (the emperor&apos;s treasure keeper) and Kurabe (lower-level officials in charge of managing the gain and loss of imperial treasures), (where &quot;Kogo-shui&quot; [historical record of the Inbe clan] indicated that the Emperor founded Uchikura [treasury of the imperial household],) but in April he died of illness at the Wakazakura no miya Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>『書紀』に70歳、『古事記』に64歳、『神皇正統記』に67歳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At his demise, he was 70 years old (according to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot;), 64 years old (&quot;Kojiki&quot;), or 67 years old (&quot;Jinno Shotoki&quot; (A Chronicle of Gods and Sovereigns)).</e>
<cmt>「崩御の時」を足しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At his demise, he was either 70 years old (according to the &quot;Nihon shoki&quot;), 64 (&quot;Kojiki&quot;), or 67 (&quot;Jinno shotoki&quot; [literally, A Chronicle of Gods and Sovereigns]).</e>
<cmt>eitherを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At his demise, he was either 70 years old (according to the &quot;Nihon shoki&quot;), 64 (&quot;Kojiki&quot;), or 67 (&quot;Jinno shotoki&quot; [literally, A Chronicle of Gods and Sovereigns]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>即位前の試練</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hardship before Enthronement</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hardship before Enthronement</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hardship before Enthronement</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>古事記では、即位前に婚約者の黒媛と、大江之伊邪本和気命本人だと偽って通じた住吉仲皇子の反乱を受け、難波高津宮から石上神宮へ逃げている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Kojiki, before his enthronement, he escaped from Takatsu Palace to Isonokami-jingu Shrine upon rebellion of Prince Suminoe no nakatsu who had a relation with his fiancee, Kurohime (there are two theories; she is the daughter of Haneda no Yashiro no Sukune or of Ashita no Sukune. She died abruptly in 404 because of god&apos;s curse?).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Kojiki,&quot; before enthronement, Oe no izahowake no mikoto (the future Emperor Richu) escaped from Naniwa Kozu-gu Palace to Isonokami-jingu Shrine upon rebellion of Suminoe no nakatsu miko who, in the disguise of Oe, had deceived Oe&apos;s fiancee, Kurohime, and had intercourse with her.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処、高津宮の読み訂正、原文に「難波」補足（「高津宮」はwikiサイト上リンク先表示。時代考証上「難波高津宮」としました。）のうえ再訳しました津宮参考：http://www5a.biglobe.ne.jp/~kazu_san/syuto.html</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Kojiki,&quot; before enthronement, Oe no izahowake no mikoto (the future Emperor Richu) escaped from Naniwa Kozu-gu Palace to Isonokami-jingu Shrine upon rebellion of Suminoe no nakatsu miko who, in the disguise of Oe, had deceived Oe&apos;s fiancee, Kurohime, and had intercourse with her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>（黒媛とは、羽田矢代宿禰の娘、葦田宿禰の娘の2説があり、履中5年に神の祟りで急死したと言われるが定かでない。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Kurohime is considered to have been a daughter of either HATA no Yashiro no Sukune or ASHIDA no sukune, and she is believed to have died abruptly in 404, allegedly due to god&apos;s curse.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処、人名読み訂正、表現</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Kurohime is considered to have been a daughter of either HATA no Yashiro no Sukune or ASHIDA no sukune, and she is believed to have died abruptly in 404, allegedly due to god&apos;s curse.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>その途中、少女に会って、伏兵が居るので、遠回りしろと教えられ、石上神宮で以下の歌を詠んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the way of escape, he met a girl who told him that an ambush was laid and he should take an circuitous route, and, at Isonokami-jingu Shrine, he composed the following waka (a Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the way of escape, Oe no izahowake no mikoto met a girl who advised him to take an circuitous route to avoid ambush, and at Isonokami-jingu Shrine he composed the following waka (a Japanese poem consisting of thirty-one syllables).</e>
<cmt>曖昧さ回避、簡潔化、文法</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the way of escape, Oe no izahowake no mikoto met a girl who advised him to take an circuitous route to avoid ambush, and at Isonokami-jingu Shrine he composed the following waka (a Japanese poem consisting of thirty-one syllables).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="21">
<j>大坂に遇うや嬢子を道問へば　直には告らず　当岐麻路を告る（おおさかにあうやおとめをみちとへば　ただにはのらず　たぎまじをのる）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Osaka, when I met a girl whom I asked for direction, she told me not to go straight but to take the Tagima Route.</e>
<cmt>「定訳不明」：「当岐麻路」は「たぎま道」（Tagima Route) と解釈しました。（参考）ウェブ：www.h5.dion.ne.jp/~kaidou/takenouchi/takenouchi.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Osaka ni au ya otome o michi toeba tada niha norazu tagimaji o noru&quot; (In Osaka, when I met a girl whom I asked for directions, she did not show me a direct route but the Tagima-ji Route).</e>
<cmt>原文：後項の読み仮名を統合し、後項一列を削除しました。和歌原文の読み補足、簡潔化、文法</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Osaka ni au ya otome o michi toeba tada niha norazu tagimaji o noru&quot; (In Osaka, when I met a girl whom I asked for directions, she did not show me a direct route but the Tagima-ji Route).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="22">
<j>直とは直越えのこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here, going straight means taking a straight route.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Here, &quot;tada&quot; means a direct route.</e>
<cmt>和歌原文の日本語を反映して再訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Here, &quot;tada&quot; means a direct route.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>直越えとは、後世、生駒山を越える道（直越道）が有名であったが、埴生坂（羽曳野丘陵）から越えようとしているので、現在の穴虫峠付近と考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for going straight, a route to get over Mt. Ikoma (the straight route) became popular in later years, but because he was trying to get over from Hanyu Pass (Habikino City), the route is thought to be somewhere around the present-day Anamushi Pass.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The direct route refers to, in later years, a famous route to cross Mt. Ikoma (Tadagoe no michi Route), but in the case of Oe no izahowake no mikoto, as he was trying to go over the mountain via the Hanyu-zaka Pass (Habikino Hills), the route is thought to be somewhere around the present-day Anamushi-toge Pass.</e>
<cmt>羽曳野「市」はリンク先表示、正しくは「丘陵」→原文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The direct route refers to, in later years, a famous route to cross Mt. Ikoma (Tadagoe no michi Route), but in the case of Oe no izahowake no mikoto, as he was trying to go over the mountain via the Hanyu-zaka Pass (Habikino Hills), the route is thought to be somewhere around the present-day Anamushi-toge Pass.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>穴虫峠の手前で出会った乙女に道を聞いたのだが、簡単に越えられるはずの直越え（穴虫峠）ではなく、遠くて、標高も高い竹之内峠越えをしろと教えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He met a girl in front of Anamushi Pass and he asked her his way, whereupon she taught him to get over Takenouchi Road, which is far and has higher altitude, rather than the straight pass (Anamushi Pass), which is easy to get over.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He met a girl in front of the Anamushi-toge Pass and asked her his way, and she taught him to get over the Takenouchi-toge Pass, which was far and located high above sea level, rather than the easier direct pass (Anamushi-toge Pass).</e>
<cmt>原文リンク先表示修正（竹之内街道）、形式、言い回し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He met a girl in front of the Anamushi-toge Pass and asked her his way, and she taught him to get over the Takenouchi-toge Pass, which was far and located high above sea level, rather than the easier direct pass (Anamushi-toge Pass).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="25">
<j>穴虫峠（二上山の北）は標高約150ｍに対して、竹之内峠（二上山の南）は標高約300ｍ、しかも数km南に遠い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Compared to Anamushi Pass (north of Mt. Nijo) with altitude of about 150m, the Takenouchi Pass (south of Mt. Nijo) has altitude of about 300m and, moreover, the latter is farther to the south by several kilometers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Compared to the Anamushi-toge Pass (north of Mt. Nijo or Futakamiyama) at an altitude of about 150 meters, the Takenouchi-toge Pass (south of Mt. Nijo) was at an altitude of about 300 meters and moreover, the latter is farther to the south by several kilometers).</e>
<cmt>言い回し、形式を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Compared to the Anamushi-toge Pass (north of Mt. Nijo or Futakamiyama) at an altitude of about 150 meters, the Takenouchi-toge Pass (south of Mt. Nijo) was at an altitude of about 300 meters and moreover, the latter is farther to the south by several kilometers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>逃げ込もうとしていた石上神宮は両峠の北東方向にあるのだから、回り道は２倍以上になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ishinokami-jingu Shrine in which he was trying to take sanctuary is located north east of the two passes and, therefore, the detour distance is twice the straight pass.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Isonokami-jingu Shrine in which he was trying to take sanctuary is located north east of the two passes, and therefore, the detour distance is twice the distance of the direct pass.</e>
<cmt>石上の読み訂正しました。形式</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Isonokami-jingu Shrine in which he was trying to take sanctuary is located north east of the two passes, and therefore, the detour distance is twice the distance of the direct pass.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>住吉仲皇子反乱の襲撃を受けたとき、難波宮で酒に酔って寝ており、部下に馬にやっと乗せて貰ったくらいだから、恐らく二日酔いで、反乱に驚いていた身には堪えたであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he was attacked by the rebellion of Prince Suminoe no nakatsu, he was sleeping drunk and, because he could barely mount on the horse with the help of his subordinate, he must have had a hangover which must have tormented him, together with the shock of the rebellion.</e>
<cmt>「二日酔いで、反乱に驚いていた身には堪えたであろう」は、意味が分かりにくいので、「二日酔いは、反乱とともに彼を苦しめたであろう」と解釈して訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When attacked by troops of rebellious Suminoe no nakatsu miko, Oe was sleeping drunk at the Naniwa no miya Palace and because he could barely mount on the horse with the help of his subordinate, he must have had a hangover which tormented him, together with the shock of the rebellion.</e>
<cmt>言い回し、形式を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When attacked by troops of rebellious Suminoe no nakatsu miko, Oe was sleeping drunk at the Naniwa no miya Palace and because he could barely mount on the horse with the help of his subordinate, he must have had a hangover which tormented him, together with the shock of the rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>これは、まさに王権を受け継ぐための試練であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was really a hardship he had to go through before inheriting the sovereignty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was really a hardship he had to go through before inheriting the sovereignty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was really a hardship he had to go through before inheriting the sovereignty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="29">
<j>（出典例：古事記歌謡　大久保正　昭和56年７月10日　講談社　Ｐ174）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Reference (for example); Songs in Kojiki, Tadashi OKUBO, July 10, 1981, Kodansha, p174)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Reference example: songs in the &quot;Kojiki,&quot; Tadashi OKUBO, July 10, 1981, Kodansha, p.174)</e>
<cmt>形式を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Reference example: songs in the &quot;Kojiki,&quot; Tadashi OKUBO, July 10, 1981, Kodansha, p.174)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="30">
<j>陵墓・霊廟</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Mausoleum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Tomb and Mausoleum</e>
<cmt>用語</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Tomb and Mausoleum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="31">
<j>百舌鳥耳原南陵（もずのみみはらのみなみのみささぎ）に葬られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was entombed in Mozu no mimihara no minami no misasagi (mausoleum).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was entombed in Mozu no mimihara no minami no misasagi (mausoleum).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was entombed in Mozu no mimihara no minami no misasagi (mausoleum).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>大阪府堺市石津ヶ丘町にある上石津ミサンザイ古墳（前方後円墳・全長365m）に比定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is identified with Kami-ishizu misanzai kofun (tumulus) (a large keyhole-shaped tumulus; total length, 365 m) located at Ishizuga-oka Town, Sakai City, Osaka Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>「読み方不明」：「上石津」は「かみいしづ」と読みました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is identified with Kami-ishizu misanzai-kofun Tumulus (a keyhole-shaped tumulus with total length of 365 meters) located at Ishizugaoka-cho Town, Sakai City, Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>言い回し、形式を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is identified with Kami-ishizu misanzai-kofun Tumulus (a keyhole-shaped tumulus with total length of 365 meters) located at Ishizugaoka-cho Town, Sakai City, Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MD242(id:11277), JAnDbot(id:66507), 霧木諒二(id:9795), Nnh(id:474), ノトス(id:42992), MIsogi(id:20599), Reggaeman(id:6214), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), 行動で挽回するしかない(id:31799), Geyogeyo(id:35444), 代言人(id:33675), 海行かば(id:115823), 名無し(id:7386), Chobot(id:20846), Loveless(id:129239), タケル(id:10666), Higashi(id:8842), Stanislaus(id:1806), Hvn0413(id:38818), Law soma(id:45202), Nallimbot(id:230812), Robbot(id:3063), Sh(id:2707), Zwobot(id:23873), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), MDR-SK(id:192066), Nidarin(id:6420), かえるちゃん(id:197260), YurikBot(id:18605), SuisuiBot(id:10165), 平惣衛門(id:99387), YOSHI438(id:174755), LeonardoRob0t(id:25875), Jade0416(id:104181), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>