<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>紀元節</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Empire Day (Kigensetsu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Empire Day (Kigensetsu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Empire Day (Kigensetsu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>紀元節（きげんせつ）は、『日本書紀』が伝える神武天皇の即位日として定めた祝日。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Empire Day was established as a national holiday on which, according to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), Emperor Jimmu ascended the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Empire Day was established as a national holiday on which, according to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), Emperor Jinmu ascended the throne.</e>
<cmt>Jimmu→Jinmu冠詞を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Empire Day was established as a national holiday on which, according to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), Emperor Jinmu ascended the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>1873年（明治6年）に、2月11日と定められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was established in February 11, 1873.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1873 it was designated to be celebrated on February 11.</e>
<cmt>「２月１１日に定めた」のでなく、「２月１１日と定められた」と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1873 it was designated to be celebrated on February 11.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>かつての祝祭日の中の四大節の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among public holidays it was formerly one of the four major festivals (shidaisetsu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was formerly one of the four major festivals (shidaisetsu).</e>
<cmt>原文にはないので冒頭を削除。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was formerly one of the four major festivals (shidaisetsu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>紀元節の制定まで</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the establishment of Empire Day</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the Establishment of National Foundation Day</e>
<cmt>タイトルなので大文字を使いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the Establishment of National Foundation Day</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>8世紀初めに編まれた『日本書紀』によれば、神武天皇の即位日は「辛酉年春正月、庚辰朔」であり、日付は正月朔日、すなわち1月1日となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot;, which was compiled at the beginning of the eighth century, the accession of Emperor Jimmu was &quot;in the year Kanoto-Tori, spring, first month, on the day Kanoe-Tatsu, the first day&quot;, the date is the first day of the first (lunar) month, that is the first of January.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; which was compiled at the beginning of the eighth century, the accession of Emperor Jinmu was on &apos;the first day of the first spring month of the year Kanoto-Tori,&apos; that is, the first of January.</e>
<cmt>コンマを移動しました。分かりやすく簡潔な表現に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; which was compiled at the beginning of the eighth century, the accession of Emperor Jinmu was on &apos;the first day of the first spring month of the year Kanoto-Tori,&apos; that is, the first of January.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>しかし、明治5年（1872年）11月15日、明治政府は神武天皇の即位をもって「紀元」と定め（明治5年太政官布告第342号）、同日には「第一月廿九日」（1月29日）を神武天皇即位の相当日として祝日にすることを定めた（明治5年太政官布告第344号）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But on November 15, 1872 the Meiji Government designated the accession of Emperor Jimmu as the beginning of the Japanese era (kigen) (Proclamation no.342 of the Grand Council of State, 1872) and on the same day declared January 29 a national holiday corresponding to the accession day of Emperor Jimmu (Proclamation no.344 of the Grand Council of State, 1872).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But on November 15, 1872 the Meiji Government designated the accession of Emperor Jinmu as the beginning of the &apos;Japanese era&apos; (kigen) (Proclamation no. 342 of the Grand Council of State, 1872) and on the same day declared &apos;January 29&apos; a national holiday corresponding to the accession day of Emperor Jinmu (Proclamation no. 344 of the Grand Council of State, 1872).</e>
<cmt>Jimmu→Jinmu“no.”の後にスペースを進入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But on November 15, 1872 the Meiji Government designated the accession of Emperor Jinmu as the beginning of the &apos;Japanese era&apos; (kigen) (Proclamation no. 342 of the Grand Council of State, 1872) and on the same day declared &apos;January 29&apos; a national holiday corresponding to the accession day of Emperor Jinmu (Proclamation no. 344 of the Grand Council of State, 1872).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>この1月29日とは、1873年（明治6年）の旧暦1月1日 (旧暦)をそのまま新暦に置き換えた日付である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This January 29 corresponds to January 1, 1873 of the old calendar, as the date was changed unaltered from the old lunar calendar to the new Gregorian calendar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 29 is the date on the Gregorian calendar in 1873 which corresponds to January 1 of the old lunar calendar.</e>
<cmt>簡潔な表現に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 29 is the date on the Gregorian calendar in 1873 which corresponds to January 1 of the old lunar calendar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>折柄、明治5年12月3日をもって1873年（明治6年）1月1日とし、新暦が施行されることになっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At just that time the Gregorian calendar became effective, December 3, 1872 became January 1, 1873.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Gregorian calendar was to become effective around that time, with December 3, 1872 becoming January 1, 1873.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Gregorian calendar was to become effective around that time, with December 3, 1872 becoming January 1, 1873.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>1873年（明治6年）1月29日、神武天皇即位日を祝って、神武天皇御陵遙拝式が各地で行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 29, 1873 the accession of Emperor Jimmu was celebrated across the country by offering prayers to the Imperial Mausoleum of Emperor Jimmu from a distance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 29, 1873 the accession of Emperor Jinmu was celebrated across the country by people offering prayers remotely to the Imperial Mausoleum of Emperor Jinmu.</e>
<cmt>簡潔な表現に修正しました。Jimmu→Jinmu</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 29, 1873 the accession of Emperor Jinmu was celebrated across the country by people offering prayers remotely to the Imperial Mausoleum of Emperor Jinmu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>同年3月7日には、神武天皇即位日を「紀元節」と称することを定めた（明治6年太政官布告第91号）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year on July, 3 it was decided to name the accession day of Emperor Jimmu &quot;Kigensetsu&quot;, time of the beginning of the Japanese era (Proclamation no.91 of the Grand Council of State, 1873).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 7 of the same year it was decided to name the accession day of Emperor Jimmu &apos;Kigensetsu,&apos; time of the beginning of the Japanese era (Proclamation no. 91 of the Grand Council of State, 1873).</e>
<cmt>日付を修正しました。コンマを移動しました。Jimmu→Jinmu“no.”の後にスペースを進入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 7 of the same year it was decided to name the accession day of Emperor Jimmu &apos;Kigensetsu,&apos; time of the beginning of the Japanese era (Proclamation no. 91 of the Grand Council of State, 1873).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>なお、同年1月には、神武天皇即位日と天長節（天皇誕生日）を祝日とする布告を出している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January in the same year the accession day of Emperor Jimmu and the birthday of the reigning emperor (tencho setsu) were declared as national holidays.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January in the same year the accession day of Emperor Jimmu and the birthday of the reigning emperor (tencho setsu) were declared as national holidays.</e>
<cmt>Jimmu→Jinmu</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January in the same year the accession day of Emperor Jimmu and the birthday of the reigning emperor (tencho setsu) were declared as national holidays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>ところで、これらの太政官布告に先立って、1872年（明治5年）11月9日に出されていた太陽暦を施行する旨の太政官布告では、祭典等の日付は、旧暦の月日を新暦の月日として施行するものと定めていた（明治5年太政官布告第337号）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But before those proclamations of the Grand Council of State there was another proclamation on November 9, 1872 to adopt the solar calendar and it was decided that the days of the festivals on the lunar calendar are to be enforced on the same dates on the solar calendar (Proclamation no.337 of the Grand Council of State, 1872).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prior to these proclamations of the Grand Council of State there had been another proclamation on November 9, 1872 to adopt the solar calendar, and it was decided that festival dates from the old lunar calendar would be transferred to the same dates on the solar calendar (Proclamation no. 337 of the Grand Council of State, 1872).</e>
<cmt>“no.”の後にスペースを進入しました。“But”は不適切なので削除しました。“Those”→”these”読みやすいよう修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prior to these proclamations of the Grand Council of State there had been another proclamation on November 9, 1872 to adopt the solar calendar, and it was decided that festival dates from the old lunar calendar would be transferred to the same dates on the solar calendar (Proclamation no. 337 of the Grand Council of State, 1872).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>これは、祭典の執行日を新暦で固定し、毎年旧暦の月日から新暦の月日に換算する煩雑さを避けるための規定である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That means, the days of festivals were fixed on the new calendar to avoid the complexity of converting the dates from the old calendar to the new calendar every year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This rule was implemented in order to fix the festival dates on the new calendar, so that the complexity of converting the dates of the old lunar calendar to the new calendar each year could be avoided.</e>
<cmt>原文に忠実になるよう修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This rule was implemented in order to fix the festival dates on the new calendar, so that the complexity of converting the dates of the old lunar calendar to the new calendar each year could be avoided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>例えば、例年1月1日に新年を祝って行われる歳旦祭は、旧暦1月1日の新暦相当日ではなく新暦1月1日に行うということになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, &quot;Saitansai&quot;, which is celebrated every year on the first of January to celebrate the New Year is not celebrated on the new calendar corresponding to the first of January of the old calendar but on the first of January on the new calendar.</e>
<cmt>Left out explanation of Saitansai, as it is not relevant here.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, Saitansai, a Shinto festival held on January 1 each year to celebrate the new year, would be held on January 1 of the new calendar, not on the date that January 1 of the old lunar calendar would be converted to.</e>
<cmt>コンマを移動しました。分かりやすく簡潔な表現に修正しました。歳旦祭の説明を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, Saitansai, a Shinto festival held on January 1 each year to celebrate the new year, would be held on January 1 of the new calendar, not on the date that January 1 of the old lunar calendar would be converted to.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="14">
<j>この規定の影響などもあって、紀元節は旧暦1月1日、すなわち旧正月を祝う祝日との誤解が国民のあいだに広まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the effects of this regulation was, that more and more people misunderstood Kigensetsu, which was on January first of the old calendar, as a national holiday which celebrates the lunar New Year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many people misunderstood Kigensetsu as a national holiday to celebrate January 1 of the old lunar calendar, or the lunar New Year, partly due to this regulation.</e>
<cmt>不要なコンマを削除しました。原文に忠実になるよう修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many people misunderstood Kigensetsu as a national holiday to celebrate January 1 of the old lunar calendar, or the lunar New Year, partly due to this regulation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>国民のこの反応を見て政府は、紀元節は神武天皇即位日を祝う祝日であるという理解が広まらないのではないかと考えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The government saw the reaction of the people and wondered, if maybe it is not commonly known that Kigensetsu is the day to celebrate the accession of Emperor Jimmu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The government saw the reaction of the people and thought that it would be difficult to have people understand that Kigensetsu was a day to celebrate the accession of Emperor Jinmu.</e>
<cmt>原文に忠実になるよう修正しました。Jimmu→Jinmu</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The government saw the reaction of the people and thought that it would be difficult to have people understand that Kigensetsu was a day to celebrate the accession of Emperor Jinmu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また、1月29日では、孝明天皇の命日（1867年1月30日、孝明天皇祭）と前後するため、不都合でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, it was also inconvenient that January 29 was just one day before the death anniversary of Emperor Komei (January 30, 1867 Komei Tenno Sai)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, it was inconvenient that January 29 was just one day before the death anniversary of Emperor Komei (January 30, 1867 Komei Tenno Sai).</e>
<cmt>Besidesとalso両方は不要なので修正しました。ピリオドを進入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides, it was inconvenient that January 29 was just one day before the death anniversary of Emperor Komei (January 30, 1867 Komei Tenno Sai).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="17">
<j>そこで、政府は、1873年（明治6年）10月14日、新たに神武天皇即位日を定め直し、2月11日を紀元節とした（明治6年太政官布告第344号）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore on October 14, 1973 the government decided anew the accession day of Emperor Jimmu and designated February 11 as Kigensetsu (Emperor Day) (Proclamation no.344 of the Grand Council of State, 1873).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore on October 14, 1973 the government re-designated the accession day of Emperor Jinmu, selecting February 11 as Kigensetsu (Proclamation no. 344 of the Grand Council of State, 1873).</e>
<cmt>Jimmu→Jinmu“no.”の後にスペースを進入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore on October 14, 1973 the government re-designated the accession day of Emperor Jinmu, selecting February 11 as Kigensetsu (Proclamation no. 344 of the Grand Council of State, 1873).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="18">
<j>2月11日という日付は、文部省天文局が算出し、暦学者の塚本明毅が審査して決定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 11 was decided after it was calculated by the Ministry of Education, bureau of astronomy and then examined by Akitake TSUKAMOTO, scholar of calendar making.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 11 was selected after it was calculated by the Ministry of Education&apos;s Bureau of Astronomy and examined by Akitake TSUKAMOTO, scholar of calendar making.</e>
<cmt>固有名詞の大文字を直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 11 was selected after it was calculated by the Ministry of Education&apos;s Bureau of Astronomy and examined by Akitake TSUKAMOTO, scholar of calendar making.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>その具体的な計算方法は明らかにされていないが、当時の説明では「干支に相より簡法相立て」としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though the concrete calculation method was not disclosed, the explanation at that time was &quot;it was done by a simple method according to the sexagenary cycle&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though the concrete calculation method was not disclosed, the explanation at that time was it was done &apos;by a simple method according to the Oriental zodiac cycle.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを移動しました。Sexagenaryよりoriental zodiacの方が一般的に分かりやすいので変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though the concrete calculation method was not disclosed, the explanation at that time was it was done &apos;by a simple method according to the Oriental zodiac cycle.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="20">
<j>実際、干支は暦法に依存せずに60の周期で単純に繰り返すので簡易に計算できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, the sexagenary cycle doesn&apos;t depend on calendar making but it is possible to simply calculate by just repeating a cycle of 60.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, since the Oriental zodiac cycle just repeats itself in cycles of 60 days without associating itself to any calendar, the calculation is very simple.</e>
<cmt>Sexagenaryよりoriental zodiacの方が一般的に分かりやすいので変更しました。簡潔な表現に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, since the Oriental zodiac cycle just repeats itself in cycles of 60 days without associating itself to any calendar, the calculation is very simple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>神武天皇の即位年の「辛酉年」は『日本書紀』の編年（720年（養老4年）に成立）を元に計算すると西暦紀元前660年に相当し、即位月は「春正月」であることから立春の前後であり、即位日の干支は「庚辰」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The year of the accession of Emperor Jimmu &quot;Kanoto-Tori&quot; was calculated as being 660 B.C.E. based on the chronicle of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (compiled 720), &quot;spring, first month&quot; means it was sometime around the first day of spring (risshun), the cyclical sign of the day is &quot;Kanoe-Tatsu&quot;(yang-metal-dragon).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year of the accession of Emperor Jinmu, &apos;Kanoto-Tori,&apos; was calculated as being 660 B.C. based on &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (compiled 720), the month being the &apos;first spring month&apos; meant it was sometime around the beginning of spring, and the Oriental zodiac sign of the date was &apos;Kanoe-Tatsu,&apos; or the 17th day of the 60-day cycle.</e>
<cmt>読みやすいよう理解に不要な日本語は削除しました。Jimmu→Jinmu</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year of the accession of Emperor Jinmu, &apos;Kanoto-Tori,&apos; was calculated as being 660 B.C. based on &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (compiled 720), the month being the &apos;first spring month&apos; meant it was sometime around the beginning of spring, and the Oriental zodiac sign of the date was &apos;Kanoe-Tatsu,&apos; or the 17th day of the 60-day cycle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>そこで西暦紀元前660年の立春に最も近い庚辰の日を探すと新暦2月11日が特定される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 11 was designated by looking for a day of &quot;Kanoe-Tatsu&quot; which was closest to the first day of spring in 660 B.C.E.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 11 was designated by looking for a day of Kanoe-Tatsu which was closest to the first day of spring in 660 B.C.</e>
<cmt>B.C.E.→B.C.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 11 was designated by looking for a day of Kanoe-Tatsu which was closest to the first day of spring in 660 B.C.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>その前後では前年12月20日と同年4月19日も庚辰の日であるが、これらは「春正月」になり得ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around that date there were two other days of &quot;Kanoe-Tatsu&quot;, one in the year before on December 20 and one in the same year on April 19, but both days couldn&apos;t be considered as spring, first month.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The two Kanoe-Tatsu before and after this date fell on December 20 of the previous year and April 19 of the same year, but neither could be considered &apos;the first spring month.&apos;</e>
<cmt>簡潔な表現に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The two Kanoe-Tatsu before and after this date fell on December 20 of the previous year and April 19 of the same year, but neither could be considered &apos;the first spring month.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>したがって、「辛酉年春正月庚辰」は紀元前660年2月11日以外には考えられない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore &quot;in the year &quot;Kanoto-Tori&quot;, spring, first month, on the day &quot; Kanoe-Tatsu&quot;, the first day&quot; is only possible on February 11, 660 B.C.E..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, no date other than February 11, 660 B.C. Could be considered &apos;the first day of the first spring month of the year Kanoto-Tori.&apos;.</e>
<cmt>簡潔な表現に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, no date other than February 11, 660 B.C. Could be considered &apos;the first day of the first spring month of the year Kanoto-Tori.&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>なお、『日本書紀』はこの日が「朔」、すなわち新月の日であったとも記載しているが、朔は暦法に依存しており「簡法」では計算できないので、明治政府による計算では考慮されなかったと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; also states this day as &quot;tsuitachi&quot;, first day of the month and also as day of the new moon, but the first day of a month depends on calendar making and cannot be calculated by a &quot;simple method&quot;, it is likely that the Meiji Government didn&apos;t consider about it in their calculation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; also states this day was &apos;tsuitachi&apos; or a day of the new moon, but as this relies on calendar rules and could not be calculated by the &apos;simple method&apos; employed, it is likely that the Meiji Government didn&apos;t consider it in their calculations.</e>
<cmt>Consider “about”は間違いなので直しました。理解に不要な日本語を削除し簡潔な表現に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; also states this day was &apos;tsuitachi&apos; or a day of the new moon, but as this relies on calendar rules and could not be calculated by the &apos;simple method&apos; employed, it is likely that the Meiji Government didn&apos;t consider it in their calculations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>また、現代の天文知識に基づき当時の月齢を計算すると、この日は天文上の朔に当たるが、これは天文上の朔にあわせるため、庚辰の日を即位日としたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Calculating the age of the moon at that time with the knowledge of astronomy today, this day falls on a new moon day, astronomically. It is considered that the day Kanoe-Tatsu was chosen as accession day in order to match it with the astronomical new moon day.</e>
<cmt>Strangely, Wikipedia&apos;s article used to say:余談であるが、現代の天文知識に基づき当時の月齢を計算すると、偶然ながらこの日は天文上の朔に当たる</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, when the moon cycle of the time is calculated based on current knowledge of astronomy this day falls on am astronomical new moon; it is thought that Kanoe-Tatsu was chosen for the accession in order to match it with the new moon.</e>
<cmt>一文にまとめました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, when the moon cycle of the time is calculated based on current knowledge of astronomy this day falls on am astronomical new moon; it is thought that Kanoe-Tatsu was chosen for the accession in order to match it with the new moon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>制定後から「建国記念の日」に変わるまで</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Empire Day to National Foundation Day</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Establishment to &apos;National Foundation Day&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文に忠実になるよう修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Establishment to &apos;National Foundation Day&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="27">
<j>紀元節には、宮中皇霊殿で天皇親祭の祭儀が行われ、各地で神武天皇陵の遙拝式も行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On Empire Day rites were conducted by the emperor in the Ancestral Spirits Sanctuary of the Imperial Palace and ceremonies to pray to the Imperial Mausoleum of Emperor Jimmu from a distance, were also held across the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On Empire Day rites were conducted by the emperor in the Ancestral Spirits Sanctuary of the Imperial Palace and ceremonies to remotely pray to the Imperial Mausoleum of Emperor Jinmu were also held across the country.</e>
<cmt>Jimmu→Jinmu</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On Empire Day rites were conducted by the emperor in the Ancestral Spirits Sanctuary of the Imperial Palace and ceremonies to remotely pray to the Imperial Mausoleum of Emperor Jinmu were also held across the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>1889年（明治22年）には、この日を期して大日本帝国憲法が発布され、これ以降、憲法発布を記念する日にもなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1889 the day was chosen to proclaim the Constitution of the Empire of Japan and since then it also became the day to commemorate the promulgation of the constitution.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1889 the day was chosen to proclaim the Constitution of the Empire of Japan and since then it has become the day to commemorate the promulgation of the constitution.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1889 the day was chosen to proclaim the Constitution of the Empire of Japan and since then it has become the day to commemorate the promulgation of the constitution.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>1891年（明治24年）には小学校祝日大祭儀式規程（明治24年6月17日文部省令第4号）が定められ、天皇皇后の御真影（写真）に対する最敬礼と万歳奉祝、校長による教育勅語の奉読などからなる儀式を小学校で行うことになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1891 Regulations for Elementary School Ceremonies on Festivals and Holidays were issued (Order of the Ministry of Education No 4 June, 17, 1891) and thus ceremonies at elementary schools were held with acts like making a deep bow in front of the portrait (picture) of the Emperor and the Empress, shouting &quot;banzai&quot; to wish for their long life and a reading of the Imperial Rescript on Education in a respectful way by the principal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1891 Regulations for Elementary School Ceremonies on Festivals and Holidays were issued (Order of the Ministry of Education no. 4, June 17, 1891) and thus ceremonies at elementary schools were held with acts like making a deep bow in front of a portrait (picture) of the Emperor and the Empress, shouting &quot;banzai&quot; to wish for their long life and a reading of the Imperial Rescript on Education in a respectful manner by the principal.</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースを削除しました。日付を修正しました。Noを他の箇所と一致するよう修正しました。冠詞を直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1891 Regulations for Elementary School Ceremonies on Festivals and Holidays were issued (Order of the Ministry of Education no. 4, June 17, 1891) and thus ceremonies at elementary schools were held with acts like making a deep bow in front of a portrait (picture) of the Emperor and the Empress, shouting &quot;banzai&quot; to wish for their long life and a reading of the Imperial Rescript on Education in a respectful manner by the principal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>1914年（大正3年）からは全国の神社で紀元節祭を行うこととなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After 1914 Empire Day was celebrated in shrines all over the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After 1914 Empire Day was celebrated in shrines all over the country.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After 1914 Empire Day was celebrated in shrines all over the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>1926年（大正15年）からは青年団や在郷軍人会などを中心とした建国祭の式典が各地で開催されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From 1926 on National Foundation Festivals were held across the country with young men&apos;s associations and veteran&apos;s associations at the core.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 1926 National Foundation Festivals were held across the country, centered around young men&apos;s associations and veterans&apos; associations at the core.</e>
<cmt>Onを削除しました。文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 1926 National Foundation Festivals were held across the country, centered around young men&apos;s associations and veterans&apos; associations at the core.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="32">
<j>第二次世界大戦後の1947年（昭和22年）、片山哲内閣により、日本国憲法にふさわしい祝日の法案に紀元節が「建国の日」として盛り込まれていたが、連合国軍最高司令官総司令部により削除され、法は1948年（昭和23年）7月に施行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the World War II in 1947 the cabinet of Tetsu KATAYAMA proposed a bill on public holidays appropriate to the constitution of Japan including Empire Day as &quot;Foundation Day&quot; (kenkoku no hi), but this was dismissed by the General Headquarters of the Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers and the law came into effect in July 1948.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After World War II in 1947 the cabinet of Tetsu KATAYAMA proposed a bill on public holidays appropriate to the constitution of Japan including Empire Day as &quot;Foundation Day&quot; (kenkoku no hi), but this was dismissed by the General Headquarters of the Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers and the law came into effect in July 1948.</e>
<cmt>冠詞を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After World War II in 1947 the cabinet of Tetsu KATAYAMA proposed a bill on public holidays appropriate to the constitution of Japan including Empire Day as &quot;Foundation Day&quot; (kenkoku no hi), but this was dismissed by the General Headquarters of the Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers and the law came into effect in July 1948.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>日本独立の1952年（昭和27年）から復活運動がおき、1958年（昭和33年）に国会への議案提出があり、1966年（昭和41年）に国民の祝日に関する法律が改正され、さらに佐藤栄作内閣によりs建国記念の日となる日を定める政令（昭和41年政令第376号）として再制定され、1967年（昭和42年）2月11日建国記念の日として実施された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the independence of Japan in 1952 revival movements occurred, in 1958 a bill was submitted to the Parliament, in 1966 the Public Holiday Law was revised, then the cabinet of Eisaku SATO issued a cabinet order (cabinet order no.376, 1966) to re-establish the day as National Foundation Day (Kenkoku Kinen no Hi), which was enforced on February 11, 1967.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A movement to revive the holiday started with the independence of Japan in 1952 – in 1958 a bill was submitted to Parliament, in 1966 the Public Holiday Law was revised, then the cabinet of Eisaku SATO issued a cabinet order (cabinet order no. 376, 1966) to re-establish the day as National Foundation Day (Kenkoku Kinen no Hi), which was enforced on February 11, 1967.</e>
<cmt>原文に不要な字があります。“no.”の後にスペースを進入しました。Movementの使用を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A movement to revive the holiday started with the independence of Japan in 1952 – in 1958 a bill was submitted to Parliament, in 1966 the Public Holiday Law was revised, then the cabinet of Eisaku SATO issued a cabinet order (cabinet order no. 376, 1966) to re-establish the day as National Foundation Day (Kenkoku Kinen no Hi), which was enforced on February 11, 1967.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>歌曲「紀元節」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Song: Kigensetsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Song: &apos;Kigensetsu&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の同じように引用府を使いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Song: &apos;Kigensetsu&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>伊沢修二作曲、高崎正風作詞により1888年に発表され、「小学唱歌」にも掲載された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Composed by Shuji IZAWA, lyrics by Masakaze TAKASAKI, published in 1888. They also published &quot;Shogaku Shoka&quot; (elementary school song).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Released in 1888 with music by Shuji IZAWA and lyrics by Masakaze TAKASAKI, also published in &apos;Shogaku Shoka&apos; (elementary school songs).</e>
<cmt>一文にまとめました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Released in 1888 with music by Shuji IZAWA and lyrics by Masakaze TAKASAKI, also published in &apos;Shogaku Shoka&apos; (elementary school songs).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>歌詞はを参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lyrics see</e>
<cmt>word is missing</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For lyrics refer to &quot;.&quot;</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For lyrics refer to &quot;.&quot;</e>
<cmt>“ ”→&quot;&quot;にしました。Webにはこの部分はなく、何を参照なのか不明のため、&quot;&quot;の部分は空白にしております。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Izayohi(id:13095), Nnh(id:474), MIsogi(id:20599), Stanislaus(id:1806), Chinamie(id:213556), 松茸(id:27535), 俊平太郎(id:34056), LiDaobing(id:14511), ごまふあざ(id:36855), Pattio(id:59449), 寒漁夫(id:99134), Johncapistrano(id:969), Kurz(id:1601), PPP(id:22924), Villeneuve1982(id:22620), DLAD(id:242635), Ns57re(id:169493), 伏儀(id:142093), Inori(id:90350), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>