<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>兼明親王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Kaneakira</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Kaneakira</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Kaneakira</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>兼明親王（かねあきらしんのう、延喜14年（914年） - 永延元年（987年））は平安時代の皇族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Kaneakira (914 ~ 987) was a member of the Iimperial Family of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Kaneakira (914 ~ 987) was a member of the Iimperial Family during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Kaneakira (914 - 987) was a member of the Imperial Family during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>~→-スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>醍醐天皇の第十六皇子で母は藤原菅根の娘藤原淑姫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is the 16th prince of the Emperor Daigo, and his mother is FUJIWARA no Yoshihime, a daughter of FUJIWARA no Sugane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is the 16th prince of the Emperor Daigo, and his mother is FUJIWARA no Yoshihime, a daughter of FUJIWARA no Sugane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is the 16th prince of the Emperor Daigo, and his mother is FUJIWARA no Yoshihime, a daughter of FUJIWARA no Sugane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>朱雀天皇、村上天皇、源高明の異母兄弟。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is a half brother of the Emperor Suzaku, the Emperor Murakami and MINAMOTO no Takaakira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is a half brother of the Emperor Suzaku, the Emperor Murakami and MINAMOTO no Takaakira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is a half brother of the Emperor Suzaku, the Emperor Murakami and MINAMOTO no Takaakira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>一時期臣籍降下して、源 兼明（みなもと の かねあきら）と名乗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once he departed from the Imperial Family member and became an allegiant, named MINAMOTO no Kaneakira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once he departed from the Imperial Family and became an allegiant, named MINAMOTO no Kaneakira.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once he departed from the Imperial Family and became an allegiant, named MINAMOTO no Kaneakira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>博学多才で前中書王と呼ばれ甥の後中書王・具平親王と共にに並び称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a of person of varied attainments and called Saki no Chusho O (originally, the the name of the head of a ministry) and admired together with his nephew Nochi no Chusho O, Imperial Prince Tomohira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a of person of varied attainments and called Saki no Chusho O (originally, the the name as the head of a ministry) and was admired together with his nephew Nochi no Chusho O, Imperial Prince Tomohira.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a of person of varied attainments and called Saki no Chusho O (originally, the name as the head of a ministry) and was admired together with his nephew Nochi no Chusho O, Imperial Prince Tomohira.</e>
<cmt>the重複削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>官位は一品中務卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His rank was ippon(the first of Imperial Princes&apos; ranks) nakatsukasa kyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His rank was ippon (the first rank for Imperial Princes&apos;) nakatsukasa kyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His rank was Ippon (First Order of an Imperial Prince) no Nakatsukasa-kyo (Minister of the Ministry of Central Affairs).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除(Minister of the Ministry of Central Affairs)補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>御子左大臣とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also called Mikohidari no otodo (prince and the minister of left).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also called Mikohidari no otodo (prince and the minister of left).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also called Mikohidari no otodo (prince and the sadaijin (minister of the left)).</e>
<cmt>&quot;minister of lef&quot;→&quot;sadaijin (minister of the left)&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>藤原佐理、藤原行成と共に三蹟の一人として数える場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is sometimes counted as one of the three great calligraphers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is sometimes counted as one of the three great calligraphers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is sometimes counted as one of the three great calligraphers along with FUJIWARA no Sukemasa and FUJIWARA no Yukinari.</e>
<cmt>along with FUJIWARA no Sukemasa and FUJIWARA no Yukinari補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The person</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The person</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>The person→Personal Profileに変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>承平2年（932年）、源姓を賜り臣籍降下し、初叙従四位上。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was given a surname &quot;Minamoto&quot; and depart from the Imperial Family and became an allegiant, and firsrly appointed to jusiino jo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) in 932.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was given a surname &quot;Minamoto&quot; and depart from the Imperial Family and became an allegiant, and firsrly appointed to jusiino jo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) in 932.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was given a surname Minamoto and departed from the Imperial Family and became an allegiant, and firstly appointed to jusiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) in 932.</e>
<cmt>原文に『』のない&quot;を削除スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その後播磨権守・右近衛中将・左近衛中将等を経て、天慶7年（944年）、参議。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he was designated as Harima no gonnokami (the interim Lord of Harima Province), ukone no chujo, sakone no chujo and finally sangi (a state councillor) in 944.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he was designated as Harima no gonnokami (the interim Lord of Harima Province), ukone no chujo, sakone no chujo and finally sangi (a state councillor) in 944.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he was designated as Harima no gonnokami (the Provisional Governor of Harima Province), ukone no chujo (Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), sakone no chujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) and finally sangi (a state councillor) in 944.</e>
<cmt>interim Lord→provisional governor他ファイルに合わせる(middle captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards)補足(Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards)補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その後も順調に累進し権中納言、中納言、従二位大納言を歴任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He successfully advanced his career to be posted as gon chunagon, chunagon and junii (Junior Second Rank) dainagon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He successfully advanced his career to be posted as gon chunagon, chunagon, and junii (Junior Second Rank) dainagon.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He successfully advanced his career to be posted as gon chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor), Chunagon (vice-councilor of state), and Junii (Junior Second Rank) dainagon (Major Counselor).</e>
<cmt>(Provisional Middle Counselor)(Middle Counselor)(Major Counselor)補足&quot;chunagon (Middle Counselor)&quot;→&quot;Chunagon (vice-councilor of state)&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>天禄2年（971年）には左大臣となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 971, he was posted to the Minister of the Left.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 971, he was posted to the Minister of the Left.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 971, he was posted to the Sadaijin (Minister of the Left).</e>
<cmt>&quot;Minister of the Left&quot;→&quot;Sadaijin (Minister of the Left)&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>貞元2年（977年）、源昭平を名乗っていた昭平親王とともに勅により親王に復し、57年ぶりに皇籍に復帰。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 977, he returned to the Imperial Prince with an Imperial edict after 57 years with Imperial Prince Akihira who referred to himself as MINAMOTO no Akihira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 977, he returned as an Imperial Prince with the Imperial edict after 57 years with Imperial Prince Akihira who referred to himself as MINAMOTO no Akihira.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 977, he returned as an Imperial Prince with the Imperial edict after 57 years with Imperial Prince Akihira who referred to himself as MINAMOTO no Akihira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>二品中務卿に任じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to nihon nakatsukasakyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to nihon nakatsukasakyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to nihon nakatsukasakyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>寛和2年（986年）、中務卿を辞し、その後は嵯峨に隠棲する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 986, he resigned nakatsukasakyo, and retired to Saga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 986, he resigned nakatsukasakyo, and retired to Saga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 986, he resigned nakatsukasakyo, and retired to Saga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>『江談抄』『本朝文粋』に詩文を残す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He left some poetries in &quot;Godansho&quot; and &quot;Honcho Monzui (The Literary Essence of Our Country)&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He left some poety in &quot;Godansho&quot; and &quot;Honcho Monzui (The Literary Essence of Our Country)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He left some poetry in &quot;Godansho&quot; (the Oe Conversations, with anecdotes and gossip) and &quot;Honcho Monzui&quot; (The Literary Essence of Our Country).</e>
<cmt>スペル(The Literary Essence of Our Country)の位置(the Oe Conversations, with anecdotes and gossip)補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>勅撰和歌集入集は後拾遺和歌集の1首のみ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Waka poem selected of his in the collection of poetries compilation by Imperial command was only one in &quot;Goshui Waka shu (Later Collection of Gleanings)&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A waka poem of his is included in the collection of poetries compilation by the Imperial command and was the only one in &quot;Goshui Waka shu (Later Collection of Gleanings)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A waka poem of his is included in the collection of poetries compilation by the Imperial command and was the only one in &quot;Goshui Waka shu&quot; (Later Collection of Gleanings).</e>
<cmt>(Later Collection of Gleanings)位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>『古今和歌六帖』の撰者に有力視されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is decisively thought to be a selector of &quot;Kokin Waka Rokujo&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is decisively thought to be a selector of &quot;Kokin Waka Rokujo&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is believed to have been a selector for &quot;Kokin Waka Rokujo (six volumes of Japanese poetry written in the middle of the Heian period)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>「古今和歌六帖」に英語の説明を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>寛和2年（986年）兼明親王が嵯峨野の亀山に山荘（雄倉殿）造営の際清泉が無いのを嘆き、亀山の神に祈って霊泉を得られたことが『本朝文粋』に記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is recorded in &quot;Honcho monzui&quot; that in 986, Imperial Prince Kaneakira lamented over there was no seisen (pure spring) when he constructed a villa (Oguradono) at Kameyama in Saga-no and prayed it for the God of Kameyama, then he could gain a spritual spring.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is recorded in &quot;Honcho monzui&quot; that in 986, Imperial Prince Kaneakira lamented because there was no seisen (pure spring) when he constructed a villa (Oguradono) at Kameyama in Saga-no and prayed to the God of Kameyama, then he could gain a spritual spring.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is recorded in &quot;Honcho monzui&quot; that in 986, Imperial Prince Kaneakira lamented because there was no seisen (pure spring) when he constructed a villa (Oguradono) at Kameyama in Saga-no and prayed to the God of Kameyama, then he could gain a spiritual spring.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>後に亀山には後嵯峨上皇が仙洞亀山殿を造営した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, the retired Emperor Gosaga constructed a villa &quot;Sento Kameyamadono&quot; in Kameyama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, the retired Emperor Gosaga constructed a villa &quot;Sento Kameyamadono&quot; in Kameyama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, the Retired Emperor Gosaga constructed a villa &quot;Sento Kameyamadono&quot; in Kameyama.</e>
<cmt>retired→Retired</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="21">
<j>親王の別称に御子左大臣・御子左があるが、これは『醍醐天皇の皇子（御子）である左大臣』という意味。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial Prince Kaneakira has other name of Mikohidari no otodo and Miko hidari, which mean the Imperial Prince of the Emperor Daigo and the minister of left.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Prince Kaneakira has other names; Mikohidari no otodo and Miko hidari, thath mean the Imperial Prince of the Emperor Daigo and the minister of left.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Prince Kaneakira has other names; Mikohidari no otodo and Miko hidari, that mean the Imperial Prince of the Emperor Daigo and Sadaijin.</e>
<cmt>スペル&quot;the minister of left&quot;→&quot;Sadaijin&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>後世、親王の邸宅に藤原長家が住したため家号となり御子左家となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the later years, FUJIWARA no Nagaie resided in the residence of the Imperial Prince, the prince&apos;s other name became the house name of the family, &quot;Mikohidari-ke (Mikohidari family)&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the later years, FUJIWARA no Nagaie resided in the residence of the Imperial Prince, the prince&apos;s other name became the house name of the family, &quot;Mikohidari-ke (Mikohidari family).&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the later years, FUJIWARA no Nagaie resided in the residence of the Imperial Prince, the prince&apos;s other name became the house name of the family, &quot;Mikohidari-ke&quot; (Mikohidari family).</e>
<cmt>(Mikohidari family).の位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>長家を御子左大納言という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagaie is called Mikohidari dainagon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagaie is called Mikohidari dainagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagaie is called Mikohidari Dainagon (chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>dainagon→Dainagon (chief councilor of state)に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="24">
<j>兼明親王が皇族に復帰させられたのは、藤原兼通・藤原兼家兄弟の争いに関係している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason why the Imperial Prince Kaneakira was forced to return to the Imperial Family was related to the conflicts between FUJIWARA no Kanemichi and FUJIWARA no Kaneie brothers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason why Imperial Prince Kaneakira was forced to return to the Imperial Family was related to the conflicts between FUJIWARA no Kanemichi and FUJIWARA no Kaneie brothers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason why Imperial Prince Kaneakira was forced to return to the Imperial Family was related to the conflicts between FUJIWARA no Kanemichi and FUJIWARA no Kaneie brothers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>兼通は、弟兼家に一時期廟堂の席次を先んじられたことを深く恨みに思い、自らが関白内大臣になった際、兼家を大納言に据えおき、従兄弟にあたる藤原頼忠を相談相手とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanemichi beard a bitter grudge against his younger brother Kaneie because he once was taken an upper order of precedence in the Court, and when he became a Kanpaku (chancellor) naidaijin, he left Kaneie at a position of dainagon as it was and trusted his cousin FUJIWARA no Yoritada as an advisor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanemichi beard a bitter grudge against his younger brother Kaneie because he once was taken an upper order of precedence in the Court, and when he became a Kanpaku (chancellor) naidaijin, he left Kaneie at a position of dainagon as it was and trusted his cousin FUJIWARA no Yoritada as an advisor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanemichi beard a bitter grudge against his younger brother Kaneie because he once was taken an upper order of precedence in the Court, and when he became a Kanpaku naidaijin (Chancellor Minister of the Center), he left Kaneie at a position of Dainagon as it was and trusted his cousin FUJIWARA no Yoritada as an advisor.</e>
<cmt>(chancellor) →(Chancellor Minister of the Center)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>そして頼忠を左大臣に引き上げるため、当時その座にあった兼明親王がとばっちりを受けたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And Kanemichi wanted to give Yoritada the post of the minister of left, so the Imperial Prince Kaneakira who was at the position was embroiled in the promotion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And Kanemichi wanted to give Yoritada the post of the minister of left, so the Imperial Prince Kaneakira who was holding the position was embroiled in promotion.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And Kanemichi wanted to give Yoritada the post of Sadaijin, so the Imperial Prince Kaneakira who was holding the position was embroiled in promotion.</e>
<cmt>”the minister of left”→&quot;Sadaijin&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>親王の歌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The waka poem of the Imperial Prince</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The waka poem of the Imperial Prince</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The waka poem of the Imperial Prince</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="27">
<j>七重八重花は咲けども山吹の実の一つだに無きぞあやしき　（後拾遺和歌集1154）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The meaning of the waka poem: Although Japanese roses bloom sevenfolds and eightfolds of flowers, that they never bear even a single fruit is a funny thing to understand. (Goshui wakshu #1154)</e>
<cmt>和歌の最後の句は私の記憶では、「～無きぞ悲しき」だったと思いますが、ネット上の文献では「あやしき」と両方出ています。分かりませんが本歌取りと考え、訳文は「あやしき」を前提に作成しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The meaning of the waka poem: Although Japanese roses bloom seven and eightfold qunatities of flowers, they never bear even a single fruit, that is a funny thing to understand. (Goshui wakshu #1154)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The meaning of the waka poem: Although Japanese roses bloom seven and eightfold of flowers, they never bear even a single fruit, that is a funny thing to understand. (Goshui wakashu #1154)</e>
<cmt>qunatities 原文とずれるので削除スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>太田道灌のエピソードとしても知られる</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also known as an episode of Dokan OTA and a girl.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also known as the episode of Dokan OTA and a girl.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also known as the episode of Dokan OTA and a girl.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>この歌を題材に取った古典落語の演目に「道灌」というものがある</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a title of &quot;Rakugo (a kind of classical Japanese story telling art)&quot;, &quot;Dokan&quot; which derived from this waka poem.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is the title; &quot;Rakugo (a kind of classical Japanese story telling art),&quot; &quot;Dokan&quot; which is derived from this waka poem.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is the title; Rakugo (a kind of classical Japanese story telling art), &apos;Dokan&apos; which is derived from this waka poem.</e>
<cmt>原文に『』のない&quot;を削除原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), Lonicera(id:20638), Yonoemon(id:55450), 玄史生(id:43670), Equaly(id:89792), 経済準学士(id:22656), 代言人(id:33675), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), 味っ子(id:17086), 唐棣色(id:64681), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>