<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>興国天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Kokoku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Kokoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Kokoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>興国 天皇（こうこく てんのう、1328年（嘉暦3年）9月 - 1397年（応永4年）3月）は、戦後、南朝 (日本)正統を主張した三浦芳聖の遠祖で、三浦皇統家第二代の天皇。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Kokoku (Kokoku Tenno, September 1328 - March 1397) was a forefather of Yoshimasa MIURA, who advocated the Legitimate Succession of the Southern Court after the World War II, and was the second Emperor of the MIURA Imperial Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Kokoku (Kokoku Tenno, September 1328 - March 1397) was an ancestor of Yoshimasa MIURA, who advocated the Legitimate Succession of the Southern Court after World War II, and was the second Emperor of the MIURA Imperial Line.</e>
<cmt>forefather-&gt;ancestor; articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Kokoku (September 1328 - March 1397) was an ancestor of Yoshimasa MIURA, who advocated the Legitimate Succession of the Southern Court after World War II, and was the second Emperor of the MIURA Imperial Line.</e>
<cmt>Kokoku Tenno, 削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>諱は守永（もりなが）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His imina (personal name) was Morinaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His imina (personal name) was Morinaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His imina (personal name) was Morinaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>父は三浦皇統家第一代東山天皇（尊良親王）、母は右大臣西園寺公顕の女・藤原清子・御匣殿（みくしげどの）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Emperor Higashiyama (Imperial Prince Takayoshi (Takanaga)), the first Emperor of the MIURA Imperial Line, and his mother was a daughter of Udaijin (Minister of the Right) Kinaki SAIONJI, 藤原清子, or Mikushigedono.</e>
<cmt>藤原清子→読み不明です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Emperor Higashiyama (Imperial Prince Takayoshi, or Takanaga), the first Emperor of the MIURA Imperial Line, and his mother was a daughter of Udaijin (Minister of the Right) Kinaki SAIONJI, 藤原清子, or Mikushigedono.</e>
<cmt>a name is Untranslated</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Emperor Higashiyama (Imperial Prince Takayoshi, or Takanaga), the first Emperor of the MIURA Imperial Line, and his mother was a daughter of Udaijin (Minister of the Right) Kinaki SAIONJI, 藤原清子, or Mikushigedono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>後醍醐天皇の猶子（纂集御系図）・第七の宮。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was an adopted child of Emperor Godaigo (Sanshu Gokeizu (pedigree chart)), and was the seventh prince.</e>
<cmt>第七の宮→定訳不明です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was an adopted child of Emperor Godaigo (Sanshu Gokeizu), and was the seventh prince.</e>
<cmt>deleted nested parentheses</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was an adopted child of Emperor Godaigo (Sanshu Gokeizu (pedigree chart)), and was the seventh prince.</e>
<cmt>(pedigree chart)戻す</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>南北朝時代 (日本)の戦乱の中で幼くして両親を失ったが、新田義貞・脇屋義助らに奉戴され1346年、白鹿の年号を用いて天下に号令を掛けた北陸朝廷の天皇（得江文書）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He lost his parents when he was little in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), but in 1346, being enthroned by Yoshisada NITTA, Yoshisuke WAKIYA and others, gave command throughout the country by using the name of the era of Hakushika, and becoming as the Emperor in the Hokuriku Imperial Court (Tokue monjo (documents of Tokue)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He lost his parents when he was little in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), but in 1346, being enthroned by Yoshisada NITTA, Yoshisuke WAKIYA and others, commanded the country using the name of the era of Hakushika, and became the Emperor in the Hokuriku Imperial Court (Tokue monjo, documents of Tokue).</e>
<cmt>articles, verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He lost his parents when he was little in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), but in 1346, being enthroned by Yoshisada NITTA, Yoshisuke WAKIYA and others, commanded the country using the name of the era of Hakushika, and became the Emperor in the Hokuriku Imperial Court (Tokue monjo, documents of Tokue).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>武家方の目を眩ます陽動作戦のため、吉野朝の後村上天皇（義良）が身代わりの天皇として表に立ったため、興国天皇（守永）は、 内伝の天皇として身分を隠し、守永親王として東日本各地を転戦した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because Emperor Gomurakami (Noriyoshi) of the Yoshino Court stood up in front to deceive samurai families in the feint operation, Emperor Kokoku (Morinaga) hid his position as the Emperor and fought in various places in the eastern side of Japan as Imperial Prince Morinaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Emperor Gomurakami (Noriyoshi) of the Yoshino Court stood up in front to distract samurai families, Emperor Kokoku (Morinaga) hid his position as the Emperor and fought in various places in the eastern side of Japan as Imperial Prince Morinaga.</e>
<cmt>feint operation-&gt;distraction</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Emperor Gomurakami (Noriyoshi) of the Yoshino Court stood up in front to distract samurai families, Emperor Kokoku (Morinaga) hid his position as the Emperor and fought in various places in the eastern side of Japan as Imperial Prince Morinaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 鈴木超世志(id:251717), 海獺(id:153448), 彩華1226(id:64711), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>