<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>神櫛王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamukushi no miko</e>
<cmt>神櫛王Kamikushi no mikとも言うようです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamukushi no Miko</e>
<cmt>頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamukushi no Miko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>神櫛王（かむくしのみこ・かみくしのみこ、生没年不詳）は、『古事記』『日本書紀』に記される日本の皇族（王族）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamukushi no miko (神櫛王: year of birth and death unknown) was a member of Japanese Imperial family (Royal family), who appears in &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>名前の漢字表記を加えました。 『古事記』→&quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) なお、以下はthe Kojikiとしました。 『日本書紀』→&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan)　なお、以下はthe Nihonshokiとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamukushi no miko (神櫛王: year of birth and death unknown) was a member of Japanese Imperial family (Royal family), who appears in the &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>&quot;Kojiki&quot;&quot;Nihonshoki&quot;の前にthe追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamukushi no miko (神櫛王: year of birth and death unknown) was a member of Japanese Imperial family (Royal family), who appears in the &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>神櫛皇子・神櫛別命・五十香彦命（いかひこのみこと）とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His name was also written as 神櫛皇子 and 神櫛別命, and he was called &apos;Ikahiko no mikoto&apos; (五十香彦命), as well.</e>
<cmt>名前の漢字表記を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His name was also written as 神櫛皇子 and 神櫛別命, and he was called &apos;Ikahiko no mikoto&apos; (五十香彦命), as well.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His name was also written as 神櫛皇子 and 神櫛別命, and he was called &apos;Ikahiko no mikoto&apos; (五十香彦命), as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>第12代景行天皇の第17皇子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the seventeenth Imperial Prince of the twelfth Emperor Keiko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the seventeenth prince of the twelfth Emperor Keiko.</e>
<cmt>Imperial Prince→princeとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the seventeenth prince of the twelfth Emperor Keiko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>『書紀』によれば、母は五十河媛（いかわひめ）で、同母弟に稲背入彦皇子（いなせいりひこのみこ）がいたとするが、『古事記』では、母を播磨稲日大郎姫（播磨稲日大郎姫）とし、兄に櫛角別王・大碓命・ヤマトタケル（日本武尊）・倭根子命がいたとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the Nihonshoki, his mother was Ikawahime, and his younger maternal half-brother was Inaseirihiko no miko, however, according to the Kojiki, his mother was Princess Harima no Inabi no Oiratsume, and his elder brothers were Kushitsunowake no miko, Ousu no mikoto, Yamato Takeru no Mikoto, Yamatoneko no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>ヤマトタケル（日本武尊）→Yamato Takeru no Mikotoは、他の名前表記法と異なります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; his mother was Ikawahime, and his younger maternal half-brother was Inaseirihiko no miko, however, according to the &quot;Kojiki,&quot; his mother was Princess Harima no Inabi no Oiratsume, and his older brothers were Kushitsunowake no miko, Ousu no mikoto, Yamato Takeru no mikoto, Yamatoneko no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>原文表記に合わせ、Nihonshoki、Kojikiにクォーテーション追加、elder brothers→older brothersとし、他の表記と合わせ、Yamato Takeru no mikotoとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; his mother was Ikawahime, and his younger maternal half-brother was Inaseirihiko no miko, however, according to the &quot;Kojiki,&quot; his mother was Princess Harima no Inabi no Oiratsume, and his older brothers were Kushitsunowake no miko, Ousu no mikoto, Yamato Takeru no mikoto, Yamatoneko no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また、讃岐国国造（讃岐公）・紀伊国の酒部阿比古（さかべのあびこ）・宇陀酒部・酒部公の祖で、国造族の子孫は寒川・植田・高松・神内・三谷・十河などの氏を名乗ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that he was the ancestor of Sanukinokuni no miyatsuko (local lord of Sanuki Province) (Sanuki no kimi), Sakabe no abiko of Kii Province, Uda no sakabe, Sakabe no kimi, and the descendents of the family of Miyatsuko (local lord) formed several clans and named themselves the Samukawa clan, Ueda clan, Takamatsu clan, Jinnai clan, Mitani clan, Sogo clan, etc.</e>
<cmt>讃岐国国造→Sanukinokuni no miyatsuko (local lord of Sanuki Province)としました。 紀伊国の酒部阿比古（さかべのあびこ）→Sakabe no abiko of Kii Provinceとしました。　</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that he was the ancestor of Sanukinokuni no miyatsuko (local lord of Sanuki Province) (Sanuki no kimi), Sakabe no abiko of Kii Province, Uda no sakabe, Sakabe no kimi, and the descendents of the family of Miyatsuko (local lord) formed several clans and named themselves the Samukawa clan, Ueda clan, Takamatsu clan, Jinnai clan, Mitani clan, Sogo clan, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that he was the ancestor of Sanukinokuni no miyatsuko (local lord of Sanuki Province) (Sanuki no kimi), Sakabe no abiko of Kii Province, Uda no sakabe, Sakabe no kimi, and the descendents of the family of Miyatsuko (local lord) formed several clans and named themselves the Samukawa clan, Ueda clan, Takamatsu clan, Jinnai clan, Mitani clan, Sogo clan, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>王墓は香川県高松市牟礼町牟礼にあり、宮内庁の管理下にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Imperial tumulus is located at Mure-cho, Takamatsu City, Kagawa Prefecture, and it is maintained by the Imperial Household Agency.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Imperial tumulus is located at Mure, Mure-cho, Takamatsu City, Kagawa Prefecture, and it is maintained by the Imperial Household Agency.</e>
<cmt>「牟礼」→訳漏れのため訳出</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Imperial tumulus is located at Mure, Mure-cho, Takamatsu City, Kagawa Prefecture, and it is maintained by the Imperial Household Agency.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また、同市由良町の清水神社・同県仲多度郡琴平町の式内社櫛梨神社に祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is also enshrined at Shimizu-jinja Shrine in Yura-cho of the same city (Takamatsu City), as well as at Kushinashi-jinja Shrine, a shrine enlisted in the Engishiki code, in Kotohira-cho, Nakatado-gun of the same prefecture (Kagawa Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is also enshrined at Shimizu-jinja Shrine in Yura-cho of the same city (Takamatsu City), as well as at Kushinashi-jinja Shrine, a shrine enlisted in the Engishiki code, in Kotohira-cho, Nakatado County of the same prefecture (Kagawa Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>Nakatado-gun→Nakatado Countyに修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is also enshrined at Shimizu-jinja Shrine in Yura-cho of the same city (Takamatsu City), as well as at Kushinashi-jinja Shrine, a shrine enlisted in the Engishiki code, in Kotohira-cho, Nakatado County of the same prefecture (Kagawa Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>なお、香川県に伝わる讃留霊王（さるれお）伝説によれば、景行天皇23年（93年）に讃留霊王が勅命を受け、瀬戸内の悪魚退治のために讃岐入りし、その地に留まって、仲哀天皇8年9月15日 (旧暦)（199年10月21日）に125歳で薨去したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the legend of Sarureo, which has been handed down in Kagawa Prefecture, in the 23rd year of Emperor Keiko&apos;s reign, Sarureo received an Imperial order from the Emperor and proceeded to Sanuki region to exterminate an evil fish sprawling around in the Seto Inland Sea, and even after getting rid of the fish, he continued staying there until he died on the fifteenth day of the ninth month of the eighth year of Emperor Chuai&apos;s reign in old lunar calendar (October 21, 199) at the age of 125.</e>
<cmt>仲哀天皇8年9月15日 (旧暦)→定訳不明：the fifteenth day of the ninth month of the eighth year of Emperor Chuai&apos;s reign in old lunar calendar (October 21, 199) としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the legend of Sarureo, which has been handed down in Kagawa Prefecture, in the year 93, Sarureo received an Imperial order from the Emperor and proceeded to Sanuki region to exterminate an evil fish sprawling around in the Seto Inland Sea, and even after getting rid of the fish, he continued staying there until he died on October 20, 199 at the age of 125.</e>
<cmt>旧暦→新暦表記(グレゴリオ暦)に修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the legend of Sarureo, which has been handed down in Kagawa Prefecture, in the year 93, Sarureo received an Imperial order from the Emperor and proceeded to Sanuki region to exterminate an evil fish sprawling around in the Seto Inland Sea, and even after getting rid of the fish, he continued staying there until he died on October 20, 199 at the age of 125.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>この讃留霊王について、東讃では神櫛王のこととし（櫛梨神社社伝も同様）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About Sarureo, in the east Sanuki region, he was identified to be Kamukushi no miko (in the legend handed down at Kushinashi-jinja Shrine also backs up this theory).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">About Sarureo, in the east Sanuki region, he was identified to be Kamukushi no miko (in the legend handed down at Kushinashi-jinja Shrine also backs up this theory).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">About Sarureo, in the east Sanuki region, he was identified to be Kamukushi no miko (in the legend handed down at Kushinashi-jinja Shrine also backs up this theory).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>西讃では武卵王（たけかいごのみこ。日本武尊の子）のこととしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, in the west Sanuki region, Sarureo was identified to be Takekaigo no miko (Yamato Takeru no Mikoto&apos;s son).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。 日本武尊→Yamato Takeru no Mikotoとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, in the west Sanuki region, Sarureo was identified to be Takekaigo no miko (Yamato Takeru no mikoto&apos;s son).</e>
<cmt>Yamato Takeru no mikotoとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, in the west Sanuki region, Sarureo was identified to be Takekaigo no miko (Yamato Takeru no mikoto&apos;s son).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 アレシンロ(id:170344), Neutality(id:184448), BAKU(id:55205), 代言人(id:33675), Charenji(id:7908), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>