<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>賀茂宮</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamo no Miya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamo no Miya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamonomiya</e>
<cmt>表記訂正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>賀茂宮（かものみや、元和 (日本)4年10月5日 （1618年11月21日） - 元和8年10月2日 （1622年11月4日））は、江戸時代前期の皇族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamo no Miya (November 21, 1618 - November 4, 1622) was a member of the Imperial family in the early part of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamo no Miya (November 21, 1618 - November 4, 1622) was a member of the Imperial family in the early part of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamonomiya (November 21, 1618 - November 4, 1622) was a member of the Imperial family in the early part of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>表記訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>後水尾天皇の第1皇子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the first son of Emperor Gomizunoo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the first son of Emperor Gomizunoo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the first son of Emperor Gomizunoo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は典侍四辻与津子（お与津御寮人）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was Yotsuko YOTSUTSUJI (Oyotsu-Goryonin), Naishi no suke (a court lady of the first rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was Yotsuko YOTSUTSUJI (Oyotsu-Goryonin), Naishi no suke (a court lady of the first rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was Yotsuko YOTSUTSUJI (Oyotsu-Goryonin), Naishi no suke (a court lady of the first rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>同母妹に文智女王がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His younger maternal sister was Bunchi-Joo (Princess Bunchi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His younger maternal sister was Bunchi-Joo (Princess Bunchi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His younger maternal sister was Princess Bunchi.</e>
<cmt>Bunchi-Jooは不要</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>後水尾天皇の第1皇子として生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as the first son of Emperor Gomizunoo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born as the first son of Emperor Gomizunoo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born as the first son of Emperor Gomizunoo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>母は典侍四辻与津子（お与津御寮人）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was Yotsuko YOTSUTSUJI (Oyotsu-Goryonin), Naishi no suke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was Yotsuko YOTSUTSUJI (Oyotsu-Goryonin), Naishi no suke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was Yotsuko YOTSUTSUJI (Oyotsu-Goryonin), Naishi no suke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>この年には徳川秀忠の娘・徳川和子が入内する予定だったが、賀茂宮の誕生により延期される事となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Judai (an Imperial Consort&apos;s bridal entry into court) by Masako TOKUGAWA, daughter of Hidetada TOKUGAWA, was planned in 1618, but, it was postponed due to birth of Kamo no Miya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Judai (an Imperial Consort&apos;s bridal entry into court) by Masako TOKUGAWA, daughter of Hidetada TOKUGAWA, was planned in 1618, but, it was postponed due to the birth of Kamonomiya.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Judai (an Imperial Consort&apos;s bridal entry into court) by Masako TOKUGAWA, daughter of Hidetada TOKUGAWA, was planned in 1618, but, it was postponed due to the birth of Kamonomiya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、翌年には梅宮（後の文智女王）が生まれて再び延期となったため、不行跡として母与津子と妹梅宮は宮中より追放させられ、伯父四辻季継・高倉嗣良を含む公卿にも流罪や出仕差し止めの処分が下された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1619, judai was postponed again due to birth of Ume-no-miya (later Bunchi-Joo); therefore, his mother, Yotsuko, and younger sister, Ume-no-miya were expelled from the Imperial Court by reason of misconduct, and court nobles including his uncles, Suetsugu YOTSUTSUJI and Tsuguyoshi TAKAKURA were also subject to punishment of banishment or suspension of attendance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1619, judai was postponed again due to birth of Ume-no-miya (later Bunchi-Joo); therefore, his mother, Yotsuko, and younger sister, Ume-no-miya were expelled from the Imperial Court for misconduct, and court nobles including his uncles, Suetsugu YOTSUTSUJI and Tsuguyoshi TAKAKURA were also subject to punishment in the form of banishment or suspension of attendance.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1619, judai was postponed again due to birth of Umenomiya (later Proncess Bunchi); therefore, his mother, Yotsuko, and younger sister, Umenomiya were expelled from the Imperial Court for misconduct, and court nobles including his uncles, Suetsugu YOTSUTSUJI and Tsuguyoshi TAKAKURA were also subject to punishment in the form of banishment or suspension of attendance.</e>
<cmt>Ume-no-miya表記訂正しました。-Joo削除Princess補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>このような不祥事があったためか、賀茂宮は一部の系図史料（『本朝皇胤紹運録』など）に掲載がされていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maybe because of above misconduct, no descriptions about Kamo no Miya are contained in some historical data about family record (&quot;Honcho koin jounroku&quot; (the Emperor&apos;s family tree, made in the Muromachi period), etc.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maybe because of the above misconduct, no descriptions of Kamo no Miya are contained in historical data concerning family records (&quot;Honcho koin jounroku&quot; or the Emperor&apos;s family tree, made in the Muromachi period, etc.).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maybe because of the above misconduct, no descriptions of Kamonomiya are contained in historical data concerning family records (&quot;Honcho koin jounroku&quot; or the Emperor&apos;s family tree, made in the Muromachi period, etc.).</e>
<cmt>Kamo no Miya表記訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>その後、賀茂宮は1622年（元和8年）10月2日（新暦11月4日）、成人することなく逝去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, Kamo no Miya passed away on November 4, 1622 without attaining manhood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamo no Miya passed away on November 4, 1622 without attaining manhood.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamonomiya passed away on November 4, 1622 without attaining manhood.</e>
<cmt>Kamo no Miya表記訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>戒名は景雲院諦月英秋。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His posthumous Buddhist name was Keiunin Teigetsu Eishu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His posthumous Buddhist name was Keiunin Teigetsu Eishu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His posthumous Buddhist name was Keiunin Teigetsu Eishu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>墓地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cemetery</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cemetery</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cemetery</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>二尊院（にそんいん）（京都府京都市右京区嵯峨二尊院門前長神町）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was buried at Nison-in Temple (Chojin-cho, Nisonin-monzen, Saga, Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was buried at Nison-in Temple (Chojin-cho, Nisonin-monzen, Saga, Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was buried at Nison-in Temple (Chojin-cho, Nisonin-monzen, Saga, Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>