<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>石川王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ishiwaka no Okimi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ishiwaka no Okimi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ishiwaka no Okimi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>石川王（いしかわのおおきみ、生年不詳 - 天武天皇8年3月9日 (旧暦)（679年4月24日））は、日本の飛鳥時代の人物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ishikawa no Okimi (year of birth unknown - April 24, 679), lived in the Asuka period in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ishikawa no Okimi (year of birth unknown - April 24, 679), lived in the Asuka period in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ishikawa no Okimi (year of birth unknown - April 24, 679), lived in the Asuka period in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>旧仮名遣いでの読みは「いしかはのおほきみ」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In old Japanese syllabary characters, his name is called &quot;Ishikawa no Ohokimi&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In old Japanese syllabary spelling, his name is called &apos;Ishikawa no Ohokimi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>characters→spelling,called→read と修正しました。クォーツ、ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In old Japanese syllabary spelling, his name is called &apos;Ishikawa no Ohokimi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>皇族だが系譜は不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a member of the Imperial family, but his lineage is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a member of the Imperial Family, but his genealogy is unknown.</e>
<cmt>Imperial family→Imperial Family,lineage→genealogy と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a member of the Imperial Family, but his genealogy is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>天武天皇の治下で吉備大宰を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a Kibi province governor-general under Emperor Tempu reign.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the province governor-general of Kibi Province under the Emperor Tenmu&apos;s reign.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。a→the,Kibi province governor-general→provincial governor-general of Kibi Province,Tempu→Tenmu&apos;s と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the province governor-general of Kibi Province under the Emperor Tenmu&apos;s reign.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>事績</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Achievement</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Achievement</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Achievement</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>『播磨国風土記』に、石川王が総領だったときに都可の村を広山の里と改名したと記す箇所がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Harimanokuni Fudoki&quot; (records of the culture and geography of the Harima Province) reported that when Ishikawa no Okimi was a governor, he changed the name of a village to Hiroyama no sato.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Harimanokuni Fudoki&quot; (records of the culture and geography of the Harima Province) describes that Ishikawa no Okimi changed the name of a village to Hiroyama no sato when he was the soryo (governor).</e>
<cmt>The を補いました。reported→describes,a→the と修正しました。 オーダーを修正しました。後述との関係より、soryoを補い、後での関連をスムースにしました。なお、「都可の村」が &quot;a village&quot;であるのかどうかの確認はとれておりません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Harimanokuni Fudoki&quot; (records of the culture and geography of the Harima Province) describes that Ishikawa no Okimi changed the name of a village to Hiroyama no sato when he was the soryo (governor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また、『日本書紀』によれば679年の死亡時に石川王は吉備大宰であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), Ishikawa no Okimi was the Kibi provincial governor-general when he died in 679.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), Ishikawa no Okimi was the provincial governor-general (oho mikoto mochi) of kibi Province when he died in 679.</e>
<cmt>Kibi provincial governor-general→provincial governor-general of Kibi Province と修正しました。後述での関連をスムースにするため、(oho mikoto mochi) をここで補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), Ishikawa no Okimi was the provincial governor-general (oho mikoto mochi) of kibi Province when he died in 679.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>総領と大宰は同一の役職の別表記と考えられているので、石川王は吉備大宰（吉備総領）として少なくとも吉備国（後の備前国・備中国・備後国・美作国）と播磨国を治めたと推測できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Soryo (総領) and oho mikoto mochi was in same position (provincial governor-general) with different expression, it is assumed that Ishikawa no okimi at least managed Kibi Province (Bizen Province, Bicchu Province, Bingo Province and Mimasaka Province) and Harima Province.</e>
<cmt>読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since soryo and oho mikoto mochi were the same post (provincial governor-general) in different writing, it is assumed that Ishikawa no okimi at least ruled Kibi Province (later Bizen Province, Bicchu Province, Bingo Province and Mimasaka Province) and Harima Province as the provincial governor-general (oho mikoto mochi) of Kibi Province (the soryo of Kibi Province).</e>
<cmt>「総領」の読みは”soryo”で確認しました。ここでの（総領）は削除しました。文脈に応じて適宜補いながらスムースに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since soryo and oho mikoto mochi were the same post (provincial governor-general) in different writing, it is assumed that Ishikawa no okimi at least ruled Kibi Province (later Bizen Province, Bicchu Province, Bingo Province and Mimasaka Province) and Harima Province as the provincial governor-general (oho mikoto mochi) of Kibi Province (the soryo of Kibi Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>672年の壬申の乱の際には当摩広島が吉備国守として同国を統治していたことが書紀に見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) reported that TAIMA no Hiroshima governed Kibi Province as governor of Kibi during the Jinshin war in 672.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) tells that TAIMA no Hiroshima ruled Kibi Province as the governor during the Jinshin War in 672.</e>
<cmt>The, the を補いました。reported→tells,governed→ruled,war→War と修正しました。of Kibi を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) tells that TAIMA no Hiroshima ruled Kibi Province as the governor during the Jinshin War in 672.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また、後述の事件から石川王が乱の勃発時に近江宮のある大津市にいたことが推測できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is assumed that Ishikawa no Okimi was in Otsu city where Omi no miya was located when the war started considering the description below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, it is assumed that Ishikawa no Okimi was in Otsu City where Omi no miya was located when the war started, by considering the incident described below.</e>
<cmt>Also, by, カンマを補いました。city→City,description below→incident described blow と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, it is assumed that Ishikawa no Okimi was in Otsu City where Omi no miya was located when the war started, by considering the incident described below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>よって石川王の大宰任命はこの乱の後ということになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Ishikawa no Okimi was appointed provincial governor-general after the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Ishikawa no Okimi was appointed to the provincial governor-general after the war.</e>
<cmt>to the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Ishikawa no Okimi was appointed to the provincial governor-general after the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>吉備太宰石川王は天武天皇8年（679年）3月9日に吉備で死んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When still Kibi province governor-general, Ishikawa no Okimi died in Kibi province on March 9, 679.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ishikawa no Okimi, the provincial governor-general of kibi Province died in Kibi Province on April 27, 679.</e>
<cmt>March 9, 679→April 27, 679 （グレゴリオ暦に変換）と修正しました。文脈に応じて修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ishikawa no Okimi, the provincial governor-general of kibi Province died in Kibi Province on April 27, 679.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>天皇はとても悲しみ、石川王に諸王二位を贈った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The emperor was greatly depressed and granted Shoo (princes without imperial proclamation) Nii (Second Rank) to Ishikawa no Okimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The emperor was greatly depressed and conferred Shoo (princes without imperial proclamation) Nii (Second Rank) to Ishikawa no Okimi.</e>
<cmt>granted→conferred と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The emperor was greatly depressed and conferred Shoo (princes without imperial proclamation) Nii (Second Rank) to Ishikawa no Okimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>大津皇子の脱出</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Otsu&apos;s escape</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Otsu&apos;s escape</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Otsu&apos;s escape</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>石川王の名は壬申の乱の中で本人の行動と関わらない形で現れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Jinshin war, the name of Ishikawa no okime appeared where not related his behavior.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Jinshin war, the name of Ishikawa no Okimi appeared as not related to his action.</e>
<cmt>okime→Okimi,where→as,related→related to,behavior→action と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Jinshin war, the name of Ishikawa no Okimi appeared as not related to his action.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>大海人皇子（天武天皇）の子、大津皇子は父の挙兵を知って味方とともに脱出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A son of Prince Oama (Emperor Tenmu), Prince Otsu escaped with his followers from the capital after he found his father had taken up arms.</e>
<cmt>一原文一翻訳の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The son of Prince Oama (Emperor Tenmu), the Prince Otsu escaped with his followers from the capital after he found his father had raised an army.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。A→The,taken up arms→raised an army と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The son of Prince Oama (Emperor Tenmu), the Prince Otsu escaped with his followers from the capital after he found his father had raised an army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>6月25日深夜に鈴鹿関に至り、そこで大海人皇子が張った封鎖線にかかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Otsu got to Suzuka-no-seki Checkpoint at midnight and was stopped by a blockade Prince Oama had setup.</e>
<cmt>一原文一翻訳の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Prince Otsu reached Suzuka-no-seki Checkpoint at midnight of June 25 (old calender), and was stopped by a blockade the Prince Oama had setup.</e>
<cmt>the, カンマを補いました。got to→reached,「6月25日」を補いました。（ただし、年号が定かでありませんので、ここは”旧暦”と加えています）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Prince Otsu reached Suzuka-no-seki Checkpoint at midnight of June 25 (old calender), and was stopped by a blockade the Prince Oama had setup.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>このとき鈴鹿関司は大津皇子らを山部王と石川王だと誤認した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, Suzuka-no-seki Checkpoint officials misidentified Prince Otsu as Yamabe no Okimi and Ishikawa no Okimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that point, the Suzuka-no-seki Checkpoint officials misidentified the Prince Otsu and others as Yamabe no Okimi and Ishikawa no Okimi.</e>
<cmt>the, and others を補いました。 At this time→At that point と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that point, the Suzuka-no-seki Checkpoint officials misidentified the Prince Otsu and others as Yamabe no Okimi and Ishikawa no Okimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>理由は書紀に明記されないが、敵味方不明の地を行く際に、少年だった大津皇子の存在を隠し、従う者の誰かが山部王らの名を騙った可能性がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No reason mentioned in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), but it is possible that Prince Otsu&apos;s followers hid Prince Otsu&apos;s identity, and named Yamabe no Okimi because they couldn&apos;t identify friend or foe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No reason mentioned in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), but it is possible that the Prince Otsu&apos;s followers hid the Prince Otsu&apos;s identity, and someone pretended to be Yamabe no Okimi, since entering the areas they could not identify friend or foe.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。named→someone pretended to be,because they couldn&apos;t →since entering the areas they could not と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No reason mentioned in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), but it is possible that the Prince Otsu&apos;s followers hid the Prince Otsu&apos;s identity, and someone pretended to be Yamabe no Okimi, since entering the areas they could not identify friend or foe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>もしこの推測が正しいとすれば、山部王と石川王はどちら側からも殺されずにすみそうな、態度のはっきりしない人物と考えられていたことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If this assumption is correct, Yamanobe no Okimi and Ishikawa no Okimi didn&apos;t make up their minds so that they were not targeted from both sides.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If this assumption is correct, Yamanobe no Okimi and Ishikawa no Okimi were thought to be those people who did not make up their minds so that they were not targeted from both sides.</e>
<cmt>よりスムースに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If this assumption is correct, Yamanobe no Okimi and Ishikawa no Okimi were thought to be those people who did not make up their minds so that they were not targeted from both sides.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), Kinori(id:443), 弥(id:61590), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>