<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>葛木二上神社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsuragi Futakami-jinja shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsuragi Futakami-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>shrine &gt; Shrine</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsuragi Futakami-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>葛木二上神社（かつらぎふたかみじんじゃ、かつらぎにじょうじんじゃ）は、奈良県葛城市の二上山 (奈良県・大阪府)雄岳山頂付近にある神社である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsuragi Futakami-jinja shrine (or Katsuragi Nijo-jinja shrine) is located around the top of the Mt. Odake in the Nijo-zan mountain range (Nara prefecture, Osaka prefecture) in Katsuragi city, Nara prefecture.</e>
<cmt>＊漢字神社名の読みが括弧内に二つかかれておりました。先頭記載のものを括弧の前にだし、後記載のものを（or…）として訳しました。＊「二上山」はMt. Nijoとの登録が用語集にありましたが、今回、連山の扱いで訳しました（雄山（岳）、雌山（岳）が含まれている関係上）。＊山の位置に関して原文に「奈良県葛城市の」とありますが、直後に「二上山（奈良県・大阪府）」と記載がございます。両方とも記載どおりに訳しました。（実際のところは括弧内の二つの府県にまたがった山であり、原文括弧内の「・」は「両方の間」の意味で使用されていると思われます。）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsuragi Futakami-jinja Shrine (or Katsuragi Nijo-jinja Shrine) is located around the top of the Mt. Odake in the Nijo-zan mountain range (Nara Prefecture and Osaka Prefecture) in Katsuragi City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Capitalisationcomma &gt; and</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsuragi Futakami-jinja Shrine (or Katsuragi Nijo-jinja Shrine) is located around the top of the Mt. Odake in the Nijo-zan mountain range (Nara Prefecture and Osaka Prefecture) in Katsuragi City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>式内社で、旧社格は郷社。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a Shikinaisha (a shrine listed in Engishiki laws) and was categorized as a Gosha (a village shrine) under the old shrine ranking system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a shikinaisha (a shrine listed in the Engishiki laws) and was categorized as a gosha (a village shrine) under the old shrine ranking system.</e>
<cmt>CapitalisationAdded &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a shikinaisha (a shrine listed in the Engishiki laws) and was categorized as a gosha (a village shrine) under the old shrine ranking system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>二上神社、葛木坐二上神社（かつらぎにいますふたかみのじんじゃ）とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shrine is also known as Futakami-jinja shrine or as Katsuraginiimasu Futakami no-jinja shrine.</e>
<cmt>＊ニ上神社の読みは推測しましたが、ふたかみじんじゃではなくにじょうじんじゃの可能性もあります</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shrine is also known as Futakami-jinja Shrine or as Katsuraginiimasu Futakami no-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>Capitalisation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shrine is also known as Futakami-jinja Shrine or as Katsuraginiimasu Futakami no-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>祭神</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saijin (enshrined deities)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enshrined Deities</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency and consistency</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enshrined Deities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>豊布都霊（とよふつのみたま）神と国魂を祀る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsuragi Futakami-jinja shrine enshrines Toyofutsunomitama no Kami and Kunitama (the spirit of the land).</e>
<cmt>＊神の名の読み方は推測。「とよふつのみたま」までは原文どおりとし、「のかみ」をつけて翻訳いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsuragi Futakami-jinja Shrine enshrines Toyofutsunomitama no Kami and Kunitama (the spirit of the land).</e>
<cmt>Capitalisation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsuragi Futakami-jinja Shrine enshrines Toyofutsunomitama no Kami and Kunitama (the spirit of the land).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>豊布都霊神が石上神宮に、大国魂神が大和神社に勧請されたという伝承がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a legend, a ceremony for kanjo (ceremonial transfer of a divided tutelary deity to a new location) was held to transfer Toyofutsunomitama no Kami and Kunitama to Isonokami-jingu Shrine and Oyamato-jinja Shrine respectively.</e>
<cmt>＊「勧請された」との動詞は、用語集も参照し、ローマ字と意味を表記しながら、「勧請の儀式を行った」との意訳にしております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a legend, a ceremony for kanjo (the ceremonial transfer of a divided tutelary deity to a new location) was held to transfer Toyofutsunomitama no Kami and Kunitama to Isonokami-jingu Shrine and Oyamato-jinja Shrine respectively.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a legend, a ceremony for kanjo (the ceremonial transfer of a divided tutelary deity to a new location) was held to transfer Toyofutsunomitama no Kami and Okunitama no Kami to Isonokami-jingu Shrine and Oyamato-jinja Shrine respectively.</e>
<cmt>Kunitama→ Okunitama no Kami</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>豊布都霊神については布都御魂の名が有名だが、何故「豊」が名前に付くのかは不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding the name of the god, Toyofutsunomitama no Kami, it is unknown why the word &apos;Toyo&apos; is attached to the head of the well known name, Futsunomitama (the sacred sword given by Amaterasu Omikami [the Sun Goddess] to Emperor Jinmu).</e>
<cmt>布都御魂http://kotobank.jp/word/%E5%B8%83%E9%83%BD%E5%BE%A1%E9%AD%82</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding the deity name &apos;Toyofutsunomitama no Kami,&apos; it is unknown why the word &apos;Toyo&apos; is attached to the head of the well known name &apos;Futsunomitama&apos; (the sacred sword given by Amaterasu Omikami [the Sun Goddess] to Emperor Jinmu).</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding the deity name &apos;Toyofutsunomitama no Kami,&apos; it is unknown why the word &apos;Toyo&apos; is attached to the head of the well known name &apos;Futsunomitama&apos; (the sacred sword given by Amaterasu Omikami [the Sun Goddess] to Emperor Jinmu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、タケミカヅチと同神とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Toyofutsunomitama no Kami and Takemikazuchi are considere to be the same god.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Toyofutsunomitama no Kami and Takemikazuchi are considered to be the same deity.</e>
<cmt>god &gt; deityconsidere &gt; considered</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Toyofutsunomitama no Kami and Takemikazuchi are considered to be the same deity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>大国魂神は国津神の大将軍とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okunitama no Kami is considered to be the Daishogun (commander in chief) of Kunitsukami (gods of the land).</e>
<cmt>大将軍はcommand in chief と登録がありましたが、commanderと致しました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okunitama no Kami is considered to be the Daishogun (commander in chief) of Kunitsukami (gods of the land).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okunitama no Kami is considered to be the Daishogun (commander in chief) of Kunitsukami (gods of the land).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>『神社要録』には「武甕槌命、大国主命」、『神祇志』には「紀豊布都霊神、大国神」と記載されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Jinja yoroku&quot; (Main records of shrines) and &quot;Jingishi&quot; (the part of &quot;Dainihonshi&quot; [Great history of Japan] about divinity) mention &apos;Takemikazuchi no mikoto, Okuninushi no mikoto&apos; and &apos;Kinotoyofutsunomitama no Kami, Daikokushin&apos; respectively.</e>
<cmt>＊「神祇志」http://komonsan.jp/mitogaku/cat34/post_267.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Jinja yoroku&quot; (Main records of shrines) and &quot;Jingishi&quot; (the part of &quot;Dainihonshi&quot; [Great history of Japan] about divinity) mention &apos;Takemikazuchi no mikoto, Okuninushi no mikoto&apos; and &apos;Kinotoyofutsunomitama no Kami, Daikokushin&apos; respectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Jinja yoroku&quot; (Main records of shrines) and &quot;Jingishi&quot; (the part of &quot;Dainihonshi&quot; [Great history of Japan] about divinity) mention &apos;Takemikazuchi no mikoto, Okuninushi no mikoto&apos; and &apos;Kinotoyofutsunomitama no Kami, Daikokushin&apos; respectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>元々は二上山の2つの山頂・雄山と雌山にそれぞれ男神・女神が祀られていたものとみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that a god and a goddess had originally been enshrined at each top of Mt. Oyama and Mt. Meyama in the Nijo-zan mountain range.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that a god and a goddess had originally been enshrined at each top of Mt. Oyama and Mt. Meyama in the Nijo-zan mountain range.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that a god and a goddess had originally been enshrined at each top of Mt. Oyama and Mt. Meyama in the Nijo-zan mountain range.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>創建の年代等は不詳である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is unknown in which era the shrine was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is unknown in which era the shrine was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is unknown in which era the shrine was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>二上山には石器の素材となる讃岐岩（サヌカイト）の層があり、古くから周辺に人が住んでいたものとみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a layer of Sanuki-gan stone (Sanukaite) (a kind of bronzite andesite), of which stone tools can be made, in the ground under the Nijo-zan mountain range, and therefore, it is believed that people had lived around there since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>＊讃岐岩（サヌカイト）は、楽器として用語集に登録されていましたが（実際楽器に使われることのある鉱物のようです）ここでは意味合いが異なりますので、調べた結果、古銅輝石安山岩(bronzite andesite）の一種である旨を訳しております。http://www.kusa.ac.jp/~tkato/microscope/list.htmlhttp://www.museum.kagawa-u.ac.jp/http://www.museum.kagawa-u.ac.jp/hokanko/sanukaite/sanukite.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a layer of Sanuki-gan stone (Sanukaite) (a kind of bronzite andesite), of which stone tools can be made, in the ground under the Nijo-zan mountain range, and therefore, it is believed that people had lived around there since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a layer of Sanuki-gan stone (Sanukaite) (a kind of bronzite andesite), of which stone tools can be made, in the ground under the Nijo-zan mountain range, and therefore, it is believed that people had lived around there since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>文献の初出は、『日本三代実録』の貞観 (日本)元年（859年）正月27日条、当社に従五位の神階を授けるという記述である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first literature record of the shrine can be found in &quot;Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku (sixth of the six classical Japanese history texts)&quot; which states that Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) of Shinkai (ranks granted to Shinto gods) was bestowed upon the shrine on January 27, 859.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first literature record of the shrine can be found in &quot;Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku&quot; (sixth of the six classical Japanese history texts) which states that the Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) shinkai (rank granted to Shinto deities) was bestowed upon the shrine on January 27, 859.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first literature record of the shrine can be found in &quot;Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku&quot; (sixth of the six classical Japanese history texts) which states that the Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) shinkai (rank granted to Shinto deities) was bestowed upon the shrine on January 27, 859.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>延喜式神名帳では「大和国葛下郡 葛木二上神社二座」と記載され、大社に列している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Engishiki jimmyocho (a register of shrines in Japan) mentions &apos;Katsuragi Futakami-jinja shrine enshrining 2 gods in Katsuraginoshimo County, Yamato Province&apos; and lists the shrine as a Taisha (grand shrine).</e>
<cmt>「二座」は2つの神を祀っている、と意訳しております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Engishiki Jinmyocho (a register of shrines in Japan) mentions &apos;Katsuragi Futakami-jinja shrine enshrining two gods in Katsuraginoshimo County, Yamato Province&apos; and lists the shrine as a taisha (grand shrine).</e>
<cmt>CapitalisationAdded &quot;The&quot;jimmyocho &gt; Jinmyocho</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Engishiki Jinmyocho (a register of shrines in Japan) mentions &apos;Katsuragi Futakami-jinja shrine enshrining two gods in Katsuraginoshimo County, Yamato Province&apos; and lists the shrine as a taisha (grand shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>当麻寺中之坊所蔵の「当麻寺付近絵図」には二上山の雌岳に神蛇大王（竜王）を祭る社もあったことが記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;Taima-dera fukin-ezu (a picture of the scenery around the Taima-dera temple)&apos; housed in Nakano-bo Hall of the Taima-dera temple revealed that there was a Yashiro (shrine) enshrining Shinjya-daio (Ryuo [dragon-king]) on Mt. Medake in the Nijo-zan mountain range.</e>
<cmt>神蛇大王は定訳不明。読み方は推測して訳しました。後の括弧内「竜王」は「龍王」と同じものと考え、用語集を見て訳しました。＊一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taima-dera fukin-ezu&apos; (a picture of the scenery around the Taima-dera temple) housed in the Nakano-bo Hall of Taima-dera temple revealed that there was a yashiro (shrine) enshrining Shinjya-daio (Ryuo [dragon-king]) on Mt. Medake in the Nijo-zan mountain range.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taima-dera fukin-ezu&apos; (a picture of the scenery around the Taima-dera temple) housed in the Nakano-bo Hall of Taima-dera temple revealed that there was a yashiro (shrine) enshrining Shinjya-daio (Ryuo [dragon-king]) on Mt. Medake in the Nijo-zan mountain range.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>現在は中之坊鎮守として遷座され、境内稲荷神社末社に竜王社の小祠となったとの伝承がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a legend, the Yashiro was transferred to the Nakano-bo Hall and enshrined as Chinju (local Shinto deity) currently, and the shrine became a Shoshi (a small shrine) of Ryuo which was a Massha (a small shrine belonging to the main shrine) belonging to Inari-jinja shrine located within the precincts of the temple.</e>
<cmt>＊一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a legend, the yashiro was transferred to Nakano-bo Hall and is currently enshrined as a chinju (local Shinto deity), and the shrine became a shoshi (a small shrine) of Ryuo which was a massha (a small shrine belonging to the main shrine) belonging to Inari-jinja shrine located within the precincts of the temple.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a legend, the yashiro was transferred to Nakano-bo Hall and is currently enshrined as a chinju (local Shinto deity), and the shrine became a shoshi (a small shrine) of Ryuo-sha which was a massha (a small shrine belonging to the main shrine) belonging to Inari-jinja shrine located within the precincts of the temple.</e>
<cmt>Ryuo→ Ryuo-sha</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>当社との関係は不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Relationship between the Yashiro and Katsuragi Futakami-jinja shrine is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Relationship between the yashiro and Katsuragi Futakami-jinja shrine is unknown.</e>
<cmt>Capitalisation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Relationship between the yashiro and Katsuragi Futakami-jinja shrine is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="20">
<j>近世には当社は「岳の権現」と呼ばれ、二上山からの水流を利用する数十か村の岳郷の氏神であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early-modern times, the shrine was called &apos;Take no Gongen (avatar of the gods enshrined in the mountain)&apos; and it was considered to be Ujigami (a guardian god or spirit of a particular place in the Shinto religion) of dozens of villages in the mountain community where watercourses descending from the Nijo mountain range were used.</e>
<cmt>＊「岳郷」は定訳不明にてmountain communityとの意訳いたしました。＊「岳の権現」は山に祀っている神の化身、との意訳をつけました。＊神社＝神ではないのではと思われましたが「当社は…氏神であった」はそのまま訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early-modern times, the shrine was called &apos;Take no Gongen (avatar of the gods enshrined in the mountain)&apos; and it was considered to be an ujigami (a guardian god or spirit of a particular place in the Shinto religion) of dozens of villages in the mountain community where watercourses descending from the Nijo mountain range were used.</e>
<cmt>Ujigami &gt; an ujigami</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early-modern times, the shrine was called &apos;Take no Gongen (avatar of the gods enshrined in the mountain)&apos; and it was considered to be an ujigami (a guardian god or spirit of a particular place in the Shinto religion) of dozens of villages in the mountain community where watercourses descending from the Nijo mountain range were used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>明治6年（1873年）4月に郷社に列格した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1873, the shrine was designated as a Gosha (village shrine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1873, the shrine was designated a gosha (village shrine).</e>
<cmt>as a Gosha &gt; a gosha</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1873, the shrine was designated a gosha (village shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="22">
<j>境内</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Precincts of the shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shrine Precinct</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shrine Precinct</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>現在の社殿は、1974年（昭和49年）の二上山大火で焼失し、翌1975年に再建されたもので、内部には小さな榊の御神体がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A small Goshintai (object of worship housed in a Shinto shrine and believed to contain the spirit of a deity) made of Sakaki (species of evergreen sacred to Shinto) is placed in the current Shaden (a shrine building), which was once burnt down by a great fire in the Nijo mountain range in 1974 and then rebuilt in the following year, 1975.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A small goshintai (object of worship housed in a Shinto shrine and believed to contain the spirit of a deity) made of sakaki (species of evergreen sacred to Shinto) is placed in the current shaden (a shrine building), which once burnt down in a great fire in the Nijo mountain range in 1974 before being rebuilt in the following year, 1975.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A small goshintai (object of worship housed in a Shinto shrine and believed to contain the spirit of a deity) made of sakaki (species of evergreen sacred to Shinto) is placed in the current shaden (a shrine building), which once burnt down in a great fire in the Nijo mountain range in 1974 before being rebuilt in the following year, 1975.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>本社の東側に大津皇子の墓がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is the tomb of Prince Otsu to the east of Honsha (main shrine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tomb of Prince Otsu stands to the east of the honsha (main shrine).</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tomb of Prince Otsu stands to the east of the honsha (main shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="25">
<j>山麓の葛木倭文坐天羽雷命神社（倭文神社）に、相殿神として当社の大国魂神が祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okunitama no kami in the shrine is also enshrined as an Aidonoshin (an enshrined god other than Shusaijin [the main enshrined deity]) in the Katsuragisitoriniimasu Amenohaikazuchinomikoto-jinja shrine (Shizuri-jinja shrine) at the base of the mountain range.</e>
<cmt>相殿神：あいどのしんhttp://heitate.blog37.fc2.com/blog-entry-2.htmlhttp://www.geocities.jp/sumeookami/oonamuchi.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The enshrined deity Okunitama no kami is also enshrined as an aidonoshin (an enshrined deity other than the main enshrined deity) in Katsuragisitoriniimasu Amenohaikazuchinomikoto-jinja Shrine (Shizuri-jinja shrine) at the base of the mountain range.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The enshrined deity Okunitama no kami is also enshrined as an aidonoshin (an enshrined deity other than the main enshrined deity) in Katsuragisitoriniimasu Amenohaikazuchinomikoto-jinja Shrine (Shizuri-jinja shrine) at the base of the mountain range.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="26">
<j>祭事</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rites</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rites</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rites</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>旱魃の年には岳郷によって「嶽の神様 幟がお好き、幟持てこい、雨降らせ」と唱和して雨乞いの登山が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a year of drought, the people in the mountain community climbed up the mountain praying together for rain, &quot;The god of the mountain likes flags. Let&apos;s bring flags to the god to ask for rain.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a year of drought, the people in the mountain community climbed up the mountain prayed for rain by chanting &quot;The god of the mountain likes flags. Let&apos;s bring flags to the god to ask for rain.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a year of drought, the people in the mountain community climbed up the mountain prayed for rain by chanting &quot;The god of the mountain likes flags. Let&apos;s bring flags to the god to ask for rain.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>現在は毎年4月23日に有志による「岳登り」が行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In present days, volunteers perform &apos;Takenobori (mountain climbing)&apos; every year on April 23.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nowadays, volunteers perform the &apos;Takenobori&apos; (mountain climbing) every year on April 23.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nowadays, volunteers perform the &apos;Takenobori&apos; (mountain climbing) every year on April 23.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="29">
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other</e>
<cmt>Others &gt; Other</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>境内（雄岳山頂）に立ち入るには美化保存協力金200円を神社に支払う必要がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People have to donate 200 yen to the shrine for its beautification and maintenance, when they enter its precincts (on the top of the Mt. Odake).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When entering the shrine precinct, it is necessary to pay 200 yen for the beautification and maintenance of the shrine.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When entering the shrine precinct, it is necessary to pay 200 yen for the beautification and maintenance of the shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="31">
<j>外照リンク</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">External links</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">External Links</e>
<cmt>Title case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">External Links</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>（延喜式神社の調査）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Investigation of Engishiki-jinja shrine)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Investigation of Engishiki-jinja shrine)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Investigation of Engishiki-jinja shrine)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>（神奈備）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Kannabi)</e>
<cmt>神奈備の意味は用語集に載っておりましたが、ここではリンクするサイトのタイトルを示していると思われたため、意味を添付して訳してはおりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Kannabi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Kannabi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), Kansai explorer(id:48975), Nnh(id:474), KENPEI(id:11349), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>