<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>吉田寺 (斑鳩町)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kichiden-ji Temple (Ikaguga-cho)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kichiden-ji Temple (Ikaguga-cho)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kichiden-ji Temple (Ikaruga-cho)</e>
<cmt>Ikaguga-cho→Ikaruga-choに修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>吉田寺（きちでんじ）は奈良県生駒郡斑鳩町にある浄土宗の寺院である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chogaku-ji is a temple of the Jodo sect of Buddhism located in Ikaruga-cho, Ikoma County, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chogaku-ji is a temple of the Jodo sect of Buddhism located in Ikaruga-cho, Ikoma County, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kichiden-ji is a temple of the Jodoshu sect of Buddhism located in Ikaruga-cho, Ikoma County, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Chogaku-ji→Kichiden-jiに修正、Jodoshu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>俗に「ぽっくり寺」の名で親しまれ、年配の参拝者が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The temple is also known as a &quot;pokkuri-dera&quot;, where worshippers pray for their own &quot;pokkuri&quot; death, i.e. they hope to pass away without having any extra suffering, and thus attracts elderly worshippers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The temple is also known as a &quot;pokkuri-dera&quot;, where worshipers pray for their own &quot;pokkuri&quot; death (i.e. they hope to pass away without having any extra suffering) and thus attracts elderly worshipers.</e>
<cmt>spelling, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The temple is also known as a &quot;pokkuri-dera,&quot; where worshipers pray for their own &quot;pokkuri&quot; death (i.e. they hope to pass away without having any extra suffering) and thus attracts elderly worshipers.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>聖霊殿（聖徳太子を祀る）と承応元年（1652）建立の多宝塔が重要文化財に指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoryoden, a building to worship the Prince Shotoku, and a multi-story pagoda that was built in 1652 are designated as Cultural Properties of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoryoden, a building to worship the Prince Shotoku, and a multi-story pagoda that was built in 1652 are designated as Cultural Properties of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoryoden, a building to worship the Prince Shotoku, and a multi-story pagoda that was built in 1652 are designated as Cultural Properties of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴 史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>天智天皇の勅願により創建されたとされ、近くには妹・間人皇女（はしひとのひめみこ）を葬る古墳がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The temple is reputedly founded at the imperial order of the Emperor Tenchi, whose reign was in the seventh century, and the ancient burial mound of Hashihito no himemiko, a younger sister of the emperor, is within its vicinity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The temple was reputedly founded at the imperial order of the Emperor Tenchi, whose reign was in the seventh century, and the ancient burial mound of Hashihito no himemiko, a younger sister of the emperor, is within its vicinity.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The temple was reputedly founded at the imperial order of the Emperor Tenchi, whose reign was in the seventh century, and the ancient burial mound of Hashihito no himemiko, a younger sister of the Emperor, is within its vicinity.</e>
<cmt>the Emperorとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>平安時代の永延元年（987年）に天台僧・恵心僧都（源信 (僧侶)）が開山したとも伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But it is also said that the temple was founded by Eshin Sozu (Genshin) of the Tendai sect in 987 in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But it is also said that the temple was founded by Eshin Sozu (Genshin) of the Tendai sect in 987 in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But it is also said that the temple was founded by Eshin Sozu (Genshin) of the Tendaishu sect in 987 in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Tendaishu sectとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>建造物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buildings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buildings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buildings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>本堂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hondo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hondo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hondo (main hall)</e>
<cmt>Hondoの補足追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>多宝塔（重要文化財）－墨書銘によると寛正４年（1463年）の建立された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tahoto, multi-story pagoda (Important Cultural Property of Japan) - The inscription indicates that it was built in 1463.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tahoto, multi-story pagoda (Important Cultural Property of Japan) - The inscription indicates that it was built in 1463.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tahoto, multi-story pagoda (Important Cultural Property of Japan) - The inscription indicates that it was built in 1463.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>小ぶりながら均整のとれた美しい塔で、内部には秘仏の大日如来像が安置されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a small but well-balanced, beautiful pagoda, and it contains a statue of Dainichi Nyorai (Vairocana), which is not disclosed to the public, in it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a small but well-balanced, beautiful pagoda, and it contains a statue of Dainichi Nyorai (Vairocana), which is not disclosed to the public.</e>
<cmt>deleted “in it”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a small but well-balanced, beautiful pagoda, and it contains a statue of Dainichi Nyorai (Vairocana), which is not disclosed to the public.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>木造阿弥陀如来坐像（重要文化財）－恵心僧都（源信）がクリの巨木から作ったと伝えられる丈六の阿弥陀如来像で、この仏に祈ると腰から下の世話をかけずに往生できるといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wooden seated statue of Amida Nyorai (Amitabha Tathagata) (Important Cultural Property) - a statue of Joroku, which is considered to be a full-scale, having one jo and six shaku (or about 4.8 meters), holding a legend that says Eshin Sozu (Genshin) created this statue out of an enormous chestnut tree, and the worshippers of this statue of Buddha can pass away without having any problems below the waist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wooden seated statue of Amida Nyorai (Amitabha Tathagata) (Important Cultural Property) - a statue of Joroku, which is considered to be full-scale, having one jo and six shaku (or about 4.8 meters), holding a legend that says Eshin Sozu (Genshin) created this statue out of an enormous chestnut tree, and the worshipers of this statue of Buddha can pass away without having any problems below the waist.</e>
<cmt>articles, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wooden seated statue of Amida Nyorai (Amitabha Tathagata) (Important Cultural Property) - a statue of Joroku, which is considered to be full-scale, having one jo and six shaku (or about 4.8 meters), holding a legend that says Eshin Sozu (Genshin) created this statue out of an enormous chestnut tree, and the worshipers of this statue of Buddha can pass away without having any problems below the waist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>アクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>JR大和路線・近鉄生駒線王寺駅より奈良交通バス「龍田神社前」下車、徒歩すぐ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Oji Station of JR Yamato Line and Kintetsu Ikoma Line, take a Nara Kotsu Bus and get off at Tatsuta-jinja Shrine bus stop, along with a little walk.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Oji Station of JR Yamato Line and Kintetsu Ikoma Line, take a Nara Kotsu Bus and get off at Tatsuta-jinja Shrine bus stop, along with a little walk.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Oji Station of the JR Yamatoji Line and the Kintetsu Ikoma Line, take a Nara Kotsu Bus and get off at &apos;Tatsuta-jinja-mae&apos; bus stop, along with a little walk.</e>
<cmt>JR Yamato Line→the JR Yamatoji Line、Tatsuta-jinja Shrine bus stop→&apos;Tatsuta-jinja-mae&apos; bus stopに修正、the Kintstsu Ikoma Lineとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Reggaeman(id:6214), Ｈｉｒｏ２００６(id:59115), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>