<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>日吉大社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiyoshi Taisha shrine (Hie Taisha shrine)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiyoshi Taisha shrine (Hie Taisha shrine)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiyoshi Taisha Shrine</e>
<cmt>(Hie Taisha shrine)削除しました。用語統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>祭神大山咋神（東本宮）大己貴神（西本宮）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ohoyamakuhi no kami god (East shrine), Onamuchi no kami god (West shrine) are enshrined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ohoyamakuhi no kami god (East shrine), Onamuchi no kami god (West shrine) are enshrined.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ohoyamakuhi no kami god (East shrine), Onamuchi no kami god (West shrine) are enshrined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>社格式内社（名神大）・二十二社・官幣大社・別表神社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shrine Ranking of Hiyoshi Taisha shrine - Shikiuchi sha or Myojin Taisha, (Shinto shrines listed in the Engishiki, books of regulations and laws), Nijuni-sha Shrines (the 22 most important Shinto shrines, as designated during the Heian period), Kanpei-taisha (Major Imperial shrine), and Beppyo jinja (Shrines on the Special List of Association of Shinto Shrines).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shrine Ranking of Hiyoshi Taisha shrine - Shikiuchi sha or Myojin Taisha, (Shinto shrines listed in the Engishiki, books of regulations and laws), Nijuni-sha Shrines (the 22 most important Shinto shrines, as designated during the Heian period), Kanpei-taisha (Major Imperial shrine), and Beppyo jinja (Shrines on the Special List of Association of Shinto Shrines).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shrine Ranking of Hiyoshi Taisha Shrine - Shikiuchi sha or Myojin Taisha, (Shinto shrines listed in the Engishiki, books of regulations and laws), Nijuni-sha Shrines (the 22 most important Shinto shrines, as designated during the Heian period), Kanpei-taisha (Major Imperial shrine), and Beppyo jinja (Shrines on the Special List of Association of Shinto Shrines).</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>本殿日吉造</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Architecture of honden (the main building) is featured with Hie zukuri (Hie design).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Architecture of honden (the main building) features Hie zukuri (Hie design).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Architecture of honden (the main building) features Hie zukuri (Hie design).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>別名山王権現</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shrine is also called Sanno Gongen (god).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shrine is also called Sanno Gongen (god).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shrine is also called Sanno Gongen (god).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>例祭4月12日 - 4月15日（山王祭）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Annual festival is held between April 12th and 15th (Sanno Festival).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Annual festival is held between April 12th and 15th (Sanno Festival).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Annual festival is held between April 12th and 15th (Sanno Festival).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>日吉大社（ひよしたいしゃ、かつては「ひえたいしゃ」）は、滋賀県大津市坂本 (大津市)にある神社。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiyoshi Taisha shrine (Hie Taisha Shrine) is in Sakamoto of Otsu City in Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiyoshi Taisha shrine (Hie Taisha Shrine) is in Sakamoto of Otsu City in Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiyoshi Taisha Shrine (Hie Taisha Shrine) is in Sakamoto of Otsu City in Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>俗に山王権現とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also known as the shrine of Sanno Gongen (god).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also known as the shrine of Sanno Gongen (god).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also known as the shrine of Sanno Gongen (god).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>日本全国に約2000社ある日吉神社の総本宮である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiyoshi Taisha is the main shrine amongst 2,000 Hiyoshi branch shrines across Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiyoshi Taisha is the main shrine amongst 2,000 Hiyoshi branch shrines across Japan.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiyoshi Taisha is the main shrine amongst 2,000 Hiyoshi branch shrines across Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>旧社格は官幣大社。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former shrine ranking is Kanpei-taisha (Major Imperial shrine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former shrine ranking is Kanpei-taisha (Major Imperial shrine).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former shrine ranking is Kanpei-taisha (Major Imperial shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>中世には二十二社の下八社のひとつとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the medieval period, it was categorized into one of the Lower Eight shrines of Nijuni-sha Shrines (the 22 most important Shinto shrines were classified into three types: Upper seven shrines, Middle seven shrines, Lower eight shrines)</e>
<cmt>「下八社」とされたのは11世紀のようです。原文には「中世」と記述されていますが、曖昧なため「In the 11th century」とした方がはっきりすると思います。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the medieval period, it was categorized into one of the Lower Eight shrines of Nijuni-sha Shrines (the 22 most important Shinto shrines were classified into three types: Upper seven shrines, Middle seven shrines, Lower eight shrines)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the medieval period, it was categorized into one of the Lower Eight shrines of Nijuni-sha Shrines (the 22 most important Shinto shrines were classified into three types: Upper seven shrines, Middle seven shrines, Lower eight shrines)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>西本宮と東本宮を中心に、400,000m&amp;ampsup2の境内を持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiyoshi Taisha shrine has precincts of 400,000㎡ mainly consisting East and West shrine.</e>
<cmt>「400,000m&amp;ampsup2」と原文にありますが、「400,000㎡」と理解し、訳出させていただきました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiyoshi Taisha shrine has precincts of 400,000㎡ mainly consisting East and West shrine.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiyoshi Taisha Shrine has precincts of 400,000 ㎡ mainly consisting East and West shrine.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。スペース挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>ニホンザルを神使として崇拝することで知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is known for worshiping monkeys as Shinshi (Divine Servant).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is known for worshiping monkeys as Shinshi (Divine Servant).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is known for worshiping monkeys as Shinshi (Divine Servant).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>祭神</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enshrined deity</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enshrined deity</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enshrined deity</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>西本宮に大己貴神（大国主）、東本宮に大山咋神を祀る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ohoyamakuhi no kami god is enshrined at East shrine, and Onamuchi no kami god (Okuninushi god) is enshrined at West shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ohoyamakuhi no kami god is enshrined at East shrine, and Onamuchi no kami god (Okuninushi god) is enshrined at West shrine.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ohoyamakuhi no kami god is enshrined at East shrine, and Onamuchi no kami god (Okuninushi god) is enshrined at West shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>2つの本宮と以下の5つの摂社は日吉七社・山王七社と呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These two main shrines and the following five sessha (auxiliary shrine) are called Hiyoshi Shichisha (the Seven Hiyoshi Shrines) or Sanno Shichisha (the Seven Sanno Shrines).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These two main shrines and the following five sessha (auxiliary shrine) are called Hiyoshi Shichisha (the Seven Hiyoshi Shrines) or Sanno Shichisha (the Seven Sanno Shrines).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These two main shrines and the following five sessha (auxiliary shrine) are called Hiyoshi Shichisha (the Seven Hiyoshi Shrines) or Sanno Shichisha (the Seven Sanno Shrines).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>牛尾宮（大山咋神荒魂）大山咋神の荒魂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ushio-gu Shrine, (the enshrined deity - Oyamakui no kami aramitama)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ushio-gu Shrine, (the enshrined deity - Oyamakui no kami aramitama)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ushio-gu Shrine, (the enshrined deity - Oyamakui no kami aramitama)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>樹下宮（鴨玉依姫命）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Juge-gu Shrine (the enshrined deity - Kamotamayorihime no kami)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Juge-gu Shrine (the enshrined deity - Kamotamayorihime no kami)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juge-gu Shrine (the enshrined deity - Kamotamayorihime no kami)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>三宮宮（鴨玉依姫命荒魂）鴨玉依姫命の荒魂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sannomiya-gu Shrine (the enshrined deity - Kamotamayorihimeno kami aramitama).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sannomiya-gu Shrine (the enshrined deity - Kamotamayorihimeno kami aramitama).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sannomiya-gu Shrine (the enshrined deity - Kamotamayorihimeno kami aramitama).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>宇佐宮（田心姫神）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Usa-gu Shrine (the enshrined deity - Tagorihime no kami)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Usa-gu Shrine (the enshrined deity - Tagorihime no kami)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Usa-gu Shrine (the enshrined deity - Tagorihime no kami)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>白山宮（菊理姫命）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hakusan-gu Shrine (The enshrined deity - Kukurihime no mikoto)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hakusan-gu Shrine (The enshrined deity - Kukurihime no mikoto)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hakusan-gu Shrine (The enshrined deity - Kukurihime no mikoto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>文献では、『古事記』に「大山咋神、亦の名を山末之大主神。此の神は近淡海国の日枝の山に坐し」とあるのが初見である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiyoshi Taisha shrine first appeared in the book called &quot;Kojiki&quot; (the Record of Ancient Matters), which says &quot;Ohoyamakuhi no kami god is also called Yamasueno Onushino Kami who is enshrined at Mt. Hiei in Chihatsu Ahaumi Province, which refers to Hiyoshi Taisha shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiyoshi Taisha shrine first appeared in the book called &quot;Kojiki&quot; (the Record of Ancient Matters), which says &quot;Ohoyamakuhi no kami god is also called Yamasueno Onushino Kami who is enshrined at Mt. Hiei in Chihatsu Ahaumi Province, which refers to Hiyoshi Taisha shrine.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiyoshi Taisha Shrine first appeared in the book called &quot;Kojiki&quot; (the Record of Ancient Matters), which says &apos;Ohoyamakuhi no kami god is also called Yamasueno Onushino Kami who is enshrined at Mt. Hiei in Chihatsu Ahaumi Province, which refers to Hiyoshi Taisha Shrine.&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。スペース削除しました。記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>牛尾山（八王子山）山頂に磐座があり、これが元々の信仰の地であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iwakura (dwelling place of a god, usually in reference to a large rock) is placed on the top of Mt. Ushio (Mt. Hachioji), and it was originally the place of the worship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iwakura (dwelling place of a god, usually in reference to a large rock) is placed on the top of Mt. Ushio (Mt. Hachioji), and it was originally a place of worship.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iwakura (dwelling place of a god, usually in reference to a large rock) is placed on the top of Mt. Ushio (Mt. Hachioji), and it was originally a place of worship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>磐座を挟んで2社の奥宮（牛尾神社・三宮神社）があり、現在の東本宮は崇神天皇7年に牛尾神社の里宮として創祀されたものと伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were two Okumiya shrines on the side of Iwakura (Shrine built on the top of a mountain as a worship space), Ushio shrine and Sannomiya shrine, and the present East shrine was first established as Satomiya shrine (shrine built in village area as a worship space) of Ushio Shrine in B.C 91.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were two Okumiya shrines on the side of Iwakura (Shrine built on the top of a mountain as a worship space), Ushio shrine and Sannomiya shrine, and the present East shrine was first established as Satomiya shrine (shrine built in village area as a worship space) of Ushio Shrine in B.C 91.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were two Okumiya shrines on the side of Iwakura (Shrine built on the top of a mountain as a worship space), Ushio shrine and Sannomiya shrine, and the present East shrine was first established as Satomiya shrine (shrine built in village area as a worship space) of Ushio Shrine in B.C. 91.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>三宮神社に対する里宮は樹下神社である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Satomiya shrine of Sannomiya Shrine is Kinosita shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Satomiya shrine of Sannomiya Shrine is Kinosita shrine.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Satomiya shrine of Sannomiya Shrine is Kinoshita shrine.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>近江京遷都の翌年である天智天皇7年、大津京鎮護のため大神神社の神を勧請した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 667, a year after Omikyo-sento (Transferring of the national capital to Omi Kyo), the god of Omiwa shrine was transferred to Hiyoshi Taisha Shrine for the sake of protection of Otsu kyo (Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 667, a year after Omikyo-sento (Transferring of the national capital to Omi Kyo), the god of Omiwa shrine was transferred to Hiyoshi Taisha Shrine for the sake of protecting Otsu kyo (Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 667, a year after Omikyo-sento (Transferring of the national capital to Omi Kyo), the god of Omiwa shrine was transferred to Hiyoshi Taisha Shrine for the sake of protecting Otsu kyo (Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>以降、元々の神である大山咋神よりも大己貴神の方が上位とみなされるようになり、「大宮」と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, the West shrine was called Omiya shrine as Onamuchi no kami god (the god enshrined at the West shrine) have been positioned as the one with higher rank than Ohoyamakuhi no kami god.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, the West shrine was called Omiya shrine as Onamuchi no kami god (the god enshrined at the West shrine) have been positioned as having a higher rank than the Ohoyamakuhi no kami god.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, the West shrine was called Omiya shrine as Onamuchi no kami god (the god enshrined at the West shrine) have been positioned as having a higher rank than the Ohoyamakuhi no kami god.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>平安京遷都により、当社が京の鬼門に当たることから、鬼門除け・災難除けの社として崇敬されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the capital transfer to Heisan Kyo (Kyoto), Hiyoshi Taisha Shrine started to receive reputation as the shrine of protecting from evils and disasters as it was located at Kimon (the northeastern (unlucky) direction) of the nation&apos;s new capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the capital being transfered to Heisan Kyo (Kyoto), Hiyoshi Taisha Shrine started to have a reputation as a shrine that protected people from evil and disasters as it was located at Kimon (the northeastern (unlucky) direction) of the nation&apos;s new capital.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the capital being transferred to Heian Kyo (Kyoto), Hiyoshi Taisha Shrine started to have a reputation as a shrine that protected people from evil and disasters as it was located at Kimon (the northeastern (unlucky) direction) of the nation&apos;s new capital.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>延喜式神名帳では名神大社に列格し、さらに二十二社の一社ともなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Engishiki Jinmyocho (the list of deities in Engishiki, books of regulations and laws), Hiyoshi Taisha shrine was listed as one of Nijuni-sha Shrines (the 22 most important Shinto shrines, as designated during the Heian period), as well as Myojin Taisha (Shinto shrines listed in the Engishiki).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Engishiki Jinmyocho (the list of deities in Engishiki, books of regulations and laws), Hiyoshi Taisha shrine was listed as one of Nijuni-sha Shrines (the 22 most important Shinto shrines, as designated during the Heian period), as well as Myojin Taisha (Shinto shrines listed in the Engishiki).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Engishiki Jinmyocho (the list of deities in Engishiki, books of regulations and laws), Hiyoshi Taisha Shrine was listed as one of Nijuni-sha Shrines (the 22 most important Shinto shrines, as designated during the Heian period), as well as Myojin Taisha (Shinto shrines listed in the Engishiki).</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>最澄が比叡山上に延暦寺を建立し、比叡山の地主神である当社を、天台宗・延暦寺の守護神として崇敬した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saicho, a Buddhism monk, erected Enryakuji temple on the Mt Hiei, and the Hyoshi Taisha shrine, jinushigami (tutelary deity) of Mt. Hiei, was admired as the shrine for protection of Enryakuji temple of Tendai syu (buddhism sect).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saicho, a Buddhism monk, erected Enryakuji temple on the Mt Hiei, and the Hyoshi Taisha shrine, jinushigami (tutelary deity) of Mt. Hiei, was admired as a shrine for protection of Enryakuji temple of Tendai syu (buddhism sect).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saicho, a Buddhism monk, erected Enryaku-ji temple on the Mt Hiei, and the Hiyoshi Taisha Shrine, jinushigami (tutelary deity) of Mt. Hiei, was admired as a shrine for protection of Enryaku-ji temple of Tendai sect.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>中国の天台宗の本山である天台山国清寺で祀られていた山王元弼真君にならって山王権現と呼ばれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiyoshi Taisha shrine was called as Sanno Gongen, named after San-no Genhitsu shinkun enshrined in Tendai-san Kokusei-ji Temple, the head temple of Tendai Shu in China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiyoshi Taisha shrine was called Sanno Gongen, named after San-no Genhitsu shinkun enshrined in Tendai-san Kokusei-ji Temple, the head temple of Tendai Shu in China.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiyoshi Taisha Shrine was called Sanno Gongen, named after San-no Genhitsu shinkun enshrined in Tendai-san Kokusei-ji Temple, the head temple of Tendai sect in China.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>延暦寺では、山王権現に対する信仰と天台宗の教えを結びつけて山王神道を説いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enryakuji temple taught Sanno-Shinto, a type of shintoism linked to doctrine of Tendai syu religion and worship towards Sanno-gongen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enryakuji temple taught Sanno-Shinto, a type of shintoism linked to the doctrine of Tendai syu religion and worshiped Sanno-gongen.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enryaku-ji Temple taught Sanno-Shinto, a type of shintoism linked to the doctrine of Tendai sect religion and worshipped Sanno-gongen.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>中世に比叡山の僧兵が強訴のために担ぎ出した神輿は日吉大社のものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the medieval period, it was Mikoshi from Hiyoshi Taisha shrine (portable shrine carried in festivals) which was used for petition by Monks of Mt.Hiei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the medieval period, it was Mikoshi from Hiyoshi Taisha shrine (portable shrine carried in festivals) which Monks of Mt.Hiei used to carry out petitions.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the medieval period, it was Mikoshi from Hiyoshi Taisha Shrine (portable shrine carried in festivals) which Monks of Mt. Hiei used to carry out petitions.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。スペース挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>天台宗が全国に広がる過程で、日吉社も全国に勧請・創建された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Branches of Hiyoshi Taisha Shrine were established and gods were transferred to those branches in the course of preaching of Tendai syu across Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Branches of Hiyoshi Taisha Shrine were established and gods were transferred to those branches while preaching Tendai syu across Japan.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Branches of Hiyoshi Taisha Shrine were established and gods were transferred to those branches while preaching Tendai sect across Japan.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>元亀2年（1571年）、織田信長の比叡山焼き討ち (1571年)により日吉大社も灰燼に帰した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1571, Hiyoshi Taisha shrine was destroyed through the fire attack against Mt. Hiei by Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1571, Hiyoshi Taisha shrine was destroyed in fire by an attack on Mt. Hiei by Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1571, Hiyoshi Taisha Shrine was destroyed in fire by an attack on Mt. Hiei by Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>現在見られる建造物は安土桃山時代以降に再建されたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Present buildings were re-constructed after Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Present buildings were re-constructed after the Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Present buildings were re-constructed after the Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>信長の死後、豊臣秀吉は当社の復興に尽力した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Nobunaga, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI contributed to the rehabilitation of the Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Nobunaga, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI contributed to the rehabilitation of the Shrine.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Nobunaga, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI contributed to the rehabilitation of the Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>これは、秀吉の幼名を「日吉丸」といい、あだ名が「猿」であることから、当社を特別な神社と考えたためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi&apos;s childhood name &quot;Hiyoshi Maru&quot; and nickname &quot;Saru&quot;(monkey) gave him an idea that this shrine was important to him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi&apos;s childhood name &quot;Hiyoshi Maru&quot; and nickname &quot;Saru&quot;(monkey) gave him the idea that this shrine was important to him.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi&apos;s childhood name &apos;Hiyoshi Maru&apos; and nickname &apos;Saru&apos; (monkey) gave him the idea that this shrine was important to him.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。スペース挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>明治に入ると神仏分離令により、仏教色が廃された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buddhism lost its momentum due to the execution of the Edict for Separation of Shinto and Buddhism in the Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buddhism lost its momentum due to the execution of the Edict for the Separation of Shinto and Buddhism in the Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddhism lost its momentum due to the execution of the Edict for the Separation of Shinto and Buddhism in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>また、本来の形に戻すとして、東本宮と西本宮の祭神を入れ替えて西本宮の大山咋神を主祭神とし、大物主神を祀る東本宮は摂社・大神神社に格下げした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to make the shrine as it was before, after enshrined gods of East shrine and West shrine were swapped, Ohoyamakuhi no kami god of West shrine becasme the main enshrined god, and East shrine enshrining Omononushi no kami god (Onamuchi no kami god) was demoted to Sessha (auxiliary shrine), Omiwa-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to make the shrine as it was before, after the enshrined gods of the East shrine and West shrine were swapped, Ohoyamakuhi no kami god of West shrine becasme the main enshrined god, and East shrine enshrining Omononushi no kami god (Onamuchi no kami god) was demoted to Sessha (auxiliary shrine), Omiwa-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to make the shrine as it was before, after the enshrined gods of the East shrine and West shrine were swapped, Ohoyamakuhi no kami god of West shrine became the main enshrined god, and East shrine enshrining Omononushi no kami god (Onamuchi no kami god) was demoted to Sessha (auxiliary shrine), Omiwa-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>昭和初年に元の形に復した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The buildings were completely recovered in 1926.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The buildings were completely recovered in 1926.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The buildings were completely recovered in 1926.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>境内</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Precincts of Hiyoshi Taisha shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Precincts of Hiyoshi Taisha shrine</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Precincts of Hiyoshi Taisha Shrine</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>かつては境内108社・境外108社と言われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once, people said that Hiyoshi Taisha Shrine has 108 shrines within its precincts and 108 shrines outside its precincts (Keidai 108 sha and Keigai 108 sha, literally meaning precincts 108 shrines and outer precincts 108 shrines).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once, people said that Hiyoshi Taisha Shrine has 108 shrines within its precincts and 108 shrines outside its precincts (Keidai 108 sha and Keigai 108 sha, literally meaning precincts 108 shrines and outer precincts 108 shrines).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once, people said that Hiyoshi Taisha Shrine has 108 shrines within its precincts and 108 shrines outside its precincts (Keidai 108 sha and Keigai 108 sha, literally meaning precincts 108 shrines and outer precincts 108 shrines).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>以下に示す21社は主なものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The major shrines are the following 21 shrines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The major shrines include the following 21 shrines.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The major shrines include the following 21 shrines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>旧称は江戸時代までの神仏習合時代の名称である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The old name of the shrine is used up until the Edo period when both Shinto and Buddhism were still taught together.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The old name of the shrine was used up until the Edo period when both Shinto and Buddhism were still taught together.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The old name of the shrine was used up until the Edo period when both Shinto and Buddhism were still taught together.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>東本宮境内の各社は、「大山咋神の家族および生活を導く神々」と説明されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, shrines in the precincts of East Shrine are described as ones which protect families and lives of Ohoyamakuhi no kami god.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, shrines in the precincts of East Shrine are described as ones which protect families and lives of Ohoyamakuhi no kami god.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, shrines in the precincts of East Shrine are described as ones which protect families and lives of Ohoyamakuhi no kami god.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cultural Heritage</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cultural Heritage</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cultural Heritage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="47">
<j>国宝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National Treasure</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National Treasure</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National Treasure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>西本宮本殿 - 1586年（天正14年）の建立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main shrine building of West Shrine - erected in 1586.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main shrine building of West Shrine - erected in 1586.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main shrine building of West Shrine - erected in 1586.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>檜皮（ひわだ）葺きで、屋根形式は「日吉造」という、日吉大社特有のもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The roof of Hiyoshi Taisha Shrine is featured in Hie design with hiwadabuki (cypress bark roof).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The roof of Hiyoshi Taisha Shrine is featured in Hie design with hiwadabuki (cypress bark roof).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The roof of Hiyoshi Taisha Shrine is featured in Hie design with hiwadabuki (cypress bark roof).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="50">
<j>正面から見ると入母屋造に見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the front view, West shrine seems to have irimoya style (building with a half-hipped roof).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the front view, West shrine seems to have irimoya style (building with a half-hipped roof).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the front view, West shrine seems to have irimoya style (building with a half-hipped roof).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>しかし、背面中央の庇（ひさし）部分の軒を切り上げ、この部分が垂直に断ち切られたような形態（縋破風）になっているのが特色。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the roof is featured in Sugaruharu style, the eaves of the roof on the back of the building is raised, and the edge of the roof is shorter as if it is cut down vertically.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the roof is featured in Sugaruharu style, the eaves of the roof on the back of the building is raised, and the edge of the roof is shorter as if being cut down vertically.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the roof is featured in Sugaruhafu style, the eaves of the roof on the back of the building is raised, and the edge of the roof is shorter as if being cut down vertically.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>東本宮本殿 - 1595年（文禄4年）の建立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main shrine building of East Shrine - erected in 1595.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main shrine building of the East Shrine - erected in 1595.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main shrine building of the East Shrine - erected in 1595.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>建築形式は西本宮本殿に似る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its arcitecture is similar that of West Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its arcitecture is similar to that of the West Shrine.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its architecture is similar to that of the West Shrine.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>昭和初期までは「大神神社本殿」と呼ばれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until the early period of Showa, East Shrine was called &quot;the main shrine building of Omiwa Jinja shrine&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until the early Showa period, the East Shrine was called &quot;the main shrine building of Omiwa Jinja shrine&quot;.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until the early Showa period, the East Shrine was called &apos;the main shrine building of Omiwa Jinja Shrine&apos;.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>重要文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural property</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important cultural property</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important cultural property</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>以下の建造物は東照宮（江戸時代の建立）を除いて安土桃山時代の建立である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The buildings below are all built in the Azuchi-Momoyama period except for Toshu-gu shrine (established in the Edo Period).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The buildings below are all built in the Azuchi-Momoyama period except for Toshu-gu shrine (established in the Edo Period).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The buildings below are all built in the Azuchi-Momoyama period except for Tosho-gu Shrine (established in the Edo period).</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>西本宮拝殿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nishi-hungu Haiden (the Hall of worship of West Shrine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nishi-hungu Haiden (the Hall of worship of West Shrine).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nishi-hongu Haiden (the Hall of worship of West Shrine).</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>西本宮楼門</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nishi-Hongu Romon (two-storied gate of West Shrine)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nishi-Hongu Romon (two-storied gate of West Shrine)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nishi-Hongu Romon (two-storied gate of West Shrine)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>東本宮拝殿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Higashi-hongu Haiden (the Hall of worship of East Shrine)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Higashi-hongu Haiden (the Hall of worship of East Shrine)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Higashi-hongu Haiden (the Hall of worship of East Shrine)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>東本宮楼門</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Higashi-Hongu Romon (two-storied gate of East Shrine)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Higashi-Hongu Romon (two-storied gate of East Shrine)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Higashi-Hongu Romon (two-storied gate of East Shrine)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>日吉三橋（大宮橋、走井橋、二宮橋） - いずれも石橋である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiyoshi Sankyo (Three main bridges of Hiyoshi Taisha Shrine, Omiya bridge, Hashiri bridge, Ninomiya bridge) - all of them are made of stones.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiyoshi Sankyo (Three main bridges of Hiyoshi Taisha Shrine, Omiya bridge, Hashiri bridge, Ninomiya bridge) - all of them are made of stones.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiyoshi Sankyo (Three main bridges of Hiyoshi Taisha Shrine, Omiya bridge, Hashiri bridge, Ninomiya bridge) - all of them are made of stones.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>摂社宇佐宮本殿 - 西本宮本殿、東本宮本殿と同様、屋根は日吉造である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">sessha Usa-gu Honden (The main building of Usa-gu shrine, auxiliary shrine) - Its roof is featured with Hoyoshi design like the main buildings of Nihon-gu shrine and Higashi Hon-gu shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">sessha Usa-gu Honden (The main building of Usa-gu shrine, auxiliary shrine) - Its roof is featured with Hoyoshi design like the main buildings of Nihon-gu shrine and Higashi Hon-gu shrine.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sessha Usa-gu Honden (The main building of Usa-gu shrine, auxiliary shrine) - Its roof is featured with Hiyoshi design like the main buildings of Nishi Hon-gu shrine and Higashi Hon-gu shrine.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>摂社宇佐宮拝殿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sessha Usa-gu Haiden (the Hall of worship of Usa-gu shrine, auxiliary shrine)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sessha Usa-gu Haiden (the Hall of worship of Usa-gu shrine, auxiliary shrine)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sessha Usa-gu Haiden (the Hall of worship of Usa-gu Shrine, auxiliary shrine)</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>摂社樹下神社（じゅげじんじゃ）本殿 - 樹下神社は東本宮と同じ敷地にあり、東本宮の参道と樹下神社の参道が直角に交わる、特異な配置になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main building of Juge-Jinja Shrine (auxiliary shrine) - Juge-Jinja shrine is located at a unique place as it is in the same precincts of East Shrine,and Sando (an approach to shrine) of these shrines are intersected vertically.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main building of Juge-Jinja Shrine (auxiliary shrine) - Juge-Jinja shrine is located in a unique location as it is in the same precinct as the East Shrine, and the Sando (an approach to the shrine) of these shrines intersect vertically.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main building of Juge-Jinja Shrine (auxiliary shrine) - Juge-Jinja shrine is located in a unique location as it is in the same precinct as the East Shrine, and the Sando (an approach to the shrine) of these shrines intersect vertically.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>摂社樹下神社拝殿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sessha Juge Jinja Honden (the Hall of worship of Juge-Jinja Shrine, auxiliary shrine)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sessha Juge Jinja Honden (the Hall of worship of Juge-Jinja Shrine, auxiliary shrine)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sessha Juge-jinja Honden (the Hall of worship of Juge-jinja Shrine, auxiliary shrine)</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>摂社白山姫神社本殿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sessha Hakusanhime-jinja Honden (the main building of Hakusanhime-jinja Shrine, auxiliary shrine)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sessha Hakusanhime-jinja Honden (the main building of Hakusanhime-jinja Shrine, auxiliary shrine)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sessha Hakusanhime-jinja Honden (the main building of Hakusanhime-jinja Shrine, auxiliary shrine)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>摂社白山姫神社拝殿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sessha Hakusanhime-jinja Haiden (the hall of worship of Hakusanhime-jinja Shrine, auxiliary shrine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sessha Hakusanhime-jinja Haiden (the hall of worship of Hakusanhime-jinja Shrine, auxiliary shrine).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sessha Hakusanhime-jinja Haiden (the hall of worship of Hakusanhime-jinja Shrine, auxiliary shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>摂社牛尾神社本殿 - 牛尾神社と三宮神社は八王子山に位置し、拝殿は懸崖造になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sessha Ushio Jinja Honden (the main building of auxiliary Ushio-jinja Shrine) - Ushio shrine and Sannomiya shrine are on Mt. Hachioji, and their halls of worship are designed with cascade architecture style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sessha Ushio Jinja Honden (the main building of auxiliary Ushio-jinja Shrine) - Ushio shrine and Sannomiya shrine are on Mt. Hachioji, and their halls of worship are designed with a cascading architecture style.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sessha Ushio-jinja Honden (the main building of auxiliary Ushio-jinja Shrine) - Ushio-jinja Shrine and Sannomiya Shrine are on Mt. Hachioji, and their halls of worship are designed with a cascading architecture style.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>摂社牛尾神社拝殿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sessha Ushio Jinja Haiden (the hall of worship of Ushio-jinja Shrine, auxiliary shrine)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sessha Ushio Jinja Haiden (the hall of worship of Ushio-jinja Shrine, auxiliary shrine)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sessha Ushio-jinja Haiden (the hall of worship of Ushio-jinja Shrine, auxiliary shrine)</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>摂社三宮神社本殿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sessha Sannomiya-Jinja shrine Honden (the main building of Sannomiya-jinja shrine, auxiliary shrine)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sessha Sannomiya-Jinja shrine Honden (the main building of Sannomiya-jinja shrine, auxiliary shrine)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sessha Sannomiya-jinja Honden (the main building of Sannomiya-jinja Shrine, auxiliary shrine)</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>摂社三宮神社拝殿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sessha Sannomiya-Jinja Haiden (the hall of worship of auxiliary Sannomiya-jinja shrine)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sessha Sannomiya-Jinja Haiden (the hall of worship of auxiliary Sannomiya-jinja shrine)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sessha Sannomiya-jinja Haiden (the hall of worship of auxiliary Sannomiya-jinja Shrine)</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>日吉東照宮本殿・石の間・拝殿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiyoshi Tosho-Gu Honden, Haiden, Ishi no Ma (the hall of worship, the main building, and Ishi-no-ma (place between the hall of worship and the main building)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiyoshi Tosho-Gu Honden, Haiden, Ishi no Ma (the hall of worship, the main building, and Ishi-no-ma (place between the hall of worship and the main building)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiyoshi Tosho-gu Honden, Haiden, Ishi no Ma (the hall of worship, the main building, and Ishi-no-ma (place between the hall of worship and the main building)</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>末社東照宮唐門</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Massha Tosho-gu Karamon (Karamon gate of Tosho-gu Shrine, subordinate shrine)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Massha Tosho-gu Karamon (Karamon gate of Tosho-gu Shrine, subordinate shrine)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Massha Tosho-gu Karamon (Karamon gate of Tosho-gu Shrine, subordinate shrine)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>末社東照宮透塀</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Massha Tosho-gu sukibei (Subordinate Tosho-gu shrine&apos;s transparent fence)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Massha Tosho-gu sukibei (Subordinate Tosho-gu shrine&apos;s transparent fence)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Massha Tosho-gu Sukibei (Subordinate Tosho-gu Shrine&apos;s transparent fence)</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>日吉山王金銅装神輿 7基</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiyoshi Sanno Kondo-so Shinyo 7 units (7 units of Gold and Copper coloured portable shrine (carried in festivals) of Hiyoshi Sanno god)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiyoshi Sanno Kondo-so Shinyo 7 units (7 units of Gold and Copper coloured portable shrine (carried in festivals) of Hiyoshi Sanno god)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiyoshi Sanno Kondo-so Shinyo 7 units (7 units of Gold and Copper colored portable shrine (carried in festivals) of Hiyoshi Sanno god)</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>史跡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Historic sites</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historic sites</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historic sites</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>日吉神社境内</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Precincts of Hiyoshi Taisha Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Precincts of Hiyoshi Taisha Shrine</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Precincts of Hiyoshi Taisha Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>指定解除された文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Deisted cultural heritage</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Deisted cultural heritage</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Delisted cultural heritage</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>東照宮橋（石橋） - 旧国宝建造物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tosho-gu bridge (stone bridge) - previously registered as national treasure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tosho-gu bridge (stone bridge) - previously registered as national treasure.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tosho-gu bridge (stone bridge) - previously registered as national treasure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>昭和10年（1935年）6月29日、水害で流出し、指定解除された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bridge was delisted as cultural heritage when it was debouched by the flood on 29th June in 1935.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bridge was delisted as cultural heritage when it was debouched by the flood on 29th June in 1935.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bridge was delisted as cultural heritage when it was debouched by the flood on June 29, 1935.</e>
<cmt>日付表記修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>行事・祭事</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Events and Festivals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Events and Festivals.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Events and festivals</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="81">
<j>山王祭（4月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanno Festival (April)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanno Festival (April)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanno Festival (April)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>みたらし祭（7月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitarashi Festival (July)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitarashi Festival (July)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitarashi Festival (July)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>もみじ祭（11月） - さまざまな行事のほか坂本 (大津市)一帯をふくめライトアップが行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Momiji Festival (November) - various evens and light up over the areas including Sakamoto (Otsu City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Momiji Festival (November) - various evens and light up over the areas including Sakamoto (Otsu City)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Momiji Festival (November) - various events and light up over the areas including Sakamoto (Otsu City).</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>交通アクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Transportation access</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Transportation access</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>鉄道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Railway</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Railway</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Railway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>西日本旅客鉄道湖西線 比叡山坂本駅から西へ1.2km。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1.2 km west from Hiei San Sakamoto Station (JR Kosei Line)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1.2 km west from Hiei San Sakamoto Station (JR Kosei Line)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1.2 km west from Hiei San Sakamoto Station (West Japan Railway Company Kosei Line)</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>京阪電気鉄道京阪石山坂本線 坂本駅 (滋賀県)から西へ0.6km。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">0.6 km west from Sakamoto Station (Shiga Prefecture), Keihan railway Ishiyama Sakamoto Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">0.6 km west from Sakamoto Station (Shiga Prefecture), Keihan railway Ishiyama Sakamoto Line.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">0.6 km west from Sakamoto Station (Shiga Prefecture), Keihan railway Ishiyama Sakamoto Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>比叡山上とはケーブルカーの比叡山鉄道比叡山鉄道線（坂本ケーブル）で結ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accessible to the top of Mr. Hiei by cable car (sakamoto cable car, Hiei railway Hiei San line).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accessible to the top of Mr. Hiei by cable car (sakamoto cable car, Hiei railway Hiei San line).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accessible to the top of Mt. Hiei by cable car (Sakamoto cable car, Hiei railway Hiei San line).</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>日本最長（2,025m）のケーブルカーである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The longest cable car in Japan (2,025m)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The longest cable car in Japan (2,025m)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The longest cable car in Japan (2,025 m)</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>自動車</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Car</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Car</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Car</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>琵琶湖西縦貫道路坂本北インターチェンジから南西へ1.8km。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1.8km southwest from Biwako nishi jukan road Sakamoto-kita interchange</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1.8km southwest from Biwako nishi jukan road Sakamoto-kita interchange</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1.8 km southwest from Biwako nishi jukan road Sakamoto-kita interchange</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>国道161号から西へ1.6km。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1.6km west from National Route 161.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1.6km west from National Route 161.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1.6 km west from National Route 161.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Los688(id:12316), Umebo(id:82785), Bakkai(id:7233), Si-take.(id:91094), Nnh(id:474), КОЛЯ(id:59429), Jmacs(id:72704), Reggaeman(id:6214), Stanislaus(id:1806), Urania(id:7213), 山重(id:277621), Himazin(id:22034), ネオン(id:59494), Ikespirit(id:120987), Oilstreet(id:31325), ブレイズマン(id:183852), Sgi1962(id:80778), Pocket-file(id:272208), KENPEI(id:11349), Deapy(id:191082), 663highland(id:18755), Point136(id:211299), Mare*i(id:220586), 弥(id:61590), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>