<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>法起寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoki-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoki-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoki-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>法起寺（ほうきじ、ほっきじ）は、奈良県生駒郡斑鳩町岡本にある聖徳宗の寺院。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoki-ji (also pronounced as Hokki-ji) is a temple in Shotoku sect located at Okamoto, Ikaruga Town, Ikoma County, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoki-ji (also pronounced as Hokki-ji) is a temple of the Shotoku sect located at Okamoto, Ikaruga Town, Ikoma County, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>in Shotoku sect→of the Shotoku sect</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoki-ji (also pronounced as Hokki-ji) is a temple of the Shotoku sect located at Okamoto, Ikaruga Town, Ikoma County, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>古くは岡本寺、池後寺（いけじりでら）とも呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the old days, it was also called Okamoto-dera Temple and Ikejiri-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the old days, it was also called Okamoto-dera Temple and Ikejiri-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the old days, it was also called Okamoto-dera Temple and Ikejiri-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>山号は「岡本山」（ただし、奈良時代以前創建の寺院にはもともと山号はなく、後世付したものである）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its sango (literally, &quot;mountain name&quot;), which is the title prefixed to the name of a Buddhist temple, is &apos;Mt. Okamoto&apos; (note: temples established before Nara period did not originally have sango; if such a temple has sango now, that is the one given later).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its sango (literally, &quot;mountain name&quot;), which is the title prefixed to the name of a Buddhist temple, is &apos;Okamoto san&apos; (however, temples established before the Nara period did not originally have sango; if such a temple has sango now, that is the one given at a later day).</e>
<cmt>is &apos;Okamoto san&apos; (however, temples established before the としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its sango (literally, &quot;mountain name&quot;), which is the title prefixed to the name of a Buddhist temple, is &apos;Okamoto san&apos; (however, temples established before the Nara period did not originally have sango; if such a temple has sango now, that is the one given at a later day).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>本尊は十一面観音。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The principal image is Eleven-faced Kannon (Goddess of Mercy).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The principal image is Eleven-faced Kannon (Goddess of Mercy).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The principal image is Eleven-faced Kannon (Goddess of Mercy).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>聖徳太子建立七大寺の一つに数えられることもあるが、寺の完成は太子が没して数十年後のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sometimes the temple is counted as one of the seven major temples Prince Shotoku erected, but the temple was completed several decades after Prince Shotoku&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sometimes the temple is counted as one of the seven major temples Prince Shotoku erected, but in fact, the temple was completed several decades after Prince Shotoku&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>in fact, を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sometimes the temple is counted as one of the seven major temples Prince Shotoku erected, but in fact, the temple was completed several decades after Prince Shotoku&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>「法隆寺地域の仏教建造物」の一部として世界遺産に登録されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The temple is registered as a World Heritage as a part of &apos;Buddhist Monuments in the Horyu-ji Area.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The temple is registered as a World Heritage as a part of &apos;Buddhist Monuments in the Horyu-ji Area.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The temple is registered as a World Heritage as a part of &apos;Buddhist Monuments in the Horyu-ji Area.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>寺名は20世紀末頃までの文献では「ほっきじ」と読んでいたが、現在、寺側では「ほうきじ」を正式の読みとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This temple had been called &apos;Hokki-ji&apos; in documents up to the end of the 20th century, but now, the official reading of the name admitted by the temple authority is &apos;Hoki-ji.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This temple had been called &apos;Hokki-ji&apos; in documents up to the end of the 20th century, but currently the official name admitted by the temple authority is &apos;Hoki-ji.&apos;</e>
<cmt>‘ ’→ &apos; &apos;now→currently the official name→the official reading of the name</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This temple had been called &apos;Hokki-ji&apos; in documents up to the end of the 20th century, but currently the official name admitted by the temple authority is &apos;Hoki-ji.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>これは、法起寺が法隆寺とともに世界遺産に登録されるにあたり、「法」の読み方に一貫性が欲しい、という理由により、高田良信法隆寺管長により、「ほうきじ」を正式とする、という判断がされたためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This decision is made by Ryoshin TAKADA, the chief abbot of Horyu-ji Temple when Horyu-ji and Hoki-ji were registered as the World Heritage at the same time, as he thought the names of Horyu-ji and Hoki-ji should desirably start with the same pronunciation because the first Chinese character of these names are the same.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This decision is made by Ryoshin TAKADA, the chief abbot of Horyu-ji Temple, when Horyu-ji and Hoki-ji were registered as the World Heritage at the same time, with the intention that the readings of the first Chinese character commonly used in the names of Horyu-ji and Hoki-ji should start with the same pronunciation &apos;ho&apos; in a consistent manner.</e>
<cmt>後半を書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This decision is made by Ryoshin TAKADA, the chief abbot of Horyu-ji Temple, when Horyu-ji and Hoki-ji were registered as the World Heritage at the same time, with the intention that the readings of the first Chinese character commonly used in the names of Horyu-ji and Hoki-ji should start with the same pronunciation &apos;ho&apos; in a consistent manner.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>長年の親しみもあり、今でも「ほっきじ」と読む人は多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even now, many people call this temple by the traditional name &apos;Hokki-ji.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even now, many people are accustomed to calling it by the traditional name &apos;Hokki-ji.&apos;</e>
<cmt>call this temple this temple→are accustomed to calling it‘ ’→ &apos; &apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even now, many people are accustomed to calling it by the traditional name &apos;Hokki-ji.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>世界遺産・法隆寺が所在する斑鳩（いかるが）の里には、他にも法起寺、法輪寺 (斑鳩町)、中宮寺など、聖徳太子ゆかりの古代寺院が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Ikaruga area where World Heritage Horyu-ji Temple is located, there are many other old temples that have connection with Prince Shotoku, such as Hoki-ji Temple, Horin-ji Temple (Ikaruga Town), Chugu-ji Temple, and others.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Ikaruga area, where World Heritage Horyu-ji Temple is located, in addition to Hoki-ji, there are many other old temples that have connection with Prince Shotoku, such as Horin-ji Temple (Ikaruga Town), Chugu-ji Temple, and others.</e>
<cmt>「他にも法起寺」とありますが、「法起寺の他にも」として訳しました。Hoki-ji Temple</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Ikaruga area, where World Heritage Horyu-ji Temple is located, in addition to Hoki-ji, there are many other old temples that have connection with Prince Shotoku, such as Horin-ji Temple (Ikaruga Town), Chugu-ji Temple, and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>この地が早くから仏教文化の栄えた地であったことがわかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to this fact, we can see that this area was a center of the Buddhist culture since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to this fact, we can see that this area was a center of the Buddhist culture since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to this fact, we can see that this area was a center of the Buddhist culture since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>法起寺は法隆寺東院の北東方の山裾の岡本地区に位置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoki-ji Temple is in Okamoto area, at the foot of a mountain in the northeast direction from Toin (East Precinct) of Horyu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoki-ji Temple is in Okamoto area, at the foot of a mountain on the northeast side of Toin (East Precinct) of Horyu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>at the foot of a mountain on the northeast side of Toin としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoki-ji Temple is in Okamoto area, at the foot of a mountain on the northeast side of Toin (East Precinct) of Horyu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>この地は聖徳太子が法華経を講じた「岡本宮」の跡地と言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This place is considered as the ruins of Okamoto Palace, where Prince Shotoku preached the Hokke-kyo Sutra (the Lotus Sutra).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This place is considered as the old site of Okamoto Palace, where Prince Shotoku preached the Hokke-kyo Sutra (the Lotus Sutra).</e>
<cmt>as the old site of Okamoto Palaceとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This place is considered as the old site of Okamoto Palace, where Prince Shotoku preached the Hokke-kyo Sutra (the Lotus Sutra).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>太子の遺言により子息の山背大兄王（やましろのおおえのおう）が岡本宮を寺に改めたのが法起寺の始まりとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that according to the will of Prince Shotoku, his son Prince Yamashiro no oe changed Okamoto Palace into a temple, and that was the origin of Hoki-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the origin of Hoki-ji Temple goes back to the time when Prince Yamashiro no oe, Prince Shotoku&apos;s son, converted Okamoto Palace into a temple according to his father&apos;s will.</e>
<cmt>構文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the origin of Hoki-ji Temple goes back to the time when Prince Yamashiro no oe, Prince Shotoku&apos;s son, converted Okamoto Palace into a temple according to his father&apos;s will.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>境内周辺の発掘調査の結果、掘立柱（礎石を据えずに地面に直接柱を立てる）建物の遺構が検出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At excavation and research of the precincts of the temple, ancient structural remnants of a dug-standing pillar building (the building whose pillars are erected directly against the ground, without using foundation stones) were found.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of the archaeological studies conducted around the temple, the remains of an ancient structures that had dug-standing pillars (a construction style in which pillars are erected directly against the ground, without using foundation stones) were found.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of the archaeological studies conducted around the temple, the remains of an ancient structures that had dug-standing pillars (a construction style in which pillars are erected directly against the ground, without using foundation stones) were found.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>つまり法起寺創建以前に何らかの前身建物が存在したことは確認されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This means that another building had been constructed here before Hoki-ji Temple was established.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This means that another building had already existed on the site before Hoki-ji Temple was established.</e>
<cmt>had already existed on the site before としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This means that another building had already existed on the site before Hoki-ji Temple was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>創建当時の法起寺の伽藍は、金堂と塔が左右（東西）に並び、法隆寺西院の伽藍配置と似る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Hoki-ji Temple was established, the Kon-do (main hall of Buddhist temple) and the pagoda placed in a row at the right side and the left side (in the east and in the west), and this placement is similar to that of Saiin (Western Precinct) of Horyu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Hoki-ji Temple was constructed, the complex had a similar layout to that of Saiin (Western Precinct) of Horyu-ji Temple with the Kondo (main hall of Buddhist temple) and the pagoda arranged side-by-side (east-west).</e>
<cmt>When Hoki-ji Temple was constructed, the complex had a similar layout to that of Saiin (Western Precinct) of Horyu-ji Temple with the Kondo (main hall of Buddhist temple) and the pagoda arranged side-by-side (east-west) …としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Hoki-ji Temple was constructed, the complex had a similar layout to that of Saiin (Western Precinct) of Horyu-ji Temple with the Kondo (main hall of Buddhist temple) and the pagoda arranged side-by-side (east-west).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>しかし法隆寺とは逆に金堂が西、塔が東に建っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Kon-do Hall was in the west and the pagoda was in the east, contrary to the placement of Horyu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in contrast to Horyu-ji Temple, its Kondo was placed in the west and the pagoda was in the east.</e>
<cmt>However, in contrast to Horyu-ji Temple,としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in contrast to Horyu-ji Temple, its Kondo was placed in the west and the pagoda was in the east.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>このような形式を「法起寺式伽藍配置」と称している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is called the &apos;Hokki-ji–style temple layout.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This layout design is called the &apos;Hokki-ji–style temple layout.&apos;</e>
<cmt>‘ ’→ &apos; &apos;This→This layout design</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This layout design is called the &apos;Hokki-ji–style temple layout.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>なお、創建当時の建築で現存するものは三重塔のみである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The original building in existence is the three-story pagoda only.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the original structures, the only building in existence is the three-storied pagoda.</e>
<cmt>Among the original structures, the only building in existence is the three-storied pagoda.としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the original structures, the only building in existence is the three-storied pagoda.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="21">
<j>三重塔の建立時期、及び寺の建立経緯については、『聖徳太子伝私記』（仁治3年・1242年、顕真著）という中世の記録に引用されている「法起寺三重塔露盤銘」という史料がよりどころとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the three-story pagoda was established and why the temple was established are shown in a historical material named &apos;Hokki-ji Sanjuno Robanmei (the description carved on the base of the pagoda finial of Hokki-ji Temple)&apos; that was cited in a record in the medieval period named &quot;Shotoku Taishi denshiki&quot; (the Private Recollections of the Life of Prince Shotoku; by Kenshin, published in 1242).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The construction period of the three-storied pagoda and the details of the temple&apos;s foundation are known based on the inscription carved on the base of the pagoda final called &apos;Hokki-ji Sanjunoto Robanmei,&apos; which was a historical material cited in a medieval document titled &quot;Shotoku Taishi denshiki&quot; (the Private Recollections of the Life of Prince Shotoku) (written by Kenshin in 1242).</e>
<cmt>前半を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the three-story pagoda was established and how the temple was constructed are shown in a historical material called &apos;Hokki-ji Sanjuno Robanmei&apos; (the description carved on the base of the pagoda finial of Hokki-ji Temple) which was cited in a medieval document titled &quot;Shotoku Taishi denshiki&quot; (the Private Recollections of the Life of Prince Shotoku) (written by Kenshin in 1242.</e>
<cmt>known based →can be referred to the historical record called前半は翻訳者の訳の構成に戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>それによれば、岡本宮は聖徳太子の遺願によって寺に改められることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the document, Okamoto Palace was changed into a temple following Prince Shotoku&apos;s will.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to this, Okamoto Palace was converted into a temple following Prince Shotoku&apos;s will.</e>
<cmt>According to thisconverted into としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to this, Okamoto Palace was converted into a temple following Prince Shotoku&apos;s will.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>舒明天皇10年（638年）、福亮僧正なる人物によって弥勒仏を本尊とする金堂が建てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 638, the Kon-do Hall was constructed by the direction of a priest, Fukuryo, with Miroku-butsu (Miroku Buddha) as its principal image.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 638, the Kondo was constructed by the direction of a priest called Fukuryo, and Miroku-butsu (Miroku Buddha) was enshrined as its principal image.</e>
<cmt>the Kondo was constructedand Miroku-butsu (Miroku Buddha) was enshrined としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 638, the Kondo was constructed by the direction of a priest called Fukuryo, and Miroku-butsu (Miroku Buddha) was enshrined as its principal image.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>塔は恵施 (僧)僧正によって天武天皇13年（684年）に起工、慶雲3年（706年）に至って完成したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The construction of the pagoda started in 684 by the direction of a priest, Eshi, and finished in 706.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The construction of the pagoda started in 684 by the direction of Priest Eshi and finished in 706.</e>
<cmt>a priest, Eshi→Priest Eshi</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The construction of the pagoda started in 684 by the direction of Priest Eshi and finished in 706.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>金堂の建立から塔の完成までには数十年を要したことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This shows it took several decades from the start of Kon-do Hall construction to the completion of the pagoda.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This shows it took several decades from the start of the construction of Kondo to the completion of the pagoda.</e>
<cmt>start of the construction of Kondoとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This shows it took several decades from the start of the construction of Kondo to the completion of the pagoda.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>「法起寺三重塔露盤銘」については、かつて建築史学者の関野貞（1868年 - 1935年）などが偽作説を唱えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An architectural historian Tadashi SEKINO (1868-1935) and others advocated that the &apos;Hokki-ji Sanjuno To Robanmei&apos; was a counterfeit.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An architectural historian Tadashi SEKINO (1868-1935) and others advocated that the &apos;Hoki-ji Sanjunoto Robanmei&apos; was a counterfeit.</e>
<cmt>&apos;Hoki-ji Sanjunoto Robanmei&apos; としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An architectural historian Tadashi SEKINO (1868-1935) and others advocated that the &apos;Hoki-ji Sanjunoto Robanmei&apos; was a counterfeit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>しかしその後の研究の進展により、おおむね信頼できる史料と認められるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, according to the research conducted later, it is now considered to be a substantially reliable historic material.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, according to the research conducted later, it is now considered to be a substantially reliable historic material.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, according to the research conducted later, it is now considered to be a substantially reliable historic material.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>建築様式の点からも、法起寺塔を706年頃の完成と見るのはおおむね妥当とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the viewpoint of architectural style, it is also considered appropriate to suppose the completion period of the Hoki-ji Temple pagoda to be around 706.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the viewpoint of architectural style, it is also considered appropriate to estimate the completion period of the Hoki-ji Temple pagoda to be around 706.</e>
<cmt>suppose→estimate</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the viewpoint of architectural style, it is also considered appropriate to estimate the completion period of the Hoki-ji Temple pagoda to be around 706.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>三重塔</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Three-story pagoda</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Three-storied pagoda</e>
<cmt>Three-storied pagodaとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Three-storied pagoda</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>建立時期については前述のとおりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The information on the period of completion is shown above,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The period of completion is stated above.</e>
<cmt>the information冗長なので削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The period of completion is stated above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>高さ24メートルで、三重塔としては日本最古である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is 24m tall and the oldest three-story pagoda in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The pagoda that measures 24 m tall is the oldest three-storied pagoda in Japan.</e>
<cmt>The pagoda that measures 24 m tall is the oldest three-storied pagoda としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The pagoda that measures 24 m tall is the oldest three-storied pagoda in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>また、特異な形式の三重塔である薬師寺東塔を除けば、日本最大の三重塔と言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also it is the largest three-story pagoda in Japan, excluding Yakushiji Toto (East Pagoda) that has a peculiar style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said to be the largest three-storied pagoda in Japan, except for Yakushi-ji Toto (East Pagoda of Yakushi-ji Temple) that has a peculiar style.</e>
<cmt>It is also said to be the としました。largest three-storied pagodaとしました。Yakushi-ji Toto (East Pagoda of Yakushi-ji Temple)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said to be the largest three-storied pagoda in Japan, except for Yakushi-ji Toto (East Pagoda of Yakushi-ji Temple) that has a peculiar style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>日本の木造塔は方三間（正側面のいずれにも柱が4本並び、柱間の数が3つになるという意味）が原則である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a general rule, wooden pagoda in Japan is constructed in hosangen (the style to use four pillars and to create three areas between the pillars on every side).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処；「方三間」について用語集ではthree squared mats となっており、畳３枚ということでここの意味とは異なるので、音訳と説明とで訳出しました（定訳は不明）。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a general rule, a wooden pagoda in Japan is constructed with hosangen method (a construction method to use four pillars and to create three areas between the pillars on every side).</e>
<cmt>is constructed with hosangen method (a construction method to use four pillarsとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a general rule, a wooden pagoda in Japan is constructed with hosangen method (a construction method to use four pillars and to create three areas between the pillars on every side).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>しかしこの塔は初層・二層の柱間が3間、三層の柱間が2間という特殊な形式になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this temple has a special style; there are three areas between the pillars in the first and second layers, while there are two areas between the pillars in the third layer.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this temple has a special style; there are three areas between the pillars in the first and second layers, while there are two areas between the pillars in the third layer.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this temple has a special style; there are three areas between the pillars in the first and second layers, while there are two areas between the pillars in the third layer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>ほぼ同時代の法隆寺五重塔も最上部の五層の柱間を2間としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The five-story pagoda in Horyu-ji Temple, constructed around the same time, also has this two-area style in its top fifth layer.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The five-storied pagoda in Horyu-ji Temple, constructed around the same time, also has this two-area style on its top fifth layer.</e>
<cmt>five-storied pagodaとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The five-storied pagoda in Horyu-ji Temple, constructed around the same time, also has this two-area style on its top fifth layer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>また法隆寺五重塔の初層・三層・五層の大きさが法起寺三重塔の初層・二層・三層にほぼ等しいことが指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also found that the sizes of the first, second and third layers of Hoki-ji Temple are almost the same as those of the first, third and fifth layers of Horyu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also pointed out that the sizes of the first, second and third layers of Hoki-ji Temple are almost the same as those of the first, third and fifth layers of Horyu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also pointed out that the sizes of the first, second and third layers of Hoki-ji Temple are almost the same as those of the first, third and fifth layers of Horyu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>この塔は中世に大きく改造され、三層の柱間も3間に変更されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The pagoda was remodeled greatly in the medieval period and the areas between the pillars in the third layer were changed into three.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The pagoda was modified greatly in the medieval time and the number of the areas existed between the pillars on the third layer were also changed into three.</e>
<cmt>The pagoda was modified in the medieval time the number of the areas existed on the third layeralso changedとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The pagoda was modified greatly in the medieval time and the number of the areas existed between the pillars on the third layer were also changed into three.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>しかし1970年～1975年の解体修理の際、部材に残る痕跡を元に、創建当時の形に復元した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, during the knock-down repair in 1970-1975, the pagoda was restored in the way it was in establishment, using the traces on the components as clues.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, during the knock-down repair in 1970-1975, the pagoda was restored to its original state, following the traces on the components as clues.</e>
<cmt>一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, during the disassembly and restoration in 1970-1975, the pagoda was restored to its original state, based on the traces left on the structural members.</e>
<cmt>自然な英語にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>二層と三層の高欄（手すり）も解体修理時の復元である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The handrails in the second and third layers were also restored during this repair.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The handrails in the second and third layers were also restored during this repair.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The handrails in the second and third layers were also restored during this repair.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>伽藍</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buddhist temple placement</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structures in the temple</e>
<cmt>以下の説明に合う意味にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structures in the temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="39">
<j>三重塔 - 既述</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Three-story pagoda: described above</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Three-storied pagoda: described above</e>
<cmt>Three-storied pagodaとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Three-storied pagoda: described above</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="40">
<j>講堂 - 1694年の再建</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kodo Hall (lecture hall): restored in 1694</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kodo (lecture hall): restored in 1694</e>
<cmt>Hall を取りました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kodo (lecture hall): restored in 1694</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="41">
<j>聖天堂 - 1863年の再建</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoten-do Hall: restored in 1863</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shotendo (a hall dedicated to a deity Shoten [Ganesha]): restored in 1863</e>
<cmt>Shotendo (a hall dedicated to a deity Shoten [Ganesha])としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shotendo (a hall dedicated to a deity Shoten [Ganesha]): restored in 1863</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="42">
<j>表門 - 江戸時代初期の再建、四脚門</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Front gate: restored at the beginning of Edo period; four-legged gate</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Front gate: restored at the beginning of Edo period; four-legged gate</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Front gate: restored at the beginning of Edo period; four-legged gate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cultural property</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cultural properties</e>
<cmt>propertiesとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cultural properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="43">
<j>境内が国の史跡に指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The precincts are designated as the national historic site.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The precincts are designated as a national historic site.</e>
<cmt>the→a</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The precincts are designated as a national historic site.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>国宝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National treasure</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National Treasure</e>
<cmt>Treasureとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National Treasure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="44">
<j>三重塔</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Three-story pagoda</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Three-storied pagoda</e>
<cmt>Three-storiedとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Three-storied pagoda</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>重要文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important Cultural Property</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>Propertiesとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="45">
<j>木造十一面観音立像 - 収蔵庫に安置。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wooden standing statue of Eleven-faced Kannon: kept in the repository</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wooden standing statue of Eleven-faced Kannon: in storage (not open to the public)</e>
<cmt>収蔵庫に安置：kept in the repository→in storage (not open to the public)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wooden standing statue of Eleven-faced Kannon: in storage (not open to the public)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>像高3.5メートル。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is 3.5m tall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is 3.5 m tall.</e>
<cmt>3.5m→3.5 m</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is 3.5 m tall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>10世紀後半の作とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered to have been made in the latter half of 10th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered to have been made in the latter half of 10th century.</e>
<cmt>10th→10th</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered to have been made in the latter half of 10th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="48">
<j>銅造菩薩立像 - 7世紀後半の作とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Standing statue of Dozo Bosatsu: considered to have been made in the latter half of the 7th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bronze standing statue of Bosatsu (Bodhisattva): considered to have been made in the latter half of the 7th century.</e>
<cmt>Standing statue of Dozo Bosatsu→Bronze standing statue of Bosatsu (Bodhisattva)7th→7th</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bronze standing statue of Bosatsu (Bodhisattva): considered to have been made in the latter half of the 7th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>奈良国立博物館に寄託。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is deposited in Nara National Museum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is deposited in Nara National Museum.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is deposited in Nara National Museum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>所在地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Address</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Address</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Address</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="50">
<j>〒636-0100 奈良県生駒郡斑鳩町大字岡本1873番地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1873 Oaza Okamoto, Ikaruga Town, Ikoma County, Nara Prefecture 636-0100</e>
<cmt>郵便番号について、原文は636-0100となっておりそのまま訳していますが、現実には636-0102かと思われます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1873 Oaza Okamoto, Ikaruga-cho, Ikoma-gun, Nara Prefecture 636-0100</e>
<cmt>Ikaruga Town, Ikoma Country→Ikaruga-cho, Ikoma-gun</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1873 Oaza Okamoto, Ikaruga-cho, Ikoma-gun, Nara Prefecture 636-0100</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>アクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="51">
<j>西日本旅客鉄道法隆寺駅下車</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">West Japan Railway Horyuji Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nearest station: Horyuji Station (West Japan Railway)</e>
<cmt>Nearest station: Horyuji Station (West Japan Railway)としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nearest station: Horyuji Station (West Japan Railway)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Butszo(id:160475), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Bueller 007(id:30970), 浩(id:70121), Mobnoboka(id:35218), КОЛЯ(id:59429), Reggaeman(id:6214), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Urania(id:7213), COCKY(id:19672), ロロ(id:104252), Loveless(id:129239), 663highland(id:18755), Dnssgh(id:118255), Ffokoob(id:259570), Ｈｉｒｏ２００６(id:59115), Ajax(id:11202), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>