<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>石園座多久虫玉神社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iwazononiimasu-takumushitama-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iwazononiimasu-takumushitama-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iwazononiimasu-takumushitama-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>石園座多久虫玉神社（いわぞのにいますたくむしたまじんじゃ）は、奈良県大和高田市片塩町に鎮座する神社である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iwazononiimasu-takumushitama-jinja Shrine is located in Katashio-cho, Yamatotakada City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iwazononiimasu-takumushitama-jinja Shrine is located in Katashio-cho, Yamatotakada City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iwazononiimasu-takumushitama-jinja Shrine is located in Katashio-cho, Yamatotakada City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>式内社で、旧社格は県社。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a Shikinai-sha (a shrine listed in Engishiki laws) and its old classification of shrines is a prefectural shrine.</e>
<cmt>式内社が初出のため、(　)内の説明を併記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a Shikinai-sha (shrine listed in the Engishiki laws) and its old shrine ranking is kensha (prefectural shrine [of prefectures other than Kyoto and Osaka]).</e>
<cmt>Engishikiの前に冠詞を挿入、「県社」は社格を表す用語なのでローマ字表記を挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a Shikinai-sha (shrine listed in the Engishiki laws) and its old shrine ranking is kensha (prefectural shrine [of prefectures other than Kyoto and Osaka]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>通称 竜王宮として地元住民からは篤い信仰を集めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is commonly known as Ryuogu, having many religious local residents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is commonly known as Ryuogu, and many local residents have strong belief in the spirit of the shrine.</e>
<cmt>後半が不自然だったので書き直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is commonly known as Ryuogu, and many local residents have strong belief in the spirit of the shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>尚、横大路に沿うように、大神神社を龍の頭、当神社を龍の胴、當麻町の長尾神社を龍の尾とする伝承がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it has been said that Omiwa-jinja Shrine is a head of a dragon, this shrine is its body, and Nagao-jinja Shrine in Taima-cho is its tail along Yokooji Road.</e>
<cmt>文脈より、横大路にはRoadを追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, it has been said that Omiwa-jinja Shrine is a head of a dragon, this shrine is its body, and Nagao-jinja Shrine in Taima-cho is its tail as these shrines line the Yokooji Road.</e>
<cmt>「横大路に沿うように」の箇所をわかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, it has been said that Omiwa-jinja Shrine is a head of a dragon, this shrine is its body, and Nagao-jinja Shrine in Taima-cho is its tail as these shrines line the Yokooji Road.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>祭神</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enshrined Deity</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enshrined Deities</e>
<cmt>Deityを複数形にしました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enshrined Deities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>建玉依比古命・建玉依比賣命を主祭神とし、豊玉比古命・トヨタマヒメを配祀する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taketamayorihiko no Mikoto and Taketamayoribime no Mikoto are shusaijin (main enshrined deities) and Toyotamahiko no Mikado and Toyotama-hime are enshrined as associate gods.</e>
<cmt>主祭神が初出のため、(　)内の説明を併記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taketamayorihiko no Mikoto and Taketamayoribime no Mikoto are shusaijin (main enshrined deities) and Toyotamahiko no Mikado and Toyotama-hime are enshrined as associate gods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taketamayorihiko no Mikoto and Taketamayoribime no Mikoto are shusaijin (main enshrined deities) and Toyotamahiko no Mikado and Toyotama-hime are enshrined as associate gods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>建玉依比古命とは、賀茂別雷神社（上賀茂神社）摂社・土師尾社や日吉大社摂社・樹下若宮に祀られる鴨玉依比古命のこととされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taketamayorihiko no Mikoto has been said to be Kamotamayorihiko no Mikoto, who has been enshrined in Hajio-sha Shrine, a sessha (auxiliary shrine (dedicated to a deity close-related to that of a main shrine)) of Kamowakeikazuchi-jinja Shrine (Kamigamo-jinja Shrine), and Kikanowakamiya Shrine, a sessya of Hiyoshi-taisha Shrine.</e>
<cmt>摂社が初出のため、(　)内の説明を併記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taketamayorihiko no Mikoto is said to be the same as Kamotamayorihiko no Mikoto, who is enshrined at Hajio-sha Shrine, a sessha (auxiliary shrine [dedicated to a deity close-related to that of a main shrine]) of Kamowakeikazuchi-jinja Shrine (also known as Kamigamo-jinja Shrine), and Kikanowakamiya Shrine, a sessha of Hiyoshi-taisha Shrine.</e>
<cmt>時制を現在形に修正しました。かっこ内のかっこを[]に変更しました。神社の別名の前には[also known as]を挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taketamayorihiko no Mikoto is said to be the same as Kamotamayorihiko no Mikoto, who is enshrined at Hajio-sha Shrine, a sessha (auxiliary shrine [dedicated to a deity close-related to that of a main shrine]) of Kamowakeikazuchi-jinja Shrine (also known as Kamigamo-jinja Shrine), and Kikanowakamiya Shrine, a sessha of Hiyoshi-taisha Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>ただし、社名からは、本来の祭神は「多久虫玉神」ということになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, according to the name of the shrine, the original enshrined deity is &quot;Takumushitama God&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the original enshrined deity should be a god called Takumushitama, written as 多久虫玉神 in Japanese, because of the name of the shrine.</e>
<cmt>全体的に書き直しが必要です。また、この後に漢字表記に関する記述があるため、訳文内に漢字表記を残しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the original enshrined deity should be a god called Takumushitama, written as &apos;多久虫玉神&apos; in Japanese, because of the name of the shrine.</e>
<cmt>&apos; &apos; 追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>「虫」は「豆（づ）」の誤記という説もあり、『大和の神祭祀』（田中昭三 編著）では、当社の本来の祭神は多久都玉命とシタテルヒメであろうと唱えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said &quot;Mushi (insects)&quot; in the name of the shrine was wrongly written instead of &quot;Zu (beans)&quot;, so &quot;Yamato no Shinsaishi&quot; (compiled by Shozo TANAKA) tells that the original enshrined deity of this shrine might be Takutsutama no Mikado and Shitateru-hime.</e>
<cmt>「虫」「豆」はローマ字表記と意味を補記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that the Chinese character 虫 (which literally means insects) in the name of the shrine was wrongly used instead of 豆 (which literally means beans), pronounced as zu in Japanese, and a book called &quot;Yamato no Shinsaishi&quot; (compiled by Shozo TANAKA) insists that the original enshrined deities of this shrine must be Takutsutama no Mikado and Shitateru-hime.</e>
<cmt>漢字表記を訳文内に残しました（名称表記に関する説明であり、ローマ字だけでは不十分と判断したため）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that the Chinese character &apos;虫&apos; (which literally means insects) in the name of the shrine was wrongly used instead of &apos;豆&apos; (which literally means beans), pronounced as zu in Japanese, and a book called &quot;Yamato no Shinsaishi&quot; (compiled by Shozo TANAKA) insists that the original enshrined deities of this shrine must be Takutsutama no Mikado and Shitateru-hime.</e>
<cmt>&apos; &apos; 追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="10">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>創建年代は不明であるが、第三代安寧天皇の時代の都である片塩浮穴宮跡の伝承地に鎮座している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is unclear when it was built, but it is located in the traditional place, Katashio Ukiana no Miyaato (the ruins of Katashio Ukiana Palace), which was the capital in the period of the third Emperor Annei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is unclear when it was built, but it is located at a traditional place called Katashio Ukiana no Miyaato (the ruins of the Katashio Ukiana Palace), which was the capital in the reign of the third Emperor, Annei.</e>
<cmt>前置詞および冠詞、カンマの用法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is unclear when it was built, but it is located at a traditional place called Katashio Ukiana no Miyaato (the ruins of the Katashio Ukiana Palace), which was the capital in the reign of the third Emperor, Annei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>崇神天皇の時代に勅祭が行われたと伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been said that chokusai (festival held by imperial order) was held in the period of Emperor Sujin.</e>
<cmt>勅祭が初出のため、(　)内の説明を併記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been said that a chokusai (festival held by imperial order) was held in the reign of Emperor Sujin.</e>
<cmt>冠詞の追加、periodをreignに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been said that a chokusai (festival held by imperial order) was held in the reign of Emperor Sujin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>延喜式神名帳では「大和国葛下郡 石園坐多久虫玉神社 二座」と記載され、大社に列し、月次・新嘗の幣帛に預ると記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Engishiki jimmyocho (a register of shrines in Japan), it was written &quot;Iwazononiimasu-takumushitama-jinja Shrine Niza in Katsuraginoshimo County, Yamato Province&quot;, listed as one of Taisha (grand shrines), and also written that the shrine was offered heihaku (a sacramental strip of silk (offered to the gods)) on monthly Niiname.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Engishiki Jimmyocho (register of shrines in Japan) says, &quot;Iwazononiimasu-takumushitama-jinja Shrine with two seats for deities in Katsuraginoshimo County, Yamato Province,&quot; this shrine is labeled as Taisha (grand shrines), and the shrine receives heihaku (Shinto offering of cloth) as a Tsukinami shrine (shrine which receives heihaku at a festival called Tsukinami-sai) and Niiname shrine (shrine which receives heihaku at an annual festival called Niiname-sai).</e>
<cmt>冠詞の修正を行いました。前半の表現を変更しました。「二座」が未翻訳だったため修正しました（座は神様の席数の単位）。「月次」が誤訳だったため訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Engishiki Jimmyocho (register of shrines in Japan) says, &apos;Iwazononiimasu-takumushitama-jinja Shrine with two seats for deities in Katsuraginoshimo County, Yamato Province,&apos; this shrine is labeled as Taisha (grand shrines), and the shrine receives heihaku (Shinto offering of cloth) as a Tsukinami shrine (shrine which receives heihaku at a festival called Tsukinami-sai) and Niiname shrine (shrine which receives heihaku at an annual festival called Niiname-sai).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot; → &apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="14">
<j>古くは「射園神：いそのかみ」と呼ばれたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In ancient times, it has been said the shrine was called &quot;Isonokami&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the shrine was called Isonokami in ancient times.</e>
<cmt>文の構成を修正、時制を修正、引用符は不要。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the shrine was called Isonokami in ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>石上神宮がある石上（いそのかみ）と何らかの関係があるのか興味深い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is interesting that it may have some relationship with Isonokami, the name of place, where Isonokami shrine is.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is interesting that it may have something to do with a place called Isonokami, where Isonokami-jingu Shrine is.</e>
<cmt>「関係がある」をhave something to do with に変更、文の構成を変更、「石上神宮」の英語表記を変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is interesting that it may have something to do with a place called Isonokami, where Isonokami-jingu Shrine is.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="16">
<j>また、宮中に祀られていた園韓神社と関係があるとの説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, there is another story that it had a relationship with Sonokarakamino-yashiro Shrine enshrined in the imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, some people believe that it had something to do with Sonokarakamino-yashiro Shrine enshrined at the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>「という説もある」の表現を変更、Imperial Courtの頭文字を大文字に。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, some people believe that it had something to do with Sonokarakamino-yashiro Shrine enshrined at the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="17">
<j>昭和6年に県社に昇格した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It promoted to a prefectural shrine in 1931.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was promoted to a prefectural shrine in 1931.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was promoted to a prefectural shrine in 1931.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>昭和41年、神社本庁の別表神社に加列された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was added to Beppyo jinja (Shrines on the Special List) in 1966.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was added to shrines on the exceptional list (called Beppyo-jinja shrine) of The Association of Shinto Shrines in 1966.</e>
<cmt>「神社本庁の別表神社」という表現を用語集通りの表現に変更しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was added to shrines on the exceptional list (called Beppyo-jinja shrine) of The Association of Shinto Shrines in 1966.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="19">
<j>アクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>鉄道：近畿日本鉄道近鉄南大阪線高田市駅下車すぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Railway; Get off at Takada-shi Station of Kintetsu Minamiosaka Line, Kinki Nippon Railway</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By Train; Takada-shi Station of the Kintetsu Minamiosaka Line, Kinki Nippon Railway</e>
<cmt>「鉄道」の表現の変更など</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By Train; Takada-shi Station of the Kintetsu Minamiosaka Line, Kinki Nippon Railway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="21">
<j>道路：国道166号</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Road: National Route 166</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By Car: National Route 166</e>
<cmt>アクセスの説明をしているので「道路」を直訳で「Road」とするのは意味がありません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By Car: National Route 166</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Ikespirit(id:120987), Nnh(id:474), Yamato(id:11885), Kiev(id:13022), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>