<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>長尾神社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagao-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagao-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagao-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>長尾神社（ながおじんじゃ）は、奈良県葛城市にある神社。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagao-jinja Shrine is located in Katsuragi City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagao-jinja Shrine is located in Katsuragi City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagao-jinja Shrine is located in Katsuragi City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>旧大和国葛下郡の式内社で、旧社格は郷社。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a Shikinai-sha (shrine listed in Engishiki laws) of Katsuragi-gun, Yamato Province and was categorized as a gosha (a village shrine) in the old shrine ranking.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a Shikinai-sha (shrine listed in ancient Engishiki laws) of Katsuragi district, Yamato Province and was categorised as a gosha (village shrine) in the old shrine ranking.</e>
<cmt>gun &gt; district. categorized &gt; categorised.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a Shikinai-sha (shrine listed in ancient Engishiki laws) of Katsuragi district, Yamato Province and was categorised as a gosha (village shrine) in the old shrine ranking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>歴史・概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History ・ Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History and Summary</e>
<cmt>記号をandにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History and Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>このあたりを支配していた長尾氏の氏神とされるが定かでない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said to have been the guardian deity of the Nagao clan who governed this area, however, that is uncertain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said to have housed the guardian deity of the Nagao clan who governed the area, however, this fact is unconfirmed.</e>
<cmt>been the &gt; housed the. that is uncertain &gt; this fact is unconfirmed.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said to have housed the guardian deity of the Nagao clan who governed the area, however, this fact is unconfirmed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また吉野連との関係があるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said to have been related to a family of Yoshinoren.</e>
<cmt>吉野連:定訳不明下記のHPによると一族の名前であるようなので、「吉野蓮一族」として訳してあります。http://yasaka.hp.infoseek.co.jp/nagaojinja.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said to have been related to the Yoshinoren family.</e>
<cmt>a family &gt; the family.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said to have been related to the Yoshinoren family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>鎮座地は竹内街道、長尾街道、横大路 (奈良県)が交差する交通の要衝であり、現在に至るまで交通安全祈願の神として祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shrine is located at the important traffic junction where Nagao-kaido Road and Yoko-oji Road (Nara Prefecture) intersect; and it has been enshrined as the god of traffic safety until today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shrine is located at the key junction where Nagao-kaido Road and Yoko-oji Road (Nara Prefecture) intersect and has been home to the god of traffic safety until today.</e>
<cmt>important &gt; key. enshrined &gt; home to.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shrine is located at the key junction where Nagao-kaido Road and Yoko-oji Road (Nara Prefecture) intersect and has been home to the god of traffic safety until today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>延喜式神名帳に「葛下郡長尾神社、大、月次、新嘗」と記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is listed as a &apos;Nagao-jinja Shrine in Katsuragi-gun, taisya (a grand shrine), Tsukinami-sai festival, Niiname-sai festival (ceremonial offering by the Emperor of newly-harvested rice to the deities)&apos; in the Engishiki jimmyocho (a register of shrines in Japan).</e>
<cmt>大:定訳不明「大社」と解釈して訳してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Engishiki jimmyocho (a register of shrines in Japan), it is listed as: &apos;A Nagao-jinja Shrine in Katsuragi-gun, taisya (a grand shrine), Tsukinami-sai festival, Niiname-sai festival (ceremonial offering by the Emperor of newly-harvested rice to the deities)&apos;</e>
<cmt>順番を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Engishiki jimmyocho (a register of shrines in Japan), it is listed as: &apos;A Nagao-jinja Shrine in Katsuragi-gun, taisha (a grand shrine), Tsukinami-sai Festival, Niiname-sai Festival (ceremonial offering by the Emperor of newly-harvested rice to the deities)&apos;</e>
<cmt>「taisya」を「taisha」に修正しました。「festival」を「Festival」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>伝説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Legend</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Legend</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Legend</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>むかし、大和に大きなヘビが住み、三輪山を三重にとりまき、その尾は長尾までとどいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A long time ago, there was a giant snake in Yamato Province; it curled three times around Mt. Miwa and its tail reached Nagao.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A long time ago, there was a giant snake in Yamato Province; it curled three times around Mt. Miwa and its tail reached Nagao.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A long time ago, there was a giant snake in Yamato Province; it curled three times around Mt. Miwa and its tail reached Nagao.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>大神神社（桜井市）が頭で、長尾神社はその尾にあたると言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Omiwa-jinja Shrine (Sakurai City) was located at the head and Nagao-jinja Shrine was at the tail.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Omiwa-jinja Shrine (Sakurai City) was located at its head and Nagao-jinja Shrine at its tail.</e>
<cmt>the &gt;its. was at the &gt; at its</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Omiwa-jinja Shrine (Sakurai City) was located at its head and Nagao-jinja Shrine at its tail.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>また、竜が住んでいたともされ、石園座多久虫玉神社（大和高田市）は竜の頭であり、長尾神社は竜の尾にあたるとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, it is also said that there was a dragon; and Iwazononiimasu-takumushitama-jinja Shrine (Yamatotakada City) was located at the head and Nagao-jinja Shrine was at the tail.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, it is also said that there was a dragon and Iwazononiimasu-takumushitama-jinja Shrine (Yamatotakada City) was located at its head and Nagao-jinja Shrine at its tail.</e>
<cmt>the &gt;its. was at the &gt; at its</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, it is also said that there was a dragon and Iwazononiimasu-takumushitama-jinja Shrine (Yamatotakada City) was located at its head and Nagao-jinja Shrine at its tail.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kansai explorer(id:48975), Point136(id:211299), KENPEI(id:11349), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>