<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>讃岐神社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanuki-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanuki-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanuki-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>讃岐神社（さぬきじんじゃ）は、奈良県北葛城郡広陵町にある神社である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanuki-jinja is located at Koryocho, Kitakatsuragigun in Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanuki-jinja Shrine is a Shinto shrine is located in Koryocho, Kitakatsuragigun, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanuki-jinja Shrine is a Shinto shrine located in Koryo-cho, Kitakatsuragi-gun, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>文法修正しました。住所表記を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>式内社で、旧社格は村社。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shikinaisha Shrine listed in the Engishiki and Sonsha Shrine (a villge shrine) in the old shrine ranking.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a shikinaisha (listed in the Engishiki Jinmyocho) and was classified as a sonsha (village shrine) under the old shrine ranking system.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a shikinaisha (listed in the Engishiki Jinmyocho) and was classified as a sonsha (village shrine) under the old shrine ranking system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>祭神</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enshrined Deities</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enshrined Deities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enshrined deities</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>現在は、国魂・若宇加能売命・大物主を祀るとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, it is said that the shrine enshrines Kunitama,,Wakaukanome-no-Mikoto and Omononushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present, it is said that the shrine enshrines Kunitama,,Wakaukanome-no-Mikoto and Omononushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present, it is said that the shrine enshrines Kunitama, Wakaukanome-no-Mikoto and Omononushi.</e>
<cmt>カンマ削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>『日本三代実録』元慶7年（883年）12月2日条には「散吉大建命・散吉伊能城神に神階従五位下を授ける」という記述があり、当社の神のこととみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku (a history book written in the Heian Period)&quot; describes, in the article of December 2 in 883, that Sanukiotakeru-no-Mikoto and Sanukiinoki-no-kami are conferred the divine rank of the Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade, which suggests they are the deities of the shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku&quot; (a history book written in the Heian Period) describes in the article of December 2 in 883 that Sanukiotakeru-no-Mikoto and Sanukiinoki-no-kami were conferred the divine rank of the Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade, which suggests they are the deities of the shrine.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku&quot; (a history book written in the Heian period) describes in the article of December 2 in 883 that Sanukiotakeru-no-Mikoto and Sanukiinoki-no-kami were conferred the divine rank of the Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade, which suggests they are the deities of the shrine.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>鎮座地名の「三吉」は「みつよし」と読むが、かつては「散吉」と書いて「さぬき」と読んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of the enshrined place&quot;三吉&quot; is pronounced as &apos;Mitsuyoshi&apos; but formerly it was written as &quot;散吉&quot;and pronounced as &apos;Sanuki&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The area in which the shrine is located (三吉) is pronounced as &apos;Mitsuyoshi&apos; but was formerly written &apos;散吉&apos;and pronounced as &apos;Sanuki&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The area in which the shrine is located (三吉) is pronounced as &apos;Mitsuyoshi&apos; but was formerly written &apos;散吉&apos; and pronounced as &apos;Sanuki.&apos;</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入しました。ピリオド位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>一帯は讃岐国の忌部氏が移り住んだ地で、讃岐の故郷の神を勧請し創建したものとみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Inbe clan moved to the area from their birthplace in Sanuki Province and founded the shrine transferring a divided tutelary deity to a new location.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Inbe clan moved to the area from their birthplace in Sanuki Province and founded the shrine, transferring a divided tutelary deity to the new location.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Inbe clan moved to the area from their birthplace in Sanuki Province and founded the shrine, transferring a divided tutelary deity to the new location.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>延喜式神名帳では「大和国広瀬郡 讃岐神社」と記載され、小社に列格している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shrine is listed as &apos;Sanuki-jinja Shrine, Hirose District, Yamato Province&apos; and ranked as shosha (small shrine) in the Engishiki law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shrine is listed as &apos;Sanuki-jinja Shrine, Hirose District, Yamato Province&apos; and ranked as shosha (small shrine) in the Engishiki law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shrine is listed as &apos;Sanuki-jinja Shrine, Hirose District, Yamato Province&apos; and ranked as shosha (small shrine) in the Engishiki law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>広瀬川合（現 廣瀬大社）の若宇加乃売命を勧請したことにより、江戸時代までは「広瀬大明神」「南川合明神」と称していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shrine was known as &apos;Hirose Daimyojin God&apos; or &apos;Minami Kawai Myojin God&apos; until the Edo period because of the transfer of the divided deity Wakaukanome-no-Mikoto from Hirose Kawai (the present Hirose Taisha Shrine) to the shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shrine was known as &apos;Hirose Daimyojin&apos; or &apos;Minami Kawai Myojin&apos; until the Edo period because of the transfer of the divided deity Wakaukanome-no-Mikoto from Hirose Kawai (the present Hirose Taisha Shrine) to the shrine.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;God&quot; (2)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shrine was known as &apos;Hirose Daimyojin&apos; or &apos;Minami Kawai Myojin&apos; until the Edo period because of the transfer of the divided deity Wakaukanome-no-Mikoto from Hirose Kawai (the present Hirose Taisha Shrine) to the shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>慶長19年（1611年）正月に火災があり、現在の本殿はそのときに再建されたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A fire broke out in January, 1611 and the existing main hall was rebuilt after the fire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A fire broke out in January, 1611 and the existing main hall was rebuilt after the fire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A fire broke out in January 1611 and the existing main hall was rebuilt after the fire.</e>
<cmt>カンマ削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>竹取物語との関連</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Relevance to Taketori Monogatari (The tale of Bamboo Cutter)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Relevance to Taketori Monogatari (The tale of Bamboo Cutter)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Relevance to Taketori Monogatari (The tale of Bamboo Cutter)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>竹取物語に登場する「竹取の翁」が名を「讃岐造（さぬきのみやつこ）」ということから、これが大和国広瀬郡散吉郷のことであるとして、「竹取物語ゆかりの神社」を称している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shrine calls itself &apos;a shrine in connection with Taketori Monogatari&apos; since &apos;Taketori no Okina&apos;,a character in the story, is also known as &apos;Sanuki-no-Miyatsuko&apos; that implies that the setting of the story is Sanuki-go, Hirose district, Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shrine claims to have a connection to Taketori Monogatari because &apos;Taketori no Okina,&apos; a character in the story, is also known as &apos;Sanuki-no-Miyatsuko,&apos; implying that the setting of the story is Sanuki-go, Hirose district, Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shrine claims to have a connection to Taketori Monogatari because &apos;Taketori no Okina,&apos; a character in the story, is also known as &apos;Sanuki-no-Miyatsuko,&apos; implying that the setting of the story is Sanuki-go, Hirose district, Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nnh(id:474), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>