<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>毘沙門堂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bishamon-do Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bishamon-do Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bishamon-do Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>毘沙門堂（びしゃもんどう）は、京都市山科区にある天台宗の寺院。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bishamon-do Temple is Buddhist temple belonging to the Tendai Sect located in Yamashina Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bishamon-do Temple is Buddhist temple belonging to the Tendai Sect located in Yamashina Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bishamon-do Temple is Buddhist temple belonging to the Tendai Sect located in Yamashina-ku Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>山号は護法山。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The honorific mountain prefix is Gohozan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The honorific mountain prefix is Gohozan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sango (literally, &quot;mountain name&quot;), which is the title prefixed to the name of a Buddhist temple is Gohozan (Mt. Goho).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>護法山安国院出雲寺とも称す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also known as Gohozan Ankoku-in Izumo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also known as Gohozan Ankoku-in Izumo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also known as Ankokuin Izumo-ji Temple on Mt. Goho.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>本尊は毘沙門天。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The principal image is Bishamonten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The principal image is Bishamonten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The principal image is Bishamonten (Vaisravana).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>天台宗京都五門跡の一であり、「毘沙門堂門跡」とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As one of the Five Monzeki Temples of Kyoto (served by head priests from the imperial family), it is also called &quot;Bishamon-do Monzeki&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As one of the Five Monzeki Temples of Kyoto (served by head priests from the imperial family), it is also called &quot;Bishamon-do Monzeki&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As one of the Five Monzeki Temples (served by head priests from the imperial family) of Tendai Sect in Kyoto, it is also called &apos;Bishamon-do Monzeki.&apos;</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>寺伝によれば、毘沙門堂の前身の出雲寺は文武天皇の勅願により、大宝3年（703年）行基が開いたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to temple legend, Izumo-ji Temple, the predecessor of Bishamon-do Temple, was founded by Gyoki in the year 703 under the order of Emperor Monmu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to temple legend, Izumo-ji Temple, the predecessor of Bishamon-do Temple, was founded by Gyoki in the year 703 under the order of Emperor Monmu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to temple legend, Izumo-ji Temple, the predecessor of Bishamon-do Temple, was founded by Gyoki in 703 under the order of the Emperor Monmu.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。&quot;the&quot; を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その後、平安時代末期には出雲寺は荒廃していたが、鎌倉時代初期、平親範が平家ゆかりの3つの寺院を合併する形で再興。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Izumo-ji Temple later fell into decline at the end of the Heian period but was revived at the beginning of the Kamakura period by TAIRA no Chikanori who merged it with three temples connected to the Taira family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Izumo-ji Temple later fell into decline at the end of the Heian period but was revived at the beginning of the Kamakura period by TAIRA no Chikanori who merged it with three temples connected to the Taira family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Izumo-ji Temple later fell into decline at the end of the Heian period but was revived at the beginning of the Kamakura period by TAIRA no Chikanori who merged it with three temples connected to the Taira family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>中世末期には再び荒廃していたが、近世に至り、天海とその弟子の公海 (僧)によって現在地に移転・復興され、天台宗京都五門跡の一として栄えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The temple again fell into ruin at the end of the middle ages but was relocated to its current site and revived by Tenkai and his disciple Kokai (a monk) where is prospered as one of the Five Monzeki Temples of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The temple again fell into ruin at the end of the middle ages but was relocated to its current site and revived by Tenkai and his disciple Kokai (a monk) where is prospered as one of the Five Monzeki Temples of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The temple again fell into ruin at the end of the middle ages but was relocated to its current site and revived by Tenkai and his disciple Kokai (a monk) where is prospered as one of the Five Monzeki Temples of Tendai Sect in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>前身寺院である出雲寺は、京都市上京区の相国寺の北、上御霊神社付近にあったと推定される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is assumed that its predecessor, Izumo-ji Temple, was located in the vicinity of Kami Goryo-jinja Shrine to the north of Shokuoku-ji Temple in Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is assumed that its predecessor, Izumo-ji Temple, was located in the vicinity of Kami Goryo-jinja Shrine to the north of Shokuoku-ji Temple in Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is assumed that its predecessor, Izumo-ji Temple, was located in the vicinity of Kamigoryo-jinja Shrine to the north of Shokoku-ji Temple in Kamigyo-ku Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>付近からは奈良時代前期にさかのぼる古瓦が出土しており、行基の開基であるかどうかは別としても、この付近に平城京遷都以前にさかのぼる寺院のあったことがわかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ancient roof tiles dating from the early Nara period have been excavated in the area and, although it has not been confirmed to have been founded by Gyoki, it is known that the temple had been situated in this area since before the relocation of the capital city to Heijo-kyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ancient roof tiles dating from the early Nara period have been excavated in the area and, although it has not been confirmed to have been founded by Gyoki, it is known that the temple had been situated in this area since before the relocation of the capital city to Heijo-kyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ancient roof tiles dating from the early Nara period have been excavated in the area and, although it has not been confirmed to have been founded by Gyoki, it is known that the temple had been situated in this area since before the relocation of Heijo-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in current Nara).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また、一帯には現在も「出雲路」の地名が残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the place name &quot;Izumo-ji&quot; still remains in use in the area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the place name &quot;Izumo-ji&quot; still remains in use in the area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the place name &apos;Izumoji&apos; still remains in use in the area.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>この出雲寺は平安時代末期には荒廃していたことが『今昔物語集』の記述などから伺われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is known from sources such as &quot;Konjaku Monogatari Shu&quot;(Tales of Times Now Past) that Izumo-ji Temple fell into decline at the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is known from sources such as &quot;Konjaku Monogatari Shu&quot;(Tales of Times Now Past) that Izumo-ji Temple fell into decline at the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is known from sources such as &quot;Konjaku Monogatari Shu&quot; (The Tale of Times Now Past) that Izumo-ji Temple fell into decline at the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>建久6年（1195年）の平親範置文（『洞院部類記』）という史料によると、同年、平親範は平等寺、尊重寺、護法寺という平家ゆかりの3つの寺院を併合し、出雲路に五間堂3棟を建てたという（「五間堂」とは間口の柱間が5つある仏堂の意）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the 1195 last will and testament of TAIRA no Chikanori, in the same year he merged Bishamon-do Temple with the three Taira family related temples Byodo-ji Temple, Sonju-ji Temple and Goho-ji Temple, and constructed three Goken-do halls in Izumo-ji (a &apos;Goken-do hall&apos; is a Buddha statue hall with a five bay long facade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the 1195 last will and testament of TAIRA no Chikanori, in the same year he merged Bishamon-do Temple with the three Taira family related temples Byodo-ji Temple, Sonju-ji Temple and Goho-ji Temple, and constructed three Goken-do halls in Izumo-ji (a &apos;Goken-do hall&apos; is a Buddha statue hall with a five bay long facade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the 1195 last will and testament of TAIRA no Chikanori (&quot;Toin buruiki&quot; (categorized collection of court events and practices by the Toin family), in the same year he merged three Taira family related temples Byodo-ji Temple, Sonju-ji Temple and Goho-ji Temple, and constructed three Goken-do halls in Izumoji (a &apos;Goken-do hall&apos; is a Buddha statue hall with a five bay long facade).</e>
<cmt>『洞院部類記』は『洞院家部類記』と思われますが、原文のままの読みにしています。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>置文によれば、平等寺は桓武天皇の皇子で桓武平氏の祖である葛原親王（かずらわらしんのう、786 - 853）の創建で、太秦（うずまさ、現京都市右京区）に所在。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This will and testament states that Byodo-ji Temple was founded by Imperial Prince Kazurawara (786-853), the son of Emperor Komu and the ancestor or Komu Heishi, and situated in Uzumasa (in present-day Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This will and testament states that Byodo-ji Temple was founded by Imperial Prince Kazurawara (786-853), the son of Emperor Komu and the ancestor or Komu Heishi, and situated in Uzumasa (in present-day Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This will and testament states that Byodo-ji Temple was founded by Imperial Prince Kazurawara (786 - 853), the son of the Emperor Kanmu and the ancestor or Kanmu Heishi (Taira clan), and situated in Uzumasa (in present-day Ukyo-ku Ward, Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。&quot;the&quot; を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>尊重寺は平親信（945 - 1017）の創建で、五辻（京都市上京区）に所在。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sonju-ji Temple was founded by TAIRA no Chikaobu (945-1017 and situated in Itsuji (Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sonju-ji Temple was founded by TAIRA no Chikaobu (945-1017 and situated in Itsuji (Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sonju-ji Temple was founded by TAIRA no Chikanobu (945 - 1017) and situated in Itsutsuji (Kamigyo-ku Ward, Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>護法寺は平親範の父・平範家が伏見（京都市伏見区）に創建したもので、応保元年（1161年）北石蔵（京都市左京区岩倉）に移転するが、長寛元年（1163年）に焼失し、本尊だけが大原（京都市左京区大原）に移されたものという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goho-ji Temple was founded by TAIRA no Chikanori&apos;s father TAIRA no Noriie in Fushimi (Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City) and relocated to Kitaiwakura (Iwakura, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City) in 1161 but destroyed by fire in 1163 with only the principal image being moved to Ohara (Ohara, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goho-ji Temple was founded by TAIRA no Chikanori&apos;s father TAIRA no Noriie in Fushimi (Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City) and relocated to Kitaiwakura (Iwakura, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City) in 1161 but destroyed by fire in 1163 with only the principal image being moved to Ohara (Ohara, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goho-ji Temple was founded by TAIRA no Chikanori&apos;s father TAIRA no Noriie in Fushimi (Fushimi-ku Ward, Kyoto City) and relocated to Kitaiwakura (Iwakura, Sakyo-ku Ward, Kyoto City) in 1161 but destroyed by fire in 1163 with only the principal image being moved to Ohara (Ohara, Sakyo-ku Ward, Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>こうしてできた寺は出雲寺の寺籍を継いで護法山出雲寺と称し、最澄（伝教大師）自作と伝える毘沙門天像を本尊としていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The temple resulting from the merger inherited the temple registration of Izumo-ji Temple to became named Gohozan Izumo-ji Temple and a Bishamonten statue said to have been carved by Saicho (Denkyo Daishi) himself was installed as principal image.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The temple resulting from the merger inherited the temple registration of Izumo-ji Temple to became named Gohozan Izumo-ji Temple and a Bishamonten statue said to have been carved by Saicho (Denkyo Daishi) himself was installed as principal image.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The temple resulting from the merger inherited the temple registration of Izumo-ji Temple to became named Izumo-ji Temple on Mt. Goho and a Bishamonten statue said to have been carved by Saicho (also known as Denkyo Daishi) himself was installed as principal image.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>中世には出雲寺は桜の名所として知られ、藤原定家の日記『明月記』や、『沙石集』（無住道暁編）にも言及されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the middle ages, Izumo-ji Temple was famous for its cherry blossoms and is mentioned in FUJIWARA no Sadaie&apos;s diary ~Meigetsu-ki&quot; and &quot;Shasekishu&quot; (compiled by Muju Dogyo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the middle ages, Izumo-ji Temple was famous for its cherry blossoms and is mentioned in FUJIWARA no Sadaie&apos;s diary ~Meigetsu-ki&quot; and &quot;Shasekishu&quot; (compiled by Muju Dogyo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the middle ages, Izumo-ji Temple was famous for its cherry blossoms and is mentioned in FUJIWARA no Sadaie&apos;s diary &quot;Meigetsu-ki&quot; and &quot;Shasekishu&quot; (collection of Buddhist stories) (compiled by Muju Dogyo).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="20">
<j>この鎌倉復興の出雲寺もやがて荒廃したが、慶長年間（17世紀初頭）に至り、天台宗の僧で徳川家康とも関係の深かった天海によって復興が開始された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This Kamakura period revival eventually turned to decline but restoration was begun by Tenkai, a Tendai Sect monk with a close relationship to Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, in the early 17th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Kamakura period revival eventually turned to decline but restoration was begun by Tenkai, a Tendai Sect monk with a close relationship to Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, in the early 17th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Kamakura period revival eventually turned to decline but restoration was begun by Tenkai, a Tendai Sect monk with a close relationship to Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, in the early 17th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>江戸幕府は山科の安祥寺 (京都市)（9世紀創建の真言宗寺院）の寺領の一部を出雲寺に与え、天海没後はその弟子の公海 (僧)が引き継ぎ、寛文5年（1665年）に完成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Edo Shogunate granted part of the estate of Ansho-ji Temple (Kyoto City) (a Shingon Sect temple founded in the 9th century) in Yamashina to Izumo-ji Temple and the its reconstruction was completed in 1665 after the death of Tenkai by his disciple Kokai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Edo Shogunate granted part of the estate of Ansho-ji Temple (Kyoto City) (a Shingon Sect temple founded in the 9th century) in Yamashina to Izumo-ji Temple and the its reconstruction was completed in 1665 after the death of Tenkai by his disciple Kokai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Edo Shogunate granted part of the estate of Ansho-ji Temple (Kyoto City) (a Shingon Sect temple founded in the 9th century) in Yamashina to Izumo-ji Temple and the its reconstruction was completed in 1665 after the death of Tenkai by his disciple Kokai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>後西天皇皇子の公弁法親王（1669 - 1716）は当寺で受戒し、晩年には当寺に隠棲している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Gosai&apos;s son Koben Hosshino (1669-1716) received the Buddhist commandments at the temple and lived there in seclusion during his final years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Gosai&apos;s son Koben Hosshino (1669-1716) received the Buddhist commandments at the temple and lived there in seclusion during his final years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor Gosai&apos;s son Cloistered Imperial Prince Koben (1669 - 1716) received the Buddhist commandments at the temple and lived there in seclusion during his final years.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。&quot;The&quot; を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>以後、門跡寺院（皇族・貴族が住持を務める格式の高い寺院の称）となり、「毘沙門堂門跡」と称されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following this, the temple became a Monzeki Temple (a high ranking temple served by a head priest from the imperial or a noble family) and came to be named &quot;Bishamon-do Temple&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following this, the temple became a Monzeki Temple (a high ranking temple served by a head priest from the imperial or a noble family) and came to be named &quot;Bishamon-do Temple&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following this, the temple became a Monzeki Temple (a high ranking temple served by a head priest from the imperial or a noble family) and came to be named &apos;Bishamon-do Monzeki.&apos;</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="24">
<j>文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>重要文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>洞院公定日記</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Diary of Kinsada TOIN</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Diary of Kinsada TOIN</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Diary of Kinsada TOIN</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>注大般涅槃経 巻第十四</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chudaihatsu Nehan-gyo Sutra</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chudaihatsu Nehan-gyo Sutra</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">14th volume of Chu Daihatsu Nehan-gyo (Commentary of the Nirvana Sutra)</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>篆隷文体</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenrei style (ancient square style)</e>
<cmt>訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="29">
<j>上記の他、大阪府・和泉市久保惣記念美術館所蔵の国宝・青磁鳳凰耳花生（せいじほうおうみみはないけ）はもと毘沙門堂にあったものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to those above, the National Treasure-designated Seiji Hoo Mimi hana-ike (a flower base) in the possession of the Kuboso Memorial Museum of Arts in Izumi City, Osaka Prefecture was originally kept at Bishamon-do Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to those above, the National Treasure-designated Seiji Hoo Mimi hana-ike (a flower base) in the possession of the Kuboso Memorial Museum of Arts in Izumi City, Osaka Prefecture was originally kept at Bishamon-do Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to those above, the National Treasure-designated Seiji Hoo Mimi hana-ike (a celadon flower base with handle of hoo (a mythological sacred bird in Chinese lore, a phoenix)) in the possession of the Kuboso Memorial Museum of Arts in Izumi City, Osaka Prefecture was originally kept at Bishamon-do Temple.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="30">
<j>交通アクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>西日本旅客鉄道・京都市営地下鉄東西線山科駅、京阪電気鉄道線京阪山科駅から北へ、徒歩約15-20分。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Travel to the JR West/Kyoto Municipal Subway Tozai Line Yamashina Station or Keihan Electric Railways Keihan Yamashina Station and walk north for approximately 15-20 minutes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Travel to the JR West/Kyoto Municipal Subway Tozai Line Yamashina Station or Keihan Electric Railways Keihan Yamashina Station and walk north for approximately 15-20 minutes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Travel to the JR West/Kyoto Municipal Subway Tozai Line Yamashina Station or Keihan Electric Railways Keihan Yamashina Station and walk north for approximately 15-20 minutes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="32">
<j>所在地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Address</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Address</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Address</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>京都府京都市山科区安朱稲荷山町18</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">18 Anshu Inariyama-cho, Yamashina Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">18 Anshu Inariyama-cho, Yamashina Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">18 Anshu Inariyama-cho, Yamashina-ku Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Co.kyoto(id:79296), 深志(id:34508), Nopira(id:29335), 金山銀山銅山(id:163855), Urania(id:7213), くっちゃめ(id:86793), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>