<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大乗院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daijo-in Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daijo-in Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daijo-in Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>大乗院（だいじょういん）は奈良県奈良市の興福寺にあった塔頭の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daijo-in Temple is one of tatchu (sub-temples in the site of main temple) in Kofuku-ji Temple in Nara City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daijo-in Temple is a tatchu (sub-temples in the site of main temple) in Kofuku-ji Temple in Nara City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daijo-in Temple is a tatchu (sub-temples in the site of main temple) in Kofuku-ji Temple in Nara City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>寛治元年（1087年）、隆禅（藤原政兼の子）が創建する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1087, Ryuzen (a son of FUJIWARA no Masakane) founded this temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1087, Ryuzen (a son of FUJIWARA no Masakane) founded this temple.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1087, Ryuzen (a son of FUJIWARA no Masakane) founded this temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>その後、関白藤原師実の子・尋範が継承したことから摂関家特に九条家系の勢力が強かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Jinpan, a biological son of FUJIWARA no Morosane who was a chancellor, inherited this temple, so Sekkan-ke (the families which produced regents), especially Kujo Family, had a strong power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Jinpan, a biological son of FUJIWARA no Morosane who was a chancellor, inherited this temple, resulting in Sekkan-ke (the families which produced regents), especially Kujo Family, becoming especially powerful.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Jinpan, a biological son of FUJIWARA no Morosane who was a chancellor, inherited this temple, resulting in Sekkan-ke (the families which produced regents), especially Kujo family, becoming especially powerful.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>第4代院主・信円（藤原忠通の子）の頃に門跡寺院とされ、中世には一乗院と並ぶ有力な塔頭で、門主は摂関家や将軍家の子弟から迎えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was regarded as a monzeki temple (a temple of high rank where members of imperial family and nobility enter the priesthood) in the time of the 4th Inju (the 4th chief of a temple), Shinen (a son of FUJIWARA no Tadamichi), and it was an influential tatchu along with Ichijo-in Temple in the Medieval period, having its chief priest from sons of Sekkan-ke or Shogun family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was regarded as a monzeki temple (a temple of high rank where members of imperial family and nobility enter the priesthood) in the time of the 4th Inju (the 4th chief of a temple), Shinen (a son of FUJIWARA no Tadamichi), and it was an influential tatchu along with Ichijo-in Temple in the Medieval period, with its chief priest having come from the sons of Sekkan-ke or the Shogun family.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was regarded as a monzeki temple (a temple of high rank where members of imperial family and nobility enter the priesthood) in the time of the 4th Inju (the 4th chief of a temple), Shinen (a son of FUJIWARA no Tadamichi), and it was an influential tatchu along with Ichijo-in Temple in the Medieval period, with its chief priest having come from the sons of Sekkan-ke or the Shogun family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>その間、治承4年（1180年）の平家による奈良攻撃、宝徳3年（1451年）の土一揆によって焼失したが、室町時代には経覚・尋尊という2人の実力のある院主が相次いで登場して奈良一帯の座を次々と支配下に収めて大いに栄えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During that time, it was burned because of the attack on Nara by Heike (the Taira family) in 1180 and a peasants&apos; uprising in 1451, but two able Inju, Kyogaku and Jinson appeared successively, who had trade guilds throughout Nara in control to flourish to a great extent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During that time, it was burned because of the attack on Nara by Heike (the Taira family) in 1180 and a peasants&apos; uprising in 1451, but two able Inju, Kyogaku and Jinson appeared successively, who had trade guilds throughout Nara in control to flourish to a great extent.</e>
<cmt>&quot; who had trade guilds throughout Nara in control to flourish to a great extent.&quot; translation doesn’t make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During that time, it was burned because of the attack on Nara by the Taira family in 1180 and a peasants&apos; uprising in 1451, but two able Inju, Kyogaku and Jinson appeared successively during the Muromachi period, who had trade guilds throughout Nara in control to flourish to a great extent.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>だが、戦国時代_(日本)に入ると次々と所領を失って江戸時代にはわずか950石にまで縮小した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the Sengoku period (period of warring states in Japan) its shoryo (territory) was lost continuously to be only 950 koku (171. 3705 cubic meters) in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the Sengoku period (period of warring states in Japan) it continuously lost its shoryo (territory) until it was reduced to 950 koku (171. 3705 cubic meters) in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the Sengoku period (period of warring states in Japan) it continuously lost its shoryo (territory) until it was reduced to 950 koku (171. 3705 cubic meters) in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>更に明治2年（1869年）の廃仏毀釈により最後の院主・大乗院門跡隆芳（九条尚忠の子）は還俗して消滅、なお還俗後に「松園尚嘉」と名乗った隆芳は華族令によって子爵を授けられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, in accordance with Genzoku (return to secular life) of the last Inju, Ryuho, Monzeki (the chief priest) of Daijo-in Temple (a son of Hisatada KUJO) due to Haibutsu-kishaku (a movement to abolish Buddhism) in 1869, the temple was lost, and Ryuho who called himself &quot;Hisayoshi MATSUZONO&quot; after Genzoku was given a viscount based on the Peerage Law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, in accordance with Genzoku (return to secular life) of the last Inju, Ryuho, Monzeki (the chief priest) of Daijo-in Temple (a son of Hisatada KUJO) due to Haibutsu-kishaku (a movement to abolish Buddhism) in 1869, the temple was lost, and Ryuho who called himself &quot;Hisayoshi MATSUZONO&quot; after Genzoku was given a viscount based on the Peerage Law.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, in accordance with Genzoku (return to secular life) of the last Inju, Ryuho, Monzeki (the chief priest) of Daijo-in Temple (a son of Hisatada KUJO) due to Haibutsu-kishaku (a movement to abolish Buddhism) in 1869, the temple was lost, and Ryuho who called himself &apos;Hisayoshi MATSUZONO&apos; after Genzoku was given a viscount based on the Peerage Law.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>跡地は奈良ホテルとなり、一部の庭園はナショナルトラスト日本における展開により復元されて見学可能となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nara Hotel was founded at its remained site and a part of its garden was restored by the project of National Trust Japan so visitors are allowed to see it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nara Hotel was founded at its remained site and a part of its garden was restored by the National Trust Japan project, allowing modern-day vistors to view it.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nara Hotel was founded at its remained site and a part of its garden was restored by the National Trust Japan project, allowing modern-day visitors to view it.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>旧大乗院庭園は国の名勝にも指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The garden of the former Daijo-in Temple is specified as the state scenic beauty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The garden of the former Daijo-in Temple is specified as a state scenic beauty.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The garden of the former Daijo-in Temple is specified as a state scenic beauty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Rusk(id:9895), Mooko(id:36162), Reggaeman(id:6214), 地図帳(id:122587), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), くっちゃめ(id:86793), 663highland(id:18755), こぶまき(id:38278), To-emon(id:23140), Ziksy(id:84091), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>