<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>一宮神社 (福知山市)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikyu-Jinjya Shrine (Fukuchiyama City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ikyu-Jinjya Shrine (Fukuchiyama City)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikkyu-jinja Shrine (Fukuchiyama City)</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>一宮神社（いっきゅうじんじゃ）は、京都府福知山市の市街地より少し南よりの位置にある神社。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikyu-Jinjya Shrine is a shrine, that is located in a little to the south of urban area in Fukuchiyama City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ikyu-Jinjya Shrine is a shrine, that is located slightly to the south of the urban area in Fukuchiyama City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikkyu-jinja Shrine is a shrine, that is located slightly to the south of the urban area in Fukuchiyama City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>伝えられているところによると奈良時代の創建。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been reported that Ikyu-Jinjya Shrine was erected in Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been reported that Ikyu-Jinjya Shrine was erected in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been reported that Ikkyu-jinja Shrine was erected in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>江戸時代、福知山藩の鎮守として栄えた神社。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This Shrine flourished as Chinju (local Shinto deity) for Fukuchiyama Domain in Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Shrine flourished as Chinju (local Shinto deity) for the Fukuchiyama Domain in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Shrine flourished as Chinju (local Shinto deity) for the Fukuchiyama Domain in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>社殿は、享保3年（1718年）に建築されたもので、福知山を代表する建築だとし、境内の脇社も含め京都府の登録文化財。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its sanctuary (the main building of a Shinto shrine) was erected in 1718 and both sanctuary and Wakisya (脇社)of precincts were registered as cultural property by Kyoto Prefecture as one of the best architectures in Fukuchiyama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its sanctuary (the main building of a Shinto shrine) was erected in 1718 and both sanctuary and Wakisya (脇社)of precincts were registered as cultural property by Kyoto Prefecture as one of the best architectures in Fukuchiyama.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its sanctuary (the main building of a Shinto shrine) was erected in 1718 and both sanctuary and Wakisha of precincts were registered as cultural property by Kyoto Prefecture as one of the best architectures in Fukuchiyama.</e>
<cmt>(脇社）削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>鎌倉時代の石灯籠が残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ishi-doro (stone lantern) in Kamakura period remains in this shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ishi-doro (stone lantern) from the Kamakura period remains in this shrine.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ishi-doro (stone lantern) from the Kamakura period remains in this shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>環境保全地区</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Environmental preservation area</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Environmental preservation area</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Environmental preservation area</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>境内の鎮守の森は、ケヤキが数多く見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A lot of zelkova trees can be seen at Chinju-no-Mori (Sacred Shrine Forest) in the precincts of shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A lot of zelkova trees can be seen at Chinju-no-Mori (Sacred Shrine Forest) in the precincts of the shrine.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A lot of zelkova trees can be seen at Chinju-no-Mori (Sacred Shrine Forest) in the precincts of the shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>サカキ・カシ・クス等の照葉樹林にモチ・イチョウが混成して境内を取り囲み、南側にスギ・ヒノキの針葉樹が植樹されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The precincts of shrine is surrounded by laurel forest such as Cleyera japonica, oak and camphor tree as well as ilex and ginkgo which are growing together there, while conifer such as Japanese cedar and a (Japanese) cypress are planted in south side of the forest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The precincts of the shrine are surrounded by a laurel forest containing trees such as Cleyera japonica, oak and camphor trees as well as ilex and ginkgo which grow together there, while conifers such as Japanese cedars and (Japanese) cypress are planted in the south side of the forest.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The precincts of the shrine are surrounded by a laurel forest containing trees such as Cleyera japonica, oak and camphor trees as well as ilex and ginkgo which grow together there, while conifers such as Japanese cedars and (Japanese) cypress are planted in the south side of the forest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>ササ・ベニシダ・フユイチゴ等が密生、環境保全地区に指定。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Chinjyu-no-Mori is thickly grown with bamboo, Japanese shield fern, Rubus buergeri, and is designated as environmental preservation area</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, Chinjyu-no-Mori is thickly grown with bamboo, Japanese shield fern, Rubus buergeri, and is designated as an environmental preservation area.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, Chinju-no-Mori is thickly grown with bamboo, Japanese shield fern, Rubus buergeri, and is designated as an environmental preservation area.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>夏には、カブトムシやクワガタムシなどの昆虫も見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In summer, insects such as Japanese dynastid beetles or stag beetles can be seen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In summer, insects such as Japanese dynastid beetles or stag beetles can be seen.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In summer, insects such as Japanese dynastid beetles or stag beetles can be seen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mobnoboka(id:35218), Nnh(id:474), Ksa-R(id:107575), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>