<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>法輪寺 (斑鳩町)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Horin-ji Temple (Ikaruga-cho)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Horin-ji Temple (Ikaruga-cho)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Horin-ji Temple (Ikaruga-cho)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>法輪寺（ほうりんじ）は、奈良県生駒郡斑鳩町にある仏教の寺院。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Horin-ji Temple is a Budhist temple located at Ikaruga-cho, Ikoma-gun, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Horin-ji Temple is a Buddhist temple located at Ikaruga-cho, Ikoma-gun, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>located in Ikaruga-choとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Horin-ji Temple is a Buddhist temple located at Ikaruga-cho, Ikoma-gun, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>三井寺（みいでら）とも呼ばれ、「法林寺」「法琳寺」とも書く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Mii-dera Temple and written as &quot;法林寺&quot; (Horin-ji Temple) or &quot;法琳寺&quot; (Horin-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called Mii-dera Temple and written as &quot;法林寺&quot; (Horin-ji Temple) or &quot;法琳寺&quot; (Horin-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called Mii-dera Temple and written as &quot;法林寺&quot; (Horin-ji Temple) or &quot;法琳寺&quot; (Horin-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>宗派は聖徳宗、本尊は薬師如来坐像。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its religious school is the Shotoku sect and the principal image is the Yakushi Nyorai zazo (sitting statue of Yakushi Nyorai, or the Healing Buddha).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a temple of the Shotoku sect and its principal image is a sitting statue of Yakushi Nyorai (Yakushi Nyorai, or the Healing Buddha).</e>
<cmt>It is a temple of the Shotoku sect and its principal image is a sitting statue of としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a temple of the Shotoku sect and its principal image is a sitting statue of Yakushi Nyorai (Yakushi Nyorai, or the Healing Buddha).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>法隆寺東院の北方に位置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yakushi Nyorai zazo is located in North part of Horyu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is located on the north of Horyu-ji Temple Toin (east area).</e>
<cmt>主語を取り違えているようです。The Yakushi Nyorai zazo→It　(法輪寺のこと）　It is located on the north of Horyu-ji Temple Toin (east area)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is located on the north of Horyu-ji Temple Toin (east area).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>現存する三重塔は1975年の再建であるため、世界遺産「法隆寺地域の仏教建造物」には含まれていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The exsisting three-storied pagoda is not included in the &quot;Buddhist Monuments of the Horyu-ji Area&quot; because it was rebuilt in 1975.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The existing three-storied pagoda is not included in the &quot;Buddhist Monuments of the Horyu-ji Area&quot; because it is a structure rebuilt in 1975.</e>
<cmt>because it is a structure rebuilt in 1975. としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The existing three-storied pagoda is not included in the &quot;Buddhist Monuments of the Horyu-ji Area&quot; because it is a structure rebuilt in 1975.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>法輪寺は寺史に関わる史料が乏しいため、創建事情の詳細は不明であるが、発掘調査の結果等から、7世紀中頃には存在していたことは間違いない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the poor temple history, foundation details are unknown; however, it is certain from excavations and research that the temple exsisted from the mid seventh century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to scares historical materials about the temple, the details of its foundation are unknown; however, judging from the archaeological findings it is certain that the temple had already existed in the mid seventh century.</e>
<cmt>一部訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to scares historical materials about the temple, the details of its foundation are unknown; however, judging from the archaeological findings it is certain that the temple had already existed in the mid seventh century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>本尊薬師如来像と虚空蔵菩薩像も飛鳥時代末期にさかのぼる古像である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The principal image,Yakushi Nyorai zazo, and Kokuzo Bosatsu-zo (statue of Akasagarbha Bodhisattva) are also very old statues, created at the end of Asuka period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The principal image, sitting statue of Yakushi Nyorai, as well as the statue of Kokuzo Bosatsu (Akasagarbha Bodhisattva) are old enough to be able to date back to the end of Asuka period.</e>
<cmt>old enough to be able to date back to the end of Asuka period.としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The principal image, sitting statue of Yakushi Nyorai and the statue of Kokuzo Bosatsu (Akasagarbha Bodhisattva) are also very old, dating back to the end of the Asuka period.</e>
<cmt>created at→dating back to Asuka period.→the Asuka periodare old enough to be able to date back to →are also very old, dating back to としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>三井寺と言う別名は、当寺のある三井の地名に由来し、付近に聖徳太子ゆかりと言われている3つの井戸があった所から来ている（3つの井戸のうちの1つが現存し、国の史跡に指定されている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The nickname, Mii-dera Temple, stemmed from the area of Mii where the temple is located and from Prince Shotoku&apos;s three wells which were also located there (one of the three wells still exsists and is an historic site).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its another name, Mii-dera Temple, stems from the area Mii where the temple is located, and the name Mii comes the three wells associated with Prince Shotoku, which existed in the area at that time (one of the three wells still remains and it is designated as a national historic site).</e>
<cmt>一部訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its another name, Mii-dera Temple, stems from the area Mii where the temple is located, and the name Mii comes the three wells associated with Prince Shotoku, which existed in the area at that time (one of the three wells still remains and it is designated as a national historic site).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>創建</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Foundation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Foundation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Foundation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>当寺の創建については、『日本書紀』や『法隆寺伽藍縁起并流記資材帳』（ほうりゅうじがらんえんぎ ならびに るきしざいちょう）には記載がなく、不明な点が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In regards to the temple&apos;s founding, there are no explanations in the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) nor in the &quot;Horyu-ji Garan Engi narabini Ruki Shizai Cho&quot; (Notes on the Origin and Materials of Horyu-ji Temple); therefore, many details remain unclear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since there is no description about the temple&apos;s founding in the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) nor in the &quot;Horyu-ji Garan Engi narabini Ruki Shizai Cho&quot; (The origin of Horyu-ji Temple and record of construction materials), many details remain unclear.</e>
<cmt>一部訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since there is no description about the temple&apos;s founding in the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) nor in the &quot;Horyu-ji Garan Engi narabini Ruki Shizai Cho&quot; (The origin of Horyu-ji Temple and record of construction materials), many details remain unclear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>創建については、古くから2つの説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are two theories regarding the foundation from long ago.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are two traditional theories regarding the foundation.</e>
<cmt>from long agoを削除し、traditional theoriesとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are two traditional theories regarding the foundation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>1つの説は『聖徳太子伝私記』（嘉禎4年・1238年、顕真著）に見えるもので、聖徳太子の子である山背大兄王が太子の病気平癒を祈るため、622年（推古30年）に建てた、とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One theory is, as it is written in &quot;Shotoku Taishi denshiki&quot; (the Private Recollections on the Life of Prince Shotoku) (written by Kenshin in 1238), Prince Yamashiro no oe, son of Prince Shotoku, built it in 622 to pray for his father&apos;s recovery from an illness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One theory is found in &quot;Shotoku Taishi denshiki&quot; (the Private Recollections on the Life of Prince Shotoku) (written by Kenshin in 1238), and according to it, Prince Yamashiro no oe, son of Prince Shotoku, built the temple in 622 to pray for his father&apos;s recovery from an illness.</e>
<cmt>一部訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One theory is found in &quot;Shotoku Taishi denshiki&quot; (the Private Recollections on the Life of Prince Shotoku) (written by Kenshin in 1238), and according to it, Prince Yamashiro no oe, son of Prince Shotoku, built the temple in 622 to pray for his father&apos;s recovery from an illness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>今一つの説は『上宮聖徳太子伝補闕記』（平安時代前期成立）および『聖徳太子伝暦』（延喜17年・917年、藤原兼輔著）に見えるもので、創建法隆寺の焼失後、百済の開法師・円明法師・下氷新物（しもつひのにいもの）の3人が建てたとするものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another theory is, as it is recounted in &quot;Jogu Shotoku Taishi Den Hoketsuki&quot;(Revised Biography of Prince Shotoku) (from the early Heian period) and &quot;Shotokutaishi Denryaku&quot; (Biography of Prince Shotoku) (written by FUJIWARA no Kanesuke in 917), it was built by three people, Kai hoshi, Enmyo hoshi, and SHIMOTSUHI no Niimono, from Baekje after the burning of the original Horyu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another theory is found in &quot;Jogu Shotoku Taishi Den Hoketsuki&quot; (Revised Biography of Prince Shotoku) (from the early Heian period) and &quot;Shotokutaishi Denryaku&quot; (Biography of Prince Shotoku) (written by FUJIWARA no Kanesuke in 917), and according to it, the temple was built by three persons from the Paekche Kingdom, Kai hoshi (Buddhist priest), Enmyo hoshi, and Shimotsui no Niimono, after the original Horyu-ji Temple was burned down.</e>
<cmt>SHIMOTSUHI no Niimono→Shimotsui no niimono 「下氷」は姓ではないと考えられるので、語頭のみ大文字にし、発音に合わせ「しもつい」のローマ字表記としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another theory is found in &quot;Jogu Shotoku Taishi Den Hoketsuki&quot; (Revised Biography of Prince Shotoku) (from the early Heian period) and &quot;Shotokutaishi Denryaku&quot; (Biography of Prince Shotoku) (written by FUJIWARA no Kanesuke in 917), and according to it, the temple was built by three persons from the Paekche Kingdom, Kai hoshi (Buddhist priest), Enmyo hoshi, and Shimotsui no Niimono, after the original Horyu-ji Temple was burned down.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>これらの人物の名前については「聞法師、円明師、下氷君雑物（しもつひのきみくさもの）とも伝えるが、いずれの人物も伝記は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While these names, Kai hoshi, Enmyo hoshi, and SHIMOTSUHI no Niimono, appear in this theory, there have not been any biographies found for these individuals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although these persons are also documented as &apos;Buddhist hoshi, Enmyo hoshi, and Shimotsui no kimi kusamono,&apos; the biography of any of these persons is unknown.</e>
<cmt>構文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although these names are also said to have been &apos;Mon shi, Enmyo shi, and Shimotsui no kimi kusamono,&apos; there have not been any biographies found for these individuals.</e>
<cmt>一部訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>発掘調査の結果、法隆寺再建伽藍（現存）に近い瓦と、それより一段階古い瓦とが出土している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of excavations and research, roof tiles for the rebuilding of Horyuji-Temple (current) and one previous building have been discovered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of excavations, roof tiles quite similar to those used for the reconstruction of Horyuji-Temple (existent architecture) and more aged ones have been found.</e>
<cmt>一部訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of excavations, roof tiles quite similar to those used for the reconstruction of Horyuji-Temple (existent architecture) and more aged ones have been found.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また、前身建物の遺構とみられる掘立柱穴や溝も検出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, the ancient structural remnants of predecessor building including pit of a pillar embedded directly in the ground and a groove were found.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳分の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Pits used for the pillars piled directly in the ground and trenches, which were considered to be the remains of the original structure, were also identified.</e>
<cmt>構文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Pits used for the pillars piled directly in the ground and trenches, which were considered to be the remains of the original structure, were also identified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>当時の創建は飛鳥時代末期、7世紀中頃までさかのぼると考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that at the time of the foundation was back in the late Asuka period and the mid seventh century.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳分の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that at the time of the foundation was back in the late Asuka period and the mid seventh century.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that at the time of the foundation was back in the late Asuka period and the mid seventh century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>1367年（貞治6年）正月3日、炎上する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 3, 1367, the temple burst into flames.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the third day of the New Year of the 6th year of the Teiji era (1367), the temple burst into flames.</e>
<cmt>正月に焼失したという情報を残すために、On February, 1367 (the third day of the New Year of the 6th year of the Teiji era)としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the third day of the New Year of the 6th year of the Teiji era (1367), the temple burst into flames.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>1645年（正保2年）、台風に罹災し、三重塔を除く建造物が倒壊する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1645, struck by a typhoon, all buildings except the three-storied pagoda were destroyed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1645, struck by a typhoon, all buildings except for the three-storied pagoda were destroyed.</e>
<cmt>except for</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1645, struck by a typhoon, all buildings except for the three-storied pagoda were destroyed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>1731年（享保16年）、妙見堂を再建する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1731, Myoken-do Hall was rebuilt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1731, Myoken-do Hall was rebuilt.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1731, Myoken-do Hall was rebuilt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>1760年（宝暦10年）、三重塔を修復する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1760, the three-storied pagoda was repaired.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1760, the three-storied pagoda was restored.</e>
<cmt>repaired→restored</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1760, the three-storied pagoda was restored.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="21">
<j>1761年（宝暦11年）、金堂･講堂･南大門を再建する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1761, Kon-do Hall (main hall of a Buddhist temple), Kodo Hall (lecture hall), and Nandai-mon gate (great south gate) were rebuilt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1761, Kondo (main hall), Kodo (lecture hall), and Nandaimon gate (great south gate) were rebuilt.</e>
<cmt>Kondo (main hall), Kodo (lecture hall), and Nandaimon gateとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1761, Kondo (main hall), Kodo (lecture hall), and Nandaimon gate (great south gate) were rebuilt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="22">
<j>1903年（明治36年）、国宝に指定されていた三重塔を解体修理する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1903, the three-storied pagoda was dismantled and repaired.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1903, the three-storied pagoda was dismantled and thoroughly restored.</e>
<cmt>was dismantled and thoroughly restoredとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1903, the three-storied pagoda was dismantled and thoroughly restored.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="23">
<j>1944年（昭和19年）7月21日、三重塔が落雷により焼失する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July 21, 1944, the three-storied pagoda was hit by lightning and burnt down.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 21, 1944, the three-storied pagoda was hit by lightning and burnt down.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July 21, 1944, the three-storied pagoda was hit by lightning and burnt down.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="24">
<j>避雷針は、太平洋戦争の金属供出で撤去されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The lightning rod was removed and metal was contributed to the Pacific War effort.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lightning rod was removed and contributed to the Pacific War effort as metal.</e>
<cmt>一部訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lightning rod was removed and contributed to the Pacific War effort as metal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="25">
<j>1950年（昭和25年）、発掘調査をする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1950, excavation and research was begun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1950, archaeological study began.</e>
<cmt>archaeological study began</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1950, archaeological study began.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="26">
<j>1975年 - 三重塔再建。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1975, the three-storied pagoda was rebuilt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1975, the three-storied pagoda was rebuilt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1975, the three-storied pagoda was rebuilt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>伽藍</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buddhist Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Complex of the temple</e>
<cmt>Complex of the templeとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Complex of the temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="27">
<j>昭和25年、仏教考古学が専門であった石田茂作（いしだ もさく、1894年-1977年）が法輪寺を発掘・調査した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1950, Mosaku ISHIDA (1894-1977) who specialized in Buddhist archaeology, excavated and researched Horin-ji Temple&apos;s history.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳分の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1950, Mosaku ISHIDA (1894-1977), who was a specialist in Buddhist archaeology, conducted the excavation and research in the complex of Horin-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>一部訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1950, Mosaku ISHIDA (1894-1977), who was a specialist in Buddhist archaeology, conducted the excavation and research in the complex of Horin-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>創建当時は東に金堂、西に塔が建つ、法隆寺式の伽藍配置で、平面規模は法隆寺の3分の2であったことがわかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He discovered the Horyu-ji Temple style was employed at this Buddhist temple at the time of its founding; the Kon-do Hall was to the East, the pagoda was to the West, and the size of the grounds were two thirds that of Horyu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳分の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He discovered that Horin-ji Temple originally had a Horyu-ji style layout with Kondo in the east and the pagoda in the west, and its dimensions were two thirds of that of Horyu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>一部訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He discovered that Horin-ji Temple originally had a Horyu-ji style layout with Kondo in the east and the pagoda in the west, and its dimensions were two thirds of that of Horyu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>金堂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kon-do Hall</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kondo (main hall)</e>
<cmt>Kondo (main hall)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kondo (main hall)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="30">
<j>講堂（収蔵庫）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kodo Hall (repository)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kodo (lecture hall including repository)</e>
<cmt>Kodo (lecture hall including repository)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kodo (lecture hall including repository)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="31">
<j>三重塔 - 1944年、雷火で焼失後、作家の幸田文らの尽力で寄金を集め、1975年に西岡常一棟梁により再建されたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Three-storied pagoda: in 1944, after it was burnt by lightning, an author Aya KODA and her collegues gathered donations for the three-storied pagoda which was then rebuilt by toryo (master builder) Tsunekazu NISHIOKA in 1975.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Three-storied pagoda: in 1944, after it was burnt by lightning, a novelist Aya KODA and her colleagues called for donations to reconstruct the pagoda, and it was rebuilt by a master carpenter Tsunekazu NISHIOKA in 1975.</e>
<cmt>一部訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Three-storied pagoda: in 1944, after it was burnt by lightning, a novelist Aya KODA and her colleagues called for donations to reconstruct the pagoda, and it was rebuilt by a master carpenter Tsunekazu NISHIOKA in 1975.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>焼失した塔は、近隣の法隆寺、法起寺の塔とともに斑鳩三塔と呼ばれ、7世紀末頃の建立と推定される貴重な建造物であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The burnt pagoda was called Ikaruga Santo (three pagodas in Ikaruga) along with neighboring Horyu-ji and Hokki-ji Temples; together they became important examples of what is thought to be seventh century architecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The burnt pagoda was counted among Ikaruga Santo (three pagodas in Ikaruga) along with the pagodas of neighboring Horyu-ji and Hokki-ji Temples, and it was highly valued as the structure that was supposed to be the architecture of the late seventh century.</e>
<cmt>一部訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The burnt pagoda was counted among Ikaruga Santo (three pagodas in Ikaruga) along with the pagodas of neighboring Horyu-ji and Hokki-ji Temples, and it was highly valued as the structure that was supposed to be the architecture of the late seventh century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="33">
<j>妙見堂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myoken-do Hall</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myokendo (hall dedicated to Myoken Bosatsu)</e>
<cmt>一部訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myokendo (hall dedicated to Myoken Bosatsu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="34">
<j>鬼子母神堂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kishibojin-do Hall</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kishibojindo (hall dedicated to Kishibojin [guardian deity of children])</e>
<cmt>一部訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kishibojindo (hall dedicated to Kishibojin [guardian deity of children])</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="35">
<j>地蔵堂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jizo-do Hall</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jizodo (hall dedicated to Jizo Bosatsu)</e>
<cmt>一部訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jizodo (hall dedicated to Jizo Bosatsu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="36">
<j>鐘楼</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoro (a bell tower)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoro (a bell tower)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoro (a bell tower)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cultural Tresures</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cultural properties</e>
<cmt>Treasures→properties</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cultural properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>重要文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important Cultural Tresures</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>Treasures→Properties</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="37">
<j>木造薬師如来坐像 - 旧金堂本尊で、現在は収蔵庫を兼ねた講堂に安置される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wooden seated statue of Yakushi Nyorai (the Healing Buddha): currently enshrined in Kodo Hall which is also a repository in former Kondo honzon (the Golden Hall).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wooden seated statue of Yakushi Nyorai (the Healing Buddha): it is the principal image of the former Kondo (main hall) and currently enshrined in the present Kodo which is also used as a repository.</e>
<cmt>一部訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wooden seated statue of Yakushi Nyorai (the Healing Buddha): it is the principal image of the former Kondo (main hall) and currently enshrined in the present Kodo which is also used as a repository.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>飛鳥時代末期の作で、当代の等身大木彫像として稀有な作である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was created in the late Auka period and is a rare work as a life-sized wooden sculpture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was created in the late Asuka period and is valuable as one of the few life-sized wooden sculptures.</e>
<cmt>一部訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was created in the late Asuka period and is valuable as one of the few life-sized wooden sculptures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>面長な顔付き、服装、台座の形式など、一見法隆寺金堂本尊の釈迦如来像（銅造）と似る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is similar to Shakyanyorai-zo (bronze statue of Shakyanyorai) in Horyu-ji Temple Kondo Honzon (the Golden Hall) at a glance in terms of its narrow face, appearance, and base; however, periodical elements can be indicated including the expression of the eyes that are not simple almond shapes but complex lines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At a glance, its narrow face, costume and pedestal are similar to those of the principal image of Horyu-ji Temple&apos;s Kondo,</e>
<cmt>構文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At a glance, its narrow face, costume and pedestal are similar to those of the principal image of Horyu-ji Temple&apos;s Kondo, the bronze statue of Shaka Nyorai.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処一文を２つに分けました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>が、両目が単純なアーモンド形でなく複雑な線で表現されるなど、やや時代の降る要素も見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, some of its elements indicate that it was created at a slightly later time; for example the eyes that are not simply almond-shaped but are depicted with complex lines.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処構文を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="41">
<j>木造虚空蔵菩薩立像 - 飛鳥時代末期の作。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wooden Kokuzo Bosatsu (wooden standing statue of Akasagarbha Bodhisattva): created in the late Asuka period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wooden standing statue of Kokuzo Bosatsu (Akasagarbha Bodhisattva): created in the late Asuka period.</e>
<cmt>Wooden standing statue of Kokuzo Bosatsu (Akasagarbha Bodhisattva)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wooden standing statue of Kokuzo Bosatsu (Akasagarbha Bodhisattva): created in the late Asuka period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>「虚空蔵菩薩」と称するが、これは聖徳太子の本地を虚空蔵菩薩とする後世の信仰によって名付けられたものと思われ、本来の像名は不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was believed by following generations that the statue was named &apos;Kokuzo Bosatsu&apos; after Prince Shotoku&apos;s honji (original ground) which was called Kokuzo Bosatsu; the original statue name, however, is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is called &apos;Kokuzo Bosatsu&apos; at present, it is believed that it came to be called by the actual name at a later time when a belief that Prince Shotoku was the incarnation of Kokuzo Bosatsu extended, and the statue&apos;s original name is unknown.</e>
<cmt>構文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is called &apos;Kokuzo Bosatsu&apos; at present, it is believed that the name was given by the people at a later time when they believed that Prince Shotoku was the incarnation of Kokuzo Bosatsu, and the statue&apos;s original name is unknown.</e>
<cmt>it came to be called by the actual name→the name was given by the people at a later time when they believed that Prince Shotoku was the incarnation of Kokuzo BosatsuTG: OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="43">
<j>木造十一面観音菩薩立像 - 講堂本尊で像高3.5メートルを超える巨像。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wooden Juichimen Kannon Bosatsu ryuzo (wooden standing statue of eleven-faced Kannon Bosatsu)-3.5 meter tall colossus at Kodo Honzon (the Golden Hall).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wooden standing statue of eleven-faced Kannon Bosatsu: the main image of Kondo with the seated height of 3.5 m.</e>
<cmt>一部訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wooden standing statue of eleven-faced Kannon Bosatsu: the main image of Kondo with the seated height of 3.5 m.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>以下の諸仏とともに平安時代の作。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a Heian period work along with the following various buddhas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is made in the Heian period like the following Buddha statues.</e>
<cmt>一部訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is made in the Heian period like the following Buddha statues.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="45">
<j>木造弥勒菩薩立像（重要文化財指定名称は「聖観音立像」）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wooden Miroko Bosatsu ritsuzo (wooden standing statue of Buddha of the Future, Bodhisattva of the Present) (designated important cultural treasure&apos;s name is &apos;wooden Sho Kannon ryuzo&apos; (wooden standing statue of Sho Kannon))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wooden standing statue of Miroku Bosatsu (Maitreya) (designated as an Important Cultural Property by the name of &apos;Sho-Kannon Ryuzo [Wooden standing statue of Holy Kannon])</e>
<cmt>一部訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wooden standing statue of Miroku Bosatsu (Maitreya) (designated as an Important Cultural Property by the name of &apos;Sho-Kannon Ryuzo [Wooden standing statue of Holy Kannon])</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="46">
<j>木造地蔵菩薩立像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wooden Jizo Bosatsu ryuzo (wooden standing statue of the Guardian Deity of Travellers and Children)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wooden standing statue of Jizo Bosatsu</e>
<cmt>一部訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wooden standing statue of Jizo Bosatsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="47">
<j>木造吉祥天立像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wooden Kisshoten ryuzo (wooden standing statue of Kisshoten in a zushi) (a miniature temple)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wooden standing statue of Kisshoten</e>
<cmt>一部訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wooden standing statue of Kisshoten</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="48">
<j>龍鬢褥（りゅうびんのじょく） - 推古天皇使用の敷物と伝わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryubin-no-joku (mat dyed in five different colors; red, purple, green, and blue): it is believed that the mat was used by Empress Suiko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryubin no joku (a mat dyed in five different colors; red, purple, green, and blue): the mat was believed to have been used by Empress Suiko.</e>
<cmt>Ryubin-no-joku (mat dyed in five different colors; red, purple, green, and blue):→Ryubin no joku (a mat dyed in five different colors; red, purple, green, and blue): と下２列の名称表記に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryubin no joku (a mat dyed in five different colors; red, purple, green, and blue): the mat was believed to have been used by Empress Suiko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="49">
<j>塔心礎納置銅壺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshinso nouchi doko (container for a person&apos;s ashes found in a central base stone of the three-storied pagoda)</e>
<cmt>http://www1.kcn.ne.jp/~horinji/gaiyou/jihou01.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshinso nouchi doko (a copper container for relic placed in a central base stone of the pagoda)</e>
<cmt>一部訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshinso nouchi doko (a copper container for relic placed in a central base stone of the pagoda)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="50">
<j>多宝塔文磬（たほうとうもん　けい）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tahotomon kei (stone chime with pagoda patterns)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tahotomon kei (a stone chime patterned with a multi-treasure pagoda)</e>
<cmt>一部訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tahotomon kei (a stone chime patterned with a multi-treasure pagoda)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="51">
<j>鴟尾（しび）残欠－飛鳥時代中期の代表的な鴟尾。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incomplete remains of Shibi (ornamental ridge-end tile): typical Shibi for the mid Asuka period.</e>
<cmt>Is &quot;Finial&quot; more appropriate for &quot;Shibi&quot;? http://tuinverbeelding.nl/new/en/?Info:Background_Info:Ridge_Tiles←Finial may be rather suitable to reffer to the top of the pagoda called &apos;Hoju.&apos;</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fragment of Shibi (ornamental tile set in pair on both end of the ridgepole): typical Shibi tile of the mid Asuka period.</e>
<cmt>一部訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fragment of Shibi (ornamental tile set in pair on both end of the ridgepole): typical Shibi tile of the mid Asuka period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>奈良県指定文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cultural treasures designated by Nara Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cultural Properties designated by Nara Prefecture</e>
<cmt>Cultural Properties</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cultural Properties designated by Nara Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="52">
<j>木造釈迦如来坐像（三重塔安置、非公開）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wooden Shaka Nyorai zazo (wooden seated statue of Shaka Nyorai) (enshrined in a three-storied pagoda, behind closed doors).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wooden seated statue of Shaka Nyorai (enshrined in the three-storied pagoda, not open to the public).</e>
<cmt>一部訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wooden seated statue of Shaka Nyorai (enshrined in the three-storied pagoda, not open to the public).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="53">
<j>銅錫杖頭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Doshakujoto (head part of copper cane that monks have used for ascetic training)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Doshakujoto (cast copper head of a walking stick used as an article for ascetic training)</e>
<cmt>一部訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Doshakujoto (cast copper head of a walking stick used as an article for ascetic training)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>その他の文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other Cultural Tresures</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other cultural properties</e>
<cmt>Other cultural propertiesとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other cultural properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="54">
<j>妙見菩薩立像（秘仏のため非公開）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Standing statue of Myoken Bosatsu (a hidden Buddist statue, behind closed doors)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Standing statue of Myoken Bosatsu (the temple&apos;s hidden Buddhist statue, not open to the public)</e>
<cmt>一部訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Standing statue of Myoken Bosatsu (the temple&apos;s hidden Buddhist statue, not open to the public)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="55">
<j>米俵乗毘沙門天立像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Standing statue of Komedawara-nori Bishamonten</e>
<cmt>Komedawara-nori: 読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Standing statue of Bishamonten (one of the Four Heavenly Kings) on a rice bale</e>
<cmt>一部訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Standing statue of Bishamonten (one of the Four Heavenly Kings) on a rice bale</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="56">
<j>木造楊柳観音立像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wooden Yoryu Kannon Ritsuzo (The wooden image of the Kannon holding a willow branch to eradicate illness)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wooden standing statue of Yoryu Kannon (Kannon holding a willow branch to eradicate illness)</e>
<cmt>Wooden standing statue of Yoryu Kannon としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wooden standing statue of Yoryu Kannon (Kannon holding a willow branch to eradicate illness)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="57">
<j>聖徳太子二歳像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shotoku Taishi Nisai zo (a statue of two-year-old Prince Shotoku)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Statue of two-year-old Prince Shotoku</e>
<cmt>Statue of としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Statue of two-year-old Prince Shotoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="58">
<j>四天王像（三重塔安置、非公開）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shitenno-zo (Image of the four guardian kings) (enshrined in a three-storied pagoda, behind closed doors)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Statues of Shitenno (Four Heavenly Kings) (enshrined in the three-storied pagoda, not open to the public)</e>
<cmt>一部訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Statues of Shitenno (Four Heavenly Kings) (enshrined in the three-storied pagoda, not open to the public)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="59">
<j>釈迦三尊十八羅漢図　3幅（奈良国立博物館に寄託）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shaka-sanzon Juhachi-rakan zu (image of Gautama Buddha flanked by two attendants and eighteen achievers of Nirvana), 3 sets (donated to the Nara National Museum)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Painting of Shaka Triad and eighteen Arhats, 3 sets (deposited in the Nara National Museum)</e>
<cmt>一部訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Painting of Shaka Triad and eighteen Arhats, 3 sets (deposited in the Nara National Museum)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="60">
<j>浄土曼荼羅図　1幅（奈良国立博物館に寄託）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jodo-mandala-zu, 1 set (donated to the Nara National Museum)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jodo (Pure Land) Mandala, 1 set (deposited in the Nara National Museum)</e>
<cmt>一部訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jodo (Pure Land) Mandala, 1 set (deposited in the Nara National Museum)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>行事</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Event</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Event</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Event</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="61">
<j>妙見護摩祈祷（毎月15日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myoken Gomakito (Myoken consecrated fire invocation) (15th, every month)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myoken Gomakito (ritual of consecrated fire dedicated to Myoken Bosatsu) (15th of every month)</e>
<cmt>一部訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myoken Gomakito (ritual of consecrated fire dedicated to Myoken Bosatsu) (15th of every month)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="62">
<j>星祭り（2月3日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Star Festival (February 3rd)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Star Festival (February 3rd)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Star Festival (February 3rd)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="63">
<j>妙見会式（4月15日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myoken eshiki (Myoken Festival) (April 15th)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myoken eshiki (Myoken Festival) (April 15th)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myoken eshiki (Myoken Festival) (April 15th)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="64">
<j>秋季特別展（11月1日-11月7日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Autumn Special Exhibition (November 1 - November 7)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Autumn Special Exhibition (November 1 - November 7)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Autumn Special Exhibition (November 1 - November 7)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>近隣情報</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Neibourhood Information</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Neighborhood Information</e>
<cmt>Neighborhood としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Neighborhood Information</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="65">
<j>法起寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hokki-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hokki-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hokki-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="66">
<j>法隆寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Horyu-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Horyu-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Horyu-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="67">
<j>中宮寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chugu-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chugu-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chugu-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>所在地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Location</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Location</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Location</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="68">
<j>〒636-0101 奈良県生駒郡斑鳩町三井1570</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1570 Mii, Ikaruga-cho, Ikoma-gun, Nara Prefecture #636-0101</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1570 Mii, Ikaruga-cho, Ikoma-gun, Nara Prefecture, 636-0101</e>
<cmt>#636-0101→636-0101</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1570 Mii, Ikaruga-cho, Ikoma-gun, Nara Prefecture, 636-0101</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>交通アクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="69">
<j>西日本旅客鉄道関西本線大和小泉駅から徒歩15分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A fifteen minute walk from the Yamato Koizumi Station, Kansai Main Line of the West Japan Railway Company.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">15- minute walk from Yamato Koizumi Station, Kansai Main Line of West Japan Railway Company.</e>
<cmt>A fifteen minute walk →15-minute walk the Yamato Koizumi Station→Yamato Koizumi Stationthe West Japan Railway Company→ West Japan Railway Company</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">15- minute walk from Yamato Koizumi Station, Kansai Main Line of West Japan Railway Company.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 花蝶風月雪月花警部(id:163674), Bueller 007(id:30970), 浩(id:70121), Mobnoboka(id:35218), Nnh(id:474), 貘(id:106080), Reggaeman(id:6214), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Urania(id:7213), 663highland(id:18755), Ffokoob(id:259570), Ｈｉｒｏ２００６(id:59115), Ziksy(id:84091), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>