<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>別表神社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Beppyo jinja (Shrines on the Special List)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Beppyo jinja (Shrines on the Special List)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Beppyo Jinja (Shrines on the Special List)</e>
<cmt>語頭大文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>別表神社（べっぴょうじんじゃ）とは、神社本庁が定めた、神社本庁が包括している一部の神社のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Beppyo jinja means some shrines designated and comprehended by Jinja-Honcho (The Association of Shinto Shrines).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Beppyo jinja refers to shrines designated and tracked by Jinja-Honcho (The Association of Shinto Shrines).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Beppyo jinja refers to shrines designated and tracked by Jinja-Honcho (The Association of Shinto Shrines).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>昭和21年（1946年）の神社の国家管理の廃止に伴い公的な社格の制度（近代社格制度）が廃止されたため、それに代わるものとして昭和23年（1948年）に定められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the public shrine ranking system (Kindai shakaku seido [Modern shrine ranking system]) was eliminated due to the elimination of management of shrines by the state in 1946, this was specified to replace it in 1948.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the public shrine ranking system (Kindai shakaku seido [Modern shrine ranking system]) was eliminated due to the elimination of management of shrines by the state in 1946, this was specified to replace it in 1948.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the public shrine ranking system (Modern shrine ranking system) was eliminated due to the elimination of management of shrines by the state in 1946, this was specified to replace it in 1948.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>社格制度廃止後は、全ての神社は対等の立場であるとされた（伊勢神宮を除く）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the elimination of the Shrine Ranking System, all shrines were regarded to be on equal footing (excluding Ise-jingu Shrine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the elimination of the Shrine Ranking System, all shrines were regarded to be on equal footing (excluding Ise-jingu Shrine).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the elimination of the Shrine Ranking System, all shrines were regarded to be on equal footing (excluding Ise-jingu Shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>しかし、旧の官国幣社や一部の規模の大きな神社については、神職の進退等に関して一般神社と同じ扱いをすると不都合があることから、「役職員進退に関する規程」において特別な扱いをすることと定めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, for old Kankoku Heisha (general term for Kanpeisha and Kokuheisha that were high rank shrines) and some large-scale shrines, it was decided to treat them separately based on &apos;regulation regarding the advance or retreat of executives and general staff&apos; since treating them in the same way with general shrines were unfavorable in terms of the advance or retreat of Shinto priesthood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, for old Kankoku Heisha (general term for Kanpeisha and Kokuheisha that were high rank shrines) and some large-scale shrines, it was decided that they would be treated separately based on &apos;regulation regarding the advance or retreat of executives and general staff&apos; since treating them in the same way with general shrines were unfavorable in terms of the advance or retreat of Shinto priesthood.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, for old Kankoku Heisha (general term for Kanpeisha and Kokuheisha that were high rank shrines) and some large-scale shrines, it was decided that they would be treated separately based on &apos;regulation regarding the advance or retreat of executives and general staff&apos; since treating them in the same way with general shrines were unfavorable in terms of the advance or retreat of Shinto priesthood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>その対象となる神社が同規程の別表に記載されていることから、「別表に掲げる神社」（別表神社）と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the object shrines are listed in Beppyo (appendix) of the official regulations, they are called &apos;Shrines on the Special List&apos; (Beppyo jinja).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the object shrines are listed in Beppyo (appendix) of the official regulations, they are called &apos;Shrines on the Special List&apos; (Beppyo jinja).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the object shrines are listed in Beppyo (appendix) of the official regulations, they are called &apos;Shrines on the Special List&apos; (Beppyo jinja).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>別表神社は、人事の面で以下のような特別の扱いがされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Beppyo jinja are treated separately as follows in terms of personnel affairs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Beppyo jinja are treated separately as follows in terms of personnel affairs.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Beppyo jinja are treated separately as follows in terms of personnel affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>一定以上の基準に達すれば宮司の下に権宮司を置くことが認められる</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When they are above certain standards, they are allowed to designate Gonguji under Guji (chief of those who serves shrine, controls festivals and general affairs).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When they are above certain standards, they are allowed to be designated as Gonguji under Guji (chief of those who serves shrine, controls festivals and general affairs).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When they are above certain standards, they are allowed to be designated as Gonguji under Guji (chief of those who serves shrine, controls festivals and general affairs).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>宮司・権宮司は明階以上の階位を有する者でなければ任用されない（一般神社では権正階以上）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only people who are in Meikai rank (for Shinto priesthood) or above are designated as Guji ・ Gonguji (for general shrines, Gon-Seikai rank or above).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only people who are of Meikai rank (for Shinto priesthood) or above are designated as Guji ・ Gonguji (for general shrines, Gon-Seikai rank or above).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only people who are of Meikai rank (for Shinto priesthood) or above are designated as Guji and Gonguji (for general shrines, Gon-Seikai rank or above).</e>
<cmt>全角削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>禰宜は正階以上の階位を有する者でなければ任用されない（一般神社では直階以上）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only people who are in seikai rank or above are designated as Negi (Shinto priest) (for general shrines, chokkai or above).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only people who are of seikai rank or above are designated as Negi (Shinto priest) (for general shrines, chokkai or above).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only people who are of seikai rank or above are designated as Negi (Shinto priest) (for general shrines, chokkai or above).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>権禰宜は権正階以上の階位を有する者でなければ任用されない（一般神社では直階以上）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only people who are in Gon-Seikai rank or above are designated as Gonnegi (assistant senior priests) (for general shrines, chokkai or above).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only people who are of Gon-Seikai rank or above are designated as Gonnegi (assistant senior priests) (for general shrines, chokkai or above).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only people who are of Gon-Seikai rank or above are designated as Gonnegi (assistant senior priests) (for general shrines, chokkai or above).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>宮司・権宮司の在任中の身分は特級、一級・二級上以外の者は二級とする</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Social status of Guji ・ Gonguji while they are in office is nikyu (second grade) except for those in tokkyu (special grade), ikkyu (first grade) ・ nikyu-jo (senior second grade).</e>
<cmt>特級、一級、二級上、二級：　tokkyu (special grade), ikkyu (first grade) ・ nikyu-jo (senior second grade), nikyu (second grade) と訳してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Social status of Guji ・ Gonguji while they are in office is nikyu (second grade) except for those in tokkyu (special grade), ikkyu (first grade) ・ nikyu-jo (senior second grade).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Social status of Guji and Gonguji while they are in office is nikyu (second grade) except for those in tokkyu (special grade), ikkyu (first grade) ・ nikyu-jo (senior second grade).</e>
<cmt>全角削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>宮司・権宮司の任免は各都道府県の神社庁長の委任事項としない（神社本庁統理の直接任免とする。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Designation and dismissal of Guji ・ Gonguji are not delegated to a chief of shrine agency in each administrative division of Japan (direct designation and dismissal by tori in Jinja-Honcho).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Designation and dismissal of Guji ・ Gonguji are not delegated to a chief of shrine agency in each administrative division of Japan (direct designation and dismissal by tori in Jinja-Honcho).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Designation and dismissal of Guji and Gonguji are not delegated to a chief of shrine agency in each administrative division of Japan (direct designation and dismissal by tori in Jinja-Honcho).</e>
<cmt>全角削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>当初の別表神社は旧官国幣社のみであったが、昭和26年（1951年）に「別表に掲げる神社選定に関する件」という通達が出され、官国幣社以外で新たに別表神社に加える神社の選定基準が示された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though Beppyo jinja were originally only the old Kankoku Heisha, a notification &apos;About Selection of Shrines specified in the Special List&apos; was issued in 1951, and standards to select shrines which are other than Kankoku Heisha and newly added in the special list were specified.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though Beppyo jinja were originally only the old Kankoku Heisha, a notification &apos;About Selection of Shrines specified in the Special List&apos; was issued in 1951, and standards to select shrines which are other than Kankoku Heisha and newly added in the special list were specified.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though Beppyo jinja were originally only the old Kankoku Heisha, a notification &apos;About Selection of Shrines specified in the Special List&apos; was issued in 1951, and standards to select shrines which are other than Kankoku Heisha and newly added in the special list were specified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>それは以下のものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The standards are as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The standards are as follows.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The standards are as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>由緒</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>Capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>社殿・境内地などの神社に関する施設の状況</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Situation of facilities related to shrines such as a main building of a Shinto shrine ・ precincts, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Situation of facilities related to shrines such as a main building of a Shinto shrine ・ precincts, etc.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Situation of facilities related to shrines such as a main building of a Shinto shrine and precincts, etc.</e>
<cmt>全角削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>常勤の神職の数</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the number of regular Shinto priests</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of regular Shinto priests</e>
<cmt>Capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of regular Shinto priests</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>最近3年間の経済状況</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Financial situation during the last three years</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Financial situation during the last three years</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Financial situation during the last three years</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>神社の活動状況</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the activities of a shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the activities of a shrine</e>
<cmt>Capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The activities of a shrine</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>氏子崇敬者の数および分布状況</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the number of reverent ujiko (shrine parishioners) and their distribution condition</e>
<cmt>氏子崇敬者： reverent ujiko (shrine parishioners) と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of reverent ujiko (shrine parishioners) and their distributed condition</e>
<cmt>Capitalization/Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of reverent ujiko (shrine parishioners) and their distributed condition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>この規定により、旧府県社・護国神社を中心に別表神社の数は次第に増加し、2006年現在で353社となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the regulations, the number of Beppyo jinja gradually increased mainly among old Fukensha (Prefectural shrines) ・ Gokoku jinja Shrines, and there are 353 of them as of 2006.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the regulations, the number of Beppyo jinja gradually increased mainly among old Fukensha (Prefectural shrines) ・ Gokoku jinja Shrines, and there are 353 of them as of 2006.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the regulations, the number of Beppyo jinja gradually increased mainly among old Fukensha (Prefectural shrines) and Gokoku jinja Shrines, and there are 353 of them as of 2006.</e>
<cmt>全角削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>逆に、神社本庁との被包括関係を解消し、別表神社でなくなる神社もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, some shrines dissolve an inclusive relationship with Jinja-Honcho and stop being Beppyo jinja.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, some shrines dissolveed their inclusive relationship with Jinja-Honcho and stopped being Beppyo jinja.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, some shrines dissolved their inclusive relationship with Jinja-Honcho and stopped being Beppyo jinja.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="23">
<j>別表神社は社格のような神社の格付けではなく、あくまでも神職の人事のみにかかわる区別である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Beppyo jinja is not a grading of shrines such as shrine ranking but absolutely differentiation dealing with personnel affairs of Shinto priests only.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Beppyo jinja is not a grading of shrines such as shrine ranking but absolutely differentiation dealing with personnel affairs of Shinto priests only.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Beppyo jinjya is not a rating system like the shrine ranking system; it is a system used only to classify Shinto shrines based on shrine personnel matters.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>しかし、別表に掲げられている神社は社殿、境内、神職の数などの面で比較的大きな規模の神社であり、一般には一種の格付けとして捉えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, shrines specified in Beppyo are rather large-scale shrines in terms of a main building of a Shinto shrine, precincts of a shrine, and the number of Shinto priests, etc., and generally it is considered as kind of grading.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, shrines specified in Beppyo are rather large-scale shrines having a main building, many precincts, and a fair number of Shinto priests, etc., and generally are considered to be a kind of grading</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, shrines specified in Beppyo are rather large-scale shrines having a main building, many precincts, and a fair number of Shinto priests, etc., and generally are considered to be a kind of grading.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除しました。ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="25">
<j>なお、社格同様、伊勢神宮は別格として別表神社に入れられていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, like shrine ranking, Ise-jingu Shrine is considered to be Bekkaku and hasn&apos;t been regarded as Beppyo jinja, and it is handled more separately since Daiguji of the Jingu is designated and dismissed by imperial decision according to &apos;the shrine regulations.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, like shrine ranking, Ise-jingu Shrine is considered to be Bekkaku and hasn&apos;t been regarded as Beppyo jinja, and it is handled more separately since Daiguji of the Jingu is designated and dismissed by imperial decision according to &apos;the shrine regulations.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Ise-jingu Shrine is considered to be a special case, it is not included in the Beppyo jinja or in the shrine ranking.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>また神宮大宮司は、「神宮規則」により、勅裁を得て任免するとされ、さらに特別の扱いがなされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &apos;shrine regulations,&apos; the chief priest of the Ise-jingu Shrine is appointed and dismissed by imperial decision, and these regulations also state that the Ise-jingu Shrine is treated as a special case.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>別表神社一覧</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">List of Beppyo jinja</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">List of Beppyo jinja</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">List of Beppyo jinja</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="27">
<j>「式内」は式内社（名神名神大社、国史国史見在社）、「近代」は近代社格制度の社格（官大官幣大社、国中国幣中社、護国内務大臣指定護国神社）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shikinai&apos; is shrine ranking of Shikinai-sha (Myojin-taisha Shrine, Kokushigenzai-sha Shrine), and &apos;kindai&apos; is shrine ranking in the modern shrine ranking system (kantai kanpei taisha, kokuchu kokuhei chusha, Gokoku-jinja Shrine designated by a prewar Home Minister for nation protection).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shikinai&apos; is a shrine ranking for Shikinai-sha (Myojin-taisha Shrine, Kokushigenzai-sha Shrine), and &apos;kindai&apos; is a shrine ranking for the modern shrine ranking system (kantai kanpei taisha, kokuchu kokuhei chusha, Gokoku-jinja Shrine designated by a prewar Home Minister for nation protection).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shikinai&apos; is a shrine ranking for Shikinai-sha (Myojin-taisha Shrine, Kokushigenzai-sha Shrine), and &apos;kindai&apos; is a shrine ranking for the modern shrine ranking system (kantai kanpei taisha, kokuchu kokuhei chusha, Gokoku-jinja Shrine designated by a prewar Home Minister for nation protection).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>「加列年」は、旧官国幣社で1948年の制度開始時時点で本庁被包括であったものについては当初より別表神社であるので、一律で1948年と記載している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since shrines which were the old Kankoku Heisha and comprehended by Jinja-Honcho at the time of starting the system in 1948 were originally Beppyo jinja, &apos;their registration year&apos; are uniformly indicated as 1948.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since shrines, which were old Kankoku Heisha and covered under the Jinja-Honcho that was started, in 1948, were originally Beppyo jinja, &apos;their registration year&apos; are uniformly indicated as being 1948.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since shrines, which were old Kankoku Heisha and covered under the Jinja-Honcho that was started in 1948, were originally Beppyo jinja, &apos;their registration year&apos; are uniformly indicated as being 1948.</e>
<cmt>カンマ削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>旧官国幣社で、1948年以降に本庁被包括となったものについては、被包括関係を設定した年を記載している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For shrines which were the old Kankoku Heisya and comprehended by Jinja-Honcho in and after 1948, the year in which the inclusive relationship was established is indicated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For shrines which were the old Kankoku Heisya and comprehended by Jinja-Honcho in and after 1948, the year in which the inclusive relationship was established is indicated.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For shrines which were the old Kankoku Heisha and comprehended by Jinja-Honcho in and after 1948, the year in which the inclusive relationship was established is indicated.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="30">
<j>旧官国幣社で別表神社でない神社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">shrines which are the old Kankoku Heisha but not Beppyo jinja</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">shrines which are the old Kankoku Heisha but not Beppyo jinja</e>
<cmt>Capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shrines which are the old Kankoku Heisha but not Beppyo jinja</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>旧官国幣社のうち、以下に掲げる各社は神社本庁と被包括関係にないため、別表神社ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the old Kankoku Heisha, shrines listed below not Beppyo jinja since they are not in an inclusive relationship with Jinja-Honcho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the old Kankoku Heisha, shrines below were listed as not being Beppyo jinja since they are not in an inclusive relationship with Jinja-Honcho.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the old Kankoku Heisha, shrines below were listed as not being Beppyo jinja since they are not in an inclusive relationship with Jinja-Honcho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>「被包括関係解消年」が1946年となっているものは、1946年の神社本庁発足当初から神社本庁との被包括関係にないものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shrines, for which &apos;the year of resolving the inclusive relationship&apos; is 1946, are not in the inclusive relationship with Jinja-Honcho from the very beginning of the inauguration of Jinja-Honcho in 1946.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shrines, for which &apos;the year of resolving the inclusive relationship&apos; is 1946, are not in the inclusive relationship with Jinja-Honcho from the very beginning of the inauguration of Jinja-Honcho in 1946.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shrines, for which &apos;the year of resolving the inclusive relationship&apos; is 1946, are not in the inclusive relationship with Jinja-Honcho from the very beginning of the inauguration of Jinja-Honcho in 1946.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Bakkai(id:7233), Nnh(id:474), Charenji(id:7908), 妙翅鳥(id:55475), Kansai explorer(id:48975), Lupinoid(id:68), Im224(id:57113), 沢田(id:40580), 桔梗Store(id:58881), Dream100(id:41924), Koyu(id:12916), Azusayumi7(id:21082), Sonic883(id:36201), Knua(id:66861), こぶまき(id:38278), ゞ(￣ー￣ )アロエ(id:48574), Jkr2255(id:16760), 翰林硯士(id:99377), 蒼海牧菜(id:78923), たね(id:10372), Bergmann(id:85282), Stanislaus(id:1806), Law soma(id:45202), 短髄彦(id:5555), Himazin(id:22034), Yanahan(id:2437), Wikindexan(id:10060), Phronimos(id:293969), Rusk(id:9895), Kouchiumi(id:19253), やる気man-man(id:36512), 663highland(id:18755), Akimoto(id:6951), 1234567(id:71369), 弥(id:61590), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>