<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>源九郎稲荷神社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genkuroinari-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genkuroinari-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genkuroinari-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>源九郎稲荷神社（げんくろういなりじんじゃ）とは、近鉄郡山駅の南西約500Mに鎮座する、源九郎狐や綿帽子を買った狐の伝説で有名な神社である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genkuroinari-jinja is a Shinto Shrine located about 500 meters south west of Kintetsu Koriyama Station which is famous for its legends about Genkuro Gitune (a fox named Genkuro) and a fox which bought a wataboshi (a cotton cap).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genkuroinari-jinja is a Shinto Shrine located about 500 meters south west of Kintetsu Koriyama Station which is famous for its legends about two foxes, one called Genkuro and one who bought wataboshi (cotton caps).</e>
<cmt>gituneを省略、綿帽子を複数形に</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genkuroinari-jinja is a Shinto Shrine located about 500 meters south west of Kintetsu Koriyama Station which is famous for its legends about two foxes, one called Genkuro and one who bought wataboshi (cotton caps).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>童謡『やまとの源九郎さん』に歌われている場所であり、地元では、「源九郎さん」の呼び名で親しまれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The location of the shrine appears in a children&apos;s song &quot;Yamato no Genkuro san&quot; which is known familiarly as &apos;Genkuro san&apos; to the local residents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The location of the shrine appears in a children&apos;s song &quot;Yamato no Genkuro san&quot; which is known familiarly as &apos;Genkuro san&apos; to the local residents.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The location of the shrine appears in a children&apos;s song &quot;Yamato no Genkuro san&quot; which is known familiarly as &apos;Genkuro san&apos; to the local residents.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>小さな稲荷であるが、日本三大稲荷の一つに数えられ、北向きの本殿に『白狐源九郎』が祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although a small Inari-jinjya Shrine, it is considered as one of the three laegest Inari-jinjya Shrines in Japan, and &quot;Byakko Genkuro (white spiritual fox named Genkuro)&quot; is enshrined in the north facing main hall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although small, it is considered as one of the three largest Inari-jinjya Shrines in Japan, and &quot;Byakko Genkuro&quot; (a white spiritual fox named Genkuro is enshrined in the North-facing main hall.</e>
<cmt>inari-jinjyaを省略し、laergestのスペルを直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although small, it is considered as one of the three largest Inari-jinja Shrines in Japan, and &quot;Byakko Genkuro&quot; (a white spiritual fox named Genkuro is enshrined in the North-facing main hall.</e>
<cmt>「Inari-jinjya」を「Inari-jinja」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>五穀豊穣・商売繁盛の御利益があり、4月の第一日曜日に、白狐面をつけた子供行列が練り歩く『源九郎稲荷春季大祭』が行なわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">worshippers are said to be blessed with bumper crop and prosperous trade, and &quot;the Genkuroinari Spring Big Festival&quot; is held on the first Sunday in April where children wearing a mask of white fox are parading on the street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Worshippers are said to be blessed with plentiful crops and prosperous trade, and &quot;the Genkuroinari Spring Big Festival&quot; is held on the first Sunday in April where children wearing white fox masks parade the streets.</e>
<cmt>bumper crop &gt; plentiful crops. a mask of white fox &gt; white fox masks. are parading one &gt; parade.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Worshippers are said to be blessed with plentiful crops and prosperous trade, and &quot;the Genkuroinari Spring Big Festival&quot; is held on the first Sunday in April where children wearing white fox masks parade the streets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>由緒</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>源義経が兄源頼朝との戦に際し、義経は幾度もこの稲荷に助けられ、この稲荷に源九郎の名を贈ったという伝説が、社名の由来となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name Genkuro comes from a legend that when MINAMOTO no Yoshitune had a battle with his older-brother MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, Yoshitune was helped by the Inari many times, so Yoshitune named this Inari Genkuro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name Genkuro comes from a legend that when MINAMOTO no Yoshitune had a battle with his older-brother MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, Yoshitune was helped by the Inari (Fox messenger) many times, so Yoshitune named this Inari Genkuro (meaning MINAMOTO the 9th).</e>
<cmt>Inariをfox messengerに説明し、genkuroも説明しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name Genkuro comes from a legend that when MINAMOTO no Yoshitune had a battle with his older-brother MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, Yoshitune was helped by the Inari (Fox messenger) many times, so Yoshitune named this Inari Genkuro (meaning MINAMOTO the 9th).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>翁の姿をした源九郎狐が、長安寺村の宝譽という僧の夢枕に立ち、郡山城に自分を祀ってくれたら、城の守護神になろう、と告げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been reported that 宝譽, the priest in Choan-ji Village had a dream of Genkuro Gitsune which had changed into an old man, told 宝譽 that if 宝譽 enshrined him in Koriyama-jo castle, he would become a guardian god of the castle, then 宝譽 told Hidenaga TOYOTOMI about that, and Inari shrine was founded in Unryukaku of the castle.</e>
<cmt>宝譽→読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been reported that 宝譽, the priest in Choan-ji Village had a dream where Genkuro Gitsune in the form of an old man, told 宝譽 that if he enshrined him in Koriyama-jo castle, he would become a guardian god of the castle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been reported that 宝譽, the priest in Choan-ji Village had a dream where Genkuro Gitsune in the form of an old man, told 宝譽 that if he enshrined him in Koriyama-jo Castle, he would become a guardian god of the castle.</e>
<cmt>「Koriyama-jo castle」を「Koriyama-jo Castle」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>宝譽は、豊臣秀長にこのことを告げ、城内竜雲郭に稲荷が創建されたと伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When 宝譽 told Hidenaga TOYOTOMI about his dream, an Inari shrine was founded in Ryuun-kaku (Hall) of the castle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When 宝譽 told Hidenaga TOYOTOMI about his dream, an Inari shrine was founded in Ryuun-kaku (Hall) of the castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>享保4年（1719年）、現在地に遷座。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1719, it was transferred to the present location.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1719, it was transferred to the present location.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1719, it was transferred to the present location.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>大正14年、現社殿が完成している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The current shrine building was completed in 1925.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The current shrine building was completed in 1925.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The current shrine building was completed in 1925.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>伝説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Legends</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Legends</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Legends</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>忠臣狐伝説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The legend of loyal subject fox</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The legend of the loyal fox subject</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The legend of the loyal fox subject</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>義経が兄頼朝に追われ、吉野山まで逃げる道中、佐藤忠信に化けた白狐が、静御前を守り通した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yoshitune was pursued by his brother Yoritomo, and was running away from him on the way to Mt. Yoshino, the white fox which had changed into Tadanobu SATO perfectly protected Shizuka Gozen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yoshitune was being pursued by his brother Yoritomo, and was fleeing through Mt. Yoshino, a white fox in the form of Tadanobu SATO protected Shizuka Gozen from harm.</e>
<cmt>running away &gt; fleeing. on the way &gt; through. which had changed &gt; in the form of. protected &gt; protected from harm.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yoshitune was being pursued by his brother Yoritomo, and was fleeing through Mt. Yoshino, a white fox in the form of Tadanobu SATO protected Shizuka Gozen from harm.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>義経はその白狐の忠義に感服した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitune admired the white fox for its loyalty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitune admired the white fox for its loyalty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitune admired the white fox for its loyalty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>狐の意中の物は、親の皮で出来た御前の鼓であったが、それを知った義経は、自分の名を与えて「源九郎」と名乗ることを許した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yoshitune knew the fact that the object of the fox&apos;s affection was Shizuka Gozen&apos;s Tsuzumi (a hand drum) made with skin of its parent, he named the fox &quot;Genkuro&quot; and allowed the fox to use the name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yoshitune found out that the fox&apos;s real priority was Shizuka Gozen&apos;s Tsuzumi (a hand drum) made from the skin of its parent, he gave the fox his own name and allowed the fox to call himself &quot;Genkuro&quot;.</e>
<cmt>knew the fact &gt; found out</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yoshitune found out that the fox&apos;s real priority was Shizuka Gozen&apos;s Tsuzumi (a hand drum) made from the skin of its parent, he gave the fox his own name and allowed the fox to call himself &quot;Genkuro&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>妖刀子狐丸伝説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The legend of Yoto Kogitune maru</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The legend of Yoto Kogitune maru</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The legend of Yoto Kogitune maru</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>菅田明神の境内に住む小狐が、近くの淵で村人を苦しめている大蛇を源九郎狐の加勢を得て退治した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A little fox which lived in the precincts of Sugata Myojin got rid of a giant snake from which the village people were suffering with a help from Genkuro Gitune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With help from Genkuro Gitune, a little fox who lived in the grounds of Sugata Myojin got rid of a giant snake which was tormenting the village people.</e>
<cmt>順番を変え、suffering &gt; tormenting.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With help from Genkuro Gitune, a little fox who lived in the grounds of Sugata Myojin got rid of a giant snake which was tormenting the village people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>大蛇の尾から宝剣が見つかり、村人はこの宝剣を「小狐丸」と名づけ、天理の石上神宮へ奉納した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Hoken (a treasured sword) was found in the tail of the giant snake, the villagers named it &quot;Kogitsune maru,&quot; and dedicated it to Isonokami-jingu Shrine located in Tenri.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a Hoken (prized sword) was found in the tail of the giant snake, the villagers named it &quot;Kogitsune maru,&quot; and dedicated it to Isonokami-jingu Shrine located in Tenri.</e>
<cmt>treasured &gt; prized</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a Hoken (prized sword) was found in the tail of the giant snake, the villagers named it &quot;Kogitsune maru,&quot; and dedicated it to Isonokami-jingu Shrine located in Tenri.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>元和の鎮火伝説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The legend of a fire extinction in Genna era</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Genna era legend of a fire extinction</e>
<cmt>順番を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Genna era legend of a fire extinction</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>元和元年(1615)、大野主馬による夜襲焼討をうけた際、城下の中心へと火が迫ってきたのを見た城主豊臣秀長が、源九郎狐に祈願をした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1615, the castle was attacked by Kazuma ONO who set on fire at night, and when Hidenaga TOYOTOMI, the lord of the castle, saw the fire coming down to the central part of the castle town, prayed to Genkuro Gitsune, it suddenly began to rain, and prevented the fire from widely spreding.</e>
<cmt>大野主馬→　おおのかずま？</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1615, when the castle was set on fire in the night by Kazuma ONO, Hidenaga TOYOTOMI, the lord of the castle, seeing the fire spreading down to the central part of the castle town, prayed to Genkuro Gitsune.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処attacked &gt; set on fire. saw &gt; seeing. coming &gt; spreading.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1615, when the castle was set on fire in the night by Kazuma ONO, Hidenaga TOYOTOMI, the lord of the castle, seeing the fire spreading down to the central part of the castle town, prayed to Genkuro Gitsune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>すると突然大雨が降り、大火を免れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On doing so it suddenly began to rain, which prevented the fire from spreading.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処on doing so を挿入し、and&gt;which.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On doing so it suddenly began to rain, which prevented the fire from spreading.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>綿帽子を買った狐伝説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The legend of a fox which bought cotton caps</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The legend of a fox who bought cotton caps</e>
<cmt>which&gt;who</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The legend of a fox who bought cotton caps</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>大和郡山の柳三丁目に帽子屋があり、ある冬の夜、婦人が綿帽子を三つ買いに来た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a cap shop in 3-chome, Yanagi, Yamatokoriyama, and one winter night, a women came to the shop to buy three cotton caps.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a cap shop in 3-chome, Yanagi, Yamatokoriyama, and one winter night, a woman came to the shop to buy three cotton caps.</e>
<cmt>women&gt;woman</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a cap shop in 3-chome, Yanagi, Yamatokoriyama, and one winter night, a woman came to the shop to buy three cotton caps.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースの削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>代金を源九郎神社へ取りに来て欲しいと言われたが、神社では、誰も心当たりがないという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the woman asked the shopowner to come to Genkuro-jinjya Shrine to receive the payment, no one in the shirine knew about that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The woman asked the shopowner to come to Genkuro-jinjya Shrine to receive payment, but when he did so no-one in the shrine knew who he was talking about.</e>
<cmt>although, theを省略しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The woman asked the shopowner to come to Genkuro-jinja Shrine to receive payment, but when he did so no-one in the shrine knew who he was talking about.</e>
<cmt>「Genkuro-jinjya」を「Genkuro-jinja」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>主人が不審に思っていると、境内から、綿帽子をかぶった三匹の小狐が現れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the whopowner felt suspicious about it, three little foxes wearing the cotton caps appeared in the precincts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Just as the shopowner started to feel suspicious, three little foxes wearing the cotton caps appeared in the Shrine grounds.</e>
<cmt>when &gt; just as. whopowner&gt;shopowner. precincts &gt; grounds.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Just as the shopowner started to feel suspicious, three little foxes wearing the cotton caps appeared in the Shrine grounds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>交通アクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>近鉄橿原線「近鉄郡山」駅下車　徒歩7分。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Take Kintetsu Kashihara line and get off at &quot;Kintetsu Koriyama Station,&quot; then walk 7 minutes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Take Kintetsu Kashihara line and get off at &quot;Kintetsu Koriyama Station,&quot; then walk 7 minutes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Take Kintetsu Kashihara line and get off at &quot;Kintetsu Koriyama Station,&quot; then walk 7 minutes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>洞泉寺の脇に鎮座。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The temple is located on the side of Dosen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The temple is located to the side of Dosen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>on&gt;to</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The temple is located to the side of Dosen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>