<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大原野神社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oharano-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oharano-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oharano-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大原野神社（おおはらのじんじゃ）は、京都市西京区大原野にある神社である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oharano-jinja Shrine is a Shinto shrine located in Oharano, Nishigyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oharano-jinja Shrine is a Shinto shrine located in Oharano, Nishigyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oharano-jinja Shrine is a Shinto shrine located in Oharano, Nishigyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>奈良春日社（現在の春日大社）から勧請を受けたもので、京春日（きょうかすが）の別称がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also known as Kyo Kasuga because the enshrined deities were separated and transferred from Kasuga-sha Shrine in Nara (present-day Kasuga Taisha Shrine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also known as Kyo Kasuga because the enshrined deities were separated and transferred from Kasuga-sha Shrine in Nara (present-day Kasuga Taisha Shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also known as Kyo Kasuga because the enshrined deities were separated and transferred from Kasuga-sha Shrine in Nara (present-day Kasuga Taisha Shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>二十二社・官幣中社に列し、現在は別表神社となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was one of the Twenty-Two Shrines and classified as a Kanpei Chusha but today it is a Beppyo Jinja.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was one of the Twenty-Two Shrines and classified as a Kanpei Chusha but today it is a Beppyo Jinja.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was one of the Twenty-Two Shrines and classified as a Kanpei Chusha (middle-scale government shrines) but today it is a Beppyo Jinja (shrines on the special list).</e>
<cmt>(middle-scale government shrines) (shrines on the special list)補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>祭神は春日大社と同じで、タケミカヅチ（武甕槌命）・経津主神（経津主命）・天児屋命（天児屋根命）・比売神（比売神）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The deities enshrined at Oharano-jinja Shrine are the same as those of Kasuga Taisha Shrine and consist of Takemikazuchi (Takemikazuchino Mikoto), Futsunushino Kami (Futsunushino Mikoto), Ameno Koyaneno Mikoto and Himenokami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The deities enshrined at Oharano-jinja Shrine are the same as those of Kasuga Taisha Shrine and consist of Takemikazuchi (Takemikazuchino Mikoto), Futsunushino Kami (Futsunushino Mikoto), Ameno Koyaneno Mikoto and Himenokami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The deities enshrined at Oharano-jinja Shrine are the same as those of Kasuga Taisha Shrine and consist of Takemikazuchi (Takemikazuchino Mikoto), Futsunushino Kami (Futsunushino Mikoto), Ameno Koyaneno Mikoto and Himenokami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>延暦3年（784年）に桓武天皇が長岡京へ遷都した際、桓武天皇の后の藤原乙牟漏が藤原氏の氏神である奈良春日社の分霊を勧請して、しばしば鷹狩を行っていた大原野に祀ったのに始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oharano-jinja Shrine originated when Emperor Komu relocated the capital to the city of Nagaoka-kyo in the year 784 and his wife, FUJIWARA no Otomuro, divided the ujigami (guardian deity) of the Fujiwara clan enshrined at Kasuga-sha Shrine and enshrined it at Oharano where she frequently engaged in falconry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oharano-jinja Shrine originated when Emperor Komu relocated the capital to the city of Nagaoka-kyo in the year 784 and his wife, FUJIWARA no Otomuro, divided the ujigami (guardian deity) of the Fujiwara clan enshrined at Kasuga-sha Shrine and enshrined it at Oharano where she frequently engaged in falconry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oharano-jinja Shrine originated when the Emperor Kanmu relocated the capital to the city of Nagaoka-kyo in the year 784 and his wife, FUJIWARA no Otomuro, divided the ujigami (guardian deity) of the Fujiwara clan enshrined at Nara Kasuga-sha Shrine and enshrined it at Oharano where she frequently engaged in falconry.</e>
<cmt>人名修正Nara補足&quot;the&quot; を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>嘉祥3年（850年）、藤原冬嗣を祖父に持つ文徳天皇が社殿を造営した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Buntoku, who was the grandson of FUJIWARA no Fuyutsugu, constructed the shrine buildings in the year 850.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Buntoku, who was the grandson of FUJIWARA no Fuyutsugu, constructed the shrine buildings in the year 850.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor Buntoku, who was the grandson of FUJIWARA no Fuyutsugu, constructed the shrine buildings in the year 850.</e>
<cmt>&quot;The&quot; を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>奈良春日社と同じ藤原氏の氏神を祀る大原野神社はそれに準ずる扱いを受け、二十二社に列した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Oharano-jinja Shrine enshrined same Fujiwara clan ujigami as Kasuga-sha Shrine, it received the same treatment and was included in the Twenty-Two Shrines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Oharano-jinja Shrine enshrined same Fujiwara clan ujigami as Kasuga-sha Shrine, it received the same treatment and was included in the Twenty-Two Shrines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Oharano-jinja Shrine enshrined same Fujiwara clan ujigami as Nara Kasuga-sha Shrine, it received the same treatment and was included in the Twenty-Two Shrines.</e>
<cmt>Nara補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>明治4年に官幣中社に列した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was classified as a Kanpei Chusha in 1871.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was classified as a Kanpei Chusha in 1871.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was classified as a Kanpei Chusha in 1871.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>藤原氏の家に女の子が生まれると、その子が皇后・中宮になれるようにと当社に祈願し、祈願通りになると行列を整えて当社に参詣することが通例となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Girls born into the Fujiwara clan would visit Oharano-jinja Shrine to pray that they would become empress or the emperor&apos;s second consort and, if their prayer came true, it became customary to organize a procession and make a pilgrimage back to the shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Girls born into the Fujiwara clan would visit Oharano-jinja Shrine to pray that they would become empress or the emperor&apos;s second consort and, if their prayer came true, it became customary to organize a procession and make a pilgrimage back to the shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Girls born into the Fujiwara clan would visit Oharano-jinja Shrine to pray that they would become empress or the emperor&apos;s second consort and, if their prayer came true, it became customary to organize a procession and make a pilgrimage back to the shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>貞観 (日本)18年（876年）、清和天皇の女御となった藤原高子（二条の后）が当社に参詣した際、右近衛権中将で高子のかつての恋人であった在原業平がその行幸につき従い、「大原や小塩の山もけふこそは 神世のことも思出づらめ」と詠んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Emperor Seiwa&apos;s wife, FUJIWARA no Takako (of the Nijo family), made her pilgrimage to Oharano-jinja Shrine in the year 876, her former lover Lieutenant General ARIWARA no Narihira followed the imperial precession and composed &quot;Ohara ya Oshio no yama mo kefu koso ha kamiyo no koto mo omoidezurame&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Emperor Seiwa&apos;s wife, FUJIWARA no Takako (of the Nijo family), made her pilgrimage to Oharano-jinja Shrine in the year 876, her former lover Lieutenant General ARIWARA no Narihira followed the imperial precession and composed &quot;Ohara ya Oshio no yama mo kefu koso ha kamiyo no koto mo omoidezurame&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Emperor Seiwa&apos;s wife, FUJIWARA no Takako (of the Nijo family), made her pilgrimage to Oharano-jinja Shrine in the year 876, her former lover, Lieutenant General ARIWARA no Narihira, followed the imperial precession and composed the following poem: &apos;Ohara ya Oshio no yama mo kefu koso ha kamiyo no koto mo omoidezurame&apos; (literally, &quot;here in the Ohara field of Mt. Oshio, the guardian gods of the Fujiwara clan are reminded of ancient times as they look down upon you, their descendent, praying here today&quot;).</e>
<cmt>「大原野の小塩山の麓にいらっしゃる藤原氏の氏神様も、子孫である貴方様のご参詣になった今日のこの日には、遥か昔の事などもきっと思い出していらっしゃるでしょう」歌の意味を調べました。翻訳の確認をお願いします。&quot;→&apos;ピリオド位置移動&quot;the&quot; を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nnh(id:474), Memeja(id:110500), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>