<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>金峯山寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinpusen-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinpusen-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinpusen-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>金峯山寺（きんぷせんじ）は、奈良県吉野郡吉野町にある修験道系の仏教寺院。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinpusen-ji Temple, located in Yoshino-cho, Yoshino-gun, Nara Prefecture, is a Buddhist temple of Shgendo lineage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinpusen-ji Temple, located in Yoshino-cho, Yoshino-gun, Nara Prefecture, is a Buddhist temple of Shgendo lineage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinpusen-ji Temple, located in Yoshino-cho, Yoshino County, Nara Prefecture, is a Buddhist temple of Shgendo lineage.</e>
<cmt>「郡」はCountyに統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>本尊は蔵王権現、開基（創立者）は役小角（えんのおづぬ）と伝える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its principal image is Zaogongen-zo and its founder has been reported to be EN no Ozunu (A semi-legendary holy man noted for his practice of mountain asceticism during the second half of the 7 century).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its principal image is Zaogongen-zo and its founder has been reported to be EN no Ozunu (A semi-legendary holy man noted for his practice of mountain asceticism during the second half of the seventh century).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its principal image is Zaogongen-zo and its founder has been reported to be EN no Ozunu (A semi-legendary holy man noted for his practice of mountain asceticism during the second half of the seventh century).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>金峯山寺の所在する吉野山は、古来桜の名所として知られ、南北朝時代 (日本)には南朝の中心地でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mt. Yoshino where Kinpusen-ji Temple is located has been known for beautiful cherry blossoms since ancient times and was the center of the Southern Court during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mt. Yoshino where Kinpusen-ji Temple is located has been known for beautiful cherry blossoms since ancient times and was the center of the Southern Court during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mt. Yoshino where Kinpusen-ji Temple is located has been known for beautiful cherry blossoms since ancient times and was the center of the Southern Court during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>「金峯山」とは、単独の峰の呼称ではなく、吉野山（奈良県吉野郡吉野町）と、その南方20数キロの大峯山系に位置する山上ヶ岳（奈良県吉野郡天川村）を含む山岳霊場を包括した名称であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kinpusen Mountain&quot; was not a name for a single mountain ridge but comprehensively referred to a sacred area in mountains covering Mt. Yoshino (Yoshino-cho, Yoshino-gun, Nara Prefecture) and Mt. Sanjogatake (Amakawa Mura, Yoshino County, Nara Prefecture), a mountain located 20 kilometer south from Mt. Yoshino and belonging to the system of Mt. Omine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kinpusen Mountain&quot; was not a name for a single mountain ridge but comprehensively referred to a sacred area in the mountains covering Mt. Yoshino (Yoshino-cho, Yoshino-gun, Nara Prefecture) and Mt. Sanjogatake (Amakawa Mura, Yoshino County, Nara Prefecture), a mountain located twenty kilometers south of Mt. Yoshino and belonging to the system of Mt. Omine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kinpusen Mountain&quot; was not a name for a single mountain ridge but comprehensively referred to a sacred area in the mountains covering Mt. Yoshino (Yoshino-cho, Yoshino County, Nara Prefecture) and Mt. Sanjogatake (Amakawa Mura, Yoshino County, Nara Prefecture), a mountain located twenty kilometers south of Mt. Yoshino and belonging to the system of Mt. Omine.</e>
<cmt>「郡」はCountyに統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>吉野・大峯は古代から山岳信仰の聖地であり、平安時代以降は霊場として多くの参詣人を集めてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshino and Omine have long been a secret place for mountain worship since ancient times and attracted many worshipers as a sacred site since the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshino and Omine have long been a secret place for mountain worship since ancient times and attracted many worshipers as a sacred site since the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshino and Omine have long been a secret place for mountain worship since ancient times and attracted many worshipers as a sacred site since the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>吉野・大峯の霊場は、和歌山県の高野山と熊野三山、及びこれら霊場同士を結ぶ巡礼路とともに世界遺産「紀伊山地の霊場と参詣道」の構成要素となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sacred site in Yoshino and Omine constitutes a component of the world heritage &quot;Sacred Sites and Pilgrimage Routes in the Kii Mountain Range,&quot; along with Koyasan, Kumano Sanzan (three major shrines, Kumano-Hongu-Taisha, Kumano-Hayatama-Taisha and Kumano-Nachi-Taisha) in Wakayama Prefecture, and Pilgrimage routes that connect these sacred sites.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sacred site in Yoshino and Omine constitutes a component of the world heritage &quot;Sacred Sites and Pilgrimage Routes in the Kii Mountain Range,&quot; along with Koyasan, Kumano Sanzan (three major shrines, Kumano-Hongu-Taisha, Kumano-Hayatama-Taisha and Kumano-Nachi-Taisha) in Wakayama Prefecture, and Pilgrimage routes that connect these sacred sites.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sacred site in Yoshino and Omine constitutes a component of the world heritage &quot;Sacred Sites and Pilgrimage Routes in the Kii Mountain Range,&quot; along with Koyasan, Kumano Sanzan (three major shrines, Kumano-Hongu-Taisha, Kumano-Hayatama-Taisha and Kumano-Nachi-Taisha) in Wakayama Prefecture, and Pilgrimage routes that connect these sacred sites.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outline</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>用語を統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>奈良県南部の吉野山に位置する金峯山寺は、7世紀に活動した伝説的な山林修行者・役小角（えんのおづぬ）が開創したと伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinpusen-ji Temple, located in Mt. Yoshino in the south of Nara Prefecture, is reported to have been founded by EN no Ozunu, a semi-legendary practitioner of austerities in mountains and forests.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinpusen-ji Temple, located in Mt. Yoshino, south of Nara Prefecture, is reported to have been founded by EN no Ozunu, a semi-legendary practitioner of austerities in mountains and forests.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinpusen-ji Temple, located in Mt. Yoshino, south of Nara Prefecture, is reported to have been founded by EN no Ozunu, a semi-legendary practitioner of austerities in mountains and forests.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>蔵王権現を本尊とする寺院である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its principle image is Zao Gongen.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its principle image is Zao Gongen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its principal image is Zao Gongen.</e>
<cmt>principle→principal</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>金峯山寺のある吉野山には吉水神社、如意輪寺、竹林院 (吉野町)、桜本坊（さくらもとぼう）、喜蔵院、吉野水分神社、金峯神社など、他にも多くの社寺が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mt. Yoshino where Kinpusen-ji Temple is located contains many other shrines and temple, such as Yoshimizu-jinja Shrine, Nyoirin-ji Temple, Chikurin-in Temple (Yoshinocho), Sakuramoto-bo, Kizo-in, Yoshino-mikumari-jinja Shrine, and Kinpu-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mt. Yoshino where Kinpusen-ji Temple is located contains many other shrines and temple, such as Yoshimizu-jinja Shrine, Nyoirin-ji Temple, Chikurin-in Temple (Yoshinocho), Sakuramoto-bo, Kizo-in, Yoshino-mikumari-jinja Shrine, and Kinpu-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mt. Yoshino where Kinpusen-ji Temple is located contains many other shrines and temple, such as Yoshimizu-jinja Shrine, Nyoirin-ji Temple, Chikurin-in Temple (Yoshinocho), Sakuramoto-bo, Kizo-in, Yoshino-mikumari-jinja Shrine, and Kinpu-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>「吉野山」とは、1つの峰を指す名称ではなく、これらの社寺が点在する山地の広域地名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Mt. Yoshino&quot; is not a name for a mountain ridge but for an extensive area where these shrines and temples are scattered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Mt. Yoshino&quot; is not a name for a mountain ridge but for an extensive area where these shrines and temples are scattered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Mt. Yoshino&quot; is not a name for a mountain ridge but for an extensive area where these shrines and temples are scattered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、吉野山の20数キロ南方、吉野郡天川村の山上ヶ岳（1,719メートル）の山頂近くには大峯山寺（おおみねさんじ）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, there is Ominesan-ji Temple 20 kilometers from Mt. Yoshino and close to the top of Mt. Sanjogatake (1,719 meters) in Amakawa Mura, Yoshino County.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, there is Ominesan-ji Temple twenty kilometers from Mt. Yoshino and close to the top of Mt. Sanjogatake (1,719 meters) in Amakawa Mura, Yoshino County.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, there is Ominesan-ji Temple twenty kilometers from Mt. Yoshino and close to the top of Mt. Sanjogatake (1,719 meters) in Amakawa Mura, Yoshino County.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>吉野山の金峯山寺と山上ヶ岳の大峯山寺とは、近代以降は分離して別個の寺院になっているが、近世までは前者を「山下（さんげ）の蔵王堂」、後者を山上の蔵王堂と呼び、両者は不可分のものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinpusen-ji Temple in Mt. Yoshino and Ominesan-ji Temple in Mt. Sanjogatake have been divided into separate temples since modern times, but they had an inseparable relationship with each other with the former being called &quot;Sange no Zao-do&quot; and the latter &quot;Sanjo no Zao-do.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinpusen-ji Temple in Mt. Yoshino and Ominesan-ji Temple in Mt. Sanjogatake have been divided into separate temples since modern times, but they had an inseparable relationship with each other with the former being called &quot;Sange no Zao-do&quot; and the latter &quot;Sanjo no Zao-do.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinpusen-ji Temple in Mt. Yoshino and Ominesan-ji Temple in Mt. Sanjogatake have been divided into separate temples since modern times, but they had an inseparable relationship with each other with the former being called &quot;Sange no Zao-do&quot; and the latter &quot;Sanjo no Zao-do.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>「金峯山寺」とは本来、山上山下の2つの蔵王堂と関連の子院などを含めた総称であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both Sange and Sanjo Zao-do and related branch temples were at first collectively called &quot;Kinpusen-ji Temple.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both Sange and Sanjo Zao-do and related branch temples were at first collectively called &quot;Kinpusen-ji Temple.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both Sange and Sanjo Zao-do and related branch temples were at first collectively called &quot;Kinpusen-ji Temple.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>役行者と蔵王権現</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">EN no Gyoja (A semi-legendary holy man noted for his practice of mountain asceticism during the second half of the 7 century) and Zao Gongen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">EN no Gyoja (A semi-legendary holy man noted for his practice of mountain asceticism during the second half of the seventh century) and Zao Gongen</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">EN no Gyoja (A semi-legendary holy man noted for his practice of mountain asceticism during the second half of the seventh century) and Zao Gongen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>国土の7割を山地が占める日本においては、山は古くから聖なる場所とされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan where mountainous districts occupy 70% of the land, mountains have been regarded as sacred places.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan where mountainous districts occupy seventy percent of the land, mountains have been regarded as sacred places.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan where mountainous districts occupy seventy percent of the land, mountains have been regarded as sacred places.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>中でも奈良県南部の吉野・大峯や和歌山県の熊野三山は、古くから山岳信仰の霊地とされ、山伏、修験者などと呼ばれる山林修行者が活動していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular, Yoshino and Omine of southern Nara Prefecture and Kumano Sanzan (three major shrines, Kumano-Hongu-Taisha, Kumano-Hayatama-Taisha and Kumano-Nachi-Taisha) in Wakayama Prefecture have been long regarded as sacred places for a mountain religion, and practitioner training Buddhism in mountains and forests called yamabushi and ascetic Buddhist monk were engaged in activities there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, Yoshino and Omine of southern Nara Prefecture and Kumano Sanzan (three major shrines, Kumano-Hongu-Taisha, Kumano-Hayatama-Taisha and Kumano-Nachi-Taisha) in Wakayama Prefecture have been long regarded as sacred places for a mountain religion, and practitioner training Buddhism in mountains and forests called yamabushi and ascetic Buddhist monk were engaged in activities there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, Yoshino and Omine of southern Nara Prefecture and Kumano Sanzan (three major shrines, Kumano-Hongu-Taisha, Kumano-Hayatama-Taisha and Kumano-Nachi-Taisha) in Wakayama Prefecture have been long regarded as sacred places for a mountain religion, and practitioner training Buddhism in mountains and forests called yamabushi and ascetic Buddhist monk were engaged in activities there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>こうした日本古来の山岳信仰が神道、仏教、道教などと習合し、日本独自の宗教として発達をとげたのが修験道である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shugendo was developed as an religion unique to Japan through incorporation of Shinto religion, Buddhism, Taoism, and so forth.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shugendo was developed as an religion unique to Japan through incorporation of Shinto religion, Buddhism, Taoism, and so forth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shugendo was developed as an mountain religion unique to Japan through incorporation of Shinto religion, Buddhism, Taoism, and so forth.</e>
<cmt>山岳信仰を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>その開祖とされているのが役小角である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">EN no Ozunu is believed to be the founder.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">EN no Ozunu is believed to have been the founder.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">EN no Ozunu is believed to have been the founder.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>役行者（えんのぎょうじゃ）の呼び名で広く知られる役小角は、7世紀前半に今の奈良県御所市に生まれ、大和国と河内国の境にある大和葛城山で修行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">EN no Ozunu widely known in the name of EN no Gyoja was born in present-day Gose City, Nara Prefecture in the early 7th century and practiced asceticism in Yamato Katsuragi Moutain located in the boundary between Yamato-no-kuni and Kawachi Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">EN no Ozunu widely known in the name of EN no Gyoja was born in present-day Gose City, Nara Prefecture in the early seventh century and practiced asceticism in Yamato Katsuragi Moutain located in the boundary between Yamato-no-kuni and Kawachi Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">EN no Ozunu widely known in the name of EN no Gyoja was born in present-day Gose City, Nara Prefecture in the early seventh century and practiced asceticism in Yamato Katsuragi Mountain located in the boundary between Yamato Province and Kawachi Province.</e>
<cmt>Yamato-no-kuni→Yamato Province</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>さまざまな験力（超人的能力）をもっていたとされる伝説的人物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a semi-legendary man that is beloved to have super human abilities.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a semi-legendary man that is believed to have had super human abilities.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a semi-legendary man that is believed to have had super human abilities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>奈良県西部から大阪府にかけての地域には金峯山寺以外にも役行者開創を伝える寺院が数多く存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to Kinpusen-ji Temple, there are a large number of temples from Western Nara Prefecture through Osaka Prefecture, which are believed to have been founded by EN no Gyoja.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to Kinpusen-ji Temple, there are a large number of temples from Western Nara Prefecture through Osaka Prefecture, believed to have been founded by EN no Gyoja.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to Kinpusen-ji Temple, there are a large number of temples from Western Nara Prefecture through Osaka Prefecture, believed to have been founded by EN no Gyoja.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>『続日本紀』の文武天皇3年（699年）の条には、役小角が伊豆へ流罪になったという記述がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 699-year section of &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued) describes that EN no Ozunu were condemned to exile.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 699-year section of &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued) describes that EN no Ozunu were condemned to exile.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 699-year section of &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued) describes that EN no Ozunu were condemned to exile to Izu.</e>
<cmt>to Izuを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>このことから役小角が実在の人物であったことはわかるが、正史に残る役小角の事績としては『続日本紀』のこの記事が唯一のものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This proves that EN no Ozunu was a real person but no official history remains except for this article of &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; describing his achievement.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This proves that EN no Ozunu was a real person, but no official history remains except for this article of &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; describing his achievement.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This proves that EN no Ozunu was a real person, but no official history remains except for this article of &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; describing his achievement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>彼の超人的イメージは修験道や山岳信仰の発達とともに後世の人々によって形成されていったものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His superhuman image was formed in the minds of people of later generations with the development of Shugendo and a mountain religion.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His superhuman image was formed in the minds of people of later generations with the development of Shugendo and a mountain religion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His superhuman image was formed in the minds of people of later generations with the development of Shugendo and a mountain religion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="24">
<j>金峯山寺は役行者が創立した修験道の根本寺院とされているが、前述のように役行者自体が半ば伝説化された人物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinpusen-ji Temple is believed to be the base temple for Shugendo founded by EN no Gyoja, but EN no Gyoja himself is a semi-legendary person as mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinpusen-ji Temple is believed to be the base temple for Shugendo founded by EN no Gyoja, but EN no Gyoja himself is a semi-legendary person as mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinpusen-ji Temple is believed to be the base temple for Shugendo founded by EN no Gyoja, but EN no Gyoja himself is a semi-legendary person as mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>そのため、金峯山寺草創の正確な事情、時期、創立当初どのような寺院であったかなどについては不詳と言わざるをえない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore it cannot help being considered as unclear what precisely lay behind the foundation of Kinpusen-ji Temple, when it was founded, and what the temple was like upon foundation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore it cannot help being considered as unclear what precisely lay behind the foundation of Kinpusen-ji Temple, when it was founded, and what the temple was like upon foundation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore it cannot help being considered as unclear what precisely lay behind the foundation of Kinpusen-ji Temple, when it was founded, and what the temple was like upon foundation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="26">
<j>金峯山寺および大峯山寺の本尊であり、中心的な信仰対象となっているのは、蔵王権現という、仏教の仏とも神道の神ともつかない、独特の尊格である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The principal images of Kinpusen-ji Temple and Ominesan-ji Temple--the central object of worship--are unique deities called Zao Gongen that are between Buddha of Buddhism and the gods of Shinto religion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The principal images of Kinpusen-ji Temple and Ominesan-ji Temple--the central object of worship--are unique deities called Zao Gongen that are between Buddha of Buddhism and the gods of Shinto religion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The principal images of Kinpusen-ji Temple and Ominesan-ji Temple--the central object of worship--are unique deities called Zao Gongen that are between Buddha of Buddhism and the gods of Shinto religion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>金峯山寺の本尊は3体の蔵王権現で、その像容は、以下の通りである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The principal images of Kinpusen-ji Temple are 3 images of Zaogongen, whose faces and figures are as follows.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The principal images of Kinpusen-ji Temple are three images of Zaogongen, whose faces and figures are as follows.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The principal images of Kinpusen-ji Temple are three images of Zaogongen, whose faces and figures are as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>火焔を背負い、頭髪は逆立ち、目を吊り上げ、口を大きく開いて忿怒の相を表わし、片足を高く上げて虚空を踏むものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They carry flame, had a forelock standing on end and eyes turning upward at the corners, open their mouths, express angers, lift up a leg, and step on empty space.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They carry flame, had a forelock standing on end and eyes turning upward at the corners, open mouths, express anger, one leg lifted up stepping on empty space.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They carry flame, had a forelock standing on end and eyes turning upward at the corners, open mouths, express anger, one leg lifted up stepping on empty space.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>インドや中国起源ではない、日本独自の尊像であり、密教彫像などの影響を受けて、日本で独自に創造されたものと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The images are not originated from India or China but are statues unique to Japan, suggesting that they were created independently under the influence of sculpture of Esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The images are not originated from India or China but are statues unique to Japan, suggesting that they were created independently under the influence of Esoteric Buddhist sculpture..</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The images are not originated from India or China but are statues unique to Japan, suggesting that they were created independently under the influence of Esoteric Buddhist sculpture..</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>修験道の伝承では、蔵王権現は役行者が金峯山での修行の際に感得した（祈りによって出現させた）ものとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a tradition of Shugendo (Japanese mountain asceticism-shamanism incorporating Shinto and Buddhist concepts), EN no Gyoja made Zao Gongen emerge through prayers during ascetic practices in Kimpusen Mountain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a tradition of Shugendo (Japanese mountain asceticism-shamanism incorporating Shinto and Buddhist concepts), EN no Gyoja made Zao Gongen emerge through prayers during ascetic practices in Kimpusen Mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a tradition of Shugendo (Japanese mountain asceticism-shamanism incorporating Shinto and Buddhist concepts), EN no Gyoja made Zao Gongen emerge through prayers during ascetic practices in Kimpusen Mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>平安時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heian period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heian period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heian period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="31">
<j>金峯山寺の中興の祖とされるのは、平安時代前期の真言宗の僧で、京都の醍醐寺を開いたことでも知られる聖宝（しょうぼう）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chuko no So (father of restoration) of Kinpusen-ji Temple is believed to be Shobo, a monk of early Heian period, who is known as a founder of Daigo-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chuko no So (father of restoration) of Kinpusen-ji Temple is believed to be Shobo, a monk of early Heian period, who is known as a founder of Daigo-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chuko no So (father of restoration) of Kinpusen-ji Temple is believed to be Shobo, a monk of early Heian period, who is known as a founder of Daigo-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>『聖宝僧正伝』によれば、聖宝は寛平6年（894年）、荒廃していた金峯山を再興し、参詣路を整備し、堂を建立して如意輪観音、毘沙門天、金剛蔵王菩薩を安置したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;authentic biography of the priest Shobo,&quot; Shobo revived devastated Kimpusen Mountain, put the path to the temple in good condition, and built a pagoda to enshrine Nyoirin Kannon, Bishamonten, and Kongo Zoo Bosatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;authentic biography of the priest Shobo,&quot; Shobo revived devastated Kimpusen Mountain, put the path to the temple back into good condition, and built a pagoda to enshrine Nyoirin Kannon, Bishamonten, and Kongo Zoo Bosatsu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;authentic biography of the priest Shobo,&quot; Shobo revived devastated Kimpusen Mountain, put the path to the temple back into good condition, and built a pagoda to enshrine Nyoirin Kannon, Bishamonten, and Kongo Zoo Bosatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>「金剛蔵王菩薩」は両界曼荼羅のうちの胎蔵生曼荼羅に見える密教尊である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kongo Zoo Bosatsu &quot;is Mikkyozon found in Taizosho mandala, one of the Ryokai mandala (Mandalas of the two Realms).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kongo Zoo Bosatsu &quot;is Mikkyozon found in Taizosho mandala, one of the Ryokai mandala (Mandalas of the two Realms).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kongo Zoo Bosatsu &quot;is Mikkyozon found in Taizosho mandala, one of the Ryokai mandala (Mandalas of the two Realms).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>この頃から金峯山は山岳信仰に密教、末法思想、浄土信仰などが融合して信仰を集めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kimpusen Mountain, Esoteric Buddhism, Mappo-shiso (the &quot;end of the world&quot; belief), and Jodo-shinko (the Pure Land faith) started to merge into mountain worship around this period, attracting people&apos;s religious belief.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On Kimpusen Mountain, Esoteric Buddhism, Mappo-shiso (the &quot;end of the world&quot; belief), and Jodo-shinko (the Pure Land faith) started to merge into mountain worship around this period, attracting people&apos;s religious belief.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On Kimpusen Mountain, Esoteric Buddhism, Mappo-shiso (the &quot;end of the world&quot; belief), and Jodo-shinko (the Pure Land faith) started to merge into mountain worship around this period, attracting people&apos;s religious belief.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>また皇族、貴族などの参詣が相次いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, one after another members of imperial families and nobles visited the mountain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, one after another members of imperial families and nobles visited the mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, one after another members of imperial families and nobles visited the mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>金峯山に参詣した著名人には、宇多天皇（昌泰3年・900年）、藤原道長（寛弘4年・1007年）、藤原師通（寛治2年・1088年）白河天皇（寛治6年・1092年）などがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Well-known people who visited Kinpusen include Uda Emperor (in 900), FUJIWARA no Michinaga (in 1007), FUJIWARA no Moromichi, and Emperor Shirakawa (1092).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Well-known people who visited Kinpusen include Uda Emperor (in 900), FUJIWARA no Michinaga (in 1007), FUJIWARA no Moromichi, and Emperor Shirakawa (1092).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Well-known people who visited Kinpusen include Uda Emperor (in 900), FUJIWARA no Michinaga (in 1007), FUJIWARA no Moromichi, and Emperor Shirakawa (1092).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="37">
<j>このうち、藤原道長は山上の蔵王堂付近に金峯山経塚を造営しており、日本最古の経塚として知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular FUJIWARA no Michinaga built Kimpusen kyozuka (mound of Buddhist scriptures), known as the oldest kyozuka in Japan, near Zao-do Hall of Sanjo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular FUJIWARA no Michinaga built Kimpusen kyozuka (mound of Buddhist scriptures), known as the oldest kyozuka in Japan, near Zao-do Hall of Sanjo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular FUJIWARA no Michinaga built Kimpusen kyozuka (mound of Buddhist scriptures), known as the oldest kyozuka in Japan, near Zao-do Hall of Sanjo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>埋納された経筒は江戸時代に発掘され現存している（奈良県吉野町金峯神社蔵、国宝）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The buried kyozutsu (a tube in which rolled Buddhist scriptures are kept) was excavated in the Edo era and is stored (as a property of Kinpu-jinja Shrine, Yoshino-cho Nara Prefecture and as national treasure).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The buried kyozutsu (a tube in which rolled Buddhist scriptures are kept) was excavated in the Edo era and is stored (as a property of Kinpu-jinja Shrine, Yoshino-cho Nara Prefecture as national treasure).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The buried kyozutsu (a tube in which rolled Buddhist scriptures are kept) was excavated in the Edo era and is stored (as a property of Kinpu-jinja Shrine, Yoshino-cho Nara Prefecture as national treasure).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>金峯山は未来仏である弥勒仏の浄土と見なされ、金峯山（山上ヶ岳）の頂上付近には多くの経塚が造営された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many kyozuka mounds were built near the summit of Kimpusen Mountain (Mt. Sanjogatake), because Kimpusen Mountain was regarded as a Pure Land of Miroku-butsu (Miroku Buddha)--future Buddha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many kyozuka mounds were built near the summit of Kimpusen Mountain (Mt. Sanjogatake), because Kimpusen Mountain was regarded as a Pure Land of Miroku-butsu (Miroku Buddha)--future Buddha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many kyozuka mounds were built near the summit of Kimpusen Mountain (Mt. Sanjogatake), because Kimpusen Mountain was regarded as a Pure Land of Miroku-butsu (Miroku Buddha)--future Buddha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>中世～近世</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Medieval Period to early-modern times</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Medieval Period to early-modern times</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Medieval Period to early-modern times</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="40">
<j>修験道は中世末期以降、「本山派」と「当山派」の2つに大きく分かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the end of mediaeval period, Shugendo (Japanese mountain asceticism-shamanism incorporating Shinto and Buddhist concepts) was divided into two major groups: &quot;Honzan school&quot; and &quot;Tozan school&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the end of Medieval period, Shugendo (Japanese mountain asceticism-shamanism incorporating Shinto and Buddhist concepts) was divided into two major groups: the&quot;Honzan school&quot; and &quot;Tozan school&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the end of Medieval period, Shugendo (Japanese mountain asceticism-shamanism incorporating Shinto and Buddhist concepts) was divided into two major groups: the &quot;Honzan school&quot; and &quot;Tozan school&quot;</e>
<cmt>スペース</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>本山派は天台宗系で、園城寺（三井寺）の円珍を開祖とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honzan school belonging to the Tendai-shu sect line, is founded by Enchin of Onjo-ji Temple (Mii-dera Temple).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Honzan school belonging to the Tendai-shu sect line, was founded by Enchin of Onjo-ji Temple (Mii-dera Temple).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Honzan school belonging to the Tendai-shu sect line, was founded by Enchin of Onjo-ji Temple (Mii-dera Temple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>この派は主に熊野で活動し、総本山は天台宗寺門派（園城寺傘下）の聖護院（京都市左京区）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This sect mainly acted in Kumano and its Sohonzan (the general head temple) is Shogoin Temple (Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City), the Jimon School of the Tendai Sect (under the jurisdiction of Onjo-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This sect mainly acted in Kumano and its Sohonzan (the general head temple) is Shogoin Temple (Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City), the Jimon School of the Tendai Sect (under the jurisdiction of Onjo-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This sect mainly acted in Kumano and its Sohonzan (the general head temple) is Shogoin Temple (Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City), the Jimon School of the Tendai Sect (under the jurisdiction of Onjo-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>一方の当山派は真言宗系で、聖宝を開祖とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Tozan school belonging to the Shingon Sect line was founded by Shobo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the Tozan school belonging to the Shingon Sect line was founded by Shobo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the Tozan school belonging to the Shingon Sect line was founded by Shobo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>吉野を主な活動地とし、総本山は醍醐寺三宝院（京都市伏見区）であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This sect mainly acted in Yoshino and its Sohonzan was Sanbo-in of Daigo-ji Temple (Fushimi-ku, Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This sect mainly acted in Yoshino and its Sohonzan was Sanbo-in of Daigo-ji Temple (Fushimi-ku, Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This sect mainly acted in Yoshino and its Sohonzan was Sanbo-in of Daigo-ji Temple (Fushimi-ku, Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>金峯山寺は中興の祖である聖宝との関係で、当山派とのつながりが強かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinpusen-ji Temple having a relation with Shobo, Chuko no So (father of restoration), had a strong tie with Tozan school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinpusen-ji Temple having a relationship with Shobo, Chuko no So (father of restoration), had a strong tie with the Tozan school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinpusen-ji Temple having a relationship with Shobo, Chuko no So (father of restoration), had a strong tie with the Tozan school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>中世の金峯山寺は山上・山下に多くの子院をもち、多くの僧兵（吉野大衆と呼ばれた）を抱えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinpusen-ji Temple in the Medieval Period had many branch temples in both Sange and Sanjo with many armed priests (called masses of Yoshino).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinpusen-ji Temple, in the Medieval Period, had many branch temples in both Sange and Sanjo with many armed priests (called masses of Yoshino).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinpusen-ji Temple, in the Medieval Period, had many branch temples in both Sange and Sanjo with many armed priests (called masses of Yoshino).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>その勢力は南都北嶺（興福寺と延暦寺の僧兵を指す）にも劣らないといわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their power was said to be as strong as counterparts of Nanto Hokurei (the Buddhism of the temples of Nara and Mt. Hiei) (that refer to armed priests of Kofuku-ji Temple and Enryaku-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their power was said to be as strong as counterparts of Nanto Hokurei (the Buddhism of the temples of Nara and Mt. Hiei) (that refer to armed priests of Kofuku-ji Temple and Enryaku-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their power was said to be as strong as counterparts of Nanto Hokurei (the Buddhism of the temples of Nara and Mt. Hiei) (that refer to armed priests of Kofuku-ji Temple and Enryaku-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>南北朝時代、後醍醐天皇が吉野に移り、南朝を興したのにも、こうした軍事的背景があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These military background lay behind the Emperor Godaigo&apos;s establishment of the Southern Court during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts, Emperor Godaigo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This military background lay behind the Emperor Godaigo&apos;s establishment of the Southern Court during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts, Emperor Godaigo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This military background lay behind the Emperor Godaigo&apos;s establishment of the Southern Court during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts, Emperor Godaigo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="49">
<j>近世に入って慶長19年（1614年）、徳川家康の命により、天台宗の僧である天海（江戸・寛永寺などの開山）が金峯山寺の学頭になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1614 in the early-modern times, Tenkai, a priest of the Tendai sect (who founded temples in Edo such as Kanei-ji Temple), became Gakuto (head student) of Kinpusen-ji Temple at the order of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1614 in the early-modern times, Tenkai, a priest of the Tendai sect (who founded temples in Edo such as Kanei-ji Temple), became Gakuto (head student) of Kinpusen-ji Temple at the order of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1614 in the early-modern times, Tenkai, a priest of the Tendai sect (who founded temples in Edo such as Kanei-ji Temple), became Gakuto (head student) of Kinpusen-ji Temple at the order of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>そのため金峯山は天台宗（日光輪王寺）の傘下に置かれることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This put Kinpusen-ji Temple under jurisdiction of the Tendai-shu sect (Nikko Rinno-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This put Kinpusen-ji Temple under jurisdiction of the Tendai-shu sect (Nikko Rinno-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This put Kinpusen-ji Temple under jurisdiction of the Tendai-shu sect (Nikko Rinno-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>近代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Modern times</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Modern times</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Modern times</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="51">
<j>近代に入って修験道の信仰は大きな打撃をこうむることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During Modern times, worshipers of mountaineering asceticism suffered heavy blows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During Modern times, worshipers of mountaineering asceticism suffered heavy blows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During Modern times, worshipers of mountaineering asceticism suffered heavy blows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>1868年（明治元年）発布された神仏分離令によって、長年吉野山で行われてきた神仏習合の信仰は禁止され、寺院は廃寺になるか、神社に名を変えて生き延びるほかなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ordinance Distinguishing Shinto and Buddhism promulgated in 1868 prohibited syncretization of Shinto with Buddhism long beloved in Mt. Yoshino, forcing temples to be abolished or changed into shrines for survival.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ordinance Distinguishing Shinto and Buddhism promulgated in 1868 prohibited syncretization of Shinto with Buddhism long beloved in Mt. Yoshino, forcing temples to be abolished or changed into shrines for survival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ordinance Distinguishing Shinto and Buddhism promulgated in 1868 prohibited syncretization of Shinto with Buddhism long beloved in Mt. Yoshino, forcing temples to be abolished or changed into shrines for survival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>1872年（明治5年）には追い討ちをかけるように修験道廃止令が発布され、1874年（明治7年）には中心寺院の金峯山寺も廃寺に追い込まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To make it worse, a decrees dismissing Shugendo was promulgated in 1872, forcing Kinpusen-ji Temple, the pivotal temple, to be abolished in 1874.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To make it worse, a decree dismissing Shugendo was promulgated in 1872, forcing Kinpusen-ji Temple, the pivotal temple, to be abolished in 1874.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To make it worse, a decree dismissing Shugendo was promulgated in 1872, forcing Kinpusen-ji Temple, the pivotal temple, to be abolished in 1874.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>その後の政府の施策の変化や、修験道側からの嘆願により、1886年（明治19年）には「天台宗修験派」として修験道の再興が許され、金峯山寺は寺院として存続できることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later a change to the government policy and pleas from the mountaineering asceticism side made it revived in 1886 into &quot;the Shugen school of Tendai sect,&quot; allowing Kinpusen-ji Temple to maintain as a temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later a change to government policy and pleas from the mountaineering asceticism side revived it in 1886 as &quot;the Shugen school of Tendai sect,&quot; allowing Kinpusen-ji Temple to be maintained as a temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later a change to government policy and pleas from the mountaineering asceticism side revived it in 1886 as &quot;the Shugen school of Tendai sect,&quot; allowing Kinpusen-ji Temple to be maintained as a temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>ただし、山上の蔵王堂は「大峯山寺」として、吉野の金峯山寺とは分離され、21世紀に至っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Zao-do Hall on Sange was separated from Kinpusen-ji Temple in Yoshino to become &quot;Ominesan-ji Temple&quot; and exists up to now in the 21st century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Zao-do Hall on Sange was separated from Kinpusen-ji Temple in Yoshino to become &quot;Ominesan-ji Temple&quot; and still exists up to now in the twenty-first century.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Zao-do Hall on Sanjo was separated from Kinpusen-ji Temple in Yoshino to become &quot;Ominesan-ji Temple&quot; and still exists up to now in the twenty-first century.</e>
<cmt>Sange→Sanjo</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="56">
<j>第二次大戦後の1948年（昭和23年）、天台宗から独立して大峯修験宗が成立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1948 after World War II, Omine Shugen sect was established independently of the Tendai-shu sect.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1948 after World War II, the Omine Shugen sect was established independently of the Tendai-shu sect.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1948 after World War II, the Omine Shugen sect was established independently of the Tendai-shu sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>1952年（昭和27年）には金峯山修験本宗と改称、金峯山寺が同宗の総本山となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1952, it changed its name to Kimpusen Shugen Main Sect, and Kinpusen-ji Temple has been the Sohonzan of the sect.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1952, it changed its name to Kimpusen Shugen Main Sect, and Kinpusen-ji Temple has been the Sohonzan of the sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1952, it changed its name to Kimpusen Shugen Main Sect, and Kinpusen-ji Temple has been the Sohonzan of the sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>伽藍</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buddhist temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buddhist temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddhist temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="58">
<j>吉野大峯ケーブル自動車の吉野山駅を出てしばらく歩くと、金峯山寺の総門である黒門がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Walking for a while from Yoshinoyama Station of Yoshino Ohmine ke-buru Ropeway bus Co.Ltd, you find Kuro-mon gate, So-mon gate of Kinpusen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Walking for a while from Yoshinoyama Station of Yoshino Ohmine ke-buru Ropeway bus Co.Ltd, you&apos;ll find Kuro-mon gate, So-mon gate of Kinpusen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Walking for a while from Yoshinoyama Station of Yoshino Ohmine ke-buru Ropeway bus Co.Ltd, you&apos;ll find Kuro-mon gate, So-mon gate of Kinpusen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>そこから旅館、飲食店、みやげ物店などの並ぶ上り坂の参道を行くと、途中に銅鳥居（かねのとりい）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is Kanenotorii Gate ahead the gate along the sando (an approach to the temple), upward slop lined with inns, restaurants and souvenir shops.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is Kanenotorii Gate ahead of the gate along the sando (an approach to the temple), upward slop lined with inns, restaurants and souvenir shops.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is Kanenotorii Gate ahead of the gate along the sando (an approach to the temple), upward slop lined with inns, restaurants and souvenir shops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>吉野山駅から徒歩10分ほどのところに仁王門、その先の小高くなった敷地に本堂（蔵王堂）が建つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After 10 minutes walk from Yoshinoyama Station, there stand Nio-mon Gate (Deva gate), and the main hall (Zao-do Hall) is found ahead on a small hill.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After a ten minute walk from Yoshinoyama Station, you&apos;ll see Nio-mon Gate (Deva gate), and the main hall (Zao-do Hall) is seen ahead on a small hill.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After a ten minute walk from Yoshinoyama Station, you&apos;ll see Nio-mon Gate (Deva gate), and the main hall (Zao-do Hall) is seen ahead on a small hill.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="61">
<j>黒門 - ケーブル吉野山駅から徒歩数分のところに建つ黒塗りの高麗門で、金峯山寺の総門である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuro-mon gate - blackening Koraimon gate, So-mon gate of Kinpusen-ji Temple, can be found standing after few minutes from Cable-Yoshino Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuro-mon gate - blackening Koraimon gate, So-mon gate of Kinpusen-ji Temple, can be found after few minutes from Cable-Yoshino Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuro-mon gate - blackening Koraimon gate, So-mon gate of Kinpusen-ji Temple, can be found after few minutes from Cable-Yoshinoyama Station.</e>
<cmt>Yoshino →Yoshinoyama</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>現存する門は1985年の再興。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The existing gate was rebuilt in 1985.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The existing gate was rebuilt in 1985.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The existing gate was rebuilt in 1985.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="63">
<j>銅鳥居（重文）－銅鳥居と書いて「かねのとりい」と読む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanenotorii Gate (Important Cultural Property) - It is written &quot;銅鳥居&quot; and read as Kanenotorii.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanenotorii Gate (Important Cultural Property) - It is written &quot;銅鳥居&quot; and read as Kanenotorii.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanenotorii Gate (Important Cultural Property) - It is written &quot;銅鳥居&quot; and read as Kanenotorii.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>聖地への入口、俗界と聖地の境界を象徴する建造物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is an architecture that represents the entrance to sacred place and the boundary between the everyday world and the sacred place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is architecture that represents the entrance to a sacred place and the boundary between the everyday world and a sacred place.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is architecture that represents the entrance to a sacred place and the boundary between the everyday world and a sacred place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>吉野から大峯山（山上ヶ岳）までの修行道には発心門、修行門、等覚門、妙覚門という、悟りへの4つの段階を象徴した門が設定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are four gates-- Hosshinmon gate, shugyomon gate (gate of practice), Togakumon gate, and Myougakumon gate--that represent the four stages to attain enlightenment along the ascetic exercise path from yoshino to Mt. Omine (Mt. Sanjogatake).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are four gates-- Hosshinmon gate, shugyomon gate (gate of practice), Togakumon gate, and Myougakumon gate--that represent the four stages to attain enlightenment along the ascetic exercise path from yoshino to Mt. Omine (Mt. Sanjogatake).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are four gates-- Hosshinmon gate, shugyomon gate (gate of practice), Togakumon gate, and Myougakumon gate--that represent the four stages to attain enlightenment along the ascetic exercise path from yoshino to Mt. Omine (Mt. Sanjogatake).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>そのうちの「発心門」にあたるのがこの鳥居である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanenotorii Gate corresponds to &quot;Hosshinmon&quot; of these four gates.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanenotorii Gate corresponds to &quot;Hosshinmon&quot; of these four gates.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanenotorii Gate corresponds to &quot;Hosshinmon&quot; of these four gates.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>鳥居の柱が蓮台の上に立っているのは、神仏習合の名残りである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The poles of the Torii stand on the lotus pedestal, showing a remnant of syncretization of Shinto with Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The poles of the Torii stand on a lotus pedestal, showing a remnant of syncretization of Shinto with Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The poles of the Torii stand on a lotus pedestal, showing a remnant of syncretization of Shinto with Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>東大寺盧舎那仏像を鋳造した際の余りの銅で造ったという伝承があるが、現存するものは室町時代の再興である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been handed down that the poles were made of copper, remains left after casting of the statue of Birushana Buddha in Todai-ji Temple, but the existing poles were rebuilt during the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been handed down that the poles were made of copper, were left after casting of the statue of Birushana Buddha in Todai-ji Temple, but the existing poles were rebuilt during the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been handed down that the poles were made of copper, which were left after casting of the statue of Birushana Buddha in Todai-ji Temple, but the existing poles were rebuilt during the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>whichを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="69">
<j>仁王門（国宝）－本堂（蔵王堂）の北側に位置する入母屋造、本瓦葺きの二重門。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nio-mon Gate (Important Cultural Property) - located south of the main hall (Zao-do Hall), it is a Niju-mon (two-story gate) of irimoya style (building with a half-hipped roof) and hongawarabuki (a style of tile roofing in which round and square tiles are laid down alternately).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nio-mon Gate (Important Cultural Property) - located south of the main hall (Zao-do Hall), it is a Niju-mon (two-story gate) of irimoya style (building with a half-hipped roof) and hongawarabuki (a style of tile roofing in which round and square tiles are laid down alternately).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nio-mon Gate (Important Cultural Property) - located north of the main hall (Zao-do Hall), it is a Niju-mon (two-story gate) of irimoya style (building with a half-hipped roof) and hongawarabuki (a style of tile roofing in which round and square tiles are laid down alternately).</e>
<cmt>south→north</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>（二重門とは2階建て門で、1階と2階の境目にも屋根の出をつくるものを指す。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Niju-mon refers to a two-story gate, having a roof protrusion at the boundary between the first and second floors, too)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Niju-mon refers to a two-story gate, having a roof protrusion at the boundary between the first and second floors, too)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Niju-mon refers to a two-story gate, having a roof protrusion at the boundary between the first and second floors, too)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>軒先に吊るしていた風鐸（ふうたく）の銘から室町時代の康正2年（1456年）の再興とわかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The inscription of a bronze wind bell hanging down at the frontage of a house shows that it was rebuilt in 1456 of the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The inscription of a bronze wind bell hanging down at the frontage of a house shows that it was rebuilt in 1456 during the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The inscription of a bronze wind bell hanging down at the frontage of a house shows that it was rebuilt in 1456 during the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>本堂が南を正面とするのに対し、仁王門は北を正面とし、互いに背を向けるように建っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main hall faces south, while Nio-mon Gate faces north; they stand as if they turn their backs on each other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main hall faces south, while the Nio-mon Gate faces north; they stand as if they are turning their backs on each other.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main hall faces south, while the Nio-mon Gate faces north; they stand as if they are turning their backs on each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>これは、熊野から吉野へ（南から北へ）向かう巡礼者と吉野から熊野へ（北から南へ）向かう巡礼者の双方に配慮したためという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that they stand as such in consideration of both pilgrims who head for Yoshino from Kumano (south to north9 and those who head for Kumano from Yoshino (north to south).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that they stand as such in consideration of both pilgrims who head for Yoshino from Kumano (south to north and those who head for Kumano from Yoshino (north to south).</e>
<cmt>typo?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that they stand as such in consideration of both pilgrims who head for Yoshino from Kumano (south to north and those who head for Kumano from Yoshino (north to south).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="74">
<j>本堂（蔵王堂）（国宝）－山上ヶ岳の大峯山寺本堂（「山上の蔵王堂」）に対し、山下（さんげ）の蔵王堂と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main hall (Zao-do Hall) (Important Cultural Property) - It is called Zao-do of Sange as compared to the main hall of Ominesan-ji Temple of Mt. Sanjogatake (Zao-do of Sanjo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Main hall (Zao-do Hall) (Important Cultural Property) - It is called Zao-do of Sange as compared to the main hall of Ominesan-ji Temple of Mt. Sanjogatake (Zao-do of Sanjo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Main hall (Zao-do Hall) (Important Cultural Property) - It is called Zao-do of Sange as compared to the main hall of Ominesan-ji Temple of Mt. Sanjogatake (Zao-do of Sanjo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>屋根は入母屋造檜皮葺き。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has an Irimoya-styled roof (hip-and-gable roof).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has an Irimoya-styled roof (hip-and-gable roof).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has an Irimoya-styled roof (hip-and-gable roof).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>2階建てのように見えるが構造的には「一重裳階（もこし）付き」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It looks like a two-storied building, but its structure is &quot;furnished with a single pent roof below the true roof.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It looks like a two-storied building, but its structure is &quot;furnished with a single pent roof below the true roof.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It looks like a two-storied building, but its structure is &quot;furnished with a single pent roof below the true roof.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>豊臣家の寄進で再興されたもので、扉金具の銘から天正19年（1592年）の建立とわかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was rebuilt by the donations of the Toyotomi family, but the inscription of metal fittings of the door shows that it was rebuilt in 1592.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was rebuilt by the donations of the Toyotomi family, but the inscription of metal fittings on the door shows that it was rebuilt in 1592.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was rebuilt by the donations of the Toyotomi family, but the inscription of metal fittings on the door shows that it was rebuilt in 1592.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>高さ34メートル、奥行、幅ともに36メートル。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is 34 meter high and 36 meter wide and deep.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thirty-four meters high and thirty-six meters wide and deep.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thirty-four meters high and thirty-six meters wide and deep.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>木造の古建築としては東大寺大仏殿に次ぐ規模をもつといわれる豪壮な建築である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a magnificent architecture second largest in sale of old wooden architectures after the Daibutsu-den Hall (the Great Buddha hall) of Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The architecture is magnificent, second largest in scale of old wooden architectures after the Daibutsu-den Hall (the Great Buddha hall) of Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The architecture is magnificent, second largest in scale of old wooden architectures after the Daibutsu-den Hall (the Great Buddha hall) of Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>内部の柱には、原木の曲がりを残した自然木に近い柱が使われていることが特色である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is featured by its inner poles made of thick wood that remains its natural shape and bending.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is featured by its inner poles made of thick wood that retains its natural shape and bend.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is featured by its inner poles made of thick wood that retains its natural shape and bend.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>ツツジ、チャンチン、梨などと称される柱が用いられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Poles called Tsuzuji, Chan-chin, and Nashi are used.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Poles called Tsuzuji, Chan-chin, and Nashi are used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Poles called Tsuzuji, Chan-chin, and Nashi are used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>内陣には巨大な厨子があり、本尊として3体の巨大な蔵王権現像（秘仏）を安置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a large zushi (a cupboard-like case with double doors in which an image of (the) Buddha, a sutra, or some other revered object is kept at a temple) in the naijin (inner sanctuary of a shrine or temple) to enshrine three images of large Zaogongen-zo (Buddhist image normally withheld from public view).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a large zushi (a cupboard-like case with double doors in which an image of (the) Buddha, a sutra, or some other revered object is kept at a temple) in the naijin (inner sanctuary of a shrine or temple) to enshrine three images of large Zaogongen-zo (Buddhist image normally withheld from public view).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a large zushi (a cupboard-like case with double doors in which an image of (the) Buddha, a sutra, or some other revered object is kept at a temple) in the naijin (inner sanctuary of a shrine or temple) to enshrine three images of large Zaogongen-zo (Buddhist image normally withheld from public view).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="83">
<j>四本桜 - 本堂前の広場に石柵で囲まれた一廓があり、4本の桜が植わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Four Cherry Trees - Four cherry trees are planted in stone wall-surrounded area in an open space in front of the main hall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Four Cherry Trees - Four cherry trees are planted in the stone wall-surrounded area in an open space in front of the main hall.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Four Cherry Trees - Four cherry trees are planted in the stone wall-surrounded area in an open space in front of the main hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>ここは、元弘3年（1333年）、北条軍に攻められた大塔宮護良親王が落城前に最後の酒宴を催した故地とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is reported to have been the site where Imperial prince Daitonomiya Moriyoshi had the last a feast (a drinking party) before surrender of a castle in an attack by armed Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is reported to have been the site where Imperial prince Daitonomiya Moriyoshi had the last a feast (a drinking party) before surrendering the castle in an attack by the armed Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is reported to have been the site where Imperial prince Daitonomiya Moriyoshi had the last a feast (a drinking party) before surrendering the castle in an attack by the armed Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>石柵内に立つ銅燈籠は文明3年（1471年）の作で、重要文化財に指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The copper garden lantern that stands within the stone walls was made in 1471 and designated as an important cultural property.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The copper garden lantern that stands within the stone walls was made in 1471 and designated as an important cultural property.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The copper garden lantern that stands within the stone walls was made in 1471 and designated as an important cultural property.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="86">
<j>二天門跡 - 本堂（蔵王堂）の南正面には現在は門がないが、かつてはここに二天門があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nitenmon Gate Ruins - Once there used to be Nitenmon Gates south front of the mail hall (Zao-do Hall), although they no longer exist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nitenmon Gate Ruins - Once there used to be Nitenmon Gates south front of the mail hall (Zao-do Hall), although they no longer exist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nitenmon Gate Ruins - Once there used to be Nitenmon Gates south front of the main hall (Zao-do Hall), although they no longer exist.</e>
<cmt>mail→main</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>信濃出身の武士であった村上義光（よしてる）は、元弘3年（1333年）、護良親王の身代わりとしてこの二天門の楼上で自害したと伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiteru MURAKAMI, a warrior from Shinano province is reported to have killed himself in the upper story of Nitenmon Gate in substitute for Imperial Prince Moriyoshi in 1333.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiteru MURAKAMI, a warrior from Shinano province is reported to have killed himself in the upper story of Nitenmon Gate as a substitute for Imperial Prince Moriyoshi in 1333.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiteru MURAKAMI, a warrior from Shinano province is reported to have killed himself in the upper story of Nitenmon Gate as a substitute for Imperial Prince Moriyoshi in 1333.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>門跡には「村上義光公忠死之所」と記した石柱が立つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A stone pillar stands describing &quot;the place where Yositeru MURAKAMI died for loyalty.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A stone pillar stands describing &quot;the place where Yositeru MURAKAMI died out of loyalty.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A stone pillar stands describing &quot;the place where Yositeru MURAKAMI died out of loyalty.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cultural property</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cultural property</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cultural property</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>国宝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National treasure</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National treasure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National treasure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="89">
<j>本堂（蔵王堂）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main hall</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Main hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Main hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>仁王門</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nio-mon Gate</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nio-mon Gate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nio-mon Gate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>大和国金峯山経塚出土品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamato Kinposen Sancho excavated articles</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamato Kinposen Sancho excavated articles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamato Kinposen Kyozuka excavated articles</e>
<cmt>経塚を訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>金銀鍍双鳥宝相華文経箱 1合</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">one gold and silver plated Socho Hosogemon Kyobako box with a lid</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">one gold and silver plated Socho Hosogemon Kyobako box with a lid</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">one gold and silver plated Socho Hosogemon Kyobako box with a lid</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>金銅経箱 台付 2合</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">two sets of Kondo Kyobako Daitsuki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">two sets of Kondo Kyobako Daitsuki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">two sets of Kondo Kyobako Daitsuki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>附紺紙金字法華経残闕 7紙、紺紙金字観普賢経残闕 2紙、経軸 2本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsuketari(Attachments): 7 sheets of Konshi Kinji Hokekyo zanketsu (incomplete remains of sutra), two gold letters on dark blue paper Kanfugenkyo (Samantabhadra Contemplation Sutra), and 2 scrolls</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsuketari(Attachments): seven sheets of Konshi Kinji Hokekyo zanketsu (incomplete remains of sutra), two gold letters on dark blue paper Kanfugenkyo (Samantabhadra Contemplation Sutra), and two scrolls</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuketari(Attachments): seven sheets of Konshi Kinji Hokekyo zanketsu (incomplete remains of sutra), two gold letters on dark blue paper Kanfugenkyo (Samantabhadra Contemplation Sutra), and two scrolls</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>重要文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural property</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important cultural property</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important cultural property</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="95">
<j>銅鳥居</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanenotorii Gate</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanenotorii Gate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanenotorii Gate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>木造蔵王権現立像 3躯－本堂内陣の巨大な厨子に安置される秘仏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Three wooden standing statues of Zao-gongen Bodhisattva - Buddhist image normally withheld from public view enshrined in a large zushi in the inner sanctuary of main hall, main temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Three standing wooden statues of Zao-gongen Bodhisattva - Buddhist image normally withheld from public view enshrined in a large zushi in the inner sanctuary of the main hall, main temple</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Three standing wooden statues of Zao-gongen Bodhisattva - Buddhist image normally withheld from public view enshrined in a large zushi in the inner sanctuary of the main hall, main temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>本堂が再興された天正19年（1592年）頃の制作と思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed to have been made in 1592, when the main hall was rebuilt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed to have been made in 1592, when the main hall was rebuilt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed to have been made in 1592, when the main hall was rebuilt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>3躯のうち中尊は像高728センチ、両脇の像も6メートル近い巨像である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The chuson (the principal statue in a group of Buddhist statues) out of the three statues is 728 centimeters, and the statues on both sides are also large with a height close to 6 meters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The chuson (the principal statue in a group of Buddhist statues) out of the three statues is 728 centimeters, and the statues on both sides are also large with a height close to 6 meters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The chuson (the principal statue in a group of Buddhist statues) out of the three statues is 728 centimeters, and the statues on both sides are also large with a height close to 6 meters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>寺伝では中央の像が釈迦如来、向かって右の像が千手観音、左の像が弥勒菩薩を本地とし、それぞれ過去・現世・来世を象徴するという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The temple legend says that the statue in the center is the manifestation of Shaka Nyorai, the statue on the right is the honji (original ground or true nature) of Senju Kannon (Thousand Armed Avalokiteshwara), and the statue on the left is the honji of Miroko Bosatsu (Buddha of the Future, Bodhisattva of the Present), each of them representing the past, current, and future worlds.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The temple legend says that the statue in the center is the manifestation of Shaka Nyorai, the statue on the right is the honji (original ground or true nature) of Senju Kannon (Thousand Armed Avalokiteshwara), and the statue on the left is the honji of Miroko Bosatsu (Buddha of the Future, Bodhisattva of the Present), each of them representing the past, current, and future worlds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The temple legend says that the statue in the center is the manifestation of Shaka Nyorai, the statue on the right is the honji (original ground or true nature) of Senju Kannon (Thousand Armed Avalokiteshwara), and the statue on the left is the honji of Miroku Bosatsu (Buddha of the Future, Bodhisattva of the Present), each of them representing the past, current, and future worlds.</e>
<cmt>Miroko→Miroku</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>（「本地」は本来の姿である仏、「権現」は仏が姿を変えて現れたものの意）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(&quot;Honji&quot; refers to original form of Buddha, while Gongen refers to a form of Buddha that appears with the change of its figure.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(&quot;Honji&quot; refers to the original form of Buddha, while Gongen refers to a form of Buddha that appears with the change of its figure.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(&quot;Honji&quot; refers to the original form of Buddha, while Gongen refers to a form of Buddha that appears with the change of its figure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>通常は秘仏で拝観できず、開帳日も定められていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are normally withheld from public view, and their kaicho(unveiling a Buddhist image; gambling)have not be set.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are normally withheld from public view, and their kaicho(unveiling a Buddhist image; gambling)have not be set.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are normally withheld from public view, and their kaicho(unveiling a Buddhist image; gambling)have not be set.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>近年では、吉野・大峯の世界遺産登録を記念して、2004年7月から翌年6月まで開帳されたほか、2007年10月4日～8日にも開帳された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent years, they were unveiled from July 2004 through June 2005 and from October 4 to 8, 2007 to commemorate the registration of world heritage of Yoshino and Omine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent years, they have been unveiled from July 2004 through June 2005 and from October 4 to 8, 2007 to commemorate the registration of world heritage of Yoshino and Omine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent years, they have been unveiled from July 2004 through June 2005 and from October 4 to 8, 2007 to commemorate the registration of world heritage of Yoshino and Omine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="103">
<j>木造蔵王権現立像（安禅寺旧本尊）－秘仏本尊とは別に本堂外陣東北隅に安置される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wooden standing statue of Zao-gongen Bodhisattva (the former principle image of Anzen-ji temple) - It is enshrined in the southern corner of Gejin (outer place of worship for public people) of the main hall separately from the unveiled principal image statues.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The standing wooden statue of Zao-gongen Bodhisattva (the former principle image of Anzen-ji temple) - It is enshrined in the southern corner of Gejin (outer place of worship for public people) of the main hall separately from the unveiled principal image statues.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The standing wooden statue of Zao-gongen Bodhisattva (the former principle image of Anzen-ji temple) - It is enshrined in the southern corner of Gejin (outer place of worship for public people) of the main hall separately from the unveiled principal image statues.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>元は吉野山の奥の院と呼ばれた安禅寺（現・金峯神社付近にあった）の本尊で、同寺が明治の神仏分離で破却されてから金峯山寺に移された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was originally the principle image of Anzen-ji temple (once located near present-day Kinpu-jinja Shrine) once called Oku no in (inner sanctuary) of Mt. Yoshino, and was moved to Kinpusen-ji Temple when Anzen-ji temple was defunct with separation of Buddhism and Shintoism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was originally the principle image of Anzen-ji temple (once located near present-day Kinpu-jinja Shrine) once called Oku no in (inner sanctuary) of Mt. Yoshino, and was moved to Kinpusen-ji Temple when Anzen-ji temple was defunct with the separation of Buddhism and Shintoism.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was originally the principle image of Anzen-ji temple (once located near present-day Kinpu-jinja Shrine) once called Oku no in (inner sanctuary) of Mt. Yoshino, and was moved to Kinpusen-ji Temple when Anzen-ji temple was defunct with the separation of Buddhism and Shintoism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>像高459センチの巨像で、制作は秘仏本尊より古く、鎌倉時代後半とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A large statue with a height of 459 centimeters, it is believed to have been built in the late Kamakura period--earlier than the unveiled principle images,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A large statue with a height of 459 centimeters, it is believed to have been built during the late Kamakura period--earlier than the unveiled principle images,</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A large statue with a height of 459 centimeters, it is believed to have been built during the late Kamakura period--earlier than the unveiled principle images,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="106">
<j>絹本著色千手千眼観音像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Silk colored Juichimen Senju Sengen Kannon (Eleven-faced, thousand-armed and thousand-eyed kannon)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Silk colored Juichimen Senju Sengen Kannon (Eleven-faced, thousand-armed and thousand-eyed kannon)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Silk colored Senju Sengen Kannon (Thousand-armed and thousand-eyed kannon)</e>
<cmt>「十一面」の部分を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>板絵著色廻船入港図額 - 万治4年（1661年）に奉納された大型の絵馬。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Itaechakushoku Kaisennyukozugaku - a large Ema (a votive horse tablet) dedicated in 1661.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Itaechakushoku Kaisennyukozugaku - a large Ema (a votive horse tablet) dedicated in 1661.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Itaechakushoku Kaisennyukozugaku - a large Ema (a votive horse tablet) dedicated in 1661.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>本堂内西側に置かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is enshrined in the west side within the main hall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is enshrined in the west side within the main hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is enshrined in the west side within the main hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="109">
<j>木造聖徳太子立像 - 鎌倉時代。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">wooden standing statue of Prince Shotoku (Shotokutaishi) - Kamakukra Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Standing wooden statue of Prince Shotoku (Shotokutaishi) - Kamakukra Period</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Standing wooden statue of Prince Shotoku (Shotokutaishi) - Kamakukra Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>外陣東側に安置。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is enshrined in the eastern side of Gejin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is enshrined in the eastern side of Gejin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is enshrined in the eastern side of Gejin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="111">
<j>木造童子立像（伝普成、普建）2躯 - 鎌倉時代。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two Mokuzo Doji Ryuzo (wooden standing statues of boys, Fusei and Fuken) - Kamakukra Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two Mokuzo Doji Ryuzo (wooden standing statues of boys, Fusei and Fuken) - Kamakukra Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two Mokuzo Doji Ryuzo (wooden standing statues of boys, Fusei and Fuken) - Kamakukra Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>本尊厨子背後のガラスケース内に安置。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are enshrined in a glass case behind the zushi for the principle images.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are enshrined in a glass case behind the zushi for the principle images.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are enshrined in a glass case behind the zushi for the principal images.</e>
<cmt>principle →principal</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="113">
<j>金銅五鈷鈴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kondo Goko Rei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kondo Goko Rei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kondo Goko Rei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>金銅装笈（こんどうそう おい）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kondo Soai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kondo Soai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kondoso oi</e>
<cmt>読みに合うように書き換えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>銅燈籠 文明三年銘</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">copper garden lantern with an inscription of the year 1471</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">copper garden lantern with an inscription of the year 1471</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">copper garden lantern with an inscription of the year 1471</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>梵鐘－永暦元年（1160年）の銘がある大型の梵鐘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Temple bell - a large bell with an inscription of 1160.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Temple bell - a large bell with the inscription of 1160.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Temple bell - a large bell with the inscription of 1160.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>東大寺の鐘（「奈良太郎」）、高野山の鐘（「高野次郎」）と並び「吉野三郎」と称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This bell is nicknamed Yoshino Saburo (a nickname of a large hanging bell in Kinpusen-ji Temple) collectively with a bell of Todaiji temple (Nara Taro (a nickname of a large hanging bell in Todai-ji Temple)) and a bell of Mt. Koya (Koya Jiro (a nickname of a large hanging bell in Koyasan)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This bell is nicknamed Yoshino Saburo (a nickname of a large hanging bell in Kinpusen-ji Temple) collectively with a bell of Todaiji temple (Nara Taro - nickname of a large hanging bell in Todai-ji Temple) and a bell of Mt. Koya (Koya Jiro - nickname of a large hanging bell in Koyasan).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This bell is nicknamed Yoshino Saburo (a nickname of a large hanging bell in Kinpusen-ji Temple) collectively with a bell of Todaiji temple (Nara Taro - nickname of a large hanging bell in Todai-ji Temple) and a bell of Mt. Koya (Koya Jiro - nickname of a large hanging bell in Koyasan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>廃絶した世尊寺の鐘で、現在も世尊寺の旧地（蔵王堂から歩いて1時間ほどの吉野水分神社近く）にある鐘楼に所在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once a bell of defunct Seson-ji Temple, it is still in a bell tower of the remains of Seson-ji Temple (near Yoshino-mikumari-jinja Shrine, about an hour walk from Zao-do Hall).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once a bell of defunct Seson-ji Temple, it is still in a bell tower of the remains of Seson-ji Temple (near Yoshino-mikumari-jinja Shrine, about an hour walk from Zao-do Hall).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once a bell of defunct Seson-ji Temple, it is still in a bell tower of the remains of Seson-ji Temple (near Yoshino-mikumari-jinja Shrine, about an hour walk from Zao-do Hall).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="119">
<j>線刻蔵王権現鏡像－鋳銅製の八稜鏡の鏡面に線刻された蔵王権現像で、線刻鏡像の中でも優れた作品である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senkoku Zaogongen Kyozo - It is a Zaogongen Kyozo line-engraved in the mirror of hachiryokyo (eight-lobed bronze mirror) of copper, one of the best works of line-engraved image.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senkoku Zaogongen Kyozo - It is a Zaogongen Kyozo line-engraved in the mirror of hachiryokyo (eight-lobed bronze mirror) of copper, one of the best works of line-engraved image.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senkoku Zaogongen Kyozo - It is a Zaogongen Kyozo line-engraved in the mirror of hachiryokyo (eight-lobed bronze mirror) of copper, one of the best works of line-engraved image.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>年中行事</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Annual event</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Annual events</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Annual events</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="120">
<j>4月11～12日 花供懺法会（はなくせんぽうえ）（花供会式大名行列）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 11 and 12: Hanakusenboe (Hanakueshiki Daimyo-gyoretsu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 11 and 12: Hanakusenboe (Hanakueshiki Daimyo-gyoretsu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 11 and 12: Hanakusenboe (Hanakueshiki Daimyo-gyoretsu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>7月7日 蓮華会・蛙飛び行事</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 7: Rengee and Kaertobi-gyoji</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 7: Rengee and Kaertobi-gyoji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 7: Rengee and Kaerutobi-gyoji</e>
<cmt>Kaeｒtobi→Kaerutobi</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>交通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="122">
<j>吉野大峯ケーブル自動車吉野山駅から黒門、銅鳥居を経て蔵王堂まで徒歩10分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">10 minute walk from Yoshinoyama Station of Yoshino Ohmine ke-buru Ropeway bus Co.Ltd, to Zao-do Hall via Kuro-mon gate and Do-torii.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ten minute walk from Yoshinoyama Station of Yoshino Ohmine ke-buru Ropeway bus Co.Ltd, to Zao-do Hall via Kuro-mon gate and Do-torii.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ten minute walk from Yoshinoyama Station of Yoshino Ohmine ke-buru Ropeway bus Co.Ltd, to Zao-do Hall via Kuro-mon gate and Do-torii.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 浩(id:70121), 深志(id:34508), K66星雲(id:16609), Reggaeman(id:6214), 0null0(id:582), Law soma(id:45202), Jt noSke(id:32855), Urania(id:7213), D.h(id:79056), ネオン(id:59494), お掃除大好き(id:99320), 秋蛇庵(id:136037), KENPEI(id:11349), Ｈｉｒｏ２００６(id:59115), ＋－(id:17104), でここ(id:9565), Opponent(id:720), Kyoto-u(id:96969), Tawashi2006(id:95112), Ikedat76(id:34218), くっちゃめ(id:86793), Knua(id:66861), 663highland(id:18755), Point136(id:211299), Woles(id:116374), Ha～Ha(id:36403), Boardimage(id:138837), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>