<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>本善寺 (吉野町)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honzen-ji Temple (Yoshino-cho)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honzen-ji Temple (Yoshino-cho)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honzen-ji Temple (Yoshino-cho)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>本善寺（ほんぜんじ）は、奈良県吉野郡吉野町にある浄土真宗本願寺派の寺院。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honzen-ji Temple is a Buddhist temple of Jodo Shinshu Hongan-ji school located in Yoshino-cho, Yoshino-gun, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honzen-ji Temple is a Buddhist temple of Jodo Shinshu Hongan-ji school located in Yoshino-cho, Yoshino-gun, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honzen-ji Temple is a Buddhist temple of Jodo Shinshu Hongan-ji school located in Yoshino-cho, Yoshino-gun, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>別称飯貝御坊、山号は六雄山（むつおざん）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another name is Iigai gobo Temple, and Sango is Mutsuozan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sango (literally, &quot;mountain name&quot;), which is the title prefixed to the name of a Buddhist temple, is Mutsuozan, and it is also known as Iigai gobo temple.</e>
<cmt>山号の説明文を入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sango (literally, &quot;mountain name&quot;), which is the title prefixed to the name of a Buddhist temple, is Mutsuozan, and it is also known as Iigai gobo temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>1476年（文明 (日本)8年）、蓮如が飯貝の地に創建。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rennyo founded this temple in Iigai in 1476.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rennyo founded this temple in Iigai in 1476.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rennyo founded this temple in Iigai in 1476.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>1495年（明応4年）に蓮如の子兼継が入寺し開基となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">兼継,the son of Rennyo entered the temple and became the patron of it in 1495.</e>
<cmt>兼継の読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rennyo&apos;s son 兼継 entered the temple and became its patron in 1495.</e>
<cmt>順番を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rennyo&apos;s son 兼継 entered the temple and became its patron in 1495.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>しかし、従来吉野一帯は金峯山寺の支配下にあったためたびたび衝突を繰り返し、背後の六雄山に砦を構えて僧兵同士の小競り合いが絶えなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this temple frequently had conflicts because Yoshino region was traditionally under the control of Kinpusen-ji Temple, so a fortress was built in Mt.Mutsuo behind the temple due to constant skirmishes among warrior monks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this temple was home to frequent conflicts because the Yoshino region was originally under the control of Kinpusen-ji Temple, so a fortress was built on Mt. Mutsuo behind the temple due to constant skirmishes among warrior monks.</e>
<cmt>frequently had &gt; was home to frequent</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this temple was home to frequent conflicts because the Yoshino region was originally under the control of Kinpusen-ji Temple, so a fortress was built on Mt. Mutsuo behind the temple due to constant skirmishes among warrior monks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>その後、吉野地方の本願寺末86ヶ寺を束ねて隆盛を得たが、戦国時代に入り本願寺が織田信長と対立すると、本善寺も門徒を率いて石山本願寺攻めに応戦。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, the temple flourished to the extent of heading 86 Matsuin of Hongan-ji Temple in Yoshino region, and when Hongan-ji Temple clashed with Nobunaga Oda in the Sengoku period (period of warring states), Honzen-ji Temple also participated in the battle against the Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple, leading its followers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, the temple flourished to the extent of controlling 86 branch temples of Hongan-ji Temple in the Yoshino region, and when Hongan-ji Temple clashed with Nobunaga Oda in the Sengoku period (Period of the Warring States), Honzen-ji Temple also leading its followers into battle against the Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple,.</e>
<cmt>heading&gt;controlling. matsuin&gt;branch temples.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, the temple flourished to the extent of controlling 86 branch temples of Hongan-ji Temple in the Yoshino region, and when Hongan-ji Temple clashed with Nobunaga ODA in the Sengoku period (Period of the Warring States), Honzen-ji Temple also leading its followers into battle against the Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>「Nobunaga Oda 」を「Nobunaga ODA 」に修正しました。余分なスペース、コンマを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>信長は筒井順慶に本善寺破却の命を下し、1578年（天正6年）、筒井軍により堂宇の大半が破壊された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Nobunaga ordered Junkei TSUTSUI to destroy the Honzen-ji Temple, the most part of the temple building was destroyed by a troop led by TSUTSUI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga ordered Junkei TSUTSUI to destroy the Honzen-ji Temple, and the majority of the temple buildings were destroyed by a troop led by TSUTSUI in 1578.</e>
<cmt>most part &gt; majority. 1578を挿入。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga ordered Junkei TSUTSUI to destroy the Honzen-ji Temple, and the majority of the temple buildings were destroyed by a troop led by TSUTSUI in 1578.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>この時、下市の願行寺も共に灰塵に帰している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that moment, Gangyo-ji Temple located in Shimoichi was also burned down.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that moment, Gangyo-ji Temple in Shimoichi was also burned down.</e>
<cmt>locatedを省略しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that moment, Gangyo-ji Temple in Shimoichi was also burned down.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>江戸時代に入って寛文年間（1670年頃）に堂宇が復興され、連枝格の別格本山（中本山）として大和地方一帯の崇敬寺院となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The temple building was restored in the Edo period (around 1670), and the temple became 崇敬寺院 in Yamato region as the Bekkaku-Honzan (quasi-head temple) of Rengikaku.</e>
<cmt>崇敬寺院→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The temple building was restored in the Edo period (around 1670), and the temple became 崇敬寺院 in Yamato region as the Bekkaku-Honzan (quasi-head temple) of Rengikaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The temple building was restored in the Edo period (around 1670), and the temple became 崇敬寺院 in Yamato region as the Bekkaku-Honzan (quasi-head temple) of Rengikaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>現在、境内には本堂のほか、欅造の山門、太鼓楼、本堂裏に蓮如墓所がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, there are a sanmon gate (temple gate) made of Keyaki (zelkova), a Taikoro tower, as well as the main hall in the precincts, and the graveyard of Rennyo is located behind the main hall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present, the grounds house a sanmon gate (temple gate) made of Keyaki (zelkova), a Taikoro tower, as well as the main hall, behind which the Rennyo&apos;s grave is located.</e>
<cmt>there are&gt;the grounds house.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present, the grounds house a sanmon gate (temple gate) made of Keyaki (zelkova), a Taikoro tower, as well as the main hall, behind which the Rennyo&apos;s grave is located.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、蓮如以降の歴代法主の遺骨が納まる納骨堂がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, there is an ossuary in which the ashes of successive head priests after Rennyo have been inurned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, there is an ossuary in which the ashes of head priests succeeding Rennyo have been inurned.</e>
<cmt>successive&gt;succeeding</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, there is an ossuary in which the ashes of head priests succeeding Rennyo have been inurned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MKT(id:6704), Carkuni(id:79281), どんどん(id:172259), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>