<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>境内</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keidai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keidai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keidai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>境内(けいだい)は、神社や寺院のある敷地のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;keidai&quot; refers to the grounds of a Shinto shrine or Buddhist Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;keidai&quot; refers to the grounds of a Shinto shrine or Buddhist Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term keidai refers to the grounds of a Shinto shrine or Buddhist temple.</e>
<cmt>原文に『』のない&quot;を削除（周出でないため）Temple→temple</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>厳密な規定は宗教法人法に書かれており、法律上は境内地とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The regulations concerning keidai are specified within Article 3 of Japan&apos;s Religious Corporation Law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regulations concerning keidai are specified within Article 3 of Japan&apos;s Religious Corporation Law.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regulations concerning keidai are specified within Japan&apos;s Religious Corporation Law and it is legally referred to as keidaichi (keidai precinct).</e>
<cmt>Article 3 of 削除「it is legally referred to as keidaichi (keidai precinct)」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>法律上の境内</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Legal Definition of &quot;Keidai&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Legal Definition of &quot;Keidai&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Legal Definition of Keidai</e>
<cmt>原文に『』のない&quot;を削除（周出でないため）</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>境内地の規定が書かれている宗教法人法 第三条を以下に記載する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The regulations concerning keidai are specified within Article 3 of Japan&apos;s Religious Corporation Law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regulations concerning keidai are specified within Article 3 of Japan&apos;s Religious Corporation Law.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regulations concerning keidaichi are specified within Article 3 of Japan&apos;s Religious Corporation Law.</e>
<cmt>keidai→keidaichi</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>第三条 　この法律において「境内建物」とは、第1号に掲げるような宗教法人の前条に規定する目的のために必要な当該宗教法人に固有の建物及び工作物をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Article 3:This law defines &quot;keidai kenbutsu&quot; as fixed buildings and structures belonging to a religious corporation as described in Number 1 that are necessary for said religious corporation to conduct activities as stipulated in the previous article.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Article 3:This law defines &quot;keidai kenbutsu&quot; as fixed buildings and structures belonging to a religious corporation as described in Number 1 that are necessary for said religious corporation to conduct activities as stipulated in the previous article.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Article 3:This law defines &apos;keidai kenbutsu&apos; as fixed buildings and structures belonging to a religious corporation as described in item 1 that are necessary for said religious corporation to conduct activities as stipulated in the previous article.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にNumber→item</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>「境内地」とは、第2号から第7号までに掲げるような宗教法人の同条に規定する目的のために必要な当該宗教法人に固有の土地をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Keidaichi&quot; is defined as the fixed land that is necessary for a religious corporation as described from Number 2 to Number 7 to conduct activities stipulated in those same articles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Keidaichi&quot; is defined as the fixed land that is necessary for a religious corporation, as described from Number 2 to Number 7, to conduct activities stipulated in those same articles.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keidaichi&apos; is defined as the fixed land that is necessary for a religious corporation, as described from item 2 to item 7, to conduct activities stipulated in those same articles.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にNumber→item</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>本殿、拝殿、本堂、会堂、僧堂、僧院、信者修行所、社務所、庫裏、教職舎、宗務庁、教務院、教団事務所その他宗教法人の前条に規定する目的のために供される建物及び工作物（附属の建物及び工作物を含む）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honden, haiden, hondo, sodo, soin, shinsha shugyosho, shadenjo, kuri, kyoshokusha, shumucho, kyomuin, kyodanjimusho and other buildings and structures (including attached structures) provided to allow a religious corporation to conduct activities as described in the previous article</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honden, haiden, hondo, sodo, soin, shinsha shugyosho, shadenjo, kuri, kyoshokusha, shumucho, kyomuin, kyodanjimusho,and other buildings and structures (including attached structures) provided to allow a religious corporation to conduct activities as described in the previous article</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honden (Shinto main sanctuaries), haiden (Shinto worship halls), hondo (Buddhist main halls), kaido (meeting halls), sodo (Buddhist meditation halls), soin (monasteries), shinsha shugyosho (ascetic practice areas), shamusho (Shinto shrine offices, kuri (Buddhist monks&apos; living quarters), kyoshokusha (teaching halls), shumucho (Buddhist sect offices), kyomuin (religious affairs offices), kyodanjimusho (religious organization offices), and other buildings and structures (including attached buildings and structures) provided to allow a religious corporation to conduct activities as described in the previous article</e>
<cmt>kaido補足shugyosho→shamushobuildings and補足本殿、拝殿、本堂、会堂、僧堂、僧院、信者修行所、社務所、庫裏、教職舎、宗務庁、教務院、教団事務所について、英語の説明を入れました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>前号に掲げる建物又は工作物が存する一画の土地（立木竹その他建物及び工作物以外の定着物を含む。以下この条において同じ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The plot of land (including scaffolding and other fixtures other than buildings and structures. This applies to the following articles) on which the buildings or structures stipulated in the previous number stand</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A plot of land (including scaffolding and other fixtures other than buildings and structures. This applies to the following articles) on which the buildings or structures stipulated in the previous number stand</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A plot of land in which buildings or structures stipulated in the previous items stand (including fixtures other than buildings and structures, such as trees and bamboo. This applies to the following articles).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>参道として用いられる土地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Land used as paths</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Land used as paths</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Land used as paths</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>宗教上の儀式行事を行うために用いられる土地（神せん田、仏供田、修道耕牧地等を含む。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Land (including agricultural land offered to Shinto deities, agricultural land offered to Buddhist deities, monastic pasture, etc.) used for the purpose of holding religious events</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Land (including agricultural land offered to Shinto deities, agricultural land offered to Buddhist deities, monastic pasture, etc.) used for the purpose of holding religious events</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Land (including agricultural land offered to Shinto deities, agricultural land offered to Buddhist deities, monastic pasture, etc.) used for the purpose of holding religious events</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>庭園、山林その他尊厳又は風致を保持するために用いられる土地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gardens, mountain forests and other areas of land that serve the purpose of maintaining sanctity and aesthetic appearance</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gardens, mountain forests, and other areas of land that serve the purpose of maintaining sanctity and aesthetic appearance</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gardens, mountain forests, and other areas of land that serve the purpose of maintaining sanctity and aesthetic appearance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>歴史、古記等によって密接な縁故がある土地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Land that has a close connection as determined by history, ancient records, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Land that has a close connection as determined by history, ancient records, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Land that has a close connection as determined by history, ancient records, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>前各号に掲げる建物、工作物又は土地の災害を防止するために用いられる土地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Land used to protect from damage the buildings, structures and land stipulated in all previous numbers</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Land used to protect from damage the buildings, structures and land stipulated in all previous numbers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Land used to protect from damage the buildings, structures and land stipulated in all previous items</e>
<cmt>numbers→items</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Pieria(id:48925), R28Bot(id:177951), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>