<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>斑鳩神社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikaruga-jinjya Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ikaruga-jinjya Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikaruga-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>数字修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>斑鳩神社（いかるがじんじゃ）は奈良県生駒郡の神社。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikaruga-jinjya is a Shinto shrine in Ikoma-gun, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ikaruga-jinja Shrine is a Shinto shrine in Ikoma-gun, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>jinjya &gt; jinja Shrine</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikaruga-jinja Shrine is a Shinto shrine in Ikoma-gun, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>法隆寺の北東の天満山に位置し、菅原道真を祀る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is located in Mt. Tenma in the north east of Horyu-ji Temple and enshrines SUGAWARA no Michizane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is located on Mt. Tenma to the north east of Horyu-ji Temple and enshrines SUGAWARA no Michizane.</e>
<cmt>in &gt; onin &gt; to</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is located on Mt. Tenma to the north east of Horyu-ji Temple and enshrines SUGAWARA no Michizane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>法隆寺鎮守神4社の1つで寺の鬼門の守護神とされ、現在も関係が深い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shrine was one of the four chinju-sha shrine (Shinto shrine on Buddhist temple grounds dedicated to the tutelary deity of the area) of Horyu-ji Temple and regarded as a guardian god which protected against Kimon (the northeastern (unlucky) direction, person or thing to be avoided) for the temple, and even today, it has close ties to Horyu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shrine was one of the four chinju-sha shrines (Shinto shrine on Buddhist temple grounds dedicated to the tutelary deity of the area) of Horyu-ji Temple and regarded as a guardian god which protected against Kimon (the northeastern (unlucky) direction, person or thing to be avoided) for the temple, and even today, it has close ties to Horyu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>shrine &gt; shrines</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shrine was one of the four chinju-sha shrines (Shinto shrine on Buddhist temple grounds dedicated to the tutelary deity of the area) of Horyu-ji Temple and regarded as a guardian god which protected against Kimon (the northeastern (unlucky) direction, person or thing to be avoided) for the temple, and even today, it has close ties to Horyu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>天慶年間に法隆寺の管主で菅原氏の湛照が創祀し、元亨4年（1324年）に僧・慶祐が社殿を造営したとの記録がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a written record that during Tengyo era (938-947), Tansho, the chief priest of Horyu-ji Temple and member of SUGAWARA clan, first enshrined SUGAWARA no Michizane, then, a priest named Keiyu constructed the main building of the shirne in 1324.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a written record that during the Tengyo era (938-947), Tansho, the chief priest of Horyu-ji Temple and member of SUGAWARA clan, first enshrined SUGAWARA no Michizane before a priest named Keiyu constructed the main building of the shrine in 1324.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;Fixed double spaces, then, &gt; before</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a written record that during the Tengyo era (938-947), Tansho, the chief priest of Horyu-ji Temple and member of Sugawara clan, first enshrined SUGAWARA no Michizane before a priest named Keiyu constructed the main building of the shrine in 1324.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>当初は天満山の西麓に位置し境内に如法経堂という堂があったが、寛文年間に火災で全焼した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, the shrine was located in the west foot of Mt. Tenma and had a hall called Nyoho Kyodo (the Sutra Hall) in the precincts, but it was burned down during Kanbun era (1661-1672).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shrine was originally located at the western base of Mt. Tenma and had a hall called Nyoho Kyodo (the Sutra Hall) in its precinct, but it was burned down during Kanbun era (1661-1672).</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shrine was originally located at the western base of Mt. Tenma and had a hall called Nyoho Kyodo (the Sutra Hall) in its precinct, but it was burned down during Kanbun era (1661-1672).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>寛文8年（1668年）に神殿が再建された後、水害のため享保10年（1725年）に現在と同じ山上に移ったと伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that after the reconstruction of the shirine building in 1668, it was moved to the top of the same mountain as it is today due to a flood disaster.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that after the reconstruction of the shrine building in 1668, it was moved to the top of the same mountain where it stands today due to a flood disaster.</e>
<cmt>as it is &gt; where it stands</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that after the reconstruction of the shrine building in 1668, it was moved to the top of the same mountain in 1725 where it stands today due to a flood disaster.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>1869年（明治2年）には、法隆寺境内にあった総社明神、五所明神、白山権現が遷祀された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1869, Sosha Myojin God, Gosho Myojin God, and Hakusan Gongen deity, which used to be in the precincts of Horyu-ji Temple, were transferred to the shirine to be re-enshrined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1869, Sosha Myojin, Gosho Myojin and Hakusan Gongen, which were enshrined in the precinct of Horyu-ji Temple, were transferred to the shrine to be re-enshrined.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluencyFixed double spaces</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1869, Sosha Myojin, Gosho Myojin and Hakusan Gongen, which were enshrined in the precinct of Horyu-ji Temple, were transferred to the shrine to be re-enshrined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>境内の社殿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shrine buildings in the precincts</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shrine Buildings in the Precinct</e>
<cmt>Title caseprecincts &gt; Precinct</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shrine buildings in the precinct</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>総社明神：かつては法隆寺の北西にあり、仁平3年（1153年）に社殿を建立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sosha Myojin God used to be in the north west of Horyu-ji Temple, the building of which was constructed in 1153.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sosha Myojin used to be enshrined to the northwest of Horyu-ji Temple, the building of which was constructed in 1153.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluencyFixed double spaces</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sosha Myojin used to be enshrined to the northwest of Horyu-ji Temple, the building of which was constructed in 1153.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>五所明神：建保6年（1218年）の創祀とされる法隆寺東院の総鎮守で、住吉神・春日神4座を祀る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gosho Myojin Gods are the Grand Gardian Gods of Toin (East Precinct) of Horyu-ji Temple which are said to have been first enshirined in 1218, and the Gods enshrined there are Sumiyoshi God and 4 Kasuga Gods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gosho Myojin are the Grand Guardian Gods of Toin (East Precinct) of Horyu-ji Temple which are said to have been first enshrined in 1218, and the Gods enshrined there are Sumiyoshi God and four Kasuga Gods.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluencyFixed double spaces</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gosho Myojin are the Grand Guardian Gods of Toin (East Precinct) of Horyu-ji Temple which are said to have been first enshrined in 1218, and the Gods enshrined there are Sumiyoshi God and four Kasuga Gods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>『延喜式神名帳』にある平群郡の平群神社五座に比定する説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also a theory that Gosho Myojin Gods were identified as five Gods of Heguri-jinjya Shrine located in Heguri-gun in &quot;Engishiki jimmyocho (a register of shrines in Japan)&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also a theory that Gosho Myojin were identified as five Gods of Heguri-jinjya Shrine located in Heguri-gun in &quot;Engishiki jimmyocho (a register of shrines in Japan)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also a theory that Gosho Myojin were identified as five Gods of Heguri-jinja Shrine located in Heguri-gun in &quot;Engishiki jinmyocho&quot; (a register of shrines in Japan).</e>
<cmt>&quot;位置移動しました。スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other</e>
<cmt>Others &gt; Other</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>奈良県山添村室津の観音堂の鰐口は元は斑鳩神社のもので、永享9年（1437年）の銘がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Waniguchi (a metal gong hanging at the front of hall in a temple) in Kanno-do hall located in Murotsu, Yamazoe-mura, Nara Prefecture originally belonged to Ikaruga-jinjya Shrine, and it has an inscription of the year 1437.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The waniguchi (a metal gong hanging at the front of hall in a temple) in Kanno-do hall located in Murotsu, Yamazoe-mura, Nara Prefecture originally belonged to Ikaruga-jinjya Shrine, and it has an inscription of the year 1437.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;The&quot;Fixed double spaces</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The waniguchi (a metal gong hanging at the front of hall in a temple) in Kanno-do hall located in Murotsu, Yamazoe-mura, Nara Prefecture originally belonged to Ikaruga-jinja Shrine, and it has an inscription of the year 1437.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), Okapia2(id:98589), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>