<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>瑞泉寺 (京都市)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zuisen-ji Temple (Kyoto City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zuisen-ji Temple (Kyoto City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zuisen-ji Temple (Kyoto City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>瑞泉寺（ずいせんじ）は 京都府京都市中京区木屋町三条下る石屋町にある寺院である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zuisen-ji Temple is a Buddhist temple loccated in Ishiya-cho, Kiyamachi Sanjo-Sagaru, Nakagyo-ku Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zuisen-ji Temple is a Buddhist temple loccated in Ishiya-cho, Kiyamachi Sanjo-Sagaru, Nakagyo-ku Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zuisen-ji Temple is a Buddhist temple located in Ishiya-cho, Kiyamachi Sanjo-Sagaru, Nakagyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>-ku削除スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>山号は慈舟山。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its honorific mountain prefix is Jishuzan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its honorific mountain prefix is Jishuzan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its honorific mountain prefix is Jishuzan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>桃山時代ここは三条河原の中洲であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until the Momoyama period, the area was a sandbank of the Sanjo-gawa River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until the Momoyama period, the area was a sandbank on the Sanjo-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until the Momoyama period, the area was a sandbank on the Sanjo-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>高瀬川 (京都府)の工事中に偶然発見された石に秀次悪逆塚と刻まれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A rock discovered by chance during work on the Takase-gawa River (Kyoto Prefetcure) had engraved on it the words Hidetsugu Akugyakuzuka (Hidetsugu Brutality Mound).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A rock discovered by chance during work on the Takase-gawa River (Kyoto Prefetcure) had engraved on it the words Hidetsugu Akugyakuzuka (Hidetsugu Brutality Mound).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A rock discovered by chance during work on the Takase-gawa River (Kyoto Prefecture) had engraved on it the words Hidetsugu Akugyakuzuka (Hidetsugu Brutality Mound).</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>それは文禄4年（1595年）自害させられた、豊臣秀次の石塔だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was the stone monument of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI who was ordered to commit suicide in 1595.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the stone monument of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI who was ordered to commit suicide in 1595.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the stone monument of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI who was ordered to commit suicide in 1595.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>実は高瀬川の開削責任者だった京都の豪商、角倉了以の実弟吉田宗恂は、秀次に仕えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sojun YOSHIDA, the younger brother of the wealthy merchant Ryoi SUMINOKURA of Kyoto who was responsible for digging Takase-gawa River, was in the service of Hidetsugu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sojun YOSHIDA, the younger brother of the wealthy merchant Ryoi SUMINOKURA of Kyoto who was responsible for digging Takase-gawa River, was in the service of Hidetsugu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sojun YOSHIDA, the younger brother of the wealthy merchant Ryoi SUMINOKURA of Kyoto who was responsible for digging Takase-gawa River, was in the service of Hidetsugu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>秀次事件への連座は免れたが、慶長15年（1610年）に亡くなっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He avoided being implicated in the Hidetsugu Incident but passed away in 1610.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He avoided being implicated in the Hidetsugu Incident, but passed away in 1610.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He avoided being implicated in the Hidetsugu Incident, but passed away in 1610.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>宗恂の一周忌の慶長16年（1611年）に、了以は秀次の菩提を弔うために、秀次の戒名「瑞泉寺殿」から名を取り、瑞泉寺を建立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1611 on the first anniversary of Sojun&apos;s death, Ryoi constructed Zuisen-ji Temple in order to pray for the soul of Hidetsugu and named it after Hidetsugu&apos;s posthumous Buddhist name &quot;Zuisen Jiden&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1611 on the first anniversary of Sojun&apos;s death, Ryoi constructed Zuisen-ji Temple in order to pray for the soul of Hidetsugu and named it after Hidetsugu&apos;s posthumous Buddhist name &quot;Zuisen Jiden&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1611 on the first anniversary of Sojun&apos;s death, Ryoi constructed Zuisen-ji Temple in order to pray for the soul of Hidetsugu and named it after Hidetsugu&apos;s posthumous Buddhist name &apos;Zuisen Jiden.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>瑞泉寺は建立以来400年間にわたり、冤罪により死罪となった豊臣秀次と一族・家臣の菩提を供養してきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For 400 years since its founding, memorial services in memory of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI whose death resulted from false criminal accusations, as well as his family and retainers have been held at Zuisen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For 400 years since its founding, memorial services in memory of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI whose death resulted from false criminal accusations, as well as his family and retainers have been held at Zuisen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For 400 years since its founding, memorial services in memory of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI whose death resulted from false criminal accusations, as well as his family and retainers have been held at Zuisen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>この地は観光地の近くとあって、当寺院に来訪する人が多く、秀次と一族・家臣の菩提に向かって、手を合わせる人が絶えることがない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As this area is near to a sightseeing spot, the temple receives many visitors and there is no end of people to pray for the souls of Hidetsugu, his family and retainers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As this area is near a sightseeing spot, the temple receives many visitors and there is no end of people that pray for the souls of Hidetsugu, his family, and retainers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As this area is near a sightseeing spot, the temple receives many visitors and there are many people who pray for the souls of Hidetsugu, his family, and retainers.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>秀次悪逆塚</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidetsugu Brutality Mound</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidetsugu Brutality Mound</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidetsugu Brutality Mound</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>秀次悪逆塚は、豊臣秀次とその妻妾子女30人余の遺骸が埋められた、京都三条河原にあった塚で、秀次の悪称とされた「殺生関白」から畜生塚ともいわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Within the Hidetsugu Akugyakuzuka (Hidetsugu Brutality Mound) are buried the remains of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI alongside over 30 others including his wife, concubines and children.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Within the Hidetsugu Akugyakuzuka (Hidetsugu Brutality Mound) are buried the remains of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI alongside over 30 others including his wife, concubines and children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidetsugu Akugyakuzuka (Hidetsugu Brutality Mound) was a burial mound containing the remains of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI alongside over 30 others including his wife, concubines and children, and was also known as &quot;Chikushozuka&quot; (Mound of Beasts) after Hidetsugu&apos;s nickname &quot;Sessho Kanpaku&quot; (lit. Murderous Kanpaku, the kanpaku was the chief advisor to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>「京都三条河原にあった塚で、秀次の悪称とされた「殺生関白」から畜生塚ともいわれた。」を訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>文禄4年7月、秀次は罪を得て関白の職を剥がれて高野山に放たれ、7月15日、切腹を命じられ、山本主殿、山田三十郎、不破伴作など5人もまた自殺し、秀次の首は伏見で秀吉の首実検に供され、三条河原で梟首（キュウシュ。さらし首）された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the 7th month of 1595, Hidetsugu was convicted of a crime, stripped of his position of Kanpaku (regent to the Emperor), and ordered to commit seppuku at Mt. Koya, which was followed by the suicide of five others including Tonomo YAMAMOTO, Sanjuro YAMADA and Bansaku FUWA, and the presentation of Hidetsugu&apos;s head to Hideyoshi for inspection in Fushimi before it was put on public display at beside Sanjo-gawa River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the 7th month of 1595, Hidetsugu was convicted of a crime, stripped of his position of Kanpaku (regent to the Emperor), and ordered to commit seppuku at Mt. Koya, which was followed by the suicide of five others including Tonomo YAMAMOTO, Sanjuro YAMADA and Bansaku FUWA, and the presentation of Hidetsugu&apos;s head to Hideyoshi for inspection in Fushimi before it was put on public display beside the Sanjo-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the 7th month of 1595, Hidetsugu was convicted of a crime, stripped of his position of Kanpaku (regent to the Emperor), and ordered to commit seppuku at Mt. Koya on the 15th day of the 7th month, which was followed by the suicide of five others including Tonomo YAMAMOTO, Sanjuro YAMADA and Bansaku FUWA, and the presentation of Hidetsugu&apos;s head to Hideyoshi for inspection in Fushimi before it was put on public display beside the Sanjo-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>on the 15th day of the 7th month補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>秀次の妻妾は多く、幼児などを合わせて30余人、捕らえられ、8月2日、三条河原で打首、秀次の首とともに河原に埋められ、塚が建てられ、石塔が置かれ、「秀次悪逆塚文禄四年七月十四日」と刻されたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Including Hidetsugu&apos;s many concubines and children, over 30 people were captured and beheaded beside Sanjo-gawa River on the 2nd day of the 8th month where they were buried with the head of Hidetsugu in a mound upon which was placed a stone monument into which &quot;Hidetsugu Brutality Mound, 14th day of the 7th month 1595&quot; was engraved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Including Hidetsugu&apos;s many concubines and children, over 30 people were captured and beheaded beside Sanjo-gawa River on the 2nd day of the 8th month where they were buried with the head of Hidetsugu in a mound upon which was placed a stone monument into which &quot;Hidetsugu Brutality Mound, 14th day of the 7th month 1595&quot; was engraved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Including Hidetsugu&apos;s many concubines and children, over 30 people were captured and beheaded beside Sanjo-gawa River on the 2nd day of the 8th month where they were buried with the head of Hidetsugu in a mound upon which was placed a stone monument into which &apos;Hidetsugu Brutality Mound, 14th day of the 7th month 1595&apos; was engraved.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>「畜生塚」と称され、かえりみる者は無かったが、順慶という行者はそのかたわらに草庵を結び、菩提を弔った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Known as &quot;Chikushozuka&quot; (Mound of Beasts), it was overlooked by all except an ascetic named Junkei who built a thatched hut beside the mound and prayed for the souls buried within.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Known as &quot;Chikushozuka&quot; (Mound of Beasts), it was overlooked by all except an ascetic named Junkei who built a thatched hut beside the mound and prayed for the souls buried within.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Known as &apos;Chikushozuka&apos; (Mound of Beasts), it was overlooked by all except an ascetic named Junkei who built a thatched hut beside the mound and prayed for the souls buried within.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>順慶の死後、洪水に塚が荒れ、慶長16年、角倉了以が高瀬川を開くとき、そのあとを哀れみ、塚を営み、石塔の「悪逆」の2文字を削り、その上に6角形の無縁塔を建て、江戸幕府に請い求めて堂を営み、「慈周山瑞泉寺」と号した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following Junkei&apos;s death, the mound was destroyed by flooding but in 1611 when Ryoi SUMINOKURA opened Takase-gawa River, he took pity on the remains, built a mound, removed the word &quot;brutality&quot; from the stone monument, constructed a hexagonal pagoda and pleaded with the Edo Shogunate to allow him to build a temple which was named Jishuzan Zuisen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following Junkei&apos;s death, the mound was destroyed by flooding, but in 1611 when Ryoi SUMINOKURA opened Takase-gawa River, he took pity on the remains, built a mound, removed the word &quot;brutality&quot; from the stone monument, constructed a hexagonal pagoda and pleaded with the Edo Shogunate to allow him to build a temple which was named Jishuzan Zuisen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following Junkei&apos;s death, the mound was destroyed by flooding, but in 1611 when Ryoi SUMINOKURA opened Takase-gawa River, he took pity on the remains, built a mound, removed the word &apos;brutality&apos; from the stone monument, constructed a hexagonal pagoda and pleaded with the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) to allow him to build a temple which was named Jishuzan Zuisen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にEdo Shogunate→Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>墓所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Graveyard</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Graveyard</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Graveyard</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>豊臣秀次　墓石（秀次の首が入れられた石の櫃）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI gravestone (a stone chest containing Hidetsugu&apos;s head)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI gravestone (a stone chest containing Hidetsugu&apos;s head)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI gravestone (a stone chest containing Hidetsugu&apos;s head)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>秀次の幼児、妻妾たち39人の五輪の塔</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Five-ring pagoda for 39 of Hidetsugu&apos;s children and concubines;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Five-ring pagoda for 39 of Hidetsugu&apos;s children and concubines;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Five-ring pagoda for 39 of Hidetsugu&apos;s children and concubines;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>賜死した家臣10人の五輪の塔</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Five-ring pagoda for 10 retainers who were ordered to commit suicide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Five-ring pagoda for 10 retainers who were ordered to commit suicide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Five-ring pagoda for 10 retainers who were ordered to commit suicide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>寺宝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Temple Treasures</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Temple Treasures</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Temple treasures</e>
<cmt>文頭以外の語頭を小文字に</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>処刑者の辞世の和歌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Waka poems written before the deaths of the executed</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Waka poems written before the deaths of the executed</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Waka poems written before the deaths of the executed</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>補足</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additional</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additional</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additional</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>豊臣秀次と母とも（智：日秀）の墓所は、善正寺 (京都市)にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The grave of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI&apos;s body and his mother (Tomo; Nisshu) is at Zensho-ji Temple (Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The grave of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI&apos;s body and his mother (Tomo; Nisshu) is at Zensho-ji Temple (Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The grave of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI&apos;s body and his mother (Tomo; Nisshu) is at Zensho-ji Temple (Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="21">
<j>毎年命日の7月15日に、善正寺と瑞龍寺 (近江八幡市)の住職により、滋賀県近江八幡市にある、八幡山（秀次の時代八幡山城があった）で、秀次の供養が行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A memorial service is held every year on the anniversary of Hidetsugu&apos;s death by the head priests of Zensho-ji Temple and Zuiryu-ji Temple (Omihachiman City) at Mt. Hachiman (where Hachimanyama Castle stood during the time of Hidetsugu) in Omihachiman, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A memorial service is held every year on the anniversary of Hidetsugu&apos;s death by the head priests of Zensho-ji Temple and Zuiryu-ji Temple (Omihachiman City) at Mt. Hachiman (where Hachimanyama Castle stood during the time of Hidetsugu) in Omihachiman, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A memorial service is held every year on July 15, the anniversary of Hidetsugu&apos;s death, by the head priests of Zensho-ji Temple and Zuiryu-ji Temple (Omihachiman City) at Mt. Hachiman (where Hachimanyama Castle stood during the time of Hidetsugu) in Omihachiman, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>July 15補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Rusk(id:9895), Andee(id:20421), Raisezu(id:206822), MCHC(id:208548), Dvorak2008(id:254100), Reggaeman(id:6214), 猫者(id:206449), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>