<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>春日大社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kasuga-Taisha Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kasuga-Taisha Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kasuga-Taisha Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>祭神武甕槌命経津主命天児屋根命比売神</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enshrined deities:Takemikazuchino mikoto, Futsunushino kami (Futsunushino mikoto), Amenokoyane no mikoto, and Hime no kami</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enshrined deities: Takemikazuchi-no-mikoto, Futsunushi-no-kami (Futsunushi-no-mikoto), Amenokoyane-no-mikoto, and Hime-no-kami</e>
<cmt>Space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enshrined deities: Takemikazuchi-no-mikoto, Futsunushi-no-kami (Futsunushi-no-mikoto), Amenokoyane-no-mikoto, and Hime-no-kami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>社格式内社（名神大）・二十二社・官幣大社・勅祭社・別表神社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classification: Shikinaisha (Myojin Taisha), Shinto shrines listed in the Engishiki, one of Nijuni-sha Shrines (the 22 most important Shinto shrines designated during the Heian period), Kanpei-taisha (large-scale state shrine), Chokusai-sha (shrine attended by imperial envoy), and Beppyo jinja (Shrines on the Special List)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classification: Shikinaisha (Myojin Taisha), Shinto shrines listed in the Engishiki; one of Nijuni-sha Shrines, the 22 most important Shinto shrines designated during the Heian period; Kanpei-taisha, large-scale state shrine; Chokusai-sha, shrine attended by imperial envoy; and Beppyo jinja, Shrines on the Special List</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classification: Shikinaisha (Myojin Taisha), Shinto shrines listed in the Engishiki; one of Nijuni-sha Shrines, the 22 most important Shinto shrines designated during the Heian period; Kanpei-taisha, large-scale state shrine; Chokusai-sha, shrine attended by imperial envoy; and Beppyo jinja, Shrines on the Special List</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>創建神護景雲2年（768年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Foundation: in 768</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Founded: 768</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Founded: 768</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>例祭3月13日（春日祭）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reisai (regular festival): March 13 (Kasuga-matsuri Festival)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reisai (regular festival): March 13 (Kasuga-matsuri Festival)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reisai (regular festival): March 13 (Kasuga-matsuri Festival)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>春日大社（かすがたいしゃ）は、奈良県奈良市の奈良公園内にある神社である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kasuga-Taisha Shrine is located in Nara Park, Nara City, Nara prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kasuga-Taisha Shrine is located in Nara Park, Nara City, Nara prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kasuga-Taisha Shrine is located in Nara Park, Nara City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>旧称春日神社。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its former name is Kasuga-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its former name is Kasuga-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its former name is Kasuga-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>式内社（名神大社）、二十二社の一社で、旧社格は官幣大社。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is classified as Shikinaisha (Myojin Taisha) listed in the Engishiki and one of Nijuni-sha Shrines (the 22 most important Shinto shrines designated during the Heian period), and its former shrine classification is Kanpei-taisha (large-scale state shrine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is classified as a Shikinaisha (Myojin Taisha) listed in the Engishiki and one of the Nijuni-sha Shrines, and its former shrine classification was Kanpei-taisha (large-scale state shrine).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is classified as a Shikinaisha (Myojin Taisha) listed in the Engishiki and one of the Nijuni-sha Shrines, and its former shrine classification was Kanpei-taisha (large-scale state shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>全国にある春日神社の総本社である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the Grand Head shrine of Kasuga-Taisha Shrines located nationwide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the Grand Head Shrine of all Kasuga-Taisha Shrines in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the Grand Head Shrine of all Kasuga-Taisha Shrines in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>藤原氏の守護神である武甕槌命と経津主命、祖神である天児屋根命と比売神を祀る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It enshrines Takemikazuchino mikoto and Futsunushino kami (Futsunushino mikoto)-- a guardian gods for the Fujiwara clan--and Amenokoyane no mikoto and Hime no kami--Soshin (ancestor honored as god).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It enshrines Takemikazuchi-no-mikoto and Futsunushi-no-kami (Futsunushi-no-mikoto), guardian gods of the Fujiwara Clan, and Amenokoyane-no-mikoto and Hime-no-kami, Soshin (ancestors honored as god) of the Fujiwara Clan.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It enshrines Takemikazuchi-no-mikoto and Futsunushi-no-kami (Futsunushi-no-mikoto), guardian gods of the Fujiwara clan, and Amenokoyane-no-mikoto and Hime-no-kami, Soshin (ancestors honored as god) of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>四神をもって藤原氏の氏神とされ、春日神と総称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These four deities collectively believed to be Ujigami (a guardian god or spirit of a particular place in the Shinto religion) for the Fujiwara clan are called Kasuga no kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These four deities, collectively believed to be &apos;ujigami&apos; (tutelary gods) of the Fujiwara Clan, are called Kasuga-no-kami.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These four deities, collectively believed to be ujigami (tutelary gods) of the Fujiwara clan, are called Kasuga-no-kami.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>神紋は下がり藤。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its crest for a shrine is Sagari fuji (hanging wisteria).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shrine&apos;s crest is a hanging wisteria (sagari fuji).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shrine&apos;s crest is a hanging wisteria (sagari fuji).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>武甕槌命が白鹿に乗ってやってきたとされることから、シカが神使とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The deer is considered as shinshi (a messenger of kami (god), because Takemikazuchino mikoto is believed to have come here riding on a white deer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The deer is considered a &apos;shinshi&apos; (a messenger of kami, or gods), because Takemikazuchi-no-mikoto is believed to have come here riding on a white deer.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The deer is considered a &apos;shinshi&apos; (a messenger of kami, or gods), because Takemikazuchi-no-mikoto is believed to have come here riding on a white deer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>奈良・平城京に遷都された710年（和銅3年）、藤原不比等が藤原氏の氏神である鹿島神（武甕槌命）を春日の御蓋山に遷して祀った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 710 when the national capital was transferred to Heijo-kyo in Nara, FUJIWARA no Fuhito transferred Kashima-no-kami (Takemikazuchino mikoto)--Fujiwara Clan&apos;s guardian god---to Mt. Mikasa in Kasuga to be enshrined there.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 710 when the national capital was transferred to Heijo-kyo in Nara, FUJIWARA no Fuhito transferred Kashima-no-kami (Takemikazuchi-no-mikoto), the Fujiwara Clan&apos;s guardian god, to Mt. Mikasa in Kasuga to be enshrined there.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 710 when the national capital was transferred to Heijo-kyo in Nara, FUJIWARA no Fuhito transferred Kashima-no-kami (Takemikazuchi-no-mikoto), the Fujiwara clan&apos;s guardian god, to Mt. Mikasa in Kasuga to be enshrined there.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>春日神と称したのに始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shrine started when the god was called Kasuga no kami.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The beginnings of the shrine date from when this god came to be called Kasuga-no-kami.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The beginnings of the shrine date from when this god came to be called Kasuga-no-kami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>社伝では、768年（神護景雲2年）に藤原永手が鹿島神宮の武甕槌命、香取神宮の経津主命と、枚岡神社に祀られていた天児屋根命・比売神を併せ、御蓋山の麓の四殿の社殿を造営したのをもって創祀としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shrine&apos;s biography says that it was founded when FUJIWARA no Nagate joined Takemikazuchino mikoto of Kashima-jingu Shrine, Futsunushino mikoto of Katori-jingu Shrine, and Amenokoyane no mikoto and Hime no kami enshrined in Hiraoka-jinja Shrine and erected four shrine buildings in the foot of Mt. Mikasa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shrine&apos;s history says that it was founded when FUJIWARA no Nagate united Takemikazuchi-no-mikoto of Kashima-jingu Shrine, Futsunushi-no-mikoto of Katori-jingu Shrine, and Amenokoyan-no-mikoto and Hime-no-kami enshrined in Hiraoka-jinja Shrine and erected four shrine buildings at the foot of Mt. Mikasa</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shrine&apos;s history says that it was founded in 768 when FUJIWARA no Nagate united Takemikazuchi-no-mikoto of Kashima-jingu Shrine, Futsunushi-no-mikoto of Katori-jingu Shrine, and Amenokoyan-no-mikoto and Hime-no-kami enshrined in Hiraoka-jinja Shrine and erected four shrine buildings at the foot of Mt. Mikasa</e>
<cmt>年号補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>ただし、近年の境内の発掘調査により、神護景雲以前よりこの地で祭祀が行われていた可能性も出てきている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the recent excavation and research works suggested that Saishi (religious services) may have been held in this region before the Jingo Keiun era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, recent excavations have suggested that rituals may have been held in this region before the Jingo-keiun period (767-770).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, recent excavations have suggested that rituals may have been held in this region before the Jingo-keiun period (767-770).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>藤原氏の隆盛とともに当社も隆盛した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This shrine became prosperous with prosperity of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Fujiwara Clan became prosperous, so did the shrine.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Fujiwara clan became prosperous, so did the shrine.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>平安時代初期には官祭が行われるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Public rites and festivals started in the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Public festivals were held in the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Public festivals were held in the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>当社の例祭である春日祭は、賀茂神社の葵祭、石清水八幡宮の石清水祭とともに三勅祭の一つとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kasuga-matsuri Festival, a reisai (regular festival) of this shrine was one of sanchokusai (three great festivals designated by Japan&apos;s imperial court) along with Aoi-Matsuri Festival of Kamo-jinja Shrine and Iwashimizu-Sai Festival of Iwashimizu Hachiman-gu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kasuga-matsuri Festival, a reisai (regular festival) of Kasuga-taisha Shrine, was one of the sanchokusai (three great festivals designated by the Imperial Court) along with Kamo-jinja Shrine&apos;s Aoi-Matsuri Festival and Iwashimizu Hachiman-gu Shrine&apos;s Iwashimizu-Sai Festival.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kasuga-matsuri Festival, a reisai (regular festival) of Kasuga-taisha Shrine, was one of the sanchokusai (three great festivals designated by the Imperial Court) along with Kamo-jinja Shrine&apos;s Aoi-Matsuri Festival and Iwashimizu Hachiman-gu Shrine&apos;s Iwashimizu-Sai Festival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>850年（嘉承3年）には武甕槌命・経津主命が、940年（天慶3年）には、朝廷から天児屋根命が最高位である正一位の神階を授かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The imperial rank of Shoichii (Senior First Rank) was conferred on Takemikazuchino mikoto and Futsunushino mikoto in 850 and Amenokoyane no mikoto in 940.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The imperial rank of Shoichii (Senior First Rank) was conferred on Takemikazuchi-no-mikoto and Futsunushi-no-mikoto in 850 and Amenokoyane-no-mikoto in 940.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The imperial rank of Shoichii (Senior First Rank) was conferred on Takemikazuchi-no-mikoto and Futsunushi-no-mikoto in 850 and Amenokoyane-no-mikoto in 940.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>延喜式神名帳には「大和国添上郡 春日祭神四座」と記載されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jinmyocho (the list of deities) of Engishiki (codes and procedures on national rites and prayers) describes:&quot;our deities of Kasuga-matsuri Festival in the village of Yamamura in Sou upper district, Yamato province.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Jinmyocho (list of deities) in the Engishiki (codes and procedures on national rites and prayers) contains the passage, &quot;our deities of Kasuga-matsuri Festival in the village of Yamamura in Soekami District, Yamato Province.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Jinmyocho (list of deities) in the Engishiki (codes and procedures on national rites and prayers) contains the passage, &apos;our deities of Kasuga-matsuri Festival in the village of Yamamura in Soekami County, Yamato Province.&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。地名を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また、名神大社に列し、月次・新嘗の幣帛に預るとも記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also describes that the shrine is listed as a Myojin-taisha Shrine and heihaku (a sacramental strip of silk (offered to the gods)) was offered on monthly Niiname.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also states that the shrine is listed as a Myojin-taisha Shrine and that heihaku (offerings of cloth to the gods) were offered at the Tsukinami and Niiname festivals.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also states that the shrine is listed as a Myojin-taisha Shrine and that heihaku (offerings of cloth to the gods) were offered at the Tsukinami and Niiname festivals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="23">
<j>藤原氏の氏神・氏寺の関係から興福寺との関係が深い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shrine has a close relation with Kofuku-ji Temple because they are connected with the Fujiwara clan--ujigami (a guardian god or spirit of a particular place in the Shinto religion) and Uji-dera Temple (temple built for praying clan&apos;s glory) of the clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shrine, which houses the Fujiwara Clan&apos;s ujigami, has a close relationship with Kofuku-ji Temple, which is the clan&apos;s &apos;ujidera&apos; (tutelary temple).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shrine, which houses the Fujiwara clan&apos;s ujigami, has a close relationship with Kofuku-ji Temple, which is the clan&apos;s &apos;ujidera&apos; (tutelary temple).</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>813年（弘仁4年）、藤原冬嗣が興福寺南円堂を建立した際、その本尊の不空絹索観音が、当社の祭神・武甕槌命の本地仏とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When FUJIWARA no Fuyutsugu had Nanen-do Hall set up in Kofuku-ji Temple in 813, Takemikazuchino mikoto of this shrine was regarded as the honji-butsu (original Buddhist divinity) of Fukukensaku Kannon (Deity of Mercy)--the honzon (principal image of Buddha).of the temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When FUJIWARA no Fuyutsugu had the Nanen-do Hall built at Kofuku-ji Temple in 813, Kasuga-taisha Shrine&apos;s Takemikazuchi-no-mikoto was held to be the Shinto version of Fukukensaku Kannon (Amoghapasa), the honzon (principal image of Buddha).of the temple.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When FUJIWARA no Fuyutsugu had the Nanen-do Hall built at Kofuku-ji Temple in 813, Kasuga-taisha Shrine&apos;s Takemikazuchi-no-mikoto was held to be the Shinto version of Fukukensaku Kannon (Amoghapasa), the honzon (principal image of Buddha) of the temple.</e>
<cmt>文中のピリオド削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>神仏習合が進むにつれ、春日大社と興福寺は一体のものとなっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the syncretization of Shinto with Buddhism, Kasuga-Taisha Shrine and Kofuku-ji Temple became regarded as a united body.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the syncretization of Shinto and Buddhism, Kasuga-Taisha Shrine and Kofuku-ji Temple became regarded as a united body.</e>
<cmt>Conjunction</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the syncretization of Shinto and Buddhism, Kasuga-Taisha Shrine and Kofuku-ji Temple became regarded as a united body.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>11世紀末から興福寺衆徒らによる強訴がたびたび行われるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were frequent direct petitions of soldiers of Kofuku-ji Temple after the end of 11th century. direct petitions shinboku-doza (moving of the sacred tree)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Towards the end of the 11th century, warrior-monks from Kofuku-ji Temple often took part in direct &apos;goso&apos; (literally, forceful protest).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Towards the end of the 11th century, warrior-monks from Kofuku-ji Temple often took part in direct &apos;goso&apos; (literally, forceful protest).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>その手段として、春日大社の神霊を移した榊の木（神木）を奉じて上洛する「神木動座」があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shinboku-doza (moving of the sacred tree)&quot; was a means of such a direct petition, in which the soldiers went up to Kyoto under the authority of the Sakaki tree (shinboku (sacred tree)) into which a divine spirit of Kasuga Taisha Shrine was infused.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One such means of &apos;goso&apos; was the &apos;shinboku-doza&apos; (moving of the sacred tree), in which the monks went up to Kyoto under the authority of the Sakaki tree (shinboku (sacred tree)) into which a divine spirit of Kasuga-taisha Shrine was infused.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One such means of &apos;goso&apos; was the &apos;shinboku-doza&apos; (moving of the sacred tree), in which the monks went up to Kyoto under the authority of the Sakaki tree (shinboku (sacred tree)) into which a divine spirit of Kasuga-taisha Shrine was infused.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="28">
<j>明治4年に春日神社に改称し、官幣大社に列した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1871, it was renamed Kasuga-jinja Shrine and listed as a Kanpeitaisha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1871, it was renamed Kasuga-jinja Shrine and listed as a Kanpeitaisha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1871, it was renamed Kasuga-jinja Shrine and listed as a Kanpeitaisha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>1946年（昭和21年）12月に現在の春日大社に改称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December, 1946, it was presently renamed as Kasuga Taisha Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December, 1946, it was given the present name of Kasuga-taisha Shrine.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December 1946, it was given the present name of Kasuga-taisha Shrine.</e>
<cmt>カンマ削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>本殿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honden (main shrine buildings)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honden (main shrine buildings)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honden (main shrine buildings)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="30">
<j>春日造の本殿が四殿並んで建っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There stand four main buildings of kasuga-zukuri style (a style of shrine architecture employed in main sanctuaries, that has the same basic form as that at Kasuga Taisha Shrine).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are four honden built in a style known as kasuga-zukuri.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are four honden built in a style known as kasuga-zukuri.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>第一殿に武甕槌命、第二殿に経津主命、第三殿に天児屋根命、第四殿に比売神が祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takemikazuchino mikoto, Futsunushino mikoto, Amenokoyane no mikoto, and Himeno-kami were enshrined in the first shrine, the second shrine, third shrine, and the fourth shrine, respectively.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takemikazuchi-no-mikoto is enshrined in the first honden, Futsunushi-no-mikoto in the second, Amenokoyane-no-mikoto in the third, and Hime-no-kami in the fourth.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takemikazuchi-no-mikoto is enshrined in the first honden, Futsunushi-no-mikoto in the second, Amenokoyane-no-mikoto in the third, and Hime-no-kami in the fourth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>拝殿はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no Haiden (hall of worship).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no haiden (hall of worship).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no haiden (hall of worship).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>一般の参拝者は幣殿の前にて、初穂料を納めて特別拝観を申し込んだ場合は本殿前の中門から参拝することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">General visitors, who have paid hatsuho-ryo (ceremony fee) in front of the votive offering hall to request special viewing, pray at the Chumon gate.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">General visitors, who have paid hatsuho-ryo (ceremony fee) in front of the votive offering hall to request special viewing, pray at the Chumon gate.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">General visitors, who have paid hatsuho-ryo (ceremony fee) in front of the votive offering hall to request special viewing, pray at the Chumon gate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>摂末社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Setsumatsu sha (smaller shrine managed under the shrine)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Setsumatsusha (auxiliary and branch shrines)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Setsumatsusha (auxiliary and branch shrines)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>広大な境内には多数の摂末社がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many Setsumatsu sha in its large precinct.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many setsumatsusha in the shrine&apos;s large precinct.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many setsumatsusha in the shrine&apos;s large precinct.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>本殿の東側には比売神の御子神として天押雲根命を祀る摂社若宮神社がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">East of the main building, Wakamiya shrine of sessha (auxiliary shrine (dedicated to a deity closely-related to that of a main shrine)) stands that enshrines Ameno-oshikumone-no-mikoto as mikogami (the child god in a shrine where parent-child gods are enshrined) of Hime no kami.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wakimiya-jinja Shrine, a sessha (auxiliary shrine) that stands to the east of the honden, enshrines Amenooshikumone-no-mikoto, the mikogami (child god) of Hime-no-kami.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wakimiya-jinja Shrine, a sessha (auxiliary shrine) that stands to the east of the honden, enshrines Amenooshikumone-no-mikoto, the mikogami (child god) of Hime-no-kami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>若宮神社、夫婦大国社を始めとする本殿東側の十二社は、「福の神十二社めぐり」として古来より崇敬を集めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The twelve shrines including Wakamiya-jinja Shrine and Meoto-daikokusha Shrine that stand east of the main building were revered since ancient times as &apos;Pilgrimage to twelve shrines of The God of Good Fortune.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The twelve shrines, including Wakamiya-jinja Shrine and Meoto-daikokusha Shrine, that stand to the east of the honden have been revered since ancient times as the &apos;Pilgrimage to the twelve shrines of The God of Good Fortune.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The twelve shrines, including Wakamiya-jinja Shrine and Meoto-daikokusha Shrine, that stand to the east of the honden have been revered since ancient times as the &apos;Pilgrimage to the twelve shrines of The God of Good Fortune.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="37">
<j>本殿廻廊の西南隅には、摂社・榎本神社（式内小社）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enomoto-jinja Shrine (Shikinai-shosha) of sessha stands at the southeast corner of the main building&apos;s cloister..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sessha Enomoto-jinja Shrine (listed as a minor shrine in the Engishiki Jinmyocho) stands at the southeastern corner of the honden&apos;s cloister.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sessha Enomoto-jinja Shrine (listed as a minor shrine in the Engishiki Jinmyocho) stands at the southwestern corner of the honden&apos;s cloister.</e>
<cmt>単語修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>榎本神社の祭神は当地の地主神であり、元々この地で祀られていた神であるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The enshrined deity of Enomoto-jinja Shrine is jinushigami (god of an area of land), a god believed to have been originally enshrined in this area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The enshrined deity of Enomoto-jinja Shrine is a jinushigami (god of an area of land), a god believed to have been originally enshrined in this area.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The enshrined deity of Enomoto-jinja Shrine is a jinushigami (god of an area of land), a god believed to have been originally enshrined in this area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>現在の祭神はサルタヒコであるが、中世までは巨勢姫明神とされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sarutahiko is the deity presently enshrined but Kosenohime Myojin God had been enshrined until the Medieval Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sarutahiko is the deity presently enshrined but Kosenohime Myojin was enshrined there until the medieval period.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sarutahiko is the deity presently enshrined but Kosenohime Myojin was enshrined there until the medieval period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>祭事・年中行事</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Festivals and annual Events</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Festivals and Annual Events</e>
<cmt>Capital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Festivals and annual events</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="40">
<j>旬祭（毎月1日・11日・21日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Season festivals (every 1st, 11th, and 21st day of the month)</e>
<cmt>旬祭は、毎月3回、1日、11日、21日に行われているようですので、そのように訂正しておきました。http://www.kasugataisha.or.jp/manabu/manabu3.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shunsai festivals - 1st, 11th, and 21st of every month</e>
<cmt>&quot;旬&quot; here means &apos;a ten-day period&apos;, not season</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shunsai festivals - 1st, 11th, and 21st of every month</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>神楽始式（1月3日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagura Hajime Shiki (the ceremony of kagura-dance) (January 3)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagura Hajime Shiki (the ceremony of kagura-dance) - January 3</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagura Hajime Shiki (the ceremony of kagura-dance) - January 3</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>御祈祷始式（1月7日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gokito Hajime Shiki (the ceremony of prayer) (January 7)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gokito Hajime Shiki (the ceremony of prayer) - January 7</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gokito Hajime Shiki (the ceremony of prayer) - January 7</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>舞楽始式（1月10日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bugaku Hajime Shiki (the ceremony of traditional Japanese Court dances) (January 10)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bugaku Hajime Shiki (the ceremony of traditional Japanese Court dances) - January 10</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bugaku Hajime Shiki (the ceremony of traditional Japanese Court dances) - January 10</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>節分万燈籠（節分の日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Setsubun Bantoro Festival (the last day of winter according to the old calendar)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Setsubun Bantoro Festival (the last day of winter according to the old calendar)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Setsubun Bantoro Festival (the last day of winter according to the old calendar)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>御田植祭（御田植神事）（3月15日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oondaue-matsuri (Rice planting Shinto ritual) (March 15)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ondaue-matsuri (rice planting Shinto ritual) - March 15</e>
<cmt>lower case letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ondaue-matsuri (rice planting Shinto ritual) - March 15</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>ひと雛まつり（4月3日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hitohina-matsuri (doll festival) (April 3)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hitohina-matsuri (doll festival) - April 3</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hitohina-matsuri (doll festival) - April 3</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>水谷神社鎮花祭（4月5日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chinka-sai (the Buddha&apos;s Birthday Festival) of Mizuya Shrine (April 5)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mizuya-jinja Chinka-sai (the Buddha&apos;s Birthday Festival) - April 5</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mizuya-jinja Chinka-sai (the Buddha&apos;s Birthday Festival) - April 5</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>菖蒲祭（端午の節供祭）（5月5日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shobu-sai (matsuri) or the Iris Festival (Tango no Sekku (Boys&apos; Day)) (May 5)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shobu-matsuri (Iris Festival) or Tango no Sekku (Boys&apos; Day) - May 5</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shobu-matsuri (Iris Festival) or Tango no Sekku (Boys&apos; Day) - May 5</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>献茶祭（5月10日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kencha-sai (Tea ceremony) (May 10)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kencha-sai (tea-offering festival) - May 10</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kencha-sai (tea-offering festival) - May 10</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>薪御能（5月11日 - 5月12日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takigiono (takigi no, Noh performance played at night) (May 11 to 12)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takigiono (outdoor nighttime Noh performance) - May 11-12</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takigiono (outdoor nighttime Noh performance) - May 11-12</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>夏越大祓式（6月30日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagoshi no Oharai-shiki (summer purification ceremony) (June 30)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagoshi no Oharai-shiki (summer purification ceremony) - June 30</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagoshi no Oharai-shiki (summer purification ceremony) - June 30</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>中元万燈籠（8月14日 - 8月15日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chugenmantoro (Lantern festival at Kasuga-tansha Grand Shrine) (August 14 to 15)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chugenmantoro (Lantern Festival) - August 14 to 15</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chugenmantoro (Lantern Festival) - August 14 to 15</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>采女祭（中秋の名月の日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uneme Matsuri Festival (the day of harvest moon)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uneme-matsuri (the day of harvest moon)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uneme-matsuri (the day of harvest moon)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>重陽節供祭・献香祭（10月9日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Choyo no Sekku Festival (Kiku no Sekku/Chrysanthemum Festival)/Kenko-sai (the Festival for offering incense) (October 9)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Choyo no Sekku (Chrysanthemum Festival), Kenko-sai (Incense-offering Festival) - October 9</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Choyo no Sekku (Chrysanthemum Festival), Kenko-sai (Incense-offering Festival) - October 9</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>文化の日舞楽演奏会（11月3日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Culture Day concert of bugaku (traditional Japanese court music accompanied by dancing) (November 3)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Culture Day bugaku concert (traditional Japanese court music accompanied by dancing) - November 3</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Culture Day bugaku concert (traditional Japanese court music accompanied by dancing) - November 3</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>春日若宮おん祭（12月15日 - 12月18日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kasuga Wakamiya Onmatsuri Festival (December 15 to 18)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kasuga Wakamiya On-matsuri - December 15-18</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kasuga Wakamiya On-matsuri - December 15-18</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>年越大祓式（12月31日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshikoshi no Oharae-shiki (Year-end Shinto ritual of purification) (December 31)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshikoshi no Oharae-shiki (year-end Shinto ritual of purification) -December 31</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshikoshi no Oharae-shiki (year-end Shinto ritual of purification) -December 31</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cultural properties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>Capital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cultural properties</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>建造物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Architectures</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buildings</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buildings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="58">
<j>国宝「春日大社 本社 本殿」（4棟）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National Treasures &quot;Kasuga-taisha main shrine Honden&quot;(four shrines)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National Treasure - &quot;Kasuga-taisha main shrine, Honden&quot; (four buildings)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National Treasure - &apos;Kasuga-taisha main shrine, Honden&apos; (four buildings)</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="59">
<j>重要文化財「春日大社 本社 中門」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural heritage &quot;Kasuga-taisha main shrine Chumon&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;Kasuga-taisha main shrine, Chumon Gate&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;Kasuga-taisha main shrine, Chumon Gate&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="60">
<j>重要文化財「春日大社 本社 東御廊」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural heritage &quot;Kasuga-taisha main shrine Higashi Oro (East corridor)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;Kasuga-taisha main shrine, Higashi Oro Corridor&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;Kasuga-taisha main shrine, Higashi Oro Corridor&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="61">
<j>重要文化財「春日大社 本社 西及び北御廊」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural heritage &quot;Kasuga-taisha main shrine Nishi and Kita Oro (West and north corridors)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;Kasuga-taisha main shrine, Nishi and Kita Oro Corridors&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;Kasuga-taisha main shrine, Nishi and Kita Oro Corridors&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="62">
<j>重要文化財「春日大社 本社 捻廊」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural heritage &quot;Kasuga-taisha main shrine Nejiro (the twisted corridor)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;Kasuga-taisha, main shrine, Nejiro Stairs&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;Kasuga-taisha, main shrine, Nejiro Stairs&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="63">
<j>重要文化財「春日大社 本社 幣殿」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural heritage &quot;Kasuga-taisha main shrine Heiden (votive offering hall)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;Kasuga-taisha main shrine, Heiden Hall&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;Kasuga-taisha main shrine, Heiden Hall&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="64">
<j>重要文化財「春日大社 本社 直会殿」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural heritage &quot;Kasuga-taisha main shrine Heiden (votive offering hall)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;Kasuga-taisha main shrine, Naoraiden Hall&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;Kasuga-taisha main shrine, Naoraiden Hall&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="65">
<j>重要文化財「春日大社 本社 移殿」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural heritage &quot;Kasuga-taisha main shrine Utsushi dono (A temporary shrine building which houses a deity or sacred object while the main hall is undergoing major repairs)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;Kasuga-taisha main shrine, Utsushi-dono Hall&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;Kasuga-taisha main shrine, Utsushi-dono Hall&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="66">
<j>重要文化財「春日大社 本社 宝庫」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural heritage &quot;Kasuga-taisha main shrine Hoko (Treasure House)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;Kasuga-taisha main shrine, Hoko Treasure House&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;Kasuga-taisha main shrine, Hoko Treasure House&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="67">
<j>重要文化財「春日大社 本社 廻廊」（5棟）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural heritage &quot;Kasuga-taisha main shrine kairo (cloister)&quot;(five buildings)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;Kasuga-taisha main shrine, kairo cloister&quot; (five buildings)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;Kasuga-taisha main shrine, kairo cloister&apos; (five buildings)</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="68">
<j>重要文化財「春日大社 本社 南門」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural heritage &quot;Kasuga-taisha Minami mon (south gate)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;Kasuga-taisha, Minami-mon Gate&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;Kasuga-taisha, Minami-mon Gate&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="69">
<j>重要文化財「春日大社 本社 慶賀門」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural heritage &quot;Kasuga-taisha Keiga-mon Gate&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;Kasuga-taisha, Keiga-mon Gate&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;Kasuga-taisha, Keiga-mon Gate&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="70">
<j>重要文化財「春日大社 本社 清浄門」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural heritage &quot;Kasuga-taisha Seijo-mon (the Gate of Seijo)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;Kasuga-taisha, Seijo-mon Gate&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;Kasuga-taisha, Seijo-mon Gate&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="71">
<j>重要文化財「春日大社 本社 内侍門」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural heritage &quot;Kasuga-taisha Naiji-mon (the Gate of Naiji)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;Kasuga-taisha, Naiji-mon Gate&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;Kasuga-taisha, Naiji-mon Gate&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="72">
<j>重要文化財「春日大社 本社 車舎」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural heritage &quot;Kasuga-taisha Kuruma yadori (car depository)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;Kasuga-taisha, Kuruma-yadori wagon shed&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;Kasuga-taisha, Kuruma-yadori wagon shed&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="73">
<j>重要文化財「春日大社 本社 着到殿」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural heritage &quot;Kasuga-taisha Chakuto-den (the hall for arrival)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;Kasuga-taisha, Chakuto-den Arrival Hall&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;Kasuga-taisha, Chakuto-den Arrival Hall&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="74">
<j>重要文化財「春日大社 本社 竈殿」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural heritage &quot;Kasuga-taisha Hetsui-dono (Kitchen)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;Kasuga-taisha, Hetsui-dono Kitchen&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;Kasuga-taisha, Hetsui-dono Kitchen&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="75">
<j>重要文化財「春日大社 本社 酒殿」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural heritage &quot;Kasuga-taisha Saka-dono (Brewery)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;Kasuga-taisha, Saka-dono Brewery&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;Kasuga-taisha, Saka-dono Brewery&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="76">
<j>重要文化財「春日大社 本社 板蔵」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural heritage &quot;Kasuga-taisha Itakura (Warehouse) &quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;Kasuga-taisha Itakura Warehouse&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;Kasuga-taisha Itakura Warehouse&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="77">
<j>重要文化財「春日大社 本社 一の鳥居」 - 気比神宮と厳島神社の大鳥居に並ぶ「日本三大鳥居」の一つ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural heritage &quot;Kasuga-taisha Ichi no torii (the first archway) &quot;- ranked with torii (the shrine gates) of Hike Jingu Shrine and Itsukushima-jinja Shrine as one of Japanese Great Three Torii</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;Kasuga-taisha Ichi no Torii Gate&quot;- ranked along with those of Hike-jingu Shrine and Itsukushima-jinja Shrine as one of the Three Great Torii of Japan</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;Kasuga-taisha Ichi no Torii Gate&apos;- ranked along with those of Hike-jingu Shrine and Itsukushima-jinja Shrine as one of the Three Great Torii of Japan</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="78">
<j>重要文化財「春日大社 摂社若宮神社 本殿」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural heritage &quot;Kasuga-taisha, the main building of Wakamiya shrine of sessha (auxiliary shrine (dedicated to a deity closely-related to that of a main shrine) &quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;Kasuga-taisha, Wakamiya-jinja Shrine, Hpnden&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity - I don&apos;t think &quot;sessha is really necessary for English speakers</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;Kasuga-taisha, Wakamiya-jinja Shrine, Honden&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="79">
<j>重要文化財「春日大社 摂社若宮神社 拝舎」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural heritage &quot;Kasuga-taisha, Haisha (Worshiped place) of Wakamiya shrine of sessha &quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;Kasuga-taisha, Wakamiya-jinja Shrine, Haisha Worship Hall&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;Kasuga-taisha, Wakamiya-jinja Shrine, Haisha Worship Hall&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="80">
<j>重要文化財「春日大社 摂社若宮神社 細殿及び神楽殿」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural heritage &quot;Hosodono (narrow room or corridor) and Kaguraden (Hall of Shinto Music and Dance) of Wakamiya shrine of sessha&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property &quot;Kasuga-taisha, Wakamiya-jinja Shrine, Hosodono Hall and Kaguraden Hall&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property &apos;Kasuga-taisha, Wakamiya-jinja Shrine, Hosodono Hall and Kaguraden Hall&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="81">
<j>重要文化財「春日大社 摂社若宮神社 手水屋」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural heritage &quot;Temizuya (the hand-washing place) of Wakamiya shrine of sessha&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property &quot;Kasuga-taisha, Wakamiya-jinja Shrine, Temizuya purification font&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property &apos;Kasuga-taisha, Wakamiya-jinja Shrine, Temizuya purification font&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="82">
<j>重要文化財「旧春日大社板倉（円窓）」（奈良県所有）（奈良公園内所在）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural heritage &quot;Ita-gura (warehouse) (round window) of the former Kasuga-taisha Shrine&quot; (owned by Nara Prefecture) (located in Nara Park)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property &quot;former Kasuga-taisha Shrine Ita-gura Warehouse (round windows)&quot; (owned by Nara Prefecture, located in Nara Park)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property &apos;former Kasuga-taisha Shrine Ita-gura Warehouse (round windows)&apos; (owned by Nara Prefecture, located in Nara Park)</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>美術工芸品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Art craftworks</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Art and Craftworks</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Art and craftworks</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="83">
<j>国宝「金地螺鈿毛抜形太刀」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National Treasure &quot;kinji (gold background) raden (mother-of-pearl inlay work) kenuki-gata tachi (tweezers style sword)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National Treasure - &quot;kinji raden kenukigata tachi (tweezers style sword with mother-of-pearl-inlay on gold ground)&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National Treasure - &apos;kinji raden kenukigata tachi&apos; (tweezers style sword with mother-of-pearl-inlay on gold ground)</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="84">
<j>国宝「沃懸地（いかけじ）獅子文毛抜形太刀 中身無銘」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National Treasure &quot;ikakeji Shishimon Kenukigata-Tachi (hair-tweezers-shape sword), blade unsigned &quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National Treasure - &quot;ikakeji shishimon kenukigata tachi (hair-tweezers-shape sword, guardian dog design)&quot;, blade unsigned</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National Treasure - &apos;ikakeji shishimon kenukigata tachi&apos; (hair-tweezers-shape sword, guardian dog design), blade unsigned</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="85">
<j>国宝「沃懸地酢漿平文（いかけじかたばみひょうもん）兵庫鎖太刀 中身無銘」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National Treasure &quot;ikakeji raden hyomon (type of lacquer ware) Katabami hyomon (type of lacquer ware) Hyogo-gusari sword, blade unsigned&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National Treasure - &quot;ikakeji raden hyomon katabami hyomon hyogogusari tachi (gold &apos;ikakeji&apos; ground with creeping wood sorrel lacquer design)&quot;, blade unsigned</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National Treasure - &apos;ikakeji raden hyomon katabami hyomon hyogogusari tachi&apos; (gold &apos;ikakeji&apos; ground with creeping wood sorrel lacquer design), blade unsigned</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="86">
<j>国宝「沃懸地酢漿紋兵庫鎖太刀 中身無銘」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National Treasure &quot;ikakeji katabamimon hyogokusari tachi (sword), blade unsigned&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National Treasure - &quot;Ikakeji Katabamimon Hyogogusari Tachi (gold &apos;ikakeji&apos; ground with creeping wood sorrel design)&quot;, blade unsigned</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National Treasure - &apos;Ikakeji Katabamimon Hyogogusari Tachi&apos; (gold &apos;ikakeji&apos; ground with creeping wood sorrel design), blade unsigned</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="87">
<j>国宝「金装花押散兵庫鎖太刀 中身無銘」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National Treasure &quot;Kinso (gold fitting) kaochirashi hyogokusari tachi (sword), blade unsigned&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National Treasure - &quot;Kinso Kaochirashi Hyogogusari Tachi (sword with gold fitting)&quot;, blade unsigned</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National Treasure - &apos;Kinso Kaochirashi Hyogogusari Tachi&apos; (sword with gold fitting), blade unsigned</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="88">
<j>国宝「菱作打刀 中身無銘（附 杉箱）」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National Treasure &quot;Hishizukuri Uchigatana (a sword borne inside the &quot;obi &quot; belt) blade unsigned (with box of sugi board) &quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National Treasure - &quot;Hishizukuri Uchigatana (sword borne inside an &apos;obi&apos; belt)&quot;, blade unsigned (with Japanese cedar case)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National Treasure - &apos;Hishizukuri Uchigatana&apos; (sword borne inside an &apos;obi&apos; belt), blade unsigned (with Japanese cedar case)</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="89">
<j>国宝「赤糸威鎧 兜、大袖付」（梅鶯金物）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National Treasure &quot;Akaito Odoshi Yoroi (odoshi armor with red strings) and Kabuto (helmet of armor, armor) with osode (large sleeves)&quot; (Ume Uguisu Kanamono (plum, bush warbler ironmongery goods))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National Treasure - &quot;Akaito Odoshi Yoroi (yoroi armor laced with red thread), helmet, &apos;osode&apos; shoulder guards&quot; (plum and bush warbler motif)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National Treasure - &apos;Akaito Odoshi Yoroi&apos; (yoroi armor laced with red thread), helmet, &apos;osode&apos; shoulder guards&apos; (plum and bush warbler motif)</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="90">
<j>国宝「赤糸威鎧 兜、大袖付」（竹虎雀金物）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National Treasure &quot;Akaito Odoshi Yoroi (odoshi armor with red strings) and Kabuto (helmet of armor, armor) with osode (large sleeves)&quot; (Take Tora Suzume Kanamono (bamboo, tiger, sparrow ironmongery goods))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National Treasure - &quot;Akaito Odoshi Yoroi, helmet, &apos;osode&apos; shoulder guards&quot; (bamboo, tiger, sparrow motif)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National Treasure - &apos;Akaito Odoshi Yoroi, helmet, &apos;osode&apos; shoulder guards&apos; (bamboo, tiger, sparrow motif)</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="91">
<j>国宝「黒韋威矢筈札胴丸（くろかわおどしやはずざねどうまる） 兜、大袖付」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National Treasure &quot;Kurokawa Odoshiya Yazuzane Domaru (armor put around the torso) Kabuto helmet (of armor, armor) with osode (large sleeves)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National Treasure - &quot;Kurokawa Odoshiya Yazuzane Domaru (armor wrapped around the torso), helmet, &apos;osode&apos; shoulder guards&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National Treasure - &apos;Kurokawa Odoshiya Yazuzane Domaru (armor wrapped around the torso), helmet, &apos;osode&apos; shoulder guards&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="92">
<j>国宝「籠手」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National Treasure &quot;kote&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National Treasure - &quot;kote (gauntlets)&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National Treasure - &apos;kote&apos; (gauntlets)</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="93">
<j>国宝「本宮御料古神宝類」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National Treasure &quot;hongu goryo (imperial property of the head shrine) Koshinhorui (Sacred Treasures)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National Treasure - &quot;hongu goryo koshinporui (imperial sacred treasures of the main shrine)&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National Treasure - &apos;hongu goryo koshinporui&apos; (imperial sacred treasures of the main shrine)</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="94">
<j>国宝「若宮御料古神宝類」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National Treasure &quot;Wamamiya goryo (imperial property of Wakamiya shrine) Koshinhorui (Sacred Treasures)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National Treasure - &quot;wakamiya goryo koshinporui (imperial sacred treasures of Wakamiya-jinja shrine)&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National Treasure - &apos;wakamiya goryo koshinporui&apos; (imperial sacred treasures of Wakamiya-jinja Shrine)</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="95">
<j>重要文化財「木造舞楽面 皇仁、新鳥蘇、地久、納曾利、崑崙八仙（ころばせ）」5面</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural property &quot;Wooden Bugaku (court dance and music) masks: Ounin, Shintoriso, Chikyu, Nasori (a dance), Korobase&quot; five masks</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;wooden bugaku (court dance and music) masks: Ounin, Shintoriso, Chikyu, Nasori, Korobase&quot; five masks</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;wooden bugaku (court dance and music) masks: Ounin, Shintoriso, Chikyu, Nasori, Korobase&apos; five masks</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="96">
<j>重要文化財「木造舞楽面 納曾利一、新鳥蘇三、散手一、貴徳鯉口一、採桑老一」7面</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural property &quot;Wooden Bugaku (court dance and music) masks: 1 Nasori (a dance) mask, 3 Shintoriso masks, 1 Sanju music mask, 1 Kitoku koikuchi mask, 1 Saisoro mask&quot; seven masks</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;wooden bugaku masks: 1 Nasori mask, 3 Shintoriso masks, 1 Sanju mask, 1 Kitoku-koikuchi mask, 1 Saisoro mask&quot; seven masks</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;wooden bugaku masks: 1 Nasori mask, 3 Shintoriso masks, 1 Sanju mask, 1 Kitoku-koikuchi mask, 1 Saisoro mask&apos; seven masks</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="97">
<j>重要文化財「だ太鼓」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural property &quot;Da daiko&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;Dadaiko (decorated drum)&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;Dadaiko&apos; (decorated drum)</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="98">
<j>重要文化財「亀甲蒔絵手箱」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural property &quot;Kikko (hexagonal pattern) maki-e tebako (cosmetic box)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;kikko maki-e tebako (hexagonal &apos;maki-e&apos; [lacquer sprinkled with gold or silver powder] cosmetic box)&quot;</e>
<cmt>*Revised for clarity but unsure if &quot;亀甲&quot; is &apos;hexagonal&apos; or &apos;tortoise shell&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;kikko maki-e tebako&apos; (hexagonal &apos;maki-e&apos; (lacquer sprinkled with gold or silver powder) cosmetic box)</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="99">
<j>重要文化財「秋草蒔絵手箱」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural property &quot;Akigusa (autumn flowers) maki-e tebako (cosmetic box)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;akigusa maki-e tebako (&apos;cosmetic box with maki-e autumn flower design)&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;akigusa maki-e tebako&apos; (cosmetic box with maki-e autumn flower design)</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="100">
<j>重要文化財「禽獣葡萄鏡 春日金竜社伝来」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural property &quot;Kin Ju Budo Kyo (mirror with birds, animals and grape design) handed down in Kasuaga Konryu sha&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;kin ju budo kyo (mirror with birds, animals and grape design), handed down in Kasuaga Konryu sha&quot;</e>
<cmt>Capital lettersPunctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;kin ju budo kyo (mirror with birds, animals and grape design), handed down in Kasuaga Konryu sha&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="101">
<j>重要文化財「古神宝銅鏡（附 黒漆八稜形鏡箱）」16面</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural property &quot;Koshinho (Sacred Treasure) a bronze mirror (with black lacquer eight trigonous mirror box)&quot; 16 mirrors</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;koshinho dokyo (ancient sacred bronze mirror with black lacquer octagonal mirror box)&quot; 16 mirrors</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;koshinho dokyo (ancient sacred bronze mirror with black lacquer octagonal mirror box)&apos; 16 mirrors</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="102">
<j>重要文化財「竹虎双雀方鏡」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural property &quot;Chikuko Sojaku Hokyo (square mirror with bamboo, tiger, and two-sparrow design)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;chikuko sojaku hokyo (square mirror with bamboo, tiger, and two-sparrow design)&quot;</e>
<cmt>Capital lettersPunctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;chikuko sojaku hokyo&apos; (square mirror with bamboo, tiger, and two-sparrow design)</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="103">
<j>重要文化財「藤花松喰鶴鏡」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural property &quot;Toka matsukuizuru enkyo (mirror with a design of a crane having wisterias and a pine branch in its mouth&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;Toka matsukuizuru enkyo (mirror with a design of a crane carrying wisterias and a pine branch in its mouth&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;Toka matsukuizuru enkyo&apos; (mirror with a design of a crane carrying wisterias and a pine branch in its mouth)</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="104">
<j>重要文化財「菊造短刀」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural property &quot;dagger with chrysanthemum design&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;kikuzou tanto (dagger with chrysanthemum design)&quot;</e>
<cmt>PunctuationMaybe should also have the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;kikuzo tanto&apos; (dagger with chrysanthemum design)</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="105">
<j>重要文化財「梅花皮（かいらぎ）腰刀」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural property &quot;Kairagi (cracked glaze that can be seen on the foot of tea bowl) koshigatana (short sword)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;kairagi koshigatana (short sword with stingray skin ornamentation)&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;kairagi koshigatana&apos; (short sword with stingray skin ornamentation)</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="106">
<j>重要文化財「柏木兎（かしわみみずく）短刀」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural property &quot;Kashiwagi (The Oak Tree) mizuku (rabbit) tanto (short sword)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;kashiwagi tanto (dagger with oak and rabbit design)&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;kashiwagi tanto&apos; (dagger with oak and rabbit design)</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="107">
<j>重要文化財「太刀 銘備州長船住家助 永享八年二月日」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural property &quot;Sword with a signature of Bishu Nagafune Ju Sukesada, Eikyoi-eight-year February&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;tachi (long sword), bearing the inscription &apos;Bishu Osafune Ju Iesuke&apos; (Iesuke of Osafune, Bizen Province) and dated the second month of 1436&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;tachi (long sword), bearing the inscription &apos;Bishu Osafune Ju Iesuke&apos; (Iesuke of Osafune, Bizen Province) and dated the second month of 1436&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="108">
<j>重要文化財「錦包太刀 中身銘助行」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural property &quot;nishiki tsutsumi tachi (the sword wrapped by brocade) with a blade signed by Sukeyuki&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;nishiki tsutsumi tachi (sword with brocade wrapping) with a blade signed by Sukeyuki&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;nishiki tsutsumi tachi (sword with brocade wrapping) with a blade signed by Sukeyuki&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="109">
<j>重要文化財「金銅柏文兵庫鎖太刀 中身銘□次」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural property &quot;Kondo (gilt bronze) Kashiwa mon Hyogo-gusari tachi (sword) &quot;</e>
<cmt>中身銘□次の意味を調べられませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;kondo kashiwamon hyogogusari tachi (gilt bronze sword with oak pattern) &quot;</e>
<cmt>*I presume &quot;□次&quot; is a name such as &quot;為次&quot; or &quot;康次&quot; but I have no idea which so I left it out</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;kondo kashiwamon hyogogusari tachi (gilt bronze sword with oak pattern)&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。スペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="110">
<j>重要文化財「三鈷柄籐巻剣」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural property &quot;Sankotsuka Fujimaki ken (blade) &quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property &quot;sankozuka fujimaki ken (sword with a three-pronged vajra style hilt decorated with fujimaki wrapping)&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property &apos;sankozuka fujimaki ken&apos; (sword with a three-pronged vajra style hilt decorated with fujimaki wrapping)</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="111">
<j>重要文化財「赤銅造太刀 友成作」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural property &quot;Shakudo-zukuri tachi (copper sword) made by Tomonari</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;Shakudo-zukuri tachi (copper sword) made by Tomonari&quot;</e>
<cmt>Capital lettersPunctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;Shakudo-zukuri tachi (copper sword) made by Tomonari&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="112">
<j>重要文化財「黒韋威胴丸 兜、大袖付」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural property &quot; Kurokawa odoshi doumaru Kabuto (helmet of armor, armor) with osode (large sleeves)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;Kurokawa odoshi domaru (domaru armor) helmet, osode shoulder guards&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;Kurokawa odoshi domaru (domaru armor) helmet, osode shoulder guards&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="113">
<j>重要文化財「鉄三十六間四方白星兜鉢及鎧金具（てつさんじゅうろっけん しほうじろ ほしかぶとばち」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural property &quot;Tetsu (iron) 36 ken shihou jiro Hoshi kabuto (helmet) bachi and yoroi kanagu (armor&apos;s metal fittings) &quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;Tetsu sanjurokken shihoujiro hoshi kabuto-bachi (bowl helmet of thirty-six iron plates and raised rivets, with four white sides) and yoroi kanagu (yoroi armor metal fittings)&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;Tetsu sanjurokken shihojiro hoshi kabuto-bachi (bowl helmet of thirty-six iron plates and raised rivets, with four white sides) and yoroi kanagu (yoroi armor metal fittings)&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="32">
<sen id="114">
<j>重要文化財「鉄十八間二方白星兜鉢及鎧金具」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural property &quot;Tetsu (iron) 18 ken nihou jiro Hoshi kabuto (helmet) bachi and yoroi kanagu (armor&apos;s metal fittings) &quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;Tetsu juhachi ken nihou jiro Hoshi kabuto-bachi (bowl helmet of eighteen iron plates and raised rivets, with two white sides) and yoroi kanagu&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;Tetsu juhachi ken niho jiro Hoshi kabuto-bachi (bowl helmet of eighteen iron plates and raised rivets, with two white sides) and yoroi kanagu&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="33">
<sen id="115">
<j>重要文化財「鉄二十八間四方白星兜鉢及鎧金具」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural property &quot;Tetsu (iron) 18 ken shihou jiro Hoshi kabuto (helmet) bachi and yoroi kanagu (armor&apos;s metal fittings) &quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;Tetsu nijuhachi ken shihou jiro Hoshi kabuto-bachi (bowl helmet of twenty-eight iron plates and raised rivets, with four white sides) and yoroi kanagu&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;Tetsu nijuhachi ken shihojiro Hoshi kabuto-bachi (bowl helmet of twenty-eight iron plates and raised rivets, with four white sides) and yoroi kanagu&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="34">
<sen id="116">
<j>重要文化財「石燈籠」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural property &quot;Ishi-doro (stone lantern)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;Ishi-doro (stone lantern)&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;Ishi-doro&apos; (stone lantern)</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="35">
<sen id="117">
<j>重要文化財「石燈籠（柚木燈籠）」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural property &quot;Ishi-doro (stone lantern) (Yunoki Ishi-doro)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;Ishi-doro (Yunoki Ishi-doro)&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;Ishi-doro (Yunoki Ishi-doro)&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="36">
<sen id="118">
<j>重要文化財「紙本墨書楽所補任」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural property &quot;Shihon bokusho (ink on paper) gakuso (chamber of music) buninn&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;Shihon bokusho gakuso bunin&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;Shihon bokusho gakuso bunin&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="37">
<sen id="119">
<j>重要文化財「紙本墨書楽書」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural property &quot;Shihon bokusho (ink on paper) Gakusho book&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;Shihon bokusho gakusho&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;Shihon bokusho gakusho&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="38">
<sen id="120">
<j>重要文化財「春日神社文書」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important cultural property &quot;Kasuga Jinja Bunsho&quot;(the document of &quot;Kasuga shrine)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property - &quot;Kasuga Jinja Bunsho (Kasuga-jinja shrine documents)&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property - &apos;Kasuga Jinja Bunsho&apos; (Kasuga-jinja shrine documents)</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="39">
<sen id="121">
<j>重要無形民俗文化財「春日若宮おん祭の神事芸能」（春日若宮おん祭保存会）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important intangible assets of folk culture &quot;public entertainment of Shinto rituals of Kasuga Wakamiya Onmatsuri Festival&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Intangible Folk Cultural Property - &quot;public entertainment of Shinto rituals of Kasuga Wakamiya Onmatsuri Festival&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Intangible Folk Cultural Property - &apos;public entertainment of Shinto rituals of Kasuga Wakamiya Onmatsuri Festival&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="40">
<sen id="122">
<j>選択無形民俗文化財「春日若宮おん祭の芸能」（春日古楽保存会）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important intangible assets of folk culture &quot;public entertainment of Shinto rituals of Kasuga Wakamiya Onmatsuri Festival&quot;(Kasuga Kogaku hozon kai (Preservation Society of Kasuga Kogaku)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Intangible Folk Cultural Property - &quot;public entertainment of Shinto rituals of Kasuga Wakamiya Onmatsuri Festival (Kasuga Kogaku hozon kai)&quot; (Preservation Society of Kasuga Kogaku)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Intangible Folk Cultural Property - &apos;public entertainment of Shinto rituals of Kasuga Wakamiya Onmatsuri Festival&apos; (Kasuga Kogaku hozon kai) (Preservation Society of Kasuga Kogaku)</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>名所・旧跡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">famous place and historic scenes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Famous and Historic Sites</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Famous and historic sites</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="123">
<j>世界遺産：文化遺産「古都奈良の文化財」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">world heritage: cultural heritage &quot;Historic Monuments of Ancient Nara&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">World Heritage Site: cultural heritage site - &quot;Historic Monuments of Ancient Nara&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">World Heritage Site: cultural heritage site - &apos;Historic Monuments of Ancient Nara&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="124">
<j>国指定史跡「春日大社境内」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Officially-designated historical site, ruins designated as a national historical relic site &quot;precincts of Kasuga-Taisha Shrine&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Officially-designated Historical Site - &quot;precincts of Kasuga-taisha Shrine&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Officially-designated Historical Site - &apos;precincts of Kasuga-taisha Shrine&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="125">
<j>天然記念物「春日神社境内ナギ樹林」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Natural monument &quot;Podocarpus lignosa within precincts of Kasuga-Taisha Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Natural Monument - &quot;nagi conifer forest within precincts Kasuga-Taisha Shrine precincts&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Natural Monument - &apos;nagi conifer forest within precincts Kasuga-Taisha Shrine precincts&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="126">
<j>特別天然記念物「春日山原始林」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Special natural monuments &quot;Kasugayama Primeval Forest&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Special Natural Monument - &quot;Kasugayama Primeval Forest&quot;</e>
<cmt>Capital lettersPlural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Special Natural Monument - &apos;Kasugayama Primeval Forest&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>交通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="127">
<j>近畿日本鉄道近鉄奈良線近鉄奈良駅、西日本旅客鉄道関西本線桜井線・奈良駅 徒歩10分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ten minute walk from Nara Station of Kintetsu Nara Line of Kinki Nippon RailwayCompany and West Japan Railway Company Kansai Main Line/Sakurai line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ten minute walk from Kintetsu-Nara Station on Kinki Nippon Railway&apos;s Kintetsu Nara Line and Nara Station on West Japan Railway Company&apos;s Kansai Main Line and Sakurai Line</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ten minute walk from Kintetsu-Nara Station on Kinki Nippon Railway&apos;s Kintetsu Nara Line and Nara Station on West Japan Railway Company&apos;s Kansai Main Line and Sakurai Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>周辺情報</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Information for nearby spots</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nearby Places of Interest</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nearby places of interest</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="128">
<j>奈良国立博物館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nara National Museum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nara National Museum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nara National Museum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>新薬師寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinyakushi-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinyakushi-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinyakushi-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>奈良公園</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nara Park</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nara Park</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nara Park</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>志賀直哉旧居 (奈良市高畑)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SHIGA Naoya Kyukyo (the former residence of Naoya SHIGA) (Takabatake-cho, Nara City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naoya SHIGA&apos;s former residence (Takabatake-cho, Nara City)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naoya SHIGA&apos;s former residence (Takabatake-cho, Nara City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 JAnDbot(id:66507), Haguii(id:1313), Modeha(id:1276), Nnh(id:474), Pazuzu(id:103079), Reggaeman(id:6214), Urania(id:7213), D.h(id:79056), Araisyohei(id:378), Extrahitz(id:26245), 水戸大納言(id:188552), Ffokoob(id:259570), 柑橘類(id:112137), Aska-sacra(id:8180), どんべー(id:31362), ＋－(id:17104), MoveFact(id:93128), ECLIPSE(id:39342), Point136(id:211299), Yas(id:739), あなん(id:6904), 翰林硯士(id:99377), Mogumin(id:28886), たね(id:10372), Bergmann(id:85282), Stanislaus(id:1806), Mikahosi(id:15740), 水野白楓(id:22811), 短髄彦(id:5555), Himazin(id:22034), MIO(id:31681), Ikespirit(id:120987), Utsuda(id:605), MDR-SK(id:192066), 663highland(id:18755), Dnssgh(id:118255), Chibang(id:19967), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>