<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>達磨寺 (北葛城郡王寺町)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daruma-ji Temple (Oji Machi, Kita-katsuragi County)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daruma-ji Temple (Oji Machi, Kita-katsuragi County)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daruma-ji Temple (Oji Machi, Kita-katsuragi County)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>達磨寺（だるまじ）は、奈良県北葛城郡王寺町にある臨済宗南禅寺派の寺院。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Darumaji-ji is a temple of the Rinzai sect Nanzen-ji ha of Buddhism located in Oji-machi, Kita-katsuragi County, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daruma-ji Temple is a temple of the Nanzen-ji school of the Rinzai sect of Buddhism, located in Oji-machi, Kita-katsuragi County, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Word order, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daruma-ji Temple is a temple of the Nanzen-ji school of the Rinzai sect of Buddhism, located in Oji-machi, Kita-katsuragi County, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>山号は片岡山。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The temple&apos;s honorific mountain name (called `sango` in Japanese) is Kataokayama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its sango (literally &quot;mountain name&quot;, a title prefixed to the name of a Buddhist temple) is Kataokayama.</e>
<cmt>Made uniform with other articles.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its sango (literally &quot;mountain name&quot;, a title prefixed to the name of a Buddhist temple) is Kataokayama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>本尊は、千手観音・達磨禅師・聖徳太子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its principal images are Senju Kannon, Daruma Zenji, and the Prince Shotoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its principal images are Senju Kannon, Daruma Zenji and the Prince Shotoku.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its principal images are Senju Kannon, Daruma Zenji and the Prince Shotoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>この寺の創建については、推古天皇21年613年の冬、聖徳太子が片岡山で飢えていた異人に衣食を施したという片岡山飢人伝説にからめて語られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of the temple has been told in relationship to the Kataokayama kijin legend that described a story happened in the winter of 613, that the Prince Shotoku met a starved stranger in Kataokayama (Mt Ktaoka) and gave him food and clothing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of the temple has been told in relation to the Kataokayama kijin legend that described a story which happened in the winter of 613, namely that Prince Shotoku met a starving stranger in Kataokayama (Mount Kataoka) and gave him food and clothing.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of the temple has been told in relation to the Kataokayama kijin legend that described a story which happened in the winter of 613, namely that Prince Shotoku met a starving stranger in Kataokayama (Mount Kataoka) and gave him food and clothing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その後は、衰退と中興が繰り返され、江戸時代には幕府から30石が与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, the temple experienced repeated rises and falls, and eventually was granted a feudal estate of 30 koku (a unit to measure harvest yield) by the Edo shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, the temple has been in a cycle of decline and restoration, and was eventually granted a feudal estate of thirty koku (a unit to measure harvest yield) by the Edo shogunate.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, the temple has been in a cycle of decline and restoration, and was eventually granted a feudal estate of thirty koku (a unit to measure harvest yield) by the Edo shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>片岡山飢人伝説とは、『日本書紀』の推古天皇21年（613年）12月条や『元亨釈書』に見える次のような話である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kataokayama kijin legend is found in an article of December 613 of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) and in &quot;Genko shakusho&quot; (History of Buddhism of the Genko period).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kataokayama kijin legend is found in the entry for December 613 of the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) and in &quot;Genko shakusho&quot; (History of Buddhism of the Genko Period).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kataokayama kijin legend is found in the entry for December 613 of the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) and in &quot;Genko shakusho&quot; (History of Buddhism of the Genko Period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>聖徳太子こと厩戸皇子が片岡山を通りかかったところ、飢えて瀕死の異人に出会った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Prince Shotoku, who was then called as Umayado no Oji, was walking in Mt. Kataoka, and met a starved stranger.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Shotoku, who was then called Umayado no Oji, was walking on Mount Kataoka, and met a starving stranger.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Shotoku, who was then called Umayado no Oji, was walking on Mount Kataoka, and met a starving stranger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>太子はその異人に当座の寒さと飢えをしのぐため、食物と自分の衣服とを与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Prince gave his own food and clothing to help the man to survive the coldness and hunger.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Prince gave his own food and clothing to help the man to survive the coldness and hunger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Prince gave his own food and clothing to help the man to survive the coldness and hunger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>翌日、使いをやって異人の様子を見に行かせたところ、すでに息絶えていたので、丁重に葬った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the next day, the Prince sent his servant to see the condition of the man, but the man was already dead; so the man was buried in a courteous manner.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The next day, the Prince sent his servant to see the condition of the man, but the man was already dead; so the man was buried in a courteous manner.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The next day, the Prince sent his servant to see the condition of the man, but the man was already dead; so the man was buried in a courteous manner.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>それからしばらくして墓の様子を見に行かせると、死体は消えており、衣服だけがきちんとたたまれて、棺の上に置かれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After a while, the Prince again sent his servant to check on the grave, but the dead body was missing and only the closing that the Prince gave to him, neatly folded, was on the top of the coffin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After a while, the Prince again sent his servant to check on the grave, but the dead body was missing and only the clothing that the Prince gave to him, neatly folded, remained on the top of the coffin.</e>
<cmt>Spelling, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After a while, the Prince again sent his servant to check on the grave, but the dead body was missing and only the clothing that the Prince gave to him, neatly folded, remained on the top of the coffin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>これを知った里人は、あの異人は達磨禅師の生まれ変わりに相違ないと言い、聖徳太子が自ら刻んだ達磨像を祀ったのが達磨寺の始まりであるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The locals noticed this episode and started to believe that the dead man must have been a reincarnation of Daruma zenji; then the Prince Shotoku sculpted an image of Daruma and enshrined it at the site where currently the Daruma-ji Temple is built.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The locals heard about this episode and started to believe that the dead man must have been a reincarnation of Daruma zenji; then the Prince Shotoku sculpted an image of Daruma and enshrined it at the site where Daruma-ji Temple currently stands.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The locals heard about this episode and started to believe that the dead man must have been a reincarnation of Daruma zenji; then the Prince Shotoku sculpted an image of Daruma and enshrined it at the site where Daruma-ji Temple currently stands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>達磨寺の境内には達磨寺1号墳・2号墳・3号墳と称される3基の古墳（6世紀頃の築造）が存在し、このうちの3号墳の上に本堂が建てられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the temple&apos;s precinct, there are three ancient tombs, constructed around the six century, called as the Daruma-ji 1st, 2nd and 3rd, and the hondo (main hall) of the temple is built on the third tomb.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the temple&apos;s precincts there are three ancient tombs which were constructed in around the six century, called the Daruma-ji first, second and third tombs, and the hondo (main hall) of the temple is built on the third tomb.</e>
<cmt>Style, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the temple&apos;s precincts there are three ancient tombs which were constructed in around the six century, called the Daruma-ji first, second and third tombs, and the hondo (main hall) of the temple is built on the third tomb.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>この古墳は平安時代には聖徳太子ゆかりの達磨禅師の塚であると信じられていたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Heian period, this ancient tomb seems to have been believed as the mound of Daruma zenji, who has been told in relationship to the Prince Shotoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Heian Period, this ancient tomb seems to have been believed to be the mound of Daruma zenji, the associate of Prince Shotoku.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Heian Period, this ancient tomb seems to have been believed to be the mound of Daruma zenji, the associate of Prince Shotoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>寺院としての形態が整うのは鎌倉時代以後と思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the Kamakura period, at the earliest, it seems that the site gradually formed itself into a temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the Kamakura Period at the earliest, it seems that the site was gradually transformed into a temple.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the Kamakura Period at the earliest, it seems that the site was gradually transformed into a temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>境内には松永久秀の墓がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is the grave of Hisahide MATSUNAGA nearby in the precinct.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The grave of Hisahide MATSUNAGA is in the grounds of the temple.nearby in the precinct.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The grave of Hisahide MATSUNAGA is in the grounds of the temple nearby in the precinct.</e>
<cmt>templeとnearbyの間のピリオド.を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>重要文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>絹本着色涅槃図</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kempon chakushoku nehanzu (painting of Buddha&apos;s death in color on silk)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kempon chakushoku nehanzu (a painting depicting Buddha&apos;s death in color on silk)</e>
<cmt>Added for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kempon chakushoku nehanzu (a painting depicting Buddha&apos;s death in color on silk)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>木造聖徳太子坐像 - 建治3年（1277年）作。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wooden seated statue of the Prince Shotoku, sculpted in 1277.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A wooden statue of Prince Shotoku seated, sculpted in 1277.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A wooden statue of Prince Shotoku seated, sculpted in 1277.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>木造達磨坐像 - 永享2年（1430年）作。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wooden seated statue of Darma, sculpted in 1430.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A wooden statue of Darma sitting, sculpted in 1430.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A wooden statue of Darma sitting, sculpted in 1430.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>水墨画家として著名な周文が彩色を担当している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shubun, a famous Suiboku painter took charge of coloring.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shubun, a famous Suiboku painter, took charge of the coloring of the statue.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shubun, a famous Suiboku painter, took charge of the coloring of the statue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="22">
<j>達磨寺中興記石幢 附石碑（嘉吉二年（1442年）銘）、青磁香炉、大甕2口</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sekido (a kind of stone tower) that describes the restoration of Daruma-ji Temple, accompanied by a stone monument being engraved as 1442, incense burner of celadon, and two big jars</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sekido (a kind of stone tower) that describes the restoration of Daruma-ji Temple, accompanied by a stone monument being engraved with 1442, a celadon incense burner, and two big jars</e>
<cmt>Grammar,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sekido (a kind of stone tower) that describes the restoration of Daruma-ji Temple, accompanied by a stone monument being engraved with 1442, a celadon incense burner, and two big jars</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>本堂背後に立つ高さ185cmの八角石柱。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An octagonal stone pillar, 185cm high, standing behind the hondo (main hall)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An octagonal stone pillar, 185cm high, standing behind the hondo (main hall)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An octagonal stone pillar, 185cm high, standing behind the hondo (main hall)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>文安5年（1448年）建立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Built in 1448.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was built in 1448.</e>
<cmt>Made into a sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was built in 1448.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>各面に達磨寺の由緒が刻まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The pedigree of Daruma-ji Temple is engraved on all sides of the tower.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The history of Daruma-ji Temple is engraved on all sides of the tower.</e>
<cmt>Word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The history of Daruma-ji Temple is engraved on all sides of the tower.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>附指定の3点は2000年に本堂改築工事に伴い石幢を移動した際、地下から検出されたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Three articles additionally designated were the ones found in 2000 from the ground, when the tower was moved in order to reconstruct the hondo (main hall).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Three articles additionally designated as significant cultural artifacts were discovered in 2000 when the tower was moved in order to reconstruct the hondo (main hall).</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Three articles additionally designated as significant cultural artifacts were discovered in 2000 when the tower was moved in order to reconstruct the hondo (main hall).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>奈良県指定文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cultural Properties designated by Nara Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cultural Properties designated by Nara Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cultural Properties designated by Nara Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="27">
<j>方丈 - 寛文7年（1667年）建。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hojo (guest house of a temple), built in 1667.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hojo (temple guest house), built in 1667.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hojo (temple guest house), built in 1667.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>王寺町指定文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cultural Property designated by Oji-machi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cultural Property designated by Oji-machi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cultural Property designated by Oji-machi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>木造千手観音像 - 室町時代作。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wooden senju kannon zo (statue of thousand armed Avalokiteshwara), sculpted in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A wooden senju kannon zo (statue of thousand-armed Avalokiteshwara), sculpted in the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A wooden senju kannon zo (statue of thousand-armed Avalokiteshwara), sculpted in the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>達磨寺石塔埋納遺構出土品 - 鎌倉時代。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unearthed articles found in the buried remains in the tower of Daruma-ji Temple - the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unearthed articles found in the buried remains of the tower of Daruma-ji Temple dating from the Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unearthed articles found in the buried remains of the tower of Daruma-ji Temple dating from the Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>平成14年（2002年）に本堂の建て替えにともなう、発掘調査を行った際に出土。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 2002, an excavation research was performed as the temple&apos;s main hall was reconstructed, and some articles were found.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 2002, an excavation was carried out as the temple&apos;s main hall was reconstructed, and some articles were found.</e>
<cmt>Word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 2002, an excavation was carried out as the temple&apos;s main hall was reconstructed, and some articles were found.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>石製宝篋印塔が本堂基壇の下の小石室に入っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The stone pagoda of Hokyointo was found in a small stone room under the foundation of the main hall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hokyointo stone pagoda was found in a small stone room under the foundations of the main hall.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hokyointo stone pagoda was found in a small stone room under the foundations of the main hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>その石製宝篋印塔の中には、土師質の合子が入っており、さらにその中には水晶製五輪塔型舎利容器が入っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, a small container of earthy material was found in the stone pagoda, and a crystal pagoda style container for Buddha&apos;s bone was found in the earthy container.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, a small container of earthy material was found in the stone pagoda, and a crystal pagoda style container for pieces of Buddha bone was found inside the earthy container.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, a small container of earthy material was found in the stone pagoda, and a crystal pagoda style container for pieces of Buddha bone was found inside the earthy container.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>さらにその舎利容器の中には、非常に小型の石英片岩の舎利が入っているという何重もの入れ子構造をとっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That was a nested structure, in which all of containers were nested and at the center of the structure there were very small pieces of Shari (Buddha&apos;s relics) made of quarts schist, contained by the pagoda style container.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is an artifact with a nested structure, in which all of the containers were nested and at the center of the structure there were very small pieces of Shari (Buddha relics) made of quartz schist cocooned in the pagoda style container.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is an artifact with a nested structure, in which all of the containers were nested and at the center of the structure there were very small pieces of Shari (Buddha relics) made of quartz schist cocooned in the pagoda style container.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>13世紀前半に達磨寺3号墳が整備され、寺院として開基するときに納められたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is thought to be buried when the site was reorganized to re-establish as a temple in the first half of the thirteenth century, after the third Daruma-ji tomb was reshaped</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is thought to have been buried when the site was reorganized as it was re-established as a temple in the first half of the thirteenth century, after the third Daruma-ji tomb was reshaped</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is thought to have been buried when the site was reorganized as it was re-established as a temple in the first half of the thirteenth century, after the third Daruma-ji tomb was reshaped</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="35">
<j>交通アクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Transportation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Transportation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Transportation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="36">
<j>電車でのアクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By train</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By train:</e>
<cmt>Punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By train:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>JR　大和路線　王寺駅　→　奈良交通バス　達磨寺前下車　→　徒歩約10分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Oji Station of JR Yamatoji, take a Nara Kotsu Bus to Darumaji bus stop, and walk for about 10 minutes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Oji Station on the JR Yamatoji Line, take the Nara Kotsu Bus to Darumaji bus stop, and the temple is about ten minutes on foot.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Oji Station on the JR Yamatoji Line, take the Nara Kotsu Bus to Darumaji bus stop, and the temple is about ten minutes on foot.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>車でのアクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By car</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By car:</e>
<cmt>Punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By car:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>西名阪自動車道　香芝インターチェンジ　国道168号</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Take Nishi-Meihan Road, and get off at Kashiba Interchange going into NR 168</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Take the Nishi-Meihan Highway, then turn onto National Route 168 at Kashiba Interchange.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Take the Nishi-Meihan Highway, then turn onto National Route 168 at Kashiba Interchange.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>参拝者用の無料駐車場有</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Free parking is available for visitors</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Free parking is available for visitors.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Free parking is available for visitors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Maxy111(id:12547), Kstigarbha(id:13376), 果心居士(id:248111), Urania(id:7213), Jinzo(id:209385), くっちゃめ(id:86793), ブレイズマン(id:183852), ごまふあざ(id:36855), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>