<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>上淀廃寺跡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The remains of Kamiyodo abandoned temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamiyodo abandoned temple</e>
<cmt>The remains of を取りました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamiyodo abandoned temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>上淀廃寺跡（かみよどはいじあと）は、鳥取県米子市淀江町福岡字櫻田・法行・垣サゴに所在する古代寺院の遺跡。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The remains of Kamiyodo abandoned temple are the remains of an ancient temple located at Sakurada, Hogyo and Kakisago sections, Fukuoka area, Yodoe Town, Yonago City, Tottori Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The site of Kamiyodo abandoned temple is an archaeological site of an ancient temple extended over Sakurada, Hogyo and Kakisago of the Fukuoka area, Yodoe-cho, Yonago City, Tottori Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>The site of Kamiyodo abandoned temple extended over Sakurada, Hogyo and Kakisago of the Fukuoka areaとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The site of Kamiyodo abandoned temple is an archaeological site of an ancient temple extended over Sakurada, Hogyo and Kakisago of the Fukuoka area, Yodoe-cho, Yonago City, Tottori Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>淀江平野東側の丘陵裾に位置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is at the foot of the hills in the east of Yodoe Plain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is at the foot of the hills in the east of Yodoe Plain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is at the foot of the hills in the east of Yodoe Plain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>1991年より淀江町教育委員会が発掘調査を実施した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yodoe Town Board of Education started the excavation and research in 1991.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yodoe Town Board of Education started the excavation and research in 1991.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yodoe Town Board of Education started the excavation and research in 1991.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>法隆寺金堂壁画と並ぶ日本最古級の仏教壁画が初めて出土し、社会的に注目された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the oldest Buddhist wall paintings, as old as that of Horyu-ji Temple Kondo, were excavated and it caught people&apos;s attention.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the oldest Buddhist wall paintings, whose antiquity is comparable to that of Horyu-ji Temple Kondo (golden hall), was excavated and it caught people&apos;s attention.</e>
<cmt>whose antiquity is comparable to that of Horyu-ji Temple Kondo (Golden Hall)としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the oldest Buddhist wall paintings, whose antiquity is comparable to that of Horyu-ji Temple Kondo (golden hall), was excavated and it caught people&apos;s attention.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>数少ない白鳳時代寺院の堂内荘厳を復元し得る遺跡と評価され、1996年3月29日に、国の史跡に指定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The remains were evaluated as one of few remains that can restore Donai Shogon (the decoration of Buddha statues and temples) in Hakuho period, and designated as a national historic site on March 29, 1996.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The site was evaluated as one of few ruins that would be able to recover Donai Shogon (the decoration of Buddha statues and temples) of the Buddhist architectural style in the Hakuho period, and designated as a national historic site on March 29, 1996.</e>
<cmt>of the Buddhist architectural style in the Hakuho period, and としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The site was evaluated as one of few ruins that would be able to recover Donai Shogon (the decoration of Buddha statues and temples) of the Buddhist architectural style in the Hakuho period, and designated as a national historic site on March 29, 1996.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>現在の指定面積は25,560平方メートル。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The present designated area is 25,560㎡.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The present designated area is 25,560㎡.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The present designated area is 25,560㎡.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>紀年銘瓦等の遺物から飛鳥時代後期（7世紀後葉）の建立、8世紀中頃の改修を経て、平安時代中期（11世紀前葉）に焼失したものと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Judging from the relics such as tiles with the name of years carved on them, it is supposed that they were established in the latter half of Asuka period (end of the 7th century), restored in the middle of the 8th century and burnt down in the middle of Heian period (beginning of 11th century).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Judging from the relics such as tiles with the years carved on them, it is supposed that they were established in the latter half of Asuka period (end of the 7th century), and after the restoration in the middle of the 8th century, it burned down in the middle of Heian period (beginning of 11th century).</e>
<cmt>the years carved on them7th and after the restoration in the middle of the 8th century11thとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Judging from the relics such as tiles with the years carved on them, it is supposed that they were established in the latter half of Asuka period (end of the 7th century), and after the restoration in the middle of the 8th century, it burned down in the middle of Heian period (beginning of 11th century).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>これまでの調査で中心伽藍、寺域、その他倉庫等の雑舎が確認されているが、講堂の所在が不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of research up to now, the remains of central temple building, temple site and other buildings such as a warehouse were found, but the Kodo Hall (lecture hall) has not been identified.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of study to date, the remains of the temple&apos;s central structure, its complex and other buildings such as a warehouse were found, but the Kodo Hall (lecture hall) has not been identified.</e>
<cmt>As a result of studies to date, the remains of the temple&apos;s central structure, its complex としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of study to date, the remains of the temple&apos;s central structure, its complex and other buildings such as a warehouse were found, but the Kodo Hall (lecture hall) has not been identified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>寺域は天平尺で東西約2町（212メートル）、南北1町（106メートル）の規格とみられ、ほぼ中央に半町（53メートル）四方の中心伽藍が位置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The size of the temple site was 212m in east-west direction and 106m in north-south direction, and in the middle was located the central temple building of 53m square.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The site of the temple measures 212 m from east to west and 106 m from north to south, and in the middle of the complex the central structure of 53 ㎡ was located.</e>
<cmt>The site of the temple measures 212 m from east to west and 106 m from north to south, and in the middle of the complex the central structure of 53 ㎡ was located.としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The site of the temple measures 212 m from east to west and 106 m from north to south, and in the middle of the complex the central structure of 53 ㎡ was located.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>伽藍配置は南を正面として、東西棟の金堂の東側に、南北に3基の塔を並べる設計とみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The temple had its façade in the south, and in the east of Kondo (main hall) stretching in east-west direction were located three pagodas in north-south direction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that the complex was designed to be oriented to the south, and on the east of Kondo (main hall) which was supposed to be the structure lying east and west, three pagodas were planned to be constructed in a row in a north-south direction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that the complex was designed to be oriented to the south, and on the east of Kondo (main hall) which was supposed to be the structure lying east and west, three pagodas were planned to be constructed in a row in a north-south direction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>ただし、北塔については心礎と造成のみで基壇は未確認である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, concerning the north pagoda, the central base and development were found but the stylobate was not.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the northern pagoda&apos;s structure including its stylobate is unidentified, although its base-stone and land preparation were confirmed.</e>
<cmt>concerning を使わない構文にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the northern pagoda&apos;s structure including its stylobate is unidentified, while its base-stone and land preparation were confirmed.</e>
<cmt>although →while</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>計画のみとしても3塔を配置する例は無く、2塔でも南北に配置する古代寺院は他に無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The plan of these pagodas might not have been completed, but even so, there are no other ancient temples with three pagodas, or with two pagodas in north-south direction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even if it was a mere planning, there are no existent ancient temples with three pagodas, nor even with two pagodas lying north and south.</e>
<cmt>一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The plan of these pagodas might not have been completed, but even so, there are no other ancient temples with three pagodas, or with two pagodas lying in north-south direction.</e>
<cmt>元の翻訳に戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>基壇の規模は、金堂が東西14.2メートル、南北12.5メートル、塔はいずれも9.5メートル四方を測る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The size of Kondo&apos;s stylobate was 14.2m in east-west direction and 12.5m in north-south direction, and that of each pagoda&apos;s was 9.5m square.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The stylobate of Kondo measures 14.2 m from east to west and 12.5 m from north to south, and that of each pagoda was a 9.5 m by 9.5 m square..</e>
<cmt>The stylobate of Kondo measures 14.2 m from east to west and 12.5 m from north to south each pagoda was a 9.5 m by 9.5 m squareとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The stylobate of Kondo measures 14.2 m from east to west and 12.5 m from north to south, and that of each pagoda was a 9.5 m by 9.5 m square..</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>金堂及び中・南塔の基壇は瓦積みの周囲に石列を設置する二重基壇で、百済の寺院に多く見られる様式である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kondo as well as middle and south pagodas had double stylobate with stone lines around the piled tiles, which style was often seen in temples in Paekche.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kondo as well as the middle and southern pagodas had a double-layer stylobate with stone lines around the piled tiles, which was a style often seen in the temples in Paekche (an ancient kingdom located in southwest Korea).</e>
<cmt>a double-layer stylobate which was a style in the temples in Paekche (an ancient kingdom located in southwest Korea)としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kondo as well as the middle and southern pagodas had a double-layer stylobate with stone lines around the piled tiles, which was a style often seen in the temples in Paekche (an ancient kingdom located in southwest Korea).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>遺物は、壁土（壁画含む）約1,300点の他に、塑像約3,500点、瓦類（鴟尾含む）、土器、鉄器、金銅製品が出土した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The excavated relics were about 1,300 pieces of wall clay (including wall paintings), about 3,500 pieces of sozo (earthen image), tiles (including Shibi [ornamental ridge-end tile]), earthware, ironware and gilt bronze products.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The excavated relics were about 1,300 pieces of wall clay (including wall paintings), about 3,500 pieces of sozo (earthen images), tiles (including Shibi [ornamental ridge-end tile]), earthware, ironware and gilt bronze products.</e>
<cmt>下線部を変更しました。 (earthen images)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The excavated relics were about 1,300 pieces of wall clay (including wall paintings), about 3,500 pieces of sozo (earthen images), tiles (including Shibi [ornamental ridge-end tile]), earthware, ironware and gilt bronze products.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>塑像は金堂跡、中・南塔跡とも周辺から、壁画は金堂周辺のみからの出土である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sozo were found from both Kondo area and middle and south pagodas area, while the wall paintings were found only from Kondo area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sozo were found from the areas of Kondo as well as the middle and southern pagodas, while the wall paintings were found only from the Kondo area.</e>
<cmt>the areas of Kondo as well as the middle and southern pagodasthe Kondo areaとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sozo were found from the areas of Kondo as well as the middle and southern pagodas, while the wall paintings were found only from the Kondo area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>壁画及び塑像は、いずれも創建時と改修時のものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both wall paintings and sozo include pieces from the establishment era and from restoration era.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both wall paintings and sozo include pieces of the original structures and the structures restored at a later date.</e>
<cmt>of the original structures and the structures restored at a later dateとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both wall paintings and sozo include pieces of the original structures and the structures restored at a later date.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>創建時は半丈六如来像を本尊として、背後に浄土変相図の類の壁画が描かれていたと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is supposed that at the time of establishment, the principal image was the Nyorai Zo whose size was half of 4.85m and at its back were wall paintings of descriptions of the transformation of the Pure Land.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is supposed that at the time of establishment, the principal image was an approximately 2.5 m high statue of Nyorai and at its back there was a wall painting of a kind of Mandala illustrating the Pure Land.</e>
<cmt>an approximately 2.5 m high statue of Nyorai a wall painting of a kind of chronological illustration としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is supposed that at the time of establishment, the principal image was an approximately 2.5 m high statue of Nyorai and at its back there was a wall painting of a kind of Mandala illustrating the Pure Land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>改修時には金堂に丈六三尊像が本尊として安置され、壁画も一部、創建時より大きいモチーフで「光背」や「蓮台」など仏像の背景的なものが描かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time of restoration, the Sanzon Zo whose size was 4.85m was settled in the Kondo as the principal image and the wall paintings with larger Buddhism images such as halo and lotus pedestal were set behind that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time of restoration, the statue of Sanzon Triad of 4.85 m was settled in the Kondo as the principal image and its background wall was partially decorated with the paintings of larger-sized Buddhist motifs of halo and lotus pedestal.</e>
<cmt>Sanzon Zo→Sanzon Triad一部修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time of restoration, the statue of Sanzon Triad of 4.85 m was settled in the Kondo as the principal image and its background wall was partially decorated with the paintings of larger-sized Buddhist motifs of halo and lotus pedestal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="20">
<j>出土品は近接する米子市淀江歴史民俗資料館に保管・展示されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The relics are kept and displayed in the Yonago City history and race resource center close to the site.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The unearthed articles are kept and displayed in the Yonago City Yodoe Minzokushiryo-kan (museum of history and folklore) close to the site.</e>
<cmt>The unearthed articles are keptthe Yonago City Yodoe Minzokushiryo-kan (museum of history and folklore)としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The unearthed articles are kept and displayed in the Yonago City Yodoe Minzokushiryo-kan (museum of history and folklore) close to the site.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>遺跡は2004年から米子市によって環境整備（公園化）が進められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The remains have been maintained and are now being changed into a park by Yonago City.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since 2004, the site has been maintained by Yonago City and an environmental improvement project (construction of a park at the site) has been carried out.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ：Since 2004加えました。the site an environmental improvement project (construction of a park at the site) has been carried outとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since 2004, the site has been maintained by Yonago City and an environmental improvement project (construction of a park at the site) has been carried out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>同じ淀江町福岡地内に史跡妻木晩田遺跡、向山古墳群が所在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The historic site Mugibanda remains and Mukaiyama Tumuli are also in Fukuoka area, Yodoe Town.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The historic sites Mukibanda remains and Mukaiyama Tumuli are also located in the same Fukuoka area, Yodoe-cho, Yonago City.</e>
<cmt>Mukibanda (むぎばんだ→むきばんだ）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The historic sites Mukibanda remains and Mukaiyama Tumuli are also located in the same Fukuoka area, Yodoe-cho, Yonago City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mnd(id:15140), Nnh(id:474), 貘(id:106080), КОЛЯ(id:59429), Reggaeman(id:6214), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Urania(id:7213), 663highland(id:18755), Shimoxx(id:9332), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>