<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>祈願所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiganjo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiganjo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiganjo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>祈願所（きがんじょ）は神社、寺院の1つで、特に人々が神仏に願い事を行う寺社を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;kiganjo&quot; refers to a Buddhist temple or Shinto shrine at which worshipers pray for favors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;kiganjo&quot; refers to a Buddhist temple or Shinto shrine at which worshipers pray for favors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term kiganjo refers to a Buddhist temple or Shinto shrine at which worshipers pray for favors.</e>
<cmt>原文に『』のない&quot;を削除（初出でないため）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>寺院の場合は祈願寺、御願寺と言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case that it is a temple, it is referred to as a &quot;kiganji&quot; or a &quot;goganji&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If it is a temple, it is referred to as a &quot;kiganji&quot; or a &quot;goganji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If it is a temple, it is referred to as a &quot;kiganji&quot; or a &quot;goganji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>また、天皇によって祈願寺となった寺院を、特に勅願寺と言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, a temple designated a kiganji by an Emperor is referred to as a &quot;chokuganji&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, a temple designated as a kiganji by the Emperor is referred to as a &quot;chokuganji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, a temple designated as a kiganji by the Emperor is referred to as a &quot;chokuganji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>起源と歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin and History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin and History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin and history</e>
<cmt>文頭以外の語頭を小文字に</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>神道の場合</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinto Shrines</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinto Shrines</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinto shrines</e>
<cmt>文頭以外の語頭を小文字に</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>神社に祈願する事は、古くから行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People have prayed at Shinto shrines since ancient times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People have prayed at Shinto shrines since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People have prayed at Shinto shrines since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>特に平安時代後期には、宇佐八幡宮が源氏の氏神となった事により、『吾妻鏡』や『太平記』に見られるように、多くの武士によって神に祈願が為された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As can be seen in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; and &quot;Taiheiki&quot;, many samurai worshipped Shinto Kami during the latter part of the Heian period as a result of Usa Hachiman-gu Shrine becoming the ujigami (ancestral deity) of the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As can be seen in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; and &quot;Taiheiki,&quot; many samurai worshipped Shinto Kami during the latter part of the Heian period as a result of Usa Hachiman-gu Shrine becoming the ujigami (ancestral deity) of the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As can be seen in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East) and &quot;Taiheiki&quot; (The Record of the Great Peace), many samurai worshipped Shinto Kami during the latter part of the Heian period as a result of Usa Hachiman-gu Shrine becoming the ujigami (ancestral deity) of the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt>(The Mirror of the East)補足(The Record of the Great Peace)補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>仏教の場合</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buddhist Temples</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buddhist Temples</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddhist temples</e>
<cmt>文頭以外の語頭を小文字に</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>飛鳥時代に日本に伝来した仏教は、その後、国家の統制下に置かれ、寺院も国家や有力氏族によって建立されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After being imported into Japan during the Asuka period, Buddhism came under state control and temples were established by the nation and influential clans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After being imported into Japan during the Asuka period, Buddhism came under state control and temples were established by the nation and influential clans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After being imported into Japan during the Asuka period, Buddhism came under state control and temples were established by the nation and influential clans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その経緯から寺院では国家の発展、疫病防除、万民の健康を祈念するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is this that led to temples becoming places at which to pray for the development of the nation, the prevention of infectious diseases and the health of the country&apos;s population.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is this that led to temples becoming places at which to pray for the development of the nation, the prevention of infectious diseases and the health of the country&apos;s population.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is this that led to temples becoming places at which to pray for the development of the nation, the prevention of infectious diseases and the health of the country&apos;s population.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>平安時代になると、仏教信仰が貴族の間にも広まり、一部では奈良時代から既に行われてきたが、各氏族で個々に寺院を建立するようになり、そこで氏族の繁栄を祈念した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Heian period, belief in Buddhism spread throughout the noble classes, with each clan constructing temples in which to pray for the prosperity of the clan, although some clans had practiced this since the Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Heian period, belief in Buddhism spread throughout the noble classes, with each clan constructed temples in which to pray for the prosperity of the clan, although some clans had practiced this since the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Heian period, belief in Buddhism spread throughout the noble classes, with each clan constructed temples in which to pray for the prosperity of the clan, although some clans had practiced this since the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>鎌倉時代になると、仏教信仰が武士にも広まり、各武士の所領に当主や一族の繁栄や無事を祈る祈願寺が建立され、やがて戦死した一族を祀る菩提寺と一体化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kamakura period, Buddhism spread to the Samurai class, with temples being constructed at which to pray for the prosperity and safety of the head of each territory as well as the entire family, and these eventually integrated became with temples founded to pray for the souls of those family members who died in battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kamakura period, Buddhism spread to the Samurai class, with temples being constructed in which to pray for the prosperity and safety of the head of each territory as well as the entire family, and these eventually integrated became with temples founded to pray for the souls of those family members who died in battle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kamakura period, Buddhism spread to the Samurai class, with temples being constructed in which to pray for the prosperity and safety of the head of each territory as well as the entire family, and these eventually became integrated with temples founded to pray for the souls of those family members who died in battle.</e>
<cmt>integrated became→became integrated</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>室町時代になると、仏教信仰が庶民の間にも広まり、各地の寺院に願い事を行うのが一般的となり、願い事を書いた祈願文が奉納されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buddhism disseminated to the common people during the Muromachi period and it became commonplace to pray at temples throughout the country, with prayers being written down and offered to the temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buddhism disseminated to the common people during the Muromachi period and it became commonplace to pray at temples throughout the country, with prayers being written down and offered to the temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddhism disseminated to the common people during the Muromachi period and it became commonplace to pray at temples throughout the country, with prayers being written down and offered to the temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>江戸時代になると、旅行が大衆化し、それまでは近隣の寺社にのみ参詣していたが、善光寺や四国八十八箇所のように、遠隔地の寺社へも参詣するようになり、様々な祈願が各地の寺社になされるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Edo period, travel became more widespread and, although until then people only visited nearby temples and shrines, it became the practice that people visited distant templs and shrines and made various prayers at temples and shrines in different locations such as Zenko-ji Temple and the Shikoku Pilgrimage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo period, travel became more widespread and, although until then people only visited nearby temples and shrines, it became the practice for people to visit distant temples and shrines and say various prayers in different locations such as Zenko-ji Temple and during the Shikoku Pilgrimage.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period, travel became more widespread and, although until then people only visited nearby temples and shrines, it became the practice for people to visit distant temples and shrines and say various prayers in different locations such as Zenko-ji Temple and the Shikoku Pilgrimage.</e>
<cmt>during削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>因みに、近代以前の祈願とは、例えば「～の願い事を叶えて頂いた暁には、燈籠を奉納します」のように神仏との契約であり、現代のように、願い事を行うだけの一方的な関係ではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pre-modern prayers were more like an agreement with deities in which, for example, a lantern would be offered if a particular prayer were answered as opposed to the modern one-sided form in which ones desires are requested.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Pre-modern prayers were more like an agreement with deities in which, for example, a lantern would be offered if a particular prayer were answered as opposed to the modern one-sided form in which ones desires are requested.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Pre-modern prayers were more like an agreement with deities in which, for example, a lantern would be offered if a particular prayer were answered as opposed to the modern one-sided form in which ones desires are requested.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>これらの契約によって行われた施設の補修や調度品の奉納などを、2005年現在も見る事が出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The repairs made to structures and the objects offered as a result of these agreements could still be seen as of 2005.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The repairs made to structures and the objects offered as a result of these agreements could still be seen as of 2005.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The repairs made to structures and the objects offered as a result of these agreements could still be seen as of 2005.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 TAMA(id:25299), Kstigarbha(id:13376), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>