<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>豊受大神社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toyuke-daijinja Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toyuke-daijinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toyuke-daijinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>豊受大神社（とゆけだいじんじゃ）は、京都府福知山市大江町に鎮座する神社。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toyuke-daijinja Shrine is located in Oe-cho, Fukuchiyama City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toyuke-daijinja Shrine is located in Oe-cho, Fukuchiyama City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toyuke-daijinja Shrine is located in Oe-cho, Fukuchiyama City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>近代社格制度は府社。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This shrine was categorized as Fusha (a prefectural shrine) in Kindai shakaku seido (Modern shrine ranking system).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This shrine was categorized as a Fusha (a prefectural shrine) in Kindai shakaku seido (modern shrine ranking system).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This shrine was categorized as a Fusha (a prefectural shrine) in Kindai shakaku seido (modern shrine ranking system).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>元伊勢の伝承を有す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This shrine is believed to be Moto Ise (shrines or places where the deities of Ise Jingu Shrine were once enshrined).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This shrine is believed to be Moto Ise (shrines or places where the deities of Ise Jingu Shrine were once enshrined).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This shrine is believed to be Moto Ise (shrines or places where the deities of Ise Jingu Shrine were once enshrined).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>社名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shrine&apos;s name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shrine name</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shrine name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>豊受大神宮の元宮であるとの伝承から、「元伊勢外宮」とも称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of the legend that this shrine is Motomiya (an origin of Miya) of the Toyouke Dai-jingu Shrine, it is also known as &quot;Motoisegeku Shrine&quot; (the old outer shrine of Ise Shrine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of the legend that this shrine is Motomiya (an origin of Miya) of the Toyouke Dai-jingu Shrine, it is also known as &quot;Motoisegeku Shrine&quot; (the old outer shrine of Ise Shrine).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of the legend that this shrine is Motomiya (an origin of Miya) of the Toyouke Dai-jingu Shrine, it is also known as &apos;Motoisegeku Shrine&apos; (the old outer shrine of Ise Shrine).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>祭神</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enshrined deity</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enshrined deity</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enshrined deity</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>豊受姫神を祭神に、日子番能邇邇芸尊、天児屋根命、天太玉命を相殿に祀る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This shrine enshrines the Toyuke Goddess, and the other deities together in the sanctuary, such as Amatsuhikoho no ninigi no mikoto, Amenokoyane no mikoto and Ame no futotama no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>用語集では&quot;Ame no Futotama no Mikoto&quot;でしたが、他に合わせてそれぞれfutotama, mikotoとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This shrine enshrines the Toyuke Goddess, and the other deities together in the sanctuary, such as Amatsuhikoho no ninigi no mikoto, Amenokoyane no mikoto and Ame no futotama no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This shrine enshrines the Toyuke Goddess, and the other deities together in the sanctuary, such as Amatsuhikoho no ninigi no mikoto, Amenokoyane no mikoto and Ame no futotama no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>由緒</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>延暦23年（804年）の『止由気宮儀式帳』に、雄略天皇が天照大神の夢託を蒙り、御食津神として等由気太神（豊受大神）を丹波国から伊勢に迎えたのが外宮であると記す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Toyukegu Gishikicho&quot; (Register of Ceremonies for Toyuke-gu Shrine) written in 804, Geku (the outer shrine of Ise) was build to enshrine Toyuke Omikami (Toyuke Great God) as Miketsukami (the God of Food) by inviting from Tanba Province, as Emperor Yuryaku had received an oracle from Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（2分割）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Toyukegu Gishikicho&quot; (Register of Ceremonies for Toyuke-gu Shrine) written in 804, Geku (the outer shrine of Ise) was built to enshrine Toyuke Omikami (Toyuke Great God) as Miketsukami (the God of Food) invited from Tanba Province, as Emperor Yuryaku had received an oracle from Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Toyukegu Gishikicho&quot; (Register of Ceremonies for Toyuke-gu Shrine) written in 804, Geku (the outer shrine of Ise) was built to enshrine Toyuke Omikami (Toyuke Great God) as Miketsukami (the God of Food) invited from Tanba Province, as Emperor Yuryaku had received an oracle from Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>それに基づいて当神社は雄略天皇22年に伊勢へ遷座したその故地であるといい（『丹後風土記』）、或いは、元鎮座地は比沼麻奈為神社（現京丹後市峰山町に鎮座）であるが、雄略天皇22年に伊勢へ遷座する途中で当神社の地にしばらく鎮座し、その跡地に建立したものであるともいう（『加佐郡誌』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said (in &quot;Tango no Kuni Fudoki&quot; (The Records of the Culture and Geography in Tango Province)) that the location of this shrine is where the god was enshrined before transferred to Ise, or according to another legend, it was originally enshrined at the location of Hinumanai-jinja Shrine (present-day Mineyama-cho, Kyotango City), and then temporarily settled where this shrine is now built on the way to Ise (&quot;The Records of Kasa-gun County&quot;).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（2分割）雄略天皇22年←西暦が不明のため記載せず。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said (in &quot;Tango no Kuni Fudoki&quot; (The Records of the Culture and Geography in Tango Province)) that the location of this shrine is where the god was enshrined before it was transferred to Ise, or according to another legend, it was originally enshrined at the location of the Hinumanai-jinja Shrine (present-day Mineyama-cho, Kyotango City), and then temporarily settled where this shrine is now built on the way to Ise (&quot;The Records of Kasa-gun County&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said (in &quot;Tango no Kuni Fudoki&quot; (The Records of the Culture and Geography in Tango Province)) that the location of this shrine is where the god was enshrined before it was transferred to Ise in 478, or according to another legend, it was originally enshrined at the location of the Hinumanai-jinja Shrine (present-day Mineyama-cho, Kyotango City), and then temporarily settled where this shrine is now built on the way to Ise (&quot;The Records of Kasa-gun County&quot;) in 478.</e>
<cmt>年号補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、それとは別に、用明天皇の第3皇子である麻呂子親王が当地の鬼を退治するに際して、内宮（現皇大神社 (福知山市)）とともに勧請したものであるとの異伝もある（宝暦11年（1761年）の『丹後州宮津府志』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also believed that Imperial Prince Maroko, the third son of Emperor Yomei, transferred the divided deity to this region together with Naiku (inner shrine) (present-day Kotai-jinja (in Fukuchiyama City)) to drive off devils (&quot;The Record of Miyatsu-fu in Tango&quot; in 1761).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also believed that Imperial Prince Maroko, the third son of Emperor Yomei, transferred the divided deity to this region together with Naiku (inner shrine) (present-day Kotai-jinja (in Fukuchiyama City)) to drive off devils (&quot;The Record of Miyatsu-fu in Tango&quot; in 1761).</e>
<cmt>Spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also believed that Imperial Prince Maroko, the third son of Emperor Yomei, transferred the divided deity to this region together with Naiku (inner shrine) (present-day Kotai-jinja (in Fukuchiyama City)) to drive off devils (&quot;The Record of Miyatsu-fu in Tango&quot; in 1761).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>近世以前の沿革は不明であるが、江戸時代には明暦2年（1656年）に宮津藩京極高国が将軍徳川家綱の疱瘡平癒を祈願して社殿を造営した（社蔵棟札）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The history before the early modern ages is unknown, but in 1656 during Edo period, Takakuni KYOGOKU from the Miyazu Domain constructed the shrine to pray for curing Ietsuna TOKUGAWA, the fourth shogun, of smallpox (historical plaque on a shrine warehouse building).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（2分割）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its history before the early modern ages is unknown, but in 1656 during the Edo period, Takakuni KYOGOKU from the Miyazu Domain constructed the shrine to pray for curing Ietsuna TOKUGAWA, the fourth shogun, of smallpox (historical plaque on a shrine warehouse building).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its history before the early modern ages is unknown, but in 1656 during the Edo period, Takakuni KYOGOKU from the Miyazu Domain constructed the shrine to pray for curing Ietsuna TOKUGAWA, the fourth shogun, of smallpox (historical plaque on a shrine warehouse building).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>延宝5年（1677年）に同永井尚長が4石 (単位)6斗4升2合の社領を寄せ、以後藩家は変わりながらも歴代藩主の社参や代参、寄進等の崇敬を受けたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naonaga NAGAI from the Miyazu Domain contributed the 4-koku (unit), 6-to (unit of volume, approx. 18 litres), 4-sho (unit of volume, approx. 1.8 litres) and 2-go (a unit of volume, approx. 0.18 litres) land to the shrine in 1677, since then the shrine has been visited and donated by the past lords of the domain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（2分割）単位について、翻訳仕様指示書では「石」はkokuでとありましたので、特に説明は加えていません。斗、升、合については用語集にあった説明を追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naonaga NAGAI from the Miyazu Domain contributed the four-koku (unit), six-to (unit of volume, approx. 18 liters), four-sho (unit of volume, approx. 1.8 liters) and two-go (a unit of volume, approx. 0.18 liters) land to the shrine in 1677, since then the shrine has been visited and donated by the past lords of the domain.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naonaga NAGAI from the Miyazu Domain contributed the four-koku (unit), six-to (unit of volume, approx. 18 liters), four-sho (unit of volume, approx. 1.8 liters) and two-go (a unit of volume, approx. 0.18 liters) land to the shrine in 1677, since then the shrine has been visited and donated by the past lords of the domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>昭和5年（1930年）府社に列し、戦後は神社本庁に参加している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This shrine was classified as Fusha in 1930, and has joined Association of Shinto Shrines after the World War II.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This shrine was classified as Fusha in 1930, and has joined the Association of Shinto Shrines after World War II.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This shrine was classified as Fusha in 1930, and has joined the Association of Shinto Shrines after World War II.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>祭祀</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Religious service</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Religious service</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Religious service</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>社殿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shrine building</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shrine building</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shrine building</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>古来60年に1度の式年遷宮が行われていたというが、現在の本殿は明治7年（1874年）の造替にかかるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In ancient times, a transfer of a deity to a new shrine building was conducted once in 60 years, but it was in 1874 when the current main building was built.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（2分割）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In ancient times, a transfer of a deity to a new shrine building was conducted once in 60 years, but it was in 1874 when the current main building was built.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In ancient times, a transfer of a deity to a new shrine building was conducted once in 60 years, but it was in 1874 when the current main building was built.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>桁行3間梁間2間の神明造茅葺で、外削ぎの千木を持ち、棟に鰹木を置く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The building has Ketayuki-sanken (3-ken in length of beam), Harima-niken (2-ken in length of crossbeam), a thatched roof in Shinmei tsukuri (style of shrine architecture based on that of Ise-jingu Shrine) style, Chigi (ornamental crossbeams on the gable of a Shinto shrine) of Sotosogi (the ends of the former are terminated with a vertical cut) and Katsuogi (ornamental logs arranged orthogonal to the ridge of a Shinto shrine) on the ridge.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（2分割）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The building has Ketayuki-sanken (three-ken in length of beam), Harima-niken (two-ken in length of crossbeam), a thatched roof in Shinmei tsukuri (style of shrine architecture based on that of Ise-jingu Shrine) style, Chigi (ornamental crossbeams on the gable of a Shinto shrine) of Sotosogi (the ends of the former are terminated with a vertical cut) and Katsuogi (ornamental logs arranged orthogonal to the ridge of a Shinto shrine) on the ridge.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The building has Ketayuki-sanken (three-ken in length of beam), Harima-niken (two-ken in length of crossbeam), a thatched roof in Shinmei tsukuri (style of shrine architecture based on that of Ise-jingu Shrine) style, Chigi (ornamental crossbeams on the gable of a Shinto shrine) of Sotosogi (the ends of the former are terminated with a vertical cut) and Katsuogi (ornamental logs arranged orthogonal to the ridge of a Shinto shrine) on the ridge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>その他、拝殿、41社の境内社、寄棟造柿葺の神楽殿がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than this, there are Haiden, a hall of worship, 41 shrine in precincts and a Kagura-den hall in Yosemune-zukuri Kokerabuki (with a hipped roof with shingles) style.</e>
<cmt>けいだい-しゃ 【境内社】. ある神社の境内に鎮座し、その管理下にある他の神社。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than this, there are Haiden, a hall of worship, 41 shrines in precincts and a Kagura-den hall in Yosemune-zukuri Kokerabuki (with a hipped roof with shingles) style.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than this, there are Haiden, a hall of worship, 41 shrines in precincts and a Kagura-den hall in Yosemune-zukuri Kokerabuki (with a hipped roof with shingles) style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>境内社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keidai-sha (sub-shrines in precincts)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keidai-sha (sub-shrines in precincts)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keidai-sha (sub-shrines in precincts)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>拝殿の左右に多賀神社と土之神社、本殿左後方に月読宮、右後方に風之宮が鎮座し、この4社を別宮とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the left and right sides of Haiden are Taga-jinja Shrine and Tsuchino-jinja Shrine, and Tsukiyomi no miya is on the left rear side of the main building and Kaze no miya (wind shrine) on the right rear side, and these four shrines are regarded as Betsugu (an associated shrine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the left and right sides of Haiden are the Taga-jinja Shrine and Tsuchino-jinja Shrine, and Tsukiyomi no miya is on the left rear side of the main building and Kaze no miya (wind shrine) on the right rear side, and these four shrines are regarded as Betsugu (an associated shrine).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the left and right sides of Haiden are the Taga-jinja Shrine and Tsuchino-jinja Shrine, and Tsukiyomi no miya is on the left rear side of the main building and Kaze no miya (wind shrine) on the right rear side, and these four shrines are regarded as Betsugu (an associated shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>本殿を囲む形で37社の末社がコの字形に配置される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">37 Masshas (branch shrines) are surrounding the main building in the U shape.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">37 Masshas (branch shrines) are surrounding the main building in a U shape.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">37 Masshas (branch shrines) are surrounding the main building in a U shape.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>当神社には御師的な役割をはたす37軒の社家があり、37社の末社はそれぞれの社家が1社ずつ祀っていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that this shrine had 37 Shakes (families of Shinto priests serving a shrine on a hereditary basis) who played a role similar to Onshi (a low-ranking Shinto priest), and that each Shake enshrined one of the 37 Masshas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that this shrine had 37 Shakes (families of Shinto priests serving a shrine on a hereditary basis) who played a role similar to Onshi (a low-ranking Shinto priest), and that each Shake enshrined one of the 37 Masshas.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that this shrine had 37 Shakes (families of Shinto priests serving a shrine on a hereditary basis) who played a role similar to Onshi (a low-ranking Shinto priest), and that each Shake enshrined one of the 37 Masshas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 胡亂堂(id:263343), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>