<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>妙法院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myoho-in Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myoho-in Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myoho-in Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>妙法院（みょうほういん）は京都市東山区にある天台宗の仏教寺院である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myoho-in Temple is a Tendai Sect Buddhist temple located in Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myoho-in Temple is a Tendai Sect Buddhist temple located in Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myoho-in Temple is a Tendai Sect Buddhist temple located in Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>山号を南叡山と称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its honorific mountain prefix is Naneizan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its honorific mountain prefix is Naneizan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its honorific mountain prefix is Mt. Nanei.</e>
<cmt>南叡山→Mt. Naneiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>本尊は普賢菩薩、開基は最澄と伝える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The temple is devoted to the principal image Fugen Bosatsu and is said to have been founded by Saicho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The temple is devoted to the principal image Fugen Bosatsu and is said to have been founded by Saicho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The temple is devoted to the principal image Fugen Bosatsu and is said to have been founded by Saicho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>皇族・貴族の子弟が歴代住持となる別格の寺院を指して「門跡」と称するが、妙法院は青蓮院、三千院（梶井門跡）とともに「天台三門跡」と並び称されてきた名門寺院である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myoho-in Temple is one of a special class of temples known as &apos;Monzeki&apos; which were traditionally served by successive head priests from the Imperial family and nobility, but is also distinguished as one of the &quot;Three Tendai Monzeki&quot; along with Shoren-in Temple and Manzen-in Temple (Kajii Monzeki).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myoho-in Temple is one of a special class of temples known as &apos;Monzeki&apos; which were traditionally served by successive head priests from the Imperial family and nobility, but is also distinguished as one of the &quot;Three Tendai Monzeki&quot; along with Shoren-in Temple and Manzen-in Temple (Kajii Monzeki).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myoho-in Temple is one of a special class of temples known as &apos;Monzeki&apos; which were traditionally served by successive head priests from the Imperial family and nobility, but is also distinguished as one of the &quot;Three Tendai Monzeki&quot; along with Shoren-in Temple and Sanzen-in Temple (Kajii Monzeki).</e>
<cmt>Manzen-in Temple→Sanzen-in Templeに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また、後白河天皇や豊臣秀吉ゆかりの寺院としても知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also known for its connection to Emperor Go-Shirakawa and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also known for its connection to Emperor Go-Shirakawa and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also known for its connection to Emperor Goshirakawa and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>Emperor Goshirakawaに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>近世には方広寺（大仏）や蓮華王院（三十三間堂）を管理下に置き、三十三間堂は近代以降も引き続き妙法院所管の仏堂となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the early modern period, the temple administered Hojo-ji Temple (Great Buddha) and Rengeo-in Temple (Sanjusangen-do Hall), with the Sanjusangen-do Hall remaining under Myoho-in Temple&apos;s jurisdiction following this period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the early modern period, the temple administered Hojo-ji Temple (Great Buddha) and Rengeo-in Temple (Sanjusangen-do Hall), with the Sanjusangen-do Hall remaining under Myoho-in Temple&apos;s jurisdiction following this period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the early modern period, the temple administered Hoko-ji Temple (Great Buddha) and Rengeo-in Temple (Sanjusangen-do Hall), with the Sanjusangen-do Hall remaining under Myoho-in Temple&apos;s jurisdiction following this period.</e>
<cmt>Hojo-ji Temple→Hoko-ji Templeに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>（三十三間堂については別項「三十三間堂」を参照。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Please refer to the separate article &apos;Sanjusangen-do&apos; for details regarding Sanjusangen-do Hall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Please refer to the separate article &apos;Sanjusangen-do&apos; for details regarding Sanjusangen-do Hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Please refer to the separate article &apos;Sanjusangen-do&apos; for details regarding Sanjusangen-do Hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>起源</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>妙法院は著名社寺が集中する京都市東山区南部に位置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myoho-in Temple is located within the southern part of Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City, renowned for its numerous prominent temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myoho-in Temple is located within the southern part of Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City, renowned for its numerous prominent temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myoho-in Temple is located within the southern part of Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City, renowned for its numerous prominent temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>付近は後白河法皇の居所であった法住寺殿の旧地であり、近隣には智積院、京都国立博物館、方広寺（大仏）、三十三間堂、新日吉神宮（いまひえじんぐう）、後白河法皇法住寺陵などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the vicinity is the former site of Hojuji-dono Palace in which Emperor Go-Shirakawa resided, and neighboring attractions include Chishaku-in Temple, the Kyoto National Museum, Hojo-ji Temple (Great Buddha), Sanjusangen-do Hall, Imahie-jingu Shrine and the mausoleum of Cloistered Emperor Go-Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the vicinity is the former site of Hojuji-dono Palace in which Emperor Go-Shirakawa resided, and neighboring attractions include Chishaku-in Temple, the Kyoto National Museum, Hojo-ji Temple (Great Buddha), Sanjusangen-do Hall, Imahie-jingu Shrine and the mausoleum of Cloistered Emperor Go-Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the vicinity is the former site of Hojuji-dono Palace in which Emperor Goshirakawa resided, and neighboring attractions include Chishaku-in Temple, the Kyoto National Museum, Hoko-ji Temple (Great Buddha), Sanjusangen-do Hall, Imahie-jingu Shrine and the Hoju-ji mausoleum of Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>Go-Shirakawa→Goshirakawa、Hojo-ji Temple→Hoko-ji Templeに修正、原文の「法住寺陵」に合わせ、&quot;the Hoju-ji mausoleum&quot;としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>近世初期建立の豪壮な庫裏（国宝）や大書院（重要文化財）などが建つが、寺内は秋季などの特別公開の時を除いて一般には公開されていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The buildings within the temple precinct include the magnificent (kuri) monks&apos; living quarters (National Treasure) constructed during the early modern period and the Daishoin (great study) (Important Cultural Property), but the temple grounds are not open to the public with the exception of special openings such as those in autumn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The buildings within the temple precinct include the magnificent (kuri) monks&apos; living quarters (National Treasure) constructed during the early modern period and the Daishoin (great study) (Important Cultural Property), but the temple grounds are not open to the public with the exception of special openings such as those in autumn.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The buildings within the temple precinct include the magnificent (kuri) monks&apos; living quarters (National Treasure) constructed during the early modern period and the Daishoin (great study) (Important Cultural Property), but the temple grounds are not open to the public with the exception of special openings such as those in autumn.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>天台宗の他の門跡寺院（青蓮院、三千院など）と同様、妙法院は比叡山上にあった坊（小寺院）がその起源とされ、初代門主は伝教大師最澄（767－822）とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As with other Tendai Sect Monzeki Temples (Shoren-in Temple and Manzen-in Temple), the origins of Myoho-in Temple are believed to lie in a bo (small temple) situated atop Mt. Hiei and the first chief priest is thought to have been Dengyo Daishi Saicho (767-822).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As with other Tendai Sect Monzeki Temples (Shoren-in Temple and Manzen-in Temple), the origins of Myoho-in Temple are believed to lie in a bo (small temple) situated atop Mt. Hiei and the first chief priest is thought to have been Dengyo Daishi Saicho (767-822).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As with other Tendai Sect Monzeki Temples (Shoren-in Temple and Sanzen-in Temple), the origins of Myoho-in Temple are believed to lie in a bo (small temple) situated atop Mt. Hiei and the first chief priest is thought to have been Dengyo Daishi Saicho (767-822).</e>
<cmt>Manzen-in Temple→Sanzen-in Templeに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その後、平安時代末期（12世紀）、後白河法皇の時代に洛中に移転し、一時は綾小路小坂（現在の京都市東山区・八坂神社の南西あたりと推定される）に所在したが、近世初期に現在地である法住寺殿跡地に移転した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The temple was later relocated to the center of Kyoto at the end of Heian period (12th century) during the reign of Emperor Go-Shirakawa, where it was temporarily located at Ayanokojikosaka (assumed to have been to the south-west of Yasaka-jinja Shrine in Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City) before being moved to its current location on the former site of Hojuji-dono Palace in the early modern period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The temple was later relocated to the center of Kyoto at the end of Heian period (12th century) during the reign of Emperor Go-Shirakawa, where it was temporarily located at Ayanokojikosaka (assumed to have been to the south-west of Yasaka-jinja Shrine in Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City) before being moved to its current location on the former site of Hojuji-dono Palace in the early modern period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The temple was later relocated to the center of Kyoto at the end of Heian period (12th century) during the reign of Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, where it was temporarily located at Ayanokojikosaka (assumed to have been to the south-west of Yasaka-jinja Shrine in Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City) before being moved to its current location on the former site of Hojuji-dono Palace in the early modern period.</e>
<cmt>後白河法皇→Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawaに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>『華頂要略』等の記録によると、比叡山三塔のうちの西塔に所在した「本覚院」が妙法院の起源とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to records such as &quot;Kachoyoryaku&quot;, &quot;Hongaku-in Temple&quot; located in the Saito area of Mt. Hiei is the origin of Myoho-in Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to records such as &quot;Kachoyoryaku&quot;, &quot;Hongaku-in Temple&quot; located in the Saito area of Mt. Hiei is the origin of Myoho-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to records such as &quot;Kachoyoryaku&quot;, &apos;Hongaku-in Temple&apos; located in the Saito area of Mt. Hiei is the origin of Myoho-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Hongaku-in Temple&quot;をシングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>しかし、妙法院と本覚院の関係は必ずしも明確でなく、本覚院から分かれて妙法院が成立したとする説、逆に妙法院から本覚院が分かれたとする説、妙法院は本覚院の別号だとする説などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the connection between Myoho-in Temple and Hongaku-in Temple is not known with any certainty, and there are theories that Myoho-in Temple was founded after separating from Honkaku-in Temple, opposing theories that Honkaku-in Temple separated from Myoho-in Temple, and a theory that Myoho-in Temple is an alias for Honkaku-in Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the connection between Myoho-in Temple and Hongaku-in Temple is not known with any certainty, and there are theories that Myoho-in Temple was founded after separating from Honkaku-in Temple, opposing theories that Honkaku-in Temple separated from Myoho-in Temple, and a theory that Myoho-in Temple is an alias for Honkaku-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the connection between Myoho-in Temple and Hongaku-in Temple is not known with any certainty, and there are theories that Myoho-in Temple was founded after separating from Hongaku-in Temple, opposing theories that Hongaku-in Temple separated from Myoho-in Temple, and a theory that Myoho-in Temple is an alias for Hongaku-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>Honkaku-in Temple→Hongaku-in Templeに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また、妙法院が比叡山から洛中に移転した時期、綾小路小坂から現在地に移転した時期についても正確なことは不明で、近世以前の寺史は錯綜している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the actual events that took place when Myoho-in Temple was moved to its current site from Ayanokojikosaka after it had been relocated to the center of Kyoto are unclear and the pre-modern history of the temple contains conflicting accounts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the actual events that took place when Myoho-in Temple was moved to its current site from Ayanokojikosaka after it had been relocated to the center of Kyoto are unclear and the pre-modern history of the temple contains conflicting accounts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the actual events that took place when Myoho-in Temple was moved to its current site from Ayanokojikosaka after it had been relocated to the center of Kyoto are unclear and the pre-modern history of the temple contains conflicting accounts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>後白河法皇と尊性法親王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cloistered Emperor Go-Shirakawa and Prince Sonsho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cloistered Emperor Go-Shirakawa and Prince Sonsho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa and Cloistered Imperial Prince Sonsho</e>
<cmt>Goshirakawaに修正、法親王を統一修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>事実上、妙法院が日本史に登場するのは後白河法皇の時代である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first actual account of Myoho-in Temple appears in the history of Japan during the time of Cloistered Emperor Go-Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first actual account of Myoho-in Temple appears in the history of Japan during the time of Cloistered Emperor Go-Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first actual account of Myoho-in Temple appears in the history of Japan during the time of Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>Goshirakawaに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>後白河天皇（1127－1192）は、在位3年足らずで譲位し、保元3年（1158年）には太上天皇、嘉応元年（1169年）には出家して法皇となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Go-Shirakawa (1127-1192) abdicated the throne after reigning for fewer than three years; becoming a retired emperor in 1158 and entering the Buddhist priesthood to serve as a cloistered emperor in 1169.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Go-Shirakawa (1127-1192) abdicated the throne after reigning for fewer than three years; becoming a retired emperor in 1158 and entering the Buddhist priesthood to serve as a cloistered emperor in 1169.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Goshirakawa (1127-1192) abdicated the throne after reigning for fewer than three years; becoming a retired emperor in 1158 and entering the Buddhist priesthood to serve as a cloistered emperor in 1169.</e>
<cmt>Goshirakawaに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>この間、後白河上皇は譲位後の居所（院御所）である法住寺殿の造営を進め、永暦2年（1161年）からはここに住むようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was during this time that the Retired Emperor Go-Shirakawa constructed his residence (In-Gosho) at Hojuji-dono Palace, which he moved into in 1161.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was during this time that the Retired Emperor Go-Shirakawa constructed his residence (In-Gosho) at Hojuji-dono Palace, which he moved into in 1161.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was during this time that the Retired Emperor Goshirakawa constructed his residence (In-Gosho) at Hojuji-dono Palace, which he moved into in 1161.</e>
<cmt>Goshirakawaに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>ここで院政が行われ、また御所の西側に千体千手観音像を安置する巨大な仏堂（蓮華王院＝三十三間堂）が建てられたことは史上名高い（三十三間堂の落慶は長寛2年/1164年）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was from here that he exerted cloistered rule and famously constructed an enormous Buddha hall (Rengeo-in Temple = Sanjusangen-do Hall) housing 1,000 statues of the thousand-armed Kannon (the celebration of Sanjusangen-do Hall&apos;s completion took place in 1164).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was from here that he exerted cloistered rule and famously constructed an enormous Buddha hall (Rengeo-in Temple = Sanjusangen-do Hall) housing 1,000 statues of the thousand-armed Kannon (the celebration of Sanjusangen-do Hall&apos;s completion took place in 1164).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was from here that he exerted cloistered rule and famously constructed an enormous Buddha hall (Rengeo-in Temple = Sanjusangen-do Hall) housing 1,000 statues of the thousand-armed Kannon (the celebration of Sanjusangen-do Hall&apos;s completion took place in 1164).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>後白河上皇は永暦元年（1160年）、御所の鎮守社として比叡山の鎮守社である日吉社を勧請し、新日吉社（いまひえしゃ）とした（新日吉社は「新日吉神宮」として現代まで存続している）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1160, the Retired Emperor Go-Shirakawa had the divided tutelary deity of Mt. Hiei&apos;s guardian god Hie-sha Shrine transferred to his temple and established Ima Hie-sha Shrine (Ima Hie-sha Shrine survives today as &quot;Ima Hie-jigu Shrine&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1160, the Retired Emperor Go-Shirakawa had the divided tutelary deity of Mt. Hiei&apos;s guardian god Hie-sha Shrine transferred to his temple and established Ima Hie-sha Shrine (Ima Hie-sha Shrine survives today as &quot;Ima Hie-jigu Shrine&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1160, the Retired Emperor Goshirakawa had the divided tutelary deity of Mt. Hiei&apos;s guardian god Hie-sha Shrine transferred to his temple and established Ima Hie-sha Shrine (Ima Hie-sha Shrine survives today as &quot;Ima Hie-jingu Shrine&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Goshirakawaに修正、Ima Hie-jigu→Ima Hie-jinguに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>この新日吉社の初代別当（代表者、責任者）に任命されたのが妙法院の昌雲という僧であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first Betto (representative, person responsible) to be assigned to Ima Hie-sha Shrine was a monk from Myoho-in Temple named Unsho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first Betto (representative, person responsible) to be assigned to Ima Hie-sha Shrine was a monk from Myoho-in Temple named Unsho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first Betto (representative, person responsible) to be assigned to Ima Hie-sha Shrine was a monk from Myoho-in Temple named Shoun.</e>
<cmt>昌雲の表記をUnsho→Shounに訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>昌雲は御子左家（みこひだりけ）の藤原忠成の子であり、天台座主（天台宗最高の地位）を務めた快修の甥にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unsho was the son of FUJIWARA no Tadanari of the Miko Hidari family and the nephew of Kaishu who held the position of Tendai Zasu (the highest post of Tendai sect).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unsho was the son of FUJIWARA no Tadanari of the Miko Hidari family and the nephew of Kaishu who held the position of Tendai Zasu (the highest post of Tendai sect).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoun was the son of FUJIWARA no Tadanari of the Miko Hidari family and the nephew of Kaishu who held the position of Tendai Zasu (the highest post of Tendai sect).</e>
<cmt>昌雲の表記をUnsho→Shounに訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>昌雲は後白河上皇の護持僧であり、上皇からの信頼が篤かったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unsho was the private guardian monk of and was highly trusted by Retired Emperor Go-Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unsho was the private guardian monk of and was highly trusted by Retired Emperor Go-Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoun was the private guardian monk of and was highly trusted by the Retired Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>Unsho→Shounに訂正、the Retired Emperor Goshirakawaに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>妙法院の門主系譜では最澄を初代として、13代が快修、15代が後白河法皇（法名は行真）、16代が昌雲となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saicho was the 1st in the line of Myoho-in chief priests, the 13th was Kaishu, the 15th was Cloistered Emperor Go-Shirakawa (under the Buddhist priest name &apos;Gyoshin&apos;), and the 16th was Uncho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saicho was the 1st in the line of Myoho-in chief priests, the 13th was Kaishu, the 15th was Cloistered Emperor Go-Shirakawa (under the Buddhist priest name &apos;Gyoshin&apos;), and the 16th was Uncho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saicho was the 1st in the line of Myoho-in chief priests, the 13th was Kaishu, the 15th was Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa (under the Buddhist priest name &apos;Gyoshin&apos;), and the 16th was Shoun.</e>
<cmt>Uncho→Shounに訂正、Goshirakawaに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>続く17代門主の実全（昌雲の弟子で甥でもある）も後に天台座主になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 17th chief priest Jitsuzen (the disciple and nephew of Shoun) went on to become Tendai Zasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 17th chief priest Jitsuzen (the disciple and nephew of Shoun) went on to become Tendai Zasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 17th chief priest Jitsuzen (the disciple and nephew of Shoun) went on to become Tendai Zasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>18代門主として尊性法親王（後高倉院皇子）が入寺してからは門跡寺院としての地位が確立し、近世末期に至るまで歴代門主の大部分が法親王（皇族で出家後に親王宣下を受けた者を指す）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The temple was established as a Monzeki Temple when Prince Sonsho (Prince Go-Takakura-in) served at the temple as the 18th chief priest, and the majority of the successive chief priests until the end of the early modern period were Hoshinno (an individual awarded the rank of &apos;Shinno&apos; after leaving the Imperial family to enter the Buddhist priesthood).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The temple was established as a Monzeki Temple when Prince Sonsho (Prince Go-Takakura-in) served at the temple as the 18th chief priest, and the majority of the successive chief priests until the end of the early modern period were Hoshinno (an individual awarded the rank of &apos;Shinno&apos; after leaving the Imperial family to enter the Buddhist priesthood).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The temple was established as a Monzeki Temple when Cloistered Imperial Prince Sonsho (a prince of Gotakakurain) served at the temple as the 18th chief priest, and the majority of the successive chief priests until the end of the early modern period were Cloistered Imperial Prince (an individual awarded the rank of &apos;Imperial Prince&apos; after leaving the Imperial family to enter the Buddhist priesthood).</e>
<cmt>尊性法親王（後高倉院皇子）→Cloistered Imperial Prince Sonsho (a prince of Gotakakurain)に修正、Hoshinno→Cloistered Imperial Prince、Shinno→Imperial Princeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="27">
<j>鎌倉時代の妙法院は「綾小路房」「綾小路御所」「綾小路宮」などと呼ばれたことが記録からわかり、現在の京都市東山区祇園町南側あたりに主要な房舎が存在したと思われるが、方広寺大仏に隣接する現在地への移転の時期などは正確にはわかっていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is known from records that Moho-in Temple was known by a number of names including &quot;Ayanokoji-bo&quot;, &quot;Ayanokoji Gosho&quot; (Ayanokoji Imperial Palace) and Ayanokoji-gu&quot; during the Kamakura period, and it is believed that the main temple quarters existed in the south of Gionmchi Minamigawa, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City but it is not known exactly when the temple was relocated to its current site adjacent to Great Buddha temple of Hoko-ji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is known from records that Moho-in Temple was known by a number of names including &quot;Ayanokoji-bo&quot;, &quot;Ayanokoji Gosho&quot; (Ayanokoji Imperial Palace) and Ayanokoji-gu&quot; during the Kamakura period, and it is believed that the main temple quarters existed in the south of Gionmchi Minamigawa, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City but it is not known exactly when the temple was relocated to its current site adjacent to Great Buddha temple of Hoko-ji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is known from records that Myoho-in Temple was known by a number of names including &apos;Ayanokoji-bo&apos;, &apos;Ayanokoji Gosho&apos; (Ayanokoji Imperial Palace) and &apos;Ayanokoji-gu&apos; during the Kamakura period, and it is believed that the main temple quarters existed in Gionmachi-Minamigawa, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City but it is not known exactly when the temple was relocated to its current site adjacent to Great Buddha of Hoko-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更、Moho-in Temple→Myoho-in Temple、in the south of Gionmchi Minamigawa→in Gionmachi-Minamigawa (住所名)、Great Buddha temple of Hoko-ji→Great Buddha of Hoko-ji Templeに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>近世以降</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Early Modern Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Early Modern Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Early Modern Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>豊臣秀吉が造営していた方広寺の大仏殿が完成したのは文禄4年（1595年）のことであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Great Buddha Hall constructed by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI at Hoko-ji Temple was completed in 1595.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Great Buddha Hall constructed by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI at Hoko-ji Temple was completed in 1595.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Great Buddha Hall constructed by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI at Hoko-ji Temple was completed in 1595.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>この年以降、秀吉は亡父母や先祖の菩提を弔うため、当時の日本仏教の八宗（天台、真言、律、禅、浄土、日蓮、時、一向）の僧を集めた「千僧供養」を「大仏経堂」で行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following this year, Hideyoshi assembled monks from the eight Buddhist sects of Japan (Tendai, Shingon, Ritsu, Zen, Pure Land, Niciren, Ji, Ikko) to hold a &quot;Senso Kuyo&quot; (a memorial service attended by 1,000 monks) at the &quot;Daibutsu Kyodo&quot; (Great Buddha Sutra Hall) to pray for the happiness of his deceased parents and ancestors in the afterlife.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following this year, Hideyoshi assembled monks from the eight Buddhist sects of Japan (Tendai, Shingon, Ritsu, Zen, Pure Land, Niciren, Ji, Ikko) to hold a &quot;Senso Kuyo&quot; (a memorial service attended by 1,000 monks) at the &quot;Daibutsu Kyodo&quot; (Great Buddha Sutra Hall) to pray for the happiness of his deceased parents and ancestors in the afterlife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following this year, Hideyoshi assembled monks from the eight Buddhist sects of Japan (Tendai, Shingon, Ritsu, Zen, Pure Land, Niciren, Ji, Ikko) to hold a &apos;Senso Kuyo&apos; (a memorial service attended by 1,000 monks) at the &apos;Daibutsu Kyodo&apos; (Great Buddha Sutra Hall) to pray for the happiness of his deceased parents and ancestors in the afterlife.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>この「大仏経堂」は妙法院に所属し、千僧供養に出仕する千人もの僧の食事を準備した台所が、現存する妙法院庫裏（国宝）だとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This Great Buddha Sutra Hall was associated with Myoho-in Temple and the kitchen used to prepare the food for the 1,000 monks who attended the Senso Kuyo is thought to be the kuri (kitchen and living quarters) at Myoho-in Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Great Buddha Sutra Hall was associated with Myoho-in Temple and the kitchen used to prepare the food for the 1,000 monks who attended the Senso Kuyo is thought to be the kuri (kitchen and living quarters) at Myoho-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Great Buddha Sutra Hall was associated with Myoho-in Temple and the kitchen used to prepare the food for the 1,000 monks who attended the Senso Kuyo is thought to be the kuri (kitchen and living quarters) at Myoho-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>庫裏自体の正確な建立年代は不明だが、秀吉の千僧供養に妙法院が関与していたことは当時の日記や文書から明らかであり、妙法院は遅くとも16世紀末には現在地へ移転していたことがわかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The precise date of the construction of the kuri is unclear but it is clear from diaries and books of the time that Myoho-in Temple was involved in Hideyoshi&apos;s Senso Kuyo, allowing the latest date of the relocation of the temple to its current site to be placed at the end of the 16th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The precise date of the construction of the kuri is unclear but it is clear from diaries and books of the time that Myoho-in Temple was involved in Hideyoshi&apos;s Senso Kuyo, allowing the latest date of the relocation of the temple to its current site to be placed at the end of the 16th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The precise date of the construction of the kuri is unclear but it is clear from diaries and books of the time that Myoho-in Temple was involved in Hideyoshi&apos;s Senso Kuyo, allowing the latest date of the relocation of the temple to its current site to be placed at the end of the 16th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="32">
<j>近世の妙法院は、方広寺、蓮華王院（三十三間堂）、新日吉社を兼帯する大寺院であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early modern period Hoko-ji Temple, Rengeo-in Temple (Sanjusangen-do Hall) and Ima Hie-sha Shrine existed as a single large temple complex.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early modern period Hoko-ji Temple, Rengeo-in Temple (Sanjusangen-do Hall) and Ima Hie-sha Shrine existed as a single large temple complex.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myoho-in Temple in the early modern period existed as a large temple complex with Hoko-ji Temple, Rengeo-in Temple (Sanjusangen-do Hall) and Ima Hie-sha Shrine.</e>
<cmt>原文の「妙法院が～を兼帯する大寺院であった」という内容に沿うよう訳文を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>妙法院門主が方広寺住職を兼務するようになったのは元和 (日本)元年（1615年）からである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was 1615 when the chief priest of Myoho-in Temple also came to serve as the chief priest of Hoko-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was 1615 when the chief priest of Myoho-in Temple also came to serve as the chief priest of Hoko-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was 1615 when the chief priest of Myoho-in Temple also came to serve as the chief priest of Hoko-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>これは大坂の陣で豊臣宗家が江戸幕府に滅ぼされたことを受けての沙汰である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This resulted from the destruction of the Toyotomi family by the Edo Shogunate in the Siege of Osaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This resulted from the destruction of the Toyotomi family by the Edo Shogunate in the Siege of Osaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This resulted from the destruction of the Toyotomi family by the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) in the Siege of Osaka.</e>
<cmt>江戸幕府→統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>戦後幕府によって進められた豊国神社 (京都市)破却の流れのなかで、当時の妙法院門主であった常胤は積極的に幕府に協力、豊国神社に保管された秀吉の遺品や神宮寺（豊国神社別当神龍院梵舜の役宅）を横領することに成功している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the battle, Join, the then chief priest of Myoho-in Temple, actively cooperated with the Shogunate in their destruction of Toyokuni-jinja Shrine (Kyoto City) and was successful in embezzling Jingu-ji Temple (residential office of Toyokuni-jinja Shrine&apos;s steward Shinryu-in Bonshun) and the possessions of the deceased Hideyoshi that were kept in Toyokuni-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the battle, Join, the then chief priest of Myoho-in Temple, actively cooperated with the Shogunate in their destruction of Toyokuni-jinja Shrine (Kyoto City) and was successful in embezzling Jingu-ji Temple (residential office of Toyokuni-jinja Shrine&apos;s steward Shinryu-in Bonshun) and the possessions of the deceased Hideyoshi that were kept in Toyokuni-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the battle, Join, the then chief priest of Myoho-in Temple, actively cooperated with the bakufu in their destruction of Toyokuni-jinja Shrine (Kyoto City) and was successful in embezzling Jingu-ji Temple (residential office of Toyokuni-jinja Shrine&apos;s steward Shinryu-in Bonshun) and the possessions of the deceased Hideyoshi that were kept in Toyokuni-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>Shogunate→bakufuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>三十三間堂については、創立者である後白河法皇との関係から、早くから妙法院が関与していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myoho-in Temple had been involved with Sanjusangen-do Hall from early on due to the relationship with the founder, Cloistered Emperor Go-Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myoho-in Temple had been involved with Sanjusangen-do Hall from early on due to the relationship with the founder, Cloistered Emperor Go-Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myoho-in Temple had been involved with Sanjusangen-do Hall from early on due to the relationship with the founder, Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>Goshirakawaに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>正応4年（1291年）の後白河法皇百回忌供養は、妙法院門主の尊教が三十三間堂において行っており、以後、50年ごとの聖忌供養は妙法院門主が三十三間堂にて行うことが慣例となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ninety-ninth anniversary memorial service of Cloistered Emperor Go-Shirakawa&apos;s death was conducted at Sanjusangen-do Hall by Sonkyo, the chief priest of Myoho-in Temple, following which it became customary to hold each 50-yearly memorial service on the site.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ninety-ninth anniversary memorial service of Cloistered Emperor Go-Shirakawa&apos;s death was conducted at Sanjusangen-do Hall by Sonkyo, the chief priest of Myoho-in Temple, following which it became customary to hold each 50-yearly memorial service on the site.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ninety-ninth anniversary memorial service of Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa&apos;s death in 1291 was conducted at Sanjusangen-do Hall by Sonkyo, the chief priest of Myoho-in Temple, following which it became customary to hold each 50-yearly memorial service on the site.</e>
<cmt>Goshirakawaに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>近代に入って方広寺と新日吉社は独立したが、三十三間堂は現代に至るまで妙法院の所属となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In modern times, Hoko-ji Temple and Ima Hie-sha Shrine became independent but Sanjusangen-do Hall remains part of Myoho-in Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In modern times, Hoko-ji Temple and Ima Hie-sha Shrine became independent but Sanjusangen-do Hall remains part of Myoho-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In modern times, Hoko-ji Temple and Ima Hie-sha Shrine became independent but Sanjusangen-do Hall remains part of Myoho-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="39">
<j>妙法院は、幕末には、三条実美ら尊皇攘夷派の公卿7人が京都から追放された「七卿落ち」の舞台ともなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myoho-in Temple was where seven Kugyo (court nobles) of Sanetomi SANJO&apos;s &quot;Sonno joi&quot; (Revere the Emperor, Expel the Barbarians) movement were expelled from Kyoto at the end of the Edo period in an incident known as &quot;The Seven Nobles of Decline&quot;.</e>
<cmt>「七卿落ち」→&quot;Shichikyo-ochi&quot;, &quot;Seven nobles of decline&quot;[http://www.ndl.go.jp/portrait/e/datas/97.html]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myoho-in Temple was where seven Kugyo (court nobles) of Sanetomi SANJO&apos;s &quot;Sonno joi&quot; (Revere the Emperor, Expel the Barbarians) movement were expelled from Kyoto at the end of the Edo period in an incident known as &quot;The Seven Nobles of Decline&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myoho-in Temple was where seven Kugyo (court nobles) of Sanetomi SANJO&apos;s &quot;Sonno joi&quot; (Revere the Emperor, Expel the Barbarians) movement were expelled from Kyoto at the end of the Edo period in an incident known as &apos;The Seven Nobles of Decline.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一部シングルクォーテーションに変更、ピリオドの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>伽藍</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buildings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buildings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buildings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="40">
<j>伽藍は西側を正面とし、東大路通りに面して唐門と通用門がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The front of the temple complex is to the south and the kara-mon gate and side gate face onto Higashioji-dori Road.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The front of the temple complex is to the south and the kara-mon gate and side gate face onto Higashioji-dori Road.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The front of the temple complex is to the west and the Kara-mon gate (Chinese gate) and side gate face onto Higashioji-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>「西側」なので&quot;to the west&quot;に訂正、Kara-mon gate (Chinese gate), Higashioji-dori Streetとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>境内は西側正面に玄関、その左手に庫裏、右手に宸殿が建ち、東側の境内奥には大書院、白書院、護摩堂、聖天堂などが建つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The entrance is on the western side of the precinct; the kuri stands to its left; the Emperor&apos;s residence stands to its right; and in the east of the grounds are the Daishoin (Great Study), the Shiroshoin (White Study Room), the Goma-do (hall for making burnt offerings) and the Seiten-do Hall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The entrance is on the western side of the precinct; the kuri stands to its left; the Emperor&apos;s residence stands to its right; and in the east of the grounds are the Daishoin (Great Study), the Shiroshoin (White Study Room), the Goma-do (hall for making burnt offerings) and the Seiten-do Hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The entrance is on the western side of the precincts; the Kuri (the priest&apos;s living quarters or the kitchen of a temple) stands to its left; the Shinden (Emperor&apos;s residence) stands to its right; and in the east of the grounds are the Daishoin (Great Study), the Shiroshoin (White Study Room), the Goma-do Hall (hall for making burnt offerings) and the Seiten-do Hall.</e>
<cmt>precinctsとし、他と表記を統一するため、庫裏→Kuri (the priest&apos;s living quarters or the kitchen of a temple), 宸殿→Shinden (Emperor&apos;s residence), Goma-do Hallとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>これらの堂宇の間は渡り廊下でつながれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These halls are linked by covered passageways.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These halls are linked by covered passageways.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These halls are linked by covered passageways.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>本尊普賢菩薩を安置する本堂（普賢堂）は、やや離れた境内東南方に建つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main hall housing the principal image statue of Fugen Bosatsu (Fugen-do Hall) stands slightly distant in the southeast of the temple precinct.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main hall housing the principal image statue of Fugen Bosatsu (Fugen-do Hall) stands slightly distant in the southeast of the temple precinct.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main hall housing the principal image statue of Fugen Bosatsu (Fugen-do Hall) stands slightly distant in the southeast of the temple precincts.</e>
<cmt>precinctsとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>国宝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National Treasures</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National Treasures</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National Treasures</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="44">
<j>庫裏－桃山時代の建築。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuri: Constructed during the Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuri: Constructed during the Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuri: Constructed during the Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>庫裏は寺院の台所兼事務所の役割を果たす内向きの建物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The kuri is an inward-facing building that serves as the temple kitchen and office.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kuri is an inward-facing building that serves as the temple kitchen and office.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kuri is an inward-facing building that serves as the temple kitchen and office.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>妙法院庫裏は、豊臣秀吉が先祖のための「千僧供養」を行った際の台所として使用されたと伝える豪壮な建物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The kuri of Myoho-in Temple is a grand building that is said to have been used as the kitchen during the &quot;Senso Kuyo&quot; ceremony held by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI for his ancestors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kuri of Myoho-in Temple is a grand building that is said to have been used as the kitchen during the &quot;Senso Kuyo&quot; ceremony held by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI for his ancestors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kuri of Myoho-in Temple is a grand building that is said to have been used as the kitchen during the &apos;Senso Kuyo&apos; ceremony held by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI for his ancestors.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>庫裏は屋根を切妻造とするものが多いが、当院の庫裏は入母屋造とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many kuri feature a kirizuma-zukuri (gable roof) but that of Myoho-in Temple is of an irimoya-zukuri (hip and gable roof) construction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many kuri feature a kirizuma-zukuri (gable roof) but that of Myoho-in Temple is of an irimoya-zukuri (hip and gable roof) construction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many kuri feature a kirizuma-zukuri (gable roof) but that of Myoho-in Temple is of an irimoya-zukuri (hip and gable roof) construction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>内部は土間、板間、座敷の3部分に分かれ、土間・板間部分は天井板を張らず、貫・梁などの構造材をそのまま見せた豪快な造りになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The interior is divided into an unfloored room, a wooden-floored room and a tatami-mat room, of which the unfloored and wooden-floored rooms do not have ceilings but allow the nuki (penetrating tie beams) and hari (beams) to be seen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The interior is divided into an unfloored room, a wooden-floored room and a tatami-mat room, of which the unfloored and wooden-floored rooms do not have ceilings but allow the nuki (penetrating tie beams) and hari (beams) to be seen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The interior is divided into an unfloored room, a wooden-floored room and a tatami-mat room, of which the unfloored and wooden-floored rooms do not have ceilings but allow the nuki (penetrating tie beams) and hari (beams) to be seen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="49">
<j>ポルトガル国印度副王親書－1588年（日本の天正16年）、インド半島西岸に位置するポルトガル領ゴア州の副王から豊臣秀吉に宛てた羊皮紙の書簡で、内容は当時の日本が行っていたキリスト教弾圧政策の緩和を求めたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Letter written by the Viceroy of Portuguese India: A sheepskin-paper letter from the Viceroy of the Portuguese-ruled state of Goa on the western coast of the Indian peninsula addressed to Hidetoshi TOYOTOMI requesting the relaxation of the oppressive policy towards Christianity in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Letter written by the Viceroy of Portuguese India: A sheepskin-paper letter from the Viceroy of the Portuguese-ruled state of Goa on the western coast of the Indian peninsula addressed to Hidetoshi TOYOTOMI requesting the relaxation of the oppressive policy towards Christianity in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Letter written by the Viceroy of Portuguese India: In 1588, a sheepskin-paper letter from the Viceroy of the Portuguese-ruled state of Goa on the western coast of the Indian peninsula addressed to Hidetoshi TOYOTOMI requesting the relaxation of the oppressive policy towards Christianity in Japan.</e>
<cmt>年号補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>豊臣秀吉を祀る豊国廟が破却された際、妙法院に移管された品の1つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of the items that were transferred to Myoho-in Temple when the Toyokuni Tomb enshrining Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI was destroyed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is one of the items that were transferred to Myoho-in Temple when the Toyokuni Tomb enshrining Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI was destroyed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is one of the items that were transferred to Myoho-in Temple when the Toyokuni Tomb enshrining Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI was destroyed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>重要文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="51">
<j>大書院－大書院と玄関は、元和5年（1619年）、東福門院入内の際に建築された女御御所の建物を移築したものと伝え、様式的にもその頃のものと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daishoin (Great study): The great study and entry hall are said to be the relocated Nyogo Gosho (court lady&apos;s palace) that was built when the imperial bridal party entered Tofukumon-in Temple, and stylistically is thought to date from around that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daishoin (Great study): The great study and entry hall are said to be the relocated Nyogo Gosho (court lady&apos;s palace) that was built when the imperial bridal party entered Tofukumon-in Temple, and stylistically is thought to date from around that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daishoin (Great study): The great study and entry hall are said to be the relocated Nyogo Gosho (court lady&apos;s palace) that was built when the imperial bridal party entered Tofukumon-in Temple in 1619, and stylistically is thought to date from around that time.</e>
<cmt>年号補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="52">
<j>玄関</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Entry hall</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Entry hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Entry hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>絹本著色後白河法皇像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Color on silk portrait of Cloistered Emperor Go-Shirakawa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Color on silk portrait of Cloistered Emperor Go-Shirakawa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Color painting on silk portrait of Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa</e>
<cmt>絹本著色→統一リストの表記に修正、Goshirakawaに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>妙法院障壁画　58面（附14面、1基）－玄関、大書院一之間・二之間の障壁画で、近世初期の狩野派の作と思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myoho-in Temple wall and sliding door paintings (including 14 walls and one screen): Consist of the wall and sliding screen paintings in the entry hall, Ichi-no-ma (room one) and Ni-no-ma (room two), and are thought to be the works of early modern Kano School artists.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myoho-in Temple wall and sliding door paintings (including 14 walls and one screen): Consist of the wall and sliding screen paintings in the entry hall, Ichi-no-ma (room one) and Ni-no-ma (room two), and are thought to be the works of early modern Kano School artists.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myoho-in Temple wall and sliding door paintings, 58 pieces (including 14 walls and one screen): Consist of the wall and sliding screen paintings in the entry hall, Ichi no ma (room one) and Ni no ma (room two), and are thought to be the works of early modern Kano School artists.</e>
<cmt>Ichi-no-ma, Ni-no-maのハイフンをとりました。 58 pieces 補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>大書院裏之間の障壁画14面と玄関所在の衝立1基は附（つけたり）指定となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 14 pieces in the Ura-no-ma (back room) of the great study and the screen in the entry hall are also included in the designation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 14 pieces in the Ura-no-ma (back room) of the great study and the screen in the entry hall are also included in the designation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 14 pieces in the Ura no ma (back room) of the great study and the screen in the entry hall are also included in the designation.</e>
<cmt>Ura-no-maのハイフンをとりました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="56">
<j>木造不動明王立像－護摩堂本尊。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wooden standing statue of Fudo Myoo: The principal image of the Goma-do Hall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wooden standing statue of Fudo Myoo: The principal image of the Goma-do Hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wooden standing statue of Fudo Myoo: The principal image of the Goma-do Hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>平安時代前期。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Created during the first part of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Created during the first part of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Created during the first part of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="58">
<j>木造普賢菩薩騎象像－本堂（普賢堂）本尊。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wooden statue of Fugen Bosatsu riding an elephant: The principal image of the main hall (Fugen-do Hall).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wooden statue of Fugen Bosatsu riding an elephant: The principal image of the main hall (Fugen-do Hall).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wooden statue of Fugen Bosatsu riding an elephant: The principal image of the main hall (Fugen-do Hall).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>平安時代末期。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Created at the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Created at the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Created at the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="60">
<j>秋草蒔絵文台</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akikusa Makie Bundai (a writing desk with gold-lacquered autumn flowers)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akikusa Makie Bundai (a writing desk with gold-lacquered autumn flowers)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akikusa Makie Bundai (a writing desk with gold-lacquered autumn flowers)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>内証仏法相承血脈譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naishobuppo sojo-kechimyaku-fu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naishobuppo sojo-kechimyaku-fu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naishobuppo sojo-kechimyaku-fu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>後小松天皇宸翰消息</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A letter written by Emperor Go-Komatsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A letter written by Emperor Go-Komatsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A letter written by Emperor Gokomatsu</e>
<cmt>Emperor Gokomatsuに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>堂供養記（春記、大記）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Do Kuyo-ki (shunki and daiki)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Do Kuyo-ki (shunki and daiki)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Do Kuyo-ki (shunki and daiki)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>アクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="64">
<j>（所在地）京都市東山区東大路通り渋谷下ル妙法院前側町</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Location: Myohoin Maekawa-cho, Shibutani sagaru, Higashioji-dori Street, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Location: Myohoin Maekawa-cho, Shibutani sagaru, Higashioji-dori Street, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Location: Myohoin Maekawa-cho, Shibutani-sagaru, Higashioji Street, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City</e>
<cmt>一部統一事項の表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>（アクセス）京都市営バス東山七条バス停下車すぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access: Near to the Kyoto City Bus Higashiyama Shichijo bus stop.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access: Near to the Kyoto City Bus Higashiyama Shichijo bus stop.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access: Near to the Kyoto City Bus Higashiyama Shichijo bus stop.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>（通常は非公開。例年11月頃に特別公開あり）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Not ordinarily open to the public. Specially opened around November each year.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Not ordinarily open to the public. Specially opened around November each year.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Not ordinarily open to the public. Specially opened around November each year.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MURMUR4040(id:27173), Yonoemon(id:55450), KMT(id:1772), 与左衛門(id:159462), Reggaeman(id:6214), Urania(id:7213), 663highland(id:18755), Extrahitz(id:26245), Toki-ho(id:10691), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>