<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>栄山寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eisan-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eisan-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eisan-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>栄山寺 （えいさんじ） は奈良県五條市にある真言宗豊山派の寺院。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eisan-ji Temple is a Shingon Shu sect Houzan Ha temple in Gojo City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eisan-ji Temple is a temple of the Hozan School of the Shingon Sect located in Gojo City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>指示書に従い変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eisan-ji Temple is a temple of the Hozan School of the Shingon Sect located in Gojo City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原武智麻呂（むちまろ）により創建された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was established by FUJIWARA no Muchimaro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was established by FUJIWARA no Muchimaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was established by FUJIWARA no Muchimaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>山号は学晶山（がくしょうさん）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sango is Gakushosan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its sango (literally, &quot;mountain name&quot;), which is the title prefixed to the name of a Buddhist temple, is Gakushosan.</e>
<cmt>説明を補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its sango (literally, &quot;mountain name&quot;), which is the title prefixed to the name of a Buddhist temple, is Gakushosan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>本尊は薬師如来。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honzon is Yakushi Nyorai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its honzon (the principal image of Buddha) is Yakushi Nyorai.</e>
<cmt>説明を補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its honzon (the principal image of Buddha) is Yakushi Nyorai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>奈良時代の建築である八角堂（国宝）があることで知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is known for its Hakkakudo (an octagonal hall, considered a national treasures) a feature of the architecture of the Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is known for Hakkakudo (an octagonal hall designated as a national treasure), which was built in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>文法ミスを直し、表現も変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is known for Hakkakudo (an octagonal hall designated as a national treasure), which was built in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>現代の五條市にあたる地域は古代には阿陀郷と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The area of current Gojo City was called Amida no Sato in ancient times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The area of current Gojo City was called Amida no Sato in ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The area of current Gojo City was called Amida no Sato in ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>「阿陀」の地名は『万葉集』にも見え、式内社（『延喜式神名帳』に記載された神社）の阿陀比売神社（あだひめじんじゃ）があるなど早くから開けた地域であったと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of land of &apos;Amida&apos; is mentioned in &quot;Manyo Shu,&quot; and also that Ada Hime Jinja Shrine was located that is Shikinaisha (the shrine mentioned in &quot;Engishiki Jinmyocho&quot;), so it is thought that it was civilized since early times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The place name of &apos;Amida&apos; is mentioned in &quot;Manyo Shu&quot; (the oldest anthology of tanka), and Adahime-Jinja Shrine, which is one of Shikinai-sha (shrines listed in &quot;Engishiki Jinmyocho&quot; [a shrine list written in Engishiki, an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers]), lies in this area; these facts suggest that this area was civilized early.</e>
<cmt>文法ミスを直し、万葉集、式内社の意味を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The place name of &apos;Amida&apos; is mentioned in &quot;Manyo Shu&quot; (the oldest anthology of tanka), and Adahime-Jinja Shrine, which is one of Shikinai-sha (shrines listed in &quot;Engishiki Jinmyocho&quot; [a shrine list written in Engishiki, an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers]), lies in this area; these facts suggest that this area was civilized early.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>栄山寺は古くは前山寺（さきやまでら）と呼ばれ、藤原不比等の長子である武智麻呂が養老3年（719年）に創建したと伝わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eisan-ji was previously known as Sakiyamadera as its old name and constructed by Muchimaro, FUJIWARA no Huhito&apos;s eldest son, in 719.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eisan-ji Temple was previously known as Sakiyama-dera Temple, which is said to have been erected by Muchimaro, FUJIWARA no Huhito&apos;s eldest son, in 719.</e>
<cmt>Templeを加えました。「と伝わる」部の訳漏れあり、補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eisan-ji Temple was previously known as Sakiyama-dera Temple, which is said to have been erected by Muchimaro, FUJIWARA no Huhito&apos;s eldest son, in 719.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その後、武智麻呂を祖とする藤原南家の菩提寺として鎌倉時代になるまで大いに栄えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It flourished as FUJIWARA Nanke family&apos;s family temple until the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, it flourished as the Fujiwara Nanke family&apos;s family temple until the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>Fujiwaraを小文字に変更し、After thatを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, it flourished as the Fujiwara Nanke family&apos;s family temple until the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>南北朝時代には南朝の後村上天皇・長慶天皇・後亀山天皇の行在所が置かれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Nanbokucho (South and North courts) period, Anzaisho (temporary accommodation built to accommodate an Imperial visit) was located here which was for Nancho&apos;s Emperor Gomurakami, Emperor Chokei and Emperor Gokameyama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the period of the Northern and the Southern Courts (Japan), an Anzaisho (a temporary lodging built to accommodate an Imperial visit) for the emperors of the Southern Court, Emperor Gomurakami, Emperor Chokei and Emperor Gokameyama, was placed here.</e>
<cmt>統一用語リストに従い用語を変更しました（南北朝時代）。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the period of the Northern and the Southern Courts (Japan), an Anzaisho (a temporary lodging built to accommodate an Imperial visit) for the emperors of the Southern Court, Emperor Gomurakami, Emperor Chokei and Emperor Gokameyama, was placed here.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>そのため「栄山寺行宮跡」として国の史跡に指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hence it is designated as a national historical landmark as &apos;Eisan-ji Angu Ruins.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hence it is designated as a national historic site, &apos;the Site of Eisan-ji Angu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>historic siteと変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hence it is designated as a national historic site, &apos;the Site of Eisan-ji Angu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>現存する八角堂は、藤原武智麻呂の没後、子の藤原仲麻呂が父の菩提を弔うために建立したと伝える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the existing Hakkakudo is what FUJIWARA no Nakamaro constructed in memory of his father, FUJIWATA no Muchimaro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the existing Hakkakudo is what FUJIWARA no Nakamaro built in memory of his father, FUJIWATA no Muchimaro.</e>
<cmt>単語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the existing Hakkakudo is what FUJIWARA no Nakamaro built in memory of his father, FUJIWATA no Muchimaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>武智麻呂の墓は当初は佐保山（奈良市街地北部の丘陵地）にあったが、天平宝字4年（760年）、栄山寺北側の山上に改葬された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Muchimaro&apos;s tomb was in Mt. Saho (North of Nara urban district) at first but it was moved to the top of the north side of Eisan-ji Temple in 760.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Muchimaro&apos;s tomb was on Mt. Saho (a hilly place in the north of the urban area of Nara City) at first but moved on the mountain to the north of Eisan-ji Temple in 760.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ部を補い、表現を一部訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Muchimaro&apos;s tomb was on Mt. Saho (a hilly place in the north of the urban area of Nara City) at first but moved on the mountain to the north of Eisan-ji Temple in 760.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>八角堂の建立時期はこの年から仲麻呂の没した天平宝字8年（764年）までの5年間に絞られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Evidence shows that the construction of this Hakkakudo must have been built between 760 and 764, the year of Nakamuro&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Hakkakudo should have been constructed within the five-year period from this year to the year Nakamaro died, 764.</e>
<cmt>過剰な表現とスペルミスを直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Hakkakudo should have been constructed within the five-year period from this year to the year Nakamaro died, 764.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>正倉院文書（もんじょ）に天平宝字7年（763年）12月20日付けの「造円堂所牒」（ぞうえんどうしょちょう）という文書があり、この「円堂」は栄山寺八角堂を指すものと考証されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Shosoin Monjo, there is a text called the &apos;Zo Endo Shocho&apos; which is considered to validate its mentioning of &apos;Endo&apos; indicates Eisan-ji Temple Hakkakudo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There exists a document known as &apos;Zoendoshocho (造円堂所牒)&apos; dated December 20, 763 in Shosoin Monjo (documents retained in Shosoin), and the word &apos;Endo (円堂)&apos; in this document is considered to refer to Hakkakudo of Eisan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れあり（天平宝字7年（763年）12月20日付けの）、補足しました。正倉院文書の説明を補足しました。分かりづらい部分があるため修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There exists a document known as &apos;Zoendoshocho (造円堂所牒)&apos; dated December 20, 763 in Shosoin Monjo (documents retained in Shosoin), and the word &apos;Endo (円堂)&apos; in this document is considered to refer to Hakkakudo of Eisan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>建造物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structure</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structures</e>
<cmt>複数形にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structures</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>本堂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main hall</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Main hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Main hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>八角堂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hakkakudo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hakkakudo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hakkakudo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>藤原武智麻呂の菩提を弔うために子の藤原仲麻呂が建立したと伝えられる本瓦葺の八角形の建物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Nakamaro constructed in memory of his father, Muchimaro, and its structure is tile roofing in octangular shape.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is an octagonal building in the Honkawarabuki tile-roofing style and considered to have been erected by FUJIWARA no Nakamaro to pray to the Buddha for the repose of the soul of his father, Muchimaro.</e>
<cmt>「菩提を弔う」の説明を補足し、文後半の分かりづらい部分を書き直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is an octagonal building in the Honkawarabuki tile-roofing style and considered to have been erected by FUJIWARA no Nakamaro to pray to the Buddha for the repose of the soul of his father, Muchimaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>平城京および斑鳩以外の地区にある奈良時代建築として稀有のものであり、建立年次がほぼ特定できる点でも貴重な建築である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is rare structure of the Nara period although there are others in Heijo-kyo City and Ikaruga, also its another distinctive feature is that you can almost identify the year of construction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a rare structure among the buildings built in the Nara period from the points that it was built in the place other than Heijo-kyo or Ikaruga and that the year of construction has been almost identified.</e>
<cmt>文法ミス、分かりづらい表現があるので全体的に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a rare structure among the buildings built in the Nara period from the points that it was built in the place other than Heijo-kyo or Ikaruga and that the year of construction has been almost identified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>外観は平面八角形であるが、内部の身舎（もや）は四角形であり、内陣周囲に立つ4本の八角柱が構造上の要となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The exterior is flat octangular shape, but the Moya (central part of the building) is square and the 4 octangular pillars surrounding the chancel play the pivotal role in its structure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is octagonal-shaped on the exterior, but the moya (the central part of the building) is square and four octagonal pillars erected at the periphery of the naijin (the inner temple) are structural pivots.</e>
<cmt>不適当な単語の使用、及び分かりづらい表現があるので、全体的に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is octagonal-shaped on the exterior, but the moya (the central part of the building) is square and four octagonal pillars erected at the periphery of the naijin (the inner temple) are structural pivots.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>屋根は明治44年（1911年）の解体修理以前には草葺きであったものを修理に際して瓦葺きに推定復元したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The roof was thatched roof until the refurbishment in 1911, when it was presumably restored into tile roof.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It used to have a thatched roof before the refurbishment in 1911, when the roof was restored with tiles.</e>
<cmt>不適当な単語の使用、及び分かりづらい表現があるので、全体的に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It used to have a thatched roof before the refurbishment in 1911, when the roof was restored with tiles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>屋根上の宝珠は修理の際に復元したものだが、当初のものとされる石造宝珠残欠が別に保存されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sacred gem on top of the roof was restored then, however the original remains of the sacred gem made of stone is separately and safely kept.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hoju (the uppermost spherical part of a pagoda finial) on the roof was restored then, but the remain of stone hoju, which is considered to be the original, is preserved separately.</e>
<cmt>文法ミスを直しました。訳出ミスがあり（宝珠）、訂正しました(EUdictウェブサイトより)。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hoju (the uppermost spherical part of a pagoda finial) on the roof was restored then, but the remain of stone hoju, which is considered to be the original, is preserved separately.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>内部の4本の柱と上部の飛貫（ひぬき）、天井の彩色絵画は剥落が甚だしいとはいえ、奈良時代絵画の遺品として貴重なもので、建物とは別個に「絵画」として重要文化財に指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The internal 4 pillars and top Hinuki (pegs/tie beam)and the painting on the ceiling is greatly damaged by peeling and falling, nevertheless it is a valuable legacy of Nara period painting, and the painting t is separately designated as an important cultural property as well as the architecture.</e>
<cmt>Hinuki (pegs/tie beam)http://www.aisf.or.jp/~jaanus/deta/h/hinuki.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The colored paintings on the internal four pillars, hinuki (a neck penetrating tie beam which extends through a pillar) on the upper part of the pillars, and the ceiling are greatly damaged by peeling and falling, but nevertheless they are a valuable legacy from the Nara period painting and designated as important cultural properties as &apos;paintings&apos; separately from the architecture.</e>
<cmt>文法ミス、若干の訳漏れと誤訳あり、修正しました。左記ウェブサイト及びhttp://kankodori.net/japaneseculture/treasure/037/index.htmlを参考し、飛抜の説明を補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The colored paintings on the internal four pillars, hinuki (a neck penetrating tie beam which extends through a pillar) on the upper part of the pillars, and the ceiling are greatly damaged by peeling and falling, but nevertheless they are a valuable legacy from the Nara period painting and designated as important cultural properties as &apos;paintings&apos; separately from the architecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>柱には楽器を奏する菩薩像、飛貫には飛天や人面をもつ鳥などが描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the pillars, there are paintings of Bodhi playing musical instruments, on Hinuki (pegs/tie beam) Hiten (angels) and birds with man&apos;s faces are painted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bodhisattva playing a musical instrument is painted on the pillars and Hiten (a flying, music-playing Buddhist angel) and birds with human&apos;s faces on hinuki.</e>
<cmt>文法を直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bodhisattva playing a musical instrument is painted on the pillars and Hiten (a flying, music-playing Buddhist angel) and birds with human&apos;s faces on hinuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cultural Property</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>複数形にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>国宝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National Treasure</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National Treasures</e>
<cmt>複数形にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National Treasures</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>八角堂（附旧石露盤残欠）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hakkakudo (</e>
<cmt>（附旧石露盤残欠）- 意味不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hakkakudo (with the remain of stone roban [a dew basin at the bottom of a pagoda finial]and hoju [the uppermost spherical part of a pagoda finial])</e>
<cmt>附旧石露盤残欠の説明を補足しました（EUdictウェブサイトより）。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hakkakudo (with the remain of stone roban [a dew basin at the bottom of a pagoda finial]and hoju [the uppermost spherical part of a pagoda finial])</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>梵鐘</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bonsho (bell)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bonsho (a temple bell)</e>
<cmt>冠詞を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bonsho (a temple bell)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>銘文から延喜17年（917年）の製作とわかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The inscription says it is made in 917.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The inscription says it was made in 917.</e>
<cmt>時制を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The inscription says it was made in 917.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>京都の神護寺、宇治の平等院の鐘と共に「平安三絶の鐘」として知られているもので、四面に菅原道真撰で、小野道風の書と伝えられる陽鋳の銘文が施されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Along with the bell in Jingo-ji Temple in Kyoto and the one in Byodoin Temple in Uji, it is one of the &apos; Heian Sanzetsu no Kane (Heian&apos;s Best ever Bells),&apos; and on its four surfaces there are inscriptions of ONO no Michikaze&apos;s calligraphy in relief.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Along with the bell in Jingo-ji Temple in Kyoto and the one in Byodo-in Temple in Uji, it is known as one of &apos;Heian Sanzetsu no Kane (Heian&apos;s Three Best Bells),&apos; and on its four sides there are bulged inscriptions of the words chosen by SUGAWARA no Michizane and calligraphed by ONO no Michikaze.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れあり、補いました（菅原道真撰で、陽鋳）。陽鋳は「銘文を浮き出させて記入する方法」とのことなのでbulged inscriptionsとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Along with the bell in Jingo-ji Temple in Kyoto and the one in Byodo-in Temple in Uji, it is known as one of &apos;Heian Sanzetsu no Kane (Heian&apos;s Three Best Bells),&apos; and on its four sides there are bulged inscriptions of the words chosen by SUGAWARA no Michizane and calligraphed by ONO no Michikaze.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>藤原武智麻呂の5世の孫である藤原道明と道明の伯父の橘澄清によって寄進されたもので、当初は山城道澄寺にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Muchimaro&apos;s 5th generation down, FUJIWARA no Michiaki and his uncle, TACHIBANA no Sumikiyo dedicated it, and initially it was in Yamashiro Docho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>山城道澄寺 -reading unknown</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was dedicated by FUJIWARA no Muchimaro&apos;s 5th generation down, FUJIWARA no Michiaki, and his uncle, TACHIBANA no Sumikiyo, and initially it was in Yamashiro Docho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>藤原武智麻呂の5世の孫</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was dedicated by FUJIWARA no Michiaki who was 5 generations after FUJIWARA no Muchimaro, and his uncle, TACHIBANA no Sumikiyo, and initially it was in Yamashiro Docho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>FUJIWARA no Muchimaro&apos;s 5th generation down→FUJIWARA no Michiaki who was 5 generations after FUJIWARA no Muchimaroとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>道澄寺は藤原道明と橘澄清の名の1字ずつを取って寺号としたもので、寺は京都市伏見区深草直違橋（すじかいばし）に現存する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Docho-ji Temple was named after FUJIWARA no Michiaki and TACHIBANA no Sumikiyo by taking one character from each of their names, and the temple is located in Sujikai-bashi Bridge, Fukakusa, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Docho-ji Temple was named after FUJIWARA no Michiaki and TACHIBANA no Sumikiyo by taking one character from each of their names, and is located in Sujikai-bashi Bridge, Fukakusa, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>the templeを省きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Docho-ji Temple was named after FUJIWARA no Michiaki and TACHIBANA no Sumikiyo by taking one character from each of their names, and is located in Sujikai-bashi Bridge, Fukakusa, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="32">
<j>重要文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important Cultural Property</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>複数形にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>八角堂内陣装飾画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hakkakudo Naijin (chancel) Decorative Painting</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hakkakudo Naijin (the inner temple) Decorative Painting</e>
<cmt>内陣はinner templeとしました(ウェブサイトEUdictより)。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hakkakudo Naijin (the inner temple) Decorative Painting</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>音声菩薩図（八角柱）4本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onjo Bosatsu (Bodhi) (4 Octangular pillars)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Painting of Onjo Bosatsu (Bodhisattva) (on Octagonal pillars) 4 pieces</e>
<cmt>Picturesを加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Painting of Onjo Bosatsu (Bodhisattva) (on Octagonal pillars) 4 pieces</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>飛天、人鳥、菩薩、神仙図（飛貫）4本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Angels, Birds with men&apos;s faces, Bodhi, hermits (4 Hinuki)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Pictures of Buddhist Angel, Bird with Human&apos;s Face, Bodhisattva, Mountain Wizard (on hinuki) 4 pieces</e>
<cmt>Picturesを加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Pictures of Buddhist Angel, Bird with Human&apos;s Face, Bodhisattva, Mountain Wizard (on hinuki) 4 pieces</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>宝相華文（天井）1面</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hosogemon (ceiling) 1 surface</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hosogemon (a flower pattern) (on the ceiling) 1 piece</e>
<cmt>宝相華文の説明を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hosogemon (a flower pattern) (on the ceiling) 1 piece</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>木造薬師如来坐像－本堂須弥壇上の黒漆塗厨子の中に安置されている像で、作風などから室町時代の作とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wooden seated image of Yakushi Nyorai Buddha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wooden Seated Image of Yakushi Nyorai Buddha – the statue enshrined in a black-lacquered miniature shrine on the dais in the hondo (the main hall), which, based on the style of its make, is considered to have been created in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れに対応しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wooden Seated Image of Yakushi Nyorai Buddha – the statue enshrined in a black-lacquered miniature shrine on the dais in the hondo (the main hall), which, based on the style of its make, is considered to have been created in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="38">
<j>木造十二神将立像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wooden standing images of 12 divine generals</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wooden standing images of 12 divine generals</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wooden standing images of 12 divine generals</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>石灯籠</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stone lantern</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stone lantern</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stone lantern</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>本堂前に据えられている弘安7年（1284年）の銘がある石灯籠で、栄山寺型と呼ばれ、造立当初の姿をよく残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This stone lantern has an inscription of 1284 and located in the main hall, it is called Eisan-ji style and it shows well its initial image.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This stone lantern has an inscription of 1284 and located in the main hall, it is called Eisan-ji style and it shows well its initial image.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This stone lantern has an inscription of 1284 and located in the main hall, it is called Eisan-ji style and it shows well its initial image.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="41">
<j>石塔婆（石造七重塔）－平安時代後期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stone Toba (stone made 7 storey tower) - later Heian period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stone Toba (a stone 7-storied tower) – built in the later Heian period.</e>
<cmt>言葉を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stone Toba (a stone 7-storied tower) – built in the later Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="42">
<j>史跡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Historic site</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historic sites</e>
<cmt>複数形にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historic sites</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>栄山寺行宮跡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eisan-ji Angu remains</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The site of Eisan-ji Angu</e>
<cmt>前表記の言葉に統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The site of Eisan-ji Angu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>栄山寺旧蔵の文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eisan-ji Kyu old stocked cultural property</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cultural Properties stored in former storehouse of Eisan-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>語順が明らかに間違っています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cultural Properties stored in former storehouse of Eisan-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="44">
<j>下記3件の古文書（各重要文化財）は、第二次大戦後に文化庁買上げとなり、現在は国立歴史民俗博物館の所蔵となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following 3 ancient texts (important cultural properties) were bought by Cultural Ministry after World War II, currently belong to the National Museum of Japanese History.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Three ancient manuscripts mentioned below (each of which is an important cultural property) were bought by the Agency for Cultural Affairs after World War II, and currently belong to the National Museum of Japanese History.</e>
<cmt>用語が間違っています（文化庁）。文法ミスもあり、直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Three ancient manuscripts mentioned below (each of which is an important cultural property) were bought by the Agency for Cultural Affairs after World War II, and currently belong to the National Museum of Japanese History.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>いずれも寺の歴史を知る上で重要な史料である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All are important material to study the history of the temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All are important historical records to study the history of the temple.</e>
<cmt>史料をhistorical recordsとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All are important historical records to study the history of the temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="46">
<j>栄山寺寺領文書 3巻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eisan-ji Temple Ryobunsho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eisan-ji Temple Jiryo (the fief owned by a temple) Monjo (documents): 3 volumes</e>
<cmt>読み方が間違っていると思います。訳漏れもあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eisan-ji Temple Jiryo (the fief owned by a temple) Monjo (documents): 3 volumes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>官宣旨 保元三年八月七日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">官宣旨 保元三年八月七日</e>
<cmt>訳し方がわからないのでそのままにしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kansenji (a formal document issued by the highest administrative agency to a temple or a shrine): dated August 7 in the 3rd year of the Hogen era (4/27/1156 to 4/20/1159)</e>
<cmt>分かる範囲で訳出しました（参考:デジタル大辞泉）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kansenji (a formal document issued by the highest administrative agency to a temple or a shrine): dated August 7 in the 3rd year of the Hogen era (April 27, 1156 to April 20, 1159)</e>
<cmt>3rdの上付きを修正しました。 (4/27/1156 to 4/20/1159)を統一表現に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>起請文 永暦元年十月二十日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">起請文 永暦元年十月二十日</e>
<cmt>訳し方がわからないのでそのままにしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kishomon (a document on which an oath [to Buddha or gods] was written): dated October 20 in the 1st year of the Eiryaku era (1/10/1160 to 9/4/1161)</e>
<cmt>分かる範囲で訳出しました（参考:デジタル大辞泉）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kishomon (a document on which an oath [to Buddha or gods] was written): dated October 20 in the 1st year of the Eiryaku era (October 1, 1160 to April 9, 1161)</e>
<cmt>1stの上付きを修正しました。1/10/1160 to 9/4/1161を統一表現に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>アクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="49">
<j>JR五条駅 (奈良県)・五條バスセンターより奈良交通バス「栄山寺前」下車。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JR Gojo Station(Nara Prefecture) Nara Kotsu Bus &apos;Eisan-ji Temple&apos; from Gojo Bus centre</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Take a Nara Kotsu bus at Gojo Bus Center at JR Gojo Station (Nara Prefecture) and get off at &apos;Eisan-ji Temple&apos;.</e>
<cmt>分かりやすく書き直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Take a Nara Kotsu bus at Gojo Bus Center at JR Gojo Station (Nara Prefecture) and get off at &apos;Eisan-ji Temple&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>但し便数は少なく休日は運休。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The buses are not frequent, and do not run on holidays.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The buses are not frequent, and do not run on holidays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The buses are not frequent, and do not run on holidays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>もしくは「栄山寺口」で下車し今井町交差点を南へ徒歩10分ほど。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Or get off at the bus stop &apos;Eisan-ji Temple Entrance&apos; and 10 minutes walk to the south at the Imaicho junction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Or get off at the bus stop &apos;Eisan-ji Guchi&apos; and walk southward for about 10 minutes from the Imai-cho intersection.</e>
<cmt>分かりやすく書き直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Or get off at the bus stop &apos;Eisan-ji Guchi&apos; and walk southward for about 10 minutes from the Imai-cho intersection.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="52">
<j>緯度・経度</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Latitude/Longitude</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Latitude/Longitude</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Latitude/Longitude</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>世界測地系による表示</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By World Geodetic System</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By World Geodetic System</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By World Geodetic System</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), Penpen(id:18815), КОЛЯ(id:59429), Urania(id:7213), D.h(id:79056), 663highland(id:18755), Enamelpajama(id:69558), Ｈｉｒｏ２００６(id:59115), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>